<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/economics/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-10-12T22:20:37+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/economics/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Drug Dilemma</title>
      <link href="/The-Drug-Dilemma" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Drug Dilemma" />
      <published>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Drug-Dilemma</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Drug-Dilemma">&lt;p&gt;It is no lie that the issue of decriminalisation or legalisation of drugs has always been a double-edged sword for policymakers across the world. Buoyed by the success in the West, several organisations have time and again advocated for the legalisation of drugs, particularly cannabis in India. But it is imperative to understand that drug decriminalisation or legalisation is not a public policy choice that is suited to a superficial debate. It requires analysis and research of an order that has been well absent despite the never-ending attention the issue receives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin with, drug legalisation refers to the ending of all government-enforced prohibition on the distribution, sale and personal use of specified drugs. On the other hand, drug decriminalisation calls for reduced control and penalties compared to existing laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Portuguese Decriminalisation Model&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very first country to decriminalise possession and consumption of all kinds of drugs was Portugal in 2001. Back in the 1990's, Portugal was in a tight grip of heroin addiction. Thousands of people could be seen on the streets engaging in drug use. Over 1% of the population was hooked on heroin and the country faced the highest rate of HIV infection in the entire EU. The government response to this menace was something that all of us are familiar with - harsh policies implemented by the criminal justice system and the leaders speaking against drug use. A result of this was that by the late 1990's, half of the population in the prisons was charged under drug-related offences.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in 2001, the country took a historic step in favour of decriminalisation. According to the Drug Policy Alliance, Portugal has experienced no major increases in drug use. Yet it has seen reduced rates of problematic and adolescent drug use, fewer people arrested and incarcerated for drugs, reduced incidence of HIV/AIDS, fewer drug-induced deaths, and a significant increase in the number of people receiving treatment. Since then, some form of decriminalisation has been adopted in 30 countries with significant differences and levels of effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analysing the Two Sides&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decriminalisation of drugs comes with its own set of pros and cons which are far more complex than what it is presented to the general public. The standard economic theory supports the intervention of the government in drug markets because of the negative externalities involved. However, prohibiting a good does not eliminate the market for it. The prices of the product rise and supply becomes difficult to procure leading to the creation of a black market of the product. Apparently, prohibition policies have not worked as planned, and have generally resulted in just a changed format of supply and demand.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is evident that drug use of any kind does involve negative externalities. However, the procurement of drugs in the illegal market probably generates more negative externalities than its purchase in the legal market. One of these additional externalities includes the ‘environmental’ effect of the drug trade. The environmental effect refers to the influence that the perception of neighbourhood can have on an individual's susceptibility to drug dependence. When drug offenders on release return home, they are often most concentrated in relatively few urban centres and poor neighbourhoods facing various social challenges. Statistically, most of these released individuals are often booked for some offence within the year of their release, and thus, this turns into a vicious cycle. This is because the incarcerated individuals are more prone to drug dependence as compared to the general population. With more people on the lookout for drugs in the illegal market, the income-generating crime that may result from the markets’ high prices and the violence associated increases as the disputes cannot be solved through legal procedures. Criminalisation inhibits the quality control of the drugs supplied leading to more accidental and overdose deaths along with a significant increase in health risks. Prohibition, therefore, has not only reduced the size of the drug market but has also led to greater negative externalities: the balance between these two effects is what any country desires!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advocates of drug decriminalisation have pointed out various expected benefits such as reduced number of arrests, increased uptake into drug treatment, reduced criminal justice costs and allocation of funds from criminal justice to health systems and minimised social exclusion of people who use drugs. This helps create a climate in which these drug users are less fearful of seeking and accessing treatment, utilising harm reduction services and receiving HIV/AIDS services - a step towards protecting people from the wide-ranging and crippling consequences of a criminal conviction. However, it is also a fact that much of the above-stated benefits are not supported by substantial evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also crucial to analyse the counter-arguments to the decriminalisation of drugs. One of the major concerns is that decriminalisation may encourage experimentation. Individuals may have genetic vulnerability towards drug use making them more susceptible to addiction and accompanied health risks. Allowing these individuals to have open access and possession of drugs seems like an open-door policy leading to adverse effects. Although many argue that decriminalisation would have no impact on drug prices, free-market economics has a different approach. In the absence of a legal barrier in effect to prevent drug access, it implies a greater supply of drugs which might lead to a fall in its prices. If some people abstain from experimenting with drugs due to price barriers, this move would make them more susceptible to experimentation. In the above list of pros, it was pointed out that decriminalisation would lead to reduced costs of incarceration and treatment. However, the current infrastructure is not well-suited to support the added number of individuals who would seek out help. This implies that added costs would come in the form of building assets to handle the needs of society. And if the implementation goes awry, the resulting costs could be even higher. Thus, given the positives and the negatives, the move toward decriminalisation or legalisation of drugs has to be in accordance with the social and economic infrastructure of a country. The move will unanimously lead to a huge cultural change and added impact on healthcare, law and order, and other components of society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is India Ready for the Move?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India is currently grappling with a growing drug problem, especially in the states of Punjab and Manipur. As per the United Nations World Drug Report, 2019, drug use in India went up by almost 30%. The drug laws, thus, seem to not have been much of a success when it comes to the menace of drug possession and consumption. Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances (NDPS) Act, 1985 was passed to curb the problem of drug abuse and was further amended in 1989, 2001 and then in 2014. The Act provides the provisions for search, forfeiture and capture of those who indulge in drug activities from any place in India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With an increasing number of countries undergoing decriminalisation in some form or the other, the demand for it in India has been getting stronger. Sikkim in 2018 became the first state to no longer prosecute drug users and somewhat treat them as patients rather than criminals in order to encourage treatment options and rehabilitation. But, decriminalisation might not be the best way to handle the situation in India. This is in light of the already vulnerable health care system and the various loopholes existing in law and order. India is struggling to control the use of three addictive substances - tobacco, alcohol and areca nut. As per the Global Adult Tobacco Survey by the World Health Organisation (2016-17), 270 million Indians use tobacco and it kills around 1.35 million Indians every year. Nearly 30% of India’s adult population is using alcohol, leading to 3.3 million deaths. Legalising drugs in the wake of this situation might only worsen the above-mentioned alarming statistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2019, a petition was also filed by the Great Legalisation Movement India Trust seeking decriminalisation of cannabis. Cannabis has been known to possess several medicinal properties and can be used as a cure for various diseases. However, people against this have pointed out that legalising cannabis may lead to its surge as a gateway drug, with research supporting that 45% people who consumed cannabis went on to try other illicit drugs as well. India is home to the maximum people in the youth category and a significant portion of the population is still immersed in poverty lacking access to basic necessities. The employment rate in India is struggling. People in various parts of the country are still not literate. With a large section of the population being highly vulnerable, increasing the access of drugs might prove to be fatal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, it is important to understand that a move meant to be beneficial for society may end up making the same society fall apart if not tackled with care and if implemented in haste. It is truly a fear of the unknown that plagues this debate. No country has the ability at present to predict how the entire society would react if drugs were decriminalised or legalised. It is a risk that a country must take only after the existing infrastructure has been upgraded to support its implementation. How these countries take on the decriminalisation of drugs is yet to be seen. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rajsi Sah</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is no lie that the issue of decriminalisation or legalisation of drugs has always been a double-edged sword for policymakers across the world. Buoyed by the success in the West, several organisations have time and again advocated for the legalisation of drugs, particularly cannabis in India. But it is imperative to understand that drug decriminalisation or legalisation is not a public policy choice that is suited to a superficial debate. It requires analysis and research of an order that has been well absent despite the never-ending attention the issue receives. To begin with, drug legalisation refers to the ending of all government-enforced prohibition on the distribution, sale and personal use of specified drugs. On the other hand, drug decriminalisation calls for reduced control and penalties compared to existing laws. The Portuguese Decriminalisation Model The very first country to decriminalise possession and consumption of all kinds of drugs was Portugal in 2001. Back in the 1990's, Portugal was in a tight grip of heroin addiction. Thousands of people could be seen on the streets engaging in drug use. Over 1% of the population was hooked on heroin and the country faced the highest rate of HIV infection in the entire EU. The government response to this menace was something that all of us are familiar with - harsh policies implemented by the criminal justice system and the leaders speaking against drug use. A result of this was that by the late 1990's, half of the population in the prisons was charged under drug-related offences.&amp;nbsp; But in 2001, the country took a historic step in favour of decriminalisation. According to the Drug Policy Alliance, Portugal has experienced no major increases in drug use. Yet it has seen reduced rates of problematic and adolescent drug use, fewer people arrested and incarcerated for drugs, reduced incidence of HIV/AIDS, fewer drug-induced deaths, and a significant increase in the number of people receiving treatment. Since then, some form of decriminalisation has been adopted in 30 countries with significant differences and levels of effectiveness. Analysing the Two Sides Decriminalisation of drugs comes with its own set of pros and cons which are far more complex than what it is presented to the general public. The standard economic theory supports the intervention of the government in drug markets because of the negative externalities involved. However, prohibiting a good does not eliminate the market for it. The prices of the product rise and supply becomes difficult to procure leading to the creation of a black market of the product. Apparently, prohibition policies have not worked as planned, and have generally resulted in just a changed format of supply and demand.&amp;nbsp; It is evident that drug use of any kind does involve negative externalities. However, the procurement of drugs in the illegal market probably generates more negative externalities than its purchase in the legal market. One of these additional externalities includes the ‘environmental’ effect of the drug trade. The environmental effect refers to the influence that the perception of neighbourhood can have on an individual's susceptibility to drug dependence. When drug offenders on release return home, they are often most concentrated in relatively few urban centres and poor neighbourhoods facing various social challenges. Statistically, most of these released individuals are often booked for some offence within the year of their release, and thus, this turns into a vicious cycle. This is because the incarcerated individuals are more prone to drug dependence as compared to the general population. With more people on the lookout for drugs in the illegal market, the income-generating crime that may result from the markets’ high prices and the violence associated increases as the disputes cannot be solved through legal procedures. Criminalisation inhibits the quality control of the drugs supplied leading to more accidental and overdose deaths along with a significant increase in health risks. Prohibition, therefore, has not only reduced the size of the drug market but has also led to greater negative externalities: the balance between these two effects is what any country desires! The advocates of drug decriminalisation have pointed out various expected benefits such as reduced number of arrests, increased uptake into drug treatment, reduced criminal justice costs and allocation of funds from criminal justice to health systems and minimised social exclusion of people who use drugs. This helps create a climate in which these drug users are less fearful of seeking and accessing treatment, utilising harm reduction services and receiving HIV/AIDS services - a step towards protecting people from the wide-ranging and crippling consequences of a criminal conviction. However, it is also a fact that much of the above-stated benefits are not supported by substantial evidence. It is also crucial to analyse the counter-arguments to the decriminalisation of drugs. One of the major concerns is that decriminalisation may encourage experimentation. Individuals may have genetic vulnerability towards drug use making them more susceptible to addiction and accompanied health risks. Allowing these individuals to have open access and possession of drugs seems like an open-door policy leading to adverse effects. Although many argue that decriminalisation would have no impact on drug prices, free-market economics has a different approach. In the absence of a legal barrier in effect to prevent drug access, it implies a greater supply of drugs which might lead to a fall in its prices. If some people abstain from experimenting with drugs due to price barriers, this move would make them more susceptible to experimentation. In the above list of pros, it was pointed out that decriminalisation would lead to reduced costs of incarceration and treatment. However, the current infrastructure is not well-suited to support the added number of individuals who would seek out help. This implies that added costs would come in the form of building assets to handle the needs of society. And if the implementation goes awry, the resulting costs could be even higher. Thus, given the positives and the negatives, the move toward decriminalisation or legalisation of drugs has to be in accordance with the social and economic infrastructure of a country. The move will unanimously lead to a huge cultural change and added impact on healthcare, law and order, and other components of society. Is India Ready for the Move? India is currently grappling with a growing drug problem, especially in the states of Punjab and Manipur. As per the United Nations World Drug Report, 2019, drug use in India went up by almost 30%. The drug laws, thus, seem to not have been much of a success when it comes to the menace of drug possession and consumption. Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances (NDPS) Act, 1985 was passed to curb the problem of drug abuse and was further amended in 1989, 2001 and then in 2014. The Act provides the provisions for search, forfeiture and capture of those who indulge in drug activities from any place in India. With an increasing number of countries undergoing decriminalisation in some form or the other, the demand for it in India has been getting stronger. Sikkim in 2018 became the first state to no longer prosecute drug users and somewhat treat them as patients rather than criminals in order to encourage treatment options and rehabilitation. But, decriminalisation might not be the best way to handle the situation in India. This is in light of the already vulnerable health care system and the various loopholes existing in law and order. India is struggling to control the use of three addictive substances - tobacco, alcohol and areca nut. As per the Global Adult Tobacco Survey by the World Health Organisation (2016-17), 270 million Indians use tobacco and it kills around 1.35 million Indians every year. Nearly 30% of India’s adult population is using alcohol, leading to 3.3 million deaths. Legalising drugs in the wake of this situation might only worsen the above-mentioned alarming statistics. In 2019, a petition was also filed by the Great Legalisation Movement India Trust seeking decriminalisation of cannabis. Cannabis has been known to possess several medicinal properties and can be used as a cure for various diseases. However, people against this have pointed out that legalising cannabis may lead to its surge as a gateway drug, with research supporting that 45% people who consumed cannabis went on to try other illicit drugs as well. India is home to the maximum people in the youth category and a significant portion of the population is still immersed in poverty lacking access to basic necessities. The employment rate in India is struggling. People in various parts of the country are still not literate. With a large section of the population being highly vulnerable, increasing the access of drugs might prove to be fatal.&amp;nbsp; In the end, it is important to understand that a move meant to be beneficial for society may end up making the same society fall apart if not tackled with care and if implemented in haste. It is truly a fear of the unknown that plagues this debate. No country has the ability at present to predict how the entire society would react if drugs were decriminalised or legalised. It is a risk that a country must take only after the existing infrastructure has been upgraded to support its implementation. How these countries take on the decriminalisation of drugs is yet to be seen.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Racism is Profitable</title>
      <link href="/Racism-is-Profitable" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Racism is Profitable" />
      <published>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Racism-is-Profitable</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Racism-is-Profitable">&lt;p&gt;This is simply not the time to be talking about how Nelson Mandela fought ‘apartheid’ in South Africa or how Rosa Parks refused to give up her bus seat to a white man, because that world was decades ago, fraught with exploitation, incarceration, brutalities, exclusion, all on the basis of a simple difference – skin colour. One may wonder that due to the efforts of these icons, the world, sixty years down the line, will be different, wherein all races are treated equally. Fast forward to 2020, does the phrase &lt;em&gt;“I can’t breathe”&lt;/em&gt; ring any bells? If it does, congratulations, you’re not living under a rock. George Floyd, an ordinary American man, was pinned down on the road, with a knee pressing on his throat, by a police officer for allegedly using a $20 counterfeit bill, “allegedly” being the keyword here. George Floyd was killed and the accused officer got so much so as a suspension. Why? Racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst the pandemic, the historic Black Lives Matter (BLM) movement took place and &lt;em&gt;#JusticeForGeorgeFloyd&lt;/em&gt; was trending all across the globe. Not just the black community, but people from all races came out in support of the cause and identified themselves as allies of the movement. Not only individuals and communities but even corporations, small and big, spoke on the cause and corporate executives expressed their contempt towards police brutality, establishing their coherence with the black community. So does this mean white supremacy has ended and finally there is socio-political and economic liberation for the black community? I think not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When multinational corporations like Amazon, Walmart, and Wall Street banks like CitiBank and JPMorgan Chase put out posters in support of the movement, the face value of it painted an empathetic picture. However, the harsh reality is that it was just a mere public relations stunt for them. Far from being the solution to systemic racism in America, these multi-billion dollar corporations have been actively perpetuating it. It is fair to say that corporate hypocrisy exists when on the one hand these banks, like JPMorgan Chase, claim to be inclusive by employing a few black employees and by giving press interviews where they urge everyone to be more inclusive in their respective workplaces and neighbourhoods, while on the other hand, they discriminate against their black customers by making them incur heavier costs for mortgage borrowing, and not addressing this form of discrimination despite recognising and identifying it. Not only customers but the figures show how JPMorgan Chase discriminates against its own employees by excluding black people from holding positions in the top tier of management. Barely about 4% of the bank’s top executives are black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason behind this is that corporations profit off of racism. The historic oppression and suppression, for example - removing native people from their land through theft and genocide, enslaving African people for work and reproductive labour, and so on- are proofs of the fact that ‘racial capitalism’ has existed for ages and continues to exist in the status quo wherein wealthy elites are motivated to keep suppressing the economic vitality of people of colour. This initiates a vicious cycle of an ‘oppression economy’ wherein this economic suppression leads on to prevent these communities from having any form of social capital and hence, hinders their political power and their ability to bring about any form of a political change in the society. In the 21st century, racism is not just limited to the difference in skin colour, but extends to acting as a means to an end; the means being the black community and the end being the flourishing of these multinational corporations. Economist Darrick Hamilton explains that the pursuit of profit, not hatred of black people, is the real root of discrimination,  &lt;em&gt;“Racism is a tool, a mechanism. In many settings, it’s purposeful. Sure, bias can become implicit or unconscious through socialization. But that is a secondary effect from the initial tool that was used”&lt;/em&gt;  said Hamilton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also an extreme economic inequality among whites and blacks in the United States. This again stems from the fact that ‘racial capitalism’ or ‘oppression economy’ inherently functions by uplifting one community meanwhile pushing down the other. In such scenarios, when a community is discriminated against, there comes a paradigm of ostracisation wherein one community is never allowed to have equal rights, which leads to them being either unemployed or underpaid. Even governments, in the past, haven’t been able to tackle the effects of racism on the economy, and this was proved right when former US President Ronald Reagan asked black citizens to trust the marketplace in case they have distrust towards the government. And it is no secret how that panned out, considering the marketplace was discriminatory in its very essence, due to the existence of racial resentment and white supremacy. Even when some progressives wanted to bring about economic equality and infrastructural development, it meant that all races have to side with the government, and since racism creates divisions and distrust among citizens, siding with one government was not an option. Therefore, the progressives deemed it best to leave the reign of bridging economic inequality with the rich multinational corporations. And hence, the vicious cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From economic inequality stems wealth inequality, which means inequality in the amount of money one could save from their incomes. This form of wealth could also be in terms of bonds or real estate properties. Since the black community has been historically oppressed, their chance at inheriting any prior wealth is negligible, but moreover, they face uncountable barriers to creating any form of wealth in the current scenario. These barriers are again due to the systemic discrimination faced by the community. This lack of wealth and savings has shown its effects during the COVID-19 pandemic for the black community since they are the ones that face the brunt of environmental injustice, implications of poverty, and systemic racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People from the black community are also highly criminalised and penalised, at least three times more than their white counterparts. This also means profit for the corporations since a higher number of criminals means a higher number of prisons, which are in fact constructed and funded for by these corporations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, the ‘oppression economy’ is not the need of the hour, but the ‘liberation economy’ is. And our only way to be able to get a ‘liberation economy’ is by firstly, supporting and electing candidates that will actively tackle issues of racism and better the economic policies for people of colour. Secondly, the unnecessary criminalisation of people from the black community has to end and the government has to tackle the root cause of the occurrence of such activities which may, in fact, stem from the socio-political or economic needs of these people. And lastly, the universal guarantee to have access to basic economic rights, healthcare and education should be made. Race is an inherent part of people’s identities and to deserve basic human decency, one should not be made to feel that they need to part with their identities. All communities together choose their governments and to simply leave the reign of controlling and dictating our lives in the hands of profit-driven corporations is a breach of democracy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This is simply not the time to be talking about how Nelson Mandela fought ‘apartheid’ in South Africa or how Rosa Parks refused to give up her bus seat to a white man, because that world was decades ago, fraught with exploitation, incarceration, brutalities, exclusion, all on the basis of a simple difference – skin colour. One may wonder that due to the efforts of these icons, the world, sixty years down the line, will be different, wherein all races are treated equally. Fast forward to 2020, does the phrase “I can’t breathe” ring any bells? If it does, congratulations, you’re not living under a rock. George Floyd, an ordinary American man, was pinned down on the road, with a knee pressing on his throat, by a police officer for allegedly using a $20 counterfeit bill, “allegedly” being the keyword here. George Floyd was killed and the accused officer got so much so as a suspension. Why? Racism.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Money Tree</title>
      <link href="/Money-Tree" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Money Tree" />
      <published>2020-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Money-Tree</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Money-Tree">&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered why countries can’t just print more money to pay off their debts, to feed the homeless, to fix unemployment or for any other issue for that matter? This may seem like a rather silly question but I think it’s one of those questions that people may always wonder about but never ask. The answer can be summed up in just one word - inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inflation is defined as a persistent and substantial increase in the general level of prices related to an increase in the volume of money resulting in a loss of value of the currency, but I’ll get to that later. First, we need to establish what exactly money is. Now, this may seem obvious to many but we still need to clarify that money has absolutely no intrinsic value. This means money in itself is only considered valuable because it can buy things. But if you were stranded on an island, money would be totally useless. Money only has value because we believe it has value. It is called the ‘Tinkerbell Effect’. The tinkerbell effect is used to describe something that only exists because we believe it exists, and this is the case with money. Hypothetically speaking, if we suddenly start believing that money has no value, it wouldn’t have any value. Of course, it wasn’t always this way. Money as a concept has been around for thousands of years, and was first used in the form of commodity money, i.e things that had actual value and uses like salt, wheat, horses and weapons as well as precious metals such as gold and silver, which technically don’t have any intrinsic value either but due to the rarity they were almost universally accepted as currency. Then we have representative money, which makes more sense since carrying around everything you own can be difficult. Basically, you deposit your gold into a bank and they keep it safe for you and in return, they give you a piece of paper acknowledging that you own that gold. These pieces of paper can therefore be used as money. Anyone can go and redeem the gold at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, today almost every country in the world uses fiat money. Fiat money requires faith and trust in the government by the people. The people will have to value their money enough to use it for transactions. If we use a young country as an example, the United States has gone through all three monetary systems within 200 years. In 1790, when the United States stopped using European money as the Coinage Act of 1792 brought the inception of the US Dollar. USD was originally in the form of commodity money, in the form of gold, silver and copper coins. The coins were actually made from real gold, silver and copper, and the value of the metal that was used to make the coins was exactly equal to their face value. The country then moved on to a mixture of commodities and representative money with the Gold Standard Act of 1900. The government issued dollar bills that could be exchanged for gold anytime. The gold standard is a type of representative money that many countries used at the time. This was an effective way to accurately calculate the exchange rates between countries. For example - if one gram of gold costs £1 in Britain and $1.50 in America, then you can easily deduce that £1= $1.5. Later, gold coins were discontinued and silver was removed from other coins, effectively ending commodity money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1971, Richard Nixon officially abandoned the gold standard, and the US moved on to fiat money. So, money today isn’t backed by gold or anything else of value. Now, back to the question at hand: basic economics tells us that an increase in supply results in a fall in price. So, the more the money in the economy, the lower the value of each dollar. This means other countries can purchase more dollars in exchange for their currencies. A second supply and demand analysis shows why this leads to a rise in prices. More money in the economy causes a shift in the demand curve for goods and services, but since this isn’t matched by an increase in economic output, prices must rise. If we use an analogy to demonstrate this, imagine there are 4 people on a desert island, they have 10 pieces of fruit each. All fruits are considered equal in value. Now, imagine they discover a whole forest of apple trees. The total nominal value of the apples have increased because there’s more of them, but the actual value of an apple has gone down due to an increase in supply. Therefore, it now costs 10 apples for 1 banana since the demand for apples is low compared to its supply but the same is high for bananas. Just to make it clear, in this analogy, people represent different countries, the fruits their respective currency and the apple trees are the printed money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not just because of economic theory that we know printing too much money is a bad idea, there are several examples throughout history. The most recent one is that of Zimbabwe, which in 2008 suffered extremely high inflation due to printing excess money. This was a result of some awful decisions by President Mugabe. When the economy took a turn for the worse, Mugabe printed more money to pay for government expenditure. This caused inflation to skyrocket and in mid-November 2008, Zimbabwe’s inflation peaked at 6.5 sextillion percent! To put that in perspective actually, first I need to provide some context. The inflation rate in the United States is around 1.5%. Economists generally agree that inflation levels around 1-3% are optimum. First world countries’ inflation rates range from 0 to 5%. A country is said to have entered hyperinflation when its inflation level exceeds 50%. So, with this in mind, Zimbabwe’s inflation at its peak got so bad that prices doubled every 24 hours. The government tried to solve the problem by printing more and more money with higher and higher denominations. They also kept knocking zeroes off the end by revaluing the Zimbabwean dollar 3 times, going through 4 different currencies with 4 different ISO codes. Before the final re-denomination, they were printing 100 trillion ZWR bills. People were literally using wheelbarrows full of cash to buy a loaf of bread. The government even made inflation illegal at one point and people were actually arrested for raising prices. In 2009, the Zimbabwean dollar was abandoned and till this day they still have no national currency, their people use currencies such as the US Dollar, the Pound sterling, or the Euro. Before the hyperinflation, the first Zimbabwean dollar was worth about $1.25. If the 100 trillion-dollar bill was worth that exchange rate, that single bill would be worth more money than there is in the entire world! But as ridiculous as this was, this is only considered to be the second-worst inflation in history after Hungary in 1946. Although Zimbabwe’s inflation peaked mid-November as of 2008, their overall highest monthly inflation was 79.6 billion percent which means prices doubled every 24.7 hours. Whereas Hungary’s highest monthly inflation took place in July 1946 which was 41.9 quadrillion percent with prices doubling every 15 hours. To put that in perspective, a country with a healthy inflation rate of around 3%, prices double every 23 years. In 1941, the exchange rate was about 5 Pengo to $1. In 1946, when the currency was discontinued, things had gotten so out of hand, that if you took every single banknote in the entire country, they would have a total value of one-tenth of a US Penny. Hungary then switched to the Fornit, where 1 Forint equaled 400 octillion Pengos. That number has 29 zeros!!! So, that’s why the government can’t just print money to pay off their debts, it does not end well. I’ll leave you with this final thought and what I think is possibly the best way to sum up why governments can’t just print unlimited amounts of money is &lt;em&gt;“If money grew on trees, wouldn’t it be as valuable as leaves?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Have you ever wondered why countries can’t just print more money to pay off their debts, to feed the homeless, to fix unemployment or for any other issue for that matter? This may seem like a rather silly question but I think it’s one of those questions that people may always wonder about but never ask. The answer can be summed up in just one word - inflation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Battle of the Superpowers</title>
      <link href="/The-Battle-of-the-Superpowers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Battle of the Superpowers" />
      <published>2020-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Battle-of-the-Superpowers</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Battle-of-the-Superpowers">&lt;p&gt;The two driving engines of the global economy have been locked in a trade war since July 6, 2018, with the United States imposing a 25% tariff on $34 billion worth of Chinese imports. While Trump claims tariff policy to be a practice to encourage the consumption of American products by making imported goods and services more expensive, it is, in fact, a tool adopted by the US to force China to make changes to its “unfair trade practices” (as termed by the United States). Economists are viewing this trade war as a by-product of the ongoing battle between the two nations for economic and technological world dominance, along with a wave of nationalism, protectionism, and self-reliance growing almost everywhere including the US. The trade war has adversely affected the economic growth of both China and the United States. With the onset of COVID-19, the grievances have increased and a sharp fall in the GDP has been observed in both the nations. The impact of the trade war is not limited to these two parties, the global economy too has witnessed a slowdown owing to the influence that the US and China possess on the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industrial growth rate has hit its seventeen-year low in China, a clear indication of the heavy brunt being felt by China. The trade war continues to threaten the rising global economic influence of China and exerts downward pressure on Chinese economic growth. Experts on the Chinese economy view this war as fatal for business operations and believe that it is likely to leave a long-lasting adverse impact. They view it as the American leadership’s eloquence disguised for selfish national interests and the desire to maintain American hegemony, which has been at play ever since the States ended its cold war with the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR). The domestic reporting on the trade war is censored in China, the situation on the ground is difficult to comment upon, but Chinese social media has managed to throw some light on the adversities by drawing reference from the Marvel Comics wherein Thanos, the villain wipes out half of all the life in the universe using the infinity gauntlet (a superpower); similarly, Trump is believed to wipe out half of China’s investors and businesses using this superpower of tariff policy. The halt in the manufacturing sector in China can be observed by understanding these events from the Chinese industrial city, Dongguan. This sprawling manufacturing hub Dongguan, nicknamed as the ‘Workshop of the World’, is the hardest hit by the ongoing trade war. The impact isn’t limited to the manufacturing sector alone, food joints and other budgeted sources of entertainment in and around the industrial complexes of Dongguan have been shut down too, the bars that were mostly over-crowded during shift changes in the factories now accommodate empty chairs. Dongguan produces and exports a majority of chunk to the United States, and specialises in shoes and brightly coloured plastic bags (for detergents, candies, apparels, dog poop and other essentials needed by Americans in their daily lives), with a double-digit tariff on these goods, the loud noises of the machines in the factories have been muted. Workers residing nearby have begun to migrate back to their native home-towns as America shifts the hub to Vietnam and Indonesia, dropping China’s exports to the US (the country it exported more to than any other country) by 12%. The Chinese economy finds itself in a swamp due to a number of structural lags like the failing banking system, lack of low-skilled workers in the factories, economic over-reliance on manufacturing, ageing workforce, etc., followed by a trade war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tariff policy has not been a cake-walk for the United States too, with 3 million people losing their jobs, the US economy has come to a standstill. The consumers, businessmen, investors and farmers have expressed their dissent on the tariff policy inflicted by Trump’s administration. Though the effect felt on American exports is comparatively smaller than its Asian rival, a number of businesses and various industrialists in the manufacturing sector have felt the brunt. The lower profit margins have infuriated American companies and the farmers protested against the $24 billion worth market they lost in China as a result of retaliatory actions from the American rival in the Asian continent. While America explores new opportunities outside China to compensate for the goods it imported from the dragon, the prices continue to inflate in the American market. Is the trade war worth the pain it has caused to the American economy, which is in the worst shape since the Great Depression?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various emerging economies have been fortunate enough to draw the attention of the American, European and Japanese investors to import the substitutes from countries like Indonesia, Vietnam, Singapore, India and others. A switch in the wave of the global market shall take time to adjust and establish a smooth-sailing ride for the world, but at present, the European market is being strangled the most because of the uncertainty that prevails in the global market. The United States of America and the European Union have always worked in coordination and agreement in like-minded economic organisations and the US continues to be Europe’s most important trade and investment partner. Thus, America’s inward-looking policies have been a matter of great concern for the European countries as well. With the global wind against China amidst the blame-game for the pandemic and China’s furious economic behaviour in the market, the European continent cannot afford to turn its neck towards the Asian giant. Europe too has expressed its grievances on the unfair trade practices by China and has expressed its concerns over the theft of intellectual property by China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the EU can manage to carve its niche in the global market by accommodating the void the two rivals create in each other’s trade. Similarly, Britain too can utilise this opportunity to establish its financial and tech markets in Washington and profit from the growing dissent between the States and the Dragon. Apart from Europe, India too should utilise this opportunity by making a shift in its manufacturing sector as both the US and China are likely to shift their investment flow towards India. Indian exporters should definitely take the risk to explore the gap that the trade war will generate, as the US imposes higher tariffs on Chinese goods and vice versa, this is the most awaited chance for exporters to fiddle and find a space in both the markets. Xiaomi, known as China’s Apple (iPhone), has the largest market in India outside China, India can and should definitely use this opportunity to establish a strong profit margin for itself. While India gained about $775 million additional exports from the US, Apple is likely to shift its base for manufacturing in India, which would make it the largest assembler of iPhones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trade war has definitely teetered the global economy to uncertainties and an unprecedented slowdown, the global pandemic made it more difficult for the economies to survive this wind and stand tall in the global market. Whether America continues to maintain its hegemony or China will take over the global market, will remain an unanswered question for a while until the world revives and breathes into a fresh economic environment post the COVID-19 period.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The two driving engines of the global economy have been locked in a trade war since July 6, 2018, with the United States imposing a 25% tariff on $34 billion worth of Chinese imports. While Trump claims tariff policy to be a practice to encourage the consumption of American products by making imported goods and services more expensive, it is, in fact, a tool adopted by the US to force China to make changes to its “unfair trade practices” (as termed by the United States). Economists are viewing this trade war as a by-product of the ongoing battle between the two nations for economic and technological world dominance, along with a wave of nationalism, protectionism, and self-reliance growing almost everywhere including the US. The trade war has adversely affected the economic growth of both China and the United States. With the onset of COVID-19, the grievances have increased and a sharp fall in the GDP has been observed in both the nations. The impact of the trade war is not limited to these two parties, the global economy too has witnessed a slowdown owing to the influence that the US and China possess on the world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Countering China</title>
      <link href="/Countering-China" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Countering China" />
      <published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Countering-China</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Countering-China">&lt;p&gt;After the Second World War, the world was divided into countries that could largely be categorised as liberal democracies or authoritarian communist nations. But interestingly, contemporary China doesn’t fit in either of these categories. It is an authoritarian market economy. Even as it adopted free-market policies and allowed private companies to grow, there were still a large number of state-owned enterprises. The Chinese Communist Party has invested a huge amount of money in these enterprises, which led to the debt-to-GDP ratio of the country to soar high (most of it, though, was domestic debt). Corruption was also rampant across various public institutions and among public servants. All this led to the above-said conclusions about the China model being weak, and it would crack down and pave the way for a democracy in the country. Xi Jinping has, however, changed this; even as he has turned to rule the country Mao-style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principal ingredients of Xinomics are a muscular state and technology. After he took control, Xi took steps to create a more business-friendly environment; giving them space to grow. For instance, his reform measures today mean that it only takes 9 days to set up a new company. Unlike in the past, where public officials ruled in case of civil disputes, courts are now given the responsibility to rule in all such matters (in non-political matters, to be precise). Since Xi assumed power, administrative lawsuits have doubled. The same can be observed in cases related to intellectual property rights and insolvency. Local officials, among whom the disobedience of court rulings was prevalent, were forced by the government to comply. Xi has, therefore, brought order to the markets. He has also made it easier for companies to raise funds through the use of equity shares. All these measures certainly enhance the ease of doing business in China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with this, he has tried to make state enterprises increase productivity. For instance, the success of these enterprises was redefined to be measured by their net profitability. On the other hand, party committees are beginning to play a crucial role in the functioning of private enterprises. Party committees are parallel bodies to the Board of Directors that consist of members from the China Communist Party (CCP). It is said that the investment decisions are being taken by these committees. What is important to note is that as long as companies abide by the party guidelines, they receive massive support from the state. But if they don’t, the state makes things painful for them. There is a strange dichotomy that exists at the heart of this plan. Xi Jinping wants public enterprises to comply and adhere to the market principles and private enterprises to adhere to the party principles. Essentially Xi wants to blur the distinction between private and public firms, which is why he is advocating for a mixed model of public and private enterprises; at least in industries that are identified as the key (eg: information technology, semiconductors) for the country’s success in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there is technology. One of the key imports into China includes electric machinery and equipment (semiconductors, vehicle parts, etc). To reduce this dependency on the world, Xi Jinping gave a clarion call for ‘Made in China 2025’. This was a new industrial policy that had a strong focus on industries that require technologies to be imported. Under this, a huge sum of money is being spent on research and development to indigenously develop key technologies. State enterprises are being used for this purpose. While this is one part of the technology, the other is soft technology. Chinese information technology firms are increasingly expanding their presence across the world. These firms restrict the information their users’ access, catering to the needs of the party, and sometimes share data with the party. WeChat is a case in point. Though it is mostly used by Chinese people, it is estimated that there are about 100-200 million international users of the app. The app is used to plant fake news and exercise censorship. It has also become a platform where Chinese spies &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/international/business/forget-tiktok-chinas-powerhouse-app-is-wechat-and-its-power-is-sweeping/articleshow/77943656.cms&quot;&gt;communicate&lt;/a&gt;. Apart from WeChat, there are companies like Huawei, Baidu, Xiaomi, whose bosses have close ties with the party and will certainly oblige to all the “requests” from the party. Chinese tech is today ubiquitous and serves as an instrument to promote and protect the interests of the party across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an opinion that is increasingly being voiced from many circles that the world (or at least major economies like the US, Japan, India) could hit China where it hurts the most – trade. They also point out that China has, quite successfully, used trade as leverage to get its way. Cutting meat imports from Australia after the country demanded a probe into China for the COVID-19 pandemic; threatening Canada after a key Huawei official was arrested are cases in point. However, this strategy might not prove effective against China because the country has been diversifying (the composition of GDP, by end-users). China is wise to expect retaliation from other major powers, owing to its cheap and dishonest actions. There has been a gradual &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/256591/share-of-chinas-exports-in-gross-domestic-product/#:~:text=China's%20share%20of%20exports%20in,17.23%20trillion%20yuan%20that%20year.&quot;&gt;reduction&lt;/a&gt; in the share of exports in its GDP. This has been the trend since 2010. As of 2017, the share of exports as a percent of GDP was only 20% (while that of investment was approximately 43%). Also, China could very well use its economic might and soft power to do exactly what the United States has been doing for a long time now – condition its aid on a mandatory adaptation of the ‘China Model’, where it forces the countries to adopt its state-capitalism model. It very well serves China if there is no opposition (both political and public) in the countries it tries to bring under its sphere of influence. This is evident from the fact that more than 50 countries agreed to join the Asian Infrastructure Investment Bank, in which China holds a 30% stake. This is only reinforced by research that indicates, “a majority in the developing world and in many middle-sized, non-Western powers prefer the authoritarian model”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing is clear: the assumption of the US foreign policy, under Obama and Bush presidencies, that the integration of China into the international system would change its domestic politics towards democracy and liberalism was wrong. However robust China may be, one must not forget that democracies are always better than authoritarian regimes. Democracies hold their leaders accountable to their people. There has been emerging, from leading think-tanks around the world, the idea of the alliance of Democracy-10 (G7 countries plus India, South Korea, and Australia) to counter China. Though there have been no official talks, US President Donald Trump’s invitation to Indian Prime Minister Modi to join G7 (it still requires the consensus of all the members of G7) is a step in a positive direction. One country may not be able to take on China. But an alliance of a group of powerful democracies certainly can.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">After the Second World War, the world was divided into countries that could largely be categorised as liberal democracies or authoritarian communist nations. But interestingly, contemporary China doesn’t fit in either of these categories. It is an authoritarian market economy. Even as it adopted free-market policies and allowed private companies to grow, there were still a large number of state-owned enterprises. The Chinese Communist Party has invested a huge amount of money in these enterprises, which led to the debt-to-GDP ratio of the country to soar high (most of it, though, was domestic debt). Corruption was also rampant across various public institutions and among public servants. All this led to the above-said conclusions about the China model being weak, and it would crack down and pave the way for a democracy in the country. Xi Jinping has, however, changed this; even as he has turned to rule the country Mao-style.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Call for Concord to Capitalise</title>
      <link href="/Concord-to-Capitalise" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Call for Concord to Capitalise" />
      <published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Concord-to-Capitalise</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Concord-to-Capitalise">&lt;p&gt;Peace is a term of our lexicon that has been a part of the discourse vis-a-vis our mind, between communities, within nations, and across boundaries. It is defined as a concept of societal camaraderie in the absence of hostility and violence. We’re well acquainted with the ironic word ‘peace-keeping forces’ which entail and propagate the use of force and coercion to maintain the virtue of peace, which should come naturally to us otherwise. Correlation between peace and other disciplines like political science, psychology, geography, cognitive science, anthropology and sociology is prevalent. However, little do we know that there is a strong nexus between peace and economics. They are central to each other and act as catalysts in each other’s process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start from the beginning. The austerity of the post-Second World War world isn’t unknown to us. The cost of human lives and their intangible grief is a deep loss that can neither be redressed nor measured using a statistical tool. Talking in monetary terms, the governments of both the axis and allied forces lost about $1 trillion in a war. Here comes the importance of peace and peace enabling structures from a financial point of view as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There exists a discipline that acts as a bridge between development and harmony. ‘Peace Economics’ is a specialised division of economics. It focuses on the creation of the landscape’s political, economic, and cultural institutions and aims at preventing, alleviating, and reconciling the violent conflict between and within societies using relevant policies. Violent conflict can both be latent or active. Peace Economics talks about the benefits of rebuilding and restoring societies based on our presumed knowledge of the cost of violence. Peace Economics has a sweeping view of attaining stable and irrevocable peace. The use of economics here is to comprehend the causes and the repercussions of hostility thereafter in the international system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another definition of the subject has been furnished by Jan Tinbergen, a Nobel prize winner in Economics. As per his scrutiny economic science is made use of to preclude war. It is used as an instrument to settle the disputes among nations and design a world order where warfare is punished. It encircles the concept of negative peace which is a word coined by Johan Galtung that equals the absence of aggression and not the presence of peace. To throw a little more light on this through a simple question, does the absence of poverty in a nation necessarily indicate the presence of opulence? A major exclusion from these definitions is the reference to international relations and no mention of civil war or violence at the individual level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a recognition that Peace Economics forms a part of both positive and normative economics. For those who are alien to these rather heavy-sounding terms, the former simply studies economic phenomena with the ‘what is’ backdrop, that is with facts and figures of the current situation. Whereas the latter as the name suggests covers the ‘what ought to be’ perspective by furnishing corrective recommendations and solutions. Contemporary economists prefer positive economics to evaluate the policies as they are and give relevant suggestions thereafter. On the other hand, normative economics sets the ‘norm’ for peace and then looks for systems that help realise this norm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sustainable economic growth can’t be achieved without peace and peace is at risk without sustainable economic growth. The above quip safely interlaces the two subjects. When governments, for instance, make sure to eradicate youth radicalisation by investing in labour-intensive public projects, it leads to full and efficient utilisation of potential, thereby assuring their operation as resources on the Production Possibility Curve (PPC) and not inside it. They become an asset for their countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quoting an example of trade here. A free trade zone is created and a treaty signed not just with the goal of bettering bilateral or multilateral relations but also facilitating the promotion of peace. The trail of this link can be traced from the 19th century, a classic case of the English Tory rebels. A modern-day illustration of the same is the South Asian Free Trade Area which ensures non-belligerent relations in the region and promises peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dating back to 1914, during the First World War there was a peace conference held in Paris. A book titled &lt;em&gt;The Economic Consequences of the Peace&lt;/em&gt; by John Maynard Keynes came into being and stated how the terms of the allies regarding truce were financially impossible to achieve for Germany and how those acted as a stimulant in encouraging them to stand steadfast, again. Keynes’ theory also very explicitly mentioned the high rise in employment being conducive to peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crunching some numbers and putting facts into the picture, the global economy is liable to pay more than $14 trillion a year owing to conflict according to the World Economic Forum. The breakdown includes spending on the military, internal security, conflict losses, and crime. India, to be specific, forfeited 9% of its GDP due to friction in 2018. It was on the 136th rank in the Global Peace Index out of 163 nations. Down at the bottom was the war-torn Syria which had to lose a massive 68% of its GDP. Iceland is at the top of this list. Another intriguing certitude is that the countries which are placed higher on the Global Peace Index have observed trends of per capita GDP growing thrice as fast as those which are not as peaceful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important for international organisations like the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund (IMF) to bolster the presence of an infrastructure that ameliorates the livelihoods of those indulged in any sort of clash. Governments need to take affirmative actions with peacebuilding attempts at the core, philanthropists and businesses should contribute and comply with the directives. An instance of the same from the new world order is of Colombia. Over 100 companies in the country marched forward towards peace by coupling their own advertising with the national peace campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A crucial reform would be to ensure domestic violence between intimate partners, workplace violence and even self-harm forms the nucleus of present-day research for peace studies. This will go a long way in delivering positive solutions and will make resorting to violence inconceivable. The Institute for Economics and Peace, a think tank is developing a yardstick to analyse peace and quantify its economic value. This will act as a concrete step in laying a firm association between peace and prosperity. Let’s hope for a world in which this theme is self-explanatory and doesn’t have to be this persuasive. Let’s live for the day when world peace isn’t a pipe dream anymore.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushi Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Peace is a term of our lexicon that has been a part of the discourse vis-a-vis our mind, between communities, within nations, and across boundaries. It is defined as a concept of societal camaraderie in the absence of hostility and violence. We’re well acquainted with the ironic word ‘peace-keeping forces’ which entail and propagate the use of force and coercion to maintain the virtue of peace, which should come naturally to us otherwise. Correlation between peace and other disciplines like political science, psychology, geography, cognitive science, anthropology and sociology is prevalent. However, little do we know that there is a strong nexus between peace and economics. They are central to each other and act as catalysts in each other’s process.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What COVID-19 Means for the US Education System?</title>
      <link href="/COVID-19-US-Education-System" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What COVID-19 Means for the US Education System?" />
      <published>2020-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/COVID-19-US-Education-System</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/COVID-19-US-Education-System">&lt;p&gt;Every generation of humanity has experienced their share of transitional periods, be it as consequential as the Second World War, or as small as being temporarily bedridden due to injury. The same concept can be used to study history in a different light - as a compilation of events that initiated the strongest ripples of transition in the various aspects of human life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As any mature and experienced enough man would tell you, change is a constant in the universe. It’s this change that led to human evolution and towards the development of society and the invention of all the things that make life worth living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as everything has exceptions, one of the few constants in life is the importance of education. It is something that has been so deeply ingrained in our culture that we cannot let go of it irrespective of the substitutes available to us. Today we see a scenario which is a clash between this constant and the period of fundamental transition fostered by COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States is a global education hub, with some of the most coveted educational institutes across the field of STEM, business, law and the arts. Students from all over the world dedicate a significant portion of their lives to the cause of securing admission into an elite US university. The country also greatly benefits from the international student community, as their annual contribution to the US GDP is at a massive $41 billion. Additionally, the cultural influence and innovation that the international community brings has, over the years, furthered the stronghold of many American companies in their respective markets. Nevertheless, the Trump administration has been rooting against international students who migrate to the USA in search of education and livelihood. That paired with a disease outbreak that has no fool-proof methods of containment has damaged educational prospects for a lot of international students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The American Council of Education predicts that a fall of as much as 25% in foreign student applications is anticipated for the upcoming academic year. This, though backed by the administration in charge, sets off a loud alarm as the impact would be drastic on the American corporate sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, America may be the pioneer in education, but it’s not the only player in the game. A lot of other countries like the UK, Canada and Australia offer equally enticing educational opportunities and have better migration and settlement policies. This may turn out to be the deciding factor for international students for whom an investment in a country other than the USA brings more to the table, especially in a highly uncertain situation like that of the present. The growing culture of administrative hostility towards immigrants would eventually lead to stagnation in diversity and curb the advantages that it offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, America is severely undermining the importance of international talent in keeping its corporate sector afloat. The influx of international funds in the form of fees, taxes, healthcare, bank deposits, etc contributes significantly to the economy. Due to the strictness of pre-existing work visa and green card policies, the proportion of foreign students that enrol in US programmes to those who actually find employment in the US to those who receive special work visas like H1B or obtain green cards moves in a decreasing order. Moreover, 1 out of 4 US startups, which are worth millions of dollars, are founded by international students. Therefore, calculation of the net impact of international students on the economy, irrespective of the time period, would yield a positive quotient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the lack of foreign influence would push the US into a state of cyclical perpetuity. The presence of international student communities supports more than just the economy, as it has been pivotal in reforming American society, and overcoming racial and cultural prejudice. This has helped American companies expand and explore international opportunities, and develop a workforce that is comfortable working outside their countries. It has popularised US education across the globe, which, over the years, has attracted countless employers and investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, many American institutions have moulded personalities who would go on to become leaders and forerunners in their respective fields. It has helped the American education system develop a global imprint, as a lot of individuals, that are its product, represent it in any sphere they venture into. Reduction in international students, after a certain point, would reduce this influence that the US enjoys in shaping leaders of various sectors, disciplines, and even nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summing it all up, the US, like any other nation, needs to evolve in various respects as and when required to maintain its reputation as a global leader. The driving force behind such evolution is the product of interactions between the international and local communities. A long term trend of decline in international students would cause the nation to involuntarily impose a glass ceiling on its growth potential. Therefore, it is indispensable for American colleges and universities to acknowledge the “new normal” and devise methods to attract international student applications. The first step that can be taken in this regard would be dismissing the suspension of student and special work visas, and ensuring that the impact of the pandemic-induced economic slowdown is minimal on college fees, educational loans and international student aid.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aryaman Dhiman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Every generation of humanity has experienced their share of transitional periods, be it as consequential as the Second World War, or as small as being temporarily bedridden due to injury. The same concept can be used to study history in a different light - as a compilation of events that initiated the strongest ripples of transition in the various aspects of human life.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Big Data and Big Entertainment</title>
      <link href="/Big-Data-and-Big-Entertainment" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Big Data and Big Entertainment" />
      <published>2020-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Big-Data-and-Big-Entertainment</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Big-Data-and-Big-Entertainment">&lt;p&gt;Go to a supermarket to buy chocolates and you’ll find yourself eyeing some fancy stationery pens, which you most definitely don’t need. You’ll find yourself at the billing counter with the chocolates you needed, but also a couple of pens that were visually appealing to you. You end up buying them and on your way back home, you think of how we all do small, silly things to find happiness in these little things. And while you walk home with a smile on your face, the shopkeeper is most likely smirking at the fact that he/she was able to control your purchase by strategically placing the stationery shelf at the best spot of the store, right at the same eye level as yours. He/She is now proud of themselves for having read the &lt;em&gt;Retailer Magazine&lt;/em&gt; that told them how consumer behaviour in a supermarket is driven by eye-candies and strategically-placed products which makes consumers think that they’re choosing to buy a product out of their own will. In turn, the &lt;em&gt;Retailer Magazine&lt;/em&gt; is happy to have influenced consumerism through the use of consumer databases that come under ‘Big Data’. Therefore, in short, your choice of buying a couple of pens was actually driven by tools of capitalism, and not your short-lived happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The air of this generation is electric with the talk of big data. Consider that the world is a kingdom, then big data is the know-it-all wish-granting ruler of this kingdom, and the subjects of this kingdom are not humans, but in fact just information databases. In layman’s language, big data is a huge volume of data that is stored, controlled and analysed to draw insights on human behaviour. Not just supermarkets, like in our example, but also multinational corporations are nothing without big data. Businesses, retailers and corporations use databases to understand consumer preferences and control them via tactics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the usage and impacts of big data better, we’re going to take an unconventional path and look into it through the lens of pop-culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The documentary &lt;em&gt;Amazon Empire: The Rise and Reign of Jeff Bezos&lt;/em&gt; highlights some extremely important takeaways on the functioning of multinational corporations and how the organisation was instrumental in paving a new course for e-commerce. The documentary shows that consumer data is the most important base for the foundation of Amazon. Using this data, Amazon devised pricing strategies and took advantage of it, being the only e-commerce company back when it started, and took a head start to get a hold of the “market segment share”, even if it meant foregoing profits in the short run. Jeff Bezos was in it for monopolisation in the long run. A widely unknown truth is that ‘Alexa’, Amazon’s virtual assistant, that is sitting idle in a lot of our homes is, in fact, the most cunning strategy of data collection, as it records our conversations and is used to improve the Alexa algorithm. The documentary also reveals insider information that the products sold on Amazon don’t necessarily meet the safety standards, but they are marketed in a way that the consumer feels like they need the product, and not just want it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an omnipresent fear of big data in our minds because we’re constantly afraid of how it is going to control our lives and it may be an inherent threat to our beings if, one day, our lives are taken over by these big corporates or the government. The very same fear of big data has been highlighted well enough in George Orwell’s 1984 which paints a dystopian world wherein a totalitarian regime exists, with an undisclosed head of state called ‘Big Brother’. This head is an ever-watching eye on the public and uses surveillance to tightly control the public and the ‘thought police’ persecutes their independent thinking and individuality. This furthermore increases people’s distrust on the controller of their data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawing parallels from the dystopian satire, &lt;em&gt;Ninety Eighty-Four&lt;/em&gt; brings me to Netflix’s &lt;em&gt;House of Cards&lt;/em&gt;, a series that highlights political campaigning in the US elections. To taint young Presidential candidate Will Conway’s election rallying, Frank Underwood deploys illegal mechanisms of obtaining voter data to be able to skew votes in his favour. While there is no inherent problem with the collection of voter data, doing so without the knowledge or permission of the voters is simply immoral and falsifies the entire meaning of election campaigning, which is to ensure interaction between the Presidential candidates and the public. This is also known as “hacking” the electorate, which means using data to appeal to specific voter groups and predicting how they will vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings me to a very important inclusion in this article, Netflix’s &lt;em&gt;The Great Hack&lt;/em&gt;. This documentary portrays the stark reality of how Facebook and Twitter use data analysis tools to exploit information on its users through tweets, posts, friends, likes and dislikes. They slyly convince us into taking certain quizzes like “What Disney character are you?” which takes up our information through permissions we usually ignore to read. All this data was passed on to a company called Cambridge Analytica, which was hired by one of the political parties in the 2016 US elections. Cambridge, in turn, used all the collected data to create fear and apathy to achieve favourable results for this political party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam McKay’s star-studded &lt;em&gt;The Big Short&lt;/em&gt; would be a great example to digress from the impact of data in politics to the impact of data in economics. The movie revolves around how data, coupled with unconventional tools to explain financial instruments like ‘Jenga’, were used to predict that the housing market is going to lead to the downfall of the US economy, which in fact proved to be true as it led to the 2007-08 Global Economic Recession. Owing to the prediction, the protagonist makes a strategic long-term investment that yields his company a $2.69 billion profit, while the entire world saw a pitfall. Moving onto a more micro example, Bennett Miller’s &lt;em&gt;Moneyball&lt;/em&gt; shows the general manager of a baseball team having to sieve out players due to underperformance and a budget crunch, he does this, amidst criticism, using tools of sabermetrics and on-base percentage depending on each player’s information. This led to a slow but eventual victory for the team he had constructed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that we’re surrounded by big data seems a little scary and we owe it to how big data has been fed to us via pop-culture. A movie like &lt;em&gt;Minority Report&lt;/em&gt; that uses big data analysis to predict crime before it occurs makes one wrong prediction which starts to disrupt the system, inevitably hurting the minority. This, in fact, strengthens the distrust in the system. The series &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;, through its different episodes highlighting different themes, showcases that we are governed by the black mirror that is the screen in our lives, which ranges from TV shows to social media and smartphones. The series focuses on how this may be just the tip of an iceberg of the myriad technologies that may unravel over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what is it that makes us afraid of big data or technology? The answer is that we’re not inherently afraid of data or technology, but the people who control it. &lt;em&gt;“More data equals more inference”&lt;/em&gt; seems fine until the controller of this data infers more than they’re supposed to. But the ultimate truth lies in the fact that we cannot escape big data. What we can do is empower ourselves with the tool of education to learn about the mechanisms of regulation and accountability that exist, and learn to adopt a system of checks and balances to avoid any breach of privacy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Go to a supermarket to buy chocolates and you’ll find yourself eyeing some fancy stationery pens, which you most definitely don’t need. You’ll find yourself at the billing counter with the chocolates you needed, but also a couple of pens that were visually appealing to you. You end up buying them and on your way back home, you think of how we all do small, silly things to find happiness in these little things. And while you walk home with a smile on your face, the shopkeeper is most likely smirking at the fact that he/she was able to control your purchase by strategically placing the stationery shelf at the best spot of the store, right at the same eye level as yours. He/She is now proud of themselves for having read the Retailer Magazine that told them how consumer behaviour in a supermarket is driven by eye-candies and strategically-placed products which makes consumers think that they’re choosing to buy a product out of their own will. In turn, the Retailer Magazine is happy to have influenced consumerism through the use of consumer databases that come under ‘Big Data’. Therefore, in short, your choice of buying a couple of pens was actually driven by tools of capitalism, and not your short-lived happiness.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Norway: The Perfect Economy?</title>
      <link href="/The-Perfect-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Norway: The Perfect Economy?" />
      <published>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Perfect-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Perfect-Economy">&lt;p&gt;Norway is a wonderful country that has time and time again been used as the poster child for a socialist-capitalist mixed economy done right. Norway has several times been compared to that child in our school who is absolutely tremendous at each and everything. The country boasts a GDP per capita of $81,995, one of the highest in the world, only falling behind Switzerland and a select group of micronations. The country has a robust trade surplus, exports of $106 billion, compared to imports of $84.8 billion, one of the highest national life expectancies at 81.8 years, an extremely skilled workforce with one of the highest proportion of university graduates at 42% of any country in the world, an extremely low unemployment rate of 0.41%, and international recognition as a place where it is very easy to do business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is more remarkable is that Norway has achieved this while also being one of the most economically equal countries in the world. After taxes, a single individual from the bottom 20% of the income earners in Norway still earns on average a quarter of what their top 20% income earners would. Now, this still sounds pretty unfair but compared to the Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) average which has top one-fifth earners making an income ten times that of their bottom one-fifth counterparts, this disparity is remarkable. The good news keeps on coming considering working conditions. Norway has workers protections which are commendable, meaning that social issues like working extremely long hours and people needing second jobs to support themselves are very rare. In fact, the OECD better life index notes that only 3% of employees work long hours when compared to the OECD average of 11% or the American average of 33%. All of this contributes to the citizens of Norway being some of the happiest in the entire world despite their country being extremely cold. Norway, by all standards, should be the model that most citizens would want to replicate in their own countries. So why haven’t other countries adopted similar economic policies to those in Norway? Is this country just a lucky outlier or could this success be replicated in other economies around the world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is that Norway wasn’t always this prosperous. In the 1960’s, it was an economy mainly based on fishing with a GDP similar in size to underdeveloped countries like Bangladesh or Nigeria. Now, in all fairness, Norway’s population was and still is far smaller than these other countries and the average Norwegian back then had a quality of life similar to a person in Spain or Greece. But Norway in the 1960’s was still far out from the economic powerhouse it is today. This all started to change in May of 1963 when the Norwegian government asserted sovereign rights over natural resources in a huge area of the North Sea. This was basically the government saying that this part of the ocean is ours now. If we happen to find any oil here that is ours too. Six years later, in 1969, a ship called the &lt;em&gt;Ocean Viking&lt;/em&gt; struck oil in the North Sea, and from that oil production in the region exploded. This meant that in the mid-1970’s Norway produced more oil per capita than any other country in the world and even today it is only beaten out by Kuwait, UAE, and Saudi Arabia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I know what you are thinking, but this is not a story about another country that just got rich off oil and now everybody in the country is living like a child handed with a rack of money. It is actually the opposite. Rather than getting drunk off the oil wealth that they had discovered; the Norwegian government was very prudent with the revenue from these finite resources. The oil boom caused Norway’s GDP to grow over five times in the 1970’s growing from $12 billion to $65 billion in this period. But this newfound wealth was not being generated by private companies but rather a publicly run and owned company called &lt;em&gt;Statoil&lt;/em&gt;. All this meant that profits from oil and natural gas sales were not going to the pockets of private shareholders but rather directly to the government. This made the Norwegian government immensely rich meaning that if they wanted, they could have easily gone on a public spending spree, building fancy cities and public infrastructure while also reducing taxes just like many of the countries have done in a similar position. This kind of an approach would have been very popular among citizens because in short term it meant lower taxes and a better quality of life but they didn’t, and even today income and business taxes in Norway are among some of the highest in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for Norway, the government had the foresight to realise that oil wealth was not forever and that the citizens of Norway would not be satisfied if they had to go back to fishing in a generations time so the government invested the money into a piggy bank, a very large piggy bank called a ‘sovereign wealth fund’, in fact, this is the largest sovereign wealth fund in the world at $1.002 trillion beating out China’s state investment corporation. This is a fund that belongs to the people of Norway. The rationale is that this oil and these natural resources were originally the property of the Norwegian people and so it is they who should receive from the sale of these resources. This means that every man, woman, and child, who is a citizen of Norway essentially has around $200,000 invested into what is a giant hedge fund. This money is unfortunately not accessible by these citizens to spend on gold plated Ferraris or yachts. The money itself is actually not even accessible to the Norwegian government. In fact, only the profit generated from these investments is used to fund things like education, which explains the very skilled workforce, a very strong welfare system, public infrastructure, and reinvestment into the fund itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, the fund made an incredible $131 billion from investments. This fund is a very diverse portfolio of stocks, bonds, cash, and commodities but what it does invest in is not nearly as interesting as what it does not invest in. The Norwegian government set up an ethical council that oversees investing decisions of all of the fund and it has excluded investing in things like weapons manufacturers, tobacco and alcohol companies, and companies that have caused severe environmental damage or companies that have breached workers rights and labour laws. Additionally, in an effort to diversify where they get their money from, the fund is also forbidden to invest in fossil energy companies. This means that all the investments in this fund are actually in foreign countries’ securities and commodities. Now, despite the massive political power this gives Norway to influence foreign companies, it also means that the fund’s performance is absolutely independent of the situation prevailing in the Norwegian economy. The fund was a fantastic piece of thoughtfulness by the Norwegian government and practically means that Norway is now the national equivalent of the guy that wins the lottery, keeps his day job, and invests the lottery money in a stock portfolio. It certainly is not as cool and it does not get as much attention as blowing all of the money on extravagant displays of wealth, but it does mean that they will be safe and secure for generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To finish it up, it is only fair to look at some of the economic issues that are present in Norway. First and foremost is that it still has an incredibly high cost of living compared to wages. Given the very high taxes, an average Norwegian worker is bringing home about $3,200 a month which is far higher than the American average of $2,730 per month. However, it does not make a considerable difference because Norway is an expensive place. A mid-range restaurant meal in America tends to run about $50, in Norway, it is about $92. A monthly utility bill in the US is expected to be around $130 whereas that same bill in Norway is $176. But the citizens of Norway almost universally agree that they are happy to put up with these high taxes and this incredibly high cost of living because in return they do not have to worry about serious economic hardships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody in Norway is going to go bankrupt because of a medical situation, nobody has to worry about drowning in crippling debt to get an education and they do not have to fear being homeless if they lose their jobs. So, the million-dollar question arises - is Norway really the perfect economy? Well no, not really. Norway is a great example of a planned social-democratic economic system. They have done everything right with the opportunities that have come their way but they were still extremely lucky, and expecting that every country can get to where Norway is today only by copying and pasting their government’s financial policies is absurd but that said I still think Norway is the economy closest to achieve perfection if they haven’t already.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Norway is a wonderful country that has time and time again been used as the poster child for a socialist-capitalist mixed economy done right. Norway has several times been compared to that child in our school who is absolutely tremendous at each and everything. The country boasts a GDP per capita of $81,995, one of the highest in the world, only falling behind Switzerland and a select group of micronations. The country has a robust trade surplus, exports of $106 billion, compared to imports of $84.8 billion, one of the highest national life expectancies at 81.8 years, an extremely skilled workforce with one of the highest proportion of university graduates at 42% of any country in the world, an extremely low unemployment rate of 0.41%, and international recognition as a place where it is very easy to do business.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Emmanuel Farhi’s Safety Trap</title>
      <link href="/Emmanuel-Farhi-Safety-Trap" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Emmanuel Farhi’s Safety Trap" />
      <published>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Emmanuel-Farhi-Safety-Trap</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Emmanuel-Farhi-Safety-Trap">&lt;p&gt;Emmanuel Farhi, considered by many to be the brightest economist of his generation, passed away in July 2020, aged only 41. Farhi, a PhD from Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) and amongst the youngest to receive tenure as Professor at Harvard University, was known to challenge traditional economic concepts that people would often take as given. Take, for example, one of his most cited works,  &lt;em&gt;The Safe Asset Shortage Conundrum&lt;/em&gt;, written on safe assets and the lack thereof, in 2008 with Ricardo Caballero of MIT and Pierre-Oliver Gourinchas of UC Berkeley. This paper augmented Keynes’ classical theory of the ‘Liquidity Trap’ and developed it to suit the modern connotation of capital markets, and is more relevant now than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world seemed to have reasonably recovered from the short run curable shocks of the Great Financial Crisis of 2008 by 2018-19, when many first-world nations, including the world’s de-facto economic capital, the US, were considered to have achieved ‘full employment’. There was, however, something anomalistic about this status, when despite high productivity, inflation seemed suppressed. This &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Inflation-Dead-Or-Dormant&quot;&gt;dormant status of inflation&lt;/a&gt;, often explained by the unorthodox policy measures taken for recovery, has evidently trickled into the prolonged COVID-19 induced recession. Monetary policy as a tool might appear crippled at this point, with nominal rates reaching their zero levels bound in most first-world economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conventional jargon would explain the situation as follows: what has basically happened in this liquidity trap is the flattening of our LM curve (a curve showing the relationship between real output and interest rates in the money market), a consequence of a high ‘h’ (which is the proportion of change in money demand, when the interest rates change by a percent). In classical (Keynesian) economic sense though, the policy decision is to change the money supply first, and the interest rate change is a consequence of that. Once a decision to increase the money supply, in hopes to revive demand, is implemented, it is accompanied by an equal increase in money demand in order for the market to equilibrate. Money demand, without an increase in income levels, can only rise if the interest rate moves down. But in case of a high ‘h’, a negligible downward movement of rates should be able to compensate for the money demand increase. Coming back to the real world, where money demand is adjusted by moving the nominal interest rates, such a scenario would render the monetary policy useless, once the zero levels bound of interest rates is reached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conventional solution to this dilemma, as given by Keynes in &lt;em&gt;The General Theory of Employment, Interest and Money&lt;/em&gt; was to make gracious use of fiscal policy in a targeted manner. But as concerns of deficit consolidation popped up, economists at the Fed came up with other heterodox mutations of conventional monetary policy to tackle the issue. It wasn’t until Farhi’s paper on ‘Safety Traps’ was published that the policymakers found a more logical chain of response to the problem. A certain category of assets, often considered immune in periods of depressed market spirits, is called ‘Safe Assets’. During recessions, their markets evidently boom leading to price hikes and consequent fall in the yields. But the yields have a lower bound of zero percent, beyond which they cannot fall, and therefore prices cannot rise. This situation of people acting in private interest, leading to a net consequence of a market failure is a classic example of ‘Fallacy of Composition’. This happens since the asset market does not equilibrate in response to the high demand. And due to nominal rigidities, this equilibrium manifests in the form of output reduction. The output during recessionary periods is entirely demand determined, and the 0-yield on the safe assets is not low enough to encourage agents to move towards consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically the solutions offered to do away with this complication include negative interest rates, forward guidance, quantitative easing, etc. However, in his paper, Farhi accounted for the fact that the market rates do not uniformly equilibrate across all assets, and a certain risk premium remains attached to equity assets, while the safe ones get to zero. This tends to dilute the policy impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we want as our end result, is that despite the high ‘Safe Asset’ demand, we generate enough supply to ensure the yields do not get to zero and there is some scope to utilise the monetary policy. This sudden paucity of safe assets is often attributed to a savings glut, accumulation of reserves by the emerging markets, and to the fact that many assets which shaped the housing market bubble were once considered safe, but were not so at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One popular policy response which was an attempt to untie the hands of monetary policy, but failed to an extent was ‘Quantitative Easing’, which allowed the Fed to pump up the market with fresh money supply while purchasing bonds in return. This measure would not revive demand to its potential if safe assets are the ones being purchased in its return. This is because a proportion of the newly printed money will look for more safe assets, which have now shrunk in supply! Instead, soaking up the risky assets in return for the newly printed money, while simultaneously issuing newer safety assets is the proper way to go about quantitative easing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forward guidance, by ensuring to keep the future rates low was also said to work, because, if the Government’s word on the policy is reliable, lower future yields will imply higher future asset prices, creating current demand for the assets. When the self-fulfilling prophecy works out, the wealth effect naturally generates demand. However, Farhi’s paper found out the misconceptions associated with the effectiveness of this policy. If assets are seen in terms of the two designated classes, then it is likely that the risky assets, with a positive risk premium, will dissipate the impact of anticipated lower rates, and the effect will not trickle to revive the output market. However, one measure that is likely to render the monetary policy free is creating a very high inflation target, which would then allow the economy to run on an output-inducing negative real rate while being on the 0-nominal rate. But then again, this has its long-run ramifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The existence of a high-risk premium is concrete evidence for the existence of a ‘safety trap’, rather than a liquidity trap. It is indicative of the fact that people are rushing towards safe assets, while equity returns remain stable and decoupled from the economic situation, as is the current case. A fiscal policy response by issuing sovereign bonds to address the scarcity of safe assets is now being encouraged with the popularisation of the ‘Modern Monetary Theory’, though Farhi considered the US’ role as the world’s banker to be unsustainable due to higher issuance of sovereign bonds leading many to question their debt levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this paper played an instrumental role in forwarding the scope of the monetary policies of the first world countries, Emmanuel Farhi’s other papers are just as revolutionary, if not as cited. In another one of his works, &lt;em&gt;Dealing with the Trilemma: Optimal Capital Controls with Fixed Exchange Rates&lt;/em&gt; he challenged the ‘Impossible Trinity’ by providing partial capital controls as a solution for emerging markets battling the exchange rate volatility. His research is a perfect amalgamation of academia and policy solutions, and he truly believed that research only made sense when it could be put in real service towards progress. Safe to say that the world of academics and research was in for a shock on his passing on the 23rd of July, 2020. Gita Gopinath, a fellow colleague at Harvard, poignantly wrote, &lt;em&gt;“Imagine the loss to economics if Samuelson had died at the age of 41, that is what we have lost with Emmanuel’s passing”&lt;/em&gt;. His best was truly yet to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Emmanuel Farhi, considered by many to be the brightest economist of his generation, passed away in July 2020, aged only 41. Farhi, a PhD from Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) and amongst the youngest to receive tenure as Professor at Harvard University, was known to challenge traditional economic concepts that people would often take as given. Take, for example, one of his most cited works, The Safe Asset Shortage Conundrum, written on safe assets and the lack thereof, in 2008 with Ricardo Caballero of MIT and Pierre-Oliver Gourinchas of UC Berkeley. This paper augmented Keynes’ classical theory of the ‘Liquidity Trap’ and developed it to suit the modern connotation of capital markets, and is more relevant now than ever.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
