<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/economics/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-09-19T10:20:51+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/economics/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Canada’s Climate Combat</title>
      <link href="/Canada-Climate-Combat" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Canada’s Climate Combat" />
      <published>2019-08-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Canada-Climate-Combat</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Canada-Climate-Combat">&lt;p&gt;Global warming and climate change: the two terms widely occupying public discourse in recent times. Something that the millennials would call upon as the mistakes of the past, that scares all the youth reminding them of sci-fi movies which show the looming dark days of the future. &lt;em&gt;Inevitable&lt;/em&gt; as some of us would put it across as. Thus, it is no surprise that movements and protests to combat climate change are picking up in many parts of the globe, especially in first world countries, where the youth is more empowered with knowledge of the future. The world has gone berserk over the issue, and reactions all across the globe seems to be mixed. While the American Government is making news by dismissing climate change and global warming as a hoax and ditching climate pacts, her northern neighbour, Canada is doing the exact opposite. The Prime Minister of Canada announced that the country will create protected marine areas in the Arctic region of the country. This decision comes across as a delight to most around the globe, and here’s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Arctic is one of the worst affected regions in the world. Deterioration of climate has led to a rise in the water level, becoming ominous to indigenous animals. Over the past three decades, the Arctic Ocean has lost an area of sea ice equivalent to Germany, France and Spain combined (2,00,000 sq km approx.). Major power players like the USA, Russia, Canada and China have long been competing to get a hold of the Arctic to extract minerals and petroleum resources promised by the region. In the wake of all these happenings, Canada’s announcement to create Protected Marine Areas (PMA) comes as new found hope. Canada has announced two PMAs namely Tuvaijuittuq (which means ‘ice never melts’) Marine Protected Area and Tallurutiup Imanga, covering an area of 427,000 square kilometres. The federal government and Qikiqtani Inuit Association (QIA) have signed Inuit Impact Benefit Agreement (IIBA) to that effect. QIA is a non-profit society that is designated to safeguard the interests of the minority Inuit community (Eskimos) and has played a key role in pulling off the agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IIBA proposes a two-fold strategy. Firstly, it forbids any anthropogenic activity and the areas are entirely closed from deep-sea mining, oil and gas extraction, dumping, and fishing. Second, it targets at providing sustainable employment to the Inuit community. For this, the government is set to invest $143 million over the next 7 years. It includes the promotion of local arts and crafts, textiles, indigenous occupations and government jobs in research and data collection as well as investments in ship harbors and boating docks. Thus, one can see that the major beneficiary of this agreement is the Inuit community of northwestern Canada. Akeeagok, QIA president, said that by investing in Inuit, the government is paying the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main principles that Economics teaches us is that there is always a tradeoff, and so is there one between economic development and environmental sustainability. Development mostly succeeds at the expense of the environment and has a ravaging effect on it. Canada’s project, however, is an exception. The project protects 14% of the country’s total marine and coastal area, exceeding the original target of protecting 10% of the area by 2020. It also protects indigenous species like narwhal, polar bear, walrus, seal, beluga and the under-ice algae that form a very important base for the entire Arctic food web. Thus, the two notified PMAs will be pivotal biodiversity conservation regions. Further, the Canadian government is actively investing in research related projects so as to support the process to conserve PMAs. It has been announced that an investment of approximately 6 million will go into a scientific research on the impacts of potential oil spills, taken up under the country’s Coastal Environmental Baseline Program, which aims at identifying the long term changes in Canada’s coastal environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this policy is being criticised as a politically motivated move. One cannot dismiss these claims because they seem to be partially true. The Inuit community, on whose betterment the agreement primarily focuses, is afterall a minority group in the country who were the victims of discrimination for ages. Justin Trudeau, the incumbent PM of Canada is seeking re-election in October 2019. Thus, critics term the government’s decision as one to woo votes and win the confidence of the people. Apart from this, the agreement says that “no new human activities will be allowed to occur in the area for up to five years, with a few exceptions.” The question is if a 5-year ban on human activities would prove effective at all and whether the exceptions in the notified areas will be able to serve their true purpose. As it was noted earlier, the activities of the previous decades had deteriorated the condition of the area. While it is uncertain if the 5-year ban will be extended, this short span is not sufficient for a sustainable revival of the Arctic. Thus lies a risk of economic growth coming to a halt and simultaneously no significant development towards environmental restoration taking place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, one thing to be noted here is that prior to the announcement of PMAs, the Canadian government had announced that it would actively explore for oil and natural gas in the Arctic. It is estimated that the proposed area of PMAs contains 56 trillion cubic feet of natural gas and 8 billion barrels of oil. However, the government has banned all activities pertaining to the extraction of these resources. This shows the government’s integrity and sends the message that Canada is serious and determined to battle against climate change. At the end, no matter the motive, what counts is the result. The initiative is one which not only empowers a certain section of the country but also helps the world delay an impending climate crisis and take up arms to promote sustainable development. Yes, agreeing to the fact that PMAs are not a panacea to climate change, it is something to begin with. It will slow down global warming and mitigate the effects thereof. To ensure success, they must be taken up together with other measures to tackle global warming and climate change. PMAs should be notified by all countries that are a part of the Arctic region. Such countries should draw inspiration from Canada and ban maximum anthropogenic activities in the region. A ban on industrial and human affairs in the region will, most definitely, help revive and restore the lost biodiversity and reduce global warming. Thus, hoping for a better future.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Global warming and climate change: the two terms widely occupying public discourse in recent times. Something that the millennials would call upon as the mistakes of the past, that scares all the youth reminding them of sci-fi movies which show the looming dark days of the future. Inevitable as some of us would put it across as. Thus, it is no surprise that movements and protests to combat climate change are picking up in many parts of the globe, especially in first world countries, where the youth is more empowered with knowledge of the future. The world has gone berserk over the issue, and reactions all across the globe seems to be mixed. While the American Government is making news by dismissing climate change and global warming as a hoax and ditching climate pacts, her northern neighbour, Canada is doing the exact opposite. The Prime Minister of Canada announced that the country will create protected marine areas in the Arctic region of the country. This decision comes across as a delight to most around the globe, and here’s why.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Indian Startup Ecosystem: A Global Perspective</title>
      <link href="/A-Global-Perspective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Indian Startup Ecosystem: A Global Perspective" />
      <published>2019-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Global-Perspective</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Global-Perspective">&lt;p&gt;A proud moment for India was to have been ranked as the 5th most startup-friendly economy in the world, in 2019. This was based on five parameters: human capital investment, research and development, entrepreneurial infrastructure, technical workforce and policy dynamics. Despite losing the first four positions to the USA, UK, Canada and Israel, India has come a long way due to various government schemes such as Startup India, Make In India, Digital India, the setting up of the Biotechnology Industry Research Assistance Council (BIRAC) and many more which foster a culture of entrepreneurship and innovation in the country. However, India has lagged behind other countries in two aspects majorly; innovation and taxation. The persistent dearth of successful innovation and the recent ‘Angel tax issue’ have discouraged investors from providing funds to Indian entrepreneurs for the creation of their own startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As per Global Innovation Index 2019, India stood at the 52nd position out of a total of 129 countries for capacity and success in innovation. For a country that is the fifth leading startup- friendly economy globally, to rank so poorly in innovation is nothing short of a disgrace. This lack of innovation is clearly depicted by India’s relatively low expenditure on research and development. Although India stands at the 7th position when it comes to absolute money spent on R&amp;amp;D (after adjusting PPP) with a mammoth expenditure of $48.1 billion. However, this generally isn’t enough, given the large geographical area and population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relative figures show a different reality altogether. India’s expenditure on R&amp;amp;D continues to be as low as 0.8% of the GDP, much lower than countries like South Korea at 4.3%, Israel at 4.2% and Japan at 3.4%. The lack of quality research is evidenced by the fact that many of India’s startups are nothing but an emulation of successful global ideas fine-tuned to serve local needs. Talk about the American Uber and Indians have an Ola. Think about Spotify and we have the Indian version &lt;em&gt;Gaana&lt;/em&gt;. For Amazon, we have Indian competitors, Flipkart and Snapdeal. For Airbnb, we have OYO Rooms. We have the Indian Zomato and Swiggy as replacements of the middle-eastern Talabat. All these foreign startups were established before we Indians copied their ideas and made it our own. One cannot deny that India has become a startup hub with a total of 8625 startups in 2018 across various fields like edtech, traveltech, fintech, logistics and healthtech, yet it is even harder to disagree with the reality that the number of these startups formed out of original new ideas of Indians is laughably low. This is perhaps due to loopholes in the Indian education system that fails to provide the requisite infrastructure, skills and highly-qualified, research-oriented teaching faculty in universities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next lies the issue of the ‘Angel tax’ which has been tormenting the Indian startup ecosystem lately. Angel tax is an ‘income tax’ payable on capital raised by ‘unlisted’ companies via issue of shares, where income refers to the share price in excess of the fair market value of the shares sold. The investors providing funds to these companies also have to pay a ‘gift tax’ on the excess amount. The Angel tax was introduced in India in 2012 with the aim to curb money laundering by various small companies by imposing a high tax rate of 30.9% on all unlisted companies in the country, along with a tax on the investors. It all started when owners of small-scale companies started laundering their tax-evaded income by selling their shares to investors at a price above the fair market value. In reality, the investors got the money to be invested in the companies from the owners themselves and charged commission for helping the owners carry out the money laundering process smoothly. The Angel tax successfully curbed such malpractices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this started creating problems for startups (which are often unlisted companies), when honest angel investors who provided seed funding to these startups had to start paying an exorbitant tax on the excess amount, they began putting their money elsewhere. This gave entrepreneurs a hard time in finding that first cheque to kick start their business, thus, resulting in unnecessary road kills of many good ideas. However, there was a sigh of relief when Indian Finance Minister Nirmala Sitharaman announced in her 2019 Budget that startups and their investors, who will provide the requisite declarations on their returns, will not be subject to scrutiny under the Angel tax. The government also eased the norms for companies to qualify as startups by increasing the upper limit for the turnover of the tax exempt startups from ₹250 million to ₹1 billion. Furthermore, an entity will now be considered a startup for upto 10 years after its incorporation, as compared to 7 years earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India has definitely come a long way, but still has a lot to learn from how other countries have successfully implemented some out-of-the-box policies to create a vibrant startup ecosystem. The global startup economy has achieved great heights with a total economic value of nearly $3 trillion in 2019, a 20% increase in worth from the prior two periods. This growth is largely driven by high-tech startups in the fields of advanced manufacturing and robotics, blockchain, agritech and new food, and artificial intelligence. Meanwhile, sectors such as edtech, digital media, gaming and adTech have seen falling levels of investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some countries have outperformed others in terms of innovation, friendly government policies and entrepreneurial mindset. Israel is one such country which boasts of the highest venture capital investments as a percentage of GDP. The influx of highly educated Jewish immigrants in the 1990’s and the training of people in sophisticated technology, due to compulsory military service, has given a boost to technological research in this small Middle-Eastern country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has played an instrumental role in ensuring that this abundant human capital does not go to waste by providing adequate funding to convert their ideas into businesses. The Matching Grants Programme is one such government initiative that was launched with the aim to eliminate the financial risk associated with the ambiguity in the outcome of a research. The firms simply have to submit their R&amp;amp;D proposals to the chief scientist, and grants are awarded on a competitive basis, with 66% to 90% of the research costs covered. These grants act as high-risk loans, where successful projects repay the funding received via a deduction of a small percentage of annual sales whereas the government bears the costs of the unsuccessful projects. This policy played a major role in boosting the high-tech industry of Israel and made it the ‘Startup Nation’ that it is today. In India, the government does provide funds to startups to carry on R&amp;amp;D, but it does not bear the risk of failure of startup. With over 90% of Indian startups failing in the initial years due to lack of original ideas and innovation, a government policy mirroring Israel’s will inculcate a sense of confidence conducive to taking bolder risks by entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canada is also known for its startup hubs like Montreal, Vancouver and Toronto. Canada has successfully launched and implemented NextAI: the first global programme to build Canada’s Artificial Intelligence ecosystem. It not only provides funding to talented teams and individuals in AI ranging from $50,000 to an additional $150,000 to the top performers, but also provides them with education from AI experts, a network of like-minded innovators and corporate mentors, office space in AI-focused hubs, and easy access to visas to entrepreneurs from abroad. R&amp;amp;D on AI is non-existent in India and initiatives like NextAI must be undertaken in collaboration with educational institutions, the corporate sector and international governments to provide Indian researchers the required expertise and monetary support to kickstart such a programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In European countries, like the UK, private companies help individuals and firms in the paperwork of proving and estimating the costs of R&amp;amp;D for a meagre commission, a facility non-existent in India. This has great prospects in India because this Asian country requires every fund-raising request to go through 14 procedural stages against the global average of 4.3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the single most important aspect which Indians lack is the Israeli ‘chutzpah’, which literally translates to audacity and boldness. Entrepreneurs in countries like USA, UK, Canada, Japan and Germany are risk-takers who are not afraid to fail. Unlike India, where being practical and financially secure is given far more significance than the ability to dream big, failure is merely seen as a learning experience and a stepping stone to success in these counties. The Indian startup economy has not yet seen its full potential due to the timid and risk-averse nature of people, which is reiterated time and again, thus, creating a mental barrier in people. However, India is changing for the better, with a bold, young generation ready to take the risks of having their own businesses. India is treading the correct path. All it needs to do is learn from the best; whether that is innovative governmental policies or Chutzpah, and finally, implement it efficiently in their country.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sanjana Chandaliya</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A proud moment for India was to have been ranked as the 5th most startup-friendly economy in the world, in 2019. This was based on five parameters: human capital investment, research and development, entrepreneurial infrastructure, technical workforce and policy dynamics. Despite losing the first four positions to the USA, UK, Canada and Israel, India has come a long way due to various government schemes such as Startup India, Make In India, Digital India, the setting up of the Biotechnology Industry Research Assistance Council (BIRAC) and many more which foster a culture of entrepreneurship and innovation in the country. However, India has lagged behind other countries in two aspects majorly; innovation and taxation. The persistent dearth of successful innovation and the recent ‘Angel tax issue’ have discouraged investors from providing funds to Indian entrepreneurs for the creation of their own startups.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Capitalist Realism</title>
      <link href="/Capitalist-Realism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Capitalist Realism" />
      <published>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Capitalist-Realism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Capitalist-Realism">&lt;p&gt;The Mayan calendar had prophesied that the world would end in 2012. Various
scientists have predicted that life on Earth will end after an asteroid hits the
planet. All these forecasts seem more or less acceptable to the general
populace. But will communism ever be the next world order? Not a chance. If one
were to inspect carefully, it is easier for us to imagine the end of the world
than to think that an alternative to capitalism exists. It is precisely this
phenomenon that Mark Fisher wrote about in his book, &lt;em&gt;Capitalist Realism - Is
There No Alternative?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalist Realism is the acceptance that “not only is capitalism the only
viable political and economic system but also that it is now impossible even to
imagine a coherent alternative to it.” While there is an acceptance of the many
faults in capitalism, the ramifications of those faults are often neglected or
undermined. Capitalist realism exists because it has managed to become
irreplaceable to us and has killed any sort of hope for a new system to take its
place. The narrative says that though we may not live in a condition of perfect
‘Goodness’, we must be grateful that we are saved from the ultimate ‘Evil’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalism is vehement in the criticism of any alternatives that may be present - while things may not be ideal, the alternatives are much worse. Here, it draws
power by painting contrasts between democracies and dictatorships, between civil
liberties and stark inequality - where one is shown to be a lesser evil, even if
reality may speak differently. The bombing of thousands of innocents in Syria is
justified, as long as it does not imitate the ruthless persecution or ethnic
cleansing that happened in countries like Rwanda. By characterising itself as a
hail-Mary from the disaster that any other alternative would lead to, capitalism
poses as a protector and gives way to capitalist realism - the foregone
conclusion that what persists is the best out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even for those who realise the problem, there is a severe lack of action. What
could be an explanation for this? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One idea theorised is that the repetition of history has saturated us. In the
time and age we are in, it seems that every action we take has already been
taken in the past. Imagine the despondency of a generation that has come after
history, “whose every move is anticipated, tracked, bought and sold before it
had even happened.” Every act of ours is an experienced cliche, already noted in
the accounts of the past. No protest is novel. The realisation is in itself a
cliche. When all our attempts to create history are old and uninspired, it
eventually leads to a detached witnessing of events instead of active
involvement and engagement. There is a saturation of history, which inspires a
sense of cultural and political exhaustion - almost sterility - into old and
young minds alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger threat of the indoctrination of capitalism is that it has penetrated
our unconscious. Our unconscious shapes our desires, hopes and aspirations. If
one introspects, he/she would realise that our ambitions are driven by a
capitalist narrative - the image of success for us is a rich, privileged
businessman, who enjoys a position of social, economic and political capital in
society. Even while mentally accepting that money is tokenistic and “cannot buy
happiness,” we fetishise money. This acceptance of capitalist aims by society as
a whole and the subsequent trickle down to an individual level further solidify
its existence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strengthening the Roots of Capitalism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is impossible to think of Stalin, Hitler or Mussolini succeeding without
propaganda - their rallies were charged with nationalist sentiment and were
publicised to the extent that the idea of a Great Reich was almost shoved down
people’s throats. But the way that capitalism promotes itself is more nuanced -
the anti-capitalist sentiment is co-opted into capitalism. In a majority of
Hollywood movies, the villain turns out to be the CEO of an evil corporation or
a wealthy fanatic in retirement. Capitalist realism, therefore, is dangerous as
it gets away with including critique within its structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We accept that capitalism has problems - but the way we perceive the solution to
these problems is problematic in itself. Poverty and income inequality are
accepted faults of capitalism. Ask yourself - can we have a world without
poverty? Can we have one where there is income equity? Can an egalitarian
society exist? The answer will be no. Sure, we are striving towards these goals,
but their actual achievement is &lt;em&gt;utopian&lt;/em&gt;. Capitalist realism allows the
acceptance of a state of crisis in a continuum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to challenge this idea is to identify how capitalist realism
escapes our notice on a day-to-day basis. Fisher gives three simple examples for
us to understand this: climate change, bureaucracy, and mental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalism is built on the idea of consumerism. A capitalist state aims to grow
and expand markets continuously. A system that wants to be on its feet
constantly, that is principally in support of bulldozing through time for
profits, can never simultaneously aim for sustenance and stability. This
dichotomy in the theory of capitalism itself is something that often gets
unnoticed. Instead of saying that institutionalised inequalities are a result of
consumerism, the narrative is spun on its head by saying that what we buy is
going to change the principle of the political theory. For example, we are told
to consume alternatives instead of questioning the practicality of usage and
reducing our consumption. Buying the right thing, from the right place is
projected as a long term solution - but it still feeds into a structure that
advocates for consumerism. Climate change can never be solved or dealt with in a
capitalist construct because expansion is the ultimate goal and usage of
resources is a way to achieve the ‘target’. We will always, despite our best
efforts, hold resources secondary to this manic need for material progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberal and neo-liberal societies, while criticising socialism and communism,
highlight the problem with giving excess power to bureaucratic structures.
Bureaucrats often exploit their power and it leads to corruption and
inefficiency in the economy. The winning pitch for capitalism to be accepted
originally was to promise that bureaucracy would vanish. Except, what is the
status quo like? Even in late capitalism, bureaucracy still exists. The
difference is that it is morphed into a different kind of bureaucracy - one that
is allowed to penetrate all forms of structures through things like demanding
memos and answering to superiors. This bureaucracy is enforced at all levels of
management, establishing its place in the micro-levels of the economy.
Capitalist realism further reinforces that we cannot ‘practically’ do without
this culture of constantly answering to someone and being monitored, making the
control of societies a self-enforcing reality. Essentially, capitalism has
failed to differentiate itself from its alternatives on this metric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalism, in its want to create overachievers and socially acceptable success
stories, has created ‘hustle culture’ - one that essentially relies on the idea
that &lt;em&gt;one mustn’t stop&lt;/em&gt;. If one chooses to listen to music instead of a podcast
on the way home, he/she is actively choosing to not add to his/her productivity.
If one does not succeed, the burden of the failure is wholly individualistic -
one must work harder or do things a particular way because regardless of the
kind of burdens one faces (for instance sociological burdens like racism),
anyone who strives enough &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; succeed. As a society, we have
pressurised people to the extent that mental health issues are on the rise among
young people - and no one ties it back to the inherent dysfunction in
capitalism. Instead of taking responsibility for this mass pressurisation, we
have privatised stress to be caused by individual chemical imbalances. By
placing the onus of a healthy state of mind exclusively on the individual
instead of accepting how society has failed him/her, we have allowed capitalist
realism to become our inevitable reality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we establish capitalist realism’s claim to fame, one must wonder how it
sustains itself. Lacan argues that the concept of the ‘big Other’ in this
regard. The PR image that capitalism creates is sustained by those who are
willing to buy into this marketing. The Other is simply one who experiences life
differently even after knowing what the truth may be. The difference between
what one chooses to accept and what exists primarily sustains the ordinary
interactions we have daily. When the Other accepts reality as it is and chooses
to ignore the narrative that is set out, it creates an abnormality. When
Khrushchev’s speech in 1965 accepted the faults in the Soviet Union, it caused
an uproar. It was not as if people did not know of the kind of human rights
violations and corruption that was happening - the declaration just ensured that
‘the Other’ could not ignore it anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, unlike Khrushchev in the Soviet Union, there is no incentive for anyone
with legitimacy in the Other’s eye to inform the Other of the kind of abominable
structure it is living in. The persons considered by the Other as leaders enjoy
the power that they hold and acceptance of truth by the masses will threaten
their hold over being able to control narratives. Thus, when people who can make
a difference choose not to, it serves to further crystallise capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Playing the Blame Game&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with capitalism is accountability. While, in principle, corporations
are supposed to be the drivers of growth, they do not take responsibility as
they aren’t supposed to look after the welfare of every citizen operating within
the ambit of the care of the government. But the government does not take
responsibility either because it says that its role is minimised and unwanted.
So, any anger towards the system is directed towards an abstraction that is,
thus, unresponsive - someone did something wrong and we are now left with the
burden of cleaning up the mess. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to hold collective responsibility for issues that plague all of us -
like climate change needs to be addressed by each one of us to get any tangible
change. The genius of capitalism is especially evident here - it protects itself
while making individuals scapegoats. For any scandal that happens, we tend to
burden the individual and ask for a more ‘morally upright’ replacement. However,
countless examples of upright individuals succumbing to the pressures and power
of a particular appointment and ending up corrupt are a testament to the fact
that vices are engendered in and by the system - as long as the system persists,
these vices will continue to sustain themselves. Therefore, Žižek argues that
placing individual responsibility due to the need for “ethical immediacy” lets
the system shirk the responsibility of cleaning itself up. He uses the example
of the 2008 credit crisis, wherein the blame was put on those ‘horrible people’
who abused the system rather than on the system that encouraged this culture of
abuse itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the acceptance of the possibility of an alternative to capitalism, none
of these problems will be effectively tackled and capitalist realism will
continue to dominate - perhaps as an unconscious undertone, but with immense
power over our economic, social and political interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Road Ahead &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There may be a glimmer of hope for the world yet. Neoliberal capitalism is no
longer secure in its throne as the days of democratic socialism are on the
horizon. As the study of late capitalism and its critique increases, protesting
voices have emerged.  There is an increasing acceptance of left leaders like
Jeremy Corbyn, Alexandria Cortez, Bernie Sanders, and their policies in states
that have been the poster-children for capitalism. Healthcare for all, free
education and opportunity for the underprivileged are being accepted by a vast
majority of people - especially those who have been victims of capitalist
structures. The gravity of the stark income inequality is being acknowledged and
called out. Corporates and the wealthy are under increasing pressure and
scrutiny to pay higher taxes and fulfil any responsibility they have towards the
less privileged. While capitalist realism paints a bleak picture of us as a
civilisation, perhaps it is time for the sleeping phoenix to rise from the ashes
and take us to a better tomorrow. The cracks in the existing system are more
prominent and visible today than ever before - the responsibility of analysing
them and creating a new order is now on us to fulfil.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aanandi Arjun</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Mayan calendar had prophesied that the world would end in 2012. Various scientists have predicted that life on Earth will end after an asteroid hits the planet. All these forecasts seem more or less acceptable to the general populace. But will communism ever be the next world order? Not a chance. If one were to inspect carefully, it is easier for us to imagine the end of the world than to think that an alternative to capitalism exists. It is precisely this phenomenon that Mark Fisher wrote about in his book, Capitalist Realism - Is There No Alternative? Capitalist Realism is the acceptance that “not only is capitalism the only viable political and economic system but also that it is now impossible even to imagine a coherent alternative to it.” While there is an acceptance of the many faults in capitalism, the ramifications of those faults are often neglected or undermined. Capitalist realism exists because it has managed to become irreplaceable to us and has killed any sort of hope for a new system to take its place. The narrative says that though we may not live in a condition of perfect ‘Goodness’, we must be grateful that we are saved from the ultimate ‘Evil’.  Capitalism is vehement in the criticism of any alternatives that may be present - while things may not be ideal, the alternatives are much worse. Here, it draws power by painting contrasts between democracies and dictatorships, between civil liberties and stark inequality - where one is shown to be a lesser evil, even if reality may speak differently. The bombing of thousands of innocents in Syria is justified, as long as it does not imitate the ruthless persecution or ethnic cleansing that happened in countries like Rwanda. By characterising itself as a hail-Mary from the disaster that any other alternative would lead to, capitalism poses as a protector and gives way to capitalist realism - the foregone conclusion that what persists is the best out there. Even for those who realise the problem, there is a severe lack of action. What could be an explanation for this?  One idea theorised is that the repetition of history has saturated us. In the time and age we are in, it seems that every action we take has already been taken in the past. Imagine the despondency of a generation that has come after history, “whose every move is anticipated, tracked, bought and sold before it had even happened.” Every act of ours is an experienced cliche, already noted in the accounts of the past. No protest is novel. The realisation is in itself a cliche. When all our attempts to create history are old and uninspired, it eventually leads to a detached witnessing of events instead of active involvement and engagement. There is a saturation of history, which inspires a sense of cultural and political exhaustion - almost sterility - into old and young minds alike. The bigger threat of the indoctrination of capitalism is that it has penetrated our unconscious. Our unconscious shapes our desires, hopes and aspirations. If one introspects, he/she would realise that our ambitions are driven by a capitalist narrative - the image of success for us is a rich, privileged businessman, who enjoys a position of social, economic and political capital in society. Even while mentally accepting that money is tokenistic and “cannot buy happiness,” we fetishise money. This acceptance of capitalist aims by society as a whole and the subsequent trickle down to an individual level further solidify its existence.  Strengthening the Roots of Capitalism It is impossible to think of Stalin, Hitler or Mussolini succeeding without propaganda - their rallies were charged with nationalist sentiment and were publicised to the extent that the idea of a Great Reich was almost shoved down people’s throats. But the way that capitalism promotes itself is more nuanced - the anti-capitalist sentiment is co-opted into capitalism. In a majority of Hollywood movies, the villain turns out to be the CEO of an evil corporation or a wealthy fanatic in retirement. Capitalist realism, therefore, is dangerous as it gets away with including critique within its structure. We accept that capitalism has problems - but the way we perceive the solution to these problems is problematic in itself. Poverty and income inequality are accepted faults of capitalism. Ask yourself - can we have a world without poverty? Can we have one where there is income equity? Can an egalitarian society exist? The answer will be no. Sure, we are striving towards these goals, but their actual achievement is utopian. Capitalist realism allows the acceptance of a state of crisis in a continuum. The only way to challenge this idea is to identify how capitalist realism escapes our notice on a day-to-day basis. Fisher gives three simple examples for us to understand this: climate change, bureaucracy, and mental health. Capitalism is built on the idea of consumerism. A capitalist state aims to grow and expand markets continuously. A system that wants to be on its feet constantly, that is principally in support of bulldozing through time for profits, can never simultaneously aim for sustenance and stability. This dichotomy in the theory of capitalism itself is something that often gets unnoticed. Instead of saying that institutionalised inequalities are a result of consumerism, the narrative is spun on its head by saying that what we buy is going to change the principle of the political theory. For example, we are told to consume alternatives instead of questioning the practicality of usage and reducing our consumption. Buying the right thing, from the right place is projected as a long term solution - but it still feeds into a structure that advocates for consumerism. Climate change can never be solved or dealt with in a capitalist construct because expansion is the ultimate goal and usage of resources is a way to achieve the ‘target’. We will always, despite our best efforts, hold resources secondary to this manic need for material progress. Liberal and neo-liberal societies, while criticising socialism and communism, highlight the problem with giving excess power to bureaucratic structures. Bureaucrats often exploit their power and it leads to corruption and inefficiency in the economy. The winning pitch for capitalism to be accepted originally was to promise that bureaucracy would vanish. Except, what is the status quo like? Even in late capitalism, bureaucracy still exists. The difference is that it is morphed into a different kind of bureaucracy - one that is allowed to penetrate all forms of structures through things like demanding memos and answering to superiors. This bureaucracy is enforced at all levels of management, establishing its place in the micro-levels of the economy. Capitalist realism further reinforces that we cannot ‘practically’ do without this culture of constantly answering to someone and being monitored, making the control of societies a self-enforcing reality. Essentially, capitalism has failed to differentiate itself from its alternatives on this metric. Capitalism, in its want to create overachievers and socially acceptable success stories, has created ‘hustle culture’ - one that essentially relies on the idea that one mustn’t stop. If one chooses to listen to music instead of a podcast on the way home, he/she is actively choosing to not add to his/her productivity. If one does not succeed, the burden of the failure is wholly individualistic - one must work harder or do things a particular way because regardless of the kind of burdens one faces (for instance sociological burdens like racism), anyone who strives enough can and must succeed. As a society, we have pressurised people to the extent that mental health issues are on the rise among young people - and no one ties it back to the inherent dysfunction in capitalism. Instead of taking responsibility for this mass pressurisation, we have privatised stress to be caused by individual chemical imbalances. By placing the onus of a healthy state of mind exclusively on the individual instead of accepting how society has failed him/her, we have allowed capitalist realism to become our inevitable reality.  Once we establish capitalist realism’s claim to fame, one must wonder how it sustains itself. Lacan argues that the concept of the ‘big Other’ in this regard. The PR image that capitalism creates is sustained by those who are willing to buy into this marketing. The Other is simply one who experiences life differently even after knowing what the truth may be. The difference between what one chooses to accept and what exists primarily sustains the ordinary interactions we have daily. When the Other accepts reality as it is and chooses to ignore the narrative that is set out, it creates an abnormality. When Khrushchev’s speech in 1965 accepted the faults in the Soviet Union, it caused an uproar. It was not as if people did not know of the kind of human rights violations and corruption that was happening - the declaration just ensured that ‘the Other’ could not ignore it anymore. However, unlike Khrushchev in the Soviet Union, there is no incentive for anyone with legitimacy in the Other’s eye to inform the Other of the kind of abominable structure it is living in. The persons considered by the Other as leaders enjoy the power that they hold and acceptance of truth by the masses will threaten their hold over being able to control narratives. Thus, when people who can make a difference choose not to, it serves to further crystallise capitalism. Playing the Blame Game The problem with capitalism is accountability. While, in principle, corporations are supposed to be the drivers of growth, they do not take responsibility as they aren’t supposed to look after the welfare of every citizen operating within the ambit of the care of the government. But the government does not take responsibility either because it says that its role is minimised and unwanted. So, any anger towards the system is directed towards an abstraction that is, thus, unresponsive - someone did something wrong and we are now left with the burden of cleaning up the mess.  We need to hold collective responsibility for issues that plague all of us - like climate change needs to be addressed by each one of us to get any tangible change. The genius of capitalism is especially evident here - it protects itself while making individuals scapegoats. For any scandal that happens, we tend to burden the individual and ask for a more ‘morally upright’ replacement. However, countless examples of upright individuals succumbing to the pressures and power of a particular appointment and ending up corrupt are a testament to the fact that vices are engendered in and by the system - as long as the system persists, these vices will continue to sustain themselves. Therefore, Žižek argues that placing individual responsibility due to the need for “ethical immediacy” lets the system shirk the responsibility of cleaning itself up. He uses the example of the 2008 credit crisis, wherein the blame was put on those ‘horrible people’ who abused the system rather than on the system that encouraged this culture of abuse itself. Without the acceptance of the possibility of an alternative to capitalism, none of these problems will be effectively tackled and capitalist realism will continue to dominate - perhaps as an unconscious undertone, but with immense power over our economic, social and political interactions. The Road Ahead  There may be a glimmer of hope for the world yet. Neoliberal capitalism is no longer secure in its throne as the days of democratic socialism are on the horizon. As the study of late capitalism and its critique increases, protesting voices have emerged.  There is an increasing acceptance of left leaders like Jeremy Corbyn, Alexandria Cortez, Bernie Sanders, and their policies in states that have been the poster-children for capitalism. Healthcare for all, free education and opportunity for the underprivileged are being accepted by a vast majority of people - especially those who have been victims of capitalist structures. The gravity of the stark income inequality is being acknowledged and called out. Corporates and the wealthy are under increasing pressure and scrutiny to pay higher taxes and fulfil any responsibility they have towards the less privileged. While capitalist realism paints a bleak picture of us as a civilisation, perhaps it is time for the sleeping phoenix to rise from the ashes and take us to a better tomorrow. The cracks in the existing system are more prominent and visible today than ever before - the responsibility of analysing them and creating a new order is now on us to fulfil.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Building the Abode of Gods…From Scratch</title>
      <link href="/Building-the-Abode-of-Gods" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building the Abode of Gods...From Scratch" />
      <published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Building-the-Abode-of-Gods</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Building-the-Abode-of-Gods">&lt;p&gt;In 2014, a southern state of India, Andhra Pradesh, was bifurcated to form the separate state of Telangana. Economically speaking, Andhra Pradesh was left with literally nothing. It did not have a major metropolitan city. Nor did it have the financials to develop one. Overnight after bifurcation, the state was deep down in debt. It had lost its capital and major source of revenue, the high-tech city of Hyderabad. Section 5(1) of the Andhra Pradesh Reorganization Act, 2014 mandates that Hyderabad will be a common capital for a period not exceeding ten years (i.e. till 2024). However, the geographical location of the city made it inconvenient for the new Andhra Pradesh government to govern from Hyderabad. Now, without a capital, how does a government function and make plans for the state? After all, state capitals are centers for administrative activities and policy formulations. Most importantly, a capital gives the state a sense of identity. Thus began plans for the construction of a new, world-class capital city of ‘&lt;em&gt;Amaravati&lt;/em&gt;’- the Abode of the Gods. The ambition as grand as the name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2014 Assembly elections, N Chandrababu Naidu of India’s Telugu Desam Party became the Chief Minister of the state. Soon, the government set up committees to finalise the area for capital construction. Amaravati was chosen by the end of 2014. There are many reasons for this selection. First, the proposed region is at the centre and is equidistant from every corner of the state. The second reason is the availability of water. The proposed capital city is situated on the banks of the river Krishna. It also has a barrage constructed which could hold up to 1 TMC of water. The third is the ease of connectivity. Amaravati is not more than 400 km from Hyderabad, Chennai and Bengaluru, capital cities of states that neighbour Andhra Pradesh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon deciding the capital, the government constituted the Andhra Pradesh Capital Region Development Authority (APCRDA) in 2014 for planning, supervising, executing, financing and developing the capital region of Andhra Pradesh. Its tasks include finalising designs, calling for tenders and administering capital construction. Right from the beginning, the state drew its inspiration from Singapore to build a world-class city. Mr Naidu always talked about how Singapore too had developed from scratch and Andhra Pradesh was in the same position. APCRDA even signed an MoU with the Singapore government for the development of a master plan for Amaravati, which was finalised recently in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting thing to be noted here is that land for the capital was pooled rather than acquired. This was done to avoid the financial burden that would arise in the form of compensations against land acquisitions. Under this land pooling scheme, the landowners (mostly farmers) who surrendered their lands to the government would get a portion of the developed plots in the capital city after a period of 10 years. A huge 33,000 acres (133.5 square kilometers) was pooled for the construction of the capital city. It is a commendable achievement because the land was pooled in a very short period, that too without a single court case. Mr Naidu played a key role in assuring the fearful farmers that they would lose nothing by sacrificing their lands. To attract investments into the capital (and the state), the Andhra Pradesh government introduced a slew of measures. It eased its industrial policy by introducing a ‘single window clearance’ for industries, under which one can easily obtain all the necessary approvals for the setting up of a business, and avoid red tape thereof. Not only did this place Andhra Pradesh at the number 1 spot in the ‘Ease of Doing Business’ index of India but also helped the state in signing a $500 million deal with the World Bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a city from scratch is an uphill task. For a state with finances like Andhra Pradesh, it is an economic nightmare. The state is so deep in a financial crisis that a recent White Paper released by the government stated that the state has to go for an overdraft almost every month! Yet, there seems to be non-cooperation from India’s central government. When the  Andhra Pradesh Reorganization Bill was up for discussion in the Rajya Sabha, the upper house of the Indian Parliament, the then Prime Minister Dr Manmohan Singh said “for the purpose of central assistance, Special Category Status (SCS) will be extended to the State of Andhra Pradesh for a period of five years. This will put the state finances on a firmer footing.” What SCS means is that the state would get preferential treatment in the transfer of funds from the central government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, SCS money never seems to come. It is estimated that construction of the new capital would require a massive sum of ₹330 billion. Out of this, a mere ₹25 billion has been allocated by India’s central government, and only ₹10.5 billion has been released till date. The administrative help from the Indian central government has been delayed too. One example of the central government’s neglect is worth mentioning here. Emirates, a world-renowned airline, sought to fly from Andhra Pradesh and establish a training facility there. It requested the state to provide the requisite land. As aviation is regulated by the central government according to India’s Constitution, this required the centre’s approval. Unfortunately, that approval never came.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given all these troubles, wouldn’t it have been more feasible for Andhra Pradesh to select an already existing city rather than build a capital from scratch? All this said, building a new capital boosts aggregate demand. A huge amount of money is invested and employment opportunities are generated. However, the government needs to take appropriate steps to invite private investment into the state. Given the high fiscal deficit of the state, 4.5% of the GSDP or Gross State Domestic Product, it is imperative that the state goes hand-in-hand with the private sector because a further increase in fiscal deficit would put the state in a financially critical position. Infrastructural development needs huge investments with a generally long gestation period. It would be burdensome for the crippled economy of Andhra Pradesh to finance such investments. Private investments would ensure that there is no stoppage in the fund flow and the projects are completed duly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the erstwhile Andhra Pradesh, excessive economic centralisation took place in and around Hyderabad. Even today, a lion’s share of Telangana’s (the newly formed state) revenue is generated by Hyderabad. It is because all major developmental activities were planned in Hyderabad and less emphasis was placed on the development of other cities and towns. Bearing this experience in mind, the new Andhra Pradesh should be diversified in its development trajectory. Single-city centric development will cost the state dearly (like it did during its bifurcation). The capital should be restricted to administrative uses. Necessary infrastructure should be built in other cities to transform them into major centres in the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, Visakhapatnam, or Vizag, in its anglicised form, is a happening port city with a notable presence of the software industry. It has the potential to emerge as a major IT hub and the government should take steps to harness the said potential. Rayalaseema, the southern part of Andhra Pradesh, receives scarce rainfall and is not as feasible for agriculture as the other regions are. On the other hand, southern India is not a manufacturing power in the country. Andhra Pradesh could fill this gap by developing the Rayalaseema region into a major industrial and manufacturing hub. Like the existing Sri City Special Economic Zone (SEZ), a rising industrial hub in the southern part of the state, more of such initiatives can be taken up for the same purpose. The lawmakers should learn from their earlier experiences. They should make plans in such a way that development is spread throughout the state rather than being concentrated in Amaravati. Andhra Pradesh should not repeat its mistakes. And using its scarce funds to create a grand city of Amaravati would be doing so, in fact, one could say it’s already doing so.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In 2014, a southern state of India, Andhra Pradesh, was bifurcated to form the separate state of Telangana. Economically speaking, Andhra Pradesh was left with literally nothing. It did not have a major metropolitan city. Nor did it have the financials to develop one. Overnight after bifurcation, the state was deep down in debt. It had lost its capital and major source of revenue, the high-tech city of Hyderabad. Section 5(1) of the Andhra Pradesh Reorganization Act, 2014 mandates that Hyderabad will be a common capital for a period not exceeding ten years (i.e. till 2024). However, the geographical location of the city made it inconvenient for the new Andhra Pradesh government to govern from Hyderabad. Now, without a capital, how does a government function and make plans for the state? After all, state capitals are centers for administrative activities and policy formulations. Most importantly, a capital gives the state a sense of identity. Thus began plans for the construction of a new, world-class capital city of ‘Amaravati’- the Abode of the Gods. The ambition as grand as the name.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Crypto-Crazed Millennials on a Saving Spree</title>
      <link href="/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Crypto-Crazed Millennials on a Saving Spree" />
      <published>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree">&lt;p&gt;The global financial markets recently completed the longest-ever bull run at the remarkable stretch of a decade. A slow and steady boom rose in March 2009 from the ashes of The Great Recession of 2008. This, however, was not enough to heal the scars that the recession and the dot com bubble had left on the minds of the then-young millennial. While the pre-teen millennials witnessed their parents go through a financial crunch, the older ones stepped right into a slough of joblessness. This has contributed to their unnaturally high sensitivity to losses. As a result, even the near-zero federal funds rate (which directs the global rates) has not been enough to channelise their funds towards the financial markets. This is a major concern for the global economy, especially when you factor in the fact that the millennials are at the cusp of surpassing the Boomers as the largest living adult generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some millennials, burdened by low-income jobs and debt obligations, living from paycheck to paycheck, are genuinely unable to finance stock purchases, the statistics tell us how even better-off millennials are straying away from investing and are preferring to save instead. Unfortunately, their risk-averse tendencies are miscalculated and are costing them precious returns, since the S&amp;amp;P 500 (adjusted for inflation and dividends reinvested) averaged a 7.92% return between 2007 to 2017, while the money market bank accounts averaged a 0.3% return during the same period. Nearly 42% of millennials are conservative investors, as opposed to 38% of GenXers and 23% of the Boomers. They are unwilling to fully embrace the financial markets, and when they do, it is only through a safer, less costly mechanism such as that of an Exchange Traded Fund (ETF), which is a type of fund that holds multiple underlying assets rather than a single stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is worth noting is that their caution seems selective. Millennials’ risk-aversion appears to be more about scepticism when one realises how they have stayed away only from what they personally saw fail - the stock markets. They are still the ones responsible for inflating the crypto-market, despite its lack of intrinsic value or any ‘faith’ backing. The only argument in defense of their wild investment choice is perhaps the sophisticated distributed ledger technology used in the asset which makes the case for fostering technological innovation in the stock markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the politically correct environment, with encouragement from Hollywood, has put capitalism out of style for many. The ones still willing to invest have raised the bar over mere profitability when making an investment decision. Company ethics and transparency are a primary consideration for millennials when they choose to invest, and these additional filters reduce the overall amount invested. The rate of investment for women is in an even poorer state. The Harris Poll survey revealed that a staggering 79% of women do not invest at all, with 70% of them stating that the process is confusing to them, while 60% of them believing how they felt investing was ‘an old-white man’s game’. Clearly, the Millennials need a better education when it comes to managing their finances and getting over &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; impression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger picture is clear: Millennials are savers and not investors. 71% of Millennial workers are saving for retirement, and begin saving at the median age of 24, which puts the GenX’s median saving age of 30 to shame. And while they rely on the banks for saving, they try to keep away from availing any of the other services. A three year study from Scratch, an in-house unit of Viacom, as a part of the &lt;em&gt;Millennial Disruption Study&lt;/em&gt;, found that not only were banks among the ‘Most Hated’ brands, but a third of this demographic cohort believed that they’d be better off without them. This is a major concern for banks, who are now resorting to appeasement techniques. Providing special discounts on credit card bills and easing out the enrollment mechanism for loans are a few examples. This has also partially fueled the rise of fintech in the formal banking system and is encouraging the development of such technologies. Developing a system with a user-friendly interface and greater transparency by incorporation of Artificial Intelligence (AI) and machine learning is an obvious solution to this issue. For instance,  a ZeroHedge survey revealed that one in three Millennials would rather invest in Bitcoin than in the stock market, simply because of the unconventional and futuristic technology involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that in traditional economics, the West had never been considered the saver’s economy, and this pattern is shifting for the better. The situation is quite akin to the rise in savings post the hyperinflationary periods in Germany after World War I, which incidentally was also a result of the psychological impact of the crisis. At the macro level, greater savings would imply lesser dependence on foreign investment. Lesser inflow of USD denominated investment in the USA implies lesser demand for the dollar. The consequent decline in appreciation of the USD is great for recovering the Current Account Deficit, which has been a primary long-term concern for the nation. But this advantage is dwarfed when growth concerns step in, as slowdowns are the projected case for the next few years. Additionally, with the rise of protectionist, right-wing governments around the globe, millennials are increasingly inclining towards what they think is socialism, which implies increased disinterest towards the financial markets. And that is a terrible prospect for growth. Hence, even though this demographic cohort has been through quite a lot at an impressionable age, they must put their concerns aside and take up a more rational approach. They have made a wise decision to save, considering the depleting ability of the burgeoning federal balance sheet to finance their post-retirement expenses. But they must learn to be comfortable with the idea of some risk.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The global financial markets recently completed the longest-ever bull run at the remarkable stretch of a decade. A slow and steady boom rose in March 2009 from the ashes of The Great Recession of 2008. This, however, was not enough to heal the scars that the recession and the dot com bubble had left on the minds of the then-young millennial. While the pre-teen millennials witnessed their parents go through a financial crunch, the older ones stepped right into a slough of joblessness. This has contributed to their unnaturally high sensitivity to losses. As a result, even the near-zero federal funds rate (which directs the global rates) has not been enough to channelise their funds towards the financial markets. This is a major concern for the global economy, especially when you factor in the fact that the millennials are at the cusp of surpassing the Boomers as the largest living adult generation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Future of Islamic Finance in the Global Economy</title>
      <link href="/The-Future-of-Islamic-Finance" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Future of Islamic Finance in the Global Economy" />
      <published>2019-07-18T00:10:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-18T00:10:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Future-of-Islamic-Finance</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Future-of-Islamic-Finance">&lt;p&gt;Islamic banks do not have a long history. The first bank started its operations
in 1963 in Egypt. The main centres worldwide are in Iran, Saudi Arabia,
Malaysia, Europe, Great Britain and Switzerland. Islamic banking and religion
are correlated (shock!). However preposterous it may sound, it is a bank that
does not charge you interest. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider that you want to start a manufacturing plant. A conventional bank will
provide you with the money and charge interest on it: the concept of
‘multiplying’ money. On the contrary, Islamic banks are forbidden from charging
interest. Instead, they will offer to be partners in your business and share
profits and losses. This strengthens the economy by reducing the burden from the
promoter’s shoulders and sharing it with financial institutions. In fact, their
peculiar business model helped Islamic banks largely avert the adverse impact of
the 2008 crisis. In particular, it was investment portfolios that were smaller
in size, partially deleveraged, and adherence to &lt;em&gt;Shariah&lt;/em&gt; principles which
prevented Islamic banks from putting money in the kind of instruments that
affected their conventional competitors and helped limit the impact of the
crisis on them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A characteristic feature of Islamic banking is the role of the bank. The basic
mission is, surprisingly, not to generate profit for the bank or multiply the
income for customers but to support local development and entrepreneurship.
Everything in the Islamic banking system is made according to  &lt;em&gt;Shariah&lt;/em&gt; law.
The things which are allowed in Islam are called ‘&lt;em&gt;halal&lt;/em&gt;’ and the things which
are forbidden are ‘&lt;em&gt;haram&lt;/em&gt;’. So, the bank is not able to invest any of their
money in the products or services forbidden in Islam. For example, in production
or trade of alcohol, nicotine, drugs, or in sectors related to pornography, the
defence sector, casino, and nightclubs. So, a customer of the Islamic bank can
be well assured that his money would not be invested in anything inconsistent
with Islam. The rule of ‘&lt;em&gt;Money makes Money&lt;/em&gt;’ does not exist in Islam because
money has no value in itself and cannot be multiplied just by rotating it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two key aspects of Islamic finance. First, it has the advantage of
being asset-backed which makes it inherently less risky than conventional
finance. Second, a prevalent risk-reward sharing arrangement exists. Apart from
this, there are some rules which guide such institutions. For example, retaining
surplus profit is unfair in this system, it is strictly related to usury -
&lt;em&gt;‘Reba’&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Reba&lt;/em&gt; is one of the most important rules in the Islamic banking
system. The second rule is &lt;em&gt;gharar&lt;/em&gt;, which is related to risky or hazardous
sales and the fact that gambling is prohibited in the Islamic world. For
instance, you cannot sell the goods or services which are not yet produced. It
can be traded upon only once it comes into existence. Moreover, nothing can be
sold unless you acquire it. This essentially eliminates the risk of not
possessing the goods. All products offered in Islamic banks have to be observed
and accepted by the Council for Islamic Banks (by their lawyers and clergy). The
most popular transaction in Islamic banking is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/m/murabaha.asp&quot;&gt;‘Murabaha’-&lt;/a&gt; a cost-plus
financing structure where the client and the bank agree on the markup or
“cost-plus” price for the item being sold. In essence, the bank purchases the
item on behalf of the client and retains its ownership rights until the client
pays back the amount (which is the cost-plus profit on the item) to the bank. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Islamic finance is growing rapidly but remains concentrated on a few
jurisdictions. Its strong growth reflects a tremendous interest on the part of
the Muslim population who have previously been underserved by the banking
industry. For the past two decades, many Islamic banks have witnessed
double-digit growth rates, surpassing their conventional peers. The industry’s
total worth, across its three main sectors (banking, capital markets, and
&lt;em&gt;Takaful&lt;/em&gt;), was estimated to be $2.05 trillion in 2017. At a mere glance, all
seems well for the Islamic banking industry. However, several potential markets
with a considerable quantum of the Muslim population remain largely unbreached,
including India and the Commonwealth of Independent States countries, made up of
the former Soviet republics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Islamic finance holds great promise for promoting macroeconomic and financial
stability but to fulfil these promises three prerequisites really need to be
met: first, a further deepening of the standard and codes for the application of
Islamic finance and their consistent application globally. Secondly, it is
essential for &lt;em&gt;Shariah&lt;/em&gt;-compliant money markets to be developed. This will allow
Islamic banks to manage their liquidity in a more effective way and free up
resources for them to invest in growth-enhancing projects. The Islamic financial
market is now facing increased competition due to the establishment of other
Islamic financial institutions and conventional banks who have established
Islamic subsidiaries or windows. Islamic banks also suffer from an overhang of
bad loans, and they lag behind their Western counterparts in technology and
expertise. The religious dimension adds an extra layer of problems with respect
to introducing new products that need to cater to both the Islamic law and the
needs of the general public. Lastly, there is a vital need for institutional
reforms in the areas of tax policy and capital markets development, which will
be needed for Islamic finance to fulfil its promise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critics consider Islamic banking similar to having a boiled ice cream-cream, it
cannot exist in real life without trickling down our confidence. For instance,
if you need a loan for purchasing a house, Islamic Banks will not charge you
interest on this money. Instead, they will buy the house for you and sell it
back to you at a higher price, demanding this amount from you in, say, 15 years,
of course, interest-free. This is a backdoor policy of interest collection. In
other words, it is interest-collection in all but name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to India, which will soon be the home to most Muslims in the
world, there has been a long-standing debate on Islamic banking. Currently, the
rules don’t allow it. Critics say it’s a bad idea because it goes against
India’s secular fabric. Is India ready for it? Will it open a Pandora’s Box?
Should we look at it through a religious prism? The opinions are sharply
divided. The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 and the Banking Regulations Act,
1949 both prohibit the setting up of an Islamic banking system. Only an act of
Parliament can set up one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, growth has sparked optimism about the future of Islamic
finance. However, as competition intensifies, Islamic financial banks are still
left with work to do. Most Islamic banks need to function more efficiently along
the entire value chain, regardless of whether the strategy is aimed at entering
a niche market, at competing with traditional banks or at both. They need to
scrutinise strategic choices and focus on operational basics to grab unused
market opportunities and overcome the changing dynamics of the industry. In all,
Islamic finance is still at a nascent stage which is yet to meet its full
potential.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>sailesh.buchasia unnati.jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Islamic banks do not have a long history. The first bank started its operations in 1963 in Egypt. The main centres worldwide are in Iran, Saudi Arabia, Malaysia, Europe, Great Britain and Switzerland. Islamic banking and religion are correlated (shock!). However preposterous it may sound, it is a bank that does not charge you interest.  Consider that you want to start a manufacturing plant. A conventional bank will provide you with the money and charge interest on it: the concept of ‘multiplying’ money. On the contrary, Islamic banks are forbidden from charging interest. Instead, they will offer to be partners in your business and share profits and losses. This strengthens the economy by reducing the burden from the promoter’s shoulders and sharing it with financial institutions. In fact, their peculiar business model helped Islamic banks largely avert the adverse impact of the 2008 crisis. In particular, it was investment portfolios that were smaller in size, partially deleveraged, and adherence to Shariah principles which prevented Islamic banks from putting money in the kind of instruments that affected their conventional competitors and helped limit the impact of the crisis on them.  A characteristic feature of Islamic banking is the role of the bank. The basic mission is, surprisingly, not to generate profit for the bank or multiply the income for customers but to support local development and entrepreneurship. Everything in the Islamic banking system is made according to  Shariah law. The things which are allowed in Islam are called ‘halal’ and the things which are forbidden are ‘haram’. So, the bank is not able to invest any of their money in the products or services forbidden in Islam. For example, in production or trade of alcohol, nicotine, drugs, or in sectors related to pornography, the defence sector, casino, and nightclubs. So, a customer of the Islamic bank can be well assured that his money would not be invested in anything inconsistent with Islam. The rule of ‘Money makes Money’ does not exist in Islam because money has no value in itself and cannot be multiplied just by rotating it.  There are two key aspects of Islamic finance. First, it has the advantage of being asset-backed which makes it inherently less risky than conventional finance. Second, a prevalent risk-reward sharing arrangement exists. Apart from this, there are some rules which guide such institutions. For example, retaining surplus profit is unfair in this system, it is strictly related to usury - ‘Reba’. Reba is one of the most important rules in the Islamic banking system. The second rule is gharar, which is related to risky or hazardous sales and the fact that gambling is prohibited in the Islamic world. For instance, you cannot sell the goods or services which are not yet produced. It can be traded upon only once it comes into existence. Moreover, nothing can be sold unless you acquire it. This essentially eliminates the risk of not possessing the goods. All products offered in Islamic banks have to be observed and accepted by the Council for Islamic Banks (by their lawyers and clergy). The most popular transaction in Islamic banking is ‘Murabaha’- a cost-plus financing structure where the client and the bank agree on the markup or “cost-plus” price for the item being sold. In essence, the bank purchases the item on behalf of the client and retains its ownership rights until the client pays back the amount (which is the cost-plus profit on the item) to the bank.  Islamic finance is growing rapidly but remains concentrated on a few jurisdictions. Its strong growth reflects a tremendous interest on the part of the Muslim population who have previously been underserved by the banking industry. For the past two decades, many Islamic banks have witnessed double-digit growth rates, surpassing their conventional peers. The industry’s total worth, across its three main sectors (banking, capital markets, and Takaful), was estimated to be $2.05 trillion in 2017. At a mere glance, all seems well for the Islamic banking industry. However, several potential markets with a considerable quantum of the Muslim population remain largely unbreached, including India and the Commonwealth of Independent States countries, made up of the former Soviet republics. Islamic finance holds great promise for promoting macroeconomic and financial stability but to fulfil these promises three prerequisites really need to be met: first, a further deepening of the standard and codes for the application of Islamic finance and their consistent application globally. Secondly, it is essential for Shariah-compliant money markets to be developed. This will allow Islamic banks to manage their liquidity in a more effective way and free up resources for them to invest in growth-enhancing projects. The Islamic financial market is now facing increased competition due to the establishment of other Islamic financial institutions and conventional banks who have established Islamic subsidiaries or windows. Islamic banks also suffer from an overhang of bad loans, and they lag behind their Western counterparts in technology and expertise. The religious dimension adds an extra layer of problems with respect to introducing new products that need to cater to both the Islamic law and the needs of the general public. Lastly, there is a vital need for institutional reforms in the areas of tax policy and capital markets development, which will be needed for Islamic finance to fulfil its promise. Critics consider Islamic banking similar to having a boiled ice cream-cream, it cannot exist in real life without trickling down our confidence. For instance, if you need a loan for purchasing a house, Islamic Banks will not charge you interest on this money. Instead, they will buy the house for you and sell it back to you at a higher price, demanding this amount from you in, say, 15 years, of course, interest-free. This is a backdoor policy of interest collection. In other words, it is interest-collection in all but name. When it comes to India, which will soon be the home to most Muslims in the world, there has been a long-standing debate on Islamic banking. Currently, the rules don’t allow it. Critics say it’s a bad idea because it goes against India’s secular fabric. Is India ready for it? Will it open a Pandora’s Box? Should we look at it through a religious prism? The opinions are sharply divided. The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 and the Banking Regulations Act, 1949 both prohibit the setting up of an Islamic banking system. Only an act of Parliament can set up one. In recent years, growth has sparked optimism about the future of Islamic finance. However, as competition intensifies, Islamic financial banks are still left with work to do. Most Islamic banks need to function more efficiently along the entire value chain, regardless of whether the strategy is aimed at entering a niche market, at competing with traditional banks or at both. They need to scrutinise strategic choices and focus on operational basics to grab unused market opportunities and overcome the changing dynamics of the industry. In all, Islamic finance is still at a nascent stage which is yet to meet its full potential.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Housing -The Millennial Pipe Dream</title>
      <link href="/The-Millennial-Pipe-Dream" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Housing -The Millennial Pipe Dream" />
      <published>2019-07-12T16:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-12T16:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Millennial-Pipe-Dream</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Millennial-Pipe-Dream">&lt;p&gt;“Like generations before them, the demographic cohort known as the millennials …
has shaped a number of social and cultural aspects, including fashion,
technology, and politics,” wrote The Fed. “One area where they’re facing
challenges in leaving their mark, however, is the economy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty years ago, the median price of a regular condominium settlement in an
American city was $108,900. Now, the figure is at $337,200. Even if one
accounts for inflation, the price has still risen astronomically, despite the
fact that the current working demographic cohort, the millennials, have
exhibited an involuntary disinclination towards homeownership, which is
reflected in the shift of the median age of homeownership from 29 in the 1970’s
to 33 presently. This global behavioural shift is attributed to more than just
the generation gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One would assume that it was the Boomers and the Gen Xers who were the hardest
hit when the housing bubble burst a decade ago, for they lost the jobs and bore
the fury of the deflated real estate and stock market. But the millennials, then
aged between their pre-teens to early 20s, had their average age of graduation
in 2010, right in the midst of the global economic meltdown. Naturally, when
they joined the workforce, the job market was rough, with lower wages and puny
scope for raises. Additionally, there was a lack of income stability, since it’s
common for most millennials to switch jobs at least three times in the five
years that follow graduation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, however, is not entirely a question of affordability, for, even
comparatively better-off millennials, earning over $50,000 a year, have chosen
not to purchase a home. Real estate is not an ‘impulse’ purchase. Many young
graduates already have the burden of student loans that overwhelms the benefits
of going to college, and upsets the debt-to-income ratio and their credit score,
despite having a reasonably good income level. As a result, it becomes harder
for them to acquire loans with easy down payment terms. Moreover, post the
foreclosure of millions of American homes during the Great Recession, new
lending reforms were implemented by most of the developed nations, like the
Dodd-Frank Act in the USA, which further exacerbated the down payment
requirements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another survey found that the millennials had an average tipping point of at
least five years of rental residentship before they would decide to purchase a
home in the area, and by this logic, even the older segment of the millennials
would have made a decision to own a home post-2013. And, at that point, the
easing of the global economy had begun to recede, and rate hikes were soon on
the table, thus making Adjustable Rate Mortgage an unattractive option, due to
the loss that would accompany the refinancing process. These economic
fluctuations at such a delicate transition point in life definitely had a
subconscious impact on the minds of young millennials, who have turned
risk-averse. Consequently, the tendency of careful considerations has
accompanied their decisions in most avenues of life, ranging from commitment to
a family to an investment like real estate. The Boomers have accused the
‘crypto-crazed’ millennials of destroying the housing markets, when in fact,
they are becoming victims to the vicious cycle of the renting market. As a
result of the unaffordability, a greater number of millennials are moving to the
rental space, pushing up the demand and thus the rents, which then lowers their
savings, and further delays homeownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it would not be fair to entirely blame the Great Recession for the modern
housing crisis. Urban sprawling is at its peak. Currently, 54% of the global
population lives in cities, and another 2.5 billion people are expected to be
added to this figure by 2050. The scarce land contributes to the skyrocketing
prices of accommodation, and there is a limit to which the cities can grow
vertically. This limit is not merely a variable of the architectural abilities
but also depends on the return factor. While most big cities have the ability to
build high skyscrapers, it becomes unaffordable once the government weighs in
all the indirect costs. When you graph the marginal construction costs against
the number of floors on the abscissa, it gives out a familiar U-shaped curve,
whose viability lies at the bottom-most point (only cost is considered, because
the return from public residential projects is one-time and only aims to cover
costs). Another reason that tall buildings are being avoided, is the NIMBYism
(Not in my backyard) displayed by the existing residents, who oppose progressive
developmental projects, citing how it would contribute to greater pollution,
rising traffic and would deflate the price of their properties. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The working population, largely composed of millennials, battles the crisis not
only in the usual suspect cities like NY, Tokyo, Hong Kong, London, Mumbai etc.,
but also has to face it in other smaller cities like Dubai. The crisis takes an
especially risky turn when it comes to the developing nations, where a
combination of bureaucratic red tape and rapidly growing population clamps
people down to an impoverished existence. Take the example of Mumbai, India,
about which the Scottish urban planner Patrick Geddes had famously remarked,
“Mumbai is not housing its workers, it’s warehousing them”. Nearly 52% of this
city’s population lives on 9% of its land, in informal settlements called slums.
Many of these slum-dwellers are educated people working in MNCs, who can afford
monthly dine-ins at the most high-end restaurants in the city, but not a decent
settlement. The slums appear to be a poverty problem for Asia, when they
actually are a real estate problem. The crisis is mainly associated with two
flawed policies. The city has an unnaturally low Floor-Space Index (FSI) at 1.3,
while cities in other Asian nations flourish at an average FSI of 7-8. The FSI
is the ratio of the floor area to the plot area. So an FSI of, say, 2, would
allow us to construct two stories if the process includes the entire plot area,
and four stories if we leave half the plot vacant. The next flawed policy for
Mumbai is one that has been famously dubbed the easiest way to destroy a city,
next only to a bombing - rent control. The rent is frozen at pre-Independence
levels, robbing landowners of any incentive to rent it out to tenants in fear of
encroachment. Such a policy often results in the formation of dilapidated ghost
towns, which has happened to many cities of China, Turkey, and the like. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, governments all over the world have come to the rescue of the working
millennials with rash and hasty policies like rent control, which have only
exacerbated the situation. The lack of attention and forethought that a basic
amenity like housing faces globally is an important contributor to a class
divide in modern cities, resulting in other socio-economic issues. Shirish B.
Patel, an urban planner, in his piece in the &lt;em&gt;Economic and Political Weekly&lt;/em&gt;,
had perfectly summed up the situation of the working class millennials of the
cities with the analogy of a big ship, which has many workers, who perform every
petty to intricate task on board, throughout the day, for which the captain pays
them well, but does not allow them to spend the night on the ship. If they
manage to survive the night in water, without getting eaten by the sharks, they
must report to work the next morning. If not, there are plenty of fish in the
sea.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Like generations before them, the demographic cohort known as the millennials … has shaped a number of social and cultural aspects, including fashion, technology, and politics,” wrote The Fed. “One area where they’re facing challenges in leaving their mark, however, is the economy.” Twenty years ago, the median price of a regular condominium settlement in an American city was $108,900. Now, the figure is at $337,200. Even if one accounts for inflation, the price has still risen astronomically, despite the fact that the current working demographic cohort, the millennials, have exhibited an involuntary disinclination towards homeownership, which is reflected in the shift of the median age of homeownership from 29 in the 1970’s to 33 presently. This global behavioural shift is attributed to more than just the generation gap. One would assume that it was the Boomers and the Gen Xers who were the hardest hit when the housing bubble burst a decade ago, for they lost the jobs and bore the fury of the deflated real estate and stock market. But the millennials, then aged between their pre-teens to early 20s, had their average age of graduation in 2010, right in the midst of the global economic meltdown. Naturally, when they joined the workforce, the job market was rough, with lower wages and puny scope for raises. Additionally, there was a lack of income stability, since it’s common for most millennials to switch jobs at least three times in the five years that follow graduation.  This, however, is not entirely a question of affordability, for, even comparatively better-off millennials, earning over $50,000 a year, have chosen not to purchase a home. Real estate is not an ‘impulse’ purchase. Many young graduates already have the burden of student loans that overwhelms the benefits of going to college, and upsets the debt-to-income ratio and their credit score, despite having a reasonably good income level. As a result, it becomes harder for them to acquire loans with easy down payment terms. Moreover, post the foreclosure of millions of American homes during the Great Recession, new lending reforms were implemented by most of the developed nations, like the Dodd-Frank Act in the USA, which further exacerbated the down payment requirements.  Another survey found that the millennials had an average tipping point of at least five years of rental residentship before they would decide to purchase a home in the area, and by this logic, even the older segment of the millennials would have made a decision to own a home post-2013. And, at that point, the easing of the global economy had begun to recede, and rate hikes were soon on the table, thus making Adjustable Rate Mortgage an unattractive option, due to the loss that would accompany the refinancing process. These economic fluctuations at such a delicate transition point in life definitely had a subconscious impact on the minds of young millennials, who have turned risk-averse. Consequently, the tendency of careful considerations has accompanied their decisions in most avenues of life, ranging from commitment to a family to an investment like real estate. The Boomers have accused the ‘crypto-crazed’ millennials of destroying the housing markets, when in fact, they are becoming victims to the vicious cycle of the renting market. As a result of the unaffordability, a greater number of millennials are moving to the rental space, pushing up the demand and thus the rents, which then lowers their savings, and further delays homeownership. But it would not be fair to entirely blame the Great Recession for the modern housing crisis. Urban sprawling is at its peak. Currently, 54% of the global population lives in cities, and another 2.5 billion people are expected to be added to this figure by 2050. The scarce land contributes to the skyrocketing prices of accommodation, and there is a limit to which the cities can grow vertically. This limit is not merely a variable of the architectural abilities but also depends on the return factor. While most big cities have the ability to build high skyscrapers, it becomes unaffordable once the government weighs in all the indirect costs. When you graph the marginal construction costs against the number of floors on the abscissa, it gives out a familiar U-shaped curve, whose viability lies at the bottom-most point (only cost is considered, because the return from public residential projects is one-time and only aims to cover costs). Another reason that tall buildings are being avoided, is the NIMBYism (Not in my backyard) displayed by the existing residents, who oppose progressive developmental projects, citing how it would contribute to greater pollution, rising traffic and would deflate the price of their properties.  The working population, largely composed of millennials, battles the crisis not only in the usual suspect cities like NY, Tokyo, Hong Kong, London, Mumbai etc., but also has to face it in other smaller cities like Dubai. The crisis takes an especially risky turn when it comes to the developing nations, where a combination of bureaucratic red tape and rapidly growing population clamps people down to an impoverished existence. Take the example of Mumbai, India, about which the Scottish urban planner Patrick Geddes had famously remarked, “Mumbai is not housing its workers, it’s warehousing them”. Nearly 52% of this city’s population lives on 9% of its land, in informal settlements called slums. Many of these slum-dwellers are educated people working in MNCs, who can afford monthly dine-ins at the most high-end restaurants in the city, but not a decent settlement. The slums appear to be a poverty problem for Asia, when they actually are a real estate problem. The crisis is mainly associated with two flawed policies. The city has an unnaturally low Floor-Space Index (FSI) at 1.3, while cities in other Asian nations flourish at an average FSI of 7-8. The FSI is the ratio of the floor area to the plot area. So an FSI of, say, 2, would allow us to construct two stories if the process includes the entire plot area, and four stories if we leave half the plot vacant. The next flawed policy for Mumbai is one that has been famously dubbed the easiest way to destroy a city, next only to a bombing - rent control. The rent is frozen at pre-Independence levels, robbing landowners of any incentive to rent it out to tenants in fear of encroachment. Such a policy often results in the formation of dilapidated ghost towns, which has happened to many cities of China, Turkey, and the like.  Clearly, governments all over the world have come to the rescue of the working millennials with rash and hasty policies like rent control, which have only exacerbated the situation. The lack of attention and forethought that a basic amenity like housing faces globally is an important contributor to a class divide in modern cities, resulting in other socio-economic issues. Shirish B. Patel, an urban planner, in his piece in the Economic and Political Weekly, had perfectly summed up the situation of the working class millennials of the cities with the analogy of a big ship, which has many workers, who perform every petty to intricate task on board, throughout the day, for which the captain pays them well, but does not allow them to spend the night on the ship. If they manage to survive the night in water, without getting eaten by the sharks, they must report to work the next morning. If not, there are plenty of fish in the sea.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The State of the Millennial in 2019</title>
      <link href="/The-State-of-the-Millennial-in-2019" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The State of the Millennial in 2019" />
      <published>2019-07-07T01:40:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-07T01:40:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-State-of-the-Millennial-in-2019</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-State-of-the-Millennial-in-2019">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Millennials (smh). Pampered and nurtured by parents, trying to avoid the
mistakes of a previous generation. You are late to graduate, late to marry and
late to have children. You’re even late to find a job (IF you find a job). To
this ever-determined and ambitious generation, we dedicate the series, ‘for’ and
‘by’ the Millennials, who are most likely still living with their parents. It’s
time we spoke about our host of issues, Gen-Y style.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a Millennial, you &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be angry. Also, if you’re a Millennial
who’s about to hit the job market, I’ve got disappointing news for you. The
Millennial unemployment rate now stands at an &lt;a href=&quot;https://americansforprosperity.org/?utm_source=GO&amp;amp;utm_medium=banner&amp;amp;utm_campaign=redirect&amp;amp;utm_content=main&quot;&gt;astounding
12.8%&lt;/a&gt;,
dwarfing the US national average. Furthermore, if you are a Millennial who has
gone through the past decade unemployed or not, you have also had to endure the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Counting-down-the-biggest-economic&quot;&gt;biggest financial
disaster&lt;/a&gt; of the past
half-century, so kudos to you for sticking around and having a firsthand account
of the experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were robbed, I tell you. The Millennials were supposed to be the ‘greatest
generation’ yet, the most technologically advanced and by far the most educated
generation ever. We were expected to come in and revolutionise the industry, do
away with the old-fashioned and bear the torch of progress. Well, so much for
trying. We have still not cracked into the industry as smoothly as we would have
wanted. Employers are unsatisfied with our over-expectant attitudes (Note: most
of them being baby-boomers, the slackers of Generation X never made it).
Overall, it has been a struggle. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, we are hard to please, overconfident and maybe a tad bit narcissistic.
We dream too much about having it all, without taking our daily dose of reality.
Flashy cars, jewellery, big condos, champagne and caviar. Well, that’s what was
sold to us ever since we got on to &lt;em&gt;MTV&lt;/em&gt; or were young enough to watch
television. We also focus too much on ourselves, often losing track of the &lt;em&gt;‘Big
Picture’.&lt;/em&gt; But we never had to answer the call of the GI generation or the
rallying cry of growth and economic development in the 80’s and 90’s. How often
were you taught to think as a generation, and not as individuals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter what, one thing is for sure. The Millennial Generation or Gen-Y as it
is called, is the most highly educated generation to date, and we are definitely
proud of it. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2018/03/16/how-millennials-compare-with-their-grandparents/ft_millennials-education_031715/&quot;&gt;Pew Research
Center&lt;/a&gt;
recently conducted a study showing that 21% and 27% of men and women (aged
18-33) had a college degree, as compared to the Baby Boomers (17% and 14%) and
Generation X (18% and 20%). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Oh, what do I hear? We aren’t learning interpersonal and communication skills?
Really?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True adulthood only hits us when we realize that these numbers do not mean
anything to the people hiring out there. They say we lack team building and the
ability to communicate effectively, and are more adept at theoretical knowledge
than actual applicable skills. Which in essence is saying that our school and
college education did not really help us at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, that just rubs us off the wrong way, especially with how
increasingly expensive university education has become, with ballooning student
debt plaguing much of the Western world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If the employer is just having a problem with me and my ways, then guess what,
I quit!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://66.media.tumblr.com/504bc9dab4a70c6c69a5696be0456568/tumblr_n22rf1CVMY1tq4of6o1_500.gif&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//lalalala.gif&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there lies another innate flaw deep within us. Maybe, it is
because a lot of us are still young and haven’t grown out of the habit of
denial. But for many, it is very hard for us to come to terms with our
shortcomings. Much too often we will just dismiss them, or much worse, put the
blame on the employer. But as we all know, that’s just a quicker way to get the
boot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are to make up ground, and reach our expectations (sky high!), we will
have to adjust to the ways of the world and not be so adamant as we strive to
perfection. But why ‘perfection’? Why are we so obsessed with getting it right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/shohan.mukherjee/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//millennials1.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer lies with the world that has been built by the last generation to
earn the ‘greatest’ title before us: the baby boomers. As baby boomers emerged
from childhood, they soon had a very jolting experience into the foray of the
professional worker. Their journey into adulthood was not as long and smoothed
out as ours. Most of them emerged from the growing middle class, at a time when
countries all across the world were engaged in a GDP scoring competition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, most of this generation were thrust directly into the workforce and found
a way to sustain themselves, thanks to their resilient nature. They ended up
earning far more than their parents, a trend which had been continuing since the
1900’s. Later on in life, most of them ended up giving birth to Generation X as
well as the Millennials. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it seems like the buck stops here, as the Millennials are suited to be the
first generation to earn &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; than their parents. It is not a surprise that
rising difficulties to secure a job coupling with employment opportunities
bottoming out post the Great Recession have led to employment protests
throughout Europe, the USA and Asia. And although Millennials are believed to be
far more open-minded and tolerant, the dire circumstances have led to growing
support for right-wing politics in many European and South Asian nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The super-saturated job market has lead to increasingly weird paradoxes. Here’s
one story from &lt;em&gt;The Huffington Post&lt;/em&gt;, which could be one of many:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“I was literally paying to work,” says Elena, a 29-year-old dietician in Texas.
As part of her master’s degree, she was required to do a yearlong “internship”
in a hospital. It was supposed to be training, but she says she worked the same
hours and did the same tasks as paid staffers. “I took out an extra \$20,000 in
student loans to pay tuition for the year I was working for free,” she says.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse yet, with the increase of contractor companies which deal especially in
security, storage and inventory management, or housekeeping activities, the
future of low-income workers is further at risk. Take the example of Mr Joe, the
security guard at the mall, who is actually signed to a contractor that has
inked a deal with the mall. In this way, the mall just has to pay the contractor
and not the individual person who is doing the job. This cuts out a lot of costs
including any form of pension or benefits. Of course, that goes out of Mr Joe’s
pocket. And out goes any form of career advancement either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Princeton-LSE grad Michael Lewis made a fortune and a legacy out of his book,
&lt;em&gt;Liar’s Poker&lt;/em&gt;, which details the rise of Lewie Ranieri and his team of traders
who made big money at Salomon Brothers back in the late-80’s. In the book he
often spoke of back office workers, including people who worked the fax and
xerox machines, later trying their hand at trading for the company after slowly
rising through the ranks over the years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, thanks to him for documenting another list of practices that went out the
window during the Financial Crisis. You can wave goodbye to that sort of career
mobility in the 21st century. After all, the Great Crash of 2008 was all about
under-skilled people working over-skilled jobs. Look at where we have arrived
now with the current wave of Millennial underemployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is because of things like these that we fear a slip up so much, even a little
one, that could send us hurtling down the tunnel of underemployment,
unemployment, and at last, poverty. No, no, don’t laugh, this is serious. You
might not have gotten out of your post-sack funk by the time you realise that
you have fallen below the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sanford.duke.edu/people/faculty/krishna-anirudh&quot;&gt;Anirudh Krishna&lt;/a&gt;, a
professor at Duke University, has documented over 1,000 cases of people who fell
into poverty, and only some of whom managed to escape it. He conducted his
search throughout India and Kenya, and revealed that poverty arises from a
series of mishaps. One broken leg, one lost job, one sick family member and you
find yourself below the line. And it is this chance of slipping (literally),
coupled with humongous college and healthcare costs, that force us Millennials
to hope against hope to strive for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inverse.com/article/53091-millennials-largest-ever-perfectionism-study&quot;&gt;perfection at every living
moment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, here we stand at the brink of a period of flux and change. Our
generation’s defining moment has come and gone in 2008, we are just afraid
another one might &lt;a href=&quot;http://fortune.com/2019/06/04/next-recession-2020-predictions/&quot;&gt;come along too
soon&lt;/a&gt;. We might
well be the first generation in decades to earn less than our parents. We will
delay our marriages as well as moving out of home. Yes, buying a home now is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://globalnews.ca/news/3230146/numbers-show-its-harder-for-millennials-to-buy-a-home-than-it-was-for-their-parents/&quot;&gt;exponentially
tougher&lt;/a&gt;
than 30 years ago. Deal with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/jan/05/perfectionism-mental-health-millennial-social-media&quot;&gt;a
problem&lt;/a&gt;
with that? We don’t, we have no choice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the future (FML).&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shohan Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Millennials (smh). Pampered and nurtured by parents, trying to avoid the mistakes of a previous generation. You are late to graduate, late to marry and late to have children. You’re even late to find a job (IF you find a job). To this ever-determined and ambitious generation, we dedicate the series, ‘for’ and ‘by’ the Millennials, who are most likely still living with their parents. It’s time we spoke about our host of issues, Gen-Y style. If you are a Millennial, you should be angry. Also, if you’re a Millennial who’s about to hit the job market, I’ve got disappointing news for you. The Millennial unemployment rate now stands at an astounding 12.8%, dwarfing the US national average. Furthermore, if you are a Millennial who has gone through the past decade unemployed or not, you have also had to endure the biggest financial disaster of the past half-century, so kudos to you for sticking around and having a firsthand account of the experience. We were robbed, I tell you. The Millennials were supposed to be the ‘greatest generation’ yet, the most technologically advanced and by far the most educated generation ever. We were expected to come in and revolutionise the industry, do away with the old-fashioned and bear the torch of progress. Well, so much for trying. We have still not cracked into the industry as smoothly as we would have wanted. Employers are unsatisfied with our over-expectant attitudes (Note: most of them being baby-boomers, the slackers of Generation X never made it). Overall, it has been a struggle.  Alright, we are hard to please, overconfident and maybe a tad bit narcissistic. We dream too much about having it all, without taking our daily dose of reality. Flashy cars, jewellery, big condos, champagne and caviar. Well, that’s what was sold to us ever since we got on to MTV or were young enough to watch television. We also focus too much on ourselves, often losing track of the ‘Big Picture’. But we never had to answer the call of the GI generation or the rallying cry of growth and economic development in the 80’s and 90’s. How often were you taught to think as a generation, and not as individuals? No matter what, one thing is for sure. The Millennial Generation or Gen-Y as it is called, is the most highly educated generation to date, and we are definitely proud of it. The Pew Research Center recently conducted a study showing that 21% and 27% of men and women (aged 18-33) had a college degree, as compared to the Baby Boomers (17% and 14%) and Generation X (18% and 20%).  “Oh, what do I hear? We aren’t learning interpersonal and communication skills? Really?” True adulthood only hits us when we realize that these numbers do not mean anything to the people hiring out there. They say we lack team building and the ability to communicate effectively, and are more adept at theoretical knowledge than actual applicable skills. Which in essence is saying that our school and college education did not really help us at all. To be honest, that just rubs us off the wrong way, especially with how increasingly expensive university education has become, with ballooning student debt plaguing much of the Western world.  “If the employer is just having a problem with me and my ways, then guess what, I quit!” Unfortunately, there lies another innate flaw deep within us. Maybe, it is because a lot of us are still young and haven’t grown out of the habit of denial. But for many, it is very hard for us to come to terms with our shortcomings. Much too often we will just dismiss them, or much worse, put the blame on the employer. But as we all know, that’s just a quicker way to get the boot! If we are to make up ground, and reach our expectations (sky high!), we will have to adjust to the ways of the world and not be so adamant as we strive to perfection. But why ‘perfection’? Why are we so obsessed with getting it right? The answer lies with the world that has been built by the last generation to earn the ‘greatest’ title before us: the baby boomers. As baby boomers emerged from childhood, they soon had a very jolting experience into the foray of the professional worker. Their journey into adulthood was not as long and smoothed out as ours. Most of them emerged from the growing middle class, at a time when countries all across the world were engaged in a GDP scoring competition.  Thus, most of this generation were thrust directly into the workforce and found a way to sustain themselves, thanks to their resilient nature. They ended up earning far more than their parents, a trend which had been continuing since the 1900’s. Later on in life, most of them ended up giving birth to Generation X as well as the Millennials.  But it seems like the buck stops here, as the Millennials are suited to be the first generation to earn less than their parents. It is not a surprise that rising difficulties to secure a job coupling with employment opportunities bottoming out post the Great Recession have led to employment protests throughout Europe, the USA and Asia. And although Millennials are believed to be far more open-minded and tolerant, the dire circumstances have led to growing support for right-wing politics in many European and South Asian nations. The super-saturated job market has lead to increasingly weird paradoxes. Here’s one story from The Huffington Post, which could be one of many: “I was literally paying to work,” says Elena, a 29-year-old dietician in Texas. As part of her master’s degree, she was required to do a yearlong “internship” in a hospital. It was supposed to be training, but she says she worked the same hours and did the same tasks as paid staffers. “I took out an extra \$20,000 in student loans to pay tuition for the year I was working for free,” she says. Worse yet, with the increase of contractor companies which deal especially in security, storage and inventory management, or housekeeping activities, the future of low-income workers is further at risk. Take the example of Mr Joe, the security guard at the mall, who is actually signed to a contractor that has inked a deal with the mall. In this way, the mall just has to pay the contractor and not the individual person who is doing the job. This cuts out a lot of costs including any form of pension or benefits. Of course, that goes out of Mr Joe’s pocket. And out goes any form of career advancement either. Princeton-LSE grad Michael Lewis made a fortune and a legacy out of his book, Liar’s Poker, which details the rise of Lewie Ranieri and his team of traders who made big money at Salomon Brothers back in the late-80’s. In the book he often spoke of back office workers, including people who worked the fax and xerox machines, later trying their hand at trading for the company after slowly rising through the ranks over the years.  Well, thanks to him for documenting another list of practices that went out the window during the Financial Crisis. You can wave goodbye to that sort of career mobility in the 21st century. After all, the Great Crash of 2008 was all about under-skilled people working over-skilled jobs. Look at where we have arrived now with the current wave of Millennial underemployment. It is because of things like these that we fear a slip up so much, even a little one, that could send us hurtling down the tunnel of underemployment, unemployment, and at last, poverty. No, no, don’t laugh, this is serious. You might not have gotten out of your post-sack funk by the time you realise that you have fallen below the line. Anirudh Krishna, a professor at Duke University, has documented over 1,000 cases of people who fell into poverty, and only some of whom managed to escape it. He conducted his search throughout India and Kenya, and revealed that poverty arises from a series of mishaps. One broken leg, one lost job, one sick family member and you find yourself below the line. And it is this chance of slipping (literally), coupled with humongous college and healthcare costs, that force us Millennials to hope against hope to strive for perfection at every living moment. Thus, here we stand at the brink of a period of flux and change. Our generation’s defining moment has come and gone in 2008, we are just afraid another one might come along too soon. We might well be the first generation in decades to earn less than our parents. We will delay our marriages as well as moving out of home. Yes, buying a home now is exponentially tougher than 30 years ago. Deal with it. And you have a problem with that? We don’t, we have no choice.  Welcome to the future (FML).</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Middle Income Trap and How India Must Avert It</title>
      <link href="/The-Middle-Income-Trap" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Middle Income Trap and How India Must Avert It" />
      <published>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Middle-Income-Trap</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Middle-Income-Trap">&lt;p&gt;While the &lt;em&gt;Mahatyohar&lt;/em&gt; (Read: General Elections) of the Indian nation concluded
with a staggering majority for the incumbent BJP, it was immediately followed by
the official revelation of certain important economic indicators that were
perhaps obscured in a mist of uncertainty during the election campaign.
Nevertheless, the unemployment rate was revealed to be at a four-decade high of
6.1% while the GDP growth rate of 2019 Q1 has dropped to nearly 5.8% after a
decline in the consumption expenditure for automobile and real estate, which
explains the recent 0.2% reduction in the IMF growth projections for India as
compared to its previous assessment in January. The growth concerns have put
more interest rate cuts by the Reserve Bank of India on the radar, and have
pushed its stance from neutral to accommodative. And while all these deviations
can be credited to the global slowdown that is being projected for 2019 as a
part of the generic economic cycle, for emerging nations like India this could
indicate the end to an era of rapid economic convergence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, amidst the chaos of the Indian elections, Rathin Roy, Director of the
National Institute of Public Finance and Policy, highlighted a bipartisan issue
of long term stagnation that the Indian economy might soon have to confront. He
identified that the long term growth of the nation is primarily spurred by what
the top 10% income bracket of the population consumes. This was good enough to
lift India to the group of lower-middle income nations back in 2008 when the per
capita income rose above $1005 for the first time. But now, this group has
become a major hindrance to reaching the upper-middle-income bracket that ranges
from $3,956 to $12,235 per capita. In order to cross this threshold, the
economy must witness a structural transformation of the non-luxury good
industries, on which the majority of the Indian population depends. Roy states
that while aspects like infrastructure, microfinance, etc. are being dealt with
by the government’s &lt;em&gt;PM Awas Yojana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;PM Mudra Yojana&lt;/em&gt; schemes respectively,
it is agriculture that clearly needs to undergo a proper revival to ameliorate
the productivity of the most basic non-luxury good; foodgrain, for which we’re
becoming increasingly dependent. Other aspects like technology and human capital
development require immediate attention for escaping the Middle Income Trap that
we’re heading into. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Middle Income Trap is an economic phenomenon that states how a poor nation
makes significant progress on its way to becoming a middle-income nation but
then finds it harder to take the shape of a fully developed, high-income nation.
This phenomenon is more frequent than one would assume. Only 13 of the 101
nations deemed to be middle-income countries in the 1960’s had achieved
high-income levels by 2011. The failure of the rest of the nations is primarily
attributed to the rising domestic wages, failure to invest in human capital,
lack of innovation and issues with macroeconomic stability. While the latter is
comparatively under control and any recent macroeconomic discrepancies have been
exogenous to the powers of the central bank, the remaining three are extremely
crucial yet underrated issues in the Indian economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roy identifies that labour-intensive business investments are increasingly being
channelled towards nations like Bangladesh, even though their wages are similar
to those of East Indian states like Bihar, Jharkhand, etc. But there, the labour
is scarce due to mass migrations towards the western states where minimum wages
are much higher, a policy which had contributed to the early popularity the
current PM Modi, during his tenure as the Chief Minister of the western state of
Gujarat. Although it is difficult to revert such populist policies, the issue of
high wages has the ability to resolve itself in time, as the nation’s
demographic structure changes, with more people contributing to the labour
supply. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the development of human capital, the current share of education-related
expenditure in India’s Union Budget is a mere 3%, much lower than the minimum 6%
required for the basic functioning of the education system, let alone its
restructuring. Innovation was encouraged through government initiatives like
&lt;em&gt;Startup India&lt;/em&gt;, which badly backfired as the government failed to encourage
investors by perpetuating the regressive Angel Tax, which charged venture
capitalists on any amount invested over and above the government’s faulty
valuation of the startups. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An observation similar to Rathin Roy’s was made in the Economic Survey of
2017-18, which identified the threat of a ‘Late Converger Stall’ that India will
have to tackle on its way to the upper-middle-income status. Economic
convergence, which is the process of developing economies catching up with the
developed ones, is divided into phases. There have been early convergers like
Japan and South Korea, who managed to take advantage of their cheap labour and
efficient productivity in time, and then there are late convergers like India,
who did not open their economy to global opportunities until the eleventh hour
and must now bear the consequences. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Economic Survey identified the major headwinds that were absent for the
early convergers and could now lead to a growth stall for the late convergers.
Hyper globalisation repudiation due to a growing sentiment of protectionism was
absent during the early convergers period, which gave Japan, China, and South
Korea, an average export boost of over 15% during their convergence period. The
global trade-to-GDP ratio is on a decline since 2011, which, from a policy
perspective, means that the late convergers must now focus more on enhancing
private investments to boost growth. Another factor identified by the survey was
the thwarted structural transformation due to wrongly channelising resources
from low productivity sectors to marginally more productive sectors rather than
high productivity sectors. Sectors like finance, technology, and other
professional services must be tapped for overcoming the stagnation.
Additionally, climate-change-induced agricultural stress and regression of human
capital are also some of the major issues that need to be addressed with greater
urgency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the middle-income trap can be avoided by both increasing domestic
demand or by boosting exports, India can only prioritise the former because
becoming an export-led economy would imply a current account surplus and capital
account deficit, and that would curb the FDI to the nation, which is evidently
undesirable for an Emerging Market Economy (EME). The policy mix of the
politically right government has, for the most part, comprised economically
left-leaning schemes combined with cleverly constructed, investment conducive
foreign policy. But that is not enough. India is one of the prime investment
destinations among its fellow EMEs, and we must fully take advantage of that
before the preferences, as they inevitably will, shift to the African nations,
for capital is faithful to none.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">While the Mahatyohar (Read: General Elections) of the Indian nation concluded with a staggering majority for the incumbent BJP, it was immediately followed by the official revelation of certain important economic indicators that were perhaps obscured in a mist of uncertainty during the election campaign. Nevertheless, the unemployment rate was revealed to be at a four-decade high of 6.1% while the GDP growth rate of 2019 Q1 has dropped to nearly 5.8% after a decline in the consumption expenditure for automobile and real estate, which explains the recent 0.2% reduction in the IMF growth projections for India as compared to its previous assessment in January. The growth concerns have put more interest rate cuts by the Reserve Bank of India on the radar, and have pushed its stance from neutral to accommodative. And while all these deviations can be credited to the global slowdown that is being projected for 2019 as a part of the generic economic cycle, for emerging nations like India this could indicate the end to an era of rapid economic convergence. Recently, amidst the chaos of the Indian elections, Rathin Roy, Director of the National Institute of Public Finance and Policy, highlighted a bipartisan issue of long term stagnation that the Indian economy might soon have to confront. He identified that the long term growth of the nation is primarily spurred by what the top 10% income bracket of the population consumes. This was good enough to lift India to the group of lower-middle income nations back in 2008 when the per capita income rose above $1005 for the first time. But now, this group has become a major hindrance to reaching the upper-middle-income bracket that ranges from $3,956 to $12,235 per capita. In order to cross this threshold, the economy must witness a structural transformation of the non-luxury good industries, on which the majority of the Indian population depends. Roy states that while aspects like infrastructure, microfinance, etc. are being dealt with by the government’s PM Awas Yojana and PM Mudra Yojana schemes respectively, it is agriculture that clearly needs to undergo a proper revival to ameliorate the productivity of the most basic non-luxury good; foodgrain, for which we’re becoming increasingly dependent. Other aspects like technology and human capital development require immediate attention for escaping the Middle Income Trap that we’re heading into.  The Middle Income Trap is an economic phenomenon that states how a poor nation makes significant progress on its way to becoming a middle-income nation but then finds it harder to take the shape of a fully developed, high-income nation. This phenomenon is more frequent than one would assume. Only 13 of the 101 nations deemed to be middle-income countries in the 1960’s had achieved high-income levels by 2011. The failure of the rest of the nations is primarily attributed to the rising domestic wages, failure to invest in human capital, lack of innovation and issues with macroeconomic stability. While the latter is comparatively under control and any recent macroeconomic discrepancies have been exogenous to the powers of the central bank, the remaining three are extremely crucial yet underrated issues in the Indian economy.  Roy identifies that labour-intensive business investments are increasingly being channelled towards nations like Bangladesh, even though their wages are similar to those of East Indian states like Bihar, Jharkhand, etc. But there, the labour is scarce due to mass migrations towards the western states where minimum wages are much higher, a policy which had contributed to the early popularity the current PM Modi, during his tenure as the Chief Minister of the western state of Gujarat. Although it is difficult to revert such populist policies, the issue of high wages has the ability to resolve itself in time, as the nation’s demographic structure changes, with more people contributing to the labour supply.  As for the development of human capital, the current share of education-related expenditure in India’s Union Budget is a mere 3%, much lower than the minimum 6% required for the basic functioning of the education system, let alone its restructuring. Innovation was encouraged through government initiatives like Startup India, which badly backfired as the government failed to encourage investors by perpetuating the regressive Angel Tax, which charged venture capitalists on any amount invested over and above the government’s faulty valuation of the startups.  An observation similar to Rathin Roy’s was made in the Economic Survey of 2017-18, which identified the threat of a ‘Late Converger Stall’ that India will have to tackle on its way to the upper-middle-income status. Economic convergence, which is the process of developing economies catching up with the developed ones, is divided into phases. There have been early convergers like Japan and South Korea, who managed to take advantage of their cheap labour and efficient productivity in time, and then there are late convergers like India, who did not open their economy to global opportunities until the eleventh hour and must now bear the consequences.  The Economic Survey identified the major headwinds that were absent for the early convergers and could now lead to a growth stall for the late convergers. Hyper globalisation repudiation due to a growing sentiment of protectionism was absent during the early convergers period, which gave Japan, China, and South Korea, an average export boost of over 15% during their convergence period. The global trade-to-GDP ratio is on a decline since 2011, which, from a policy perspective, means that the late convergers must now focus more on enhancing private investments to boost growth. Another factor identified by the survey was the thwarted structural transformation due to wrongly channelising resources from low productivity sectors to marginally more productive sectors rather than high productivity sectors. Sectors like finance, technology, and other professional services must be tapped for overcoming the stagnation. Additionally, climate-change-induced agricultural stress and regression of human capital are also some of the major issues that need to be addressed with greater urgency. Although the middle-income trap can be avoided by both increasing domestic demand or by boosting exports, India can only prioritise the former because becoming an export-led economy would imply a current account surplus and capital account deficit, and that would curb the FDI to the nation, which is evidently undesirable for an Emerging Market Economy (EME). The policy mix of the politically right government has, for the most part, comprised economically left-leaning schemes combined with cleverly constructed, investment conducive foreign policy. But that is not enough. India is one of the prime investment destinations among its fellow EMEs, and we must fully take advantage of that before the preferences, as they inevitably will, shift to the African nations, for capital is faithful to none.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Africa Sees a New Dawn</title>
      <link href="/Africa-Sees-a-New-Dawn" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Africa Sees a New Dawn" />
      <published>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Africa-Sees-a-New-Dawn</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Africa-Sees-a-New-Dawn">&lt;p&gt;As the US and China are engaged in a trade war, and debates about the
unpredictability of relationships between the EU and Britain continue to linger,
the continent of Africa is taking steps to create a close-knit relationship to
realise the vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063. On May 30, 2019, the
African Continental Free Trade Agreement (AfCFTA) came into force after being
ratified by the parliaments of 24 countries. The CFTA is an attempt by the
African governments to “unlock Africa’s tremendous potential” and deliver
prosperity to all Africans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AfCFTA seeks to create a single unified African continental market for goods and
services with free movement of business, people and investment. The AfCFTA will
bring together all 55 member states of the African Union covering a market of
more than 1.2 billion people and a combined GDP of more than $3.4 trillion. In
terms of the number of participating countries, the AfCFTA will be the world’s
largest free trade area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single market for goods and services enables free movement of goods, services,
and labour from one country to another. Trade among the 55 African Union member
states is only 18% of the total exports from the continent. A free market
improves these numbers prodigiously. Improved intra-continental trade would
benefit the consumers across the continent, as the goods and services would
become relatively cheaper. This increases the real income of consumers, part of
which again is spent. The ambitious project seeks to remove tariffs on 90% of
the goods traded between the signatories to the agreement, and gradually
eliminate other non-tariff barriers to trade in goods and services. As an
economist would argue, removal of these barriers would increase the producer and
consumer surplus, and overall efficiency of these economies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The manufacturing sector is the backbone of Africa. The new agreement promotes
competition among the firms and aids Africa in unlocking its true potential and
thus boosting its export of manufactured goods to the rest of the world. The
relatively small size of many African markets is one of the reasons that inhibit
private sector investment. A unified market will enable the continent to attract
foreign direct investment. By and large, these would lead to an increase in
consumption and investment components and add to an overall increase in GDP.  By
2030, the African market size is expected to reach 1.7 billion people, with a
combined consumer and business spending of $6.7 trillion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A study by UNCTAD concedes that the long term monetary benefits that AfCFTA
shall yield are annual welfare gains as high as $16 billion. Estimates from the
UN Economic Commission for Africa (UNECA) suggest that the AfCFTA has the
potential to boost intra-African trade by 52.3%. There’s a substantial amount of
evidence to show that free movement boosts the economies of countries. A study
has shown that nations could increase their per-capita GDP growth by 12%, simply
by being a member of the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AfCFTA document says one of its goals is to “foster a competitive
manufacturing sector and promote economic diversification”. Even as 43% of the
goods traded within Africa are from the manufacturing sector, it represents only
about 10% of the total GDP in Africa, lagging behind other developing countries.
Africa’s low level of intra-regional trade is one of the reasons for the
continent’s enduring poverty and lack of a strong manufacturing base. The
African economies can, therefore, leverage their gigantic population size of 1.2
billion to expand their manufacturing sector and gain a comparative cost
advantage over other nations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from AfCFTA, there are some Regional Economic Communities (REC) in Africa
such as ECA, SADC, ECOWAS, and COMESCA. While ECOWAS was quite successful, the
other blocs have problems. Disputes continue to hamper relations and drive the
countries toward not honouring agreements. For instance, Kenya and Tanzania,
both members of ECA, have been engaged in a trade war. Tanzania has been known
to kick out Kenyan executives and impound Kenyan imports at the border, in
violation of ECA rules. While Tanzania scrapped preferential access to Kenyan
textiles, Kenya allowed goods from Export Processing Zones to be sold in local
markets, which prevented Tanzanian goods from being competitive. Members of
COMESCA, Kenya, Tanzania and Uganda have also been blaming each other for
exploiting the low import duties on sugar. That AfCFTA doesn’t have a clause to
repeal all the existing trade blocs would prove a real challenge as it creates
ambiguity. Then there is also the threat of countries acting in favour of their
trading partners from “the regional blocs.” The success of the agreement depends
on how efficiently the AU deals with these RECs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AfCFTA is to face some more challenges. The two largest economies of Africa,
Nigeria and South Africa haven’t ratified the agreement yet. South Africa has
assured that it would sign it once domestic legal requirements have been
satisfied. However, Nigeria backed out from signing the agreement citing “the
agreement would drastically affect the small business sector of the country.”
“We will not agree to anything that will undermine local manufacturers and
entrepreneurs, or that may lead to Nigeria becoming a dumping ground for
finished goods,” Nigeria has stated. The pervasive nature of Small and Medium
Enterprises (SMEs) in virtually every sector of the Nigerian economy and their
place in national development is conspicuous. SMEs in Nigeria are believed to
account for about 40% of GDP and 70% of industrial employment. Rice is also a
factor that is preventing the largest African economy from signing the deal. 
Due to various government initiatives, rice is starting to command 40% more
price than what it used to 3 years back in the Nigerian markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly,  Nigeria would largely benefit from signing the deal. With a
rapidly growing population of almost 200 million, Nigeria has more workers and
consumers than anywhere in Africa. For many businesses, there is no other place
in Africa that can offer such a scale. This will provide a competitive advantage
to Nigeria in firms’ considerations of where to set up facilities and do
business. AfCFTA will expose local Nigerian firms to better practices and
technologies, often through partnerships with the MNCs and sometimes through
competition. This sort of exposure will challenge entrepreneurs in the country
and give them greater access to the skills and partnerships they need to be
dynamic in today’s world. By giving businesses access to a larger market beyond
their home country, the trade agreement would allow the establishments in
Nigeria (that are not profitable now) to take advantage of the economies of
scale and industries to take advantage of the growth in intra-Africa relations.
Remaining a non-signatory to the agreement might cost Nigeria dearly. The
country’s isolation makes it difficult for local businesses to scale abroad,
thus making them less attractive for foreign direct investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In launching the African Continental Free Trade Area and making it work, Africa
is overcoming the historic fragmentation and isolation of her economies by
opening up huge commercial opportunities as well as improving transport and
communication linkages among the countries. This connectivity will enable the
vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063: “An integrated, prosperous, and
peaceful Africa, driven by its citizens, representing a dynamic force in the
global arena.” However, there are many roadblocks for AU to overcome in the
process of successful implementation of the agreement and realising her dream of
“Agenda 2063: The Africa We Want [Pan-Africanism]’’. The success of the
agreement depends on how well AU manages the disputes among member nations and
oversees the implementation of the agreement in true spirit.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As the US and China are engaged in a trade war, and debates about the unpredictability of relationships between the EU and Britain continue to linger, the continent of Africa is taking steps to create a close-knit relationship to realise the vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063. On May 30, 2019, the African Continental Free Trade Agreement (AfCFTA) came into force after being ratified by the parliaments of 24 countries. The CFTA is an attempt by the African governments to “unlock Africa’s tremendous potential” and deliver prosperity to all Africans. AfCFTA seeks to create a single unified African continental market for goods and services with free movement of business, people and investment. The AfCFTA will bring together all 55 member states of the African Union covering a market of more than 1.2 billion people and a combined GDP of more than $3.4 trillion. In terms of the number of participating countries, the AfCFTA will be the world’s largest free trade area. A single market for goods and services enables free movement of goods, services, and labour from one country to another. Trade among the 55 African Union member states is only 18% of the total exports from the continent. A free market improves these numbers prodigiously. Improved intra-continental trade would benefit the consumers across the continent, as the goods and services would become relatively cheaper. This increases the real income of consumers, part of which again is spent. The ambitious project seeks to remove tariffs on 90% of the goods traded between the signatories to the agreement, and gradually eliminate other non-tariff barriers to trade in goods and services. As an economist would argue, removal of these barriers would increase the producer and consumer surplus, and overall efficiency of these economies.  The manufacturing sector is the backbone of Africa. The new agreement promotes competition among the firms and aids Africa in unlocking its true potential and thus boosting its export of manufactured goods to the rest of the world. The relatively small size of many African markets is one of the reasons that inhibit private sector investment. A unified market will enable the continent to attract foreign direct investment. By and large, these would lead to an increase in consumption and investment components and add to an overall increase in GDP.  By 2030, the African market size is expected to reach 1.7 billion people, with a combined consumer and business spending of $6.7 trillion A study by UNCTAD concedes that the long term monetary benefits that AfCFTA shall yield are annual welfare gains as high as $16 billion. Estimates from the UN Economic Commission for Africa (UNECA) suggest that the AfCFTA has the potential to boost intra-African trade by 52.3%. There’s a substantial amount of evidence to show that free movement boosts the economies of countries. A study has shown that nations could increase their per-capita GDP growth by 12%, simply by being a member of the European Union. The AfCFTA document says one of its goals is to “foster a competitive manufacturing sector and promote economic diversification”. Even as 43% of the goods traded within Africa are from the manufacturing sector, it represents only about 10% of the total GDP in Africa, lagging behind other developing countries. Africa’s low level of intra-regional trade is one of the reasons for the continent’s enduring poverty and lack of a strong manufacturing base. The African economies can, therefore, leverage their gigantic population size of 1.2 billion to expand their manufacturing sector and gain a comparative cost advantage over other nations.  Apart from AfCFTA, there are some Regional Economic Communities (REC) in Africa such as ECA, SADC, ECOWAS, and COMESCA. While ECOWAS was quite successful, the other blocs have problems. Disputes continue to hamper relations and drive the countries toward not honouring agreements. For instance, Kenya and Tanzania, both members of ECA, have been engaged in a trade war. Tanzania has been known to kick out Kenyan executives and impound Kenyan imports at the border, in violation of ECA rules. While Tanzania scrapped preferential access to Kenyan textiles, Kenya allowed goods from Export Processing Zones to be sold in local markets, which prevented Tanzanian goods from being competitive. Members of COMESCA, Kenya, Tanzania and Uganda have also been blaming each other for exploiting the low import duties on sugar. That AfCFTA doesn’t have a clause to repeal all the existing trade blocs would prove a real challenge as it creates ambiguity. Then there is also the threat of countries acting in favour of their trading partners from “the regional blocs.” The success of the agreement depends on how efficiently the AU deals with these RECs. AfCFTA is to face some more challenges. The two largest economies of Africa, Nigeria and South Africa haven’t ratified the agreement yet. South Africa has assured that it would sign it once domestic legal requirements have been satisfied. However, Nigeria backed out from signing the agreement citing “the agreement would drastically affect the small business sector of the country.” “We will not agree to anything that will undermine local manufacturers and entrepreneurs, or that may lead to Nigeria becoming a dumping ground for finished goods,” Nigeria has stated. The pervasive nature of Small and Medium Enterprises (SMEs) in virtually every sector of the Nigerian economy and their place in national development is conspicuous. SMEs in Nigeria are believed to account for about 40% of GDP and 70% of industrial employment. Rice is also a factor that is preventing the largest African economy from signing the deal.  Due to various government initiatives, rice is starting to command 40% more price than what it used to 3 years back in the Nigerian markets. Interestingly,  Nigeria would largely benefit from signing the deal. With a rapidly growing population of almost 200 million, Nigeria has more workers and consumers than anywhere in Africa. For many businesses, there is no other place in Africa that can offer such a scale. This will provide a competitive advantage to Nigeria in firms’ considerations of where to set up facilities and do business. AfCFTA will expose local Nigerian firms to better practices and technologies, often through partnerships with the MNCs and sometimes through competition. This sort of exposure will challenge entrepreneurs in the country and give them greater access to the skills and partnerships they need to be dynamic in today’s world. By giving businesses access to a larger market beyond their home country, the trade agreement would allow the establishments in Nigeria (that are not profitable now) to take advantage of the economies of scale and industries to take advantage of the growth in intra-Africa relations. Remaining a non-signatory to the agreement might cost Nigeria dearly. The country’s isolation makes it difficult for local businesses to scale abroad, thus making them less attractive for foreign direct investment. In launching the African Continental Free Trade Area and making it work, Africa is overcoming the historic fragmentation and isolation of her economies by opening up huge commercial opportunities as well as improving transport and communication linkages among the countries. This connectivity will enable the vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063: “An integrated, prosperous, and peaceful Africa, driven by its citizens, representing a dynamic force in the global arena.” However, there are many roadblocks for AU to overcome in the process of successful implementation of the agreement and realising her dream of “Agenda 2063: The Africa We Want [Pan-Africanism]’’. The success of the agreement depends on how well AU manages the disputes among member nations and oversees the implementation of the agreement in true spirit.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
