<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/economics/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-03-23T21:28:34+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/economics/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why India as a Superpower is a Distant Reality Part II</title>
      <link href="/Why-India-as-a-Superpower-is-a-Distant-Reality-Part-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why India as a Superpower is a Distant Reality Part II" />
      <published>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-India-as-a-Superpower-is-a-Distant-Reality-Part-II</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-India-as-a-Superpower-is-a-Distant-Reality-Part-II">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This article is the final part of the two-part series discussing the perils in the path of India becoming a superpower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Judicial Reforms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Law enforcement and the judicial system are the pillars on which the effectiveness of justice delivery depends. We have looked at the problems bugging India’s law enforcement in the first part of the article. Here we discuss the judiciary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The primary problem with the Indian judiciary is the pendency of cases. At the time of this writing, a total of 37,206,322 are&lt;a href=&quot;https://njdg.ecourts.gov.in/njdgnew/?p=main/pend_dashboard&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://njdg.ecourts.gov.in/njdgnew/?p=main/pend_dashboard&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pending&lt;/a&gt; before the District and subordinate courts in India. Another 5,660,908 cases, of which 87.54% are cases more than a year old, are pending before the High Courts in India. The result is one of an overburdened and sub-optimal judiciary. Some estimates put the time taken to resolve all the pending cases before the Indian Courts close to 300 years! So, what is the way forward?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;One suggestion is to establish appellate courts to expedite the pending cases. Courts of appeals at the district level, state level and national level can help reduce the burden on the courts. The Supreme Court of India also acts as an appellate Court, apart from acting as the Constitutional Court (which the Court can do under Article 133 and 134 of the Indian Constitution in civil and criminal matters respectively). This puts additional burden on the Supreme Court, and it is in fact plagued by a huge workload. To reduce this burden, the appellate work of the Supreme Court may be separated by setting up a Supreme Appellate Court, and its benches could be set up across the country. Apart from this, cognitive technologies could be incorporated into the dispute resolution mechanism (in civil cases). For instance, the biggest litigants today are the various governments in India. Government officials, who decide not to appeal an adverse order, often run the risk of having to justify why they did not pursue the matter more vigorously. Incorporating cognitive technologies can help these officials analyse the chances of a successful appeal better. They can also help the judges in the decision-making process, which could lead to faster decisions and thus, could dispose of a case quickly. But most important of all, the lower rung of courts should be strengthened by filling the vacancies, establishing new posts and developing the infrastructure; for, most of the cases are filed at the lower level and most of the disputes are settled there itself.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another problem with the courts today is the lack of accountability. The introduction of the collegium system in 1998 means that the judges across all the Indian courts are appointed by the higher courts but not the political executive. This is clearly against the principle of checks and balances. The Government of India tried to establish a National Judicial Appoints Committee in 2014. Despite the Parliament of India clearing it, the Supreme Court struck it down saying it violated ‘the basic structure’ doctrine. Collegium, therefore, can only be abolished if all the members of Parliament come together and stand up to the highest court of the land and force its hand. They should do it because it is in the best interest of the country. The Supreme Court should also exercise restraint when it wades into the duties of the executive and legislature and uphold the doctrine of separation of powers. This judicial activism, which has sometimes worked well to deliver justice, has also harmed the Indian economy (from the cancelation of 2G spectrum auctions, the cancellation of coal licences to the recent staying of the farm laws enacted by the Indian Parliament).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;After all is said and done, the judiciary, for all its failures, provides places for discussion and debate. IT acts as a forum for a certain amount of churn. Reforming the judiciary, therefore, is in the best interest of India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social indicators should be improved&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;We Indians are constantly obsessed with ranks. “India is the world’s fastest growing economy,” “India is the world’s third largest economy” we exclaim. But economic growth is not everything, we forget. A look at the social indicators of the country paints a much darker picture. India lags behind its neighbours in human development and social development indicators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;By comparing India with its neighbours, we can analyse the situation. The infant mortality rate, the number of infant deaths per 1,000 births, is 32 in India while it was 27 in Bangladesh in 2017. As of 2015, India’s life expectancy is 68.35, lagging behind Sri Lanka, Bangladesh, Nepal and Bhutan. Between 2003 and 2015 Bangladesh was successful in bringing down the open-defecation rate from 43% to 1%, while India is still struggling with it. Back in 2010 only, infant immunization for DPT and measles in Bangladesh, Sri Lanka and Nepal was about 80%, while India stood somewhere around 65%. In terms of sanitation facilities too, India’s neighbours outperform, though the situation is improving in India. The first&amp;nbsp; phase of the National Family Health Survey (NFHS) released in December 2020 indicates that India could be seeing an increase in child undernutrition. Child undernutrition, measured using three indicators namely stunting, wasting and underweight, has grown in many of the states in the latest NFHS. A rise in the all-India figures would mean that India is reversing the gains it had achieved since 1998-1999. Of all, the problem of stunting is serious in that it affects the cognitive abilities of the children and it could take up to three generations to undo the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It is not that the Indian government is not capable of delivering things. It had successfully carried out the polio vaccination programme and eradicated polio. More recently, it succeeded in getting the people to wear masks to combat the COVID-19 pandemic and proved false the many estimates which predicted 200-300 million deaths due to the pandemic. To improve the social indicators, the government can start by educating people through spreading information via cell phones when someone calls the other. Most importantly, NGOs in India are doing a commendable job in tackling various social problems in India. Government can very well incorporate them and work alongside them to change things where India’s performance lacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There are many other areas which need complete overhaul or effective management. For instance, from modernization of military equipment to facing the challenge of low diplomatic corps, India’s external security faces many challenges. India faces major national security challenges from a more authoritative China and an unstable Pakistan. Another area is that of data collection. Data collection faces huge problems and the depth of the problem is drastic. Often, due to lack of coordination among the various government departments, same data is collected by different departments and, sometimes, the departments arrive at different conclusions! To make cross-state comparisons, one often has to move mountains to gather and then interpret data. It is important to have standardised data collection mechanisms and data interpretations platforms so as to formulate policies that are relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Finally, the problems are huge. And they should be fixed if India has any hopes of playing an important role globally. India faces a (funny?) paradox. On the one hand, various governments in India are among the largest employment providers in the country and on the other practically every department is understaffed. This tells us that we need more personnel, but in the right places. India should also invest in creating a knowledge base for all relevant and necessary functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India is a pre-industrial economy living through an information age. Often, the state has to play a strong role in an industrial economy, but has to take a back seat in the information economy. How the Indian state sets about resolving this paradox also determines India’s future. If we look at history, the most resistance to change comes from villages; and they tend to become violent to resist change. This also presents India with unique challenges. However, the biggest of the problems is in realising all that we have discussed are not any of these. It is that these policies present huge political risks. In a country where the political representation is so heavily skewed towards rural India, whose population is about 30%-40%, the political priorities are also skewed towards rural India and their problems. India needs a leader who focuses on not winning the next election, but on doing the right thing, to get what we have discussed done. That leader may not come to power, but he/she/the will forever changed the fate of the country for the better.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This article is the final part of the two-part series discussing the perils in the path of India becoming a superpower. Judicial Reforms Law enforcement and the judicial system are the pillars on which the effectiveness of justice delivery depends. We have looked at the problems bugging India’s law enforcement in the first part of the article. Here we discuss the judiciary. The primary problem with the Indian judiciary is the pendency of cases. At the time of this writing, a total of 37,206,322 are pending before the District and subordinate courts in India. Another 5,660,908 cases, of which 87.54% are cases more than a year old, are pending before the High Courts in India. The result is one of an overburdened and sub-optimal judiciary. Some estimates put the time taken to resolve all the pending cases before the Indian Courts close to 300 years! So, what is the way forward?&amp;nbsp; One suggestion is to establish appellate courts to expedite the pending cases. Courts of appeals at the district level, state level and national level can help reduce the burden on the courts. The Supreme Court of India also acts as an appellate Court, apart from acting as the Constitutional Court (which the Court can do under Article 133 and 134 of the Indian Constitution in civil and criminal matters respectively). This puts additional burden on the Supreme Court, and it is in fact plagued by a huge workload. To reduce this burden, the appellate work of the Supreme Court may be separated by setting up a Supreme Appellate Court, and its benches could be set up across the country. Apart from this, cognitive technologies could be incorporated into the dispute resolution mechanism (in civil cases). For instance, the biggest litigants today are the various governments in India. Government officials, who decide not to appeal an adverse order, often run the risk of having to justify why they did not pursue the matter more vigorously. Incorporating cognitive technologies can help these officials analyse the chances of a successful appeal better. They can also help the judges in the decision-making process, which could lead to faster decisions and thus, could dispose of a case quickly. But most important of all, the lower rung of courts should be strengthened by filling the vacancies, establishing new posts and developing the infrastructure; for, most of the cases are filed at the lower level and most of the disputes are settled there itself.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Another problem with the courts today is the lack of accountability. The introduction of the collegium system in 1998 means that the judges across all the Indian courts are appointed by the higher courts but not the political executive. This is clearly against the principle of checks and balances. The Government of India tried to establish a National Judicial Appoints Committee in 2014. Despite the Parliament of India clearing it, the Supreme Court struck it down saying it violated ‘the basic structure’ doctrine. Collegium, therefore, can only be abolished if all the members of Parliament come together and stand up to the highest court of the land and force its hand. They should do it because it is in the best interest of the country. The Supreme Court should also exercise restraint when it wades into the duties of the executive and legislature and uphold the doctrine of separation of powers. This judicial activism, which has sometimes worked well to deliver justice, has also harmed the Indian economy (from the cancelation of 2G spectrum auctions, the cancellation of coal licences to the recent staying of the farm laws enacted by the Indian Parliament). After all is said and done, the judiciary, for all its failures, provides places for discussion and debate. IT acts as a forum for a certain amount of churn. Reforming the judiciary, therefore, is in the best interest of India. Social indicators should be improved We Indians are constantly obsessed with ranks. “India is the world’s fastest growing economy,” “India is the world’s third largest economy” we exclaim. But economic growth is not everything, we forget. A look at the social indicators of the country paints a much darker picture. India lags behind its neighbours in human development and social development indicators. By comparing India with its neighbours, we can analyse the situation. The infant mortality rate, the number of infant deaths per 1,000 births, is 32 in India while it was 27 in Bangladesh in 2017. As of 2015, India’s life expectancy is 68.35, lagging behind Sri Lanka, Bangladesh, Nepal and Bhutan. Between 2003 and 2015 Bangladesh was successful in bringing down the open-defecation rate from 43% to 1%, while India is still struggling with it. Back in 2010 only, infant immunization for DPT and measles in Bangladesh, Sri Lanka and Nepal was about 80%, while India stood somewhere around 65%. In terms of sanitation facilities too, India’s neighbours outperform, though the situation is improving in India. The first&amp;nbsp; phase of the National Family Health Survey (NFHS) released in December 2020 indicates that India could be seeing an increase in child undernutrition. Child undernutrition, measured using three indicators namely stunting, wasting and underweight, has grown in many of the states in the latest NFHS. A rise in the all-India figures would mean that India is reversing the gains it had achieved since 1998-1999. Of all, the problem of stunting is serious in that it affects the cognitive abilities of the children and it could take up to three generations to undo the problem. It is not that the Indian government is not capable of delivering things. It had successfully carried out the polio vaccination programme and eradicated polio. More recently, it succeeded in getting the people to wear masks to combat the COVID-19 pandemic and proved false the many estimates which predicted 200-300 million deaths due to the pandemic. To improve the social indicators, the government can start by educating people through spreading information via cell phones when someone calls the other. Most importantly, NGOs in India are doing a commendable job in tackling various social problems in India. Government can very well incorporate them and work alongside them to change things where India’s performance lacks. There are many other areas which need complete overhaul or effective management. For instance, from modernization of military equipment to facing the challenge of low diplomatic corps, India’s external security faces many challenges. India faces major national security challenges from a more authoritative China and an unstable Pakistan. Another area is that of data collection. Data collection faces huge problems and the depth of the problem is drastic. Often, due to lack of coordination among the various government departments, same data is collected by different departments and, sometimes, the departments arrive at different conclusions! To make cross-state comparisons, one often has to move mountains to gather and then interpret data. It is important to have standardised data collection mechanisms and data interpretations platforms so as to formulate policies that are relevant. Finally, the problems are huge. And they should be fixed if India has any hopes of playing an important role globally. India faces a (funny?) paradox. On the one hand, various governments in India are among the largest employment providers in the country and on the other practically every department is understaffed. This tells us that we need more personnel, but in the right places. India should also invest in creating a knowledge base for all relevant and necessary functions. India is a pre-industrial economy living through an information age. Often, the state has to play a strong role in an industrial economy, but has to take a back seat in the information economy. How the Indian state sets about resolving this paradox also determines India’s future. If we look at history, the most resistance to change comes from villages; and they tend to become violent to resist change. This also presents India with unique challenges. However, the biggest of the problems is in realising all that we have discussed are not any of these. It is that these policies present huge political risks. In a country where the political representation is so heavily skewed towards rural India, whose population is about 30%-40%, the political priorities are also skewed towards rural India and their problems. India needs a leader who focuses on not winning the next election, but on doing the right thing, to get what we have discussed done. That leader may not come to power, but he/she/the will forever changed the fate of the country for the better.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Will the Bills Bear Fruit?!</title>
      <link href="/Will-the-Bills-Bear-Fruit" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Will the Bills Bear Fruit?!" />
      <published>2021-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Will-the-Bills-Bear-Fruit</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Will-the-Bills-Bear-Fruit">&lt;p&gt;The past year was certainly filled with uncertainty at every point! The pandemic affected lives and livelihoods in the most unexpected manner and the entire world was in a state of despair. Most of us are very hopeful that 2021 will be different. As we start this year full of hope and joy, there are many who welcomed it in the most unforeseen manner. The ongoing farmers' protest in and around Delhi, India is in full swing. The farmers are determined and have been protesting for over 60 days now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Indian government passed three farm bills in September 2020. The bills claim to revolutionise the agriculture sector and related services. They also aim to double the income of farmers with the help of new rules and regulations. Even after these promises, the farmers are reluctant and want the government to withdraw the bills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The bills are as follows:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-&amp;nbsp; 	The Farmers’ Produce Trade and Commerce (Promotion and Facilitation) Bill, 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-&amp;nbsp; 	The Farmers (Empowerment and Protection) Agreement of Price Assurance and Farm Services Bill, 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-&amp;nbsp; 	The Essential Commodities (Amendment) Bill, 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the existing system, farmers were supposed to sell their produce in registered Agricultural Produce Market Committee (APMC) markets (&lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt;). As the first bill comes into effect, it will allow the farmers to sell their produce outside of these APMC markets. This gives free entry to private corporations in the market and to directly deal with the farmers. Even though this sounds good, as farmers will now have autonomy regarding where to sell their produce, it won’t be as beneficial as it claims to be. Reports show that 85% of the farmers fall in the category of marginal or small farmers who own less than 2 hectares of land. These farmers will now have to face competition in the open market as government regulations will be reduced. Since most of them are marginal farmers, big corporates will certainly try to exploit them during transactions. Thus, these farmers will be worse off in the revolutionised era. The corporations will find it easy to buy produce at minimum prices, thereby increasing their profits. Without government intervention, it will be easy for corporations to use unfair practices during trade. The effects of the bills on farmers are manifold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second bill allows farmers to enter into contract farming with agribusiness firms, wholesale vendors or large retailers at pre-agreed prices. Even though this move helps the big farmers as they won’t be regulated by a third party, the marginal farmers won’t be gaining much out of the scheme. No regulation from the government's end also gives an edge to the firms in negotiations. Farmers are seeing this bill as an opportunity for agribusiness firms and retailers to expand themselves and dominate the market. They would definitely earn more profits without the imposition of rules. Thus, the bill is more beneficial for the corporations rather than the farmers, especially the small farmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third bill removes many commodities like pulses, cereals, onions, etc. from the essential commodities list. This allows firms and retailers to hoard these commodities for longer periods. This essentially gives them the power to manipulate pricing and dominate the farmers during trade and transactions. This also means that the minimum support price (MSP) won’t be given for these commodities. This leaves the farmers with little or no incentive to continue the production of the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above explanation gives us an idea that the three bills don’t directly benefit the farmers much. They are simply easing the regulation that existed in the agricultural sector. It gives a free entry to private players who in turn will exploit the marginal and poor farmers for their personal gains. As soon as the government steps out, the negotiating power of the farmers also reduces. They will be more vulnerable and the removal of MSP from certain commodities makes it even worse for them. As mentioned before, 85% of the farmers are small and thus are barely making any profits. These bills do not incentivise them in any way. The demands of the farmers still remain the same and unheard. Improved infrastructure and farming supplements at subsidised prices would benefit them way more than the privatisation which these bills indirectly aim at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protest has prolonged since September and the Indian government&amp;nbsp; has ignored it all along. The maximum population of our country is involved in agriculture and thus makes it a vital part of our economy. These disruptions directly affect the flow of business cycles as well. The bills have been painting a very rosy picture which doesn’t really fit the frame. The only people who will make money after the implementation will be the rich retailers and firm owners. The exploitation will increase without government intervention and thus farmers will have to struggle more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are currently witnessing the largest protest ever held and that conveys the urgency of the issue. It directly hits the poor who will most likely lose out on their meagre incomes once these laws come into play. The consequences are cyclic and the propensity of loss increases on this side. Welfare has always been a priority for our state. We have managed to follow a mixed economic model, which has proved&amp;nbsp; beneficial for all sectors. Privatisation might be the next step towards the reform but not at the cost of farmers losing out on their livelihoods. The need of the hour is to make them more self-reliant and provide them with farming supplements at cheaper rates. Reforms are only helpful when everyone is capable of making the best out of the available opportunities!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The past year was certainly filled with uncertainty at every point! The pandemic affected lives and livelihoods in the most unexpected manner and the entire world was in a state of despair. Most of us are very hopeful that 2021 will be different. As we start this year full of hope and joy, there are many who welcomed it in the most unforeseen manner. The ongoing farmers' protest in and around Delhi, India is in full swing. The farmers are determined and have been protesting for over 60 days now. The Indian government passed three farm bills in September 2020. The bills claim to revolutionise the agriculture sector and related services. They also aim to double the income of farmers with the help of new rules and regulations. Even after these promises, the farmers are reluctant and want the government to withdraw the bills. The bills are as follows: -&amp;nbsp; The Farmers’ Produce Trade and Commerce (Promotion and Facilitation) Bill, 2020 -&amp;nbsp; The Farmers (Empowerment and Protection) Agreement of Price Assurance and Farm Services Bill, 2020 -&amp;nbsp; The Essential Commodities (Amendment) Bill, 2020 In the existing system, farmers were supposed to sell their produce in registered Agricultural Produce Market Committee (APMC) markets (mandis). As the first bill comes into effect, it will allow the farmers to sell their produce outside of these APMC markets. This gives free entry to private corporations in the market and to directly deal with the farmers. Even though this sounds good, as farmers will now have autonomy regarding where to sell their produce, it won’t be as beneficial as it claims to be. Reports show that 85% of the farmers fall in the category of marginal or small farmers who own less than 2 hectares of land. These farmers will now have to face competition in the open market as government regulations will be reduced. Since most of them are marginal farmers, big corporates will certainly try to exploit them during transactions. Thus, these farmers will be worse off in the revolutionised era. The corporations will find it easy to buy produce at minimum prices, thereby increasing their profits. Without government intervention, it will be easy for corporations to use unfair practices during trade. The effects of the bills on farmers are manifold. The second bill allows farmers to enter into contract farming with agribusiness firms, wholesale vendors or large retailers at pre-agreed prices. Even though this move helps the big farmers as they won’t be regulated by a third party, the marginal farmers won’t be gaining much out of the scheme. No regulation from the government's end also gives an edge to the firms in negotiations. Farmers are seeing this bill as an opportunity for agribusiness firms and retailers to expand themselves and dominate the market. They would definitely earn more profits without the imposition of rules. Thus, the bill is more beneficial for the corporations rather than the farmers, especially the small farmers. The third bill removes many commodities like pulses, cereals, onions, etc. from the essential commodities list. This allows firms and retailers to hoard these commodities for longer periods. This essentially gives them the power to manipulate pricing and dominate the farmers during trade and transactions. This also means that the minimum support price (MSP) won’t be given for these commodities. This leaves the farmers with little or no incentive to continue the production of the same. The above explanation gives us an idea that the three bills don’t directly benefit the farmers much. They are simply easing the regulation that existed in the agricultural sector. It gives a free entry to private players who in turn will exploit the marginal and poor farmers for their personal gains. As soon as the government steps out, the negotiating power of the farmers also reduces. They will be more vulnerable and the removal of MSP from certain commodities makes it even worse for them. As mentioned before, 85% of the farmers are small and thus are barely making any profits. These bills do not incentivise them in any way. The demands of the farmers still remain the same and unheard. Improved infrastructure and farming supplements at subsidised prices would benefit them way more than the privatisation which these bills indirectly aim at. The protest has prolonged since September and the Indian government&amp;nbsp; has ignored it all along. The maximum population of our country is involved in agriculture and thus makes it a vital part of our economy. These disruptions directly affect the flow of business cycles as well. The bills have been painting a very rosy picture which doesn’t really fit the frame. The only people who will make money after the implementation will be the rich retailers and firm owners. The exploitation will increase without government intervention and thus farmers will have to struggle more than ever. We are currently witnessing the largest protest ever held and that conveys the urgency of the issue. It directly hits the poor who will most likely lose out on their meagre incomes once these laws come into play. The consequences are cyclic and the propensity of loss increases on this side. Welfare has always been a priority for our state. We have managed to follow a mixed economic model, which has proved&amp;nbsp; beneficial for all sectors. Privatisation might be the next step towards the reform but not at the cost of farmers losing out on their livelihoods. The need of the hour is to make them more self-reliant and provide them with farming supplements at cheaper rates. Reforms are only helpful when everyone is capable of making the best out of the available opportunities!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why India as a Superpower is a Distant Reality Part I</title>
      <link href="/Why-India-as-a-Superpower-is-a-Distant-Reality-Part-I" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why India as a Superpower is a Distant Reality Part I" />
      <published>2021-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-India-as-a-Superpower-is-a-Distant-Reality-Part-I</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-India-as-a-Superpower-is-a-Distant-Reality-Part-I">&lt;p&gt;The changing geopolitical structure of the contemporary world will expect India to play a larger role in world affairs. Coupling this with the call made by Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi to make India a $5 trillion economy, we are looking at a scenario where India is a potential superpower candidate in the 21st century. And Indians have always believed, owing to the rich civilisational heritage the country had in the past, that they deserve to lead the world – becoming the &lt;em&gt;viswaguru &lt;/em&gt;('lord of the world')&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; For this, India must present its world view and leverage its soft power to influence the world. At the same time, it is important for the country to get its ducks in a row; for, without resolving its domestic problems, we can forget about leading the world. In this article, I try to highlight some crucial problems that need immediate attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Law and Order&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first major roadblock pertains to law and order in India. With the Indian police, the issues pertain to distrust, understaffing, accountability and inefficiency. First, there is a lot of distrust towards the police among the public. A 2018&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lokniti.org/media/upload_files/Report%20Police%20Survey.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lokniti.org/media/upload_files/Report%20Police%20Survey.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt; found that less than 25% of Indians trust the police. This distrust can be attributed to the prevalent corruption in the police departments, the police-politician nexus and the abuse of power by the police. In the Indian Corruption&lt;a href=&quot;https://transparencyindia.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/11/India-Corruption-Survey-2019.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://transparencyindia.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/11/India-Corruption-Survey-2019.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Survey&lt;/a&gt; 2019, the police department was found to be the second most corrupt department in the country.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second issue is the understaffing of the police force. As recently as in 2017, 30% of all the sanctioned posts were vacant in the country. The police-to-population ratio, therefore, is low in the country and makes the Indian police force one of the weakest in the world. From delays in investigation, increased response time and an increased toll on the mental health of the police, this issue births many other problems which leads to grave consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third issue is accountability. Many-a-times there is no action taken against a police officer when a complaint is lodged against them for various reasons. Often times, higher officials tend to overlook such complaints due to political pressure or for being complicit with the accused. There is no other mechanism available to lodge complaints against the police. Lack of accountability also includes the cases of fake encounters and deaths in police custody (a Google search shows that as recently as last year, two custodial deaths took place in Telangana, India).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fourth problem is that of inefficiency. The educational qualifications for a constable, the lowest cadre in the police – who account for almost 85% of the police force, is passing class 10 or 12 in many states. But the responsibilities of constables are wide-ranging. They are expected to exercise their judgement in intelligence gathering, assist with investigations and maintain public contact. It is often the case that these constables are insensitive and rude to the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not that there are no solutions. There have been many committees which made several recommendations, only to find the politicians to dump them in the dustbin. In 2006, the Supreme Court of India issued seven directions to reform the police force. Though states have implemented some of them, in practice they have been rendered useless. There are four things that have to be done. First, an increase in the size of the police force 6-10 times than the current number. Second, investment in police training which should focus on getting the police personnel to clearly understand the law of the land and also be sensitive to the public. Third, giving a greater degree of autonomy to the police.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To reduce the police’s dependence on politicians, the Supreme Court recommended the setting up of a Police Establishment Board in every state that will decide postings, transfers and promotions for officers below the rank of Deputy Superintendent of Police, and make recommendations to the state government for officers of higher ranks. The fourth recommendation is to make the police accountable. For this, the Supreme Court recommended constituting Police Complaints Authorities at the state and district levels to inquire into allegations of serious misconduct and abuse of power by police personnel. Police reforms are the most important area to focus on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Education&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Education, particularly primary education, is one area where India has failed enormously. While it succeeded in building prominent universities like IITs and IISCs, it is unable to provide primary education to everyone. The primary school system in India also focuses more on getting done with the syllabus and scoring marks in the exam. Problem-solving doesn’t come automatically to us because we are not equipped with the necessary tools in the classroom. Students are made to, encouraged in some cases, to mug up answers rather than think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pratham &lt;/em&gt;surveys frequently indicate how school students, mainly from government schools, fail at basic math and writing their name in English. However, the idea that government schools cannot produce results but only the private sector can, is false. My own experience tells me how corporate state board schools operate. In most of the cases, teachers do not have a Bachelors of Education degree. The management often sets unrealistic targets for the teachers to complete the syllabus and leave no time for the students for other extracurricular activities. Students are segregated based on their ability to score marks and the slow-learners (euphemism for those students that can’t score well) are put in one section and are hardly cared for. Private schools can also be pretty bad. If one looks at the school system in Sri Lanka, one can find that government schools can also achieve success and all it needs is initiative on the part of political leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a simple solution. Invest in primary education heavily. Both in terms of infrastructure building and teacher training. In many instances, it was found that government school teachers in some states could not even get the basics right. Also, the new education policy revealed by the Indian government assumes that there is manoeuvre for the teachers to engage in skills-based education. This is a classic example of a third'world country looking for first-world solutions. Teachers in many government schools, who are highly qualified, are unable to do this, let alone the private schools. This is why investing in teacher training is crucial to get Indian education on to the right track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked to propose solutions to any social problems, often the first solution that comes up is to create awareness. By investing in primary education and educating the people, that goal can be successfully accomplished. Also, education is the most important tool for social mobility. Neglecting it does not make sense. Third, caste politics and this sense of belonging to the same caste can be countered by educating your people. Caste politics depends on a patronage system. The moment we ensure basic things are available to everyone, it acts as a deterrent to caste politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Urban Cities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India is undergoing rapid urbanisation. Since 2009, the rate of urbanisation in the country has been around 30%. With such a high rate of urbanisation, Indian urban areas are becoming increasingly crowded and haphazard. For all the talk about how &lt;em&gt;asli Bharat gaaon mein basta hein &lt;/em&gt;('real India lives in villages'), we must not forget that it is cities that are the centres of economic activity and result in economies of scale for the firms operating in them. However, with rapid urbanisation new challenges have emerged in city management in India. First and foremost is the problem of pollution. Indian cities are one of the most polluted in the world. The national capital Delhi regularly figures in the list of most polluted cities, mostly in the top ten spots. The second problem is that most of the cities that exist today are naturally formed and they were not planned. This in itself led to problems like a lack of proper sanitation systems, waste disposal systems, the inability to regulate traffic efficiently, illegal constructions and many more. The third problem is that there are many departments to regulate various aspects of the cities and due to lack of coordination among them there is inefficient planning and land use. Often, these departments are also zones of rampant corruption. The fourth and other important problem is lack of availability of funds. In most of the cases, the cities have very poor budgetary allocations and the revenue they get in the form of taxes is also low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To solve the funding problems, governments can consider transferring the revenue they get from public transport to the city development authorities. About 50% of the expenditure incurred by the city administrations is on administrative expenditures like salary, pensions, operation and maintenance of offices, and property, among other things. One solution is to cut personnel wherever it is possible by moving the services online. Certain departments, like water and sanitation, can be clubbed so as to cut staff. It is important to recognise that the bottom-up approach is best and hence there should be a transfer of greater funds to the local bodies. Creating a strong bond market and leveraging the land-based instruments can also be considered to raise revenue.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equally important is the concentration on city planning. As was mentioned earlier, many of the top Indian cities were not planned and the consequences of that are for everyone to see. Many state governments and local bodies do have planning departments and planning officials. The problem is either they are under-equipped or the staff has no proper knowledge regarding urban planning. It is therefore also important to invest in and encourage people to pursue degrees in urban planning.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from the three areas, which need the Indian state's immediate attention, there are three more which I think have high importance in facilitating India onto the superpower path. I will discuss those in the next part.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The changing geopolitical structure of the contemporary world will expect India to play a larger role in world affairs. Coupling this with the call made by Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi to make India a $5 trillion economy, we are looking at a scenario where India is a potential superpower candidate in the 21st century. And Indians have always believed, owing to the rich civilisational heritage the country had in the past, that they deserve to lead the world – becoming the viswaguru ('lord of the world'). For this, India must present its world view and leverage its soft power to influence the world. At the same time, it is important for the country to get its ducks in a row; for, without resolving its domestic problems, we can forget about leading the world. In this article, I try to highlight some crucial problems that need immediate attention. Law and Order The first major roadblock pertains to law and order in India. With the Indian police, the issues pertain to distrust, understaffing, accountability and inefficiency. First, there is a lot of distrust towards the police among the public. A 2018 survey found that less than 25% of Indians trust the police. This distrust can be attributed to the prevalent corruption in the police departments, the police-politician nexus and the abuse of power by the police. In the Indian Corruption Survey 2019, the police department was found to be the second most corrupt department in the country.&amp;nbsp; The second issue is the understaffing of the police force. As recently as in 2017, 30% of all the sanctioned posts were vacant in the country. The police-to-population ratio, therefore, is low in the country and makes the Indian police force one of the weakest in the world. From delays in investigation, increased response time and an increased toll on the mental health of the police, this issue births many other problems which leads to grave consequences. The third issue is accountability. Many-a-times there is no action taken against a police officer when a complaint is lodged against them for various reasons. Often times, higher officials tend to overlook such complaints due to political pressure or for being complicit with the accused. There is no other mechanism available to lodge complaints against the police. Lack of accountability also includes the cases of fake encounters and deaths in police custody (a Google search shows that as recently as last year, two custodial deaths took place in Telangana, India).&amp;nbsp; The fourth problem is that of inefficiency. The educational qualifications for a constable, the lowest cadre in the police – who account for almost 85% of the police force, is passing class 10 or 12 in many states. But the responsibilities of constables are wide-ranging. They are expected to exercise their judgement in intelligence gathering, assist with investigations and maintain public contact. It is often the case that these constables are insensitive and rude to the public. It is not that there are no solutions. There have been many committees which made several recommendations, only to find the politicians to dump them in the dustbin. In 2006, the Supreme Court of India issued seven directions to reform the police force. Though states have implemented some of them, in practice they have been rendered useless. There are four things that have to be done. First, an increase in the size of the police force 6-10 times than the current number. Second, investment in police training which should focus on getting the police personnel to clearly understand the law of the land and also be sensitive to the public. Third, giving a greater degree of autonomy to the police.&amp;nbsp; To reduce the police’s dependence on politicians, the Supreme Court recommended the setting up of a Police Establishment Board in every state that will decide postings, transfers and promotions for officers below the rank of Deputy Superintendent of Police, and make recommendations to the state government for officers of higher ranks. The fourth recommendation is to make the police accountable. For this, the Supreme Court recommended constituting Police Complaints Authorities at the state and district levels to inquire into allegations of serious misconduct and abuse of power by police personnel. Police reforms are the most important area to focus on. Education Education, particularly primary education, is one area where India has failed enormously. While it succeeded in building prominent universities like IITs and IISCs, it is unable to provide primary education to everyone. The primary school system in India also focuses more on getting done with the syllabus and scoring marks in the exam. Problem-solving doesn’t come automatically to us because we are not equipped with the necessary tools in the classroom. Students are made to, encouraged in some cases, to mug up answers rather than think. Pratham surveys frequently indicate how school students, mainly from government schools, fail at basic math and writing their name in English. However, the idea that government schools cannot produce results but only the private sector can, is false. My own experience tells me how corporate state board schools operate. In most of the cases, teachers do not have a Bachelors of Education degree. The management often sets unrealistic targets for the teachers to complete the syllabus and leave no time for the students for other extracurricular activities. Students are segregated based on their ability to score marks and the slow-learners (euphemism for those students that can’t score well) are put in one section and are hardly cared for. Private schools can also be pretty bad. If one looks at the school system in Sri Lanka, one can find that government schools can also achieve success and all it needs is initiative on the part of political leadership. There is a simple solution. Invest in primary education heavily. Both in terms of infrastructure building and teacher training. In many instances, it was found that government school teachers in some states could not even get the basics right. Also, the new education policy revealed by the Indian government assumes that there is manoeuvre for the teachers to engage in skills-based education. This is a classic example of a third'world country looking for first-world solutions. Teachers in many government schools, who are highly qualified, are unable to do this, let alone the private schools. This is why investing in teacher training is crucial to get Indian education on to the right track. When asked to propose solutions to any social problems, often the first solution that comes up is to create awareness. By investing in primary education and educating the people, that goal can be successfully accomplished. Also, education is the most important tool for social mobility. Neglecting it does not make sense. Third, caste politics and this sense of belonging to the same caste can be countered by educating your people. Caste politics depends on a patronage system. The moment we ensure basic things are available to everyone, it acts as a deterrent to caste politics. Urban Cities India is undergoing rapid urbanisation. Since 2009, the rate of urbanisation in the country has been around 30%. With such a high rate of urbanisation, Indian urban areas are becoming increasingly crowded and haphazard. For all the talk about how asli Bharat gaaon mein basta hein ('real India lives in villages'), we must not forget that it is cities that are the centres of economic activity and result in economies of scale for the firms operating in them. However, with rapid urbanisation new challenges have emerged in city management in India. First and foremost is the problem of pollution. Indian cities are one of the most polluted in the world. The national capital Delhi regularly figures in the list of most polluted cities, mostly in the top ten spots. The second problem is that most of the cities that exist today are naturally formed and they were not planned. This in itself led to problems like a lack of proper sanitation systems, waste disposal systems, the inability to regulate traffic efficiently, illegal constructions and many more. The third problem is that there are many departments to regulate various aspects of the cities and due to lack of coordination among them there is inefficient planning and land use. Often, these departments are also zones of rampant corruption. The fourth and other important problem is lack of availability of funds. In most of the cases, the cities have very poor budgetary allocations and the revenue they get in the form of taxes is also low. To solve the funding problems, governments can consider transferring the revenue they get from public transport to the city development authorities. About 50% of the expenditure incurred by the city administrations is on administrative expenditures like salary, pensions, operation and maintenance of offices, and property, among other things. One solution is to cut personnel wherever it is possible by moving the services online. Certain departments, like water and sanitation, can be clubbed so as to cut staff. It is important to recognise that the bottom-up approach is best and hence there should be a transfer of greater funds to the local bodies. Creating a strong bond market and leveraging the land-based instruments can also be considered to raise revenue.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Equally important is the concentration on city planning. As was mentioned earlier, many of the top Indian cities were not planned and the consequences of that are for everyone to see. Many state governments and local bodies do have planning departments and planning officials. The problem is either they are under-equipped or the staff has no proper knowledge regarding urban planning. It is therefore also important to invest in and encourage people to pursue degrees in urban planning.&amp;nbsp; Apart from the three areas, which need the Indian state's immediate attention, there are three more which I think have high importance in facilitating India onto the superpower path. I will discuss those in the next part.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Beat The Casinos</title>
      <link href="/Beat-The-Casinos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beat The Casinos" />
      <published>2021-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Beat-The-Casinos</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Beat-The-Casinos">&lt;p&gt;Being a huge &lt;em&gt;Hangover&lt;/em&gt; fan, there is something that I have always wanted to do in my life and that is, gambling all night at a casino in Las Vegas for once. Within the walls of the 51 licensed casinos of the Las Vegas Strip, there are 2,879 gaming tables collectively bringing in $3.1 billion in revenue annually, or over a million dollars in each table. In addition, there are some 38,864 slot machines bringing in another $3.4 billion dollars. A single large Las Vegas casino, like the Bellagio, makes more than some small countries, annually.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is because the casino business model is pretty much bulletproof. Overall, the odds are always in the casino’s favour. If this weren’t true, casinos would fail - so these floors just print money. MGM International, for example, one of the world’s largest multinational gaming companies, has about 2.5 million square feet of casino floor worldwide meaning it makes, on average, $1,038 per square foot. With the money their casinos bring in, they could line every inch of every foot of their casino floor worldwide with a brand-new iPad and still have money left over. This is all to say, casinos make a lot of money, but to do so, they need a lot more money coming through their doors. You see, the casino business model all revolves around risk. With every game they have, the odds are in their favour, but doesn’t mean the house will always win. Their advantage varies from game to game - in Roulette, it is about 5.25%, in Poker, it is about 3.35%, and in Blackjack, it is about 0.5%.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, given how tight these margins are, there’s natural variability, so casinos can come out behind or lose money on a given table on a given night but overall, with enough tables and enough nights, they average out these odds. However, in order to do so, they need an immense amount of money running through their casinos. Blackjack, for example, is one of the games with the lowest house edge so if the casino wants to earn $1 billion in a given year from the game, they would need $200 billion changing hands within their doors each year. That’s pretty much the entire GDP of New Zealand. When you have such a rapid throughput of money, very slight changes in the odds can make a huge variation in the gaming company’s earnings. If, for example, the house edge in the Blackjack changed from 0.5% to 0.4%, they would lose $200 million, assuming $200 billion in annual play. This is why making sure these odds stay in their favour is so important to the casinos. It could quite literally be the difference between millions of dollars in profit or filing for bankruptcy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite what the movie culture might portray, a casino’s biggest problem is not robbers or hackers or even technically cheaters, because each of those is relatively easy to prevent and detect. Rather, their biggest problem is people who are able to turn the odds in their favour without robbing, hacking or even cheating. Cheating in a casino is generally illegal, however, it’s possible for a player to consistently win without cheating. The best-known example of this is card counting, a type of advantage play used in the Blackjack family of games which is not illegal and in some cases is even legally protected. This play technique takes the basic principles of the game of Blackjack and uses them against the casino, and these principles are fairly simple.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start a game, each player bets an amount of money and then six decks of cards are shuffled together to form what’s called the Shoe. Each player is dealt two cards face-up while the dealer gets one face-up and one face-down card. The goal for all the participants is simple, it’s to get their cards to total as close to 21 without going above 21. Starting from the left, each player will either decide to stick with the total they have or to take another card to add to it. Of course, the player doesn’t know what the next card will be worth in between one to 11, so it’s a gamble on whether it’ll make the total go over 21 – in which case their bet is lost.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The higher the original sum, the riskier it is to take another card but there is in fact a mathematically optimal choice for every scenario called the 'basic strategy'. Once every player is done taking cards, the dealer reveals the face-down card and automatically if their total is below 17, they take additional cards until it isn’t over 17. If it's 17 or higher, they leave it as it is. There are then 3 scenarios. If the dealer goes above 21, all players’ bets are doubled, as long as they didn’t go above 21 first. If the player’s total is higher than the dealer’s then the player's bet is doubled, however, if the player's total is lower, they lose their bet.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this explanation skipped over plenty of smaller rules and less likely edge-cases, but it is these fundamental elements of game-play that tie into why card counting works. Now, without getting too much into the math, on average, in Blackjack, higher value cards benefit the player, while the lower value cards benefit the dealers. While the explanation for the higher cards is more complex, lower card benefit is based on the fact that the dealer is required to take additional cards when their total is less than 17 and so a greater density of lower cards makes it less likely that they will go over 21 – in which case each player’s bet is doubled. Therefore, if you know that a bunch of low cards are coming, you know that the odds are against you and so you should reduce your bet or not play but the question is how do you know what’s coming in a randomly shuffled deck. Well, you perform the process of elimination or even more simply you count the cards you see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are hundreds of different forms of card counting that work in hundreds of different ways, but all are more or less based on what’s known as the 'Hi-Lo' system. With this, each card is assigned a value. Cards ranging from two to six are assigned 'one', cards from seven to nine are assigned 'zero', and card 10 and ace and all the face cards are assigned 'minus one'. This is based on the fact that every time a high-value card is dealt there are fewer of them left in the deck, which means the odds get worse for the player considering that high-value cards are better for them and vice versa. With every card a player sees, they add up its assigned value. So, if there are three players and they are dealt the cards in &lt;em&gt;figure 1&lt;/em&gt;, the running count would be two.&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/cardlayouteuan.png&quot; /&gt;Figure 1: Cards dealt to three players and their running count - Euan Decourt, 23/01/2020&lt;/div&gt;As the play goes on and they get deeper into the deck, the running count will generally increase in one direction or the other giving the player more confidence on where the odds stand. So, for example, if the running count equals 20, the player would know that the odds are greatly in their favour and therefore that they should bet big on the next round as they have a greater than 50% chance of winning. This is how people can reliably make money in Blackjack. If a player changes their bet by a factor of 15 depending on the odds, and the dealer waits until they’re through five of the six decks before shuffling, a player, following a perfect Blackjack strategy, could earn an advantage of about 1.182% over the house. That means that if assuming a table completes a round of play every minute and an average bet is around $200, a card counter could profit on average about $110 an hour - enough that some people can and do make a living by sitting at Blackjack tables, counting cards. However, how simple and reliable this advantage play method is, casinos go to great lengths to stop it which is very, very difficult. That’s because the advantage is all in the mind—there’s no good way to fully prove that a person is counting cards. Sometimes, people are just lucky and it is quite a bad look for casinos to kick people out just because they are winning. That’s why instead of trying to prove it, most casinos implement rules to try and stop card counting from working as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that, generally, the running count will get further into positive or negative the further into the game one goes because the card counter would have seen more cards that are now in the discard pile, and therefore cannot be dealt. While a few rounds in the running count might be in the single digits positive or negative, further on, it will get into the double digits which gives the counter great confidence whether they should bet big or not. It is towards the end of the Shoes, when card counters really make their money, so to make it less profitable, casinos can just have their dealers shuffle earlier on. If they shuffle 4 decks deep into a six-deck show rather than five, that decreases the player’s advantage from 1.182 to just 0.568%. However, shuffling earlier and more often also cuts into the casino’s profits because, anytime the dealer is shuffling the non-advantaged players aren’t playing and losing money, which is how the casino makes its money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another option for casinos is to increase the number of decks they shuffle together to make a show. Back before card-counting first became a widespread issue for casinos, they would play Blackjack with just a single deck of cards but if they did this today, it would only be a matter of minutes before a card counter would have high confidence about the odds. Therefore, they typically now play with six decks shuffled together, which increases the time it takes to get to high confidence and since time is money for a card counter, this decreases their profits. Some casinos take this a step further by using a continuous shuffling machine. With no discard piles, there is no increase or decrease in the beneficial cards in the shoe, so card counting is completely ineffective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these methods deal with stopping or reducing a player’s ability to actually know what the odds are at a given moment, the other method involves stopping a player’s ability to respond to this knowledge by changing the size of their bets. Essentially, if a dealer or a pit boss suspects someone might be counting cards, they’ll change the rules on them and require flat betting which means making a player choose one bet size for all rounds and not allowing them to change the bet in future rounds when the count is in their favour. However, that poses the question, how do you spot a card counter? Well, one of the signs is if a player changes their bet from 100 to 1000 right before a series of wins or as the Shoe is close to finish, that’s a good sign that they know what the odds are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end, the casinos aren’t much affected by card counters as they make a very small proportion of all the players and they consider it as a cost of running the business. Till this time these games continue to exist, players will always try to find new ways to shift the odds in their favour and this causes a never-ending cycle, but what we must know is that if we use basic math we can outwit some of these casinos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about Blackjack, click &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.blackjackapprenticeship.com/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Being a huge Hangover fan, there is something that I have always wanted to do in my life and that is, gambling all night at a casino in Las Vegas for once. Within the walls of the 51 licensed casinos of the Las Vegas Strip, there are 2,879 gaming tables collectively bringing in $3.1 billion in revenue annually, or over a million dollars in each table. In addition, there are some 38,864 slot machines bringing in another $3.4 billion dollars. A single large Las Vegas casino, like the Bellagio, makes more than some small countries, annually.&amp;nbsp; This is because the casino business model is pretty much bulletproof. Overall, the odds are always in the casino’s favour. If this weren’t true, casinos would fail - so these floors just print money. MGM International, for example, one of the world’s largest multinational gaming companies, has about 2.5 million square feet of casino floor worldwide meaning it makes, on average, $1,038 per square foot. With the money their casinos bring in, they could line every inch of every foot of their casino floor worldwide with a brand-new iPad and still have money left over. This is all to say, casinos make a lot of money, but to do so, they need a lot more money coming through their doors. You see, the casino business model all revolves around risk. With every game they have, the odds are in their favour, but doesn’t mean the house will always win. Their advantage varies from game to game - in Roulette, it is about 5.25%, in Poker, it is about 3.35%, and in Blackjack, it is about 0.5%.&amp;nbsp; Of course, given how tight these margins are, there’s natural variability, so casinos can come out behind or lose money on a given table on a given night but overall, with enough tables and enough nights, they average out these odds. However, in order to do so, they need an immense amount of money running through their casinos. Blackjack, for example, is one of the games with the lowest house edge so if the casino wants to earn $1 billion in a given year from the game, they would need $200 billion changing hands within their doors each year. That’s pretty much the entire GDP of New Zealand. When you have such a rapid throughput of money, very slight changes in the odds can make a huge variation in the gaming company’s earnings. If, for example, the house edge in the Blackjack changed from 0.5% to 0.4%, they would lose $200 million, assuming $200 billion in annual play. This is why making sure these odds stay in their favour is so important to the casinos. It could quite literally be the difference between millions of dollars in profit or filing for bankruptcy.&amp;nbsp; Despite what the movie culture might portray, a casino’s biggest problem is not robbers or hackers or even technically cheaters, because each of those is relatively easy to prevent and detect. Rather, their biggest problem is people who are able to turn the odds in their favour without robbing, hacking or even cheating. Cheating in a casino is generally illegal, however, it’s possible for a player to consistently win without cheating. The best-known example of this is card counting, a type of advantage play used in the Blackjack family of games which is not illegal and in some cases is even legally protected. This play technique takes the basic principles of the game of Blackjack and uses them against the casino, and these principles are fairly simple.&amp;nbsp; To start a game, each player bets an amount of money and then six decks of cards are shuffled together to form what’s called the Shoe. Each player is dealt two cards face-up while the dealer gets one face-up and one face-down card. The goal for all the participants is simple, it’s to get their cards to total as close to 21 without going above 21. Starting from the left, each player will either decide to stick with the total they have or to take another card to add to it. Of course, the player doesn’t know what the next card will be worth in between one to 11, so it’s a gamble on whether it’ll make the total go over 21 – in which case their bet is lost.&amp;nbsp; The higher the original sum, the riskier it is to take another card but there is in fact a mathematically optimal choice for every scenario called the 'basic strategy'. Once every player is done taking cards, the dealer reveals the face-down card and automatically if their total is below 17, they take additional cards until it isn’t over 17. If it's 17 or higher, they leave it as it is. There are then 3 scenarios. If the dealer goes above 21, all players’ bets are doubled, as long as they didn’t go above 21 first. If the player’s total is higher than the dealer’s then the player's bet is doubled, however, if the player's total is lower, they lose their bet.&amp;nbsp; Of course, this explanation skipped over plenty of smaller rules and less likely edge-cases, but it is these fundamental elements of game-play that tie into why card counting works. Now, without getting too much into the math, on average, in Blackjack, higher value cards benefit the player, while the lower value cards benefit the dealers. While the explanation for the higher cards is more complex, lower card benefit is based on the fact that the dealer is required to take additional cards when their total is less than 17 and so a greater density of lower cards makes it less likely that they will go over 21 – in which case each player’s bet is doubled. Therefore, if you know that a bunch of low cards are coming, you know that the odds are against you and so you should reduce your bet or not play but the question is how do you know what’s coming in a randomly shuffled deck. Well, you perform the process of elimination or even more simply you count the cards you see. There are hundreds of different forms of card counting that work in hundreds of different ways, but all are more or less based on what’s known as the 'Hi-Lo' system. With this, each card is assigned a value. Cards ranging from two to six are assigned 'one', cards from seven to nine are assigned 'zero', and card 10 and ace and all the face cards are assigned 'minus one'. This is based on the fact that every time a high-value card is dealt there are fewer of them left in the deck, which means the odds get worse for the player considering that high-value cards are better for them and vice versa. With every card a player sees, they add up its assigned value. So, if there are three players and they are dealt the cards in figure 1, the running count would be two.Figure 1: Cards dealt to three players and their running count - Euan Decourt, 23/01/2020As the play goes on and they get deeper into the deck, the running count will generally increase in one direction or the other giving the player more confidence on where the odds stand. So, for example, if the running count equals 20, the player would know that the odds are greatly in their favour and therefore that they should bet big on the next round as they have a greater than 50% chance of winning. This is how people can reliably make money in Blackjack. If a player changes their bet by a factor of 15 depending on the odds, and the dealer waits until they’re through five of the six decks before shuffling, a player, following a perfect Blackjack strategy, could earn an advantage of about 1.182% over the house. That means that if assuming a table completes a round of play every minute and an average bet is around $200, a card counter could profit on average about $110 an hour - enough that some people can and do make a living by sitting at Blackjack tables, counting cards. However, how simple and reliable this advantage play method is, casinos go to great lengths to stop it which is very, very difficult. That’s because the advantage is all in the mind—there’s no good way to fully prove that a person is counting cards. Sometimes, people are just lucky and it is quite a bad look for casinos to kick people out just because they are winning. That’s why instead of trying to prove it, most casinos implement rules to try and stop card counting from working as well.&amp;nbsp; Remember that, generally, the running count will get further into positive or negative the further into the game one goes because the card counter would have seen more cards that are now in the discard pile, and therefore cannot be dealt. While a few rounds in the running count might be in the single digits positive or negative, further on, it will get into the double digits which gives the counter great confidence whether they should bet big or not. It is towards the end of the Shoes, when card counters really make their money, so to make it less profitable, casinos can just have their dealers shuffle earlier on. If they shuffle 4 decks deep into a six-deck show rather than five, that decreases the player’s advantage from 1.182 to just 0.568%. However, shuffling earlier and more often also cuts into the casino’s profits because, anytime the dealer is shuffling the non-advantaged players aren’t playing and losing money, which is how the casino makes its money. Another option for casinos is to increase the number of decks they shuffle together to make a show. Back before card-counting first became a widespread issue for casinos, they would play Blackjack with just a single deck of cards but if they did this today, it would only be a matter of minutes before a card counter would have high confidence about the odds. Therefore, they typically now play with six decks shuffled together, which increases the time it takes to get to high confidence and since time is money for a card counter, this decreases their profits. Some casinos take this a step further by using a continuous shuffling machine. With no discard piles, there is no increase or decrease in the beneficial cards in the shoe, so card counting is completely ineffective. While these methods deal with stopping or reducing a player’s ability to actually know what the odds are at a given moment, the other method involves stopping a player’s ability to respond to this knowledge by changing the size of their bets. Essentially, if a dealer or a pit boss suspects someone might be counting cards, they’ll change the rules on them and require flat betting which means making a player choose one bet size for all rounds and not allowing them to change the bet in future rounds when the count is in their favour. However, that poses the question, how do you spot a card counter? Well, one of the signs is if a player changes their bet from 100 to 1000 right before a series of wins or as the Shoe is close to finish, that’s a good sign that they know what the odds are. At the end, the casinos aren’t much affected by card counters as they make a very small proportion of all the players and they consider it as a cost of running the business. Till this time these games continue to exist, players will always try to find new ways to shift the odds in their favour and this causes a never-ending cycle, but what we must know is that if we use basic math we can outwit some of these casinos. If you want to learn more about Blackjack, click here.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Pandemic of Inequality</title>
      <link href="/The-Pandemic-of-Inequality" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Pandemic of Inequality" />
      <published>2021-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Pandemic-of-Inequality</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Pandemic-of-Inequality">&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus outbreak has plunged the entire globe into a deep ‘shock’ with simultaneous disruptions to both the demand and supply side in a highly interdependent and interconnected world economy. The increased incidence of infections has led to a large reduction in labour supply and the initial period of lockdowns have led to a loss of income for several households. Yet, there has been one section of people that have been worst hit by the pandemic - ‘the poor’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a general view that crises and pandemics like this often lead to the redistribution of resources among the masses, as the spread of the virus sees no caste, class and gender differences. However, this couldn’t be further away from reality. The COVID-19 has had a uniform impact on the entire world when it comes to the possibilities of being infected, but the social and economic impacts have been the most on the vulnerable sections of the society. In a recent study by the World Bank, “&lt;em&gt;Global extreme poverty is expected to rise in 2020 for the first time in over 20 years. The COVID-19 pandemic is estimated to push an additional 88 million to 115 million people into extreme poverty this year, with the total rising to as many as 150 million by 2021.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article is thus an attempt to shed light on how the pandemic transformed into a pandemic of inequality using various arguments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Past Experiences&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A comparative analysis of the novel coronavirus and other past epidemics is often made to understand the relationship between the pandemics and inequalities caused across countries. The first example that comes into the mind is that of the 14th century Black Death which suggested that pandemics seem to reduce inequality in the long run. According to various studies conducted, the Black Death re-balanced the population, and available resources led to a useful reorganisation of agrarian production and triggered significant increases in real wages across the European continent. But the pandemics in recent history seem to have defied this theory. If recent episodes of pandemics are included, ranging from plagues to cholera pandemic &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;, they fail to prove the substantial reduction in inequality levels. Instead, the levels have been observed to be increasing substantially, coinciding with the occurrence of these events. Therefore the impact of Black Death turns out to be an ‘exception’ in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An Uneven Playing Field&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we begin analysing this relationship between a pandemic and inequality, have a look at the rising income trend in the figure given below and keep it in mind. &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/#:~:text=The%20world%20population%20increased%20from,to%201.05%25%20per%20year%20today.&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/worldbank1.png&quot; /&gt;Figure 1. Source: World Bank &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, economic inequality refers to the unequal distribution of income and opportunity between different groups in society. According to Tony Atkinson, a renowned British economist, “&lt;em&gt;Inequality of outcome among today’s generation is the source of the unfair advantage received by the next generation. If we are concerned about equality of opportunity tomorrow, we need to be concerned about inequality of outcome today.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today’s world, inequality is a pressing concern transforming into a situation of emergency. The figure below visualises the inequality in living conditions between the world’s best-off and worst-off countries.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/#:~:text=The%20world%20population%20increased%20from,to%201.05%25%20per%20year%20today.&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/worldbank2.png&quot; /&gt;Figure 2. Source: World Bank&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Income and wealth inequality have particularly witnessed an upward trend in all major advanced economies while for the emerging ones, the income distribution trends have been mixed but most of them are experiencing an upward trend too, led by major emerging economies such as China and India. In this scenario, the increase in inequality due to the current pandemic is quite worrisome.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a study conducted Oxfam, a non-profit operating across the world, it is estimated that there are as much as 121 million more people on the brink of starvation today due to mass unemployment, disruption to food production and supplies. “&lt;em&gt;As many as 12,000 people could die every day from COVID-linked hunger&lt;/em&gt;,” stated Oxfam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the wake of these figures, it becomes imperative to understand the two-way relationship between pandemics and inequality, i.e. inequality is not just an impact of the pandemic, it is the cause of the outbreak itself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is no doubt that it is the extreme socio-economic inequalities and the lack of access to public healthcare facilities that have led to stark ill-proportioned costs being borne by these downtrodden individuals, both in terms of infection incidences as well as the economic well-being. But how exactly does this play out?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin with, the countries facing a sustained rise in population levels also experience an increasing population density, which therefore leads to a rise in the ability of the disease to reproduce and spread. At the same time, due to an increase in the labour force, the wages are driven down due to an excess supply of labour. On the other hand, the richer and affluent sections of the society become richer and richer, on account of declining labour wages. These sections are generally the ones having major wealth in the form of capital holdings.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result of the stark differences in the income levels, the poor people face a major problem of poverty and undernutrition, the cause of which can be broken down into three aspects: Parental Resources (low awareness and education among the poor, high morbidity), Household Resources (income levels of households) and Community Resources (unavailability of safe drinking water and sanitation). This leads to higher susceptibility to infections making them less capable to fight the pathogens. And when it comes to being tested positive for the virus, these individuals are likely to face higher mortality due to lack of access to public health services. Apart from this, we also observe large scale migration of poor from rural to urban areas in search of employment opportunities, which leads to increased population density in cities and makes them breeding ground for diseases again.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Particularly, the outbreak of novel coronavirus has led to an emergence of the ‘new normal’- work from home (WFH), since it is the only option to continue working and minimising the risk of virus exposure. Even though recent studies have shown an increase in average labour incomes because of this positive shift to work from home, the potential benefit will be highly asymmetrical,&amp;nbsp; favouring highly-educated and high-paid employees. Also, there are numerous jobs which cannot come under the ambit of this new normal, and individuals in these sectors have been rendered unemployed, worsening the income distribution.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The IMF, in its recent study, has analysed the aggregate decrease in income levels using its GDP growth projections for 2020. It has been found that the estimated effect of COVID-19 will be larger than that caused by the past pandemics and that gains achieved since the global financial crisis (2008) might be reversed. The analysis shows that the average &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gini_coefficient&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gini coefficient&lt;/a&gt; for emerging markets and developing economies will rise to 42.7, which is comparable to the level in 2008. The impact would be larger for low-income developing countries despite slower progress since 2008. The pandemic could also possibly reduce welfare by about 8% in emerging economies and developing nations with more than 50% change coming from the increase in inequality due to WFH feasibility.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imf.org/en/Publications/WEO#:~:text=Description%3A%20Global%20growth%20is%20projected,Economic%20Outlook%20(WEO)%20forecast.&amp;amp;text=In%202021%20global%20growth%20is,19%20projections%20of%20January%202020.&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/worldecon1.png&quot; /&gt;Figure 2. Source: World Bank&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problems don’t end here. When the vaccines for the virus come out, the market mechanism comes into play to dictate the distribution over and within the countries. The poor countries are very likely to be crowded out of the markets as they receive the vaccines at the very end, as these countries are plagued with poor health infrastructure. Within countries, the most vulnerable sections will find themselves unable to access the necessary medical aid. Even if in the end they are able to administer the vaccine, the damage would have been done. The pathogens might have been rendered ineffective. And therefore, the future generation is bound to face the ripples of the pandemic too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way the generation is doomed is the asymmetries in access to health and education services. With the mode of teaching being shifted online, children belonging to poor households face an amplified barrier to schooling and education.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And lastly, the social inequalities will create ‘avenues for development of unrest and discontentment among the people’ which in the long run leads to political upheavals and the rise of populist leaders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the pandemic proves to be perilous to the society in a multitude of ways that go over and above health risks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above-mentioned impact is on a global level. Now let’s analyse the impact of the pandemic so far on India, to understand how it is particularly bad.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In August 2020, Mukesh Ambani became the 4th richest person in the world. On the same day, a man reportedly committed suicide and killed his family because of job loss induced by the pandemic. The above case exactly represents the tale of two Indias and how badly this pandemic has affected the already high inequality in the country.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last 20 years, the increase in inequality has been the highest in India except Russia. As the rich get richer even amidst a pandemic, nearly 400 million workers are at the cusp of falling into abject poverty, as reported by the International Labour Organisation (ILO).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is often said that epidemics are true mirrors of society, and the COVID-19 outbreak has effectively mirrored the broken public healthcare system in India. In India, there exists significant inter-state and intra-state disparities. When it comes to distribution of doctors in urban and rural areas, there is a huge skewness observable. In terms of availability of hospital beds, states like Bihar are well below the national average of 0.55 beds in the public sector per 1,000 population while others like West Bengal (2.25 beds/1000) and Sikkim (2.34 beds/1000) have considerably more. The pandemic hit the country at a time when the country was facing an economic slowdown, and the public health crisis of this magnitude is going to have a further negative impact on the Indian economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of inequality is with respect to gender. With many companies enforcing strict social distancing guidelines and WFH policy, women even with full-time paid employment are facing reduced efficiency because of the additional and disproportionate share of the workload. Additionally, the concerns of rising domestic violence and sexual abuse paints a grim picture of state of women currently.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the line with the foregoing discussion, the first and foremost task is to secure the livelihoods of the most vulnerable sections of the society. The empowerment and growth of the global community is linked to the socio-economic well-being of each individual. While the impact of the pandemic can never be ascertained 100%, the policy measure taken today will be responsible for the outcomes for the future generations.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rajsi Sah</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The coronavirus outbreak has plunged the entire globe into a deep ‘shock’ with simultaneous disruptions to both the demand and supply side in a highly interdependent and interconnected world economy. The increased incidence of infections has led to a large reduction in labour supply and the initial period of lockdowns have led to a loss of income for several households. Yet, there has been one section of people that have been worst hit by the pandemic - ‘the poor’.&amp;nbsp; It is a general view that crises and pandemics like this often lead to the redistribution of resources among the masses, as the spread of the virus sees no caste, class and gender differences. However, this couldn’t be further away from reality. The COVID-19 has had a uniform impact on the entire world when it comes to the possibilities of being infected, but the social and economic impacts have been the most on the vulnerable sections of the society. In a recent study by the World Bank, “Global extreme poverty is expected to rise in 2020 for the first time in over 20 years. The COVID-19 pandemic is estimated to push an additional 88 million to 115 million people into extreme poverty this year, with the total rising to as many as 150 million by 2021.” The article is thus an attempt to shed light on how the pandemic transformed into a pandemic of inequality using various arguments.&amp;nbsp; Past Experiences A comparative analysis of the novel coronavirus and other past epidemics is often made to understand the relationship between the pandemics and inequalities caused across countries. The first example that comes into the mind is that of the 14th century Black Death which suggested that pandemics seem to reduce inequality in the long run. According to various studies conducted, the Black Death re-balanced the population, and available resources led to a useful reorganisation of agrarian production and triggered significant increases in real wages across the European continent. But the pandemics in recent history seem to have defied this theory. If recent episodes of pandemics are included, ranging from plagues to cholera pandemic et al, they fail to prove the substantial reduction in inequality levels. Instead, the levels have been observed to be increasing substantially, coinciding with the occurrence of these events. Therefore the impact of Black Death turns out to be an ‘exception’ in this case. An Uneven Playing Field Before we begin analysing this relationship between a pandemic and inequality, have a look at the rising income trend in the figure given below and keep it in mind. &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Figure 1. Source: World Bank Fundamentally, economic inequality refers to the unequal distribution of income and opportunity between different groups in society. According to Tony Atkinson, a renowned British economist, “Inequality of outcome among today’s generation is the source of the unfair advantage received by the next generation. If we are concerned about equality of opportunity tomorrow, we need to be concerned about inequality of outcome today.” In today’s world, inequality is a pressing concern transforming into a situation of emergency. The figure below visualises the inequality in living conditions between the world’s best-off and worst-off countries.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Figure 2. Source: World Bank&amp;nbsp; Income and wealth inequality have particularly witnessed an upward trend in all major advanced economies while for the emerging ones, the income distribution trends have been mixed but most of them are experiencing an upward trend too, led by major emerging economies such as China and India. In this scenario, the increase in inequality due to the current pandemic is quite worrisome.&amp;nbsp; In a study conducted Oxfam, a non-profit operating across the world, it is estimated that there are as much as 121 million more people on the brink of starvation today due to mass unemployment, disruption to food production and supplies. “As many as 12,000 people could die every day from COVID-linked hunger,” stated Oxfam. In the wake of these figures, it becomes imperative to understand the two-way relationship between pandemics and inequality, i.e. inequality is not just an impact of the pandemic, it is the cause of the outbreak itself.&amp;nbsp; It is no doubt that it is the extreme socio-economic inequalities and the lack of access to public healthcare facilities that have led to stark ill-proportioned costs being borne by these downtrodden individuals, both in terms of infection incidences as well as the economic well-being. But how exactly does this play out?&amp;nbsp; To begin with, the countries facing a sustained rise in population levels also experience an increasing population density, which therefore leads to a rise in the ability of the disease to reproduce and spread. At the same time, due to an increase in the labour force, the wages are driven down due to an excess supply of labour. On the other hand, the richer and affluent sections of the society become richer and richer, on account of declining labour wages. These sections are generally the ones having major wealth in the form of capital holdings.&amp;nbsp; As a result of the stark differences in the income levels, the poor people face a major problem of poverty and undernutrition, the cause of which can be broken down into three aspects: Parental Resources (low awareness and education among the poor, high morbidity), Household Resources (income levels of households) and Community Resources (unavailability of safe drinking water and sanitation). This leads to higher susceptibility to infections making them less capable to fight the pathogens. And when it comes to being tested positive for the virus, these individuals are likely to face higher mortality due to lack of access to public health services. Apart from this, we also observe large scale migration of poor from rural to urban areas in search of employment opportunities, which leads to increased population density in cities and makes them breeding ground for diseases again.&amp;nbsp; Particularly, the outbreak of novel coronavirus has led to an emergence of the ‘new normal’- work from home (WFH), since it is the only option to continue working and minimising the risk of virus exposure. Even though recent studies have shown an increase in average labour incomes because of this positive shift to work from home, the potential benefit will be highly asymmetrical,&amp;nbsp; favouring highly-educated and high-paid employees. Also, there are numerous jobs which cannot come under the ambit of this new normal, and individuals in these sectors have been rendered unemployed, worsening the income distribution.&amp;nbsp; The IMF, in its recent study, has analysed the aggregate decrease in income levels using its GDP growth projections for 2020. It has been found that the estimated effect of COVID-19 will be larger than that caused by the past pandemics and that gains achieved since the global financial crisis (2008) might be reversed. The analysis shows that the average Gini coefficient for emerging markets and developing economies will rise to 42.7, which is comparable to the level in 2008. The impact would be larger for low-income developing countries despite slower progress since 2008. The pandemic could also possibly reduce welfare by about 8% in emerging economies and developing nations with more than 50% change coming from the increase in inequality due to WFH feasibility.&amp;nbsp; Figure 2. Source: World Bank The problems don’t end here. When the vaccines for the virus come out, the market mechanism comes into play to dictate the distribution over and within the countries. The poor countries are very likely to be crowded out of the markets as they receive the vaccines at the very end, as these countries are plagued with poor health infrastructure. Within countries, the most vulnerable sections will find themselves unable to access the necessary medical aid. Even if in the end they are able to administer the vaccine, the damage would have been done. The pathogens might have been rendered ineffective. And therefore, the future generation is bound to face the ripples of the pandemic too.&amp;nbsp; Another way the generation is doomed is the asymmetries in access to health and education services. With the mode of teaching being shifted online, children belonging to poor households face an amplified barrier to schooling and education.&amp;nbsp; And lastly, the social inequalities will create ‘avenues for development of unrest and discontentment among the people’ which in the long run leads to political upheavals and the rise of populist leaders.&amp;nbsp; Thus, the pandemic proves to be perilous to the society in a multitude of ways that go over and above health risks.&amp;nbsp; The above-mentioned impact is on a global level. Now let’s analyse the impact of the pandemic so far on India, to understand how it is particularly bad.&amp;nbsp; In August 2020, Mukesh Ambani became the 4th richest person in the world. On the same day, a man reportedly committed suicide and killed his family because of job loss induced by the pandemic. The above case exactly represents the tale of two Indias and how badly this pandemic has affected the already high inequality in the country.&amp;nbsp; In the last 20 years, the increase in inequality has been the highest in India except Russia. As the rich get richer even amidst a pandemic, nearly 400 million workers are at the cusp of falling into abject poverty, as reported by the International Labour Organisation (ILO). It is often said that epidemics are true mirrors of society, and the COVID-19 outbreak has effectively mirrored the broken public healthcare system in India. In India, there exists significant inter-state and intra-state disparities. When it comes to distribution of doctors in urban and rural areas, there is a huge skewness observable. In terms of availability of hospital beds, states like Bihar are well below the national average of 0.55 beds in the public sector per 1,000 population while others like West Bengal (2.25 beds/1000) and Sikkim (2.34 beds/1000) have considerably more. The pandemic hit the country at a time when the country was facing an economic slowdown, and the public health crisis of this magnitude is going to have a further negative impact on the Indian economy.&amp;nbsp; Another aspect of inequality is with respect to gender. With many companies enforcing strict social distancing guidelines and WFH policy, women even with full-time paid employment are facing reduced efficiency because of the additional and disproportionate share of the workload. Additionally, the concerns of rising domestic violence and sexual abuse paints a grim picture of state of women currently.&amp;nbsp; In the line with the foregoing discussion, the first and foremost task is to secure the livelihoods of the most vulnerable sections of the society. The empowerment and growth of the global community is linked to the socio-economic well-being of each individual. While the impact of the pandemic can never be ascertained 100%, the policy measure taken today will be responsible for the outcomes for the future generations.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Understanding India’s Foreign Kitty Surge</title>
      <link href="/Understanding-India-s-Foreign-Kitty-Surge" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding India’s Foreign Kitty Surge" />
      <published>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Understanding-India-s-Foreign-Kitty-Surge</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-India-s-Foreign-Kitty-Surge">&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, the foreign exchange reserves of India, maintained by its Central Bank, have consistently managed to surpass their own all-time-high benchmarks. Since the COVID-19 crisis, the frequency of this phenomenon has risen to as often as every alternate week. As of writing this piece, the last surge recorded in the week ending November 6, 2020, was of $7.78 billion, pushing the forex reserves to touch a record high of $568.5 billion. The week prior, the reserves had risen by $183 million. While some renowned (pseudo) economists have celebrated these figures as a mark of the rising relative strength of the Indian rupee, this stance couldn’t be farther from the truth, and is therefore misleading and perhaps even partisan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foreign exchange reserves are maintained by the Central Bank of an economy for the sake of convenience for liquidity and currency value management, as well as for non-prosaic purposes such as maintaining favourable exchange rates for export competitiveness. They tend to be constituted of foreign currency assets (FCAs), Treasury bills, US government securities, gold reserves, special drawing rights, etc. To put it in quite a crude way, these assets are exchanged for the domestic currency of a country, by its Central Bank, in order to regulate its value relative to these assets. Therefore, the forex operations affect the exchange rate, and consequently the trade balances as well. Since the exchange of the Indian rupee, for or against the forex reserves, takes place between the Central Bank and the domestic financial institutions (which receive forex assets through market-driven influx), these operations also affect the domestic liquidity status. The status of special drawing rights (denoted by the acronym XDRs) in this mechanism is weak and disputed. They are maintained by the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and were created to overcome the shortcomings of the Bretton Woods System, which was in effect from 1945 to 1972. The monetary system which pegged every currency to the US Dollar, which in turn was pegged to gold at the rate of $35/ounce, practically mandated the use of USD as the global reserve currency. However, owing to the conservative monetary policy of the USA at that point, the XDRs acted as a debt instrument to cover for the shortfall of USD and provide sufficient liquidity globally. After the apparently invariable transition of the USA’s policy stance to profligate practices, the system came to an end in 1972, rendering the XDRs as mere foreign exchange reserve assets, on which interest is payable or receivable if they are kept below or beyond (respectively) the level allocated by the IMF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India, over the past three decades, has transitioned from the pre-liberalisation levels of $5 billion of foreign exchange reserves to exceeding $560 billion last October, registering a 10,000% increase, which makes it the fifth-largest reserves accumulated by any economy. The fact that the status of the low reserve mapped with the 1991 economic crisis, does not by any chance imply that the all-time high reserves are indicative of economic prosperity. Although the level of foreign exchange reserves impacts the domestic liquidity status, it is not actively used as a monetary policy tool. More so, it is used to regulate the foreign exchange rate, through which it impacts the domestic liquidity. So an increase in the reserves is a response to mitigate unruly upward fluctuation in the value of the domestic currency. By increasing the forex reserves, usually done by increasing the FCAs, the relative demand for the foreign currency rises, bringing down the value of the domestic currency relative to the chosen forex asset. Whether the increase in an economy’s forex reserves is good news or not depends on what the source of the appreciation is. India’s balance of payments (BoP) status usually follows the pattern of a current account deficit, i.e., a trade deficit, and a capital account surplus, indicating investment inflows. Due to India’s popular Emerging Market Economy (EME) status, the capital inflows spiked amidst the dovish environment in the developed economies last year. Such inflows cause an appreciation of the Indian rupee, which can adversely affect the trade balance by making the exports less competitive in the global economy. The increase in forex reserves to avoid the appreciation involves purchasing USD from the local banks in exchange for the Indian rupee. As a result, domestic liquidity rises even if the economy does not need it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the classic impossible trinity issue India faces, where in order to retain near-fixed exchange rates and a free flow in capital markets, the economy must partially let go of the independence of its monetary policy. This excess liquidity in domestic markets would be inflationary and could create macro-level imbalances. Of course, many argue that this liquidity can be merely sterilised. Sterilisation involves soaking up the excess liquidity without involving the forex assets so that the original purpose of exchange rate stability does not get defeated. So the RBI could simply sell government bonds through open market operations (OMOs) and take back the rupees that the markets were flooded with. But this would be counterproductive. By selling government securities through OMOs, their market supply rises and the prices fall, which results in a reduction in the domestic rates, thus discouraging the inflow of foreign investment. This would render the entire exercise futile. Clearly, there is no evident pathway towards resolving the trilemma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in the current scenario, something much graver is under effect. The BoP surplus is a consequence of both investment inflows, as well as a (once in a blue moon) trade surplus that was registered due to feeble global demand. In order to prevent the exacerbation of the trade imbalances through appreciation, the forex reserves have been rising at an all-time high pace. As opposed to the previous scenario, this would mean that the resultant increase in domestic liquidity is not a major issue because the domestic economy is also recessionary and therefore could use this liquidity. This is also why we have not seen the policy rates being slashed despite the tight situation. Any more liquidity would mean risking inflationary pressures. Additionally, most economists would agree that the recessionary situation needs to be dealt with in a more targeted way, i.e. through fiscal policy. The problem is, how would the government finance its expenditure?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India’s fiscal response to the situation, despite all its cautiousness, has been projected to take the fiscal deficit to 13.1% of GDP in the fiscal year 2020-21. This increase in deficits, though in line with the average increase registered by Emerging Market Economies, remains insufficient in the case of India. This is primarily due to the composition of the deficits. A major chunk of the deficits is owed to the reduction in collection of GST, and other automatic cyclical responses. Only a small proportion, 1.8% of the GDP, is the fiscal deficit owed to discretionary fiscal response, one that arises due to an increase in the expenditure or reduction of taxes. In order to get the economic cycle running again, more discretionary expenditure needs to be undertaken, which will not be possible unless the Reserve Bank of India manages to finance it by creating demand for government securities via OMO. But that would mean adding further liquidity to an economy where the fires of inflationary pressures have already been stoked by the forex operations. With nearly two lost years to get to pre-pandemic levels of output, the economy must make a choice between securing its interests in the international markets or getting the internal demand cycle running first.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Over the past year, the foreign exchange reserves of India, maintained by its Central Bank, have consistently managed to surpass their own all-time-high benchmarks. Since the COVID-19 crisis, the frequency of this phenomenon has risen to as often as every alternate week. As of writing this piece, the last surge recorded in the week ending November 6, 2020, was of $7.78 billion, pushing the forex reserves to touch a record high of $568.5 billion. The week prior, the reserves had risen by $183 million. While some renowned (pseudo) economists have celebrated these figures as a mark of the rising relative strength of the Indian rupee, this stance couldn’t be farther from the truth, and is therefore misleading and perhaps even partisan. The foreign exchange reserves are maintained by the Central Bank of an economy for the sake of convenience for liquidity and currency value management, as well as for non-prosaic purposes such as maintaining favourable exchange rates for export competitiveness. They tend to be constituted of foreign currency assets (FCAs), Treasury bills, US government securities, gold reserves, special drawing rights, etc. To put it in quite a crude way, these assets are exchanged for the domestic currency of a country, by its Central Bank, in order to regulate its value relative to these assets. Therefore, the forex operations affect the exchange rate, and consequently the trade balances as well. Since the exchange of the Indian rupee, for or against the forex reserves, takes place between the Central Bank and the domestic financial institutions (which receive forex assets through market-driven influx), these operations also affect the domestic liquidity status. The status of special drawing rights (denoted by the acronym XDRs) in this mechanism is weak and disputed. They are maintained by the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and were created to overcome the shortcomings of the Bretton Woods System, which was in effect from 1945 to 1972. The monetary system which pegged every currency to the US Dollar, which in turn was pegged to gold at the rate of $35/ounce, practically mandated the use of USD as the global reserve currency. However, owing to the conservative monetary policy of the USA at that point, the XDRs acted as a debt instrument to cover for the shortfall of USD and provide sufficient liquidity globally. After the apparently invariable transition of the USA’s policy stance to profligate practices, the system came to an end in 1972, rendering the XDRs as mere foreign exchange reserve assets, on which interest is payable or receivable if they are kept below or beyond (respectively) the level allocated by the IMF. India, over the past three decades, has transitioned from the pre-liberalisation levels of $5 billion of foreign exchange reserves to exceeding $560 billion last October, registering a 10,000% increase, which makes it the fifth-largest reserves accumulated by any economy. The fact that the status of the low reserve mapped with the 1991 economic crisis, does not by any chance imply that the all-time high reserves are indicative of economic prosperity. Although the level of foreign exchange reserves impacts the domestic liquidity status, it is not actively used as a monetary policy tool. More so, it is used to regulate the foreign exchange rate, through which it impacts the domestic liquidity. So an increase in the reserves is a response to mitigate unruly upward fluctuation in the value of the domestic currency. By increasing the forex reserves, usually done by increasing the FCAs, the relative demand for the foreign currency rises, bringing down the value of the domestic currency relative to the chosen forex asset. Whether the increase in an economy’s forex reserves is good news or not depends on what the source of the appreciation is. India’s balance of payments (BoP) status usually follows the pattern of a current account deficit, i.e., a trade deficit, and a capital account surplus, indicating investment inflows. Due to India’s popular Emerging Market Economy (EME) status, the capital inflows spiked amidst the dovish environment in the developed economies last year. Such inflows cause an appreciation of the Indian rupee, which can adversely affect the trade balance by making the exports less competitive in the global economy. The increase in forex reserves to avoid the appreciation involves purchasing USD from the local banks in exchange for the Indian rupee. As a result, domestic liquidity rises even if the economy does not need it.&amp;nbsp; This is the classic impossible trinity issue India faces, where in order to retain near-fixed exchange rates and a free flow in capital markets, the economy must partially let go of the independence of its monetary policy. This excess liquidity in domestic markets would be inflationary and could create macro-level imbalances. Of course, many argue that this liquidity can be merely sterilised. Sterilisation involves soaking up the excess liquidity without involving the forex assets so that the original purpose of exchange rate stability does not get defeated. So the RBI could simply sell government bonds through open market operations (OMOs) and take back the rupees that the markets were flooded with. But this would be counterproductive. By selling government securities through OMOs, their market supply rises and the prices fall, which results in a reduction in the domestic rates, thus discouraging the inflow of foreign investment. This would render the entire exercise futile. Clearly, there is no evident pathway towards resolving the trilemma. However, in the current scenario, something much graver is under effect. The BoP surplus is a consequence of both investment inflows, as well as a (once in a blue moon) trade surplus that was registered due to feeble global demand. In order to prevent the exacerbation of the trade imbalances through appreciation, the forex reserves have been rising at an all-time high pace. As opposed to the previous scenario, this would mean that the resultant increase in domestic liquidity is not a major issue because the domestic economy is also recessionary and therefore could use this liquidity. This is also why we have not seen the policy rates being slashed despite the tight situation. Any more liquidity would mean risking inflationary pressures. Additionally, most economists would agree that the recessionary situation needs to be dealt with in a more targeted way, i.e. through fiscal policy. The problem is, how would the government finance its expenditure?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; India’s fiscal response to the situation, despite all its cautiousness, has been projected to take the fiscal deficit to 13.1% of GDP in the fiscal year 2020-21. This increase in deficits, though in line with the average increase registered by Emerging Market Economies, remains insufficient in the case of India. This is primarily due to the composition of the deficits. A major chunk of the deficits is owed to the reduction in collection of GST, and other automatic cyclical responses. Only a small proportion, 1.8% of the GDP, is the fiscal deficit owed to discretionary fiscal response, one that arises due to an increase in the expenditure or reduction of taxes. In order to get the economic cycle running again, more discretionary expenditure needs to be undertaken, which will not be possible unless the Reserve Bank of India manages to finance it by creating demand for government securities via OMO. But that would mean adding further liquidity to an economy where the fires of inflationary pressures have already been stoked by the forex operations. With nearly two lost years to get to pre-pandemic levels of output, the economy must make a choice between securing its interests in the international markets or getting the internal demand cycle running first.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Modern Monetary Theory: The Solution to Developing Countries’ Problems?</title>
      <link href="/Modern-Monetary-Theory" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modern Monetary Theory: The Solution to Developing Countries’ Problems?" />
      <published>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Modern-Monetary-Theory</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Modern-Monetary-Theory">&lt;p&gt;Modern Monetary Theory (MMT) is increasingly gaining traction in today’s public discourse. While there is huge literature available regarding MMT, it is often ridiculed by statements claiming to explain the theory, such as “&lt;em&gt;money printer gone brrrr&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; It is important to know that MMT doesn’t advocate for money printing. To borrow from L Randall Wray, a pioneer of the field, MMT argues that a sovereign government that issues its own “nonconvertible” currency cannot become insolvent (in terms of its own currency). It cannot be forced into involuntary default on its obligations denominated in its own currency. It can “afford” to buy anything for sale that is priced in its own currency. Here sovereignty is defined in monetary terms in that a state has monetary sovereignty when it issues its own currency, taxes its people in that currency, accepts that currency in payment of the imposed obligations, and issues debt in its own currency. Along with this, a fifth consideration, according to Wray, is to have a floating exchange rate regime (which is what “nonconvertible” currency means); so that it provides more fiscal space for the government.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MMTers argue that their descriptions and prescriptions equally hold for the developing nations as for the developed nations. While this is largely true, there are however some constraints with regard to the developing countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first such constraint is the need for a developing country to accumulate foreign currency, especially the international reserve currency - the dollar. One major factor that leads to this accumulation is the necessity to import various types of goods (which could be for various reasons). So, with the accumulation of external debt, the demand for foreign currency also increases because it leads to higher debt service obligations and also because it increases risk perception as there is greater exposure to currency mismatch. The accumulation of foreign debt means that the balance of payments becomes a major limitation on the policy front for a developing country. In the current account of the balance of payments, a trade deficit (imports &amp;gt; exports) is compensated by positive capital inflows (which leads to a surplus in the capital account). That is, a current account deficit must be balanced by the sum of the capital account. Randal Wray once wrote that “&lt;em&gt;MMT makes no claim that floating rates eliminate current account deficits, indeed, MMT does not argue that elimination of current account deficits is even desirable”&lt;/em&gt;. But, the said balancing does not mean that a country can sustain any level of the current account deficit, over time. There is ample evidence available that the higher the current account deficit, the less likely that it can be sustained. What all this means is that the current account deficit chips away the monetary sovereignty of developing countries and thus the validity of MMT in such countries becomes uncertain.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second issue, which is related here is that Wray suggests that in a floating exchange regime a government does not need to fear that it will run out of foreign currency reserves (or gold reserves) for the simple reason that it does not convert its domestic currency to foreign currency at a fixed exchange rate. Indeed, the government does not have to promise to make any conversions at all. But a developing country necessarily concerns itself with the capital flows not because of the issue of convertibility of currency, but because it needs to pay for its imports (or some sort of short-term obligation). All this is to say that a developing country may very well face the risk of foreign debt default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fadhel Kaboub, another MMT economist, identifies three broad areas from where a trade deficit arises. It arises because the developing country lacks food sovereignty, energy sovereignty and they essentially export low-value goods and import high-value goods. He says that this is a trap, in that a trade deficit leads a country to accumulate foreign currency. To do this, domestic resources are diverted from the areas of the government’s priority to areas that earn foreign exchange for the country. For instance, a government may prioritise the needs of foreign tourists as they spend the foreign currency or the government may announce tax concessions with the hope to attract foreign investors and end up losing revenue which could otherwise be used to develop local government. So, his advice to developing countries is to invest in sustainable agriculture to reach a level of self-sufficiency, to invest in renewable energy production that allows the countries to set their priorities, to invest in education, and to prepare an industrial strategy to move up the value chain from producing low-value-added goods to high-value-added goods. All these will provide resilience for a country from external shocks that a country may face.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A third important constraint is inflation. MMT argues that while a sovereign can never default, there are limits as to how much it can spend; that is, there are certain limits on the fiscal deficit a sovereign runs. These limits are in the form of constraints on the part of real resources in an economy. If a government spends more than what these real resources could absorb, it risks the possibility of price hikes, i.e. inflation. MMT’s prescription to this problem is that the government could increase tax rates so that the purchasing power of the economy as a whole falls and thus inflation could be arrested (note that MMT also says tax revenue does not pay for anything but gives several other reasons for justifying the taxes). Now, in developing countries, there are two main problems with this. First, the tax base is lower in developing countries. Therefore, even when taxes are increased there might not be the desired effect of reducing purchasing power and thus controlling inflation. The prevalence of the informal economy on a large scale is also a constraint in this context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is true that developing economies face certain constraints that the MMT approach has not fully gauged. For instance, a developed country might not have constraints of fiscal space due to the current account of the balance of payments (and due to implications thereof). However, it can also be argued that it is precisely the understanding and the implementation of MMT that is required for the developing countries to overcome these constraints. The primary focus of MMT on real resources can be an important takeaway for developing economies because the development of real resources (in part) entails huge investments in developing human capital, green resources, and health resources. Despite many constraints, MMT also opens many doors for the developing economies.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Modern Monetary Theory (MMT) is increasingly gaining traction in today’s public discourse. While there is huge literature available regarding MMT, it is often ridiculed by statements claiming to explain the theory, such as “money printer gone brrrr”. It is important to know that MMT doesn’t advocate for money printing. To borrow from L Randall Wray, a pioneer of the field, MMT argues that a sovereign government that issues its own “nonconvertible” currency cannot become insolvent (in terms of its own currency). It cannot be forced into involuntary default on its obligations denominated in its own currency. It can “afford” to buy anything for sale that is priced in its own currency. Here sovereignty is defined in monetary terms in that a state has monetary sovereignty when it issues its own currency, taxes its people in that currency, accepts that currency in payment of the imposed obligations, and issues debt in its own currency. Along with this, a fifth consideration, according to Wray, is to have a floating exchange rate regime (which is what “nonconvertible” currency means); so that it provides more fiscal space for the government.&amp;nbsp; MMTers argue that their descriptions and prescriptions equally hold for the developing nations as for the developed nations. While this is largely true, there are however some constraints with regard to the developing countries.&amp;nbsp; The first such constraint is the need for a developing country to accumulate foreign currency, especially the international reserve currency - the dollar. One major factor that leads to this accumulation is the necessity to import various types of goods (which could be for various reasons). So, with the accumulation of external debt, the demand for foreign currency also increases because it leads to higher debt service obligations and also because it increases risk perception as there is greater exposure to currency mismatch. The accumulation of foreign debt means that the balance of payments becomes a major limitation on the policy front for a developing country. In the current account of the balance of payments, a trade deficit (imports &amp;gt; exports) is compensated by positive capital inflows (which leads to a surplus in the capital account). That is, a current account deficit must be balanced by the sum of the capital account. Randal Wray once wrote that “MMT makes no claim that floating rates eliminate current account deficits, indeed, MMT does not argue that elimination of current account deficits is even desirable”. But, the said balancing does not mean that a country can sustain any level of the current account deficit, over time. There is ample evidence available that the higher the current account deficit, the less likely that it can be sustained. What all this means is that the current account deficit chips away the monetary sovereignty of developing countries and thus the validity of MMT in such countries becomes uncertain.&amp;nbsp; A second issue, which is related here is that Wray suggests that in a floating exchange regime a government does not need to fear that it will run out of foreign currency reserves (or gold reserves) for the simple reason that it does not convert its domestic currency to foreign currency at a fixed exchange rate. Indeed, the government does not have to promise to make any conversions at all. But a developing country necessarily concerns itself with the capital flows not because of the issue of convertibility of currency, but because it needs to pay for its imports (or some sort of short-term obligation). All this is to say that a developing country may very well face the risk of foreign debt default. Fadhel Kaboub, another MMT economist, identifies three broad areas from where a trade deficit arises. It arises because the developing country lacks food sovereignty, energy sovereignty and they essentially export low-value goods and import high-value goods. He says that this is a trap, in that a trade deficit leads a country to accumulate foreign currency. To do this, domestic resources are diverted from the areas of the government’s priority to areas that earn foreign exchange for the country. For instance, a government may prioritise the needs of foreign tourists as they spend the foreign currency or the government may announce tax concessions with the hope to attract foreign investors and end up losing revenue which could otherwise be used to develop local government. So, his advice to developing countries is to invest in sustainable agriculture to reach a level of self-sufficiency, to invest in renewable energy production that allows the countries to set their priorities, to invest in education, and to prepare an industrial strategy to move up the value chain from producing low-value-added goods to high-value-added goods. All these will provide resilience for a country from external shocks that a country may face.&amp;nbsp; A third important constraint is inflation. MMT argues that while a sovereign can never default, there are limits as to how much it can spend; that is, there are certain limits on the fiscal deficit a sovereign runs. These limits are in the form of constraints on the part of real resources in an economy. If a government spends more than what these real resources could absorb, it risks the possibility of price hikes, i.e. inflation. MMT’s prescription to this problem is that the government could increase tax rates so that the purchasing power of the economy as a whole falls and thus inflation could be arrested (note that MMT also says tax revenue does not pay for anything but gives several other reasons for justifying the taxes). Now, in developing countries, there are two main problems with this. First, the tax base is lower in developing countries. Therefore, even when taxes are increased there might not be the desired effect of reducing purchasing power and thus controlling inflation. The prevalence of the informal economy on a large scale is also a constraint in this context. It is true that developing economies face certain constraints that the MMT approach has not fully gauged. For instance, a developed country might not have constraints of fiscal space due to the current account of the balance of payments (and due to implications thereof). However, it can also be argued that it is precisely the understanding and the implementation of MMT that is required for the developing countries to overcome these constraints. The primary focus of MMT on real resources can be an important takeaway for developing economies because the development of real resources (in part) entails huge investments in developing human capital, green resources, and health resources. Despite many constraints, MMT also opens many doors for the developing economies.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Are Economists Evolving to be Engineers?</title>
      <link href="/Are-Economists-Evolving-to-be-Engineers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are Economists Evolving to be Engineers?" />
      <published>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Are-Economists-Evolving-to-be-Engineers</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Are-Economists-Evolving-to-be-Engineers">&lt;p&gt;The opening match of the Indian Premier League 2020 was viewed by over 200 million people. A record-breaking viewership figure for the opening-day of a sports event in any country. This shows the buzz among viewers for this annually conducted India-based event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes the show more breathtaking is the custom of the auction of players that takes place months prior to the final episode. Cricket admirers would also be aware of the most tragic bids of cricket history. Recall Tymal Mills, one of the players auctioned, was one of the most expensive purchases of season 10. Consequently, he struggled to find a purchaser in the following season because of his disappointing performance in the former season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why did the team pay an exorbitantly high sum of ₹120 million for such a player? What could be the reason behind the faulty valuation of Tymal Mills? The truth is that such glitches and miscalculations in auctions are not uncommon as the modern form of auctions is not just restricted to the disposal of a bankrupt’s property. It is a lot more than that. Auctioning telecom spectrums, oil wells, airport landing slots - it is indeed a mind boggling process. And a solution to such a process fetched the Nobel Prize 2020 for economics to Paul R Milgrom and Robert B Wilson. These researchers tried to evaluate the outcomes of different rules of bidding and final prices and devised a framework “&lt;em&gt;for improvements to auction theory and invention of new auction formats.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story dates back to the times when the telecom spectrum was sold to companies in the form of beauty contests. Basically, the one with the best plan was the winner. However, it was subject to lobbying. Approaches like political markets and lotteries were also adopted though both of these approaches were biased and led to unjustified distribution. As a resort, in 1994, the laureates introduced ‘simultaneous multiple round auctions’ for radio spectrum sale. This arrangement helped governments to sell the commodity rights at a competitive price - a price not too trivial which could result in losses and not too high. It ultimately helped the sellers find the buyer who values his product most. This format initially adopted by the USA’s Federal Communications Commission (FCC) is now used throughout the world for the allocation of natural resources.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Auction theory sounds simple considering that the buyer’s motive is to be able to purchase something at the lowest possible price. Economists also try their hands at game theory to find out all the predictions that could be made by bidders before quoting a price. However, in real life auctions, this prognosis won’t be a smooth ride. As bidders with little information available about the product struggle to find out its worth. At the same time, sellers face problems executing the sale of a bunch of items at the same time. They have to protect the auction from purchasers who might collaborate amongst themselves behind the scenes hence hampering the dignity of the auction. The auction theory of these Stanford University-affiliated economists aided in implementing the sale of complex goods. Their thesis is based on the following three factors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;They explained how rules of auction affect the behaviour of bidders and revenues brought in for sellers hence defying the ‘revenue equivalence theorem’. Are the bids open or closed? How many times can a participant bid? What amount shall the winner be liable to pay? All such statutes cause changes in the bidders’ attitude. The most suitable example of such a situation was quoted in a case study by &lt;em&gt;The Hindu&lt;/em&gt; which narrated a spectrum auction of New Zealand which took place in 1990. The auction was a Vickrey auction. Here, the winner was liable to pay the second-highest bid. Due to this, a company that actually bid NZ$100,000 ultimately ended up paying just NZ$6. Hence a difference in guidelines brought a major transformation in the amount the seller would have earned if the rules were slightly different.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The commodity or service that is being put to sale. The circumstances of a painting being auctioned shall enormously vary from telecom auctions.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;What are the uncertainties involved in the sale? What is the information available to a bidder about the product? A bidder is aware of the royal history of a mansion might view it differently from one unaware of it.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wilson, according to the prize committee devised that the auction of objects with a common value which is uncertain earlier becomes common for everyone at the end and that winners should bid below the common value of a product to eschew the winner’s curse. For a more extensive understanding let’s find out what is this common value, private value, and the winner’s curse.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Winner’s curse refers to a situation when the intrinsic value of a product is lower than its estimated value. This is a phenomenon that usually arises when bidders have no way of evaluating the exact intrinsic value of a product and offer a price as per their own assessment of the object. As happened in the case of Tymal Mills stated above - the team overestimated the performance of this player ending up winning the bid but losing the game. The winner is usually the one with the most optimistic estimation of the product while he may later realise that valuation by him was way higher in comparison to other bidders. This paradox was quoted by the 2017 Economics Nobel prize winner, Richard Thaler in &lt;em&gt;Misbehaving: The making of behavioural economics&lt;/em&gt; as “&lt;em&gt;When many bidders compete for the same object, the winner of the auction is often the bidder who most overvalues the product being sold&lt;/em&gt;”. This phenomenon even poses a question to the hypothesis of efficient markets. If the markets would have been efficient then there wouldn’t be such variation in the valuation by different bidders as all shall possess symmetric information.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another deciding factor for the price is the private value of the commodity. It is an individual’s outlook towards a product based on the personal information he possesses. For instance, in the auction of a painting, the private value of that art shall be the pleasure that the bidder is seeking from it for his own sake. However, when he would like to sell that painting in the future then what shall matter to him is the common value which is based on what others think will be the possible price. It is due to the private value of an object that bidders might have massive variations in their bids depending on their own circumstances. For instance, a company with an ability to sell oil at higher prices or process it at a lower price might be ready to bid higher for crude oil.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering this, Wilson studied the buyers who overpaid for US oil leases in the 1970's and earned lower returns due to the winner’s curse. He argued that the most rational approach is to place a bid below the perceived common value of resources. Milgrom nonetheless focused on a more general theory of auction and analysed different bidding strategies in a plethora of auction formats and concluded that it shall be the most profitable deal for the seller when they share more information with potential buyers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, these laureates have made a major contribution to society by devising a theory that has practical engineering applications. This new auction format is a more sorted approach to sell complex goods and is a well-designed system for both private and public sellers to design their auctions proficiently. With this theory, the researchers advocate that like physics and chemistry, economic theories can also create useful technologies for both companies and the government. This even justifies how economists who earlier only acted as advisors to government now play an indispensable role in corporate companies too.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pragati Agrawal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The opening match of the Indian Premier League 2020 was viewed by over 200 million people. A record-breaking viewership figure for the opening-day of a sports event in any country. This shows the buzz among viewers for this annually conducted India-based event. What makes the show more breathtaking is the custom of the auction of players that takes place months prior to the final episode. Cricket admirers would also be aware of the most tragic bids of cricket history. Recall Tymal Mills, one of the players auctioned, was one of the most expensive purchases of season 10. Consequently, he struggled to find a purchaser in the following season because of his disappointing performance in the former season. So why did the team pay an exorbitantly high sum of ₹120 million for such a player? What could be the reason behind the faulty valuation of Tymal Mills? The truth is that such glitches and miscalculations in auctions are not uncommon as the modern form of auctions is not just restricted to the disposal of a bankrupt’s property. It is a lot more than that. Auctioning telecom spectrums, oil wells, airport landing slots - it is indeed a mind boggling process. And a solution to such a process fetched the Nobel Prize 2020 for economics to Paul R Milgrom and Robert B Wilson. These researchers tried to evaluate the outcomes of different rules of bidding and final prices and devised a framework “for improvements to auction theory and invention of new auction formats.” The story dates back to the times when the telecom spectrum was sold to companies in the form of beauty contests. Basically, the one with the best plan was the winner. However, it was subject to lobbying. Approaches like political markets and lotteries were also adopted though both of these approaches were biased and led to unjustified distribution. As a resort, in 1994, the laureates introduced ‘simultaneous multiple round auctions’ for radio spectrum sale. This arrangement helped governments to sell the commodity rights at a competitive price - a price not too trivial which could result in losses and not too high. It ultimately helped the sellers find the buyer who values his product most. This format initially adopted by the USA’s Federal Communications Commission (FCC) is now used throughout the world for the allocation of natural resources.&amp;nbsp; Auction theory sounds simple considering that the buyer’s motive is to be able to purchase something at the lowest possible price. Economists also try their hands at game theory to find out all the predictions that could be made by bidders before quoting a price. However, in real life auctions, this prognosis won’t be a smooth ride. As bidders with little information available about the product struggle to find out its worth. At the same time, sellers face problems executing the sale of a bunch of items at the same time. They have to protect the auction from purchasers who might collaborate amongst themselves behind the scenes hence hampering the dignity of the auction. The auction theory of these Stanford University-affiliated economists aided in implementing the sale of complex goods. Their thesis is based on the following three factors: They explained how rules of auction affect the behaviour of bidders and revenues brought in for sellers hence defying the ‘revenue equivalence theorem’. Are the bids open or closed? How many times can a participant bid? What amount shall the winner be liable to pay? All such statutes cause changes in the bidders’ attitude. The most suitable example of such a situation was quoted in a case study by The Hindu which narrated a spectrum auction of New Zealand which took place in 1990. The auction was a Vickrey auction. Here, the winner was liable to pay the second-highest bid. Due to this, a company that actually bid NZ$100,000 ultimately ended up paying just NZ$6. Hence a difference in guidelines brought a major transformation in the amount the seller would have earned if the rules were slightly different.The commodity or service that is being put to sale. The circumstances of a painting being auctioned shall enormously vary from telecom auctions.What are the uncertainties involved in the sale? What is the information available to a bidder about the product? A bidder is aware of the royal history of a mansion might view it differently from one unaware of it. Wilson, according to the prize committee devised that the auction of objects with a common value which is uncertain earlier becomes common for everyone at the end and that winners should bid below the common value of a product to eschew the winner’s curse. For a more extensive understanding let’s find out what is this common value, private value, and the winner’s curse.&amp;nbsp; Winner’s curse refers to a situation when the intrinsic value of a product is lower than its estimated value. This is a phenomenon that usually arises when bidders have no way of evaluating the exact intrinsic value of a product and offer a price as per their own assessment of the object. As happened in the case of Tymal Mills stated above - the team overestimated the performance of this player ending up winning the bid but losing the game. The winner is usually the one with the most optimistic estimation of the product while he may later realise that valuation by him was way higher in comparison to other bidders. This paradox was quoted by the 2017 Economics Nobel prize winner, Richard Thaler in Misbehaving: The making of behavioural economics as “When many bidders compete for the same object, the winner of the auction is often the bidder who most overvalues the product being sold”. This phenomenon even poses a question to the hypothesis of efficient markets. If the markets would have been efficient then there wouldn’t be such variation in the valuation by different bidders as all shall possess symmetric information.&amp;nbsp; Another deciding factor for the price is the private value of the commodity. It is an individual’s outlook towards a product based on the personal information he possesses. For instance, in the auction of a painting, the private value of that art shall be the pleasure that the bidder is seeking from it for his own sake. However, when he would like to sell that painting in the future then what shall matter to him is the common value which is based on what others think will be the possible price. It is due to the private value of an object that bidders might have massive variations in their bids depending on their own circumstances. For instance, a company with an ability to sell oil at higher prices or process it at a lower price might be ready to bid higher for crude oil.&amp;nbsp; Considering this, Wilson studied the buyers who overpaid for US oil leases in the 1970's and earned lower returns due to the winner’s curse. He argued that the most rational approach is to place a bid below the perceived common value of resources. Milgrom nonetheless focused on a more general theory of auction and analysed different bidding strategies in a plethora of auction formats and concluded that it shall be the most profitable deal for the seller when they share more information with potential buyers. Hence, these laureates have made a major contribution to society by devising a theory that has practical engineering applications. This new auction format is a more sorted approach to sell complex goods and is a well-designed system for both private and public sellers to design their auctions proficiently. With this theory, the researchers advocate that like physics and chemistry, economic theories can also create useful technologies for both companies and the government. This even justifies how economists who earlier only acted as advisors to government now play an indispensable role in corporate companies too.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Drama in Action: ‘Rent a Womb but at what Cost?’</title>
      <link href="/A-Drama-in-Action" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Drama in Action: ‘Rent a Womb but at what Cost?’" />
      <published>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Drama-in-Action</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Drama-in-Action">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene One: The Backdrop&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Change is the only constant. Evolution took humans from a hunch-backed species to one that stands upright, from broader jaws to narrower ones and, if we were to believe scientific findings, from a smaller brain size to a larger one. The species evolved and evolved from one huge scientific name to another. But three things that make humans what they inherently are remained unchanged – the body, the soul and expectations. If we are to believe religious and spiritual texts, the body and the soul are accompanied by the mind, but the mind begets expectations arising from desires, and hence for the sake of simplicity, just like an economist would do, we assume the mind to be our expectations. Therefore, even though humans evolved and changed in their physical form, one thing did in fact remain unchanged and constant, that is their expectations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene Two: The Groundwork&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drifting a little away from evolution and bringing ourselves to the present, societies are laden with a myriad of desires and expectations, more so than just their needs, and sometimes overstepping their wants. The sort of mindset embedded in a society’s head is that of the likelihood of certain outcomes, rather than a proven possibility of them to actually occur. Put in simpler words, the likelihood of someone getting severely hurt someday leads to families saving some money, the likelihood of earning profits leads to investments, and so on. This mirage of an outcome in the future leads to tremendous amounts of pressure in the society to do exactly what the society dictates and deems as 'fit' to exist. And society dictates – every married couple must have a child.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene Three: The Curtain Raiser.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equating happiness with expecting a child, millions of couples resort to the method of surrogacy to have a child of their own. In simple words, surrogacy is a process wherein a woman carries and cares for the child in her womb, that is not her own, but she is willingly carrying for the intended parents who can’t carry a child of their own. Whenever the intended parents compensate the surrogate mother monetarily, it is known as ‘commercial surrogacy’, and otherwise, an ‘altruistic surrogacy’, usually done by a relative/friend. The legality of such agreements between intended parents and the surrogate mother are subjective to various countries and their jurisdictions on the issue. While some countries have banned commercial surrogacy altogether, some developing countries are hubs of surrogacy with an incremental flow of intended parents to these hubs to fulfil their desires. This form of a transnational surrogacy has opened way too many doors for intended parents to exploit and prey on the poor and vulnerable surrogate mothers who are in dire need of the money they could have potentially earned by putting their bodies up for use.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene Four: The Highlight.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There hasn’t been a lack of debates around surrogacy and while most countries have spoken and passed laws in favour of altruistic surrogacy, there are still questions of whether it is ethical to commodify women’s bodies and the kinds of economic impacts attached with the legality of surrogacy. First issues first, the commodification of the bodies of these surrogate mothers is more than just an ethical question. Women who willingly opt to become surrogate mothers usually belong to the weaker sections of the society, which brings to light the kind of structural flaws existing in these developing economies that the women find it to be the last resort to put up their bodies to use in order to live from hand to mouth. Their livelihoods rely on this sort of money, and even when governments choose to ban commercial surrogacy to be able to curb the commodification of bodies, they don’t provide these women with a safety net, and hence their upliftment goes out of the question. In fact, for some, this is the only means of livelihood. For that, they have to go through so much emotional and physical labour and also have to change their entire lives’ priorities. Moreover, the fact that in a market, a commodity is taken from its producer and sold off to a consumer stands rather highly unethically true in this case, but it’s not the child being sold off here since the intended parents already have a right on it, but the gestational services of the surrogate being sold off as a mere commodity and as any other labour activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the economic implications of the legality of surrogacy come with a deep understanding of how economics in general works. The kind of expectations talked about at the beginning of the article is as much part of economics as any other economic jargon. That is because expectations lead to desires and wants, which is when we as rational humans choose to make decisions that provide us with maximum satisfaction and utility.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any legal agreement, the two sides of parties always choose the kind of terms that provide the maximum utility to each of them. Naturally, everybody responds to incentives and here, the intended parents wish for a child while the surrogate mother wishes to obtain that sum of money that she needs for herself or her family. The enforceability of these contracts is rather highly pedestaled by these parties because both of them want their end of the contract to be fulfilled. This is when the aspect of exploitation comes into play when these vulnerable women fail to understand the nitty-gritty of such contracts, of which the intended parents, who are in fact financially stable, take undue advantage and get away with paying less to no amount of money to these surrogate mothers. For several small towns in developing economies, the money coming in from surrogacy is extremely essential for the survival of families, and with the rise in exploitation, they are not just left economically worse-off, but also emotionally. The kind of emotional labour that goes into bearing a child is also something that the surrogate mothers already go through, but with the money coming in, it is marginally easier for them to let go of this attachment and to place the welfare of their families above everything. But when they are stripped off of this money, it becomes all the more difficult letting go of the emotional burden of having done so much for a child and seeing it go for no good of their own. Altruistic surrogacy does them no good either because now the ambit to earn the smallest amount of money through this is also taken away from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene Five: Culmination&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, surrogacy as an activity ends up reducing women to their wombs, and ends up monetising not just their services but also the life decisions they made in order to be able to carry a child, not just once but as many times as their body permits and their conditions demand. For many women, the cost of surrogacy can be enormous and simply not worthwhile. For other women, this cost can be minimal in comparison with choices they prefer to have and which they value more. The kind of opportunity costs these women have to incur are way beyond any measurable financial costs.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Scene One: The Backdrop.&amp;nbsp; Change is the only constant. Evolution took humans from a hunch-backed species to one that stands upright, from broader jaws to narrower ones and, if we were to believe scientific findings, from a smaller brain size to a larger one. The species evolved and evolved from one huge scientific name to another. But three things that make humans what they inherently are remained unchanged – the body, the soul and expectations. If we are to believe religious and spiritual texts, the body and the soul are accompanied by the mind, but the mind begets expectations arising from desires, and hence for the sake of simplicity, just like an economist would do, we assume the mind to be our expectations. Therefore, even though humans evolved and changed in their physical form, one thing did in fact remain unchanged and constant, that is their expectations.&amp;nbsp; Scene Two: The Groundwork.&amp;nbsp; Drifting a little away from evolution and bringing ourselves to the present, societies are laden with a myriad of desires and expectations, more so than just their needs, and sometimes overstepping their wants. The sort of mindset embedded in a society’s head is that of the likelihood of certain outcomes, rather than a proven possibility of them to actually occur. Put in simpler words, the likelihood of someone getting severely hurt someday leads to families saving some money, the likelihood of earning profits leads to investments, and so on. This mirage of an outcome in the future leads to tremendous amounts of pressure in the society to do exactly what the society dictates and deems as 'fit' to exist. And society dictates – every married couple must have a child.&amp;nbsp; Scene Three: The Curtain Raiser.&amp;nbsp; Equating happiness with expecting a child, millions of couples resort to the method of surrogacy to have a child of their own. In simple words, surrogacy is a process wherein a woman carries and cares for the child in her womb, that is not her own, but she is willingly carrying for the intended parents who can’t carry a child of their own. Whenever the intended parents compensate the surrogate mother monetarily, it is known as ‘commercial surrogacy’, and otherwise, an ‘altruistic surrogacy’, usually done by a relative/friend. The legality of such agreements between intended parents and the surrogate mother are subjective to various countries and their jurisdictions on the issue. While some countries have banned commercial surrogacy altogether, some developing countries are hubs of surrogacy with an incremental flow of intended parents to these hubs to fulfil their desires. This form of a transnational surrogacy has opened way too many doors for intended parents to exploit and prey on the poor and vulnerable surrogate mothers who are in dire need of the money they could have potentially earned by putting their bodies up for use.&amp;nbsp; Scene Four: The Highlight. There hasn’t been a lack of debates around surrogacy and while most countries have spoken and passed laws in favour of altruistic surrogacy, there are still questions of whether it is ethical to commodify women’s bodies and the kinds of economic impacts attached with the legality of surrogacy. First issues first, the commodification of the bodies of these surrogate mothers is more than just an ethical question. Women who willingly opt to become surrogate mothers usually belong to the weaker sections of the society, which brings to light the kind of structural flaws existing in these developing economies that the women find it to be the last resort to put up their bodies to use in order to live from hand to mouth. Their livelihoods rely on this sort of money, and even when governments choose to ban commercial surrogacy to be able to curb the commodification of bodies, they don’t provide these women with a safety net, and hence their upliftment goes out of the question. In fact, for some, this is the only means of livelihood. For that, they have to go through so much emotional and physical labour and also have to change their entire lives’ priorities. Moreover, the fact that in a market, a commodity is taken from its producer and sold off to a consumer stands rather highly unethically true in this case, but it’s not the child being sold off here since the intended parents already have a right on it, but the gestational services of the surrogate being sold off as a mere commodity and as any other labour activity. Secondly, the economic implications of the legality of surrogacy come with a deep understanding of how economics in general works. The kind of expectations talked about at the beginning of the article is as much part of economics as any other economic jargon. That is because expectations lead to desires and wants, which is when we as rational humans choose to make decisions that provide us with maximum satisfaction and utility.&amp;nbsp; In any legal agreement, the two sides of parties always choose the kind of terms that provide the maximum utility to each of them. Naturally, everybody responds to incentives and here, the intended parents wish for a child while the surrogate mother wishes to obtain that sum of money that she needs for herself or her family. The enforceability of these contracts is rather highly pedestaled by these parties because both of them want their end of the contract to be fulfilled. This is when the aspect of exploitation comes into play when these vulnerable women fail to understand the nitty-gritty of such contracts, of which the intended parents, who are in fact financially stable, take undue advantage and get away with paying less to no amount of money to these surrogate mothers. For several small towns in developing economies, the money coming in from surrogacy is extremely essential for the survival of families, and with the rise in exploitation, they are not just left economically worse-off, but also emotionally. The kind of emotional labour that goes into bearing a child is also something that the surrogate mothers already go through, but with the money coming in, it is marginally easier for them to let go of this attachment and to place the welfare of their families above everything. But when they are stripped off of this money, it becomes all the more difficult letting go of the emotional burden of having done so much for a child and seeing it go for no good of their own. Altruistic surrogacy does them no good either because now the ambit to earn the smallest amount of money through this is also taken away from them. Scene Five: Culmination.&amp;nbsp; All in all, surrogacy as an activity ends up reducing women to their wombs, and ends up monetising not just their services but also the life decisions they made in order to be able to carry a child, not just once but as many times as their body permits and their conditions demand. For many women, the cost of surrogacy can be enormous and simply not worthwhile. For other women, this cost can be minimal in comparison with choices they prefer to have and which they value more. The kind of opportunity costs these women have to incur are way beyond any measurable financial costs.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">One Nation One Ration Card: Forerunner in Fight against Food Insecurity</title>
      <link href="/One-Nation-One-Ration-Card" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One Nation One Ration Card: Forerunner in Fight against Food Insecurity" />
      <published>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/One-Nation-One-Ration-Card</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/One-Nation-One-Ration-Card">&lt;p&gt;While the unprecedented COVID-19 crisis has had a calamitous impact on all of us, the poorest of the poor have been the worst sufferers. The daily wage workers in India who migrate from the remote parts of the country to economically advanced cities in search of better opportunities were stripped of their economic security in the blink of an eye. Businesses crashed and all activities came to a complete standstill because of the nationwide lockdown. The lockdown put a full stop on all kinds of mobility and discontinued modes of transport. The public was in a state of frenzy, even the well-off strata was apprehensive about the supply of necessities and hence started hoarding. The government assured a continual supply of essential commodities to us but what about the migrant workers, were they given any certainty? In the absence of food security and of any means to commute, along with no pennies in their pocket, they indulged in reverse migration, back to their families.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Food security refers to ensuring adequate food supply for people, especially those who are deprived of basic nutrition, the bare minimum. There are 195 million undernourished people in India, adding up to a quarter of the global hunger burden, as per UN-India. Furthermore, India has recently been ranked 94 out of 107 countries in the Global Hunger Index and has been placed in the ‘serious’ hunger category. As an attempt to alleviate the ill effects of the hunger crisis, the National Food Security Act (NFSA) came into force in 2013. Economist Jean Dreze called this bill an “investment in human capital”. According to the NFSA, 810 million people are entitled to subsidised food grains. The prices of rice, wheat and coarse grain have been set at ₹3, ₹2, and ₹1 per kg respectively. About 235 million ration cards have been issued to nearly 810 million beneficiaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These ration card holders can lift their share of the food grains from the designated Fair Price Shop (FPS) in their locality, where they reside. For instance, if a family resides in Bastar in Chhattisgarh and a few members move to Delhi to work on a construction site, they will no longer be able to purchase their quota of food at subsidised rates from a Public Distribution Shop (PDS) shop in Delhi. This limitation of the existing system divests a large migratory population of their allotted proportion of ration. The national rollout of ‘One Nation, One Ration Card’ is a welcome move in this light. Under this scheme, the beneficiaries can get their share from any of the 540,000 fair price shops across the length and breadth of India. This reform is expected to attain success at a pan-India level by March 31, 2021. However, two prerequisites for the same are 100% installation of Electronic Point of Sale (ePoS) devices and 100% Aadhaar seeding.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technological solution to the problem posed by the earlier system entails identification through biometric authentication on ePoS devices installed at the FPSs. A question might pop up: What is an ePoS? It is a device that electronically records the distribution of ration to different ration cardholders. Connectivity issues are stated as one major bottleneck in the seamless functioning of the framework. However, ePoS also works in offline mode, according to officials. It will most certainly reduce the manual recording of transactions in registers by the dealers. 90% of the PDS shops have been equipped with these devices. As far as the linkage of ration cards with Aadhaar number is concerned, 90% of the 235 million ration cards issued have been seeded.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Integrated Management of Public Distribution System (IMPDS) and &lt;em&gt;Annavitran&lt;/em&gt; are two portals that will help in smooth facilitation of the process at the inter and intra-state level correspondingly. Talking about one more intricacy, the card will now be in a bilingual format, one of the languages will be the local one and the other can either be Hindi or English. This is because when the recipient is not in his/her native place, there should be ease in comprehending the details and uniformity should be maintained.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critical challenges in realising the goal are studying and record-keeping of labour migration patterns. If a family is scattered in two locations, reconciling data at both locations would be a major task. Food Corporation of India (FCI) godowns and other storage facilities need to function parallel to the demand for grains created by the immigration/emigration of the labour force. Just a recent illustration of the change in demand for goods because of reverse migration is that of the Flipkart and Amazon festive sale. Sales doubled up in the first two days when compared to the 2019 edition. In the wake of discounts, an upswing in new shoppers from Tier 2 and Tier 3 cities has been witnessed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, the interstate ration card portability cluster is 28 states and union territories strong. Some states with an influx of labour are still laggards in the instalment of ePoS and undertaking biometric authentication. States like West Bengal and Assam, which are still not on board need to be pushed to complete the necessary requirements for true integration of state portals to that of the centre. Computerisation of the supply network of FCI will boost the efficacy and help translate the chalked down scheme into a wholesome reality. Once fully implemented, the scheme is sure to uplift the country in the&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Global Hunger Index. Will it mitigate the suffering of the downtrodden section dying, helplessly walking miles trying to shelter themselves, unable to feed themselves, let alone two but even one square meal? Let us choose to be optimistic in this regard. Even a step forward in the right direction is progress for humankind.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushi Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">While the unprecedented COVID-19 crisis has had a calamitous impact on all of us, the poorest of the poor have been the worst sufferers. The daily wage workers in India who migrate from the remote parts of the country to economically advanced cities in search of better opportunities were stripped of their economic security in the blink of an eye. Businesses crashed and all activities came to a complete standstill because of the nationwide lockdown. The lockdown put a full stop on all kinds of mobility and discontinued modes of transport. The public was in a state of frenzy, even the well-off strata was apprehensive about the supply of necessities and hence started hoarding. The government assured a continual supply of essential commodities to us but what about the migrant workers, were they given any certainty? In the absence of food security and of any means to commute, along with no pennies in their pocket, they indulged in reverse migration, back to their families.&amp;nbsp; Food security refers to ensuring adequate food supply for people, especially those who are deprived of basic nutrition, the bare minimum. There are 195 million undernourished people in India, adding up to a quarter of the global hunger burden, as per UN-India. Furthermore, India has recently been ranked 94 out of 107 countries in the Global Hunger Index and has been placed in the ‘serious’ hunger category. As an attempt to alleviate the ill effects of the hunger crisis, the National Food Security Act (NFSA) came into force in 2013. Economist Jean Dreze called this bill an “investment in human capital”. According to the NFSA, 810 million people are entitled to subsidised food grains. The prices of rice, wheat and coarse grain have been set at ₹3, ₹2, and ₹1 per kg respectively. About 235 million ration cards have been issued to nearly 810 million beneficiaries. These ration card holders can lift their share of the food grains from the designated Fair Price Shop (FPS) in their locality, where they reside. For instance, if a family resides in Bastar in Chhattisgarh and a few members move to Delhi to work on a construction site, they will no longer be able to purchase their quota of food at subsidised rates from a Public Distribution Shop (PDS) shop in Delhi. This limitation of the existing system divests a large migratory population of their allotted proportion of ration. The national rollout of ‘One Nation, One Ration Card’ is a welcome move in this light. Under this scheme, the beneficiaries can get their share from any of the 540,000 fair price shops across the length and breadth of India. This reform is expected to attain success at a pan-India level by March 31, 2021. However, two prerequisites for the same are 100% installation of Electronic Point of Sale (ePoS) devices and 100% Aadhaar seeding.&amp;nbsp; The technological solution to the problem posed by the earlier system entails identification through biometric authentication on ePoS devices installed at the FPSs. A question might pop up: What is an ePoS? It is a device that electronically records the distribution of ration to different ration cardholders. Connectivity issues are stated as one major bottleneck in the seamless functioning of the framework. However, ePoS also works in offline mode, according to officials. It will most certainly reduce the manual recording of transactions in registers by the dealers. 90% of the PDS shops have been equipped with these devices. As far as the linkage of ration cards with Aadhaar number is concerned, 90% of the 235 million ration cards issued have been seeded.&amp;nbsp; Integrated Management of Public Distribution System (IMPDS) and Annavitran are two portals that will help in smooth facilitation of the process at the inter and intra-state level correspondingly. Talking about one more intricacy, the card will now be in a bilingual format, one of the languages will be the local one and the other can either be Hindi or English. This is because when the recipient is not in his/her native place, there should be ease in comprehending the details and uniformity should be maintained.&amp;nbsp; Critical challenges in realising the goal are studying and record-keeping of labour migration patterns. If a family is scattered in two locations, reconciling data at both locations would be a major task. Food Corporation of India (FCI) godowns and other storage facilities need to function parallel to the demand for grains created by the immigration/emigration of the labour force. Just a recent illustration of the change in demand for goods because of reverse migration is that of the Flipkart and Amazon festive sale. Sales doubled up in the first two days when compared to the 2019 edition. In the wake of discounts, an upswing in new shoppers from Tier 2 and Tier 3 cities has been witnessed.&amp;nbsp; Currently, the interstate ration card portability cluster is 28 states and union territories strong. Some states with an influx of labour are still laggards in the instalment of ePoS and undertaking biometric authentication. States like West Bengal and Assam, which are still not on board need to be pushed to complete the necessary requirements for true integration of state portals to that of the centre. Computerisation of the supply network of FCI will boost the efficacy and help translate the chalked down scheme into a wholesome reality. Once fully implemented, the scheme is sure to uplift the country in the Global Hunger Index. Will it mitigate the suffering of the downtrodden section dying, helplessly walking miles trying to shelter themselves, unable to feed themselves, let alone two but even one square meal? Let us choose to be optimistic in this regard. Even a step forward in the right direction is progress for humankind.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
