<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/economics/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-04-17T19:46:32+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/economics/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What is Wrong with Britain’s Economy?</title>
      <link href="/British-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Wrong with Britain’s Economy?" />
      <published>2020-04-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/British-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/British-Economy">&lt;p&gt;Brexit is not the only factor that is affecting the British economy at the moment. It is no longer the most important issue for the country. It just seems like a convenient issue to cite in order to justify the low productivity that has plagued the nation in recent years. No matter how big that decision is, there are other things as well that Britain needs to focus on to improve its stagnating economic condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recently introduced skills-focused points-based immigration policy by PM Boris Johnson is going to have a huge impact on the economy. More than one-third of doctors, pharmacists, and dentists in the UK are foreign-born, as are more than 20% of nurses. Seven in 10 workers in the meat-processing industry are from the EU. However, next year onwards, the UK’s Byzantine immigration system for non-EU migrants will also apply to those from the EU. While immigration criteria for skilled labour will be loosened, it will be almost impossible for non-skilled labour to obtain a work visa. One of the hardest-hit sectors will be ‘care for’ the elderly. There is already a shortage of workers in this sector. Moreover, ‘care for’ work is the occupation with the most projected employment growth in the coming years. The UK under the guise of treating EU and non-EU migrants equally on the basis of skills is actually turning away industrious and enterprising individuals who help power its economy and provide for the basic needs of its greying population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the recent examples of what the British government is doing wrong. There are certain structural problems as well that need to be addressed. Capital spending as a share of GDP has fallen to around 17% from 20% in 2007. Capital investment is required in order to ensure long-term economic growth by increasing future production capacity. Moreover, the expenditure on R&amp;amp;D remains persistently below 2% of the GDP. In addition to this, the output per person has remained well below than what would have been termed as satisfactory. The unemployment figures have been relatively good recently, however, these have come at the cost of stagnating real wages and lower labour productivity per hour. Moreover, there has been a constant increase in the number of &lt;em&gt;zero-hour&lt;/em&gt; contracts. In such contracts, the workers have no guarantee of how many hours of work they will be getting. This could be one of the major reasons for under-employment in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of 2019, the manufacturing activity took a turn for the worse with the sharpest deterioration in output in more than seven years. The IHS Markit/CIPS manufacturing Purchasing Managers’ Index sank to 47.5 in December from 48.9 in November, although it was marginally higher than an initial flash estimate of 47.4. The figure marks the eighth consecutive month with a reading below 50, which indicates a majority of businesses reporting deteriorating activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has a large current account deficit as well. It was around 4.6% of the GDP in 2019. This has been majorly due to negative investor sentiments because of all the political instability. Also, the UK economy has been hit badly by the economic slowdown in the major trading partners, namely, China and the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another worrying aspect is the monopoly power in public utility services like electricity and gas. A lack of competition keeps prices high and affects the real incomes of millions of consumers. Moreover, economic, social and demographic pressures continue to mount on public services such as the NHS. Some economists argue that the NHS needs a major injection of extra funding over the next 5-10 years; others believe that there are enough savings still to be achieved by addressing inefficiencies in public health care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With economic forecasts suggesting that the UK’s GDP growth won’t exceed 1.5%, the government will have to watch its discretionary spending even if a recession is avoided, because of spending on national services like the NHS. Moreover, there is also an additional threat to the economy posed by coronavirus. Much remains to be seen how the policymakers will tackle this burden and if the economy will be able to overcome this. The current situation doesn’t leave room for high hopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to plunging stock markets worldwide, the Bank of England cut its key rate by half a percentage point to 0.25%.  The Bank of England introduced a new program for cheap credit and reduced a special capital buffer to give banks more room to lend as well. Rishi Sunak, the Chancellor of the Exchequer,  also scrapped business rates for small firms to help them deal with the disruption caused by the outbreak of coronavirus. Business rates are taxes to help pay for UK local services, charged on most commercial properties. Britain’s retail sector has complained for the longest time that the current business rates system was unfair and needed reform. While the retail sector accounts for 5% of the UK economy, it is burdened with 10% of all business taxes, and 25% of business rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chancellor Sunak also scrapped a planned cut in corporation tax, and he is expected to raise around £6 billion from scrapping a planned drop, money he indicated could be spent on hospitals and doctors across the country. He also announced that the government would establish a coronavirus job retention scheme for all employers, large or small, that will cover 80% of wages, up to £2,500 a month. This scheme was introduced for an initial period of three months but can also be extended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a month after stepping into the new job, Rishi Sunak has a lot to prove. There are a lot of expectations for the new Chancellor. Additionally, when the UK is facing an increasing threat from the coronavirus, his job becomes all the more important. It remains to be seen whether Rishi Sunak will break free of any puppet strings or be swept aside by a Treasury insider. Brexit coupled with the coronavirus outbreak has left the country on borrowed time to revamp the economy. What happens in the next few weeks could possibly define the future of the country in the coming years. What we need to wait and watch is whether the government and its policies fall into place in order to break free the shackles of a never-ending system of going back and forth.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Amrit Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Brexit is not the only factor that is affecting the British economy at the moment. It is no longer the most important issue for the country. It just seems like a convenient issue to cite in order to justify the low productivity that has plagued the nation in recent years. No matter how big that decision is, there are other things as well that Britain needs to focus on to improve its stagnating economic condition.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Can India Keep Up with The Coronavirus?</title>
      <link href="/Can-India-Keep-Up-with-the-Coronavirus" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can India Keep Up with The Coronavirus?" />
      <published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Can-India-Keep-Up-with-the-Coronavirus</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Can-India-Keep-Up-with-the-Coronavirus">&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus, a tiny virus, has been causing chaos across the world since January. Countries are going into lockdowns, international travel has been banned, businesses are shutting down and healthcare systems are coming under unprecedented pressure. The virus has led to a global standstill and thus, to a global slowdown of economic growth, if not a global recession. Policymakers are now considering or already taking quick large steps to both ease the health care challenges and stem the economic pain. The Economist Intelligence Unit (of &lt;em&gt;The Economist&lt;/em&gt; magazine) estimates a negative growth rate of 2.2% of the GDP in countries of the G20 group for 2020. Amidst this crisis, one probably would have come across the talks about the trade-off between the lives of the people and the economy. No doubt, lives are of utmost importance, but not paying attention to the economy will critically affect the lives of the people once the crisis is over. The crisis will have an adverse impact on India which is already on the path of a slower growth rate. In this context, what has India done? And what can it do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian Prime Minister has announced a nation-wide lockdown from March 23, 2020, for a period of 3 weeks, till April 15. Following this came the decisions to ban international travel and shut the state borders, with an exception to vehicles transporting essentials. All of the non-essential businesses (manufacturing, construction, IT, etc) have come to a grinding halt and this has led to a supply and demand shock to the economy of India. It is crucial to note that 92% of the Indian workforce is engaged in the informal sector and one could find hordes of people migrating across the country in search of a job. These people are largely construction workers or people working in farms and survive on their daily wages only. Two days after the lockdown was announced, the Central Government announced a package of ₹1.7 trillion to help the poorest sections of the society. The wages under the National Rural Employment Scheme (NRES) were increased to ₹202 (i.e. about $2.69) from ₹182 (i.e. about $2.42). The Central Government, among other things, has also announced an allowance of 5 kg rice (or wheat per person) and 1 kg of pulses per family each month for 3 months. Some Indian states have announced cash transfers to all subsidy cardholders, in addition to the Centre’s cash transfers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these two measures have some problems. First, the objective of a total lockdown is to practice social distancing and thereby, no one is allowed out. Now, transferring cash through NRES wouldn’t work because people cannot come out to work; and even if they did, they will form a gathering and hence, defeat the purpose of a lockdown. Second, the average daily minimum wage in India in 2014 was ₹272 (i.e. about $3.62 in todays money). For simplification purposes, let us assume it to be ₹200. Now, if a person works for, say, 5 days a week that person would earn ₹1,000. This would total to ₹4,000 a month. What this means is that they earn more than what is being offered now, and the ₹1,500-₹ 2,000 (Central plus State Governments) per month given to these migrant workers is simply not enough of an incentive for them to stay indoors, thus once again, defeating the purpose of the lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing worth considering here is the prices of essential commodities. Given the shortage of supply, prices of some essentials are likely to increase. This will slash the real value of the money being distributed to the beneficiaries and would not be able to support them. Therefore, the government should increase the amount (Amit Seru, a prominent economist from Stanford has said this should be 5-6% of the GDP) disbursed to the targeted groups, not restricting the scope of the beneficiaries. That a large proportion of people are in the informal sector makes the transfers difficult, but India has the mechanism to carry out these transfers. It is also imperative to note that without much emphasis on the accurate number of beneficiaries, India must rather focus on transferring the amount because time is of the essence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, due to the crisis there are demand and supply side shocks to all the economies. A majority of the economists polled by the IGM Booth panel, however, opined that the economic effects of demand side shocks are larger than those from the supply side. As the businesses shut, the income of the people fell and so did the demand for goods and services in the economy. This is a critical cycle where income and demand depend on each other and when one falls it drives down the other and this is accompanied by a sharp rise in unemployment (in the informal sector mainly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economic crisis entailing the global pandemic is the textbook example of the good old Keynesian economics. And the conventional cure to this problem is fiscal expansion. Fiscal expansion, by way of government spending, will yield results with immediate effect. One cannot be concerned about the rise of fiscal deficit, given the seriousness of the current situation and it should be allowed to rise both at the Centre and the state level. The Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management Act (FRBM) can be amended or an ordinance can be issued to that effect. A greater degree of autonomy should be given to the states by means of allocation of funds or disbursal of the welfare schemes, as it is much faster to implement all these at the state level. For this, the contributions to the newly started PM-CARES should be distributed on war footing starting from the worst affected states. The government can also consider cutting down income tax rates (preferably, the lower brackets) and GST slabs at least for some period to boost the revival of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Governor of the Reserve Bank of India (RBI), the Indian central bank, has also announced a slew of measures by employing the tools of monetary policy alongside the government’s fiscal measures. The RBI cut down the repo rate by 0.75% and Cash Reserve Ratio by 100 basis points to 3%. The Reserve bank estimates these measures would result in an injection of ₹3.74 trillion into the economy. However, this should not be taken as is. For we do not know if the banks will slash the lending rates even as the RBI slashed the repo rate. Additionally, the demand is bound to increase after the lockdown is lifted. However, the question one must ask is will the demand be sufficient for the businesses to borrow money from the banks. Hence, we do not know whether the reduced interest rates would lead to an increase in investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, one thing is clear. This crisis is not conventional in the sense that the economy cannot be rescued in these times. This is because the non-essential services are shut down and cannot be opened until the lockdown is lifted. Even if India reopens, many businesses might find it difficult to start production because of the disruption of supply chains owing to the lockdown in other countries. Hence, growth will slow down. All India can do is take measures to revive demand once the world settles down.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Coronavirus, a tiny virus, has been causing chaos across the world since January. Countries are going into lockdowns, international travel has been banned, businesses are shutting down and healthcare systems are coming under unprecedented pressure. The virus has led to a global standstill and thus, to a global slowdown of economic growth, if not a global recession. Policymakers are now considering or already taking quick large steps to both ease the health care challenges and stem the economic pain. The Economist Intelligence Unit (of The Economist magazine) estimates a negative growth rate of 2.2% of the GDP in countries of the G20 group for 2020. Amidst this crisis, one probably would have come across the talks about the trade-off between the lives of the people and the economy. No doubt, lives are of utmost importance, but not paying attention to the economy will critically affect the lives of the people once the crisis is over. The crisis will have an adverse impact on India which is already on the path of a slower growth rate. In this context, what has India done? And what can it do?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Echoes of the Estates-General: A Comparison between Ancient Regime France and 21st Century America (Part I)</title>
      <link href="/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Echoes of the Estates-General: A Comparison between Ancient Regime France and 21st Century America (Part I)" />
      <published>2020-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General">&lt;p&gt;The background to the French Revolution chronicles the decline of the once-powerful State, beset by a multitude of economic and social problems. Chief among these issues were: a bourgeoning national debt brought on by the cost of war, the increasing antagonisms between an unproductive class of nepotistic oligarchs and an impoverished mass of peasants and small artisans, and the increasing irrelevance of the country in comparison to other, more economically dynamic states. The United States in the 21st Century bears striking similarities to the pre-revolutionary France, as discontent with stagnating wages and widening inequality reaches a fever pitch as the 2020 election draws nearer. This is the first of two articles examining the economic and political similarities between them, at a volatile time in the history of both nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;State Debt and Poor Finances&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between 1720 and 1780, France’s overseas trade had quadrupled, yet commercial prosperity was not enough to offset the abysmal condition of state finances. The combined cost of fighting the Seven Years’ War and the American War of Independence was 3.1 billion livres, over 4 times the Crown’s annual revenue. This was exacerbated by the fact that spending on war, the navy and diplomacy constituted 25% of Crown expenditure, in addition to the 50% that serviced the existing debt. Coupled with high interest rates that deterred moneylenders and an inefficient tax system that failed to raise revenue and allowed the nobility to remove officials who attempted to raise either direct or indirect taxes on them, there was a serious economic crisis by 1789.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 9/11, the United States has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2016/09/cost-wars-iraq-afghanistan/499007/&quot;&gt;poured $3.2 trillion into wars, reaching a total of $4.8 trillion once obligations to veterans have been paid.&lt;/a&gt;  Engagements in Iraq, Afghanistan, Libya, Syria and other places have caused excessive deficit spending, and like in France in the 1780’s, an inefficient system of taxation that has involved lower taxes on the wealthy has only shifted the burden of debt onto the poor and future generations. George W Bush’s tax cuts in 2001 and 2003, and the tax breaks given to the billionaires by Trump are analogous to the exemptions that the French nobles received at the time of mass social breakdown at the end of the 1780’s. Against the backdrop of ballooning debt and the 2008 Financial Crisis, the concerns of the younger generations of Americans who have flocked to Bernie Sanders can be understood as a revolt against a system that allocates inordinate amounts of money towards wars and bank bailouts, but claims that education and healthcare are too costly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inequality and Social Unrest&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The schisms and fissures that have opened up in American society as a result of widening inequality and resentment at excessive accumulation and monopolisation by unaccountable billionaires is reminiscent of the tax immunities and feudal privileges that exempted the French nobility from accountability along with the predominance of feudal privileges such as internal customs barriers and tolls that prevented the establishment of a home market for manufacturers, which Turgot’s reforms had failed to redress in 1774. The stultifying stagnation imposed on the French economy by the system of noble privileges made the conditions of the peasantry significantly worse, indicating that it was not only the burden of debt but mass social unrest that resulted from the Ancien Regime. Eric Hobsbawm, in his book the &lt;em&gt;Age of Revolution&lt;/em&gt; stated that the nobility encroached considerably on the autonomy of the peasantry as feudal dues, tithes and taxes occupied an increasing share of peasants’ income. Ground between the millstones of noble exactions and price inflation, social breakdown and revolts among the peasantry were made practically inevitable by the late 1780’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Kropotkin, writing in &lt;em&gt;The Great French Revolution&lt;/em&gt;, argued that the inequalities between the nobility and the peasantry, combined with the obstinacy of those in power, illustrated the sclerotic and outdated nature of what would later become the first and second estates of the Estates-General. He stated that “if despair and misery impelled the people to riot, it was the hope of obtaining some relief that incited them to revolt”. In 1777, 1,100,000 peasants were declared to be beggars. Between 1730 and 1789, wages rose by 22% but were unable to keep pace with prices, which rose by 60%, causing further immiseration for the French peasantry and precipitating risings of both the rural and the urban poor in 1788/1789. Inflation of the price of agrarian produce prevented the urban workers from gaining access to bread, and wage stagnation crippled a key market for manufactured goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three wealthiest billionaires in the United States: Jeff Bezos, Bill Gates and Warren Buffett, own as much wealth as the bottom half of the American population combined, indicating that capitalist accumulation has acted as an enormous fetter on the development of the productive forces, and that the majority of sectors of the economy have been sacrificed on the altar of short-term profit. Capital simply ‘goes on strike’ until it can find an adequate return on investment, as Big Pharma, for instance, has not produced a single new antibiotic in the nearly 4 decades since it was deregulated. Apple and Samsung, in lieu of investing in new technologies, have spent 7 years engaged in a costly ‘patent war’ over copying iPhones, have outsourced production to the Global South, or simply gambled on the stock exchange. The billionaire class in America has become a parasitic oligarchy that mirrors the nobility in Ancien Regime France, suffused with government subsidies and content with shoring up their positions on the market, as the nobility once clung to their feudal dues and court pensions. The unproductive nobility, who were not earners by birth, and who were barred from entering professions, influenced politics to increase their privileges, much as America’s unproductive billionaires buy off politicians today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether anything resembling the 1788/1789 agrarian riots will happen in America remains to be seen, although the levels of poverty in America have continued to climb recently. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2016/05/my-secret-shame/476415/&quot;&gt;49% of Americans now live paycheck to paycheck&lt;/a&gt;, and recent studies have linked &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-healthcare-deaths/study-links-45000-u-s-deaths-to-lack-of-insurance-idUSTRE58G6W520090917&quot;&gt;45,000 deaths per year to lack of health insurance.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loss of Global Hegemony&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The loss of power and influence on the world stage to other countries with expanding economies and greater political and technological capabilities is another major point of comparison between latter-day Ancien Regime France and 21st Century America. By the late 1780’s, Great Britain was already beginning to industrialise, buoyed by the prospect of free trade with the newly independent United States, the growing importance of slave-picked cotton from the American South, and the opening up of new markets in Latin America such as Brazil and Cuba whose economies of scale made them more profitable than mercantilist West Indian markets. The 1770’s and 1780’s saw the development of puddling furnaces, rolling mills and James Watt’s steam engine, alongside agricultural techniques that increased enclosures and developed profitable cash crops. France, by contrast, was still hampered by the inefficiency of feudal dues and tithes during Louis XVI’s administration, remaining &lt;em&gt;“a nation of agriculture and handicrafts”&lt;/em&gt; according to Georges Lefebvre. Its commercial and colonial supremacy began to decline, and its traditional economic methods, internal trade restrictions and inadequate transport links acted as a bottleneck on economic progress, as Great Britain surged ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collapse of American hegemony and the rise of China is one of the defining changes in modern geopolitics that radically &lt;em&gt;reorients&lt;/em&gt; the global balance of power. Once again, the domestic unrest and discontent fermenting amongst a people can be contextualised within the decline of the country at large. There are countless examples in history of leaders using patriotism and perceived national importance to distract from economic failures by galvanising the spirit of the population. This becomes increasingly difficult at a time of national decline, as shown by Trump’s recent attempts to escalate tensions with Iran. Public opinion polls found that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.people-press.org/2019/07/30/climate-change-and-russia-are-partisan-flashpoints-in-publics-views-of-global-threats/&quot;&gt;just 43% of the American public approved of the killing of General Soleimani&lt;/a&gt;, showing that the cynical use of patriotism to offset economic decline is becoming less tenable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the United States’ persistent refusal to allow the state to play a directing role in the allocation of resources has culminated in the United States ceding ground to the bureaucratic and ruthlessly efficient Chinese State, whose monopolistic tech companies exert a growing influence over countries ranging from Central Asia to Latin America. The United States remains a service economy, sustained by low wages, cheap credit and cheap imports which have led to a ballooning trade deficit of $616.8 billion (by late 2019). The Chinese, on the other hand, have understood the importance of digital infrastructure to the modern, interconnected global economy through the expansion of the Belt and Road Initiative and the Digital Silk Road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The background to the French Revolution shows that national decline, combined with economic stagnation and an unaccountable and bureaucratic class of elites who produce and contribute little of value can mobilise a mass of the labouring poor who recognise the injustice of the system they are living under. The concept of the ‘American Dream’ is becoming increasingly untenable as neoliberal capitalism proves itself incapable of innovation and only of injecting money into assets and speculation, while concentrating power and wealth in the hands of a few billionaires. From the demise of Bernie Sanders’ campaign to the desperate attempts of the ruling class to consolidate power in the wake of the Coronavirus by printing $1.5 trillion to stabilise markets while millions are still without health insurance, there is a significant chance that the current crisis of American neoliberalism may result in either social upheaval, or a revolutionary transformation of the economic system.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The background to the French Revolution chronicles the decline of the once-powerful State, beset by a multitude of economic and social problems. Chief among these issues were: a bourgeoning national debt brought on by the cost of war, the increasing antagonisms between an unproductive class of nepotistic oligarchs and an impoverished mass of peasants and small artisans, and the increasing irrelevance of the country in comparison to other, more economically dynamic states. The United States in the 21st Century bears striking similarities to the pre-revolutionary France, as discontent with stagnating wages and widening inequality reaches a fever pitch as the 2020 election draws nearer. This is the first of two articles examining the economic and political similarities between them, at a volatile time in the history of both nations.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Art, the Artist and the Investor</title>
      <link href="/Art-Artist-Investor" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Art, the Artist and the Investor" />
      <published>2020-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Art-Artist-Investor</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Art-Artist-Investor">&lt;p&gt;Creativity has its own timeline, and art can only blossom through experience and patience. It takes its own sweet time getting through to people letting the art ripen naturally, instead of spoon-feeding its patrons, and is usually a mark of the artist’s authenticity. Take Van Gogh or Kafka, for instance, with both dying in ignorance of the ingenuity of their works. Their patience, or rather underconfidence, eventually led to the posthumous recognition, capitalised on by whoever could claim to ignite the inspiration, rendering their lives analogous to a sad art film, that yet still, managed to inspire people further. But not every artist wants to make a sad art film of their lives. It isn’t simply about the lack of patience or existence of confidence to market their work, it is, quite often, about &lt;em&gt;survival&lt;/em&gt;. Putting all stakes in an industry that isn’t entirely welcoming to new works due to their abstract nature is certainly a dicey choice for one’s career. Looking for popular platforms that can get you eyeballs is only natural.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These platforms are the ones that claim to ‘discover’ the artists, and subsequently, capitalise on the lifetime of earnings through their artwork. Take the music industry, for example. Artists still make their music, but that is not exactly how they make their money. The commercialisation of the records by label companies has been in place for decades now. Singers would only get a proportion of the sales revenue generated when new music would be released, which is only fair. Associating a famous record label’s name with the music of a new artist is a high-risk position to take business-wise, and hence it’s only natural to expect higher returns. Labels own master recordings, the copyrights associated and the back catalogues of artists. These assets are owned to compensate them in exchange for the risks taken by the platform in financing the artists’ careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in the 80’s &amp;amp; 90’s, the transparency of record deals wasn’t exactly crystal clear, both record labels and the singers managed to make good money because their primary source of revenue was the literal sale of the songs via CDs, vinyl records, etc. Currently, the music sales revenue, though growing, in absolute terms, by nearly $1 billion per year, is only about 60% of what it was in 1999. The industry took its major hit post the year 2000 when internet services began illegally offering easy access to the free download of music. The advent of pirated downloading of music drove down the record sales and seemingly marked a Malthusian-style prophecy of the end of the commercialised and profitable era. That was until the streaming platforms stepped in. Although a third of the global music listeners still pirate their music (as per a report by the International Federation of Phonographic Industry), a massive rise in legal streaming platforms like Spotify, Apple Music and Tidal seems to have curbed the illegal consumption of music. And while the revenues and the contract transparency is on the rise, the monetary credit accrued to the actual artists has fallen with the steepening of the industry’s growth trajectory. Private equity (PE) players have stepped in to invest in the record labels, adding complicated layers to the revenue distribution model, and thus, leaving even lower residual amount that goes to the singers. Now, how do these big-money investors in PE corporates that, at the very least, expect consistency in their returns, align themselves with an industry that has its own volatile timeline? They &lt;em&gt;undershare&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The labels now provide to the artists a platform, and that’s nearly all. An estimate suggests that an average artist gets around one-tenth of a cent per play of an associated song on Spotify. The streaming platform generally takes up 15-30% of the revenue generated, and then a major chunk is instantly slashed off in the name of the record label. At this point, less than 40% of the revenue remains before singers, songwriters or publishers. The final average payout is dependent on how much ownership of the master recordings and the compositions the artists can exert. To put it into perspective, a star as big as Beyoncé makes only 10% of her money through music sales. One would think that music tours and concerts ought to make up for the deficiencies, but they’re simply a marketing programme, an attempt to keep the artists relevant, which becomes evident once you realise that rarely do any of the global or national level tour revenues ever break-even. The artists are paid only a proportional royalty of any other public performance not financed by the label, but by talk-shows or award shows. The payment structure often leaves the singers earning off of advertisements and endorsements, robbing them of their ‘authenticity’ tag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the highest-paid pop-artist in 2017, Diddy, who made the money from his Cirac vodka deal, hadn’t even released an album in over 7 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while the streaming platforms aren’t exactly killing the music industry, they’re still skewed in favour of the private equity players, and hence are the primary drivers of the aggregate growth recorded in the revenues, dwarfing the ability of the actual artists to exert any influence. However, some of the bigger names are now coming out against the unregulated PE influence in the industry. Recently Big Machine Records, which owned the rights to the music catalogue of all of Taylor Swift’s past albums, except for &lt;em&gt;Lover&lt;/em&gt;, was sold out for $300-$350 Million, to Scooter Braun’s Ithaca Holdings, disallowing Swift to perform her own songs at the AMAs, and leading to a highly publicised feud between the two. The sale was backed by the renowned Carlyle Group, that was already facing backlash for its indirect stake in defence contractors who had actively supplied weapons to fund the bombings in Yemen by Saudi Arabia, and now came under the heat of the fans as well as Alexandria Ocasio Cortez and Elizabeth Warren. While the matter remains unresolved, it is likely that this time the artist might register a victory, since Swift has threatened to re-record her past albums. The victory would put her in the rare company of the few major-label artists like Metallica, Janet Jackson and Jay-Z to gain control of the assets associated with their music. The outcome of the lawsuit pursued by EDM artist Martin Garrix against the label Spinnin’ Records has also brought some good news, with Garrix being given the rights and masters to some of his biggest hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The investors are constantly innovating to capitalise on the gains of the music industry, with some even experimenting with removal of ownership exclusivity and opening song rights for public offerings. An Initial Song Offering (ISO) was made for Drake’s &lt;em&gt;Jodeci Freestyle&lt;/em&gt;, wherein 10% of the copyright stake was available for public purchase to the top 100 subscribers, with Ethereum based payments. While such innovations are in the interest of the public and allow them to channelise their savings towards better investment options, it needs to be realised that the lack of tangibility of both the output and most of the inputs of this industry is an important consideration in the face of the financial innovations that should follow. Therefore, the battle between rights and arts will continue for an indefinite period, as long as we, as a corporate, wouldn’t stop patronising the creative skills of the people involved in this field.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Creativity has its own timeline, and art can only blossom through experience and patience. It takes its own sweet time getting through to people letting the art ripen naturally, instead of spoon-feeding its patrons, and is usually a mark of the artist’s authenticity. Take Van Gogh or Kafka, for instance, with both dying in ignorance of the ingenuity of their works. Their patience, or rather underconfidence, eventually led to the posthumous recognition, capitalised on by whoever could claim to ignite the inspiration, rendering their lives analogous to a sad art film, that yet still, managed to inspire people further. But not every artist wants to make a sad art film of their lives. It isn’t simply about the lack of patience or existence of confidence to market their work, it is, quite often, about survival. Putting all stakes in an industry that isn’t entirely welcoming to new works due to their abstract nature is certainly a dicey choice for one’s career. Looking for popular platforms that can get you eyeballs is only natural.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">India will become a $5 Trillion Economy – Attainable or a Pipe Dream?</title>
      <link href="/India-will-become-a-5-Trillion-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="India will become a $5 Trillion Economy – Attainable or a Pipe Dream?" />
      <published>2020-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/India-will-become-a-5-Trillion-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/India-will-become-a-5-Trillion-Economy">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;India will become a $5 Trillion Economy – Attainable or a Pipe Dream?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India, a behemoth economy with a great civilisation, heritage and the immense possibility of creating global influence, has been attaining the status of being one of the most formidable nations in recent times. In accordance with the latest GDP estimates, India is exhibited as the fifth-largest economy in the world with a nominal GDP of $2.9 trillion. The Modi-led government has set an exalted yet magnificent objective of seeing India maturing into a ‘Five Trillion Dollar’ economy by the end of the ‘Modi 2.0 era’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This goal might seem a little intimidating or a bridge too far, but the fact is that every developing nation needs an ambitious target so that every sector, company and all other essential stakeholders align themselves and put emphasis on reaching it. Before we examine the attainability of this ambition, let us know how much of a growth rate and GDP value would be required for the target. With inflation of 3.5% and keeping rupee depreciation under check, a nominal growth of 11.5% is paramount for realising the 5 trillion mark to reap a real growth rate of about 8-9%. Sustaining such a significant rate of growth is very challenging for any economy and substantially arduous for India owing to its high unemployment rate of 6.1%, additionally over three hundred thousand people have lost their jobs due to the crumbling auto sector coupled with growth rate hovering around just 5% in the April-June quarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, since Independence, India has become a $2 trillion nation and within the last five years, it has added a feather of $1 trillion to its cap of GDP value. Therefore, acquiring that 5 trillion mark seems pretty practical. India has shown a fairly robust and persistent record of healthy growth drivers and the recent leapfrogging of 23 notches to rank 77th in the Ease of Doing Business index paves the way for reaching that goal. While no one can deny the reality that certain industries are facing downswing or recessionary conditions, there exist many sectors like IT and BPO service exports which are doing exceedingly well amidst the low global growth of 3.2%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another question is the possibility to expand at 9%. Well, it is conceivable and other countries have made it possible. For instance, Russia developed exponentially between the 1950’s and 1970’s at over 10% per annum. Even China (in the early 1990’s) and USA (1965-1975) are a testimony to the fact that growth over 10% is plausible. To accomplish this grand vision, every Indian state must demonstrate healthy signs of progress and this is seemingly true for the BIMARU states (Bihar, MP, Rajasthan and UP). In 2017-18, Bihar outran other states by displaying 11.3% growth, which was way above the overall economic growth of 6.7%. In fact, all but one of these ‘poor BIMARU states’, grew more than the national average implying enhanced law and order conditions and business-amiable government. Thus, the likelihood of unleashing the potential of every state is apparently pretty high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, India’s stable inflation rate (around 3%) and low global inflationary trends is a favourable situation for the country. If the rupee-dollar foreign exchange rate is also maintained and the rupee does not depreciate considerably, achieving the target is credible. The government is set to pump in $1.4 trillion for infrastructure investments to make developments in highways, railways, airports, power sectors, etc. Funding will also be backed by international players. For example, the UAE will invest $75 billion and the Abu Dhabi Investment Authority (ADIA) will supposedly spend $1 trillion for boosting the Indian infrastructure sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, in order to become a 5 trillion economy, India needs to make remarkable structural and sectoral moderations and initiate various reforms. Reforms like the latest corporate tax cuts (from 35% to 25%) proved fruitful for the economy as the stock market reacted positively, strengthening exports and enticing investors. With the ongoing economic tussle between the US and China, MNCs are on the lookout for a substitute manufacturing hub. Currently, holding just 2% of the global trade market share, India can reap the benefits of this war by minimising trade barriers and leveraging such opportunities by upgrading trade value chains. In fact, the manufacturing sector has the capability to absorb surplus labour from the agricultural or any informal sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The service sector has been on the rise lately with a contribution of up to 56.5% of GDP but employing only 30% of people. With automation around the corner and chances of loss in jobs in export-intensive IT sector, development of expertise in IoT, AI, Machine Learning, etc. will definitely boost the economy. Even the travel and tourism sector with 10% GDP share, providing 40 million jobs, can grow manifold by project-driven investments in medical tourism, tourist safety and budget hotels. Healthcare sector also calls for overall transformation as over 100 million workers would be desired globally in the coming years. Service and industry sectors have the greatest possibilities of value additions, and, therefore, skilled labour and strategic investments would assist heavily in economic expansion. Along with this, various land reforms would be necessary to facilitate growth. Major Indian cities, such as Bangalore, Mumbai have high potential to become global hubs, hence, tactical budget allocations and investments can boost the overall economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus should also be placed on establishing environment-friendly ways as it is an impediment to the 5 trillion economy dream. According to the World Bank report, environmental degradation costs India $80 billion per year. To tackle this, the creation of green jobs and community development through various already existing organisations can be done. Environmental or carbon taxes prove advantageous. Also, cutting down on oil imports can serve the dual purpose of opening up a ₹400 billion domestic market in the aviation sector whilst simultaneously mitigating environmental pollution by the usage of biofuels. According to the Union Road &amp;amp; Transport Minister, Nitin Gadkari, his Ministry is already taking crucial steps in this regard. Investments would entail a demand boost, creation of capacity, the introduction of new technologies, generation of jobs and enhanced labour productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Bottom Line&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India cannot prosper if certain states and sectors (like the construction sector) with high untapped potential do not start developing. In fact, state-wise spending must grow. The government’s $5 trillion goal is definitely ambitious but this intent can only be executed through a concrete plan of action. All that is required is a target-based approach, meticulous elimination of all the policy shortcomings and unclogging stalled projects. The aspiration to fulfil the quest with sustained growth can open up employment for over a million young people. A more balanced approach towards development and making sure that the government is able to run a clean, harmonious and efficient mechanism is all that will take to make the dream come alive.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sparsh Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">India will become a $5 Trillion Economy – Attainable or a Pipe Dream?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">GDP as a Tool of Economic Misdirection: Moving ‘To and Fro’ on the Growth Bar?</title>
      <link href="/GPD-as-a-Tool-of-Economic-Misdirection" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GDP as a Tool of Economic Misdirection: Moving 'To and Fro' on the Growth Bar?" />
      <published>2020-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/GPD-as-a-Tool-of-Economic-Misdirection</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/GPD-as-a-Tool-of-Economic-Misdirection">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GDP as a Tool of Economic Misdirection: Moving ‘To and Fro’ on the Growth Bar?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we really where we predicted? Or are we here because we overestimated? You, me or a few economists are not alone in thinking of GDP as a miscalculated benchmark for national economic well-being. Adjudged as one of the greatest inventions of the 20th century, it has long been a closely-watched tool for politicians, economists and journalists alike. But for nearly as long as GDP has been revered, it has faced strong criticism too. And rightly so because it captures what economic historians call a “somewhat arbitrary slice of reality.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gross Domestic Product (GDP) is the total monetary or market value of all the finished goods and services produced within a country’s borders in a specific time period (usually a year). As a relatively broad measure of overall domestic production, it works as a comprehensive scorecard of the country’s economic health. This definition excludes a lot. To name a few, we can look at the following qualitative parameters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Services have replaced goods, freelancers and agencies are a growing share of the workforce, and value is increasingly derived from intangible assets like design, branding and software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Unpaid labour like parental housework and childcare does not figure in, nor does volunteering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many loopholes exist, but let’s focus upon one in particular: &lt;em&gt;inequality&lt;/em&gt;. In recent times, income inequality has shot almost everywhere globally. As per the data summarised by the World Economic Forum, one scenario exists wherein growth is uneven between the poorest 50%, the middle 40% and the richest 10%. While earners at all income levels receive some benefit, nearly half of the population saw about half of the 5% GDP growth for the total economy. On the other hand, taking another stance, 90% of the population sees none of that growth. In fact, incomes for the bottom 50% actually contract. Still, GDP growth looks strong, let’s say, at 5.5%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rich get Richer: Production Factor and Financial Imbalance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One aspect to ponder upon is that a growing fraction of innovation is not measured at all. In a world where houses are private suites and private cars are Uber/Meru taxis, where a free software upgrade renews old computers, and Facebook, Instagram and YouTube bring hours of entertainment to millions at no price at all, many suspect GDP is becoming an ever more misleading measure. Unfortunately, nothing is perfect. And GDP is no exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as GDP is widely used as a measure of output, or even as a measure of a country’s well-being, GDP has irrefutable limitations. Conventionally and quite literally, GDP calculates only output that is bought and sold. I have strong reasons to believe that it is a fairly limited approach. First, market transactions are taxable and, therefore, of interest to the exchequer, an important consumer of GDP statistics. Second, they can be influenced by policies to manage aggregate demand. Third, where there are market prices, it is fairly straightforward to put a value on output. This convention means that the so-called “home production”, such as housework or caring for an elderly relative or children, is excluded from GDP even though such unpaid services have considerable value. Fourth, despite the convention, a lot of what is included in GDP lies outside the market economy. Many government services are provided for free, and for decades the value given to such output was simply the cost of provision. It is fairly recently that statisticians have started to measure some bits of public sector output directly, for instance, by counting the number of operations performed by health services or the number of students taught in schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is Price Parity causing a Hindrance?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adjusting for the ever-rising increase in prices over a considerable period of time (inflation, yes) has further complicated the situation. Then comes the adjustments for changes in quality. This year’s iPhone might cost more than last year’s, but if so- it is because it is capable of rendering more. If statisticians focus only on changes in price, they will *overstate the true inflation rate *by missing improvements in performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the advent of newer technologies some physical marketable products have turned into digital services, the value of which is harder to track. It seems likely, for instance, that more the physical copies of books are being read to than ever before, but revenue for publications has shrunk by a significant margin from its peak. (Thanks to e-books and kindle?) Consumers once bought newspapers and maps and paid middlemen to book holidays. Now they do much more themselves, an effort which doesn’t show up in GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These problems do not invalidate or negate the use of GDP but given the significant increase in technological change, they seem likely to grow much more than before, and solutions to them are both hard and imperfect. Measuring the consumer surplus from new or free products relies on calculated assumptions; estimates vary considerably depending on which ones are used!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ankita Punjani</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">GDP as a Tool of Economic Misdirection: Moving ‘To and Fro’ on the Growth Bar?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Unending Battle of Keeping Trade Secrets a Secret</title>
      <link href="/The-Unending-Battle-of-Keeping-Trade-Secrets-Secret" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Unending Battle of Keeping Trade Secrets a Secret" />
      <published>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Unending-Battle-of-Keeping-Trade-Secrets-Secret</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Unending-Battle-of-Keeping-Trade-Secrets-Secret">&lt;p&gt;Ever heard of the secret recipe of the most popular drink in the world – Coca Cola? Or the algorithm Google uses to rank various websites in its search engine results pages? You would have heard rumours disclosing the special ingredients used to make Coke or the data used by Google to rank websites based on relevance to users. But, none of them would have the backing to be true, neither the practical applicability nor the affirmation from the companies themselves. These secrets are known as &lt;em&gt;trade secrets&lt;/em&gt;. As the name suggests, any sensitive information such as a formula, pattern, compilation, program, device, method, technique or process that needs to be protected from the general public comes under the purview of trade secrets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might wonder why Coca Cola and Google chose not to file for a patent instead. The obvious reason here is that the highly confidential information would have been disclosed to the public, despite giving the companies an exclusive right to the patented process, design or invention for a designated period. Unlike other intellectual property rights, trade secrets protect a much wider range of subject matter such as a business strategy, a new product roadmap, or lists of suppliers and customers and are not limited to set terms of protection. However, they can’t be enforced against anyone who independently discovers the secret. They are actionable only when there is any unlawful acquisition, disclosure or misuse either under breach of confidence or theft. Under such circumstances, the proprietor of the trade secret is eligible to get compensation from the party who committed this unlawful act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With growing cases of infringement of trade secrets, both the organisations and governments worldwide have responded by amending and introducing increasingly robust rules to protect trade secret owners and their rights. On the flip side, it must be ensured that the companies themselves do not misuse the protection provided to them by law and defraud the public by not disclosing harmful information that might lead the company to lose the competitive advantage it has earned due to the trade secret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classic example of a company engaged in this malpractice has been Theranos – the blood-testing startup with the big vision of testing patients for over 200 conditions off just a small sample of blood from the fingertip, thus saying goodbye to the big, bad needles. The innovative technology soon gained momentum, with the company valuing at $9 billion in 2015 and its CEO Elizabeth Holmes, the darling Stanford dropout of the Silicon Valley, continuously featuring in the lists of top global executives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before Theranos reached its peak in 2015, questions were raised regarding the reliability of the technology and the honesty of the company. The first decade of inception of Theranos in 2003 saw several collaborations such as partnering with Walgreens as well as Safeway to run health clinics, however, things started getting tense gradually when experts started showing concerns of discrepancies in blood test results of patients. The events that followed were clearly indicative of the secrets frauds committed by the company, with the chief scientist of Theranos committing suicide in 2013, President Sunny Balwani leaving the company in 2016 and an end to the partnerships with Walgreens and Safeway leading to the shutting down of wellness centres and clinical labs combined with the laying-off of employees and the piling up of lawsuits filed by investors, patients and collaborators. Such cases prove that although trade secrets give a competitive advantage to the owner of such confidential information, it can also result in misuse by way of not disclosing significant facts – the process of conducting tests in case of Theranos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many countries, like India, do not have sufficient laws to protect businesses from increasingly sophisticated infringers and at the same time to ensure that the companies make use of the protection provided to them by the state. The scenario is changing with the US and Europe, two of the most prominent markets, taking a step forward and implementing new laws that make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The protection of trade secrets was addressed by individual states in the EU before the implementation of Directive in 2016, which led to the harmonisation of laws across all EU member nations. The countries were given the autonomy to go beyond the minimum requirements and level of protection set out by the directive. The aim was not of full harmonisation, but rather to ensure that every EU nation at least achieves the bare minimum safeguard against the illegal acquisition, disclosure and use of trade secrets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK government introduced The Trade Secrets (Enforcement, etc.) Regulations in 2018 as a complement to the already existing Trade Secrets Directive applicable in the entire EU. The Directive was adopted by the UK so as to ensure that UK-based businesses having offices in other countries of the EU can rely on equivalent protection to their trade secrets in the local jurisdictions of other nations. Even post Brexit, the Directive will be applicable, regardless of where the secret holder is domiciled, provided the damage took place in a Member State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As per UK law, the cases are solved in a court of law wherein the plaintiff has to prove that the relevant information had the quality of confidence in the sense of not being generally known and not being of trivial nature. It has to be shown that the information was disclosed to the defendant in circumstances of confidence, and the defendant used or disclosed the information without permission or had threatened to do so. However, the Directive has placed restrictions by mandating the organisation to prove that it has taken reasonable steps to safeguard their secret, failing to do so results in loss of protection to the organisation. That apart, the Directive has scaled back the earlier system of confidential hearings and redacted publication of court documents, which may disincentivise companies to actually engage in litigation due to the fear of their trade secret becoming public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike other countries, the Defend Trade Secrets Act, 2016 of the US offers the parties the option of settling disputes under either state or federal laws. The parties have the option to choose from three different forums for litigation related to trade secrets – Federal District Courts, US state courts or the US International Trade Commission. These forums deal with any sensitive information acquired by “improper means” namely theft, bribery, misrepresentation, breach or inducement of breach of duty to maintain secrecy, espionage through electronic or other means. Although the laws at the state and central levels differ in some aspects, there is a great deal of similarity among state laws as the majority of them have adopted certain variations of the Uniform Trade Secrets Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prime onus to prevent misappropriation of trade secrets lies on the shoulders of the organisation itself, and not on the government. The business must clearly identify and classify its trade secrets, restrict access and educate employees on the importance of adhering to confidentiality. The employees must be made to sign Non-Disclosure Agreements (NDAs), legally restricting the employees from disclosing private information either to the competitor or the public at large. Exit interviews with outgoing employees can also be used to reinforce the organisation’s trade secret policy. Some special tactics of preventing data leak include &lt;em&gt;read-only&lt;/em&gt; files; password and firewall protection; check-in and check-out procedures; document destruction policies; and review of publications, presentations, at trade shows, on websites, etc. Wherein information is exorbitantly sensitive and would result in immense losses, the companies must segregate this precious information, under lock and key, designated as &lt;em&gt;confidential&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With rampant cybercrime, easier and faster decryption of data by hackers, the cases of data leak and misuse are growing day-by-day. In such an era, this serious yet undiscussed issue of trade secrets can be solved only by nudging the countries across the globe for the adoption of laws with stricter consequences of committing such crimes at international platforms.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sanjana Chandaliya</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Ever heard of the secret recipe of the most popular drink in the world – Coca Cola? Or the algorithm Google uses to rank various websites in its search engine results pages? You would have heard rumours disclosing the special ingredients used to make Coke or the data used by Google to rank websites based on relevance to users. But, none of them would have the backing to be true, neither the practical applicability nor the affirmation from the companies themselves. These secrets are known as trade secrets. As the name suggests, any sensitive information such as a formula, pattern, compilation, program, device, method, technique or process that needs to be protected from the general public comes under the purview of trade secrets.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘Woke’ Capital: Pinkwashing Exploitation</title>
      <link href="/Pinkwashing-Exploitation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘Woke’ Capital: Pinkwashing Exploitation" />
      <published>2020-01-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Pinkwashing-Exploitation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Pinkwashing-Exploitation">&lt;p&gt;“What do we have to show for the billions spent on pink ribbon products? A lot of us are done with awareness. We want action.” - Karuna Jagger, Executive Director of Breast Cancer Action&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is no longer enough to simply sell a product. The percolation of market fundamentalism into every facet of life has blurred the distinction between our identities and our consumption habits, meaning that we now desire products that carry a deeper significance, i.e. a message about social justice. The result? A pernicious and contradictory phenomenon: Capital with a human face. ‘Woke’ Capitalism involves corporations cynically utilising socially progressive causes such as LGBTQ and women’s issues, or climate change, to sell their products while maintaining the same underlying structures of profit-maximisation and exploitation of workers and resources around the world, particularly in the global South. Moreover, in a post-2008 era of economic turmoil, ‘Woke Capital’ provides an opportunity for the Right to assert that large corporations are in fact, the tools of a left-wing elite that is hostile to the common man, and so doing, to downplay the culpability of capitalism itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘free’ market is not an entity that exists in a vacuum, independent of the social and cultural paradigms surrounding it. To consistently make profits and remain competitive in a crowded marketplace, businesses must appeal to the ever-changing social attitudes of consumers, and the growing acceptance of LGBTQ identity has provided an ideal marketing opportunity for large corporations. Pride parades festooned with the presence of multinational corporations are not uncommon in the modern day: Pharmaceuticals company Gilead sponsored New York Pride, despite having patented the HIV risk-reducing drug Truvada, causing some of the poorest people in the United States to die due to lack of access to it. LGBTQ Black men, who have a higher HIV rate than any other group in the United States, comprise just 9% of applicants for Truvada, demonstrating the effects of these barriers to entry. Although this is arguably one of the most galling examples of the hypocrisy of corporations who cynically feign awareness and progressivism while continuing the profiteering, it is by no means the only example. The establishment of monopoly control over production and distribution through patents is no aberration; it is a logical step for large corporations, and will continue for as long as the profit motive continues to be the dominant force in the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, former San Francisco 49ers Quarterback Colin Kaepernick became the face of Nike’s campaign, which celebrated the 30th anniversary of its’ ‘Just Do It’ slogan. The cooptation of Kaepernick’s protest against police brutality and the maltreatment of African-Americans is particularly striking given that it has come from Nike, a company that still employs Black and Brown workers at below poverty wages in the global South. Despite co-founder Phil Knight being forced to admit to using sweatshops and child labour in 1998 and to change Nike’s business practices, a fresh wave of recent accusations have impugned the company further. In Vietnam, where Nike employs 400,000 workers and has 91 factories, workers are being paid at wage rates that are only just over half of the living wage. In Indonesia, where Nike has 39 factories and around 200,000 workers, the wages paid to workers were $200 less than that which would be required to meet their basic needs. It is, therefore, unsurprising that Nike has earned the support of William Stepp of the libertarian Mises Institute, who has argued against the minimum wage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The response from corporations such as Nike, Ford and others to the climate crisis and increasing awareness of environmental issues is, perhaps, the most egregious illustration of their hypocrisy. Apple, for instance, displays its low carbon footprint as an example of its progressivism while outsourcing production to China, where &lt;a href=&quot;https://spectator.us/pursuit-woke-capital/&quot;&gt;greenhouse gases are pumped into the atmosphere at alarming rates.&lt;/a&gt; Nestle also promotes environmental sustainability on their website, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2017/jul/21/pepsico-unilever-and-nestle-accused-of-complicity-in-illegal-rainforest-destruction&quot;&gt;were accused of complicity in the illegal destruction of rainforests in Sumatra&lt;/a&gt;. The exacerbation of the conditions of already critically endangered species in the region is one of many consequences that large corporations’ vast economies of scale have on the environment, but environmentalism to them is merely a discardable fad that will generate revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pernicious impact of ‘Woke’ Capital goes beyond just its hypocrisy and continuation of exploitation; it affords the Right an opportunity to portray the Left as elites while exonerating themselves and obscuring the true problem: the underlying imperatives in the forces and relations of production. Why acknowledge that the aforementioned ‘woke’ corporations are simply doing what corporations have always done: appeal to consumers in the interests of short-term profits, when you could brand them as ideologically-motivated, left-wing, virtue signalling elites who despise ordinary people and their families? Indeed, this is exactly what Tucker Carlson is extremely effective at doing: arguing that 2019 is the year of the ‘woke’ billionaire, he has claimed that an unholy alliance had taken place between virtue-signalling billionaires and the ‘socialist’ Democratic Party. This tactic is quintessential to the reactionary Right, as the portrayal of the Left and the Billionaires being motivated by the same progressive, internationalist ideology makes it easier to appeal to ‘Middle America’, and to dissuade them from examining the root of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Hobsbawm, writing in his book &lt;em&gt;Age of Extremes&lt;/em&gt; about the rise of fascism, argued that one of the common themes in these movements was the resentment of “&lt;em&gt;the little man&lt;/em&gt;” in a society dominated by the interests of big business and organised labour. The reactionary Right, in an attempt to preserve the status quo in a time of economic collapse, would attempt to stave off forces of socialism and internationalism by portraying themselves as the allies of working people against the perceived unholy alliance between ‘the Left’ and big business. In Europe’s fascist States during the 1930’s, this was an important tool that brought such regimes to power. A concoction of privatisation, tax cuts for the wealthy and a bonfire of workers’ rights followed, demonstrating the true nature of their regimes. The recent attempts by Tucker Carlson to deflect from the culpability of the neoliberal system in an era of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/u-s-income-inequality-highest-level-50-years-economic-gap-n1058956&quot;&gt;rampant inequality&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hamiltonproject.org/assets/files/UnionsEA_Web_8.19.pdf&quot;&gt;limited bargaining power &lt;/a&gt;and &lt;a href=&quot;https://fas.org/sgp/crs/misc/R45090.pdf&quot;&gt;plummeting wages&lt;/a&gt; are clearly part of a similar ploy; arguing that the large corporations are acting in the interests of the Left increases Middle America’s hatred of socialism, and in doing so, prevents any substantive anti-capitalist case from being heard, thereby maintaining the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Woke Capital, therefore, absolves the reactionary Right of having to face the consequences of their own economic orthodoxy. The Right do not have to face the fact that mass immigration to Western nations is, in part, a result of unequal terms of trade that have subjected the local farming and small industries of global South nations to debilitating competition, forcing vast numbers of people to flee, if they can argue that immigration is a deliberate tool of ‘woke corporations’. Once again, the portrayal of corporate greed as a Leftist idea precludes any rigorous analysis of Capital from taking place, and reduces the factors precipitating mass immigration from material realities to abstract ideological forces. The consequent scapegoating and vilification of immigrants that characterises them as interlopers in Western societies, which parties across Europe and North America continue to engage in, allows the rich to get richer and maintain their power at the expense of the rest of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The veneer of altruism and inclusivity feigned by ‘progressive’ multinational corporations disappears with a cursory examination of their productive processes, which reveal that, at heart, their modus operandi is driven by the same unscrupulous exploitation of labour-power and resources that it always was. The rejection of liberal, faux-progressive corporatism and the bogus contention that Capitalism can be made any less ruthless or exploitative by dressing it up in rainbow colours is an important part of a genuine socialist ethos. Only a persuasive, comprehensive and thorough analysis of the contradictions of capitalism will allow the Left to fight back against the contention that ‘Woke’ Capitalism is in any way progressive, and to champion the cause of those who are most exploited by it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“What do we have to show for the billions spent on pink ribbon products? A lot of us are done with awareness. We want action.” - Karuna Jagger, Executive Director of Breast Cancer Action</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Sports Betting in India: an Argument for Legalisation</title>
      <link href="/Sports-Betting-in-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sports Betting in India: an Argument for Legalisation" />
      <published>2020-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Sports-Betting-in-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Sports-Betting-in-India">&lt;p&gt;Gambling or other forms of betting are legalised as games all across the world. However, with India, there is especially a culture revolving around this, which goes on to make it an immoral sport. Since ancient times, betting is considered as something that one should not indulge in. The Indian epic &lt;em&gt;Mahabharata&lt;/em&gt; is a classic example, wherein King Yudhishthira lost his kingdom, fortune, brothers and wife due to his obsession with gambling. The &lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt; also renounces the sport as an immoral one, and considers the fact that it is addictive in nature. The impact of the religious texts and traditionally followed rules have built the perception of gambling or betting. It generally brings to our minds an image of a person who must have defaulted on payments and subsequently ruined his life and people close to him. This is something that has been fed into the systems of most Indians from a young age. But this article doesn’t focus on the perceptions revolving around this subject matter, instead it highlights the laws in place and how legalisation of betting could churn benefits for the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In India, the Public Gaming Act, 1867 prohibits most forms of betting other than horse racing, lottery and rummy. Other than these three fields, no person is allowed to engage in any form of betting, online or offline. Any person violating the law has to face ‘dire’ consequences (please note the sarcasm) of paying a fine up to ₹200 or face jail for 3 months. This is how bad and ineffective the British-era enacted law is. The law, since ages, has failed to achieve what it tries to, i.e. to discourage the activity in its entirety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the South Indian state of Andhra Pradesh, cock fights are famous during the &lt;em&gt;Makar Sankranti&lt;/em&gt; (Solar New Year) season. People from every profession, lawmakers included, participate. Estimates say that during every season more than tens of billions of rupees exchanges hands. Though the event, held across the state, is widely known to everyone, neither the police nor the judiciary bats an eye. If any, the ban has only promoted the underworld to associate itself with betting and create a parallel economy, of sorts, where the organisers are ruthless people who go to any lengths to recover their betting money. The ban in no way has been a success in preventing betting. If anything, the ban, in a way, has led to an increase in crime, corruption and money laundering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the prohibition also costs the exchequer of the government dearly. For example, betting in cricket is the costliest of all. It is no exaggeration to say that it is a market worth tens of billions of rupees, especially due to the Indian Premier League. It is estimated that the value of bets waged every year in India, of which cricket claims a lion’s share, accounts for at least $40 billion. The Federation of Indian Chambers for Commerce and Industry (FICCI) believes that the government is forfeiting revenue of ₹1.9 trillion by not legalising betting. Moreover, Goa, one of the states where betting is legal, has earned ₹40 billion from casinos in 2018-19. In recent times, owing to the wider availability of smartphones and data, online betting has gained popularity. This has opened new dimensions for betting and created a global market for it. As Indian laws do not apply to international online gambling sites, Indian government cannot police them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Betting is a ‘state’ subject under the Indian Constitution, meaning every Indian state has the power to enact their own laws. It seems only right to legalise all forms of betting. How should this be done? The answer is: Regulation. Licences should be issued to betting houses and individual bookmakers. It should be clearly laid out as to who can participate and how they can participate. Sports persons should be banned from betting as it might affect their play. One of the main arguments that critics of legal betting present is that crime will increase. Strict state vigilance can solve that problem quite easily. Another argument is about addiction. When rules about how much a person can bet are in place, the addiction problem can be tackled and it is not that everyone who gambles is addicted and affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When hearing Indian Premier League corruption case, the Indian Supreme Court of India asked the Law Commission of India (LCI) about how to tackle betting, and the corruption arising from it . The LCI has stated that betting ought to be legalised whilst providing recommendations for bringing a framework in place to regulate gambling and betting in sports in order to bring down fraud and money laundering. One can only add here that there should also be separate regulations for offline and online betting, as the methods on which they operate are different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, technology has further bridged the gap between bookmakers and wagers, which makes regulation of betting a serious challenge. Try googling ‘sports betting in India.’ You will be amazed by the number of online betting sites that will pop-up. All these sites go unguarded and they pretty much make their own rules. With no operations in India, the authorities cannot control them which makes it easy for Indians to access the websites and pay through e-wallets. All these organisations will fall in line, when there are strict regulations in place. Robust regulation that governs betting will eventually weed out the black market and its operators and pave the way for the growth of a service industry: sports gambling industry. Moreover, when it is legalised, people in the betting business will have some incentive to improve services to customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ancient Hindu texts have also been for legalization of gambling. References to that effect can be found in the &lt;em&gt;Manusmriti&lt;/em&gt;, India’s most well-known Hindu law book and the &lt;em&gt;Atharva Veda&lt;/em&gt;, a foundational text of Hinduism. Kautilya, an ancient political scientist, also suggested in his famous book &lt;em&gt;Arthashastra&lt;/em&gt; (literally, ‘Economics Text’) that the state could collect 5% tax on betting. This clearly shows precedent for the argument for legalisation of betting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many say that betting leads to crime, corruption and money laundering. In contrast, not having vigilance has helped these problems develop in the first place. According to the FICCI, gambling has only become a socio-economic problem due to the absence of regulation in place. Betting constitutes a vast global market. Our extant laws need to be updated taking reality into account. The ban on betting only translates to an increase in crime, money laundering whilst causing parallel economies to spring up and revenue to be lost to the government. The government should, therefore, realise what is at stake and take steps to legalise betting. The success stories of Goa and Sikkim should not be forgotten. When the small states are earning billions of rupees, imagine how much bigger states, with a much bigger population, could earn by taking the right measures. Of course, there are problems. There will be. But legalisation of betting more than offsets the negative effects of not legalising it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Gambling or other forms of betting are legalised as games all across the world. However, with India, there is especially a culture revolving around this, which goes on to make it an immoral sport. Since ancient times, betting is considered as something that one should not indulge in. The Indian epic Mahabharata is a classic example, wherein King Yudhishthira lost his kingdom, fortune, brothers and wife due to his obsession with gambling. The Quran also renounces the sport as an immoral one, and considers the fact that it is addictive in nature. The impact of the religious texts and traditionally followed rules have built the perception of gambling or betting. It generally brings to our minds an image of a person who must have defaulted on payments and subsequently ruined his life and people close to him. This is something that has been fed into the systems of most Indians from a young age. But this article doesn’t focus on the perceptions revolving around this subject matter, instead it highlights the laws in place and how legalisation of betting could churn benefits for the economy.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Pubcast on the Indian Economy</title>
      <link href="/Pubcast-on-the-Indian-Econoomy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Pubcast on the Indian Economy" />
      <published>2019-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Pubcast-on-the-Indian-Econoomy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Pubcast-on-the-Indian-Econoomy">&lt;p&gt;The second of The Pangean’s pubcasts is with Mr Achyut Chandra, an MSME businessman engaged in the field of manufacturing printing and packaging solutions. Mr Chandra is the Chairman of the New Market Development Committee of the Federation of Corrugated Box Manufacturers’ Association of India, an umbrella organisation of box manufacturing organisations in India. He’s also the current Vice-President of the Corrugated Box Manufacturers’ Association of Eastern India and is an active member of the Bharat Chambers of Commerce. The pubcast with Mr Chandra is in two parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part I&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(0)&quot;&gt;00:00&lt;/a&gt;) - an on-ground overview of what is going wrong with the Indian economy, i.e. the current slowdown, and a brief overview of the state of the MSME sector, in particular&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part II&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(2246)&quot;&gt;37:26&lt;/a&gt;) - a vision for India’s economy, including a broad roadmap for future prosperity and for unleashing the potential of India’s small businesses&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;audio id=&quot;pubcast-2&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; controlsList=&quot;nodownload&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/Podcast2-final.mp3&quot;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    var aud = document.getElementById(&quot;pubcast-2&quot;);
    function setTime(x) {
      aud.currentTime = x;
    }

&lt;/script&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The second of The Pangean’s pubcasts is with Mr Achyut Chandra, an MSME businessman engaged in the field of manufacturing printing and packaging solutions. Mr Chandra is the Chairman of the New Market Development Committee of the Federation of Corrugated Box Manufacturers’ Association of India, an umbrella organisation of box manufacturing organisations in India. He’s also the current Vice-President of the Corrugated Box Manufacturers’ Association of Eastern India and is an active member of the Bharat Chambers of Commerce. The pubcast with Mr Chandra is in two parts: Part I (00:00) - an on-ground overview of what is going wrong with the Indian economy, i.e. the current slowdown, and a brief overview of the state of the MSME sector, in particular Part II (37:26) - a vision for India’s economy, including a broad roadmap for future prosperity and for unleashing the potential of India’s small businesses Your browser does not support the audio element.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
