<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/economics/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-05-07T20:24:18+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/economics/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Rational Pirates</title>
      <link href="/The-Rational-Pirates" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rational Pirates" />
      <published>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Rational-Pirates</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Rational-Pirates">&lt;p&gt;So today while watching videos on YouTube, (which is what I am usually doing almost every second while I am not busy) I came across a brilliant riddle. I clicked on the video and found out that it involved game theory and behavioural economics, and that really fascinated me. I wanted to share the riddle with you, and try to explain and help you better understand the concept of game theory. First of all, you need to know what game theory actually means. Simply kept, game theory is a theoretical structure for understanding social situations among competing players. In some respects, game theory is the science of ‘strategic play’, or at least the optimal decision-making of competing players in a situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I would like to share the riddle with you and try to explain the solution and how game theory can help us in various situations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a good day to be a pirate. Andrew and his 4 mates, Brandon, Christian, David and Edmund have struck gold, a chest with 100 coins. But now, they must divide up the treasure according to the pirate code. The code is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the captain, Andrew gets to propose first about how to distribute the coins. Then, each pirate including Andrew himself gets to vote either ‘yes’ or ‘no’. If the vote passes, or if there is a tie, the coins are divided according to the plan proposed by Andrew, but if the majority votes ‘no’, Andrew must walk the plank into the deep sea and Brandon becomes the captain. Then, Brandon gets to propose a new distribution and all remaining pirates would vote again. If his plan is rejected, he walks the plank too and Christian takes his place. This process repeats with the captain’s hat moving to David and then to Edmund until either a proposal is accepted or there is only one pirate left.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each pirate’s primary objective is to stay alive while getting as much gold as possible. But since they are pirates, none of them trust each other so they can’t really collaborate in advance.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If anyone thinks they will end up with the same amount of gold in two different scenarios, they will vote to make the captain walk the plank just for fun.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, each pirate is excellent at logical thinking and knows that the other pirates are too.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question here is, what distribution should Andrew propose to make sure he lives and gets as much gold as possible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we follow our intuition, it seems like Andrew should try to bribe other pirates with most of the gold to increase the chances of his plan being accepted or maybe to propose a distribution like 40-30-20-10-0 or any other combination for that matter and hope for the best, but it turns out Andrew can do much better than that. Let’s have a look at the solution!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like you know, the pirates know each other to be top-notch logicians. So, when each one votes, they won’t just be thinking about the current proposal but about all the possible outcomes down the line. Moreover, because the rank order is known in advance, each one of them can accurately predict how others would vote in any situation and adjust their own votes accordingly. Since Edmund is last, he has the most outcomes to consider so let us start by following his thought process. He would reason out by working backward from the last possible scenario with only him and David remaining. David would obviously propose to keep all the gold and Edmund’s one vote would not be enough to override it. So, Edmund wants to avoid this situation at all costs. Now, we move to the previous decision point with three pirates left and Christian making the proposal. Everyone knows that if he is outvoted, the decision shifts to David who would then get all the gold while Edmund gets nothing. So to secure Edmund’s vote, Christian only needs to offer slightly more than nothing, that is, one coin. Since this ensures his support, Christian doesn’t need to offer David anything at all. What if there were 4 pirates? As captain, Brandon would still only need one other vote for his plan to pass. He knows that David wouldn’t want the decision to pass to Christian so he would offer David one coin for his support with nothing for Christian or Edmund. Going forward with other possible scenarios, now we’re back at the initial vote with all 5 pirates standing. Having considered all the other scenarios, Andrew knows that if he goes overboard, the decision comes down to Brandon which would be bad news for Christian and Edmund, so he offers one coin each to them, thus, keeping 98 for himself. Brandon and David vote ‘no’, but Christian and Edmund grudgingly vote ‘yes’, knowing that the alternative would be worse for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pirate game involves some amusing concepts from game theory. One is the concept of ‘common knowledge’ where each person is aware of what the others know and uses this to predict their reasoning and final distribution. Had it been the case where the pirates didn’t know the intellectual capabilities of each other, the situation would flip altogether and there would have been no accurate solution to the riddle but fortunately that wasn’t the case. This is a classic example of ‘Nash-equilibrium’, where each player knows every other player’s strategy and chooses them accordingly. Even though it may lead to a worse outcome for everyone than cooperating would, no individual player can benefit by changing their strategy. So, it seems like Andrew gets to keep most of the gold coins (98 to be precise) and the other pirates might need to find better ways to use those impressive logic skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole intention behind this article was to explain to you how a simple concept of game theory can help you gain more in life. The example here was not an appropriate one for you to relate to in real life (unless you obviously decide to become a pirate) but there are several other instances in which it might help you. The decision involving whether to go for a movie or a concert with your friends also involves game theory where we know what the other person wants and we try to manipulate the final result so as to do what we want. Also, in financial markets, the decision to invest in a certain bond or a stock after having all the relevant information about the company involves game theory as well. By investing in the company, you become a player and what the company does with that investment determines your gain or loss. These are just some cases where you can utilise game theory, the scope of it is wide-ranging and unexplored, and left for you to discover. As the British writer Charles Lamb rightly said, “Man is a gaming animal. He must always be trying to get better in something or other.”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">So today while watching videos on YouTube, (which is what I am usually doing almost every second while I am not busy) I came across a brilliant riddle. I clicked on the video and found out that it involved game theory and behavioural economics, and that really fascinated me. I wanted to share the riddle with you, and try to explain and help you better understand the concept of game theory. First of all, you need to know what game theory actually means. Simply kept, game theory is a theoretical structure for understanding social situations among competing players. In some respects, game theory is the science of ‘strategic play’, or at least the optimal decision-making of competing players in a situation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Economy Incarcerated</title>
      <link href="/Economy-Incarcerated" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Economy Incarcerated" />
      <published>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Economy-Incarcerated</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Economy-Incarcerated">&lt;p&gt;Prison, jail, penitentiary are all the same things. They are meant for the mental reform of a person convicted of criminal activities. However, sometimes they can even enhance the business acumen of a person. They are supposed to have very limited trade and economic activity. In such a world, the only way one could earn is through working official chores assigned by the prison and the only place to spend is the official commissary, or a canteen, extant in the jail premises. However, more often than not, the prisoners trade informally themselves. Goods are smuggled in and a variety of services are offered by the prisoners with skills. Such an informal or underground economy is a common sight in prisons, especially in prisons with people serving quite longer sentences. This article is an attempt to explain why informal economies spring up and how they are operated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many reasons why an informal economy springs up. Often the demand of the prisoners is not satisfied by the officials or the prison canteen. An exhaustive list of things that are trivial to the ‘free people’ and are taken for granted are luxuries for the prisoners and hence, have put a huge value on the. Such small things, like a blanket or warm and delicious food, are difficult to get hold of. The only way they can get the items is through illicit means. Second, although there is a canteen present in prison, it is practically the only shop and exercises monopoly power. This results, often, in the sale of goods for a premium on their original price. Many prisons prohibit prisoners from carrying cash with a concern that they would bribe the guards to get their way. Instead, each prisoner is assigned a card; into which they can load money and use it to make purchases. These cards can be loaded either by funds sent in for them by someone and/or the earnings of the prisoners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above the only legal ways to earn money is to do the work allotted by the prison officials. However, the wages offered in the prison are diminutive, even below the statutory minimum in many countries. For instance, the average wage in the federal prisons in the US is &lt;a href=&quot;https://psmag.com/social-justice/taking-freedom-modern-day-slavery&quot;&gt;31 cents per hour&lt;/a&gt;, way below the minimum requirement of $7.25 per hour. The Indian prisons compete with their US counterparts in this aspect. The average amount of wage paid is approximately &lt;a href=&quot;https://in.news.yahoo.com/jailonomics--how-to-survive-inside-an-indian-prison-100808012.html&quot;&gt;₹48 per day&lt;/a&gt; (the actual wage varies from state to state, as prisons fall under the state list), which is one-fourth of the prescribed minimum wage in the country. This clearly points out the enormous gap between the wages and the prices in a prison. Even if the goods were to be sold at the Maximum Retail Price, it would not be possible for the prisoners to afford it. It is also the case that the quality of food is abysmal and sometimes becomes quite hard to eat. This is another reason for the existence of an economy where it is not supposed to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore one thing is clear: there is a demand for goods and services (smuggling in drugs can also be categorised as a service!) in prison. This demand creates opportunities for prisoners to make money. The cost of a good mainly depends on the risk it takes to smuggle in the good. The stronger the security, costlier the good is. Supply of a good can come from two sources: either the prisoners get in the good through their external contact or pay the prison guards to bring the good. In his famous book, &lt;em&gt;Extreme Economies&lt;/em&gt;, Richard Davies quotes an ex-convict who served time in the Louisiana State penitentiary saying “…these [guards] are young and uneducated, they can triple their wages by bringing these things in.” This is mostly true for guards serving in other prisons as well because often the salary paid to these guards is often very low. For this reason, often, the guards are also willing to smuggle in the goods for prisoners. Therefore, the trading prisoners strike a deal with the guards and pay them commissions. Now that we have seen how the supply and demand are satisfied, we need to look at what is the medium of exchange. As cash is prohibited, prisoners come up with innovative ideas to solve their problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can find the most popular medium of exchange for the most part of history has been ‘cigarettes’. Apart from cigarettes shower gel capsules, rosary beads, cigarette paper, etc. have also been used in UK prisons. In the US, after cigarettes, the most popular exchange mediums were postage stamps. Notice all the above items perfectly satisfy all the properties of a currency: store of value, a medium of exchange, and a measure of value. In recent times, however, a popular ‘currency’ emerged in the US: ‘mackerel’ (a type of packaged fish). The validity of a currency depends on the convention that ‘everyone values the currency because they expect everyone else to value it.’ This is exactly what happened with mackerel. While such an exchange was perfectly possible among the prisoners, convincing a guard to take it is hard; as they would only accept cash as payment. Richard Davies explains how the prisoners of Louisiana prison overcame this conundrum (this is also what happens across most of the US prisons): prepaid cards. Using a debit or credit card, one could purchase these prepaid cards (which have an upper limit of $500) basically anywhere. All you need to do is tell the beneficiary the 14-digit number that is behind the card and they could redeem it. So, the buyer and the beneficiary need not even know each other and the transaction happens. Moreover, the fact that no proof or ID is required to buy these cards means that it leaves no digital trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prisoners also engage in these activities because it provides a sense of identity and purpose to the prisoners. They find their lost dignity, in the society, by working and proving useful to their fellow prisoners. Also, the scarcity of the basic goods and, sometimes, prohibited goods means that they can be traded for huge sums. Prisoners that come from families with a relatively lower standard of living support their families with the income earned by engaging in the informal trade inside the prison. There are also success stories where people, after leaving prison, started their own businesses using the skills acquired during their time in prison. It is also important to take note of the fact that people can put their skills into negative use, say, by engaging in smuggling of drugs. Therefore, the solution to this informal arrangement, if one were to find such an economy harmful, is to recognise the fact the prisoners are people with unsatisfied needs, tastes, and demands; increase the wages substantially, to treat them like normal humans and to let them retain their sense of dignity.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Prison, jail, penitentiary are all the same things. They are meant for the mental reform of a person convicted of criminal activities. However, sometimes they can even enhance the business acumen of a person. They are supposed to have very limited trade and economic activity. In such a world, the only way one could earn is through working official chores assigned by the prison and the only place to spend is the official commissary, or a canteen, extant in the jail premises. However, more often than not, the prisoners trade informally themselves. Goods are smuggled in and a variety of services are offered by the prisoners with skills. Such an informal or underground economy is a common sight in prisons, especially in prisons with people serving quite longer sentences. This article is an attempt to explain why informal economies spring up and how they are operated.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Quality or Quantity?</title>
      <link href="/Quality-or-Quantity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quality or Quantity?" />
      <published>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Quality-or-Quantity</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Quality-or-Quantity">&lt;p&gt;Why are so many students convinced that they should get good grades just because they spent so many hours on a particular paper? It is not a belief about the quality of those papers rather it is a belief about the hours and hours spent on writing them. This fundamental misconception about the value of labour lies at the root of Marx’s critique of capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For hundreds of years, many economists believed that goods should be valued on the basis of the number of hours the labour spent to produce those goods. It was considered that any two goods that took the same time to be produced had the same value. This was termed as the ‘Labour Value of Theory’. One of the best-known advocates of this theory was Karl Marx. However, this theory has fallen out of favour among economists since the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory did have some superficial plausibility as it does seem that a good which involves a higher number of labour hours should be valued higher. However, the theory got increasingly complicated as it tried to explain some obvious objections. If we go by this theory the value of land should be nil, as there is no amount of labour that goes into ‘producing’ the land. What about the great pieces of art which hold hefty price tags, despite the fact that they do not require intense labour? What about the exorbitant prices paid to Michelin starred chefs? The theory failed to give a logical reason for these exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Marx, the labour value of theory lied at the center of the problems related to capitalism. The argument that capitalism exploited labourers depended crucially on the theory that labour was the source of all value-added, and that capitalists stole the profits from these labourers who deserved it more. According to him, capitalism destroyed our ability to enjoy the work that we do and forced us to work under their tyranny. Without the theory, Marx would have failed to justify the problems associated with capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It became increasingly difficult for the proponents of the theory to come up with logical explanations for the various exceptions to this theory. An individual’s skill set was completely ignored, it failed to account for the difference in the amount of time it takes for different individuals to perform a certain task. Moreover, it is clearly possible to spend a large amount of time on a product that ends up having no value eventually (something like a sandcastle). Additionally, goods that require the same amount of time to be produced should have the same market value, however, this is not always the case. Different goods have varying values in the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opposition to the labour value of theory was proposed by Carl Menger when he stated that the value of goods is ‘subjective’. While the labour theory argued that the price of inputs determines the value of the final good, the subjectivist theory claimed that the value of a good is derived from the human perception of its usefulness. Value is not something that is objective or can be standardised for every person. It is a function of the role that an object plays in the plans of a certain human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, according to the subjectivists, land has value not because of the labour that goes into tilling it but because of the utility that people expect to derive out of it (such as growing crops to eat). People pay a high amount for solid coloured canvases not because of the painter’s efforts, but because of the beauty that they saw in the painting. Michelin starred restaurants are so pricey not because of the hours and hours that the chef spends in preparation of the food, but because of the satisfaction people get from eating that food. Therefore, the theory drew a line between the economic value of a good and the scientific value of the good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subjective theory of value gave a new meaning to the value of labour: the value of inputs like labour depended on the value of outputs that they helped to produce. Hence, labour gets rewarded on the basis of producing things that others value. When you consider that combining labour with capital enables that labour to produce goods that others value, Marx’s arguments seem invalid. Capitalism, hence, provides tools to the labourers to produce valuable goods and thereby increases their remuneration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, capitalism is basically a communication process through which humans try to make the best possible use of the limited resources available with them to satisfy their most urgent wants. Many academics are simply unaware of the fact. It depends on an individual what he values more, ‘quality’ or ‘quantity’.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Amrit Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Why are so many students convinced that they should get good grades just because they spent so many hours on a particular paper? It is not a belief about the quality of those papers rather it is a belief about the hours and hours spent on writing them. This fundamental misconception about the value of labour lies at the root of Marx’s critique of capitalism.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Horrendous Memories of the Raj: Colonial Rule and the Indian Economy</title>
      <link href="/The-Horrendous-Memories-of-the-Raj" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Horrendous Memories of the Raj: Colonial Rule and the Indian Economy" />
      <published>2020-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Horrendous-Memories-of-the-Raj</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Horrendous-Memories-of-the-Raj">&lt;p&gt;Before British rule in India, India was a self-sufficient and robust economy. It was popularly known as the ‘golden eagle’ signifying the wealth it had accumulated. India had already established itself on the world map as the largest exporter in the world with a global trade share of more than 27%. By the late 17th century, almost the whole of India (as we know it in its present form), along with Pakistan and a part of Afghanistan, was united under the name of the Mughal empire and became the largest economy and manufacturing power in the world, producing about a quarter of the global GDP. India was the world leader in manufacturing, producing 25% of the world’s total output until the mid-18th century. It was the world’s biggest producer of textiles, agricultural products, and precious metals and stones, including diamonds. The fact that industrialisation was on the doorstep of the Indian economy cannot be denied. Although primarily it was an agrarian economy, many manufacturing activities started picking up pace in pre-colonial India, and the exchange of ideas and technology with the western world had been free-flowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these developments in the Indian sub-continent lured and attracted the British to capture India and use it as a cash-cow to fulfill the needs of their home country. The British came to India with the motive of colonisation. Their plans involved using India as a feeder colony for their own flourishing economy back in Britain. This exploitation continued for about two centuries, ending at last in 1947 after endless dark days of persecution, plunder and exploitation. The British took steps that ensured the development and promotion of the interests of their home country. They were in no way concerned about the course of the Indian economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India experienced deindustrialisation and cessation of various craft industries under British rule, which along with fast economic and population growth in the West, resulted in India’s share of the world economy declining from 24.4% in 1700 to 4.1% in 1950, with its share in global trade declining from 27% in 1750 to 2% in the 1900’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indian weavers and textile industries were well-known all over the world. They made superior and very fine quality cloth, it was actually known to be the ‘lightest woven-air’. The British came right in, smashed their thumbs, broke their looms, asserted tariffs and duties, and shipped the raw material from India to Britain. They shipped back industrially mass-produced stitched garments back to India, flooding the world’s market with what became the products of the dark and satanic Victorian era. This meant that the weavers and handloom workers in India went from being acknowledged worldwide for their work to being beggars and hence, destroying the forever thriving cloth and textile industry of India, in which it held its utmost pride. The Indian textile industry still hasn’t been able to fully recover from the effects that colonisation had on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British always emphasised the positives that took place during their reign. One such thing in which they took pride was that they built the railways in India. To this, the argument stands that a lot of other countries didn’t need to be colonised in order to build its railways. Railways were built just to serve the British purpose. They were used to transport troops and raw material from the hinterland to the ports to be shipped to Britain. The needs of the Indian public were incidental and there was no consideration to match the demand and supply of the railway services for the general public movement. The fact is that the building of railways was just another gimmick or as one might say a trick implemented by the British to ensure an extravagant return to its own people. They supplied all the equipment, controlled the technology, and promised the British investors vast returns on their investments in railways which were eventually paid out of the Indian taxpayers’ money, as pointed out by Shashi Tharoor. All this resulted in causing the cost of building 1 km of railways to inflate and become almost double of what it took to build in Canada or Australia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving forward to the First World War, India and the rest of the British dominions had no control over Indian defence and foreign policy in 1914. So, when the United Kingdom declared war on Germany on August 4, India and the rest of the British colonies were automatically at war with the Central Powers. Though India was suffering from recession, poverty and hunger at that time, the country supplied not only manpower but also 170,000 animals, 3.7 million tonnes of supplies, jute for sandbags, and a large loan (the equivalent of about £2 billion today) to the British government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;World War II was even worse; more than 2.4 million Indian men served in that war and out of Britain’s total war debt of £3 billion (in 1945 money), £1.25 billion was owed to India and was never really paid back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian economy frequently faced the occurrence of famines too during British rule. Commercialisation of agriculture hampered the production of food grains by transferring land from the cultivation of food crops to non-food crops like industrial raw materials. Moreover, the destruction of Indian handicrafts increased the pressure of population on land. All these led to the frequent occurrences of famines in India causing untold misery and suffering for the Indian cultivators and general people. Anywhere around 15 to 29 million Indians died due to British-induced famines in India during colonial rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even after all the miseries and horrendous exploitation incited by the British on India, they never accepted nor did they apologise for the wrongdoings that happened during that period. Today, after 73 years, India stands strong at a global stage as the 5th largest economy in the world, way ahead of its colonial rulers. Although India still has a lot to achieve in the field of sanitation, healthcare, education and other pillars of the economy, it has done a tremendous job till now and has risen above all the exploitation and plunder they suffered for 200 years as a British colony.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Before British rule in India, India was a self-sufficient and robust economy. It was popularly known as the ‘golden eagle’ signifying the wealth it had accumulated. India had already established itself on the world map as the largest exporter in the world with a global trade share of more than 27%. By the late 17th century, almost the whole of India (as we know it in its present form), along with Pakistan and a part of Afghanistan, was united under the name of the Mughal empire and became the largest economy and manufacturing power in the world, producing about a quarter of the global GDP. India was the world leader in manufacturing, producing 25% of the world’s total output until the mid-18th century. It was the world’s biggest producer of textiles, agricultural products, and precious metals and stones, including diamonds. The fact that industrialisation was on the doorstep of the Indian economy cannot be denied. Although primarily it was an agrarian economy, many manufacturing activities started picking up pace in pre-colonial India, and the exchange of ideas and technology with the western world had been free-flowing.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Japan: Testing the Limits of Pandemic Economics</title>
      <link href="/Testing-the-Limits-of-Pandemic-Economics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Japan: Testing the Limits of Pandemic Economics" />
      <published>2020-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Testing-the-Limits-of-Pandemic-Economics</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Testing-the-Limits-of-Pandemic-Economics">&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus has brought the entire world economy down to its knees, gasping for a breath of fresh air, production cycles all around the world have come to a halt, supply chains disrupted, and many businesses are on the brink of a shutdown. Social distancing is the measure being adopted throughout the world to reduce the spread of this disease leading to the imposition of total lockdowns in various countries, be it a developed or an underdeveloped nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One developed nation facing the brunt of the virus is Japan, which is actually trying to cushion the impact the virus is having by declaring a state of emergency. However, it seems like the end of the tunnel is near for Japan and that the government has already planned to launch a multipronged economic stimulus package to restart the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The package has been announced in two phases with a value of ¥117 trillion (translating to about $1.1 trillion), which is about 20% of Japan’s GDP, to expand cash payouts to its citizens as the virus threatens to push the world’s third-largest economy into depression. Japan will sell additional bonds worth more than ¥18 trillion to fund the package, adding to its huge debt which is almost 257% of its GDP. However, since the debt is owed to itself, there is little chance of a debt crisis. According to the Japanese Economic Minister, Yasutoshi Nishimura, the economic package is set to boost the real Japanese GDP by 4.4%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first phase of the package aims to curb job losses and bankruptcies, while the second round of aid, after the virus is contained, will try to support a V-shaped economic recovery; wherein even after suffering a sharp recession, the economic stimulus will be able to support the economy on the steep curve to recovery. The package is designed to give more than ¥6 trillion in cash payouts to households and small businesses and ¥26 trillion to allow deferred social security and tax payments. Apart from this, the government announced an increase in direct fiscal spending amounting to a whopping ¥39 trillion to help the economy get back on its feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Japan is planning to distribute ¥300,000 to lower-income households that have lost their livelihoods due to the virus along with households with children. Moreover, the government has encouraged businesses to keep workers on their payroll and has also proposed subsidies for the same. Additionally, it has offered to defer income and regional tax payments for a year for virus-hit companies, which has led to multiple small businesses reducing their property taxes to near zero. Furthermore, the government has offered emergency loans for those facing wage cuts or job losses due to a virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China, the home ground of the virus, has been facing global backlash due to the inefficient measures to contain the virus’ spread. As is known, most MNCs have set up production facilities in China owing to the low-cost of production in the country. This is also the case with Japanese companies, however, as a part of its economic package, the Japanese government has announced $2.2 billion to help its companies to shift their manufacturing units out of China, accommodating both the shift to Japan and other countries in the world. The Japanese government intends to shift all high value production to Japan and to diversify production across South East Asia. The world has indeed realised the consequences of depending on one country too much. This is a change we can expect to see in the post lockdown world when instead of concentrating production in one country, the global economy will move on to having diverse models to prevent complete disruption of production cycles (like this one) in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impact on the Japanese economy has been severe with the pandemic slowing down the economy of China, followed by that of the US, two of Japan’s largest trading partners. Anyhow, the Japanese government’s stimulus package might not be successful. The small businesses are disappointed at the size of the package to mitigate the economic fallout due to the virus, they say that not only is it insufficient, it might also be a little too late. The Reuters Corporate Survey found 46% of firms felt the government’s stimulus was somewhat not enough and 29% deemed it quite insufficient, keeping Abe’s government under pressure to top-up last week’s spending package. While 5% said it was too much, just 21% said it was sufficient and appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The poll indicates how not only the amounts are insufficient but the measures are too, people ask for bolder steps like sales tax cuts for small businesses apart from the very insufficient cash payouts. The companies demand higher public spending and more support for financing. While the package might superficially seem enough, when one delves deeper into the public opinion, we find how the package is actually insufficient and unsatisfying. However, the question is if the world’s most indebted country can afford to increase its spending in a bid to stimulate the economy?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kashish Jindal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Coronavirus has brought the entire world economy down to its knees, gasping for a breath of fresh air, production cycles all around the world have come to a halt, supply chains disrupted, and many businesses are on the brink of a shutdown. Social distancing is the measure being adopted throughout the world to reduce the spread of this disease leading to the imposition of total lockdowns in various countries, be it a developed or an underdeveloped nation. One developed nation facing the brunt of the virus is Japan, which is actually trying to cushion the impact the virus is having by declaring a state of emergency. However, it seems like the end of the tunnel is near for Japan and that the government has already planned to launch a multipronged economic stimulus package to restart the economy. The package has been announced in two phases with a value of ¥117 trillion (translating to about $1.1 trillion), which is about 20% of Japan’s GDP, to expand cash payouts to its citizens as the virus threatens to push the world’s third-largest economy into depression. Japan will sell additional bonds worth more than ¥18 trillion to fund the package, adding to its huge debt which is almost 257% of its GDP. However, since the debt is owed to itself, there is little chance of a debt crisis. According to the Japanese Economic Minister, Yasutoshi Nishimura, the economic package is set to boost the real Japanese GDP by 4.4%.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Fiscal Consolidation: The Choice Between Prudence and Progress</title>
      <link href="/Fiscal-Consolidation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fiscal Consolidation: The Choice Between Prudence and Progress" />
      <published>2020-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Fiscal-Consolidation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Fiscal-Consolidation">&lt;p&gt;The growth projections for 2020-21 are in, and to hardly anyone’s surprise, it does not look good. It is during times like these, that the age-old ‘Growth vs Welfare’ debates are resurrected. However, as the pandemic curves around the globe get close to flattening themselves, it is only pragmatic to acknowledge that once we pass these anomalistic times, both variables will once again walk hand in hand. The ones monitoring the movements of these variables have assigned a downward revision to the targeted estimates. The recovery speculated to be V-shaped, will lead us through a phase of growth rates as low as -3%, as projected by the IMF, under the assumption that the pandemic fades by the second half of 2020. Governments, too politically motivated, cannot engage in conducting indirect bail-outs just yet, in the increasingly left sympathising world. So, the Central Banks around the globe have stepped in to stretch their balance sheets as usual. Besides the regular rate cuts, nations like the US, where rates have reached the zero base, have resorted to heterodox ways of stimulating the stock markets. The indices, taking mixed signals from the $4 trillion QE influx, and the climbing unemployment rate, close to 8%, have managed to rally against the odds. Other nations follow the lead as they ease out withdrawal norms, EMI payments, etc., attempting to bring a disequilibrium to the trade-off between consumption expenditure and investing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India, while still expected to grow at 1.9%, has not attempted to take up any targeted policy measures, save for the Prime Minister Garib Kalyan Scheme, which isn’t an economically motivated initiative. As a result of lack of productivity, the revenue side of the federal budget has nearly entirely collapsed, with states urging the centre to transfer resources sooner as 70% of the revenue via GST streams has ceased. It is evident that the fiscal deficit target of 3% set under the Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management (FRBM) Act (2003) will be violated by a bold margin, giving the markets another reason to panic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The need for a consumption-driven nation like India to keep the deficits in check arises from its reliance on foreign investments, due to the dearth of local savings. This stringency gets rationalised by the validation it receives from the economists grumbling at the nation’s twin balance sheet problem, i.e., both fiscal deficit and a trade deficit, which basically arises from running fiscal deficits by cutting taxes. That causes consumption to rise and thus, savings to fall. A reduction in savings prompts the government to borrow funds from abroad to finance their fiscal expenditure. An influx of investment raises the demand for local currency, which in turn results in its appreciation, and that makes domestic commodities relatively expensive to purchase, thus causing a trade deficit, which transforms into a current account deficit. It can be explained mathematically through a simple equation,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y = C + I + G + NX can be written as,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Y - C - Tax + Transfer) + (Tax - G - Transfer) = I + NX, which signifies&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Private Savings + Public Saving = Domestic Investment + Net Foreign Investment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, imagine a decline in Public Savings, due to cutting taxes and causing a fiscal deficit. This can be offset by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Rise in Private Savings&lt;/strong&gt;: As per “Ricardian equivalence”, tax cuts prompt people to increase savings, because they expect taxes to rise in the future. This, though economically ideal, is unlikely in the real-life context of the non-rational people.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Fall in Domestic Investment&lt;/strong&gt;: The crowding-out effect, it’s never good.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Fall in the Net foreign Investment&lt;/strong&gt;: The Twin Deficits dilemma&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In India’s case 2) &amp;amp; 3) have happened more often than any growing economy would be comfortable with. Several economies that are a member of the twin deficits club are the US, UK, Greece, etc. So, it’s safe to say we’re certainly not in great company since the twin deficits in each of these economies have aggravated the impacts of recessions, even cyclical ones. Though as many believe so, we have not managed to escape a crisis while running twin deficits. The 1991 Balance of Payments (BoP) crisis was essentially that of the twin deficits, owed to years of profligacy and the fiscal crisis of the 1980s. Post the FRBM Act, the deficits did come under targets, but the actual figures remained higher as certain bonds were kept off the balance sheets and remained unaccounted for, rendering the actual adjusted figures higher by 0.5% to 1% from what was reported. However, over the decade, with the combination of FRBM guidelines and the Rajan-era monetary policy, we have restrained the fiscal deficit partially and managed to raise enough Forex reserves to keep the Current Account deficits controlled. Additionally, as we move closer to having a higher proportion of capital expenditures, as compared to the previous budgets, we are setting up a base for investment to crowd in rather than crowd out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fiscal consolidation is necessary when the BoP situation is volatile and reliance on international investment is high. However, for an emerging nation like India, it’s irrational to take the 3% target as a divine ordinance. We would only end up creating a psychological benchmark out of it, exacerbating the volatility in exercises over our markets in recessionary periods. Fiscal prudence makes sense in good times to develop a cushion for bad times and allow targeted policies to take over the recovery. Blindly restricting expenditure ends up being counterproductive.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The growth projections for 2020-21 are in, and to hardly anyone’s surprise, it does not look good. It is during times like these, that the age-old ‘Growth vs Welfare’ debates are resurrected. However, as the pandemic curves around the globe get close to flattening themselves, it is only pragmatic to acknowledge that once we pass these anomalistic times, both variables will once again walk hand in hand. The ones monitoring the movements of these variables have assigned a downward revision to the targeted estimates. The recovery speculated to be V-shaped, will lead us through a phase of growth rates as low as -3%, as projected by the IMF, under the assumption that the pandemic fades by the second half of 2020. Governments, too politically motivated, cannot engage in conducting indirect bail-outs just yet, in the increasingly left sympathising world. So, the Central Banks around the globe have stepped in to stretch their balance sheets as usual. Besides the regular rate cuts, nations like the US, where rates have reached the zero base, have resorted to heterodox ways of stimulating the stock markets. The indices, taking mixed signals from the $4 trillion QE influx, and the climbing unemployment rate, close to 8%, have managed to rally against the odds. Other nations follow the lead as they ease out withdrawal norms, EMI payments, etc., attempting to bring a disequilibrium to the trade-off between consumption expenditure and investing.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What is Wrong with Britain’s Economy?</title>
      <link href="/British-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Wrong with Britain’s Economy?" />
      <published>2020-04-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/British-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/British-Economy">&lt;p&gt;Brexit is not the only factor that is affecting the British economy at the moment. It is no longer the most important issue for the country. It just seems like a convenient issue to cite in order to justify the low productivity that has plagued the nation in recent years. No matter how big that decision is, there are other things as well that Britain needs to focus on to improve its stagnating economic condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recently introduced skills-focused points-based immigration policy by PM Boris Johnson is going to have a huge impact on the economy. More than one-third of doctors, pharmacists, and dentists in the UK are foreign-born, as are more than 20% of nurses. Seven in 10 workers in the meat-processing industry are from the EU. However, next year onwards, the UK’s Byzantine immigration system for non-EU migrants will also apply to those from the EU. While immigration criteria for skilled labour will be loosened, it will be almost impossible for non-skilled labour to obtain a work visa. One of the hardest-hit sectors will be ‘care for’ the elderly. There is already a shortage of workers in this sector. Moreover, ‘care for’ work is the occupation with the most projected employment growth in the coming years. The UK under the guise of treating EU and non-EU migrants equally on the basis of skills is actually turning away industrious and enterprising individuals who help power its economy and provide for the basic needs of its greying population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the recent examples of what the British government is doing wrong. There are certain structural problems as well that need to be addressed. Capital spending as a share of GDP has fallen to around 17% from 20% in 2007. Capital investment is required in order to ensure long-term economic growth by increasing future production capacity. Moreover, the expenditure on R&amp;amp;D remains persistently below 2% of the GDP. In addition to this, the output per person has remained well below than what would have been termed as satisfactory. The unemployment figures have been relatively good recently, however, these have come at the cost of stagnating real wages and lower labour productivity per hour. Moreover, there has been a constant increase in the number of &lt;em&gt;zero-hour&lt;/em&gt; contracts. In such contracts, the workers have no guarantee of how many hours of work they will be getting. This could be one of the major reasons for under-employment in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of 2019, the manufacturing activity took a turn for the worse with the sharpest deterioration in output in more than seven years. The IHS Markit/CIPS manufacturing Purchasing Managers’ Index sank to 47.5 in December from 48.9 in November, although it was marginally higher than an initial flash estimate of 47.4. The figure marks the eighth consecutive month with a reading below 50, which indicates a majority of businesses reporting deteriorating activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK has a large current account deficit as well. It was around 4.6% of the GDP in 2019. This has been majorly due to negative investor sentiments because of all the political instability. Also, the UK economy has been hit badly by the economic slowdown in the major trading partners, namely, China and the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another worrying aspect is the monopoly power in public utility services like electricity and gas. A lack of competition keeps prices high and affects the real incomes of millions of consumers. Moreover, economic, social and demographic pressures continue to mount on public services such as the NHS. Some economists argue that the NHS needs a major injection of extra funding over the next 5-10 years; others believe that there are enough savings still to be achieved by addressing inefficiencies in public health care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With economic forecasts suggesting that the UK’s GDP growth won’t exceed 1.5%, the government will have to watch its discretionary spending even if a recession is avoided, because of spending on national services like the NHS. Moreover, there is also an additional threat to the economy posed by coronavirus. Much remains to be seen how the policymakers will tackle this burden and if the economy will be able to overcome this. The current situation doesn’t leave room for high hopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to plunging stock markets worldwide, the Bank of England cut its key rate by half a percentage point to 0.25%.  The Bank of England introduced a new program for cheap credit and reduced a special capital buffer to give banks more room to lend as well. Rishi Sunak, the Chancellor of the Exchequer,  also scrapped business rates for small firms to help them deal with the disruption caused by the outbreak of coronavirus. Business rates are taxes to help pay for UK local services, charged on most commercial properties. Britain’s retail sector has complained for the longest time that the current business rates system was unfair and needed reform. While the retail sector accounts for 5% of the UK economy, it is burdened with 10% of all business taxes, and 25% of business rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chancellor Sunak also scrapped a planned cut in corporation tax, and he is expected to raise around £6 billion from scrapping a planned drop, money he indicated could be spent on hospitals and doctors across the country. He also announced that the government would establish a coronavirus job retention scheme for all employers, large or small, that will cover 80% of wages, up to £2,500 a month. This scheme was introduced for an initial period of three months but can also be extended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a month after stepping into the new job, Rishi Sunak has a lot to prove. There are a lot of expectations for the new Chancellor. Additionally, when the UK is facing an increasing threat from the coronavirus, his job becomes all the more important. It remains to be seen whether Rishi Sunak will break free of any puppet strings or be swept aside by a Treasury insider. Brexit coupled with the coronavirus outbreak has left the country on borrowed time to revamp the economy. What happens in the next few weeks could possibly define the future of the country in the coming years. What we need to wait and watch is whether the government and its policies fall into place in order to break free the shackles of a never-ending system of going back and forth.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Amrit Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Brexit is not the only factor that is affecting the British economy at the moment. It is no longer the most important issue for the country. It just seems like a convenient issue to cite in order to justify the low productivity that has plagued the nation in recent years. No matter how big that decision is, there are other things as well that Britain needs to focus on to improve its stagnating economic condition.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Can India Keep Up with The Coronavirus?</title>
      <link href="/Can-India-Keep-Up-with-the-Coronavirus" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can India Keep Up with The Coronavirus?" />
      <published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Can-India-Keep-Up-with-the-Coronavirus</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Can-India-Keep-Up-with-the-Coronavirus">&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus, a tiny virus, has been causing chaos across the world since January. Countries are going into lockdowns, international travel has been banned, businesses are shutting down and healthcare systems are coming under unprecedented pressure. The virus has led to a global standstill and thus, to a global slowdown of economic growth, if not a global recession. Policymakers are now considering or already taking quick large steps to both ease the health care challenges and stem the economic pain. The Economist Intelligence Unit (of &lt;em&gt;The Economist&lt;/em&gt; magazine) estimates a negative growth rate of 2.2% of the GDP in countries of the G20 group for 2020. Amidst this crisis, one probably would have come across the talks about the trade-off between the lives of the people and the economy. No doubt, lives are of utmost importance, but not paying attention to the economy will critically affect the lives of the people once the crisis is over. The crisis will have an adverse impact on India which is already on the path of a slower growth rate. In this context, what has India done? And what can it do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian Prime Minister has announced a nation-wide lockdown from March 23, 2020, for a period of 3 weeks, till April 15. Following this came the decisions to ban international travel and shut the state borders, with an exception to vehicles transporting essentials. All of the non-essential businesses (manufacturing, construction, IT, etc) have come to a grinding halt and this has led to a supply and demand shock to the economy of India. It is crucial to note that 92% of the Indian workforce is engaged in the informal sector and one could find hordes of people migrating across the country in search of a job. These people are largely construction workers or people working in farms and survive on their daily wages only. Two days after the lockdown was announced, the Central Government announced a package of ₹1.7 trillion to help the poorest sections of the society. The wages under the National Rural Employment Scheme (NRES) were increased to ₹202 (i.e. about $2.69) from ₹182 (i.e. about $2.42). The Central Government, among other things, has also announced an allowance of 5 kg rice (or wheat per person) and 1 kg of pulses per family each month for 3 months. Some Indian states have announced cash transfers to all subsidy cardholders, in addition to the Centre’s cash transfers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these two measures have some problems. First, the objective of a total lockdown is to practice social distancing and thereby, no one is allowed out. Now, transferring cash through NRES wouldn’t work because people cannot come out to work; and even if they did, they will form a gathering and hence, defeat the purpose of a lockdown. Second, the average daily minimum wage in India in 2014 was ₹272 (i.e. about $3.62 in todays money). For simplification purposes, let us assume it to be ₹200. Now, if a person works for, say, 5 days a week that person would earn ₹1,000. This would total to ₹4,000 a month. What this means is that they earn more than what is being offered now, and the ₹1,500-₹ 2,000 (Central plus State Governments) per month given to these migrant workers is simply not enough of an incentive for them to stay indoors, thus once again, defeating the purpose of the lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing worth considering here is the prices of essential commodities. Given the shortage of supply, prices of some essentials are likely to increase. This will slash the real value of the money being distributed to the beneficiaries and would not be able to support them. Therefore, the government should increase the amount (Amit Seru, a prominent economist from Stanford has said this should be 5-6% of the GDP) disbursed to the targeted groups, not restricting the scope of the beneficiaries. That a large proportion of people are in the informal sector makes the transfers difficult, but India has the mechanism to carry out these transfers. It is also imperative to note that without much emphasis on the accurate number of beneficiaries, India must rather focus on transferring the amount because time is of the essence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, due to the crisis there are demand and supply side shocks to all the economies. A majority of the economists polled by the IGM Booth panel, however, opined that the economic effects of demand side shocks are larger than those from the supply side. As the businesses shut, the income of the people fell and so did the demand for goods and services in the economy. This is a critical cycle where income and demand depend on each other and when one falls it drives down the other and this is accompanied by a sharp rise in unemployment (in the informal sector mainly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economic crisis entailing the global pandemic is the textbook example of the good old Keynesian economics. And the conventional cure to this problem is fiscal expansion. Fiscal expansion, by way of government spending, will yield results with immediate effect. One cannot be concerned about the rise of fiscal deficit, given the seriousness of the current situation and it should be allowed to rise both at the Centre and the state level. The Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management Act (FRBM) can be amended or an ordinance can be issued to that effect. A greater degree of autonomy should be given to the states by means of allocation of funds or disbursal of the welfare schemes, as it is much faster to implement all these at the state level. For this, the contributions to the newly started PM-CARES should be distributed on war footing starting from the worst affected states. The government can also consider cutting down income tax rates (preferably, the lower brackets) and GST slabs at least for some period to boost the revival of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Governor of the Reserve Bank of India (RBI), the Indian central bank, has also announced a slew of measures by employing the tools of monetary policy alongside the government’s fiscal measures. The RBI cut down the repo rate by 0.75% and Cash Reserve Ratio by 100 basis points to 3%. The Reserve bank estimates these measures would result in an injection of ₹3.74 trillion into the economy. However, this should not be taken as is. For we do not know if the banks will slash the lending rates even as the RBI slashed the repo rate. Additionally, the demand is bound to increase after the lockdown is lifted. However, the question one must ask is will the demand be sufficient for the businesses to borrow money from the banks. Hence, we do not know whether the reduced interest rates would lead to an increase in investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, one thing is clear. This crisis is not conventional in the sense that the economy cannot be rescued in these times. This is because the non-essential services are shut down and cannot be opened until the lockdown is lifted. Even if India reopens, many businesses might find it difficult to start production because of the disruption of supply chains owing to the lockdown in other countries. Hence, growth will slow down. All India can do is take measures to revive demand once the world settles down.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Coronavirus, a tiny virus, has been causing chaos across the world since January. Countries are going into lockdowns, international travel has been banned, businesses are shutting down and healthcare systems are coming under unprecedented pressure. The virus has led to a global standstill and thus, to a global slowdown of economic growth, if not a global recession. Policymakers are now considering or already taking quick large steps to both ease the health care challenges and stem the economic pain. The Economist Intelligence Unit (of The Economist magazine) estimates a negative growth rate of 2.2% of the GDP in countries of the G20 group for 2020. Amidst this crisis, one probably would have come across the talks about the trade-off between the lives of the people and the economy. No doubt, lives are of utmost importance, but not paying attention to the economy will critically affect the lives of the people once the crisis is over. The crisis will have an adverse impact on India which is already on the path of a slower growth rate. In this context, what has India done? And what can it do?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Echoes of the Estates-General: A Comparison between Ancient Regime France and 21st Century America (Part I)</title>
      <link href="/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Echoes of the Estates-General: A Comparison between Ancient Regime France and 21st Century America (Part I)" />
      <published>2020-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General">&lt;p&gt;The background to the French Revolution chronicles the decline of the once-powerful State, beset by a multitude of economic and social problems. Chief among these issues were: a bourgeoning national debt brought on by the cost of war, the increasing antagonisms between an unproductive class of nepotistic oligarchs and an impoverished mass of peasants and small artisans, and the increasing irrelevance of the country in comparison to other, more economically dynamic states. The United States in the 21st Century bears striking similarities to the pre-revolutionary France, as discontent with stagnating wages and widening inequality reaches a fever pitch as the 2020 election draws nearer. This is the first of two articles examining the economic and political similarities between them, at a volatile time in the history of both nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;State Debt and Poor Finances&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between 1720 and 1780, France’s overseas trade had quadrupled, yet commercial prosperity was not enough to offset the abysmal condition of state finances. The combined cost of fighting the Seven Years’ War and the American War of Independence was 3.1 billion livres, over 4 times the Crown’s annual revenue. This was exacerbated by the fact that spending on war, the navy and diplomacy constituted 25% of Crown expenditure, in addition to the 50% that serviced the existing debt. Coupled with high interest rates that deterred moneylenders and an inefficient tax system that failed to raise revenue and allowed the nobility to remove officials who attempted to raise either direct or indirect taxes on them, there was a serious economic crisis by 1789.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 9/11, the United States has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2016/09/cost-wars-iraq-afghanistan/499007/&quot;&gt;poured $3.2 trillion into wars, reaching a total of $4.8 trillion once obligations to veterans have been paid.&lt;/a&gt;  Engagements in Iraq, Afghanistan, Libya, Syria and other places have caused excessive deficit spending, and like in France in the 1780’s, an inefficient system of taxation that has involved lower taxes on the wealthy has only shifted the burden of debt onto the poor and future generations. George W Bush’s tax cuts in 2001 and 2003, and the tax breaks given to the billionaires by Trump are analogous to the exemptions that the French nobles received at the time of mass social breakdown at the end of the 1780’s. Against the backdrop of ballooning debt and the 2008 Financial Crisis, the concerns of the younger generations of Americans who have flocked to Bernie Sanders can be understood as a revolt against a system that allocates inordinate amounts of money towards wars and bank bailouts, but claims that education and healthcare are too costly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inequality and Social Unrest&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The schisms and fissures that have opened up in American society as a result of widening inequality and resentment at excessive accumulation and monopolisation by unaccountable billionaires is reminiscent of the tax immunities and feudal privileges that exempted the French nobility from accountability along with the predominance of feudal privileges such as internal customs barriers and tolls that prevented the establishment of a home market for manufacturers, which Turgot’s reforms had failed to redress in 1774. The stultifying stagnation imposed on the French economy by the system of noble privileges made the conditions of the peasantry significantly worse, indicating that it was not only the burden of debt but mass social unrest that resulted from the Ancien Regime. Eric Hobsbawm, in his book the &lt;em&gt;Age of Revolution&lt;/em&gt; stated that the nobility encroached considerably on the autonomy of the peasantry as feudal dues, tithes and taxes occupied an increasing share of peasants’ income. Ground between the millstones of noble exactions and price inflation, social breakdown and revolts among the peasantry were made practically inevitable by the late 1780’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Kropotkin, writing in &lt;em&gt;The Great French Revolution&lt;/em&gt;, argued that the inequalities between the nobility and the peasantry, combined with the obstinacy of those in power, illustrated the sclerotic and outdated nature of what would later become the first and second estates of the Estates-General. He stated that “if despair and misery impelled the people to riot, it was the hope of obtaining some relief that incited them to revolt”. In 1777, 1,100,000 peasants were declared to be beggars. Between 1730 and 1789, wages rose by 22% but were unable to keep pace with prices, which rose by 60%, causing further immiseration for the French peasantry and precipitating risings of both the rural and the urban poor in 1788/1789. Inflation of the price of agrarian produce prevented the urban workers from gaining access to bread, and wage stagnation crippled a key market for manufactured goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three wealthiest billionaires in the United States: Jeff Bezos, Bill Gates and Warren Buffett, own as much wealth as the bottom half of the American population combined, indicating that capitalist accumulation has acted as an enormous fetter on the development of the productive forces, and that the majority of sectors of the economy have been sacrificed on the altar of short-term profit. Capital simply ‘goes on strike’ until it can find an adequate return on investment, as Big Pharma, for instance, has not produced a single new antibiotic in the nearly 4 decades since it was deregulated. Apple and Samsung, in lieu of investing in new technologies, have spent 7 years engaged in a costly ‘patent war’ over copying iPhones, have outsourced production to the Global South, or simply gambled on the stock exchange. The billionaire class in America has become a parasitic oligarchy that mirrors the nobility in Ancien Regime France, suffused with government subsidies and content with shoring up their positions on the market, as the nobility once clung to their feudal dues and court pensions. The unproductive nobility, who were not earners by birth, and who were barred from entering professions, influenced politics to increase their privileges, much as America’s unproductive billionaires buy off politicians today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether anything resembling the 1788/1789 agrarian riots will happen in America remains to be seen, although the levels of poverty in America have continued to climb recently. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2016/05/my-secret-shame/476415/&quot;&gt;49% of Americans now live paycheck to paycheck&lt;/a&gt;, and recent studies have linked &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-healthcare-deaths/study-links-45000-u-s-deaths-to-lack-of-insurance-idUSTRE58G6W520090917&quot;&gt;45,000 deaths per year to lack of health insurance.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loss of Global Hegemony&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The loss of power and influence on the world stage to other countries with expanding economies and greater political and technological capabilities is another major point of comparison between latter-day Ancien Regime France and 21st Century America. By the late 1780’s, Great Britain was already beginning to industrialise, buoyed by the prospect of free trade with the newly independent United States, the growing importance of slave-picked cotton from the American South, and the opening up of new markets in Latin America such as Brazil and Cuba whose economies of scale made them more profitable than mercantilist West Indian markets. The 1770’s and 1780’s saw the development of puddling furnaces, rolling mills and James Watt’s steam engine, alongside agricultural techniques that increased enclosures and developed profitable cash crops. France, by contrast, was still hampered by the inefficiency of feudal dues and tithes during Louis XVI’s administration, remaining &lt;em&gt;“a nation of agriculture and handicrafts”&lt;/em&gt; according to Georges Lefebvre. Its commercial and colonial supremacy began to decline, and its traditional economic methods, internal trade restrictions and inadequate transport links acted as a bottleneck on economic progress, as Great Britain surged ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collapse of American hegemony and the rise of China is one of the defining changes in modern geopolitics that radically &lt;em&gt;reorients&lt;/em&gt; the global balance of power. Once again, the domestic unrest and discontent fermenting amongst a people can be contextualised within the decline of the country at large. There are countless examples in history of leaders using patriotism and perceived national importance to distract from economic failures by galvanising the spirit of the population. This becomes increasingly difficult at a time of national decline, as shown by Trump’s recent attempts to escalate tensions with Iran. Public opinion polls found that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.people-press.org/2019/07/30/climate-change-and-russia-are-partisan-flashpoints-in-publics-views-of-global-threats/&quot;&gt;just 43% of the American public approved of the killing of General Soleimani&lt;/a&gt;, showing that the cynical use of patriotism to offset economic decline is becoming less tenable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the United States’ persistent refusal to allow the state to play a directing role in the allocation of resources has culminated in the United States ceding ground to the bureaucratic and ruthlessly efficient Chinese State, whose monopolistic tech companies exert a growing influence over countries ranging from Central Asia to Latin America. The United States remains a service economy, sustained by low wages, cheap credit and cheap imports which have led to a ballooning trade deficit of $616.8 billion (by late 2019). The Chinese, on the other hand, have understood the importance of digital infrastructure to the modern, interconnected global economy through the expansion of the Belt and Road Initiative and the Digital Silk Road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The background to the French Revolution shows that national decline, combined with economic stagnation and an unaccountable and bureaucratic class of elites who produce and contribute little of value can mobilise a mass of the labouring poor who recognise the injustice of the system they are living under. The concept of the ‘American Dream’ is becoming increasingly untenable as neoliberal capitalism proves itself incapable of innovation and only of injecting money into assets and speculation, while concentrating power and wealth in the hands of a few billionaires. From the demise of Bernie Sanders’ campaign to the desperate attempts of the ruling class to consolidate power in the wake of the Coronavirus by printing $1.5 trillion to stabilise markets while millions are still without health insurance, there is a significant chance that the current crisis of American neoliberalism may result in either social upheaval, or a revolutionary transformation of the economic system.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The background to the French Revolution chronicles the decline of the once-powerful State, beset by a multitude of economic and social problems. Chief among these issues were: a bourgeoning national debt brought on by the cost of war, the increasing antagonisms between an unproductive class of nepotistic oligarchs and an impoverished mass of peasants and small artisans, and the increasing irrelevance of the country in comparison to other, more economically dynamic states. The United States in the 21st Century bears striking similarities to the pre-revolutionary France, as discontent with stagnating wages and widening inequality reaches a fever pitch as the 2020 election draws nearer. This is the first of two articles examining the economic and political similarities between them, at a volatile time in the history of both nations.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Art, the Artist and the Investor</title>
      <link href="/Art-Artist-Investor" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Art, the Artist and the Investor" />
      <published>2020-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Art-Artist-Investor</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Art-Artist-Investor">&lt;p&gt;Creativity has its own timeline, and art can only blossom through experience and patience. It takes its own sweet time getting through to people letting the art ripen naturally, instead of spoon-feeding its patrons, and is usually a mark of the artist’s authenticity. Take Van Gogh or Kafka, for instance, with both dying in ignorance of the ingenuity of their works. Their patience, or rather underconfidence, eventually led to the posthumous recognition, capitalised on by whoever could claim to ignite the inspiration, rendering their lives analogous to a sad art film, that yet still, managed to inspire people further. But not every artist wants to make a sad art film of their lives. It isn’t simply about the lack of patience or existence of confidence to market their work, it is, quite often, about &lt;em&gt;survival&lt;/em&gt;. Putting all stakes in an industry that isn’t entirely welcoming to new works due to their abstract nature is certainly a dicey choice for one’s career. Looking for popular platforms that can get you eyeballs is only natural.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These platforms are the ones that claim to ‘discover’ the artists, and subsequently, capitalise on the lifetime of earnings through their artwork. Take the music industry, for example. Artists still make their music, but that is not exactly how they make their money. The commercialisation of the records by label companies has been in place for decades now. Singers would only get a proportion of the sales revenue generated when new music would be released, which is only fair. Associating a famous record label’s name with the music of a new artist is a high-risk position to take business-wise, and hence it’s only natural to expect higher returns. Labels own master recordings, the copyrights associated and the back catalogues of artists. These assets are owned to compensate them in exchange for the risks taken by the platform in financing the artists’ careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in the 80’s &amp;amp; 90’s, the transparency of record deals wasn’t exactly crystal clear, both record labels and the singers managed to make good money because their primary source of revenue was the literal sale of the songs via CDs, vinyl records, etc. Currently, the music sales revenue, though growing, in absolute terms, by nearly $1 billion per year, is only about 60% of what it was in 1999. The industry took its major hit post the year 2000 when internet services began illegally offering easy access to the free download of music. The advent of pirated downloading of music drove down the record sales and seemingly marked a Malthusian-style prophecy of the end of the commercialised and profitable era. That was until the streaming platforms stepped in. Although a third of the global music listeners still pirate their music (as per a report by the International Federation of Phonographic Industry), a massive rise in legal streaming platforms like Spotify, Apple Music and Tidal seems to have curbed the illegal consumption of music. And while the revenues and the contract transparency is on the rise, the monetary credit accrued to the actual artists has fallen with the steepening of the industry’s growth trajectory. Private equity (PE) players have stepped in to invest in the record labels, adding complicated layers to the revenue distribution model, and thus, leaving even lower residual amount that goes to the singers. Now, how do these big-money investors in PE corporates that, at the very least, expect consistency in their returns, align themselves with an industry that has its own volatile timeline? They &lt;em&gt;undershare&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The labels now provide to the artists a platform, and that’s nearly all. An estimate suggests that an average artist gets around one-tenth of a cent per play of an associated song on Spotify. The streaming platform generally takes up 15-30% of the revenue generated, and then a major chunk is instantly slashed off in the name of the record label. At this point, less than 40% of the revenue remains before singers, songwriters or publishers. The final average payout is dependent on how much ownership of the master recordings and the compositions the artists can exert. To put it into perspective, a star as big as Beyoncé makes only 10% of her money through music sales. One would think that music tours and concerts ought to make up for the deficiencies, but they’re simply a marketing programme, an attempt to keep the artists relevant, which becomes evident once you realise that rarely do any of the global or national level tour revenues ever break-even. The artists are paid only a proportional royalty of any other public performance not financed by the label, but by talk-shows or award shows. The payment structure often leaves the singers earning off of advertisements and endorsements, robbing them of their ‘authenticity’ tag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the highest-paid pop-artist in 2017, Diddy, who made the money from his Cirac vodka deal, hadn’t even released an album in over 7 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while the streaming platforms aren’t exactly killing the music industry, they’re still skewed in favour of the private equity players, and hence are the primary drivers of the aggregate growth recorded in the revenues, dwarfing the ability of the actual artists to exert any influence. However, some of the bigger names are now coming out against the unregulated PE influence in the industry. Recently Big Machine Records, which owned the rights to the music catalogue of all of Taylor Swift’s past albums, except for &lt;em&gt;Lover&lt;/em&gt;, was sold out for $300-$350 Million, to Scooter Braun’s Ithaca Holdings, disallowing Swift to perform her own songs at the AMAs, and leading to a highly publicised feud between the two. The sale was backed by the renowned Carlyle Group, that was already facing backlash for its indirect stake in defence contractors who had actively supplied weapons to fund the bombings in Yemen by Saudi Arabia, and now came under the heat of the fans as well as Alexandria Ocasio Cortez and Elizabeth Warren. While the matter remains unresolved, it is likely that this time the artist might register a victory, since Swift has threatened to re-record her past albums. The victory would put her in the rare company of the few major-label artists like Metallica, Janet Jackson and Jay-Z to gain control of the assets associated with their music. The outcome of the lawsuit pursued by EDM artist Martin Garrix against the label Spinnin’ Records has also brought some good news, with Garrix being given the rights and masters to some of his biggest hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The investors are constantly innovating to capitalise on the gains of the music industry, with some even experimenting with removal of ownership exclusivity and opening song rights for public offerings. An Initial Song Offering (ISO) was made for Drake’s &lt;em&gt;Jodeci Freestyle&lt;/em&gt;, wherein 10% of the copyright stake was available for public purchase to the top 100 subscribers, with Ethereum based payments. While such innovations are in the interest of the public and allow them to channelise their savings towards better investment options, it needs to be realised that the lack of tangibility of both the output and most of the inputs of this industry is an important consideration in the face of the financial innovations that should follow. Therefore, the battle between rights and arts will continue for an indefinite period, as long as we, as a corporate, wouldn’t stop patronising the creative skills of the people involved in this field.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Creativity has its own timeline, and art can only blossom through experience and patience. It takes its own sweet time getting through to people letting the art ripen naturally, instead of spoon-feeding its patrons, and is usually a mark of the artist’s authenticity. Take Van Gogh or Kafka, for instance, with both dying in ignorance of the ingenuity of their works. Their patience, or rather underconfidence, eventually led to the posthumous recognition, capitalised on by whoever could claim to ignite the inspiration, rendering their lives analogous to a sad art film, that yet still, managed to inspire people further. But not every artist wants to make a sad art film of their lives. It isn’t simply about the lack of patience or existence of confidence to market their work, it is, quite often, about survival. Putting all stakes in an industry that isn’t entirely welcoming to new works due to their abstract nature is certainly a dicey choice for one’s career. Looking for popular platforms that can get you eyeballs is only natural.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
