<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/economics/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2022-05-10T21:09:55+01:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/economics/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Sri Lanka’s Economic Crisis: What Led to Such a Disaster</title>
      <link href="/Sri-Lanka-s-Economic-Crisis-What-Led-to-Such-a-Disaster" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sri Lanka’s Economic Crisis: What Led to Such a Disaster" />
      <published>2022-05-06T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2022-05-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Sri-Lanka-s-Economic-Crisis-What-Led-to-Such-a-Disaster</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Sri-Lanka-s-Economic-Crisis-What-Led-to-Such-a-Disaster">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Sri Lanka is currently facing its worst economic crisis in decades in the form of a combined &lt;strong&gt;balance of payment and sovereign debt crisis&lt;/strong&gt;. The Mahinda Rajapaksa government is finding it difficult to pay for essential imports after a 70% drop in foreign exchange reserves over two years which triggered a currency devaluation. Prices of food and essential goods have increased tremendously, fuel is in short supply and protests have broken out. With a population of 2.19 crore, Sri Lanka has announced its decision to &lt;em&gt;default on its foreign debt of $51 billion &lt;/em&gt;as of April 12. As per the data, Sri Lanka's primary creditors include China and the Asian Development Bank (ADB). 36.4% of Sri Lanka's debt is in international sovereign bonds, with ADB accounting for 14.6%, Japan 10.9% and China 10.8%. India has already extended a $1 billion line of credit to help Sri Lanka buy fuel, food and medicine but some analysts warned that this assistance might prolong the crisis rather than solve it. Sri Lanka is now seeking financial help from the IMF and Sri Lanka finance minister Basil Rajapaksa will also meet with World Bank officials next month to seek support from the United States-headquartered agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What really happened to the Sri Lankan economy?&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The crisis in Sri Lanka is broadly seen as a result of &lt;em&gt;mismanagement of government finances and ill-timed tax cuts, in addition to the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic&lt;/em&gt;. Post-independence in 1948, Sri Lanka's agriculture was dominated by export-oriented crops such as tea, coffee, rubber and spices. But a decline in exports put foreign exchange reserves under strain. Therefore, from 1965 onwards, Sri Lanka obtained 16 loans from the IMF. To make matters worse in April 2021, the government &lt;em&gt;banned the import of fertilizer&lt;/em&gt; which affected the production of tea and rubber. Though in November 2021 the ban was lifted, the earnings from agriculture had declined significantly.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A gloomy situation turned worse with two economic shocks in 2019&lt;/em&gt;. First, there was a series of bomb blasts in churches and hotels in Colombo in April 2019. This led to an 80% decline in tourist arrivals. At the same time, the world was struck by an unprecedented pandemic. Being a tourism dependent country, its situation got worse due to the pandemic. According to the IMF recent report, COVID-19 has severely hit the Sri Lankan economy. The annual GDP growth rate of 2.3% in 2019 declined to -3.6% in 2020. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Second, the Rajapaksa government introduced populist tax cuts prior to the pandemic, limiting the government’s revenue options from corporate tax revenue. Value added tax rates were cut from 15% to 8%, whereas the government reduced the corporate tax rates from 28% to 24%. Foreign remittances from Sri Lankan workers abroad were drying up already. With a weak revenue base, the adverse impact of COVID-19 and the announced relief spending measures led to higher government expenditure which made fiscal deficits to be larger than 10% of GDP in 2020 and 2021, while the economy witnessed a rapid expansion in public debt to 119% of GDP in 2021, i.e., it has borrowed more money than it can produce via goods and services.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In 2020, Sri Lanka lost its access to international capital markets, leading to a decline of international reserves to critically low levels and large-scale direct lending to the government by the Central Bank of Sri Lanka (CBSL). A widening current account deficit and huge external debt repayments led to foreign exchange (FX) shortages, while the official exchange rate remained de facto &lt;em&gt;fixed since&lt;/em&gt; April 2021. All these impacted imports of fuel and other essential goods which sent prices soaring. The war in Ukraine hasn't helped either; the cost of fuel surged by 40% within a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lives of people in Sri Lanka&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;For Sri Lankans, the crisis has turned their daily lives into an endless cycle of waiting in queues for essential goods, many of which are being rationed. Soldiers are stationed at gas stations to calm customers, who line up for hours in the searing heat to fill their tanks. Life of Sri Lankans is made more difficult by frequent power cuts that plunge Colombo into darkness, sometimes for more than 10 hours at a time. Shops have been forced to shut just because they can't run fridges, air conditioners, or fans. Hospitals have refused to do any surgeries because of shortage of medical supplies. People have to wait for hours for propane gas to cook food for their families. The situation in Sri Lanka is so bad that people have now started to flee out of the country. According to experts, bad macroeconomic policy management further accentuated the economic crisis making the common citizenry suffer. Public frustration and anger erupted on April 1, when thousands of people came out on the streets to protest the crippling power cuts and shortages of essential commodities caused by the country’s economic meltdown. Consequently, Sri Lanka’s President Gotabaya Rajapaksa &lt;strong&gt;declared an Emergency on April 1.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What should Sri Lanka do now ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to some experts, Sri Lanka should establish a &lt;em&gt;three-year repayment structure&lt;/em&gt;. They believe that doing so would reduce the burden on citizens of Sri Lanka. As per the Verité Research Executive Director and Economist Dr Nishan de Mel, &quot;&lt;em&gt;Sri Lanka is unreasonably committed to repaying its debt. It is more important to press pause on debt repayment and take care of critical economic needs&lt;/em&gt;”. The Lankan economy would need a robust path towards revenue based fiscal consolidation. Reforms must focus on strengthening value added taxes, income and corporate taxes, through gradual rate increases and base broadening measures. In order to reduce fiscal risks from loss-making public enterprises, fiscal adjustment would need to be accompanied by energy pricing reforms.  Short-term monetary contractionary policy is needed to reduce the inflation. As the IMF report suggests institution building reforms, such as revamping the fiscal rule, would also help ensure the credibility of the strategy. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Other longer-term reforms include establishing a flexible exchange rate policy and a medium-to-long-term debt reduction strategy, while ensuring that most of government spending is in targeted social areas for developmental objectives such as in areas of healthcare, education and social security goals.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Cheshta Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="main" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Sri Lanka is currently facing its worst economic crisis in decades in the form of a combined balance of payment and sovereign debt crisis. The Mahinda Rajapaksa government is finding it difficult to pay for essential imports after a 70% drop in foreign exchange reserves over two years which triggered a currency devaluation. Prices of food and essential goods have increased tremendously, fuel is in short supply and protests have broken out. With a population of 2.19 crore, Sri Lanka has announced its decision to default on its foreign debt of $51 billion as of April 12. As per the data, Sri Lanka's primary creditors include China and the Asian Development Bank (ADB). 36.4% of Sri Lanka's debt is in international sovereign bonds, with ADB accounting for 14.6%, Japan 10.9% and China 10.8%. India has already extended a $1 billion line of credit to help Sri Lanka buy fuel, food and medicine but some analysts warned that this assistance might prolong the crisis rather than solve it. Sri Lanka is now seeking financial help from the IMF and Sri Lanka finance minister Basil Rajapaksa will also meet with World Bank officials next month to seek support from the United States-headquartered agency. What really happened to the Sri Lankan economy?&amp;nbsp; The crisis in Sri Lanka is broadly seen as a result of mismanagement of government finances and ill-timed tax cuts, in addition to the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic. Post-independence in 1948, Sri Lanka's agriculture was dominated by export-oriented crops such as tea, coffee, rubber and spices. But a decline in exports put foreign exchange reserves under strain. Therefore, from 1965 onwards, Sri Lanka obtained 16 loans from the IMF. To make matters worse in April 2021, the government banned the import of fertilizer which affected the production of tea and rubber. Though in November 2021 the ban was lifted, the earnings from agriculture had declined significantly.&amp;nbsp; A gloomy situation turned worse with two economic shocks in 2019. First, there was a series of bomb blasts in churches and hotels in Colombo in April 2019. This led to an 80% decline in tourist arrivals. At the same time, the world was struck by an unprecedented pandemic. Being a tourism dependent country, its situation got worse due to the pandemic. According to the IMF recent report, COVID-19 has severely hit the Sri Lankan economy. The annual GDP growth rate of 2.3% in 2019 declined to -3.6% in 2020. &amp;nbsp; Second, the Rajapaksa government introduced populist tax cuts prior to the pandemic, limiting the government’s revenue options from corporate tax revenue. Value added tax rates were cut from 15% to 8%, whereas the government reduced the corporate tax rates from 28% to 24%. Foreign remittances from Sri Lankan workers abroad were drying up already. With a weak revenue base, the adverse impact of COVID-19 and the announced relief spending measures led to higher government expenditure which made fiscal deficits to be larger than 10% of GDP in 2020 and 2021, while the economy witnessed a rapid expansion in public debt to 119% of GDP in 2021, i.e., it has borrowed more money than it can produce via goods and services.&amp;nbsp; In 2020, Sri Lanka lost its access to international capital markets, leading to a decline of international reserves to critically low levels and large-scale direct lending to the government by the Central Bank of Sri Lanka (CBSL). A widening current account deficit and huge external debt repayments led to foreign exchange (FX) shortages, while the official exchange rate remained de facto fixed since April 2021. All these impacted imports of fuel and other essential goods which sent prices soaring. The war in Ukraine hasn't helped either; the cost of fuel surged by 40% within a week. Lives of people in Sri Lanka For Sri Lankans, the crisis has turned their daily lives into an endless cycle of waiting in queues for essential goods, many of which are being rationed. Soldiers are stationed at gas stations to calm customers, who line up for hours in the searing heat to fill their tanks. Life of Sri Lankans is made more difficult by frequent power cuts that plunge Colombo into darkness, sometimes for more than 10 hours at a time. Shops have been forced to shut just because they can't run fridges, air conditioners, or fans. Hospitals have refused to do any surgeries because of shortage of medical supplies. People have to wait for hours for propane gas to cook food for their families. The situation in Sri Lanka is so bad that people have now started to flee out of the country. According to experts, bad macroeconomic policy management further accentuated the economic crisis making the common citizenry suffer. Public frustration and anger erupted on April 1, when thousands of people came out on the streets to protest the crippling power cuts and shortages of essential commodities caused by the country’s economic meltdown. Consequently, Sri Lanka’s President Gotabaya Rajapaksa declared an Emergency on April 1. What should Sri Lanka do now ? According to some experts, Sri Lanka should establish a three-year repayment structure. They believe that doing so would reduce the burden on citizens of Sri Lanka. As per the Verité Research Executive Director and Economist Dr Nishan de Mel, &quot;Sri Lanka is unreasonably committed to repaying its debt. It is more important to press pause on debt repayment and take care of critical economic needs”. The Lankan economy would need a robust path towards revenue based fiscal consolidation. Reforms must focus on strengthening value added taxes, income and corporate taxes, through gradual rate increases and base broadening measures. In order to reduce fiscal risks from loss-making public enterprises, fiscal adjustment would need to be accompanied by energy pricing reforms.  Short-term monetary contractionary policy is needed to reduce the inflation. As the IMF report suggests institution building reforms, such as revamping the fiscal rule, would also help ensure the credibility of the strategy. &amp;nbsp; Other longer-term reforms include establishing a flexible exchange rate policy and a medium-to-long-term debt reduction strategy, while ensuring that most of government spending is in targeted social areas for developmental objectives such as in areas of healthcare, education and social security goals.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Economic Sanctions: A Silent Weapon of War</title>
      <link href="/Economic-Sanctions-A-Silent-Weapon-of-War" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Economic Sanctions: A Silent Weapon of War" />
      <published>2022-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Economic-Sanctions-A-Silent-Weapon-of-War</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Economic-Sanctions-A-Silent-Weapon-of-War">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘The United States has imposed severe sanctions over the state of North Korea for their new ballistic missile test.’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This is how a typical headline in global politics looks like when a jaw-dropping geopolitically motivated event occurs. At first glance, one might wonder why a country such as the US is so vested in the fund allocation of the North Korean treasury. It all essentially boils down to the degree of influence that a superpower (assumption being that the US is the lone superpower) has over nation states when it comes to their economy and people.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The US does so in the larger interest of the world, and considers itself to be the saviour of our generation when it comes to averting a nuclear catastrophe. Since it cannot (and must not) threaten war on many already poverty stricken and poor states, it imposes a series of Keynesian tool-based economic sanctions that prohibit the economic growth of the nation state, as they directly affect the demand and supply chains of the economy and tend to cut them off from more states that are members of ‘the bloc’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The unsettling reality is that disasters similar to Hiroshima and Nagasaki continue to occur in Middle Eastern countries, where war has been raging for decades, and yet we've been so oblivious to their occurrences when we accidentally switch to &lt;em&gt;BBC International&lt;/em&gt; after cheering for our football team on the previous channel. But beneath the thick glorious boasts of killing ISIS leaders, annihilating Sanaa (again), and killing millions, there is the far more destructive layer of economic sanctions imposed on seemingly rogue states that disagree with the ideology of the world's leading nation state. The inconvenient reality is that those sanctions, in a roundabout way, have an effect on the health of citizens and frequently bring about devastating consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Economic sanctions are of three types: (1) suspension of loans or aid withdrawal by the sender; (2) denial of access to international financial markets; and (3) bans on capital investment in the targeted state. They often involve a sector-specific ban such as an oil ban, textile ban, a ban on using a particular currency or engaging with particular financial operators (such as banks). Intended to impose constraints on the economic activities of the targeted state, economic sanctions aim to prevent a state from importing certain goods or services. They may also prevent a state from exporting its natural resources, agricultural, or manufactured products.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another type of economic sanction specifically targets the banking and financial sectors. Overseas assets, for example, can be frozen or transactions put on hold. Foreign aid may be withheld as well. Economic sanctions are most likely to be detrimental to a country. Refusing to import goods or services from a country can act as a kind of protectionist policy for the target country. This can create a constituency for such policies, making them difficult to repeal. A ban on exporting certain goods and services to a country, such as agricultural products, on the other hand, can harm influential sectors of the target country and make it difficult to impose or sustain such measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to Farrokh Habibzadeh's paper &lt;em&gt;Economic sanction: a weapon of mass destruction&lt;/em&gt;, the UN Security Council Resolution 661-3 imposed a multilateral sanction on Iraq in 1990, prohibiting the import of all substances other than those intended for scientific purposes, food, and various humanitarian items. The sanction killed approximately 1.5 million people (including more than half a million children) in Iraq - more than the number of people killed in Hiroshima in the aftermath of the nuclear bomb detonation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Many critical life-saving tablets become unavailable due to the imposition of sanctions. Even the production of a few drugs is reduced, if not halted, due to a scarcity of basic substances or spare device components required for drug production. The cost of medicines rises to a point that people with low incomes can only afford a small portion of it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This results in growth of black markets as locations where medicines (occasionally forged) are illegally traded. Additionally, the lack of spare components tends to affect not only medical devices, but also different critical infrastructures such as electric powered generators. Consequently, frequent power outages result in severe problems such as lack of vaccines, tablets, ventilators, monitors, etc. Thus, hundreds of thousands of people die in silence as a result of diseases.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This quiet mass homicide in a tumultuous sector is not always noticed, and may even be overlooked. The same can be said about the current COVID crisis, in which the US refused to lift sanctions against Iran despite the fact that it was dealing with COVID-19 and low vaccination rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Seen in this light, sanctions act as a terrifying mechanism for bringing a country to its knees. There are many ways to deal with 'rogue' states, but depriving people of their humanity is not one of them.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shreyansh Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">‘The United States has imposed severe sanctions over the state of North Korea for their new ballistic missile test.’ This is how a typical headline in global politics looks like when a jaw-dropping geopolitically motivated event occurs. At first glance, one might wonder why a country such as the US is so vested in the fund allocation of the North Korean treasury. It all essentially boils down to the degree of influence that a superpower (assumption being that the US is the lone superpower) has over nation states when it comes to their economy and people.&amp;nbsp; The US does so in the larger interest of the world, and considers itself to be the saviour of our generation when it comes to averting a nuclear catastrophe. Since it cannot (and must not) threaten war on many already poverty stricken and poor states, it imposes a series of Keynesian tool-based economic sanctions that prohibit the economic growth of the nation state, as they directly affect the demand and supply chains of the economy and tend to cut them off from more states that are members of ‘the bloc’. The unsettling reality is that disasters similar to Hiroshima and Nagasaki continue to occur in Middle Eastern countries, where war has been raging for decades, and yet we've been so oblivious to their occurrences when we accidentally switch to BBC International after cheering for our football team on the previous channel. But beneath the thick glorious boasts of killing ISIS leaders, annihilating Sanaa (again), and killing millions, there is the far more destructive layer of economic sanctions imposed on seemingly rogue states that disagree with the ideology of the world's leading nation state. The inconvenient reality is that those sanctions, in a roundabout way, have an effect on the health of citizens and frequently bring about devastating consequences. Economic sanctions are of three types: (1) suspension of loans or aid withdrawal by the sender; (2) denial of access to international financial markets; and (3) bans on capital investment in the targeted state. They often involve a sector-specific ban such as an oil ban, textile ban, a ban on using a particular currency or engaging with particular financial operators (such as banks). Intended to impose constraints on the economic activities of the targeted state, economic sanctions aim to prevent a state from importing certain goods or services. They may also prevent a state from exporting its natural resources, agricultural, or manufactured products.&amp;nbsp; Another type of economic sanction specifically targets the banking and financial sectors. Overseas assets, for example, can be frozen or transactions put on hold. Foreign aid may be withheld as well. Economic sanctions are most likely to be detrimental to a country. Refusing to import goods or services from a country can act as a kind of protectionist policy for the target country. This can create a constituency for such policies, making them difficult to repeal. A ban on exporting certain goods and services to a country, such as agricultural products, on the other hand, can harm influential sectors of the target country and make it difficult to impose or sustain such measures. According to Farrokh Habibzadeh's paper Economic sanction: a weapon of mass destruction, the UN Security Council Resolution 661-3 imposed a multilateral sanction on Iraq in 1990, prohibiting the import of all substances other than those intended for scientific purposes, food, and various humanitarian items. The sanction killed approximately 1.5 million people (including more than half a million children) in Iraq - more than the number of people killed in Hiroshima in the aftermath of the nuclear bomb detonation.&amp;nbsp; Many critical life-saving tablets become unavailable due to the imposition of sanctions. Even the production of a few drugs is reduced, if not halted, due to a scarcity of basic substances or spare device components required for drug production. The cost of medicines rises to a point that people with low incomes can only afford a small portion of it.&amp;nbsp; This results in growth of black markets as locations where medicines (occasionally forged) are illegally traded. Additionally, the lack of spare components tends to affect not only medical devices, but also different critical infrastructures such as electric powered generators. Consequently, frequent power outages result in severe problems such as lack of vaccines, tablets, ventilators, monitors, etc. Thus, hundreds of thousands of people die in silence as a result of diseases.&amp;nbsp; This quiet mass homicide in a tumultuous sector is not always noticed, and may even be overlooked. The same can be said about the current COVID crisis, in which the US refused to lift sanctions against Iran despite the fact that it was dealing with COVID-19 and low vaccination rates. Seen in this light, sanctions act as a terrifying mechanism for bringing a country to its knees. There are many ways to deal with 'rogue' states, but depriving people of their humanity is not one of them.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Bitcoin: The 21st Century Dutch Tulip Mania</title>
      <link href="/Bitcoin-The-21st-Century-Dutch-Tulip-Mania" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bitcoin: The 21st Century Dutch Tulip Mania" />
      <published>2022-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Bitcoin-The-21st-Century-Dutch-Tulip-Mania</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Bitcoin-The-21st-Century-Dutch-Tulip-Mania">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Amsterdam Stock Exchange (AEX), regarded as the predecessor of contemporary investing, paved the way for modern stock exchanges. However, it was also responsible for facilitating the first financial bubble in history, namely, the ‘Dutch tulip bulb market bubble’. It happened in Holland during the early 1600’s when speculation drove the value of tulip bulbs to extremes. At the market’s peak, the rarest tulip bulbs were traded for as much as six times the average person's annual salary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Tulips first arrived in Western Europe from native Turkey in the late 1500’s. Initially purchased as a status symbol by the wealthy, they attracted the attention of the middle class. In 1634, tulip mania swept through Holland. Charles Mackay stated: &quot;The rage among the Dutch to possess (tulip bulbs) was so great that the ordinary industry of the country was neglected, and the population, even to its lowest dregs, embarked in the tulip trade.&quot; According to McKay, a single bulb could be worth as much as 4,000 or even 5,500 florins. In today's monetary terms, the best tulips would cost upwards of $750,000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;By 1636, the demand for the tulip trade was so high that regular marts for their sale were established on the Stock Exchange of Amsterdam, in Rotterdam, Haarlem, and other towns. Professional traders joined in at that time, and everyone seemed to be making money just by purchasing these rare bulbs. The price of tulips seemed to only go up. People began buying tulips with leverage, using derivatives contracts to acquire more than they could afford. Despite the promising start, confidence got quickly shattered.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;By the end of the year 1637, prices began to decline and then never really went up. The rapid decline was largely caused by people purchasing bulbs on credit in the hope of repaying their loans when they sold them for a profit. As prices fell, the bulb holders were forced to liquidate and declare bankruptcy.&amp;nbsp; By 1638, tulip bulb prices had crashed, returning to the price levels they had once commanded upon their arrival in Holland. As a result of the Dutch tulip mania, the economy slowed down in the Dutch Golden Age. As the prices fell, demand decreased along with household spending, resulting in a shrinking economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, the actual impact of the incident is often questioned by cynics. Irrespective of the scale of the event, it does teach us an important lesson in investing: be wary of financial bubbles. Bubbles occur when market value erupts rapidly, particularly in the price of assets. Following this rapid inflation, a subsequent contraction occurs. A bubble usually forms when asset prices surge due to exuberant market behaviour. During a bubble, assets typically trade at prices that exceed their intrinsic value by a significant margin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Several such economic bubbles have occurred throughout history, such as the South Sea Bubble of 1720, Japan's Asset Price Bubble of the 1980's, the Dotcom bubble, and the 2008 US Housing Bubble. These are some of history's largest financial bubbles, but in recent times, Michael Hartnett, Chief Investment Strategist at Bank of America, has dubbed Bitcoin &quot;the mother of all bubbles.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The scenario around Bitcoin has almost all of the signs of a financial bubble. Bitcoin was launched in 2009 and took two years to reach the price of $1 in February, 2011. However, ten years later, in 2021, at one point it was worth just under $45,000. Hence, it has grown a staggering 45,000 times in ten years, a CAGR (compound annual growth rate) of 191.16%.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Even now, when Bitcoin has become culturally mainstream, it continues to be volatile. It doubled investors’ wealth in 2020, but it also halved in 30 days from mid-April to mid-May in 2021. These fluctuations have started to have major impacts on conventional markets such as the stock markets. Bitcoin reached a market cap of over $1 trillion in May of 2021, which is more than the combined market cap of Visa and JPMorgan. Due to its sheer size and the amount of money tied up in this cryptocurrency, when the bubble bursts and Bitcoin hits near-zero, it will be the 'mother of all financial bubbles'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Besides the inexplicable astronomical rise in value, there are numerous other indicators that point to Bitcoin being a quintessential financial bubble. Bitcoin has been labelled as a speculative bubble by eight winners of the Nobel Prize in Economics namely, Paul Krugman, Robert J Shiller, Joseph Stiglitz, Richard Thaler, James Heckman, Thomas Sargent, Angus Deaton, and Oliver Hart. While these economists have discussed a variety of issues concerning Bitcoin and cryptocurrency, the following are the primary reasons for classifying it as a speculative bubble:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lack of Intrinsic Value:&lt;/em&gt; While fiat currencies, which have been in use for as long as one can remember, have no intrinsic value and are backed by faith in the government, they work as a store of value because they can be used to trade almost anywhere and anytime. Furthermore, fluctuations in these currencies are effectively monitored by governments in order to avoid excessive volatility and protect people from unwarranted losses. It is in this regard that Bitcoin completely fails. According to Maddie Shepherd of Fundera, out of an estimated 582 million entrepreneurs in the world, only 15,174 businesses accept Bitcoin as of December 2020. Since it is not an effective medium of exchange, it also fails as a real store of value since it lacks real utility. Furthermore, its volatility is another reason why it is not a reliable store of value. As a result, it is not a real asset and has no intrinsic value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Susceptibility to market manipulation: &lt;/em&gt;Bitcoin has been artificially driven by tweets from eminent personalities such as Tesla CEO Elon Musk, demonstrating how fickle this market is. The Tesla boss initially supported Bitcoin. In February, he purchased $1.5 billion in Bitcoin for Tesla's balance sheet, and a month later, he announced that the company would begin accepting Bitcoin for electric vehicle purchases. After 49 days, he tweeted that Tesla would no longer accept Bitcoin due to the adverse environmental impact of mining it and subsequently turned his attention to Dogecoin. Thus, tweets with little or no substance are creating and erasing hundreds of billions of dollars in Bitcoin market value. This is a clear indication that a bubble has been brewing for some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Price is driven by momentum and attention from retail investors: &lt;/em&gt;Two factors that are behind the soaring price of Bitcoin are momentum and the attention that people pay to it. Momentum means that if Bitcoin goes up more than usual, it will, on average, continue to rise. The fear of missing out on this supposed ‘get rich quick scheme’ keeps the prices high. Similarly, if there are more Google searches for the word Bitcoin, for example, Bitcoin prices tend to go up. Hence, a large proportion of Bitcoin's gains are due to hype, as Bitcoin seems to be at the ‘Peak of Inflated Expectations’ phase on Gartner’s Hype Cycle for Emerging Technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another noteworthy point is that there are no readily identifiable real-world correlations. For example, it is well-known that gold and the US dollar have an inverse relationship. When the dollar is declining in value, gold is likely rising in value. This is a correlation that's been established over a long period. Enthusiasts have pointed out how Bitcoin is a hedge against inflation, but they forget that Bitcoin has both risen and fallen when the money supply expanded rapidly or slowly. Cryptocurrency is driven by emotion and technical analysis, primarily because it has no real-world correlations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Due to its monumental returns and growing popularity, Bitcoin has gone from being a relatively small niche of the tech industry to a cheat code for institutional investors to boost fund returns at the expense of ignorant retail investors. While the arrival of these investors triggers a spurt in prices, it also marks the beginning of the end for most financial bubbles. There is very little contrast between the Tulip Mania of 400 years ago and the current Bitcoin situation. Both started insignificantly, only to become public frenzies very soon. And in the pursuit of making an easy profit, the Tulip Bulbs imploded, which points to what is inevitably coming for Bitcoin. The bubble will eventually burst.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Raghav Dhariwal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Amsterdam Stock Exchange (AEX), regarded as the predecessor of contemporary investing, paved the way for modern stock exchanges. However, it was also responsible for facilitating the first financial bubble in history, namely, the ‘Dutch tulip bulb market bubble’. It happened in Holland during the early 1600’s when speculation drove the value of tulip bulbs to extremes. At the market’s peak, the rarest tulip bulbs were traded for as much as six times the average person's annual salary. Tulips first arrived in Western Europe from native Turkey in the late 1500’s. Initially purchased as a status symbol by the wealthy, they attracted the attention of the middle class. In 1634, tulip mania swept through Holland. Charles Mackay stated: &quot;The rage among the Dutch to possess (tulip bulbs) was so great that the ordinary industry of the country was neglected, and the population, even to its lowest dregs, embarked in the tulip trade.&quot; According to McKay, a single bulb could be worth as much as 4,000 or even 5,500 florins. In today's monetary terms, the best tulips would cost upwards of $750,000. By 1636, the demand for the tulip trade was so high that regular marts for their sale were established on the Stock Exchange of Amsterdam, in Rotterdam, Haarlem, and other towns. Professional traders joined in at that time, and everyone seemed to be making money just by purchasing these rare bulbs. The price of tulips seemed to only go up. People began buying tulips with leverage, using derivatives contracts to acquire more than they could afford. Despite the promising start, confidence got quickly shattered.&amp;nbsp; By the end of the year 1637, prices began to decline and then never really went up. The rapid decline was largely caused by people purchasing bulbs on credit in the hope of repaying their loans when they sold them for a profit. As prices fell, the bulb holders were forced to liquidate and declare bankruptcy.&amp;nbsp; By 1638, tulip bulb prices had crashed, returning to the price levels they had once commanded upon their arrival in Holland. As a result of the Dutch tulip mania, the economy slowed down in the Dutch Golden Age. As the prices fell, demand decreased along with household spending, resulting in a shrinking economy. However, the actual impact of the incident is often questioned by cynics. Irrespective of the scale of the event, it does teach us an important lesson in investing: be wary of financial bubbles. Bubbles occur when market value erupts rapidly, particularly in the price of assets. Following this rapid inflation, a subsequent contraction occurs. A bubble usually forms when asset prices surge due to exuberant market behaviour. During a bubble, assets typically trade at prices that exceed their intrinsic value by a significant margin. Several such economic bubbles have occurred throughout history, such as the South Sea Bubble of 1720, Japan's Asset Price Bubble of the 1980's, the Dotcom bubble, and the 2008 US Housing Bubble. These are some of history's largest financial bubbles, but in recent times, Michael Hartnett, Chief Investment Strategist at Bank of America, has dubbed Bitcoin &quot;the mother of all bubbles.&quot; The scenario around Bitcoin has almost all of the signs of a financial bubble. Bitcoin was launched in 2009 and took two years to reach the price of $1 in February, 2011. However, ten years later, in 2021, at one point it was worth just under $45,000. Hence, it has grown a staggering 45,000 times in ten years, a CAGR (compound annual growth rate) of 191.16%.&amp;nbsp; Even now, when Bitcoin has become culturally mainstream, it continues to be volatile. It doubled investors’ wealth in 2020, but it also halved in 30 days from mid-April to mid-May in 2021. These fluctuations have started to have major impacts on conventional markets such as the stock markets. Bitcoin reached a market cap of over $1 trillion in May of 2021, which is more than the combined market cap of Visa and JPMorgan. Due to its sheer size and the amount of money tied up in this cryptocurrency, when the bubble bursts and Bitcoin hits near-zero, it will be the 'mother of all financial bubbles'. Besides the inexplicable astronomical rise in value, there are numerous other indicators that point to Bitcoin being a quintessential financial bubble. Bitcoin has been labelled as a speculative bubble by eight winners of the Nobel Prize in Economics namely, Paul Krugman, Robert J Shiller, Joseph Stiglitz, Richard Thaler, James Heckman, Thomas Sargent, Angus Deaton, and Oliver Hart. While these economists have discussed a variety of issues concerning Bitcoin and cryptocurrency, the following are the primary reasons for classifying it as a speculative bubble: Lack of Intrinsic Value: While fiat currencies, which have been in use for as long as one can remember, have no intrinsic value and are backed by faith in the government, they work as a store of value because they can be used to trade almost anywhere and anytime. Furthermore, fluctuations in these currencies are effectively monitored by governments in order to avoid excessive volatility and protect people from unwarranted losses. It is in this regard that Bitcoin completely fails. According to Maddie Shepherd of Fundera, out of an estimated 582 million entrepreneurs in the world, only 15,174 businesses accept Bitcoin as of December 2020. Since it is not an effective medium of exchange, it also fails as a real store of value since it lacks real utility. Furthermore, its volatility is another reason why it is not a reliable store of value. As a result, it is not a real asset and has no intrinsic value. Susceptibility to market manipulation: Bitcoin has been artificially driven by tweets from eminent personalities such as Tesla CEO Elon Musk, demonstrating how fickle this market is. The Tesla boss initially supported Bitcoin. In February, he purchased $1.5 billion in Bitcoin for Tesla's balance sheet, and a month later, he announced that the company would begin accepting Bitcoin for electric vehicle purchases. After 49 days, he tweeted that Tesla would no longer accept Bitcoin due to the adverse environmental impact of mining it and subsequently turned his attention to Dogecoin. Thus, tweets with little or no substance are creating and erasing hundreds of billions of dollars in Bitcoin market value. This is a clear indication that a bubble has been brewing for some time. Price is driven by momentum and attention from retail investors: Two factors that are behind the soaring price of Bitcoin are momentum and the attention that people pay to it. Momentum means that if Bitcoin goes up more than usual, it will, on average, continue to rise. The fear of missing out on this supposed ‘get rich quick scheme’ keeps the prices high. Similarly, if there are more Google searches for the word Bitcoin, for example, Bitcoin prices tend to go up. Hence, a large proportion of Bitcoin's gains are due to hype, as Bitcoin seems to be at the ‘Peak of Inflated Expectations’ phase on Gartner’s Hype Cycle for Emerging Technologies. Another noteworthy point is that there are no readily identifiable real-world correlations. For example, it is well-known that gold and the US dollar have an inverse relationship. When the dollar is declining in value, gold is likely rising in value. This is a correlation that's been established over a long period. Enthusiasts have pointed out how Bitcoin is a hedge against inflation, but they forget that Bitcoin has both risen and fallen when the money supply expanded rapidly or slowly. Cryptocurrency is driven by emotion and technical analysis, primarily because it has no real-world correlations. Due to its monumental returns and growing popularity, Bitcoin has gone from being a relatively small niche of the tech industry to a cheat code for institutional investors to boost fund returns at the expense of ignorant retail investors. While the arrival of these investors triggers a spurt in prices, it also marks the beginning of the end for most financial bubbles. There is very little contrast between the Tulip Mania of 400 years ago and the current Bitcoin situation. Both started insignificantly, only to become public frenzies very soon. And in the pursuit of making an easy profit, the Tulip Bulbs imploded, which points to what is inevitably coming for Bitcoin. The bubble will eventually burst.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘Code Red for Humanity’ - the IPCC Report on Climate Change</title>
      <link href="/Code-Red-for-Humanity-the-IPCC-Report-on-Climate-Change" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘Code Red for Humanity’ - the IPCC Report on Climate Change" />
      <published>2022-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Code-Red-for-Humanity-the-IPCC-Report-on-Climate-Change</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Code-Red-for-Humanity-the-IPCC-Report-on-Climate-Change">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Humans have deferred restraining their fossil fuel emissions for so long that it's nearly impossible to stop global warming from intensifying over the next 30 years. The evidence of human-induced climate change in every region across the globe is irrefutable and some of these changes are already ‘irreversible’ for centuries to millennia, according to the IPCC report.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ipcc.ch/about/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change&lt;/a&gt; (IPCC) was set up by the United Nations Environment Programme and the World Meteorological Organisation in 1988. Its main purpose is to provide governments at all levels with scientific information which they can use to develop climate-related policies. The sixth assessment report, compiled by more than 200 scientists over a period of several years and approved by 195 governments is the first in a trio gauging the state of climate change, efforts to alleviate it and to adapt to it. The document, which was described as &lt;em&gt;&quot;a code red for humanity&quot;&lt;/em&gt; by UN Secretary-General António Guterres, arrived less than three months before the major global climate summit in Glasgow, UK, which took place from October 31 to November 12, 2021, and where governments had the opportunity to make pledges to reverse course and reduce emissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The report identifies that “&lt;em&gt;anthropogenic activities have caused approximately 1.0°C of global warming above pre-industrial levels and if no action isn’t taken, global warming is likely to reach 1.5°C by 2030”&lt;/em&gt;. This warming is set to persist for generations, even if zero emission pathways are enforced incontinently. The effects of 1°C global warming are already visible in sea level rise, surge in intensity of heat waves, glacier retreat, coral deaths, more frequent and more severe storms, floods and droughts. According to the report, there will be “&lt;em&gt;no region that will be left unscathed by the impacts of climate change”&lt;/em&gt;, with huge human and economic costs that far outweigh the costs of action. Regions like the Mediterranean, Southern Africa, the western United States, the Amazon and Australia will experience increased droughts and fires, which will affect not only the ecosystems but livelihoods, agriculture, and water systems. Infrastructure, transport, energy production and tourism in North America, the Arctic, Europe, the Andes, and more might be hugely impacted by the changes in snow, ice and river flooding. Storms will probably become more severe over most of North America, Europe, and the Mediterranean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The report points out that the Earth's precious carbon sinks, land and oceans, are at immense risk. They presently perform an astounding service in absorbing the bulk of the carbon dioxide the world emits, but as emissions rise, they will become less effective at absorbing CO2. These land sinks will eventually turn into a source, emitting CO2 instead of sucking it in; for example, the southeast Amazon rainforest is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-01871-6&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;no longer a carbon sink&lt;/a&gt; mainly because of deforestation and local warming. This can lead to uncontrolled warming, which will not only affect the world’s climate efforts, but can pose significant food and water security risks to countries in the region, and may lead to irreversible biodiversity loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to Govindasamy Bala, professor of Climate Change, for the first time, the new report clarifies the ‘&lt;em&gt;delicate balance’&lt;/em&gt; between aerosols and GHG emissions and their influence on precipitation by noting that “&lt;em&gt;greenhouse gas warming is partially offset by aerosol cooling&lt;/em&gt;.” Greenhouse gas-induced warming leads to intensification of rainfall, but from the 1950’s to 1980’s, there was a drop in global land monsoon precipitation and it was somewhat attributed to human-caused Northern Hemisphere aerosol ejection, which signifies that the aerosol cooling effect overpowered the greenhouse effect during the 30 year period. We don't see any trend in &lt;a href=&quot;https://india.mongabay.com/2020/11/how-wildlife-outside-protected-areas-responds-to-climate-extremes/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;monsoon&lt;/a&gt; rainfall in the last three decades, mainly because the effects of GHGs and aerosols are almost balanced. In the coming couple of decades this delicate balance may continue but by mid or end of the century the report predicts that we will see a surge in precipitation, Bala explained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to the IPCC, there is a &lt;em&gt;direct link between the surge in global warming and extreme climate changes&lt;/em&gt;. At 2°C of global warming, heat shocks are more likely to reach critical forbearance thresholds for biodiversity, i.e. out of the 105,000 species that were studied, it is predicted that 8% of plants, 9.6% of insects and 4% of vertebrates will lose over half of their geographic range at 1.5°C, compared with 16% of plants, 18% of insects and 8% of vertebrates at 2°C.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Repercussions associated with other biodiversity-related risks, for instance, the spread of non-native species and forest fires, are lower at 1.5°C compared to 2°C of global warming.&amp;nbsp; Extreme sea level events that used to occur once a century previously could happen every year by 2100.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Thus, the report ascertains that there will be major benefits to limiting global warming to 1.5°C above the pre-industrial level, but doing so will need “&lt;em&gt;rapid, far reaching and extraordinary changes in all aspects of society&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pathways to safety&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As reported by the IPCC, around 85% of CO₂ emissions come from burning fossil fuels. It is much easier to stop releasing more CO₂ into the atmosphere than it is to eliminate it, and the more we emit, the further we degrade the ecosystems that naturally soak it up. Therefore, global net CO₂ emissions by humans have to shrink by about 45% by 2030 relative to 2010 levels and reach net zero by 2050. This is actually achievable, contrary to popular belief through mitigation measures in the energy sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;About 70–85% of electricity is expected to be supplied by renewable sources in 2050. Shares of nuclear and fossil energy with Carbon Capture and Sequestration/Storage (CCS) are modelled to increase, allowing the share of carbon emitted in the atmosphere to fall and natural gas to generate about 8% of global electricity in 2050. All these mitigation measures will need an annual average investment in the energy system of around $2.4 trillion (at 2010 prices) between 2016 and 2035, representing about 2.5% of the world GDP;&amp;nbsp;however, the cost of inaction and delay will be many times more.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Following these pathways, the use of coal will be almost negligible by 2050, which might worry Indian policymakers, who are still talking about getting 45% of the country’s electricity from coal around the middle of the century. It's expected that by 2050, about 75–90% of CO₂ emissions from industry will be lower relative to current levels. The IPCC says this can be accomplished through &quot;&lt;em&gt;combinations of new and already existing technologies and practises, including product substitution, electrification, sustainable bio-based feedstock, carbon capture, utilisation, and storage.&lt;/em&gt;&quot; All this will not only help us tackle the climate change situation but also help us achieve Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result of the COVID-19 pandemic, greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions are expected to rise. Because economies have been hard hit, every country is desperate for recovery, which can primarily be accomplished with the current brown economy, which includes using coal, gas, and oil to ratchet up growth as quickly as possible. But the good news is that we have technologies that can disrupt the current fossil-fuel-driven industrial system. We cannot wait for disruptive technologies; rather, we must be disruptive in action or it will be too late. As climatologist Xuebin Zhang says, &quot;&lt;em&gt;the evidence is everywhere, if we don’t act now, the situation is going to get really bad&lt;/em&gt;.&quot;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Cheshta Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Humans have deferred restraining their fossil fuel emissions for so long that it's nearly impossible to stop global warming from intensifying over the next 30 years. The evidence of human-induced climate change in every region across the globe is irrefutable and some of these changes are already ‘irreversible’ for centuries to millennia, according to the IPCC report.&amp;nbsp; The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) was set up by the United Nations Environment Programme and the World Meteorological Organisation in 1988. Its main purpose is to provide governments at all levels with scientific information which they can use to develop climate-related policies. The sixth assessment report, compiled by more than 200 scientists over a period of several years and approved by 195 governments is the first in a trio gauging the state of climate change, efforts to alleviate it and to adapt to it. The document, which was described as &quot;a code red for humanity&quot; by UN Secretary-General António Guterres, arrived less than three months before the major global climate summit in Glasgow, UK, which took place from October 31 to November 12, 2021, and where governments had the opportunity to make pledges to reverse course and reduce emissions. The report identifies that “anthropogenic activities have caused approximately 1.0°C of global warming above pre-industrial levels and if no action isn’t taken, global warming is likely to reach 1.5°C by 2030”. This warming is set to persist for generations, even if zero emission pathways are enforced incontinently. The effects of 1°C global warming are already visible in sea level rise, surge in intensity of heat waves, glacier retreat, coral deaths, more frequent and more severe storms, floods and droughts. According to the report, there will be “no region that will be left unscathed by the impacts of climate change”, with huge human and economic costs that far outweigh the costs of action. Regions like the Mediterranean, Southern Africa, the western United States, the Amazon and Australia will experience increased droughts and fires, which will affect not only the ecosystems but livelihoods, agriculture, and water systems. Infrastructure, transport, energy production and tourism in North America, the Arctic, Europe, the Andes, and more might be hugely impacted by the changes in snow, ice and river flooding. Storms will probably become more severe over most of North America, Europe, and the Mediterranean. The report points out that the Earth's precious carbon sinks, land and oceans, are at immense risk. They presently perform an astounding service in absorbing the bulk of the carbon dioxide the world emits, but as emissions rise, they will become less effective at absorbing CO2. These land sinks will eventually turn into a source, emitting CO2 instead of sucking it in; for example, the southeast Amazon rainforest is no longer a carbon sink mainly because of deforestation and local warming. This can lead to uncontrolled warming, which will not only affect the world’s climate efforts, but can pose significant food and water security risks to countries in the region, and may lead to irreversible biodiversity loss. According to Govindasamy Bala, professor of Climate Change, for the first time, the new report clarifies the ‘delicate balance’ between aerosols and GHG emissions and their influence on precipitation by noting that “greenhouse gas warming is partially offset by aerosol cooling.” Greenhouse gas-induced warming leads to intensification of rainfall, but from the 1950’s to 1980’s, there was a drop in global land monsoon precipitation and it was somewhat attributed to human-caused Northern Hemisphere aerosol ejection, which signifies that the aerosol cooling effect overpowered the greenhouse effect during the 30 year period. We don't see any trend in monsoon rainfall in the last three decades, mainly because the effects of GHGs and aerosols are almost balanced. In the coming couple of decades this delicate balance may continue but by mid or end of the century the report predicts that we will see a surge in precipitation, Bala explained. According to the IPCC, there is a direct link between the surge in global warming and extreme climate changes. At 2°C of global warming, heat shocks are more likely to reach critical forbearance thresholds for biodiversity, i.e. out of the 105,000 species that were studied, it is predicted that 8% of plants, 9.6% of insects and 4% of vertebrates will lose over half of their geographic range at 1.5°C, compared with 16% of plants, 18% of insects and 8% of vertebrates at 2°C.&amp;nbsp; Repercussions associated with other biodiversity-related risks, for instance, the spread of non-native species and forest fires, are lower at 1.5°C compared to 2°C of global warming.&amp;nbsp; Extreme sea level events that used to occur once a century previously could happen every year by 2100.&amp;nbsp; Thus, the report ascertains that there will be major benefits to limiting global warming to 1.5°C above the pre-industrial level, but doing so will need “rapid, far reaching and extraordinary changes in all aspects of society”. Pathways to safety As reported by the IPCC, around 85% of CO₂ emissions come from burning fossil fuels. It is much easier to stop releasing more CO₂ into the atmosphere than it is to eliminate it, and the more we emit, the further we degrade the ecosystems that naturally soak it up. Therefore, global net CO₂ emissions by humans have to shrink by about 45% by 2030 relative to 2010 levels and reach net zero by 2050. This is actually achievable, contrary to popular belief through mitigation measures in the energy sector.&amp;nbsp; About 70–85% of electricity is expected to be supplied by renewable sources in 2050. Shares of nuclear and fossil energy with Carbon Capture and Sequestration/Storage (CCS) are modelled to increase, allowing the share of carbon emitted in the atmosphere to fall and natural gas to generate about 8% of global electricity in 2050. All these mitigation measures will need an annual average investment in the energy system of around $2.4 trillion (at 2010 prices) between 2016 and 2035, representing about 2.5% of the world GDP;&amp;nbsp;however, the cost of inaction and delay will be many times more.&amp;nbsp; Following these pathways, the use of coal will be almost negligible by 2050, which might worry Indian policymakers, who are still talking about getting 45% of the country’s electricity from coal around the middle of the century. It's expected that by 2050, about 75–90% of CO₂ emissions from industry will be lower relative to current levels. The IPCC says this can be accomplished through &quot;combinations of new and already existing technologies and practises, including product substitution, electrification, sustainable bio-based feedstock, carbon capture, utilisation, and storage.&quot; All this will not only help us tackle the climate change situation but also help us achieve Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs). As a result of the COVID-19 pandemic, greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions are expected to rise. Because economies have been hard hit, every country is desperate for recovery, which can primarily be accomplished with the current brown economy, which includes using coal, gas, and oil to ratchet up growth as quickly as possible. But the good news is that we have technologies that can disrupt the current fossil-fuel-driven industrial system. We cannot wait for disruptive technologies; rather, we must be disruptive in action or it will be too late. As climatologist Xuebin Zhang says, &quot;the evidence is everywhere, if we don’t act now, the situation is going to get really bad.&quot;&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Through a Gender Lens: The Impact of Sanitation on Economic Development</title>
      <link href="/Through-a-Gender-Lens-The-Impact-of-Sanitation-on-Economic-Development" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Through a Gender Lens: The Impact of Sanitation on Economic Development" />
      <published>2022-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Through-a-Gender-Lens-The-Impact-of-Sanitation-on-Economic-Development</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Through-a-Gender-Lens-The-Impact-of-Sanitation-on-Economic-Development">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A simple internet search on the growth of a country would pop up uncountable figures on how each country is performing economically. Digging deeper into it would display numbers showing how each country compares with its international counterpart or neighbouring countries. Governments boast of their economic growth figures on international platforms but do these figures translate into actual economic development? Seldom do these numbers take into account how growth affects each individual in an economy. In neglecting the intersectionality a country possesses, governments often fail to account for the needs of the more vulnerable,&amp;nbsp; and equitable access to resources takes a backseat.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A classic example of this practice is the lack of discussion, and the subsequent lack of policy measures, on the provision of sanitation facilities across various developing countries. The neglect of sanitation tends to disproportionately affect women and girls globally since social constraints dictate women to carry out their sanitation activities at far off locations during odd hours.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In most cultures and across low income countries in Asia and Africa, women and girls are primarily responsible for the management of household water supply, sanitation and health. It is a time-consuming and taxing activity that involves travelling great distances and leaving work or school if water is made available during working hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Yet, when policy discussions on sanitation take place, female users’ involvement in the design and location of sanitation facilities is kept severely limited. It is alarming how despite playing prominent roles and responsibilities in household water and sanitation, women are often out of the purview of consideration when such facilities are in the pipeline. Such discrimination leads to an excess burden on women and girls, and their productive participation in the economy suffers as a result since most of their time is spent performing unpaid domestic work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Moreover, women are often subjected to abuse and gender-based violence when they are forced to walk to shared sanitation facilities or open defecation sites. The fear of sexual assault and harassment among women and girls while conducting sanitation activities has been documented extensively in places like Ethiopia, India and several refugee or internally-displaced persons' camps. There are several issues with women's access to open defecation. To reduce their vulnerability to sexual assault, they are forced to visit open defecation sites before dawn or at night, and in groups. This is proof of the looming fear of sexual violence that can limit freedom of movement and affect equal opportunities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Defecation in public causes its own set of issues, such as polluted water and an increase in the prevalence of water-borne illnesses, ultimately affecting the entire society at large. Women in India that can access public sanitation facilities find them typically filthy. In addition, men congregate near these facilities to verbally and sexually assault women as they attempt to use the facilities. Consequently, women tend to walk in groups to such facilities and often face time constraints and scheduling issues. The resulting health issues from poor sanitation, the absence of access to facilities at a convenient time and place, and the risk of violence has been severely under-investigated in sanitation-related research globally.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The World Health Organisation (WHO) came up with a measure called ‘sanitation insecurity score’, which measures the relationship between access to functioning sanitation facilities and psychological distress prevalent among women and found the former is predictive of the latter.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In rural India, women and girls have a high sanitation insecurity score, which naturally leads to poor mental health. Further research on the physical and mental consequences of poor sanitation facilities on women, and how that deepens the gender divide and distorts the economic well-being of women and girls is an urgent necessity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another area of concern is the effect of poor sanitation on women’s physical and mental health during the time of menstruation, pregnancy, child-rearing, and other illnesses. Their specific hygiene needs are severely unmet during such times, which makes girls and women more vulnerable to health-related risks. These unmet needs often result in the restriction of equal participation of women in society.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Various studies have indicated a strong association between poor sanitation and adverse pregnancy outcomes, such as preterm birth and low birth rate. However, a lot more needs to be studied on the overall health implications of inadequate sanitation on women and girls. The lack of sanitation facilities in schools and workplaces also has a significant impact on female literacy and labour force participation rates.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While there is much evidence of the impact of lack of toilets in schools on girls’ participation in education, there is far less evidence gathered on the absence of proper sanitation on working women, especially in the informal sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A priority area of focus in today’s age should be the participation of women in sanitation and hygiene decision-making. The effective use of water and sanitation facilities will be dependent on both men and women participating in the location and technology of such facilities, as well as taking responsibility for their operation and maintenance. There is evidence that empowering women to make sanitation decisions can improve household and community performance outcomes since their influence on sanitation and hygiene behaviour in households is undeniable.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There is a lot that is yet to be achieved in terms of gender equity in several developing countries and regions of the world. The imminent need to adopt equitable practices into policy at all levels will be crucial to achieving the desired sanitation goals of any country. Furthermore, inequitable practices have cost millions of girls and women a chance at education and work and have severely limited the economic productivity of several developing countries by restricting the participation of women. With better access to safe sanitation facilities, the world will certainly witness improvements in health, educational outcomes, and productivity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Essentially, sanitation accounts for a major chunk of the sustainable development goals (SDGs) of any country, which also includes education and work. The sanitation discussion draws our attention to the need to reject the notion that economic growth figures demonstrate a country's overall performance. The need to assess economic development while accounting for equitable distribution and access to resources is pressing. Gender-sensitive approaches to policy discussions on one’s basic human rights, like sanitation, can help us minimize the existing gender gap in society and approach development in its true sense.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      
        <category term="humanity" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A simple internet search on the growth of a country would pop up uncountable figures on how each country is performing economically. Digging deeper into it would display numbers showing how each country compares with its international counterpart or neighbouring countries. Governments boast of their economic growth figures on international platforms but do these figures translate into actual economic development? Seldom do these numbers take into account how growth affects each individual in an economy. In neglecting the intersectionality a country possesses, governments often fail to account for the needs of the more vulnerable,&amp;nbsp; and equitable access to resources takes a backseat.&amp;nbsp; A classic example of this practice is the lack of discussion, and the subsequent lack of policy measures, on the provision of sanitation facilities across various developing countries. The neglect of sanitation tends to disproportionately affect women and girls globally since social constraints dictate women to carry out their sanitation activities at far off locations during odd hours.&amp;nbsp; In most cultures and across low income countries in Asia and Africa, women and girls are primarily responsible for the management of household water supply, sanitation and health. It is a time-consuming and taxing activity that involves travelling great distances and leaving work or school if water is made available during working hours. Yet, when policy discussions on sanitation take place, female users’ involvement in the design and location of sanitation facilities is kept severely limited. It is alarming how despite playing prominent roles and responsibilities in household water and sanitation, women are often out of the purview of consideration when such facilities are in the pipeline. Such discrimination leads to an excess burden on women and girls, and their productive participation in the economy suffers as a result since most of their time is spent performing unpaid domestic work. Moreover, women are often subjected to abuse and gender-based violence when they are forced to walk to shared sanitation facilities or open defecation sites. The fear of sexual assault and harassment among women and girls while conducting sanitation activities has been documented extensively in places like Ethiopia, India and several refugee or internally-displaced persons' camps. There are several issues with women's access to open defecation. To reduce their vulnerability to sexual assault, they are forced to visit open defecation sites before dawn or at night, and in groups. This is proof of the looming fear of sexual violence that can limit freedom of movement and affect equal opportunities.&amp;nbsp; Defecation in public causes its own set of issues, such as polluted water and an increase in the prevalence of water-borne illnesses, ultimately affecting the entire society at large. Women in India that can access public sanitation facilities find them typically filthy. In addition, men congregate near these facilities to verbally and sexually assault women as they attempt to use the facilities. Consequently, women tend to walk in groups to such facilities and often face time constraints and scheduling issues. The resulting health issues from poor sanitation, the absence of access to facilities at a convenient time and place, and the risk of violence has been severely under-investigated in sanitation-related research globally.&amp;nbsp; The World Health Organisation (WHO) came up with a measure called ‘sanitation insecurity score’, which measures the relationship between access to functioning sanitation facilities and psychological distress prevalent among women and found the former is predictive of the latter.&amp;nbsp; In rural India, women and girls have a high sanitation insecurity score, which naturally leads to poor mental health. Further research on the physical and mental consequences of poor sanitation facilities on women, and how that deepens the gender divide and distorts the economic well-being of women and girls is an urgent necessity. Another area of concern is the effect of poor sanitation on women’s physical and mental health during the time of menstruation, pregnancy, child-rearing, and other illnesses. Their specific hygiene needs are severely unmet during such times, which makes girls and women more vulnerable to health-related risks. These unmet needs often result in the restriction of equal participation of women in society.&amp;nbsp; Various studies have indicated a strong association between poor sanitation and adverse pregnancy outcomes, such as preterm birth and low birth rate. However, a lot more needs to be studied on the overall health implications of inadequate sanitation on women and girls. The lack of sanitation facilities in schools and workplaces also has a significant impact on female literacy and labour force participation rates.&amp;nbsp; While there is much evidence of the impact of lack of toilets in schools on girls’ participation in education, there is far less evidence gathered on the absence of proper sanitation on working women, especially in the informal sector.&amp;nbsp; A priority area of focus in today’s age should be the participation of women in sanitation and hygiene decision-making. The effective use of water and sanitation facilities will be dependent on both men and women participating in the location and technology of such facilities, as well as taking responsibility for their operation and maintenance. There is evidence that empowering women to make sanitation decisions can improve household and community performance outcomes since their influence on sanitation and hygiene behaviour in households is undeniable.&amp;nbsp; There is a lot that is yet to be achieved in terms of gender equity in several developing countries and regions of the world. The imminent need to adopt equitable practices into policy at all levels will be crucial to achieving the desired sanitation goals of any country. Furthermore, inequitable practices have cost millions of girls and women a chance at education and work and have severely limited the economic productivity of several developing countries by restricting the participation of women. With better access to safe sanitation facilities, the world will certainly witness improvements in health, educational outcomes, and productivity.&amp;nbsp; Essentially, sanitation accounts for a major chunk of the sustainable development goals (SDGs) of any country, which also includes education and work. The sanitation discussion draws our attention to the need to reject the notion that economic growth figures demonstrate a country's overall performance. The need to assess economic development while accounting for equitable distribution and access to resources is pressing. Gender-sensitive approaches to policy discussions on one’s basic human rights, like sanitation, can help us minimize the existing gender gap in society and approach development in its true sense.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Greenhouse Gases and Empty Bowls</title>
      <link href="/Greenhouse-Gases-and-Empty-Bowls" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Greenhouse Gases and Empty Bowls" />
      <published>2022-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Greenhouse-Gases-and-Empty-Bowls</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Greenhouse-Gases-and-Empty-Bowls">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In October 2021, the Global Hunger Index ranked India at 101, slipping it seven ranks from 94, in a span of a single year. Even though the situation is particularly grim for India, the world, at present, stands on no winning side.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;One out of seven people sleep on an empty stomach every night. India is not the only country of concern, rather its position is not as concerning as the African countries in the Sahara. While the condition in Somalia is ‘extremely alarming’, in countries like Chad, the Democratic Republic of Congo, Yemen, Madagascar and a few others, the condition has been categorised as ‘alarming’. Few of the South Asian countries too are the hotspots of hunger.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The adoption of the United Nations Sustainable Development Goals (2) aims at eradicating hunger, achieving food security, improving nutrition and promoting sustainable agriculture. This was signed by 193 countries that aim to eradicate any and all forms of malnutrition by 2030, which now looks implausible.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;With 820 million people suffering from chronic hunger, 20.5 million babies being born with low birth weight as their mothers couldn’t get enough nutrition, hunger has resulted in stunted growth of 149 million children. We, definitely, have a long road to travel!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Amidst the numerous reasons behind the rising hunger, the escalating climate emergency is a major contributor to this humanitarian emergency. The rapid economic growth that has been taking place for the last 150 years has resulted in a consequent rise in greenhouse gas emissions. This has pushed the average global temperature to 1°C above pre-industrial levels. The current rate of emissions, according to experts, will result in the average global temperature rising to somewhere between 1.5°C to 2°C in the period between 2030-2050.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Countries are predicted to have extremely hot weather conditions, untimely and heavy precipitation on the one hand, and a greater probability of droughts, on the other. These predictions are of utmost concern. Human systems, which includes food systems, will be largely affected due to these extreme conditions. Hunger and climate crises are inextricable in nature.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The United Nations World Food Programme (UNWFP) has analysed that a 2 °C rise in the average global temperature when compared to pre-industrial levels will result in an additional 189 million people being pushed to starve. The communities that are most vulnerable to this change include fishing, livestock and subsistence agriculture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To sum it up, all the communities that contribute the least to the climate crisis shall bear the maximum repercussions with no pillar to hold during the blow. Lack of safety nets will leave these communities dependent on humanitarian aid for their survival like the migrants of war across the world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Not only this, the UNWFP has predicted that 41 million people (across 43 countries) shall bear the brunt of extreme famine. The poorer and underdeveloped countries are going to be the worst hit, even though they (i.e. the top ten food-insecure nations) contribute to only 0.08% of the global carbon emissions. Water scarcity, untimely rain, crop failure and declining nutrition due to multi-breadbasket failures shall threaten millions who have very little or no contribution to climate change.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The weather anomalies will affect the prices of food, and thus, its access to the poorer sections. Such effects shall not remain limited to specific regions as there exists a high degree of cross-connectedness between global food systems. Thus, extreme events in some regions hold the potential to disrupt the global food system. The lower-income countries will be, once again, the worst affected.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Lack of safeguards against food insecurity and a fragile, rather deficit, capacity to adapt to climate change remain some of the many concerns for these countries. But the buck doesn’t stop here!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The nutrient value of the food items and the nutrients absorbed also change with changes in climatic conditions. The food item cultivated is likely to contain a decreased amount of protein, zinc and iron. This is because higher concentrations of carbon dioxide in the environment result in the reduction of these nutrients; this has been backed by recent studies. An additional 175 million people could be deficient in zinc with 122 million more people experiencing protein deficiency by 2050, if this trend continues.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The impact is not limited to crops, livestock shall suffer equally. Livestock is the second worst-hit sector during droughts. Those dependent on aquatic life as a means of living and for food, are not better-placed either. The fish are extremely vulnerable to constant changes in temperature and climate extremes. No surprise that the affected regions will include South and Southeast Asia, Africa and the Middle East. The amalgamation of these deficiencies, increased prices and poor health infrastructure does not present a very happy picture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Resilience-building amongst the vulnerable sections is the need of the hour in order to attain food security. The absence of collective and large-scale action increases the distance between the world and the goals of Agenda 2030 (to eradicate any and all forms of malnutrition by 2030).&amp;nbsp; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Grassroot-level actions plans and locally adaptable dietary plans will work in the long run instead of generic and single plans for the entire world. Wondering, why? Red meat consumption amongst Americans is 6.5 times more than the recommendation. On the other hand, South Asians consume only half of what is required for a healthy body. In the absence of the same starting line, how will we achieve the same milestone together?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;We must view the food systems using the prism of adaptation to climate change and mitigation. This includes making the most vulnerable sections resilient to both climate change and pandemics. The continuous efforts to a greener and more sustainable planet should not lose the spotlight in this process. Governments need to come together with stronger partnerships and cooperation. Sailing the boat will become easier if the private sector and civil society organisations are also roped in. Financing the adaptation needs to be discussed in detail. The current kitty is insufficient in building resilience to climate change. Multilateral development banks and other financial institutions will have to be put to good use in order to attain the goals of Agenda 2030.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the meantime, protecting and improving the livelihoods of the vulnerable communities, adaptation practices in agriculture (for climate resilient crops like millet) can be put into place for nutritional security. Innovation for small-holder farmers coupled with information related to climate change, and inculcating preparedness can help the ‘developing’ countries like India.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Reimagining food systems towards sustainability, mitigation and balancing growth should be the new route to eradicate hunger.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      
        <category term="humanity" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In October 2021, the Global Hunger Index ranked India at 101, slipping it seven ranks from 94, in a span of a single year. Even though the situation is particularly grim for India, the world, at present, stands on no winning side.&amp;nbsp; One out of seven people sleep on an empty stomach every night. India is not the only country of concern, rather its position is not as concerning as the African countries in the Sahara. While the condition in Somalia is ‘extremely alarming’, in countries like Chad, the Democratic Republic of Congo, Yemen, Madagascar and a few others, the condition has been categorised as ‘alarming’. Few of the South Asian countries too are the hotspots of hunger.&amp;nbsp; The adoption of the United Nations Sustainable Development Goals (2) aims at eradicating hunger, achieving food security, improving nutrition and promoting sustainable agriculture. This was signed by 193 countries that aim to eradicate any and all forms of malnutrition by 2030, which now looks implausible.&amp;nbsp; With 820 million people suffering from chronic hunger, 20.5 million babies being born with low birth weight as their mothers couldn’t get enough nutrition, hunger has resulted in stunted growth of 149 million children. We, definitely, have a long road to travel! Amidst the numerous reasons behind the rising hunger, the escalating climate emergency is a major contributor to this humanitarian emergency. The rapid economic growth that has been taking place for the last 150 years has resulted in a consequent rise in greenhouse gas emissions. This has pushed the average global temperature to 1°C above pre-industrial levels. The current rate of emissions, according to experts, will result in the average global temperature rising to somewhere between 1.5°C to 2°C in the period between 2030-2050.&amp;nbsp; Countries are predicted to have extremely hot weather conditions, untimely and heavy precipitation on the one hand, and a greater probability of droughts, on the other. These predictions are of utmost concern. Human systems, which includes food systems, will be largely affected due to these extreme conditions. Hunger and climate crises are inextricable in nature.&amp;nbsp; The United Nations World Food Programme (UNWFP) has analysed that a 2 °C rise in the average global temperature when compared to pre-industrial levels will result in an additional 189 million people being pushed to starve. The communities that are most vulnerable to this change include fishing, livestock and subsistence agriculture.&amp;nbsp; To sum it up, all the communities that contribute the least to the climate crisis shall bear the maximum repercussions with no pillar to hold during the blow. Lack of safety nets will leave these communities dependent on humanitarian aid for their survival like the migrants of war across the world.&amp;nbsp; Not only this, the UNWFP has predicted that 41 million people (across 43 countries) shall bear the brunt of extreme famine. The poorer and underdeveloped countries are going to be the worst hit, even though they (i.e. the top ten food-insecure nations) contribute to only 0.08% of the global carbon emissions. Water scarcity, untimely rain, crop failure and declining nutrition due to multi-breadbasket failures shall threaten millions who have very little or no contribution to climate change.&amp;nbsp; The weather anomalies will affect the prices of food, and thus, its access to the poorer sections. Such effects shall not remain limited to specific regions as there exists a high degree of cross-connectedness between global food systems. Thus, extreme events in some regions hold the potential to disrupt the global food system. The lower-income countries will be, once again, the worst affected.&amp;nbsp; Lack of safeguards against food insecurity and a fragile, rather deficit, capacity to adapt to climate change remain some of the many concerns for these countries. But the buck doesn’t stop here!&amp;nbsp; The nutrient value of the food items and the nutrients absorbed also change with changes in climatic conditions. The food item cultivated is likely to contain a decreased amount of protein, zinc and iron. This is because higher concentrations of carbon dioxide in the environment result in the reduction of these nutrients; this has been backed by recent studies. An additional 175 million people could be deficient in zinc with 122 million more people experiencing protein deficiency by 2050, if this trend continues.&amp;nbsp; The impact is not limited to crops, livestock shall suffer equally. Livestock is the second worst-hit sector during droughts. Those dependent on aquatic life as a means of living and for food, are not better-placed either. The fish are extremely vulnerable to constant changes in temperature and climate extremes. No surprise that the affected regions will include South and Southeast Asia, Africa and the Middle East. The amalgamation of these deficiencies, increased prices and poor health infrastructure does not present a very happy picture.&amp;nbsp; Resilience-building amongst the vulnerable sections is the need of the hour in order to attain food security. The absence of collective and large-scale action increases the distance between the world and the goals of Agenda 2030 (to eradicate any and all forms of malnutrition by 2030).&amp;nbsp; Grassroot-level actions plans and locally adaptable dietary plans will work in the long run instead of generic and single plans for the entire world. Wondering, why? Red meat consumption amongst Americans is 6.5 times more than the recommendation. On the other hand, South Asians consume only half of what is required for a healthy body. In the absence of the same starting line, how will we achieve the same milestone together?&amp;nbsp; We must view the food systems using the prism of adaptation to climate change and mitigation. This includes making the most vulnerable sections resilient to both climate change and pandemics. The continuous efforts to a greener and more sustainable planet should not lose the spotlight in this process. Governments need to come together with stronger partnerships and cooperation. Sailing the boat will become easier if the private sector and civil society organisations are also roped in. Financing the adaptation needs to be discussed in detail. The current kitty is insufficient in building resilience to climate change. Multilateral development banks and other financial institutions will have to be put to good use in order to attain the goals of Agenda 2030.&amp;nbsp; In the meantime, protecting and improving the livelihoods of the vulnerable communities, adaptation practices in agriculture (for climate resilient crops like millet) can be put into place for nutritional security. Innovation for small-holder farmers coupled with information related to climate change, and inculcating preparedness can help the ‘developing’ countries like India.&amp;nbsp; Reimagining food systems towards sustainability, mitigation and balancing growth should be the new route to eradicate hunger.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Healthcare Mantra for This Decade: Actionable, Accessible, Affordable!</title>
      <link href="/The-Healthcare-Mantra-for-This-Decade-Actionable-Accessible-Affordable" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Healthcare Mantra for This Decade: Actionable, Accessible, Affordable! " />
      <published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Healthcare-Mantra-for-This-Decade-Actionable-Accessible-Affordable-</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Healthcare-Mantra-for-This-Decade-Actionable-Accessible-Affordable">&lt;p&gt;While I was lazing around on a Sunday evening after spending the day watching some pointless TV show on Netflix, which would never further my intellect at any particular matter, my father pointedly remarked to me, ‘Health is Wealth! Go exercise your muscles for once.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That statement truly struck my brain muscles. I decided to exercise those for a change since I was too much of a sloth to get out and workout. It dawned upon me that the statement was absolutely bogus. Wonder why? In my limited experience of 23 years on this planet, it has often become vividly clear to me that indeed the reverse is true, ‘Wealth is Health.’ To die a death of peace, without gasping for oxygen, while sitting on a wheelchair, waiting outside a hospital for a bed and a cylinder, you would have needed (on an average) a few hundred thousand rupees back in May 2021 in New Delhi.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want to know the median household income in India? Well, it’s a handsome round off of about fifty thousand rupees per annum. Which begs the ultimate question, why is basic healthcare so expensive?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With socio-health inequalities being a raging issue of debate for most forums amidst the Covid era, the discussion has always started and ended with the incompetency of the government and the neglect of the public health infrastructure, respectively. Do I agree with that? Not in its entirety. But to delve deeper into how this mechanism works, it would be prudent for one to revisit the consequential economic steppingstones to such inequities around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Health Inequity, not Inequality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to address that health inequality should not be diluted into the mix of health inequity. That’s simply because health inequality is generally a by-product of disorders which kick in with older age, and often are hereditary, or genetic problems. For example, my mother’s forlorn battle with &lt;em&gt;Rheumatoid arthritis&lt;/em&gt; is one such inequality that couldn’t be helped.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the health inequity that the modern world faces so rampantly today, is different from my mother’s story. Health inequity often stems from a valley surrounded by the challenging mountains of income, physical environment, social support inequalities. Those are few of the major inequalities which isolate the socio-economically disadvantaged population into facing the burnt of a forged inequity arising from the disbalanced opportunities across our demographies. You literally must climb up the socio-economic mountain to attain the accessibility of such refined services and thus, better your chances at living a healthier and longer life. For example, research shows that asthma hospitalisations are over 1.5 times more in the lower-income neighbourhoods compared to the higher-income ones. Now this combined with our improved understanding of climate change, the ill-effects of bad air quality, and the ever-so-frequent cyclones, and floods, it is no joke when we finally realise that the physical and economic confinements of an individual lead them to bearing significant disadvantages in a health battle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Health is a Right, not a Commodity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, as an Economics major (which I am not sure if I should pride myself in), I cannot help but look at the notions of demand, supply, and utility in all aspects of life. They start with me succumbing to the urges of buying more affordable clothing from regular labour law abusers to deliberating if it's the healthcare policies which are truly at fault or not.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the situation from a strict Demand-Supply angle, I concede to the concept that government intervention is useless and give into the argument “let the forces of market play out to acquire efficiency”. Ah yes, ‘efficiency,’ the ‘It’ word of Economics. It is supposed to solve all our problems, right? Well, again not entirely true, just like every other ‘rational’ answer in economics which is based on an unstable jenga of numerous assumptions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allow me to explain the jargon of ‘efficiency’ to you. &lt;em&gt;Economic efficiency&lt;/em&gt; is defined as a state where all goods and factors of production are distributed or productively allocated amongst the consumers to eliminate any chances of waste. However, what the jargon often leaves behind is the inability of efficiency to incorporate all players in the market. For example, if someone has more money at his or her disposal, then that person is perfectly capable and encouraged to acquire the scarce resource at a higher price while defeating another without those means. You know the saddest truth of healthcare? It is a Scarce Resource.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the statement “let the market play out” along with the assumption that the intervention of government only leads to market failures (through monopolistic behaviour) is ridiculous and a sure shot at worsening the pickle that we already find ourselves in. Therefore, it is time to set the record straight, “Affordable healthcare is my Right, no matter if I am poor or rich, today or tomorrow.”&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big Pharma: Saints or Satan?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter the number of conventions, agreements and vigilance of health authorities, the pharmaceutical companies can not stop making billions off the pain of the global citizens. Again, going back to the demand and supply argument. The demand and supply should meet at equilibrium to fix the market prices. But it is a little different for drugs, especially life-saving ones. People simply don't have the option to refuse the exorbitant prices of drugs such as Hepatitis C or HIV, which gives the companies a massive leverage to fix prices as per their whims and profit margin targets.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, let’s talk about Turing Pharmaceuticals and the CEO Martin Shkreli who hiked the price of an essential drug, &lt;em&gt;Daraprim&lt;/em&gt;, by 5,000% (from $13.50 to $750). This begs the question: Can buying licences to public funded research and innovations, and then hiking prices to make the public pay for it, even legal? According to the laws, mostly it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview when asked about what he would have liked to do differently, Shkreli went on to answer that “Healthcare prices are inelastic, I could have raised it higher and made more profits for my shareholders.” This one statement sums up the motive with which big pharma operates; they are not responsible for their patients, they are answerable to their shareholders and investors.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unrivalled power in the lobbying halls of the American Congress and parliaments around the world has made big pharma the ultimate power player when it comes to deciding if we even have a shot at surviving. Even though they operate within the realms of humanity, they possess the strings to make us all dance on their commands. Recurring malaria symptoms due to a sudden lack of affordability to &lt;em&gt;Daraprim&lt;/em&gt; is not fateful, it is planned.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Public-Private Partnerships: A farce or a force?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strategic intervention of public policy in the healthcare sector is the need of the hour. In recent years, governments, international organisations and even private players have conceded to the argument that equality of opportunity should be the moral foundation to build our policies. The World Bank, for instance, has started using a Human Opportunity Index as one of the relevant indicators to assess social, human and economic development aspects.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many government initiatives, for example the Midday Meal Scheme in India, is geared towards ensuring social and educational protection routed through the maintenance of nutritional standards for children hailing from lower income communities. As deeply deliberated by economists Amartya Sen and Jean Dreze, nutritional inadequacies can often lead to future health problems, thus, making the poor vulnerable in a competitive labour market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, socio-health protection can stimulate economic growth for developing nations and be a key factor to combat a macroeconomic crisis. But the main problem, when seen through the lenses of developing countries, is often the laid-back attitude of the public sector projects which when coupled with a bar of fiscal deficit, can be difficult obstacles in planning a long-term inclusive plan. To bring in the private players into this mold would mean that it would contribute to capital accumulation and investment, risk management and offer diverse potential advantages to indirect stakeholders through multiplier effects. Therefore, bringing in private funding with the main hold of government in steering things to the correct conclusion, pricing, can be the way forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having suggested the inclusion of private players into the mold of healthcare, I must address the problem of private players slowly taking the charge to invest and maximise profits through expensive medication (inelastic demand). Therefore, the onus must lie upon the government to take action, diversify research, be responsible and accountable to the public at large, and be strict with the pricing models.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Am I Satisfied or Worried?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I would say, I am ‘impressed’. Don’t get me wrong, the statistics of COVID-19 cases unfolding while I cough my heart out to write these soulful words, has me chilled to my bones. But the honest truth is that the pandemic is here to stay. Yes, we already have a delta plus omicron variant and booster jabs available but it is not that which has impressed me (I am not a supporter of dystopia, in fact I am already dreading the advent of “oxicron”). I am impressed by the fact that our newsrooms, classrooms, zoom meetings and daily chats are now (more than ever before) focused on ‘health.’ It is probably for the first time in history that we have realised how much our lives are worth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one of my favourite dialogues from the movie &lt;em&gt;Troy&lt;/em&gt; (2004), the character Odysseus goes on to tell Achilles that “War is young men dying, and old men talking.” In my opinion, this battle against Covid has proven yet again that neglect in the healthcare systems will cost us lives at all fronts, no matter how boldly the wise, grey haired intellectuals deliberate on fixing the situation without adequate expenditures. The advent of COVID-19 with the surges in internet usage around the globe has made interaction possible between people living in different continents. The debate of healthcare affordability is now no longer limited to the fancy parliament halls and the elite think tanks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, the global citizens, have proudly taken a step forward to progress the discussions on affordable healthcare, equitable healthcare, climate change and so much more. The GDP figures are not impressive any more. In fact they are on a dedicated downhill safari. What will it take to impress us? An increase in human development and opportunity indices, for starters, would be good. The discussions on our physical and mental health would be even better.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier (pre-Covid) the politics in my country India would generally revolve around two parties trying to degrade one another with quirkier rhetoric. Now, I am not denying that those rhetorics weren’t fun. They are an absolute amaze, both for meme and conversation purposes. Who in the world would not enjoy a wholesome trash talk between the ‘defenders of faith’. It is terribly fun to watch. But it is not the essence of our existence as politics made us believe in. Our population will only truly prosper when everyone has equal opportunities and access. The world has finally started demanding what is truly theirs, and now we are debating these topics in our homes. Home, where the general scope of discussion was limited to taking trash out and gossiping about neighbours. That is steep progress according to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I am hopeful when I say that I am looking forward to this decade’s unfolding. This will no doubt be one of the most ‘efficient,’ remarkable and decisive decades of human history. This time the war will not be fought on the enemy lines, rather it will be fought within our homes as we sanitise our hands and take those jabs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 has brought more than 19 months of caged life. So much so that going out without a mask feels alien to me at this point. But what it also helped us realise is that being healthy (and ‘negative’) is golden. Therefore, socio-health protection, extensive public health research funding and awareness is required if we are to be the ‘defenders of human existence’ and strike down these ultra effective viruses and other anomalies. By being ultra productive in building infrastructure for it and investing in pertinent research, maybe we will have a shot at it. But above all what is to be appreciated amid all of this chaos, is the resilience of humankind in not giving up. So, three cheers to humanity at large!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      
        <category term="humanity" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">While I was lazing around on a Sunday evening after spending the day watching some pointless TV show on Netflix, which would never further my intellect at any particular matter, my father pointedly remarked to me, ‘Health is Wealth! Go exercise your muscles for once.’ That statement truly struck my brain muscles. I decided to exercise those for a change since I was too much of a sloth to get out and workout. It dawned upon me that the statement was absolutely bogus. Wonder why? In my limited experience of 23 years on this planet, it has often become vividly clear to me that indeed the reverse is true, ‘Wealth is Health.’ To die a death of peace, without gasping for oxygen, while sitting on a wheelchair, waiting outside a hospital for a bed and a cylinder, you would have needed (on an average) a few hundred thousand rupees back in May 2021 in New Delhi.&amp;nbsp; Want to know the median household income in India? Well, it’s a handsome round off of about fifty thousand rupees per annum. Which begs the ultimate question, why is basic healthcare so expensive? With socio-health inequalities being a raging issue of debate for most forums amidst the Covid era, the discussion has always started and ended with the incompetency of the government and the neglect of the public health infrastructure, respectively. Do I agree with that? Not in its entirety. But to delve deeper into how this mechanism works, it would be prudent for one to revisit the consequential economic steppingstones to such inequities around the world. Health Inequity, not Inequality It is important to address that health inequality should not be diluted into the mix of health inequity. That’s simply because health inequality is generally a by-product of disorders which kick in with older age, and often are hereditary, or genetic problems. For example, my mother’s forlorn battle with Rheumatoid arthritis is one such inequality that couldn’t be helped.&amp;nbsp; However, the health inequity that the modern world faces so rampantly today, is different from my mother’s story. Health inequity often stems from a valley surrounded by the challenging mountains of income, physical environment, social support inequalities. Those are few of the major inequalities which isolate the socio-economically disadvantaged population into facing the burnt of a forged inequity arising from the disbalanced opportunities across our demographies. You literally must climb up the socio-economic mountain to attain the accessibility of such refined services and thus, better your chances at living a healthier and longer life. For example, research shows that asthma hospitalisations are over 1.5 times more in the lower-income neighbourhoods compared to the higher-income ones. Now this combined with our improved understanding of climate change, the ill-effects of bad air quality, and the ever-so-frequent cyclones, and floods, it is no joke when we finally realise that the physical and economic confinements of an individual lead them to bearing significant disadvantages in a health battle. Health is a Right, not a Commodity Now, as an Economics major (which I am not sure if I should pride myself in), I cannot help but look at the notions of demand, supply, and utility in all aspects of life. They start with me succumbing to the urges of buying more affordable clothing from regular labour law abusers to deliberating if it's the healthcare policies which are truly at fault or not.&amp;nbsp; Looking at the situation from a strict Demand-Supply angle, I concede to the concept that government intervention is useless and give into the argument “let the forces of market play out to acquire efficiency”. Ah yes, ‘efficiency,’ the ‘It’ word of Economics. It is supposed to solve all our problems, right? Well, again not entirely true, just like every other ‘rational’ answer in economics which is based on an unstable jenga of numerous assumptions.&amp;nbsp; Allow me to explain the jargon of ‘efficiency’ to you. Economic efficiency is defined as a state where all goods and factors of production are distributed or productively allocated amongst the consumers to eliminate any chances of waste. However, what the jargon often leaves behind is the inability of efficiency to incorporate all players in the market. For example, if someone has more money at his or her disposal, then that person is perfectly capable and encouraged to acquire the scarce resource at a higher price while defeating another without those means. You know the saddest truth of healthcare? It is a Scarce Resource.&amp;nbsp; Therefore, the statement “let the market play out” along with the assumption that the intervention of government only leads to market failures (through monopolistic behaviour) is ridiculous and a sure shot at worsening the pickle that we already find ourselves in. Therefore, it is time to set the record straight, “Affordable healthcare is my Right, no matter if I am poor or rich, today or tomorrow.”&amp;nbsp; Big Pharma: Saints or Satan? No matter the number of conventions, agreements and vigilance of health authorities, the pharmaceutical companies can not stop making billions off the pain of the global citizens. Again, going back to the demand and supply argument. The demand and supply should meet at equilibrium to fix the market prices. But it is a little different for drugs, especially life-saving ones. People simply don't have the option to refuse the exorbitant prices of drugs such as Hepatitis C or HIV, which gives the companies a massive leverage to fix prices as per their whims and profit margin targets.&amp;nbsp; For instance, let’s talk about Turing Pharmaceuticals and the CEO Martin Shkreli who hiked the price of an essential drug, Daraprim, by 5,000% (from $13.50 to $750). This begs the question: Can buying licences to public funded research and innovations, and then hiking prices to make the public pay for it, even legal? According to the laws, mostly it is. In an interview when asked about what he would have liked to do differently, Shkreli went on to answer that “Healthcare prices are inelastic, I could have raised it higher and made more profits for my shareholders.” This one statement sums up the motive with which big pharma operates; they are not responsible for their patients, they are answerable to their shareholders and investors.&amp;nbsp; The unrivalled power in the lobbying halls of the American Congress and parliaments around the world has made big pharma the ultimate power player when it comes to deciding if we even have a shot at surviving. Even though they operate within the realms of humanity, they possess the strings to make us all dance on their commands. Recurring malaria symptoms due to a sudden lack of affordability to Daraprim is not fateful, it is planned.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Public-Private Partnerships: A farce or a force? Strategic intervention of public policy in the healthcare sector is the need of the hour. In recent years, governments, international organisations and even private players have conceded to the argument that equality of opportunity should be the moral foundation to build our policies. The World Bank, for instance, has started using a Human Opportunity Index as one of the relevant indicators to assess social, human and economic development aspects.&amp;nbsp; Many government initiatives, for example the Midday Meal Scheme in India, is geared towards ensuring social and educational protection routed through the maintenance of nutritional standards for children hailing from lower income communities. As deeply deliberated by economists Amartya Sen and Jean Dreze, nutritional inadequacies can often lead to future health problems, thus, making the poor vulnerable in a competitive labour market. Therefore, socio-health protection can stimulate economic growth for developing nations and be a key factor to combat a macroeconomic crisis. But the main problem, when seen through the lenses of developing countries, is often the laid-back attitude of the public sector projects which when coupled with a bar of fiscal deficit, can be difficult obstacles in planning a long-term inclusive plan. To bring in the private players into this mold would mean that it would contribute to capital accumulation and investment, risk management and offer diverse potential advantages to indirect stakeholders through multiplier effects. Therefore, bringing in private funding with the main hold of government in steering things to the correct conclusion, pricing, can be the way forward. Having suggested the inclusion of private players into the mold of healthcare, I must address the problem of private players slowly taking the charge to invest and maximise profits through expensive medication (inelastic demand). Therefore, the onus must lie upon the government to take action, diversify research, be responsible and accountable to the public at large, and be strict with the pricing models.&amp;nbsp; Am I Satisfied or Worried? Well, I would say, I am ‘impressed’. Don’t get me wrong, the statistics of COVID-19 cases unfolding while I cough my heart out to write these soulful words, has me chilled to my bones. But the honest truth is that the pandemic is here to stay. Yes, we already have a delta plus omicron variant and booster jabs available but it is not that which has impressed me (I am not a supporter of dystopia, in fact I am already dreading the advent of “oxicron”). I am impressed by the fact that our newsrooms, classrooms, zoom meetings and daily chats are now (more than ever before) focused on ‘health.’ It is probably for the first time in history that we have realised how much our lives are worth.&amp;nbsp; In one of my favourite dialogues from the movie Troy (2004), the character Odysseus goes on to tell Achilles that “War is young men dying, and old men talking.” In my opinion, this battle against Covid has proven yet again that neglect in the healthcare systems will cost us lives at all fronts, no matter how boldly the wise, grey haired intellectuals deliberate on fixing the situation without adequate expenditures. The advent of COVID-19 with the surges in internet usage around the globe has made interaction possible between people living in different continents. The debate of healthcare affordability is now no longer limited to the fancy parliament halls and the elite think tanks.&amp;nbsp; We, the global citizens, have proudly taken a step forward to progress the discussions on affordable healthcare, equitable healthcare, climate change and so much more. The GDP figures are not impressive any more. In fact they are on a dedicated downhill safari. What will it take to impress us? An increase in human development and opportunity indices, for starters, would be good. The discussions on our physical and mental health would be even better.&amp;nbsp; Earlier (pre-Covid) the politics in my country India would generally revolve around two parties trying to degrade one another with quirkier rhetoric. Now, I am not denying that those rhetorics weren’t fun. They are an absolute amaze, both for meme and conversation purposes. Who in the world would not enjoy a wholesome trash talk between the ‘defenders of faith’. It is terribly fun to watch. But it is not the essence of our existence as politics made us believe in. Our population will only truly prosper when everyone has equal opportunities and access. The world has finally started demanding what is truly theirs, and now we are debating these topics in our homes. Home, where the general scope of discussion was limited to taking trash out and gossiping about neighbours. That is steep progress according to me. Therefore, I am hopeful when I say that I am looking forward to this decade’s unfolding. This will no doubt be one of the most ‘efficient,’ remarkable and decisive decades of human history. This time the war will not be fought on the enemy lines, rather it will be fought within our homes as we sanitise our hands and take those jabs.&amp;nbsp; COVID-19 has brought more than 19 months of caged life. So much so that going out without a mask feels alien to me at this point. But what it also helped us realise is that being healthy (and ‘negative’) is golden. Therefore, socio-health protection, extensive public health research funding and awareness is required if we are to be the ‘defenders of human existence’ and strike down these ultra effective viruses and other anomalies. By being ultra productive in building infrastructure for it and investing in pertinent research, maybe we will have a shot at it. But above all what is to be appreciated amid all of this chaos, is the resilience of humankind in not giving up. So, three cheers to humanity at large!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Optimistic Economics</title>
      <link href="/Optimistic-Economics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Optimistic Economics" />
      <published>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Optimistic-Economics</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Optimistic-Economics">&lt;p&gt;Reason and expectations have a peculiar connection. It would seem that expectations emanate from reasonable assumptions or logical discourse amongst the public. Facts are juxtaposed with their probabilities and resource capacities, and then expectations are formed. However, the opposite happens. Popular reason derives from the people’s expectations. People find a way to justify what they expect. But how are their expectations formed?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the former half of 2020, when some parts of the world, including India, were experiencing the lethal first wave of COVID-19, predictions of economic recovery were more or less inclined towards a swoosh-shaped recovery. It is a layman’s way to state that an economy would first experience a sharp plunge, a slow rebound and an even slower recovery in the long term. There is a major role of expectations in the economy after this. But before that, it is important to know the expectations. People thought a V-shaped economic recovery was too optimistic. So, they discounted their optimism a little to come down to the level of reality. They shaped their predictions to expect a recovery only a little slower compared to the V-shaped, which boiled their expectations down to a U-shaped recovery.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first wave of COVID-19 in 2020, the world still suffered from optimism bias because they had not yet felt the shock of the second wave. Financial analysts across the world predicted a K-shaped recovery, which stands to mean that after an economy crashes, some sectors not only recover but scale up to more than pre-recession levels, and some sectors plummet even below the pre-recession levels. This happens because there was an anticipation of an approaching second wave in the world. It made the majority of the population increase its acceptance of the virtual means of entertainment, education, pharmacy, and shopping etc.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This culminated in thriving ed-tech, internet pharmacy, over the top (OTT) platforms and e-commerce businesses. Taking the complete picture into account, this is resources reallocation in play: schools and coaching centres to ed-tech, local chemist shops to internet pharmacies, cable TVs and cinemas to OTT platforms and from local stores and malls to e-commerce. Hence, just the expectation of a second wave brought about such a drastic change not only in the GDP increase from -24% in the first quarter of 2020-21 to 1.64% in the fourth quarter of 2020-21 but also in the composition of GDP due to the increased contribution of some sectors and decreasing contribution of others.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A noteworthy observation in this interplay of people’s expectations and economic outcomes is that you would never find L-shaped, W-shaped or Z-shaped recoveries in these predictions, however hard you hunt. In case you are wondering if it is because of the low probability of these recovery shapes, then let me tell you it is not so.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Great Depression of the 1930’s is a testament to the reality of L-shaped economic recoveries when the economy experiences a sudden crash followed by stagnation in GDP and persistent unemployment over a long period. L-shape signifies the most horrendous recovery prospects because it essentially means no recovery at all for a considerable period. It stands for lost incomes and production. It is a nightmare, to say the least. Even India in the 1960’s and 1970’s lost a major portion of its production owing to wars with hostile neighbours and global oil price shocks. Japan experienced the same in 1989 and the following decade, which is often called the Lost Decade for Japan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the pre-2008 years as well, people, as well as the governments, failed to acknowledge any possibility of an economic collapse even in the face of public debates and discussions about the approaching collapse of the housing bubble in the United States and the consequent financial crisis. People’s optimistic expectations led them to invest more and more in the housing market to expand it so much that when the bubble burst, not just the US but the whole world felt the economic shock.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even today, when the debate about a post-COVID economic recovery is piping hot across the world, there are fewer economists and even fewer people talking about L or W or Z shaped recoveries even though a W or Z shaped recovery seems almost logical. A W-shaped recovery is when an economic recession is followed by a recovery attempt, unfortunately leading to another economic crash followed by a steady recovery. The incoming nature of the second wave of COVID-19 wave in 2020 should have warranted predictions of a W-shaped recovery, logically speaking. However, even in the survey of financial analysts across the world, only 11% thought that a W-shaped recovery would be imminent. Even a Z-shaped recovery that symbolises an economy that first experiences a sudden crash, recovery followed by another recession would seem likely. But these ideas were rarely found in post-COVID expectations and predictions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, there is a major tilt towards optimism when people talk about economic recovery. The idea of economic recovery is covertly hazy in people’s minds. It is unnecessarily associated with utopian optimism. In economics, they call it pro-growth expectations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of India, the first and second waves of COVID-19 blatantly exposed the ill state of education and health infrastructure in the country, depriving millions of poor children of a year or more of learning and giving hundreds of people an ignominious death of oxygen scarcity. Millions of workers migrating across states on foot lay bare the callous anomalies of the informal sector and urban economy based on casual labour.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time a crisis happens, it does well to expose the loopholes of the economic system. In the face of such shocks, how the governments and the people respond determines how the economy responds. As discussed, V, U and swoosh-shaped recoveries lie at the heart of most macroeconomic predictions. This optimism is reflected in the stock market bubble. With the Government of India’s numerous lines of credit and welfare schemes flowing like water to stimulate the economy, investor sentiment and consumer demand are positive as well. Whether this is a bubble that will burst in the following three to four years or would it be accompanied by correction mechanisms to culminate in long-term growth will largely depend on the actions of financial institutions and governments. Simply put, for all optimists, a V is out of reach now, and a U or swoosh is some reforms away!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Priyal Batheja</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Reason and expectations have a peculiar connection. It would seem that expectations emanate from reasonable assumptions or logical discourse amongst the public. Facts are juxtaposed with their probabilities and resource capacities, and then expectations are formed. However, the opposite happens. Popular reason derives from the people’s expectations. People find a way to justify what they expect. But how are their expectations formed?&amp;nbsp; In the former half of 2020, when some parts of the world, including India, were experiencing the lethal first wave of COVID-19, predictions of economic recovery were more or less inclined towards a swoosh-shaped recovery. It is a layman’s way to state that an economy would first experience a sharp plunge, a slow rebound and an even slower recovery in the long term. There is a major role of expectations in the economy after this. But before that, it is important to know the expectations. People thought a V-shaped economic recovery was too optimistic. So, they discounted their optimism a little to come down to the level of reality. They shaped their predictions to expect a recovery only a little slower compared to the V-shaped, which boiled their expectations down to a U-shaped recovery.&amp;nbsp; After the first wave of COVID-19 in 2020, the world still suffered from optimism bias because they had not yet felt the shock of the second wave. Financial analysts across the world predicted a K-shaped recovery, which stands to mean that after an economy crashes, some sectors not only recover but scale up to more than pre-recession levels, and some sectors plummet even below the pre-recession levels. This happens because there was an anticipation of an approaching second wave in the world. It made the majority of the population increase its acceptance of the virtual means of entertainment, education, pharmacy, and shopping etc.&amp;nbsp; This culminated in thriving ed-tech, internet pharmacy, over the top (OTT) platforms and e-commerce businesses. Taking the complete picture into account, this is resources reallocation in play: schools and coaching centres to ed-tech, local chemist shops to internet pharmacies, cable TVs and cinemas to OTT platforms and from local stores and malls to e-commerce. Hence, just the expectation of a second wave brought about such a drastic change not only in the GDP increase from -24% in the first quarter of 2020-21 to 1.64% in the fourth quarter of 2020-21 but also in the composition of GDP due to the increased contribution of some sectors and decreasing contribution of others.&amp;nbsp; A noteworthy observation in this interplay of people’s expectations and economic outcomes is that you would never find L-shaped, W-shaped or Z-shaped recoveries in these predictions, however hard you hunt. In case you are wondering if it is because of the low probability of these recovery shapes, then let me tell you it is not so.&amp;nbsp; The Great Depression of the 1930’s is a testament to the reality of L-shaped economic recoveries when the economy experiences a sudden crash followed by stagnation in GDP and persistent unemployment over a long period. L-shape signifies the most horrendous recovery prospects because it essentially means no recovery at all for a considerable period. It stands for lost incomes and production. It is a nightmare, to say the least. Even India in the 1960’s and 1970’s lost a major portion of its production owing to wars with hostile neighbours and global oil price shocks. Japan experienced the same in 1989 and the following decade, which is often called the Lost Decade for Japan.&amp;nbsp; In the pre-2008 years as well, people, as well as the governments, failed to acknowledge any possibility of an economic collapse even in the face of public debates and discussions about the approaching collapse of the housing bubble in the United States and the consequent financial crisis. People’s optimistic expectations led them to invest more and more in the housing market to expand it so much that when the bubble burst, not just the US but the whole world felt the economic shock.&amp;nbsp; Even today, when the debate about a post-COVID economic recovery is piping hot across the world, there are fewer economists and even fewer people talking about L or W or Z shaped recoveries even though a W or Z shaped recovery seems almost logical. A W-shaped recovery is when an economic recession is followed by a recovery attempt, unfortunately leading to another economic crash followed by a steady recovery. The incoming nature of the second wave of COVID-19 wave in 2020 should have warranted predictions of a W-shaped recovery, logically speaking. However, even in the survey of financial analysts across the world, only 11% thought that a W-shaped recovery would be imminent. Even a Z-shaped recovery that symbolises an economy that first experiences a sudden crash, recovery followed by another recession would seem likely. But these ideas were rarely found in post-COVID expectations and predictions.&amp;nbsp; Needless to say, there is a major tilt towards optimism when people talk about economic recovery. The idea of economic recovery is covertly hazy in people’s minds. It is unnecessarily associated with utopian optimism. In economics, they call it pro-growth expectations.&amp;nbsp; In the case of India, the first and second waves of COVID-19 blatantly exposed the ill state of education and health infrastructure in the country, depriving millions of poor children of a year or more of learning and giving hundreds of people an ignominious death of oxygen scarcity. Millions of workers migrating across states on foot lay bare the callous anomalies of the informal sector and urban economy based on casual labour.&amp;nbsp; Every time a crisis happens, it does well to expose the loopholes of the economic system. In the face of such shocks, how the governments and the people respond determines how the economy responds. As discussed, V, U and swoosh-shaped recoveries lie at the heart of most macroeconomic predictions. This optimism is reflected in the stock market bubble. With the Government of India’s numerous lines of credit and welfare schemes flowing like water to stimulate the economy, investor sentiment and consumer demand are positive as well. Whether this is a bubble that will burst in the following three to four years or would it be accompanied by correction mechanisms to culminate in long-term growth will largely depend on the actions of financial institutions and governments. Simply put, for all optimists, a V is out of reach now, and a U or swoosh is some reforms away!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">COVID-19 and Economic Policy: From Saving Banks to Saving Businesses</title>
      <link href="/COVID-19-and-Economic-Policy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19 and Economic Policy: From Saving Banks to Saving Businesses" />
      <published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/COVID-19-and-Economic-Policy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/COVID-19-and-Economic-Policy">&lt;p&gt;Though any professional strategist, worth his/her salt, understands that no plan can be executed in its entirety, under any preconceived framework, however, the COVID -19 pandemic rattled the status-quo with such force that everything came to a grinding halt - literally. It neutered any semblance between the factors of the past and the present that influence policy-making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However unpalatable it may seem, the category that serves as one of the biggest pillars of any economy, sometimes simply by the virtue of its existence, is big business. That’s one of the reasons why the primary response that any government undertakes in such a case inevitably includes rushing through legislation that safeguards the existence of strategically selected corporations who can keep the economic juices flowing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking about such corporations - the only masters they serve are the shareholders. A lot of big-money companies try to leverage up as soon as they see an opening so that the maximum benefits go to a select class of shareholders. Though the phenomenon was global, a great pinpointed example would be the second quarter of the Trump presidency in the USA. The economy was booming and a Republican-led legislature had just passed a tax reform bill that slashed corporate tax rates on domestic and international incomes. Owing to all these factors, corporations like AT&amp;amp;T bought back stock and outsourced labour to Asian countries, effectively increasing their financial and operating leverage ratios.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming back to the point stated earlier, COVID struck like an angry bull, which put every leveraged-up corporation in harm's way. Supply chain lock jams and the absence of a physical workforce pushed companies towards defaults, leading to avoidable bankruptcies and undervalued dumping of assets.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help businesses of every scale sail through this hardship, governments of almost every country have reached across-the-aisle agreements on how they can alter the existing rules regarding a company's ability to negotiate its debts. As the Primary Impact of COVID was observed in Asia, Europe and North America, we can analyse the policy changes in India, UK and USA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The United Kingdom&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever corporations renegotiate debt, the creditors can be viewed as the aggrieved party because it, in essence, undermines their interests to ensure that the company is safe. Moreover, minor alterations in any of the affirmative or negative covenants running with the debt can shift the entire power dynamic. Therefore, creditors of all categories are engaged in the process of minimising the possibilities of future disagreements.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new restructuring guidelines ensure that the restructuring negotiations can proceed without the approval of classes of creditors or members who do not have an economic interest in the company. This prevents them from blocking common-sense reform because of motivations not rooted in the wellbeing of the corporation. Also, the requirement that a majority of creditors, of any particular class, must approve a scheme has not been included. The sole requirement is that holders representing 75% of the value of those voting approve the changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the amendments also prevent any supplier to a company from relying on any contractual provision to terminate the supply of goods or services because the company has entered into an insolvency process. A supplier will not be able to block the supply of goods and services on the pretext prior debts have not been satisfied&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;India&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Reserve Bank of India had announced, as a part of its COVID relief measures, guidelines for restructuring of loans up to ₹250 million. The approach was different from the UK's because it lays greater emphasis on institutional debt, effectively adding rung on the ladder.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The policy goal in the UK's case was to relax regulations on the extent and ease with which corporations can restructure debt, while Indian policy aimed at inducing the lending institutions to offer relief within a thin-lined framework and a high degree of discretion in terms of institution-specific suitability. The general framework entailed modification of repayment plans and an increased moratorium period to help alleviate the potential stress. Another important point to mention here is that once restructured, every loan would be considered standard and negotiations could not be reopened. The reconstruction framework was revamped for a second round with minor changes. The policy in India was focused on small scale businesses, which are the backbone of its economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The United States&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a part of various local and federal COVID-19 relief and stimulus bills, the Federal government and the states have implemented several amendments in their restructuring policies. The stark difference, when compared to policies of the UK and India, is the presence of an extensive evaluative framework to classify debt into different categories and sub-categories. By extension, the restructuring framework also differs for individual sub-categories or a basket of sub-categories along with discretion for deciding the rights of parties involved. As a midway point between India and UK, US policies have no fixed target segment and the power dynamic in terms of party rights has to be evaluated on a case-by-case basis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important element is the amortisation of fees/costs, which are also highly variable across loan sub-categories. For example - If a restructured loan is considered a 'new loan', any unamortised net fees or costs, as well as any prepayment penalties from the original loan, would be recognised in interest income when the said the new loan is granted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;America has gone to the greatest length to preserve the integrity of pre-entered contracts between corporations, individuals and government entities at all levels.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The policy toolkit that different countries have adopted to deal with the breakdowns caused by the pandemic has been deeply influenced by their circumstances. But the main takeaway is that the financial services sector has been asked to take a backseat. While in earlier crises, bailing out the big banks was priority number one, now, the systemic priority has been to ensure that employers stay afloat even if the banks have to take the hit for it. Will this bring about a fundamental shift in how we conduct economic policy? That is something only time can tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aryaman Dhiman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Though any professional strategist, worth his/her salt, understands that no plan can be executed in its entirety, under any preconceived framework, however, the COVID -19 pandemic rattled the status-quo with such force that everything came to a grinding halt - literally. It neutered any semblance between the factors of the past and the present that influence policy-making. However unpalatable it may seem, the category that serves as one of the biggest pillars of any economy, sometimes simply by the virtue of its existence, is big business. That’s one of the reasons why the primary response that any government undertakes in such a case inevitably includes rushing through legislation that safeguards the existence of strategically selected corporations who can keep the economic juices flowing.&amp;nbsp; Talking about such corporations - the only masters they serve are the shareholders. A lot of big-money companies try to leverage up as soon as they see an opening so that the maximum benefits go to a select class of shareholders. Though the phenomenon was global, a great pinpointed example would be the second quarter of the Trump presidency in the USA. The economy was booming and a Republican-led legislature had just passed a tax reform bill that slashed corporate tax rates on domestic and international incomes. Owing to all these factors, corporations like AT&amp;amp;T bought back stock and outsourced labour to Asian countries, effectively increasing their financial and operating leverage ratios.&amp;nbsp; Coming back to the point stated earlier, COVID struck like an angry bull, which put every leveraged-up corporation in harm's way. Supply chain lock jams and the absence of a physical workforce pushed companies towards defaults, leading to avoidable bankruptcies and undervalued dumping of assets.&amp;nbsp; To help businesses of every scale sail through this hardship, governments of almost every country have reached across-the-aisle agreements on how they can alter the existing rules regarding a company's ability to negotiate its debts. As the Primary Impact of COVID was observed in Asia, Europe and North America, we can analyse the policy changes in India, UK and USA. The United Kingdom Whenever corporations renegotiate debt, the creditors can be viewed as the aggrieved party because it, in essence, undermines their interests to ensure that the company is safe. Moreover, minor alterations in any of the affirmative or negative covenants running with the debt can shift the entire power dynamic. Therefore, creditors of all categories are engaged in the process of minimising the possibilities of future disagreements.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The new restructuring guidelines ensure that the restructuring negotiations can proceed without the approval of classes of creditors or members who do not have an economic interest in the company. This prevents them from blocking common-sense reform because of motivations not rooted in the wellbeing of the corporation. Also, the requirement that a majority of creditors, of any particular class, must approve a scheme has not been included. The sole requirement is that holders representing 75% of the value of those voting approve the changes. Finally, the amendments also prevent any supplier to a company from relying on any contractual provision to terminate the supply of goods or services because the company has entered into an insolvency process. A supplier will not be able to block the supply of goods and services on the pretext prior debts have not been satisfied India The Reserve Bank of India had announced, as a part of its COVID relief measures, guidelines for restructuring of loans up to ₹250 million. The approach was different from the UK's because it lays greater emphasis on institutional debt, effectively adding rung on the ladder.&amp;nbsp; The policy goal in the UK's case was to relax regulations on the extent and ease with which corporations can restructure debt, while Indian policy aimed at inducing the lending institutions to offer relief within a thin-lined framework and a high degree of discretion in terms of institution-specific suitability. The general framework entailed modification of repayment plans and an increased moratorium period to help alleviate the potential stress. Another important point to mention here is that once restructured, every loan would be considered standard and negotiations could not be reopened. The reconstruction framework was revamped for a second round with minor changes. The policy in India was focused on small scale businesses, which are the backbone of its economy.&amp;nbsp; The United States As a part of various local and federal COVID-19 relief and stimulus bills, the Federal government and the states have implemented several amendments in their restructuring policies. The stark difference, when compared to policies of the UK and India, is the presence of an extensive evaluative framework to classify debt into different categories and sub-categories. By extension, the restructuring framework also differs for individual sub-categories or a basket of sub-categories along with discretion for deciding the rights of parties involved. As a midway point between India and UK, US policies have no fixed target segment and the power dynamic in terms of party rights has to be evaluated on a case-by-case basis.&amp;nbsp; Another important element is the amortisation of fees/costs, which are also highly variable across loan sub-categories. For example - If a restructured loan is considered a 'new loan', any unamortised net fees or costs, as well as any prepayment penalties from the original loan, would be recognised in interest income when the said the new loan is granted. America has gone to the greatest length to preserve the integrity of pre-entered contracts between corporations, individuals and government entities at all levels.&amp;nbsp; The policy toolkit that different countries have adopted to deal with the breakdowns caused by the pandemic has been deeply influenced by their circumstances. But the main takeaway is that the financial services sector has been asked to take a backseat. While in earlier crises, bailing out the big banks was priority number one, now, the systemic priority has been to ensure that employers stay afloat even if the banks have to take the hit for it. Will this bring about a fundamental shift in how we conduct economic policy? That is something only time can tell.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Future of Energy!</title>
      <link href="/The-Future-of-Energy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Future of Energy!" />
      <published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Future-of-Energy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Future-of-Energy">&lt;p&gt;With the latest round of global climate talks coming up in a few weeks, all eyes are set on our world leaders and their stand on the issue. The members of business groups, media, civil society, etc, will gather for the event to express their views and concerns.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The global climate conference will be held in Glasgow, United Kingdom and can be referred to as the COP26 (Conference of the Parties to the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://unfccc.int/process-and-meetings/the-convention/what-is-the-united-nations-framework-convention-on-climate-change&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1992 United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change&lt;/a&gt;). The nations have finally realised the impacts of climate change and the need to counter it.	&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of renewable energy is being promoted across continents in order to cut carbon emissions and hence, decarbonise the planet. At present, the major renewable energy resources are centered around solar, wind and water energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However recently, Green Hydrogen has been making headlines, owed mainly to its ease and efficient mode of production. Unlike coal and oil, it only emits water vapours and with hydrogen being the most abundant element available to us, this gas has the potential to be used across industries. Some observers even dub it as the ‘fuel of the future’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, there are a few challenges which need to be dealt with before this hydrogen produced fuel makes its way to commercial and domestic use. Until now, hydrogen is used as a building block to produce other carbon-neutral synthetic fuels. Use of pure hydrogen as an energy source is a fairly new practice and thus, new infrastructure and technology will be a prerequisite.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's dive in to understand the so-called future of energy!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is green hydrogen and how is it produced?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Green hydrogen is a hydrogen fuel which is formed using renewable resources instead of fossil fuels. The generation of green hydrogen is done through the chemical process of electrolysis. This process separates the hydrogen from oxygen in water with the help of an electric current. It can help in supplying up to 25% of the world’s energy needs. The entire process is sustainable and can help cut carbon emissions by a huge amount.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost of production and other challenges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost of production of green hydrogen is very expensive. In a report published in 2019, the&amp;nbsp;International Energy Agency (IEA)&amp;nbsp;puts the cost of producing green hydrogen at&amp;nbsp;$3-$7.50 per kilo, compared to the production cost of $0.90- $3.20 of steam methane reformation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electrolysers constitute a major proportion of the costs involved and it needs to be cut down in order to make the production process effective. According to the claims of IEA, This will only be possible by 2040.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Storage and transportation of green hydrogen is not an easy task either. It is a highly inflammable gas and requires a lot of space, making steel pipes and welds brittle, and prone to failure. A safe transportation of the gas requires construction of pipelines which would eventually add to the price.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the major uses of green hydrogen?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Green hydrogen is an efficient and sustainable source of energy which makes it an attractive source. It can be applied across various industries, thus making its versatility a lucrative option for big business houses and nations. Issues pertaining to storage and transportation do not impede its acceptance as they are not just exclusive to this fuel alone.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Green hydrogen in the Indian context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India is already working on various sustainable energy projects. It has emerged as the sixth largest producer of wind and solar energy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a developing country, which is yet to fully realise its potential, investing in sustainable energy is a huge dilemma. Nonetheless, the nation has never backed out of protocols and has always supported the steps needed to be taken to curb global emissions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the country’s 75th Independence Day, Prime Minister Narendra Modi announced the government’s vision of making the nation ‘energy independent by 2047’. This goal is a very ambitious target for a country which heavily relies on fossil fuels for its energy requirements.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his speech, he also initiated the National Hydrogen Mission (NHM) to curb global warming, consequently accelerating the country’s pace of embarking on the sustainable journey. The Ministry of New and Renewable Energy has been undertaking&amp;nbsp; research &amp;amp; developmental programmes on the sustainable future including hydrogen fuels. Additionally, the country has collaborated with Norway to manufacture India-centric technology for green hydrogen production.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Kerry, the US presidential envoy for climate, in his visit to India in September 2021, also launched the Climate Action and Finance Mobilisation Dialogue (CAFMD) under India-US Climate Clean Energy Agenda 2030.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the main objectives of CAFMD is finance mobilisation which would focus on attracting capital and technologies for India to scale up its renewable energy generation capacities. The US envoy said, ”&lt;em&gt;Over the past months, six of the largest banks in America had publicly committed to investing a minimum of $4.16 trillion in the next 10 years to make the transition happen&lt;/em&gt;”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nations such as Germany are extending financial help outside their region for investment in sustainable projects, particularly relating to green hydrogen.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, China is the largest producer of green hydrogen with an output of 20 million ton. The European Union is also following the same steps by investing heavily in this fuel. Their extensive network of underground pipelines and storage facilities would enable them to store and even have the potential to transport green hydrogen across the continent. This can act to their advantage by allowing them to dominate the green hydrogen market in the near future. Oil rich nations such as Oman and Saudi Arabia are also proceeding in this direction.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first quarter of 2021-22, Mukesh Ambani, the chairman of the largest company of the country - Reliance Industries, unveiled the company's push into green energy by committing to invest $10.1 billion in the sector by 2024. This investment will involve setting up energy production plants (including those for hydrogen fuels) and building battery grids to store electricity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coal shortage in India in early October 2021 and the consequent fears of power blackouts gives us yet another reason to move to an untapped and unlimited source of sustainable energy. The mass availability and properties of hydrogen seems to be the perfect alternative for most of our energy needs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every nation is on the move to decarbonise, and is looking for sustainable substitutes for mass production with lower costs. The goal of minimum cost will be achieved in future by means of economies of scale, however at present, it is essential to make the investments with new and appropriate infrastructure and technology. This will require time and consistent efforts but the outcome makes it worth the effort.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first major step towards a sustainable planet has been taken and many more are yet to come.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll have to wait till COP26 to find out about the latest green initiatives our world leaders have in store for us, till then let's all make a conscious effort to move towards sustainable habits in day-to-day lives.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">With the latest round of global climate talks coming up in a few weeks, all eyes are set on our world leaders and their stand on the issue. The members of business groups, media, civil society, etc, will gather for the event to express their views and concerns.&amp;nbsp; The global climate conference will be held in Glasgow, United Kingdom and can be referred to as the COP26 (Conference of the Parties to the&amp;nbsp;1992 United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change). The nations have finally realised the impacts of climate change and the need to counter it. The use of renewable energy is being promoted across continents in order to cut carbon emissions and hence, decarbonise the planet. At present, the major renewable energy resources are centered around solar, wind and water energy. However recently, Green Hydrogen has been making headlines, owed mainly to its ease and efficient mode of production. Unlike coal and oil, it only emits water vapours and with hydrogen being the most abundant element available to us, this gas has the potential to be used across industries. Some observers even dub it as the ‘fuel of the future’. Nonetheless, there are a few challenges which need to be dealt with before this hydrogen produced fuel makes its way to commercial and domestic use. Until now, hydrogen is used as a building block to produce other carbon-neutral synthetic fuels. Use of pure hydrogen as an energy source is a fairly new practice and thus, new infrastructure and technology will be a prerequisite.&amp;nbsp; Let's dive in to understand the so-called future of energy!&amp;nbsp; What is green hydrogen and how is it produced? Green hydrogen is a hydrogen fuel which is formed using renewable resources instead of fossil fuels. The generation of green hydrogen is done through the chemical process of electrolysis. This process separates the hydrogen from oxygen in water with the help of an electric current. It can help in supplying up to 25% of the world’s energy needs. The entire process is sustainable and can help cut carbon emissions by a huge amount.&amp;nbsp; Cost of production and other challenges The cost of production of green hydrogen is very expensive. In a report published in 2019, the&amp;nbsp;International Energy Agency (IEA)&amp;nbsp;puts the cost of producing green hydrogen at&amp;nbsp;$3-$7.50 per kilo, compared to the production cost of $0.90- $3.20 of steam methane reformation.&amp;nbsp; Electrolysers constitute a major proportion of the costs involved and it needs to be cut down in order to make the production process effective. According to the claims of IEA, This will only be possible by 2040.&amp;nbsp; Storage and transportation of green hydrogen is not an easy task either. It is a highly inflammable gas and requires a lot of space, making steel pipes and welds brittle, and prone to failure. A safe transportation of the gas requires construction of pipelines which would eventually add to the price.&amp;nbsp; What are the major uses of green hydrogen? Green hydrogen is an efficient and sustainable source of energy which makes it an attractive source. It can be applied across various industries, thus making its versatility a lucrative option for big business houses and nations. Issues pertaining to storage and transportation do not impede its acceptance as they are not just exclusive to this fuel alone.&amp;nbsp; Green hydrogen in the Indian context India is already working on various sustainable energy projects. It has emerged as the sixth largest producer of wind and solar energy.&amp;nbsp; For a developing country, which is yet to fully realise its potential, investing in sustainable energy is a huge dilemma. Nonetheless, the nation has never backed out of protocols and has always supported the steps needed to be taken to curb global emissions.&amp;nbsp; On the country’s 75th Independence Day, Prime Minister Narendra Modi announced the government’s vision of making the nation ‘energy independent by 2047’. This goal is a very ambitious target for a country which heavily relies on fossil fuels for its energy requirements.&amp;nbsp; In his speech, he also initiated the National Hydrogen Mission (NHM) to curb global warming, consequently accelerating the country’s pace of embarking on the sustainable journey. The Ministry of New and Renewable Energy has been undertaking&amp;nbsp; research &amp;amp; developmental programmes on the sustainable future including hydrogen fuels. Additionally, the country has collaborated with Norway to manufacture India-centric technology for green hydrogen production.&amp;nbsp; John Kerry, the US presidential envoy for climate, in his visit to India in September 2021, also launched the Climate Action and Finance Mobilisation Dialogue (CAFMD) under India-US Climate Clean Energy Agenda 2030.&amp;nbsp; One of the main objectives of CAFMD is finance mobilisation which would focus on attracting capital and technologies for India to scale up its renewable energy generation capacities. The US envoy said, ”Over the past months, six of the largest banks in America had publicly committed to investing a minimum of $4.16 trillion in the next 10 years to make the transition happen”.&amp;nbsp; Nations such as Germany are extending financial help outside their region for investment in sustainable projects, particularly relating to green hydrogen.&amp;nbsp; Currently, China is the largest producer of green hydrogen with an output of 20 million ton. The European Union is also following the same steps by investing heavily in this fuel. Their extensive network of underground pipelines and storage facilities would enable them to store and even have the potential to transport green hydrogen across the continent. This can act to their advantage by allowing them to dominate the green hydrogen market in the near future. Oil rich nations such as Oman and Saudi Arabia are also proceeding in this direction.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; In the first quarter of 2021-22, Mukesh Ambani, the chairman of the largest company of the country - Reliance Industries, unveiled the company's push into green energy by committing to invest $10.1 billion in the sector by 2024. This investment will involve setting up energy production plants (including those for hydrogen fuels) and building battery grids to store electricity.&amp;nbsp; The coal shortage in India in early October 2021 and the consequent fears of power blackouts gives us yet another reason to move to an untapped and unlimited source of sustainable energy. The mass availability and properties of hydrogen seems to be the perfect alternative for most of our energy needs.&amp;nbsp; Every nation is on the move to decarbonise, and is looking for sustainable substitutes for mass production with lower costs. The goal of minimum cost will be achieved in future by means of economies of scale, however at present, it is essential to make the investments with new and appropriate infrastructure and technology. This will require time and consistent efforts but the outcome makes it worth the effort.&amp;nbsp; The first major step towards a sustainable planet has been taken and many more are yet to come.&amp;nbsp; We’ll have to wait till COP26 to find out about the latest green initiatives our world leaders have in store for us, till then let's all make a conscious effort to move towards sustainable habits in day-to-day lives.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
