<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/economics/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-06-05T12:57:15+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/economics/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Having Kids? Well, What’s in it for Me?</title>
      <link href="/Having-Kids-Whats-in-it-for-Me" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Having Kids? Well, What’s in it for Me?" />
      <published>2020-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Having-Kids-Whats-in-it-for-Me</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Having-Kids-Whats-in-it-for-Me">&lt;p&gt;Since time immemorial, parents have struggled with the question of the optimum number of children they should have. Well, everything is driven by incentives: we offer an economic perspective on happiness, nature, and nurturing as we analyse the marginal cost of a child against its benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The birth of a child is considered a moment of unbound joy and is believed to provide families with a wholesome experience. What follows next is a series of sleepless nights, great anxiety, and several &lt;em&gt;potty&lt;/em&gt; training sessions. Raising a child in today’s world is no piece of cake, be it in terms of personal devotion, child-care responsibilities or financial needs. Families, rich and poor alike, face their own set of challenges with respect to the same. Putting this into perspective, these issues arising from varied aspects add up to one big question: what is in it for the parents? Let alone going through the process more than once, is it all truly worth it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raising this question, we believe children born in different set-ups, in terms of beliefs and economic backing, add varied sorts of value to the particular household. A family belonging to the lower-income group generally believes that having a larger number of children means more hands to work in the field or otherwise, completely negating the cost of actually raising these children. For those poor, rural families, children are not only seen as an economic asset but also as an insurance policy for old age, especially in societies with zero state pension and health care. However, we observe that as the income of a family increases, the smaller the family is, i.e. they prefer to have fewer children. With rising incomes, families don’t need their children to be an economic asset; the family can afford for their children to be an economic liability. Furthermore, people with a superior economic standing believe in providing better education and lifestyle to their children. Hence, while, children in impoverished communities contribute to their family income, children in the developed world subtract from family finances through the cost of their education and upbringing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can also be measured by weighing the marginal cost against the marginal utility of procreating. The marginal cost and utility, incurred and reaped respectively, largely depend upon the budget constraint of each household. Hence, so does the optimum number of children. This brings us to the conclusion that there is a negative correlation between family income and family size which further leads to a trade-off between the quantity and the quality of children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the idea that having a higher number of children reduces the cost of raising each additional child; in short, highlighting diminishing marginal cost. The reason behind this is that most of the necessary child raising equipment- like high chairs, cribs, and clothes - can be passed onto the next child, and no additional money is required to be spent on the same. Moreover, with many family and parent-child health insurance plans, the monthly premium remains the same, irrespective of the number of children. This points to a lower cost per person. Additionally, there are several universities in the States that provide various benefits to families with more than one child. Therefore, it could so happen that due to these benefits the cost per unit of putting ten children through college could be less than that of putting one. Who says houses cannot be run on economies of scale?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irrespective of the economies of scale, there are substantial costs that remain fixed: a large number of children leads to the dilution of parental resources- financial as well as time. These fixed costs include expenses on food, healthcare, and basic clothes for lower-income groups. Similarly, the fixed costs of higher-income groups are much larger as they involve education, and extra-curricular activities amongst others. Moreover, these children also give their parents a fair share of headaches. Being anxious about everything pertaining to their children forms a crucial part of a parent’s identity. This leads us to another opportunity cost which is the personal freedom of these caregivers. This causes the parents to juggle between giving time to their children and finding time for themselves and their work. Therefore, as the number of children increases, there is a marked drop in the time spent with each child. Many of them might grow up feeling neglected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like identified in the foregoing paragraphs, the utility and benefits that the parents reap from their children can be seen in the form of economic and old-age support. However, it is also important to realise that as the number of children that a couple has increases, there is a decline in the marginal utility. This is because, with each additional child, there is a decreasing extra satisfaction that the couple will gain. This can be seen in the way that if a couple has 5 children then they will receive more satisfaction with their firstborn than they did from their last born (5th child in this case). Hence, as the number of children a couple has increases, the law of diminishing returns starts to hold true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, what is truly in it for the parents purely depends upon the type of income groups that they belong to. Thus, regardless of whether couples want children for personal attachment or joy, it all eventually boils down to the economic cost and utility of having one!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>kabir.kochar sanya.puri</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Since time immemorial, parents have struggled with the question of the optimum number of children they should have. Well, everything is driven by incentives: we offer an economic perspective on happiness, nature, and nurturing as we analyse the marginal cost of a child against its benefit.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">European Central Bank: The Saviour of Europe?</title>
      <link href="/European-Central-Bank" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="European Central Bank: The Saviour of Europe?" />
      <published>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/European-Central-Bank</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/European-Central-Bank">&lt;p&gt;Time and again, Ms Lagarde, the first President of the European Central Bank (ECB) warned the European Union (EU) governments against the COVID-19 pandemic turning into a calamity. The pressures have been mounting as the largest economies of the Eurozone like France and Italy crumble. The EU, one of the world’s largest economies, has decided to take certain measures via its monetary policy, however, the question is how much can the ECB afford?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms Lagarde, however, is of the view that monetary policy is not the first line of defence and feels that fiscal response must be given much more importance. The persistent heterogeneity in the Euro area has also been a long-standing concern for the single monetary policy. It severely complicates the conduct of this policy. The current crisis exposed these vulnerabilities, once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since 2008, the EU has been in a non-stop crisis mode. Even the interest rate it charges to the commercial banks is almost nil leaving very little margin for further rate cuts to stimulate the economy out of this rut. The ECB has acknowledged how they are facing an unprecedented crisis with historic consequences which might just push the European economy to worse than what it was in 2008. If the crisis is not controlled by the stimuli, it risks pushing the already wobbly European economy to the state of recession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 16, the ECB went ahead and announced the measures it will be taking on the monetary policy front while it gives time to the respective governments to formulate fiscal policy measures. The ECB took certain measures to prevent the crisis from becoming a full-blown financial crisis with two broad objectives: first, to restore the orderly functioning of presently volatile European financial markets, and second, to ensure that the accommodative monetary policy measures support firms and households in incurring the social and economic costs of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ECB response consists of three major mutually reinforcing grounds. The first one relating to broad-based asset purchases to address illiquidity and volatility in core segments of the European economy. The temporary Pandemic Emergency Purchase Programme (PEPP) constitutes the core of this component. The economies in the entire Eurozone have been struggling with tightening fiscal and economic conditions, the PEPP expects to release the pressure on these economies. It foresees purchases at a volume of €750 billion of eligible private and public securities throughout this year, and longer if needed.  The ECB also aims to mitigate the impact of the crisis on the funding conditions of businesses and banks. For the same, it has decided to divert a considerable fraction of the additional €120 billion purchase envelope under the Asset Purchase Programmes (APP), as well as of the PEPP, for eligible private sector bonds. However, one cannot turn a blind eye to the fact that the bank has already been conducting purchases of government bonds, and now, it does not have much to re-purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, measures to ensure that the banks remain effective carriers of the monetary policy of the ECB have been introduced. The enhanced Targeted Longer-Term Refinancing Operations (TLTROs), as well as a comprehensive set of collateral easing measures, form part of this component.  The interest rate on all targeted TLTROs was reduced by 25 basis points to -0.5% from June 2020 to June 2021. Measures to ensure the solvency of banks by holding up the role of lender of the last resort to the banks which will help the ECB drive the way for economic growth. This becomes all the more necessary considering that the European economy is majorly a bank-based economy than a financial market one, so just supporting the financial markets would not help alleviate the effects of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measures for small and medium-sized firms are equally necessary, which include bank lending and loan guarantee schemes to protect the already overdrawn credit lines by cash strapped firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Italy, for example, bank lending conditions for firms remained remarkably resilient in recent years despite significant swings in market-based funding conditions of the banks and firms. Again, the measures can provide a valuable bridge to the future and help keep aggregate external funding costs of firms stable until the economy recovers and uncertainty diminishes further. This also includes accepting a wider range of assets as collaterals from small and medium-sized firms along with consistently working on the liquidity conditions of the banks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the ECB fails to improve liquidity indirectly through these measures, it always has the option to exercise its right to issue ‘helicopter money’. This alternative would put the money straight into the ‘hands’ of the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through these measures, the ECB hopes to improve liquidity and market behaviour in the sovereign yield bonds market, which in turn form the basis of pricing of assets in the economy. The ECB uses the GDP-weighted Euro area government bond yield curve as a measure for the effectiveness of the economy, but currently, this curve has been badly disrupted. So the ECB will focus on stabilising this curve and reversing the steepness of the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, while the Eurozone faces an increasingly threatening risk of a slowdown in the economy, which can take years to recover from and get back to the normal levels, the ECB and various governments are taking steps to tackle this challenge. The cluster of countries has recovered from far worse situations in the past, like the global economic crisis of 2008, and emerged stronger than ever. It remains to be seen what other steps the European Union takes as a much worse crisis than COVID-19 awaits the global economy and how the relief package unravels for the Union.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kashish Jindal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Time and again, Ms Lagarde, the first President of the European Central Bank (ECB) warned the European Union (EU) governments against the COVID-19 pandemic turning into a calamity. The pressures have been mounting as the largest economies of the Eurozone like France and Italy crumble. The EU, one of the world’s largest economies, has decided to take certain measures via its monetary policy, however, the question is how much can the ECB afford?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Can Self-Reliance be the New Norm: A Take on India’s ‘Atma-nirbharata’</title>
      <link href="/Can-Self-Reliance-be-the-New-Norm" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can Self-Reliance be the New Norm: A Take on India’s ‘Atma-nirbharata’" />
      <published>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Can-Self-Reliance-be-the-New-Norm</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Can-Self-Reliance-be-the-New-Norm">&lt;p&gt;“To stand on one’s own feet” is how 10th-grade economics teachers sum up the concept of self-reliance. The thinking behind India’s advocacy for this concept is premised upon the scars of colonialism. However, with the liberalisation of the Indian economy by the Narasimha Rao-led government, the concept had practically faded away from Indian public policy discourse. 29 years later, with Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi calling upon Indians to ‘be vocal for local’ and emphasising self-reliance, it seems to be taking the centre-stage once again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-reliance can be defined as “dependence on one’s own natural resources to produce goods and services to satisfy the demand”. One of the many problems with this is that every economy faces a dearth of resources, which are inputs required to produce goods (and services). One rather famous quip in economics goes like this: ‘resources are limited, while [human] wants are unlimited’. Every nation cannot produce everything on a scale sufficient to meet its domestic demand. Even if we suppose, for argument’s sake, that we could achieve the impossible, it is important to realise that self-reliance is a dynamic concept. If you look at it, achieving self-reliance is to successfully meet the aggregate demand of all the people in an economy; that is, conforming production along the lines of consumers’ tastes and preferences. There is no guarantee that these tastes will remain constant (unless, of course, if states ‘determine’ tastes!). So, if one were to adhere to the definition of self-reliance, one ought to change production constantly, keeping pace with the change in tastes and demands of the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, the scarcity of resources prompts states to resort to protectionist measures so as to encourage local producers. There is no ruling-out of a misallocation of resources in such circumstances, due to lack of economies of scale (a resultant of protectionist policies). This leads to a drastic loss in the productivity of a country and results in a deadweight loss for society. To put this in perspective, let us look at the total factor productivity of India. Total Factor Production may be defined as the increase in the growth of output that can be attributed to factors other than capital and labour. This can be the result of many reasons including a change in the quality of inputs, new techniques of production, better management of resources, and so on. One study finds that the average total factor productivity growth was negative for the 1970’s, when protectionism was at its heyday. In fact, there were frequent instances of negative growth in total factor production (where total factor production fell below zero) before 1991. Only after reforms, did the metric pick up pace, remaining positive throughout. From 2001-2008, total factor production grew at an average of 3.36%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second impact of protectionist measures is that the cost of production is (relatively) high and results in higher prices for the consumers. Why should a government, in the name of self-sufficiency, let its consumers pay a higher price for a good that would be available for a cheaper price when imported? This certainly is not how a rational entity would (or should) behave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The definition of self-reliance also begs the question of who is to determine the scale and intensity of production to achieve this self-reliance and how is this to be determined. If history is any guide, this is often determined by the state. And this means curtailing of choices on the part of the consumer and a massive involvement of the government in the supply side or the production side. It implies that the allocation of resources is controlled by the government and every producer (or entrepreneur) relies heavily on the government to take any decision. This control is exercised by the way of issuing licenses. The infamously dubbed practice of ‘license raj’ is exactly this. This can also discourage potential entrepreneurs from coming forward to start a business. Accepting this excessive government control would mean that bureaucrats, with no experience in business management whatsoever, would run the businesses rather than people competent to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidently, this is not the type of self-reliance a country should be aiming for. A country should be aiming at self-reliance in terms of human capital. In today’s global world, ideas and innovation are what sets a country apart. As renowned economist and Nobel laureate Paul Romer said, “&lt;em&gt;Growth springs from better recipes, not just from better cooking&lt;/em&gt;”. His view was that ideas of non-rival character, generated by profit-maximising entrepreneurs will lead to economic growth. This emphasises the role of human capital in the course of economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, for many reasons, there has been a constant outflow of human capital from our country to advanced nations like the US and the UK. It is crucial for India to recognise that every emigrant is productivity lost and innovation foregone. So, when I say self-reliance on human capital, I mean the creation of institutions of the highest excellence to truly harness human capital. However, the disappointing budget allocation for education by the Indian government (4.6% of the GDP in 2019-2020) shows that it has no plans to improve in this specific sector. India ought to increase education spending and allocate (and disburse) more funds toward PhD research, which are now sparse and available mainly for technology courses. Only self-reliance in terms of human capital is sustaining and yields increasing returns and hence should be a priority for the government. This is important to arrest the outflow of human capital out of the country whether for studies or permanent migration.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“To stand on one’s own feet” is how 10th-grade economics teachers sum up the concept of self-reliance. The thinking behind India’s advocacy for this concept is premised upon the scars of colonialism. However, with the liberalisation of the Indian economy by the Narasimha Rao-led government, the concept had practically faded away from Indian public policy discourse. 29 years later, with Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi calling upon Indians to ‘be vocal for local’ and emphasising self-reliance, it seems to be taking the centre-stage once again.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">China’s Banking Assets: A Recipe for Financial Crisis</title>
      <link href="/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="China’s Banking Assets: A Recipe for Financial Crisis" />
      <published>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis">&lt;p&gt;The global economy finds itself in a synchronised slowdown, with growth downgraded to as low as 3% in 2019, the lowest since the Global Financial Crisis. Adding to the economic tensions is COVID-19, which has brought the world economies to a near shutdown phase as they adopt preventive measures inclusive of complete lockdowns. What is more concerning is the fact that the two major engines of global growth, the United States of America and China, are the worst hit among many others. What makes the economic crisis worse in China? It is the worsening predicament of the banking sector which becomes a matter of immediate concern as China’s banking sector is three times larger than the size of its entire economy. The gigantic Chinese banking sector is capable of dwarfing out banking sectors in other parts of the world, including that of the United States of America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2019 China Financial Stability Report published by the People’s Bank of China officially deems 586 out of 4,379 Chinese lenders to be ‘high-risk’. The figures came into light only after the failure of a third bank within three months as national economic growth manifested a 30-year low. The Hengfeng Bank has become the third bank, after Baoshang Bank and Bank of Jinzhou, to suffer an economic collapse after a $40 trillion debt. But the Chinese government isn’t exceedingly famous for its honesty and transparency, thus the reported figure is likely masking the true extent of the banking quandary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chinese government has bailed out many of the high risk lenders. Precarious private shareholders have been effectively replaced by the ones backed by the state, often weaker in terms of their finances. The fact that bailouts are offered only for companies whose bankruptcy has a grave adverse impact on the economy as a whole and not just on a specified sector, cannot be ignored. Moreover, any amount of bailout allocated to this sector will have a domino effect on the Chinese economy which will be several times greater. For instance, the banking system calls for a 5-6% bailout which is equal to 20-24% of the Chinese GDP. A bailout of 20% of the GDP is a non-viable deal for any economy, even if it is China. The numeric is a statement of the fact that any pebble aimed at the banking sector shall bring ripples to the entire economy that in turn will shake China’s status of being a global economic power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The People’s Bank of China conducted a stress test in the first half of 2019 on 1,171 commercial banks, 7.7% were stated to be at ‘extreme risk’ and deemed incapable of absorbing even a light shock, 13.6% will probably not be able to endure the financial crisis that shall follow. In November, Yingkou Coastal Bank and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scmp.com/economy/china-economy/article/3035596/wechat-rumour-sparks-run-rural-chinese-bank-fresh-sign&quot;&gt;Yichuan Rural Commercial Bank&lt;/a&gt; – despite boasting healthy capital adequacy ratios – suffered bank runs as customers rushed to withdraw cash, fearing that the banks would close down, displaying a lack of confidence in banking institutions. The current situation is very similar to the one that cropped up in the late 1990’s. Towards the end of 1997, 20% of the main banks were non-performing, which was equivalent to a value of ¥1.19 trillion on the books of state-owned banks, which was deemed to be equal to 15.6% of the GDP. In order to resolve these crises and recapitalise the banks, ¥270 billion of special government bonds were issued and injected by August 1998. Walking on the same rope, the Chinese government is peddling its way through the crisis by adopting a somewhat similar technique. Today, the interbank market has been injected with around ¥2 trillion by the People’s Bank of China after the Baoshang Bank collapse. Along with this, a helping hand of the sovereign fund, China Investment Corporation, the Central Huijin Investment Company is injecting ¥60 billion into Hengfeng Bank. One of the 12 nationwide joint-stock banks in China, Hengfeng Bank is stacked up with non-performing loans and the situation became grimmer as the bank’s former president was handed out a death sentence for purloining funds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the similarities, overlooking the different macroeconomic situation shall prove fatal to the Chinese economy in the present scenario. The key antidote for the crisis back then was the spurt of hyper economic growth in the early 2000’s. If China wants to avoid tormenting its economy with the inevitability of bad loans and its weakening banking structure, it will have to aim for a masterful economic growth. However, this stands as a challenge with the outbreak of COVID-19 and its likely aftermath on the global economy. Secondly, continuous evolution over the years has resulted in an entwined and fragile banking structure. The financial system in modern times has given rise to an integrated market that ensures banking transactions are speeded up and are facile in nature. Since the speed of transactions and their impact on the economy is brisk, it also means that any kind of shock in the structure is transmitted faster than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The corporate and interbank customers suffer heavy losses, the volume of negotiable certificates of deposit—which are securities traded between financial institutions for short-term liquidity—has plunged by 90%. The situation threatens to cause the entire banking system to seize up as small and medium-sized banks are heavily dependent on liquidity in the interbank market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crisis should be an eye-opener for the administration as it calls for reforms in the entire financial system which has been overreliant on its banking sector for channeling funds. The fact that the financial structure has changed barely in the last fourteen years is an explanation for the crisis at hand. The world continues to keep a close watch on China, as this crisis is far too big to ignore because any large scale disruption in the driving engine of the global economy will lead the other economies into recession.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The global economy finds itself in a synchronised slowdown, with growth downgraded to as low as 3% in 2019, the lowest since the Global Financial Crisis. Adding to the economic tensions is COVID-19, which has brought the world economies to a near shutdown phase as they adopt preventive measures inclusive of complete lockdowns. What is more concerning is the fact that the two major engines of global growth, the United States of America and China, are the worst hit among many others. What makes the economic crisis worse in China? It is the worsening predicament of the banking sector which becomes a matter of immediate concern as China’s banking sector is three times larger than the size of its entire economy. The gigantic Chinese banking sector is capable of dwarfing out banking sectors in other parts of the world, including that of the United States of America.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Know Your Worth</title>
      <link href="/Know-Your-Worth" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Know Your Worth" />
      <published>2020-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Know-Your-Worth</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Know-Your-Worth">&lt;p&gt;I wonder sometimes whether people, in their daily lives, ponder over the functionalities that help us exist as citizens. How does the worth of my country depend on my income? I place my faith in the system to consider how various decisions will affect me before assessing the country’s human capital or even formulating the annual budget. And when I place my faith in the system, I am also hopeful of the judicial system to come to my rescue if I am faced with injustice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But how do I know if the details of my income or personal life will be taken into account when I am standing in the court of law?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is when ‘Forensic Economics’ comes into play. Conceived as economics applied to legal matters, forensic economics assesses major issues regarding economic damages in the context of litigation. It is a broad discipline that applies economic theories and methods to matters which are subject to legal review. A forensic economist creates an alternative world with assumptions, wherein the particular citizen is not faced with injustice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand better where Forensic Economics can be applied in a citizen’s daily life, we will use the most widely accepted defining factor of an individual’s life, that is, ‘work’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worth of a citizen, economically, can be found out by measuring his/her human capital. In order to measure that, one is required to estimate the work-life expectancy of an individual. Now the question is: &lt;em&gt;What is work-life expectancy?&lt;/em&gt; As the word itself suggests, it is the number of years an individual is expected to be in the workforce. The factors that affect each individual’s work-life expectancy include education attained, race, marital status, parental status, and, most importantly, gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economists resort to the approach of Forensic Economics to be able to measure an individual’s work-life expectancy, which is contingent on the underlying factors of the individual’s personal life. Under this, they establish the fact that work is not restricted to being involved in only paid employment, but also unpaid non-market work, which also holds certain economic value, thereby, defining ‘total work-life expectancy’ as a sum of market work and non-market work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us establish two imaginary individuals to make our observation simpler: Sheila, a woman, and Joel, a man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gender as a factor of their ‘total work-life expectancy’&lt;/em&gt;: The idea that taking care of a household or family is actual work is uncontested and women lead men in that activity. Many times the reason people usually cite for not participating in market work is taking care of household or family. Let’s consider here that both Joel and Sheila are between the ages of 18 to 24. Using the approach of forensic economics, it is found out that the maximum number of men who take care of their households belong to the age group of 18 to 24. However, as we start moving up the total percentage of men participating in non-market work reduces. On the contrary, the percentage of women participating in non-market work starts rising from 18 to 24 and reaches its peak in the age group of 30 to 34, after which it starts to decline. Therefore, a 25-year-old Joel would have about 35 years of market work-life and 1 year of non-market work-life remaining, whereas a 25-year-old Sheila would have about 30 years of market work-life and 6 years of non-market work-life. Both their ‘total work-life expectancy’ would equal 36 years but the difference lies in the market and non-market work based on their gender. This conclusion has been drawn from the Markov Increment Decrement Model (MID).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Race, education, and marriage as factors of their ‘total work-life expectancy’&lt;/em&gt;: The factors of race, education, and marital status of an individual are inherently intertwined in determining his/her work-life expectancy. Let us assume that Sheila is a 30-year-old white woman and X is a non-white woman. If both, Sheila and X, have educational qualifications of less than a high school degree then, Sheila’s work-life expectancy will exceed that of X by only a year. Conversely, if both Sheila and X are employed and have high school degrees, the work-life expectancy of Sheila will exceed that of X by over two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if we consider Joel to be a 30-year-old white man and Y to be a non-white man, we get different results. If both, Joel and Y, have educational qualifications of less than a high school degree, they get the same result as Sheila and X. However, if Joel and Y (both single) have high school degrees, then the work-life expectancy for Joel exceeds that of Y by around 4 years; and by 3.5 years if both men were married. This acute difference between white and non-white men is essentially because men tend to face more discrimination on the basis of their race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There exists a negative relationship between marriage and the work-life expectancy of women. Generally, women of all races face a setback in their market work participation post-marriage. Women with higher degrees face a larger setback than those with lower or no degree at all. This is largely because of two reasons– (a) women tend to be more productive in non-market or household work, and (b) women have a lesser dilemma to face in terms of opportunity cost because women already get lesser pay in comparison to their male counterparts. This leads me to establish the fact that the relationship between marriage and work-life expectancy for men is essentially positive. The work-life expectancy of a married white man exceeds that of an unmarried white man by about 3 years, and a married non-white man has a work-life expectancy of about 4 years more than an unmarried non-white man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Parental status as a factor of their ‘total work-life expectancy’&lt;/em&gt;: Let us suppose that Sheila wants to bear a child, but she also wants to keep her work-life expectancy high. To achieve that, she turns to Forensic Economics and realises that the work-life expectancy of a single mother exceeds that of a married mother by 2-3 years. On the contrary, Joel realises that a married man’s work-life expectancy changes negligibly in the case of a child but changes considerably if he chooses to be a single father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having analysed the most basic underlying factors to the work-life expectancy of individuals, it is imperative to establish the fact that the aforementioned observations were made using the Markov Increment Decrement Model (MID) under Forensic Economics. This brings us to the conclusion that when the productivity of non-market work is recognised, the work-life expectancy of women is negligibly different than that of men, which busts the myth that men are more productive than women. Therefore, we come to where we started off: the worth of a citizen is measured only after taking into account what I, as an individual citizen, possess with regard to my personal life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And hence, the deliberation ends.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I wonder sometimes whether people, in their daily lives, ponder over the functionalities that help us exist as citizens. How does the worth of my country depend on my income? I place my faith in the system to consider how various decisions will affect me before assessing the country’s human capital or even formulating the annual budget. And when I place my faith in the system, I am also hopeful of the judicial system to come to my rescue if I am faced with injustice.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Rational Pirates</title>
      <link href="/The-Rational-Pirates" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rational Pirates" />
      <published>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Rational-Pirates</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Rational-Pirates">&lt;p&gt;So today while watching videos on YouTube, (which is what I am usually doing almost every second while I am not busy) I came across a brilliant riddle. I clicked on the video and found out that it involved game theory and behavioural economics, and that really fascinated me. I wanted to share the riddle with you, and try to explain and help you better understand the concept of game theory. First of all, you need to know what game theory actually means. Simply kept, game theory is a theoretical structure for understanding social situations among competing players. In some respects, game theory is the science of ‘strategic play’, or at least the optimal decision-making of competing players in a situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I would like to share the riddle with you and try to explain the solution and how game theory can help us in various situations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a good day to be a pirate. Andrew and his 4 mates, Brandon, Christian, David and Edmund have struck gold, a chest with 100 coins. But now, they must divide up the treasure according to the pirate code. The code is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the captain, Andrew gets to propose first about how to distribute the coins. Then, each pirate including Andrew himself gets to vote either ‘yes’ or ‘no’. If the vote passes, or if there is a tie, the coins are divided according to the plan proposed by Andrew, but if the majority votes ‘no’, Andrew must walk the plank into the deep sea and Brandon becomes the captain. Then, Brandon gets to propose a new distribution and all remaining pirates would vote again. If his plan is rejected, he walks the plank too and Christian takes his place. This process repeats with the captain’s hat moving to David and then to Edmund until either a proposal is accepted or there is only one pirate left.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each pirate’s primary objective is to stay alive while getting as much gold as possible. But since they are pirates, none of them trust each other so they can’t really collaborate in advance.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If anyone thinks they will end up with the same amount of gold in two different scenarios, they will vote to make the captain walk the plank just for fun.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, each pirate is excellent at logical thinking and knows that the other pirates are too.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question here is, what distribution should Andrew propose to make sure he lives and gets as much gold as possible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we follow our intuition, it seems like Andrew should try to bribe other pirates with most of the gold to increase the chances of his plan being accepted or maybe to propose a distribution like 40-30-20-10-0 or any other combination for that matter and hope for the best, but it turns out Andrew can do much better than that. Let’s have a look at the solution!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like you know, the pirates know each other to be top-notch logicians. So, when each one votes, they won’t just be thinking about the current proposal but about all the possible outcomes down the line. Moreover, because the rank order is known in advance, each one of them can accurately predict how others would vote in any situation and adjust their own votes accordingly. Since Edmund is last, he has the most outcomes to consider so let us start by following his thought process. He would reason out by working backward from the last possible scenario with only him and David remaining. David would obviously propose to keep all the gold and Edmund’s one vote would not be enough to override it. So, Edmund wants to avoid this situation at all costs. Now, we move to the previous decision point with three pirates left and Christian making the proposal. Everyone knows that if he is outvoted, the decision shifts to David who would then get all the gold while Edmund gets nothing. So to secure Edmund’s vote, Christian only needs to offer slightly more than nothing, that is, one coin. Since this ensures his support, Christian doesn’t need to offer David anything at all. What if there were 4 pirates? As captain, Brandon would still only need one other vote for his plan to pass. He knows that David wouldn’t want the decision to pass to Christian so he would offer David one coin for his support with nothing for Christian or Edmund. Going forward with other possible scenarios, now we’re back at the initial vote with all 5 pirates standing. Having considered all the other scenarios, Andrew knows that if he goes overboard, the decision comes down to Brandon which would be bad news for Christian and Edmund, so he offers one coin each to them, thus, keeping 98 for himself. Brandon and David vote ‘no’, but Christian and Edmund grudgingly vote ‘yes’, knowing that the alternative would be worse for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pirate game involves some amusing concepts from game theory. One is the concept of ‘common knowledge’ where each person is aware of what the others know and uses this to predict their reasoning and final distribution. Had it been the case where the pirates didn’t know the intellectual capabilities of each other, the situation would flip altogether and there would have been no accurate solution to the riddle but fortunately that wasn’t the case. This is a classic example of ‘Nash-equilibrium’, where each player knows every other player’s strategy and chooses them accordingly. Even though it may lead to a worse outcome for everyone than cooperating would, no individual player can benefit by changing their strategy. So, it seems like Andrew gets to keep most of the gold coins (98 to be precise) and the other pirates might need to find better ways to use those impressive logic skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole intention behind this article was to explain to you how a simple concept of game theory can help you gain more in life. The example here was not an appropriate one for you to relate to in real life (unless you obviously decide to become a pirate) but there are several other instances in which it might help you. The decision involving whether to go for a movie or a concert with your friends also involves game theory where we know what the other person wants and we try to manipulate the final result so as to do what we want. Also, in financial markets, the decision to invest in a certain bond or a stock after having all the relevant information about the company involves game theory as well. By investing in the company, you become a player and what the company does with that investment determines your gain or loss. These are just some cases where you can utilise game theory, the scope of it is wide-ranging and unexplored, and left for you to discover. As the British writer Charles Lamb rightly said, “Man is a gaming animal. He must always be trying to get better in something or other.”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">So today while watching videos on YouTube, (which is what I am usually doing almost every second while I am not busy) I came across a brilliant riddle. I clicked on the video and found out that it involved game theory and behavioural economics, and that really fascinated me. I wanted to share the riddle with you, and try to explain and help you better understand the concept of game theory. First of all, you need to know what game theory actually means. Simply kept, game theory is a theoretical structure for understanding social situations among competing players. In some respects, game theory is the science of ‘strategic play’, or at least the optimal decision-making of competing players in a situation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Economy Incarcerated</title>
      <link href="/Economy-Incarcerated" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Economy Incarcerated" />
      <published>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Economy-Incarcerated</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Economy-Incarcerated">&lt;p&gt;Prison, jail, penitentiary are all the same things. They are meant for the mental reform of a person convicted of criminal activities. However, sometimes they can even enhance the business acumen of a person. They are supposed to have very limited trade and economic activity. In such a world, the only way one could earn is through working official chores assigned by the prison and the only place to spend is the official commissary, or a canteen, extant in the jail premises. However, more often than not, the prisoners trade informally themselves. Goods are smuggled in and a variety of services are offered by the prisoners with skills. Such an informal or underground economy is a common sight in prisons, especially in prisons with people serving quite longer sentences. This article is an attempt to explain why informal economies spring up and how they are operated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many reasons why an informal economy springs up. Often the demand of the prisoners is not satisfied by the officials or the prison canteen. An exhaustive list of things that are trivial to the ‘free people’ and are taken for granted are luxuries for the prisoners and hence, have put a huge value on the. Such small things, like a blanket or warm and delicious food, are difficult to get hold of. The only way they can get the items is through illicit means. Second, although there is a canteen present in prison, it is practically the only shop and exercises monopoly power. This results, often, in the sale of goods for a premium on their original price. Many prisons prohibit prisoners from carrying cash with a concern that they would bribe the guards to get their way. Instead, each prisoner is assigned a card; into which they can load money and use it to make purchases. These cards can be loaded either by funds sent in for them by someone and/or the earnings of the prisoners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above the only legal ways to earn money is to do the work allotted by the prison officials. However, the wages offered in the prison are diminutive, even below the statutory minimum in many countries. For instance, the average wage in the federal prisons in the US is &lt;a href=&quot;https://psmag.com/social-justice/taking-freedom-modern-day-slavery&quot;&gt;31 cents per hour&lt;/a&gt;, way below the minimum requirement of $7.25 per hour. The Indian prisons compete with their US counterparts in this aspect. The average amount of wage paid is approximately &lt;a href=&quot;https://in.news.yahoo.com/jailonomics--how-to-survive-inside-an-indian-prison-100808012.html&quot;&gt;₹48 per day&lt;/a&gt; (the actual wage varies from state to state, as prisons fall under the state list), which is one-fourth of the prescribed minimum wage in the country. This clearly points out the enormous gap between the wages and the prices in a prison. Even if the goods were to be sold at the Maximum Retail Price, it would not be possible for the prisoners to afford it. It is also the case that the quality of food is abysmal and sometimes becomes quite hard to eat. This is another reason for the existence of an economy where it is not supposed to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore one thing is clear: there is a demand for goods and services (smuggling in drugs can also be categorised as a service!) in prison. This demand creates opportunities for prisoners to make money. The cost of a good mainly depends on the risk it takes to smuggle in the good. The stronger the security, costlier the good is. Supply of a good can come from two sources: either the prisoners get in the good through their external contact or pay the prison guards to bring the good. In his famous book, &lt;em&gt;Extreme Economies&lt;/em&gt;, Richard Davies quotes an ex-convict who served time in the Louisiana State penitentiary saying “…these [guards] are young and uneducated, they can triple their wages by bringing these things in.” This is mostly true for guards serving in other prisons as well because often the salary paid to these guards is often very low. For this reason, often, the guards are also willing to smuggle in the goods for prisoners. Therefore, the trading prisoners strike a deal with the guards and pay them commissions. Now that we have seen how the supply and demand are satisfied, we need to look at what is the medium of exchange. As cash is prohibited, prisoners come up with innovative ideas to solve their problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can find the most popular medium of exchange for the most part of history has been ‘cigarettes’. Apart from cigarettes shower gel capsules, rosary beads, cigarette paper, etc. have also been used in UK prisons. In the US, after cigarettes, the most popular exchange mediums were postage stamps. Notice all the above items perfectly satisfy all the properties of a currency: store of value, a medium of exchange, and a measure of value. In recent times, however, a popular ‘currency’ emerged in the US: ‘mackerel’ (a type of packaged fish). The validity of a currency depends on the convention that ‘everyone values the currency because they expect everyone else to value it.’ This is exactly what happened with mackerel. While such an exchange was perfectly possible among the prisoners, convincing a guard to take it is hard; as they would only accept cash as payment. Richard Davies explains how the prisoners of Louisiana prison overcame this conundrum (this is also what happens across most of the US prisons): prepaid cards. Using a debit or credit card, one could purchase these prepaid cards (which have an upper limit of $500) basically anywhere. All you need to do is tell the beneficiary the 14-digit number that is behind the card and they could redeem it. So, the buyer and the beneficiary need not even know each other and the transaction happens. Moreover, the fact that no proof or ID is required to buy these cards means that it leaves no digital trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prisoners also engage in these activities because it provides a sense of identity and purpose to the prisoners. They find their lost dignity, in the society, by working and proving useful to their fellow prisoners. Also, the scarcity of the basic goods and, sometimes, prohibited goods means that they can be traded for huge sums. Prisoners that come from families with a relatively lower standard of living support their families with the income earned by engaging in the informal trade inside the prison. There are also success stories where people, after leaving prison, started their own businesses using the skills acquired during their time in prison. It is also important to take note of the fact that people can put their skills into negative use, say, by engaging in smuggling of drugs. Therefore, the solution to this informal arrangement, if one were to find such an economy harmful, is to recognise the fact the prisoners are people with unsatisfied needs, tastes, and demands; increase the wages substantially, to treat them like normal humans and to let them retain their sense of dignity.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Prison, jail, penitentiary are all the same things. They are meant for the mental reform of a person convicted of criminal activities. However, sometimes they can even enhance the business acumen of a person. They are supposed to have very limited trade and economic activity. In such a world, the only way one could earn is through working official chores assigned by the prison and the only place to spend is the official commissary, or a canteen, extant in the jail premises. However, more often than not, the prisoners trade informally themselves. Goods are smuggled in and a variety of services are offered by the prisoners with skills. Such an informal or underground economy is a common sight in prisons, especially in prisons with people serving quite longer sentences. This article is an attempt to explain why informal economies spring up and how they are operated.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Quality or Quantity?</title>
      <link href="/Quality-or-Quantity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quality or Quantity?" />
      <published>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Quality-or-Quantity</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Quality-or-Quantity">&lt;p&gt;Why are so many students convinced that they should get good grades just because they spent so many hours on a particular paper? It is not a belief about the quality of those papers rather it is a belief about the hours and hours spent on writing them. This fundamental misconception about the value of labour lies at the root of Marx’s critique of capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For hundreds of years, many economists believed that goods should be valued on the basis of the number of hours the labour spent to produce those goods. It was considered that any two goods that took the same time to be produced had the same value. This was termed as the ‘Labour Value of Theory’. One of the best-known advocates of this theory was Karl Marx. However, this theory has fallen out of favour among economists since the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory did have some superficial plausibility as it does seem that a good which involves a higher number of labour hours should be valued higher. However, the theory got increasingly complicated as it tried to explain some obvious objections. If we go by this theory the value of land should be nil, as there is no amount of labour that goes into ‘producing’ the land. What about the great pieces of art which hold hefty price tags, despite the fact that they do not require intense labour? What about the exorbitant prices paid to Michelin starred chefs? The theory failed to give a logical reason for these exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Marx, the labour value of theory lied at the center of the problems related to capitalism. The argument that capitalism exploited labourers depended crucially on the theory that labour was the source of all value-added, and that capitalists stole the profits from these labourers who deserved it more. According to him, capitalism destroyed our ability to enjoy the work that we do and forced us to work under their tyranny. Without the theory, Marx would have failed to justify the problems associated with capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It became increasingly difficult for the proponents of the theory to come up with logical explanations for the various exceptions to this theory. An individual’s skill set was completely ignored, it failed to account for the difference in the amount of time it takes for different individuals to perform a certain task. Moreover, it is clearly possible to spend a large amount of time on a product that ends up having no value eventually (something like a sandcastle). Additionally, goods that require the same amount of time to be produced should have the same market value, however, this is not always the case. Different goods have varying values in the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opposition to the labour value of theory was proposed by Carl Menger when he stated that the value of goods is ‘subjective’. While the labour theory argued that the price of inputs determines the value of the final good, the subjectivist theory claimed that the value of a good is derived from the human perception of its usefulness. Value is not something that is objective or can be standardised for every person. It is a function of the role that an object plays in the plans of a certain human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, according to the subjectivists, land has value not because of the labour that goes into tilling it but because of the utility that people expect to derive out of it (such as growing crops to eat). People pay a high amount for solid coloured canvases not because of the painter’s efforts, but because of the beauty that they saw in the painting. Michelin starred restaurants are so pricey not because of the hours and hours that the chef spends in preparation of the food, but because of the satisfaction people get from eating that food. Therefore, the theory drew a line between the economic value of a good and the scientific value of the good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subjective theory of value gave a new meaning to the value of labour: the value of inputs like labour depended on the value of outputs that they helped to produce. Hence, labour gets rewarded on the basis of producing things that others value. When you consider that combining labour with capital enables that labour to produce goods that others value, Marx’s arguments seem invalid. Capitalism, hence, provides tools to the labourers to produce valuable goods and thereby increases their remuneration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, capitalism is basically a communication process through which humans try to make the best possible use of the limited resources available with them to satisfy their most urgent wants. Many academics are simply unaware of the fact. It depends on an individual what he values more, ‘quality’ or ‘quantity’.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Amrit Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Why are so many students convinced that they should get good grades just because they spent so many hours on a particular paper? It is not a belief about the quality of those papers rather it is a belief about the hours and hours spent on writing them. This fundamental misconception about the value of labour lies at the root of Marx’s critique of capitalism.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Horrendous Memories of the Raj: Colonial Rule and the Indian Economy</title>
      <link href="/The-Horrendous-Memories-of-the-Raj" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Horrendous Memories of the Raj: Colonial Rule and the Indian Economy" />
      <published>2020-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Horrendous-Memories-of-the-Raj</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Horrendous-Memories-of-the-Raj">&lt;p&gt;Before British rule in India, India was a self-sufficient and robust economy. It was popularly known as the ‘golden eagle’ signifying the wealth it had accumulated. India had already established itself on the world map as the largest exporter in the world with a global trade share of more than 27%. By the late 17th century, almost the whole of India (as we know it in its present form), along with Pakistan and a part of Afghanistan, was united under the name of the Mughal empire and became the largest economy and manufacturing power in the world, producing about a quarter of the global GDP. India was the world leader in manufacturing, producing 25% of the world’s total output until the mid-18th century. It was the world’s biggest producer of textiles, agricultural products, and precious metals and stones, including diamonds. The fact that industrialisation was on the doorstep of the Indian economy cannot be denied. Although primarily it was an agrarian economy, many manufacturing activities started picking up pace in pre-colonial India, and the exchange of ideas and technology with the western world had been free-flowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these developments in the Indian sub-continent lured and attracted the British to capture India and use it as a cash-cow to fulfill the needs of their home country. The British came to India with the motive of colonisation. Their plans involved using India as a feeder colony for their own flourishing economy back in Britain. This exploitation continued for about two centuries, ending at last in 1947 after endless dark days of persecution, plunder and exploitation. The British took steps that ensured the development and promotion of the interests of their home country. They were in no way concerned about the course of the Indian economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India experienced deindustrialisation and cessation of various craft industries under British rule, which along with fast economic and population growth in the West, resulted in India’s share of the world economy declining from 24.4% in 1700 to 4.1% in 1950, with its share in global trade declining from 27% in 1750 to 2% in the 1900’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indian weavers and textile industries were well-known all over the world. They made superior and very fine quality cloth, it was actually known to be the ‘lightest woven-air’. The British came right in, smashed their thumbs, broke their looms, asserted tariffs and duties, and shipped the raw material from India to Britain. They shipped back industrially mass-produced stitched garments back to India, flooding the world’s market with what became the products of the dark and satanic Victorian era. This meant that the weavers and handloom workers in India went from being acknowledged worldwide for their work to being beggars and hence, destroying the forever thriving cloth and textile industry of India, in which it held its utmost pride. The Indian textile industry still hasn’t been able to fully recover from the effects that colonisation had on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British always emphasised the positives that took place during their reign. One such thing in which they took pride was that they built the railways in India. To this, the argument stands that a lot of other countries didn’t need to be colonised in order to build its railways. Railways were built just to serve the British purpose. They were used to transport troops and raw material from the hinterland to the ports to be shipped to Britain. The needs of the Indian public were incidental and there was no consideration to match the demand and supply of the railway services for the general public movement. The fact is that the building of railways was just another gimmick or as one might say a trick implemented by the British to ensure an extravagant return to its own people. They supplied all the equipment, controlled the technology, and promised the British investors vast returns on their investments in railways which were eventually paid out of the Indian taxpayers’ money, as pointed out by Shashi Tharoor. All this resulted in causing the cost of building 1 km of railways to inflate and become almost double of what it took to build in Canada or Australia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving forward to the First World War, India and the rest of the British dominions had no control over Indian defence and foreign policy in 1914. So, when the United Kingdom declared war on Germany on August 4, India and the rest of the British colonies were automatically at war with the Central Powers. Though India was suffering from recession, poverty and hunger at that time, the country supplied not only manpower but also 170,000 animals, 3.7 million tonnes of supplies, jute for sandbags, and a large loan (the equivalent of about £2 billion today) to the British government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;World War II was even worse; more than 2.4 million Indian men served in that war and out of Britain’s total war debt of £3 billion (in 1945 money), £1.25 billion was owed to India and was never really paid back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian economy frequently faced the occurrence of famines too during British rule. Commercialisation of agriculture hampered the production of food grains by transferring land from the cultivation of food crops to non-food crops like industrial raw materials. Moreover, the destruction of Indian handicrafts increased the pressure of population on land. All these led to the frequent occurrences of famines in India causing untold misery and suffering for the Indian cultivators and general people. Anywhere around 15 to 29 million Indians died due to British-induced famines in India during colonial rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even after all the miseries and horrendous exploitation incited by the British on India, they never accepted nor did they apologise for the wrongdoings that happened during that period. Today, after 73 years, India stands strong at a global stage as the 5th largest economy in the world, way ahead of its colonial rulers. Although India still has a lot to achieve in the field of sanitation, healthcare, education and other pillars of the economy, it has done a tremendous job till now and has risen above all the exploitation and plunder they suffered for 200 years as a British colony.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Before British rule in India, India was a self-sufficient and robust economy. It was popularly known as the ‘golden eagle’ signifying the wealth it had accumulated. India had already established itself on the world map as the largest exporter in the world with a global trade share of more than 27%. By the late 17th century, almost the whole of India (as we know it in its present form), along with Pakistan and a part of Afghanistan, was united under the name of the Mughal empire and became the largest economy and manufacturing power in the world, producing about a quarter of the global GDP. India was the world leader in manufacturing, producing 25% of the world’s total output until the mid-18th century. It was the world’s biggest producer of textiles, agricultural products, and precious metals and stones, including diamonds. The fact that industrialisation was on the doorstep of the Indian economy cannot be denied. Although primarily it was an agrarian economy, many manufacturing activities started picking up pace in pre-colonial India, and the exchange of ideas and technology with the western world had been free-flowing.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Japan: Testing the Limits of Pandemic Economics</title>
      <link href="/Testing-the-Limits-of-Pandemic-Economics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Japan: Testing the Limits of Pandemic Economics" />
      <published>2020-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Testing-the-Limits-of-Pandemic-Economics</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Testing-the-Limits-of-Pandemic-Economics">&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus has brought the entire world economy down to its knees, gasping for a breath of fresh air, production cycles all around the world have come to a halt, supply chains disrupted, and many businesses are on the brink of a shutdown. Social distancing is the measure being adopted throughout the world to reduce the spread of this disease leading to the imposition of total lockdowns in various countries, be it a developed or an underdeveloped nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One developed nation facing the brunt of the virus is Japan, which is actually trying to cushion the impact the virus is having by declaring a state of emergency. However, it seems like the end of the tunnel is near for Japan and that the government has already planned to launch a multipronged economic stimulus package to restart the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The package has been announced in two phases with a value of ¥117 trillion (translating to about $1.1 trillion), which is about 20% of Japan’s GDP, to expand cash payouts to its citizens as the virus threatens to push the world’s third-largest economy into depression. Japan will sell additional bonds worth more than ¥18 trillion to fund the package, adding to its huge debt which is almost 257% of its GDP. However, since the debt is owed to itself, there is little chance of a debt crisis. According to the Japanese Economic Minister, Yasutoshi Nishimura, the economic package is set to boost the real Japanese GDP by 4.4%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first phase of the package aims to curb job losses and bankruptcies, while the second round of aid, after the virus is contained, will try to support a V-shaped economic recovery; wherein even after suffering a sharp recession, the economic stimulus will be able to support the economy on the steep curve to recovery. The package is designed to give more than ¥6 trillion in cash payouts to households and small businesses and ¥26 trillion to allow deferred social security and tax payments. Apart from this, the government announced an increase in direct fiscal spending amounting to a whopping ¥39 trillion to help the economy get back on its feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Japan is planning to distribute ¥300,000 to lower-income households that have lost their livelihoods due to the virus along with households with children. Moreover, the government has encouraged businesses to keep workers on their payroll and has also proposed subsidies for the same. Additionally, it has offered to defer income and regional tax payments for a year for virus-hit companies, which has led to multiple small businesses reducing their property taxes to near zero. Furthermore, the government has offered emergency loans for those facing wage cuts or job losses due to a virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China, the home ground of the virus, has been facing global backlash due to the inefficient measures to contain the virus’ spread. As is known, most MNCs have set up production facilities in China owing to the low-cost of production in the country. This is also the case with Japanese companies, however, as a part of its economic package, the Japanese government has announced $2.2 billion to help its companies to shift their manufacturing units out of China, accommodating both the shift to Japan and other countries in the world. The Japanese government intends to shift all high value production to Japan and to diversify production across South East Asia. The world has indeed realised the consequences of depending on one country too much. This is a change we can expect to see in the post lockdown world when instead of concentrating production in one country, the global economy will move on to having diverse models to prevent complete disruption of production cycles (like this one) in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impact on the Japanese economy has been severe with the pandemic slowing down the economy of China, followed by that of the US, two of Japan’s largest trading partners. Anyhow, the Japanese government’s stimulus package might not be successful. The small businesses are disappointed at the size of the package to mitigate the economic fallout due to the virus, they say that not only is it insufficient, it might also be a little too late. The Reuters Corporate Survey found 46% of firms felt the government’s stimulus was somewhat not enough and 29% deemed it quite insufficient, keeping Abe’s government under pressure to top-up last week’s spending package. While 5% said it was too much, just 21% said it was sufficient and appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The poll indicates how not only the amounts are insufficient but the measures are too, people ask for bolder steps like sales tax cuts for small businesses apart from the very insufficient cash payouts. The companies demand higher public spending and more support for financing. While the package might superficially seem enough, when one delves deeper into the public opinion, we find how the package is actually insufficient and unsatisfying. However, the question is if the world’s most indebted country can afford to increase its spending in a bid to stimulate the economy?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kashish Jindal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Coronavirus has brought the entire world economy down to its knees, gasping for a breath of fresh air, production cycles all around the world have come to a halt, supply chains disrupted, and many businesses are on the brink of a shutdown. Social distancing is the measure being adopted throughout the world to reduce the spread of this disease leading to the imposition of total lockdowns in various countries, be it a developed or an underdeveloped nation. One developed nation facing the brunt of the virus is Japan, which is actually trying to cushion the impact the virus is having by declaring a state of emergency. However, it seems like the end of the tunnel is near for Japan and that the government has already planned to launch a multipronged economic stimulus package to restart the economy. The package has been announced in two phases with a value of ¥117 trillion (translating to about $1.1 trillion), which is about 20% of Japan’s GDP, to expand cash payouts to its citizens as the virus threatens to push the world’s third-largest economy into depression. Japan will sell additional bonds worth more than ¥18 trillion to fund the package, adding to its huge debt which is almost 257% of its GDP. However, since the debt is owed to itself, there is little chance of a debt crisis. According to the Japanese Economic Minister, Yasutoshi Nishimura, the economic package is set to boost the real Japanese GDP by 4.4%.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
