<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/economics/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-04-07T21:11:15+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/economics/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Bike-Sharing: Ending Soon?</title>
      <link href="/Bike-Sharing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bike-Sharing: Ending Soon?" />
      <published>2019-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Bike-Sharing</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Bike-Sharing">&lt;p&gt;In the past few years, what scholars term the ‘sharing economy’ has attracted tremendous attention and massive venture capital. Prominent platforms such as Airbnb  and Uber  are experiencing explosive growth, which has led to both virtues and detriments. Advocates of the sharing economy claim the system yields positive outcomes such as empowerment of ordinary people, efficiency in commerce and even lower carbon footprints. On the other hand, critics accuse it of promoting economic self-interest rather than sharing and decry it as being exploitative and predatory. Today, bike-sharing services are among the most prevalent start-up business models purportedly constituting the sharing economy. Comparable to other businesses of its kind however, bike-sharing companies have begun encountering issues ranging from regulatory hurdles to unethical business practices, vandalism and theft to uncooperative customers and communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharing remains a routine practice even today: families sharing the rewards of their labour, communities sharing access to resources and countries sharing intelligence, among other examples. While ‘sharing’ is as old as humankind, the ‘sharing economy’ in its current understanding is a fairly recent concept. However, despite its instant growth and enormous popularity among consumers, it is extremely perplexing to propose a universally applicable definition for ‘sharing economy’, especially one that reflects clarity whilst also addressing the variety of ways in which the term is used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The generic meaning of ‘sharing’ omits methods of exchange that involve a monetary connotation, which means schemes based on peer-to-peer (P2P) asset dealings should be excluded from the sharing economy. However, if we elucidate that access to an asset can be shared instead of the asset itself, the attachment of a monetary implication becomes irrelevant and activities based on peer-to-peer asset sharing should be included in the sharing economy. Due to its ambiguous definition, scholars today consider ‘sharing economy’ an umbrella term with a variety of meanings. It is, however, most appropriate to think of it as a marketplace that connects individuals on a peer-to-peer basis, enabling them to share assets that are otherwise underutilised and idling in exchange for a price. A sharing economy, thus, offers an economical and convenient alternative to actually purchasing the asset, since the cost of sharing is considerably lower than the cost incurred on owning the asset. Hence, this model can also be called a ‘collaborative economy’ or a ‘peer economy’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise of this ‘peer economy’ has been highly transformative over recent years. It has altered the way we commute, lodge, holiday and borrow, by employing ‘dead capital’ in more productive fashions. Accredited with altering the way we commute, among other examples, is the bike-sharing industry. It has received increasing spotlight in recent years for enlarging mobility options and lowering transportation costs for consumers. The bike-sharing industry has augmented the use of public transport, reduced traffic congestion and fuel consumption, delivered health benefits and improved environmental awareness among the public. It also acts as a resort to the ‘first mile-last mile’ problem of transit. Bixi, a bike-sharing company,  proudly professes that it has helped reduce over 3 million pounds of greenhouse gases in Montreal in 2009. Another such program that began in France in 2005 or so claims it has saved the equivalent of 18.6 million pounds of carbon dioxide pollution from the atmosphere in a year. In 2008, 28% of Vélib’s  customers, a bike-sharing company based out of Paris, stated they were less likely to use their personal vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the question is, is the bike-sharing industry truly a part of the sharing economy? Undertakings in the sharing economy are immensely diverse. TaskRabbit, an errands site, is considered a part of it but Mechanical Turk, Amazon’s online labour market, is not. Airbnb  is virtually synonymous with the sharing economy, but conventional bed and breakfasts are rarely included in it. Even though they serve similar agendas, public libraries, community centers and parks are not counted in the sharing economy. When Juliet Schor, Professor of Sociology at Boston College, presented these puzzles to a few scholars, they gave a pragmatic response rather than an analytical one: “self-definition by the platforms and the press defines who is in and who is out”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, most bike-sharing companies function as business-to-peer organisations rather than peer-to-peer organisations. This stands in violation of the ‘peer-to-peer sharing’ characteristic of a sharing economy that we established earlier in this article. Technically, an ideal model of the peer economy involves a company, customers and non-company owners of the physical asset providing customers a service, in this case, bikes. My view is that bike-sharing companies contravene &lt;em&gt;marketing ethics&lt;/em&gt; by advertising themselves as part of the sharing economy. These companies themselves own the physical asset. Furthermore, these bikes are neither underutilised assets, nor are they idling: they are perpetually available for customers. Therefore, the honest approach would be to label it a ‘bike-renting’ business rather than a ‘bike-sharing’ business, because bikes are actually rented out to consumers and not peer-shared. Take Uber  or Airbnb  as examples to compare bike-sharing with the true model of a sharing business. We find that genuine sharing-companies work as aggregators of vendors and partners who are simply connected to customers, in exchange for a commission for this straightforward networking service. On the contrary, bike-sharing companies act as vendors themselves, and instead of a commission, charge the entire price upon renting the bikes independently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of ethical conduct and positioning of these companies as a part of the sharing economy further deepens on evaluating their core strategy. Given the public affinity to the current wave of peer-sharing, bike-sharing companies, or perhaps more appropriately now, bike-renting companies, are attempting to build a consumer behaviour of routine and habitual renting, leveraging the sentiment of people who find peer-sharing trendy to be the ‘in thing’, or the only resort to the miseries of mankind. This has led to speculations of inflated company valuations, rendering a scar on the industry’s &lt;em&gt;financial ethics&lt;/em&gt;, besides forming a bubble waiting to burst as the demand dips after the initial euphoria is over and more players enter the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet another bane of the bike-sharing industry is its eagle-eye for big data and metadata, an agenda that endangers user privacy. Over the last few years, bike-sharing companies have received billions of dollars in funding, but have failed to generate consequential revenue. There is widespread concern as billions are being invested in loss-making bike-sharing companies that have no profit model. These companies consume cash just to build vast user networks in order to justify higher valuations in subsequent fundraising. Despite marginal returns, investors are constantly investing in these companies, with increased frequency and greater magnitude. The real objective for these investors is securing access to millions of ‘tech-savvy’ customers, and surprising enough is their ability to go to any extent to achieve this objective. In fact, Ofo  gave away rides for free when they launched in Chongqing, China. Users were merely required to register on the online app, and free rides they got. As a result of technological advancements and innovations, most bike-sharing companies today operate through online applications. External players like investors and content creators, are hungry for access to online user information from as many sources as possible, so as to build a massive customer network for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies like Chinese e-commerce giant Alibaba, whose financial affiliate, Ant Financial, is an investor for the bike-sharing company Ofo, are exploring opportunities to deliver other products and services to these digital customers they are monitoring on the aforementioned applications. “They are keen to access valuable data on users’ commuting habits and rental history”, says Zhou Wei, founder of China Creation Ventures. “These bike services are of high strategic importance to Alibaba and Tencent. It is an indispensable way to get data on frequent users”. Access to user data also provides information on a person’s credit history, social media conduct, and online shopping habits. Surveillance like this reveals our individual details to unidentified players who establish ‘&lt;em&gt;echo chambers&lt;/em&gt;’ and ‘&lt;em&gt;filter bubbles&lt;/em&gt;’ on our network so as to create custom content and influence our online buying and selling activities, news feeds and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another allegation that social activists and governments always shower bike-sharing companies with is the ‘bring-your-own-helmet’ practice, which helps these companies evade liability towards the safety of their customers. In a recent case, an 11-year old boy riding an Ofo  bike met with a fatal accident in Shanghai when he was hit by a bus. Road safety laws in China prohibit children under the age of 12 from riding bikes on public roads. However, bike-sharing companies have been flouting this law openly. Despite its lapse in allowing an 11-year old to rent their bike, Ofo simply expressed condolences over the mishap but failed to take responsibility for the event. As part of an example from outside China, we may note that only 20% of Hubway riders in Boston bike wear helmets. This means only &lt;strong&gt;two out of ten shared-bike riders riding in heavy traffic are likely to survive in the event of an accident&lt;/strong&gt;. Absence of helmets in bike-sharing services also conflicts with insurance laws, wherein injuries or fatalities may not be covered by insurance companies. The Hangzhou bike-sharing system in China is one of the very few systems of its kind to cover any injuries that riders sustain while using their bikes. The Cambridge Cycling Campaign has also raised concerns over the absence of lights in front of most shared-bikes in China. They are apprehensive over the legal permissibility of the commercial use of such bikes. During the dark, if streets lack sufficient lighting, riders can meet with accidents and the same argument on liability is repeated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding to the problem of traffic congestion, bike-sharing companies are also accused of using ‘bike visibility’ as a mode of marketing. They are heavily investing in a model that perpetually releases bikes into the market but abandons their maintenance and upkeep. In terms of ‘fleet size’, 17 of the world’s top 20 bike-sharing schemes are based out of China. Despite truncated demand, China currently has over 10 million shared-bikes on its streets, 1.5 million of which are active in Shanghai alone. The industry is engaging in cut-throat competition, with the winner title supposedly going to the company that has most bikes on the road. This has aggravated traffic congestion and hence reduced road-safety. Companies are attempting to make regional monopolies of their own: Ofo  operates 2.2 million bikes across China, Mobike,  about a million, and then there are over forty other startups expanding in different parts of the Mainland. “Piles of bikes dumped outside subway stations are now a common sight”, says Yang Fengchun, a professor at Peking University’s School of Government. This is happening due to the lack of docking facilities in urban cities. Bike-sharing companies are saving costs by not installing adequate docking stations. Even if the companies operate on a dock-less model, they have dusted their hands off the responsibility to manage bikes that clog public streets, parks, condominiums, sidewalks and office areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Non-cooperating communities also play a major role in the theft and vandalism of shared-bikes. In an interesting case recently, bike-sharing went on to symbolise inequality and discrimination for the economically backward black community residing in peripheral parts of San Francisco. The launch of the Ford GoBike  scheme became a scapegoat for people who were distressed due to the housing crisis and troubled by the problem of rising income inequalities. They identified the bike-sharing trend as an indulgence of rich techies, hipsters and young professionals, who used them to commute to popular coffee shops and high-end food joints. Bike-sharing has hence been criticised in localities that lack efficient and organised city services. In such an environment, the industry produces more adversaries than peers, thus encouraging unethical practices and inappropriate conduct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, several bike-sharing companies have had to seal operations from time to time. Wukong Bicycle  lost 90% of its bikes to theft and vandalism, hence having to end operations in June 2017. In a similar case in November 2017, Bluegogo  declared bankruptcy since most of its bikes had either been stolen or wrecked, leaving no other option for the company but to shut down operations. Outside China, the state of affairs is no better. Seattle ended its Pronto  scheme this March; a bike-sharing program in Melbourne also ended in failure when its demand dipped after the enforcement of a law that mandated wearing helmets while riding. Spain seems to have suffered the highest casualties: 65 of the 130 schemes that began in Spain back in 2010 have shut down, half of them concluding operations within three years of opening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, it is also important that we examine the morals of governments. Why are cities being designed only for cars? Why does urbanisation involve more automobiles and not more ‘thought-o-mobiles’? Is it not unfair to disregard people who perhaps choose to cycle due to financial constraints or health motivations? The world is tirelessly discussing climate change and the impact it will have on future generations. Governments themselves are pledging to relegate pollution in a variety of ways. One of these ways is to reduce motorised vehicles on the road. While governments do advocate the necessity of owning lesser cars and using them less often, they end up sponsoring hypocrisy by failing to provide and support alternative measures. The bike-sharing industry could have structured a new way of life by now, where the main mode of transport for citizens was a shared-bike. But, consistent with their neo-capitalistic propaganda, governments are busy building highways and expressways to facilitate motorised commute while resource allocation to boost bike-sharing barely seems existent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can cogently affirm that the bike-sharing industry is not a true manifestation of the sharing economy. In reality, it is modelled more on a rental service than a peer-sharing facility. Further, all evidence presented throw light on a spectrum of problems: several people have lost their jobs and perhaps still remain unemployed with bike-sharing companies having to shut down operations; land, plant and machinery have gone largely underutilised on account of the same; the industry has witnessed numerous regulatory hurdles that include infringement of current legislations and the imperative need for new and more comprehensive ones; the government has been unsuccessful in extracting benefits of the industry for the public; and finally, criminal activity by society has gone largely unpunished. The bike-sharing industry can hence be identified with more negatives than positives today. Bike-sharing companies, the society and governments, all have a role to play in its flawed model of business and sheer disregard for ethics. Though seemingly pacing ahead with consistent innovation and expansion, the bike-sharing industry has begun its gradual decline. It will soon meet its end lest all its stakeholders pedal to survive…&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shivang Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In the past few years, what scholars term the ‘sharing economy’ has attracted tremendous attention and massive venture capital. Prominent platforms such as Airbnb and Uber are experiencing explosive growth, which has led to both virtues and detriments. Advocates of the sharing economy claim the system yields positive outcomes such as empowerment of ordinary people, efficiency in commerce and even lower carbon footprints. On the other hand, critics accuse it of promoting economic self-interest rather than sharing and decry it as being exploitative and predatory. Today, bike-sharing services are among the most prevalent start-up business models purportedly constituting the sharing economy. Comparable to other businesses of its kind however, bike-sharing companies have begun encountering issues ranging from regulatory hurdles to unethical business practices, vandalism and theft to uncooperative customers and communities.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Apple’s China problems ft. Future Apple and the Coase Conjecture</title>
      <link href="/Apple-China-Problems" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Apple’s China problems ft. Future Apple and the Coase Conjecture" />
      <published>2019-03-28T02:03:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-28T02:03:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Apple-China-Problems</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Apple-China-Problems">&lt;p&gt;The Apple craze in China is officially over a decade old. During my days in
China, more often than not, I would take the early bus to Tianjin, along with 20
people glued to the glare of their phone screens. Take a walk across a busy
intersection on a weekday morning and you will find dozens of people marching to
work, busy on their smartphones. Not just any smartphones―the Apple iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/lb38KXlz1F2TllikTfKpV3QKflZ14w92D3AnAwq8xIDHYLYtaELdYAwVWzngy9CZL74x2d-m5T_5E5xvwu8CCnNjQQZdB_1EhYWv6BH0lrHxWevAoriAgQAx-uvdWf0jM9KdcirH&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/1509730264519.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why I did not specify which models are most popular is that the
iPhone craze in China is more about class than tech specs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“The people don’t bother which generation it is, as long as it’s an iPhone”--
Mobile store owner, Tianjin, China
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 4th Generation all the way to the latest models, the Chinese make a big
deal out of the iPhone, even if they are not the ones to show it. Despite this,
Apple’s returns for the holiday quarter have not been good. One may attribute
this to the slowing Chinese economy but there are other factors at play. Things
have turned so bad that Apple has had to scale down its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investors.com/news/apple-chinese-iphones-demand-revenue/&quot;&gt;revenue forecasts by an
estimated $5 billion- $9
billion&lt;/a&gt;.
The announcement (made way back in January) sent its stock
&lt;a href=&quot;https://finance.yahoo.com/quote/aapl/&quot;&gt;(AAPL)&lt;/a&gt; tumbling, falling by about 10
percentage points, though it has managed to recover since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The struggle for Apple in the Chinese market was real and people were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apnews.com/e0a2c907669c4821814763035b562c55&quot;&gt;simply
not buying iPhones&lt;/a&gt; as
they found the price tag too demanding. What seemed to be the problem? Was there
a new competitor on the block? If so, who was causing the disruption?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is pretty simple, it was Apple - yes, Apple from the Future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To break this down, we have to take a look at the Cupertino smartphone giant and
its position in the Chinese market. Yes, they make smartphones, but not just any
smartphone. They are makers of the most sought-after digital product in China.
No, not the BlackBerry. With an iPhone comes class, finesse, style, elegance,
efficiency, exclusivity and a burning hole in the pocket. This is where Apple
separates itself from the Huaweis and the Xiaomis of the market. To be honest,
Apple is a monopoly, with no competition in the foreseeable future. But wait,
our good friend Ronald Coase, a Nobel-winning economist, has something important
to say…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“[A]s soon as the consumers who are willing to pay the monopoly price make
their purchases, the monopolist has an incentive to lower his price and sell to
some of the remaining consumers. Immediately after the next round of sales, the
monopolist would find it worthwhile to lower his price yet again. This process
would continue until all buyers with reservation prices above marginal cost are
served. But rational consumers would anticipate this rapid fall of prices and
wait until the market price reaches its ultimate level before making any
purchases”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that went over your head, do not panic. What he means to say is that in a
market for a durable good (whose resale is not possible) with only one primary
seller (monopoly), once the first lot of goods is sold at a particular price,
the remaining goods are sold at a lower price. Now of the further remaining
goods, some are sold at an even lower price than before and those still
remaining shall be sold even cheaper and this goes on. If a rational buyer
anticipates this and waits for the price to keep falling, he can nab the good at
a much lower price than before. This is what we call the Coase Conjecture. In
effect, the Coase Conjecture holds that a monopolist faces competition from
future incarnations of himself, even though he is the only producer in the
market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if we take an iPhone (any generation) to be a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://bgr.com/2018/05/28/iphone-x-vs-iphone-7-case-screen-scratches/&quot;&gt;durable&lt;/a&gt;
good, as most of the Chinese market prefers it to be, and Apple as the
monopolist, there will be competition faced by Apple. From whom one may ask?
From the Apple of tomorrow, its future self. And as a result, Apple will be
forced to drive down prices to encourage purchases. Oh, look, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.notebookcheck.net/Apple-cuts-iPhone-8-and-XR-prices-in-China-by-20-percent.394146.0.html&quot;&gt;it’s already
taking
place&lt;/a&gt;.
Time to get yourself an iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/ZTgkOCzIQP3kJpWuDzoY5rOmUl3jCg11OTrIRKWgguK_Qc8JXos7VycoRldaD2_HHOTOFTtfklC5r8vT2j8JDSeOcyM1IPjIfgIDQmCm78DiUmHKLevdmnuwMw2le3Yx_MSrDOTk&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/gettyimages-93081350.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people in China know this well enough and this is why they keep sitting on
the iPhones, waiting for prices to drop. That, ladies and gentlemen, is exactly
how most of the Chinese middle class enjoys an excess of iPhones. Nevermind them
showing off models released six years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appears that there is little Apple can do to rid themselves of such a
predicament. They could try introducing a new spec of such a high quality that
people simply &lt;em&gt;have to have&lt;/em&gt; the new model. Or, as an alternative, they could
simply refuse to lower the price of new models for such a period of time that
people are practically forced into a purchase. But neither of these seem like
realistic solutions. The former will likely fail due to the notional loyalty to
&lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; iPhone. The latter will fall short also, as long as older models continue
to function. The question is then, what next for Apple in the Chinese market? Is
there an unexploited strategy waiting to lure the Chinese public into parting
with their hard earned cash, or is Apple destined to be a fashion item?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shohan Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Apple craze in China is officially over a decade old. During my days in China, more often than not, I would take the early bus to Tianjin, along with 20 people glued to the glare of their phone screens. Take a walk across a busy intersection on a weekday morning and you will find dozens of people marching to work, busy on their smartphones. Not just any smartphones―the Apple iPhone. The reason why I did not specify which models are most popular is that the iPhone craze in China is more about class than tech specs. “The people don’t bother which generation it is, as long as it’s an iPhone”-- Mobile store owner, Tianjin, China From 4th Generation all the way to the latest models, the Chinese make a big deal out of the iPhone, even if they are not the ones to show it. Despite this, Apple’s returns for the holiday quarter have not been good. One may attribute this to the slowing Chinese economy but there are other factors at play. Things have turned so bad that Apple has had to scale down its revenue forecasts by an estimated $5 billion- $9 billion. The announcement (made way back in January) sent its stock (AAPL) tumbling, falling by about 10 percentage points, though it has managed to recover since. The struggle for Apple in the Chinese market was real and people were simply not buying iPhones as they found the price tag too demanding. What seemed to be the problem? Was there a new competitor on the block? If so, who was causing the disruption? The answer is pretty simple, it was Apple - yes, Apple from the Future. To break this down, we have to take a look at the Cupertino smartphone giant and its position in the Chinese market. Yes, they make smartphones, but not just any smartphone. They are makers of the most sought-after digital product in China. No, not the BlackBerry. With an iPhone comes class, finesse, style, elegance, efficiency, exclusivity and a burning hole in the pocket. This is where Apple separates itself from the Huaweis and the Xiaomis of the market. To be honest, Apple is a monopoly, with no competition in the foreseeable future. But wait, our good friend Ronald Coase, a Nobel-winning economist, has something important to say… “[A]s soon as the consumers who are willing to pay the monopoly price make their purchases, the monopolist has an incentive to lower his price and sell to some of the remaining consumers. Immediately after the next round of sales, the monopolist would find it worthwhile to lower his price yet again. This process would continue until all buyers with reservation prices above marginal cost are served. But rational consumers would anticipate this rapid fall of prices and wait until the market price reaches its ultimate level before making any purchases” If that went over your head, do not panic. What he means to say is that in a market for a durable good (whose resale is not possible) with only one primary seller (monopoly), once the first lot of goods is sold at a particular price, the remaining goods are sold at a lower price. Now of the further remaining goods, some are sold at an even lower price than before and those still remaining shall be sold even cheaper and this goes on. If a rational buyer anticipates this and waits for the price to keep falling, he can nab the good at a much lower price than before. This is what we call the Coase Conjecture. In effect, the Coase Conjecture holds that a monopolist faces competition from future incarnations of himself, even though he is the only producer in the market. Now, if we take an iPhone (any generation) to be a durable good, as most of the Chinese market prefers it to be, and Apple as the monopolist, there will be competition faced by Apple. From whom one may ask? From the Apple of tomorrow, its future self. And as a result, Apple will be forced to drive down prices to encourage purchases. Oh, look, it’s already taking place. Time to get yourself an iPhone. The people in China know this well enough and this is why they keep sitting on the iPhones, waiting for prices to drop. That, ladies and gentlemen, is exactly how most of the Chinese middle class enjoys an excess of iPhones. Nevermind them showing off models released six years ago. It appears that there is little Apple can do to rid themselves of such a predicament. They could try introducing a new spec of such a high quality that people simply have to have the new model. Or, as an alternative, they could simply refuse to lower the price of new models for such a period of time that people are practically forced into a purchase. But neither of these seem like realistic solutions. The former will likely fail due to the notional loyalty to any iPhone. The latter will fall short also, as long as older models continue to function. The question is then, what next for Apple in the Chinese market? Is there an unexploited strategy waiting to lure the Chinese public into parting with their hard earned cash, or is Apple destined to be a fashion item?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Crimea and Iraq: A Lesson in Economic Sanctions</title>
      <link href="/Crimea-and-Iraq" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crimea and Iraq: A Lesson in Economic Sanctions" />
      <published>2019-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Crimea-and-Iraq</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Crimea-and-Iraq">&lt;p&gt;In an increasingly globalised world, nations are often called upon to intervene in situations thousands of miles from their own borders. This may be in the response to atrocities such as genocide, as happened in Rwanda in 1994. Or, it may be needed to prevent a hostile escalation, such as the one which occurred when Russia annexed Crimea in 2014. It is often the case that the oppressed group is far smaller than its attacker and therefore needs outside assistance. As a result, often through public pressure, countries are forced into action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to such events, the powers-that-be have several tools at their disposal. A more mellow approach could come in the form of a political warning such as a leader’s speech, in the hope that actual, costly action would not be required. The other extreme is military intervention. This, however, has obvious drawbacks such as huge financial costs, loss of life and the risk of civilian casualties. A commonly argued alternative comes in the form of economic sanctions, often seen as an effective, peaceful form of coercion with a lesser risk to human life. However, these beliefs are often unfounded, and evidence would suggest its utility as a form of coercion is minimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prevailing view is that economic sanctions provide the optimal middle-ground between a peaceful approach and military warfare. The former is often viewed as weak, ineffective and more often than not, pointless. Leaders who take this avenue are viewed to be doing so simply to please their audience, possibly responding to public calls for crisis response. Leaders’ statements often serve the purpose of audience appeasement, amid fear of a backlash to inaction. Of course, there are possible arguments in favour of this approach. A powerful country may be able to impose some authority merely through an ultimatum if their reputation precedes them. Furthermore, if successful, it provides a completely costless solution. The targeted country will concede with no cost to the demanding nation. The positives are there, it’s just a shame that words are rarely enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is economic sanctions. These too are a varied tool and can range from action against individuals, such as business leaders, or the political elite, or broader blanket-sanctions on nations as a whole. The underlying logic is that the sanctions will over time cripple a country into submission, forcing them to concede to demands. Although this may cost the sanctioning nation in lost trade, it is usually far cheaper than troop mobilisation or air warfare. However, in the modern world, this is much easier said than done. Most countries are no longer dependant on a single commodity or links to a handful of trading partners. To have any significant impact, sanctions often need to be multilateral, often requiring the support of not just several countries, but from international bodies such as the United Nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was one of the many stumbling blocks with the Crimean crisis. Sanctions primarily came from the United States and Europe. Although together they accounted for a substantial portion of Russia’s trade, they failed to gain the support of crucial Asian states, as a result failing to eradicate their trade links. Russia was able to ease any economic suffering by strengthening ties with China and North Korea. The costs to Russia needed to be severe enough that it would have little choice but to modify its behaviour. As Russia was able to partially circumvent the sanctions and relieve some of the damage, the chance of sanction success drastically decreased. Cooperation from North Korea and China would have resulted in much more severe economic damage, and therefore a higher chance of Russia modifying its behaviour and sanction success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second crucial factor when evaluating the probability of sanction success is the presence of domestic audience pressure. The leader in question, in this case Putin, needs to be accountable to his people, who should have the ability and motivation to remove him should the economy start to suffer. It is clear that a democratic audience has the opportunity, via elections, to remove a leader or force him into policy change. However, a common misconception is that this scenario only exists within a democracy. Work by Jessica Weeks demonstrates that this may also occur in dictatorships, albeit in a different fashion. In a country with a political make-up akin to Russia, a political elite may choose to overthrow a leader if they stand to benefit and have the capacity to do so. This may occur if the elite stand to gain more through a coup than maintaining the status quo, as may be the case during a sanctions-induced economic crisis. In Russia, this was not the case. No democratic audience exists, and Putin has established an elite whose fate is tied to his. So, Putin’s approval rating soared when the sanctions hit, creating an anti-western “rally around the flag” effect as the economic suffering was blamed on Europe and the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empirical studies have shown these two influences, multilateral sanctions, and audience pressure, to be the most important factors. But even then, the success rate is weak. The ground-breaking HSE study into sanction success found only a third of 120 cases to be a success. Even more damning is further work by Robert Pape which showed only 5 of these cases to be successful. In the Crimean case, the sanctions ultimately failed in their objective to remove Russia from Crimea, and given their generally appalling success rate it begs the question, why even bother?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strong answer is that sanctions can be ‘smart’ and limit civilian suffering. A common objection to military action is that they often result in accidental civilian casualties, and if we instead use economic sanctions this will reduce the likelihood of such consequences. But again, this has not always gone to plan. As was the case with Iraq.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a response to Iraq’s invasion of Kuwait in August 1990, the United Nations enforced economic sanctions. The initial aim was to pressure Iraq into withdrawing from Kuwait, and a demand to give up any weapons of mass destruction was soon added. Although the sanctions may have been relatively effective, more noticeable was the alarming impact on child mortality. The economic impacts were severe which, whilst admittedly being the aim, had devastating effects on innocent civilians, particularly children. Some estimates place the number of deaths attributable to sanctions between half-a-million and a million, although there is much controversy surrounding these claims. Further surveys by UNICEF in 1999 concluded that in certain areas, children under five were dying at more than twice the rate they were ten years before, clean water and medical supplies were particular issues. This sheds some harsh reality on the potential cost to civilian life under economic sanctions, to a degree comparable with warfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The saving grace for world leaders is that they may simply have no other choice. Threats are often deemed empty and fall on deaf ears. To save face, action is required, yet military action is often opposed by the public. As a result, some form of economic sanction is required. However, with a success rate between 5% and 36%, this seems futile. The next question, then, is how do we respond to such events? It would be wrong to stand by as a spectator, yet no response seems suitable. Of course, as many scholars have pointed out, long-term solutions provide the best answer. Preventing such disasters from ever occurring is the desired outcome. But until then, a preferable alternative to economic sanctions must be sought.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Stephen McAndrew</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In an increasingly globalised world, nations are often called upon to intervene in situations thousands of miles from their own borders. This may be in the response to atrocities such as genocide, as happened in Rwanda in 1994. Or, it may be needed to prevent a hostile escalation, such as the one which occurred when Russia annexed Crimea in 2014. It is often the case that the oppressed group is far smaller than its attacker and therefore needs outside assistance. As a result, often through public pressure, countries are forced into action.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">“HELICOPTER” MONEY: The Way Ahead?</title>
      <link href="/Helicopter-Money" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“HELICOPTER” MONEY: The Way Ahead?" />
      <published>2019-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Helicopter-Money</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Helicopter-Money">&lt;p&gt;Suppose, a developed economy is experiencing a period of stagnation coupled with really low-interest rates and the government approaches the central bank to devise a way to spur spending and output in the economy. The central bank tries the conventional way of reducing interest rates to stimulate spending, inflation, growth and output but it falls flat as the interest rates were already very close to zero. Hence, the changes in the interest rates were not substantial enough to bring about a major change in output and spending. Worried, the central bank finds itself in a tough spot with limited monetary options to get out of this fix, none of which are effective. According to Friedman, the only solution would be to fly a helicopter above a community, literally dropping 100 dollar notes out of the sky for the general public to freely spend on commodities and services, therefore stimulating spending, output, and growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially developed as a classroom theory, ‘Helicopter Money’ refers to direct money transfers, virtual or cash, from the central bank to the general public with an aim of increasing spending, output, inflation and growth in an economy trapped in stagnation coupled with a liquidity crisis. The tool remained as a textbook chapter for most of the latter part of the 20th century. However, it was brought to light in 2002 by the then Fed governor Ben Bernanke who considered it as a suitable option to revive the US as well as Japan from the deflation which hit most developed countries at the beginning of the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, how does ‘Helicopter Money’ succeed when all other monetary methods fail to stimulate expenditure and output in the economy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that quantitative easing, rate cuts and other monetary methods generally adopted by a central bank fail when the interest rates hover around zero. This is because when the interest rates are near zero, a further rate cut, buying up of government bonds or negative interest rates would not increase the money supply in the economy sufficiently to increase spending. Moreover, most of these traditional financial methods have already been used and proven inefficient in various developed economies at various points in time, such as Japan in the 1990’s and the US in the early 2000’s. Hence, the only method which still remains unused is the Helicopter Drop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helicopter Drop has been hypothetically proven to stimulate demand in the economy. As the measure requires a one-time direct cash transfer to the general public, it is sure to stimulate spending. This is because the money supply in the economy increases by the amount of cash transferred by the central bank to the public which then increases the purchasing power of the individual. Naturally, with a higher purchasing power, spending would increase by the MPC (Marginal Propensity to Consume) amount in the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prospect of a Helicopter Drop is rather fascinating and sounds too good to be true. Realistically, Helicopter Drops and similar stimulus pose many questions to the central bank, from accounting to distribution. In spite of logistical issues such as how to disperse the amount equitably among the general public, another question which comes up is how will the central bank account for these Helicopter Drops?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the cases of traditional quantitative easing methods, such as open market operations, it is very easy for the central bank to account how much high-powered money has been circulated in the economy. As each accounting transaction has two sides, a debit and a credit, the central bank has to ensure that each accounting debit has its respective credit entry as well. In the case of open market operations, the amount of bonds bought from the market is an increase in the assets of the central bank, which is a debit entry. While the money circulated in the economy is a reduction in the assets of the central bank, hence a credit entry. However, in the case of Helicopter Drop, there is only a reduction in the assets of the central bank. This means that there is only a credit side to this entry, which violates the fundamental principle of accounting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To counter this, the central bank assumes that it has bought perpetual bonds from the market which have zero interest coupons on it. Basically, this means that The Central Banks assumes that for the money circulated among the general public as helicopter drops, it has bought from the market bonds which are irredeemable for perpetuity and which do not pay interest at all. This ensures that there is a debit side to the accounting entry for Helicopter Drops and that the fundamental principles of accounting are not violated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this solves the issue of accounting, it raises another important question. Nowadays, most economists are concerned with whether a monetary method is reversible or not. In the case of traditional monetary methods such as rate cuts, open market operations, and reserve ratios, all are reversible. Rates and reserve ratios can be increased or decreased as per the situation as the central bank can always buy or sell back government bonds in the market. However, Helicopter Drops are irreversible in nature. That is, once a drop is made, neither its effects on the economy nor the drop itself can be reversed. This limitation makes the economists weary and they argue as a normative proposition, that these drops, if used, should be at most used as a stimulus package to increase one-time spending, output, growth, and inflation in the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inconvertible fiat currency is unique in the fact that it has a positive exchange value against commodities as it can be produced at essentially zero cost. Therefore, there is always a potential temptation for central banks to undertake such action by the virtue of printing more and more currency. However, one needs to keep a check on the amount of currency circulated in the economy to ensure that hyperinflation does not occur and the intrinsic value of all commodities do not fall to zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helicopter Drops are dangerous as they conjure up the illusion that monetary magic can whip up real goods and services out of nothing. If this notion holds among those who influence monetary policy, then rational policymaking would become literally impossible. This is because policymakers would become so addicted to Helicopter Money that the overissue of fiat currency would only be dealt with a larger issue of currency until the economy collapses. Therefore, there is a good reason why Helicopter Money has not been used as a monetary policy tool but kept as a classroom experiment. And if Milton Friedman would have been alive today, he would have been horrified at what the Keynesians, the Classicals and the world at large have done to his innocent classroom experiment.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhishek Sancheti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Suppose, a developed economy is experiencing a period of stagnation coupled with really low-interest rates and the government approaches the central bank to devise a way to spur spending and output in the economy. The central bank tries the conventional way of reducing interest rates to stimulate spending, inflation, growth and output but it falls flat as the interest rates were already very close to zero. Hence, the changes in the interest rates were not substantial enough to bring about a major change in output and spending. Worried, the central bank finds itself in a tough spot with limited monetary options to get out of this fix, none of which are effective. According to Friedman, the only solution would be to fly a helicopter above a community, literally dropping 100 dollar notes out of the sky for the general public to freely spend on commodities and services, therefore stimulating spending, output, and growth.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">“Ti Amo Italia”, the EU’s Rhetoric?</title>
      <link href="/the-EU-Rhetoric" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Ti Amo Italia”, the EU's Rhetoric?" />
      <published>2019-03-15T15:18:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-15T15:18:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/the-EU-Rhetoric</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/the-EU-Rhetoric">&lt;p&gt;Although the rest of the world may think so, Brexit and Greece are not the only
problems which are troubling the European Union right now. While there is no
denying the fact that the Union has seen many ups-and-downs in its 26-year
history and has averted many crises, it now stands at a juncture where its
future looks bleak, at best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From getting the upper-hand in the Brexit negotiations to bailing out Greece,
the European Union saw to it that it tackled both these headaches. On one hand,
it has punished Britain for leaving the Union while on the other hand, it has
somewhat saved the Euro and the Grecian economy from going haywire. At the
moment, however, it is concerned about the third largest economy of the Union
which is at the verge of failure even though it was branded as “too big to
fail”. This economy, called Italy, is marred with high levels of unemployment
and unsustainable levels of debt. If it fails, no matter what measures Paris and
Berlin may take, the European Union would most probably break up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Italy’s condition was not always like that. The economy had been doing
pretty good, growing at a respectable pace of 4% up until the global financial
crisis of 2008. The Italians were taking full advantage of the available cheap
credit and were borrowing freely and heavily from the market to finance their
developmental and infrastructural projects. Before anyone could know, the total
debt of Italy was already more than 100% of the GDP. Even though the situation
was alarming, the banks and investors had confidence in Italy paying off its
debt as its economy was prospering and taking full advantage of the boom.
However, when the financial crisis of 2008 hit the Italians, it hit them hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economy was pushed into a recession and since then, Italy has lost 6-7% of
its GDP, the largest loss in the European Union after Greece. When it tried to
recover, the 2011 debt crisis hit back, with the investors losing confidence in
the Euro. What saved Italy from bankruptcy and the European Union from
destruction was Mario Draghi, the Italian President of the European Central
Bank. He famously stated, “I will do whatever it takes me to preserve the Euro.
And believe me, it will be enough.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His decision of printing money to buy up government bonds in the European Union,
reluctantly supported by Germans, is what averted the crisis and pushed it back
further. However, the debt crisis and the lost confidence of investors in the
Euro led to the ousting of the then Prime Minister of Italy, Silvio Berlusconi
in the year 2011. Since then, political instability has also added to the woes
of the Italian economy as the country did not have an elected Prime Minister
till the end of 2018. The present government is being headed by Giuseppe Conte
and is a coalition of the extreme-left Five Star Movement and the extreme-right
League. To add to that instability, the government is currently facing a dilemma
between the European Union and its citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real GDP of Italy is still below what it was before the financial crisis of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The per capita GDP is lower than what it was two decades ago. Industrial
production is down by 25%, which has led to massive outbursts of unemployment.
Currently, the official unemployment rate in Italy stands at 10%. However, youth
unemployment is currently between 30-35%. In South Italy, the situation is
absolutely catastrophic with devastating unemployment rates of 60-70%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly speaking, the Italian government does not have money to finance projects
for employment generation. Italy’s sovereign debt stands at $2.1 trillion and
it pays $80 billion as interest each year. Hence, the investors are losing
confidence in Italian government bonds, which is reflected in Moody’s rating of
Baa3, its lowest investment grade above junk status. This has made the cost of
raising debt far too costly for the government of Italy as the difference
between the rate of interest of Italian bonds and German bonds has already
breached the 300-point mark, which is a sign of concern for Italy right now.
This is why foreign investors are selling their Italian bonds like hot cakes in
the market and getting the hell out of the country as they fear Italy to be the
next Greece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason for the empty pockets of the government is shadow economy and tax
evasion. 30% of the economy is unaccounted for, which leads to the government
losing out on a huge amount of tax revenue. Moreover, low labour productivity
coupled with minimum wages makes Italy unattractive as a manufacturing hub. To
add to this, the population of Italy is ageing. Each woman on an average
produces only 1.3 children which has led to the rapid ageing of the Italian
population. This means a higher expenditure for the government on social
security and lower productivity of the citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of its empty pockets, the left-right government of Italy has proposed
ambitious plans for the restructuring and redevelopment of the economy and
various employment generation programmes for its citizens in its budget of 2019.
This led to the fiscal deficit of the government to rise to 2.4% of the GDP
which is beyond the accepted limits of 2% of the European Union. Hence, the
European Union Commission asked the Italian government to reduce its fiscal
deficit in order to comply with the EU norms or face severe penalties of up to
0.5% of the GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, doing so would mean the government would have to cut out on employment
generation programmes or drop some of its plans for the redevelopment of the
economy. This would lead to its citizens going through at least one more year of
unemployment and low standards of living. It is clear that the Italian
government can choose either of the two. Either its citizens or the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Negotiations and talks with the European Union Commission and its President
Jean-Claude Juncker haven’t resulted in any resolutions or compromises from
either side. With both sides in a deadlock, this clash could easily be a recipe
for a disaster. Jean-Claude Juncker has expressed his feelings by voicing his
thoughts, “&lt;em&gt;Ti Amo Italia&lt;/em&gt;” and promising to do something about the situation.
However, this looks more like a crowd-pleasing, fake promise in the form of
rhetoric from the Commission President. Matteo Salvini, Italy’s most powerful
politician, has voiced the government’s anger on the stance of the ECB and the
EU on this matter, stating that “&lt;em&gt;the enemies of Europe are those barricaded in
the bunker of Brussels&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This clash between Italy’s populists and the EU’s imperialists could all too
easily set a chain of motions which would lead to far bigger problems for the
EU. This time, the damage would be greater than Brexit or Greece, or both
combined. All that is required is one decision of the government, one investor
losing confidence or one bank failing. With the economists already predicting a
global financial crisis, would Italy be the one to start it all?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhishek Sancheti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Although the rest of the world may think so, Brexit and Greece are not the only problems which are troubling the European Union right now. While there is no denying the fact that the Union has seen many ups-and-downs in its 26-year history and has averted many crises, it now stands at a juncture where its future looks bleak, at best. From getting the upper-hand in the Brexit negotiations to bailing out Greece, the European Union saw to it that it tackled both these headaches. On one hand, it has punished Britain for leaving the Union while on the other hand, it has somewhat saved the Euro and the Grecian economy from going haywire. At the moment, however, it is concerned about the third largest economy of the Union which is at the verge of failure even though it was branded as “too big to fail”. This economy, called Italy, is marred with high levels of unemployment and unsustainable levels of debt. If it fails, no matter what measures Paris and Berlin may take, the European Union would most probably break up. But Italy’s condition was not always like that. The economy had been doing pretty good, growing at a respectable pace of 4% up until the global financial crisis of 2008. The Italians were taking full advantage of the available cheap credit and were borrowing freely and heavily from the market to finance their developmental and infrastructural projects. Before anyone could know, the total debt of Italy was already more than 100% of the GDP. Even though the situation was alarming, the banks and investors had confidence in Italy paying off its debt as its economy was prospering and taking full advantage of the boom. However, when the financial crisis of 2008 hit the Italians, it hit them hard. The economy was pushed into a recession and since then, Italy has lost 6-7% of its GDP, the largest loss in the European Union after Greece. When it tried to recover, the 2011 debt crisis hit back, with the investors losing confidence in the Euro. What saved Italy from bankruptcy and the European Union from destruction was Mario Draghi, the Italian President of the European Central Bank. He famously stated, “I will do whatever it takes me to preserve the Euro. And believe me, it will be enough.” His decision of printing money to buy up government bonds in the European Union, reluctantly supported by Germans, is what averted the crisis and pushed it back further. However, the debt crisis and the lost confidence of investors in the Euro led to the ousting of the then Prime Minister of Italy, Silvio Berlusconi in the year 2011. Since then, political instability has also added to the woes of the Italian economy as the country did not have an elected Prime Minister till the end of 2018. The present government is being headed by Giuseppe Conte and is a coalition of the extreme-left Five Star Movement and the extreme-right League. To add to that instability, the government is currently facing a dilemma between the European Union and its citizens. The real GDP of Italy is still below what it was before the financial crisis of The per capita GDP is lower than what it was two decades ago. Industrial production is down by 25%, which has led to massive outbursts of unemployment. Currently, the official unemployment rate in Italy stands at 10%. However, youth unemployment is currently between 30-35%. In South Italy, the situation is absolutely catastrophic with devastating unemployment rates of 60-70%. Frankly speaking, the Italian government does not have money to finance projects for employment generation. Italy’s sovereign debt stands at $2.1 trillion and it pays $80 billion as interest each year. Hence, the investors are losing confidence in Italian government bonds, which is reflected in Moody’s rating of Baa3, its lowest investment grade above junk status. This has made the cost of raising debt far too costly for the government of Italy as the difference between the rate of interest of Italian bonds and German bonds has already breached the 300-point mark, which is a sign of concern for Italy right now. This is why foreign investors are selling their Italian bonds like hot cakes in the market and getting the hell out of the country as they fear Italy to be the next Greece. Another reason for the empty pockets of the government is shadow economy and tax evasion. 30% of the economy is unaccounted for, which leads to the government losing out on a huge amount of tax revenue. Moreover, low labour productivity coupled with minimum wages makes Italy unattractive as a manufacturing hub. To add to this, the population of Italy is ageing. Each woman on an average produces only 1.3 children which has led to the rapid ageing of the Italian population. This means a higher expenditure for the government on social security and lower productivity of the citizens. In spite of its empty pockets, the left-right government of Italy has proposed ambitious plans for the restructuring and redevelopment of the economy and various employment generation programmes for its citizens in its budget of 2019. This led to the fiscal deficit of the government to rise to 2.4% of the GDP which is beyond the accepted limits of 2% of the European Union. Hence, the European Union Commission asked the Italian government to reduce its fiscal deficit in order to comply with the EU norms or face severe penalties of up to 0.5% of the GDP. However, doing so would mean the government would have to cut out on employment generation programmes or drop some of its plans for the redevelopment of the economy. This would lead to its citizens going through at least one more year of unemployment and low standards of living. It is clear that the Italian government can choose either of the two. Either its citizens or the EU. Negotiations and talks with the European Union Commission and its President Jean-Claude Juncker haven’t resulted in any resolutions or compromises from either side. With both sides in a deadlock, this clash could easily be a recipe for a disaster. Jean-Claude Juncker has expressed his feelings by voicing his thoughts, “Ti Amo Italia” and promising to do something about the situation. However, this looks more like a crowd-pleasing, fake promise in the form of rhetoric from the Commission President. Matteo Salvini, Italy’s most powerful politician, has voiced the government’s anger on the stance of the ECB and the EU on this matter, stating that “the enemies of Europe are those barricaded in the bunker of Brussels.” This clash between Italy’s populists and the EU’s imperialists could all too easily set a chain of motions which would lead to far bigger problems for the EU. This time, the damage would be greater than Brexit or Greece, or both combined. All that is required is one decision of the government, one investor losing confidence or one bank failing. With the economists already predicting a global financial crisis, would Italy be the one to start it all?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Understanding the Great Divergence and the Great Convergence</title>
      <link href="/Understanding-the-Great-Divergence-and-the-Great-Convergence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding the Great Divergence and the Great Convergence" />
      <published>2019-03-15T15:18:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-15T15:18:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Understanding-the-Great-Divergence-and-the-Great-Convergence</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-the-Great-Divergence-and-the-Great-Convergence">&lt;p&gt;Prior to the beginning of the 19th century, economies around the world were
highly localised and agrarian. Commerce was seemingly restricted to domestic
production and self-consumption, compelling countries to thrive independently;
transnational trade was underdeveloped at the time. However, with the advent of
the Industrial Revolution in Western Europe around 1760, nations discovered new
methods of production and advanced ways of transportation that employed
inventive machinery and steam power. This facilitated trade by lowering the
costs of moving goods across borders, thus marking the dawn of an age of
globalisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an unprecedented change in the environment for trade gave way to what
scholars term the “Great Divergence”. Between 1820 and 1990, the Great
Divergence is said to have sponsored a rise in the share of global income going
to the Western world from one-fifth of the total to an estimated two-thirds.
Conversely, however, today that share has plunged to where it was in 1900, thus
representing what academics have named the “Great Convergence”. Identified with
reduced communication costs in addition to low trade costs, the Great
Convergence has endorsed the rapid growth of developing and underdeveloped
countries, collectively bringing them almost at par with the share of global GDP
going to the Western world today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the history of humankind, there have been three elaborate phases that
have led to the development of today’s global economy. Phase One, which existed
between 200,000 BCE and 10,000 BCE, was predominantly characterised by the
procurement of food over various seasons and regions. The early man moved around
in search of new locations where he could hunt or cultivate. Food was the
primary good of exchange. Hence, this phase was characterised by
self-locomotion, rather than the movement of goods. In Phase Two, the global
economy progressed towards localisation, and witnessed the exchange of diverse
goods and services between 10,000 BCE and 1820 CE. Revolutions in agriculture
and science triggered population growth, which led to the formation of
civilisations and food surpluses.  Countries termed the &lt;em&gt;Ancient Seven&lt;/em&gt; or the
&lt;em&gt;A7&lt;/em&gt; flourished extensively and witnessed sizeable economic growth. These were
India, China, Egypt, Turkey, Iran, Iraq, and Greece/Italy. It was more
profitable for these countries to manufacture and sell within domestic
territories rather than globally. Local market conditions determined prices,
while international factors had almost no role to play. Although trade did
emerge with the development of the Silk Route and Spice Route among other means,
globalisation in its modern understanding had not yet begun on account of high
trade costs, high communication costs, and high face-to-face costs. It was only
after 1820 that Phase Three witnessed true globalisation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having harnessed steam power, the Industrial Revolution in Western Europe
emphasised the importance of iron and steel in modern manufacturing while
augmenting the establishment of factories and industrial districts. Production
was micro-clustered to gain from economies of scale by channeling
specialisation, division of labour and better allocation of resources. With the
development of railroads and steamships, trade costs dipped, thus enlarging
international trade volumes significantly. Incomes of Western countries
subsequently diverged and marked the beginning of the Great Divergence. Kenneth
Pomeranz’s book, &lt;em&gt;The Great Divergence&lt;/em&gt;, is accredited with making the term
popular among business historians and economists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, why did the incomes of the West and the Rest diverge? Since 1500, India and
China had been enjoying the largest shares of world output with high per capita
incomes and wealthy trade. What caused the sudden divergence of Western incomes
that led to what some have termed the “North-South income gap”? There are three
prominent explanations. The first explanation stresses on &lt;em&gt;cultural factors&lt;/em&gt;.
Niall Ferguson, author of &lt;em&gt;Civilization: West and the Rest&lt;/em&gt;, identifies the
Protestant work ethic as a killer model of capitalist enterprise. The &lt;em&gt;Group of
Seven&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;G7&lt;/em&gt; countries: United States, Britain, France, Germany, Canada,
Japan, and Italy, underwent rapid industrialization and overtook the &lt;em&gt;A7&lt;/em&gt; in
world dominance and wealth. The West apparently had the ‘right’ culture while
the Rest had the ‘wrong’ culture for sustenance in the international market post
Phase Three&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; Unsurprisingly, this explanation is highly contested and lacks
adequate evidence for its validity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second explanation highlights &lt;em&gt;institutional factors&lt;/em&gt;. It is said that the
West had at its disposal, access to better institutions and progressive
political establishments, thus facilitating faster growth in the modern era. On
the contrary, countries like India suffered adverse colonial rule while
countries like China witnessed regular instabilities with changing regimes and
leaders. Similarly, the legal systems in &lt;em&gt;G7&lt;/em&gt; countries were more advanced and
accountable relative to their &lt;em&gt;A7&lt;/em&gt; counterparts. There is sufficient evidence to
back these claims, however, the Great Divergence was not entirely based on the
foundations of this explanation. And reinforcing this criticism, the final
explanation talks about &lt;em&gt;educational factors&lt;/em&gt; as determinants of global wealth
and poverty.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Claudia Goldin claims in the research paper &lt;em&gt;The Human-Capital Century and
American Leadership:&lt;/em&gt; “the unique egalitarian mass provision of post-elementary
schooling achieved in the United States during the early twentieth century”
validates the educational superiority of the West compared to the Rest. Western
Europe and North America witnessed higher literacy rates and more spending on
education in the modern era, thus augmenting their abilities in trade and
commerce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would say that the harmonisation of all these factors can be said to have led
to the Great Divergence. For most of the modern era, the West outshone the Rest
in all three – cultural, institutional, and educational factors. But then, what
really led to the Great Convergence? Was it the West that lost pace or the Rest
that gathered it? Well, both happened simultaneously…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth of the West is said to have slowed down after attaining a certain
degree of development, while growth of the Rest is said to have sped up so as to
attain that certain degree of development. The mutual decrease in trade and
communication costs is what facilitated the Great Convergence. With the advent
of information technology, the cost of moving &lt;em&gt;ideas&lt;/em&gt; across borders, besides
&lt;em&gt;goods&lt;/em&gt;, fell significantly. This made it possible for multinational firms to
shift labour-intensive work to underdeveloped and developing nations, thus
saving private as well as social costs. However, in order to preserve and
maintain the entire production process, in addition to outsourcing jobs, these
firms also had to transfer their technical, managerial, financial, and marketing
know-how to these countries – mainly the currently &lt;em&gt;Industrialising Six&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;I6&lt;/em&gt;
– China, India, Poland, Korea, Thailand, and Indonesia.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The West aimed at gaining from the unification of advanced technology and
skilled workers, both of which were easily and economically available in these
countries. While this promoted the industrialisation of the &lt;em&gt;I6&lt;/em&gt;, it also
triggered the deindustrialisation of the &lt;em&gt;G7&lt;/em&gt;. Moreover, towards the end of the
20th century, &lt;em&gt;I6&lt;/em&gt; countries began investing considerably in improving their
institutions and extending education to more citizens. Most exploited countries
were no longer under colonial rule; there was more political stability within
nations and greater international peace after the Second World War. These
factors collectively helped developing countries amplify their growth, and
secure higher incomes with better standards of living for their people.
Therefore, investment brought into developing countries by developed ones, and
self-investment by developing countries themselves, are what mutually led to a
decline in the Western share of global GDP and a convergence of income
inequalities between the global North and South. The stagnated and shrunken
economies of China and India, among others, in the &lt;em&gt;I6&lt;/em&gt; revived remarkably.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, &lt;em&gt;I6&lt;/em&gt; countries and &lt;em&gt;G7&lt;/em&gt; countries enjoy more or less the same share of
global income and output. Although the &lt;em&gt;G7&lt;/em&gt; might still be richer than the
&lt;em&gt;I6&lt;/em&gt;, they no longer treasure the dominance that they once did. Poverty in
developing countries is on the fall owing to an increase in employment and
improved quality of life. Contrastingly, wealth in developed countries is on the
fall owing to debt burdens, reduced employment, brain-drain, and monetary
advances to the rest of the world.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may affirm that the two final phases in the evolution of globalisation were
responsible for both the Great Divergence and the Great Convergence; only these
two phases differed vastly from one another. The former of the two phases
witnessed the growth of the Asian economies until the 19th century, after which
the European-Atlantic Economy surpassed the income levels and growth rates
prevalent in pre-modern Asia. The latter of the two phases is accredited with
subduing the growth of modern European-Atlantic countries, while elevating Asian
ones to better income levels and improved growth rates. This reversed cycle
confirms that both phases of globalisation are opposite to each other in nature.
Currently, we live in its second phase attributed to advanced information
technology and global income parity. And there is no better way to end this
economic-history article than asking, “&lt;em&gt;What Next?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shivang Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Prior to the beginning of the 19th century, economies around the world were highly localised and agrarian. Commerce was seemingly restricted to domestic production and self-consumption, compelling countries to thrive independently; transnational trade was underdeveloped at the time. However, with the advent of the Industrial Revolution in Western Europe around 1760, nations discovered new methods of production and advanced ways of transportation that employed inventive machinery and steam power. This facilitated trade by lowering the costs of moving goods across borders, thus marking the dawn of an age of globalisation. Such an unprecedented change in the environment for trade gave way to what scholars term the “Great Divergence”. Between 1820 and 1990, the Great Divergence is said to have sponsored a rise in the share of global income going to the Western world from one-fifth of the total to an estimated two-thirds. Conversely, however, today that share has plunged to where it was in 1900, thus representing what academics have named the “Great Convergence”. Identified with reduced communication costs in addition to low trade costs, the Great Convergence has endorsed the rapid growth of developing and underdeveloped countries, collectively bringing them almost at par with the share of global GDP going to the Western world today. Throughout the history of humankind, there have been three elaborate phases that have led to the development of today’s global economy. Phase One, which existed between 200,000 BCE and 10,000 BCE, was predominantly characterised by the procurement of food over various seasons and regions. The early man moved around in search of new locations where he could hunt or cultivate. Food was the primary good of exchange. Hence, this phase was characterised by self-locomotion, rather than the movement of goods. In Phase Two, the global economy progressed towards localisation, and witnessed the exchange of diverse goods and services between 10,000 BCE and 1820 CE. Revolutions in agriculture and science triggered population growth, which led to the formation of civilisations and food surpluses.  Countries termed the Ancient Seven or the A7 flourished extensively and witnessed sizeable economic growth. These were India, China, Egypt, Turkey, Iran, Iraq, and Greece/Italy. It was more profitable for these countries to manufacture and sell within domestic territories rather than globally. Local market conditions determined prices, while international factors had almost no role to play. Although trade did emerge with the development of the Silk Route and Spice Route among other means, globalisation in its modern understanding had not yet begun on account of high trade costs, high communication costs, and high face-to-face costs. It was only after 1820 that Phase Three witnessed true globalisation.   Having harnessed steam power, the Industrial Revolution in Western Europe emphasised the importance of iron and steel in modern manufacturing while augmenting the establishment of factories and industrial districts. Production was micro-clustered to gain from economies of scale by channeling specialisation, division of labour and better allocation of resources. With the development of railroads and steamships, trade costs dipped, thus enlarging international trade volumes significantly. Incomes of Western countries subsequently diverged and marked the beginning of the Great Divergence. Kenneth Pomeranz’s book, The Great Divergence, is accredited with making the term popular among business historians and economists. But, why did the incomes of the West and the Rest diverge? Since 1500, India and China had been enjoying the largest shares of world output with high per capita incomes and wealthy trade. What caused the sudden divergence of Western incomes that led to what some have termed the “North-South income gap”? There are three prominent explanations. The first explanation stresses on cultural factors. Niall Ferguson, author of Civilization: West and the Rest, identifies the Protestant work ethic as a killer model of capitalist enterprise. The Group of Seven or G7 countries: United States, Britain, France, Germany, Canada, Japan, and Italy, underwent rapid industrialization and overtook the A7 in world dominance and wealth. The West apparently had the ‘right’ culture while the Rest had the ‘wrong’ culture for sustenance in the international market post Phase Three. Unsurprisingly, this explanation is highly contested and lacks adequate evidence for its validity. The second explanation highlights institutional factors. It is said that the West had at its disposal, access to better institutions and progressive political establishments, thus facilitating faster growth in the modern era. On the contrary, countries like India suffered adverse colonial rule while countries like China witnessed regular instabilities with changing regimes and leaders. Similarly, the legal systems in G7 countries were more advanced and accountable relative to their A7 counterparts. There is sufficient evidence to back these claims, however, the Great Divergence was not entirely based on the foundations of this explanation. And reinforcing this criticism, the final explanation talks about educational factors as determinants of global wealth and poverty.   As Claudia Goldin claims in the research paper The Human-Capital Century and American Leadership: “the unique egalitarian mass provision of post-elementary schooling achieved in the United States during the early twentieth century” validates the educational superiority of the West compared to the Rest. Western Europe and North America witnessed higher literacy rates and more spending on education in the modern era, thus augmenting their abilities in trade and commerce. I would say that the harmonisation of all these factors can be said to have led to the Great Divergence. For most of the modern era, the West outshone the Rest in all three – cultural, institutional, and educational factors. But then, what really led to the Great Convergence? Was it the West that lost pace or the Rest that gathered it? Well, both happened simultaneously… The growth of the West is said to have slowed down after attaining a certain degree of development, while growth of the Rest is said to have sped up so as to attain that certain degree of development. The mutual decrease in trade and communication costs is what facilitated the Great Convergence. With the advent of information technology, the cost of moving ideas across borders, besides goods, fell significantly. This made it possible for multinational firms to shift labour-intensive work to underdeveloped and developing nations, thus saving private as well as social costs. However, in order to preserve and maintain the entire production process, in addition to outsourcing jobs, these firms also had to transfer their technical, managerial, financial, and marketing know-how to these countries – mainly the currently Industrialising Six or I6 – China, India, Poland, Korea, Thailand, and Indonesia.   The West aimed at gaining from the unification of advanced technology and skilled workers, both of which were easily and economically available in these countries. While this promoted the industrialisation of the I6, it also triggered the deindustrialisation of the G7. Moreover, towards the end of the 20th century, I6 countries began investing considerably in improving their institutions and extending education to more citizens. Most exploited countries were no longer under colonial rule; there was more political stability within nations and greater international peace after the Second World War. These factors collectively helped developing countries amplify their growth, and secure higher incomes with better standards of living for their people. Therefore, investment brought into developing countries by developed ones, and self-investment by developing countries themselves, are what mutually led to a decline in the Western share of global GDP and a convergence of income inequalities between the global North and South. The stagnated and shrunken economies of China and India, among others, in the I6 revived remarkably.   Today, I6 countries and G7 countries enjoy more or less the same share of global income and output. Although the G7 might still be richer than the I6, they no longer treasure the dominance that they once did. Poverty in developing countries is on the fall owing to an increase in employment and improved quality of life. Contrastingly, wealth in developed countries is on the fall owing to debt burdens, reduced employment, brain-drain, and monetary advances to the rest of the world.   We may affirm that the two final phases in the evolution of globalisation were responsible for both the Great Divergence and the Great Convergence; only these two phases differed vastly from one another. The former of the two phases witnessed the growth of the Asian economies until the 19th century, after which the European-Atlantic Economy surpassed the income levels and growth rates prevalent in pre-modern Asia. The latter of the two phases is accredited with subduing the growth of modern European-Atlantic countries, while elevating Asian ones to better income levels and improved growth rates. This reversed cycle confirms that both phases of globalisation are opposite to each other in nature. Currently, we live in its second phase attributed to advanced information technology and global income parity. And there is no better way to end this economic-history article than asking, “What Next?”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Can Minimum Wage Reduce Poverty?</title>
      <link href="/Can-Minimum-Wage-Reduce-Poverty" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can Minimum Wage Reduce Poverty?" />
      <published>2019-03-08T23:45:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-08T23:45:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Can-Minimum-Wage-Reduce-Poverty</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Can-Minimum-Wage-Reduce-Poverty">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A guide to its effective implementation…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minimum wage in the United Kingdom is considered one of the most successful
government policies ever implemented. It was intricately planned and structured
over a significant length of time. And with one of the lowest unemployment rates
in Europe, Britain, at first sight, appears to illustrate an accurate balance
between executing a minimum wage policy and preserving the uniform availability
of job opportunities (even if Brexit could change that drastically). Apart from
Britain, even Hong Kong has witnessed an upward trend in median monthly wages of
unskilled workers by 43% in money terms and 20% in real terms between 2010 and 2014. Synchronously, the 2014 Report on Annual Earnings and Hours Survey
published by The Census and Statistics Department outlines inputs from the
Minimum Wage Commission that indicate a fall in the unemployment rate for
elementary occupations from 4.4% in 2010 to 3.3% in 2014. Advocates of minimum
wage legislation argue that it can alter the income distribution in favour of
the low-paid labour force by attenuating the bottom tail of the distribution
model. Opponents criticise its “Disemployment Effect” and emphasise that it
might shrink the share of earnings going to the impoverished and destitute
workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A higher minimum wage, evidently, increases costs for firms. This may curtail
them from hiring the exceptionally low-wage, low-skill workers. David Neumark,
an American labour economist, terms this the “Disemployment Effect”. It is
characterised by the loss of jobs, reduction in working hours, automation, or
the struggle to enter into new jobs. The Disemployment Effect, if necessitated
by a minimum wage, invalidates the purpose of bringing in such a policy in the
first place. But this effect can be overcome. Firms can be offered economic
incentives such as subsidies and grants, to compensate for their increased
costs. Lower taxes and excise duties could also serve as economic incentives,
ensuring more cash is available for businesses to absorb the costs of paying a
higher minimum wage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Disemployment Effect is not the only uncertain outcome of a minimum
wage policy, especially in developing countries. As the minimum wage and poverty
lines are closer to each other in developing nations, an increase in minimum
wage could lift workers out of destitution. Yet, several minimum wage workers in
developing countries are young, work part-time, and belong to high-income
households. Correspondingly, most households in poverty seldom have anyone in
the workforce&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; Hence, more often than not, a minimum wage ends up helping
the privileged and ignoring the needy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To end poverty, a minimum wage should be determined for households and not
individuals. This will facilitate the redistribution of income to poor families
over low-earners of rich families. Simultaneously, governments must increase
spending on education and skill development to build an economy with a speedily
employable workforce, hence fostering growth and development. A minimum wage
policy also needs to tackle the problem of incomplete and irregular legal
coverage. Although minimum wages seem to be extensively applicable, in several
cases the coverage is ineffective and disregards those most in need of social
security, such as domestic workers or homeworkers. By neglecting a few crucial
sectors of the economy, we fail to fully utilise the potential of minimum wage
legislation. Even though legal coverage of the minimum wage developed from the
mid-2000’s to the late 2000’s in India and South Africa, it covered only about
70% of low-paid workers by late 2000’s; in Peru, domestic workers were barred
from the statutory minimum wage&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; Research suggests that weak legal coverage
may at times ignore around one-third of all wage earners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may confront this perplexity by undertaking comprehensive legislation that
gratifies all sectors of an economy, and by ensuring that such legislation is
strictly enforced. This, while a herculean task, can be accomplished by the
extensive and intensive consultation of all stakeholders and a thorough analysis
of a variety of socioeconomic and employment data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minimum wage is fast becoming a universally adopted policy today and the
principal question is how to operate the system in order to maximise its
benefits. A conscientiously devised minimum wage policy can relegate low pay,
inequalities, and poverty, at little or no adverse cost to employment. Yet, the
minimum wage either continues to be low in many countries, or applies solely to
certain select sectors. But with a little more fine-tuning, as I have suggested,
I believe it is possible to shape an effective minimum wage policy that
successfully reduces poverty and income inequalities across countries without
hurting the job market.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shivang Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A guide to its effective implementation… The minimum wage in the United Kingdom is considered one of the most successful government policies ever implemented. It was intricately planned and structured over a significant length of time. And with one of the lowest unemployment rates in Europe, Britain, at first sight, appears to illustrate an accurate balance between executing a minimum wage policy and preserving the uniform availability of job opportunities (even if Brexit could change that drastically). Apart from Britain, even Hong Kong has witnessed an upward trend in median monthly wages of unskilled workers by 43% in money terms and 20% in real terms between 2010 and 2014. Synchronously, the 2014 Report on Annual Earnings and Hours Survey published by The Census and Statistics Department outlines inputs from the Minimum Wage Commission that indicate a fall in the unemployment rate for elementary occupations from 4.4% in 2010 to 3.3% in 2014. Advocates of minimum wage legislation argue that it can alter the income distribution in favour of the low-paid labour force by attenuating the bottom tail of the distribution model. Opponents criticise its “Disemployment Effect” and emphasise that it might shrink the share of earnings going to the impoverished and destitute workforce. A higher minimum wage, evidently, increases costs for firms. This may curtail them from hiring the exceptionally low-wage, low-skill workers. David Neumark, an American labour economist, terms this the “Disemployment Effect”. It is characterised by the loss of jobs, reduction in working hours, automation, or the struggle to enter into new jobs. The Disemployment Effect, if necessitated by a minimum wage, invalidates the purpose of bringing in such a policy in the first place. But this effect can be overcome. Firms can be offered economic incentives such as subsidies and grants, to compensate for their increased costs. Lower taxes and excise duties could also serve as economic incentives, ensuring more cash is available for businesses to absorb the costs of paying a higher minimum wage. However, the Disemployment Effect is not the only uncertain outcome of a minimum wage policy, especially in developing countries. As the minimum wage and poverty lines are closer to each other in developing nations, an increase in minimum wage could lift workers out of destitution. Yet, several minimum wage workers in developing countries are young, work part-time, and belong to high-income households. Correspondingly, most households in poverty seldom have anyone in the workforce. Hence, more often than not, a minimum wage ends up helping the privileged and ignoring the needy. To end poverty, a minimum wage should be determined for households and not individuals. This will facilitate the redistribution of income to poor families over low-earners of rich families. Simultaneously, governments must increase spending on education and skill development to build an economy with a speedily employable workforce, hence fostering growth and development. A minimum wage policy also needs to tackle the problem of incomplete and irregular legal coverage. Although minimum wages seem to be extensively applicable, in several cases the coverage is ineffective and disregards those most in need of social security, such as domestic workers or homeworkers. By neglecting a few crucial sectors of the economy, we fail to fully utilise the potential of minimum wage legislation. Even though legal coverage of the minimum wage developed from the mid-2000’s to the late 2000’s in India and South Africa, it covered only about 70% of low-paid workers by late 2000’s; in Peru, domestic workers were barred from the statutory minimum wage. Research suggests that weak legal coverage may at times ignore around one-third of all wage earners. We may confront this perplexity by undertaking comprehensive legislation that gratifies all sectors of an economy, and by ensuring that such legislation is strictly enforced. This, while a herculean task, can be accomplished by the extensive and intensive consultation of all stakeholders and a thorough analysis of a variety of socioeconomic and employment data. The minimum wage is fast becoming a universally adopted policy today and the principal question is how to operate the system in order to maximise its benefits. A conscientiously devised minimum wage policy can relegate low pay, inequalities, and poverty, at little or no adverse cost to employment. Yet, the minimum wage either continues to be low in many countries, or applies solely to certain select sectors. But with a little more fine-tuning, as I have suggested, I believe it is possible to shape an effective minimum wage policy that successfully reduces poverty and income inequalities across countries without hurting the job market.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Micro Economies: Big Challenges and Small Opportunities</title>
      <link href="/Micro-Economies" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Micro Economies: Big Challenges and Small Opportunities" />
      <published>2019-03-08T23:30:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-08T23:30:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Micro-Economies</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Micro-Economies">&lt;p&gt;Niue (a small island nation in the Pacific Ocean) has a population even less
than the number of students studying in the Shri Ram College of Commerce,
University of Delhi. According to the World Bank, all economies with a
population of less than 0.5 million are considered to be “micro.” At present,
there are 29 such countries which constitute around 15% of the total number of
countries in the world. They are usually found together in groups and are
prevalent in three regions: the Caribbean, the Pacific, and Africa. Despite
their spread across the world, they have negligible say in the functioning of
the world economy. And this article is an attempt to understand the economic
systems of the ‘subaltern’ countries of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These economies (also called micro-economies) are either landlocked countries or
island nations, mostly present in the middle of nowhere. In either case, they
are isolated from the ‘markets’. This increases the cost of transportation as
the goods either have to travel long distances over oceans or through several
countries. This increases the overall cost of production which makes the goods
produced in these countries unattractive in international markets, and imports
costly. As a result, exports in the commodity sector is low in these economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Micro-economies have limited labour supply in the market. A labourer is expected
to perform several duties which leads to the overburdening of work. This reduces
labour productivity and labourers are unable to specialise in one kind of work.
Thus, the economy cannot receive the benefits of specialisation and division of
labour. Contrary to enjoying economies of scale, micro-economies face
‘&lt;em&gt;diseconomies of size’&lt;/em&gt; due to low demand and high production costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very evidently, micro-economies are unattractive for new market entrants. Hence,
these markets are generally a monopoly or an oligopoly, which provide a limited
range of products and services at high costs. High costs, in turn, lead to
poverty and large income inequalities. This can be substantiated from the fact
that countries like Lesotho, Guinea-Bissau, Gambia, Gabon, Suriname have more
than 40% of their total population living below the internationally accepted
poverty line of $1.90 per day. Limited production also leads to extremely low
GNP per capita: Comoros, Gambia, Guinea-Bissau and Sao Tome and Principe have a
GNP per capita of less than $500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Production is not the only area where economies of scale benefit a country. It
is seen that economies of scale greatly benefits an economy when it comes to
providing social security and creating social and economic infrastructure, as
well. A country with a huge population and a higher number of taxpayers has huge
amounts of money to spend on infrastructure. The cost of social security, as
well as social and economic infrastructure, is spread over a larger population.
This reduces the cost incurred per person for providing these facilities. In the
case of small economies, the population, as well as the number of taxpayers, is
low. Hence, the governments of these countries have almost no money to spend on
building and developing economic infrastructures such as highways and roadways,
and social infrastructures like schools and hospitals. All this ensures foreign
investment never comes into these countries, creating a &lt;em&gt;chakravyuh&lt;/em&gt; (vicious cycle) of poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With limited production capacities and little diversification, micro-economies
are generally capable of specialising in the production of one good or service,
in which they have an advantage over other economies. Due to the low population,
the demand for their commodities is low and limited. This means that they are
ready to export the commodity in which they have a competitive advantage over
the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of these economies are also highly dependent on tourism. This is evident
from the fact that tourism constitutes more than 50% in Fiji and more than 40%
in Vanuatu and the Caribbean States as part of their total exports. In fact,
imports and exports combined constitute more than 100% of the GDP of these
countries. But this high degree of openness also makes it highly vulnerable to
international events and shocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their vulnerability can be seen as how these economies developed at staggering
paces of more than 8% per annum before 2008. But, as soon as the 2008 financial
crisis hit, the income from tourism sector plummeted rapidly. This had such an
impact on the economies that these countries grew at -1% to 0% for the next two
years. Vulnerability also makes income more volatile. It is seen that the
standard deviation of the real per capita GDP growth is more than 9. This means
that there can be an average of 9% change per annum in their per capita GDP, as
compared to the world average of 3.2%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These economies also function as parasites. Just like parasites feed upon the
parent trees, these economies feed and depend upon a large economy which is
beside them. The Caribbean States depend upon Mexico and the US, the African
island nations in the Indian Ocean depend upon India, and those in the Pacific
depend upon Australia and New Zealand. Most of their trade (over 90%) is carried
out with these large economies and in most cases, they take up their currency as
well. Therefore, how these large economies fare in the global market decides the
fate of these micro-economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these ‘parent economies’ seldom take interest in investing in their
children. Hence, micro-economies turn towards the International Monetary Fund,
the International Development Association and various other regional and
international development banks for grants and unilateral advances for
developmental funding. These grants go a long way in helping micro-economies
provide their citizens with basic necessities. Research suggests that these
grants have helped reduce poverty levels by around 2-5% in different
micro-economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the recent challenges that these countries face is global warming and
increased danger of disasters. As most of these countries are islands or chains
of islands, they are just metres above sea level. The rising sea level and
the increased frequency of natural disasters has increased the risk of complete
disappearance of these island nations. Adequate disaster management is
necessary, which requires funds. Owing to lack of funds, these countries have to
look towards the international community and the United Nations for their
sustenance and to equip them with various techniques of disaster risk
management. &lt;em&gt;Debt bells ringing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of having so many problems, micro-economies have some advantages as
well. As most of these small economies are a group of islands, they have access
to huge amounts of the ocean as their territory. Thus, these economies have
Exclusive Economic Zones (EEZ’s) in the oceans. These economies usually grant
foreign multinational corporations permission for fishing and extract resources
from the EEZs against a charge. This has become one of the main sources of
income, apart from allowing military bases of other countries to be set up on
their territory (China and India are watching closely).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these economies also serve as tax havens for the rich billionaires and
multinational corporations. They have very lax to no tax laws. The most
prominent example would be of Cayman Islands (population - 23,000), which by the
mid-1990’s, became the world’s fifth largest banking centre measured by
deposits. There are more than 560 banks registered in this micro-nation,
including major accounting, audit and law firms. The Caymans are the ideal tax
haven as they provide “tax efficient asset protection”. There are no taxes, no
exchange controls and no threat to the ‘confidentiality’ of deposits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Alberto Alesina said in his book &lt;em&gt;Size of Nations&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Whether country size matters for economic prosperity depends on a country’s
degree of economic integration with the rest of the world.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, these economies too, have to integrate with the world economy if they
wish to develop and prosper. They cannot depend on a single economy or a single
commodity for their development. Maldives and Fiji are two micro-economies which
have seen tremendous growth in these recent years after opening up their
economies to the world. They are not totally dependent on their regional powers
or a single commodity for trade. However, they are still part of the exception
than the norm. Other micro-economies too can look up to them, and try, develop,
progress and finally contribute to the global economy. Recognising the existence
of microeconomics, and understanding their nuanced problems, will go a long way
in bringing a change.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhishek Sancheti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Niue (a small island nation in the Pacific Ocean) has a population even less than the number of students studying in the Shri Ram College of Commerce, University of Delhi. According to the World Bank, all economies with a population of less than 0.5 million are considered to be “micro.” At present, there are 29 such countries which constitute around 15% of the total number of countries in the world. They are usually found together in groups and are prevalent in three regions: the Caribbean, the Pacific, and Africa. Despite their spread across the world, they have negligible say in the functioning of the world economy. And this article is an attempt to understand the economic systems of the ‘subaltern’ countries of the world. These economies (also called micro-economies) are either landlocked countries or island nations, mostly present in the middle of nowhere. In either case, they are isolated from the ‘markets’. This increases the cost of transportation as the goods either have to travel long distances over oceans or through several countries. This increases the overall cost of production which makes the goods produced in these countries unattractive in international markets, and imports costly. As a result, exports in the commodity sector is low in these economies. Micro-economies have limited labour supply in the market. A labourer is expected to perform several duties which leads to the overburdening of work. This reduces labour productivity and labourers are unable to specialise in one kind of work. Thus, the economy cannot receive the benefits of specialisation and division of labour. Contrary to enjoying economies of scale, micro-economies face ‘diseconomies of size’ due to low demand and high production costs. Very evidently, micro-economies are unattractive for new market entrants. Hence, these markets are generally a monopoly or an oligopoly, which provide a limited range of products and services at high costs. High costs, in turn, lead to poverty and large income inequalities. This can be substantiated from the fact that countries like Lesotho, Guinea-Bissau, Gambia, Gabon, Suriname have more than 40% of their total population living below the internationally accepted poverty line of $1.90 per day. Limited production also leads to extremely low GNP per capita: Comoros, Gambia, Guinea-Bissau and Sao Tome and Principe have a GNP per capita of less than $500. Production is not the only area where economies of scale benefit a country. It is seen that economies of scale greatly benefits an economy when it comes to providing social security and creating social and economic infrastructure, as well. A country with a huge population and a higher number of taxpayers has huge amounts of money to spend on infrastructure. The cost of social security, as well as social and economic infrastructure, is spread over a larger population. This reduces the cost incurred per person for providing these facilities. In the case of small economies, the population, as well as the number of taxpayers, is low. Hence, the governments of these countries have almost no money to spend on building and developing economic infrastructures such as highways and roadways, and social infrastructures like schools and hospitals. All this ensures foreign investment never comes into these countries, creating a chakravyuh (vicious cycle) of poverty. With limited production capacities and little diversification, micro-economies are generally capable of specialising in the production of one good or service, in which they have an advantage over other economies. Due to the low population, the demand for their commodities is low and limited. This means that they are ready to export the commodity in which they have a competitive advantage over the rest of the world. Many of these economies are also highly dependent on tourism. This is evident from the fact that tourism constitutes more than 50% in Fiji and more than 40% in Vanuatu and the Caribbean States as part of their total exports. In fact, imports and exports combined constitute more than 100% of the GDP of these countries. But this high degree of openness also makes it highly vulnerable to international events and shocks. Their vulnerability can be seen as how these economies developed at staggering paces of more than 8% per annum before 2008. But, as soon as the 2008 financial crisis hit, the income from tourism sector plummeted rapidly. This had such an impact on the economies that these countries grew at -1% to 0% for the next two years. Vulnerability also makes income more volatile. It is seen that the standard deviation of the real per capita GDP growth is more than 9. This means that there can be an average of 9% change per annum in their per capita GDP, as compared to the world average of 3.2%. These economies also function as parasites. Just like parasites feed upon the parent trees, these economies feed and depend upon a large economy which is beside them. The Caribbean States depend upon Mexico and the US, the African island nations in the Indian Ocean depend upon India, and those in the Pacific depend upon Australia and New Zealand. Most of their trade (over 90%) is carried out with these large economies and in most cases, they take up their currency as well. Therefore, how these large economies fare in the global market decides the fate of these micro-economies. However, these ‘parent economies’ seldom take interest in investing in their children. Hence, micro-economies turn towards the International Monetary Fund, the International Development Association and various other regional and international development banks for grants and unilateral advances for developmental funding. These grants go a long way in helping micro-economies provide their citizens with basic necessities. Research suggests that these grants have helped reduce poverty levels by around 2-5% in different micro-economies. One of the recent challenges that these countries face is global warming and increased danger of disasters. As most of these countries are islands or chains of islands, they are just metres above sea level. The rising sea level and the increased frequency of natural disasters has increased the risk of complete disappearance of these island nations. Adequate disaster management is necessary, which requires funds. Owing to lack of funds, these countries have to look towards the international community and the United Nations for their sustenance and to equip them with various techniques of disaster risk management. Debt bells ringing. In spite of having so many problems, micro-economies have some advantages as well. As most of these small economies are a group of islands, they have access to huge amounts of the ocean as their territory. Thus, these economies have Exclusive Economic Zones (EEZ’s) in the oceans. These economies usually grant foreign multinational corporations permission for fishing and extract resources from the EEZs against a charge. This has become one of the main sources of income, apart from allowing military bases of other countries to be set up on their territory (China and India are watching closely). Some of these economies also serve as tax havens for the rich billionaires and multinational corporations. They have very lax to no tax laws. The most prominent example would be of Cayman Islands (population - 23,000), which by the mid-1990’s, became the world’s fifth largest banking centre measured by deposits. There are more than 560 banks registered in this micro-nation, including major accounting, audit and law firms. The Caymans are the ideal tax haven as they provide “tax efficient asset protection”. There are no taxes, no exchange controls and no threat to the ‘confidentiality’ of deposits. As Alberto Alesina said in his book Size of Nations: “Whether country size matters for economic prosperity depends on a country’s degree of economic integration with the rest of the world.” Similarly, these economies too, have to integrate with the world economy if they wish to develop and prosper. They cannot depend on a single economy or a single commodity for their development. Maldives and Fiji are two micro-economies which have seen tremendous growth in these recent years after opening up their economies to the world. They are not totally dependent on their regional powers or a single commodity for trade. However, they are still part of the exception than the norm. Other micro-economies too can look up to them, and try, develop, progress and finally contribute to the global economy. Recognising the existence of microeconomics, and understanding their nuanced problems, will go a long way in bringing a change.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Higher Ups: Appointments and Disappointments</title>
      <link href="/The-Higher-Ups" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Higher Ups: Appointments and Disappointments" />
      <published>2019-02-15T01:50:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-15T01:50:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Higher-Ups</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Higher-Ups">&lt;p&gt;In this article, we take a look at the people in the past decade and more who had exponential burdens placed on their shoulders and examine how they fared. The men and women who moved markets and sentiments; whose names were heard on the internet and in households across the globe, setting examples to follow and learn from, for the generation ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mario-draghi-ecb&quot;&gt;Mario Draghi (ECB)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/5/55/Mario_Draghi_-_World_Economic_Forum_Annual_Meeting_2012.jpg/1024px-Mario_Draghi_-_World_Economic_Forum_Annual_Meeting_2012.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Mario-Draghi.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; Italy &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; La Sapienza University, Massachusetts Institute of Technology&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mario Draghi has been in and out of &lt;i&gt;Most Influential&lt;/i&gt; around the world for more than a decade, topping out at number 2 on &lt;a href=&quot;http://fortune.com/worlds-greatest-leaders/mario-draghi-2/&quot;&gt;Fortune greatest&lt;/a&gt; world leaders. Before taking Jean-Claude Trichet’s place at the top of the European Central Bank, he had served as the Governor of the Bank of Italy and was elected as Chairman of the Financial Stability Forum of 2006. But his biggest achievements came in the form of righting the ship that was the European economy, which was on the brink of collapse with a host of countries running on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=10&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjh6Nj26aPgAhULS48KHV9fDZkQFjAJegQIChAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.telegraph.co.uk%2Fnews%2F0%2Feuropean-debt-crisis-not-just-greece-drowning-debt%2F&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0sq0KE3R4uEWXWRaxmklU1&quot;&gt;failing&lt;/a&gt; economies, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=2&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwivr_fr6aPgAhUGSY8KHc-uAcsQFjABegQICBAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.thebalance.com%2Fwhat-is-the-greece-debt-crisis-3305525&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1nusWDPX7zHeB3hayomLwC&quot;&gt;huge debts&lt;/a&gt; and crippling deficits. He said he would  do “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Pq1V0aPEO3c&quot;&gt;…whatever it takes…&lt;/a&gt;” to preserve the Euro and so he did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only time will tell how this proven leader will stand up to the task of a Britain-less EU economy, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: President of the European Central Bank&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;jean-claude-trichet-ecb&quot;&gt;Jean-Claude Trichet (ECB)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/117994717@N06/15890096265&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Jean-Claude-Trichet.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; France &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; University of Paris, Sciences Po&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming off the worst &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/france/1401696/French-candidate-to-head-Euro-bank-faces-fraud-trial.html&quot;&gt;banking scandal&lt;/a&gt; in French History, Jean-Claude Trichet was able to successfully manoeuvre himself out of the French Treasury and into the leading post at the ECB. It was under his Presidency that Europe plunged into the Great Recession of the 21st Century, and many still believe that he should get most of the blame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was 2009 when an IMF report showing telling signs of a Greek default came out, but Mr Trichet was not ready to budge, standing firmly in resistance stating, “no European country could ever be allowed to go bankrupt”. Instead of fixing the problems &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/06/business/global/europes-two-years-of-denials-trapped-greece.html?_r=1&quot;&gt;he chose to resist any contemplation of a default&lt;/a&gt; until October 2011, when a consensus to devalue Greek bonds was reached. He resigned as President before the end of the month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: Board of Directors, Airbus Group&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;janet-yellen-federal-reserve&quot;&gt;Janet Yellen (Federal Reserve)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/fordschool/33842410502&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Janet-Yellen.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; United States of America &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; Brown University, Yale University&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one of the huge success stories of the last decade, Janet Yellen has done more than defy expectations and targets set for the economy. Starting her term as Vice-Chair in 2010, and later serving as 14th Chair of the Federal Reserve, she replaced the outgoing Ben Bernanke whose $3 trillion stimulus package she &lt;a href=&quot;http://money.cnn.com/2013/11/14/news/economy/janet-yellen-confirmation-hearing/&quot;&gt;defended throughout&lt;/a&gt; the Senate hearings. She has successfully overseen a gradual return to full employment as well as an increase in real income growth. She has even managed to scale back the stimulus packages to the economy while simultaneously leaving inflation rates stagnant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//higherups-graph.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although considered to be a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20131113032024/http://www.sfgate.com/business/investopedia/article/Janet-Yellen-Background-And-Philosophy-4902126.php&quot;&gt;dove&lt;/a&gt;”, she has gradually raised interest rates in the past few years from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/robertlenzner/2017/12/16/janet-yellen-leaves-us-with-goldilocks-economy/#4067146794b6&quot;&gt;1.5% to 2.25%&lt;/a&gt;. Donald Trump may not approve of her but the people definitely do, as she has left a great inheritance for Trump’s nominee Jay Powell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: Distinguished Fellow in Residence at Brookings Institution&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;john-stumpf-wells-fargo&quot;&gt;John Stumpf (Wells Fargo)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/hieronymus/3635257139&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//John-Stumpf.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; United States of America &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; St Cloud State University, University of Minnesota&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Stumpf was the commander and captain of a $1.9 trillion empire. Today he has lost it all; well, nearly all of it. Rising steadily through the ranks from 1998 he finally assumed the position of Chairman and CEO of Wells Fargo Bank, the fourth-largest bank in the US by total assets, and it was all going well as Wells Fargo emerged as arguably the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=2&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwigwbiEqqTgAhWOT30KHdKfDK8QFjABegQIBxAF&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.fool.com%2Finvesting%2Fgeneral%2F2015%2F11%2F04%2Fwells-fargo-is-the-biggest-bank-in-america-accordi.aspx&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3kFZ7WWDtQhkoh2bN7nYuX&quot;&gt;biggest player&lt;/a&gt; in the American economy. In December 2008, when the world was in the middle of an economic collapse, he led the &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20121213150723/https://www.wellsfargo.com/about/corporate/executive_officers/stumpf&quot;&gt;purchase of Wachovia bank&lt;/a&gt;, one of the biggest mergers in the history of banking. However, in September of 2016, the bank was charged with opening &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/business/2016/oct/12/wells-fargo-ceo-john-stumpf-retires-fake-accounts&quot;&gt;2 million accounts without customers’ permission&lt;/a&gt;, just so that they could meet the sales quotas of the company. Slapped with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/oct/14/john-stumpf-retirement-wells-fargo-ceo-jail-time&quot;&gt;$185 million fine&lt;/a&gt; by US regulators for their fraudulent activities, John Stumpf had to eventually resign in the wake of the disaster. His story is still a matter of public hatred, as he got away with a hefty &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usatoday.com/story/money/markets/2016/10/12/wells-fargo-ceo-retires-under-fire/91964778/&quot;&gt;$134 million paycheck&lt;/a&gt;, although a Wells Fargo spokeswoman had this to say, “Mr.John Stump will not receive any severance payment”. At least when it comes to banking, no severance payment doesn’t mean severance from a payday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: Just bought a $3.77M mansion in the Arizona valley&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;christine-lagarde-imf&quot;&gt;Christine Lagarde (IMF)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/1/1e/Women_in_Economic_Decision-making_Christine_Lagarde_%288414041294%29.jpg/1024px-Women_in_Economic_Decision-making_Christine_Lagarde_%288414041294%29.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Christine-Lagarde.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; France &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; Paris West University, Institute of Political Studies- Aix&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 2011 the IMF made history by electing Christine Lagarde as its first ever woman head. It was also slap-bang in the middle of the European sovereign debt crisis and Europe needed her, to call her strict or strong would be an understatement. She has repeatedly shown her unforgiving nature, especially when it comes to doing what needs to be done, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/financialcrisis/9293602/Irate-Greeks-vilify-IMF-chief-on-Facebook-after-she-brands-them-tax-dodgers.html&quot;&gt;Greece knows it far too well&lt;/a&gt;. If you were to ask her about the way she handles such issues, she &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vogue.com/article/christine-lagarde-changing-of-the-guard&quot;&gt;says that she relates&lt;/a&gt; to “Adam Smith— that is liberal”. Initially hesitant towards writing off Greek debts, she had repeatedly asked for austerity measures to be carried out. But when the people of Greece decided &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/may/25/payback-time-lagarde-greeks&quot;&gt;to just not pay&lt;/a&gt; their taxes, she was forced to take the initiative of creating a rescue package for the debt-ridden country. When she knew that the help arranged was still &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424127887324299104578527202781667088&quot;&gt;not enough&lt;/a&gt; to save the country, she decided to finally write off the debts and was even ready to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/business/2015/jul/17/imf-steps-up-greek-bailout-criticism-debt-relief-package&quot;&gt;call for debt relief on a global scale&lt;/a&gt; on behalf of the IMF. This IMF MD is as close as an “Iron lady” as you can find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: Managing Director and Chair of the IMF&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;raghuram-rajan-rbi&quot;&gt;Raghuram Rajan (RBI)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d5/Raghuram_Rajan%2C_IMF_69MS040421048l.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Raghuram-Rajan.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; India &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; IIT Delhi, IIM Ahmedabad, MIT Sloan School of Management&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He started out as an assistant professor of finance in 1991 at the Chicago Booth School of Business, but his book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=2&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiZrrP0t6TgAhXIEHIKHUUpBkgQFjABegQICRAC&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Ffaculty.chicagobooth.edu%2Fluigi.zingales%2Fpapers%2Fresearch%2Fcapintro.pdf&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0fVqHg4mb3p14Lobhs89dX&quot;&gt;Saving Capitalism from the Capitalists&lt;/a&gt; caught the eye of the IMF’s first deputy managing director Anne Krueger, who appointed him as the Chief Economist. This made him the first Indian and the youngest ever at his post. He helped the IMF make huge strides in financial sector analysis and led increasing research into their effects on a macro level. In 2012, he was appointed chief economic adviser of India and even prepared the Economic Survey of India for the year. It was less than a year later that he was appointed Governor of the Reserve Bank of India. It was under his tenure that India experienced a fall of 6 percentage points in its retail inflation rate and a historically low rate of wholesale inflation. With global support on his side, India’s foreign exchange reserves &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiqxbnlt6TgAhWKF3IKHXy1ALEQFjAAegQICRAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fqz.com%2Findia%2F774034%2Fa-comparison-of-indias-economy-when-raghuram-rajan-took-charge-at-rbi-and-now-as-urjit-patel-steps-in%2F&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1c_zvCu7ALa8t76Xctf9lk&quot;&gt;ballooned to $380 million in a matter of only two years&lt;/a&gt; and with the election of the new government, prospects of the Indian economy were as bright as ever, despite the many tussles with the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, his will to return to academia got the better of him and the government wanted to head in a different direction (Note: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=2&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwja6vfHt6TgAhVab30KHY1IDuYQFjABegQIBxAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Findianexpress.com%2Farticle%2Fbusiness%2Feconomy%2Fdemonetisation-rbi-gst-raghuram-rajan-economic-growth-5440435%2F&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1qs88yKq6IarMKs5iGYswa&quot;&gt;Demonetization&lt;/a&gt;) while he preferred taxation to tackle the issues of black money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: Katherine Dusak Miller Distinguished Service Professor of Finance at University of Chicago&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;zhou-xiaochuan-pboc&quot;&gt;Zhou Xiaochuan (PBOC)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/f/fb/Secretary_Geithner_and_People%27s_Bank_of_China_Governor_Zhou_Xiaochuan%2C_following_a_working_lunch_on_May_23%2C_2010_in_Beijing.jpg/1220px-Secretary_Geithner_and_People%27s_Bank_of_China_Governor_Zhou_Xiaochuan%2C_following_a_working_lunch_on_May_23%2C_2010_in_Beijing.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Zhou-Xiaochuan.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; China&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; Beijing Institute of Chemical Technology, Tsinghua University&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After serving as president of China Construction Bank and Chairman of the China Securities Regulatory Commission, he was appointed as governor of the People’s Bank of China by Premier Zhu Rongji, a tenure which lasted a whopping 15 years. Unlike its contemporaries from across the globe, the People’s Bank of China is not independent. Almost everything has to go through the State Council whose members prefer to have low interest rates and lots of credit. Yet it is through these confines that Zhou Xiaochuan has managed to manoeuvre policies &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/2013/03/16/china-parliament-zhou-idUSL3N0C7CV920130316&quot;&gt;in and outside of his jurisdiction&lt;/a&gt; that truly set up the Chinese economy as an international investment opportunity. He is responsible for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/0631ab2e-2387-11e8-8138-569c3d7ab0a7&quot;&gt;internationalising the renminbi, encouraging the growth of online banking&lt;/a&gt; throughout the nation and clearing up more than $800 million in bad loans. The man is considered among the most academically capable among the Chinese leadership, has an increasingly friendly openness toward the media and is the only Chinese higher-up who has been published in a Western Journal. Add to that his attitude toward markets,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;If the market can solve the problem, let the market do it. I am just a referee. I am neither a sportsman nor a coach.&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and you probably have one of the biggest reasons why China has roared into the foray as a global economic powerhouse over the past decade. After opening up the Chinese economy through a legacy of financial reform, he stepped down in 2018, just as the fear of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/East-Asia-Growth-in-a-Bubble&quot;&gt;Chinese slowdown&lt;/a&gt; was materialising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Currently in 2019: Member of China Investment Corp.’s (CIC) International Advisory Council&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shohan Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In this article, we take a look at the people in the past decade and more who had exponential burdens placed on their shoulders and examine how they fared. The men and women who moved markets and sentiments; whose names were heard on the internet and in households across the globe, setting examples to follow and learn from, for the generation ahead.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What Social Responsibility, if Any, Do or Should Corporations Have in Society Today?</title>
      <link href="/Corporate-Social-Responsibility" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Social Responsibility, if Any, Do or Should Corporations Have in Society Today?" />
      <published>2019-02-14T21:30:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-14T21:30:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Corporate-Social-Responsibility</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Corporate-Social-Responsibility">&lt;p&gt;Consistent with McWilliams and Siegel’s approach in &lt;i&gt;The Academy of Management Review&lt;/i&gt;, we define Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR) as the spectrum of undertakings in which the firm goes beyond compliance and engages in “actions that appear to further some social good, beyond the interests of the firm”. It is said to be the company’s way of giving back to the community it is making so much out of, i.e. a sort of return gift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gifts, of course, make consumers happy and this is the basic logic behind the social responsibility of corporations today: to make sure elated customers return to provide more business. This process of giving back to society adds to the goodwill of the company and ensures consumer loyalty. In professional language, this art of deceiving customers by producing a philanthropic image of a corporation is termed “corporate strategy”. It is a framework, as argued by Fombrun &amp;amp; Shanley in the &lt;i&gt;Academy of Management Journal&lt;/i&gt; that demonstrates how the reputation of a firm captures returns to socially responsible behaviour. Consumers tend to give more business to a firm that perhaps donates a part of its income to some village in Saharan Africa, than to one that does nothing of the sort or does something similar but of a lesser magnitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the same reason, Fortune 500 companies and multinational corporations are in a race over who can be more charitable, simply because CSR happens to have somewhat substituted direct advertising. Even though it is not legally required in most economies, companies seem to have diverted a significant proportion of their funds exclusively for CSR, rather than investing them in sales or advertising, as they traditionally did. They have realised that they can leverage social responsibility as a vehicle to bring customers to their doorstep, rather than making the effort of going to theirs. Therefore, we see a dramatic change in the policies of corporations today relative to just a few decades ago. They are using the same marketing budget in a much more efficient way and sustaining customer relationships by showing them a movie. The funny part is customers are actually enjoying the movie, but they fail to see the reality behind the seemingly altruistic endeavours of these corporations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Disney’s classic retelling of the fable &lt;i&gt;Pinocchio&lt;/i&gt;, after the Blue Fairy grants him life, Geppetto’s wooden boy is granted a conscience. Now, since corporations do not have a conscience, they need a reliable external source to show them right from wrong. But what is that external source? Is it a set of laws like the several others these corporations never follow? Is it the government that in fact partners with them at times to privatise services like the provision of clean drinking water? Or is it people like you and me who are busy watching the movie these corporations are showing us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporations have always had just one responsibility – the responsibility to serve themselves. They do not care about the consequences their activities have on society. After being declared “legal persons”, 288 of the 307 appellants who sought jurisdiction of the Supreme Court of the United States of America under the 14th Amendment, were corporations and not African-Americans, for whom the amendment had actually been made. This just goes on to prove how self-centred and blatantly selfish corporations are. But wait a minute, why shouldn’t they be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it be harm to human health by companies such as Monsanto or harm to the environment by a variety of industries, corporations can cross any limits and employees need not even regret their wrongdoings because well – limited liability – they’re safe! How can they be held accountable for decisions that a corporation took? After all, a corporation doesn’t have the ability to base decisions on morals or feelings, then how can we expect it to be socially responsible? But then, what is the social responsibility of businesses?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Milton Friedman once stated in the &lt;i&gt;The New York Times Magazine&lt;/i&gt;: “The social responsibility of business is to increase its profits.” Friedman wanted to clearly bring out a distinction between the legal and ethical aspects involved in the debate on social responsibility, by affirming that businesses are simply groups of people and that only people have responsibilities, not inanimate entities! To quote J. Hood of the &lt;i&gt;Foundation for Economic Education&lt;/i&gt;“If a corporation makes a donation to charity without the shareholders’ authorization, wrote Friedman, the managers are deciding how to spend other people’s money. It would be better to return the money to shareholders as dividends or capital gains and let them decide which charities to support.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An alternative and opposite theory to Friedman’s was developed by Freeman, who argued in his book &lt;i&gt;Strategic Management: A Stakeholder Approach&lt;/i&gt; that corporate social responsibility is a vital part of strategic management. His argument was based on the thought that firms are associated with numerous parties whose interests should be considered, since the firm can’t continue to survive without the support of these stakeholders – employees, customers, suppliers and the community. This view was expanded by Donaldson &amp;amp; Davis by the introduction of Stewardship Theory in the&lt;i&gt;Australian Journal of Management&lt;/i&gt;. According to this theory, there is a moral imperative for managers to “do the right thing,” without regard to how such decisions affect the firm’s financial performance. This rationale becomes difficult to adhere to internationally, because there may be no consensus on what “the right thing” is. However, this was a more ethically-centred approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s a simpler question to be asked in all this scholarly debate. Before managing social responsibility outside their organisation, shouldn’t corporations focus on fulfilling their internal social responsibility? Paying a few cents to workers who produce products that sell for hundreds of dollars! Is it not hypocritical of companies to talk big about social responsibility while they exploit their own employees? It is clear to me that corporations survive on externalities and that they are purely utilitarian. They want to make others pay the cost for their impact on society, while they luxuriate in soaring profits. But then again, isn’t this why corporations exist in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe corporations do have a social responsibility, however, that responsibility predominantly lies confined to their own internal affairs: first, the demands of employees, financers and executives ought to be delivered. Commercial activity in itself comes with social benefits such as greater employment, improved standards of living, globalisation and a better quality of life. These benefits aren’t derived from any extra effort by corporations – it’s not obligatory for them to put in extra effort anyway – but they are derived simply by virtue of the existence of corporations. Since a corporation can’t think and feel like a human with flesh and blood, it need not care about any other social responsibility, unless it comes with an advantage. If community giving helps boost sales and multiply profits, implement CSR. This means we’ll still be watching a movie, however, there will certainly be a simultaneous social impact, to whatever small extent possible. So, corporations may consider their dedicated business undertakings a social responsibility, or, their newfound marketing technique – either one suits me…as long as it does some good, especially to those people on whom the corporation truly depends for its profits.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shivang Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Consistent with McWilliams and Siegel’s approach in The Academy of Management Review, we define Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR) as the spectrum of undertakings in which the firm goes beyond compliance and engages in “actions that appear to further some social good, beyond the interests of the firm”. It is said to be the company’s way of giving back to the community it is making so much out of, i.e. a sort of return gift.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
