<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/economics/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-12-04T01:18:44+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/economics/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Understanding India’s Foreign Kitty Surge</title>
      <link href="/Understanding-India-s-Foreign-Kitty-Surge" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding India’s Foreign Kitty Surge" />
      <published>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Understanding-India-s-Foreign-Kitty-Surge</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-India-s-Foreign-Kitty-Surge">&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, the foreign exchange reserves of India, maintained by its Central Bank, have consistently managed to surpass their own all-time-high benchmarks. Since the COVID-19 crisis, the frequency of this phenomenon has risen to as often as every alternate week. As of writing this piece, the last surge recorded in the week ending November 6, 2020, was of $7.78 billion, pushing the forex reserves to touch a record high of $568.5 billion. The week prior, the reserves had risen by $183 million. While some renowned (pseudo) economists have celebrated these figures as a mark of the rising relative strength of the Indian rupee, this stance couldn’t be farther from the truth, and is therefore misleading and perhaps even partisan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foreign exchange reserves are maintained by the Central Bank of an economy for the sake of convenience for liquidity and currency value management, as well as for non-prosaic purposes such as maintaining favourable exchange rates for export competitiveness. They tend to be constituted of foreign currency assets (FCAs), Treasury bills, US government securities, gold reserves, special drawing rights, etc. To put it in quite a crude way, these assets are exchanged for the domestic currency of a country, by its Central Bank, in order to regulate its value relative to these assets. Therefore, the forex operations affect the exchange rate, and consequently the trade balances as well. Since the exchange of the Indian rupee, for or against the forex reserves, takes place between the Central Bank and the domestic financial institutions (which receive forex assets through market-driven influx), these operations also affect the domestic liquidity status. The status of special drawing rights (denoted by the acronym XDRs) in this mechanism is weak and disputed. They are maintained by the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and were created to overcome the shortcomings of the Bretton Woods System, which was in effect from 1945 to 1972. The monetary system which pegged every currency to the US Dollar, which in turn was pegged to gold at the rate of $35/ounce, practically mandated the use of USD as the global reserve currency. However, owing to the conservative monetary policy of the USA at that point, the XDRs acted as a debt instrument to cover for the shortfall of USD and provide sufficient liquidity globally. After the apparently invariable transition of the USA’s policy stance to profligate practices, the system came to an end in 1972, rendering the XDRs as mere foreign exchange reserve assets, on which interest is payable or receivable if they are kept below or beyond (respectively) the level allocated by the IMF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India, over the past three decades, has transitioned from the pre-liberalisation levels of $5 billion of foreign exchange reserves to exceeding $560 billion last October, registering a 10,000% increase, which makes it the fifth-largest reserves accumulated by any economy. The fact that the status of the low reserve mapped with the 1991 economic crisis, does not by any chance imply that the all-time high reserves are indicative of economic prosperity. Although the level of foreign exchange reserves impacts the domestic liquidity status, it is not actively used as a monetary policy tool. More so, it is used to regulate the foreign exchange rate, through which it impacts the domestic liquidity. So an increase in the reserves is a response to mitigate unruly upward fluctuation in the value of the domestic currency. By increasing the forex reserves, usually done by increasing the FCAs, the relative demand for the foreign currency rises, bringing down the value of the domestic currency relative to the chosen forex asset. Whether the increase in an economy’s forex reserves is good news or not depends on what the source of the appreciation is. India’s balance of payments (BoP) status usually follows the pattern of a current account deficit, i.e., a trade deficit, and a capital account surplus, indicating investment inflows. Due to India’s popular Emerging Market Economy (EME) status, the capital inflows spiked amidst the dovish environment in the developed economies last year. Such inflows cause an appreciation of the Indian rupee, which can adversely affect the trade balance by making the exports less competitive in the global economy. The increase in forex reserves to avoid the appreciation involves purchasing USD from the local banks in exchange for the Indian rupee. As a result, domestic liquidity rises even if the economy does not need it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the classic impossible trinity issue India faces, where in order to retain near-fixed exchange rates and a free flow in capital markets, the economy must partially let go of the independence of its monetary policy. This excess liquidity in domestic markets would be inflationary and could create macro-level imbalances. Of course, many argue that this liquidity can be merely sterilised. Sterilisation involves soaking up the excess liquidity without involving the forex assets so that the original purpose of exchange rate stability does not get defeated. So the RBI could simply sell government bonds through open market operations (OMOs) and take back the rupees that the markets were flooded with. But this would be counterproductive. By selling government securities through OMOs, their market supply rises and the prices fall, which results in a reduction in the domestic rates, thus discouraging the inflow of foreign investment. This would render the entire exercise futile. Clearly, there is no evident pathway towards resolving the trilemma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in the current scenario, something much graver is under effect. The BoP surplus is a consequence of both investment inflows, as well as a (once in a blue moon) trade surplus that was registered due to feeble global demand. In order to prevent the exacerbation of the trade imbalances through appreciation, the forex reserves have been rising at an all-time high pace. As opposed to the previous scenario, this would mean that the resultant increase in domestic liquidity is not a major issue because the domestic economy is also recessionary and therefore could use this liquidity. This is also why we have not seen the policy rates being slashed despite the tight situation. Any more liquidity would mean risking inflationary pressures. Additionally, most economists would agree that the recessionary situation needs to be dealt with in a more targeted way, i.e. through fiscal policy. The problem is, how would the government finance its expenditure?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India’s fiscal response to the situation, despite all its cautiousness, has been projected to take the fiscal deficit to 13.1% of GDP in the fiscal year 2020-21. This increase in deficits, though in line with the average increase registered by Emerging Market Economies, remains insufficient in the case of India. This is primarily due to the composition of the deficits. A major chunk of the deficits is owed to the reduction in collection of GST, and other automatic cyclical responses. Only a small proportion, 1.8% of the GDP, is the fiscal deficit owed to discretionary fiscal response, one that arises due to an increase in the expenditure or reduction of taxes. In order to get the economic cycle running again, more discretionary expenditure needs to be undertaken, which will not be possible unless the Reserve Bank of India manages to finance it by creating demand for government securities via OMO. But that would mean adding further liquidity to an economy where the fires of inflationary pressures have already been stoked by the forex operations. With nearly two lost years to get to pre-pandemic levels of output, the economy must make a choice between securing its interests in the international markets or getting the internal demand cycle running first.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Over the past year, the foreign exchange reserves of India, maintained by its Central Bank, have consistently managed to surpass their own all-time-high benchmarks. Since the COVID-19 crisis, the frequency of this phenomenon has risen to as often as every alternate week. As of writing this piece, the last surge recorded in the week ending November 6, 2020, was of $7.78 billion, pushing the forex reserves to touch a record high of $568.5 billion. The week prior, the reserves had risen by $183 million. While some renowned (pseudo) economists have celebrated these figures as a mark of the rising relative strength of the Indian rupee, this stance couldn’t be farther from the truth, and is therefore misleading and perhaps even partisan. The foreign exchange reserves are maintained by the Central Bank of an economy for the sake of convenience for liquidity and currency value management, as well as for non-prosaic purposes such as maintaining favourable exchange rates for export competitiveness. They tend to be constituted of foreign currency assets (FCAs), Treasury bills, US government securities, gold reserves, special drawing rights, etc. To put it in quite a crude way, these assets are exchanged for the domestic currency of a country, by its Central Bank, in order to regulate its value relative to these assets. Therefore, the forex operations affect the exchange rate, and consequently the trade balances as well. Since the exchange of the Indian rupee, for or against the forex reserves, takes place between the Central Bank and the domestic financial institutions (which receive forex assets through market-driven influx), these operations also affect the domestic liquidity status. The status of special drawing rights (denoted by the acronym XDRs) in this mechanism is weak and disputed. They are maintained by the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and were created to overcome the shortcomings of the Bretton Woods System, which was in effect from 1945 to 1972. The monetary system which pegged every currency to the US Dollar, which in turn was pegged to gold at the rate of $35/ounce, practically mandated the use of USD as the global reserve currency. However, owing to the conservative monetary policy of the USA at that point, the XDRs acted as a debt instrument to cover for the shortfall of USD and provide sufficient liquidity globally. After the apparently invariable transition of the USA’s policy stance to profligate practices, the system came to an end in 1972, rendering the XDRs as mere foreign exchange reserve assets, on which interest is payable or receivable if they are kept below or beyond (respectively) the level allocated by the IMF. India, over the past three decades, has transitioned from the pre-liberalisation levels of $5 billion of foreign exchange reserves to exceeding $560 billion last October, registering a 10,000% increase, which makes it the fifth-largest reserves accumulated by any economy. The fact that the status of the low reserve mapped with the 1991 economic crisis, does not by any chance imply that the all-time high reserves are indicative of economic prosperity. Although the level of foreign exchange reserves impacts the domestic liquidity status, it is not actively used as a monetary policy tool. More so, it is used to regulate the foreign exchange rate, through which it impacts the domestic liquidity. So an increase in the reserves is a response to mitigate unruly upward fluctuation in the value of the domestic currency. By increasing the forex reserves, usually done by increasing the FCAs, the relative demand for the foreign currency rises, bringing down the value of the domestic currency relative to the chosen forex asset. Whether the increase in an economy’s forex reserves is good news or not depends on what the source of the appreciation is. India’s balance of payments (BoP) status usually follows the pattern of a current account deficit, i.e., a trade deficit, and a capital account surplus, indicating investment inflows. Due to India’s popular Emerging Market Economy (EME) status, the capital inflows spiked amidst the dovish environment in the developed economies last year. Such inflows cause an appreciation of the Indian rupee, which can adversely affect the trade balance by making the exports less competitive in the global economy. The increase in forex reserves to avoid the appreciation involves purchasing USD from the local banks in exchange for the Indian rupee. As a result, domestic liquidity rises even if the economy does not need it.&amp;nbsp; This is the classic impossible trinity issue India faces, where in order to retain near-fixed exchange rates and a free flow in capital markets, the economy must partially let go of the independence of its monetary policy. This excess liquidity in domestic markets would be inflationary and could create macro-level imbalances. Of course, many argue that this liquidity can be merely sterilised. Sterilisation involves soaking up the excess liquidity without involving the forex assets so that the original purpose of exchange rate stability does not get defeated. So the RBI could simply sell government bonds through open market operations (OMOs) and take back the rupees that the markets were flooded with. But this would be counterproductive. By selling government securities through OMOs, their market supply rises and the prices fall, which results in a reduction in the domestic rates, thus discouraging the inflow of foreign investment. This would render the entire exercise futile. Clearly, there is no evident pathway towards resolving the trilemma. However, in the current scenario, something much graver is under effect. The BoP surplus is a consequence of both investment inflows, as well as a (once in a blue moon) trade surplus that was registered due to feeble global demand. In order to prevent the exacerbation of the trade imbalances through appreciation, the forex reserves have been rising at an all-time high pace. As opposed to the previous scenario, this would mean that the resultant increase in domestic liquidity is not a major issue because the domestic economy is also recessionary and therefore could use this liquidity. This is also why we have not seen the policy rates being slashed despite the tight situation. Any more liquidity would mean risking inflationary pressures. Additionally, most economists would agree that the recessionary situation needs to be dealt with in a more targeted way, i.e. through fiscal policy. The problem is, how would the government finance its expenditure?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; India’s fiscal response to the situation, despite all its cautiousness, has been projected to take the fiscal deficit to 13.1% of GDP in the fiscal year 2020-21. This increase in deficits, though in line with the average increase registered by Emerging Market Economies, remains insufficient in the case of India. This is primarily due to the composition of the deficits. A major chunk of the deficits is owed to the reduction in collection of GST, and other automatic cyclical responses. Only a small proportion, 1.8% of the GDP, is the fiscal deficit owed to discretionary fiscal response, one that arises due to an increase in the expenditure or reduction of taxes. In order to get the economic cycle running again, more discretionary expenditure needs to be undertaken, which will not be possible unless the Reserve Bank of India manages to finance it by creating demand for government securities via OMO. But that would mean adding further liquidity to an economy where the fires of inflationary pressures have already been stoked by the forex operations. With nearly two lost years to get to pre-pandemic levels of output, the economy must make a choice between securing its interests in the international markets or getting the internal demand cycle running first.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Modern Monetary Theory: The Solution to Developing Countries’ Problems?</title>
      <link href="/Modern-Monetary-Theory" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modern Monetary Theory: The Solution to Developing Countries’ Problems?" />
      <published>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Modern-Monetary-Theory</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Modern-Monetary-Theory">&lt;p&gt;Modern Monetary Theory (MMT) is increasingly gaining traction in today’s public discourse. While there is huge literature available regarding MMT, it is often ridiculed by statements claiming to explain the theory, such as “&lt;em&gt;money printer gone brrrr&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; It is important to know that MMT doesn’t advocate for money printing. To borrow from L Randall Wray, a pioneer of the field, MMT argues that a sovereign government that issues its own “nonconvertible” currency cannot become insolvent (in terms of its own currency). It cannot be forced into involuntary default on its obligations denominated in its own currency. It can “afford” to buy anything for sale that is priced in its own currency. Here sovereignty is defined in monetary terms in that a state has monetary sovereignty when it issues its own currency, taxes its people in that currency, accepts that currency in payment of the imposed obligations, and issues debt in its own currency. Along with this, a fifth consideration, according to Wray, is to have a floating exchange rate regime (which is what “nonconvertible” currency means); so that it provides more fiscal space for the government.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MMTers argue that their descriptions and prescriptions equally hold for the developing nations as for the developed nations. While this is largely true, there are however some constraints with regard to the developing countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first such constraint is the need for a developing country to accumulate foreign currency, especially the international reserve currency - the dollar. One major factor that leads to this accumulation is the necessity to import various types of goods (which could be for various reasons). So, with the accumulation of external debt, the demand for foreign currency also increases because it leads to higher debt service obligations and also because it increases risk perception as there is greater exposure to currency mismatch. The accumulation of foreign debt means that the balance of payments becomes a major limitation on the policy front for a developing country. In the current account of the balance of payments, a trade deficit (imports &amp;gt; exports) is compensated by positive capital inflows (which leads to a surplus in the capital account). That is, a current account deficit must be balanced by the sum of the capital account. Randal Wray once wrote that “&lt;em&gt;MMT makes no claim that floating rates eliminate current account deficits, indeed, MMT does not argue that elimination of current account deficits is even desirable”&lt;/em&gt;. But, the said balancing does not mean that a country can sustain any level of the current account deficit, over time. There is ample evidence available that the higher the current account deficit, the less likely that it can be sustained. What all this means is that the current account deficit chips away the monetary sovereignty of developing countries and thus the validity of MMT in such countries becomes uncertain.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second issue, which is related here is that Wray suggests that in a floating exchange regime a government does not need to fear that it will run out of foreign currency reserves (or gold reserves) for the simple reason that it does not convert its domestic currency to foreign currency at a fixed exchange rate. Indeed, the government does not have to promise to make any conversions at all. But a developing country necessarily concerns itself with the capital flows not because of the issue of convertibility of currency, but because it needs to pay for its imports (or some sort of short-term obligation). All this is to say that a developing country may very well face the risk of foreign debt default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fadhel Kaboub, another MMT economist, identifies three broad areas from where a trade deficit arises. It arises because the developing country lacks food sovereignty, energy sovereignty and they essentially export low-value goods and import high-value goods. He says that this is a trap, in that a trade deficit leads a country to accumulate foreign currency. To do this, domestic resources are diverted from the areas of the government’s priority to areas that earn foreign exchange for the country. For instance, a government may prioritise the needs of foreign tourists as they spend the foreign currency or the government may announce tax concessions with the hope to attract foreign investors and end up losing revenue which could otherwise be used to develop local government. So, his advice to developing countries is to invest in sustainable agriculture to reach a level of self-sufficiency, to invest in renewable energy production that allows the countries to set their priorities, to invest in education, and to prepare an industrial strategy to move up the value chain from producing low-value-added goods to high-value-added goods. All these will provide resilience for a country from external shocks that a country may face.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A third important constraint is inflation. MMT argues that while a sovereign can never default, there are limits as to how much it can spend; that is, there are certain limits on the fiscal deficit a sovereign runs. These limits are in the form of constraints on the part of real resources in an economy. If a government spends more than what these real resources could absorb, it risks the possibility of price hikes, i.e. inflation. MMT’s prescription to this problem is that the government could increase tax rates so that the purchasing power of the economy as a whole falls and thus inflation could be arrested (note that MMT also says tax revenue does not pay for anything but gives several other reasons for justifying the taxes). Now, in developing countries, there are two main problems with this. First, the tax base is lower in developing countries. Therefore, even when taxes are increased there might not be the desired effect of reducing purchasing power and thus controlling inflation. The prevalence of the informal economy on a large scale is also a constraint in this context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is true that developing economies face certain constraints that the MMT approach has not fully gauged. For instance, a developed country might not have constraints of fiscal space due to the current account of the balance of payments (and due to implications thereof). However, it can also be argued that it is precisely the understanding and the implementation of MMT that is required for the developing countries to overcome these constraints. The primary focus of MMT on real resources can be an important takeaway for developing economies because the development of real resources (in part) entails huge investments in developing human capital, green resources, and health resources. Despite many constraints, MMT also opens many doors for the developing economies.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Modern Monetary Theory (MMT) is increasingly gaining traction in today’s public discourse. While there is huge literature available regarding MMT, it is often ridiculed by statements claiming to explain the theory, such as “money printer gone brrrr”. It is important to know that MMT doesn’t advocate for money printing. To borrow from L Randall Wray, a pioneer of the field, MMT argues that a sovereign government that issues its own “nonconvertible” currency cannot become insolvent (in terms of its own currency). It cannot be forced into involuntary default on its obligations denominated in its own currency. It can “afford” to buy anything for sale that is priced in its own currency. Here sovereignty is defined in monetary terms in that a state has monetary sovereignty when it issues its own currency, taxes its people in that currency, accepts that currency in payment of the imposed obligations, and issues debt in its own currency. Along with this, a fifth consideration, according to Wray, is to have a floating exchange rate regime (which is what “nonconvertible” currency means); so that it provides more fiscal space for the government.&amp;nbsp; MMTers argue that their descriptions and prescriptions equally hold for the developing nations as for the developed nations. While this is largely true, there are however some constraints with regard to the developing countries.&amp;nbsp; The first such constraint is the need for a developing country to accumulate foreign currency, especially the international reserve currency - the dollar. One major factor that leads to this accumulation is the necessity to import various types of goods (which could be for various reasons). So, with the accumulation of external debt, the demand for foreign currency also increases because it leads to higher debt service obligations and also because it increases risk perception as there is greater exposure to currency mismatch. The accumulation of foreign debt means that the balance of payments becomes a major limitation on the policy front for a developing country. In the current account of the balance of payments, a trade deficit (imports &amp;gt; exports) is compensated by positive capital inflows (which leads to a surplus in the capital account). That is, a current account deficit must be balanced by the sum of the capital account. Randal Wray once wrote that “MMT makes no claim that floating rates eliminate current account deficits, indeed, MMT does not argue that elimination of current account deficits is even desirable”. But, the said balancing does not mean that a country can sustain any level of the current account deficit, over time. There is ample evidence available that the higher the current account deficit, the less likely that it can be sustained. What all this means is that the current account deficit chips away the monetary sovereignty of developing countries and thus the validity of MMT in such countries becomes uncertain.&amp;nbsp; A second issue, which is related here is that Wray suggests that in a floating exchange regime a government does not need to fear that it will run out of foreign currency reserves (or gold reserves) for the simple reason that it does not convert its domestic currency to foreign currency at a fixed exchange rate. Indeed, the government does not have to promise to make any conversions at all. But a developing country necessarily concerns itself with the capital flows not because of the issue of convertibility of currency, but because it needs to pay for its imports (or some sort of short-term obligation). All this is to say that a developing country may very well face the risk of foreign debt default. Fadhel Kaboub, another MMT economist, identifies three broad areas from where a trade deficit arises. It arises because the developing country lacks food sovereignty, energy sovereignty and they essentially export low-value goods and import high-value goods. He says that this is a trap, in that a trade deficit leads a country to accumulate foreign currency. To do this, domestic resources are diverted from the areas of the government’s priority to areas that earn foreign exchange for the country. For instance, a government may prioritise the needs of foreign tourists as they spend the foreign currency or the government may announce tax concessions with the hope to attract foreign investors and end up losing revenue which could otherwise be used to develop local government. So, his advice to developing countries is to invest in sustainable agriculture to reach a level of self-sufficiency, to invest in renewable energy production that allows the countries to set their priorities, to invest in education, and to prepare an industrial strategy to move up the value chain from producing low-value-added goods to high-value-added goods. All these will provide resilience for a country from external shocks that a country may face.&amp;nbsp; A third important constraint is inflation. MMT argues that while a sovereign can never default, there are limits as to how much it can spend; that is, there are certain limits on the fiscal deficit a sovereign runs. These limits are in the form of constraints on the part of real resources in an economy. If a government spends more than what these real resources could absorb, it risks the possibility of price hikes, i.e. inflation. MMT’s prescription to this problem is that the government could increase tax rates so that the purchasing power of the economy as a whole falls and thus inflation could be arrested (note that MMT also says tax revenue does not pay for anything but gives several other reasons for justifying the taxes). Now, in developing countries, there are two main problems with this. First, the tax base is lower in developing countries. Therefore, even when taxes are increased there might not be the desired effect of reducing purchasing power and thus controlling inflation. The prevalence of the informal economy on a large scale is also a constraint in this context. It is true that developing economies face certain constraints that the MMT approach has not fully gauged. For instance, a developed country might not have constraints of fiscal space due to the current account of the balance of payments (and due to implications thereof). However, it can also be argued that it is precisely the understanding and the implementation of MMT that is required for the developing countries to overcome these constraints. The primary focus of MMT on real resources can be an important takeaway for developing economies because the development of real resources (in part) entails huge investments in developing human capital, green resources, and health resources. Despite many constraints, MMT also opens many doors for the developing economies.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Are Economists Evolving to be Engineers?</title>
      <link href="/Are-Economists-Evolving-to-be-Engineers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are Economists Evolving to be Engineers?" />
      <published>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Are-Economists-Evolving-to-be-Engineers</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Are-Economists-Evolving-to-be-Engineers">&lt;p&gt;The opening match of the Indian Premier League 2020 was viewed by over 200 million people. A record-breaking viewership figure for the opening-day of a sports event in any country. This shows the buzz among viewers for this annually conducted India-based event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes the show more breathtaking is the custom of the auction of players that takes place months prior to the final episode. Cricket admirers would also be aware of the most tragic bids of cricket history. Recall Tymal Mills, one of the players auctioned, was one of the most expensive purchases of season 10. Consequently, he struggled to find a purchaser in the following season because of his disappointing performance in the former season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why did the team pay an exorbitantly high sum of ₹120 million for such a player? What could be the reason behind the faulty valuation of Tymal Mills? The truth is that such glitches and miscalculations in auctions are not uncommon as the modern form of auctions is not just restricted to the disposal of a bankrupt’s property. It is a lot more than that. Auctioning telecom spectrums, oil wells, airport landing slots - it is indeed a mind boggling process. And a solution to such a process fetched the Nobel Prize 2020 for economics to Paul R Milgrom and Robert B Wilson. These researchers tried to evaluate the outcomes of different rules of bidding and final prices and devised a framework “&lt;em&gt;for improvements to auction theory and invention of new auction formats.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story dates back to the times when the telecom spectrum was sold to companies in the form of beauty contests. Basically, the one with the best plan was the winner. However, it was subject to lobbying. Approaches like political markets and lotteries were also adopted though both of these approaches were biased and led to unjustified distribution. As a resort, in 1994, the laureates introduced ‘simultaneous multiple round auctions’ for radio spectrum sale. This arrangement helped governments to sell the commodity rights at a competitive price - a price not too trivial which could result in losses and not too high. It ultimately helped the sellers find the buyer who values his product most. This format initially adopted by the USA’s Federal Communications Commission (FCC) is now used throughout the world for the allocation of natural resources.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Auction theory sounds simple considering that the buyer’s motive is to be able to purchase something at the lowest possible price. Economists also try their hands at game theory to find out all the predictions that could be made by bidders before quoting a price. However, in real life auctions, this prognosis won’t be a smooth ride. As bidders with little information available about the product struggle to find out its worth. At the same time, sellers face problems executing the sale of a bunch of items at the same time. They have to protect the auction from purchasers who might collaborate amongst themselves behind the scenes hence hampering the dignity of the auction. The auction theory of these Stanford University-affiliated economists aided in implementing the sale of complex goods. Their thesis is based on the following three factors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;They explained how rules of auction affect the behaviour of bidders and revenues brought in for sellers hence defying the ‘revenue equivalence theorem’. Are the bids open or closed? How many times can a participant bid? What amount shall the winner be liable to pay? All such statutes cause changes in the bidders’ attitude. The most suitable example of such a situation was quoted in a case study by &lt;em&gt;The Hindu&lt;/em&gt; which narrated a spectrum auction of New Zealand which took place in 1990. The auction was a Vickrey auction. Here, the winner was liable to pay the second-highest bid. Due to this, a company that actually bid NZ$100,000 ultimately ended up paying just NZ$6. Hence a difference in guidelines brought a major transformation in the amount the seller would have earned if the rules were slightly different.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The commodity or service that is being put to sale. The circumstances of a painting being auctioned shall enormously vary from telecom auctions.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;What are the uncertainties involved in the sale? What is the information available to a bidder about the product? A bidder is aware of the royal history of a mansion might view it differently from one unaware of it.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wilson, according to the prize committee devised that the auction of objects with a common value which is uncertain earlier becomes common for everyone at the end and that winners should bid below the common value of a product to eschew the winner’s curse. For a more extensive understanding let’s find out what is this common value, private value, and the winner’s curse.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Winner’s curse refers to a situation when the intrinsic value of a product is lower than its estimated value. This is a phenomenon that usually arises when bidders have no way of evaluating the exact intrinsic value of a product and offer a price as per their own assessment of the object. As happened in the case of Tymal Mills stated above - the team overestimated the performance of this player ending up winning the bid but losing the game. The winner is usually the one with the most optimistic estimation of the product while he may later realise that valuation by him was way higher in comparison to other bidders. This paradox was quoted by the 2017 Economics Nobel prize winner, Richard Thaler in &lt;em&gt;Misbehaving: The making of behavioural economics&lt;/em&gt; as “&lt;em&gt;When many bidders compete for the same object, the winner of the auction is often the bidder who most overvalues the product being sold&lt;/em&gt;”. This phenomenon even poses a question to the hypothesis of efficient markets. If the markets would have been efficient then there wouldn’t be such variation in the valuation by different bidders as all shall possess symmetric information.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another deciding factor for the price is the private value of the commodity. It is an individual’s outlook towards a product based on the personal information he possesses. For instance, in the auction of a painting, the private value of that art shall be the pleasure that the bidder is seeking from it for his own sake. However, when he would like to sell that painting in the future then what shall matter to him is the common value which is based on what others think will be the possible price. It is due to the private value of an object that bidders might have massive variations in their bids depending on their own circumstances. For instance, a company with an ability to sell oil at higher prices or process it at a lower price might be ready to bid higher for crude oil.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering this, Wilson studied the buyers who overpaid for US oil leases in the 1970's and earned lower returns due to the winner’s curse. He argued that the most rational approach is to place a bid below the perceived common value of resources. Milgrom nonetheless focused on a more general theory of auction and analysed different bidding strategies in a plethora of auction formats and concluded that it shall be the most profitable deal for the seller when they share more information with potential buyers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, these laureates have made a major contribution to society by devising a theory that has practical engineering applications. This new auction format is a more sorted approach to sell complex goods and is a well-designed system for both private and public sellers to design their auctions proficiently. With this theory, the researchers advocate that like physics and chemistry, economic theories can also create useful technologies for both companies and the government. This even justifies how economists who earlier only acted as advisors to government now play an indispensable role in corporate companies too.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pragati Agrawal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The opening match of the Indian Premier League 2020 was viewed by over 200 million people. A record-breaking viewership figure for the opening-day of a sports event in any country. This shows the buzz among viewers for this annually conducted India-based event. What makes the show more breathtaking is the custom of the auction of players that takes place months prior to the final episode. Cricket admirers would also be aware of the most tragic bids of cricket history. Recall Tymal Mills, one of the players auctioned, was one of the most expensive purchases of season 10. Consequently, he struggled to find a purchaser in the following season because of his disappointing performance in the former season. So why did the team pay an exorbitantly high sum of ₹120 million for such a player? What could be the reason behind the faulty valuation of Tymal Mills? The truth is that such glitches and miscalculations in auctions are not uncommon as the modern form of auctions is not just restricted to the disposal of a bankrupt’s property. It is a lot more than that. Auctioning telecom spectrums, oil wells, airport landing slots - it is indeed a mind boggling process. And a solution to such a process fetched the Nobel Prize 2020 for economics to Paul R Milgrom and Robert B Wilson. These researchers tried to evaluate the outcomes of different rules of bidding and final prices and devised a framework “for improvements to auction theory and invention of new auction formats.” The story dates back to the times when the telecom spectrum was sold to companies in the form of beauty contests. Basically, the one with the best plan was the winner. However, it was subject to lobbying. Approaches like political markets and lotteries were also adopted though both of these approaches were biased and led to unjustified distribution. As a resort, in 1994, the laureates introduced ‘simultaneous multiple round auctions’ for radio spectrum sale. This arrangement helped governments to sell the commodity rights at a competitive price - a price not too trivial which could result in losses and not too high. It ultimately helped the sellers find the buyer who values his product most. This format initially adopted by the USA’s Federal Communications Commission (FCC) is now used throughout the world for the allocation of natural resources.&amp;nbsp; Auction theory sounds simple considering that the buyer’s motive is to be able to purchase something at the lowest possible price. Economists also try their hands at game theory to find out all the predictions that could be made by bidders before quoting a price. However, in real life auctions, this prognosis won’t be a smooth ride. As bidders with little information available about the product struggle to find out its worth. At the same time, sellers face problems executing the sale of a bunch of items at the same time. They have to protect the auction from purchasers who might collaborate amongst themselves behind the scenes hence hampering the dignity of the auction. The auction theory of these Stanford University-affiliated economists aided in implementing the sale of complex goods. Their thesis is based on the following three factors: They explained how rules of auction affect the behaviour of bidders and revenues brought in for sellers hence defying the ‘revenue equivalence theorem’. Are the bids open or closed? How many times can a participant bid? What amount shall the winner be liable to pay? All such statutes cause changes in the bidders’ attitude. The most suitable example of such a situation was quoted in a case study by The Hindu which narrated a spectrum auction of New Zealand which took place in 1990. The auction was a Vickrey auction. Here, the winner was liable to pay the second-highest bid. Due to this, a company that actually bid NZ$100,000 ultimately ended up paying just NZ$6. Hence a difference in guidelines brought a major transformation in the amount the seller would have earned if the rules were slightly different.The commodity or service that is being put to sale. The circumstances of a painting being auctioned shall enormously vary from telecom auctions.What are the uncertainties involved in the sale? What is the information available to a bidder about the product? A bidder is aware of the royal history of a mansion might view it differently from one unaware of it. Wilson, according to the prize committee devised that the auction of objects with a common value which is uncertain earlier becomes common for everyone at the end and that winners should bid below the common value of a product to eschew the winner’s curse. For a more extensive understanding let’s find out what is this common value, private value, and the winner’s curse.&amp;nbsp; Winner’s curse refers to a situation when the intrinsic value of a product is lower than its estimated value. This is a phenomenon that usually arises when bidders have no way of evaluating the exact intrinsic value of a product and offer a price as per their own assessment of the object. As happened in the case of Tymal Mills stated above - the team overestimated the performance of this player ending up winning the bid but losing the game. The winner is usually the one with the most optimistic estimation of the product while he may later realise that valuation by him was way higher in comparison to other bidders. This paradox was quoted by the 2017 Economics Nobel prize winner, Richard Thaler in Misbehaving: The making of behavioural economics as “When many bidders compete for the same object, the winner of the auction is often the bidder who most overvalues the product being sold”. This phenomenon even poses a question to the hypothesis of efficient markets. If the markets would have been efficient then there wouldn’t be such variation in the valuation by different bidders as all shall possess symmetric information.&amp;nbsp; Another deciding factor for the price is the private value of the commodity. It is an individual’s outlook towards a product based on the personal information he possesses. For instance, in the auction of a painting, the private value of that art shall be the pleasure that the bidder is seeking from it for his own sake. However, when he would like to sell that painting in the future then what shall matter to him is the common value which is based on what others think will be the possible price. It is due to the private value of an object that bidders might have massive variations in their bids depending on their own circumstances. For instance, a company with an ability to sell oil at higher prices or process it at a lower price might be ready to bid higher for crude oil.&amp;nbsp; Considering this, Wilson studied the buyers who overpaid for US oil leases in the 1970's and earned lower returns due to the winner’s curse. He argued that the most rational approach is to place a bid below the perceived common value of resources. Milgrom nonetheless focused on a more general theory of auction and analysed different bidding strategies in a plethora of auction formats and concluded that it shall be the most profitable deal for the seller when they share more information with potential buyers. Hence, these laureates have made a major contribution to society by devising a theory that has practical engineering applications. This new auction format is a more sorted approach to sell complex goods and is a well-designed system for both private and public sellers to design their auctions proficiently. With this theory, the researchers advocate that like physics and chemistry, economic theories can also create useful technologies for both companies and the government. This even justifies how economists who earlier only acted as advisors to government now play an indispensable role in corporate companies too.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Drama in Action: ‘Rent a Womb but at what Cost?’</title>
      <link href="/A-Drama-in-Action" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Drama in Action: ‘Rent a Womb but at what Cost?’" />
      <published>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Drama-in-Action</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Drama-in-Action">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene One: The Backdrop&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Change is the only constant. Evolution took humans from a hunch-backed species to one that stands upright, from broader jaws to narrower ones and, if we were to believe scientific findings, from a smaller brain size to a larger one. The species evolved and evolved from one huge scientific name to another. But three things that make humans what they inherently are remained unchanged – the body, the soul and expectations. If we are to believe religious and spiritual texts, the body and the soul are accompanied by the mind, but the mind begets expectations arising from desires, and hence for the sake of simplicity, just like an economist would do, we assume the mind to be our expectations. Therefore, even though humans evolved and changed in their physical form, one thing did in fact remain unchanged and constant, that is their expectations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene Two: The Groundwork&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drifting a little away from evolution and bringing ourselves to the present, societies are laden with a myriad of desires and expectations, more so than just their needs, and sometimes overstepping their wants. The sort of mindset embedded in a society’s head is that of the likelihood of certain outcomes, rather than a proven possibility of them to actually occur. Put in simpler words, the likelihood of someone getting severely hurt someday leads to families saving some money, the likelihood of earning profits leads to investments, and so on. This mirage of an outcome in the future leads to tremendous amounts of pressure in the society to do exactly what the society dictates and deems as 'fit' to exist. And society dictates – every married couple must have a child.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene Three: The Curtain Raiser.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equating happiness with expecting a child, millions of couples resort to the method of surrogacy to have a child of their own. In simple words, surrogacy is a process wherein a woman carries and cares for the child in her womb, that is not her own, but she is willingly carrying for the intended parents who can’t carry a child of their own. Whenever the intended parents compensate the surrogate mother monetarily, it is known as ‘commercial surrogacy’, and otherwise, an ‘altruistic surrogacy’, usually done by a relative/friend. The legality of such agreements between intended parents and the surrogate mother are subjective to various countries and their jurisdictions on the issue. While some countries have banned commercial surrogacy altogether, some developing countries are hubs of surrogacy with an incremental flow of intended parents to these hubs to fulfil their desires. This form of a transnational surrogacy has opened way too many doors for intended parents to exploit and prey on the poor and vulnerable surrogate mothers who are in dire need of the money they could have potentially earned by putting their bodies up for use.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene Four: The Highlight.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There hasn’t been a lack of debates around surrogacy and while most countries have spoken and passed laws in favour of altruistic surrogacy, there are still questions of whether it is ethical to commodify women’s bodies and the kinds of economic impacts attached with the legality of surrogacy. First issues first, the commodification of the bodies of these surrogate mothers is more than just an ethical question. Women who willingly opt to become surrogate mothers usually belong to the weaker sections of the society, which brings to light the kind of structural flaws existing in these developing economies that the women find it to be the last resort to put up their bodies to use in order to live from hand to mouth. Their livelihoods rely on this sort of money, and even when governments choose to ban commercial surrogacy to be able to curb the commodification of bodies, they don’t provide these women with a safety net, and hence their upliftment goes out of the question. In fact, for some, this is the only means of livelihood. For that, they have to go through so much emotional and physical labour and also have to change their entire lives’ priorities. Moreover, the fact that in a market, a commodity is taken from its producer and sold off to a consumer stands rather highly unethically true in this case, but it’s not the child being sold off here since the intended parents already have a right on it, but the gestational services of the surrogate being sold off as a mere commodity and as any other labour activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the economic implications of the legality of surrogacy come with a deep understanding of how economics in general works. The kind of expectations talked about at the beginning of the article is as much part of economics as any other economic jargon. That is because expectations lead to desires and wants, which is when we as rational humans choose to make decisions that provide us with maximum satisfaction and utility.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any legal agreement, the two sides of parties always choose the kind of terms that provide the maximum utility to each of them. Naturally, everybody responds to incentives and here, the intended parents wish for a child while the surrogate mother wishes to obtain that sum of money that she needs for herself or her family. The enforceability of these contracts is rather highly pedestaled by these parties because both of them want their end of the contract to be fulfilled. This is when the aspect of exploitation comes into play when these vulnerable women fail to understand the nitty-gritty of such contracts, of which the intended parents, who are in fact financially stable, take undue advantage and get away with paying less to no amount of money to these surrogate mothers. For several small towns in developing economies, the money coming in from surrogacy is extremely essential for the survival of families, and with the rise in exploitation, they are not just left economically worse-off, but also emotionally. The kind of emotional labour that goes into bearing a child is also something that the surrogate mothers already go through, but with the money coming in, it is marginally easier for them to let go of this attachment and to place the welfare of their families above everything. But when they are stripped off of this money, it becomes all the more difficult letting go of the emotional burden of having done so much for a child and seeing it go for no good of their own. Altruistic surrogacy does them no good either because now the ambit to earn the smallest amount of money through this is also taken away from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene Five: Culmination&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, surrogacy as an activity ends up reducing women to their wombs, and ends up monetising not just their services but also the life decisions they made in order to be able to carry a child, not just once but as many times as their body permits and their conditions demand. For many women, the cost of surrogacy can be enormous and simply not worthwhile. For other women, this cost can be minimal in comparison with choices they prefer to have and which they value more. The kind of opportunity costs these women have to incur are way beyond any measurable financial costs.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Scene One: The Backdrop.&amp;nbsp; Change is the only constant. Evolution took humans from a hunch-backed species to one that stands upright, from broader jaws to narrower ones and, if we were to believe scientific findings, from a smaller brain size to a larger one. The species evolved and evolved from one huge scientific name to another. But three things that make humans what they inherently are remained unchanged – the body, the soul and expectations. If we are to believe religious and spiritual texts, the body and the soul are accompanied by the mind, but the mind begets expectations arising from desires, and hence for the sake of simplicity, just like an economist would do, we assume the mind to be our expectations. Therefore, even though humans evolved and changed in their physical form, one thing did in fact remain unchanged and constant, that is their expectations.&amp;nbsp; Scene Two: The Groundwork.&amp;nbsp; Drifting a little away from evolution and bringing ourselves to the present, societies are laden with a myriad of desires and expectations, more so than just their needs, and sometimes overstepping their wants. The sort of mindset embedded in a society’s head is that of the likelihood of certain outcomes, rather than a proven possibility of them to actually occur. Put in simpler words, the likelihood of someone getting severely hurt someday leads to families saving some money, the likelihood of earning profits leads to investments, and so on. This mirage of an outcome in the future leads to tremendous amounts of pressure in the society to do exactly what the society dictates and deems as 'fit' to exist. And society dictates – every married couple must have a child.&amp;nbsp; Scene Three: The Curtain Raiser.&amp;nbsp; Equating happiness with expecting a child, millions of couples resort to the method of surrogacy to have a child of their own. In simple words, surrogacy is a process wherein a woman carries and cares for the child in her womb, that is not her own, but she is willingly carrying for the intended parents who can’t carry a child of their own. Whenever the intended parents compensate the surrogate mother monetarily, it is known as ‘commercial surrogacy’, and otherwise, an ‘altruistic surrogacy’, usually done by a relative/friend. The legality of such agreements between intended parents and the surrogate mother are subjective to various countries and their jurisdictions on the issue. While some countries have banned commercial surrogacy altogether, some developing countries are hubs of surrogacy with an incremental flow of intended parents to these hubs to fulfil their desires. This form of a transnational surrogacy has opened way too many doors for intended parents to exploit and prey on the poor and vulnerable surrogate mothers who are in dire need of the money they could have potentially earned by putting their bodies up for use.&amp;nbsp; Scene Four: The Highlight. There hasn’t been a lack of debates around surrogacy and while most countries have spoken and passed laws in favour of altruistic surrogacy, there are still questions of whether it is ethical to commodify women’s bodies and the kinds of economic impacts attached with the legality of surrogacy. First issues first, the commodification of the bodies of these surrogate mothers is more than just an ethical question. Women who willingly opt to become surrogate mothers usually belong to the weaker sections of the society, which brings to light the kind of structural flaws existing in these developing economies that the women find it to be the last resort to put up their bodies to use in order to live from hand to mouth. Their livelihoods rely on this sort of money, and even when governments choose to ban commercial surrogacy to be able to curb the commodification of bodies, they don’t provide these women with a safety net, and hence their upliftment goes out of the question. In fact, for some, this is the only means of livelihood. For that, they have to go through so much emotional and physical labour and also have to change their entire lives’ priorities. Moreover, the fact that in a market, a commodity is taken from its producer and sold off to a consumer stands rather highly unethically true in this case, but it’s not the child being sold off here since the intended parents already have a right on it, but the gestational services of the surrogate being sold off as a mere commodity and as any other labour activity. Secondly, the economic implications of the legality of surrogacy come with a deep understanding of how economics in general works. The kind of expectations talked about at the beginning of the article is as much part of economics as any other economic jargon. That is because expectations lead to desires and wants, which is when we as rational humans choose to make decisions that provide us with maximum satisfaction and utility.&amp;nbsp; In any legal agreement, the two sides of parties always choose the kind of terms that provide the maximum utility to each of them. Naturally, everybody responds to incentives and here, the intended parents wish for a child while the surrogate mother wishes to obtain that sum of money that she needs for herself or her family. The enforceability of these contracts is rather highly pedestaled by these parties because both of them want their end of the contract to be fulfilled. This is when the aspect of exploitation comes into play when these vulnerable women fail to understand the nitty-gritty of such contracts, of which the intended parents, who are in fact financially stable, take undue advantage and get away with paying less to no amount of money to these surrogate mothers. For several small towns in developing economies, the money coming in from surrogacy is extremely essential for the survival of families, and with the rise in exploitation, they are not just left economically worse-off, but also emotionally. The kind of emotional labour that goes into bearing a child is also something that the surrogate mothers already go through, but with the money coming in, it is marginally easier for them to let go of this attachment and to place the welfare of their families above everything. But when they are stripped off of this money, it becomes all the more difficult letting go of the emotional burden of having done so much for a child and seeing it go for no good of their own. Altruistic surrogacy does them no good either because now the ambit to earn the smallest amount of money through this is also taken away from them. Scene Five: Culmination.&amp;nbsp; All in all, surrogacy as an activity ends up reducing women to their wombs, and ends up monetising not just their services but also the life decisions they made in order to be able to carry a child, not just once but as many times as their body permits and their conditions demand. For many women, the cost of surrogacy can be enormous and simply not worthwhile. For other women, this cost can be minimal in comparison with choices they prefer to have and which they value more. The kind of opportunity costs these women have to incur are way beyond any measurable financial costs.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">One Nation One Ration Card: Forerunner in Fight against Food Insecurity</title>
      <link href="/One-Nation-One-Ration-Card" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One Nation One Ration Card: Forerunner in Fight against Food Insecurity" />
      <published>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/One-Nation-One-Ration-Card</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/One-Nation-One-Ration-Card">&lt;p&gt;While the unprecedented COVID-19 crisis has had a calamitous impact on all of us, the poorest of the poor have been the worst sufferers. The daily wage workers in India who migrate from the remote parts of the country to economically advanced cities in search of better opportunities were stripped of their economic security in the blink of an eye. Businesses crashed and all activities came to a complete standstill because of the nationwide lockdown. The lockdown put a full stop on all kinds of mobility and discontinued modes of transport. The public was in a state of frenzy, even the well-off strata was apprehensive about the supply of necessities and hence started hoarding. The government assured a continual supply of essential commodities to us but what about the migrant workers, were they given any certainty? In the absence of food security and of any means to commute, along with no pennies in their pocket, they indulged in reverse migration, back to their families.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Food security refers to ensuring adequate food supply for people, especially those who are deprived of basic nutrition, the bare minimum. There are 195 million undernourished people in India, adding up to a quarter of the global hunger burden, as per UN-India. Furthermore, India has recently been ranked 94 out of 107 countries in the Global Hunger Index and has been placed in the ‘serious’ hunger category. As an attempt to alleviate the ill effects of the hunger crisis, the National Food Security Act (NFSA) came into force in 2013. Economist Jean Dreze called this bill an “investment in human capital”. According to the NFSA, 810 million people are entitled to subsidised food grains. The prices of rice, wheat and coarse grain have been set at ₹3, ₹2, and ₹1 per kg respectively. About 235 million ration cards have been issued to nearly 810 million beneficiaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These ration card holders can lift their share of the food grains from the designated Fair Price Shop (FPS) in their locality, where they reside. For instance, if a family resides in Bastar in Chhattisgarh and a few members move to Delhi to work on a construction site, they will no longer be able to purchase their quota of food at subsidised rates from a Public Distribution Shop (PDS) shop in Delhi. This limitation of the existing system divests a large migratory population of their allotted proportion of ration. The national rollout of ‘One Nation, One Ration Card’ is a welcome move in this light. Under this scheme, the beneficiaries can get their share from any of the 540,000 fair price shops across the length and breadth of India. This reform is expected to attain success at a pan-India level by March 31, 2021. However, two prerequisites for the same are 100% installation of Electronic Point of Sale (ePoS) devices and 100% Aadhaar seeding.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technological solution to the problem posed by the earlier system entails identification through biometric authentication on ePoS devices installed at the FPSs. A question might pop up: What is an ePoS? It is a device that electronically records the distribution of ration to different ration cardholders. Connectivity issues are stated as one major bottleneck in the seamless functioning of the framework. However, ePoS also works in offline mode, according to officials. It will most certainly reduce the manual recording of transactions in registers by the dealers. 90% of the PDS shops have been equipped with these devices. As far as the linkage of ration cards with Aadhaar number is concerned, 90% of the 235 million ration cards issued have been seeded.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Integrated Management of Public Distribution System (IMPDS) and &lt;em&gt;Annavitran&lt;/em&gt; are two portals that will help in smooth facilitation of the process at the inter and intra-state level correspondingly. Talking about one more intricacy, the card will now be in a bilingual format, one of the languages will be the local one and the other can either be Hindi or English. This is because when the recipient is not in his/her native place, there should be ease in comprehending the details and uniformity should be maintained.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critical challenges in realising the goal are studying and record-keeping of labour migration patterns. If a family is scattered in two locations, reconciling data at both locations would be a major task. Food Corporation of India (FCI) godowns and other storage facilities need to function parallel to the demand for grains created by the immigration/emigration of the labour force. Just a recent illustration of the change in demand for goods because of reverse migration is that of the Flipkart and Amazon festive sale. Sales doubled up in the first two days when compared to the 2019 edition. In the wake of discounts, an upswing in new shoppers from Tier 2 and Tier 3 cities has been witnessed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, the interstate ration card portability cluster is 28 states and union territories strong. Some states with an influx of labour are still laggards in the instalment of ePoS and undertaking biometric authentication. States like West Bengal and Assam, which are still not on board need to be pushed to complete the necessary requirements for true integration of state portals to that of the centre. Computerisation of the supply network of FCI will boost the efficacy and help translate the chalked down scheme into a wholesome reality. Once fully implemented, the scheme is sure to uplift the country in the&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Global Hunger Index. Will it mitigate the suffering of the downtrodden section dying, helplessly walking miles trying to shelter themselves, unable to feed themselves, let alone two but even one square meal? Let us choose to be optimistic in this regard. Even a step forward in the right direction is progress for humankind.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushi Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">While the unprecedented COVID-19 crisis has had a calamitous impact on all of us, the poorest of the poor have been the worst sufferers. The daily wage workers in India who migrate from the remote parts of the country to economically advanced cities in search of better opportunities were stripped of their economic security in the blink of an eye. Businesses crashed and all activities came to a complete standstill because of the nationwide lockdown. The lockdown put a full stop on all kinds of mobility and discontinued modes of transport. The public was in a state of frenzy, even the well-off strata was apprehensive about the supply of necessities and hence started hoarding. The government assured a continual supply of essential commodities to us but what about the migrant workers, were they given any certainty? In the absence of food security and of any means to commute, along with no pennies in their pocket, they indulged in reverse migration, back to their families.&amp;nbsp; Food security refers to ensuring adequate food supply for people, especially those who are deprived of basic nutrition, the bare minimum. There are 195 million undernourished people in India, adding up to a quarter of the global hunger burden, as per UN-India. Furthermore, India has recently been ranked 94 out of 107 countries in the Global Hunger Index and has been placed in the ‘serious’ hunger category. As an attempt to alleviate the ill effects of the hunger crisis, the National Food Security Act (NFSA) came into force in 2013. Economist Jean Dreze called this bill an “investment in human capital”. According to the NFSA, 810 million people are entitled to subsidised food grains. The prices of rice, wheat and coarse grain have been set at ₹3, ₹2, and ₹1 per kg respectively. About 235 million ration cards have been issued to nearly 810 million beneficiaries. These ration card holders can lift their share of the food grains from the designated Fair Price Shop (FPS) in their locality, where they reside. For instance, if a family resides in Bastar in Chhattisgarh and a few members move to Delhi to work on a construction site, they will no longer be able to purchase their quota of food at subsidised rates from a Public Distribution Shop (PDS) shop in Delhi. This limitation of the existing system divests a large migratory population of their allotted proportion of ration. The national rollout of ‘One Nation, One Ration Card’ is a welcome move in this light. Under this scheme, the beneficiaries can get their share from any of the 540,000 fair price shops across the length and breadth of India. This reform is expected to attain success at a pan-India level by March 31, 2021. However, two prerequisites for the same are 100% installation of Electronic Point of Sale (ePoS) devices and 100% Aadhaar seeding.&amp;nbsp; The technological solution to the problem posed by the earlier system entails identification through biometric authentication on ePoS devices installed at the FPSs. A question might pop up: What is an ePoS? It is a device that electronically records the distribution of ration to different ration cardholders. Connectivity issues are stated as one major bottleneck in the seamless functioning of the framework. However, ePoS also works in offline mode, according to officials. It will most certainly reduce the manual recording of transactions in registers by the dealers. 90% of the PDS shops have been equipped with these devices. As far as the linkage of ration cards with Aadhaar number is concerned, 90% of the 235 million ration cards issued have been seeded.&amp;nbsp; Integrated Management of Public Distribution System (IMPDS) and Annavitran are two portals that will help in smooth facilitation of the process at the inter and intra-state level correspondingly. Talking about one more intricacy, the card will now be in a bilingual format, one of the languages will be the local one and the other can either be Hindi or English. This is because when the recipient is not in his/her native place, there should be ease in comprehending the details and uniformity should be maintained.&amp;nbsp; Critical challenges in realising the goal are studying and record-keeping of labour migration patterns. If a family is scattered in two locations, reconciling data at both locations would be a major task. Food Corporation of India (FCI) godowns and other storage facilities need to function parallel to the demand for grains created by the immigration/emigration of the labour force. Just a recent illustration of the change in demand for goods because of reverse migration is that of the Flipkart and Amazon festive sale. Sales doubled up in the first two days when compared to the 2019 edition. In the wake of discounts, an upswing in new shoppers from Tier 2 and Tier 3 cities has been witnessed.&amp;nbsp; Currently, the interstate ration card portability cluster is 28 states and union territories strong. Some states with an influx of labour are still laggards in the instalment of ePoS and undertaking biometric authentication. States like West Bengal and Assam, which are still not on board need to be pushed to complete the necessary requirements for true integration of state portals to that of the centre. Computerisation of the supply network of FCI will boost the efficacy and help translate the chalked down scheme into a wholesome reality. Once fully implemented, the scheme is sure to uplift the country in the Global Hunger Index. Will it mitigate the suffering of the downtrodden section dying, helplessly walking miles trying to shelter themselves, unable to feed themselves, let alone two but even one square meal? Let us choose to be optimistic in this regard. Even a step forward in the right direction is progress for humankind.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Inflation Check!</title>
      <link href="/Inflation-Check" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inflation Check!" />
      <published>2020-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Inflation-Check</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Inflation-Check">&lt;p&gt;The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) was established by the Reserve Bank of India Act in 1934. The Act vests in RBI the powers to operate the monetary policy framework of the country. It also defines the primary objective of monetary policy as “&lt;em&gt;maintaining price stability while keeping in mind the objective of growth&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; Maintaining price stability, that is inflation, is pivotal for achieving sustained growth, and with the current conditions prevailing around the world, it has become all the more important to keep prices under check.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tools to Control Inflation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the pivotal functions of the RBI is that of the controller of credit. Credit money, the money lent out by the financial institutions, forms the most important part of the money supply. Money supply, in turn, has important implications for the economic stability of a country. For these reasons, the RBI can control inflation by controlling the credit in the economy. The first and foremost instrument that the RBI uses for inflation control is the ‘Policy Rate’ (popularly known as the Repo Rate). Repo rate is the interest rate at which the Reserve Bank provides overnight liquidity to banks (against the collateral of government and other approved securities). By setting the repo rate, RBI controls the borrowing rates of the banks. When RBI wants to control inflation, the rates are increased. Therefore, the borrowing costs for the banks and other lenders increase. They pass this increased cost on to their customers by charging a higher interest rate to lend money. This reduces the demand for money in the economy and helps in controlling inflation. Another tool is the ‘Reverse Repo Rate’. It is the rate at which RBI borrows money from commercial banks. An increase in this rate can drain money out of the banking system (i.e. reduce money supply). Another instrument is the ‘Bank Rate’, which is the rate at which RBI buys or rediscounts bills of exchange or other commercial papers. When the bank rate is increased, it will have a similar impact as the repo rate has on inflation control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central bank can also use variable reserve requirements, Cash Reserve Ratio&lt;em&gt; (CRR)&lt;/em&gt; and Statutory Liquidity Ratio&lt;em&gt; (SLR)&lt;/em&gt;, to control credit. CRR is the balance that a commercial bank is required to maintain with RBI in the form of cash reserves. SLR is the share of its total deposits that a bank has to maintain in the form of liquid assets, such as gold and government securities. By changing these ratios, RBI can control credit in the economy. If the Bank wants to, say, discourage credit, (so as to control inflation) it can increase these ratios. Raising these rates will reduce the surplus cash reserves that the banks could offer as credit. These two statutory requirements are vital. The repo rate will successfully manifest into an inflation controlling tool because of the existence of these requirements. A commercial bank will borrow from RBI when it has a dearth of funds to meet the CRR and SLR requirements. If the banks could meet the requirements without borrowing from the RBI, the transmission of the monetary policy becomes uncertain (commercial banks may not pass to their customers the benefits of rate cuts by the RBI). Another monetary policy tool is the ‘Liquidity Adjustment Facility’ (LAF). The LAF consists of overnight as well as term repo auctions. The aim of term repo is to develop “&lt;em&gt;an inter-bank term money market, which in turn can set market-based benchmarks for pricing of loans and deposits, and hence improve the transmission of monetary policy&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;RBI can also indulge in ‘Open Market Operations’ (OMO) to affect the money supply in an economy and thereby the inflation. These operations are direct sales and purchases of government securities so as to absorb or inject liquidity into the economy, respectively. OMOs help in altering the quantity of money in circulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Monetary Framework&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An agreement, which was later incorporated into the RBI Act, was signed in 2015 by the RBI and the Central government to formulate a new monetary framework. By this, India had adopted flexible inflation targeting as a mandate for RBI and the setting up of a Monetary Policy Committee (to set the policy rate). This new framework specified that the RBI should conduct inflation-targeting using the policy rate. This is a significant move away from the erstwhile approach of a multiple indicators approach where inflation control and economic growth were given equal priority. An inflation-targeting approach is one where the Central Bank tries to maintain inflation at a pre-decided level; or within a pre-decided band. However, this move has faced criticism. Concerns were raised as to how effective can the Reserve Bank be in controlling inflation and about the ramifications of attempting such control.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pulapre Balakrishnan, a noted economist, points out that since 2008 inflation recorded an upward shift for about five years. He&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thehindu.com/opinion/lead/going-beyond-inflation-targeting/article7550932.ece&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thehindu.com/opinion/lead/going-beyond-inflation-targeting/article7550932.ece&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt;, “&lt;em&gt;It would be difficult to square this (the rise in inflation) with the suggestion that it reflects the Bank’s efforts to maintain growth, for growth has actually been lower in this period&lt;/em&gt;”. Dr V Anantha Nageswaran, a member of the PM Economic Advisory Council,&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livemint.com/news/india/why-rbi-s-inflation-regime-is-broken-11600269451733.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livemint.com/news/india/why-rbi-s-inflation-regime-is-broken-11600269451733.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;quoted&lt;/a&gt; how research from New Zealand indicated “&lt;em&gt;even firms did not form their inflation expectations based on the Central Bank’s inflation target and monetary policy framework&lt;/em&gt;”. He further added that Central Banks can neither control economic growth nor inflation, but only credit growth. He suggested that Central Banks should redefine their mandate to control the ‘overheating’, which manifests into credit growth, asset markets, trade deficits, and (sometimes) inflation; and consequently, return to the “multiple indicators approach”. There is also an increasing consensus among economists that the high inflation in India is primarily because of supply-side rigidities, food and fuel prices, and high fiscal expansion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One must understand that the Central Banks hold a greater sway on the financial and money markets; and by that, they can significantly influence these two markets. Therefore, they are better equipped to influence risk-taking behaviour in the asset market. However, monetary policy is less powerful in determining the long-term performance of an economy. Monetary policy, for instance, can hardly increase the aggregate demand in the economy over the long run. Former New Zealand Central Bank Governor Graeme Wheeler remarked, “&lt;em&gt;even in the shorter term, monetary policy’s influence may be low in an environment where debt levels are high and where there is considerable uncertainty about economic prospects&lt;/em&gt;”. It is, perhaps, time for India to find a new monetary framework.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) was established by the Reserve Bank of India Act in 1934. The Act vests in RBI the powers to operate the monetary policy framework of the country. It also defines the primary objective of monetary policy as “maintaining price stability while keeping in mind the objective of growth”. Maintaining price stability, that is inflation, is pivotal for achieving sustained growth, and with the current conditions prevailing around the world, it has become all the more important to keep prices under check. Tools to Control Inflation One of the pivotal functions of the RBI is that of the controller of credit. Credit money, the money lent out by the financial institutions, forms the most important part of the money supply. Money supply, in turn, has important implications for the economic stability of a country. For these reasons, the RBI can control inflation by controlling the credit in the economy. The first and foremost instrument that the RBI uses for inflation control is the ‘Policy Rate’ (popularly known as the Repo Rate). Repo rate is the interest rate at which the Reserve Bank provides overnight liquidity to banks (against the collateral of government and other approved securities). By setting the repo rate, RBI controls the borrowing rates of the banks. When RBI wants to control inflation, the rates are increased. Therefore, the borrowing costs for the banks and other lenders increase. They pass this increased cost on to their customers by charging a higher interest rate to lend money. This reduces the demand for money in the economy and helps in controlling inflation. Another tool is the ‘Reverse Repo Rate’. It is the rate at which RBI borrows money from commercial banks. An increase in this rate can drain money out of the banking system (i.e. reduce money supply). Another instrument is the ‘Bank Rate’, which is the rate at which RBI buys or rediscounts bills of exchange or other commercial papers. When the bank rate is increased, it will have a similar impact as the repo rate has on inflation control. The central bank can also use variable reserve requirements, Cash Reserve Ratio (CRR) and Statutory Liquidity Ratio (SLR), to control credit. CRR is the balance that a commercial bank is required to maintain with RBI in the form of cash reserves. SLR is the share of its total deposits that a bank has to maintain in the form of liquid assets, such as gold and government securities. By changing these ratios, RBI can control credit in the economy. If the Bank wants to, say, discourage credit, (so as to control inflation) it can increase these ratios. Raising these rates will reduce the surplus cash reserves that the banks could offer as credit. These two statutory requirements are vital. The repo rate will successfully manifest into an inflation controlling tool because of the existence of these requirements. A commercial bank will borrow from RBI when it has a dearth of funds to meet the CRR and SLR requirements. If the banks could meet the requirements without borrowing from the RBI, the transmission of the monetary policy becomes uncertain (commercial banks may not pass to their customers the benefits of rate cuts by the RBI). Another monetary policy tool is the ‘Liquidity Adjustment Facility’ (LAF). The LAF consists of overnight as well as term repo auctions. The aim of term repo is to develop “an inter-bank term money market, which in turn can set market-based benchmarks for pricing of loans and deposits, and hence improve the transmission of monetary policy”. RBI can also indulge in ‘Open Market Operations’ (OMO) to affect the money supply in an economy and thereby the inflation. These operations are direct sales and purchases of government securities so as to absorb or inject liquidity into the economy, respectively. OMOs help in altering the quantity of money in circulation. The Monetary Framework An agreement, which was later incorporated into the RBI Act, was signed in 2015 by the RBI and the Central government to formulate a new monetary framework. By this, India had adopted flexible inflation targeting as a mandate for RBI and the setting up of a Monetary Policy Committee (to set the policy rate). This new framework specified that the RBI should conduct inflation-targeting using the policy rate. This is a significant move away from the erstwhile approach of a multiple indicators approach where inflation control and economic growth were given equal priority. An inflation-targeting approach is one where the Central Bank tries to maintain inflation at a pre-decided level; or within a pre-decided band. However, this move has faced criticism. Concerns were raised as to how effective can the Reserve Bank be in controlling inflation and about the ramifications of attempting such control.&amp;nbsp; Pulapre Balakrishnan, a noted economist, points out that since 2008 inflation recorded an upward shift for about five years. He said, “It would be difficult to square this (the rise in inflation) with the suggestion that it reflects the Bank’s efforts to maintain growth, for growth has actually been lower in this period”. Dr V Anantha Nageswaran, a member of the PM Economic Advisory Council, quoted how research from New Zealand indicated “even firms did not form their inflation expectations based on the Central Bank’s inflation target and monetary policy framework”. He further added that Central Banks can neither control economic growth nor inflation, but only credit growth. He suggested that Central Banks should redefine their mandate to control the ‘overheating’, which manifests into credit growth, asset markets, trade deficits, and (sometimes) inflation; and consequently, return to the “multiple indicators approach”. There is also an increasing consensus among economists that the high inflation in India is primarily because of supply-side rigidities, food and fuel prices, and high fiscal expansion. One must understand that the Central Banks hold a greater sway on the financial and money markets; and by that, they can significantly influence these two markets. Therefore, they are better equipped to influence risk-taking behaviour in the asset market. However, monetary policy is less powerful in determining the long-term performance of an economy. Monetary policy, for instance, can hardly increase the aggregate demand in the economy over the long run. Former New Zealand Central Bank Governor Graeme Wheeler remarked, “even in the shorter term, monetary policy’s influence may be low in an environment where debt levels are high and where there is considerable uncertainty about economic prospects”. It is, perhaps, time for India to find a new monetary framework.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Contracting India</title>
      <link href="/Contracting-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=" Contracting India" />
      <published>2020-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Contracting-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Contracting-India">&lt;p&gt;The Indian economy contracted by a drastic 23.9% in the April-June quarter of 2020-21 which is being stated as the most drastic fall in the Indian economy. What is more worrisome is the fact that this diminution is the worst amongst the world’s top economies and is an issue of immense concern for a major developing economy like India. The extent of the damage is expected to be manifold with the informal sector being the worst hit and revival looking like a prolonged journey. This can be supported by a statement made by Professor Arun Kumar of &lt;em&gt;New Delhi’s Institute of Social Sciences&lt;/em&gt; wherein he estimates the economic slide to be a negative 40% if the informal sector is taken into account. While the outbreak of COVID-19 is the prime cause of the gloomy economy, the already prevalent global economic slowdown and side-effects of the trade war cannot be overlooked.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On March 25, 2020, India declared a complete national lockdown which was the world’s largest lockdown owing to the widespread pandemic. Apart from the limited movement of essential commodities, all businesses either came to a standstill with bleak immunity to have a revival spurt or they got wiped out. With people losing jobs in various sectors of the economy, the rise in unemployment has only deepened the strain. Experts analyse the figures and the trend as the onset of India’s largest recession since 1996.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For emerging economies, the prospects of a speedy recovery seem to be dim as per the International Monetary Fund (IMF), but the scenario is worst for India as the GDP contracted by a way larger margin than what was actually predicted. Adding to the crisis is the prediction by IMF which forecasted a contraction of 10.3% in the GDP in the fiscal year 2021, against the Central Bank’s prediction of 9.5%. The forecast in itself brings about a cloud of panic as this rate was predicted to be 4.5% in June 2020, the 5.8% leap is a near-indigestible figure for an economy of a great significance like that of India. The global economic significance that the nation has managed to engrave and give a stiff fight to its neighbour finds itself dwindling as China’s road to revival is far stronger than what was anticipated. While households and small businesses stand wrecked as an aftermath of the lockdown, the government has been continuously chalking out strategies to boost demand as a measure to curtail the downfall of one of the world’s major economies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quake in the economy shook all the sectors but the major contributors like construction, manufacturing and transportation were the worst hit. While agriculture did fairly well with an unexpected growth of 3.4%, it wasn’t strong enough to nullify the 39.3% contraction in the manufacturing sector, 23.3% in the mining sector, and 50.3% in the construction sector. Not only this, transportation along with trade, hotels, communication and broadcasting shrank by 47% in the first quarter. The pandemic forced the export shipments to dry out, people were locked at home with no eating out and no tourism. Businessmen had to either shut down their trade or put it to a halt. The prostration of the real-estate sector cannot be overlooked, which is clearly evident from the sharp fall in the rates and lack of demand for property. Along with this, tenants began emptying spaces already rented-out, as many started moving back to native places owing to no job in hand. Hence, the sectors that managed to keep themselves afloat in these troubled times could not stop the others from slipping down a sharp cliff.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the most profound problem that the Indian economy faces is that of its informal sector. While India’s large and a considerable proportion of workforce adjusts itself in the informal sector, fled back to its hometowns with a lesser impetus to come back. With no food to fill their stomachs, this downtrodden section of the society finds itself in a quagmire.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The road to revival is definitely a tough one, but the government is gearing up itself in all and every way possible. With a systematic unlocking of the economy, the growth is finding its way back. While the experts call for a need to introduce a fresh stimulus package for the middle class, the government seems to be delaying its actions aimed at fighting the slowdown. But why a stimulus package for the middle class? The answer lies in the urgent need to revive the private consumption, that is to generate demand. The driving factor behind the slowdown remains a slowed consumption and lack of demand from the middle-class which forms an important chunk of the population consuming the most. A stimulus package to this sect of the population would mean kickstarting the revival process, and 85-90% of the population in this section is employed either in the government sector or in Public Sector Units (PSUs). It is evident that the government is functioning to the best of its capacity in these unprecedented times. Nevertheless, it is very important to clear state dues at the earliest in order to ensure revival in each and every part of the country. While the states and the Centre have been in a tussle over pending Goods and Sales Tax (GST) compensations, the Centre clearly stated that it cannot submit these pending compensations to the states owing to the medical and financial emergency and has, in fact, demanded the states to pay their GST dues for the year by borrowing, thus adding to the stress for the State governments who are already struggling to extract revenue. This is in complete contradiction to the ex-RBI Governor, Raghuram Rajan’s, statement who clearly stated in a recent article the dire need to replenish the state’s coffers as a crucial move towards recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With enough food for thought and tremendous scope to plan out recovery models, there is another contradiction this article will close itself with. At the beginning of 2020, while presenting the budget, the Honourable Finance Minister, Nirmala Sitharaman had assumed a GDP growth of 10% for the fiscal year and moving closer to the target of a $5 trillion economy by 2024. On the contrary, the world’s fifth-largest economy in the pre-Covid era is believed to get 10% smaller as per economists across the world. The dire need to act real quick along with substantial stimulus packages is expected out of the government without any further delay, otherwise, the re-examination of the targets and goals stated in the budget for the financial year 2020-21 will be the last resort.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Indian economy contracted by a drastic 23.9% in the April-June quarter of 2020-21 which is being stated as the most drastic fall in the Indian economy. What is more worrisome is the fact that this diminution is the worst amongst the world’s top economies and is an issue of immense concern for a major developing economy like India. The extent of the damage is expected to be manifold with the informal sector being the worst hit and revival looking like a prolonged journey. This can be supported by a statement made by Professor Arun Kumar of New Delhi’s Institute of Social Sciences wherein he estimates the economic slide to be a negative 40% if the informal sector is taken into account. While the outbreak of COVID-19 is the prime cause of the gloomy economy, the already prevalent global economic slowdown and side-effects of the trade war cannot be overlooked.&amp;nbsp; On March 25, 2020, India declared a complete national lockdown which was the world’s largest lockdown owing to the widespread pandemic. Apart from the limited movement of essential commodities, all businesses either came to a standstill with bleak immunity to have a revival spurt or they got wiped out. With people losing jobs in various sectors of the economy, the rise in unemployment has only deepened the strain. Experts analyse the figures and the trend as the onset of India’s largest recession since 1996.&amp;nbsp; For emerging economies, the prospects of a speedy recovery seem to be dim as per the International Monetary Fund (IMF), but the scenario is worst for India as the GDP contracted by a way larger margin than what was actually predicted. Adding to the crisis is the prediction by IMF which forecasted a contraction of 10.3% in the GDP in the fiscal year 2021, against the Central Bank’s prediction of 9.5%. The forecast in itself brings about a cloud of panic as this rate was predicted to be 4.5% in June 2020, the 5.8% leap is a near-indigestible figure for an economy of a great significance like that of India. The global economic significance that the nation has managed to engrave and give a stiff fight to its neighbour finds itself dwindling as China’s road to revival is far stronger than what was anticipated. While households and small businesses stand wrecked as an aftermath of the lockdown, the government has been continuously chalking out strategies to boost demand as a measure to curtail the downfall of one of the world’s major economies. The quake in the economy shook all the sectors but the major contributors like construction, manufacturing and transportation were the worst hit. While agriculture did fairly well with an unexpected growth of 3.4%, it wasn’t strong enough to nullify the 39.3% contraction in the manufacturing sector, 23.3% in the mining sector, and 50.3% in the construction sector. Not only this, transportation along with trade, hotels, communication and broadcasting shrank by 47% in the first quarter. The pandemic forced the export shipments to dry out, people were locked at home with no eating out and no tourism. Businessmen had to either shut down their trade or put it to a halt. The prostration of the real-estate sector cannot be overlooked, which is clearly evident from the sharp fall in the rates and lack of demand for property. Along with this, tenants began emptying spaces already rented-out, as many started moving back to native places owing to no job in hand. Hence, the sectors that managed to keep themselves afloat in these troubled times could not stop the others from slipping down a sharp cliff.&amp;nbsp; On the other hand, the most profound problem that the Indian economy faces is that of its informal sector. While India’s large and a considerable proportion of workforce adjusts itself in the informal sector, fled back to its hometowns with a lesser impetus to come back. With no food to fill their stomachs, this downtrodden section of the society finds itself in a quagmire.&amp;nbsp; The road to revival is definitely a tough one, but the government is gearing up itself in all and every way possible. With a systematic unlocking of the economy, the growth is finding its way back. While the experts call for a need to introduce a fresh stimulus package for the middle class, the government seems to be delaying its actions aimed at fighting the slowdown. But why a stimulus package for the middle class? The answer lies in the urgent need to revive the private consumption, that is to generate demand. The driving factor behind the slowdown remains a slowed consumption and lack of demand from the middle-class which forms an important chunk of the population consuming the most. A stimulus package to this sect of the population would mean kickstarting the revival process, and 85-90% of the population in this section is employed either in the government sector or in Public Sector Units (PSUs). It is evident that the government is functioning to the best of its capacity in these unprecedented times. Nevertheless, it is very important to clear state dues at the earliest in order to ensure revival in each and every part of the country. While the states and the Centre have been in a tussle over pending Goods and Sales Tax (GST) compensations, the Centre clearly stated that it cannot submit these pending compensations to the states owing to the medical and financial emergency and has, in fact, demanded the states to pay their GST dues for the year by borrowing, thus adding to the stress for the State governments who are already struggling to extract revenue. This is in complete contradiction to the ex-RBI Governor, Raghuram Rajan’s, statement who clearly stated in a recent article the dire need to replenish the state’s coffers as a crucial move towards recovery. With enough food for thought and tremendous scope to plan out recovery models, there is another contradiction this article will close itself with. At the beginning of 2020, while presenting the budget, the Honourable Finance Minister, Nirmala Sitharaman had assumed a GDP growth of 10% for the fiscal year and moving closer to the target of a $5 trillion economy by 2024. On the contrary, the world’s fifth-largest economy in the pre-Covid era is believed to get 10% smaller as per economists across the world. The dire need to act real quick along with substantial stimulus packages is expected out of the government without any further delay, otherwise, the re-examination of the targets and goals stated in the budget for the financial year 2020-21 will be the last resort.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">COVID-19 and the Indian Labour Market</title>
      <link href="/COVID-19-and-the-Indian-Labour-Market" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19 and the Indian Labour Market" />
      <published>2020-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/COVID-19-and-the-Indian-Labour-Market</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/COVID-19-and-the-Indian-Labour-Market">&lt;p&gt;The outbreak of coronavirus has resulted in an unparalleled public health and socio-economic crisis. COVID-19 has heavily impacted the daily lives of people and has thwarted their ability to earn their livelihood. The case is no different for India. With the view of maintaining social distancing and other preventive health measures followed, work-from-home has become the new normal. However, it is important to understand that not all the segments of the labour market are able to function this way. The dual shock of the lockdown and pandemic has thus resulted in major disruptions in the labour market, and job and income losses of millions of people.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spread of coronavirus has been rampant in India, with a steep increase in the number of cases being reported on a daily basis. Before the outbreak of COVID-19, India had already been experiencing an economic slowdown, with the growth rate in GDP declining to 3.1% in Jan-March quarter 2020. However, in the Apr-Jun quarter of the financial year 2020-21, the GDP growth rate has fallen to a negative 23.9%, the worst ever in economic history. All the crucial parameters like manufacturing, construction, trade and the hotel industry have witnessed a steep decline, registering negative growth rates as well. According to the Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation (MOSPI), India's Industrial Production (IIP) fell by 16.7% year-on-year in March 2020.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impact on the Indian Labour Market&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the worst-hit in this situation has been the labour market. According to the Centre for Monitoring Indian Economy (CMIE), a Mumbai-based think tank, during the period of lockdown (March-May), the unemployment rate went up from 8% to 24.3%. As of April 2020, 122 million people have suffered a job loss, with casual workers and self-employed accounting for a major proportion of this, pegging at 90 million. The effect of the shocks induced by the ongoing crisis has been particularly harsh for a specific group of people in the labour market. They can be identified as less educated individuals with low incomes who are engaged in risky and unstable working conditions. These individuals form a major portion of the informal sector. On the other hand, only a small share of the labour force is employed in salaried jobs with the perks of social security benefits. Hence, an outcome of this scenario will be a sheer rise in income inequalities. The most recent data available on the labour force is the Periodic Labour Force Survey (PLFS 2018-19). According to the survey, the labour force participation rate in 2018-19 stands at 37.5%. The share of people self-employed, as casual labourers and as regular salaried workers in rural and urban areas can be observed in the table below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pib.gov.in/PressReleaseIframePage.aspx?PRID=1629366&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/periodiclabourforcesurvey.png&quot; /&gt;Source: Periodic Labour Force Survey 2018-19&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the regular salaried workers, white-collar professionals and other employees have witnessed the biggest loss of jobs. These include software engineers, physicians, teachers, accountants, analysts and the type who are professionally qualified and are employed in some private or government organisation. According to CMIE, the employment of these professionally qualified white-collar workers fell steeply to 12.2 million during the wave of May-August 2020. This is the lowest employment of these professionals since 2016. An unprecedented 21 million salaried employees had lost their jobs by the end of August. All the gains made in their employment over the past four years were washed away during the lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, those who are self-employed, only a minor proportion of them can be classified as employers. Of these 57.4% rural self-employed households, most of them are marginal cultivators and petty artisans, while 38.7% of self-employed households in urban areas are engaged in small shops, low-scale businesses or intermediation activities. Similarly, the casual labour households that make up almost 20% of the labour force are also extremely vulnerable and fragile in coping up with this economic downturn.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the people categorised as self-employed or as casual workers are faced with no income stability or job security and are outside the umbrella of the employment benefits offered by firms. Compared to them, the regular salaried workers do receive a salary on a periodic basis, but even then, not all of them have access to social security benefits or secure job contracts. It is thus these casual workers that are at the bottom of the hierarchy and are financially vulnerable. A sudden loss of income to these people will lead them to fall into deep poverty. The impact of the pandemic has been the worst for these sectors where the options for remote work are limited or negligible.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the World Bank, the shock of the pandemic is expected to push 12 million people into extreme poverty in India. Some reports have suggested that poverty in India had started rising even before the COVID-19 crisis, therefore the above estimates might even be higher. With the cloud of uncertainty looming over their heads, and the loss of jobs and incomes, the poor and the illiterate do not have the option to stay unemployed or wait for a job which serves their needs. In rural areas, we still have Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee Act (MGNREGA) as a fallback employment option. But such a safety net doesn’t exist for the urban labourers, who are also faced with high costs of living. The ones rendered unemployed have taken up low income and low productivity jobs, while some have migrated back to their homes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As was expected, with the declaration of a nationwide lockdown, there was an unprecedented large-scale reverse migration of labour wherein millions of workers travelled across the state borders amidst food shortages and uncertainty about their work prospects in the future. While the government schemes ensure the availability of rations, the distribution system failed to be effective. Penniless and stranded, workers left cities for their villages on foot or bicycles, cramped in trucks and later by trains.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This inter-state migration has thus put some of India’s biggest sectors at risk. Sectors such as manufacturing, retail and wholesale trade, mining and hospitality services are heavily dependent on migrants from other states, as analysed by India Ratings and Research. “A consequence of this is a labour crunch that might hit capacity utilisation for several firms. The manufacturing sector which employs over 6 million migrant workers from other states, highest as compared to other sectors, has started suffering. The sector contributes almost 8% of the country’s GDP. Thus the manufacturing sector might face a labour shortage in the near term if labourers do not return in the coming months. This will lead to an increase in wages in the short run and a fall in profits. Another obvious impact is on the mining sector, which has been observing a decline in the past few months.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amidst all this, many state governments have repealed labour laws. The government of the North Indian state of Uttar Pradesh has cleared an ordinance that suspends all the labour laws for a period of three years with the exceptions of laws related to the abolishment of bonded labour, ex gratia payments to workers in case of work-related diseases and disabilities and timely wage payments. Similar actions have been taken by the state governments of Madhya Pradesh and Gujarat with a few variations. The decision has been taken to encourage new investments, setting up of new infrastructure, and for the upliftment of existing industries and factories.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Lies Ahead?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the latest estimates by CMIE, the unemployment rates have dropped to 6.4%, which is the lowest rate seen in a while, but this is hardly a cause for celebration. Other weekly labour metrics have only deteriorated, for example, the average labour participation rate fell down to 20.7% in the first three weeks of September as opposed to 40.96% in August. Similarly, the average employment rate during the first three weeks of August at 37.9% is substantially higher than the rates seen recently. But the slope is negative since the recovery is distinctly negative.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the country recently declared ‘Unlock 5.0’, the economy is still far from being on a path of recovery. The economy is still worse off as compared to the conditions before the lockdown. The recent labour statistics only highlight the fear of India slipping from this ‘incomplete’ recovery unless the government comes up with a well-calculated recovery plan.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rajsi Sah</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The outbreak of coronavirus has resulted in an unparalleled public health and socio-economic crisis. COVID-19 has heavily impacted the daily lives of people and has thwarted their ability to earn their livelihood. The case is no different for India. With the view of maintaining social distancing and other preventive health measures followed, work-from-home has become the new normal. However, it is important to understand that not all the segments of the labour market are able to function this way. The dual shock of the lockdown and pandemic has thus resulted in major disruptions in the labour market, and job and income losses of millions of people.&amp;nbsp; The spread of coronavirus has been rampant in India, with a steep increase in the number of cases being reported on a daily basis. Before the outbreak of COVID-19, India had already been experiencing an economic slowdown, with the growth rate in GDP declining to 3.1% in Jan-March quarter 2020. However, in the Apr-Jun quarter of the financial year 2020-21, the GDP growth rate has fallen to a negative 23.9%, the worst ever in economic history. All the crucial parameters like manufacturing, construction, trade and the hotel industry have witnessed a steep decline, registering negative growth rates as well. According to the Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation (MOSPI), India's Industrial Production (IIP) fell by 16.7% year-on-year in March 2020.&amp;nbsp; Impact on the Indian Labour Market&amp;nbsp; One of the worst-hit in this situation has been the labour market. According to the Centre for Monitoring Indian Economy (CMIE), a Mumbai-based think tank, during the period of lockdown (March-May), the unemployment rate went up from 8% to 24.3%. As of April 2020, 122 million people have suffered a job loss, with casual workers and self-employed accounting for a major proportion of this, pegging at 90 million. The effect of the shocks induced by the ongoing crisis has been particularly harsh for a specific group of people in the labour market. They can be identified as less educated individuals with low incomes who are engaged in risky and unstable working conditions. These individuals form a major portion of the informal sector. On the other hand, only a small share of the labour force is employed in salaried jobs with the perks of social security benefits. Hence, an outcome of this scenario will be a sheer rise in income inequalities. The most recent data available on the labour force is the Periodic Labour Force Survey (PLFS 2018-19). According to the survey, the labour force participation rate in 2018-19 stands at 37.5%. The share of people self-employed, as casual labourers and as regular salaried workers in rural and urban areas can be observed in the table below: Source: Periodic Labour Force Survey 2018-19 Among the regular salaried workers, white-collar professionals and other employees have witnessed the biggest loss of jobs. These include software engineers, physicians, teachers, accountants, analysts and the type who are professionally qualified and are employed in some private or government organisation. According to CMIE, the employment of these professionally qualified white-collar workers fell steeply to 12.2 million during the wave of May-August 2020. This is the lowest employment of these professionals since 2016. An unprecedented 21 million salaried employees had lost their jobs by the end of August. All the gains made in their employment over the past four years were washed away during the lockdown. Furthermore, those who are self-employed, only a minor proportion of them can be classified as employers. Of these 57.4% rural self-employed households, most of them are marginal cultivators and petty artisans, while 38.7% of self-employed households in urban areas are engaged in small shops, low-scale businesses or intermediation activities. Similarly, the casual labour households that make up almost 20% of the labour force are also extremely vulnerable and fragile in coping up with this economic downturn.&amp;nbsp; Thus, the people categorised as self-employed or as casual workers are faced with no income stability or job security and are outside the umbrella of the employment benefits offered by firms. Compared to them, the regular salaried workers do receive a salary on a periodic basis, but even then, not all of them have access to social security benefits or secure job contracts. It is thus these casual workers that are at the bottom of the hierarchy and are financially vulnerable. A sudden loss of income to these people will lead them to fall into deep poverty. The impact of the pandemic has been the worst for these sectors where the options for remote work are limited or negligible.&amp;nbsp; According to the World Bank, the shock of the pandemic is expected to push 12 million people into extreme poverty in India. Some reports have suggested that poverty in India had started rising even before the COVID-19 crisis, therefore the above estimates might even be higher. With the cloud of uncertainty looming over their heads, and the loss of jobs and incomes, the poor and the illiterate do not have the option to stay unemployed or wait for a job which serves their needs. In rural areas, we still have Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee Act (MGNREGA) as a fallback employment option. But such a safety net doesn’t exist for the urban labourers, who are also faced with high costs of living. The ones rendered unemployed have taken up low income and low productivity jobs, while some have migrated back to their homes.&amp;nbsp; As was expected, with the declaration of a nationwide lockdown, there was an unprecedented large-scale reverse migration of labour wherein millions of workers travelled across the state borders amidst food shortages and uncertainty about their work prospects in the future. While the government schemes ensure the availability of rations, the distribution system failed to be effective. Penniless and stranded, workers left cities for their villages on foot or bicycles, cramped in trucks and later by trains.&amp;nbsp; This inter-state migration has thus put some of India’s biggest sectors at risk. Sectors such as manufacturing, retail and wholesale trade, mining and hospitality services are heavily dependent on migrants from other states, as analysed by India Ratings and Research. “A consequence of this is a labour crunch that might hit capacity utilisation for several firms. The manufacturing sector which employs over 6 million migrant workers from other states, highest as compared to other sectors, has started suffering. The sector contributes almost 8% of the country’s GDP. Thus the manufacturing sector might face a labour shortage in the near term if labourers do not return in the coming months. This will lead to an increase in wages in the short run and a fall in profits. Another obvious impact is on the mining sector, which has been observing a decline in the past few months.&amp;nbsp; Amidst all this, many state governments have repealed labour laws. The government of the North Indian state of Uttar Pradesh has cleared an ordinance that suspends all the labour laws for a period of three years with the exceptions of laws related to the abolishment of bonded labour, ex gratia payments to workers in case of work-related diseases and disabilities and timely wage payments. Similar actions have been taken by the state governments of Madhya Pradesh and Gujarat with a few variations. The decision has been taken to encourage new investments, setting up of new infrastructure, and for the upliftment of existing industries and factories.&amp;nbsp; What Lies Ahead? According to the latest estimates by CMIE, the unemployment rates have dropped to 6.4%, which is the lowest rate seen in a while, but this is hardly a cause for celebration. Other weekly labour metrics have only deteriorated, for example, the average labour participation rate fell down to 20.7% in the first three weeks of September as opposed to 40.96% in August. Similarly, the average employment rate during the first three weeks of August at 37.9% is substantially higher than the rates seen recently. But the slope is negative since the recovery is distinctly negative.&amp;nbsp; While the country recently declared ‘Unlock 5.0’, the economy is still far from being on a path of recovery. The economy is still worse off as compared to the conditions before the lockdown. The recent labour statistics only highlight the fear of India slipping from this ‘incomplete’ recovery unless the government comes up with a well-calculated recovery plan.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Drug Dilemma</title>
      <link href="/The-Drug-Dilemma" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Drug Dilemma" />
      <published>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Drug-Dilemma</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Drug-Dilemma">&lt;p&gt;It is no lie that the issue of decriminalisation or legalisation of drugs has always been a double-edged sword for policymakers across the world. Buoyed by the success in the West, several organisations have time and again advocated for the legalisation of drugs, particularly cannabis in India. But it is imperative to understand that drug decriminalisation or legalisation is not a public policy choice that is suited to a superficial debate. It requires analysis and research of an order that has been well absent despite the never-ending attention the issue receives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin with, drug legalisation refers to the ending of all government-enforced prohibition on the distribution, sale and personal use of specified drugs. On the other hand, drug decriminalisation calls for reduced control and penalties compared to existing laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Portuguese Decriminalisation Model&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very first country to decriminalise possession and consumption of all kinds of drugs was Portugal in 2001. Back in the 1990's, Portugal was in a tight grip of heroin addiction. Thousands of people could be seen on the streets engaging in drug use. Over 1% of the population was hooked on heroin and the country faced the highest rate of HIV infection in the entire EU. The government response to this menace was something that all of us are familiar with - harsh policies implemented by the criminal justice system and the leaders speaking against drug use. A result of this was that by the late 1990's, half of the population in the prisons was charged under drug-related offences.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in 2001, the country took a historic step in favour of decriminalisation. According to the Drug Policy Alliance, Portugal has experienced no major increases in drug use. Yet it has seen reduced rates of problematic and adolescent drug use, fewer people arrested and incarcerated for drugs, reduced incidence of HIV/AIDS, fewer drug-induced deaths, and a significant increase in the number of people receiving treatment. Since then, some form of decriminalisation has been adopted in 30 countries with significant differences and levels of effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analysing the Two Sides&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decriminalisation of drugs comes with its own set of pros and cons which are far more complex than what it is presented to the general public. The standard economic theory supports the intervention of the government in drug markets because of the negative externalities involved. However, prohibiting a good does not eliminate the market for it. The prices of the product rise and supply becomes difficult to procure leading to the creation of a black market of the product. Apparently, prohibition policies have not worked as planned, and have generally resulted in just a changed format of supply and demand.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is evident that drug use of any kind does involve negative externalities. However, the procurement of drugs in the illegal market probably generates more negative externalities than its purchase in the legal market. One of these additional externalities includes the ‘environmental’ effect of the drug trade. The environmental effect refers to the influence that the perception of neighbourhood can have on an individual's susceptibility to drug dependence. When drug offenders on release return home, they are often most concentrated in relatively few urban centres and poor neighbourhoods facing various social challenges. Statistically, most of these released individuals are often booked for some offence within the year of their release, and thus, this turns into a vicious cycle. This is because the incarcerated individuals are more prone to drug dependence as compared to the general population. With more people on the lookout for drugs in the illegal market, the income-generating crime that may result from the markets’ high prices and the violence associated increases as the disputes cannot be solved through legal procedures. Criminalisation inhibits the quality control of the drugs supplied leading to more accidental and overdose deaths along with a significant increase in health risks. Prohibition, therefore, has not only reduced the size of the drug market but has also led to greater negative externalities: the balance between these two effects is what any country desires!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advocates of drug decriminalisation have pointed out various expected benefits such as reduced number of arrests, increased uptake into drug treatment, reduced criminal justice costs and allocation of funds from criminal justice to health systems and minimised social exclusion of people who use drugs. This helps create a climate in which these drug users are less fearful of seeking and accessing treatment, utilising harm reduction services and receiving HIV/AIDS services - a step towards protecting people from the wide-ranging and crippling consequences of a criminal conviction. However, it is also a fact that much of the above-stated benefits are not supported by substantial evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also crucial to analyse the counter-arguments to the decriminalisation of drugs. One of the major concerns is that decriminalisation may encourage experimentation. Individuals may have genetic vulnerability towards drug use making them more susceptible to addiction and accompanied health risks. Allowing these individuals to have open access and possession of drugs seems like an open-door policy leading to adverse effects. Although many argue that decriminalisation would have no impact on drug prices, free-market economics has a different approach. In the absence of a legal barrier in effect to prevent drug access, it implies a greater supply of drugs which might lead to a fall in its prices. If some people abstain from experimenting with drugs due to price barriers, this move would make them more susceptible to experimentation. In the above list of pros, it was pointed out that decriminalisation would lead to reduced costs of incarceration and treatment. However, the current infrastructure is not well-suited to support the added number of individuals who would seek out help. This implies that added costs would come in the form of building assets to handle the needs of society. And if the implementation goes awry, the resulting costs could be even higher. Thus, given the positives and the negatives, the move toward decriminalisation or legalisation of drugs has to be in accordance with the social and economic infrastructure of a country. The move will unanimously lead to a huge cultural change and added impact on healthcare, law and order, and other components of society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is India Ready for the Move?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India is currently grappling with a growing drug problem, especially in the states of Punjab and Manipur. As per the United Nations World Drug Report, 2019, drug use in India went up by almost 30%. The drug laws, thus, seem to not have been much of a success when it comes to the menace of drug possession and consumption. Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances (NDPS) Act, 1985 was passed to curb the problem of drug abuse and was further amended in 1989, 2001 and then in 2014. The Act provides the provisions for search, forfeiture and capture of those who indulge in drug activities from any place in India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With an increasing number of countries undergoing decriminalisation in some form or the other, the demand for it in India has been getting stronger. Sikkim in 2018 became the first state to no longer prosecute drug users and somewhat treat them as patients rather than criminals in order to encourage treatment options and rehabilitation. But, decriminalisation might not be the best way to handle the situation in India. This is in light of the already vulnerable health care system and the various loopholes existing in law and order. India is struggling to control the use of three addictive substances - tobacco, alcohol and areca nut. As per the Global Adult Tobacco Survey by the World Health Organisation (2016-17), 270 million Indians use tobacco and it kills around 1.35 million Indians every year. Nearly 30% of India’s adult population is using alcohol, leading to 3.3 million deaths. Legalising drugs in the wake of this situation might only worsen the above-mentioned alarming statistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2019, a petition was also filed by the Great Legalisation Movement India Trust seeking decriminalisation of cannabis. Cannabis has been known to possess several medicinal properties and can be used as a cure for various diseases. However, people against this have pointed out that legalising cannabis may lead to its surge as a gateway drug, with research supporting that 45% people who consumed cannabis went on to try other illicit drugs as well. India is home to the maximum people in the youth category and a significant portion of the population is still immersed in poverty lacking access to basic necessities. The employment rate in India is struggling. People in various parts of the country are still not literate. With a large section of the population being highly vulnerable, increasing the access of drugs might prove to be fatal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, it is important to understand that a move meant to be beneficial for society may end up making the same society fall apart if not tackled with care and if implemented in haste. It is truly a fear of the unknown that plagues this debate. No country has the ability at present to predict how the entire society would react if drugs were decriminalised or legalised. It is a risk that a country must take only after the existing infrastructure has been upgraded to support its implementation. How these countries take on the decriminalisation of drugs is yet to be seen. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rajsi Sah</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is no lie that the issue of decriminalisation or legalisation of drugs has always been a double-edged sword for policymakers across the world. Buoyed by the success in the West, several organisations have time and again advocated for the legalisation of drugs, particularly cannabis in India. But it is imperative to understand that drug decriminalisation or legalisation is not a public policy choice that is suited to a superficial debate. It requires analysis and research of an order that has been well absent despite the never-ending attention the issue receives. To begin with, drug legalisation refers to the ending of all government-enforced prohibition on the distribution, sale and personal use of specified drugs. On the other hand, drug decriminalisation calls for reduced control and penalties compared to existing laws. The Portuguese Decriminalisation Model The very first country to decriminalise possession and consumption of all kinds of drugs was Portugal in 2001. Back in the 1990's, Portugal was in a tight grip of heroin addiction. Thousands of people could be seen on the streets engaging in drug use. Over 1% of the population was hooked on heroin and the country faced the highest rate of HIV infection in the entire EU. The government response to this menace was something that all of us are familiar with - harsh policies implemented by the criminal justice system and the leaders speaking against drug use. A result of this was that by the late 1990's, half of the population in the prisons was charged under drug-related offences.&amp;nbsp; But in 2001, the country took a historic step in favour of decriminalisation. According to the Drug Policy Alliance, Portugal has experienced no major increases in drug use. Yet it has seen reduced rates of problematic and adolescent drug use, fewer people arrested and incarcerated for drugs, reduced incidence of HIV/AIDS, fewer drug-induced deaths, and a significant increase in the number of people receiving treatment. Since then, some form of decriminalisation has been adopted in 30 countries with significant differences and levels of effectiveness. Analysing the Two Sides Decriminalisation of drugs comes with its own set of pros and cons which are far more complex than what it is presented to the general public. The standard economic theory supports the intervention of the government in drug markets because of the negative externalities involved. However, prohibiting a good does not eliminate the market for it. The prices of the product rise and supply becomes difficult to procure leading to the creation of a black market of the product. Apparently, prohibition policies have not worked as planned, and have generally resulted in just a changed format of supply and demand.&amp;nbsp; It is evident that drug use of any kind does involve negative externalities. However, the procurement of drugs in the illegal market probably generates more negative externalities than its purchase in the legal market. One of these additional externalities includes the ‘environmental’ effect of the drug trade. The environmental effect refers to the influence that the perception of neighbourhood can have on an individual's susceptibility to drug dependence. When drug offenders on release return home, they are often most concentrated in relatively few urban centres and poor neighbourhoods facing various social challenges. Statistically, most of these released individuals are often booked for some offence within the year of their release, and thus, this turns into a vicious cycle. This is because the incarcerated individuals are more prone to drug dependence as compared to the general population. With more people on the lookout for drugs in the illegal market, the income-generating crime that may result from the markets’ high prices and the violence associated increases as the disputes cannot be solved through legal procedures. Criminalisation inhibits the quality control of the drugs supplied leading to more accidental and overdose deaths along with a significant increase in health risks. Prohibition, therefore, has not only reduced the size of the drug market but has also led to greater negative externalities: the balance between these two effects is what any country desires! The advocates of drug decriminalisation have pointed out various expected benefits such as reduced number of arrests, increased uptake into drug treatment, reduced criminal justice costs and allocation of funds from criminal justice to health systems and minimised social exclusion of people who use drugs. This helps create a climate in which these drug users are less fearful of seeking and accessing treatment, utilising harm reduction services and receiving HIV/AIDS services - a step towards protecting people from the wide-ranging and crippling consequences of a criminal conviction. However, it is also a fact that much of the above-stated benefits are not supported by substantial evidence. It is also crucial to analyse the counter-arguments to the decriminalisation of drugs. One of the major concerns is that decriminalisation may encourage experimentation. Individuals may have genetic vulnerability towards drug use making them more susceptible to addiction and accompanied health risks. Allowing these individuals to have open access and possession of drugs seems like an open-door policy leading to adverse effects. Although many argue that decriminalisation would have no impact on drug prices, free-market economics has a different approach. In the absence of a legal barrier in effect to prevent drug access, it implies a greater supply of drugs which might lead to a fall in its prices. If some people abstain from experimenting with drugs due to price barriers, this move would make them more susceptible to experimentation. In the above list of pros, it was pointed out that decriminalisation would lead to reduced costs of incarceration and treatment. However, the current infrastructure is not well-suited to support the added number of individuals who would seek out help. This implies that added costs would come in the form of building assets to handle the needs of society. And if the implementation goes awry, the resulting costs could be even higher. Thus, given the positives and the negatives, the move toward decriminalisation or legalisation of drugs has to be in accordance with the social and economic infrastructure of a country. The move will unanimously lead to a huge cultural change and added impact on healthcare, law and order, and other components of society. Is India Ready for the Move? India is currently grappling with a growing drug problem, especially in the states of Punjab and Manipur. As per the United Nations World Drug Report, 2019, drug use in India went up by almost 30%. The drug laws, thus, seem to not have been much of a success when it comes to the menace of drug possession and consumption. Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances (NDPS) Act, 1985 was passed to curb the problem of drug abuse and was further amended in 1989, 2001 and then in 2014. The Act provides the provisions for search, forfeiture and capture of those who indulge in drug activities from any place in India. With an increasing number of countries undergoing decriminalisation in some form or the other, the demand for it in India has been getting stronger. Sikkim in 2018 became the first state to no longer prosecute drug users and somewhat treat them as patients rather than criminals in order to encourage treatment options and rehabilitation. But, decriminalisation might not be the best way to handle the situation in India. This is in light of the already vulnerable health care system and the various loopholes existing in law and order. India is struggling to control the use of three addictive substances - tobacco, alcohol and areca nut. As per the Global Adult Tobacco Survey by the World Health Organisation (2016-17), 270 million Indians use tobacco and it kills around 1.35 million Indians every year. Nearly 30% of India’s adult population is using alcohol, leading to 3.3 million deaths. Legalising drugs in the wake of this situation might only worsen the above-mentioned alarming statistics. In 2019, a petition was also filed by the Great Legalisation Movement India Trust seeking decriminalisation of cannabis. Cannabis has been known to possess several medicinal properties and can be used as a cure for various diseases. However, people against this have pointed out that legalising cannabis may lead to its surge as a gateway drug, with research supporting that 45% people who consumed cannabis went on to try other illicit drugs as well. India is home to the maximum people in the youth category and a significant portion of the population is still immersed in poverty lacking access to basic necessities. The employment rate in India is struggling. People in various parts of the country are still not literate. With a large section of the population being highly vulnerable, increasing the access of drugs might prove to be fatal.&amp;nbsp; In the end, it is important to understand that a move meant to be beneficial for society may end up making the same society fall apart if not tackled with care and if implemented in haste. It is truly a fear of the unknown that plagues this debate. No country has the ability at present to predict how the entire society would react if drugs were decriminalised or legalised. It is a risk that a country must take only after the existing infrastructure has been upgraded to support its implementation. How these countries take on the decriminalisation of drugs is yet to be seen.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Racism is Profitable</title>
      <link href="/Racism-is-Profitable" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Racism is Profitable" />
      <published>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Racism-is-Profitable</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Racism-is-Profitable">&lt;p&gt;This is simply not the time to be talking about how Nelson Mandela fought ‘apartheid’ in South Africa or how Rosa Parks refused to give up her bus seat to a white man, because that world was decades ago, fraught with exploitation, incarceration, brutalities, exclusion, all on the basis of a simple difference – skin colour. One may wonder that due to the efforts of these icons, the world, sixty years down the line, will be different, wherein all races are treated equally. Fast forward to 2020, does the phrase &lt;em&gt;“I can’t breathe”&lt;/em&gt; ring any bells? If it does, congratulations, you’re not living under a rock. George Floyd, an ordinary American man, was pinned down on the road, with a knee pressing on his throat, by a police officer for allegedly using a $20 counterfeit bill, “allegedly” being the keyword here. George Floyd was killed and the accused officer got so much so as a suspension. Why? Racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst the pandemic, the historic Black Lives Matter (BLM) movement took place and &lt;em&gt;#JusticeForGeorgeFloyd&lt;/em&gt; was trending all across the globe. Not just the black community, but people from all races came out in support of the cause and identified themselves as allies of the movement. Not only individuals and communities but even corporations, small and big, spoke on the cause and corporate executives expressed their contempt towards police brutality, establishing their coherence with the black community. So does this mean white supremacy has ended and finally there is socio-political and economic liberation for the black community? I think not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When multinational corporations like Amazon, Walmart, and Wall Street banks like CitiBank and JPMorgan Chase put out posters in support of the movement, the face value of it painted an empathetic picture. However, the harsh reality is that it was just a mere public relations stunt for them. Far from being the solution to systemic racism in America, these multi-billion dollar corporations have been actively perpetuating it. It is fair to say that corporate hypocrisy exists when on the one hand these banks, like JPMorgan Chase, claim to be inclusive by employing a few black employees and by giving press interviews where they urge everyone to be more inclusive in their respective workplaces and neighbourhoods, while on the other hand, they discriminate against their black customers by making them incur heavier costs for mortgage borrowing, and not addressing this form of discrimination despite recognising and identifying it. Not only customers but the figures show how JPMorgan Chase discriminates against its own employees by excluding black people from holding positions in the top tier of management. Barely about 4% of the bank’s top executives are black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason behind this is that corporations profit off of racism. The historic oppression and suppression, for example - removing native people from their land through theft and genocide, enslaving African people for work and reproductive labour, and so on- are proofs of the fact that ‘racial capitalism’ has existed for ages and continues to exist in the status quo wherein wealthy elites are motivated to keep suppressing the economic vitality of people of colour. This initiates a vicious cycle of an ‘oppression economy’ wherein this economic suppression leads on to prevent these communities from having any form of social capital and hence, hinders their political power and their ability to bring about any form of a political change in the society. In the 21st century, racism is not just limited to the difference in skin colour, but extends to acting as a means to an end; the means being the black community and the end being the flourishing of these multinational corporations. Economist Darrick Hamilton explains that the pursuit of profit, not hatred of black people, is the real root of discrimination,  &lt;em&gt;“Racism is a tool, a mechanism. In many settings, it’s purposeful. Sure, bias can become implicit or unconscious through socialization. But that is a secondary effect from the initial tool that was used”&lt;/em&gt;  said Hamilton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also an extreme economic inequality among whites and blacks in the United States. This again stems from the fact that ‘racial capitalism’ or ‘oppression economy’ inherently functions by uplifting one community meanwhile pushing down the other. In such scenarios, when a community is discriminated against, there comes a paradigm of ostracisation wherein one community is never allowed to have equal rights, which leads to them being either unemployed or underpaid. Even governments, in the past, haven’t been able to tackle the effects of racism on the economy, and this was proved right when former US President Ronald Reagan asked black citizens to trust the marketplace in case they have distrust towards the government. And it is no secret how that panned out, considering the marketplace was discriminatory in its very essence, due to the existence of racial resentment and white supremacy. Even when some progressives wanted to bring about economic equality and infrastructural development, it meant that all races have to side with the government, and since racism creates divisions and distrust among citizens, siding with one government was not an option. Therefore, the progressives deemed it best to leave the reign of bridging economic inequality with the rich multinational corporations. And hence, the vicious cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From economic inequality stems wealth inequality, which means inequality in the amount of money one could save from their incomes. This form of wealth could also be in terms of bonds or real estate properties. Since the black community has been historically oppressed, their chance at inheriting any prior wealth is negligible, but moreover, they face uncountable barriers to creating any form of wealth in the current scenario. These barriers are again due to the systemic discrimination faced by the community. This lack of wealth and savings has shown its effects during the COVID-19 pandemic for the black community since they are the ones that face the brunt of environmental injustice, implications of poverty, and systemic racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People from the black community are also highly criminalised and penalised, at least three times more than their white counterparts. This also means profit for the corporations since a higher number of criminals means a higher number of prisons, which are in fact constructed and funded for by these corporations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, the ‘oppression economy’ is not the need of the hour, but the ‘liberation economy’ is. And our only way to be able to get a ‘liberation economy’ is by firstly, supporting and electing candidates that will actively tackle issues of racism and better the economic policies for people of colour. Secondly, the unnecessary criminalisation of people from the black community has to end and the government has to tackle the root cause of the occurrence of such activities which may, in fact, stem from the socio-political or economic needs of these people. And lastly, the universal guarantee to have access to basic economic rights, healthcare and education should be made. Race is an inherent part of people’s identities and to deserve basic human decency, one should not be made to feel that they need to part with their identities. All communities together choose their governments and to simply leave the reign of controlling and dictating our lives in the hands of profit-driven corporations is a breach of democracy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This is simply not the time to be talking about how Nelson Mandela fought ‘apartheid’ in South Africa or how Rosa Parks refused to give up her bus seat to a white man, because that world was decades ago, fraught with exploitation, incarceration, brutalities, exclusion, all on the basis of a simple difference – skin colour. One may wonder that due to the efforts of these icons, the world, sixty years down the line, will be different, wherein all races are treated equally. Fast forward to 2020, does the phrase “I can’t breathe” ring any bells? If it does, congratulations, you’re not living under a rock. George Floyd, an ordinary American man, was pinned down on the road, with a knee pressing on his throat, by a police officer for allegedly using a $20 counterfeit bill, “allegedly” being the keyword here. George Floyd was killed and the accused officer got so much so as a suspension. Why? Racism.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
