<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/economics/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-07-16T15:31:16+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/economics/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Large Fiscal Deficits and No Defaults: Is it Possible?</title>
      <link href="/Large-Fiscal-Deficits" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Large Fiscal Deficits and No Defaults: Is it Possible?" />
      <published>2020-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Large-Fiscal-Deficits</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Large-Fiscal-Deficits">&lt;p&gt;Modern Monetary Theory (MMT) is an unconventional economic theory that has been gaining traction recently. Though the theory has been in development for many years now, the coronavirus pandemic sparked a debate about the usefulness of the theory in the real world. So, this might be the right time to know what the theory is about and what are the implications of it. For better understanding, let us try to contrast this with conventional economic theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Taxes and Inflation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MMT states that countries with a higher degree of monetary sovereignty can run large fiscal deficits without worrying about defaulting on the debt. A country is said to have monetary sovereignty if it prints its own currency, issues debt in its currency, and does not promise to convert it into, say, any other currency or gold. The theory asserts that governments are not dependent on taxes or borrowings to finance their expenditure. According to MMT, taxes are instruments through which governments create demand for their currency. This makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if the Indian government were to declare that taxes are to be paid in the form of rice crops from tomorrow, all the transactions would shift to being carried in rice crops and it would become the medium of exchange. Therefore, by ordaining the acceptable medium to settle one’s debt obligation, a country is essentially creating demand for that medium (dollars, rupees, etc.). The power to levy taxes and to issue currency makes the government a ‘money monopolist’. This is in contrast to mainstream economics which says that the government needs to borrow or increase taxes to bridge the government deficit. According to MMT, the only constraint on government expenditure is inflation and the availability of real resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MMT also says that as long as there is no (excess) inflation, the government can spend money to achieve full employment in the economy. It further supports the idea of a tax to control inflation: increase taxes to rein in inflation and decreases in taxes to boost aggregate demand. However, for tax cuts to work well, they should benefit people whose marginal propensity to spend is high. MMT rejects the idea of Non-Accelerating Inflation Rate of Unemployment (NAIRU), which is the level of unemployment below which inflation begins to increase. It is a theoretical concept which cannot be observed or calculated, and one can only find it when a further rise in employment (or fall in unemployment) raises inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What all the central banks across the world do today is that they set an inflation target and alter the interest rate to reach the target, withstanding any amount of unemployment in the process. Dr Stephanie Kelton, a proponent of MMT, observed in her book &lt;em&gt;The Deficit Myth&lt;/em&gt; that, &lt;em&gt;“to put it crudely, the [central banks] use unemployed human beings as [their] primary weapon against inflation.”&lt;/em&gt; Instead, MMT prescribes a universal job guarantee to combat unemployment. It believes that such a job guarantee will act as an automatic stabiliser that will promote both full employment and price stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interest Rates&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conventional economic theory states that huge government debts will lead to an increase in the interest rates in the long run, which is harmful to the economy. This idea, however, is rejected by MMT. According to MMT, since the central banks have control over the short-term interest rate and also significant influence over the long-term interest rates, large debts will not increase interest rates. Apart from this, MMT also notes that markets can always be stripped off of any influence over the interest rates. Japan is a case in point. With a debt-to-GDP ratio of 238%, highest in the world, the interest rates are near-zero. This is because, along with influencing the short-term interest rates, the bank of Japan (BoJ) had committed to maintaining the interest rates on ten-year government bonds near zero (which is done by buying government bonds on large quantities, i.e. buying government debt). Note how both long-term and short-term interest rates are influenced by the central bank of Japan. By doing this, the central banks anywhere in the world can prevent interest rates from rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One could question whether this would not lead to inflation. (The answer is, no) Eric Lonergan, an economist and a hedge fund manager has an answer to this question. It goes like this. When BoJ buys the Japan government bonds and pays out cash, the investors, instead of government bonds, will now hold the same value (of that of bonds) in cash. While there is no effect on wealth, there is a loss of interest income. So essentially, paying off government debt will lead to a fall in interest income in the private sector. MMT further argues that there is no need for a government to buy bonds to finance its debt and it is only a choice the government makes. This is because the government can spend by crediting the appropriate bank account (through the central bank), without issuing any bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crowding Out Effect&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conventional thinking is that the government will compete with the private sector from a limited pool of savings to fund its deficits. When the fiscal deficit increases, the government will have to borrow more; which will leave lesser funds available for the private sector, leading to the crowding out effect. This idea is also contested by MMT. According to MMT, government spending is self-financing. Government running deficits, in the first place, will put the money the private sector uses to buy bonds. Let’s understand this using some equations given by an important MMT figure, Wynne Godley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Y= National Income; C= Consumption; I=Investment; G= Government expenditure; X-M= net exports; S= savings; T= taxes)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y = C + I + G + X - M — (1)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y = C + S + T — (2)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From (1) and (2)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;S + T = I + G + X - M&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reordering,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(S - I) = (G-T) + (X-M)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If (X-M) &amp;lt;= 0, there is no current account surplus,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For (S-I) to be positive, (G-T) must be positive. Therefore, government deficit means private surplus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, when the government issues bonds to bridge its fiscal deficit, the deficit itself is supplying the money necessary to purchase the bonds. For this very reason, MMT states that there will be no crowding out. It is also apparent from the above equations that government deficits will always lead to a fiscal surplus (surplus in financial assets) in the non-government sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indian Context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us now look at MMT from an Indian vantage point. Though India doesn’t have the monetary sovereignty as high as the US, UK or Japan etc., Indian government borrows in Indian rupees only. That leaves scope for implementation of MMT prescriptions. In fact, one study shows that despite &lt;a href=&quot;https://macromyths.blogspot.com/2018/02/mmt-at-work-case-of-india.html&quot;&gt;high fiscal deficits&lt;/a&gt; there has been ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncaer.org/free-download.php?pID=290&quot;&gt;crowding in’ effect&lt;/a&gt; rather than crowding out effect in India in the period 1980-2015. This is clearly in agreement with the MMT theory. The high fiscal deficits that India ran could very well be the reason for the faster growth that India achieved since the 1991 reforms. Also, India already has in place the job guarantee scheme advocated by MMT economists, MNREGA, although not universally. But there are some problems in India as far as MMT recommendations are concerned. First, the number of taxpayers in India is marginal. Second, the underground economy is prevalent in India. These two factors might not be very effective when it comes to using taxes to create space for fiscal expansion. However, there is also one &lt;a href=&quot;https://macromyths.blogspot.com/2018/02/mmt-at-work-case-of-india.html&quot;&gt;argument&lt;/a&gt; that India is already using MMT solutions unwittingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MMT essentially argues for a greater role of fiscal policy and subsidiary role of monetary policy. Prescriptions like a universal job guarantee, using taxes to cut inflation, etc. are cases in point. According to MMT economists, taxes (or borrowing) pay for nothing. However, taxes are important for other purposes like controlling inflation to create space for fiscal expansion, redistribution of wealth, ensuring not too much political power is concentrated in a few hands, and so on. For them, the universal job guarantee is an automatic stabiliser which will provide employment to all those who are unemployed by the private sector, and mitigate the pains for those who are fired from employment. The final result is that MMT wants everyone to focus on economic balance, full employment, and price stability. All that MMT asks from you is to concentrate on the economic outcomes rather than budget outcomes and economic balance rather than balanced budgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For more on MMT, you can read the following books:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1.  The Deficit Myth – Stephanie Kelton&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2.  The Case for a Job Guarantee - Pavlina R. Tcherneva&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3.  Soft Currency Economics II: The Origin of Modern Monetary Theory – Warren Mosler&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;4.  Modern Money Theory: A Primer on Macroeconomics for Sovereign Monetary Systems - L. Randall Wray&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Modern Monetary Theory (MMT) is an unconventional economic theory that has been gaining traction recently. Though the theory has been in development for many years now, the coronavirus pandemic sparked a debate about the usefulness of the theory in the real world. So, this might be the right time to know what the theory is about and what are the implications of it. For better understanding, let us try to contrast this with conventional economic theory.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Coughing Losses: Indian States Subject to Austerity</title>
      <link href="/Coughing-Losses" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coughing Losses: Indian States Subject to Austerity" />
      <published>2020-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Coughing-Losses</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Coughing-Losses">&lt;p&gt;As the number of COVID-19 cases continue to burgeon around the globe, most countries are experiencing an unprecedented slowdown with a shrinkage in economic activities. The already prevailing global slowdown in the pre-corona months has fused with the present-day scenario, resulting in an economic jolt. The ‘Great Lockdown’ as the IMF calls it, will give birth to economies with lowered interest rates and public debts reaching record levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India stands as the third worst-hit country globally with a tally nearing 700,000 cases. Looking deeper into the domestic circumstances, it is an unfortunate coincidence that the five gravely affected Indian states: Maharashtra, Tamil Nadu, Delhi, Gujarat and Uttar Pradesh, constitute 42% of India’s GDP. It is estimated that these five will make-up 48% of the total losses all the states will incur in 2020-21. Dried-up cash inflows have disconcerted both the Union and State Governments, however, as the actual battle is being fought by the State Governments and they are incurring the associated expenditure, the hardship is greater for them. With grave fiscal constraints, dealing with the loss of livelihoods has become a matter of concern for most states just as saving lives has. Cash handouts and provisions for subsidised food/ration have been put in place by states as humanitarian expenditure, not to ease the crisis. The return of migrant workers has exacerbated the problem with the disbursement on transport, quarantine facilities and rehabilitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite ironically, the ₹20.9 trillion stimulus package, which has been claimed to be 10% of the national GDP by the Union Government, is, in fact, an exiguous 0.8% of the GDP, as authenticated by a DSB Bank report and several other experts. This is one reason why the States have been demanding resources from the Union Government. The prime reason still lies in the fact that all the influential contributors (states) generated 60-70% of revenue from their own sources. These states gave us 75% of the GDP generated and hence, were the driving engines of the national economy—and therefore need and deserve more financial packages. Moreover, due to the already existing economic crunch that had affected the nation even before COVID-19, State Governments have been experiencing serious revenue impediments through the second half of 2019-20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Value Added Tax (VAT) on petroleum and excise duty on alcohol are the two predominant sources of revenue for states. Alcohol fosters the generation of ₹150 billion for states, on average, every month, along with ₹2 trillion brought in by petroleum products. The lockdown witnessed a plunge in the demand for petroleum and a collapse in the sale of alcohol, drying up the states’ revenues. The states generating a major portion of finances through their own resources are worst affected owing to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even as the lockdown begins to ease out, relief is a far away dream for the states, liquor vendors are expecting a 25% fall in sales this year and bars have barely witnessed any footfall. Even though Delhi increased the excise duty on liquor, the gains weren’t fruitful enough to make good the deficit. Although oil prices in the international market stand truncated, the Union Government has continued to keep the prices high along with an escalation in the central excise duty to make good its deficit, so even if states increase VAT on petroleum, they are left with a very cramped taxing area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Goods and Services Tax (GST), which is collected by the Centre and then shared with the states comprises 43-44% of the revenue. Ever since its implementation, states have complained of revenue losses. One principal reason for this is the delayed and uneven release of the GST compensation. Compensation for December 2019 to February 2020 was released only in June, this led to much hue and cry as the states were starved of revenue during the lockdown. The Union Government’s assurance of a 14% annual growth for the next five years in the states’ GST revenue concoct mere dreams as the target is highly unachievable as they are likely to grow at a much lower rate. The only escape is borrowing, either the Centre borrows to issue grants to the states or the GST Council will have to borrow in order to keep pace with the share of compensation due to the states during these times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the crisis in hand, the Indian states have limited recourse. They can either cut down on their budgeted expenditure or increase tax buoyancy or increase their borrowings. Expenditure taps in the form of salaries, pensions, allowances, interests, etc. have already been turned off by many states as a cut in salaries, freezing of allowances and increments have been ordered by the State Governments. This compression of public expenditure is unlikely to provide the desired results. Borrowing from the market looks like candy to the eye and shall curb the issue of revenue in the short run, but states can’t afford to ignore the hindrances in borrowing, such as an expansion of the fiscal deficit in the long run. The second reason looks more political in nature, the Centre has inflicted four conditions on states – universalisation of ration cards, improvement in ease of doing business, reforms to make state-owned power distribution companies more profitable, and shoring up urban local body revenues. On the one hand, these conditions restrict the borrowing tendency of the states and on the other hand, the Centre has conveniently brimmed-up their coffer from ₹4.2 trillion to ₹12 trillion by inflating borrowings by 54% over the estimated budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nation joins hands to fight the contagious virus but it seems that there is a grave disagreement between the States and the Centre when it comes to revenue generation, allotment and financial grants. The Centre curtails the income opportunities of the States through numerous constraints, yet expects States to fight the crisis on their own. The States look for grants in order to release the salaries of their employees and expects the Centre to reveal a package of at least 4-5% of the GDP. Many economists believe that an addition to the 15th Indian Finance Commission report, which allocates financial resources between the Centre and the states, in the form of a COVID-19 grant to states shall be a helping hand. A collaborative effort towards a common strategy aimed at rooting out the pandemic to ‘mask the losses being coughed by the states’ is the actual need of the hour.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As the number of COVID-19 cases continue to burgeon around the globe, most countries are experiencing an unprecedented slowdown with a shrinkage in economic activities. The already prevailing global slowdown in the pre-corona months has fused with the present-day scenario, resulting in an economic jolt. The ‘Great Lockdown’ as the IMF calls it, will give birth to economies with lowered interest rates and public debts reaching record levels.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Britain’s ‘New Deal’?</title>
      <link href="/Britain-New-Deal" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Britain’s ‘New Deal’?" />
      <published>2020-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Britain-New-Deal</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Britain-New-Deal">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Build, build, build”&lt;/em&gt; was the mantra set out by the British Prime Minister Boris Johnson last week in the town of Dudley. Infrastructure spending will be the way out of the current malaise. On the surface, his plan sounds bold. Using billions of pounds of public money to improve railways and hospitals sounds more like a traditional Labour pledge than a Tory one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The intent is noble. Anyone journeying around this green and pleasant land can’t fail to realise that our towns are in need of more than just a lick of paint. But saying that infrastructure spending alone will return us to growth takes a stretch even the PM isn’t capable of. His plan to build the economy out of the crisis is reminiscent of a seven-year old’s understanding of how an economy works. &lt;em&gt;“Build more! Make more!”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with the PM’s plan is that it is a clear attempt to keep unemployment as low as possible, whatever the cost. Employing people to build bridges and fill potholes is a good public service, but it won’t grow the economy. In bad times, what an economy needs is not jobs. It needs increased productivity and savings derived from those jobs. With the best will in the world, paying six people a pittance to repaint a double-yellow in Ipswich, for the sake of keeping down unemployment, won’t do this. In the Soviet Union, everyone had a job, but nobody was producing anything valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boris Johnson has been desperate to compare his own plan to Roosevelt’s fabled ‘New Deal’, which promised to save America from the Great Depression by laying down new highways and putting up countless public works. But Roosevelt found out the productive limits of infrastructure spending the hard way. Across the 1930’s, US industrial production and national income fell by around a third, and the public works programmes failed to put a dent in unemployment numbers, which stayed above 15% until 1940. It was supplying the Allies in Europe with domestically produced weaponry, as well as America’s Pacific war with Japan, which eventually rescued the US from the worst manufacturing slump in its history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all our countries, we will spend the next two or three years discussing how to recover from the fallout of the COVID-19 pandemic. I will wager now that few of the plans put forth by the political establishment at that time will address the most important question of this episode. And it’s this: &lt;em&gt;why did the governments of the developed nations have to intervene in their economies in such an extreme way?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is that most of the state intervention carried out in Europe and America since March would not have been necessary if our households and our businesses had savings to fall back on. But they don’t. Before the pandemic, British household debt was almost £1.3 trillion, 30% of Americans had less than $1,000 in savings, and corporate debt in both countries was at record highs. No economy in such a shape can withstand a shock like a lockdown. Or any shock, in fact - if it hadn’t been the coronavirus, something else would have had the same effect: a cyber hack, an energy meltdown, financial collapse or a nuclear exchange in Korea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why it is so futile to suggest solutions as oversimplified as the one which the PM cooked up this week. Britain doesn’t need more low-paid jobs, or more welfare, it needs more assets. It needs to produce more and sell more. And most of all, people in the country have to save what they earn. That way, missing a paycheck is irritating, but it’s not a calamity. Any state solution, from left or right, which doesn’t acknowledge this glaring blind spot is a non-starter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I hear there are plenty of construction jobs in Bristol putting up new statues. I expect I’ll have company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Thomas Leeman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thomas Leeman is a Politics and Spanish graduate of the University of Bristol with a keen interest in European and US politics. His pearls of good humour don’t merely fall from trees.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>.</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Build, build, build” was the mantra set out by the British Prime Minister Boris Johnson last week in the town of Dudley. Infrastructure spending will be the way out of the current malaise. On the surface, his plan sounds bold. Using billions of pounds of public money to improve railways and hospitals sounds more like a traditional Labour pledge than a Tory one.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Are Britain’s Regulators Too Good to Fail?</title>
      <link href="/Too-Good-to-Fail" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are Britain's Regulators Too Good to Fail?" />
      <published>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Too-Good-to-Fail</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Too-Good-to-Fail">&lt;p&gt;Not long ago, the Bank of England cancelled the annual stress tests of different UK banks this year due to the COVID-19 pandemic. The Prudential Regulatory Authority (PRA), Britain’s prudential regulator for all systemically important financial firms, signalled its willingness to reevaluate the timetable for the new Basel norms on international banking regulation. These relaxations in regulatory scrutiny and planning were based on the health check of UK banks conducted last year, which, according to the Bank of England, “showed that the UK banking system was resilient to deep simultaneous recessions in the UK and global economies that are more severe overall than the global financial crisis, combined with large falls in asset prices and a separate stress of misconduct costs”. Despite the use of dry language, the sheer optimism of this outlook is undeniable, which obviously begs the question of its veracity. More specifically, it is worthwhile to ask: are the UK’s regulatory policies really that good? Can the Bank of England really have that much faith in the stewardship of the financial regulators?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good starting point for exploring the issues that are thematic and recurrent in the UK’s broader regulatory ideology is its handling of competition and innovation. The Financial Conduct Authority (FCA), Britain’s financial services consumer champion, has been explicitly mandated by the Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 (FSMA 2000) to promote competition and to ensure the removal of market barriers and encourage innovation in pursuance of the same. The PRA also has the competition objective as its secondary objective. The FCA and PRA have worked together to set-up the New Bank Start-up Unit and the FCA has set-up the Regulatory Sandbox for fintech firms. Prima facie, these measures seem to be very successful. Under cohort 5 of the Regulatory Sandbox, 29 businesses have gained entry with 99 applications— the highest so far. The rise of the new banks has been impressive as well: 1 in every 4 millennials is the customer of a challenger bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it would be glib to argue that the rise of fintech and challenger banks represents a true policy success. For instance, the Regulatory Sandbox, rather than being a hub of clinical trials for new financial products, is becoming a way for firms to gain funding and legitimacy before their product is deemed safe. As &lt;a href=&quot;http://ftalphaville.ft.com/2018/12/05/1543986004000/A--fintech-sandbox--might-sound-like-a-harmless-idea--It-s-not/&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Financial Times&lt;/em&gt;, in the 2018 cohort, around 40% of the Sandbox entrants gained funding just after entry. Moreover, around half of the start-ups that did gain entry had something to do with crypto-currency— a dangerous financial product, to say the least. This should be the cause for grave concern as it exposes that promoting innovation for the sake of innovation creates critical risks for a financial system, after all, payment protection insurance and subprime mortgages were the results of cutting edge innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A deeper analysis of the regulators’ policies on challenger banks exposes the tensions inherent in trying to keep a system both safe and competitive. While challenger banks have grown, they have not really posed a threat to traditional lenders. In 2000, the top six firms had 80% personal current accounts, by 2017 that figure rose to 87%. The reason for this is the high regulatory burden on challenger banks, such as the higher ‘minimum requirement for own funds and eligible liabilities’ or MREL put forth by the Bank of England under the Banking Act 2009. The MREL, as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bba.org.uk/news/bba-voice/mrel-the-home-straight/#.XvuI08ZX40M&quot;&gt;explained&lt;/a&gt; by Mark Russell of the British Bankers Association, is necessary to prevent government bail-outs, but it requires smaller banks on an average to have an MREL that is 22% of their risk-weighted liabilities, which is too heavy a burden. So, while the New Bank Start-up Unit is not itself a failure, there is a lack of policies accompanying it that would achieve greater stability through optimal competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another key set of measures that dominates the current regulatory landscape is the change from a ‘light touch’ and ‘tick box’ approach to a more ‘judgment-based’ and ‘outcomes-based’ style of regulation. This kind of regulation ensures that instead of mechanically following certain procedures or protocols that are merely presumed to ensure the safety of the financial system and consumer protection, firms actively engage in adopting strategies and policies which actually achieve the outcomes of better consumer protection and greater systemic stability. This regulatory approach is based on the notion that a one-size-fits-all kind of regulation is ill-suited to the financial and banking sector and that, practically speaking, firms have to be trusted to regulate themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implications of this approach, which incorporates influences from behavioural economics, is that there is a greater emphasis on banking culture and individual responsibility. In addition, there is an understanding that firms are free to develop their own innovative methods on how to reach certain outcomes. While all of this represents a significant and welcome departure from the pre-2008 approach, problems do exist. Two issues are worth highlighting. First, there is the issue of technology. Regulators lack the technical know-how that firms have and they may find it difficult to assess whether a product is safe. They could be &lt;a href=&quot;https://minnesotalawreview.org/2017/05/17/the-algorithm-made-me-do-it-and-other-bad-excuses/&quot;&gt;duped&lt;/a&gt; by an algorithm supplied by the firm, given algorithms, like human decisions, are made on incomplete data and imperfect logic. Moreover, firms could deliberately seek to mislead regulators using algorithms. As Miranda Mowbray, a former lecturer of computer science at the University of Bristol pointed out in a podcast to &lt;em&gt;The Pangean&lt;/em&gt;, algorithms could lead to the next VW scandal. To the regulator, the algorithm may appear regulation-compliant, whereas, in reality, it may not be so. The consequences of a regulator being duped or misled may remain invisible, quietly wreaking havoc until it is too late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other issue is that cultural change can be exceedingly difficult. While individual responsibility is important and can go a long way, culture is bigger than any single individual. The attitude people have towards risk and the extent to which they value regulatory compliance and customer protection is something that a regulator has minimum control over. Regulators can ensure management is well-qualified but they cannot stop the idolisation of Gordon Gekko in &lt;em&gt;Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; and Jordan Belfort in &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; by the whole industry. Moreover, the regulatory culture and banking culture go hand-in-hand. If a regulator arguably starts prioritising innovation for the sake of it by routinely encouraging crypto startups (see above), then it signals its willingness to support potentially dangerous ideas, which inevitably has the effect of engendering a similar openness to exceedingly risky ideas in the banking industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final policy approach worth discussing is the elephant in the room, i.e. stress testing. Indeed, stress testing is a laudable policy measure and practice. Last year’s stress test even involved checking if firms could weather a climate catastrophe. But no policy measure is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stress tests are published as part of the financial stability report prepared by the Financial Policy Committee, a committee of the Bank of England that is headed by its Governor, under the Financial Services Act. This report is published after approval in a meeting of the Committee, where the Governor of the Bank of England is required to maintain consensus. The effect of this is that the voices of those who may strongly dissent with the majority’s (likely) positive assessment are suppressed. As we know from past experience, this is a bad idea simply because, to quote Alastair Hudson, &lt;em&gt;“there is as much a need for Eeyore as there is Piglet in macro-prudential regulation”&lt;/em&gt;. Besides, the only accountability that the Governor has for the financial stability report is ‘tea’ with the Chancellor of the Exchequer, i.e. a meeting with him, which, undeniably, is not ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, it would seem that the UK’s broad regulatory policies are far from fool-proof and adequately robust. While on the surface they seem to be doing their task of ensuring a stronger, more stable financial system, a closer analysis exposes serious problems brewing beneath the surface. These problems present a strong warning against any sense of complacency and remind us that a lot of work remains to be done. This is not to say that the Bank of England was wrong to cancel this year’s stress tests or that the PRA was wrong in delaying the implementation of Basel IV, it is only to say that the (over) confidence with which regulatory oversight has been eschewed is deeply misplaced. Britain’s regulatory architecture, to put it bluntly, is simply not as strong as it thinks it is. And it better recognise that before things come crashing down once again.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Not long ago, the Bank of England cancelled the annual stress tests of different UK banks this year due to the COVID-19 pandemic. The Prudential Regulatory Authority (PRA), Britain’s prudential regulator for all systemically important financial firms, signalled its willingness to reevaluate the timetable for the new Basel norms on international banking regulation. These relaxations in regulatory scrutiny and planning were based on the health check of UK banks conducted last year, which, according to the Bank of England, “showed that the UK banking system was resilient to deep simultaneous recessions in the UK and global economies that are more severe overall than the global financial crisis, combined with large falls in asset prices and a separate stress of misconduct costs”. Despite the use of dry language, the sheer optimism of this outlook is undeniable, which obviously begs the question of its veracity. More specifically, it is worthwhile to ask: are the UK’s regulatory policies really that good? Can the Bank of England really have that much faith in the stewardship of the financial regulators?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Vietnam Model</title>
      <link href="/The-Vietnam-Model" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Vietnam Model" />
      <published>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Vietnam-Model</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Vietnam-Model">&lt;p&gt;In a dynamic new world order, change is the only constant. With the centre of gravity of world politics shifting, albeit modestly, towards Asia-Pacific, it is worth looking at one country in south-east Asia that has been on a growth trajectory since the beginning of this millennium, Vietnam. It has been growing constantly, so much so that it emerged as one of the fastest-growing countries in Asia (and the world), achieving a growth rate of 7% in 2018. This country with a single-party government had a modest period of 20 years to achieve this feat; that is probably why it is worth talking about. Plagued with the socialistic approach of the state and heavy sanctions from the US, the country was one of the poorest economies in Asia until the 1990’s. Various factors nudged the country to open itself up to the world economy and so did the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story began in 1986. It was a rough year for the country with food shortages, scarcity of goods, rising foreign debts, and inflation rose over 700%, thanks to the communist policies practised by the country. The worsening domestic economy coupled with the trade embargo sanctions by the US, due to the Vietnam war, further degraded the country’s economic stability. A crisis, in a way, serves as both sufficient and necessary condition for a country to bring about path-breaking reforms and transform itself. That is what happened in Vietnam. It shed the Soviet model and embraced free-markets to become a ‘socialist-oriented market economy.’ The country abruptly transitioned from socialism to capitalism. Under the Doi Moi policy, which translates to ‘renovation’, the country granted property rights on land to the farmers, rolled back on price controls, put an end to the agricultural and industrial cooperatives, shut the inefficient government monopolies and the government brought laws that cleared the way for the establishment of private businesses. The reforms yielded positive outcomes soon. They bolstered the transition of a low-income country into a middle-income country. Per-capita income which was $200 in the 1980’s, rose to $2566 in 2018. Then came the second wave of decisions that furthered the growth of the country. In 2001, it signed a bilateral trade treaty with the US and joined the World Trade Organization in 2007. All these measures ensured a consistent annual growth rate of 5% for Vietnam. In 1994, foreign direct investments into the country reached 10% of the country’s GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the country had increasing growth since 2006-07, the biggest turn in its favour probably came with the election of Donald Trump as the President of the United States. Trump, looking at everything from a prism of profit maximisation – for he is a businessman, after all – engaged in a trade war with China as an attempt to reduce the ballooning trade deficit that the US has with China. The increased tariffs imposed by the Trump administration made the goods coming out of China relatively expensive. Vietnam’s proximity to China, especially to the southern region where most of the manufacturing is concentrated, resulted in minimal costs to move out of China. This made Vietnam the destination for businesses that wished to move out of China. In fact, many Chinese firms too moved out of their country to escape the US tariffs. Some businesses that could not afford to completely move out, moved parts of their production processes to Vietnam. Today, Vietnam is a manufacturing hub, particularly for electronics, garments and automobile components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2019, the total registered foreign capital was $350.5 billion. The biggest investor of all is Samsung, with an investment of $17 billion in the country. As Vietnam transitioned into the middle-income category of countries, its middle class contributed to a surge in consumer demand in the country. A population of 95 million provided an attractive market for many foreign firms. The total revenue generated from retail sales and consumer services in Vietnam in 2018 reached $191 billion, up 11.7% compared to 2017. However, the model that Vietnam followed was one that was similar to China - export and investment-led model. This is evident from the fact that exports are 105% of its GDP (which suggests that Vietnam is an export-oriented economy). All in all, Vietnam has emerged as the winner out of the US-China trade war. In 2018, exports to the US had increased by 34.8% (over 2017) and two-way trade with the US is now worth a massive $60 billion (it enjoys a surplus of $46.98 billion with the US). The country recorded a trade surplus of $11.12 billion (from trade with the world) in 2018. The country is also signing free trade agreements aggressively, mainly to diversify its export options, and thereby cushioning the impact of unforeseen external shocks. It has recently signed free trade agreements with the European Union and the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are, on the other hand, some constraints that might pose a problem to the country in the future. First and foremost is its excess dependence on the US and China. 30% of the required components for its electronic industries are imported from China. Vietnam also has a trade deficit of $34.04 billion with China, which also happens to be its largest trading partner. China, being a hegemon, is already engaged in border disputes with Vietnam over the South-China sea. Second, the country is still dependent on agriculture in terms of providing employment to its citizens. Over 40% of the population is still employed in agriculture which contributes only 14.7% to its GDP. Third, there are speculations juxtaposing Vietnam with China concluding Vietnam can become the world’s factory, occupying China’s spot. This is quite difficult to achieve. For one, the population of China is almost 15 times larger than that of Vietnam. Vietnam clearly lacks the human resources that China has. Also, Vietnam has a serious dearth of resources – imports as a percentage of the GDP is 102.47% for the country (for China this is 14.47%) – which clearly is a hindrance for the country. On top of all these reasons, Vietnam is an export-oriented economy and relies heavily on exports for its domestic growth. Such heavy reliance on external economies is always a risk that entails the huge surplus from the external trade. The coronavirus shock is a case in point. It remains to be seen as to how the country actually overcomes these major hindrances in its way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, despite its success from the early 2000’s, there is a huge amount of uncertainty about Vietnam in the long run because of the resource constraints the country faces and the huge dependence on external factors that it has. How Vietnam transforms the massive potential it has to be a global manufacturing hub and eventually a superpower is the real question. Will it be yet another case of ‘what (it) could have been’ or will it actually prove its mettle at the global stage?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In a dynamic new world order, change is the only constant. With the centre of gravity of world politics shifting, albeit modestly, towards Asia-Pacific, it is worth looking at one country in south-east Asia that has been on a growth trajectory since the beginning of this millennium, Vietnam. It has been growing constantly, so much so that it emerged as one of the fastest-growing countries in Asia (and the world), achieving a growth rate of 7% in 2018. This country with a single-party government had a modest period of 20 years to achieve this feat; that is probably why it is worth talking about. Plagued with the socialistic approach of the state and heavy sanctions from the US, the country was one of the poorest economies in Asia until the 1990’s. Various factors nudged the country to open itself up to the world economy and so did the country.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Green Paradox</title>
      <link href="/Green-Paradox" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Green Paradox" />
      <published>2020-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Green-Paradox</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Green-Paradox">&lt;p&gt;The colour ‘green’ has a multitude of connotations running with it and is associated with the meanings of growth, freshness, fertility, and the environment. It is also commonly used to represent nature. In the discipline of economics, the term ‘nature’ indicates the gargantuan cluster of resources that it provides, and not the spiritual or primordial aspects associated with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tenability of an economy can be deciphered by ascertaining the number of natural resources it wields. Thus, safeguarding the environment and its resources has been one of the most imperative concerns of economists and planners across the globe. The standard way by which an economy tries to accomplish it is through government intervention. The authorities try to strike a balance between effective utilisation and adequate cushioning of its scarce resources. Almost every government in an economy with abounding resources introduces legislative provisions with the intent of achieving this balance. Thus, policies or acts of legislation, passed with such or similar intent, are known as &lt;em&gt;green policies&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a side note, it is impossible to conceive the idea of an economy devoid of human wants, as it is one of its salient features and is the catalyst that drives it. An interesting attribute of human wants is that they are unbiased of any moral/legal presumption associated with them. This is what shapes a consumer to be rational. However, with the popularity of the concept of social cost on the uprise, one cannot help but notice the toll that rationality takes on the resources. The interlinkage of every entity in an economy with the other, the behaviour they display in certain situations as predicted by the economic principles, and the deviations/alterations in such predictions by the dynamic external forces and circumstances sometimes cause these principles to fail. This gives rise to a paradoxical situation, characterised by the display of discrepancy in behaviour by these principals/constants. On connecting the dots, it can be observed that the unpredictability of the human psyche, tinted with negotiable morality, exposes certain chinks and loopholes in the policies introduced by the authorities. This sometimes leads to a display of contrary results, and subsequent failure of such policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best examples of this would be green policies, as they display paradoxical tendency in the long run. The main rationale responsible is the resistance of human wants to such restrictive measures. The level of pollution/environmental degradation is measured by the bulk of pollutant particles accumulated in a specific environmental sample. One of the primary contributors to such pollutants is fossil fuels. The social cost incurred on account of the consumption of fossil fuel is the corrosion of the environment. Every molecule of the fuel extracted, upon combustion, would contribute to the addition of carbon to the atmosphere. Even on employing the most efficient methods, the emission cannot be curbed significantly, as a quarter of the emitted carbon would dwell in the atmosphere practically forever, thereby contributing to global warming. As a result, the authorities are backed into a corner, and forced to choose the restrictive use policy as a last resort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the government cannot make restrictions unannounced. The general rule is that it is obligated to make a reasonably prior notification to the resource owners. The resource owners anticipate the prices to fall in the future, as the clogging of permitted extraction and use of these resources causes the long-run demand to decrease. Thus, the utility of these resources as assets falls for their owners, as they would not enjoy any future appreciation from them. This induces them to intensify the extraction in the current period when the restrictions are not yet active and the demand is still fair. Then, they divest by selling off the stock of the extracted resources and reinvest the proceeds into something with better prospects of future appreciation. This renders the policy useless, as the share of resources that are to be used judicially in the future is squandered in the current period. The human instinct of self-preservation causes the entire policy framework to collapse. Such a situation is called the ‘green paradox’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term was first coined by the German economist, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hans-Werner_Sinn&quot;&gt;Hans-Werner Sinn&lt;/a&gt;, and has since become one of the most controversial topics under environmental economics. The green paradox is rooted in the fundamental argument of Hotelling’s rule- which states that for the owners of non-renewable resources, time acts as the deciding factor for the extraction of the resources they possess. Because of their scarce nature, non-renewable resources will always command a price that is higher than the cost of their extraction. The owner ends up at a crossroads between keeping the resource intact in the hope of a better price in the future, or extracting and selling it to invest the proceeds in higher-yielding security. Hence, for the paradox to operate, obedience to the Hotelling’s rule is a prerequisite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst all the scepticism, there have been several accounts of empirical evidence in full or partial support of the rule and paradox. When the carbon cap bill was introduced in the US senate in 2010, the expectation of a possible demand shortage had started to induce excessive extractions in the current period. Till the time the bill collapsed, a 12 million ton increase in the normal CO2 emission rate was observed. Also, the price of oil and coal for the future contracts that expired before the imposition of the cap showed a significant rise. However, the evidence from the US Acid Rain Project states that though the prices were driven down as a result of the paradox, there was no material increase in the persisting rate of coal extraction. This goes to show that due to a large number of factors, the predicted outcomes seldom fully confirm the theoretically suggested outcomes. Moreover, the reliance of the outcome on the sentiment of the suppliers also creates a lot of room for deviations. Though only a portion of the entire phenomenon can be observed in a given sample, it is still safe to say that the fundamental premises of the argument hold when subjected to the practical aspect of the markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greatest challenge for economists and policymakers is to develop a climate policy in which the paradox and the variation in its significance at the national and global level is accounted for, and which also reduces the overall extraction of these resources rather than restricting their usage. A good point to start would be to develop an effective formula/algorithm to update and revamp the allocation of the global carbon budget to different countries, using an effective evaluation system to calculate the weightage of the dynamic political and economic factors.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aryaman Dhiman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The colour ‘green’ has a multitude of connotations running with it and is associated with the meanings of growth, freshness, fertility, and the environment. It is also commonly used to represent nature. In the discipline of economics, the term ‘nature’ indicates the gargantuan cluster of resources that it provides, and not the spiritual or primordial aspects associated with it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Reliance Jio: The Next Big Thing?</title>
      <link href="/Reliance-Jio" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reliance Jio: The Next Big Thing?" />
      <published>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Reliance-Jio</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Reliance-Jio">&lt;p&gt;There have been several tremendous investments and operations undertaken by large corporations in the past, which have changed the world as we know it. One such investment that hopefully turned out to be absolutely triumphant was the Reliance Industries’ new telecom venture named ‘Reliance Jio’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mukesh Ambani, the head of Reliance Industries, India’s largest conglomerate, shelled out $35 billion of the company’s money to provide the South Asian nation with its first all-4G network. By offering free calls and data for peanuts, the telecom latecomer upended the industry, setting off a cheap internet tsunami that is opening the market of 1.3 billion people to global tech and opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will try to analyse how Reliance Jio turned the telecom industry upside down, how successful Jio has been, and what allowed them to have such a clear path to success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gadgets.ndtv.com/tags/reliance-jio&quot;&gt;Reliance Jio&lt;/a&gt; officially launched its commercial operation on September 5, 2016, and it has drastically changed the telecom sector with its free voice calls and cheap 4G services that changed the way Indian users consumed data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mukesh Ambani was well versed in the revenue streams of the existing players in the market. Upwards of 60-70% of the revenue was generated through voice call charges. Also, there existed a strong price war for voice call charges. The telecom industry was absolutely saturated with the negligible scope of any growth or outsider’s entry. But, Ambani being one of the greatest business minds on the face of the Earth, knew exactly where to strike and reap the benefits. The mobile data market in India was very limited mostly because of the high prices. Out of the 1.05 billion connections, only 10% used 4G and internet and therefore, mobile data lacked competition and had the biggest headroom for growth and development. Ambani found a sweet spot to invest in within such a saturated market and created an all-new space in the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He brought in the latest 4G technology in India whereas other service providers such as Airtel, Vodafone, and Idea needed huge capital to upgrade their existing 2G and 3G networks to 4G. He invested a whopping $35 billion into the new technology which was 3 times bigger than the combined capital of all the three major service providers at the time. Other service providers did not have the resources to counter and bring in the latest technology. Additionally, there existed an exit barrier for them as they had already invested huge sums of money in the older technology whereas Jio didn’t have any such obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having invested so heavily in Reliance Jio, the biggest hurdle for the company to be successful was to attract customers, and this is where the genius business model of Jio comes into play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jio used a loss-leading strategy for the first six months after launch, providing free unlimited voice calls and mobile data. The company’s 4G data services provided consumers the option to watch more online videos and other content than ever before, something that became apparent when India jumped ahead of the US and China to take the position of world’s biggest consumer of mobile data. Eventually, the company’s services did become paid, but that did not stop the Jio juggernaut– primarily because of the ultra-low tariff the company levied for its data. This strategy not only shifted the customer base towards Jio but also acted as an entry barrier for other providers in the industry as they could not operate under such conditions which, eventually, helped Jio to create a sort of monopoly in the mobile data market. The biggest advantage Jio had was its low cost of capital. Reliance used the cash flow from its traditional businesses to subsidise cheap prices to potential subscribers, and to kill off weaker competitors that had to rely on expensive bank loans. Moreover, they extended their free services to March 31, 2017, in order to retain the customer base and also expand it even further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a look at how the telecom industry revolutionised after Jio’s entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ultra-cheap data: Before the entry of Reliance Jio, data was rather expensive and consumers had to shell out up to ₹450 (on some networks) for 1GB of data. The highlight of Jio’s launch offer was the free data it was offering to consumers, with 4GB of high-speed 4G data per day, followed by continued data at 128kbps speed. Eventually, the company had to launch chargeable plans after incumbent operators protested, but even then the tariff was so low that consumers paid roughly Rs. 10 per GB of 4G data - something other operators also started to offer in response.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Increased consumption of online content: India saw an exponential rise in the consumption of online content with the availability of free data. Jio claims India’s data consumption went from 200 million GB to 1200 million GB in six months.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Free voice calls: Voice calls became free for all consumers across networks when Jio launched operations. The company has said both local and STD calls will always be free on its network, to all networks.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Proliferation of 4G smartphones: The market for 4G smartphones exploded as a result of the gun and bullet strategy after Jio services were launched as everyone had access to the company’s 4G network for free.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Faster mobile data: With 4G becoming the norm in the market, mobile data speeds rose too, considering most people were on 3G networks before that. According to the latest data by the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (TRAI), Jio offers an average download speed of around 18mbps.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A record in user acquisition: In February, Jio claimed its telecom network had garnered 100 million users in less than six months of operations. At the time, Chairman Mukesh Ambani had said this growth is faster than even what global giants such as Facebook and WhatsApp recorded. The Jio user base currently stands at more than 387 million.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Improved broadband internet availability: With the free internet, millions of people got access to high-speed 4G services, and Jio became the country’s biggest provider of broadband internet – and that’s without even counting in the JioFiber service that the company recently started.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only has Jio revolutionised the telecom industry, but it is also bringing in changes in society and education. With the easy availability of internet services in every remote corner of the country, people are now much more aware than they ever were about what is happening around the globe. Additionally, the online education industry has seen a boom with companies like Byju’s and Unacademy making great progress as every student with a mobile phone can now access the resources which earlier were not available to them. Kids living in villages where teachers often never show up for classes can now use their Jio smartphones to study online. Offsprings of the elite- who are sent to expensive cram schools to prepare for entrance exams- will now face competition from kids who have studied online in the hinterlands, thanks to Jio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jio is on the way to transforming itself into a platform for the vast population of India. A platform from whose ecosystem people cannot escape. We have been witnesses to the meteoric rise of many such platforms across the globe. Not only that, but we have also been the victims of such platforms for the last decade. Today, people’s lives seem incomplete without WhatsApp or Instagram, which is Facebook’s way of confining us within its limits. Google, Amazon, Apple, every major global player you name has a way of limiting our reach to their own services. And Jio’s move to be that platform provider for India has attracted global attention in these past few months. Everyone wants to be a part of this revolution and wants to get access to the large market that India offers to the world. Because of this, Reliance has been able to make Jio net debt-free ahead of its goal of March 31, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is very simple that after the white and green revolutions, Jio has brought a digital revolution in India. In the 21st century, data is the new oxygen and Jio has provided a way to access this data and bring a change. The success of Jio shows how a single man’s vision can bring a change in the lives of 1.3 billion people.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There have been several tremendous investments and operations undertaken by large corporations in the past, which have changed the world as we know it. One such investment that hopefully turned out to be absolutely triumphant was the Reliance Industries’ new telecom venture named ‘Reliance Jio’.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Guess the Average!</title>
      <link href="/Guess-the-Average" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Guess the Average!" />
      <published>2020-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Guess-the-Average</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Guess-the-Average">&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I appeared for an online competitive exam and one of the questions absolutely boggled my brain and I didn’t have the slightest idea on what could be the possible answer. The question went something like this: “Given a range of integers from 0 to 100, guess the whole number closest to two-thirds of the average of all the numbers guessed by others giving the same exam. So if the average of all guesses is 60, the correct guess will be 40”. What number do you think is the correct guess? I just randomly chose ‘23’ and moved on to the next question. After submitting the exam, the seemingly absurd question kept lingering in my mind and my curiosity and eagerness to know the answer made me go through various websites, and finally, I understood the concept behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll try to explain it to you and we’ll reason our way to the answer. This game is played under the condition known to the game theorists as ‘common knowledge’. Not only does every player have the same information, but each player also knows that every other player knows this. Now, the highest possible average that can occur is 100 which is possible only if every person guessed 100. In that case, two-thirds of the average would be 66.66. Since everyone can figure this out, it wouldn’t make sense to guess anything higher than 67. If every player comes to the same conclusion, no one will guess higher than 67.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now 67 is the new highest possible average so no reasonable guess should be higher than two-thirds of that which is 44. This logic can be extended further and further. With each step, the highest possible logical answer keeps getting smaller. So it would seem sensible to guess the lowest number possible and indeed if everyone chose zero, the game would reach what is known as ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/The-Rational-Pirates&quot;&gt;Nash Equilibrium&lt;/a&gt;’ (which I extensively explained in my previous article on game theory). This is a state where every player has chosen the best possible strategy for themselves given everyone else playing, and no individual player can benefit by choosing differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that’s not what happens in the real world. People, as it turns out, either aren’t perfectly rational or they don’t expect each other to be perfectly rational. Or, perhaps, it might be some combination of the two. When this game is played in real-world settings, the average tends to be somewhere between 20 and 35. Danish newspaper, &lt;em&gt;Politiken&lt;/em&gt;, ran the game with over 19000 readers participating, resulting in an average of roughly 22, making the correct answer 14. Economic game theorists have a way of modelling this interplay between rationality and practicality called ‘K-level Reasoning’, where ‘K’ stands for the number of times a cycle of reasoning is repeated. A person playing at ‘K-level zero’ would approach our game naively and guess a number randomly without thinking about other players. At ‘K-level-1’, a player would assume everyone else is playing at level zero, resulting in an average of 50 (everyone choosing integers at random between 0 to 100 gives an average of 50) and thus guess 33. At ‘K-level-2’, they’d assume that everyone else is playing at level-1 leading them to guess 22. It will take twelve K-levels to reach zero. The pieces of evidence and various studies suggest that most people stop at 1 or 2 K-levels and that’s useful to know because K-level thinking comes into play at high stake situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, stock traders evaluate stocks not only based on earning reports, but also on the value that others place on those numbers. Another example is during penalty kicks in soccer, both the shooter and the goalie decide whether to go right or left based on what they think the other person is thinking. Goalies often memorise the pattern of their opponents well in advance but penalty shooters know that and can play accordingly. In each case, participants must weigh their own understanding of the best course of action against how well they think other participants understand the situation but 1 or 2 K-levels is by no means a hard and fast rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I think you would wonder what would happen if people played this game after understanding the difference between the most logical approach and the most common? The answer is that it is up to the person’s understanding and intuition.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A few weeks ago, I appeared for an online competitive exam and one of the questions absolutely boggled my brain and I didn’t have the slightest idea on what could be the possible answer. The question went something like this: “Given a range of integers from 0 to 100, guess the whole number closest to two-thirds of the average of all the numbers guessed by others giving the same exam. So if the average of all guesses is 60, the correct guess will be 40”. What number do you think is the correct guess? I just randomly chose ‘23’ and moved on to the next question. After submitting the exam, the seemingly absurd question kept lingering in my mind and my curiosity and eagerness to know the answer made me go through various websites, and finally, I understood the concept behind it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Having Kids? Well, What’s in it for Me?</title>
      <link href="/Having-Kids-Whats-in-it-for-Me" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Having Kids? Well, What’s in it for Me?" />
      <published>2020-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Having-Kids-Whats-in-it-for-Me</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Having-Kids-Whats-in-it-for-Me">&lt;p&gt;Since time immemorial, parents have struggled with the question of the optimum number of children they should have. Well, everything is driven by incentives: we offer an economic perspective on happiness, nature, and nurturing as we analyse the marginal cost of a child against its benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The birth of a child is considered a moment of unbound joy and is believed to provide families with a wholesome experience. What follows next is a series of sleepless nights, great anxiety, and several &lt;em&gt;potty&lt;/em&gt; training sessions. Raising a child in today’s world is no piece of cake, be it in terms of personal devotion, child-care responsibilities or financial needs. Families, rich and poor alike, face their own set of challenges with respect to the same. Putting this into perspective, these issues arising from varied aspects add up to one big question: what is in it for the parents? Let alone going through the process more than once, is it all truly worth it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raising this question, we believe children born in different set-ups, in terms of beliefs and economic backing, add varied sorts of value to the particular household. A family belonging to the lower-income group generally believes that having a larger number of children means more hands to work in the field or otherwise, completely negating the cost of actually raising these children. For those poor, rural families, children are not only seen as an economic asset but also as an insurance policy for old age, especially in societies with zero state pension and health care. However, we observe that as the income of a family increases, the smaller the family is, i.e. they prefer to have fewer children. With rising incomes, families don’t need their children to be an economic asset; the family can afford for their children to be an economic liability. Furthermore, people with a superior economic standing believe in providing better education and lifestyle to their children. Hence, while, children in impoverished communities contribute to their family income, children in the developed world subtract from family finances through the cost of their education and upbringing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can also be measured by weighing the marginal cost against the marginal utility of procreating. The marginal cost and utility, incurred and reaped respectively, largely depend upon the budget constraint of each household. Hence, so does the optimum number of children. This brings us to the conclusion that there is a negative correlation between family income and family size which further leads to a trade-off between the quantity and the quality of children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the idea that having a higher number of children reduces the cost of raising each additional child; in short, highlighting diminishing marginal cost. The reason behind this is that most of the necessary child raising equipment- like high chairs, cribs, and clothes - can be passed onto the next child, and no additional money is required to be spent on the same. Moreover, with many family and parent-child health insurance plans, the monthly premium remains the same, irrespective of the number of children. This points to a lower cost per person. Additionally, there are several universities in the States that provide various benefits to families with more than one child. Therefore, it could so happen that due to these benefits the cost per unit of putting ten children through college could be less than that of putting one. Who says houses cannot be run on economies of scale?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irrespective of the economies of scale, there are substantial costs that remain fixed: a large number of children leads to the dilution of parental resources- financial as well as time. These fixed costs include expenses on food, healthcare, and basic clothes for lower-income groups. Similarly, the fixed costs of higher-income groups are much larger as they involve education, and extra-curricular activities amongst others. Moreover, these children also give their parents a fair share of headaches. Being anxious about everything pertaining to their children forms a crucial part of a parent’s identity. This leads us to another opportunity cost which is the personal freedom of these caregivers. This causes the parents to juggle between giving time to their children and finding time for themselves and their work. Therefore, as the number of children increases, there is a marked drop in the time spent with each child. Many of them might grow up feeling neglected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like identified in the foregoing paragraphs, the utility and benefits that the parents reap from their children can be seen in the form of economic and old-age support. However, it is also important to realise that as the number of children that a couple has increases, there is a decline in the marginal utility. This is because, with each additional child, there is a decreasing extra satisfaction that the couple will gain. This can be seen in the way that if a couple has 5 children then they will receive more satisfaction with their firstborn than they did from their last born (5th child in this case). Hence, as the number of children a couple has increases, the law of diminishing returns starts to hold true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, what is truly in it for the parents purely depends upon the type of income groups that they belong to. Thus, regardless of whether couples want children for personal attachment or joy, it all eventually boils down to the economic cost and utility of having one!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>kabir.kochar sanya.puri</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Since time immemorial, parents have struggled with the question of the optimum number of children they should have. Well, everything is driven by incentives: we offer an economic perspective on happiness, nature, and nurturing as we analyse the marginal cost of a child against its benefit.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">European Central Bank: The Saviour of Europe?</title>
      <link href="/European-Central-Bank" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="European Central Bank: The Saviour of Europe?" />
      <published>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/European-Central-Bank</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/European-Central-Bank">&lt;p&gt;Time and again, Ms Lagarde, the first President of the European Central Bank (ECB) warned the European Union (EU) governments against the COVID-19 pandemic turning into a calamity. The pressures have been mounting as the largest economies of the Eurozone like France and Italy crumble. The EU, one of the world’s largest economies, has decided to take certain measures via its monetary policy, however, the question is how much can the ECB afford?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms Lagarde, however, is of the view that monetary policy is not the first line of defence and feels that fiscal response must be given much more importance. The persistent heterogeneity in the Euro area has also been a long-standing concern for the single monetary policy. It severely complicates the conduct of this policy. The current crisis exposed these vulnerabilities, once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since 2008, the EU has been in a non-stop crisis mode. Even the interest rate it charges to the commercial banks is almost nil leaving very little margin for further rate cuts to stimulate the economy out of this rut. The ECB has acknowledged how they are facing an unprecedented crisis with historic consequences which might just push the European economy to worse than what it was in 2008. If the crisis is not controlled by the stimuli, it risks pushing the already wobbly European economy to the state of recession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 16, the ECB went ahead and announced the measures it will be taking on the monetary policy front while it gives time to the respective governments to formulate fiscal policy measures. The ECB took certain measures to prevent the crisis from becoming a full-blown financial crisis with two broad objectives: first, to restore the orderly functioning of presently volatile European financial markets, and second, to ensure that the accommodative monetary policy measures support firms and households in incurring the social and economic costs of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ECB response consists of three major mutually reinforcing grounds. The first one relating to broad-based asset purchases to address illiquidity and volatility in core segments of the European economy. The temporary Pandemic Emergency Purchase Programme (PEPP) constitutes the core of this component. The economies in the entire Eurozone have been struggling with tightening fiscal and economic conditions, the PEPP expects to release the pressure on these economies. It foresees purchases at a volume of €750 billion of eligible private and public securities throughout this year, and longer if needed.  The ECB also aims to mitigate the impact of the crisis on the funding conditions of businesses and banks. For the same, it has decided to divert a considerable fraction of the additional €120 billion purchase envelope under the Asset Purchase Programmes (APP), as well as of the PEPP, for eligible private sector bonds. However, one cannot turn a blind eye to the fact that the bank has already been conducting purchases of government bonds, and now, it does not have much to re-purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, measures to ensure that the banks remain effective carriers of the monetary policy of the ECB have been introduced. The enhanced Targeted Longer-Term Refinancing Operations (TLTROs), as well as a comprehensive set of collateral easing measures, form part of this component.  The interest rate on all targeted TLTROs was reduced by 25 basis points to -0.5% from June 2020 to June 2021. Measures to ensure the solvency of banks by holding up the role of lender of the last resort to the banks which will help the ECB drive the way for economic growth. This becomes all the more necessary considering that the European economy is majorly a bank-based economy than a financial market one, so just supporting the financial markets would not help alleviate the effects of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measures for small and medium-sized firms are equally necessary, which include bank lending and loan guarantee schemes to protect the already overdrawn credit lines by cash strapped firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Italy, for example, bank lending conditions for firms remained remarkably resilient in recent years despite significant swings in market-based funding conditions of the banks and firms. Again, the measures can provide a valuable bridge to the future and help keep aggregate external funding costs of firms stable until the economy recovers and uncertainty diminishes further. This also includes accepting a wider range of assets as collaterals from small and medium-sized firms along with consistently working on the liquidity conditions of the banks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the ECB fails to improve liquidity indirectly through these measures, it always has the option to exercise its right to issue ‘helicopter money’. This alternative would put the money straight into the ‘hands’ of the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through these measures, the ECB hopes to improve liquidity and market behaviour in the sovereign yield bonds market, which in turn form the basis of pricing of assets in the economy. The ECB uses the GDP-weighted Euro area government bond yield curve as a measure for the effectiveness of the economy, but currently, this curve has been badly disrupted. So the ECB will focus on stabilising this curve and reversing the steepness of the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, while the Eurozone faces an increasingly threatening risk of a slowdown in the economy, which can take years to recover from and get back to the normal levels, the ECB and various governments are taking steps to tackle this challenge. The cluster of countries has recovered from far worse situations in the past, like the global economic crisis of 2008, and emerged stronger than ever. It remains to be seen what other steps the European Union takes as a much worse crisis than COVID-19 awaits the global economy and how the relief package unravels for the Union.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kashish Jindal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Time and again, Ms Lagarde, the first President of the European Central Bank (ECB) warned the European Union (EU) governments against the COVID-19 pandemic turning into a calamity. The pressures have been mounting as the largest economies of the Eurozone like France and Italy crumble. The EU, one of the world’s largest economies, has decided to take certain measures via its monetary policy, however, the question is how much can the ECB afford?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
