<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/economics/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-07-02T10:47:08+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/economics/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Vietnam Model</title>
      <link href="/The-Vietnam-Model" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Vietnam Model" />
      <published>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Vietnam-Model</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Vietnam-Model">&lt;p&gt;In a dynamic new world order, change is the only constant. With the centre of gravity of world politics shifting, albeit modestly, towards Asia-Pacific, it is worth looking at one country in south-east Asia that has been on a growth trajectory since the beginning of this millennium, Vietnam. It has been growing constantly, so much so that it emerged as one of the fastest-growing countries in Asia (and the world), achieving a growth rate of 7% in 2018. This country with a single-party government had a modest period of 20 years to achieve this feat; that is probably why it is worth talking about. Plagued with the socialistic approach of the state and heavy sanctions from the US, the country was one of the poorest economies in Asia until the 1990’s. Various factors nudged the country to open itself up to the world economy and so did the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story began in 1986. It was a rough year for the country with food shortages, scarcity of goods, rising foreign debts, and inflation rose over 700%, thanks to the communist policies practised by the country. The worsening domestic economy coupled with the trade embargo sanctions by the US, due to the Vietnam war, further degraded the country’s economic stability. A crisis, in a way, serves as both sufficient and necessary condition for a country to bring about path-breaking reforms and transform itself. That is what happened in Vietnam. It shed the Soviet model and embraced free-markets to become a ‘socialist-oriented market economy.’ The country abruptly transitioned from socialism to capitalism. Under the Doi Moi policy, which translates to ‘renovation’, the country granted property rights on land to the farmers, rolled back on price controls, put an end to the agricultural and industrial cooperatives, shut the inefficient government monopolies and the government brought laws that cleared the way for the establishment of private businesses. The reforms yielded positive outcomes soon. They bolstered the transition of a low-income country into a middle-income country. Per-capita income which was $200 in the 1980’s, rose to $2566 in 2018. Then came the second wave of decisions that furthered the growth of the country. In 2001, it signed a bilateral trade treaty with the US and joined the World Trade Organization in 2007. All these measures ensured a consistent annual growth rate of 5% for Vietnam. In 1994, foreign direct investments into the country reached 10% of the country’s GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the country had increasing growth since 2006-07, the biggest turn in its favour probably came with the election of Donald Trump as the President of the United States. Trump, looking at everything from a prism of profit maximisation – for he is a businessman, after all – engaged in a trade war with China as an attempt to reduce the ballooning trade deficit that the US has with China. The increased tariffs imposed by the Trump administration made the goods coming out of China relatively expensive. Vietnam’s proximity to China, especially to the southern region where most of the manufacturing is concentrated, resulted in minimal costs to move out of China. This made Vietnam the destination for businesses that wished to move out of China. In fact, many Chinese firms too moved out of their country to escape the US tariffs. Some businesses that could not afford to completely move out, moved parts of their production processes to Vietnam. Today, Vietnam is a manufacturing hub, particularly for electronics, garments and automobile components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2019, the total registered foreign capital was $350.5 billion. The biggest investor of all is Samsung, with an investment of $17 billion in the country. As Vietnam transitioned into the middle-income category of countries, its middle class contributed to a surge in consumer demand in the country. A population of 95 million provided an attractive market for many foreign firms. The total revenue generated from retail sales and consumer services in Vietnam in 2018 reached $191 billion, up 11.7% compared to 2017. However, the model that Vietnam followed was one that was similar to China - export and investment-led model. This is evident from the fact that exports are 105% of its GDP (which suggests that Vietnam is an export-oriented economy). All in all, Vietnam has emerged as the winner out of the US-China trade war. In 2018, exports to the US had increased by 34.8% (over 2017) and two-way trade with the US is now worth a massive $60 billion (it enjoys a surplus of $46.98 billion with the US). The country recorded a trade surplus of $11.12 billion (from trade with the world) in 2018. The country is also signing free trade agreements aggressively, mainly to diversify its export options, and thereby cushioning the impact of unforeseen external shocks. It has recently signed free trade agreements with the European Union and the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are, on the other hand, some constraints that might pose a problem to the country in the future. First and foremost is its excess dependence on the US and China. 30% of the required components for its electronic industries are imported from China. Vietnam also has a trade deficit of $34.04 billion with China, which also happens to be its largest trading partner. China, being a hegemon, is already engaged in border disputes with Vietnam over the South-China sea. Second, the country is still dependent on agriculture in terms of providing employment to its citizens. Over 40% of the population is still employed in agriculture which contributes only 14.7% to its GDP. Third, there are speculations juxtaposing Vietnam with China concluding Vietnam can become the world’s factory, occupying China’s spot. This is quite difficult to achieve. For one, the population of China is almost 15 times larger than that of Vietnam. Vietnam clearly lacks the human resources that China has. Also, Vietnam has a serious dearth of resources – imports as a percentage of the GDP is 102.47% for the country (for China this is 14.47%) – which clearly is a hindrance for the country. On top of all these reasons, Vietnam is an export-oriented economy and relies heavily on exports for its domestic growth. Such heavy reliance on external economies is always a risk that entails the huge surplus from the external trade. The coronavirus shock is a case in point. It remains to be seen as to how the country actually overcomes these major hindrances in its way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, despite its success from the early 2000’s, there is a huge amount of uncertainty about Vietnam in the long run because of the resource constraints the country faces and the huge dependence on external factors that it has. How Vietnam transforms the massive potential it has to be a global manufacturing hub and eventually a superpower is the real question. Will it be yet another case of ‘what (it) could have been’ or will it actually prove its mettle at the global stage?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In a dynamic new world order, change is the only constant. With the centre of gravity of world politics shifting, albeit modestly, towards Asia-Pacific, it is worth looking at one country in south-east Asia that has been on a growth trajectory since the beginning of this millennium, Vietnam. It has been growing constantly, so much so that it emerged as one of the fastest-growing countries in Asia (and the world), achieving a growth rate of 7% in 2018. This country with a single-party government had a modest period of 20 years to achieve this feat; that is probably why it is worth talking about. Plagued with the socialistic approach of the state and heavy sanctions from the US, the country was one of the poorest economies in Asia until the 1990’s. Various factors nudged the country to open itself up to the world economy and so did the country.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Green Paradox</title>
      <link href="/Green-Paradox" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Green Paradox" />
      <published>2020-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Green-Paradox</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Green-Paradox">&lt;p&gt;The colour ‘green’ has a multitude of connotations running with it and is associated with the meanings of growth, freshness, fertility, and the environment. It is also commonly used to represent nature. In the discipline of economics, the term ‘nature’ indicates the gargantuan cluster of resources that it provides, and not the spiritual or primordial aspects associated with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tenability of an economy can be deciphered by ascertaining the number of natural resources it wields. Thus, safeguarding the environment and its resources has been one of the most imperative concerns of economists and planners across the globe. The standard way by which an economy tries to accomplish it is through government intervention. The authorities try to strike a balance between effective utilisation and adequate cushioning of its scarce resources. Almost every government in an economy with abounding resources introduces legislative provisions with the intent of achieving this balance. Thus, policies or acts of legislation, passed with such or similar intent, are known as &lt;em&gt;green policies&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a side note, it is impossible to conceive the idea of an economy devoid of human wants, as it is one of its salient features and is the catalyst that drives it. An interesting attribute of human wants is that they are unbiased of any moral/legal presumption associated with them. This is what shapes a consumer to be rational. However, with the popularity of the concept of social cost on the uprise, one cannot help but notice the toll that rationality takes on the resources. The interlinkage of every entity in an economy with the other, the behaviour they display in certain situations as predicted by the economic principles, and the deviations/alterations in such predictions by the dynamic external forces and circumstances sometimes cause these principles to fail. This gives rise to a paradoxical situation, characterised by the display of discrepancy in behaviour by these principals/constants. On connecting the dots, it can be observed that the unpredictability of the human psyche, tinted with negotiable morality, exposes certain chinks and loopholes in the policies introduced by the authorities. This sometimes leads to a display of contrary results, and subsequent failure of such policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best examples of this would be green policies, as they display paradoxical tendency in the long run. The main rationale responsible is the resistance of human wants to such restrictive measures. The level of pollution/environmental degradation is measured by the bulk of pollutant particles accumulated in a specific environmental sample. One of the primary contributors to such pollutants is fossil fuels. The social cost incurred on account of the consumption of fossil fuel is the corrosion of the environment. Every molecule of the fuel extracted, upon combustion, would contribute to the addition of carbon to the atmosphere. Even on employing the most efficient methods, the emission cannot be curbed significantly, as a quarter of the emitted carbon would dwell in the atmosphere practically forever, thereby contributing to global warming. As a result, the authorities are backed into a corner, and forced to choose the restrictive use policy as a last resort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the government cannot make restrictions unannounced. The general rule is that it is obligated to make a reasonably prior notification to the resource owners. The resource owners anticipate the prices to fall in the future, as the clogging of permitted extraction and use of these resources causes the long-run demand to decrease. Thus, the utility of these resources as assets falls for their owners, as they would not enjoy any future appreciation from them. This induces them to intensify the extraction in the current period when the restrictions are not yet active and the demand is still fair. Then, they divest by selling off the stock of the extracted resources and reinvest the proceeds into something with better prospects of future appreciation. This renders the policy useless, as the share of resources that are to be used judicially in the future is squandered in the current period. The human instinct of self-preservation causes the entire policy framework to collapse. Such a situation is called the ‘green paradox’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term was first coined by the German economist, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hans-Werner_Sinn&quot;&gt;Hans-Werner Sinn&lt;/a&gt;, and has since become one of the most controversial topics under environmental economics. The green paradox is rooted in the fundamental argument of Hotelling’s rule- which states that for the owners of non-renewable resources, time acts as the deciding factor for the extraction of the resources they possess. Because of their scarce nature, non-renewable resources will always command a price that is higher than the cost of their extraction. The owner ends up at a crossroads between keeping the resource intact in the hope of a better price in the future, or extracting and selling it to invest the proceeds in higher-yielding security. Hence, for the paradox to operate, obedience to the Hotelling’s rule is a prerequisite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst all the scepticism, there have been several accounts of empirical evidence in full or partial support of the rule and paradox. When the carbon cap bill was introduced in the US senate in 2010, the expectation of a possible demand shortage had started to induce excessive extractions in the current period. Till the time the bill collapsed, a 12 million ton increase in the normal CO2 emission rate was observed. Also, the price of oil and coal for the future contracts that expired before the imposition of the cap showed a significant rise. However, the evidence from the US Acid Rain Project states that though the prices were driven down as a result of the paradox, there was no material increase in the persisting rate of coal extraction. This goes to show that due to a large number of factors, the predicted outcomes seldom fully confirm the theoretically suggested outcomes. Moreover, the reliance of the outcome on the sentiment of the suppliers also creates a lot of room for deviations. Though only a portion of the entire phenomenon can be observed in a given sample, it is still safe to say that the fundamental premises of the argument hold when subjected to the practical aspect of the markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greatest challenge for economists and policymakers is to develop a climate policy in which the paradox and the variation in its significance at the national and global level is accounted for, and which also reduces the overall extraction of these resources rather than restricting their usage. A good point to start would be to develop an effective formula/algorithm to update and revamp the allocation of the global carbon budget to different countries, using an effective evaluation system to calculate the weightage of the dynamic political and economic factors.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aryaman Dhiman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The colour ‘green’ has a multitude of connotations running with it and is associated with the meanings of growth, freshness, fertility, and the environment. It is also commonly used to represent nature. In the discipline of economics, the term ‘nature’ indicates the gargantuan cluster of resources that it provides, and not the spiritual or primordial aspects associated with it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Reliance Jio: The Next Big Thing?</title>
      <link href="/Reliance-Jio" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reliance Jio: The Next Big Thing?" />
      <published>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Reliance-Jio</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Reliance-Jio">&lt;p&gt;There have been several tremendous investments and operations undertaken by large corporations in the past, which have changed the world as we know it. One such investment that hopefully turned out to be absolutely triumphant was the Reliance Industries’ new telecom venture named ‘Reliance Jio’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mukesh Ambani, the head of Reliance Industries, India’s largest conglomerate, shelled out $35 billion of the company’s money to provide the South Asian nation with its first all-4G network. By offering free calls and data for peanuts, the telecom latecomer upended the industry, setting off a cheap internet tsunami that is opening the market of 1.3 billion people to global tech and opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will try to analyse how Reliance Jio turned the telecom industry upside down, how successful Jio has been, and what allowed them to have such a clear path to success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gadgets.ndtv.com/tags/reliance-jio&quot;&gt;Reliance Jio&lt;/a&gt; officially launched its commercial operation on September 5, 2016, and it has drastically changed the telecom sector with its free voice calls and cheap 4G services that changed the way Indian users consumed data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mukesh Ambani was well versed in the revenue streams of the existing players in the market. Upwards of 60-70% of the revenue was generated through voice call charges. Also, there existed a strong price war for voice call charges. The telecom industry was absolutely saturated with the negligible scope of any growth or outsider’s entry. But, Ambani being one of the greatest business minds on the face of the Earth, knew exactly where to strike and reap the benefits. The mobile data market in India was very limited mostly because of the high prices. Out of the 1.05 billion connections, only 10% used 4G and internet and therefore, mobile data lacked competition and had the biggest headroom for growth and development. Ambani found a sweet spot to invest in within such a saturated market and created an all-new space in the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He brought in the latest 4G technology in India whereas other service providers such as Airtel, Vodafone, and Idea needed huge capital to upgrade their existing 2G and 3G networks to 4G. He invested a whopping $35 billion into the new technology which was 3 times bigger than the combined capital of all the three major service providers at the time. Other service providers did not have the resources to counter and bring in the latest technology. Additionally, there existed an exit barrier for them as they had already invested huge sums of money in the older technology whereas Jio didn’t have any such obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having invested so heavily in Reliance Jio, the biggest hurdle for the company to be successful was to attract customers, and this is where the genius business model of Jio comes into play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jio used a loss-leading strategy for the first six months after launch, providing free unlimited voice calls and mobile data. The company’s 4G data services provided consumers the option to watch more online videos and other content than ever before, something that became apparent when India jumped ahead of the US and China to take the position of world’s biggest consumer of mobile data. Eventually, the company’s services did become paid, but that did not stop the Jio juggernaut– primarily because of the ultra-low tariff the company levied for its data. This strategy not only shifted the customer base towards Jio but also acted as an entry barrier for other providers in the industry as they could not operate under such conditions which, eventually, helped Jio to create a sort of monopoly in the mobile data market. The biggest advantage Jio had was its low cost of capital. Reliance used the cash flow from its traditional businesses to subsidise cheap prices to potential subscribers, and to kill off weaker competitors that had to rely on expensive bank loans. Moreover, they extended their free services to March 31, 2017, in order to retain the customer base and also expand it even further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a look at how the telecom industry revolutionised after Jio’s entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ultra-cheap data: Before the entry of Reliance Jio, data was rather expensive and consumers had to shell out up to ₹450 (on some networks) for 1GB of data. The highlight of Jio’s launch offer was the free data it was offering to consumers, with 4GB of high-speed 4G data per day, followed by continued data at 128kbps speed. Eventually, the company had to launch chargeable plans after incumbent operators protested, but even then the tariff was so low that consumers paid roughly Rs. 10 per GB of 4G data - something other operators also started to offer in response.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Increased consumption of online content: India saw an exponential rise in the consumption of online content with the availability of free data. Jio claims India’s data consumption went from 200 million GB to 1200 million GB in six months.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Free voice calls: Voice calls became free for all consumers across networks when Jio launched operations. The company has said both local and STD calls will always be free on its network, to all networks.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Proliferation of 4G smartphones: The market for 4G smartphones exploded as a result of the gun and bullet strategy after Jio services were launched as everyone had access to the company’s 4G network for free.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Faster mobile data: With 4G becoming the norm in the market, mobile data speeds rose too, considering most people were on 3G networks before that. According to the latest data by the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (TRAI), Jio offers an average download speed of around 18mbps.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A record in user acquisition: In February, Jio claimed its telecom network had garnered 100 million users in less than six months of operations. At the time, Chairman Mukesh Ambani had said this growth is faster than even what global giants such as Facebook and WhatsApp recorded. The Jio user base currently stands at more than 387 million.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Improved broadband internet availability: With the free internet, millions of people got access to high-speed 4G services, and Jio became the country’s biggest provider of broadband internet – and that’s without even counting in the JioFiber service that the company recently started.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only has Jio revolutionised the telecom industry, but it is also bringing in changes in society and education. With the easy availability of internet services in every remote corner of the country, people are now much more aware than they ever were about what is happening around the globe. Additionally, the online education industry has seen a boom with companies like Byju’s and Unacademy making great progress as every student with a mobile phone can now access the resources which earlier were not available to them. Kids living in villages where teachers often never show up for classes can now use their Jio smartphones to study online. Offsprings of the elite- who are sent to expensive cram schools to prepare for entrance exams- will now face competition from kids who have studied online in the hinterlands, thanks to Jio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jio is on the way to transforming itself into a platform for the vast population of India. A platform from whose ecosystem people cannot escape. We have been witnesses to the meteoric rise of many such platforms across the globe. Not only that, but we have also been the victims of such platforms for the last decade. Today, people’s lives seem incomplete without WhatsApp or Instagram, which is Facebook’s way of confining us within its limits. Google, Amazon, Apple, every major global player you name has a way of limiting our reach to their own services. And Jio’s move to be that platform provider for India has attracted global attention in these past few months. Everyone wants to be a part of this revolution and wants to get access to the large market that India offers to the world. Because of this, Reliance has been able to make Jio net debt-free ahead of its goal of March 31, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is very simple that after the white and green revolutions, Jio has brought a digital revolution in India. In the 21st century, data is the new oxygen and Jio has provided a way to access this data and bring a change. The success of Jio shows how a single man’s vision can bring a change in the lives of 1.3 billion people.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There have been several tremendous investments and operations undertaken by large corporations in the past, which have changed the world as we know it. One such investment that hopefully turned out to be absolutely triumphant was the Reliance Industries’ new telecom venture named ‘Reliance Jio’.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Guess the Average!</title>
      <link href="/Guess-the-Average" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Guess the Average!" />
      <published>2020-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Guess-the-Average</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Guess-the-Average">&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I appeared for an online competitive exam and one of the questions absolutely boggled my brain and I didn’t have the slightest idea on what could be the possible answer. The question went something like this: “Given a range of integers from 0 to 100, guess the whole number closest to two-thirds of the average of all the numbers guessed by others giving the same exam. So if the average of all guesses is 60, the correct guess will be 40”. What number do you think is the correct guess? I just randomly chose ‘23’ and moved on to the next question. After submitting the exam, the seemingly absurd question kept lingering in my mind and my curiosity and eagerness to know the answer made me go through various websites, and finally, I understood the concept behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll try to explain it to you and we’ll reason our way to the answer. This game is played under the condition known to the game theorists as ‘common knowledge’. Not only does every player have the same information, but each player also knows that every other player knows this. Now, the highest possible average that can occur is 100 which is possible only if every person guessed 100. In that case, two-thirds of the average would be 66.66. Since everyone can figure this out, it wouldn’t make sense to guess anything higher than 67. If every player comes to the same conclusion, no one will guess higher than 67.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now 67 is the new highest possible average so no reasonable guess should be higher than two-thirds of that which is 44. This logic can be extended further and further. With each step, the highest possible logical answer keeps getting smaller. So it would seem sensible to guess the lowest number possible and indeed if everyone chose zero, the game would reach what is known as ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/The-Rational-Pirates&quot;&gt;Nash Equilibrium&lt;/a&gt;’ (which I extensively explained in my previous article on game theory). This is a state where every player has chosen the best possible strategy for themselves given everyone else playing, and no individual player can benefit by choosing differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that’s not what happens in the real world. People, as it turns out, either aren’t perfectly rational or they don’t expect each other to be perfectly rational. Or, perhaps, it might be some combination of the two. When this game is played in real-world settings, the average tends to be somewhere between 20 and 35. Danish newspaper, &lt;em&gt;Politiken&lt;/em&gt;, ran the game with over 19000 readers participating, resulting in an average of roughly 22, making the correct answer 14. Economic game theorists have a way of modelling this interplay between rationality and practicality called ‘K-level Reasoning’, where ‘K’ stands for the number of times a cycle of reasoning is repeated. A person playing at ‘K-level zero’ would approach our game naively and guess a number randomly without thinking about other players. At ‘K-level-1’, a player would assume everyone else is playing at level zero, resulting in an average of 50 (everyone choosing integers at random between 0 to 100 gives an average of 50) and thus guess 33. At ‘K-level-2’, they’d assume that everyone else is playing at level-1 leading them to guess 22. It will take twelve K-levels to reach zero. The pieces of evidence and various studies suggest that most people stop at 1 or 2 K-levels and that’s useful to know because K-level thinking comes into play at high stake situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, stock traders evaluate stocks not only based on earning reports, but also on the value that others place on those numbers. Another example is during penalty kicks in soccer, both the shooter and the goalie decide whether to go right or left based on what they think the other person is thinking. Goalies often memorise the pattern of their opponents well in advance but penalty shooters know that and can play accordingly. In each case, participants must weigh their own understanding of the best course of action against how well they think other participants understand the situation but 1 or 2 K-levels is by no means a hard and fast rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I think you would wonder what would happen if people played this game after understanding the difference between the most logical approach and the most common? The answer is that it is up to the person’s understanding and intuition.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A few weeks ago, I appeared for an online competitive exam and one of the questions absolutely boggled my brain and I didn’t have the slightest idea on what could be the possible answer. The question went something like this: “Given a range of integers from 0 to 100, guess the whole number closest to two-thirds of the average of all the numbers guessed by others giving the same exam. So if the average of all guesses is 60, the correct guess will be 40”. What number do you think is the correct guess? I just randomly chose ‘23’ and moved on to the next question. After submitting the exam, the seemingly absurd question kept lingering in my mind and my curiosity and eagerness to know the answer made me go through various websites, and finally, I understood the concept behind it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Having Kids? Well, What’s in it for Me?</title>
      <link href="/Having-Kids-Whats-in-it-for-Me" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Having Kids? Well, What’s in it for Me?" />
      <published>2020-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Having-Kids-Whats-in-it-for-Me</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Having-Kids-Whats-in-it-for-Me">&lt;p&gt;Since time immemorial, parents have struggled with the question of the optimum number of children they should have. Well, everything is driven by incentives: we offer an economic perspective on happiness, nature, and nurturing as we analyse the marginal cost of a child against its benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The birth of a child is considered a moment of unbound joy and is believed to provide families with a wholesome experience. What follows next is a series of sleepless nights, great anxiety, and several &lt;em&gt;potty&lt;/em&gt; training sessions. Raising a child in today’s world is no piece of cake, be it in terms of personal devotion, child-care responsibilities or financial needs. Families, rich and poor alike, face their own set of challenges with respect to the same. Putting this into perspective, these issues arising from varied aspects add up to one big question: what is in it for the parents? Let alone going through the process more than once, is it all truly worth it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raising this question, we believe children born in different set-ups, in terms of beliefs and economic backing, add varied sorts of value to the particular household. A family belonging to the lower-income group generally believes that having a larger number of children means more hands to work in the field or otherwise, completely negating the cost of actually raising these children. For those poor, rural families, children are not only seen as an economic asset but also as an insurance policy for old age, especially in societies with zero state pension and health care. However, we observe that as the income of a family increases, the smaller the family is, i.e. they prefer to have fewer children. With rising incomes, families don’t need their children to be an economic asset; the family can afford for their children to be an economic liability. Furthermore, people with a superior economic standing believe in providing better education and lifestyle to their children. Hence, while, children in impoverished communities contribute to their family income, children in the developed world subtract from family finances through the cost of their education and upbringing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can also be measured by weighing the marginal cost against the marginal utility of procreating. The marginal cost and utility, incurred and reaped respectively, largely depend upon the budget constraint of each household. Hence, so does the optimum number of children. This brings us to the conclusion that there is a negative correlation between family income and family size which further leads to a trade-off between the quantity and the quality of children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the idea that having a higher number of children reduces the cost of raising each additional child; in short, highlighting diminishing marginal cost. The reason behind this is that most of the necessary child raising equipment- like high chairs, cribs, and clothes - can be passed onto the next child, and no additional money is required to be spent on the same. Moreover, with many family and parent-child health insurance plans, the monthly premium remains the same, irrespective of the number of children. This points to a lower cost per person. Additionally, there are several universities in the States that provide various benefits to families with more than one child. Therefore, it could so happen that due to these benefits the cost per unit of putting ten children through college could be less than that of putting one. Who says houses cannot be run on economies of scale?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irrespective of the economies of scale, there are substantial costs that remain fixed: a large number of children leads to the dilution of parental resources- financial as well as time. These fixed costs include expenses on food, healthcare, and basic clothes for lower-income groups. Similarly, the fixed costs of higher-income groups are much larger as they involve education, and extra-curricular activities amongst others. Moreover, these children also give their parents a fair share of headaches. Being anxious about everything pertaining to their children forms a crucial part of a parent’s identity. This leads us to another opportunity cost which is the personal freedom of these caregivers. This causes the parents to juggle between giving time to their children and finding time for themselves and their work. Therefore, as the number of children increases, there is a marked drop in the time spent with each child. Many of them might grow up feeling neglected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like identified in the foregoing paragraphs, the utility and benefits that the parents reap from their children can be seen in the form of economic and old-age support. However, it is also important to realise that as the number of children that a couple has increases, there is a decline in the marginal utility. This is because, with each additional child, there is a decreasing extra satisfaction that the couple will gain. This can be seen in the way that if a couple has 5 children then they will receive more satisfaction with their firstborn than they did from their last born (5th child in this case). Hence, as the number of children a couple has increases, the law of diminishing returns starts to hold true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, what is truly in it for the parents purely depends upon the type of income groups that they belong to. Thus, regardless of whether couples want children for personal attachment or joy, it all eventually boils down to the economic cost and utility of having one!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>kabir.kochar sanya.puri</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Since time immemorial, parents have struggled with the question of the optimum number of children they should have. Well, everything is driven by incentives: we offer an economic perspective on happiness, nature, and nurturing as we analyse the marginal cost of a child against its benefit.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">European Central Bank: The Saviour of Europe?</title>
      <link href="/European-Central-Bank" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="European Central Bank: The Saviour of Europe?" />
      <published>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/European-Central-Bank</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/European-Central-Bank">&lt;p&gt;Time and again, Ms Lagarde, the first President of the European Central Bank (ECB) warned the European Union (EU) governments against the COVID-19 pandemic turning into a calamity. The pressures have been mounting as the largest economies of the Eurozone like France and Italy crumble. The EU, one of the world’s largest economies, has decided to take certain measures via its monetary policy, however, the question is how much can the ECB afford?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms Lagarde, however, is of the view that monetary policy is not the first line of defence and feels that fiscal response must be given much more importance. The persistent heterogeneity in the Euro area has also been a long-standing concern for the single monetary policy. It severely complicates the conduct of this policy. The current crisis exposed these vulnerabilities, once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since 2008, the EU has been in a non-stop crisis mode. Even the interest rate it charges to the commercial banks is almost nil leaving very little margin for further rate cuts to stimulate the economy out of this rut. The ECB has acknowledged how they are facing an unprecedented crisis with historic consequences which might just push the European economy to worse than what it was in 2008. If the crisis is not controlled by the stimuli, it risks pushing the already wobbly European economy to the state of recession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 16, the ECB went ahead and announced the measures it will be taking on the monetary policy front while it gives time to the respective governments to formulate fiscal policy measures. The ECB took certain measures to prevent the crisis from becoming a full-blown financial crisis with two broad objectives: first, to restore the orderly functioning of presently volatile European financial markets, and second, to ensure that the accommodative monetary policy measures support firms and households in incurring the social and economic costs of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ECB response consists of three major mutually reinforcing grounds. The first one relating to broad-based asset purchases to address illiquidity and volatility in core segments of the European economy. The temporary Pandemic Emergency Purchase Programme (PEPP) constitutes the core of this component. The economies in the entire Eurozone have been struggling with tightening fiscal and economic conditions, the PEPP expects to release the pressure on these economies. It foresees purchases at a volume of €750 billion of eligible private and public securities throughout this year, and longer if needed.  The ECB also aims to mitigate the impact of the crisis on the funding conditions of businesses and banks. For the same, it has decided to divert a considerable fraction of the additional €120 billion purchase envelope under the Asset Purchase Programmes (APP), as well as of the PEPP, for eligible private sector bonds. However, one cannot turn a blind eye to the fact that the bank has already been conducting purchases of government bonds, and now, it does not have much to re-purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, measures to ensure that the banks remain effective carriers of the monetary policy of the ECB have been introduced. The enhanced Targeted Longer-Term Refinancing Operations (TLTROs), as well as a comprehensive set of collateral easing measures, form part of this component.  The interest rate on all targeted TLTROs was reduced by 25 basis points to -0.5% from June 2020 to June 2021. Measures to ensure the solvency of banks by holding up the role of lender of the last resort to the banks which will help the ECB drive the way for economic growth. This becomes all the more necessary considering that the European economy is majorly a bank-based economy than a financial market one, so just supporting the financial markets would not help alleviate the effects of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measures for small and medium-sized firms are equally necessary, which include bank lending and loan guarantee schemes to protect the already overdrawn credit lines by cash strapped firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Italy, for example, bank lending conditions for firms remained remarkably resilient in recent years despite significant swings in market-based funding conditions of the banks and firms. Again, the measures can provide a valuable bridge to the future and help keep aggregate external funding costs of firms stable until the economy recovers and uncertainty diminishes further. This also includes accepting a wider range of assets as collaterals from small and medium-sized firms along with consistently working on the liquidity conditions of the banks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the ECB fails to improve liquidity indirectly through these measures, it always has the option to exercise its right to issue ‘helicopter money’. This alternative would put the money straight into the ‘hands’ of the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through these measures, the ECB hopes to improve liquidity and market behaviour in the sovereign yield bonds market, which in turn form the basis of pricing of assets in the economy. The ECB uses the GDP-weighted Euro area government bond yield curve as a measure for the effectiveness of the economy, but currently, this curve has been badly disrupted. So the ECB will focus on stabilising this curve and reversing the steepness of the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, while the Eurozone faces an increasingly threatening risk of a slowdown in the economy, which can take years to recover from and get back to the normal levels, the ECB and various governments are taking steps to tackle this challenge. The cluster of countries has recovered from far worse situations in the past, like the global economic crisis of 2008, and emerged stronger than ever. It remains to be seen what other steps the European Union takes as a much worse crisis than COVID-19 awaits the global economy and how the relief package unravels for the Union.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kashish Jindal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Time and again, Ms Lagarde, the first President of the European Central Bank (ECB) warned the European Union (EU) governments against the COVID-19 pandemic turning into a calamity. The pressures have been mounting as the largest economies of the Eurozone like France and Italy crumble. The EU, one of the world’s largest economies, has decided to take certain measures via its monetary policy, however, the question is how much can the ECB afford?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Can Self-Reliance be the New Norm: A Take on India’s ‘Atma-nirbharata’</title>
      <link href="/Can-Self-Reliance-be-the-New-Norm" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can Self-Reliance be the New Norm: A Take on India’s ‘Atma-nirbharata’" />
      <published>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Can-Self-Reliance-be-the-New-Norm</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Can-Self-Reliance-be-the-New-Norm">&lt;p&gt;“To stand on one’s own feet” is how 10th-grade economics teachers sum up the concept of self-reliance. The thinking behind India’s advocacy for this concept is premised upon the scars of colonialism. However, with the liberalisation of the Indian economy by the Narasimha Rao-led government, the concept had practically faded away from Indian public policy discourse. 29 years later, with Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi calling upon Indians to ‘be vocal for local’ and emphasising self-reliance, it seems to be taking the centre-stage once again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-reliance can be defined as “dependence on one’s own natural resources to produce goods and services to satisfy the demand”. One of the many problems with this is that every economy faces a dearth of resources, which are inputs required to produce goods (and services). One rather famous quip in economics goes like this: ‘resources are limited, while [human] wants are unlimited’. Every nation cannot produce everything on a scale sufficient to meet its domestic demand. Even if we suppose, for argument’s sake, that we could achieve the impossible, it is important to realise that self-reliance is a dynamic concept. If you look at it, achieving self-reliance is to successfully meet the aggregate demand of all the people in an economy; that is, conforming production along the lines of consumers’ tastes and preferences. There is no guarantee that these tastes will remain constant (unless, of course, if states ‘determine’ tastes!). So, if one were to adhere to the definition of self-reliance, one ought to change production constantly, keeping pace with the change in tastes and demands of the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, the scarcity of resources prompts states to resort to protectionist measures so as to encourage local producers. There is no ruling-out of a misallocation of resources in such circumstances, due to lack of economies of scale (a resultant of protectionist policies). This leads to a drastic loss in the productivity of a country and results in a deadweight loss for society. To put this in perspective, let us look at the total factor productivity of India. Total Factor Production may be defined as the increase in the growth of output that can be attributed to factors other than capital and labour. This can be the result of many reasons including a change in the quality of inputs, new techniques of production, better management of resources, and so on. One study finds that the average total factor productivity growth was negative for the 1970’s, when protectionism was at its heyday. In fact, there were frequent instances of negative growth in total factor production (where total factor production fell below zero) before 1991. Only after reforms, did the metric pick up pace, remaining positive throughout. From 2001-2008, total factor production grew at an average of 3.36%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second impact of protectionist measures is that the cost of production is (relatively) high and results in higher prices for the consumers. Why should a government, in the name of self-sufficiency, let its consumers pay a higher price for a good that would be available for a cheaper price when imported? This certainly is not how a rational entity would (or should) behave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The definition of self-reliance also begs the question of who is to determine the scale and intensity of production to achieve this self-reliance and how is this to be determined. If history is any guide, this is often determined by the state. And this means curtailing of choices on the part of the consumer and a massive involvement of the government in the supply side or the production side. It implies that the allocation of resources is controlled by the government and every producer (or entrepreneur) relies heavily on the government to take any decision. This control is exercised by the way of issuing licenses. The infamously dubbed practice of ‘license raj’ is exactly this. This can also discourage potential entrepreneurs from coming forward to start a business. Accepting this excessive government control would mean that bureaucrats, with no experience in business management whatsoever, would run the businesses rather than people competent to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidently, this is not the type of self-reliance a country should be aiming for. A country should be aiming at self-reliance in terms of human capital. In today’s global world, ideas and innovation are what sets a country apart. As renowned economist and Nobel laureate Paul Romer said, “&lt;em&gt;Growth springs from better recipes, not just from better cooking&lt;/em&gt;”. His view was that ideas of non-rival character, generated by profit-maximising entrepreneurs will lead to economic growth. This emphasises the role of human capital in the course of economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, for many reasons, there has been a constant outflow of human capital from our country to advanced nations like the US and the UK. It is crucial for India to recognise that every emigrant is productivity lost and innovation foregone. So, when I say self-reliance on human capital, I mean the creation of institutions of the highest excellence to truly harness human capital. However, the disappointing budget allocation for education by the Indian government (4.6% of the GDP in 2019-2020) shows that it has no plans to improve in this specific sector. India ought to increase education spending and allocate (and disburse) more funds toward PhD research, which are now sparse and available mainly for technology courses. Only self-reliance in terms of human capital is sustaining and yields increasing returns and hence should be a priority for the government. This is important to arrest the outflow of human capital out of the country whether for studies or permanent migration.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“To stand on one’s own feet” is how 10th-grade economics teachers sum up the concept of self-reliance. The thinking behind India’s advocacy for this concept is premised upon the scars of colonialism. However, with the liberalisation of the Indian economy by the Narasimha Rao-led government, the concept had practically faded away from Indian public policy discourse. 29 years later, with Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi calling upon Indians to ‘be vocal for local’ and emphasising self-reliance, it seems to be taking the centre-stage once again.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">China’s Banking Assets: A Recipe for Financial Crisis</title>
      <link href="/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="China’s Banking Assets: A Recipe for Financial Crisis" />
      <published>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis">&lt;p&gt;The global economy finds itself in a synchronised slowdown, with growth downgraded to as low as 3% in 2019, the lowest since the Global Financial Crisis. Adding to the economic tensions is COVID-19, which has brought the world economies to a near shutdown phase as they adopt preventive measures inclusive of complete lockdowns. What is more concerning is the fact that the two major engines of global growth, the United States of America and China, are the worst hit among many others. What makes the economic crisis worse in China? It is the worsening predicament of the banking sector which becomes a matter of immediate concern as China’s banking sector is three times larger than the size of its entire economy. The gigantic Chinese banking sector is capable of dwarfing out banking sectors in other parts of the world, including that of the United States of America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2019 China Financial Stability Report published by the People’s Bank of China officially deems 586 out of 4,379 Chinese lenders to be ‘high-risk’. The figures came into light only after the failure of a third bank within three months as national economic growth manifested a 30-year low. The Hengfeng Bank has become the third bank, after Baoshang Bank and Bank of Jinzhou, to suffer an economic collapse after a $40 trillion debt. But the Chinese government isn’t exceedingly famous for its honesty and transparency, thus the reported figure is likely masking the true extent of the banking quandary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chinese government has bailed out many of the high risk lenders. Precarious private shareholders have been effectively replaced by the ones backed by the state, often weaker in terms of their finances. The fact that bailouts are offered only for companies whose bankruptcy has a grave adverse impact on the economy as a whole and not just on a specified sector, cannot be ignored. Moreover, any amount of bailout allocated to this sector will have a domino effect on the Chinese economy which will be several times greater. For instance, the banking system calls for a 5-6% bailout which is equal to 20-24% of the Chinese GDP. A bailout of 20% of the GDP is a non-viable deal for any economy, even if it is China. The numeric is a statement of the fact that any pebble aimed at the banking sector shall bring ripples to the entire economy that in turn will shake China’s status of being a global economic power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The People’s Bank of China conducted a stress test in the first half of 2019 on 1,171 commercial banks, 7.7% were stated to be at ‘extreme risk’ and deemed incapable of absorbing even a light shock, 13.6% will probably not be able to endure the financial crisis that shall follow. In November, Yingkou Coastal Bank and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scmp.com/economy/china-economy/article/3035596/wechat-rumour-sparks-run-rural-chinese-bank-fresh-sign&quot;&gt;Yichuan Rural Commercial Bank&lt;/a&gt; – despite boasting healthy capital adequacy ratios – suffered bank runs as customers rushed to withdraw cash, fearing that the banks would close down, displaying a lack of confidence in banking institutions. The current situation is very similar to the one that cropped up in the late 1990’s. Towards the end of 1997, 20% of the main banks were non-performing, which was equivalent to a value of ¥1.19 trillion on the books of state-owned banks, which was deemed to be equal to 15.6% of the GDP. In order to resolve these crises and recapitalise the banks, ¥270 billion of special government bonds were issued and injected by August 1998. Walking on the same rope, the Chinese government is peddling its way through the crisis by adopting a somewhat similar technique. Today, the interbank market has been injected with around ¥2 trillion by the People’s Bank of China after the Baoshang Bank collapse. Along with this, a helping hand of the sovereign fund, China Investment Corporation, the Central Huijin Investment Company is injecting ¥60 billion into Hengfeng Bank. One of the 12 nationwide joint-stock banks in China, Hengfeng Bank is stacked up with non-performing loans and the situation became grimmer as the bank’s former president was handed out a death sentence for purloining funds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the similarities, overlooking the different macroeconomic situation shall prove fatal to the Chinese economy in the present scenario. The key antidote for the crisis back then was the spurt of hyper economic growth in the early 2000’s. If China wants to avoid tormenting its economy with the inevitability of bad loans and its weakening banking structure, it will have to aim for a masterful economic growth. However, this stands as a challenge with the outbreak of COVID-19 and its likely aftermath on the global economy. Secondly, continuous evolution over the years has resulted in an entwined and fragile banking structure. The financial system in modern times has given rise to an integrated market that ensures banking transactions are speeded up and are facile in nature. Since the speed of transactions and their impact on the economy is brisk, it also means that any kind of shock in the structure is transmitted faster than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The corporate and interbank customers suffer heavy losses, the volume of negotiable certificates of deposit—which are securities traded between financial institutions for short-term liquidity—has plunged by 90%. The situation threatens to cause the entire banking system to seize up as small and medium-sized banks are heavily dependent on liquidity in the interbank market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crisis should be an eye-opener for the administration as it calls for reforms in the entire financial system which has been overreliant on its banking sector for channeling funds. The fact that the financial structure has changed barely in the last fourteen years is an explanation for the crisis at hand. The world continues to keep a close watch on China, as this crisis is far too big to ignore because any large scale disruption in the driving engine of the global economy will lead the other economies into recession.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The global economy finds itself in a synchronised slowdown, with growth downgraded to as low as 3% in 2019, the lowest since the Global Financial Crisis. Adding to the economic tensions is COVID-19, which has brought the world economies to a near shutdown phase as they adopt preventive measures inclusive of complete lockdowns. What is more concerning is the fact that the two major engines of global growth, the United States of America and China, are the worst hit among many others. What makes the economic crisis worse in China? It is the worsening predicament of the banking sector which becomes a matter of immediate concern as China’s banking sector is three times larger than the size of its entire economy. The gigantic Chinese banking sector is capable of dwarfing out banking sectors in other parts of the world, including that of the United States of America.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Know Your Worth</title>
      <link href="/Know-Your-Worth" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Know Your Worth" />
      <published>2020-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Know-Your-Worth</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Know-Your-Worth">&lt;p&gt;I wonder sometimes whether people, in their daily lives, ponder over the functionalities that help us exist as citizens. How does the worth of my country depend on my income? I place my faith in the system to consider how various decisions will affect me before assessing the country’s human capital or even formulating the annual budget. And when I place my faith in the system, I am also hopeful of the judicial system to come to my rescue if I am faced with injustice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But how do I know if the details of my income or personal life will be taken into account when I am standing in the court of law?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is when ‘Forensic Economics’ comes into play. Conceived as economics applied to legal matters, forensic economics assesses major issues regarding economic damages in the context of litigation. It is a broad discipline that applies economic theories and methods to matters which are subject to legal review. A forensic economist creates an alternative world with assumptions, wherein the particular citizen is not faced with injustice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand better where Forensic Economics can be applied in a citizen’s daily life, we will use the most widely accepted defining factor of an individual’s life, that is, ‘work’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worth of a citizen, economically, can be found out by measuring his/her human capital. In order to measure that, one is required to estimate the work-life expectancy of an individual. Now the question is: &lt;em&gt;What is work-life expectancy?&lt;/em&gt; As the word itself suggests, it is the number of years an individual is expected to be in the workforce. The factors that affect each individual’s work-life expectancy include education attained, race, marital status, parental status, and, most importantly, gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economists resort to the approach of Forensic Economics to be able to measure an individual’s work-life expectancy, which is contingent on the underlying factors of the individual’s personal life. Under this, they establish the fact that work is not restricted to being involved in only paid employment, but also unpaid non-market work, which also holds certain economic value, thereby, defining ‘total work-life expectancy’ as a sum of market work and non-market work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us establish two imaginary individuals to make our observation simpler: Sheila, a woman, and Joel, a man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gender as a factor of their ‘total work-life expectancy’&lt;/em&gt;: The idea that taking care of a household or family is actual work is uncontested and women lead men in that activity. Many times the reason people usually cite for not participating in market work is taking care of household or family. Let’s consider here that both Joel and Sheila are between the ages of 18 to 24. Using the approach of forensic economics, it is found out that the maximum number of men who take care of their households belong to the age group of 18 to 24. However, as we start moving up the total percentage of men participating in non-market work reduces. On the contrary, the percentage of women participating in non-market work starts rising from 18 to 24 and reaches its peak in the age group of 30 to 34, after which it starts to decline. Therefore, a 25-year-old Joel would have about 35 years of market work-life and 1 year of non-market work-life remaining, whereas a 25-year-old Sheila would have about 30 years of market work-life and 6 years of non-market work-life. Both their ‘total work-life expectancy’ would equal 36 years but the difference lies in the market and non-market work based on their gender. This conclusion has been drawn from the Markov Increment Decrement Model (MID).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Race, education, and marriage as factors of their ‘total work-life expectancy’&lt;/em&gt;: The factors of race, education, and marital status of an individual are inherently intertwined in determining his/her work-life expectancy. Let us assume that Sheila is a 30-year-old white woman and X is a non-white woman. If both, Sheila and X, have educational qualifications of less than a high school degree then, Sheila’s work-life expectancy will exceed that of X by only a year. Conversely, if both Sheila and X are employed and have high school degrees, the work-life expectancy of Sheila will exceed that of X by over two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if we consider Joel to be a 30-year-old white man and Y to be a non-white man, we get different results. If both, Joel and Y, have educational qualifications of less than a high school degree, they get the same result as Sheila and X. However, if Joel and Y (both single) have high school degrees, then the work-life expectancy for Joel exceeds that of Y by around 4 years; and by 3.5 years if both men were married. This acute difference between white and non-white men is essentially because men tend to face more discrimination on the basis of their race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There exists a negative relationship between marriage and the work-life expectancy of women. Generally, women of all races face a setback in their market work participation post-marriage. Women with higher degrees face a larger setback than those with lower or no degree at all. This is largely because of two reasons– (a) women tend to be more productive in non-market or household work, and (b) women have a lesser dilemma to face in terms of opportunity cost because women already get lesser pay in comparison to their male counterparts. This leads me to establish the fact that the relationship between marriage and work-life expectancy for men is essentially positive. The work-life expectancy of a married white man exceeds that of an unmarried white man by about 3 years, and a married non-white man has a work-life expectancy of about 4 years more than an unmarried non-white man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Parental status as a factor of their ‘total work-life expectancy’&lt;/em&gt;: Let us suppose that Sheila wants to bear a child, but she also wants to keep her work-life expectancy high. To achieve that, she turns to Forensic Economics and realises that the work-life expectancy of a single mother exceeds that of a married mother by 2-3 years. On the contrary, Joel realises that a married man’s work-life expectancy changes negligibly in the case of a child but changes considerably if he chooses to be a single father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having analysed the most basic underlying factors to the work-life expectancy of individuals, it is imperative to establish the fact that the aforementioned observations were made using the Markov Increment Decrement Model (MID) under Forensic Economics. This brings us to the conclusion that when the productivity of non-market work is recognised, the work-life expectancy of women is negligibly different than that of men, which busts the myth that men are more productive than women. Therefore, we come to where we started off: the worth of a citizen is measured only after taking into account what I, as an individual citizen, possess with regard to my personal life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And hence, the deliberation ends.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I wonder sometimes whether people, in their daily lives, ponder over the functionalities that help us exist as citizens. How does the worth of my country depend on my income? I place my faith in the system to consider how various decisions will affect me before assessing the country’s human capital or even formulating the annual budget. And when I place my faith in the system, I am also hopeful of the judicial system to come to my rescue if I am faced with injustice.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Rational Pirates</title>
      <link href="/The-Rational-Pirates" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rational Pirates" />
      <published>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Rational-Pirates</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Rational-Pirates">&lt;p&gt;So today while watching videos on YouTube, (which is what I am usually doing almost every second while I am not busy) I came across a brilliant riddle. I clicked on the video and found out that it involved game theory and behavioural economics, and that really fascinated me. I wanted to share the riddle with you, and try to explain and help you better understand the concept of game theory. First of all, you need to know what game theory actually means. Simply kept, game theory is a theoretical structure for understanding social situations among competing players. In some respects, game theory is the science of ‘strategic play’, or at least the optimal decision-making of competing players in a situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I would like to share the riddle with you and try to explain the solution and how game theory can help us in various situations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a good day to be a pirate. Andrew and his 4 mates, Brandon, Christian, David and Edmund have struck gold, a chest with 100 coins. But now, they must divide up the treasure according to the pirate code. The code is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the captain, Andrew gets to propose first about how to distribute the coins. Then, each pirate including Andrew himself gets to vote either ‘yes’ or ‘no’. If the vote passes, or if there is a tie, the coins are divided according to the plan proposed by Andrew, but if the majority votes ‘no’, Andrew must walk the plank into the deep sea and Brandon becomes the captain. Then, Brandon gets to propose a new distribution and all remaining pirates would vote again. If his plan is rejected, he walks the plank too and Christian takes his place. This process repeats with the captain’s hat moving to David and then to Edmund until either a proposal is accepted or there is only one pirate left.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each pirate’s primary objective is to stay alive while getting as much gold as possible. But since they are pirates, none of them trust each other so they can’t really collaborate in advance.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If anyone thinks they will end up with the same amount of gold in two different scenarios, they will vote to make the captain walk the plank just for fun.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, each pirate is excellent at logical thinking and knows that the other pirates are too.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question here is, what distribution should Andrew propose to make sure he lives and gets as much gold as possible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we follow our intuition, it seems like Andrew should try to bribe other pirates with most of the gold to increase the chances of his plan being accepted or maybe to propose a distribution like 40-30-20-10-0 or any other combination for that matter and hope for the best, but it turns out Andrew can do much better than that. Let’s have a look at the solution!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like you know, the pirates know each other to be top-notch logicians. So, when each one votes, they won’t just be thinking about the current proposal but about all the possible outcomes down the line. Moreover, because the rank order is known in advance, each one of them can accurately predict how others would vote in any situation and adjust their own votes accordingly. Since Edmund is last, he has the most outcomes to consider so let us start by following his thought process. He would reason out by working backward from the last possible scenario with only him and David remaining. David would obviously propose to keep all the gold and Edmund’s one vote would not be enough to override it. So, Edmund wants to avoid this situation at all costs. Now, we move to the previous decision point with three pirates left and Christian making the proposal. Everyone knows that if he is outvoted, the decision shifts to David who would then get all the gold while Edmund gets nothing. So to secure Edmund’s vote, Christian only needs to offer slightly more than nothing, that is, one coin. Since this ensures his support, Christian doesn’t need to offer David anything at all. What if there were 4 pirates? As captain, Brandon would still only need one other vote for his plan to pass. He knows that David wouldn’t want the decision to pass to Christian so he would offer David one coin for his support with nothing for Christian or Edmund. Going forward with other possible scenarios, now we’re back at the initial vote with all 5 pirates standing. Having considered all the other scenarios, Andrew knows that if he goes overboard, the decision comes down to Brandon which would be bad news for Christian and Edmund, so he offers one coin each to them, thus, keeping 98 for himself. Brandon and David vote ‘no’, but Christian and Edmund grudgingly vote ‘yes’, knowing that the alternative would be worse for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pirate game involves some amusing concepts from game theory. One is the concept of ‘common knowledge’ where each person is aware of what the others know and uses this to predict their reasoning and final distribution. Had it been the case where the pirates didn’t know the intellectual capabilities of each other, the situation would flip altogether and there would have been no accurate solution to the riddle but fortunately that wasn’t the case. This is a classic example of ‘Nash-equilibrium’, where each player knows every other player’s strategy and chooses them accordingly. Even though it may lead to a worse outcome for everyone than cooperating would, no individual player can benefit by changing their strategy. So, it seems like Andrew gets to keep most of the gold coins (98 to be precise) and the other pirates might need to find better ways to use those impressive logic skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole intention behind this article was to explain to you how a simple concept of game theory can help you gain more in life. The example here was not an appropriate one for you to relate to in real life (unless you obviously decide to become a pirate) but there are several other instances in which it might help you. The decision involving whether to go for a movie or a concert with your friends also involves game theory where we know what the other person wants and we try to manipulate the final result so as to do what we want. Also, in financial markets, the decision to invest in a certain bond or a stock after having all the relevant information about the company involves game theory as well. By investing in the company, you become a player and what the company does with that investment determines your gain or loss. These are just some cases where you can utilise game theory, the scope of it is wide-ranging and unexplored, and left for you to discover. As the British writer Charles Lamb rightly said, “Man is a gaming animal. He must always be trying to get better in something or other.”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">So today while watching videos on YouTube, (which is what I am usually doing almost every second while I am not busy) I came across a brilliant riddle. I clicked on the video and found out that it involved game theory and behavioural economics, and that really fascinated me. I wanted to share the riddle with you, and try to explain and help you better understand the concept of game theory. First of all, you need to know what game theory actually means. Simply kept, game theory is a theoretical structure for understanding social situations among competing players. In some respects, game theory is the science of ‘strategic play’, or at least the optimal decision-making of competing players in a situation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
