<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/economics/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-02-08T18:37:10+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/economics/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How does Finance Benefit Society?</title>
      <link href="/How-Finance-Benefits-Society" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How does Finance Benefit Society?" />
      <published>2019-02-07T04:28:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T04:28:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/How-Finance-Benefits-Society</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/How-Finance-Benefits-Society">&lt;p&gt;There are several theories that illustrate the crucial role played by finance in the world today: managing risk, providing important price signals, curbing agency problems and eliminating informational irregularities being the most essential ones. There is adequate evidence that demonstrates how finance fosters growth, promotes entrepreneurship, favours education, alleviates poverty and reduces inequality. Yet, this impression is not subscribed to by society at large. The global financial crisis, that erupted in September 2008, propelled economies around the world towards recession. It destabilized several major financial institutions in the US and elsewhere, while severely damaging the global economy. A sample of American adults was surveyed in 2015, three years after the end of the Great Recession and seven years since the financial crisis. They were asked: &lt;i&gt;“Overall, how much, if at all, do you think the US financial system benefits or hurts the US economy?”&lt;/i&gt; An aggregate of 48% responded that finance hurts the US economy; only 34% said that it benefits it, while the remaining could not comment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sentiment is not just the result of the crisis: throughout history, finance has been perceived as a ‘rent-seeking’ activity. The aftermath of the 2007-08 financial crisis has only worsened this view. Prohibitions against finance date as far back as the Old Testament. From Libor fixing to exchange rate manipulation; from gold price rigging to outright financial fraud in subprime mortgages, not a day passes without news of a fresh financial scandal. But, why does this happen? Financial capitalism periodically undergoes a systemic crisis. Kotz (2008) validates that the crisis of 2008 exemplified a &lt;em&gt;“neoliberal form of capitalism”&lt;/em&gt;. This capitalism intensively promoted economic liberalization policies such as privatisation, deregulation and free trade. And this process disproportionately and perversely empowered financial institutions, hence helping the sector create a profiteering monopoly of its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result was intricately planned scandals that duped customers of their savings, retirement funds, pensions, and homes; while financial institutions continued to build their empire on the relics of their crimes. The seeds of the 2008 catastrophe were sown in the credit explosion that peaked in 2007, which was characterised by the reckless dispensing of subprime mortgages, a consequent growth of the housing bubble, and amplified predatory lending and overleveraging by investment banks. Financial institutions in the US had placed bets against Collateralized Debt Obligations (CDOs), they had deliberately sold to customers who couldn’t afford to pay back. The implication? Billions in profits for investors and insurance companies. Until, of  course, the financial sector witnessed panic and turmoil following the bankruptcy of Lehman Brothers and Merrill Lynch, and government seizures of Fannie Mae, Freddie Mac, and AIG. Prices across commodities dropped, employment fell drastically, the cost of corporate and bank borrowing rose substantially, and financial market volatility rose to levels that have rarely been seen. The &lt;em&gt;“neo-capitalistic era”&lt;/em&gt; ended up sponsoring misery and deprivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what aided this wreckage? Over the years, the financial sector has been able to apprehend the political system of countries across the globe. CEOs and other top executives of banks and other financial institutions end up holding important positions in government administration, thus endowing exclusive benefits to the financial sector. Ken Lay, the Chairman of Enron, was very close to the Bush family. He serves as a pertinent representation of the border where finance meets politics. George H. Bush had helped &lt;em&gt;“Kennie Boy”&lt;/em&gt; secure subsidies and other benefits for the company. Ken had also been proclaimed mascot of the new era of deregulation. To continue a favourable relationship with the government, Enron had made enormous financial contributions towards the Presidential campaign of Bush Jr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another accurate example of the finance-politics companionship was the merger of Citicorp and Travelers to form Citigroup, which violated the Glass-Steagall Act. However, instead of criminally prosecuting Citigroup, Congress passed the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act of 1999, legalizing the merger. Analogously, in May 1999, Brooksley Born of the Commodity Futures Trading Commission (CFTC) had proposed legislation to regulate the derivatives market. In response to this, the then Secretary of the Treasury, Larry Summers, instructed her to withdraw her proposal immediately. Furthermore, Alan Greenspan, Robert Rubin, and US Securities and Exchange Commission Chairman, Arthur Levitt, came up with a joint-statement condemning Born’s proposal. Finally, to ice the cake, The Commodity Futures Modernization Act of 2000 was passed by the Congress, which banned the regulation of derivatives. All this had been done to maintain the profit standards of the unregulated market. These examples point to the immoral and corrupt disposition of &lt;em&gt;“Wall Street governments”&lt;/em&gt;. There seems to be a blatant disregard for the impact their actions have on society. Not a single financial services firm had been prosecuted criminally for securities or accounting fraud till mid-2010. The agencies that blindly distributed ‘Triple-A’ ratings to disastrous loans had also not been castigated appropriately. Kristin Davis’ account of the 10,000 frequent customers in her prostitution racket, 40-50% of which were from Wall Street, enlightens us on how the financial sector is still indulging in complete hedonism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we readily tend to associate finance with the mortgage and debt hangover that plagued the world back in 2008. However, notwithstanding anything said previously in this article, finance should not be condemned as a system of recklessness. Even though critics are right in some of their accusations, we cannot term finance a curse for the society. It might not be a boon either, but we can improve it through transformation and reform; these changes should focus on broadening the scope of financial innovation rather than confining it. We must work towards achieving a refined, more fundamental, expedient, and sustainable form of finance that serves the society before serving itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finance is meant to extend support to social goals – greater employment, economic welfare, wider education, skill development and equality, among several other things. It should be seen as a tool that can, in fact, ensure a more prosperous and unregimented society. I believe that, while financial capitalism and financial innovation collectively shape the way forward, regulations, restrictions, corporate governance, and risk management should be pragmatically enforced in order to help financial institutions function in the interests of society. It can be thought of as merely codifying rules of a game; rules that are best conceived by the players of the game themselves. As Shiller (2013) states, &lt;i&gt;“imperfect as our financial system is, I still find myself admiring it for what it does, and imagining how much more impressive it can be in the future.”&lt;/i&gt; Think about insurance: thriving in modern society would be impossible without it, or, for that matter, banking, mortgages or even pensions. It is an interesting yet unknown fact that the word ‘finance’ has actually been derived from a classical Latin word for ‘goal’. It reflects our interests in careers, hopes for our families, ambitions for our businesses, aspirations for our culture, and ideals for our society. Finance does not tell us what the goals are; finance itself does not embody a goal either. Finance is the goal…&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shivang Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There are several theories that illustrate the crucial role played by finance in the world today: managing risk, providing important price signals, curbing agency problems and eliminating informational irregularities being the most essential ones. There is adequate evidence that demonstrates how finance fosters growth, promotes entrepreneurship, favours education, alleviates poverty and reduces inequality. Yet, this impression is not subscribed to by society at large. The global financial crisis, that erupted in September 2008, propelled economies around the world towards recession. It destabilized several major financial institutions in the US and elsewhere, while severely damaging the global economy. A sample of American adults was surveyed in 2015, three years after the end of the Great Recession and seven years since the financial crisis. They were asked: “Overall, how much, if at all, do you think the US financial system benefits or hurts the US economy?” An aggregate of 48% responded that finance hurts the US economy; only 34% said that it benefits it, while the remaining could not comment.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Behind the Veil of Economic Growth</title>
      <link href="/Behind-the_Veil-of-Economic-Growth" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Behind the Veil of Economic Growth" />
      <published>2019-02-07T04:15:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T04:15:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Behind-the_Veil-of-Economic-Growth</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Behind-the_Veil-of-Economic-Growth">&lt;p&gt;India’s short period of fast economic growth has been considerably eulogized. We are now the fastest growing economy in the world—an achievement that we pat ourselves on the back for. Yet, this shred of data is difficult to embrace after being a witness to ground realities. The rapid growth has manifested itself in a plethora of opportunities for many while leaving many others in conditions that seem to be helpless. One can’t help but feel something’s amiss in the “Indian Growth Story” narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the 21st century, there will be 1.5 billion Indians and 1.1 billion Chinese. Simply as a consequence of the number of people, India will continue to be among the world’s biggest economic powers. This will hold true even if the economy stagnates sometime in the future, or even if India’s efforts to become a middle-income country fall behind. In fact, we could be the largest economy with slightly more than two-thirds of China’s current per capita GDP by that time. It is well established that economic prosperity doesn’t imply people lead satisfied lives. The aspect which has failed to come to the forefront is how rapid economic growth doesn’t necessarily translate to better living standards. Their relationship hinges on how the government employs public revenue generated from economic growth. Unless the expenditure facilitates advancement in human capabilities, it isn’t really ‘growth’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While India is climbing up the ladder of per capita income, it is slipping down when it comes to social indicators. Public revenue generated from economic growth has not been used to expand social and physical infrastructure in a well-planned manner. While the middle and upper-middle classes have fared extremely well in terms of improved standards of living during the last three decades, the same cannot be said for those employed in the informal sector, who make up to 81% of India’s 487 million person workforce. For them, the pace of growth has been excruciatingly slow. Growth in real wages for poorer sections of the population has been severely lacking when compared to other developing economies. The reason lies in the failure to generate adequate employment, in what is best described as “jobless growth”. Rapid economic growth was led by the services sector. Since growth was concentrated in skill-intensive sectors rather than labour-intensive sectors, the educated labour force has been able to earn much higher wages and salaries. The rest of the workforce is employed in activities where wages and productivity have remained very low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Official poverty estimates tell us that the poverty rate in the country has nearly halved in the ten years between 2006 and 2016. This appears to be a huge leap at first. However, as the density effect explains, since there are so many people just a little below the poverty line in India, a tiny increase in per capita income is enough to lift large numbers above the poverty line. It also explains why the official poverty line is so low (₹32 per day for rural India and ₹47 per day for urban India, which is equivalent to less than a US dollar per day). One may argue that India cannot rely on income growth alone to transform living conditions. But, the concern remains that India is not doing well in many respects even in comparison with some of the poorest countries in the world. India’s Human Development Index (HDI) ranking is 130 out of 189 countries, with a score of 0.64. Moreover, when inequality-adjusted HDI is considered, this value further falls by another 26.8%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “big brother” of the South Asian subcontinent is falling behind every other South Asian country in terms of many social indicators, notwithstanding it does much better in the growth of per capita income. Despite being much poorer than India, Bangladesh does better in terms of life expectancy, Infant Mortality Rate (IMR), immunization rates, Total Fertility Rate (TFR) and access to improved sanitation. It also fares better in the data on mean years of schooling and female literacy. Perhaps more intriguing is the case of Nepal, a country enmeshed in unstable politics and governance. In 1990, Nepal was severely lagging behind in terms of every development indicator. Over the years it has caught up with India and even overtaken it in maternal mortality, infant immunization, and female literacy. The comparison with Pakistan is more favourable to India, but not particularly flattering either. In 1990, only Sri Lanka had better social indicators than India. Now India appears to be the second worst in the region, ahead of Pakistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although India is the poorest among the BRICS countries, much more needs to be done to bridge these gaps than to catch up in terms of per capita income. When compared with other BRICS countries which have the commonality of large populations, India lags abysmally behind in every social indicator, especially undernourishment among children below 5, child immunization rates, and universal literacy. Experiences within the country itself have been starkly contrasting. The Multi-Dimensional Poverty Index (MPI) places the North Indian states of Bihar and Jharkhand in the same category as Mozambique and Sierra Leone. However, the growth model in states like Kerala, Himachal Pradesh and Tamil Nadu continue to serve as examples of how economic growth can be complemented with sustained successful social policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What clearly works for rapid social progress is the universal provision of essential public services: school education, primary health care, electricity connections, sanitation and drinking water. Their provision has to be facilitated by an efficient administration that takes into account the structure of social inequality in the area while ensuring the involvement of local communities. Among BRICS countries, India is the only one that hasn’t gone through a phase of expansion of public support (elementary education, health care, social security) or economic redistribution. It also has the lowest expenditure on education and health, which have yet again taken a back seat in the face of a populist budget. The nation has much to learn from the policies and achievements of two of its neighbouring countries. From Bangladesh, it must learn female literacy programmes, microcredit and community mobilization to bring about social change. And from Sri Lanka, it should adopt the health care and public schooling system. India can have a serious advantage over these countries in implementing these same programmes. As Amartya Sen phrased it, “A poor country may have less money to spend on healthcare but it also needs to spend less to provide the same labour-intensive services.” Healthcare and education are primarily labour-intensive activities. Since wages are low in populous and poor India, these community building services can be provided at low costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions about the nature of economic growth require much greater attention than they receive. Recently, a leaked government report put India’s unemployment rate on a 45-year high. Prominent NSSO employees (the institution who had prepared the report) had resigned in protest because the government was not releasing the report. The government’s reply to the leaked report? “You can’t be growing at 7.2% and say no jobs are being created.” A discussion on India’s economy lacks sufficient inquiry on the provision of jobs to the 1 million people who reach working age &lt;i&gt;every month&lt;/i&gt;, or the transparency on data for economic indicators, or the massive improvement required in malnutrition indicators. Unless we end our obsession with GDP numbers, we cannot expect our governments to focus on social indicators. After all, what a democratic system achieves depends largely on the issues that are brought into political engagement.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reema Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">India’s short period of fast economic growth has been considerably eulogized. We are now the fastest growing economy in the world—an achievement that we pat ourselves on the back for. Yet, this shred of data is difficult to embrace after being a witness to ground realities. The rapid growth has manifested itself in a plethora of opportunities for many while leaving many others in conditions that seem to be helpless. One can’t help but feel something’s amiss in the “Indian Growth Story” narrative.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Tobacco and Marketing: An Anomaly?</title>
      <link href="/Tobacco-and-Marketing-An-Anomaly" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tobacco and Marketing: An Anomaly?" />
      <published>2019-02-07T03:57:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T03:57:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Tobacco-and-Marketing-An-Anomaly</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Tobacco-and-Marketing-An-Anomaly">&lt;p&gt;In September 1995, Pierre Omidyar, a 28-year old computer programmer finished the code for what would soon become eBay. Searching around for a test item, he put up a broken laser pointer for sale with the base price as $1. The laser pointer sold for $14.83. Shocked, Omidyar contacted the winning bidder to make sure he understood the laser pointer was broken. “Oh yes”, the bidder replied, “I am a collector of broken laser pointers.” Trade creates value by moving goods from people who value them less to people who value them more. Tobacco happens to be a product valued greatly by a variety of stakeholders. It is for this reason that we continue to trade and rampantly consume it in spite of its tribulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like the laser pointer, tobacco products are also ‘broken’ goods – unfit for use. Regardless, however, one can always find people wanting to purchase them, even if they have to bid high to acquire them. But, has anyone cared to wonder why? The answer to this question is obscure and complicated, yet evident and simple: &lt;i&gt;“They are cool, available, and addictive.”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are they cool? Well, celebrities endorse them in movies; Mickey Mouse, Popeye and The Flintstones on television. Why are they available? Probably because we want them, just as governments want their tax revenues and companies their profits. But they are addictive! Are McDonald’s, PUBG, and One Direction not? Tobacco products are like any other commodity. They have a demand and hence a supply. Now, in order to help demand meet supply, companies need to reach out to consumers by marketing themselves. These companies too, are like all other companies. They have a profit maximisation target and hence a purpose for existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, despite having brought the tobacco industry at par with other industries, can we permit it to be part of the same marketing ambit? Or can we even permit it to market its products in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earliest known advertisement in the United States was for the snuff and tobacco products of &amp;lt;P. Lorillard and Company and was placed in the New York daily papers in 1789. Advertising was an emerging concept, and tobacco-related advertisements were not seen as any different from those for other products: their negative impact on health was unknown at the time. American Tobacco was engaged in competitive advertising of its Bull Durham chewable tobacco leaves as well. Around the Great Depression, it ran campaigns like the &lt;i&gt;“Roll Your Own”&lt;/i&gt; campaign and boosted outdoor advertising by way of elegant wall paintings and graffiti. These cleverly designed advertisements were made to persuade the lower and middle-class masses to imitate the upper-class gentry by purchasing elite yet economical tobacco products: a bag of tobacco for just a nickel at the time. Through their &lt;i&gt;“Hit the Bull”&lt;/i&gt; campaign, the Blackwell Company was able to rope in baseball players to endorse their brand. If we observe carefully, such marketing techniques are not only ludicrous but also morally unacceptable today. An advertisement depicting class distinction would bring doom upon the company, and no sports person would endorse these products, parents would rush to scrape off wall paintings before their children could have a glance. Why is there this sudden change in our attitude towards tobacco? It is generally a legal substance after all, unless specifically prohibited as done in a few countries…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer lies in our awareness: I believe we are more informed about the dangers of tobacco than ever before. The first noteworthy scientific report concerning the dangers of cigarettes was published in 1964, by the Surgeon General of the United States. Terry (1964) illustrates important deductions by the Advisory Committee – smoking was found to be: “A cause of lung cancer and laryngeal cancer in men, a probable cause of lung cancer in women, the most important cause of chronic bronchitis.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senators in the US, thereafter, passed several laws to regulate the advertising of tobacco products. The Federal Cigarette Labeling and Advertising Act of 1965 mandated all cigarette boxes to come with a warning label. In 1971, there was a ban on the advertisement of tobacco products on television and radio. Countries like Australia have defeated giants like Philip Morris by legislating “plain packaging” of cigarettes in order to intensify the fight against tobacco. Very similar to a depiction in the movie &lt;i&gt;Thank you for Smoking&lt;/i&gt;(2005), cigarette companies in India have attempted partnering with Bollywood to get celebrities to promote smoking. The government has hence made it mandatory to include cautionary messages in films and music videos that show people smoking. This comes in response to cigarette companies trying to attract and indulge youngsters in embracing their poison. &lt;i&gt;“They try to hook our kids using cartoons and symbols.”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The global population of smokers increased from 721 million in 1980 to 967 million in 2012, and the number of cigarettes smoked has risen from 4.96 trillion to 6.25 trillion between the same time periods. Of the 1.22 billion smokers today, 1 billion of them live in developing or transitional economies. Rates of smoking have levelled off or declined in the developed world. In the developing world, tobacco consumption is rising by 3.4% every year. In 2002, about 20% of teens aged 13 to 15 smoked tobacco worldwide. Approximately 80,000 to 100,000 children in this age bracket begin smoking every day. Half of those who begin smoking in adolescent years are projected to go on to smoke for 15 to 20 years. Today’s teenager is tomorrow’s potential regular customer. It has been rightly said that &lt;i&gt;“tobacco takes care of its own”&lt;/i&gt; and own only: an invisible Invisible Hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Against all odds, we are striving to change the &lt;i&gt;“smoking is cool”&lt;/i&gt; notion, we are motivated to invent new kinds of alternatives that are not ‘addictive’ and also come up with treatments for lung diseases, but, in the face of our numerous measures to counter the tobacco menace, nothing really seems to be working. Probably because of its extensive ‘availability’ that no one is willing to put an end to. Why would they? The global spending, right from manufacturing cigarettes to treating the diseases they leave behind, is unbelievably enormous. The tobacco industry generates an income for not only its own farmers and employees but also other industries, their stakeholders, and governments at large. In 2014, tobacco companies spent more than $9 billion on marketing cigarettes and smokeless tobacco in the United States. This amount translates to nearly $25 million each day, or about $1 million every hour (Federal Trade Commission, 2016). Smoking-related illness in the United States costs more than $300 billion each year (US Department of Health and Human Services, 2014). Notwithstanding the economic wonders (including tax revenues) it is doing, only truly passionate, non-profit, non-governmental organizations are capable of opposing the ‘availability’ of tobacco. But, how many of these godly organizations actually exist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having intricately analyzed the trade mechanics of tobacco and its marketing approach, I can obviously agree that tobacco products do not qualify as ethically marketable products. I will certainly not provide marketing services to Big Tobacco or be one of those lawyers that protect cigarette companies in lawsuits. However, this being said, I also do not believe it is morally correct for us to deprive tobacco companies of access to marketing. Should it be regulated? Absolutely. Can we allow it to cater to all age groups? Absolutely not. But should we not ban its marketing completely? If and only if we are also banning cigarettes and all other forms of tobacco. Half-convinced that would never happen, I believe there at least needs to be stringent legislation on a code of conduct for tobacco firms to follow for advertisement of their products locally. What is ethical for one country might be the gravest of crimes for another. We cannot have a universal code of conduct in this aspect, nor can we decide for legal consumers: that would be morally presumptuous. After all, they have a choice of their own.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shivang Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In September 1995, Pierre Omidyar, a 28-year old computer programmer finished the code for what would soon become eBay. Searching around for a test item, he put up a broken laser pointer for sale with the base price as $1. The laser pointer sold for $14.83. Shocked, Omidyar contacted the winning bidder to make sure he understood the laser pointer was broken. “Oh yes”, the bidder replied, “I am a collector of broken laser pointers.” Trade creates value by moving goods from people who value them less to people who value them more. Tobacco happens to be a product valued greatly by a variety of stakeholders. It is for this reason that we continue to trade and rampantly consume it in spite of its tribulations.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">East Asia - The Lesson Learnt?</title>
      <link href="/East-Asia-The-Lesson-Learnt" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="East Asia - The Lesson Learnt?" />
      <published>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/East-Asia-The-Lesson-Learnt</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/East-Asia-The-Lesson-Learnt">&lt;p&gt;All human beings have an insatiable need to continuously develop themselves, be it monetarily, spiritually or physically. The same applies to economies, just that they crave GDP, HDI, and other economic indices. Over time, humans have understood that there is no shortcut to success, except hard work. But the irony remains that economies, which are run by these same humans, tend to forget this. In order to accelerate their economic growth, some economies like Indonesia, South Korea, Thailand, and Malaysia had turned towards various short-cut methods. While these methods help an economy to boom in the short run, they have adverse effects in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same happened with these East Asian economies. They witnessed exponential growth in the 1980’s and early 1990’s. But this quest for rapid growth and development lead to various cracks in the economy. Eventually, these cracks burst the growth bubble which led to severe impacts on the economy and dipping of growth rates. People, society, and the economy suffered. Therefore, what these economies needed now was &lt;i&gt;‘sustainable growth and development’&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/East-Asia-Growth-in-a-Bubble&quot;&gt;This was part 1 of the edition on East Asia&lt;/a&gt;. This part will focus on the question of whether the East Asian economies have learnt their lesson or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aftermath of the 1997 Asian Financial Crisis saw the end of many ruling political parties and policymakers. In most of these economies, long-standing governments were removed and replaced with new ones, peacefully in most of them, and in some, with force. The new governments took the help of the International Monetary Fund (IMF) to overcome their external debt crisis. The IMF proposed a series of bailout packages for these economies in return of austere monetary and fiscal measures to curb the damage. These measures included higher interest rates on loans, reduced government expenditure, restructuring of financial and banking sector, and a period of curbed international borrowings to reduce the overall debt in the economy. All East Asian economies except Indonesia accepted the bailout package proposed by the IMF. Indonesia, who didn’t accept the terms and conditions of the IMF, unofficially implemented the same in its economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Austerity measures had a devastating impact on the economy in the short term. Reduced government expenditure led to cuts in many social benefits and services provided by the governments to their people. There was reduced spending on healthcare, education and other socio-economic overheads which directly impacted the lives of citizens. Reduced sanctioning of loans led to reduced investment in infrastructure development projects. Thus, thousands of jobs were lost in the informal sector due to the unavailability of work. The citizens found themselves wanting new jobs with no government support behind them in this acute crisis. Naturally, this led to constant civil unrests and uprisings in these economies which was followed by frequent government changes. However, nothing could be done about this as this was for the “greater good”, according to the leaders of these economies, and more importantly, the IMF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These economies witnessed a major overhaul in the banking and financial sector as well. The banking sector was revamped with tighter regulations and policies in place. Several private banks, which had defaulted, were shut down, instead of being merged with other nationalized banks. This meant several thousand employees without a job, which furthered heightened the unemployment problem. New rules and regulations were also brought to keep a check on the amount of external debt being borrowed and ensured an adequate amount of liquidity and solvency in the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stringent measures were necessary to upgrade the economy and ensure its “sustainable growth and development”. However, a huge cost in terms of time, resources, and people had to be paid. These measures put the economy back by 5 years at least. While there was nominal growth in GDP in 1999, real growth in GDP was recorded only in 2002. This is when these East Asian economies regained the confidence of investors and the international community. A renewed flow of foreign capital finally provided the basis for long-term sustainable growth and development, which was slow and steady.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, the East Asian economies were careful not to commit the same mistake which dearly cost them during the 1997 Financial Crisis. They created and maintained huge amounts of International Reserves (IR). Basically, they stockpiled hard currency in order to ensure that there were no major fluctuations in their local currency in times of crisis. Such was the implementation of this policy that today these economies hold 19-20% of the world’s entire forex reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like a dramatic turnover, right? Not so fast, there is a slight problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;85% of trade by these economies is carried out in US Dollars. Moreover, 80% of their IR is made up of US Dollars. This makes these economies highly vulnerable to the monetary and fiscal policies of the United States. Basically, these economies are unguarded from any action that the US takes or any action which affects the US Dollar. This is why their trade cycles closely match with that of the US. Booms and busts in the US trade cycle are exactly reproduced in these economies. This is because, in times of recession, the interest rates in the US shoot up, which leads to outflow and flight of capital from these economies to the US. However, the great stock of forex reserves helps these economies in maintaining their exchange rates and nominal values of their foreign debt, keeping the situation in control. This is precisely what happened in the aftermath of the 2008 Recession. Thanks to the forex reserves, the situation was in control and these economies passed 2008 off as a normal blip in the trade cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, with predictions of another worldwide recession in 2020, and with the rise of the Chinese Renminbi as the currency of global choice, it is very interesting to see what would happen to these economies. Will these East Asian economies manage to stay on their path of slow and steady “sustainable growth and development”? Or, will the shortcut which they took by pegging all their trade and reserves to the US Dollar cost them dearly in the near future?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhishek Sancheti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">All human beings have an insatiable need to continuously develop themselves, be it monetarily, spiritually or physically. The same applies to economies, just that they crave GDP, HDI, and other economic indices. Over time, humans have understood that there is no shortcut to success, except hard work. But the irony remains that economies, which are run by these same humans, tend to forget this. In order to accelerate their economic growth, some economies like Indonesia, South Korea, Thailand, and Malaysia had turned towards various short-cut methods. While these methods help an economy to boom in the short run, they have adverse effects in the long run.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Bullpen on a Rollercoaster</title>
      <link href="/Bullpen-on-a-Rollercoaster" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bullpen on a Rollercoaster" />
      <published>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Bullpen-on-a-Rollercoaster</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Bullpen-on-a-Rollercoaster">&lt;p&gt;The convention of projecting the economic rise of the East over the West comes with its own ups and downs. The Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership or RCEP is trying to set up a free (not completely, but not important here) trade area between economies with different levels of openness. Consisting of India, China, Japan, South Korea, Australia, New Zealand, and the 10 ASEAN countries, RCEP (if signed) is set to be a major trading bloc in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ASEAN bloc, a major part of RCEP, has itself not been completely integrated despite two decades into its existence. The reasons are numerous and quite technical but I am going to pose a twisted version to the readers: why are they even together? Clearly, it is two things: trade and finance. After the 1990’s, they have understood that they all face the same problem, namely, market sentiments of western countries―the &lt;i&gt;wiseguys&lt;/i&gt; with the greenback. The idea of presenting a united front and avoiding a skewed economy which pulls down the entire region is at the heart of the ASEAN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In RCEP, however, different countries are at different places on the development curve, and economists can only ponder what they will prioritize upon reckoning with trouble. This can be extended to a related concern: which country is going to be the engine to which the economies chain themselves in RCEP? The core problem lies in the fact that RCEP is mismatch between developing economies and developed economies. To put it in a light manner, countries like India are the bride behind the veil and economies like Singapore play the groom. The bride is expected to keep the veil on for as long as possible and the groom is expected to act against that. And it is this skewered relationship which creates the confusion. Drawing parallels, the bride’s act of “&lt;i&gt;keeping the veil&lt;/i&gt;” symbolises the act of ‘protectionism’, while the groom’s act of trying to remove it symbolises greater ‘openness’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A topic where China has the smirk is the power of its political economy. Even though US tariffs have blistered China and the wound is still fresh. As is suspected, China is going into RCEP to expand its influence on the world economy. With the volatility of the Indian rupee (INR), oil prices and other assorted delicacies for a cancerous Current Account Deficit (CAD), Indians are sleeping through the negotiations with one eye open, pondering over the numbers but more importantly, over the political issues which have nothing but negative rents for the current Indian government. India is also in the cross-hairs due to the services-led structure of its economy. As there is no backstopping authority regarding RCEP, running huge trade deficits is not an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economics is simple here. It is an election year in India and the fiscal taps are going to open; and countries are sitting with their eyes fixed on this. A market as large as India, with an increased demand due to populist government spending, will be exactly what the ‘hawks’ in a free trade agreement would desire. In simple terms, excessive demand in India means more exports for other countries in RCEP. The cost? India’s CAD.
The moment India nudges on the services sector, labour arbitrage (body shopping) will open itself up. Pharmaceuticals too, are a big thorn in some countries’ beds thanks to India, which is referred to as the “&lt;i&gt;pharmacy of the developing world&lt;/i&gt;” due to the cheap generic medicines it can provide. While exporters might see India (with its young population) as a potential market to tap, India’s services and pharma industry themselves threaten to destroy local competition in many RCEP countries.  Add on to this the fact that India has not been a part of any major free trade agreement like this before, and you can see why India can be a problem for both the bloc and itself. India is both threatened (by an explosion of imports from RCEP) and a threat (thanks to its services and pharmaceuticals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, political stability and a quest for a quasi-hyper globalised trade acting along with inward-looking policy making, cannot go hand-in-hand. This is a serious fault line etching itself into existence. All countries want to cash the dividends but not face rents of such an action. There are various tools, from basic common sense to game theoretic models to prove that, with the potential problems/costs all countries face, the RCEP might lead to policies which are de facto tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may ask why am I being so pessimistic about RCEP? There are two reasons – firstly, I can see the chinks in the contract; and secondly, the winds in global trade have become strong. The world does need a major bloc (in terms of GDP) from the oriental side to put certain perspectives on the global macroeconomic spotlight, ranging from the composition of major international institutions to the skewness sewed into global policy actions. RCEP could be a forum for coordinated action and a backstop to the forceful push of adoption to the western macroeconomic framework. It can also provide an opportunity to end the age of capital imperialism. There are numerous reasons why RCEP should be an opportunity pursued but it doesn’t really look like it could be. To that end, I hope the friends see the milk and cookies after the fight on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Adarsh Agarwal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The convention of projecting the economic rise of the East over the West comes with its own ups and downs. The Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership or RCEP is trying to set up a free (not completely, but not important here) trade area between economies with different levels of openness. Consisting of India, China, Japan, South Korea, Australia, New Zealand, and the 10 ASEAN countries, RCEP (if signed) is set to be a major trading bloc in the world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How Oil Trickled Through the Decade</title>
      <link href="/How-Oil-Trickled-through-the-Decade" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Oil Trickled Through the Decade" />
      <published>2019-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/How-Oil-Trickled-through-the-Decade</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/How-Oil-Trickled-through-the-Decade">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt; It all started with the oil. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 20, 2010, the &lt;i&gt;Deepwater Horizon&lt;/i&gt;, an oil drilling rig owned by British Petroleum in the Gulf of Mexico, exploded. It was the largest marine oil spill in the history of the petroleum industry; an estimated 4.9 million barrels of crude oil in over 87 days was supposed to have been spilled. At the time, 126 crew members were on board and eleven workers were never found despite multiple US Coast Guard search operations. The &lt;i&gt;Deepwater Horizon&lt;/i&gt; sank two days later. Official reports say the oil spill has likely harmed or killed approximately 82,000 birds of 102 species, and approximately &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20160130231923/http://news.discovery.com/animals/whales-dolphins/record-dolphin-sea-turtle-deaths-since-gulf-spill-130402.htm&quot;&gt;6,165 sea turtles, and up to 25,900 marine mammals.&lt;/a&gt; The entire rescue, response and cleanup operations took 4 months, 4 weeks and 2 days. British Petroleum paid more than $20 billion in fines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Obama Effect&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;i&gt;The consequences of our inaction are now in plain sight. Countries like China are investing in clean energy jobs and industries that should be here in America. Each day, we send nearly $1 billion of our wealth to foreign countries for their oil. We cannot consign our children to this future. The tragedy unfolding on our coast is the most painful and powerful reminder yet. The time to embrace a clean energy future is now.&lt;/i&gt; “– Barack Obama, June 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 44th President of the United States had just been in office for over a year and yet he had already done the unimaginable. Pulling the economy out of The Great Recession, Obama became a symbol of hope to the post-crash America. &lt;i&gt;Hope&lt;/i&gt;. The most important word on his campaign trail; something he hoped to carry on with him into the White House.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But on this June morning, addressing the Mississippi crowd, he focused on two things: clean energy and China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barack Obama’s struggle towards clean energy has been tough and why shouldn’t it be? When you have an unresponsive Congress who won’t budge because of a Republican majority; when the Congress won’t lend an ear to clean energy because their donors are rich oil magnates; when nobody in your government seems to be rooting for you, what do you do? You look outside. It was at the 2009 United Nations Climate Change Conference at Copenhagen, where he championed the cause of alternative sources of energy for a cleaner environment before member nations of the UNFCCC. It was called the COP15 but they called it ‘&lt;i&gt;Hope&lt;/i&gt;nhagen’.  Unfortunately, things were ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://unfccc.int/resource/docs/2009/cop15/eng/l07.pdf&quot;&gt;taken note of&lt;/a&gt;’ and not ‘adopted’. Things would remain the same in coming years. Obama had the intentions, but people questioned his execution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chinese Production or Possibilities?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, China’s economy was on the rise. Just look at the number of billionaires shoot up post-2000:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/oilrig1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the turn of the decade, China had a GDP growth rate bordering on 10% with investors high about the potential that the Chinese market had. Even the US markets were looking at the Far East manufacturing powerhouse as a likely rival in the coming future, with experts predicting their economic output to be at par by 2018. China was not only becoming a force to be reckoned with but also a major consumer of oil which was expected to lead a huge boost in global oil demand. But &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/yuwahedrickwong/2018/08/23/the-reality-of-chinas-economic-slowdown/#2c7990464d86&quot;&gt;predictions do not always come true, do they?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spring in the Arab Desert&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early years of the decade, just as the world was reeling from the financial disaster that was, the markets were shaken by another catastrophic series of events. A revolution broke out in Tunisia, powered majorly by the newfound abilities of social media. All of a sudden, one country after another started falling to popular uprisings, social violence and major protests with regimes being overthrown in at least five other countries in the Middle East and North Africa region. This time, again, it was the oil markets which faced the brunt of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energy and Middle East scholar at Oxford, &lt;a href=&quot;http://rebeleconomy.com/economy/how-the-arab-spring-shook-up-oil-markets/&quot;&gt;Justin Dargin&lt;/a&gt; put it this way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;i&gt;“Global investors speculated that in the beginning months of the Arab Spring, there could be oil production disruption in the oil-producing Gulf countries. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;

There was the fear that perhaps several important sea-lanes and canals, such as the Strait of Hormuz or the Suez Canal, could be blocked. Furthermore, a bit later on during the Arab Spring, terrorism fears grew and it was thought that the regional power vacuum could encourage militant groups to launch attacks on MENA energy infrastructure.”&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;i&gt;‘fear premium&lt;/i&gt;’(price rise due to speculations about significant events that will negatively affect markets) caused a surge that the world was definitely not prepared for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/oilrig2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sheikh Vs. Shale&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 2015, Crude oil prices ended &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=13&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiZrMawhvLfAhUQfSsKHdylDWEQFjAMegQIBBAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washingtonpost.com%2Fopinions%2Frobert-samuelson-key-facts-about-the-great-oil-crash-of-2014%2F2014%2F12%2F03%2Fa1e2fd94-7b0f-11e4-b821-503cc7efed9e_story.html&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3vc-XO8xnUKemMPPF_GwR9&quot;&gt;below $40 per barrel&lt;/a&gt;, the lowest level since 2009. Prices were above $100 just a year ago, only to be met by an inconceivable bust to the oil markets. Lower crude oil prices in 2015 reflected the sustained excess of crude oil supply over global demand. There had been a major supply gut which caused global crude oil inventories to increase steadily through the year. With China facing a gradual slowdown in its economy, the hopes for higher crude oil demand looked slim. What had happened?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most surprising fact of all was the conflict in the Middle East, including the Syrian Crisis, had little to no effect on the oil markets. If these forces did not affect the markets, then who did? OPEC? Saudi Arabia?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/oilrig3.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, and No. The Saudis were partially to blame. But they were completely responsible for one of the &lt;i&gt;greatest tricks pulled in economic history&lt;/i&gt;. Since 2008, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ihsmarkit.com/press-release/energy-power/tight-oil-test-us-production-growth-remains-resilient-amid-lower-crude-oi&quot;&gt;US had been steadily increasing&lt;/a&gt; their production of ‘shale’ oil, obtained from organic-rich sedimentary rock found primarily in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2018/11/23/669198912/after-struggles-north-dakota-grows-into-its-ongoing-oil-boom&quot;&gt;Texas and North Dakota&lt;/a&gt;. By 2014, they had shaved off 50% of their imports from OPEC while expanding production by a hefty 70 percent. This boost to supply caused oil prices to drop globally and at a frenetic pace, unchecked by the OPEC disagreeing on whether to lower their production. So Saudi Arabia held out, their Oil Minister saying he &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwipvYmKjfLfAhWCXSsKHc33CJcQFjAAegQIAxAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.businessinsider.com%2Fr-saudis-naimi-says-opec-will-not-cut-output-however-far-oil-falls-mees-2014-12&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2O8qH49yL33uAaNlFrEgoY&quot;&gt;doesn’t care&lt;/a&gt; even if prices fell to $20 a barrel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon the outwitted Americans realised that the oil prices were falling far too low to maintain production at a sustainable (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiE4Z7FjfLfAhUGbo8KHWIgAiEQFjAAegQICBAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Foilprice.com%2FEnergy%2FCrude-Oil%2FThe-Struggle-Continues-For-Bankrupt-Shale-Drillers.html&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1L4UlPPBvNj8c_0HHOwo42&quot;&gt;let alone profitable&lt;/a&gt;) pace. Even at $60-$80 a barrel, shale oil was going for a loss, and a toss. The OPEC had won again, this time, thanks to the clever Saudi Arabians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Volatile shifts and the Trump Era&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slump had caused economic contractions in oil-producing countries like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/e1c89278-c33c-3fbe-83ae-985497365cf6&quot;&gt;Brazil&lt;/a&gt; and Venezuela, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-venezuela-economy/venezuelas-economy-shrank-16-5-percent-in-2016-government-idUSKBN1EG06V&quot;&gt;whose economy shrunk by 16.5%&lt;/a&gt;. Even Saudi Arabia took on austerity measures, dropping capital spending by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/middle-east/saudi-arabia-capital-spending-drop-71-per-cent-2016-amid-cheaper-oil-austerity-a7357666.html&quot;&gt;whopping 71 percent&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prayers were finally heard in 2016. The OPEC cut its production in November, which hadn’t happened since the global crisis of ‘08. The cut, which was joined by the likes of Russia, helped push oil costs sharply higher. Crude oil jumped at least five per cent when the OPEC decided to limit production to thirty-three million barrels daily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As things seem to be moving towards a period of stability by the end of the year, Donald Trump wins the elections and is ushered into the White House, sailing on a campaign of lambasting the Obama administration and in particular the Iran Deal (JCPOA):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;“John Kerry can’t get over the fact that he had his chance and blew it!”&lt;/i&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/realDonaldTrump/status/993815373190492160&quot;&gt;Trump wrote&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;i&gt;“Stay away from negotiations John, you are hurting your country!”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Venezuela whose economy was (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2018/12/15/having-wrecked-the-economy-venezuelas-rulers-see-no-reason-to-change&quot;&gt;and still is&lt;/a&gt;) reeling from Nicholas Maduro’s autocracy, had their production declining so much that they could no longer satisfy their domestic needs, let alone foreign customers. Then they went out and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/venezuela-bolivar-cryptocurrency-economy-crisis-collapse-petro-bitcoin-a8499266.html&quot;&gt;pegged their failing currency to their almost failing oil market&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But back in the global oil markets, things were looking better. Prices were rising steadily for the latter half of 2017 and most of 2018, which prompted Trump to tweet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;“Oil prices are too high, OPEC is at it again. Not good!”—US President Donald Trump in June 2018&lt;/i&gt;
This prompted the 23rd June meeting of OPEC ministers in Vienna where they decided to boost production by 1 million barrels/day. Unfortunately, it was soon overshadowed by Trump’s announcement of US withdrawal from the JCPOA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/realdonaldtrump/status/1021234525626609666?lang=en&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/oilrig4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This action, as the market expected, would result in a greater loss of supply than the initial estimates of 500,000 bl/d. As a result, the market began &lt;a href=&quot;https://oilprice.com/Energy/Crude-Oil/Iran-Claims-Its-Oil-Revenues-Surged-Despite-Sanctions.html&quot;&gt;preparing for the worst&lt;/a&gt;(even overestimating shortages) and sources reveal that OPEC had started to hike its production way before the June 2018 meeting.
Contrary to economic understanding, when November 4th approached, the day the sanctions on Iran would be enforced again, the price of crude oil &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/why-oil-prices-are-plunging-despite-us-sanctions-on-irans-energy-sector-2018-11-01&quot;&gt;dropped like a rock&lt;/a&gt;.Factor in the growing fears of an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/chinas-coming-recession-has-pushed-oil-below-60-2018-11-13&quot;&gt;oncoming recession in China&lt;/a&gt; (the world’s largest importer of oil) and the ensuing fall in demand, and we have another spectacular swing again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/oilrig5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New Year may bring new sentiments but much remains to be seen. Only Oil can affect geopolitics so greatly. Or is it the other way around? At least for the past century, one thing’s for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It all started with the oil.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shohan Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It all started with the oil.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Understanding Surplus Transfers between Central Banks and Governments</title>
      <link href="/Understanding-Surplus-Transfers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding Surplus Transfers between Central Banks and Governments" />
      <published>2019-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Understanding-Surplus-Transfers</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-Surplus-Transfers">&lt;p&gt;The trend over the last few decades for greater independence of central banks has raised the question of their financial independence. There has been increasing discussion on whether central banks require capital and if so, how much? The central bank (CB) mainly has two functions: print currency notes that are held by the public, and issue deposits to commercial banks. These are liabilities for which it does not have to pay any interest. At the same time, it purchases financial assets in the form of domestic and foreign government bonds on which it gets interest. As the cost of printing currency is on average 1/7th of the net interest income, the result is a large net interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any time the CB issues currency, undertakes foreign exchange operations, investments, conducts monetary policy operations, or provides liquidity assistance, its net worth is impacted. For central banks, much like commercial banks, the capital buffer or net worth on balance sheets allows them to absorb any potential losses. This means that it’s net worth impacts its ability to achieve monetary policy objectives, which include keeping the inflation rate within the set target. But there are no rules that dictate the amount of capital a central bank must possess. And different countries have taken different approaches based on their unique circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt; Up until the 1980’s, CBs in most countries weren’t as independent as we know them to be today. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CBs usually served under the government. They had myriad roles like financing government expenditure, maintaining financial stability, ensuring stability of prices and stimulating economic activity. But they did not have independence. The 90’s and 2000’s saw a trend in favour of independence for central banks to improve long run economic performance. This resulted from a consensus that a central bank independent from the government would be more capable of conducting a credible monetary policy. Market expectations that are more responsive to its actions will make it easier to achieve the monetary policy objectives. The main role of the CBs became the maintenance of price stability, although it was still expected to safeguard financial stability in the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When central banks served as an arm of the Ministry of Finance/Treasury, the level of CB capital and rules for distribution of profits to governments weren’t of consequence. As and when CBs across countries were allowed to set a monetary policy without interference from the government, these questions came under contention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When capital becomes sufficiently negative, there are two ways for the central bank to move forward: it has to either be recapitalised; or it has to cover losses on a cash-flow basis from the government. In latter case, which is most common, the government can insist it have discretion over the time and magnitude of the transfer, which effectively places the monetary policy in its hands. Now, the former case may seem more appealing. However, in countries that have negative capital as well as budget deficits, concerns for government interference resurface with recapitalisation as well. A government that is cash-strapped itself would not be able to render a large amount of capital to a CB in need. This was seen in the case of Argentina, where CB losses were 23.5% of the GDP in 1989 and in Jamaica, where losses were 53% of the GDP from 1988 to 1991. Financing these losses implied abandonment of monetary policy objectives that were conflicting with the government’s objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to all these issues plaguing banks with negative capital, central banks with positive amounts of capital and legal independence have been able to resist such pressures. Moreover, it is during banking crises that the CB’s demonstration of its ability to maintain financial stability becomes of utmost importance. A market that believes the central bank may change its policy to avoid losses undermines its credibility. This deters investors and delays restructuring of distressed assets, suppressing fiscal revenue and growth in the process. Indeed, in cases like Peru, Bolivia, and Chile, recapitalisation has led to a gradual improvement in financial position. But it is important to note that in these case studies, recapitalisation was brought about in conjunction with new central bank laws and economic reforms that sought to restore the public’s faith. So, it appears that if credibility is important for success of the monetary policy, the central bank must be financially strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The next question that arises is how much capital do CBs need?&lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Peter Stella in a paper written in 2005 identified four different ways that central banks have determined their level of capital:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An absolute nominal value of capital. (e.g. Bank of Canada)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A target ratio of capital to another central bank balance sheet item. (e.g. Bank of Japan)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A target ratio of capital to a macroeconomic variable. (e.g. US Federal Reserve)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Based on the perceived risks to the solvency of the bank.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, the optimal level of capital depends on a large number of factors, such as the macroeconomic environment, how vulnerable the CB is to large financial shocks, its historical legacy, policy obligations (like a fixed or pegged exchange rate) and the volatility of profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(e.g. Reserve Bank of India, Reserve Bank of New Zealand)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also follows that in developing countries and countries with narrow capital markets, the CB should have larger capital. Countries where governments have frequent or constant budget deficits and those with fixed or pegged exchange rates should pursue the same path. It is only after taking into consideration policy objectives, such as price or exchange rate stability, can an ideal level of capital be determined. The determination of the minimum financial strength should also take into account the exposure to risk. Finally, a mechanism and sufficient resources must to be available to absorb the risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the determination of an ideal level of capital, profit in excess of what is required by the central bank has to be transferred to the government. This is another source of discord. Usually the amount to be transferred is decided by both the parties before the budget for the year is set. In some cases, such as Japan, the government decides the quantum. Governments want a higher surplus in order to reduce fiscal deficit or provide assistance to distressed financial institutions, while CBs want to be cautious and keep reserves from profits for unforeseen risk. A debate follows on whether the CB is holding more capital than it requires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is little doubt that clear rules for allocation of profits would alleviate some of the strain between the CB and the government. Since the amount is subject to much fluctuation, it is also advisable to have a committee that reviews the surplus distribution policy. The rules should also contain contingencies for cases in which CB capital becomes negative. Clearly specified and transparent principles will safeguard the bank’s independence in the event that CB capital is seriously depleted. Most important of all, it would enhance the credibility of commitment to price stability on the part of both the government and the CB in the public eye.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reema Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The trend over the last few decades for greater independence of central banks has raised the question of their financial independence. There has been increasing discussion on whether central banks require capital and if so, how much? The central bank (CB) mainly has two functions: print currency notes that are held by the public, and issue deposits to commercial banks. These are liabilities for which it does not have to pay any interest. At the same time, it purchases financial assets in the form of domestic and foreign government bonds on which it gets interest. As the cost of printing currency is on average 1/7th of the net interest income, the result is a large net interest.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">East Asia - Growth in a Bubble</title>
      <link href="/East-Asia-Growth-in-a-Bubble" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="East Asia - Growth in a Bubble" />
      <published>2019-01-15T00:35:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-15T00:35:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/East-Asia-Growth-in-a-Bubble</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/East-Asia-Growth-in-a-Bubble">&lt;p&gt;The Second World War had just ended. Even though the Axis powers had lost, one could argue that all of humanity was the loser. Millions of people had been killed, wounded or displaced. Assets worth billions of dollars were lost and socio-economic infrastructure in various countries was in tatters. The war, directly or indirectly, also contributed to the freedom of various colonies in Asia. But the question remained was that how these former colonies would prosper economically after being completely decimated by a war between their colonial masters? It would require a miracle, no less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a miracle it was. Between 1965-90, the East Asian Economies and the High Performing Asian Economies (HPAEs) grew at an average of more than 5% per annum. Their growth rate was three times faster than Latin America and South Asia, and five times faster than Sub-Saharan Africa. During the same period, their real income per capita more than doubled. It was clear that this group of economies, which included Indonesia, Malaysia, Thailand, South Korea, Japan, Hong Kong and Singapore had clearly outperformed the rest of the world in terms of economic growth and development. Some analysts and economists have argued that these seven economies shared some common economic characteristics which set them apart from the rest. Even though these seven countries were highly diverse in population, culture, economic policy, natural resources and types of governance, there were some characteristics common to all of them which led to the growth story of these highly diverse economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Textbook Economics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For starters, public policy played a major contributing role in the rapid development of these economies. These countries were simply able to get the basics right. The governments of these economies were able to provide a stable macroeconomic environment, a sound legal framework, limited fiscal deficit, and moderate and predictable inflation. They also invested extensively in education, infrastructure and technological know-how. They welcomed investment both in terms of domestic savings and Foreign Direct Investment (FDI) by providing a favourable environment which included high and steady interest rates and lax tax policy. These initiatives by the government boosted growth and development in the economy along with human capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workforce forms the base of any economy. And government-financed education led to an increase in the literacy rate of these economies. The pains taken by the government in the field of education bore fruit: all these countries had a strong, educated and dedicated workforce. These economies also followed a unique and creative approach while dealing with labour problems and unions. Instead of giving in to the demand of labour unions to increase wages, the government focused on job creation. The increase in the number of jobs led to an increase in the demand for labour which automatically increased the productivity as well as the wage of labour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To rapidly develop their economies, the governments focused on infrastructure development, leading to a booming real estate market. And this (keeping in mind the high wages) ensured housing for the population which once again kept the people happy. The governments ensured that the investment coming from domestic as well as foreign investors was fully utilized. They also specifically invested in particular sectors so as to gain a comparative advantage in that sector (example, South Korea in the electronics sector). This extra effort paid its dividends as there was a rapid increase in the number of MSMEs and full-scale industries, which led to an increase in total output and increased exports. East Asia was a beautiful car ride where everyone was happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Illiquidity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as it is said, all good things must end. As already mentioned, these governments had kept high-interest rates and kept on encouraging FDI. Soon, it was seen that the amount of short-term foreign debt obligations which these economies had to pay in the international market far exceeded their foreign exchange reserves. This type of a situation in which the amount of short-term foreign debt obligations exceeded the total reserves of foreign exchange is called international illiquidity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;International illiquidity became one of the main factors contributing to the fall of these economies in the Asian Financial Crisis of 1997. These countries had excessively liberalized their financial structure to attract more foreign investment. Foreign loans kept piling up as late as May 1997 before someone took notice of it. But alas, it was too late to notice. The ratio of short-term debt to foreign reserves rose to about 7 in Indonesia and Korea, and 4.5 in the Philippines. In other East Asian Economies of Malaysia, Bangkok, Singapore, and Japan, this ratio was well above 1. The government policies of these East Asian Economies to increase investment by moving towards a freer, more market-oriented financial system came to bite them back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it happened, most of these economies kept a fixed exchange rate to maintain real interest rates and to woo investors. They maintained the exchange rate by buying up foreign exchange in case of excess supply and selling foreign exchange in case of excess demand. However, as the short-term debt was well over the amount of foreign exchange these economies had, the economy would not be able to meet all the short-term debt obligations if they came at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, on the other half of the globe, the US Federal reserve started increasing the interest rates on US Treasury Bonds to woo investment and revive America from the 1990-91 recession. As this increase in interest rates was not matched by these East Asian Economies, the investors started pulling out investments from these economies and started investing in risk-free US Bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let the Speculation Begin…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 14 and 15, 1997, the Thai Bhat was hit by speculative crisis and investors started pulling out their investments. As feared, the economy ran out of forex reserves to maintain the exchange rate and it was forced to devalue the Bhat. Consequently, the Thai Bhat lost more than 60% of its value in a single day of trading. The news spread like wildfire in the international community and the sentiment of the investors turned against the East Asian Economies. As markets are run on sentiments, investors viewed these economies to be highly volatile and started pulling out their investments. In a span of few days, the Indonesian Rupiah, the Malaysian Ringgit, the Philippine Peso, and the Korean Won were also devalued. These currencies were losing as much as 85% of their face value in a single day of trading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This devaluation of currency led to an increase in the nominal value of loans which these economies had borrowed from the international market. As the economy had taken these loans in hard currency and loaned the general public in local currency, this burden could not be passed on to the general public. Therefore, the economy and private banks had to take this hit and sell off their assets in order to repay these loans. An increase in the supply of assets in the markets led to fall in the price of these assets in the markets. And the banks were not able to raise enough funds to pay back these loans to the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Thing Leads to Another…Again&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, a large number of banks and financial institutions collapsed in these economies. Thousands of jobs were lost, there was a fall in nominal GNP per capita, a fall in income per capita, a fall in purchasing power parity, and a fall in economic growth rate. Moreover, the economy had little to no funds to undertake developmental projects and provide subsidies and concessions. The real estate market, MSME sector, education sector, human resource sector, and others, which depended on government aid and support, crashed terribly. As a result, economic growth and prosperity of these countries almost came to a standstill. It is believed that more than 10,000 people committed suicide in Hong Kong, Japan, and South Korea as a result of this crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What started as a blessing for these East Asian Economies and helped them undertake rapid growth in a span of 30 years took all it gave in a matter of few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Were the East Asian Economies able to bounce back in the international community and reach the pinnacle of growth and prosperity? Or, was this setback the final nail in the coffin and led them to a period of economic darkness? The second part of this story in the next article.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhishek Sancheti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Second World War had just ended. Even though the Axis powers had lost, one could argue that all of humanity was the loser. Millions of people had been killed, wounded or displaced. Assets worth billions of dollars were lost and socio-economic infrastructure in various countries was in tatters. The war, directly or indirectly, also contributed to the freedom of various colonies in Asia. But the question remained was that how these former colonies would prosper economically after being completely decimated by a war between their colonial masters? It would require a miracle, no less.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Counting Down the Biggest Economic Policy Announcements since the 2008 Financial Crash</title>
      <link href="/Counting-down-the-biggest-economic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Counting Down the Biggest Economic Policy Announcements since the 2008 Financial Crash" />
      <published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Counting-down-the-biggest-economic</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Counting-down-the-biggest-economic">&lt;p&gt;In economics, recessions and depressions are supposed to have taught us many valuable lessons (Keynes was one of them). What about the last major recession? It’s been a decade since the Global Markets Crash of ’08. As we enter 2019, let’s see how our governments and institutions have used their financial knowledge over the decade. Many of these announcements are a direct cause of the crisis, while the rest were too important to be left out. Here you go:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 - American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is early 2009, the United States, reeling from the 2008 Financial Crisis, has the New Year as the only positive yet (besides the new President). Obama outlined throughout his 2008 campaign plans for an economic stimulus package and this was delivery time. On February 17, 2009, President Obama signed the fiscal stimulus passed by Congress, which would raise overall demand in the economy by an initial $780-billion worth of federal spending and tax cuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This indeed was a necessary follow-up to President Bush’s Troubled Asset Recovery Program, which bailed out the big banks of Wall Street still at the point of revival (sorry, Lehman Brothers). It was only later in 2012 that Congress added to the ARRA making it stand at &lt;i&gt;eight-hundred-and-forty-billion-dollars&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Act was largely successful, ending the Recession in July 2009, just 5 months after the bill’s passing. Although many people were skeptical whether they received any tax benefits, the program was hailed for its effectiveness and served as a model for a country that appears later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 - North Korea ‘Won’, 2009&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, they did not win 2009. There have not been many cases of currency revaluation or demonetization in the 21st Century; in fact, less than the number of fingers on your hand. Yet for an occurrence this rare, the 2nd entry on our list has not had the fanfare it deserves. We travel far East to the Korea of the daily news cycle. You guessed it, welcome to North Korea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2009, the North Korean government decided to devalue their currency, the Won, for the first time in 50 years. Many speculated this was a move either initiated or approved personally by Supreme Leader Kim Jong-Il, father of Kim Jon-Un. Seen as a move against private market activity, it also wiped out many North Koreans’ savings. To make matters worse, the announcement was made to foreign embassies but not to North Korean State media. The old notes ceased to be legal tender on November 30, with new notes not being delivered until December 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can only think of ways to &lt;i&gt;spend&lt;/i&gt; that week without monetary transaction possible. Needless to say, things were chaotic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 - The Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act 2010&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can blame the Housing markets all they want. But the reason why banks went overboard was in large part due to the repealing of the Glass-Steagall Act in 1999. The Glass–Steagall Act was enacted after the Great Depression of 1930. It separated commercial banks and investment banks, to avoid potential conflicts of interest between the lending activities of the former and rating activities of the latter. Economist Joseph Stiglitz said the repeal would mean the risk-taking culture of investment banking dominated the more risk-averse commercial banking culture, leading to increased levels of risk-taking and leverage during the boom period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the Dodd-Frank reforms. Spelled out over roughly 2,300 pages, this piece of financial reform intends to decrease various risks in the U.S. financial system. The Act established a number of new government agencies tasked with overseeing various aspects of the banking system. Apart from monitoring the financial stability of major firms whose failure could have a major negative impact on the economy, it also provides for regulations keeping a check on Wall Street, which is why President Trump looks to repeal it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4 - Austerity returns—to Ireland, Greece, the U.K., and, perhaps to the U.S.A., 2011&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, dear, Austerity! The things you promised us, and now look at what you did to the PIGS (and Italy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t know who or what I’m talking about, the reduction of &lt;i&gt;government budget deficits&lt;/i&gt; through &lt;i&gt;spending cuts, tax increases,&lt;/i&gt; or a &lt;i&gt;combination of both&lt;/i&gt; is referred to as &lt;em&gt;Austerity&lt;/em&gt;. It is a series of strict measures to deal with governments unable to pay their debts, viz. Greece (which lost 25% of its GDP) and the members of the Eurozone who have spectacularly contributed to its economic failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/irelandbust2010.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the European debt crisis, many countries embarked on austerity programs, reducing their budget deficits relative to GDP from 2010 to 2011. According to the CIA World Factbook, Greece decreased its budget deficit from 10.4% of GDP in 2010 to 9.6% in 2011. Iceland, Italy, Ireland, Portugal, France, and Spain also decreased their budget deficits from 2010 to 2011 relative to GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reality, the European people found it too tough to cope up with the heavy tax burdens and unemployment went from 10.3% in 2011 to 12.1% in 2013. Even Paul Krugman saw no sign of success, “this also implies that 1 euro of austerity yields only about 0.4 euros of reduced deficit, even in the short run. No wonder, then, that the whole austerity enterprise is spiraling into disaster.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5 - Cyprus and the Big Bailout, 2013&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a story with a happy ending―but it starts off just as bad as the Eurozone. Back in 2013, Europe looked on in despair as yet another country appeared on the brink of collapse. Panic spread through the Cyprus financial system as government bonds were downgraded to junk status and long queues formed outside cash machines as the country failed to make ends meet. Cyprus struck a last-minute bailout deal worth 10 billion euro ($11 billion) in the early hours of Monday morning, aimed at preventing the island becoming the first country forced out of the single European currency. Guess where the help came from- Russian Oligarchs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyprus’s second-largest bank, Laiki Bank was closed. Its €4.2bn in deposits over €100,000 were wiped out entirely. All lenders to Laiki saw their investments wiped out, in a first for a Eurozone bailout. Bank of Cyprus survived the axe. Fast forward to March 2016 via a rescue package program, raft of reforms and austerity measures (finally worked!)  and the country is exiting its three-year, 10 billion euro financial aid package as one of the more robust Eurozone economies. Voila!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6 - Japan’s Quantitative Easing is like the USA on steroids!,  2014&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States did quantitative easing the right way; with loads and loads of asset purchases by the government. Under the most recent incarnation of monetary easing - dubbed “QE3” - the central bank has purchased around $1.6 trillion in government bonds and mortgage-backed securities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Japanese then went out and did this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Abenomics6036.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Here’s a graph, showing the BoJ’s asset purchases, source: Haver Analytics)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as the Federal Reserve was winding down, the Bank of Japan (BoJ) voted by 5:4 in a hotly-contested decision to boost its asset purchases by a quarter to roughly $700bn a year, covering the fiscal deficit and the lion’s share of Japan’s annual budget. Governor Haruhiko Kuroda said the fresh stimulus was intended to “pre-empt” mounting deflation risks in the world and vowed to do whatever it takes to see through Japan’s &lt;i&gt;“Abenomics”&lt;/i&gt; revolution. “We are at a critical moment in our efforts to break free from the deflationary mindset,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hans Redeker, from Morgan Stanley, believes that Japan’s aggressive measures seem to be putting pressure on the rest of their economic competitors in Asia to raise government spending too. But this is where China finds it tough to compete with a large budget deficit, slowing economy and FDI gradually turning negative. No wonder the Dragon is angry at its eastern neighbour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7 - Greece becomes first advanced economy ever to fail in arrears to the IMF, 2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“2015 was all about Greece”—is an understatement. 2015 saw Greece’s debt crisis, Greece’s referendum, Greece’s bailout, Greece’s election, Greece’s second election. At one point it really seemed that the battered country, which has been through so much, would finally crash out of the eurozone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;i&gt;No Bailouts&lt;/i&gt; campaign securing 61.31% majority, won the referendum. In a television address, PM Alex Tsipras said the outcome showed that democracy could not be blackmailed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a week later, however, he would be forced to accept a bailout of further austerity measures and economic reforms, even more onerous than those the nation had so dramatically rejected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/chart6034.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8 - India’s Demonetization and the GST Bill, 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two polar opposites. One nobody saw coming and the other that had been there all along. No, I’m not referring to the Congress and the BJP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Demonetization Scheme struck like a lightning rod throughout Indian society, affecting both the poor and rich equally (so much for inequality). In a move targeted at debilitating the shadow economy, counterfeit cash and “black money” used to fund illegal activity, Rs. 500 and Rs. 1000 banknotes were demonetized and new Rs. 500 and Rs. 2000 notes were introduced. The GST Bill, on the other hand, was first put forth by the Vajpayee administration almost 20 years ago but only saw the light of day in late 2016. It has successfully eliminated the Cascading effect of taxes (tax on a tax) and taken its place as the Destination tax of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being initially met with protests, litigation, and strikes, it has received support from many eminent bankers and the IMF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9 - Venezuela devalues its currency by the crypto, 2018&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have truly reached the advent of technology when Venezuela decides to peg the Bolivar to an oil-backed cryptocurrency called the petro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venezuela under Nicolas Maduro is an economic autocracy at best. Since 2014, they have lied on reports and economic statistics and by 2016, were in an economic collapse, with the IMF estimating a 500% inflation rate and a 10% GDP contraction and as of today, are experiencing Hyperinflation—Wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the government decided to slash five zeros off and devalue the currency, and back it by their oil and mineral reserves; the only things not spiraling out of control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really a sneak peek of the decade to come!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shohan Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In economics, recessions and depressions are supposed to have taught us many valuable lessons (Keynes was one of them). What about the last major recession? It’s been a decade since the Global Markets Crash of ’08. As we enter 2019, let’s see how our governments and institutions have used their financial knowledge over the decade. Many of these announcements are a direct cause of the crisis, while the rest were too important to be left out. Here you go:</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Diary of a Confused Indian Economics Student</title>
      <link href="/Confused-Indian-Econs-Student" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diary of a Confused Indian Economics Student" />
      <published>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Confused-Indian-Econs-Student</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Confused-Indian-Econs-Student">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dear Diary,&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I return to you, yet again. You have been a constant support in times like these. I wonder if this happens with everyone- for days, you are the king of your small world, a world which you understand; then, all of a sudden, everything crumbles down, every fact which you thought was true becomes fiction, every emotion you had turns out to be shallow, every moment you lived seems worthless. I feel shelterless, the roof of meaning taken away from above my head. Hence, here I am, meaningless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must be used to my spiraling down of emotions by now. However, this time, it’s different (trust me). Unlike all my previous breakdowns, there is no particular person to blame, and this leaves me even more clueless. How puny us humans are, always looking for a guilty party, to make ourselves feel lighter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On to the issue now. The reason behind my sudden disillusionment with the world is the new Indian GDP back series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is it? Oh, of course, I have to explain it, you are just a silly diary!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, the GDP growth rate of our country over the past decade or so has been revised and updated. As per the updated GDP data, India grew at 6.7% between 2004 and 2014. This is in contrast to previous figures of 8.1% from 2004-09 and 7.46% from 2009-14.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s the issue with that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I AM NOT SURE. That’s the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not sure if we are a high growth economy or not. The world thinks so (or thought so). Even I thought so, till yesterday. However, the new data doesn’t. We never crossed the 9% growth rate, EVER.  Some numbers here and there, and I am questioning my own country’s growth story, something which I was proud of (till yesterday, of course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this mean we never grew at the pace we thought we had? But, I have seen luxuries become necessities for the consumer every five years, middle class getting richer, sons earning in their first year more than what their fathers earned throughout their lives. Doesn’t this count as exceptional growth? Or worse, what we experienced in the past decade was nothing exceptional, and the Indian economy, even after 70 years, has nothing to show for achievements. No, no, this cannot be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, if we didn’t achieve high growth (more than 9%), what explains the high inflation we faced towards the end of 2013? How can there be high inflation without high growth? Was the inflation JUST because of external factors like Oil? So much purchasing power wiped away by double digit inflation rates because a few countries (Read: OPEC) wanted to have fun with the world? The worst of my thoughts are yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world knows that we have a highly indebted banking sector. Rising NPAs (non-performing assets, basically loans given by banks which don’t get repaid completely) have been the single largest threat to the Indian economy for the past 5 years, at least. It is widely acknowledged that banks lent rapidly (and sometimes indiscriminately) between 2008 and 2014, which has led to this problem today. However, in the short-term, this excessive lending helped us achieve exceptional growth rates, even touching 10.3% in 2010-11. All this, obviously, as per the old data. Now, the ‘excessive lending’ (should we still call it that?), which has created an unprecedented crisis in our economy, didn’t even help us achieve ‘high growth’ phase. Much ado about nothing. Why doesn’t the government also downgrade the NPAs in the economy? I am sure there is a way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh Diary, spare a thought for all the poor foreign investors who were fooled into investing into this apparently ‘high growth’ economy which wasn’t! A decade of optimism, all for nothing. It was a lie. A scam. In case I haven’t made it clear enough, an economy is in a ‘high growth’ phase when it crosses 9% growth, which India didn’t (I know I have made it pretty clear. I just needed another reason to repeat it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s interesting is that the new GDP data has been released by NITI Aayog, a government think-tank, and not by the Central Statistics Office, as is the norm. I feel sad for poor Adarsh, my close friend. He is working so hard to join the Indian Statistical Institute in Kolkata, only to find his dream job is being taken over by a bureaucrat run organization!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two beneficiaries from the new data, though, and this (somewhat) gives me a reason to smile: Unemployed youth and distressed farmers. These poor fellows had been wondering how did a high-growth phase not create enough jobs/ increase the standard of living for them. They now have an answer: there was no high growth economy to produce jobs/ increase standard of living in the first place!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I am just overreacting. Yes, yes. I am overreacting. Arvind Virmani, our former Chief Economic Advisor, has said that usually GDP data updates like this one lead to a downgrade of a country’s growth. He must know better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just, one thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before this data was released, another revised GDP data was ‘leaked’. As per this particular leaked data, India actually grew at a faster pace than even previously estimated. Yes! We touched double digit growth more often than we had thought. However, the government (this happened a few months ago) had then said that the revision of GDP numbers is still under process and these are not the final numbers. What I understand is that there are several ways to revise GDP numbers, and the leaked and the newly released official version are only two of the many alternatives. SURELY, the government won’t intentionally recognize a methodology to discredit the growth rates under it’s political rival. Surely, it won’t. Not before an election year. Definitely not. After all, this government is known for respecting institutions (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ndtv.com/india-news/rbi-vs-government-10-things-to-know-1941159&quot;&gt;Read: RBI&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am really sorry, I know I am going over-board. I just have a few silly questions to end with (Don’t laugh). If our percentage growth has been downgraded, our absolute GDP must have come down too, wouldn’t it? I was hearing that Indian GDP (nominal basis) will overtake United Kingdom’s in 2019. I suppose this won’t happen. OR will it? Why hasn’t our absolute GDP number been downgraded, yet? Data also shows that India did not recover from the global financial crisis as quickly as initially thought. Are we a resilient economy as we thought we were, or not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several international institutions have been coming up with research (using old data) showing the huge number of people India lifted out of poverty, something which I take pride in. A low GDP growth means more people must still be under poverty than previously estimated. &lt;em&gt;‘A stroke of a pen and millions are poor again’&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t end on such a melancholic note. Hear this story:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
 Last week, I asked my philosophy teacher this, “What GDP number, what military capability, what standard of living, what cultural clout do we need to achieve in order to become a Superpower?”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My teacher’s answer left me thinking, and it seems relevant today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

“0”

&lt;br /&gt;

“0?”, I asked confused.

&lt;br /&gt;

He said, “What use is any of what you said to a nation whose soul is great enough to capture hearts of billions? Develop the soul of your nation.”

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diary, you know what’s the best part about developing the soul of my nation? No methodology can downgrade it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidyarthi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Dear Diary,</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
