<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/economics/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-07-06T12:26:12+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/economics/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Middle Income Trap and How India Must Avert It</title>
      <link href="/The-Middle-Income-Trap" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Middle Income Trap and How India Must Avert It" />
      <published>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Middle-Income-Trap</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Middle-Income-Trap">&lt;p&gt;While the &lt;em&gt;Mahatyohar&lt;/em&gt; (Read: General Elections) of the Indian nation concluded
with a staggering majority for the incumbent BJP, it was immediately followed by
the official revelation of certain important economic indicators that were
perhaps obscured in a mist of uncertainty during the election campaign.
Nevertheless, the unemployment rate was revealed to be at a four-decade high of
6.1% while the GDP growth rate of 2019 Q1 has dropped to nearly 5.8% after a
decline in the consumption expenditure for automobile and real estate, which
explains the recent 0.2% reduction in the IMF growth projections for India as
compared to its previous assessment in January. The growth concerns have put
more interest rate cuts by the Reserve Bank of India on the radar, and have
pushed its stance from neutral to accommodative. And while all these deviations
can be credited to the global slowdown that is being projected for 2019 as a
part of the generic economic cycle, for emerging nations like India this could
indicate the end to an era of rapid economic convergence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, amidst the chaos of the Indian elections, Rathin Roy, Director of the
National Institute of Public Finance and Policy, highlighted a bipartisan issue
of long term stagnation that the Indian economy might soon have to confront. He
identified that the long term growth of the nation is primarily spurred by what
the top 10% income bracket of the population consumes. This was good enough to
lift India to the group of lower-middle income nations back in 2008 when the per
capita income rose above $1005 for the first time. But now, this group has
become a major hindrance to reaching the upper-middle-income bracket that ranges
from $3,956 to $12,235 per capita. In order to cross this threshold, the
economy must witness a structural transformation of the non-luxury good
industries, on which the majority of the Indian population depends. Roy states
that while aspects like infrastructure, microfinance, etc. are being dealt with
by the government’s &lt;em&gt;PM Awas Yojana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;PM Mudra Yojana&lt;/em&gt; schemes respectively,
it is agriculture that clearly needs to undergo a proper revival to ameliorate
the productivity of the most basic non-luxury good; foodgrain, for which we’re
becoming increasingly dependent. Other aspects like technology and human capital
development require immediate attention for escaping the Middle Income Trap that
we’re heading into. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Middle Income Trap is an economic phenomenon that states how a poor nation
makes significant progress on its way to becoming a middle-income nation but
then finds it harder to take the shape of a fully developed, high-income nation.
This phenomenon is more frequent than one would assume. Only 13 of the 101
nations deemed to be middle-income countries in the 1960’s had achieved
high-income levels by 2011. The failure of the rest of the nations is primarily
attributed to the rising domestic wages, failure to invest in human capital,
lack of innovation and issues with macroeconomic stability. While the latter is
comparatively under control and any recent macroeconomic discrepancies have been
exogenous to the powers of the central bank, the remaining three are extremely
crucial yet underrated issues in the Indian economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roy identifies that labour-intensive business investments are increasingly being
channelled towards nations like Bangladesh, even though their wages are similar
to those of East Indian states like Bihar, Jharkhand, etc. But there, the labour
is scarce due to mass migrations towards the western states where minimum wages
are much higher, a policy which had contributed to the early popularity the
current PM Modi, during his tenure as the Chief Minister of the western state of
Gujarat. Although it is difficult to revert such populist policies, the issue of
high wages has the ability to resolve itself in time, as the nation’s
demographic structure changes, with more people contributing to the labour
supply. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the development of human capital, the current share of education-related
expenditure in India’s Union Budget is a mere 3%, much lower than the minimum 6%
required for the basic functioning of the education system, let alone its
restructuring. Innovation was encouraged through government initiatives like
&lt;em&gt;Startup India&lt;/em&gt;, which badly backfired as the government failed to encourage
investors by perpetuating the regressive Angel Tax, which charged venture
capitalists on any amount invested over and above the government’s faulty
valuation of the startups. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An observation similar to Rathin Roy’s was made in the Economic Survey of
2017-18, which identified the threat of a ‘Late Converger Stall’ that India will
have to tackle on its way to the upper-middle-income status. Economic
convergence, which is the process of developing economies catching up with the
developed ones, is divided into phases. There have been early convergers like
Japan and South Korea, who managed to take advantage of their cheap labour and
efficient productivity in time, and then there are late convergers like India,
who did not open their economy to global opportunities until the eleventh hour
and must now bear the consequences. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Economic Survey identified the major headwinds that were absent for the
early convergers and could now lead to a growth stall for the late convergers.
Hyper globalisation repudiation due to a growing sentiment of protectionism was
absent during the early convergers period, which gave Japan, China, and South
Korea, an average export boost of over 15% during their convergence period. The
global trade-to-GDP ratio is on a decline since 2011, which, from a policy
perspective, means that the late convergers must now focus more on enhancing
private investments to boost growth. Another factor identified by the survey was
the thwarted structural transformation due to wrongly channelising resources
from low productivity sectors to marginally more productive sectors rather than
high productivity sectors. Sectors like finance, technology, and other
professional services must be tapped for overcoming the stagnation.
Additionally, climate-change-induced agricultural stress and regression of human
capital are also some of the major issues that need to be addressed with greater
urgency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the middle-income trap can be avoided by both increasing domestic
demand or by boosting exports, India can only prioritise the former because
becoming an export-led economy would imply a current account surplus and capital
account deficit, and that would curb the FDI to the nation, which is evidently
undesirable for an Emerging Market Economy (EME). The policy mix of the
politically right government has, for the most part, comprised economically
left-leaning schemes combined with cleverly constructed, investment conducive
foreign policy. But that is not enough. India is one of the prime investment
destinations among its fellow EMEs, and we must fully take advantage of that
before the preferences, as they inevitably will, shift to the African nations,
for capital is faithful to none.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">While the Mahatyohar (Read: General Elections) of the Indian nation concluded with a staggering majority for the incumbent BJP, it was immediately followed by the official revelation of certain important economic indicators that were perhaps obscured in a mist of uncertainty during the election campaign. Nevertheless, the unemployment rate was revealed to be at a four-decade high of 6.1% while the GDP growth rate of 2019 Q1 has dropped to nearly 5.8% after a decline in the consumption expenditure for automobile and real estate, which explains the recent 0.2% reduction in the IMF growth projections for India as compared to its previous assessment in January. The growth concerns have put more interest rate cuts by the Reserve Bank of India on the radar, and have pushed its stance from neutral to accommodative. And while all these deviations can be credited to the global slowdown that is being projected for 2019 as a part of the generic economic cycle, for emerging nations like India this could indicate the end to an era of rapid economic convergence. Recently, amidst the chaos of the Indian elections, Rathin Roy, Director of the National Institute of Public Finance and Policy, highlighted a bipartisan issue of long term stagnation that the Indian economy might soon have to confront. He identified that the long term growth of the nation is primarily spurred by what the top 10% income bracket of the population consumes. This was good enough to lift India to the group of lower-middle income nations back in 2008 when the per capita income rose above $1005 for the first time. But now, this group has become a major hindrance to reaching the upper-middle-income bracket that ranges from $3,956 to $12,235 per capita. In order to cross this threshold, the economy must witness a structural transformation of the non-luxury good industries, on which the majority of the Indian population depends. Roy states that while aspects like infrastructure, microfinance, etc. are being dealt with by the government’s PM Awas Yojana and PM Mudra Yojana schemes respectively, it is agriculture that clearly needs to undergo a proper revival to ameliorate the productivity of the most basic non-luxury good; foodgrain, for which we’re becoming increasingly dependent. Other aspects like technology and human capital development require immediate attention for escaping the Middle Income Trap that we’re heading into.  The Middle Income Trap is an economic phenomenon that states how a poor nation makes significant progress on its way to becoming a middle-income nation but then finds it harder to take the shape of a fully developed, high-income nation. This phenomenon is more frequent than one would assume. Only 13 of the 101 nations deemed to be middle-income countries in the 1960’s had achieved high-income levels by 2011. The failure of the rest of the nations is primarily attributed to the rising domestic wages, failure to invest in human capital, lack of innovation and issues with macroeconomic stability. While the latter is comparatively under control and any recent macroeconomic discrepancies have been exogenous to the powers of the central bank, the remaining three are extremely crucial yet underrated issues in the Indian economy.  Roy identifies that labour-intensive business investments are increasingly being channelled towards nations like Bangladesh, even though their wages are similar to those of East Indian states like Bihar, Jharkhand, etc. But there, the labour is scarce due to mass migrations towards the western states where minimum wages are much higher, a policy which had contributed to the early popularity the current PM Modi, during his tenure as the Chief Minister of the western state of Gujarat. Although it is difficult to revert such populist policies, the issue of high wages has the ability to resolve itself in time, as the nation’s demographic structure changes, with more people contributing to the labour supply.  As for the development of human capital, the current share of education-related expenditure in India’s Union Budget is a mere 3%, much lower than the minimum 6% required for the basic functioning of the education system, let alone its restructuring. Innovation was encouraged through government initiatives like Startup India, which badly backfired as the government failed to encourage investors by perpetuating the regressive Angel Tax, which charged venture capitalists on any amount invested over and above the government’s faulty valuation of the startups.  An observation similar to Rathin Roy’s was made in the Economic Survey of 2017-18, which identified the threat of a ‘Late Converger Stall’ that India will have to tackle on its way to the upper-middle-income status. Economic convergence, which is the process of developing economies catching up with the developed ones, is divided into phases. There have been early convergers like Japan and South Korea, who managed to take advantage of their cheap labour and efficient productivity in time, and then there are late convergers like India, who did not open their economy to global opportunities until the eleventh hour and must now bear the consequences.  The Economic Survey identified the major headwinds that were absent for the early convergers and could now lead to a growth stall for the late convergers. Hyper globalisation repudiation due to a growing sentiment of protectionism was absent during the early convergers period, which gave Japan, China, and South Korea, an average export boost of over 15% during their convergence period. The global trade-to-GDP ratio is on a decline since 2011, which, from a policy perspective, means that the late convergers must now focus more on enhancing private investments to boost growth. Another factor identified by the survey was the thwarted structural transformation due to wrongly channelising resources from low productivity sectors to marginally more productive sectors rather than high productivity sectors. Sectors like finance, technology, and other professional services must be tapped for overcoming the stagnation. Additionally, climate-change-induced agricultural stress and regression of human capital are also some of the major issues that need to be addressed with greater urgency. Although the middle-income trap can be avoided by both increasing domestic demand or by boosting exports, India can only prioritise the former because becoming an export-led economy would imply a current account surplus and capital account deficit, and that would curb the FDI to the nation, which is evidently undesirable for an Emerging Market Economy (EME). The policy mix of the politically right government has, for the most part, comprised economically left-leaning schemes combined with cleverly constructed, investment conducive foreign policy. But that is not enough. India is one of the prime investment destinations among its fellow EMEs, and we must fully take advantage of that before the preferences, as they inevitably will, shift to the African nations, for capital is faithful to none.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Africa Sees a New Dawn</title>
      <link href="/Africa-Sees-a-New-Dawn" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Africa Sees a New Dawn" />
      <published>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Africa-Sees-a-New-Dawn</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Africa-Sees-a-New-Dawn">&lt;p&gt;As the US and China are engaged in a trade war, and debates about the
unpredictability of relationships between the EU and Britain continue to linger,
the continent of Africa is taking steps to create a close-knit relationship to
realise the vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063. On May 30, 2019, the
African Continental Free Trade Agreement (AfCFTA) came into force after being
ratified by the parliaments of 24 countries. The CFTA is an attempt by the
African governments to “unlock Africa’s tremendous potential” and deliver
prosperity to all Africans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AfCFTA seeks to create a single unified African continental market for goods and
services with free movement of business, people and investment. The AfCFTA will
bring together all 55 member states of the African Union covering a market of
more than 1.2 billion people and a combined GDP of more than $3.4 trillion. In
terms of the number of participating countries, the AfCFTA will be the world’s
largest free trade area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single market for goods and services enables free movement of goods, services,
and labour from one country to another. Trade among the 55 African Union member
states is only 18% of the total exports from the continent. A free market
improves these numbers prodigiously. Improved intra-continental trade would
benefit the consumers across the continent, as the goods and services would
become relatively cheaper. This increases the real income of consumers, part of
which again is spent. The ambitious project seeks to remove tariffs on 90% of
the goods traded between the signatories to the agreement, and gradually
eliminate other non-tariff barriers to trade in goods and services. As an
economist would argue, removal of these barriers would increase the producer and
consumer surplus, and overall efficiency of these economies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The manufacturing sector is the backbone of Africa. The new agreement promotes
competition among the firms and aids Africa in unlocking its true potential and
thus boosting its export of manufactured goods to the rest of the world. The
relatively small size of many African markets is one of the reasons that inhibit
private sector investment. A unified market will enable the continent to attract
foreign direct investment. By and large, these would lead to an increase in
consumption and investment components and add to an overall increase in GDP.  By
2030, the African market size is expected to reach 1.7 billion people, with a
combined consumer and business spending of $6.7 trillion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A study by UNCTAD concedes that the long term monetary benefits that AfCFTA
shall yield are annual welfare gains as high as $16 billion. Estimates from the
UN Economic Commission for Africa (UNECA) suggest that the AfCFTA has the
potential to boost intra-African trade by 52.3%. There’s a substantial amount of
evidence to show that free movement boosts the economies of countries. A study
has shown that nations could increase their per-capita GDP growth by 12%, simply
by being a member of the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AfCFTA document says one of its goals is to “foster a competitive
manufacturing sector and promote economic diversification”. Even as 43% of the
goods traded within Africa are from the manufacturing sector, it represents only
about 10% of the total GDP in Africa, lagging behind other developing countries.
Africa’s low level of intra-regional trade is one of the reasons for the
continent’s enduring poverty and lack of a strong manufacturing base. The
African economies can, therefore, leverage their gigantic population size of 1.2
billion to expand their manufacturing sector and gain a comparative cost
advantage over other nations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from AfCFTA, there are some Regional Economic Communities (REC) in Africa
such as ECA, SADC, ECOWAS, and COMESCA. While ECOWAS was quite successful, the
other blocs have problems. Disputes continue to hamper relations and drive the
countries toward not honouring agreements. For instance, Kenya and Tanzania,
both members of ECA, have been engaged in a trade war. Tanzania has been known
to kick out Kenyan executives and impound Kenyan imports at the border, in
violation of ECA rules. While Tanzania scrapped preferential access to Kenyan
textiles, Kenya allowed goods from Export Processing Zones to be sold in local
markets, which prevented Tanzanian goods from being competitive. Members of
COMESCA, Kenya, Tanzania and Uganda have also been blaming each other for
exploiting the low import duties on sugar. That AfCFTA doesn’t have a clause to
repeal all the existing trade blocs would prove a real challenge as it creates
ambiguity. Then there is also the threat of countries acting in favour of their
trading partners from “the regional blocs.” The success of the agreement depends
on how efficiently the AU deals with these RECs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AfCFTA is to face some more challenges. The two largest economies of Africa,
Nigeria and South Africa haven’t ratified the agreement yet. South Africa has
assured that it would sign it once domestic legal requirements have been
satisfied. However, Nigeria backed out from signing the agreement citing “the
agreement would drastically affect the small business sector of the country.”
“We will not agree to anything that will undermine local manufacturers and
entrepreneurs, or that may lead to Nigeria becoming a dumping ground for
finished goods,” Nigeria has stated. The pervasive nature of Small and Medium
Enterprises (SMEs) in virtually every sector of the Nigerian economy and their
place in national development is conspicuous. SMEs in Nigeria are believed to
account for about 40% of GDP and 70% of industrial employment. Rice is also a
factor that is preventing the largest African economy from signing the deal. 
Due to various government initiatives, rice is starting to command 40% more
price than what it used to 3 years back in the Nigerian markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly,  Nigeria would largely benefit from signing the deal. With a
rapidly growing population of almost 200 million, Nigeria has more workers and
consumers than anywhere in Africa. For many businesses, there is no other place
in Africa that can offer such a scale. This will provide a competitive advantage
to Nigeria in firms’ considerations of where to set up facilities and do
business. AfCFTA will expose local Nigerian firms to better practices and
technologies, often through partnerships with the MNCs and sometimes through
competition. This sort of exposure will challenge entrepreneurs in the country
and give them greater access to the skills and partnerships they need to be
dynamic in today’s world. By giving businesses access to a larger market beyond
their home country, the trade agreement would allow the establishments in
Nigeria (that are not profitable now) to take advantage of the economies of
scale and industries to take advantage of the growth in intra-Africa relations.
Remaining a non-signatory to the agreement might cost Nigeria dearly. The
country’s isolation makes it difficult for local businesses to scale abroad,
thus making them less attractive for foreign direct investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In launching the African Continental Free Trade Area and making it work, Africa
is overcoming the historic fragmentation and isolation of her economies by
opening up huge commercial opportunities as well as improving transport and
communication linkages among the countries. This connectivity will enable the
vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063: “An integrated, prosperous, and
peaceful Africa, driven by its citizens, representing a dynamic force in the
global arena.” However, there are many roadblocks for AU to overcome in the
process of successful implementation of the agreement and realising her dream of
“Agenda 2063: The Africa We Want [Pan-Africanism]’’. The success of the
agreement depends on how well AU manages the disputes among member nations and
oversees the implementation of the agreement in true spirit.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As the US and China are engaged in a trade war, and debates about the unpredictability of relationships between the EU and Britain continue to linger, the continent of Africa is taking steps to create a close-knit relationship to realise the vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063. On May 30, 2019, the African Continental Free Trade Agreement (AfCFTA) came into force after being ratified by the parliaments of 24 countries. The CFTA is an attempt by the African governments to “unlock Africa’s tremendous potential” and deliver prosperity to all Africans. AfCFTA seeks to create a single unified African continental market for goods and services with free movement of business, people and investment. The AfCFTA will bring together all 55 member states of the African Union covering a market of more than 1.2 billion people and a combined GDP of more than $3.4 trillion. In terms of the number of participating countries, the AfCFTA will be the world’s largest free trade area. A single market for goods and services enables free movement of goods, services, and labour from one country to another. Trade among the 55 African Union member states is only 18% of the total exports from the continent. A free market improves these numbers prodigiously. Improved intra-continental trade would benefit the consumers across the continent, as the goods and services would become relatively cheaper. This increases the real income of consumers, part of which again is spent. The ambitious project seeks to remove tariffs on 90% of the goods traded between the signatories to the agreement, and gradually eliminate other non-tariff barriers to trade in goods and services. As an economist would argue, removal of these barriers would increase the producer and consumer surplus, and overall efficiency of these economies.  The manufacturing sector is the backbone of Africa. The new agreement promotes competition among the firms and aids Africa in unlocking its true potential and thus boosting its export of manufactured goods to the rest of the world. The relatively small size of many African markets is one of the reasons that inhibit private sector investment. A unified market will enable the continent to attract foreign direct investment. By and large, these would lead to an increase in consumption and investment components and add to an overall increase in GDP.  By 2030, the African market size is expected to reach 1.7 billion people, with a combined consumer and business spending of $6.7 trillion A study by UNCTAD concedes that the long term monetary benefits that AfCFTA shall yield are annual welfare gains as high as $16 billion. Estimates from the UN Economic Commission for Africa (UNECA) suggest that the AfCFTA has the potential to boost intra-African trade by 52.3%. There’s a substantial amount of evidence to show that free movement boosts the economies of countries. A study has shown that nations could increase their per-capita GDP growth by 12%, simply by being a member of the European Union. The AfCFTA document says one of its goals is to “foster a competitive manufacturing sector and promote economic diversification”. Even as 43% of the goods traded within Africa are from the manufacturing sector, it represents only about 10% of the total GDP in Africa, lagging behind other developing countries. Africa’s low level of intra-regional trade is one of the reasons for the continent’s enduring poverty and lack of a strong manufacturing base. The African economies can, therefore, leverage their gigantic population size of 1.2 billion to expand their manufacturing sector and gain a comparative cost advantage over other nations.  Apart from AfCFTA, there are some Regional Economic Communities (REC) in Africa such as ECA, SADC, ECOWAS, and COMESCA. While ECOWAS was quite successful, the other blocs have problems. Disputes continue to hamper relations and drive the countries toward not honouring agreements. For instance, Kenya and Tanzania, both members of ECA, have been engaged in a trade war. Tanzania has been known to kick out Kenyan executives and impound Kenyan imports at the border, in violation of ECA rules. While Tanzania scrapped preferential access to Kenyan textiles, Kenya allowed goods from Export Processing Zones to be sold in local markets, which prevented Tanzanian goods from being competitive. Members of COMESCA, Kenya, Tanzania and Uganda have also been blaming each other for exploiting the low import duties on sugar. That AfCFTA doesn’t have a clause to repeal all the existing trade blocs would prove a real challenge as it creates ambiguity. Then there is also the threat of countries acting in favour of their trading partners from “the regional blocs.” The success of the agreement depends on how efficiently the AU deals with these RECs. AfCFTA is to face some more challenges. The two largest economies of Africa, Nigeria and South Africa haven’t ratified the agreement yet. South Africa has assured that it would sign it once domestic legal requirements have been satisfied. However, Nigeria backed out from signing the agreement citing “the agreement would drastically affect the small business sector of the country.” “We will not agree to anything that will undermine local manufacturers and entrepreneurs, or that may lead to Nigeria becoming a dumping ground for finished goods,” Nigeria has stated. The pervasive nature of Small and Medium Enterprises (SMEs) in virtually every sector of the Nigerian economy and their place in national development is conspicuous. SMEs in Nigeria are believed to account for about 40% of GDP and 70% of industrial employment. Rice is also a factor that is preventing the largest African economy from signing the deal.  Due to various government initiatives, rice is starting to command 40% more price than what it used to 3 years back in the Nigerian markets. Interestingly,  Nigeria would largely benefit from signing the deal. With a rapidly growing population of almost 200 million, Nigeria has more workers and consumers than anywhere in Africa. For many businesses, there is no other place in Africa that can offer such a scale. This will provide a competitive advantage to Nigeria in firms’ considerations of where to set up facilities and do business. AfCFTA will expose local Nigerian firms to better practices and technologies, often through partnerships with the MNCs and sometimes through competition. This sort of exposure will challenge entrepreneurs in the country and give them greater access to the skills and partnerships they need to be dynamic in today’s world. By giving businesses access to a larger market beyond their home country, the trade agreement would allow the establishments in Nigeria (that are not profitable now) to take advantage of the economies of scale and industries to take advantage of the growth in intra-Africa relations. Remaining a non-signatory to the agreement might cost Nigeria dearly. The country’s isolation makes it difficult for local businesses to scale abroad, thus making them less attractive for foreign direct investment. In launching the African Continental Free Trade Area and making it work, Africa is overcoming the historic fragmentation and isolation of her economies by opening up huge commercial opportunities as well as improving transport and communication linkages among the countries. This connectivity will enable the vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063: “An integrated, prosperous, and peaceful Africa, driven by its citizens, representing a dynamic force in the global arena.” However, there are many roadblocks for AU to overcome in the process of successful implementation of the agreement and realising her dream of “Agenda 2063: The Africa We Want [Pan-Africanism]’’. The success of the agreement depends on how well AU manages the disputes among member nations and oversees the implementation of the agreement in true spirit.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘Missing’ Firms in GDP Calculation</title>
      <link href="/Missing-Firms-in-GDP-Calculation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="'Missing' Firms in GDP Calculation" />
      <published>2019-06-13T17:34:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-13T17:34:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Missing-Firms-in-GDP-Calculation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Missing-Firms-in-GDP-Calculation">&lt;p&gt;The controversies regarding India’s GDP numbers, with 2011-2012 as the base
year, seem to be not coming to an end. The Indian National Sampling Survey
Office’s (NSSO) study, ending June 2017, revealed that 38% of the companies
which are a part of the MCA21 database (the Modi government’s e-governance
initiative) were missing. The study implied that the inclusion of data from such
companies would grossly overestimate GDP figures.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, the Central Statistical Office (CSO) of India issued a new GDP series,
wherein the routine 2004-05 base year was replaced with 2011-12. According to Dr
R. Nagaraj, such a revision usually leads to a slight expansion of the absolute
GDP in the base year, keeping the growth rate constant. But this time, the
absolute GDP was reduced slightly in the base year and the growth rate had an
unprecedented rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were significant changes in the methodology this time. The CSO had shifted
to the latest global template, the System of National Accounts 2008, for
calculations. Moreover, the income accruing to the Private Corporate Sector
(PCS) was directly estimated using the Ministry of Corporate Affairs’ (MCA)
statutory filing of financial returns, i.e. the aforementioned MCA-21. The PCS
accounts for over one-third of the GDP, and has affected estimates of many
industries. The CSO claims that GDP calculation through MCA-21, which is a
larger database than the Annual Survey of Industries for Manufacturing used
previously, better captures the economy’s value addition, especially of smaller
enterprises and services activities. The critics, however, fear that this has
led to a gross overestimation of GDP.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The NSSO Survey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent report of the NSSO titled &lt;em&gt;Technical Report on Service Sector
Enterprises in India&lt;/em&gt; found nearly 38% of the companies surveyed using MCA21
database to be unusable for data collection purposes. Of this, 21% were “out of
coverage” firms, 12% were designated untraceable and 4.5% were closed. Many of
these companies according to Dr R. Nagaraj, are shell/fake/spurious entities
that remain legally registered (but merely on paper) but do not produce goods
and services. The only purpose is to help the owner hide the profits and, thus,
reduce the taxable income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is GDP Overestimated?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pronab Sen, former Chief Statistician, disagrees with the fact that GDP is
overestimated due to the data from the ‘missing’ firms. He explains that for the
purpose of measurement of GDP, it is more important for the statisticians that
the shell companies are submitting their balance sheets regularly to the MCA21.
These firms are involved in some form of economic activity, and not measuring
their output would mean severe underestimation of the GDP. The value creation is
happening by some other company, but the transactions are being routed through
these shell companies. Ignoring them would mean a part of the business of the
registered company is being ignored, which is wrong. Hence, the GDP will only be
correctly estimated if we include the data from the shell companies. However,
the taxable income accruing to the private sector and thus the private savings
will surely be underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, growth rates are measured over a period of time and are influenced by
the regularity with which the companies file the returns. Thus, the fact that a
large number of companies are not being measured affects the level of the
economy, but not the growth profile.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the MCA21 database is a compilation of the audited financial returns
filed by the companies. The returns are reconciled with the corporate tax
collected by the Income Tax Department. Mr Sen explains that the audit data from
MCA21 would always be better than unaudited data, the one collected from the
field. The MCA data captures value creation by an entity which is a registered
corporate. The value may be coming from the company itself or simply a book
entry from some other company. This doesn’t matter as far as gross value
addition (GVA) is concerned.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MCA21: Foolproof?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of MCA21 database, however, does have its disadvantages. The presence of
spurious firms creates low-level problems related to growth rates and gross
value addition (GVA) by different sectors. For instance, a manufacturing company
can create a shell company as a trading firm. The creation of a fake company of
such kind will lead to some of the GVA by the manufacturing sector being counted
as the GVA by the services sector.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To consider the argument that all active companies under the MCA have filed
statutory returns at least once during the last three years to be true will be a
mistake. If it were true, there would at least be one year for which there would
existent data for seven to eight hundred thousand companies, which has never
been the case. For most years data is available for around three hundred
thousand active companies. The estimates of gross value added for these three
hundred thousand companies is inflated to obtain the GVA of the universe of 10
hundred thousand companies.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There can be no denying the fact that MCA21 contains information from shell
companies. The data from such fictitious units cannot be ignored to prevent
underestimation. The only way to make the process of GDP calculation efficient
and transparent would be to weed out these shell companies. The Ministry of
Corporate Affairs (MCA) has started the process of geo-tagging the registered
offices in the returns filed with the Registrar of Companies (RoC). Geo-tagging
is the process of attaching geographical meta-data (exact latitudinal and
longitudinal information) with an online return filing system, alerting the
government if too many companies are registered on the same premises. The
process of geo-tagging is still underway and it would be too early to comment on
its effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debate on the inclusion of figures from shell companies for the calculation
of GDP and the veracity of the GDP numbers is raging. There is a need for
statisticians, economists and policymakers to sit together and find solutions to
these technical issues related to GDP calculation. Additional steps need to be
taken by the Income Tax Department and the Enforcement Directorate (India’s
white collar crime watchdog) to clamp down on the operations of such spurious
companies. The Justice Shah Commission, constituted in 2015, highlighted the
role of such companies in money laundering, which is a punishable offence under
Prevention of Money Laundering Act, 2002. A holistic government approach is
necessary to fight the menace of shell companies.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gurleen Kaur</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The controversies regarding India’s GDP numbers, with 2011-2012 as the base year, seem to be not coming to an end. The Indian National Sampling Survey Office’s (NSSO) study, ending June 2017, revealed that 38% of the companies which are a part of the MCA21 database (the Modi government’s e-governance initiative) were missing. The study implied that the inclusion of data from such companies would grossly overestimate GDP figures.   The Background In 2015, the Central Statistical Office (CSO) of India issued a new GDP series, wherein the routine 2004-05 base year was replaced with 2011-12. According to Dr R. Nagaraj, such a revision usually leads to a slight expansion of the absolute GDP in the base year, keeping the growth rate constant. But this time, the absolute GDP was reduced slightly in the base year and the growth rate had an unprecedented rise. There were significant changes in the methodology this time. The CSO had shifted to the latest global template, the System of National Accounts 2008, for calculations. Moreover, the income accruing to the Private Corporate Sector (PCS) was directly estimated using the Ministry of Corporate Affairs’ (MCA) statutory filing of financial returns, i.e. the aforementioned MCA-21. The PCS accounts for over one-third of the GDP, and has affected estimates of many industries. The CSO claims that GDP calculation through MCA-21, which is a larger database than the Annual Survey of Industries for Manufacturing used previously, better captures the economy’s value addition, especially of smaller enterprises and services activities. The critics, however, fear that this has led to a gross overestimation of GDP.   The NSSO Survey A recent report of the NSSO titled Technical Report on Service Sector Enterprises in India found nearly 38% of the companies surveyed using MCA21 database to be unusable for data collection purposes. Of this, 21% were “out of coverage” firms, 12% were designated untraceable and 4.5% were closed. Many of these companies according to Dr R. Nagaraj, are shell/fake/spurious entities that remain legally registered (but merely on paper) but do not produce goods and services. The only purpose is to help the owner hide the profits and, thus, reduce the taxable income. Is GDP Overestimated? Mr Pronab Sen, former Chief Statistician, disagrees with the fact that GDP is overestimated due to the data from the ‘missing’ firms. He explains that for the purpose of measurement of GDP, it is more important for the statisticians that the shell companies are submitting their balance sheets regularly to the MCA21. These firms are involved in some form of economic activity, and not measuring their output would mean severe underestimation of the GDP. The value creation is happening by some other company, but the transactions are being routed through these shell companies. Ignoring them would mean a part of the business of the registered company is being ignored, which is wrong. Hence, the GDP will only be correctly estimated if we include the data from the shell companies. However, the taxable income accruing to the private sector and thus the private savings will surely be underestimated. Second, growth rates are measured over a period of time and are influenced by the regularity with which the companies file the returns. Thus, the fact that a large number of companies are not being measured affects the level of the economy, but not the growth profile.   Moreover, the MCA21 database is a compilation of the audited financial returns filed by the companies. The returns are reconciled with the corporate tax collected by the Income Tax Department. Mr Sen explains that the audit data from MCA21 would always be better than unaudited data, the one collected from the field. The MCA data captures value creation by an entity which is a registered corporate. The value may be coming from the company itself or simply a book entry from some other company. This doesn’t matter as far as gross value addition (GVA) is concerned.   MCA21: Foolproof? The use of MCA21 database, however, does have its disadvantages. The presence of spurious firms creates low-level problems related to growth rates and gross value addition (GVA) by different sectors. For instance, a manufacturing company can create a shell company as a trading firm. The creation of a fake company of such kind will lead to some of the GVA by the manufacturing sector being counted as the GVA by the services sector.   To consider the argument that all active companies under the MCA have filed statutory returns at least once during the last three years to be true will be a mistake. If it were true, there would at least be one year for which there would existent data for seven to eight hundred thousand companies, which has never been the case. For most years data is available for around three hundred thousand active companies. The estimates of gross value added for these three hundred thousand companies is inflated to obtain the GVA of the universe of 10 hundred thousand companies.   There can be no denying the fact that MCA21 contains information from shell companies. The data from such fictitious units cannot be ignored to prevent underestimation. The only way to make the process of GDP calculation efficient and transparent would be to weed out these shell companies. The Ministry of Corporate Affairs (MCA) has started the process of geo-tagging the registered offices in the returns filed with the Registrar of Companies (RoC). Geo-tagging is the process of attaching geographical meta-data (exact latitudinal and longitudinal information) with an online return filing system, alerting the government if too many companies are registered on the same premises. The process of geo-tagging is still underway and it would be too early to comment on its effectiveness. The debate on the inclusion of figures from shell companies for the calculation of GDP and the veracity of the GDP numbers is raging. There is a need for statisticians, economists and policymakers to sit together and find solutions to these technical issues related to GDP calculation. Additional steps need to be taken by the Income Tax Department and the Enforcement Directorate (India’s white collar crime watchdog) to clamp down on the operations of such spurious companies. The Justice Shah Commission, constituted in 2015, highlighted the role of such companies in money laundering, which is a punishable offence under Prevention of Money Laundering Act, 2002. A holistic government approach is necessary to fight the menace of shell companies.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Inflation - Dead Or Dormant?</title>
      <link href="/Inflation-Dead-Or-Dormant" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inflation - Dead Or Dormant?" />
      <published>2019-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Inflation-Dead-Or-Dormant</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Inflation-Dead-Or-Dormant">&lt;p&gt;The US Federal Reserve, in its recent Open Market Operations Committee Meeting, chose an ambiguous stance by leaving the federal funds rate unchanged at the range of 2.25-2.5%, much to the dismay of the markets and the Government, who long awaited a rate cut. As the growth rates declined across Europe, China and US in Q1 2019, the Fed was expected to finally move away from the rate hikes, which were also offsetting the fiscal concessions provided by the US government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This monetary tightening began in late 2015, as an attempt to counter the inflation that was expected in the aftermath of using heterodox mutations like Quantitative Easing (QE) to recover demand in the largest Post-War Recession of 2008. While the Fiscal Policy has become increasingly pro-cyclical in the recent (Trump) years, the hawkish Monetary Policy attempts to counter the inflation that is already locked far behind its 2% benchmark, which has resulted in the Trump’s disapproval of Jerome Powell (thus, the threats of replacing him with political cronies like Herman Cain). The low expected inflation has not only caused the recessionary air to resurface but has also invited wild justifications for credibility restoration. Fed’s Loretta Mester recently went as far as to claim that the economy has finally reached its equilibrium in her (neo)classic defense of the recent speculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But none of the justifications explained why inflation is globally stifled for the developed economies despite the rising-but-low rates. The observation remains that the Monetary Policy is losing grip over the rate of inflation. Prices are no longer as sensitive to the interest rates as they used to be, thus, explaining the recent surge in various financial forums pronouncing inflation dead, attributing it mainly to technological advancements. In times of prosperity, inflation is high due to the increased productivity and employment, which gives the workforce the ability to bargain for greater wages, that will push up the costs and then the prices. With improved technology and reduced labour intensity, the ability of the workers to demand greater wages during an upswing has declined. Additionally, the prophecy paradox, that embodies the self-fulfilling nature of expectations in economics, comes to play. The general level of expected inflation in the markets is low which is seen to be taking its effect on the actual figures, and though these expectations are being publicized as a reflective of the credibility of the Fed, they certainly don’t go in tandem with the economic or the fiscal cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the major setback has been taken by the theory of the Phillips curve, which describes the inverse relationship between inflation and unemployment via the cost-wage spiral. This relation was violated once back in the 70s when stagflation hit the American economy. It was chiefly blamed at the rising oil prices, when in fact it was the abolition of Bretton Woods by Nixon that took a toll on the economy. Though its collapse provided the US with a monetary policy that extended beyond the clasp of the Special Drawing Rights, it immediately resulted in inflation which was previously limited to the $35/ounce gold peg. In order to tackle the inflation, the government bought in price controls which reduced the profitability of businesses, and ended up in large scale layoffs. But this direct relation had helped Milton Friedman in developing a long run perspective to the theory, and concluding that in the long run, the Phillips curve is vertical. In the short-run, however, there is sufficient scope for monetary policy to smooth out fluctuations around the independent pathway of potential output by affecting cyclical unemployment and price levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The curve has currently flattened, and this relation is no longer as strong for the developed economies as it used to be, considering how unemployment is presently at 3.9% in the USA, below its natural rate that stands at 4%, but inflation has shown no signs of a revival. A similar pattern had been witnessed right before the tech bubble had burst. This flattening of the curve is possibly a structural problem, not amenable to macroeconomic measures and it reduces the capability of the Central Banks to reach their inflation targets. But if the theory still survives, it could only mean that the Fed anticipates a pending risk for the inflation to resurface, for which the rate hikes, under the alias of a ‘friendly normalisation’, are being pursued. Perhaps inflation is not dead, but dormant and potentially on a rise, although it is ‘inflation targeting’ that might be officially dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, this inflation-interest rate relation, which is hardly ever questioned, was never a strong one, to begin with. J.Stiglitz asserts &lt;em&gt;“this rudimentary method is based on a weak economic theory and little empirical evidence…and there is no reason to believe that, whatever the source of inflation, the best solution is to raise interest rates.”&lt;/em&gt; The Central Banks have been over-relying on the Monetary Policy for every minor inconvenience as if it is a panacea for the dearth of aggregate demand. And why not? It’s the easiest way out, 2008 stands witness. But that is if we remain unreasonably adamant on the “In the long run, we’re all dead” approach. While the Fiscal Policy, despite its implementation imperfections, attempts to systematically address the economic issues at their core, the monetary policy has been globally reduced to an interest fluctuation switch, whose volatility takes its toll on its own ability. It is an important but overexploited tool that was ideally supposed to address the Dual Mandate on both price stability and employment issues through a suitable policy mix, but there seems to be no coordination among the fiscal and the monetary policy. The past few centuries stand witness to the fact that no monetary system has stood firm for over 50 years, citing the changes that the monetary policy faced in 1913, 1933, 1945 and 1971. And considering its ageing ability to address inflation, people have already started coming up with alternatives to the existing system, the most prominent one being the Modern Monetary Theory (MMT).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a fringe economic model, MMT stems out of the monetary theory of Marx, which later seems to have influenced Keynes, and is nowadays gaining mainstream attention, such as being proposed for financing the Green New Deal by Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez. It basically states that a country with its own currency can simply pay off its debt by printing more currency. The idea would seem questionable even to a layman, but this is only true if the debt is denominated in the domestic currency, which though is not the case for most of the nations, it’s certainly applicable for the USA as an advantage of USD being the major global reserve currency. This theory is often criticised for its utter disregard for the size of the deficits and the impact on inflation, but it does address these issues by manipulating the revenue side. Additionally, being a brain-child of the left doesn’t imply that it will not be accepted by the right since it can just as easily help in financing tax cuts. Major investors such as Ray Dalio, who feed off of capitalism, have stated that something like MMT will inevitably be replacing the Central Banks. In fact, MMT appears to be the only way to elude the burgeoning debt and the declining credibility of the Fed. It will help finance the fiscal profligacy every US government has inherited from its fear of lobbyists, be it progressive or conservative. Either way, it might ameliorate the system after the hawks have devoured what’s left of their monetary policy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The US Federal Reserve, in its recent Open Market Operations Committee Meeting, chose an ambiguous stance by leaving the federal funds rate unchanged at the range of 2.25-2.5%, much to the dismay of the markets and the Government, who long awaited a rate cut. As the growth rates declined across Europe, China and US in Q1 2019, the Fed was expected to finally move away from the rate hikes, which were also offsetting the fiscal concessions provided by the US government.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Robots: Magic to Manic to Toxic</title>
      <link href="/Magic-Manic-Toxic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Robots: Magic to Manic to Toxic" />
      <published>2019-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Magic-Manic-Toxic</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Magic-Manic-Toxic">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How can mankind prevail in the face of such exponential and encompassing technological change?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each new development comes at a cost. We frequently witness the dawn of a new era at the expense of the old, such as the Iron Age following the Bronze, which itself followed the Stone Age. The advent of the Industrial Revolution wiped out the livelihood of millions, such as cobblers and weavers who were forced to adapt or be left behind, and this dynamic process continues today, only now at a much faster rate. In this era of ‘The New Machine Age’, we enter a dramatical phase where even highly skilled jobs are at risk, and where there will be increasing technology and potentially decreasing jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The realities of the new Machine Age are becoming clear and we can use them to chart the challenging yet abundant economy that we are creating. According to research at Oxford University, almost one out of every two jobs has a high risk of being automated by machines. Machine Learning, the most powerful branch of Artificial Intelligence, is the technology which is to be blamed for this alarming disruption. It basically permits machines to learn from data and mimic some of the routine jobs that we humans perform, but much more efficiently. And, evidently, this can prove game-changing or extremely problematic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent study from Forrester Research goes so far as to predict that 25 million jobs might disappear over the next decade. To put that in perspective, that is three times as many as jobs lost in the aftermath of the Financial Crisis. In fact, 87% of the lost manufacturing jobs have been eliminated as a result of improvements to our own productivity through automation. Automation is spreading to every production sector in every country around the globe. Output in the manufacturing sector in the US is actually growing, but we are losing jobs and lots of them. In fact, from 2000-2010, 5.7 million manufacturing jobs were lost to machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just the blue-collar jobs that are at risk, even those at the top of the ladder, including the highest-paid people, will be affected. What is clear that no matter whatever your job, at least some of it will be done by a robot in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is that the reason why visionaries like Mark Zuckerberg and Bill Gates are talking about government-funded minimum income levels? By the time today’s elementary school students are college-aged, we could be living in a robotic world largely unemployed and stuck in an ‘ungreat depression’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is supplemented by the dangers of technological advancement beyond automation and job replacement. Consider the tasks that are now done by a phone. Navigating a strange city? Impossible without Google Maps. Can’t decide where to take your next trip? MakeMyTrip will tell me. No time to answer all my texts? Siri will do it for me. These “artificial brains” are modifying quickly from knowing me to representing me to being me. In fact, they are starting to become an e-copy of us—and if that thought is not yet disturbing, imagine the power of this digital human amplified 100x in the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose we give an AI programme the goal to make humans smile. When the AI is weak, it causes humans to smile by performing normal amusing actions. However, when the AI is super intelligent, it realises there is a more effective way to achieve this goal: take control of the world and stick electrodes into the facial muscles of humans to cause constant, beaming grins. Of course, while such a scenario sounds very alarmistic, it does highlight a fundamental problem. AI is a genie inside a bottle, so the only solution is to find a way that when it gets out, it is on our side through shared values. This does not involve spelling out a long list of what we care about in computer code, rather an AI could use its ‘intelligence’ to learn what we value. Because, after all, the real worry isn’t enmity, but competence. A superintelligent AI can attain its goals, however for the common good of the world, we need to ensure that its goals are aligned with ours. For instance, humans don’t generally hate bees, but we’re more intelligent than they are – so if humans want to build a home in the place of a beehive, too bad for the bees. The beneficial AI movement is simply a way of avoiding placing humanity in the position of those bees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work that brings everyday surprise is designed for humans and not machines. And an area in which we are most certainly able to compete with and beat any machine conceivable is creativity. Machines have made very little progress in tackling novel situations. The fundamental limitation of Machine Learning is that it requires huge volumes of past data which we humans don’t require. We have the capability to connect seemingly disparate threads to find a solution to crisis situations or problems we have never seen before. The ability of the human mind to take strands from reality and weave them into something beautiful using a vivid imagination cannot be surpassed by bits of code, no matter how intelligent it is. Indeed, an AI programme has made music, but the capacities of such programmes have a critical limitation: they cannot do something new, which is the foundation of human creativity, they can only replicate and mutate the data that is given them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, it would seem that, with the right kind of limitations on what Machine Learning is used for and an investment in human beings, we can really herald a society where man and AI work together. First, we need to change our educational institutions to help foster more and more creativity, thereby preparing the jobs market for a situation where humans no longer do many mundane jobs. The efficiencies created by this division of labour between humans and AI will reap rewards that can only be imagined. Second, we need to align AI with our value systems and morals, using it as a purposeful instrument for human betterment rather than as a sterile but disastrously potent machine. With these two broad approaches, we humans can reach even greater heights of civilisation in the coming Age. After all, to quote Max Tegmark, President of the Future of Life Institute:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Everything we love about civilization is a product of intelligence, so amplifying our human intelligence with artificial intelligence has the potential of helping a civilization flourish like never before – as long as we manage to keep the technology beneficial.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>unnati.jain sailesh.buchasia</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">How can mankind prevail in the face of such exponential and encompassing technological change?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Fintech Effect: How Digital Innovators are Disrupting Banking</title>
      <link href="/The-Fintech-Effect" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fintech Effect: How Digital Innovators are Disrupting Banking" />
      <published>2019-05-03T02:33:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-03T02:33:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Fintech-Effect</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Fintech-Effect">&lt;p&gt;The world stands on the brink of a 4th industrial revolution that will
fundamentally alter the way everyone functions, which includes the complete
disruption of many industries and their business models. Banking is one such
industry which has experienced major turmoil when it comes to digital services
and mechanisation. Every transaction, be it online shopping, foreign currency
exchange, stock investments, or money transfers, is possible digitally at our
fingertips. At the intersection of finance and technology lies this altering
phenomenon, Fintech, which has been accelerating the pace of change at a
remarkable rate and is reshaping the industry’s status quo. ‘Fintech’ is a term
that has become the new trend in the media and in technology circles. Yet,
despite being widely discussed, many – including tech-savvy and clued-up
entrepreneurs – don’t quite have a handle on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While traditionally fintech was used for back-office functions to help banks
manage customer databases, facilitate transactions and record accounts, today it
has DIY modes where customers have a plethora of digital platforms at their
disposal, almost eliminating their dependence on a brick and mortar bank. With
24/7 device-sceptic access, virtually every transaction is now digitally
possible. The relevance of having several brick and mortar bank branches is
reducing as banking permeates all digital channels (cell phones, social and
online channels). According to some studies, in the European Union itself, more
than nine thousand bank branches were closed at the end of 2016 due to the wider
introduction of electronic payments and online/mobile banking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digital Disruption: What next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legacy financial institutions looking to become digitally-enabled encounter two
main problems. First, the business models and personal skills that have been
imbibed in the industry for decades have been disrupted by digital innovation,
and no longer hold the same degree of importance in the new banking ecosystem.
Second is “the innovator’s dilemma”. The innovator’s dilemma implies that when
companies adopt new technology and allocate the resources accordingly, they end
up disrupting the existing methods, something which they were already nurturing.
Hence, they might prefer to focus resources on existing methods to avoid
disruption, which, in turn, might make them uncompetitive in the long run.
Tackling this dilemma distinguishes successful firms and how they react to
change or ‘innovation’. For banks, attempts to create new models for the digital
age will wallow unless people and organisations are willing to disrupt
themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fintech affects or disrupts the financial sector in many ways which are beyond
our supposition. For instance, the mechanism which works behind the software of
chatbots is designed to capture natural language and human interactions through
machine learning and artificial intelligence. They assist banks to direct
customers to relevant departments more efficiently while handling queries.
Leading banks in Japan have chatbots that guide customers to information on its
website. Erica, the Bank of America’s chatbot provides investment advice too.
Customer emails containing transaction orders or details can be scanned and
executed within two minutes by robots which would otherwise take over 45
minutes. This process reduces costs, improves customer satisfaction and saves
time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next big development: a blockchain for digital transactions - cryptocurrency - is triumphing over the financial industry by providing consumers with a
speedier and cheaper way to carry on transactions. According to NASDAQ, the
greatest visible application of blockchain will be in how it moulds the payment
mechanism for the banks and users in order to dwindle away the transaction time.
In addition, with a unique trust system, blockchain offers a complete trading
platform for exchanges of securities which is achieved through transparency,
minimisation of risk, human error and transaction costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The importance of fintech will increase as the next few years will see the
disappearance of the Baby Boomer generation and the coming forth of the
Millennials or Gen Y (people born between 1980-1999). As they gain purchasing
power, they will cause drastic changes in client pattern, behaviour, decision
making, demographics and expectations. Their preference for a state-of-the-art
customer experience, high speed and convenience at the click of a button will
further accelerate the inculcation of fintech solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, digital disruption is not only about the positives. Cyber-crimes are
ever growing (malware, ransomware, phishing, etc.) along with digitisation. So,
stereotyped verification mechanisms are no longer enough to thwart fraudulent
attempts. The answer to this problem also lies in technology. More secure
protocols and extreme and extensive real-time, cross-channel fraud detection
systems are now available to protect the industry. There exists machine Learning
as well as artificial intelligence for disclosure of fraudulent activities. The
security softwares generate alarms on the plausibility of a fraud. Thereupon, it
is up to the investigators to figure out whether the transaction is a false
positive or an actual peril. The adoption of data aggregation floors, machine
learning steered statistical modelling and process automation can revamp
anti-money laundering activities by inculcating advanced efficiencies. Data
aggregation platforms can provide a 360-degree client view and facilitate
speedier transaction validation as already discussed. Further, machine learning
algorithms can leverage historical records to ascertain patterns and foresee the
happening of fraud and attacks, curtailing human endeavour by nearly half of
what it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In search of a safe and personal banking experience, as well as applications for
mobile devices, smartphones, and online payments, a new chapter of introducing
financial technologies in the financial services sector is being adopted. Today,
fintech covers everything, from chatbots to customer service, from machine
learning algorithms to blockchains for fraud analysis, from digital transactions
to biometrics. Retail banks have become a new player in providing all this to
their customers, forcing traditional banks to strategically invest in innovative
technologies. All of this will eventually lead to higher consumer retention.
While fintech, like any other technology, brings with it its set of disruptions,
the best is yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>sailesh.buchasia unnati.jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The world stands on the brink of a 4th industrial revolution that will fundamentally alter the way everyone functions, which includes the complete disruption of many industries and their business models. Banking is one such industry which has experienced major turmoil when it comes to digital services and mechanisation. Every transaction, be it online shopping, foreign currency exchange, stock investments, or money transfers, is possible digitally at our fingertips. At the intersection of finance and technology lies this altering phenomenon, Fintech, which has been accelerating the pace of change at a remarkable rate and is reshaping the industry’s status quo. ‘Fintech’ is a term that has become the new trend in the media and in technology circles. Yet, despite being widely discussed, many – including tech-savvy and clued-up entrepreneurs – don’t quite have a handle on it. While traditionally fintech was used for back-office functions to help banks manage customer databases, facilitate transactions and record accounts, today it has DIY modes where customers have a plethora of digital platforms at their disposal, almost eliminating their dependence on a brick and mortar bank. With 24/7 device-sceptic access, virtually every transaction is now digitally possible. The relevance of having several brick and mortar bank branches is reducing as banking permeates all digital channels (cell phones, social and online channels). According to some studies, in the European Union itself, more than nine thousand bank branches were closed at the end of 2016 due to the wider introduction of electronic payments and online/mobile banking. Digital Disruption: What next? Legacy financial institutions looking to become digitally-enabled encounter two main problems. First, the business models and personal skills that have been imbibed in the industry for decades have been disrupted by digital innovation, and no longer hold the same degree of importance in the new banking ecosystem. Second is “the innovator’s dilemma”. The innovator’s dilemma implies that when companies adopt new technology and allocate the resources accordingly, they end up disrupting the existing methods, something which they were already nurturing. Hence, they might prefer to focus resources on existing methods to avoid disruption, which, in turn, might make them uncompetitive in the long run. Tackling this dilemma distinguishes successful firms and how they react to change or ‘innovation’. For banks, attempts to create new models for the digital age will wallow unless people and organisations are willing to disrupt themselves. Fintech affects or disrupts the financial sector in many ways which are beyond our supposition. For instance, the mechanism which works behind the software of chatbots is designed to capture natural language and human interactions through machine learning and artificial intelligence. They assist banks to direct customers to relevant departments more efficiently while handling queries. Leading banks in Japan have chatbots that guide customers to information on its website. Erica, the Bank of America’s chatbot provides investment advice too. Customer emails containing transaction orders or details can be scanned and executed within two minutes by robots which would otherwise take over 45 minutes. This process reduces costs, improves customer satisfaction and saves time. The next big development: a blockchain for digital transactions - cryptocurrency - is triumphing over the financial industry by providing consumers with a speedier and cheaper way to carry on transactions. According to NASDAQ, the greatest visible application of blockchain will be in how it moulds the payment mechanism for the banks and users in order to dwindle away the transaction time. In addition, with a unique trust system, blockchain offers a complete trading platform for exchanges of securities which is achieved through transparency, minimisation of risk, human error and transaction costs. The importance of fintech will increase as the next few years will see the disappearance of the Baby Boomer generation and the coming forth of the Millennials or Gen Y (people born between 1980-1999). As they gain purchasing power, they will cause drastic changes in client pattern, behaviour, decision making, demographics and expectations. Their preference for a state-of-the-art customer experience, high speed and convenience at the click of a button will further accelerate the inculcation of fintech solutions. However, digital disruption is not only about the positives. Cyber-crimes are ever growing (malware, ransomware, phishing, etc.) along with digitisation. So, stereotyped verification mechanisms are no longer enough to thwart fraudulent attempts. The answer to this problem also lies in technology. More secure protocols and extreme and extensive real-time, cross-channel fraud detection systems are now available to protect the industry. There exists machine Learning as well as artificial intelligence for disclosure of fraudulent activities. The security softwares generate alarms on the plausibility of a fraud. Thereupon, it is up to the investigators to figure out whether the transaction is a false positive or an actual peril. The adoption of data aggregation floors, machine learning steered statistical modelling and process automation can revamp anti-money laundering activities by inculcating advanced efficiencies. Data aggregation platforms can provide a 360-degree client view and facilitate speedier transaction validation as already discussed. Further, machine learning algorithms can leverage historical records to ascertain patterns and foresee the happening of fraud and attacks, curtailing human endeavour by nearly half of what it was. In search of a safe and personal banking experience, as well as applications for mobile devices, smartphones, and online payments, a new chapter of introducing financial technologies in the financial services sector is being adopted. Today, fintech covers everything, from chatbots to customer service, from machine learning algorithms to blockchains for fraud analysis, from digital transactions to biometrics. Retail banks have become a new player in providing all this to their customers, forcing traditional banks to strategically invest in innovative technologies. All of this will eventually lead to higher consumer retention. While fintech, like any other technology, brings with it its set of disruptions, the best is yet to come.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">United in Pay, Divided in Dues</title>
      <link href="/United-in-pay" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="United in Pay, Divided in Dues" />
      <published>2019-05-03T02:14:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-03T02:14:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/United-in-pay</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/United-in-pay">&lt;p&gt;India’s Jet Airways may have shut down all operations, but they are not the only
ones with their international business up in flames due to a financial crisis.
The United Nations has been jostling with its latest set of money problems as
well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have not been living under a rock for the past couple of weeks, you must
have already come across numerous articles like these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dmicdc.com/about-DMICDC&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//united-in-pay-1.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost every publication on the Internet that you could think of has been
reeling from this news and successfully copy-pasting news from one another.
Whichever side you look at, whatever your source is, it does not make a
difference. There have been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=moYojoQsedU&quot;&gt;YouTube
videos&lt;/a&gt;, Facebook posts, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5hJzKSJCtn8&quot;&gt;TV
monologues&lt;/a&gt; and private rants about
it. The same thing, boxed up and packaged differently, again and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Ok! The United Nations owes India money, lots of money. Now get over it”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with the discussion is that it is pointed in the wrong direction and
the whole narrative is messed up. To be honest, the United Nations is not really
at fault here. When you have a situation like this, news consumers tend to
simplify the news in their terms and react to it in the most primitive way
possible: by losing their minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dmicdc.com/about-DMICDC&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//united-in-pay-2.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, let’s get down to business. The United Nations is under a financial
crisis of unusual proportions. It is facing severe shortages in its Regular
Budget compensation, as well as its Peacekeeping Budget, which is the main
reason why they are finding it tough to repay their dues to the
Police-Contributing Countries (PCCs) and Troop-Contributing Countries (TCCs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of the beginning of April 2019, the United Nations is yet to complete $256
million in total payments, with the likes of India, Bangladesh, Nepal, Pakistan
and Rwanda each being &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/defence/un-owes-india-usd-38-million-for-peacekeeping-operations-unsg-report/articleshow/68904063.cms&quot;&gt;owed $23-38
million&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This situation has a direct link with the state of the United Nations’ cash
balance, which has fallen by $735 million since the beginning of the decade. It
currently stands at an abysmal -$323 million (yes, the minus sign is a negative
balance).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How could such a dangerous cash crunch bite the UN at this point of time? To
understand things, we have to get a better understanding of the way the UN gets
its money to function. It is a bit complex, but if you know basic maths and
possess an above-average attention span, then you will definitely get a grip of
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it works like this. The United Nations decides the amount that each country
should pay to the Regular Budget, based on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/ny.gnp.mktp.cd&quot;&gt;Gross National Income
(GNI)&lt;/a&gt; of the respective
country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It then makes a series of adjustments based on the amount of external debt of
the country, whether the country has a very low per-capita GNI and if it belongs
to the list of Least Developed Countries or not. If so, the contributions by the
country will be capped at 0.01% of the total budget. Also, every country must
pay at least 0.001% of the budget, called the minimum pay adjustment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and lastly, if a country’s share exceeds 22%, it will be brought down to and
capped at 22% of the total budget amount. The United States whose estimated
share is 23.069% is the only country that is getting a discount, in having to
pay only 22%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a great infographic from &lt;a href=&quot;https://qz.com/author/ashendrukqz/&quot;&gt;Amanda
Shendruk&lt;/a&gt; of Quartz.com, who sums it up
perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shohan Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">India’s Jet Airways may have shut down all operations, but they are not the only ones with their international business up in flames due to a financial crisis. The United Nations has been jostling with its latest set of money problems as well. If you have not been living under a rock for the past couple of weeks, you must have already come across numerous articles like these. Almost every publication on the Internet that you could think of has been reeling from this news and successfully copy-pasting news from one another. Whichever side you look at, whatever your source is, it does not make a difference. There have been YouTube videos, Facebook posts, TV monologues and private rants about it. The same thing, boxed up and packaged differently, again and again. “Ok! The United Nations owes India money, lots of money. Now get over it” The problem with the discussion is that it is pointed in the wrong direction and the whole narrative is messed up. To be honest, the United Nations is not really at fault here. When you have a situation like this, news consumers tend to simplify the news in their terms and react to it in the most primitive way possible: by losing their minds. Alright, let’s get down to business. The United Nations is under a financial crisis of unusual proportions. It is facing severe shortages in its Regular Budget compensation, as well as its Peacekeeping Budget, which is the main reason why they are finding it tough to repay their dues to the Police-Contributing Countries (PCCs) and Troop-Contributing Countries (TCCs). As of the beginning of April 2019, the United Nations is yet to complete $256 million in total payments, with the likes of India, Bangladesh, Nepal, Pakistan and Rwanda each being owed $23-38 million. This situation has a direct link with the state of the United Nations’ cash balance, which has fallen by $735 million since the beginning of the decade. It currently stands at an abysmal -$323 million (yes, the minus sign is a negative balance). How could such a dangerous cash crunch bite the UN at this point of time? To understand things, we have to get a better understanding of the way the UN gets its money to function. It is a bit complex, but if you know basic maths and possess an above-average attention span, then you will definitely get a grip of it. So, it works like this. The United Nations decides the amount that each country should pay to the Regular Budget, based on the Gross National Income (GNI) of the respective country. It then makes a series of adjustments based on the amount of external debt of the country, whether the country has a very low per-capita GNI and if it belongs to the list of Least Developed Countries or not. If so, the contributions by the country will be capped at 0.01% of the total budget. Also, every country must pay at least 0.001% of the budget, called the minimum pay adjustment. Oh, and lastly, if a country’s share exceeds 22%, it will be brought down to and capped at 22% of the total budget amount. The United States whose estimated share is 23.069% is the only country that is getting a discount, in having to pay only 22%. Here is a great infographic from Amanda Shendruk of Quartz.com, who sums it up perfectly.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Exposing the Irrational Voter, Mathematically!</title>
      <link href="/Exposing-the-Irrational-Voter" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exposing the Irrational Voter, Mathematically!" />
      <published>2019-04-26T01:45:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-26T01:45:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Exposing-the-Irrational-Voter</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Exposing-the-Irrational-Voter">&lt;p&gt;The Indian elections are right around the corner and the mood is currently in
full swing. Check the papers and you’ll barely find any real estate left for
anything else (but you can always check back with &lt;a href=&quot;http://thepangean.com&quot;&gt;The
Pangean&lt;/a&gt; for more). The juries are out and so are the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloombergquint.com/bq-blue-exclusive/elections-2019-a-manifesto-for-political-manifestos&quot;&gt;manifestos&lt;/a&gt;.
The line between celebrities and candidates gets blurrier by the day and
election campaigns are &lt;a href=&quot;https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/city/kolkata/for-mimi-chakraborty-its-all-work-and-no-sleep-before-poll-drill-starts/articleshow/68434360.cms&quot;&gt;quickly turning into promotional
tours&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One has to feel sorry for the manifestos, which the &lt;em&gt;majority&lt;/em&gt; of voters will
probably have only a glance of at most. Studies at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S002205310800080X?via%3Dihub&quot;&gt;frontiers of decision
theory&lt;/a&gt;
have shown that when people do not pay attention to candidate policy choices,
uninformed voters end up making decisions based on personalities. This seems to
explain most of the name-calling and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MkqIEWY2-aY&quot;&gt;on-stage
singing&lt;/a&gt; that candidates have
resorted to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the midst of all this, three main talking points have emerged: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiainfoline.com/article/general-blog/rising-unemployment-and-the-future-of-indian-youth-118112200298_1.html&quot;&gt;youth
unemployment&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fairobserver.com/region/central_south_asia/indian-farmer-suicides-india-south-asian-world-news-latest-32349/&quot;&gt;farmer’s
perils&lt;/a&gt;
and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2018/06/27/india-ranked-worlds-most-dangerous-place-for-women-reigniting-debate-about-womens-safety/?noredirect=on&amp;amp;utm_term=.933d533d9a10&quot;&gt;safety of
women&lt;/a&gt;.
It is no doubt that these topics will be sticking out as the major drivers of
the 2019 Indian election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a look at some data that will give us some insight into the State of the
Nation. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cmie.com/kommon/bin/sr.php?kall=warticle&amp;amp;dt=2019-01-08%2009:28:37&amp;amp;msec=666&quot;&gt;Centre for Monitoring Indian
Economy&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cmie.com/kommon/bin/sr.php?kall=warticle&amp;amp;dt=2019-01-08%2009:28:37&amp;amp;msec=666&quot;&gt;CMIE&lt;/a&gt;)
estimated that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thehindu.com/opinion/lead/surveying-indias-unemployment-numbers/article26218615.ece&quot;&gt;11 million
jobs&lt;/a&gt;
were lost in 2018 – pushing the unemployment rate to 7.38%. A leaked NSSO report
pegged the unemployment rate at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.business-standard.com/article/economy-policy/unemployment-rate-at-four-decade-high-nsso-survey-compared-past-figures-119020100042_1.html&quot;&gt;6.1%&lt;/a&gt;,
the highest in over four decades. Things do not look so good for our youth at
work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about the farmers, the bedrock of our society? Well, this is where
things go further downhill. According to Wholesale Price Index
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://tradingeconomics.com/india/producer-prices-change&quot;&gt;WPI&lt;/a&gt;) data for the
month of December released by the Ministry of Commerce and Industry, the WPI
sub-component for primary food articles has been negative for six consecutive
months beginning July 2018. This is a direct indication of the sliding prices
that farmers have been facing for their produce, which has led to innumerable
suicides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women’s safety is also experiencing issues that India cannot seem to get away
from that have been lingering for far too long and are only getting worse.
According to a recent poll of 548 experts by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://poll2018.trust.org/country/?id=india&quot;&gt;Thomson Reuters
Foundation&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“India ranked 1st among the world’s most dangerous countries for women.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No progress here, ladies and gentlemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The situation is dire and the immediate need for change is crystal clear. It is
also understood that this summer the onus is on the people to effect change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But can we &lt;em&gt;trust&lt;/em&gt; the voters? How rational are they when it comes to making
decisions? How rational are &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where our rant comes to an end and the &lt;em&gt;dissection&lt;/em&gt; begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us play a little game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elections are only about promises and promises do not hold up most of the time,
so we reduce them to a matter of &lt;em&gt;probability&lt;/em&gt;. Now, let’s see how you and your
choices fare in our mock election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let there be two political parties, A and B, standing in the elections. Party A
promises to reduce unemployment by 20%, with a 100% chance of fulfilling his
promise. Whereas, Party B promises to reduce unemployment by 35%, with a 15 out
of 16 chance of fulfilling his promise. To put it neatly,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;20% unemployment drop, with certainty (100% Guarantee).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;35% unemployment reduction, with 15/16 chance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go on. Take your pick. Is it party A or party B? Who would you bank on for the
country’s sake?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, here’s a second case to choose from.  Party A promises a 20% reduction in
unemployment, only now with a 16% chance of fulfilling his promise. Whereas,
Party B promises 35% fall, with a 15% chance. Restating it,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;20% unemployment drop, with a 16% chance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;35% unemployment reduction, with a 15% chance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, whom did you pick? If you happened to pick Party A in Case 1, then you are
like the majority, who prefer certainty over chance. For those who chose Party B
in the first case, you were ready to take the risk for the greater reward. But
there is nothing wrong with either choice, the real game starts with Case 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, what about Case 2?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, here’s the bombshell. Case 2 is equal to Case 1 with a one-sixth chance.
That is, Case 2 is the same situation as Case 1, only with a 16% probability.
The change between the party’s probability of fulfilling promises in both cases
was proportional and thus, renders both cases to be the absolute same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if the problem never changed, did your choice of candidates change? From B to
A, or A to B?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you did not, then congratulations, you have
rational preferences. If you did, then there are more than a few things at work
here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us try another problem of this sort. Whether or not the government promised
to deposit &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businesstoday.in/current/economy-politics/bjp-never-promised-to-deposit-rs-15-lakh-in-people-bank-accounts-rajnath-singh/story/335629.html&quot;&gt;Rs. 15
Lakh&lt;/a&gt;
in everyone’s accounts, it is always possible another party will make a similar
promise in the run-up to the elections. Farmers are definitely in need of severe
financial help, so take Party A and Party B who make the respective
&lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/economy/agriculture/budget-2019-income-support-for-farmers-a-progressive-step-but-not-enough-to-mitigate-stress/articleshow/67802322.cms&quot;&gt;income-support&lt;/a&gt;
promises:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 11,000 a year, with an 11% chance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 11,000 a year, &lt;b&gt;guaranteed&lt;/b&gt; (100% chance).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance, and Rs 11,000 a year, with an 89%
chance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who gets the vote, in each case, this time around? Did you choose the same party
both times, or different parties? Choosing different parties is a sign of
incoherent decision-making. This is because Case 1 is once again of a similar
form as Case 2. There has been no significant change in the factors that should
influence your decision-making. Yet there will be more than a few instances of
people making unidentical choices for Cases 1 and 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time to do a bit of explaining. Consider these cases as lotteries. Both Party A
and Party B have an 89% chance of not fulfilling any promise in Case 1. But
wait? Didn’t Party B promise a 10% chance? So it gives us (100% -10%=) 90%
chance of empty-handed farmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, there is the existence of a lottery within a lottery; a &lt;strong&gt;compound&lt;/strong&gt;
lottery, so to speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lottery within is actually a 10 out of 11 chance of receiving Rs 15000 and 1
out of 11 chance of getting Rs 0. So when it is nested inside the outer lottery
of Party B, we get&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;11% x [( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)]   + 89% x Rs 0&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is essentially,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance and Rs 0, with a 90% chance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know, things are getting discombobulated in your head, but stay with me.
Eventually, what we are left with is a much detailed way to re-write and
represent Cases 1 and 2 as &lt;em&gt;nested&lt;/em&gt; probabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: 11% x &lt;em&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;Rs 11,000&lt;/span&gt; +   &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;89% x Rs 0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;11% x [&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)&lt;/span&gt;]   +  &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;89% x Rs 0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: 11% x &lt;em&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;Rs 11,000&lt;/span&gt; +   &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;89% x Rs 11,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;11% x [&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)&lt;/span&gt;]   + &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;89% x Rs 11,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parts marked in &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;Red&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; are the actual &lt;em&gt;determinants&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; factors
when it comes to decision-making between the two parties. The segments marked in
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;Blue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; are offered by &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; parties and thus, should not be a determining
factor in rational choosing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you ended up choosing A in Case 1 and B in Case 2 (or vice versa), you
have just chosen two different answers for the same problem. Do you see it now?
That is where rational preferences are violated and we can now find our
&lt;em&gt;irrational voter&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all this, we come to the origins of the problem. The lack of coherence
empirically observed above is called the &lt;strong&gt;Allais Paradox&lt;/strong&gt;, and has been the
talk of game theorists and psychologists for years. First published in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://wolfweb.unr.edu/homepage/pingle/Teaching/BADM%20791/Week%206%20Decision%20Making%20Under%20Uncertainty/Allais%20Paradox%201953.pdf&quot;&gt;1953&lt;/a&gt;,
in the &lt;em&gt;Econometrica&lt;/em&gt; journal by French economist Maurice Allais, the Allais
Paradox was observed among subjects who, when presented with choices such as the
ones above, made snap decisions that were proven to be incoherent upon further
study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although not everyone got it wrong, a significant number of people made the
error which prompted him to wonder whether there was more than just rationality
behind human choices. So the Allais Paradox started off as more of a standout
against conventional rationality theory, than as the rationality test that it
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/zJZvoiwydJ5zvzTHK/the-allais-paradox&quot;&gt;has evolved to
today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maurice Allais did end up &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/economic-sciences/1988/summary/&quot;&gt;winning the 1988 Nobel Prize in
Economics&lt;/a&gt;
but it was not until 20 years after it was first published, that the Allais
Paradox was brought back to the mainstream by Daniel Kahneman. In a way, the
Allais Paradox was what got Nobel laureate Daniel Kahneman (2002 Nobel laureate)
into economics. He along with Amos Tversky, were two young psychologists back in
the 1970s who came across this paradox and were so intrigued by the study of
human approach towards uncertainty that they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1207/S15427579JPFM0402_01&quot;&gt;opened up new
dimensions&lt;/a&gt; in
the world of economics and &lt;a href=&quot;http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/economics/laureates/2002/&quot;&gt;decision-making under
uncertainty&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maurice Allais had made one of the foremost and yet perplexing dives into human
rationality and for that, today, the world is in a better position to understand
human behaviour and decision-making. And while we are on the topic of making
decisions, we get back to the decision of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This election may be driven by 3 &lt;em&gt;central&lt;/em&gt; issues: unemployment, farmers and
women’s protection. But at the end of the day, it is the people who &lt;em&gt;drive&lt;/em&gt;
elections. Yet what we often overlook is what drives the &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt; and their
&lt;em&gt;choices&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we as smart as we think we are? Does being &lt;em&gt;irrational&lt;/em&gt; only mean being
‘unreasonable’ or ‘baseless’ as the Dictionary says? Or is there more to this
than meets the eye &lt;em&gt;or brain&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On that note, we ask you to think twice before calling someone else irrational.
Oh, and yes, don’t forget to think twice before voting. Happy elections!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*31st May, 2019 marks the 108th Birth Anniversary of French physicist and
economist Maurice Allais, best known for his contributions to the neoclassical
synthesis and the Allais Paradox.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shohan Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Indian elections are right around the corner and the mood is currently in full swing. Check the papers and you’ll barely find any real estate left for anything else (but you can always check back with The Pangean for more). The juries are out and so are the manifestos. The line between celebrities and candidates gets blurrier by the day and election campaigns are quickly turning into promotional tours. One has to feel sorry for the manifestos, which the majority of voters will probably have only a glance of at most. Studies at the frontiers of decision theory have shown that when people do not pay attention to candidate policy choices, uninformed voters end up making decisions based on personalities. This seems to explain most of the name-calling and on-stage singing that candidates have resorted to. In the midst of all this, three main talking points have emerged: youth unemployment, farmer’s perils and the safety of women. It is no doubt that these topics will be sticking out as the major drivers of the 2019 Indian election. Here’s a look at some data that will give us some insight into the State of the Nation. The Centre for Monitoring Indian Economy (CMIE) estimated that 11 million jobs were lost in 2018 – pushing the unemployment rate to 7.38%. A leaked NSSO report pegged the unemployment rate at 6.1%, the highest in over four decades. Things do not look so good for our youth at work. But what about the farmers, the bedrock of our society? Well, this is where things go further downhill. According to Wholesale Price Index (WPI) data for the month of December released by the Ministry of Commerce and Industry, the WPI sub-component for primary food articles has been negative for six consecutive months beginning July 2018. This is a direct indication of the sliding prices that farmers have been facing for their produce, which has led to innumerable suicides. Women’s safety is also experiencing issues that India cannot seem to get away from that have been lingering for far too long and are only getting worse. According to a recent poll of 548 experts by the Thomson Reuters Foundation, “India ranked 1st among the world’s most dangerous countries for women.” No progress here, ladies and gentlemen. The situation is dire and the immediate need for change is crystal clear. It is also understood that this summer the onus is on the people to effect change. But can we trust the voters? How rational are they when it comes to making decisions? How rational are you? This is where our rant comes to an end and the dissection begins. Let us play a little game. Elections are only about promises and promises do not hold up most of the time, so we reduce them to a matter of probability. Now, let’s see how you and your choices fare in our mock election. Let there be two political parties, A and B, standing in the elections. Party A promises to reduce unemployment by 20%, with a 100% chance of fulfilling his promise. Whereas, Party B promises to reduce unemployment by 35%, with a 15 out of 16 chance of fulfilling his promise. To put it neatly, Case 1 A: 20% unemployment drop, with certainty (100% Guarantee). B: 35% unemployment reduction, with 15/16 chance. Go on. Take your pick. Is it party A or party B? Who would you bank on for the country’s sake? Ok, here’s a second case to choose from.  Party A promises a 20% reduction in unemployment, only now with a 16% chance of fulfilling his promise. Whereas, Party B promises 35% fall, with a 15% chance. Restating it, Case 2 A: 20% unemployment drop, with a 16% chance. B: 35% unemployment reduction, with a 15% chance. So, whom did you pick? If you happened to pick Party A in Case 1, then you are like the majority, who prefer certainty over chance. For those who chose Party B in the first case, you were ready to take the risk for the greater reward. But there is nothing wrong with either choice, the real game starts with Case 2. Now, what about Case 2? Well, here’s the bombshell. Case 2 is equal to Case 1 with a one-sixth chance. That is, Case 2 is the same situation as Case 1, only with a 16% probability. The change between the party’s probability of fulfilling promises in both cases was proportional and thus, renders both cases to be the absolute same. So if the problem never changed, did your choice of candidates change? From B to A, or A to B? If you did not, then congratulations, you have rational preferences. If you did, then there are more than a few things at work here. Let us try another problem of this sort. Whether or not the government promised to deposit Rs. 15 Lakh in everyone’s accounts, it is always possible another party will make a similar promise in the run-up to the elections. Farmers are definitely in need of severe financial help, so take Party A and Party B who make the respective income-support promises: Case 1 A: Rs 11,000 a year, with an 11% chance B: Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance Case 2 A: Rs 11,000 a year, guaranteed (100% chance). B: Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance, and Rs 11,000 a year, with an 89% chance Who gets the vote, in each case, this time around? Did you choose the same party both times, or different parties? Choosing different parties is a sign of incoherent decision-making. This is because Case 1 is once again of a similar form as Case 2. There has been no significant change in the factors that should influence your decision-making. Yet there will be more than a few instances of people making unidentical choices for Cases 1 and 2. Time to do a bit of explaining. Consider these cases as lotteries. Both Party A and Party B have an 89% chance of not fulfilling any promise in Case 1. But wait? Didn’t Party B promise a 10% chance? So it gives us (100% -10%=) 90% chance of empty-handed farmers. Here, there is the existence of a lottery within a lottery; a compound lottery, so to speak. The lottery within is actually a 10 out of 11 chance of receiving Rs 15000 and 1 out of 11 chance of getting Rs 0. So when it is nested inside the outer lottery of Party B, we get B: 11% x [( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)]   + 89% x Rs 0 Which is essentially, B: Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance and Rs 0, with a 90% chance I know, things are getting discombobulated in your head, but stay with me. Eventually, what we are left with is a much detailed way to re-write and represent Cases 1 and 2 as nested probabilities. Case 1 A: 11% x Rs 11,000 +   89% x Rs 0 B: 11% x [( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)]   +  89% x Rs 0 Case 2 A: 11% x Rs 11,000 +   89% x Rs 11,000 B: 11% x [( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)]   + 89% x Rs 11,000 The parts marked in Red are the actual determinants and the only factors when it comes to decision-making between the two parties. The segments marked in Blue are offered by both parties and thus, should not be a determining factor in rational choosing. So if you ended up choosing A in Case 1 and B in Case 2 (or vice versa), you have just chosen two different answers for the same problem. Do you see it now? That is where rational preferences are violated and we can now find our irrational voter. After all this, we come to the origins of the problem. The lack of coherence empirically observed above is called the Allais Paradox, and has been the talk of game theorists and psychologists for years. First published in 1953, in the Econometrica journal by French economist Maurice Allais, the Allais Paradox was observed among subjects who, when presented with choices such as the ones above, made snap decisions that were proven to be incoherent upon further study. Although not everyone got it wrong, a significant number of people made the error which prompted him to wonder whether there was more than just rationality behind human choices. So the Allais Paradox started off as more of a standout against conventional rationality theory, than as the rationality test that it has evolved to today. Maurice Allais did end up winning the 1988 Nobel Prize in Economics but it was not until 20 years after it was first published, that the Allais Paradox was brought back to the mainstream by Daniel Kahneman. In a way, the Allais Paradox was what got Nobel laureate Daniel Kahneman (2002 Nobel laureate) into economics. He along with Amos Tversky, were two young psychologists back in the 1970s who came across this paradox and were so intrigued by the study of human approach towards uncertainty that they opened up new dimensions in the world of economics and decision-making under uncertainty. Maurice Allais had made one of the foremost and yet perplexing dives into human rationality and for that, today, the world is in a better position to understand human behaviour and decision-making. And while we are on the topic of making decisions, we get back to the decision of the year. This election may be driven by 3 central issues: unemployment, farmers and women’s protection. But at the end of the day, it is the people who drive elections. Yet what we often overlook is what drives the people and their choices. Are we as smart as we think we are? Does being irrational only mean being ‘unreasonable’ or ‘baseless’ as the Dictionary says? Or is there more to this than meets the eye or brain? On that note, we ask you to think twice before calling someone else irrational. Oh, and yes, don’t forget to think twice before voting. Happy elections! *31st May, 2019 marks the 108th Birth Anniversary of French physicist and economist Maurice Allais, best known for his contributions to the neoclassical synthesis and the Allais Paradox.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">CLO’s - The New Danger to Financial Markets?</title>
      <link href="/CLO" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CLO’s - The New Danger to  Financial Markets?" />
      <published>2019-04-25T14:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-25T14:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/CLO</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/CLO">&lt;p&gt;It’s funny to see the people who run financial markets so eagerly rushing into
committing the same mistake. Rushing for what? The same old, usual story. The
enticement of higher profits by undertaking higher risks provides the same high
to these investors as drugs do to teens. The global financial markets, which had
a near-death experience with CDOs just a decade ago, face a new product ready to
facilitate its total obliteration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The product in question this time is CLOs, or Collateralized Loan Obligations.
Believed to be a safer version of the infamous CDOs, or Collateralized Debt
Obligations, which was one of the main culprits of the 2008 Financial Crisis,
CLOs are already raising eyebrows all around the world. With the Governor of The
Bank of England Mark Carney and the former Fed Chairman Janet Yellen warning
about the potential risks, governments and the public are becoming wary.
However, it looks like these warnings are having no effect on banks and
institutional investors, for whom it was intended, as they continue buying CLOs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A CLO is very similar to a CDO which, as mentioned earlier, was the main reason
for the downfall of the financial markets in 2008. A CLO is basically a huge
collection of loans given out by a bank for sale to banks and institutional
investors in small tranches or groups. The benefit that an investor gains from
buying a CLO is that he gets to earn the entire interest from the loans in his
group or “tranche”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the amount of CLOs currently outstanding in the world crossing  $700
billion, and with $100 billion being added each year, the amount of CLOs has
already reached the levels of CDOs before the Financial Crisis of 2008. The
structuring of a CLO is the same as a CDO. The groups of CLOs are rated by
rating agencies on the basis of the overall creditworthiness and mortgaged
assets. The CLO groups are majorly rated into AA, BBB+, BBB- and so on. Within
each individual group, each specific tranche is also rated. Hence, in an AA
class group, there are tranches rated AA, BBB+, BBB- and so forth. The same goes
for the BBB+ class group and all the other groups which follow. The highest
tranche of the highest group is paid first, followed by all the tranches in the
highest group, which is followed by all the groups and their respective
tranches. Hence, the lowest class tranche of the lowest group is the riskiest,
and promises the highest return, whereas, the highest class tranche of the
highest group is the safest and promises least return. This allows investors to
invest in groups and tranches according to their risk appetite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way in which CLOs have differed from CDOs have been stricter banking
regulations and the type of loans which are being put into the groups. Instead
of having only housing loans, CLOs offer a wide variety of loans such as
automobiles, housing, retail and so on. Moreover, stricter regulations demand
that banks hold some proportion of each group of CLOs in order to ensure that to
earn a riskless profit, the banks are not just giving loans to any individual
they meet, which happened in the case of CDOs during the Financial Crisis of
2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proponents of CLOs point towards the double-digit returns, low default rates and
resilience to rising interest rates. With banks such as Credit Suisse, Nomura,
Barclays and JP Morgan Chase showing confidence in CLOs due to its high returns
and substantially low risks, the demand for CLOs is rising in international
markets. The industry is stressing the fact that CLOs are not as vulnerable to
rising interest rates as CDOs were a decade ago. They also stress the fact that
only 36 tranches among the 1500 plus CLOs rated by S&amp;amp;P Global Ratings have
defaulted since 1994.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are downfalls. Investors assume that the portfolios are safer as
they are better diversified. But, diversification of portfolios has led to them
being made of fewer and larger loans, which increases concentration risk. These
leveraged loans are highly sensitive to economic conditions, with many loans
defaulting as soon as the economic conditions take a downturn. The condition
will be particularly adverse for Japanese banks, which have bought 75% of AAA
tranches and one-third of all CLOs, finance their operations by borrowing from
international markets. Losses can lead to difficulties in continuing operations,
which in turn may lead to a liquidity squeeze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of a downturn, the CLOs pose a risk of creating adverse feedback
loops. Banks will be stuck with unsold loans clogging up inventories due to a
decrease in demand. Falling prices and tightening credit availability will cause
credit markets to seize up. Tighter credit will feed into the real economy
triggering losses, selling and price declines. Fears about the financial
positions of banks and investors will create havoc as depositors refuse to fund
banks and investors demand their money back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, it is clear that governments need to set in motion regulations and a
robust framework on how to go about dealing with CLOs. This is extremely
necessary as everyone today is accepting the fact that CLOs are a potentially
dangerous item capable of causing devastating chaos in the international
markets. Still, banks and institutional investors are pouring money into this
product with the hopes of higher returns from the higher risks they undertake.
It is clear that CLOs have the capability to topple the global financial markets
if it spirals out of control. Therefore, with the world talking of another
financial crisis, the question that needs to be answered is will it be the
phoenix of CDOs that proves to be the catalyst? The danger that currently
beholds us is that if we keep allowing investment junkies to get their
risk-fuelled fix, it will be the rest of us left to pick up the tab if the
international financial system enters rehab.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhishek Sancheti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It’s funny to see the people who run financial markets so eagerly rushing into committing the same mistake. Rushing for what? The same old, usual story. The enticement of higher profits by undertaking higher risks provides the same high to these investors as drugs do to teens. The global financial markets, which had a near-death experience with CDOs just a decade ago, face a new product ready to facilitate its total obliteration. The product in question this time is CLOs, or Collateralized Loan Obligations. Believed to be a safer version of the infamous CDOs, or Collateralized Debt Obligations, which was one of the main culprits of the 2008 Financial Crisis, CLOs are already raising eyebrows all around the world. With the Governor of The Bank of England Mark Carney and the former Fed Chairman Janet Yellen warning about the potential risks, governments and the public are becoming wary. However, it looks like these warnings are having no effect on banks and institutional investors, for whom it was intended, as they continue buying CLOs. A CLO is very similar to a CDO which, as mentioned earlier, was the main reason for the downfall of the financial markets in 2008. A CLO is basically a huge collection of loans given out by a bank for sale to banks and institutional investors in small tranches or groups. The benefit that an investor gains from buying a CLO is that he gets to earn the entire interest from the loans in his group or “tranche”. With the amount of CLOs currently outstanding in the world crossing  $700 billion, and with $100 billion being added each year, the amount of CLOs has already reached the levels of CDOs before the Financial Crisis of 2008. The structuring of a CLO is the same as a CDO. The groups of CLOs are rated by rating agencies on the basis of the overall creditworthiness and mortgaged assets. The CLO groups are majorly rated into AA, BBB+, BBB- and so on. Within each individual group, each specific tranche is also rated. Hence, in an AA class group, there are tranches rated AA, BBB+, BBB- and so forth. The same goes for the BBB+ class group and all the other groups which follow. The highest tranche of the highest group is paid first, followed by all the tranches in the highest group, which is followed by all the groups and their respective tranches. Hence, the lowest class tranche of the lowest group is the riskiest, and promises the highest return, whereas, the highest class tranche of the highest group is the safest and promises least return. This allows investors to invest in groups and tranches according to their risk appetite. The only way in which CLOs have differed from CDOs have been stricter banking regulations and the type of loans which are being put into the groups. Instead of having only housing loans, CLOs offer a wide variety of loans such as automobiles, housing, retail and so on. Moreover, stricter regulations demand that banks hold some proportion of each group of CLOs in order to ensure that to earn a riskless profit, the banks are not just giving loans to any individual they meet, which happened in the case of CDOs during the Financial Crisis of 2008. Proponents of CLOs point towards the double-digit returns, low default rates and resilience to rising interest rates. With banks such as Credit Suisse, Nomura, Barclays and JP Morgan Chase showing confidence in CLOs due to its high returns and substantially low risks, the demand for CLOs is rising in international markets. The industry is stressing the fact that CLOs are not as vulnerable to rising interest rates as CDOs were a decade ago. They also stress the fact that only 36 tranches among the 1500 plus CLOs rated by S&amp;amp;P Global Ratings have defaulted since 1994. However, there are downfalls. Investors assume that the portfolios are safer as they are better diversified. But, diversification of portfolios has led to them being made of fewer and larger loans, which increases concentration risk. These leveraged loans are highly sensitive to economic conditions, with many loans defaulting as soon as the economic conditions take a downturn. The condition will be particularly adverse for Japanese banks, which have bought 75% of AAA tranches and one-third of all CLOs, finance their operations by borrowing from international markets. Losses can lead to difficulties in continuing operations, which in turn may lead to a liquidity squeeze. In the case of a downturn, the CLOs pose a risk of creating adverse feedback loops. Banks will be stuck with unsold loans clogging up inventories due to a decrease in demand. Falling prices and tightening credit availability will cause credit markets to seize up. Tighter credit will feed into the real economy triggering losses, selling and price declines. Fears about the financial positions of banks and investors will create havoc as depositors refuse to fund banks and investors demand their money back. Hence, it is clear that governments need to set in motion regulations and a robust framework on how to go about dealing with CLOs. This is extremely necessary as everyone today is accepting the fact that CLOs are a potentially dangerous item capable of causing devastating chaos in the international markets. Still, banks and institutional investors are pouring money into this product with the hopes of higher returns from the higher risks they undertake. It is clear that CLOs have the capability to topple the global financial markets if it spirals out of control. Therefore, with the world talking of another financial crisis, the question that needs to be answered is will it be the phoenix of CDOs that proves to be the catalyst? The danger that currently beholds us is that if we keep allowing investment junkies to get their risk-fuelled fix, it will be the rest of us left to pick up the tab if the international financial system enters rehab.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Industrial Corridors in India: A New Vehicle for Industrialisation</title>
      <link href="/Industrial-Corridors-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Industrial Corridors in India: A New Vehicle for Industrialisation" />
      <published>2019-04-19T23:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-19T23:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Industrial-Corridors-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Industrial-Corridors-India">&lt;p&gt;According to a Briefing Paper prepared for the UK’s House of Commons, China’s
share as a percentage of world manufacturing is 20% and as a percentage of its
GDP, it is 27%. In contrast, for India, the corresponding figures stand dismally
at 4% and 16% respectively. The Report has taken manufacturing output in 2015 as
the basis, using 2005 exchange rates. The burgeoning services sector
contribution to India’s GDP during the last decade has gone past 60%, whereas
the contribution of manufacturing activity to GDP has remained virtually
stagnant. This clearly indicates that India has been quick to adopt
technological advances in the services sector, but has failed to encourage
manufacturing entrepreneurship. Over the years, a clear need has been felt to
boost manufacturing activity in India. Mass consumerization of Indian society
due to rising disposable income and increased rural electrification have led to
a rise in demand for electronic consumer goods. It is expected to reach ₹3.15
trillion in the year 2022. If quality domestic products are not available,
people will buy imported goods. All this has further added to the necessity of
manufacturing led industrialisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to boost domestic manufacturing, the Indian Government tried to emulate
the Chinese experience as China had immensely benefited from its SEZ (Special
Economic Zones) policy. On similar lines, India enacted the SEZ Act in 2005.
However, Indian SEZs lacked the all-important connectivity to ports and thus,
failed to augment manufacturing activity in the country. It is this realisation
that has resulted in the introduction of the concept of industrial corridors
that is modelled on similar corridors in Japan and China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is an Industrial Corridor?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An industrial corridor or economic corridor is a pathway comprising
manufacturing clusters, ancillary units and smart cities connected with rail,
road, air or sea links. The Indian government has envisaged five integrated
industrial corridors across the country in partnership with the respective State
governments. The National Industrial Corridor Development &amp;amp; Implementation Trust
(NICDIT) has been established as the apex body to oversee development of all
industrial corridors across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dmicdc.com/about-DMICDC&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Industrial_Corridors.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Source:&lt;/b&gt; http://www.dmicdc.com/about-DMICDC
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Industrial Corridor as Wheels of Progress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industrial corridors recognise the interdependence of various sectors of the
economy and offer effective integration between industry and infrastructure
leading to overall socio-economic development. Industrial corridors lead to the
creation of state-of-art infrastructure such as high-speed transportation
(rail/road) networks, ports with advanced cargo handling equipment, modern
airports, special economic regions/ industrial areas, logistic parks, etc. that
are focused on fulfilling the requirements of the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The late C.K. Prahalad, a renowned management expert, had said that over the
next three decades if India does not create new cities to accommodate a whopping
500 million people desirous of urban life, every existing city would become a
slum. The establishment of manufacturing zones along the industrial corridors
will prevent distress migration and provide people with job opportunities close
to their dwelling place. The new smart cities created will mark the beginning of
a new wave of urbanisation in India and reduce pressure on existing cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The buzz word connecting the various programmes PM of Modi’s Government - Make
in India, Digital India, and Skill India - is employment generation. Smart
cities and industrial corridors are no exceptions. The educational institutions,
roads, railways, airports, hospitals that will come up in these corridors is
expected to generate employment and raise the overall standard of living. The
government is targeting 100 million new jobs through industrial corridors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Way Forward&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘The wheels of progress’ are encountering a plethora of issues on their road to
success, however. Of all the issues, acquisition of land at a snail’s pace is
the single biggest concern owing to the Right to Fair Compensation and
Transparency in Land Acquisition, Rehabilitation and Resettlement Act, 2013. To
take an example, the $100-billion Delhi-Mumbai Industrial Corridor (DMIC) was
expected to be completed in three phases spread over nine years starting from
January 2008. However, owing to mostly land acquisition issues, the first phase
is likely to be completed by December 2019 and revised deadlines for the second
phase and third phase have already been shifted to 2027 and 2037. The
governments at both India’s Central and State levels need to work out a
comprehensive land acquisition policy and not approach this issue in a piecemeal
manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, as India lacks technological expertise, it is prudent to bring in
foreign direct investment through established foreign entities that have the
required skill. At the same time, it is also important to encourage Indian
investment in setting up ancillary units in the same sector. This will provide
for smooth backward integration by ensuring regular supply of raw materials and
forward integration by providing ready markets. For example, the Chennai to
Bengaluru defence production corridor in India’s southern States will pass
through towns such as Trichy, Coimbatore, Salem and Hosur and will connect
ordnance factories and defence public sector units to ancillary units (which are
small and medium scale industries in the said corridor). The supplies from these
units to factories and Public Sector Undertakings is an example of forward
integration and purchases by the latter is backward integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, in order to encourage FDI, the government needs to rationalise the tax
structure. India’s corporate tax rate is high in comparison to many ASEAN
countries and stands at 30%. It is 20% in Cambodia, Thailand and Vietnam.
Moreover, India also has very high import tariffs that make manufacturing of
products with imported components economically unviable or expensive as compared
to countries like Taiwan. To achieve success, the government should rationalise
the tariff structure, realising that it is export promotion not import
prevention that actually benefits an economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategy of industrial corridors is poised to develop a sound industrial
base, characterised by excellent infrastructure and uninhibited growth of
manufacturing. However, all this would remain only rhetoric if stumbling blocks
are not removed and issues plaguing industrial corridor projects are not
resolved. This requires a holistic approach and involvement of all the
government departments, stakeholders such as farmers from whom land is to be
acquired, manufacturers who would be setting units for production, transport
operators, etc. With the onset of election season in India, it would be naive to
assume anyone has the time to truly calibrate policy, but with a new Government
and new ambitions post elections, one can only hope that the Industrial
Corridors project will take on new heights.  &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">According to a Briefing Paper prepared for the UK’s House of Commons, China’s share as a percentage of world manufacturing is 20% and as a percentage of its GDP, it is 27%. In contrast, for India, the corresponding figures stand dismally at 4% and 16% respectively. The Report has taken manufacturing output in 2015 as the basis, using 2005 exchange rates. The burgeoning services sector contribution to India’s GDP during the last decade has gone past 60%, whereas the contribution of manufacturing activity to GDP has remained virtually stagnant. This clearly indicates that India has been quick to adopt technological advances in the services sector, but has failed to encourage manufacturing entrepreneurship. Over the years, a clear need has been felt to boost manufacturing activity in India. Mass consumerization of Indian society due to rising disposable income and increased rural electrification have led to a rise in demand for electronic consumer goods. It is expected to reach ₹3.15 trillion in the year 2022. If quality domestic products are not available, people will buy imported goods. All this has further added to the necessity of manufacturing led industrialisation. In order to boost domestic manufacturing, the Indian Government tried to emulate the Chinese experience as China had immensely benefited from its SEZ (Special Economic Zones) policy. On similar lines, India enacted the SEZ Act in 2005. However, Indian SEZs lacked the all-important connectivity to ports and thus, failed to augment manufacturing activity in the country. It is this realisation that has resulted in the introduction of the concept of industrial corridors that is modelled on similar corridors in Japan and China. What is an Industrial Corridor? An industrial corridor or economic corridor is a pathway comprising manufacturing clusters, ancillary units and smart cities connected with rail, road, air or sea links. The Indian government has envisaged five integrated industrial corridors across the country in partnership with the respective State governments. The National Industrial Corridor Development &amp;amp; Implementation Trust (NICDIT) has been established as the apex body to oversee development of all industrial corridors across the country. Source: http://www.dmicdc.com/about-DMICDC Industrial Corridor as Wheels of Progress Industrial corridors recognise the interdependence of various sectors of the economy and offer effective integration between industry and infrastructure leading to overall socio-economic development. Industrial corridors lead to the creation of state-of-art infrastructure such as high-speed transportation (rail/road) networks, ports with advanced cargo handling equipment, modern airports, special economic regions/ industrial areas, logistic parks, etc. that are focused on fulfilling the requirements of the industry. The late C.K. Prahalad, a renowned management expert, had said that over the next three decades if India does not create new cities to accommodate a whopping 500 million people desirous of urban life, every existing city would become a slum. The establishment of manufacturing zones along the industrial corridors will prevent distress migration and provide people with job opportunities close to their dwelling place. The new smart cities created will mark the beginning of a new wave of urbanisation in India and reduce pressure on existing cities. The buzz word connecting the various programmes PM of Modi’s Government - Make in India, Digital India, and Skill India - is employment generation. Smart cities and industrial corridors are no exceptions. The educational institutions, roads, railways, airports, hospitals that will come up in these corridors is expected to generate employment and raise the overall standard of living. The government is targeting 100 million new jobs through industrial corridors.   The Way Forward ‘The wheels of progress’ are encountering a plethora of issues on their road to success, however. Of all the issues, acquisition of land at a snail’s pace is the single biggest concern owing to the Right to Fair Compensation and Transparency in Land Acquisition, Rehabilitation and Resettlement Act, 2013. To take an example, the $100-billion Delhi-Mumbai Industrial Corridor (DMIC) was expected to be completed in three phases spread over nine years starting from January 2008. However, owing to mostly land acquisition issues, the first phase is likely to be completed by December 2019 and revised deadlines for the second phase and third phase have already been shifted to 2027 and 2037. The governments at both India’s Central and State levels need to work out a comprehensive land acquisition policy and not approach this issue in a piecemeal manner. Secondly, as India lacks technological expertise, it is prudent to bring in foreign direct investment through established foreign entities that have the required skill. At the same time, it is also important to encourage Indian investment in setting up ancillary units in the same sector. This will provide for smooth backward integration by ensuring regular supply of raw materials and forward integration by providing ready markets. For example, the Chennai to Bengaluru defence production corridor in India’s southern States will pass through towns such as Trichy, Coimbatore, Salem and Hosur and will connect ordnance factories and defence public sector units to ancillary units (which are small and medium scale industries in the said corridor). The supplies from these units to factories and Public Sector Undertakings is an example of forward integration and purchases by the latter is backward integration. Thirdly, in order to encourage FDI, the government needs to rationalise the tax structure. India’s corporate tax rate is high in comparison to many ASEAN countries and stands at 30%. It is 20% in Cambodia, Thailand and Vietnam. Moreover, India also has very high import tariffs that make manufacturing of products with imported components economically unviable or expensive as compared to countries like Taiwan. To achieve success, the government should rationalise the tariff structure, realising that it is export promotion not import prevention that actually benefits an economy. The strategy of industrial corridors is poised to develop a sound industrial base, characterised by excellent infrastructure and uninhibited growth of manufacturing. However, all this would remain only rhetoric if stumbling blocks are not removed and issues plaguing industrial corridor projects are not resolved. This requires a holistic approach and involvement of all the government departments, stakeholders such as farmers from whom land is to be acquired, manufacturers who would be setting units for production, transport operators, etc. With the onset of election season in India, it would be naive to assume anyone has the time to truly calibrate policy, but with a new Government and new ambitions post elections, one can only hope that the Industrial Corridors project will take on new heights.  </summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
