<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/economics/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-09-02T12:11:16+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/economics/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What COVID-19 Means for the US Education System?</title>
      <link href="/COVID-19-US-Education-System" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What COVID-19 Means for the US Education System?" />
      <published>2020-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/COVID-19-US-Education-System</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/COVID-19-US-Education-System">&lt;p&gt;Every generation of humanity has experienced their share of transitional periods, be it as consequential as the Second World War, or as small as being temporarily bedridden due to injury. The same concept can be used to study history in a different light - as a compilation of events that initiated the strongest ripples of transition in the various aspects of human life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As any mature and experienced enough man would tell you, change is a constant in the universe. It’s this change that led to human evolution and towards the development of society and the invention of all the things that make life worth living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as everything has exceptions, one of the few constants in life is the importance of education. It is something that has been so deeply ingrained in our culture that we cannot let go of it irrespective of the substitutes available to us. Today we see a scenario which is a clash between this constant and the period of fundamental transition fostered by COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States is a global education hub, with some of the most coveted educational institutes across the field of STEM, business, law and the arts. Students from all over the world dedicate a significant portion of their lives to the cause of securing admission into an elite US university. The country also greatly benefits from the international student community, as their annual contribution to the US GDP is at a massive $41 billion. Additionally, the cultural influence and innovation that the international community brings has, over the years, furthered the stronghold of many American companies in their respective markets. Nevertheless, the Trump administration has been rooting against international students who migrate to the USA in search of education and livelihood. That paired with a disease outbreak that has no fool-proof methods of containment has damaged educational prospects for a lot of international students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The American Council of Education predicts that a fall of as much as 25% in foreign student applications is anticipated for the upcoming academic year. This, though backed by the administration in charge, sets off a loud alarm as the impact would be drastic on the American corporate sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, America may be the pioneer in education, but it’s not the only player in the game. A lot of other countries like the UK, Canada and Australia offer equally enticing educational opportunities and have better migration and settlement policies. This may turn out to be the deciding factor for international students for whom an investment in a country other than the USA brings more to the table, especially in a highly uncertain situation like that of the present. The growing culture of administrative hostility towards immigrants would eventually lead to stagnation in diversity and curb the advantages that it offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, America is severely undermining the importance of international talent in keeping its corporate sector afloat. The influx of international funds in the form of fees, taxes, healthcare, bank deposits, etc contributes significantly to the economy. Due to the strictness of pre-existing work visa and green card policies, the proportion of foreign students that enrol in US programmes to those who actually find employment in the US to those who receive special work visas like H1B or obtain green cards moves in a decreasing order. Moreover, 1 out of 4 US startups, which are worth millions of dollars, are founded by international students. Therefore, calculation of the net impact of international students on the economy, irrespective of the time period, would yield a positive quotient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the lack of foreign influence would push the US into a state of cyclical perpetuity. The presence of international student communities supports more than just the economy, as it has been pivotal in reforming American society, and overcoming racial and cultural prejudice. This has helped American companies expand and explore international opportunities, and develop a workforce that is comfortable working outside their countries. It has popularised US education across the globe, which, over the years, has attracted countless employers and investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, many American institutions have moulded personalities who would go on to become leaders and forerunners in their respective fields. It has helped the American education system develop a global imprint, as a lot of individuals, that are its product, represent it in any sphere they venture into. Reduction in international students, after a certain point, would reduce this influence that the US enjoys in shaping leaders of various sectors, disciplines, and even nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summing it all up, the US, like any other nation, needs to evolve in various respects as and when required to maintain its reputation as a global leader. The driving force behind such evolution is the product of interactions between the international and local communities. A long term trend of decline in international students would cause the nation to involuntarily impose a glass ceiling on its growth potential. Therefore, it is indispensable for American colleges and universities to acknowledge the “new normal” and devise methods to attract international student applications. The first step that can be taken in this regard would be dismissing the suspension of student and special work visas, and ensuring that the impact of the pandemic-induced economic slowdown is minimal on college fees, educational loans and international student aid.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aryaman Dhiman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Every generation of humanity has experienced their share of transitional periods, be it as consequential as the Second World War, or as small as being temporarily bedridden due to injury. The same concept can be used to study history in a different light - as a compilation of events that initiated the strongest ripples of transition in the various aspects of human life.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Norway: The Perfect Economy?</title>
      <link href="/The-Perfect-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Norway: The Perfect Economy?" />
      <published>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Perfect-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Perfect-Economy">&lt;p&gt;Norway is a wonderful country that has time and time again been used as the poster child for a socialist-capitalist mixed economy done right. Norway has several times been compared to that child in our school who is absolutely tremendous at each and everything. The country boasts a GDP per capita of $81,995, one of the highest in the world, only falling behind Switzerland and a select group of micronations. The country has a robust trade surplus, exports of $106 billion, compared to imports of $84.8 billion, one of the highest national life expectancies at 81.8 years, an extremely skilled workforce with one of the highest proportion of university graduates at 42% of any country in the world, an extremely low unemployment rate of 0.41%, and international recognition as a place where it is very easy to do business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is more remarkable is that Norway has achieved this while also being one of the most economically equal countries in the world. After taxes, a single individual from the bottom 20% of the income earners in Norway still earns on average a quarter of what their top 20% income earners would. Now, this still sounds pretty unfair but compared to the Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) average which has top one-fifth earners making an income ten times that of their bottom one-fifth counterparts, this disparity is remarkable. The good news keeps on coming considering working conditions. Norway has workers protections which are commendable, meaning that social issues like working extremely long hours and people needing second jobs to support themselves are very rare. In fact, the OECD better life index notes that only 3% of employees work long hours when compared to the OECD average of 11% or the American average of 33%. All of this contributes to the citizens of Norway being some of the happiest in the entire world despite their country being extremely cold. Norway, by all standards, should be the model that most citizens would want to replicate in their own countries. So why haven’t other countries adopted similar economic policies to those in Norway? Is this country just a lucky outlier or could this success be replicated in other economies around the world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is that Norway wasn’t always this prosperous. In the 1960’s, it was an economy mainly based on fishing with a GDP similar in size to underdeveloped countries like Bangladesh or Nigeria. Now, in all fairness, Norway’s population was and still is far smaller than these other countries and the average Norwegian back then had a quality of life similar to a person in Spain or Greece. But Norway in the 1960’s was still far out from the economic powerhouse it is today. This all started to change in May of 1963 when the Norwegian government asserted sovereign rights over natural resources in a huge area of the North Sea. This was basically the government saying that this part of the ocean is ours now. If we happen to find any oil here that is ours too. Six years later, in 1969, a ship called the &lt;em&gt;Ocean Viking&lt;/em&gt; struck oil in the North Sea, and from that oil production in the region exploded. This meant that in the mid-1970’s Norway produced more oil per capita than any other country in the world and even today it is only beaten out by Kuwait, UAE, and Saudi Arabia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I know what you are thinking, but this is not a story about another country that just got rich off oil and now everybody in the country is living like a child handed with a rack of money. It is actually the opposite. Rather than getting drunk off the oil wealth that they had discovered; the Norwegian government was very prudent with the revenue from these finite resources. The oil boom caused Norway’s GDP to grow over five times in the 1970’s growing from $12 billion to $65 billion in this period. But this newfound wealth was not being generated by private companies but rather a publicly run and owned company called &lt;em&gt;Statoil&lt;/em&gt;. All this meant that profits from oil and natural gas sales were not going to the pockets of private shareholders but rather directly to the government. This made the Norwegian government immensely rich meaning that if they wanted, they could have easily gone on a public spending spree, building fancy cities and public infrastructure while also reducing taxes just like many of the countries have done in a similar position. This kind of an approach would have been very popular among citizens because in short term it meant lower taxes and a better quality of life but they didn’t, and even today income and business taxes in Norway are among some of the highest in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for Norway, the government had the foresight to realise that oil wealth was not forever and that the citizens of Norway would not be satisfied if they had to go back to fishing in a generations time so the government invested the money into a piggy bank, a very large piggy bank called a ‘sovereign wealth fund’, in fact, this is the largest sovereign wealth fund in the world at $1.002 trillion beating out China’s state investment corporation. This is a fund that belongs to the people of Norway. The rationale is that this oil and these natural resources were originally the property of the Norwegian people and so it is they who should receive from the sale of these resources. This means that every man, woman, and child, who is a citizen of Norway essentially has around $200,000 invested into what is a giant hedge fund. This money is unfortunately not accessible by these citizens to spend on gold plated Ferraris or yachts. The money itself is actually not even accessible to the Norwegian government. In fact, only the profit generated from these investments is used to fund things like education, which explains the very skilled workforce, a very strong welfare system, public infrastructure, and reinvestment into the fund itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, the fund made an incredible $131 billion from investments. This fund is a very diverse portfolio of stocks, bonds, cash, and commodities but what it does invest in is not nearly as interesting as what it does not invest in. The Norwegian government set up an ethical council that oversees investing decisions of all of the fund and it has excluded investing in things like weapons manufacturers, tobacco and alcohol companies, and companies that have caused severe environmental damage or companies that have breached workers rights and labour laws. Additionally, in an effort to diversify where they get their money from, the fund is also forbidden to invest in fossil energy companies. This means that all the investments in this fund are actually in foreign countries’ securities and commodities. Now, despite the massive political power this gives Norway to influence foreign companies, it also means that the fund’s performance is absolutely independent of the situation prevailing in the Norwegian economy. The fund was a fantastic piece of thoughtfulness by the Norwegian government and practically means that Norway is now the national equivalent of the guy that wins the lottery, keeps his day job, and invests the lottery money in a stock portfolio. It certainly is not as cool and it does not get as much attention as blowing all of the money on extravagant displays of wealth, but it does mean that they will be safe and secure for generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To finish it up, it is only fair to look at some of the economic issues that are present in Norway. First and foremost is that it still has an incredibly high cost of living compared to wages. Given the very high taxes, an average Norwegian worker is bringing home about $3,200 a month which is far higher than the American average of $2,730 per month. However, it does not make a considerable difference because Norway is an expensive place. A mid-range restaurant meal in America tends to run about $50, in Norway, it is about $92. A monthly utility bill in the US is expected to be around $130 whereas that same bill in Norway is $176. But the citizens of Norway almost universally agree that they are happy to put up with these high taxes and this incredibly high cost of living because in return they do not have to worry about serious economic hardships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody in Norway is going to go bankrupt because of a medical situation, nobody has to worry about drowning in crippling debt to get an education and they do not have to fear being homeless if they lose their jobs. So, the million-dollar question arises - is Norway really the perfect economy? Well no, not really. Norway is a great example of a planned social-democratic economic system. They have done everything right with the opportunities that have come their way but they were still extremely lucky, and expecting that every country can get to where Norway is today only by copying and pasting their government’s financial policies is absurd but that said I still think Norway is the economy closest to achieve perfection if they haven’t already.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Norway is a wonderful country that has time and time again been used as the poster child for a socialist-capitalist mixed economy done right. Norway has several times been compared to that child in our school who is absolutely tremendous at each and everything. The country boasts a GDP per capita of $81,995, one of the highest in the world, only falling behind Switzerland and a select group of micronations. The country has a robust trade surplus, exports of $106 billion, compared to imports of $84.8 billion, one of the highest national life expectancies at 81.8 years, an extremely skilled workforce with one of the highest proportion of university graduates at 42% of any country in the world, an extremely low unemployment rate of 0.41%, and international recognition as a place where it is very easy to do business.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Emmanuel Farhi’s Safety Trap</title>
      <link href="/Emmanuel-Farhi-Safety-Trap" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Emmanuel Farhi’s Safety Trap" />
      <published>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Emmanuel-Farhi-Safety-Trap</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Emmanuel-Farhi-Safety-Trap">&lt;p&gt;Emmanuel Farhi, considered by many to be the brightest economist of his generation, passed away in July 2020, aged only 41. Farhi, a PhD from Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) and amongst the youngest to receive tenure as Professor at Harvard University, was known to challenge traditional economic concepts that people would often take as given. Take, for example, one of his most cited works,  &lt;em&gt;The Safe Asset Shortage Conundrum&lt;/em&gt;, written on safe assets and the lack thereof, in 2008 with Ricardo Caballero of MIT and Pierre-Oliver Gourinchas of UC Berkeley. This paper augmented Keynes’ classical theory of the ‘Liquidity Trap’ and developed it to suit the modern connotation of capital markets, and is more relevant now than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world seemed to have reasonably recovered from the short run curable shocks of the Great Financial Crisis of 2008 by 2018-19, when many first-world nations, including the world’s de-facto economic capital, the US, were considered to have achieved ‘full employment’. There was, however, something anomalistic about this status, when despite high productivity, inflation seemed suppressed. This &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Inflation-Dead-Or-Dormant&quot;&gt;dormant status of inflation&lt;/a&gt;, often explained by the unorthodox policy measures taken for recovery, has evidently trickled into the prolonged COVID-19 induced recession. Monetary policy as a tool might appear crippled at this point, with nominal rates reaching their zero levels bound in most first-world economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conventional jargon would explain the situation as follows: what has basically happened in this liquidity trap is the flattening of our LM curve (a curve showing the relationship between real output and interest rates in the money market), a consequence of a high ‘h’ (which is the proportion of change in money demand, when the interest rates change by a percent). In classical (Keynesian) economic sense though, the policy decision is to change the money supply first, and the interest rate change is a consequence of that. Once a decision to increase the money supply, in hopes to revive demand, is implemented, it is accompanied by an equal increase in money demand in order for the market to equilibrate. Money demand, without an increase in income levels, can only rise if the interest rate moves down. But in case of a high ‘h’, a negligible downward movement of rates should be able to compensate for the money demand increase. Coming back to the real world, where money demand is adjusted by moving the nominal interest rates, such a scenario would render the monetary policy useless, once the zero levels bound of interest rates is reached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conventional solution to this dilemma, as given by Keynes in &lt;em&gt;The General Theory of Employment, Interest and Money&lt;/em&gt; was to make gracious use of fiscal policy in a targeted manner. But as concerns of deficit consolidation popped up, economists at the Fed came up with other heterodox mutations of conventional monetary policy to tackle the issue. It wasn’t until Farhi’s paper on ‘Safety Traps’ was published that the policymakers found a more logical chain of response to the problem. A certain category of assets, often considered immune in periods of depressed market spirits, is called ‘Safe Assets’. During recessions, their markets evidently boom leading to price hikes and consequent fall in the yields. But the yields have a lower bound of zero percent, beyond which they cannot fall, and therefore prices cannot rise. This situation of people acting in private interest, leading to a net consequence of a market failure is a classic example of ‘Fallacy of Composition’. This happens since the asset market does not equilibrate in response to the high demand. And due to nominal rigidities, this equilibrium manifests in the form of output reduction. The output during recessionary periods is entirely demand determined, and the 0-yield on the safe assets is not low enough to encourage agents to move towards consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically the solutions offered to do away with this complication include negative interest rates, forward guidance, quantitative easing, etc. However, in his paper, Farhi accounted for the fact that the market rates do not uniformly equilibrate across all assets, and a certain risk premium remains attached to equity assets, while the safe ones get to zero. This tends to dilute the policy impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we want as our end result, is that despite the high ‘Safe Asset’ demand, we generate enough supply to ensure the yields do not get to zero and there is some scope to utilise the monetary policy. This sudden paucity of safe assets is often attributed to a savings glut, accumulation of reserves by the emerging markets, and to the fact that many assets which shaped the housing market bubble were once considered safe, but were not so at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One popular policy response which was an attempt to untie the hands of monetary policy, but failed to an extent was ‘Quantitative Easing’, which allowed the Fed to pump up the market with fresh money supply while purchasing bonds in return. This measure would not revive demand to its potential if safe assets are the ones being purchased in its return. This is because a proportion of the newly printed money will look for more safe assets, which have now shrunk in supply! Instead, soaking up the risky assets in return for the newly printed money, while simultaneously issuing newer safety assets is the proper way to go about quantitative easing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forward guidance, by ensuring to keep the future rates low was also said to work, because, if the Government’s word on the policy is reliable, lower future yields will imply higher future asset prices, creating current demand for the assets. When the self-fulfilling prophecy works out, the wealth effect naturally generates demand. However, Farhi’s paper found out the misconceptions associated with the effectiveness of this policy. If assets are seen in terms of the two designated classes, then it is likely that the risky assets, with a positive risk premium, will dissipate the impact of anticipated lower rates, and the effect will not trickle to revive the output market. However, one measure that is likely to render the monetary policy free is creating a very high inflation target, which would then allow the economy to run on an output-inducing negative real rate while being on the 0-nominal rate. But then again, this has its long-run ramifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The existence of a high-risk premium is concrete evidence for the existence of a ‘safety trap’, rather than a liquidity trap. It is indicative of the fact that people are rushing towards safe assets, while equity returns remain stable and decoupled from the economic situation, as is the current case. A fiscal policy response by issuing sovereign bonds to address the scarcity of safe assets is now being encouraged with the popularisation of the ‘Modern Monetary Theory’, though Farhi considered the US’ role as the world’s banker to be unsustainable due to higher issuance of sovereign bonds leading many to question their debt levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this paper played an instrumental role in forwarding the scope of the monetary policies of the first world countries, Emmanuel Farhi’s other papers are just as revolutionary, if not as cited. In another one of his works, &lt;em&gt;Dealing with the Trilemma: Optimal Capital Controls with Fixed Exchange Rates&lt;/em&gt; he challenged the ‘Impossible Trinity’ by providing partial capital controls as a solution for emerging markets battling the exchange rate volatility. His research is a perfect amalgamation of academia and policy solutions, and he truly believed that research only made sense when it could be put in real service towards progress. Safe to say that the world of academics and research was in for a shock on his passing on the 23rd of July, 2020. Gita Gopinath, a fellow colleague at Harvard, poignantly wrote, &lt;em&gt;“Imagine the loss to economics if Samuelson had died at the age of 41, that is what we have lost with Emmanuel’s passing”&lt;/em&gt;. His best was truly yet to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Emmanuel Farhi, considered by many to be the brightest economist of his generation, passed away in July 2020, aged only 41. Farhi, a PhD from Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) and amongst the youngest to receive tenure as Professor at Harvard University, was known to challenge traditional economic concepts that people would often take as given. Take, for example, one of his most cited works, The Safe Asset Shortage Conundrum, written on safe assets and the lack thereof, in 2008 with Ricardo Caballero of MIT and Pierre-Oliver Gourinchas of UC Berkeley. This paper augmented Keynes’ classical theory of the ‘Liquidity Trap’ and developed it to suit the modern connotation of capital markets, and is more relevant now than ever.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Narrating The Plodding South-African Economy</title>
      <link href="/Narrating-The-Plodding-South-African-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Narrating The Plodding South-African Economy" />
      <published>2020-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Narrating-The-Plodding-South-African-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Narrating-The-Plodding-South-African-Economy">&lt;p&gt;The second-largest producer of gold in the world is in dire need of its sluggish economic growth to be narrated and analysed. Along with gold, diamond and platinum are the top three exports of South Africa, it is the largest producer of chrome, manganese, platinum, vanadium, and vermiculite; second largest producer of ilmenite, palladium, rutile and zirconium, and most significantly, it is the world’s third-largest exporter of coal. Despite being a king-pin in precious gemstones and minerals, three in every four South Africans live with a constant threat of poverty taking over their daily lives. The most industrialised country of the African continent has not expanded by more than 2.5% a year since 2013, with nearly 50% of the South African population living in the state of poverty. Astoundingly, the swamp isn’t a decade old but has been impending for decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Struggling with a mere growth rate of 1.1% per year, the economy cannot absorb the rapidly growing population, leading to a higher rate of deprivation among the people. The cyclical tools which are veiled in monetary and fiscal policies cannot break down the encumbrances of structural weaknesses in the economy. To begin with, even after showcasing improvement, the household saving rate in South Africa is a meagre 0.2% (as per the fourth quarter of 2017). Why is the saving rate a matter of significance? Well, it is the savings that generate capital for investment spending, with no space for investment, the economy can never accelerate due to the lagging infrastructure that has the potential for future growth and provision of high returns to the Gross Domestic Product (GDP). The present rate of household savings is utterly unfavourable when compared to other emerging market countries which usually maintain a rate above 2% and invest rigorously in infrastructural development along with measures to generate and expand the capacity for new capital, unlike the African country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Education, the pavement to advancement, has continued to be an issue of concern for South Africa as it was ranked the 75th nation out of 76 in the ‘Table of Education Systems’ drawn by Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD). The fourth industrial revolution hovers over the globe and calls for a skilled workforce, which has been a clear lag for the African country, the paucity of a skilled workforce arising out of an underdeveloped education system has been ranked as the third-most problematic factor for doing business in South Africa. Revamping the educational structure and enhancing its delivery should be the top-notch priority while restructuring the government policies in order to escalate economic progress, standard of living, ease of doing business, and to attract global as well as domestic investors. The smooth functioning of small and medium-sized enterprises in a developing nation is as cardinal as education to eradicate unemployment and foster a healthy living index. Government bureaucracy, heavy tax burden, and constrictive labour regulations are few of the many unnecessary curtailments for the small and medium enterprises (SMEs). The state-owned enterprises, deployed to generate utility for the public have been relocated to cushion the coffers of a selected few. The public enterprises have capitulated to inefficiency, mismanagement of revenue, bureaucratic lapses, tender rigging, delay in project delivery. This has resulted in a distorted infrastructure, scanty services, and has robbed the national treasure of billions in terms of opportunity cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How disinteresting has it been for the investors? Well, South Africa was ranked 82 out of 190 countries in the ‘Ease of Doing Business Index’ drawn by the World Bank in 2017. It might seem impressive to find a country with numerous economic and financial blemishes to find a spot in the middle of the Index, but the 32nd rank in 2008 is an epiphany to the swift fall. The plethora of monetary policies that have been put into effect will remain ineffective if the grass-root structure of the economic administration is not revamped and paralleled with the fast-paced world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entering its 70th month of a downward cycle, the longest since 1945, the economy is stuck in a mire, with rescue looking like a far-fetched dream. A surfeit of sectors felt the tremors of the contracting economy but manufacturing, mining and trade, catering and accommodation, agriculture, and the power sector have been the worst hit. Experts are of the view that low demand, sharp rising fuel prices, and Eskom’s load shedding are the prime factors contributing to the contraction of the economy. Eskom is amongst the top twenty power utilities worldwide, it generates more than 90% of South Africa’s power and 40% of the electricity in the African continent. The surging salary, fuel, and debt-servicing costs along with mismanagement and corruption scandals have led to Eskom having a $30 billion debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lack of ambitious economic programmes accompanied by the coronavirus pandemic will deepen the crack in the economy. As the nation is in a state of lockdown, hue and cry amongst the public with a lack of essentials and power cuts have worsened the strain on the government. South Africa was one of the few nations to implement the most draconian containment measures to curb the spread of the virus, with an already dwindling economy, a complete shutdown of all the major industries has piled up the heap of debts for the administration. A failure in the political atmosphere, inefficiency of the government to deliver to the public instead of stocking up their coffers, and inviting projects with vested interests have continued to cause a haemorrhage with no defined antidote to the South African economy. Revival seems like a mere dream when the present trends of a global slowdown are observed, the various developed nations which were key importers of the South African minerals and precious gems have curtailed their imports, leaving South Africa with a depleting repository. Failing to engage investors, the government continues to borrow in order to repay its already mounting debts, the matter of concern still remains a part of the vicious cycle as no monetary policy or financial injections can break down the persisting swamp which has driven half of South Africa into poverty.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The second-largest producer of gold in the world is in dire need of its sluggish economic growth to be narrated and analysed. Along with gold, diamond and platinum are the top three exports of South Africa, it is the largest producer of chrome, manganese, platinum, vanadium, and vermiculite; second largest producer of ilmenite, palladium, rutile and zirconium, and most significantly, it is the world’s third-largest exporter of coal. Despite being a king-pin in precious gemstones and minerals, three in every four South Africans live with a constant threat of poverty taking over their daily lives. The most industrialised country of the African continent has not expanded by more than 2.5% a year since 2013, with nearly 50% of the South African population living in the state of poverty. Astoundingly, the swamp isn’t a decade old but has been impending for decades.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Free Market Conundrum</title>
      <link href="/The-Free-Market-Conundrum" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Free Market Conundrum" />
      <published>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Free-Market-Conundrum</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Free-Market-Conundrum">&lt;p&gt;The 1980’s was an important era in the history of economics and the world. With the election of President Ronald Regan in the United States and Baroness Thatcher of Kesteven as Prime in the United Kingdom, economic policies in the West underwent a major overhaul. Subsequently, international institutions made these policies a prerequisite for granting loans to the countries that were on the brink of bankruptcy. The policies that I am talking about are the neo-liberal economic policies, and the framework they are built upon is the fundamental assumption of the efficiency of free markets. Every undergraduate economics student is taught that leaving markets to function without any intervention by the State will accrue benefits to the society as a whole. This article is an attempt to look at why free markets are not so free and why they do not always lead to the best of outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every transaction takes place with an implicit assumption that the other party will uphold their end of the bargain. If that does not happen, they are likely to approach the police or courts for justice. This tells us that to function freely, markets depend on some rules and regulations. The rhetoric around the free markets often fails to appreciate these rules because they are taken for granted. In fact, for the markets to function, property rights need to be clearly defined and enforceable. Therefore, it is absolutely correct to say that government laws, rules and regulations create scope for the markets to function and form the basis that drives competition. Then there are patents. Though there are strong arguments as to the requirement of such laws in place, they themselves act as obstacles to market freedom. Patents can lead to situations where the goods are out of reach of those who value (value here is not in terms of the amount paid but in terms of necessity) them the most. &lt;em&gt;Gleevac&lt;/em&gt;, a leukaemia drug, is a case in point. The cost of this drug in the US is $70,000 since Novartis, the company that manufactures the drug has a patent in the US. Thanks to the refusal of the Supreme Court of India to grant a patent, it is available for $2,500 in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem with free markets is that of ‘asymmetric information’. Asymmetric information arises when one party (typically the seller) possesses more information or knowledge about goods or services being sold. One common example that you will come across is about how the buyers of health insurance have an incentive to conceal their health information to get a better insurance deal. This example portrays how the sellers are at a loss. But today, you see almost every insurance company has a physician only from whom you are allowed to take a medical checkup. For a more general example, consider a clothes shop or a tech gadget shop. Old stock is prominently displayed so as to dispose of the stock and in such situations, the seller has more information than the buyer. Of course, there are resources available today that help bridge the information gap, but still the problem is more commonplace than we all think. The economic theory treats this asymmetry of information as an anomaly — one of the three instances of market failure. What it fails to recognise is that this phenomenon is not an exception, but a ubiquitous conundrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inherent characteristic of the free markets, that has hardly ever been a part of the public discourse, is that they are indifferent to human needs and provide only those goods and services that are profitable. Take, for example, the case of Google. Over the years the search engine giant has altered its webpage to show pre-packaged information when we search for something, rather than sending traffic to other websites. This may not affect you or me directly; but will result in the loss of customers to many businesses, whose business models rely on Google sending traffic to their websites. Another example is the pharmaceutical industry. During the initial stages in the coronavirus outbreak in February 2020, Rolf Hilgenfeld, a structural biologist, told the scientific journal &lt;em&gt;Nature, “The total number of people infected, if you combine SARS, MERS [previous related coronavirus outbreaks] and this new virus, is under 12,500 people. That’s not a market. The number of cases is too small. Pharmaceutical companies are not interested”&lt;/em&gt;. Though the trails for a vaccine are underway, one cannot miss the larger point. One more example is the Indian realty market. Despite the requirement of an additional 20 million houses, there is no sign of falling housing prices. This is partly because the developers prevent a fall in price in anticipation of a boost in demand in the future. Sometimes, by delaying construction, they demand higher amounts from the buyers to complete the construction. The end result is, despite a huge population without their own houses and large inventories held by realtors, the market is unable to satisfy the needs of the end-users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this time, you might have come to the conclusion that I am a communist; I am not. What I am trying to get across is that while free markets benefit society in many ways, there are also many faults associated with free markets. Even as free markets provide what most people want, they will deceive, manipulate, and tempt us into buying things that might be harmful to us. Renowned economists George Akerlof and Robert Shiller said, &lt;em&gt;“Markets are not benign forces working for the greater good but instead are filled with businesses that ‘phish’ by exploiting our weaknesses to get us to buy their products”&lt;/em&gt;. From the 1980’s, in many countries across the world, the role of the state was cut down, paving ways for the ‘free markets’ to operate. There has been little debate about the flaws in the free market system and economists fail to acknowledge the problem. The failure in understanding the markets will only result in the formulation of bad policies. The failure to rectify the existing problems will tilt the markets to work in favour of a few and will result in wide sections of society being worse off. The capitalist system works well not just because there are free markets but also because there are a wide range of institutional arrangements that act as checks and balances on these markets. It is important to recognise that the state plays as important a role as the markets to bring the economy to equilibrium. Finally, there is nothing wrong with wanting free markets; but to think that they can’t go wrong is a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The 1980’s was an important era in the history of economics and the world. With the election of President Ronald Regan in the United States and Baroness Thatcher of Kesteven as Prime in the United Kingdom, economic policies in the West underwent a major overhaul. Subsequently, international institutions made these policies a prerequisite for granting loans to the countries that were on the brink of bankruptcy. The policies that I am talking about are the neo-liberal economic policies, and the framework they are built upon is the fundamental assumption of the efficiency of free markets. Every undergraduate economics student is taught that leaving markets to function without any intervention by the State will accrue benefits to the society as a whole. This article is an attempt to look at why free markets are not so free and why they do not always lead to the best of outcomes.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Shutting Our Doors?</title>
      <link href="/Shutting-Our-Doors" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shutting Our Doors?" />
      <published>2020-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Shutting-Our-Doors</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Shutting-Our-Doors">&lt;p&gt;Observation has reached its peak for me as I find my eyes looking for details behind each jar of Nutella or on the side of our microwave. All thanks to the lockdown that has dragged me back home from college and given me enough free time to look around the house with a magnifying glass, which I wouldn’t have done otherwise on my busy school days as a child. And observation, mixed with a little bit of research, has led me to the understanding that my house, which in fact buys everything from local stores, actually reeks of products from China. From the water geyser to the processor in the ceiling fan, from the dinner crockery to the food processor, from parts of our mobile phones to our daily t-shirts, nothing is spared from the clenching claws of China. The fact that all these products were available to us in the local stores at prices comfortable enough for our pockets, speaks volumes about the kind of consumerism China has created in each and every household, office, company, factory, industry and restaurant in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The calls to boycott Chinese goods had started gaining momentum when the martyrdom of twenty Indian soldiers in the Ladakh stand-off against China aroused public sentiment, and they took to their hands to avenge the soldiers’ deaths by publicly breaking TV sets of Chinese brands. These calls couldn’t have gone unnoticed by the government which then had to take a step to show India’s hostility towards China. A violent uprising, that had cost us our soldiers’ lives, very recently, was discarded as a move from our end, also taking into account that China had retreated from the Indian borders. Now the question was :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Can India afford to boycott China?&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feasibilities of numbers of steps like - import reduction, import-substitution, self-reliance, and lastly, a blanket ban - were pondered upon. While the other options were on the table, considering the sentimental charge of the public, the possible implications of a blanket ban were considered. A blanket ban is a complete prohibition, which in this case would mean banning not just imports from China but also trade and investment. A superpower like the US has openly made hate speeches on China and has also taken moves such as shutting down a Chinese consulate in Texas. But considering the Indian economy’s huge dependence on China, can India really impose a blanket ban on China and move to self-reliance as quickly as we think? A step-by-step analysis will help us understand the implications of this move better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trade:&lt;/strong&gt; The Indian economy is heavily dependent on Chinese imports that include intermediate and finished goods. Intermediate goods from China, such as chemicals, pharmaceuticals, electronic components, have long helped industries in India sustain. But if India wishes to take a few steps back in its trading chain with China, India will have to adopt medium to long-term policy moves. These include, but are not restricted to, financial support or subsidising micro, small and medium businesses that can actually manufacture the products that we import from China. The informal sector in the production chain in India, with the right kind of policy support, can eventually lead us to self-reliance in a matter of a few years. However, a step backwards in the import chain from China could also mean opening doors to imports from other countries. For India to become a favourable import destination, certain financial supports like import duty exemption and cash subsidy on imports from other countries are necessary to match the cost of Chinese imports. In the short-term, expediting Free Trade Agreements (FTAs) to lure imports and investments from other countries is one of the most viable options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investment:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian start-ups, with the right kind of investment boost, have a tendency of growing big in this ever-evolving capitalistic world of ours. But a lot of local start-ups fail to garner the kind of investment from major Indian ventures, which is what China has taken advantage of for close to a decade now. Alibaba, invested in an Indian start-up Paytm, back in 2015 when the future of Paytm itself was bleak, but China slyly took advantage of the gap in investment that existed. Moreover, China has not blinked an eye before investing in a lot of local start-ups, knowing very well that like most other start-ups, these too may be loss-making. The reason behind this is that China is ready to make a trade-off of investing in a loss-making start-up to be able to get a footing in the market share of the Indian market. Eventually, when the local start-ups grow enough to have a valuation of over $1 billion and come under the category of ‘Unicorns’, is when it finally comes to our eyes that the major Indian start-ups, like Snapdeal, Ola, Swiggy, Paytm, Flipkart and so many more, have a Chinese investor. To combat the issue of Chinese investors, like Alibaba, monopolising in the Indian market by investing in most Indian unicorns and creating an obvious outsized impact, the Indian government decided to amend the Foreign Direct Investment (FDI) rules to cap off the number of companies an investor can invest in, so as to prevent any hostile takeovers of the Indian market by any foreign investor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology:&lt;/strong&gt; We’re no aliens to the fact that China practically holds the lion’s share in the smartphone market of India, while India has little to no alternatives in the smartphone arena. It would require huge amounts of investment in research and technology to be able to reduce dependence on China for smartphone technology and components. In addition, Chinese tech firms, like Alibaba, and apps like TikTok, reach the Indian consumers as much as applications like Google, Amazon, Facebook, and Instagram. The Indian government has recently made a move to ban the likes of these Chinese applications that actually have local alternatives, and this as a strategic move has a lasting impact on the kind of hostility India wants to opt for. In fact, a restriction in the telecommunications sector, such as banning Huawei, is also a feasible move considering that Indian alternatives, such as Jio and BSNL, are easily available to the Indian consumers. To top it off, Huawei could also be banned from India’s 5G rollout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, answering the bigger question: &lt;em&gt;Can India really shut its doors by imposing a blanket ban on China&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, a blanket ban on China will result in a very quick supply disruption leaving the Indian consumers exposed to only a minimal amount of not-so-pocket friendly alternatives. Furthermore, the economy will have to bear high input costs and therefore, this move will prove to be a costly one for India. Instead, the viable solution would be to allow steady withdrawal of Chinese products by allowing import substitution as well as funding the budding industries in the unorganised sector. India will have to take slow steps forward, keeping in mind cost-effectiveness and affordability.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Observation has reached its peak for me as I find my eyes looking for details behind each jar of Nutella or on the side of our microwave. All thanks to the lockdown that has dragged me back home from college and given me enough free time to look around the house with a magnifying glass, which I wouldn’t have done otherwise on my busy school days as a child. And observation, mixed with a little bit of research, has led me to the understanding that my house, which in fact buys everything from local stores, actually reeks of products from China. From the water geyser to the processor in the ceiling fan, from the dinner crockery to the food processor, from parts of our mobile phones to our daily t-shirts, nothing is spared from the clenching claws of China. The fact that all these products were available to us in the local stores at prices comfortable enough for our pockets, speaks volumes about the kind of consumerism China has created in each and every household, office, company, factory, industry and restaurant in India.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Saviour of Europe</title>
      <link href="/The-Saviour-of-Europe" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Saviour of Europe" />
      <published>2020-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Saviour-of-Europe</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Saviour-of-Europe">&lt;p&gt;On July 21, 2020, at 5:30 am, the President of the European Council, Charles Michel posted in a single word tweet, “&lt;em&gt;Deal!&lt;/em&gt;”. He was, of course, referring to a deal that was unanimously voted by all the member nations of the European Union (EU) at the Special meeting of the European Council. The meeting which was supposed to be a four-day summit was extended to a fifth day so as to bring about consensus among the EU members to get a unanimous vote on the proposed deal. So, what is the deal in question and what does it mean for the European Union?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Council, one of the three wings of the European Union, met in Brussels to vote on what is called the Multiannual Financial Framework (MFF). MFF is a seven-year financial framework that regulates the annual budget of the Union. To put it simply, it is the EU’s budget for a period of seven years. This budget is funded by the members on a pro-rata basis. MMF contains a set of goals – an EU-wide common policy, and this ‘EU budget’ allots funds to the members to spend under the agreed heads. The framework which came into force in 2014 is set to expire in 2020. Therefore, a new framework for the period of 2021-2027 had to be agreed on this year. This is precisely the reason for the Brussels summit. However, that does not explain the importance surrounding the summit. Apart from MFF, the EU and its member states agreed on a specific recovery fund, called Next Generation EU (NGEU), for the sole purpose of tackling the COVID-19 crisis. Under NGEU, the European Commission will borrow a sum of €750 billion from the capital markets. Out of this €750 billion, a sum of €390 billion will be disbursed to the members as grants; while the rest, €360 billion, will be provided in the form of loans. While the European Commission as a whole has borrowed only sparsely in the past, it is a first for the Commission to borrow on such a large scale. Therefore, the deal that we are talking about has two parts: MFF and the NGEU. With a €1.074 trillion seven-year budget and the €750 billion recovery fund, the financial package amounts to an enormous €1.82 trillion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three things that stand out in the budget. First is the political authority clause. The deal document states that “&lt;em&gt;[the] Budgetary Authority shall exercise political control, to be defined in the agreement between the European Parliament, the Council and the Commission&lt;/em&gt;”. This can be seen as a measure that could cause problems for Hungary and Poland. The European Commission had initiated proceedings against both these countries over rule of law concerns. Many leaders demanded that the EU funding to its member nations be linked to the condition that states follow democratic principles and “EU’s founding values”. During the discussions in the summit, the Hungarian Prime Minister Viktor Orbán threatened to veto the Commission’s proposal and demanded that the funding not be linked to the rule of law practices. However, the wording “political control” means that the money will also be linked to the observing the rule of law. Second, the deal contained clauses that put “emergency brakes” on the funding to a member state, if the state failed to adhere to the reform conditions attached to the funding. This move came after intense pressure from the premier of Netherlands Mark Rutte, who was the voice of the “frugal four”. Frugal four is an informal association of Sweden, Denmark, Austria, and the Netherlands. Initially, French President Emmanuel Macron had proposed for a sum of €500 billion in the form of grants and another €250 billion in the form of loans to the member countries. The frugal four along with Finland had opposed the idea of providing huge sums in the form of grants and wanted grants to be limited to below €300 billion. This proposal was unacceptable for Italy and Spain; the two countries worst hit by the COVID-19 pandemic refused to accept any total grant amount below €400 billion. Eventually, a compromise was reached and the grant amount was settled at €390 billion. The Netherlands Prime Minister, however, scored a victory by successfully getting the members to agree to a review clause. Third, the deal puts the issue of climate change at the forefront. It says, “&lt;em&gt;Climate action will be mainstreamed in policies and programmes financed under the MFF and NGEU&lt;/em&gt;”. According to the deal document, a total of 30% of the expenditure of the €1.82 trillion will be used to reach the climate targets in conformity to the objectives of the Paris agreements. It also has a provision that rules that the European Commission should publish a report on climate expenditure annually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another key element to the deal is the specifications about how the revenue will be raised to pay off the debt that the European Commission will borrow under the NGEU provisions. The deal sets the deadline of 2058 to repay the whole amount. It was agreed that a tax on non-recycled plastic should be imposed. Another tax on imported goods from countries with lower carbon-emitting standards than the EU is also envisaged. Revenue from these taxes will be transferred to the EU for the purpose of repayment of the borrowings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deal is historic for many reasons. It is the first time ever that all the countries have agreed and empowered the European Commission to borrow a huge amount. But most importantly, with Brexit and the inward-looking policies being adopted all across the globe, many feared that the failure of the EU to reach a deal will pose an existential threat to the Union. However, the euro hit an 18-month high, as soon as the announcement of the deal came out, stock markets across Europe surged, and the European shares bounced. This deal now must pass through the European Parliament and must be ratified by all member states, which in all possibility seems likely. In a world where multilateral institutions and dialogue are on the wane, one can only hope this deal will exemplify the need of international institutions in coordinating responses to 21st-century problems that are increasingly cross-national.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On July 21, 2020, at 5:30 am, the President of the European Council, Charles Michel posted in a single word tweet, “Deal!”. He was, of course, referring to a deal that was unanimously voted by all the member nations of the European Union (EU) at the Special meeting of the European Council. The meeting which was supposed to be a four-day summit was extended to a fifth day so as to bring about consensus among the EU members to get a unanimous vote on the proposed deal. So, what is the deal in question and what does it mean for the European Union?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lebanon Quagmire Spins Out of Control</title>
      <link href="/Lebanon-Quagmire-Spins-Out-of-Control" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lebanon Quagmire Spins Out of Control " />
      <published>2020-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Lebanon-Quagmire-Spins-Out-of-Control</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lebanon-Quagmire-Spins-Out-of-Control">&lt;p&gt;On October 17,  2019, the Government of Lebanon, the world’s third most indebted country, decided to impose a tax on WhatsApp messaging application to engulf its amassed fiscal deficit. Unfortunately, nothing changed except the calamity exacerbating with each passing day. As the prices for basic commodities soar high, people find it difficult to feed themselves and have resorted to selling their gold in order to fill their empty stomachs. Adding to the troubles, the pandemic is likely to downgrade the economy, which is already unable to withstand the jolts it has received, by 12-13%. With an urgent requirement of aid to 75% of its population, an instantaneous revival for the economy reminds me of the Gucci shoes in my shopping wishlist for years that have never been able to find their path to ‘add to cart’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lebanese have been known for maintaining a fine standard of living, the bars and restaurants have always stayed open even during the wars. The unhygienic water, heckling power supply, etc. was never a matter of concern for the middle-class until they enjoyed their affordable foreign tours. Despite a kaput monetary system, the luxuries and seamless interaction with the world have been courtesy of the Lebanese currency’s 22-year-old peg to the US currency, but who knew that this could turn into a substantial contributor to the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For several years, the Government has continued to borrow from global as well as domestic lenders to keep up with the pegged US dollars. As the Central Bank liberally hiked the interest rates, Lebanon became a strong magnet for the opulent investors across the globe. The unrealistic peg at 1,507 Lebanese pounds to a dollar and thriving efforts to keep up with it when there was a shortage of dollars in the market led to enormous debts. Further, to escape from the deficit, the Central Bank increased the interest rate to attract more investors. Nearly 50% of the state revenue goes into paying the debt, a major chunk of the remaining portion is put in effect for the government employees’ salaries, leaving very little margin for infrastructure development, capital investment, and expenditure on human resources. Thus, the Lebanese economy closes its boundary for revenue generation as there is no scope from other sectors, all the money is burned for consumption through imports, real estate and to defend the peg. Despite a sluggish economy, the government kept piling on the debts through depraved spendings, majorly on the expanded public sector which was put in effect to brim up their vote banks and divert focus from an ailing power grid. The situation became even more hostile owing to the political instability and the Prime Minister disappearing into Saudi Arabia, this shook the confidence of the Lebanese affluents who then decided to transfer their deposits out of the country. With the fear of depleting the country’s reserves, the banks had to close owing to the shortage of dollars. This has been a major concern for ordinary citizens, who have to stand in long queues to only return with a tiny amount of cash in hand which is insufficient to buy the daily bread, and have to sleep with an empty stomach during this pandemic. Economists view it as a matter of concern as the government continues to prioritise foreign creditors who hold an enormous $12 billion of the Lebanese debt, at the expense of the empty stomachs of its citizens. The banking sector, which has enjoyed mellow relations with the country’s political elite who held shares in some of these banks is a significant culprit. As the ordinary citizens fear a risk to their deposits, the commercial lenders who were always on the receiving end, even after capital controls in action have managed to pave their way for profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With an uncertain political atmosphere, inefficient government policies driven with self-interest, faulty monetary system, and much more on the home-front, there are a few external factors that also act as a cherry to this toppling cake. A small country with a population of six million is largely dependent on remittances. 12.7% of the Lebanese GDP constitutes remittances from family members living abroad and majorly from the majestic oil-producers in the Middle-Eastern country, second only to Palestine. As coronavirus grips the world and the global GDP, numerous people have lost their jobs in various parts of the world. Owing to the global crisis, the number of people transferring and depositing money in Lebanon for their families and for tax exemptions abroad has seen a significant drop. In fact, they seek withdrawal from their already deposited funds in the Lebanese banks. The truncated oil prices have aggravated the revenue crisis for Lebanon. Moving closer, the oil-rich nations neighbouring the state of Lebanon that inhabited Lebanese emigrants have already cut down on the remittances they provided at regular intervals. These nations formulated the major chunk of the revenue Lebanon generated from remittances and used it further to fund its additional debt. With a threat of Saudi Arabia likely to expel Lebanese nationals, the inflow of remittance dollars that would support the dysfunctional peg has begun to diminish at a petrifying rate, making the situation even more muddled up for the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lebanese economy finds itself amidst a thick forest, and the process of revival is definitely going to be a prolonged one along with a dire need for sustained efforts. With an urgent need for external liquidity that is possible only with the IMF reform programme which comes with a set of associated reforms that all the nations need to abide by when subscribing to the stimulus package. As the IMF estimates a debt reaching 155% of the Lebanese GDP, the government remains reluctant to adopt the IMF reforms and slashes the reports presented by the organisation. The economic experts and advisors, both within the state and globally, have to ultimately adopt the IMF reforms package to survive and provide daily bread to its citizens and the refugees. This detailed analysis is food for thought for further plan of action and devastating experience to learn from for the other countries.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On October 17, 2019, the Government of Lebanon, the world’s third most indebted country, decided to impose a tax on WhatsApp messaging application to engulf its amassed fiscal deficit. Unfortunately, nothing changed except the calamity exacerbating with each passing day. As the prices for basic commodities soar high, people find it difficult to feed themselves and have resorted to selling their gold in order to fill their empty stomachs. Adding to the troubles, the pandemic is likely to downgrade the economy, which is already unable to withstand the jolts it has received, by 12-13%. With an urgent requirement of aid to 75% of its population, an instantaneous revival for the economy reminds me of the Gucci shoes in my shopping wishlist for years that have never been able to find their path to ‘add to cart’.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Football for Global Influence</title>
      <link href="/Football-for-Global-Influence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Football for Global Influence" />
      <published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Football-for-Global-Influence</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Football-for-Global-Influence">&lt;p&gt;I have a big question for all the football fans reading this article. What does Schalke 04, Red Star Belgrade, and Zenit have in common? I believe it’s difficult to answer this question so let me give you a hint: it’s something printed on their jerseys. Still didn’t get it? It’s the ‘Gazprom’ logo on their jerseys. From being on the jerseys of major football teams from various countries in Europe, it also features on the sidelines and advertisements during games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logo belongs to Gazprom, a Russian natural gas company. Logo sponsorships are normal in football. Teams make money offering jersey spaces to sponsors selling things like credit cards, cars and cell phones but Gazprom isn’t like most sponsors, i.e. private companies with products that football fans can buy. Instead, it’s a company owned by the Russian government that makes money selling natural gas to foreign countries. Yet, it’s everywhere in European football. So, if football fans can’t buy what they are selling, why is Gazprom spending millions to sponsor football games? The answer is part of a larger story that’s changing the sport of football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d7/Major_russian_gas_pipelines_to_europe.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/russiangaspipes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia has the world’s largest natural gas reserves and most of them are located in the Arctic gas fields controlled by Gazprom. The company is led by Alexey Miller, a close ally of Russian President Vladimir Putin. Since 2005, the Russian government has owned a majority stake in Gazprom. This means that the company profits are under Putin’s control, and gas sellers, along with oil, account for around 50% of Russia’s annual budget. Eastern European countries like Finland, Estonia, Lithuania, Poland, Slovakia depend on Russian oil for 75-100% of their natural gas needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we move further towards the West, the countries’ dependence begins to fall. At the end of the 20th century, Germany represented the biggest opportunity for Gazprom. German Chancellor Gerhard Schroeder had announced plans to phase out coal and nuclear power which meant Germany needed more natural gas to maintain their energy supply. Gazprom wanted to give it to them but there was a problem. To get to Germany, Russia’s gas needed to pass through pipelines crossing other countries that charged Gazprom transport fees. And most of them went through Ukraine, a country that has complicated political relations with Russia. Today, Ukraine still charges upwards of $3 billion each year to pump gas to Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, starting back in 2005, Russia began working on a strategy to bypass Ukraine and ship their gas directly to Western Europe through the Nord Stream pipeline, a route through the Baltic sea straight to Northern Germany. In late 2005, Gazprom was in the final stages of financing the project and Germany’s Chancellor was preparing for an election. During his time in the office, Gerhard Schroeder had become friendly with Putin, and critics in Germany were increasingly concerned about the Russian leader’s growing influence. Just a few weeks before the election, Schroeder met with Putin signing an agreement officially approving the pipeline. Two months later, he lost his re-election. However, by March, he found a new job overseeing Gazprom’s pipeline to Germany. It also came out that, before leaving office Schroeder had approved a secret Gazprom loan that provided over a billion euros to finance the project. This led to Gazprom’s big project being called a “story of scandal, corruption, and the creeping influence of Russia in Germany”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However in 2006 the story changed, Gazprom signed a deal to sponsor the German soccer team FC Schalke 04. At the time Schalke’s finances were worrying the team officials and Gazprom’s sponsorship provided money that the team desperately needed. At a press conference announcing the deal, a Gazprom chairman stated that Schalke’s connections with the German energy sector were the reason behind their decision to become its sponsors. Schalke played in Gelsenkirchen, a town in Germany’s Ruhr Valley, where much of the country’s energy industry is based. It’s also near the town of Rehden, a hub for pipelines to the rest of Europe and home to western Europe’s largest natural gas storage facilities. Schalke wasn’t Gazprom’s first football deal. The year before, they had bought a controlling stake in a team on the other end of the Nord Stream route: the Russian team Zenit St Petersburg. Gazprom’s investment made Zenit a major force in football. Two years after taking control, Zenit won their first-ever league championship. They’ve been able to sign expensive foreign stars like Axel Wetzel and Hulk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, as Gazprom logos were revealed around Schalke’s stadium, German headlines were hailing the Russian gas giant for pumping millions into the German team and hence, creating a positive image in German minds for the company. And over the next few years, the Gazprom logo would become a team symbol displayed at Schalke’s games and printed on official merchandise. Schalke also won a championship in 2011. By then, Nord Stream had been completed and it had started pumping gas to Germany. There was also another struggling team whose jerseys started featuring Gazprom’s logo, the Serbian team: Red Star Belgrade. Red Star was about $25 million in debt when Gazprom signed to become their jersey sponsor and again, there was also another pipeline: the south stream would have bypassed Ukraine by going directly through Serbia to Southern Europe. That project closed in 2014, but Gazprom further increased its access to Europe by building Nord Stream 2, a second pipeline doubling the amount of gas flowing from Russia to Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years in addition to its pipeline empire, Gazprom has also expanded its influence over global football to include energy partnership with Chelsea football club, UEFA Champions League, and the sport’s most famous tournament: the FIFA World Cup. These sponsorships have made Gazprom’s logo familiar to not only the fans in Europe but across the world. It also did something which boosted the Russian economy. Russia became the world’s largest exporter of natural gas and provided for almost half of all the natural gas supply to Europe becoming a major player in the energy field in Europe. This created a reliance of other countries on Russia for the supply of natural gas, power and energy generation. The strategy adopted by Russia turned out to be a ‘game-changer’ and as of 2019, Russia supplied 199 billion cubic meters of natural gas to Europe. The oil-and-gas sector accounted for 16% of GDP, 52% of federal budget revenues, and over 70% of total exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, Russia is the skipper when it comes to energy supply and generation in Europe and other countries are learning from their example. As the example of Gazprom shows, having prominent soccer sponsorship offers a way around bad publicity by winning approval on the field. Many companies such as Qatar Airways, Etihad Airways and Emirates Airlines have started sponsoring major teams in Europe such as AS Roma, Manchester City and AC Milan respectively. As an avid football supporter, I feel like it’s a big opportunity: their money helps teams win major championships and tournaments, but it is changing the sport itself. Now that it has become common to see a German team sponsored by Russia’s gas company facing off against an Italian team sponsored by Dubai’s state-owned airline, it is starting to seem like the field is hosting two competitions at once: a match between the two teams and larger play for a foreign influence that continues long after the final whistle.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I have a big question for all the football fans reading this article. What does Schalke 04, Red Star Belgrade, and Zenit have in common? I believe it’s difficult to answer this question so let me give you a hint: it’s something printed on their jerseys. Still didn’t get it? It’s the ‘Gazprom’ logo on their jerseys. From being on the jerseys of major football teams from various countries in Europe, it also features on the sidelines and advertisements during games.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Economic Indicator 007</title>
      <link href="/Economic-Indicator-007" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Economic Indicator 007" />
      <published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Economic-Indicator-007</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Economic-Indicator-007">&lt;p&gt;Economic trends are inordinately erratic and display a tendency to react to the smallest stimulus. Unfortunately, the patterns manifested by these trends is all we have to predict the trajectory of the economic system. Going by the book, we have a predominant set of indices that are used to portray an economy’s state of affairs, overriding among them being the GDP, GNP, unemployment rate, inflation rate, rate of interest, consumer price index, etc. However, that’s not even the half of it, as there are a prodigious number of accurate indicators that are undermined by economic planners and analysts. Who thought James Bond would be one of them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know who James Bond is. His reputation as an international man of mystery, a guru of gadgets and espionage thrills, and as the one licensed to kill, precedes him. Since its creation in 1953 by Ian Fleming, the character has etched itself into pop culture and earned itself a spot on the Mount Rushmore of Hollywood. But that’s not the end of its legacy- turns out that it has established one of the most unusual precedents in the economic history of the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &lt;em&gt;Casino Royale&lt;/em&gt; was first published in 1953, the US economy was greatly compromised. The US war spending had helped add $236 billion to the debt. It was a 1048% increase, the largest percentage increase to debt for any President. A recession also sprouted, owing to the demobilisation following the Korean war, and the unemployment levels reached their loftiest at 6.1% in 1954. The same could not be said for Bond, as the book became one of the hottest on the shelves. People started loving the persona of Bond: a dashing agent with seemingly limitless resources and abilities, and he unknowingly became a ridiculously accurate economic barometer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first on-screen adaptation of Bond came with the release of &lt;em&gt;Dr No&lt;/em&gt; in 1962. The times were good, as the economy was exalted as a result of the post the Second World War expansion. President Kennedy had introduced various reforms to revive the economy from the 1960-61 recession. These comprised an increase in the minimum wage for a larger pool of workers, an increase in unemployment compensation plus increased aid to children of unemployed workers, increased social security benefits, emergency relief for feed grain farmers, area redevelopment, vocational training for displaced workers, federal funding for home building and slum eradication and tax cuts. Overseas investment also rose. The film was conferred with critical acclaim, but came up short in commercial success, and is ranked as one of the least earning Bond movies. Still, the film had a significance of its own, as it formed the bedrock for the dazzling success of future installments. What no one seemed to notice was that the success of Bond films and the state of economic well-being were displaying a nebulously accurate disagreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trail of years that followed were not kind to America. President John F Kennedy, the man pivotal in uplifting the economy and perpetuating its growth, had been assassinated. The country’s economy was facing the corroding effects of the Vietnam War, the most famous highlight of which was ‘The Great Botch’ of 1966. The botch involved miscalculation of the war cost by the Defense Department under President Johnson’s administration. The budget was underestimated by a staggering 100%, which squandered the steady income and employment growth rate achieved post the Second World War. The budget deficit also escalated at an alarming rate, hitting the $23 billion mark in 1968.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film franchise, on the other hand, unveiled to the world its most popular antagonist - a fat, decadent psychopath who covers everything in gold and is literally trying to steal all of America’s money - Auric Goldfinger. &lt;em&gt;Thunderball&lt;/em&gt; (1965), &lt;em&gt;Goldfinger&lt;/em&gt; (1964), and &lt;em&gt;You Only Live Twice&lt;/em&gt; (1967) were massive commercial blockbusters, grossing a whopping total of $1.5 billion. Actor Sean Connery got the biggest piece of the pie, as he received a great push towards a legendary career, accompanied by a big fat pay-cheque. The decade ended with a shift in the scales of power, as Richard Nixon took the reigns in 1969.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 70’s witnessed an oscillatory trend for Bond cinema, displaying perfectly negative parallelism to what the economy was enduring. When &lt;em&gt;Diamonds Are Forever&lt;/em&gt; hit the screens in 1971, the US was witnessing a decline in its economic power, and the economy was pegging away to recover from the 1970 recession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Nixon fought the recession by turning the American dollar into a fiat currency, as a result of which the dollar was devalued and millions of foreigners holding dollars, including Arab oil barons with tens of millions of petro-dollars, saw the value of dollars slashed. He also imposed wage and price controls. As you can guess now, the movie was average. It made decent money and was fairly appreciated, but it was no &lt;em&gt;Goldfinger&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the arrival of 1973, the economy stumbled deeper into the trenches. The USA was facing the severest recession since the Second World War, with the rate of inflation at a deplorable 8.8% in the fourth quarter. The Organisation of Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) was blamed for quadrupling oil prices, but that was just the tip of the iceberg. President Nixon’s price controls kept prices too high, reducing demand, while wage controls made salaries too high and forced businesses to lay off workers. Additionally, Nixon took the United States off the gold standard in response to a run on the gold held at Fort Knox, which led to inflation. The price of gold skyrocketed to $120 an ounce while the dollar’s value plummeted. Negative GDP growth of 2.1% was also observed in the third quarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roger Moore’s &lt;em&gt;Live and Let Die&lt;/em&gt; came during the same year, and by now it shouldn’t be a surprise that it was the highest-grossing Bond movie of the 70’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next came time for another turn of tables, with the release of &lt;em&gt;The Man with the Golden Gun&lt;/em&gt; in December 1974. Owing to its late release, its primary collection period was the year 1975, the same year American economy began emerging from recession. An upturn in GDP and industrial output was evident, alongside the dwindling rate of inflation (from 10.4% in 1974 to 6.5 % in 1975). The volume of shares traded on the New York stock exchange also rose from 3.5 to 4.7 billion shares. &lt;em&gt;The Man with the Golden Gun&lt;/em&gt; is still considered to be the most flawed and pointless addition to the Bond universe, loathed by critics and the audience alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The climax for the 70’s economy came with another capricious change in economic trends, displayed by cascading economic growth. Inflation and unemployment were up again, and the economic system was slithering into another recession. The timing could not have been better for &lt;em&gt;The Spy Who Loved Me&lt;/em&gt; (1977) and &lt;em&gt;Moonraker&lt;/em&gt; (1979), as both of them grossed a stupendous $1.3 billion combined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the year 1981 rolled in, the recession boomeranged back to plague the economy. The Regan government caused this recession by raising interest rates to curb inflation, which undesirably reduced business spending. The Iranian oil embargo added fuel to the fire, as it reduced US oil supplies, which drove up the prices. GDP growth was negative for the whole year, the worst being the second quarter at a negative 8.0%. Unemployment rose to 10.8% in November and December 1982, the highest level in any modern recession. President Reagan lowered the tax rate and boosted the defense budget, helping to end the recession. Summing it up, the economy was toiling to fend off the unemployment and inflationary outbreaks. The commercial struggle of &lt;em&gt;For Your Eyes Only&lt;/em&gt; (1983) epitomised a more complicated one going on in the economy. However, the film is the best Bond portrayal of the 1980’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining decade was all Reagan-show, as he painted a masterpiece on the economic canvas. The first step was signing the Economic Recovery Tax Act of 1981, which brought reductions in individual income tax rates, the expensing of depreciable property, incentives for small businesses and incentives for savings. So began the Reagan Recovery. A few years later, the Tax Reform Act of 1986 brought the lowest individual and corporate income tax rates of any major industrialised country in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The numbers tell the story. Over the eight years of the Reagan Administration:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• 20 million new jobs were created. Employment of African-Americans rose by more than 25% between 1982 and 1988, and more than half of the new jobs created went to women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Inflation dropped from 13.5% in 1980 to 4.1% by 1988.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Unemployment fell from 7.6% to 5.5%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Net worth of families earning between $20,000 and $50,000 annually grew by 27%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Real gross national product rose by 26%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• The prime interest rate was slashed by more than half, from an unprecedented 21.5% in January 1981 to 10% in August 1988.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Growth in government spending plummeted from 10% in 1982 to just over 1% in 1987. With inflation factored in, federal spending actually went down in 1987– the first time that had happened in well over a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the economy boomed, Bond got tanked again, facing consecutive low earning entries in the series. The decade leached away Bond’s persona as the charismatic spy who could always get the job done and turned him into a goofy, lethargic and confused man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to 1995, the economy was recovering from the recession of 1990-91 and was turning increasingly healthy in performance as the 1990’s progressed. The fall of the Soviet Union and Eastern European communism in the late 1980’s opened up trade opportunities across the world. Technological developments brought a wide range of new, more efficient electronic products, and innovations in telecommunications and computer networking spawned a vast computer hardware and software industry. This, in turn, revolutionised the way many other industries operated. The growth rate and corporate earnings rose rapidly. A combination of desirable inflation, unemployment, and corporate profits sent the stock market surging. Moreover, the Dow Jones Industrial Average, which had stood at just 1,000 in the late 1970’s, hit the 11,000 mark in 1999, adding substantially to the wealth of many - though not all - Americans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An idiosyncrasy of the final decade of the century was the increasing speculation in online websites, also known as the ‘dot-com bubble’. People were rapidly dumping cash in online domains. Capital from venture capitalists was also easy to raise, as investment banks profited from the Initial Public Offers (IPOs). A combination of rapidly increasing stock prices in the quaternary sector of the economy and confidence that the companies would turn future profits created an environment in which many investors were willing to overlook traditional metrics, such as the price-earnings ratio, and base confidence on technological advancements, which ultimately led to a stock market bubble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar was the case with Bond movies. Almost all of the previous Bond films had an average budget of about $30 million. So 1989’s &lt;em&gt;License to Kill&lt;/em&gt;, which is still the worst-performing entry of the entire franchise, wound up earning almost four times its budget. Though 1999’s &lt;em&gt;Tomorrow Never Dies&lt;/em&gt; grossed way more, producers had dumped over $110 million into it and funneled even more cash into the next two installments. Such a large investment in movies led to the formation of an investment bubble of its own. However, filmmakers’ bulletproof investment bubble burst, just like all the dot-coms of the 90’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decade changed, but the story didn’t. Bond made millions whenever inflation and unemployment got the better of the economy. Be it &lt;em&gt;Quantum of Solace&lt;/em&gt; (2008) and the financial crisis 2007-08 or &lt;em&gt;Skyfall&lt;/em&gt; (2012) and the global economic crisis 2012, it’s always the same. Higher the severity of the crisis, the more dollars Bond films rake in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the phenomenon first got noticed, it was spurned as a mere case of coincidences. Till today, no one has been able to decipher the reason behind this absurd correlation. In my opinion, one aspect of it can be identified as what is known as the ‘butter popcorn effect’, which is an unconventional economic indicator. The rationale behind it is that during the initial stages of a recession, people show a greater inclination towards entertainment, as they want to escape the hardships of the real world. As this pushes more people into cinema halls, the sale of butter popcorn also increases. For instance, the box office posted one of its biggest years during the 2009 recession, before plateauing as markets eased. Still, there is no solid explanation about why Bond films fail during economic expansion.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aryaman Dhiman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Economic trends are inordinately erratic and display a tendency to react to the smallest stimulus. Unfortunately, the patterns manifested by these trends is all we have to predict the trajectory of the economic system. Going by the book, we have a predominant set of indices that are used to portray an economy’s state of affairs, overriding among them being the GDP, GNP, unemployment rate, inflation rate, rate of interest, consumer price index, etc. However, that’s not even the half of it, as there are a prodigious number of accurate indicators that are undermined by economic planners and analysts. Who thought James Bond would be one of them?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
