<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/economics/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-08-02T13:32:04+01:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/economics/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Varsity Blues Scandal: An Insight</title>
      <link href="/Varsity-Blues-Scandal-An-Insight" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Varsity Blues Scandal: An Insight" />
      <published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-07-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Varsity-Blues-Scandal-An-Insight</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Varsity-Blues-Scandal-An-Insight">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;On March 12, 2019, the United States Department of Justice revealed the largest college admissions scandal prosecution ever in US history, filing charges against over 50 people as a part of the conspiracy. The scandal was proof of privilege gone wild wherein some students got in through pure merit, while others due to preferences that are skewed in favour of the rich and white. The mastermind behind the whole conspiracy was William Rick Singer, an admissions consultant and ex-athletic coach helping the most flush family kids to get into elite colleges. It was estimated that over $25 million was paid to Singer for his services, which fell under the category of ‘charity.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There were two distinct parts to the charges that explained the entire operation. First, the parents reportedly paid Singer to bribe coaches at schools to help recruit their kids into sports programs without having proven athletic ability. Second, the test preparation moderators were bribed by Singer to favourably evaluate students’ answers and extend the time limit on entrance tests. The investigation, code-named &lt;em&gt;Operation Varsity Blues&lt;/em&gt;, disclosed that this unethical college admission process was followed for as many as 750 families!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Since the uncovering, several measures have been taken. Singer and parents involved have pleaded guilty, indicted coaches have been fired or suspended, and some of the schools have rescinded the admission offers to students who were unethically inducted. While lawsuits have been filed and committees have been set up to review the allegations, the larger question remains: Why did this happen? Is it the over-fixation with the elite colleges in society, skewed ownership of social assets, or the guarantee of a successful life ahead attached to these premier institutions? The answer is a mixture of all three factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not The First Scandal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While the 2019 scandal may seem like a new breaking phenomenon, it was not the first. Scandals like this have occurred in the past and are not unheard of in universities across the United States. In July 2019, a Florida-based business executive, Philip Esformes, faced indictment for bribing a basketball coach at the University of Pennsylvania to help his son get admitted to Penn. Another such scandal was unearthed at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. It was disclosed that the university officials had favoured the admission of over 800 students in the class of 2005-2009. Such instances are proof of a broken system, as the 800 students favoured meant that 800 deserving students were denied the opportunity to obtain education at the institution. Similarly, a lawsuit against Harvard’s admission processes revealed the maintenance of a secret list of applicants by the college who are the kin of major donors of the university. The students on this donor list have a 42% acceptance rate against the overall 4.6% acceptance rate at Harvard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Parenting, Cultural Capital and College Admissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;At the heart of the scandal lies a complex relationship between parenting, admissions, and cultural capital. In an article about the scandal in the &lt;em&gt;Los Angeles Times&lt;/em&gt;, the term &quot;parenting on steroids&quot; was used in the article describing the process, synonymous with terms like intensive mothering. The notion behind this term was to explain a family complex that upper and middle-class parents seem to be grappling with to achieve certain standards.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The constant fixation on attending a prestigious institution regardless of the child’s interest, in the name of holding social and parental status, is troublesome. The other cause of worry is the lack of belief in the child’s ability to earn admission into a college on their own. The parent, therefore, ends up playing a role in shielding their kids from disappointments rather than assisting them to become independent. Hence, the college process is seemingly harder on parents as it is a relentless test on what it means to be a good parent in the present time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It is no secret that the scheme worked because of an education system that is broken. The 2019 college admissions scandal and the past episodes are all a result of structural inequality too. The elite schools are designed to favour the well-heeled. The US political and economic elites enjoy several advantages in the admission process, most of them legal! The students coming from families donating millions to the school are more likely to be considered. Further, over half of the private colleges and universities and a fraction of the public ones consider legacy admissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There has also been a sharp rise in the number of private college counsellors, supporting the idea that higher education has become just another booming business where the wealthy have an upper hand. Similarly, SAT and ACT tutors are also common among those that are willing to pay. Therefore, even without the manipulation of test scores by people like Singer, the axis tilts heavily towards the affluent; as the students from this background can perform better in standardised tests in comparison to their peers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A result is colleges and universities, including Ivy Leagues, being disproportionately populated by students from wealthy families. According to a 2017 &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt; analysis, there are more students from the top 1% of families by income against the bottom 60% at 38 colleges, including Yale, Princeton, Dartmouth and the University of Pennsylvania. Presumably, most of these admissions were bagged through years of leads that accrue from wealth: good education and test preparations, access to tutoring services, sports coaching and private lessons, and the absence of the tribulations that accompany poverty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Thus, American higher education in its entirety is just one big pay-to-play scheme making equal opportunity seem impossible to achieve. What is needed on the part of these elite universities is a reimagination of their objectives and the admission practices where one’s acceptance is not determined by their wealth or status, but pure merit. Along with that, the ethical lapses on the part of the parents to provide their kids with everything is essentially robbing them of skills that count. If the parents keep on pursuing their fixation with these handful of selective schools, there are going to be more such scandals in future. American higher education is not only supposed to prepare the best and the brightest generation of leaders, it is also supposed to nurture a principled foundation as the basis for its own existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rajsi Sah</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On March 12, 2019, the United States Department of Justice revealed the largest college admissions scandal prosecution ever in US history, filing charges against over 50 people as a part of the conspiracy. The scandal was proof of privilege gone wild wherein some students got in through pure merit, while others due to preferences that are skewed in favour of the rich and white. The mastermind behind the whole conspiracy was William Rick Singer, an admissions consultant and ex-athletic coach helping the most flush family kids to get into elite colleges. It was estimated that over $25 million was paid to Singer for his services, which fell under the category of ‘charity.’ There were two distinct parts to the charges that explained the entire operation. First, the parents reportedly paid Singer to bribe coaches at schools to help recruit their kids into sports programs without having proven athletic ability. Second, the test preparation moderators were bribed by Singer to favourably evaluate students’ answers and extend the time limit on entrance tests. The investigation, code-named Operation Varsity Blues, disclosed that this unethical college admission process was followed for as many as 750 families! Since the uncovering, several measures have been taken. Singer and parents involved have pleaded guilty, indicted coaches have been fired or suspended, and some of the schools have rescinded the admission offers to students who were unethically inducted. While lawsuits have been filed and committees have been set up to review the allegations, the larger question remains: Why did this happen? Is it the over-fixation with the elite colleges in society, skewed ownership of social assets, or the guarantee of a successful life ahead attached to these premier institutions? The answer is a mixture of all three factors. Not The First Scandal While the 2019 scandal may seem like a new breaking phenomenon, it was not the first. Scandals like this have occurred in the past and are not unheard of in universities across the United States. In July 2019, a Florida-based business executive, Philip Esformes, faced indictment for bribing a basketball coach at the University of Pennsylvania to help his son get admitted to Penn. Another such scandal was unearthed at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. It was disclosed that the university officials had favoured the admission of over 800 students in the class of 2005-2009. Such instances are proof of a broken system, as the 800 students favoured meant that 800 deserving students were denied the opportunity to obtain education at the institution. Similarly, a lawsuit against Harvard’s admission processes revealed the maintenance of a secret list of applicants by the college who are the kin of major donors of the university. The students on this donor list have a 42% acceptance rate against the overall 4.6% acceptance rate at Harvard. Parenting, Cultural Capital and College Admissions At the heart of the scandal lies a complex relationship between parenting, admissions, and cultural capital. In an article about the scandal in the Los Angeles Times, the term &quot;parenting on steroids&quot; was used in the article describing the process, synonymous with terms like intensive mothering. The notion behind this term was to explain a family complex that upper and middle-class parents seem to be grappling with to achieve certain standards.&amp;nbsp; The constant fixation on attending a prestigious institution regardless of the child’s interest, in the name of holding social and parental status, is troublesome. The other cause of worry is the lack of belief in the child’s ability to earn admission into a college on their own. The parent, therefore, ends up playing a role in shielding their kids from disappointments rather than assisting them to become independent. Hence, the college process is seemingly harder on parents as it is a relentless test on what it means to be a good parent in the present time. It is no secret that the scheme worked because of an education system that is broken. The 2019 college admissions scandal and the past episodes are all a result of structural inequality too. The elite schools are designed to favour the well-heeled. The US political and economic elites enjoy several advantages in the admission process, most of them legal! The students coming from families donating millions to the school are more likely to be considered. Further, over half of the private colleges and universities and a fraction of the public ones consider legacy admissions. There has also been a sharp rise in the number of private college counsellors, supporting the idea that higher education has become just another booming business where the wealthy have an upper hand. Similarly, SAT and ACT tutors are also common among those that are willing to pay. Therefore, even without the manipulation of test scores by people like Singer, the axis tilts heavily towards the affluent; as the students from this background can perform better in standardised tests in comparison to their peers.&amp;nbsp; A result is colleges and universities, including Ivy Leagues, being disproportionately populated by students from wealthy families. According to a 2017 New York Times analysis, there are more students from the top 1% of families by income against the bottom 60% at 38 colleges, including Yale, Princeton, Dartmouth and the University of Pennsylvania. Presumably, most of these admissions were bagged through years of leads that accrue from wealth: good education and test preparations, access to tutoring services, sports coaching and private lessons, and the absence of the tribulations that accompany poverty. Thus, American higher education in its entirety is just one big pay-to-play scheme making equal opportunity seem impossible to achieve. What is needed on the part of these elite universities is a reimagination of their objectives and the admission practices where one’s acceptance is not determined by their wealth or status, but pure merit. Along with that, the ethical lapses on the part of the parents to provide their kids with everything is essentially robbing them of skills that count. If the parents keep on pursuing their fixation with these handful of selective schools, there are going to be more such scandals in future. American higher education is not only supposed to prepare the best and the brightest generation of leaders, it is also supposed to nurture a principled foundation as the basis for its own existence.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Wars: The Hole in a Country’s Pocket</title>
      <link href="/Wars-The-Hole-in-a-Country-s-Pocket" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wars: The Hole in a Country’s Pocket" />
      <published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Wars-The-Hole-in-a-Country-s-Pocket</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Wars-The-Hole-in-a-Country-s-Pocket">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;What gives rise to wars? Well, conflicts are an inevitable part of the survival of the human race; especially when existence is heterogeneous in nature. When conflicts intersect with political ideals and ideologies, land rights, religious dominance, etc they have the potential to churn out a war.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Time and time again, countries around the world have stepped down to avoid war but a few remain unlucky and suffer the aftermath. The cost of war is immeasurable for all the parties involved. No matter who wins the battle, the loss is suffered on all ends; and usually, it is equal in magnitude. Economics is well-stitched into a war, so much so that experts believe every war entails an economic motive irrespective of the reason presented to the public. This is probably why one will never come across two entities fighting for a barren land with no water sources, no mineral wealth and no means of attracting investment in any form. Even if the total area of such land can help the country expand its territorial boundaries, it is not worth a war!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To lay the foundation it is important to understand the ‘war economy’. When a nation is in a state of war, the prioritisation principle witnesses a shift in expenditure. The production of goods and services that support war efforts and strengthen the defence front of the country assume importance. A country at war re-configures its budget and diverts all the taxes towards national security, the nation might also borrow to fund its requirements. One ramification of war is that it encourages innovation. War economies demonstrate more technological, industrial and medical advancements as they are in competition to create cheaper defence products along with the emergency medical units to be well prepared. This is an instance of infrastructural development. However, the focus is not the welfare of its citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;One might expect wealthy nations to be more violent as they have more to fight over. However, the econometric evidence is divided, most researches show that wealth reduces the probability of a civil war by manifolds. In addition, economic growth acts as a shield against violence, while recession increases the probability. The most common reason for this is that wealthier societies are able to better protect assets, thus making violence less attractive for would-be rebels. Another explanation, given by political scientist Thomas Homer-Dixon argues that poverty causes violence, and points to cases where scarcity leads to migrations that result in conflicts between identity groups over resources. The cost of physical capital destruction and human capital destruction remain inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;Do wars benefit anyone?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It will be paradoxical to state that war will benefit the country. A conflict that results in loss of human lives, destruction of property, trauma, leaving hundreds of people homeless, and the list goes on, cannot do good to anyone. However, economics rises a notch above human sentiments and reflects on the infrastructural developments and a shift in the demand-supply chain. A country that is in a state of war will accommodate its working population in order to work to the brim and achieve the fullest of its capacity, thus aiming at full employment across different sectors.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Spike in employment, the surge in working capacity and inclusion of the latest technology to produce efficiently helps in boosting economic growth. The government invests in the latest technology in order to keep pace with the war which in turn boosts innovation in the territory and paves way for research and development (R&amp;amp;D).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another important side effect of war is the change in social outlook and attitudes. History is evidence of the fact that women have stepped out of their houses in order to be a part of the labour force contributing to the battle whenever a war breaks out. Healthcare, a major support system during wars, witnesses women participating in large numbers to save the lives of soldiers. Various industries that work to boost the supplies welcome women in order to elevate the production capacity while the men go out to the battlefield. Women have played an important role in all the wars that humanity has witnessed till now, so much so that they became aware of their rights after World War I and World War II and with a stride of independence they continued to voice their rights and soon the demand for ‘vote’ was raised by women across the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is at stake for Israel-Palestine?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In May 2021, Israel and Pakistan counted 11 days of hostilities that resulted in the loss of life and physical capital on both ends. The housing ministry of Gaza stated that 16,800 housing units have been damaged. The electricity grids across Gaza remain dismantled with barely three-four hours of power supply in a day. The Hamas media office estimated the bombardments had caused $40 million in damage to factories and the strip’s industrial zone and other industrial facilities, in addition to $22 million in damage to the energy sector. In addition, the sanitation facilities have been damaged and the water supply remains disrupted with limited or no access to water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Israeli economy already contracted by 6.5% in the first quarter due to the pandemic.&amp;nbsp; The Central Bureau of Statistics predicts that the road to revival is likely to stay disrupted owing to the fight between Israel and Palestine. Israel’s manufacturers’ association reported a loss of $166 million as of 13 May 2021 because the south and centre of the country witnessed intense rocket fire from Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The economic relations between Israel and Palestine date back to 1967 when Israel occupied the West Bank and Gaza Strip and integrated their markets with its own. The Israeli economy was about ten times the size of its neighbour’s economy and the manufacturing sector’s GDP share was over four times larger. Thus the difference was between a large, rich and advanced economy and a small, poor and underdeveloped economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Both theoretical analysis and empirical studies suggest that the dynamics of such a relationship always generates two opposing forces that disproportionately affect the smaller economy and shape its development. A favourable repercussion is an increased demand for the products of the small economy, diffusion of technology and knowledge. Unfavourable repercussions arise from the disappearance of many industries in the small economy, its confinement to producing low-skill goods, and the emigration of a sizable segment of its labour force to the neighbouring economy, as well as to other countries. This suppression of a powerful neighbour has resulted in numerous incidents of violence, time and again. The end consequence has been that the region of Palestine has seen practically no development and has remained war torn.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Nevertheless, “who benefits from war?” remains unanswered.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">What gives rise to wars? Well, conflicts are an inevitable part of the survival of the human race; especially when existence is heterogeneous in nature. When conflicts intersect with political ideals and ideologies, land rights, religious dominance, etc they have the potential to churn out a war.&amp;nbsp; Time and time again, countries around the world have stepped down to avoid war but a few remain unlucky and suffer the aftermath. The cost of war is immeasurable for all the parties involved. No matter who wins the battle, the loss is suffered on all ends; and usually, it is equal in magnitude. Economics is well-stitched into a war, so much so that experts believe every war entails an economic motive irrespective of the reason presented to the public. This is probably why one will never come across two entities fighting for a barren land with no water sources, no mineral wealth and no means of attracting investment in any form. Even if the total area of such land can help the country expand its territorial boundaries, it is not worth a war!&amp;nbsp; To lay the foundation it is important to understand the ‘war economy’. When a nation is in a state of war, the prioritisation principle witnesses a shift in expenditure. The production of goods and services that support war efforts and strengthen the defence front of the country assume importance. A country at war re-configures its budget and diverts all the taxes towards national security, the nation might also borrow to fund its requirements. One ramification of war is that it encourages innovation. War economies demonstrate more technological, industrial and medical advancements as they are in competition to create cheaper defence products along with the emergency medical units to be well prepared. This is an instance of infrastructural development. However, the focus is not the welfare of its citizens. One might expect wealthy nations to be more violent as they have more to fight over. However, the econometric evidence is divided, most researches show that wealth reduces the probability of a civil war by manifolds. In addition, economic growth acts as a shield against violence, while recession increases the probability. The most common reason for this is that wealthier societies are able to better protect assets, thus making violence less attractive for would-be rebels. Another explanation, given by political scientist Thomas Homer-Dixon argues that poverty causes violence, and points to cases where scarcity leads to migrations that result in conflicts between identity groups over resources. The cost of physical capital destruction and human capital destruction remain inevitable. &amp;nbsp;Do wars benefit anyone? It will be paradoxical to state that war will benefit the country. A conflict that results in loss of human lives, destruction of property, trauma, leaving hundreds of people homeless, and the list goes on, cannot do good to anyone. However, economics rises a notch above human sentiments and reflects on the infrastructural developments and a shift in the demand-supply chain. A country that is in a state of war will accommodate its working population in order to work to the brim and achieve the fullest of its capacity, thus aiming at full employment across different sectors.&amp;nbsp; Spike in employment, the surge in working capacity and inclusion of the latest technology to produce efficiently helps in boosting economic growth. The government invests in the latest technology in order to keep pace with the war which in turn boosts innovation in the territory and paves way for research and development (R&amp;amp;D).&amp;nbsp; Another important side effect of war is the change in social outlook and attitudes. History is evidence of the fact that women have stepped out of their houses in order to be a part of the labour force contributing to the battle whenever a war breaks out. Healthcare, a major support system during wars, witnesses women participating in large numbers to save the lives of soldiers. Various industries that work to boost the supplies welcome women in order to elevate the production capacity while the men go out to the battlefield. Women have played an important role in all the wars that humanity has witnessed till now, so much so that they became aware of their rights after World War I and World War II and with a stride of independence they continued to voice their rights and soon the demand for ‘vote’ was raised by women across the world. What is at stake for Israel-Palestine? In May 2021, Israel and Pakistan counted 11 days of hostilities that resulted in the loss of life and physical capital on both ends. The housing ministry of Gaza stated that 16,800 housing units have been damaged. The electricity grids across Gaza remain dismantled with barely three-four hours of power supply in a day. The Hamas media office estimated the bombardments had caused $40 million in damage to factories and the strip’s industrial zone and other industrial facilities, in addition to $22 million in damage to the energy sector. In addition, the sanitation facilities have been damaged and the water supply remains disrupted with limited or no access to water. The Israeli economy already contracted by 6.5% in the first quarter due to the pandemic.&amp;nbsp; The Central Bureau of Statistics predicts that the road to revival is likely to stay disrupted owing to the fight between Israel and Palestine. Israel’s manufacturers’ association reported a loss of $166 million as of 13 May 2021 because the south and centre of the country witnessed intense rocket fire from Gaza. The economic relations between Israel and Palestine date back to 1967 when Israel occupied the West Bank and Gaza Strip and integrated their markets with its own. The Israeli economy was about ten times the size of its neighbour’s economy and the manufacturing sector’s GDP share was over four times larger. Thus the difference was between a large, rich and advanced economy and a small, poor and underdeveloped economy.&amp;nbsp; Both theoretical analysis and empirical studies suggest that the dynamics of such a relationship always generates two opposing forces that disproportionately affect the smaller economy and shape its development. A favourable repercussion is an increased demand for the products of the small economy, diffusion of technology and knowledge. Unfavourable repercussions arise from the disappearance of many industries in the small economy, its confinement to producing low-skill goods, and the emigration of a sizable segment of its labour force to the neighbouring economy, as well as to other countries. This suppression of a powerful neighbour has resulted in numerous incidents of violence, time and again. The end consequence has been that the region of Palestine has seen practically no development and has remained war torn.&amp;nbsp; Nevertheless, “who benefits from war?” remains unanswered.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Is Simple Good?</title>
      <link href="/Is-simple-good" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Simple Good?" />
      <published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Is-simple-good</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Is-simple-good">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;When Netﬂix released its adventure interactive series ‘You vs Wild’ it left its viewers in a dilemma of choosing between a muddy swamp full of crocodiles and a turfy route traversed along by wild animals, one of which could be a potential life-saving course for the show’s host Bear Grylls, it saw its viewers’ brains work in wondrous ways to be able to make a decision in the blink of an eye.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As for viewers, they weren’t met with a life altering decision to make, but instead a gripping show that gave them the adrenaline rush with each passing course of action. Their decisions were based on a simpler question - I wonder what happens next. These viewers, in most cases, aren’t individuals who have or will ever go on a full-ﬂedged adventure; therefore, their decisions in the series are based out of whatever incomplete prior knowledge they have or out of sheer instinct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The behaviour that our brain adapts to simplify the decision-making process is called heuristics. It is a shortcut that our brain mechanises to reach a reasonable decision under uncertainty and risk and especially when the perfect decision is unknowable or unreachable. It usually devises a method by which our brain substitutes a complex problem at hand with a simpler question, one which is readily answerable by the stakeholder. In our example, the viewers’ brains substituted the complex problem of saving Bear Grylls’ life with the simpler question: I wonder what happens next?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Heuristics has multiple types, but narrowing it down to two broad categories gives us heuristics in terms of cognitive biases and intuition-based heuristics. Cognitive biases can be understood as the context in which an individual looks at a problem. The context could be anything: the way a problem was presented to the individual, prior judgement or perception of the individual acting as an anchor to their decision-making, peer inﬂuence, prior beliefs supported by ancillary evidence, or simply the brain retaining and believing the most recent piece of information, ignoring relevant facts and evidences in favour of or against the individual’s claimed decision. Cognitive biases aren’t necessarily ﬂaws because they depict the behavioural process an individual will adopt in incorporating the context and conditioning they come from.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;An individual cannot be isolated from their context, and hence rationality should assume subjective cognitive capabilities playing their respective roles in determining an individual’s decision. As for intuition-based heuristics, they are simply the built-in or learned capacities of humans to approach a certain problem. For example, to catch a ball thrown at you, there’s an imminent risk on you and hence you use your sight and reﬂexes to catch or dodge the ball, instead of adopting the more complicated and time-taking method of ﬁnding out the trajectory of the ball mathematically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Post the behavioural economics revolution, which has transformed the way economics looks at how humans approach their own behaviours, it has become imperative for us to understand how this particular human psyche could be used as a problem-solving tactic on a macroeconomic canvas.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Heuristics are tools to reach beyond the shelves of customarily understanding. Using them to make good and reduce bad in our world is our job”&lt;/em&gt;, said Warren Weaver. The application of heuristics by ordinary individuals is well understood, however, practitioners, analysts and policy makers have for long associated with the traditional techniques of research, systems analysis and quantitative modelling for policy recommendations, which are often presumed to be understood by well-educated individuals, thereby making it highly complex and a depoliticised exercise, out of reach for common individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;More often than not, policymaking is embedded in quantitative techniques and formal analysis that sometimes fails to take into account the qualitative and abstract policy concepts which are not included as variables or parameters within a policy analysis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This stringent policy model framework tends to underemphasise certain errors or inadequately deﬁne a problem, therefore analysing the wrong problem or a problem which is analysable using formal methods. Policy analysis requires policymakers to be aware of and to incorporate the conditions and context an issue is arising from. Policy issues are deeply layered and solving them is a step-by-step procedure, one that is backed by data but also abstract concepts like conditioning, decision-making and other socio-economic factors. Such issues are solved by arriving at a consensus, which is the opposite of how traditional policymaking works. It essentially assumes the reactions to when a new policy or law is announced, without actually drawing a link between passing of the law and actual human behaviour, which is not as analytical in its approach to problems like professional policymakers and analysts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The essential goal of policymaking is not just problem solving but of problem ﬁnding and structuring it around the needs of people. Policymaking by professionals can adopt the approach of understanding and comprehending individual decision-making or to view decision-making as problem solving, which is largely determined by heuristics. This approach also poses another relevant question - why should the methods of problem solving and policy analysis be different at all?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The answer lies in a framework, which lies at the intersection of the existing methods and heuristics, an analysis which revises the existing policy making methods in constructive ways that incorporates human behaviour and then constructs a policy. The process of construction must incorporate ﬂexibility in criteria, variables and solutions and must devise alternatives and rank them in order of effectiveness. It must eliminate those alternatives that are unrealistic or unattainable.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The policy should be such that it focuses on creating habits among individuals that become an accepted social norm over the course of time. Such accepted habits are constantly reinforced by the public themselves as a demonstrated cognitive behaviour. Certain examinations like Randomised Controlled Trials (RCTs) are a stepping stone towards incorporating behavioural insights into analysis, which ﬁnds itself at the intersection of formal methods and human behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Heuristic analysis has its value in its ability to improve decisions and in dissociating from stringent models and placing emphasis on individual behaviour and informed judgement. Policymaking can become a cognisant process with conscious efforts instead of complex methods becoming a constraint, for it affects the lives of people on a national scale. It addresses some limitations of traditional policy analysis, however it does come with its own set of limitations - lack of subjective knowledge or access to communities or social settings, lack of resources and time to conduct in-depth surveys, errors in judgement by the policy maker, etc. These can be dealt with on a structural level if a conclusive framework is organised.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">When Netﬂix released its adventure interactive series ‘You vs Wild’ it left its viewers in a dilemma of choosing between a muddy swamp full of crocodiles and a turfy route traversed along by wild animals, one of which could be a potential life-saving course for the show’s host Bear Grylls, it saw its viewers’ brains work in wondrous ways to be able to make a decision in the blink of an eye.&amp;nbsp; As for viewers, they weren’t met with a life altering decision to make, but instead a gripping show that gave them the adrenaline rush with each passing course of action. Their decisions were based on a simpler question - I wonder what happens next. These viewers, in most cases, aren’t individuals who have or will ever go on a full-ﬂedged adventure; therefore, their decisions in the series are based out of whatever incomplete prior knowledge they have or out of sheer instinct. The behaviour that our brain adapts to simplify the decision-making process is called heuristics. It is a shortcut that our brain mechanises to reach a reasonable decision under uncertainty and risk and especially when the perfect decision is unknowable or unreachable. It usually devises a method by which our brain substitutes a complex problem at hand with a simpler question, one which is readily answerable by the stakeholder. In our example, the viewers’ brains substituted the complex problem of saving Bear Grylls’ life with the simpler question: I wonder what happens next? Heuristics has multiple types, but narrowing it down to two broad categories gives us heuristics in terms of cognitive biases and intuition-based heuristics. Cognitive biases can be understood as the context in which an individual looks at a problem. The context could be anything: the way a problem was presented to the individual, prior judgement or perception of the individual acting as an anchor to their decision-making, peer inﬂuence, prior beliefs supported by ancillary evidence, or simply the brain retaining and believing the most recent piece of information, ignoring relevant facts and evidences in favour of or against the individual’s claimed decision. Cognitive biases aren’t necessarily ﬂaws because they depict the behavioural process an individual will adopt in incorporating the context and conditioning they come from.&amp;nbsp; An individual cannot be isolated from their context, and hence rationality should assume subjective cognitive capabilities playing their respective roles in determining an individual’s decision. As for intuition-based heuristics, they are simply the built-in or learned capacities of humans to approach a certain problem. For example, to catch a ball thrown at you, there’s an imminent risk on you and hence you use your sight and reﬂexes to catch or dodge the ball, instead of adopting the more complicated and time-taking method of ﬁnding out the trajectory of the ball mathematically. Post the behavioural economics revolution, which has transformed the way economics looks at how humans approach their own behaviours, it has become imperative for us to understand how this particular human psyche could be used as a problem-solving tactic on a macroeconomic canvas.&amp;nbsp; “Heuristics are tools to reach beyond the shelves of customarily understanding. Using them to make good and reduce bad in our world is our job”, said Warren Weaver. The application of heuristics by ordinary individuals is well understood, however, practitioners, analysts and policy makers have for long associated with the traditional techniques of research, systems analysis and quantitative modelling for policy recommendations, which are often presumed to be understood by well-educated individuals, thereby making it highly complex and a depoliticised exercise, out of reach for common individuals. More often than not, policymaking is embedded in quantitative techniques and formal analysis that sometimes fails to take into account the qualitative and abstract policy concepts which are not included as variables or parameters within a policy analysis.&amp;nbsp; This stringent policy model framework tends to underemphasise certain errors or inadequately deﬁne a problem, therefore analysing the wrong problem or a problem which is analysable using formal methods. Policy analysis requires policymakers to be aware of and to incorporate the conditions and context an issue is arising from. Policy issues are deeply layered and solving them is a step-by-step procedure, one that is backed by data but also abstract concepts like conditioning, decision-making and other socio-economic factors. Such issues are solved by arriving at a consensus, which is the opposite of how traditional policymaking works. It essentially assumes the reactions to when a new policy or law is announced, without actually drawing a link between passing of the law and actual human behaviour, which is not as analytical in its approach to problems like professional policymakers and analysts. The essential goal of policymaking is not just problem solving but of problem ﬁnding and structuring it around the needs of people. Policymaking by professionals can adopt the approach of understanding and comprehending individual decision-making or to view decision-making as problem solving, which is largely determined by heuristics. This approach also poses another relevant question - why should the methods of problem solving and policy analysis be different at all?&amp;nbsp; The answer lies in a framework, which lies at the intersection of the existing methods and heuristics, an analysis which revises the existing policy making methods in constructive ways that incorporates human behaviour and then constructs a policy. The process of construction must incorporate ﬂexibility in criteria, variables and solutions and must devise alternatives and rank them in order of effectiveness. It must eliminate those alternatives that are unrealistic or unattainable.&amp;nbsp; The policy should be such that it focuses on creating habits among individuals that become an accepted social norm over the course of time. Such accepted habits are constantly reinforced by the public themselves as a demonstrated cognitive behaviour. Certain examinations like Randomised Controlled Trials (RCTs) are a stepping stone towards incorporating behavioural insights into analysis, which ﬁnds itself at the intersection of formal methods and human behaviour. Heuristic analysis has its value in its ability to improve decisions and in dissociating from stringent models and placing emphasis on individual behaviour and informed judgement. Policymaking can become a cognisant process with conscious efforts instead of complex methods becoming a constraint, for it affects the lives of people on a national scale. It addresses some limitations of traditional policy analysis, however it does come with its own set of limitations - lack of subjective knowledge or access to communities or social settings, lack of resources and time to conduct in-depth surveys, errors in judgement by the policy maker, etc. These can be dealt with on a structural level if a conclusive framework is organised.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Post-COVID World Economy</title>
      <link href="/The-Post-COVID-World-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Post-COVID World Economy" />
      <published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Post-COVID-World-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Post-COVID-World-Economy">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The history of the world economy demonstrates a trend of economic shocks emerging in every generation. The World Health Organisation (WHO) declared COVID-19 as a global pandemic on March 11, 2020; and since then, almost every human endeavour has been disrupted.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The impact on the global economy is particularly worrying. We witnessed global supply chains being severely disrupted and strained, financial markets unsettled, resulting in a cross-border economic disaster. Border closures and lockdowns shattered the core sustaining pillars of modern world economies, with the economic shock due to these measures still being weighed across the globe. The ramifications of these disruptions are more far-reaching than anticipated, and the legacies of COVID-19 will shape global growth for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Even though economies are recovering at different paces throughout the world, the world economy is well on the way to recovery from a slump the likes of which none of its 7.7 billion inhabitants has seen in their lifetimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The new paradigms enforced in the COVID-19 era have led to an unprecedented acceleration in automation and digitisation of operations whilst highlighting the importance of upskilling the workforce. Turbulent labour markets provide additional challenges to professionals as the pace of technology adoption remains unabated while automation, in tandem with the COVID-19 recession, is creating a 'double-disruption' scenario for the labour force. There is more inequality between and within countries, and governments are playing a larger role in the lives of citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Looking at historical precedents, the World Economic Forum postulates that the pandemic is about three times as bad as the global financial crisis of 2008 in terms of GDP decline on an annual basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2020/09/an-economist-explains-what-covid-19-has-done-to-the-global-economy/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/IHS-Markit-gdp-growth.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Economists surmise that adopting a circular economy would be the best way for the world's economy to recover, whilst enabling the transition to an essentially low-carbon economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The pandemic also catalysed the rise of the digital economy, with the influx of digital behaviour such as remote working and learning, telemedicine, and delivery services. Due to this rapid digitisation, other structural changes can also be anticipated, including regionalisation of supply chains and a further explosion of cross-border data flows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The future of work has arrived faster, along with its myriad challenges such as worker vulnerability, income polarisation, more gig work, and the need for workers to adapt to occupational transitions multiplied in potential. This acceleration is the result not only of technological advances and recession, but also of new considerations for health and safety, and economies and labour markets will take time to recover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The quantum of the amplification of these trends and the realities of this crisis have also triggered a reconsideration of several beliefs, with implicit and long-lasting effects on the economy and society and attitudes about efficiency versus resilience, the future of capitalism, densification of economic activity and peoples’ lifestyles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The pandemic has also accelerated some of the key geopolitical trends that will shape our next world order - de-globalisation and nationalism, for instance, along with debilitating China’s hegemony in the supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While the quantitative disruptions in the economy, structured finance and credit facilities are quite explicit, the more permanent changes are perhaps the ones considered from humanitarian perspectives. The most prominent qualities that were on display during this time of distress were the adaptability and versatility of people, which caused the cataclysmic shift of buying patterns to the online medium and helped to keep it afloat while intensifying the focus on the triple bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Over the past two decades, in advancing economies, the onus of security has generally shifted from institutions to individuals. Healthcare systems are being tested and often found wanting, while benefits from paid sick leave to universal basic income are getting reviewed. There is potential for a long-term shift in how institutions offer support, through safety nets, and a more inclusive social contract.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;History bears witness that choices made during crises can shape the world for decades to come. What remains critical is the need for collective action to build economies that deliver inclusive economic growth, prosperity, and safety for all.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Maanya Oberoi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The history of the world economy demonstrates a trend of economic shocks emerging in every generation. The World Health Organisation (WHO) declared COVID-19 as a global pandemic on March 11, 2020; and since then, almost every human endeavour has been disrupted.&amp;nbsp; The impact on the global economy is particularly worrying. We witnessed global supply chains being severely disrupted and strained, financial markets unsettled, resulting in a cross-border economic disaster. Border closures and lockdowns shattered the core sustaining pillars of modern world economies, with the economic shock due to these measures still being weighed across the globe. The ramifications of these disruptions are more far-reaching than anticipated, and the legacies of COVID-19 will shape global growth for years to come. Even though economies are recovering at different paces throughout the world, the world economy is well on the way to recovery from a slump the likes of which none of its 7.7 billion inhabitants has seen in their lifetimes. The new paradigms enforced in the COVID-19 era have led to an unprecedented acceleration in automation and digitisation of operations whilst highlighting the importance of upskilling the workforce. Turbulent labour markets provide additional challenges to professionals as the pace of technology adoption remains unabated while automation, in tandem with the COVID-19 recession, is creating a 'double-disruption' scenario for the labour force. There is more inequality between and within countries, and governments are playing a larger role in the lives of citizens. Looking at historical precedents, the World Economic Forum postulates that the pandemic is about three times as bad as the global financial crisis of 2008 in terms of GDP decline on an annual basis. Economists surmise that adopting a circular economy would be the best way for the world's economy to recover, whilst enabling the transition to an essentially low-carbon economy. The pandemic also catalysed the rise of the digital economy, with the influx of digital behaviour such as remote working and learning, telemedicine, and delivery services. Due to this rapid digitisation, other structural changes can also be anticipated, including regionalisation of supply chains and a further explosion of cross-border data flows. The future of work has arrived faster, along with its myriad challenges such as worker vulnerability, income polarisation, more gig work, and the need for workers to adapt to occupational transitions multiplied in potential. This acceleration is the result not only of technological advances and recession, but also of new considerations for health and safety, and economies and labour markets will take time to recover. The quantum of the amplification of these trends and the realities of this crisis have also triggered a reconsideration of several beliefs, with implicit and long-lasting effects on the economy and society and attitudes about efficiency versus resilience, the future of capitalism, densification of economic activity and peoples’ lifestyles. The pandemic has also accelerated some of the key geopolitical trends that will shape our next world order - de-globalisation and nationalism, for instance, along with debilitating China’s hegemony in the supply chain. While the quantitative disruptions in the economy, structured finance and credit facilities are quite explicit, the more permanent changes are perhaps the ones considered from humanitarian perspectives. The most prominent qualities that were on display during this time of distress were the adaptability and versatility of people, which caused the cataclysmic shift of buying patterns to the online medium and helped to keep it afloat while intensifying the focus on the triple bottom line. Over the past two decades, in advancing economies, the onus of security has generally shifted from institutions to individuals. Healthcare systems are being tested and often found wanting, while benefits from paid sick leave to universal basic income are getting reviewed. There is potential for a long-term shift in how institutions offer support, through safety nets, and a more inclusive social contract. History bears witness that choices made during crises can shape the world for decades to come. What remains critical is the need for collective action to build economies that deliver inclusive economic growth, prosperity, and safety for all.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Digital Yuan: The Start of the End for the US Dollar?</title>
      <link href="/Digital-Yuan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Digital Yuan: The Start of the End for the US Dollar?" />
      <published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Digital-Yuan</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Digital-Yuan">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Crypto currency mania has gripped the world, as increasing acceptance of blockchain technology by major financial institutions has propelled the likes of Bitcoin into the mainstream. Whether you believe in crypto or not, the emergence of crypto currencies threatens to usurp fiat money. The Chinese government has identified the threat early, and has taken significant steps to ensure they have a meaningful head start on digitising their commercial sector and money supply. China’s long anticipated and recently released digital Yuan threatens to undermine the US dollar’s (USD) supremacy as we know it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;China’s digital Yuan project is the first of its kind for any major global economy. It is a version of normal Chinese currency, deployed on a blockchain; the highly encrypted and secure online ledger technology that underpins digital coins like Bitcoin and Ethereum. The People’s Bank of China (PBOC) has led work on the digital Yuan project, which is classified as a central bank digital currency (CBDC) that aims to replace some of the cash in circulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;China has been trialling the digital currency since late 2020, and in 11 different regions since April, including in major cities such as Suzhou and Shenzhen, where the digital Yuan has been used for transport, food and retail. The digital Yuan bypasses the need for central banks in transaction processes, eliminating service fees and speeding up transaction times. China has plans for international use of the digital Yuan by 2024 or 2025, and has already established partnerships with the UAE, Hong Kong, and Thailand to promote international use of CBDCs. Given the vast extent of China’s bilateral trade relations globally, and the increasing likelihood of China overtaking the US as the world's largest economy, the internalisation of the digital Yuan is seeming inevitable.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decline of the Dollar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The emergence of the digital Yuan coincides with a difficult period for the US dollar. The US dollar has become increasingly fragile of late, perhaps mirroring America’s decline within the international system, with its status as the ultimate reserve currency looking increasingly likely to be challenged in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The US dollar has seen a steady fall since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic. It is down about 10-12% relative to America’s major trading partners. Some have even suggested that the dollar will decline in value by 35% by the end of 2021. Ongoing political instability in the US has had a detrimental effect on global trust in the US dollar. The debasing of the US dollar through massive US government debt and central bank stimulus raises the question of the dollar’s long-term viability as the ultimate reserve currency.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To demonstrate this effect, we can look at the declining market of the US-China bilateral trade. The US imports from China dropped by $87.3 billion in 2019 from 2018, and continue to drop annually. The Chinese need for the US dollar is declining. The use of the US dollar in China-Russia transactions has declined from 90% in 2015 to less than 50% in the first quarter of 2020. At a rate of 10% annual decline, it will not be long before the US dollar is no longer used at all in China’s transactions. This vacuum left by the USD will allow for the growth of other currencies such as the digital Yuan. As more countries decide not to use the US dollar, the use of alternative currency reserves will increase. Given China’s extensive trade relations, the digital Yuan is well positioned to take over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;China not Attempting to Replace USD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While it appears that the US dollar and digital Yuan are moving in opposite directions, Chinese officials have claimed that the development of the digital Yuan is not intended to ‘replace the USD’ as the ultimate reserve currency. Deputy governor of the PBOC Li Bo claimed that “efforts to create the digital Yuan are aimed at domestic use,” while Governor of the PBOC, Zhou Xiachuan, echoed that Beijing is not aiming to immediately take on the USD as a currency reserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Regardless of China’s intentions for the digital Yuan, the reality is that the growth of the new digital currency will likely further contribute to the weakening and destabilisation of the USD. Much like when China developed paper currency in the 7th century during the Tang dynasty, China is today leading the way in a key transitional phase of the global financial system. The CBDC space certainly has potential to be a key battleground in the larger US-China struggle for global hegemony. Perhaps it is time for the US central bank to explore the implementation of a CBDC project more urgently. Should they fail to do so, there is a pressing possibility for the USD to get left behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;-Noam Konyn&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Noam Konyn is a graduate of the University of Bristol. He is currently pursuing an MA Government Specialisation in diplomacy and conflict at Interdisciplinary Centre Herzliya, Israel. He has previously worked in Elminda, a brain health medical device company in Tel Aviv, Israel.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Guest</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Crypto currency mania has gripped the world, as increasing acceptance of blockchain technology by major financial institutions has propelled the likes of Bitcoin into the mainstream. Whether you believe in crypto or not, the emergence of crypto currencies threatens to usurp fiat money. The Chinese government has identified the threat early, and has taken significant steps to ensure they have a meaningful head start on digitising their commercial sector and money supply. China’s long anticipated and recently released digital Yuan threatens to undermine the US dollar’s (USD) supremacy as we know it. China’s digital Yuan project is the first of its kind for any major global economy. It is a version of normal Chinese currency, deployed on a blockchain; the highly encrypted and secure online ledger technology that underpins digital coins like Bitcoin and Ethereum. The People’s Bank of China (PBOC) has led work on the digital Yuan project, which is classified as a central bank digital currency (CBDC) that aims to replace some of the cash in circulation. China has been trialling the digital currency since late 2020, and in 11 different regions since April, including in major cities such as Suzhou and Shenzhen, where the digital Yuan has been used for transport, food and retail. The digital Yuan bypasses the need for central banks in transaction processes, eliminating service fees and speeding up transaction times. China has plans for international use of the digital Yuan by 2024 or 2025, and has already established partnerships with the UAE, Hong Kong, and Thailand to promote international use of CBDCs. Given the vast extent of China’s bilateral trade relations globally, and the increasing likelihood of China overtaking the US as the world's largest economy, the internalisation of the digital Yuan is seeming inevitable.&amp;nbsp; Decline of the Dollar The emergence of the digital Yuan coincides with a difficult period for the US dollar. The US dollar has become increasingly fragile of late, perhaps mirroring America’s decline within the international system, with its status as the ultimate reserve currency looking increasingly likely to be challenged in the long term. The US dollar has seen a steady fall since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic. It is down about 10-12% relative to America’s major trading partners. Some have even suggested that the dollar will decline in value by 35% by the end of 2021. Ongoing political instability in the US has had a detrimental effect on global trust in the US dollar. The debasing of the US dollar through massive US government debt and central bank stimulus raises the question of the dollar’s long-term viability as the ultimate reserve currency.&amp;nbsp; To demonstrate this effect, we can look at the declining market of the US-China bilateral trade. The US imports from China dropped by $87.3 billion in 2019 from 2018, and continue to drop annually. The Chinese need for the US dollar is declining. The use of the US dollar in China-Russia transactions has declined from 90% in 2015 to less than 50% in the first quarter of 2020. At a rate of 10% annual decline, it will not be long before the US dollar is no longer used at all in China’s transactions. This vacuum left by the USD will allow for the growth of other currencies such as the digital Yuan. As more countries decide not to use the US dollar, the use of alternative currency reserves will increase. Given China’s extensive trade relations, the digital Yuan is well positioned to take over. China not Attempting to Replace USD While it appears that the US dollar and digital Yuan are moving in opposite directions, Chinese officials have claimed that the development of the digital Yuan is not intended to ‘replace the USD’ as the ultimate reserve currency. Deputy governor of the PBOC Li Bo claimed that “efforts to create the digital Yuan are aimed at domestic use,” while Governor of the PBOC, Zhou Xiachuan, echoed that Beijing is not aiming to immediately take on the USD as a currency reserve. Regardless of China’s intentions for the digital Yuan, the reality is that the growth of the new digital currency will likely further contribute to the weakening and destabilisation of the USD. Much like when China developed paper currency in the 7th century during the Tang dynasty, China is today leading the way in a key transitional phase of the global financial system. The CBDC space certainly has potential to be a key battleground in the larger US-China struggle for global hegemony. Perhaps it is time for the US central bank to explore the implementation of a CBDC project more urgently. Should they fail to do so, there is a pressing possibility for the USD to get left behind. -Noam Konyn Noam Konyn is a graduate of the University of Bristol. He is currently pursuing an MA Government Specialisation in diplomacy and conflict at Interdisciplinary Centre Herzliya, Israel. He has previously worked in Elminda, a brain health medical device company in Tel Aviv, Israel.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Indian Pharma Industry: Present and Future</title>
      <link href="/The-Indian-Pharma-Industry" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Indian Pharma Industry: Present and Future" />
      <published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-05-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Indian-Pharma-Industry</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Indian-Pharma-Industry">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;On March 11, 2020, the World Health Organisation (WHO) declared the coronavirus, SARS-CoV-2 to be a pandemic. More than a year after the outbreak, over three million people have lost their lives with approximately 152 million cases across the globe. The pandemic has managed to cause a complete upheaval in people’s lifestyle along with businesses running losses and workers losing their jobs. Amidst this scenario, it is the pharmaceutical industry that has taken centre stage in the fight against this menace, assisting world governments in fulfilling their population's needs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The global pharmaceutical industry in 2019 achieved a market value of approximately $1,217 billion with a compound annual growth rate of 6.7%. This value is expected to decline to $1,209 billion in 2020 owing to the COVID-19 outbreak.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The pharmaceutical (or pharma) industry can be defined as a “&lt;em&gt;complex system of processes, operations, and organisations involved in the discovery, development, and manufacturing of drugs&lt;/em&gt;”. Firms functioning in the industry are responsible for research and development (R&amp;amp;D) activities, development and manufacturing of active pharmaceutical ingredients and manufacturing of drugs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In 2019, Germany occupied the top position in the pharma industry with a 14.5% share in the export of drugs and medicines. It was followed by Switzerland and Netherlands with a share of 12.2% and 7.9% respectively. Among other countries, Denmark, Netherlands and Italy are the fastest growing exporters of drugs and medicines since 2015. However, three countries have witnessed a decline in the exported drugs and medicines sales in the last five years. These are, namely, the United Kingdom (26.7%), Ireland (18.9%) and the United States (6.1%).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In recent years, growth patterns in developed economies have observed a flat trend which has induced firms to shift their focus to emerging markets, thus finding new sources of revenue and profitability. The same has been witnessed for the pharmaceutical industry. The pharmaceutical emerging markets, or 'pharmerging' markets hold the potential of an extraordinary growth story.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In 2016, emerging markets accounted for over 30% of the development in pharma markets. This shift has been attributed to the economic and demographic development in these economies with a rise in health expectancy, access to healthcare services and improved funding for the healthcare sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another major factor is the sharp decline in firms’ revenue as a result of the expiration of patents. This is known as the patent cliff, which is now affecting several branded drugs that have been in the market for years. The shift towards the use of generic drugs worldwide, increasing availability of biosimilar drugs, a significant differential in manufacturing costs and prices, and change in disease patterns in emerging countries are some of the other major reasons for the shift being observed in the pharmaceutical industry. These factors have induced the emerging economies into becoming the key drivers of the global pharmaceutical market.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Among the emerging markets, five countries namely China, Brazil, Russia, India and South Africa are the ones in domination with their role becoming increasingly important in the coming decade.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pharmaceutical Industry in India&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the last fifty years, India’s pharmaceutical industry has grown by leaps and bounds. From having a 5% share of the total medicine consumption in India in 1969, Indian pharma holds an 85% share of the same in 2020. Today, India is not only able to meet its domestic needs but has also established itself as a leader in the global pharma landscape and is known as the ‘pharmacy of the world’. The industry today is recognised for the quality and cost-effectiveness of its products. Widely known as the ‘archetype of affordable healthcare’, the Indian industry has had a significant contribution towards the improvement of public health outcomes, both within India and across the globe.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;With a market size of $41 billion in 2018-19 and a market growth rate of 10-12%, the Indian pharma industry exported $16.3 billion worth of bulk drugs, intermediates, drug formulations, herbal products, surgical equipment and other goods in 2019-20. Particularly, the industry contributes more than 20% by volume to the global generics market and 62% of the global demand for vaccines. Fourteenth largest in the world in terms of value and 3rd largest in terms of volume, the industry is expected to grow to $100 billion by 2025.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Within India, the industry plays an important role in India’s economic growth and is recognised as one of the top sectors attracting foreign direct investment (FDI) and reducing the trade deficit. The sector attracted a total of $16.54 billion worth of FDI inflow between April 2000 and June 2020. The sector’s importance is further underlined due to the amount of trade surplus generated with exports accounting for $20.7 billion and imports at $2.31 billion in the year 2020. The industry generates employment for over 2.7 million people, directly or indirectly.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COVID-19 and Opportunity for India in Post-Pandemic World&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The outbreak of the virus has challenged healthcare systems around the globe. From the United States, a country that undertakes the highest expenditure on its healthcare system, to the sophisticated European healthcare systems, each country is struggling to contain the spread. Despite the plethora of measures undertaken by countries, the massive inpouring of coronavirus infected patients has exceeded the existing infrastructure and resources in several countries, with the disease causing huge loss of life and human suffering. Additionally, there is a shortage of essential equipment, medicinal supplies and even medicines. The pandemic has also brought forth the existing inequalities in access to healthcare globally.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Amidst these challenges, the global pharmaceutical markets are facing major discontinuities. For instance, there have been concerns regarding global over-dependence on China for active pharmaceutical ingredients (API), particularly in India, the US and Europe. As a result, in the past few months, several countries have been experiencing disruption in the pharma supply chain. The pandemic has also reinforced issues like re-shoring, nearshoring and shortening supply chains.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Indian pharmaceutical industry has been a key contributor in improving the healthcare outcomes in the country with the pandemic presenting several opportunities and challenges for the industry. The growing distrust in China comes as an opportunity for India even so the economy will be facing increased competition from countries like Vietnam and Malaysia.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To utilise the post-pandemic potential to the fullest, the industry has to build on its strength along with taking a giant leap towards innovation. The introduction of new capabilities is necessary to bring efficiencies to facilitate the industry to move up the value chain. A two-fold approach can be adopted to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;First, India needs to explore opportunities in complex generics, biosimilars, vaccines and preventives and other complex products. Having attained leadership in the generic market globally, India now needs to consolidate its position in other markets to move up the value chain. Focusing on complex products for this matter will help to achieve long-term sustained growth for the sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;These complex generics involve a comparatively more difficult production process, face less competition and involve higher margins. Similarly, biosimilars can play an equally important role in expanding India’s pharma sector. Domestically, India is leading in the world when it comes to launching biosimilars, however, only a few Indian companies are able to infiltrate US and European markets due to the non-alignment of India's regulatory guidelines with the regulations in these markets. In addition to the generics market, India has also established itself as a strong contender in the global vaccines market, with the country supplying 60% of the world's vaccine requirements. The step further is thus to develop new and complex vaccines, especially in times like these.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The second approach should be with respect to innovation. India needs to set up an environment conducive to innovation by bringing together academia, pharma companies, entrepreneurs and medical institutions. A look at the global scenario reveals that there is a concentration of research and development activities in the US and Europe, reflecting their dominance in innovation. India also does not compare well with its counterpart China which has twice the number of R&amp;amp;D sites and innovation centres. Therefore, there exists tremendous scope for India to establish itself as a global innovation hub.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In conclusion, the increasing shift of pharmaceutical firms from western economies to emerging economies presents India with a golden opportunity to enhance its pharma production along with emerging as a strong contender in the R&amp;amp;D sector. Even though the pandemic has resulted in innumerable challenges to the economy and the pharma industry in particular, it has also presented the industry with an opportunity to rise to the occasion and establish itself as a leading global player. Whether the country is able to perform on this front remains to be seen!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rajsi Sah</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On March 11, 2020, the World Health Organisation (WHO) declared the coronavirus, SARS-CoV-2 to be a pandemic. More than a year after the outbreak, over three million people have lost their lives with approximately 152 million cases across the globe. The pandemic has managed to cause a complete upheaval in people’s lifestyle along with businesses running losses and workers losing their jobs. Amidst this scenario, it is the pharmaceutical industry that has taken centre stage in the fight against this menace, assisting world governments in fulfilling their population's needs.&amp;nbsp; The global pharmaceutical industry in 2019 achieved a market value of approximately $1,217 billion with a compound annual growth rate of 6.7%. This value is expected to decline to $1,209 billion in 2020 owing to the COVID-19 outbreak.&amp;nbsp; The pharmaceutical (or pharma) industry can be defined as a “complex system of processes, operations, and organisations involved in the discovery, development, and manufacturing of drugs”. Firms functioning in the industry are responsible for research and development (R&amp;amp;D) activities, development and manufacturing of active pharmaceutical ingredients and manufacturing of drugs.&amp;nbsp; In 2019, Germany occupied the top position in the pharma industry with a 14.5% share in the export of drugs and medicines. It was followed by Switzerland and Netherlands with a share of 12.2% and 7.9% respectively. Among other countries, Denmark, Netherlands and Italy are the fastest growing exporters of drugs and medicines since 2015. However, three countries have witnessed a decline in the exported drugs and medicines sales in the last five years. These are, namely, the United Kingdom (26.7%), Ireland (18.9%) and the United States (6.1%).&amp;nbsp; In recent years, growth patterns in developed economies have observed a flat trend which has induced firms to shift their focus to emerging markets, thus finding new sources of revenue and profitability. The same has been witnessed for the pharmaceutical industry. The pharmaceutical emerging markets, or 'pharmerging' markets hold the potential of an extraordinary growth story.&amp;nbsp; In 2016, emerging markets accounted for over 30% of the development in pharma markets. This shift has been attributed to the economic and demographic development in these economies with a rise in health expectancy, access to healthcare services and improved funding for the healthcare sector.&amp;nbsp; Another major factor is the sharp decline in firms’ revenue as a result of the expiration of patents. This is known as the patent cliff, which is now affecting several branded drugs that have been in the market for years. The shift towards the use of generic drugs worldwide, increasing availability of biosimilar drugs, a significant differential in manufacturing costs and prices, and change in disease patterns in emerging countries are some of the other major reasons for the shift being observed in the pharmaceutical industry. These factors have induced the emerging economies into becoming the key drivers of the global pharmaceutical market.&amp;nbsp; Among the emerging markets, five countries namely China, Brazil, Russia, India and South Africa are the ones in domination with their role becoming increasingly important in the coming decade.&amp;nbsp; Pharmaceutical Industry in India In the last fifty years, India’s pharmaceutical industry has grown by leaps and bounds. From having a 5% share of the total medicine consumption in India in 1969, Indian pharma holds an 85% share of the same in 2020. Today, India is not only able to meet its domestic needs but has also established itself as a leader in the global pharma landscape and is known as the ‘pharmacy of the world’. The industry today is recognised for the quality and cost-effectiveness of its products. Widely known as the ‘archetype of affordable healthcare’, the Indian industry has had a significant contribution towards the improvement of public health outcomes, both within India and across the globe.&amp;nbsp; With a market size of $41 billion in 2018-19 and a market growth rate of 10-12%, the Indian pharma industry exported $16.3 billion worth of bulk drugs, intermediates, drug formulations, herbal products, surgical equipment and other goods in 2019-20. Particularly, the industry contributes more than 20% by volume to the global generics market and 62% of the global demand for vaccines. Fourteenth largest in the world in terms of value and 3rd largest in terms of volume, the industry is expected to grow to $100 billion by 2025.&amp;nbsp; Within India, the industry plays an important role in India’s economic growth and is recognised as one of the top sectors attracting foreign direct investment (FDI) and reducing the trade deficit. The sector attracted a total of $16.54 billion worth of FDI inflow between April 2000 and June 2020. The sector’s importance is further underlined due to the amount of trade surplus generated with exports accounting for $20.7 billion and imports at $2.31 billion in the year 2020. The industry generates employment for over 2.7 million people, directly or indirectly.&amp;nbsp; COVID-19 and Opportunity for India in Post-Pandemic World The outbreak of the virus has challenged healthcare systems around the globe. From the United States, a country that undertakes the highest expenditure on its healthcare system, to the sophisticated European healthcare systems, each country is struggling to contain the spread. Despite the plethora of measures undertaken by countries, the massive inpouring of coronavirus infected patients has exceeded the existing infrastructure and resources in several countries, with the disease causing huge loss of life and human suffering. Additionally, there is a shortage of essential equipment, medicinal supplies and even medicines. The pandemic has also brought forth the existing inequalities in access to healthcare globally.&amp;nbsp; Amidst these challenges, the global pharmaceutical markets are facing major discontinuities. For instance, there have been concerns regarding global over-dependence on China for active pharmaceutical ingredients (API), particularly in India, the US and Europe. As a result, in the past few months, several countries have been experiencing disruption in the pharma supply chain. The pandemic has also reinforced issues like re-shoring, nearshoring and shortening supply chains.&amp;nbsp; The Indian pharmaceutical industry has been a key contributor in improving the healthcare outcomes in the country with the pandemic presenting several opportunities and challenges for the industry. The growing distrust in China comes as an opportunity for India even so the economy will be facing increased competition from countries like Vietnam and Malaysia.&amp;nbsp; To utilise the post-pandemic potential to the fullest, the industry has to build on its strength along with taking a giant leap towards innovation. The introduction of new capabilities is necessary to bring efficiencies to facilitate the industry to move up the value chain. A two-fold approach can be adopted to achieve this. First, India needs to explore opportunities in complex generics, biosimilars, vaccines and preventives and other complex products. Having attained leadership in the generic market globally, India now needs to consolidate its position in other markets to move up the value chain. Focusing on complex products for this matter will help to achieve long-term sustained growth for the sector.&amp;nbsp; These complex generics involve a comparatively more difficult production process, face less competition and involve higher margins. Similarly, biosimilars can play an equally important role in expanding India’s pharma sector. Domestically, India is leading in the world when it comes to launching biosimilars, however, only a few Indian companies are able to infiltrate US and European markets due to the non-alignment of India's regulatory guidelines with the regulations in these markets. In addition to the generics market, India has also established itself as a strong contender in the global vaccines market, with the country supplying 60% of the world's vaccine requirements. The step further is thus to develop new and complex vaccines, especially in times like these.&amp;nbsp; The second approach should be with respect to innovation. India needs to set up an environment conducive to innovation by bringing together academia, pharma companies, entrepreneurs and medical institutions. A look at the global scenario reveals that there is a concentration of research and development activities in the US and Europe, reflecting their dominance in innovation. India also does not compare well with its counterpart China which has twice the number of R&amp;amp;D sites and innovation centres. Therefore, there exists tremendous scope for India to establish itself as a global innovation hub.&amp;nbsp; In conclusion, the increasing shift of pharmaceutical firms from western economies to emerging economies presents India with a golden opportunity to enhance its pharma production along with emerging as a strong contender in the R&amp;amp;D sector. Even though the pandemic has resulted in innumerable challenges to the economy and the pharma industry in particular, it has also presented the industry with an opportunity to rise to the occasion and establish itself as a leading global player. Whether the country is able to perform on this front remains to be seen!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Medical Tourism: An Oar to the Indian Economy</title>
      <link href="/Medical-Tourism-An-Oar-to-the-Indian-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Medical Tourism: An Oar to the Indian Economy" />
      <published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Medical-Tourism-An-Oar-to-the-Indian-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Medical-Tourism-An-Oar-to-the-Indian-Economy">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Tourism is an important and rapidly growing industry of the Indian economy. This industry contributes to around 8-9% of India’s total GDP and creates millions of employment opportunities. Being home to various cultures, our country attracts tourists throughout the year. With an efficient and well-established infrastructure in terms of communication, transportation and a tourist-friendly visa policy, the number of tourists has seen a growth with each passing year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Apart from this, medical tourism has witnessed considerable growth and success in the Indian economy. Indian medical tourism sector is estimated to be worth 3 billion US dollars and is growing at a speedy rate with each passing year. The top ten source countries contributing to India’s medical tourism include Bangladesh, Afghanistan, Iraq, Maldives, Oman, Yemen, Uzbekistan, Kenya, Nigeria and Tanzania.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Apart from Chennai, Mumbai and Delhi, various other cities have seen an increase in the number of patients from various countries. Medical tourism in India is largely promoted by the government and fueled by the corporate boom in medical care. There are a number of reasons contributing to this industry, the two major reasons being affordability and accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What seeds medical tourism?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Globalisation brings with it a plethora of opportunities for consumers to choose from and for countries to expand their scope of development. Apart from evolution, it also provides an opportunity for countries to collaborate their resources and provide the best in terms of education and health to the citizens of the world. One such brilliant example is India’s efficient medical facilities that are made available to the citizens at an affordable price.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India offers a complete posy of healthcare facilities available at an affordable and attractive price which is less than 40% than any developed western country without any compromise on the quality and care. Adding to this the travel, accommodation and insurance are also made available at a very reasonable rate.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While the cost of living in India is 66.54% lower than in the USA and the rent in India is 85% lower than in the USA which is another major reason why people fly to India for treatments that require staying at the place of treatment for a long period of time. People across the globe consider themselves as global citizens, thus ensure exploring the best opportunities across the world and India’s personalised touch of care in the form of Atithi-Devo-Bhava plays a crucial role in the recent growth of medical tourism in the country.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The accessibility and comfort are also the reasons why India is favourable for treatments and attracts patients from across the globe. To begin with, the medical visa norms of the country are very simplified and easy to gain access to, this ensures hassle-free travel, treatment and stay for the patient as well as the attendant.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The medical visa assures multiple entries and longer stays, the recent development of e-medical visa that was launched by the Union Government has been viewed as a key element in boosting medical tourism in India. Alongside, India is home to multiple cuisines and offers organically prepared food that speeds up the process of getting healthier also attracts people for getting treated with the least disturbance to their comfort zone. India also ensures no language barrier as it is claimed to be the second-largest English speaking country in the world. Lean or no waiting for surgeries as compared to long waiting for even simple surgeries in the western countries also pegs the way for tourists visiting India for medicinal purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India has always been a hub of genius brains that can excel in all the fields. Technology and medicine have been going hand-in-hand lately. India has shown the fastest adoption of recent medical technology when compared to its developing counterparts. With more than 500 accredited healthcare providers, India offers a variety of options at different locations in the country to choose from as per the visitor’s convenience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Indian doctors, medicinal research, treatment and technology has been found to be at par with the western standard so much so that over 12% of doctors practising in the UK and US are from India. Staffed by expert professional and healthcare providers who are efficient in the use of the latest methods of treatments using the required technology along with modern infrastructure boosts the number of visitors each year that visit the diverse nation for medical treatment.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the Home Front&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The metropolitan cities continue to be the top listers when asked for the preferred city for treatment. To begin with, Chennai is known as the medical capital of the country as it attracts 40% of medical tourists annually for its high-quality treatment and world-class natural medicinal treatments. It attracts patients seeking bone marrow transplant, cardiac bypass, eye surgery, hip replacement and alternative treatments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Next in line is Mumbai, the business capital of India is also a hub of commendable medical facilities housed inside efficient infrastructure with numerous super-speciality hospitals, Research and Diagnostic Centre for Orthopaedic and weight-loss surgeries. Mumbai attracts a large number of patients seeking cosmetic surgery and Ayurveda treatment. Coming up next is the National Capital Territory of Delhi, it is home to several well-equipped private hospitals that offer special packages to foreign patients for general surgeries, eye surgery, heart care and neuro-surgeries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The upward trend in medical tourism is a piece of good news for the domestic citizens as well. With more and more people travelling to India for medical benefits it speeds up the pace of infrastructural development in the health sector. The development is not limited to building better hospitals that are equipped with the latest technology and staffing healthcare professional that are well versed with the most efficient treatments, or preparing medical students that can give birth to unique treatments with their genius but also providing these world-class to its very own citizens in their own country at the best price possible.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with healthcare facilities, medical tourism plays a key role in keeping the hospitality industry running and enhancing its presence in the world. The advent of the novel coronavirus and India’s excellent plan to control the mass damage has fetched it another brownie point for the citizens to trust the Indian healthcare system. Our effective vaccination drive, which is inaugurated by bringing into use the vaccines made at home (India) and the Prime Minister’s drive to help other nations in need is a commendable combination of the personal touch added to the treatment, &lt;em&gt;atithi-devo-bhava &lt;/em&gt;(guest is equivalent to God), our history of extending arms in times of crisis and most importantly, the genius brain of our scientists and doctors!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Tourism is an important and rapidly growing industry of the Indian economy. This industry contributes to around 8-9% of India’s total GDP and creates millions of employment opportunities. Being home to various cultures, our country attracts tourists throughout the year. With an efficient and well-established infrastructure in terms of communication, transportation and a tourist-friendly visa policy, the number of tourists has seen a growth with each passing year.&amp;nbsp; Apart from this, medical tourism has witnessed considerable growth and success in the Indian economy. Indian medical tourism sector is estimated to be worth 3 billion US dollars and is growing at a speedy rate with each passing year. The top ten source countries contributing to India’s medical tourism include Bangladesh, Afghanistan, Iraq, Maldives, Oman, Yemen, Uzbekistan, Kenya, Nigeria and Tanzania.&amp;nbsp; Apart from Chennai, Mumbai and Delhi, various other cities have seen an increase in the number of patients from various countries. Medical tourism in India is largely promoted by the government and fueled by the corporate boom in medical care. There are a number of reasons contributing to this industry, the two major reasons being affordability and accessibility. What seeds medical tourism? Globalisation brings with it a plethora of opportunities for consumers to choose from and for countries to expand their scope of development. Apart from evolution, it also provides an opportunity for countries to collaborate their resources and provide the best in terms of education and health to the citizens of the world. One such brilliant example is India’s efficient medical facilities that are made available to the citizens at an affordable price.&amp;nbsp; India offers a complete posy of healthcare facilities available at an affordable and attractive price which is less than 40% than any developed western country without any compromise on the quality and care. Adding to this the travel, accommodation and insurance are also made available at a very reasonable rate.&amp;nbsp; While the cost of living in India is 66.54% lower than in the USA and the rent in India is 85% lower than in the USA which is another major reason why people fly to India for treatments that require staying at the place of treatment for a long period of time. People across the globe consider themselves as global citizens, thus ensure exploring the best opportunities across the world and India’s personalised touch of care in the form of Atithi-Devo-Bhava plays a crucial role in the recent growth of medical tourism in the country.&amp;nbsp; The accessibility and comfort are also the reasons why India is favourable for treatments and attracts patients from across the globe. To begin with, the medical visa norms of the country are very simplified and easy to gain access to, this ensures hassle-free travel, treatment and stay for the patient as well as the attendant.&amp;nbsp; The medical visa assures multiple entries and longer stays, the recent development of e-medical visa that was launched by the Union Government has been viewed as a key element in boosting medical tourism in India. Alongside, India is home to multiple cuisines and offers organically prepared food that speeds up the process of getting healthier also attracts people for getting treated with the least disturbance to their comfort zone. India also ensures no language barrier as it is claimed to be the second-largest English speaking country in the world. Lean or no waiting for surgeries as compared to long waiting for even simple surgeries in the western countries also pegs the way for tourists visiting India for medicinal purposes. India has always been a hub of genius brains that can excel in all the fields. Technology and medicine have been going hand-in-hand lately. India has shown the fastest adoption of recent medical technology when compared to its developing counterparts. With more than 500 accredited healthcare providers, India offers a variety of options at different locations in the country to choose from as per the visitor’s convenience.&amp;nbsp; Indian doctors, medicinal research, treatment and technology has been found to be at par with the western standard so much so that over 12% of doctors practising in the UK and US are from India. Staffed by expert professional and healthcare providers who are efficient in the use of the latest methods of treatments using the required technology along with modern infrastructure boosts the number of visitors each year that visit the diverse nation for medical treatment.&amp;nbsp; On the Home Front The metropolitan cities continue to be the top listers when asked for the preferred city for treatment. To begin with, Chennai is known as the medical capital of the country as it attracts 40% of medical tourists annually for its high-quality treatment and world-class natural medicinal treatments. It attracts patients seeking bone marrow transplant, cardiac bypass, eye surgery, hip replacement and alternative treatments.&amp;nbsp; Next in line is Mumbai, the business capital of India is also a hub of commendable medical facilities housed inside efficient infrastructure with numerous super-speciality hospitals, Research and Diagnostic Centre for Orthopaedic and weight-loss surgeries. Mumbai attracts a large number of patients seeking cosmetic surgery and Ayurveda treatment. Coming up next is the National Capital Territory of Delhi, it is home to several well-equipped private hospitals that offer special packages to foreign patients for general surgeries, eye surgery, heart care and neuro-surgeries.&amp;nbsp; The upward trend in medical tourism is a piece of good news for the domestic citizens as well. With more and more people travelling to India for medical benefits it speeds up the pace of infrastructural development in the health sector. The development is not limited to building better hospitals that are equipped with the latest technology and staffing healthcare professional that are well versed with the most efficient treatments, or preparing medical students that can give birth to unique treatments with their genius but also providing these world-class to its very own citizens in their own country at the best price possible.&amp;nbsp; Along with healthcare facilities, medical tourism plays a key role in keeping the hospitality industry running and enhancing its presence in the world. The advent of the novel coronavirus and India’s excellent plan to control the mass damage has fetched it another brownie point for the citizens to trust the Indian healthcare system. Our effective vaccination drive, which is inaugurated by bringing into use the vaccines made at home (India) and the Prime Minister’s drive to help other nations in need is a commendable combination of the personal touch added to the treatment, atithi-devo-bhava (guest is equivalent to God), our history of extending arms in times of crisis and most importantly, the genius brain of our scientists and doctors!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Sinews of an Industrialised Economy</title>
      <link href="/The-Sinews-of-an-Industrialised-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Sinews of an Industrialised Economy" />
      <published>2021-04-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-04-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Sinews-of-an-Industrialised-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Sinews-of-an-Industrialised-Economy">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The industrial sector, manufacturing, in particular, plays an important role in transforming a country from a low-income one, with agriculture dominating the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) composition, to a high-income, services-oriented country. The industrialisation of a country is a crucial phase in this transformation. Industrialisation is not only about a country becoming a manufacturing hub. There is a huge societal transformation that accompanies such industrialisation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Though the process of industrialisation is disruptive, it results in an increase in the income of the people. People become more refined in their behaviour, and education becomes a top priority in industrial society. Thus giving top priority to human investment. The state gains a monopoly over violence, the institutions of the state become more competent, and many other changes are observed. But the initiation of the process of industrialisation begins with the sectoral composition of the GDP moving from agriculture to industry, along with a similar shift in employment patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The transition from agriculture to an industrial economy is an important transformation that places a country on a high growth path. There is a tranche of changes that occur in different domains that facilitate a country in kick-starting its progression into a developed country.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;First, emerging as an industrial society increases the income of the people. There will be a guaranteed income flow for the average person in the society, unlike an agrarian economy where there is too much uncertainty in income generation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Second, with large scale migrations from rural to urban areas, whole new sectors emerge on the stage (e.g. daycare centres, dog walkers etc.) and the demand in the economy as a whole goes up.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Third, as people become more urban there is a deep social change that occurs, a change for good; this includes an increase in women's participation in the labour force, women becoming more independent and having a say in many things. Industrialisation can also be a factor that eases out the population pressure on society. Industrialisation also paves the way for education to become a major aspect in society. People hitherto employing their children on fields will send their kids to school because their income will suffice to support the family without the children having to work in the fields. But in all this, it is important to remember that industrialisation is a very disruptive activity. It, therefore, demands a strong state with strong enforcement mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The initial stages of industrialisation are, however, characterised by a population that has had only the experiences of a pre-industrial society. Literacy levels are generally low, most people are uneducated. This is where manufacturing comes into the picture. Manufacturing has the potential to absorb a large pool of labour. This is because of its fundamental characteristic of being dependent on labour for various reasons, despite the onset of technology.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;An increase in manufacturing also leads to a division of labour which increases mamifold the productivity of all sectors. To encourage manufacturing, however, there are a set of factors that need to be set in place. To discuss the factors that have to be put in place we may take the example of India, a textbook example of a country in the midst of the transformation from an agrarian society to an industrial one.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;First, India has reformed its archaic labour laws, which are a nightmare to anyone starting an industry. While regulation is desirable anytime, Indian labour laws are a case of over-regulation and need reform.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Second, India has to bring about land reforms. The Land Acquisition Bill, which was introduced in the Indian Parliament in 2014, was withdrawn due to a lack of political will. It is high time now that India passes that bill and makes land acquisitions easier.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, a consistent effort must be made to transition from an agricultural economy to an industrial economy. For this, a two-fold approach may be recommended. The Indian government should take all necessary steps to encourage industry, especially manufacturing; at the same time, it must improve the urban facilities of the country so as to accommodate the migration that occurs in the process of urbanisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the context of transforming India into an industrial economy, looking at China may offer some lessons. China began its reform process with agriculture by moving from the commune-based system to the household responsibility system, and by revising agricultural prices upwards by more than 20%, the results were for everyone to see. The agricultural growth rate jumped to 7.1% per annum during 1978-84, up from 2.5% during the pre-reform period of 1966-1977. This was followed by a dramatic reduction of poverty from 33% to 15% in the reform period between 1978 and 1984. Farm income in China grew by almost 14% per annum. It is high growth in farm incomes that boosted demand for manufacturing goods produced by town and village enterprises, kick-starting the manufacturing revolution in China.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In this context, Indian farm reforms are a welcome first step; though, a lot more could be done. India also has the necessary requirements in place. For instance, the Make in India scheme encourages the setting up of industries in India. It is imperative to back it up with other necessary steps. Initiatives like Skill India can be used for this purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Today, the Indian industry is complaining that rural demand is collapsing. One reason for that is the consistent reduction in rural population in India since the 1991 economic reforms. Another reason for this outcome is that India never had any major reforms with respect to its labour laws, land laws and agriculture laws; and farmers’ incomes have remained very low. However, it is also important to note that industry is not a substitute for agriculture, rather they are complementary to one another. Both these sectors are so intertwined that it is not possible to increase the growth of one sector without the improvement of the other sector. Industrialisation is also important to increase farm incomes in the country. This is because industrialisation moves people from farms to industries, thus consolidating the land holdings and thereby increasing productivity in the agriculture sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the long term, it is also imperative that India plan to address the issues of education and employment. There is a two-way correlation between industrialisation and education. In education, India seriously lacks skills-based education as the primary focus is always scoring marks rather than problem-solving and skills enhancement. To address this issue the government can partner with the industry to tailor the curriculum to suit the needs of the industry. The focus should shift to develop problem-solving skills. The government can also ask companies to spend their CSR amount on skills development programs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The elasticity of employment generation has been constantly falling and has come down to near zero in the last decade. This shows the grave danger that is in store in regards to job creation. In India, more often than not, entrepreneurs focus on price controls to cut down costs rather than on efficiency. In many cases, producers compete on the basis of price rather than efficiency. This should also change and for that, the government should incentivise firms to focus on efficiency rather than prices. India should act fast to take advantage of the changing scenario on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The economic reforms of 1991 have transformed the lives of the Indian people in many ways. The reforms led to new aspirations among the people, as the expectation was that the Indian economy would grow and India was going to be the next big thing on the world stage. Since the 1991 economic reforms were not adequately followed up, India has witnessed jobless growth for most of the period of its golden economic period of 2003-2008. Despite this, the Indian economy remained among the fastest-growing large economies of the world. Yet, it might appear paradoxical that with respect to achievements in human development, India is ranked at 129 out of 189 countries, according to the human development report 2019.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manufacturing has been the engine of modern economic growth, be it in Britain and the USA of the 19th century or Russia of the 20th century or China of the 21st century. India’s first plans to industrialise go as far back in time as the 1950's. The second Five-Year Plan spoke at lengths about the need for industrialisation and outlined the steps for the same. Unfortunately, India failed to industrialise. The Nehruvian model that the Indian state adopted subsequently proved disastrous for the country. Today, the time frame for India to take off and reap benefits of its demographic dividend is too small. India should act fast. Else, the future might be bleaker than we imagine today.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The industrial sector, manufacturing, in particular, plays an important role in transforming a country from a low-income one, with agriculture dominating the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) composition, to a high-income, services-oriented country. The industrialisation of a country is a crucial phase in this transformation. Industrialisation is not only about a country becoming a manufacturing hub. There is a huge societal transformation that accompanies such industrialisation.&amp;nbsp; Though the process of industrialisation is disruptive, it results in an increase in the income of the people. People become more refined in their behaviour, and education becomes a top priority in industrial society. Thus giving top priority to human investment. The state gains a monopoly over violence, the institutions of the state become more competent, and many other changes are observed. But the initiation of the process of industrialisation begins with the sectoral composition of the GDP moving from agriculture to industry, along with a similar shift in employment patterns. The transition from agriculture to an industrial economy is an important transformation that places a country on a high growth path. There is a tranche of changes that occur in different domains that facilitate a country in kick-starting its progression into a developed country.&amp;nbsp; First, emerging as an industrial society increases the income of the people. There will be a guaranteed income flow for the average person in the society, unlike an agrarian economy where there is too much uncertainty in income generation.&amp;nbsp; Second, with large scale migrations from rural to urban areas, whole new sectors emerge on the stage (e.g. daycare centres, dog walkers etc.) and the demand in the economy as a whole goes up.&amp;nbsp; Third, as people become more urban there is a deep social change that occurs, a change for good; this includes an increase in women's participation in the labour force, women becoming more independent and having a say in many things. Industrialisation can also be a factor that eases out the population pressure on society. Industrialisation also paves the way for education to become a major aspect in society. People hitherto employing their children on fields will send their kids to school because their income will suffice to support the family without the children having to work in the fields. But in all this, it is important to remember that industrialisation is a very disruptive activity. It, therefore, demands a strong state with strong enforcement mechanisms. The initial stages of industrialisation are, however, characterised by a population that has had only the experiences of a pre-industrial society. Literacy levels are generally low, most people are uneducated. This is where manufacturing comes into the picture. Manufacturing has the potential to absorb a large pool of labour. This is because of its fundamental characteristic of being dependent on labour for various reasons, despite the onset of technology.&amp;nbsp; An increase in manufacturing also leads to a division of labour which increases mamifold the productivity of all sectors. To encourage manufacturing, however, there are a set of factors that need to be set in place. To discuss the factors that have to be put in place we may take the example of India, a textbook example of a country in the midst of the transformation from an agrarian society to an industrial one.&amp;nbsp; First, India has reformed its archaic labour laws, which are a nightmare to anyone starting an industry. While regulation is desirable anytime, Indian labour laws are a case of over-regulation and need reform.&amp;nbsp; Second, India has to bring about land reforms. The Land Acquisition Bill, which was introduced in the Indian Parliament in 2014, was withdrawn due to a lack of political will. It is high time now that India passes that bill and makes land acquisitions easier.&amp;nbsp; However, a consistent effort must be made to transition from an agricultural economy to an industrial economy. For this, a two-fold approach may be recommended. The Indian government should take all necessary steps to encourage industry, especially manufacturing; at the same time, it must improve the urban facilities of the country so as to accommodate the migration that occurs in the process of urbanisation. In the context of transforming India into an industrial economy, looking at China may offer some lessons. China began its reform process with agriculture by moving from the commune-based system to the household responsibility system, and by revising agricultural prices upwards by more than 20%, the results were for everyone to see. The agricultural growth rate jumped to 7.1% per annum during 1978-84, up from 2.5% during the pre-reform period of 1966-1977. This was followed by a dramatic reduction of poverty from 33% to 15% in the reform period between 1978 and 1984. Farm income in China grew by almost 14% per annum. It is high growth in farm incomes that boosted demand for manufacturing goods produced by town and village enterprises, kick-starting the manufacturing revolution in China.&amp;nbsp; In this context, Indian farm reforms are a welcome first step; though, a lot more could be done. India also has the necessary requirements in place. For instance, the Make in India scheme encourages the setting up of industries in India. It is imperative to back it up with other necessary steps. Initiatives like Skill India can be used for this purpose. Today, the Indian industry is complaining that rural demand is collapsing. One reason for that is the consistent reduction in rural population in India since the 1991 economic reforms. Another reason for this outcome is that India never had any major reforms with respect to its labour laws, land laws and agriculture laws; and farmers’ incomes have remained very low. However, it is also important to note that industry is not a substitute for agriculture, rather they are complementary to one another. Both these sectors are so intertwined that it is not possible to increase the growth of one sector without the improvement of the other sector. Industrialisation is also important to increase farm incomes in the country. This is because industrialisation moves people from farms to industries, thus consolidating the land holdings and thereby increasing productivity in the agriculture sector. In the long term, it is also imperative that India plan to address the issues of education and employment. There is a two-way correlation between industrialisation and education. In education, India seriously lacks skills-based education as the primary focus is always scoring marks rather than problem-solving and skills enhancement. To address this issue the government can partner with the industry to tailor the curriculum to suit the needs of the industry. The focus should shift to develop problem-solving skills. The government can also ask companies to spend their CSR amount on skills development programs.&amp;nbsp; The elasticity of employment generation has been constantly falling and has come down to near zero in the last decade. This shows the grave danger that is in store in regards to job creation. In India, more often than not, entrepreneurs focus on price controls to cut down costs rather than on efficiency. In many cases, producers compete on the basis of price rather than efficiency. This should also change and for that, the government should incentivise firms to focus on efficiency rather than prices. India should act fast to take advantage of the changing scenario on the world stage. The economic reforms of 1991 have transformed the lives of the Indian people in many ways. The reforms led to new aspirations among the people, as the expectation was that the Indian economy would grow and India was going to be the next big thing on the world stage. Since the 1991 economic reforms were not adequately followed up, India has witnessed jobless growth for most of the period of its golden economic period of 2003-2008. Despite this, the Indian economy remained among the fastest-growing large economies of the world. Yet, it might appear paradoxical that with respect to achievements in human development, India is ranked at 129 out of 189 countries, according to the human development report 2019.&amp;nbsp; Manufacturing has been the engine of modern economic growth, be it in Britain and the USA of the 19th century or Russia of the 20th century or China of the 21st century. India’s first plans to industrialise go as far back in time as the 1950's. The second Five-Year Plan spoke at lengths about the need for industrialisation and outlined the steps for the same. Unfortunately, India failed to industrialise. The Nehruvian model that the Indian state adopted subsequently proved disastrous for the country. Today, the time frame for India to take off and reap benefits of its demographic dividend is too small. India should act fast. Else, the future might be bleaker than we imagine today.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Strike of the Tax Cobra</title>
      <link href="/The-Strike-of-the-Tax-Cobra" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Strike of the Tax Cobra " />
      <published>2021-04-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-04-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Strike-of-the-Tax-Cobra</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Strike-of-the-Tax-Cobra">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There is diametric collinearity between humans and perishable commodities, both of them face an end, that is, both of them die. Ideas, on the other hand, are perennial. Of course with the advent of new ideas, the old ones may become obsolete, but they never die down, they’re there to stay.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A ton of macroeconomic growth theories are based on the foundation of ideas, economists like Solow and Romer are there to testify. One may think that all ideas come in the snap of a finger, like a light bulb over your head, capable of revolutionising, like some sort of a miracle, but that’s obviously not how it works in the real world. Because the real world is a lasagna of problems that exist in multiple layers. And no, they cannot be solved in a snap.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Hence, researchers and experts are perpetually working to give birth to or discover new ideas that help solve a pinch of the problems of this world we live in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Economists too are constantly working with the government to roll out new policies and strategies each consecutive year that make the economy run efficiently and satisfactorily, like a butter knife spreading butter on a slice of bread. Except, policies do not always pan out the way they were expected to. And this isn't where I talk about the policies giving an alternate outcome of what was expected, but the entirely opposite outcome, which worsens the problem at hand.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This brings me to talk about ‘The Cobra Effect’, which in literal terms means a policy or a strategy, made for the greater good, that leafs to certain unforeseen post-implementation consequences that don't just make the policy or strategy redundant, but also backfire well enough to compel the government to not just repeal the said policy/strategy but also make another move in the positive direction, a well-analysed one keeping the after-effects of it in mind.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A simple example to illustrate the idea better could be none other than road safety in India. With the massive population of India and its mortality rate existing in a spectrum of causes, road accidents are a major one. Imagine a handful of sand and then imagine the rate at which it slips out of your clenched fists. That’s the rate at which people riding on two-wheelers and cars face road accidents in India. To prevent this, the government decided to roll out a rule that car drivers would be fined a penalty amount in case they are seen driving without a seatbelt. &lt;em&gt;What did this do?&lt;/em&gt; This made the car drivers wear a seatbelt to prevent incurring the fine, but also made them counter-incentivised to now drive more recklessly thereby increasing their own risk to injury but also passersby’s and pedestrians’ risk to a road accident. Hence, this move didn’t just give an alternate outcome, but a diametrically opposite one to what was expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Digressing a little from the Cobra Effect, let us look at a topic that is very essentially affecting India as we speak, something that is also very politicised and very heavily debated upon across news platforms and social media, the ‘Goods and Services Tax’ or GST - a tax system formulated and applied and amended a total of 950 times, to aid the ease of doing business and to eliminate corruption by levying the tax on the value added to a good at every stage till it reaches the consumer. In a move to reduce costs incurred by producers and retailers by making far-reaching changes in the tax system, GST has surely brought about its own set of concerns, ones that are inherently opposed to its intended outcome.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To understand the negative implications of GST, let's look at a few reasons behind the recent protest by the Indian traders’ associations against it. Although we have been told our entire lives that making mistakes is okay, the same does not hold true when it comes to small businesses making mistakes while filing their returns. It is a huge irony to what some people, playing on the acronym, call it a 'Good and Simple Tax'. With the three categories under GST, namely - Central GST (CGST), State GST (SGST) and Inter-state GST (IGST), the government portal for GST allows no trading firm to review their purchase returns once filed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In multiple instances, firms mistakenly enter the IGST returns under CGST and SGST, or vice versa, and the only mechanism that the government then provides is to either cease your Input Tax Credit (ITC) for that particular transaction by sending a mismatch notice or claim your mistakenly filed returns under “assessment” and not refund the excess amount. This has effected a blow on the export industry who was already badly affected by the e-way bill amendment to GST.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The e-way bill was introduced so goods can be transported inter-state with ease, except the reality is that its the most strenuous process for any business, considering the government’s mandates of filling in all details, including vehicle numbers, specific goods’ names, and so on, on the online portal post. Moreover, a truck carrying a consignment with an expired e-way bill or an erroneous e-way bill is penalised 200% of the tax value.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The space that GST has allowed for natural human errors or even software errors is extremely narrow. What is making things even more difficult for such traders is that the grunt of the glitches in the online GST portal is also faced by these traders, and not the government. This makes it legit for the traders’ body to then claim that GST is begetting &lt;em&gt;'tax terrorism' &lt;/em&gt;in India and giving arbitrary powers to the government.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The worst hit by the entire situation are the ones that GST claimed to make better off, the Small and Medium Enterprises (SME). The cost of purchasing the software and hiring tax professionals, like chartered accountants, has made these firms incur more operational and overhead costs than anticipated. Moreover, since the new rule is that all businesses with a turnover exceeding Rupees 20 lakhs need to pay GST, another rule for the SMEs dictates that business with a turnover of up to ₹7.5 million can opt for the composition scheme and pay only 1% tax on turnover in exchange of GST and enjoy lesser compliances. &lt;em&gt;Sounds like a simple decision, doesn’t it? &lt;/em&gt;Except, it isn’t, since there is the catch to this - the businesses that opt for this will not be able to claim any Input Tax Credit (ITC), hence leaving these SMEs in a dilemma to choose between a deep-sea and a cliff.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;All in all, my view is that GST most definitely has a Cobra Effect on the Indian economy as it fails to fulfil the one thing it promised - good governance and ease of doing business. Of course, there are ways to change that by listening to the genuine demands of traders, entrepreneurs and various other industries and making compliances in a manner that in order to eliminate a few bads, we do not end up destroying the innocents. Because all they have got as humans are their ideas and their perishables.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There is diametric collinearity between humans and perishable commodities, both of them face an end, that is, both of them die. Ideas, on the other hand, are perennial. Of course with the advent of new ideas, the old ones may become obsolete, but they never die down, they’re there to stay.&amp;nbsp; A ton of macroeconomic growth theories are based on the foundation of ideas, economists like Solow and Romer are there to testify. One may think that all ideas come in the snap of a finger, like a light bulb over your head, capable of revolutionising, like some sort of a miracle, but that’s obviously not how it works in the real world. Because the real world is a lasagna of problems that exist in multiple layers. And no, they cannot be solved in a snap.&amp;nbsp; Hence, researchers and experts are perpetually working to give birth to or discover new ideas that help solve a pinch of the problems of this world we live in. Economists too are constantly working with the government to roll out new policies and strategies each consecutive year that make the economy run efficiently and satisfactorily, like a butter knife spreading butter on a slice of bread. Except, policies do not always pan out the way they were expected to. And this isn't where I talk about the policies giving an alternate outcome of what was expected, but the entirely opposite outcome, which worsens the problem at hand.&amp;nbsp; This brings me to talk about ‘The Cobra Effect’, which in literal terms means a policy or a strategy, made for the greater good, that leafs to certain unforeseen post-implementation consequences that don't just make the policy or strategy redundant, but also backfire well enough to compel the government to not just repeal the said policy/strategy but also make another move in the positive direction, a well-analysed one keeping the after-effects of it in mind.&amp;nbsp; A simple example to illustrate the idea better could be none other than road safety in India. With the massive population of India and its mortality rate existing in a spectrum of causes, road accidents are a major one. Imagine a handful of sand and then imagine the rate at which it slips out of your clenched fists. That’s the rate at which people riding on two-wheelers and cars face road accidents in India. To prevent this, the government decided to roll out a rule that car drivers would be fined a penalty amount in case they are seen driving without a seatbelt. What did this do? This made the car drivers wear a seatbelt to prevent incurring the fine, but also made them counter-incentivised to now drive more recklessly thereby increasing their own risk to injury but also passersby’s and pedestrians’ risk to a road accident. Hence, this move didn’t just give an alternate outcome, but a diametrically opposite one to what was expected. Digressing a little from the Cobra Effect, let us look at a topic that is very essentially affecting India as we speak, something that is also very politicised and very heavily debated upon across news platforms and social media, the ‘Goods and Services Tax’ or GST - a tax system formulated and applied and amended a total of 950 times, to aid the ease of doing business and to eliminate corruption by levying the tax on the value added to a good at every stage till it reaches the consumer. In a move to reduce costs incurred by producers and retailers by making far-reaching changes in the tax system, GST has surely brought about its own set of concerns, ones that are inherently opposed to its intended outcome.&amp;nbsp; To understand the negative implications of GST, let's look at a few reasons behind the recent protest by the Indian traders’ associations against it. Although we have been told our entire lives that making mistakes is okay, the same does not hold true when it comes to small businesses making mistakes while filing their returns. It is a huge irony to what some people, playing on the acronym, call it a 'Good and Simple Tax'. With the three categories under GST, namely - Central GST (CGST), State GST (SGST) and Inter-state GST (IGST), the government portal for GST allows no trading firm to review their purchase returns once filed.&amp;nbsp; In multiple instances, firms mistakenly enter the IGST returns under CGST and SGST, or vice versa, and the only mechanism that the government then provides is to either cease your Input Tax Credit (ITC) for that particular transaction by sending a mismatch notice or claim your mistakenly filed returns under “assessment” and not refund the excess amount. This has effected a blow on the export industry who was already badly affected by the e-way bill amendment to GST.&amp;nbsp; The e-way bill was introduced so goods can be transported inter-state with ease, except the reality is that its the most strenuous process for any business, considering the government’s mandates of filling in all details, including vehicle numbers, specific goods’ names, and so on, on the online portal post. Moreover, a truck carrying a consignment with an expired e-way bill or an erroneous e-way bill is penalised 200% of the tax value.&amp;nbsp; The space that GST has allowed for natural human errors or even software errors is extremely narrow. What is making things even more difficult for such traders is that the grunt of the glitches in the online GST portal is also faced by these traders, and not the government. This makes it legit for the traders’ body to then claim that GST is begetting 'tax terrorism' in India and giving arbitrary powers to the government.&amp;nbsp; The worst hit by the entire situation are the ones that GST claimed to make better off, the Small and Medium Enterprises (SME). The cost of purchasing the software and hiring tax professionals, like chartered accountants, has made these firms incur more operational and overhead costs than anticipated. Moreover, since the new rule is that all businesses with a turnover exceeding Rupees 20 lakhs need to pay GST, another rule for the SMEs dictates that business with a turnover of up to ₹7.5 million can opt for the composition scheme and pay only 1% tax on turnover in exchange of GST and enjoy lesser compliances. Sounds like a simple decision, doesn’t it? Except, it isn’t, since there is the catch to this - the businesses that opt for this will not be able to claim any Input Tax Credit (ITC), hence leaving these SMEs in a dilemma to choose between a deep-sea and a cliff.&amp;nbsp; All in all, my view is that GST most definitely has a Cobra Effect on the Indian economy as it fails to fulfil the one thing it promised - good governance and ease of doing business. Of course, there are ways to change that by listening to the genuine demands of traders, entrepreneurs and various other industries and making compliances in a manner that in order to eliminate a few bads, we do not end up destroying the innocents. Because all they have got as humans are their ideas and their perishables.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why India as a Superpower is a Distant Reality Part II</title>
      <link href="/Why-India-as-a-Superpower-is-a-Distant-Reality-Part-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why India as a Superpower is a Distant Reality Part II" />
      <published>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-India-as-a-Superpower-is-a-Distant-Reality-Part-II</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-India-as-a-Superpower-is-a-Distant-Reality-Part-II">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This article is the final part of the two-part series discussing the perils in the path of India becoming a superpower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Judicial Reforms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Law enforcement and the judicial system are the pillars on which the effectiveness of justice delivery depends. We have looked at the problems bugging India’s law enforcement in the first part of the article. Here we discuss the judiciary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The primary problem with the Indian judiciary is the pendency of cases. At the time of this writing, a total of 37,206,322 are&lt;a href=&quot;https://njdg.ecourts.gov.in/njdgnew/?p=main/pend_dashboard&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://njdg.ecourts.gov.in/njdgnew/?p=main/pend_dashboard&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pending&lt;/a&gt; before the District and subordinate courts in India. Another 5,660,908 cases, of which 87.54% are cases more than a year old, are pending before the High Courts in India. The result is one of an overburdened and sub-optimal judiciary. Some estimates put the time taken to resolve all the pending cases before the Indian Courts close to 300 years! So, what is the way forward?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;One suggestion is to establish appellate courts to expedite the pending cases. Courts of appeals at the district level, state level and national level can help reduce the burden on the courts. The Supreme Court of India also acts as an appellate Court, apart from acting as the Constitutional Court (which the Court can do under Article 133 and 134 of the Indian Constitution in civil and criminal matters respectively). This puts additional burden on the Supreme Court, and it is in fact plagued by a huge workload. To reduce this burden, the appellate work of the Supreme Court may be separated by setting up a Supreme Appellate Court, and its benches could be set up across the country. Apart from this, cognitive technologies could be incorporated into the dispute resolution mechanism (in civil cases). For instance, the biggest litigants today are the various governments in India. Government officials, who decide not to appeal an adverse order, often run the risk of having to justify why they did not pursue the matter more vigorously. Incorporating cognitive technologies can help these officials analyse the chances of a successful appeal better. They can also help the judges in the decision-making process, which could lead to faster decisions and thus, could dispose of a case quickly. But most important of all, the lower rung of courts should be strengthened by filling the vacancies, establishing new posts and developing the infrastructure; for, most of the cases are filed at the lower level and most of the disputes are settled there itself.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another problem with the courts today is the lack of accountability. The introduction of the collegium system in 1998 means that the judges across all the Indian courts are appointed by the higher courts but not the political executive. This is clearly against the principle of checks and balances. The Government of India tried to establish a National Judicial Appoints Committee in 2014. Despite the Parliament of India clearing it, the Supreme Court struck it down saying it violated ‘the basic structure’ doctrine. Collegium, therefore, can only be abolished if all the members of Parliament come together and stand up to the highest court of the land and force its hand. They should do it because it is in the best interest of the country. The Supreme Court should also exercise restraint when it wades into the duties of the executive and legislature and uphold the doctrine of separation of powers. This judicial activism, which has sometimes worked well to deliver justice, has also harmed the Indian economy (from the cancelation of 2G spectrum auctions, the cancellation of coal licences to the recent staying of the farm laws enacted by the Indian Parliament).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;After all is said and done, the judiciary, for all its failures, provides places for discussion and debate. IT acts as a forum for a certain amount of churn. Reforming the judiciary, therefore, is in the best interest of India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social indicators should be improved&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;We Indians are constantly obsessed with ranks. “India is the world’s fastest growing economy,” “India is the world’s third largest economy” we exclaim. But economic growth is not everything, we forget. A look at the social indicators of the country paints a much darker picture. India lags behind its neighbours in human development and social development indicators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;By comparing India with its neighbours, we can analyse the situation. The infant mortality rate, the number of infant deaths per 1,000 births, is 32 in India while it was 27 in Bangladesh in 2017. As of 2015, India’s life expectancy is 68.35, lagging behind Sri Lanka, Bangladesh, Nepal and Bhutan. Between 2003 and 2015 Bangladesh was successful in bringing down the open-defecation rate from 43% to 1%, while India is still struggling with it. Back in 2010 only, infant immunization for DPT and measles in Bangladesh, Sri Lanka and Nepal was about 80%, while India stood somewhere around 65%. In terms of sanitation facilities too, India’s neighbours outperform, though the situation is improving in India. The first&amp;nbsp; phase of the National Family Health Survey (NFHS) released in December 2020 indicates that India could be seeing an increase in child undernutrition. Child undernutrition, measured using three indicators namely stunting, wasting and underweight, has grown in many of the states in the latest NFHS. A rise in the all-India figures would mean that India is reversing the gains it had achieved since 1998-1999. Of all, the problem of stunting is serious in that it affects the cognitive abilities of the children and it could take up to three generations to undo the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It is not that the Indian government is not capable of delivering things. It had successfully carried out the polio vaccination programme and eradicated polio. More recently, it succeeded in getting the people to wear masks to combat the COVID-19 pandemic and proved false the many estimates which predicted 200-300 million deaths due to the pandemic. To improve the social indicators, the government can start by educating people through spreading information via cell phones when someone calls the other. Most importantly, NGOs in India are doing a commendable job in tackling various social problems in India. Government can very well incorporate them and work alongside them to change things where India’s performance lacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There are many other areas which need complete overhaul or effective management. For instance, from modernization of military equipment to facing the challenge of low diplomatic corps, India’s external security faces many challenges. India faces major national security challenges from a more authoritative China and an unstable Pakistan. Another area is that of data collection. Data collection faces huge problems and the depth of the problem is drastic. Often, due to lack of coordination among the various government departments, same data is collected by different departments and, sometimes, the departments arrive at different conclusions! To make cross-state comparisons, one often has to move mountains to gather and then interpret data. It is important to have standardised data collection mechanisms and data interpretations platforms so as to formulate policies that are relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Finally, the problems are huge. And they should be fixed if India has any hopes of playing an important role globally. India faces a (funny?) paradox. On the one hand, various governments in India are among the largest employment providers in the country and on the other practically every department is understaffed. This tells us that we need more personnel, but in the right places. India should also invest in creating a knowledge base for all relevant and necessary functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India is a pre-industrial economy living through an information age. Often, the state has to play a strong role in an industrial economy, but has to take a back seat in the information economy. How the Indian state sets about resolving this paradox also determines India’s future. If we look at history, the most resistance to change comes from villages; and they tend to become violent to resist change. This also presents India with unique challenges. However, the biggest of the problems is in realising all that we have discussed are not any of these. It is that these policies present huge political risks. In a country where the political representation is so heavily skewed towards rural India, whose population is about 30%-40%, the political priorities are also skewed towards rural India and their problems. India needs a leader who focuses on not winning the next election, but on doing the right thing, to get what we have discussed done. That leader may not come to power, but he/she/the will forever changed the fate of the country for the better.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This article is the final part of the two-part series discussing the perils in the path of India becoming a superpower. Judicial Reforms Law enforcement and the judicial system are the pillars on which the effectiveness of justice delivery depends. We have looked at the problems bugging India’s law enforcement in the first part of the article. Here we discuss the judiciary. The primary problem with the Indian judiciary is the pendency of cases. At the time of this writing, a total of 37,206,322 are pending before the District and subordinate courts in India. Another 5,660,908 cases, of which 87.54% are cases more than a year old, are pending before the High Courts in India. The result is one of an overburdened and sub-optimal judiciary. Some estimates put the time taken to resolve all the pending cases before the Indian Courts close to 300 years! So, what is the way forward?&amp;nbsp; One suggestion is to establish appellate courts to expedite the pending cases. Courts of appeals at the district level, state level and national level can help reduce the burden on the courts. The Supreme Court of India also acts as an appellate Court, apart from acting as the Constitutional Court (which the Court can do under Article 133 and 134 of the Indian Constitution in civil and criminal matters respectively). This puts additional burden on the Supreme Court, and it is in fact plagued by a huge workload. To reduce this burden, the appellate work of the Supreme Court may be separated by setting up a Supreme Appellate Court, and its benches could be set up across the country. Apart from this, cognitive technologies could be incorporated into the dispute resolution mechanism (in civil cases). For instance, the biggest litigants today are the various governments in India. Government officials, who decide not to appeal an adverse order, often run the risk of having to justify why they did not pursue the matter more vigorously. Incorporating cognitive technologies can help these officials analyse the chances of a successful appeal better. They can also help the judges in the decision-making process, which could lead to faster decisions and thus, could dispose of a case quickly. But most important of all, the lower rung of courts should be strengthened by filling the vacancies, establishing new posts and developing the infrastructure; for, most of the cases are filed at the lower level and most of the disputes are settled there itself.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Another problem with the courts today is the lack of accountability. The introduction of the collegium system in 1998 means that the judges across all the Indian courts are appointed by the higher courts but not the political executive. This is clearly against the principle of checks and balances. The Government of India tried to establish a National Judicial Appoints Committee in 2014. Despite the Parliament of India clearing it, the Supreme Court struck it down saying it violated ‘the basic structure’ doctrine. Collegium, therefore, can only be abolished if all the members of Parliament come together and stand up to the highest court of the land and force its hand. They should do it because it is in the best interest of the country. The Supreme Court should also exercise restraint when it wades into the duties of the executive and legislature and uphold the doctrine of separation of powers. This judicial activism, which has sometimes worked well to deliver justice, has also harmed the Indian economy (from the cancelation of 2G spectrum auctions, the cancellation of coal licences to the recent staying of the farm laws enacted by the Indian Parliament). After all is said and done, the judiciary, for all its failures, provides places for discussion and debate. IT acts as a forum for a certain amount of churn. Reforming the judiciary, therefore, is in the best interest of India. Social indicators should be improved We Indians are constantly obsessed with ranks. “India is the world’s fastest growing economy,” “India is the world’s third largest economy” we exclaim. But economic growth is not everything, we forget. A look at the social indicators of the country paints a much darker picture. India lags behind its neighbours in human development and social development indicators. By comparing India with its neighbours, we can analyse the situation. The infant mortality rate, the number of infant deaths per 1,000 births, is 32 in India while it was 27 in Bangladesh in 2017. As of 2015, India’s life expectancy is 68.35, lagging behind Sri Lanka, Bangladesh, Nepal and Bhutan. Between 2003 and 2015 Bangladesh was successful in bringing down the open-defecation rate from 43% to 1%, while India is still struggling with it. Back in 2010 only, infant immunization for DPT and measles in Bangladesh, Sri Lanka and Nepal was about 80%, while India stood somewhere around 65%. In terms of sanitation facilities too, India’s neighbours outperform, though the situation is improving in India. The first&amp;nbsp; phase of the National Family Health Survey (NFHS) released in December 2020 indicates that India could be seeing an increase in child undernutrition. Child undernutrition, measured using three indicators namely stunting, wasting and underweight, has grown in many of the states in the latest NFHS. A rise in the all-India figures would mean that India is reversing the gains it had achieved since 1998-1999. Of all, the problem of stunting is serious in that it affects the cognitive abilities of the children and it could take up to three generations to undo the problem. It is not that the Indian government is not capable of delivering things. It had successfully carried out the polio vaccination programme and eradicated polio. More recently, it succeeded in getting the people to wear masks to combat the COVID-19 pandemic and proved false the many estimates which predicted 200-300 million deaths due to the pandemic. To improve the social indicators, the government can start by educating people through spreading information via cell phones when someone calls the other. Most importantly, NGOs in India are doing a commendable job in tackling various social problems in India. Government can very well incorporate them and work alongside them to change things where India’s performance lacks. There are many other areas which need complete overhaul or effective management. For instance, from modernization of military equipment to facing the challenge of low diplomatic corps, India’s external security faces many challenges. India faces major national security challenges from a more authoritative China and an unstable Pakistan. Another area is that of data collection. Data collection faces huge problems and the depth of the problem is drastic. Often, due to lack of coordination among the various government departments, same data is collected by different departments and, sometimes, the departments arrive at different conclusions! To make cross-state comparisons, one often has to move mountains to gather and then interpret data. It is important to have standardised data collection mechanisms and data interpretations platforms so as to formulate policies that are relevant. Finally, the problems are huge. And they should be fixed if India has any hopes of playing an important role globally. India faces a (funny?) paradox. On the one hand, various governments in India are among the largest employment providers in the country and on the other practically every department is understaffed. This tells us that we need more personnel, but in the right places. India should also invest in creating a knowledge base for all relevant and necessary functions. India is a pre-industrial economy living through an information age. Often, the state has to play a strong role in an industrial economy, but has to take a back seat in the information economy. How the Indian state sets about resolving this paradox also determines India’s future. If we look at history, the most resistance to change comes from villages; and they tend to become violent to resist change. This also presents India with unique challenges. However, the biggest of the problems is in realising all that we have discussed are not any of these. It is that these policies present huge political risks. In a country where the political representation is so heavily skewed towards rural India, whose population is about 30%-40%, the political priorities are also skewed towards rural India and their problems. India needs a leader who focuses on not winning the next election, but on doing the right thing, to get what we have discussed done. That leader may not come to power, but he/she/the will forever changed the fate of the country for the better.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
