<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/economics/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-06-14T00:48:23+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/economics/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Inflation - Dead Or Dormant?</title>
      <link href="/Inflation-Dead-Or-Dormant" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inflation - Dead Or Dormant?" />
      <published>2019-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Inflation-Dead-Or-Dormant</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Inflation-Dead-Or-Dormant">&lt;p&gt;The US Federal Reserve, in its recent Open Market Operations Committee Meeting, chose an ambiguous stance by leaving the federal funds rate unchanged at the range of 2.25-2.5%, much to the dismay of the markets and the Government, who long awaited a rate cut. As the growth rates declined across Europe, China and US in Q1 2019, the Fed was expected to finally move away from the rate hikes, which were also offsetting the fiscal concessions provided by the US government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This monetary tightening began in late 2015, as an attempt to counter the inflation that was expected in the aftermath of using heterodox mutations like Quantitative Easing (QE) to recover demand in the largest Post-War Recession of 2008. While the Fiscal Policy has become increasingly pro-cyclical in the recent (Trump) years, the hawkish Monetary Policy attempts to counter the inflation that is already locked far behind its 2% benchmark, which has resulted in the Trump’s disapproval of Jerome Powell (thus, the threats of replacing him with political cronies like Herman Cain). The low expected inflation has not only caused the recessionary air to resurface but has also invited wild justifications for credibility restoration. Fed’s Loretta Mester recently went as far as to claim that the economy has finally reached its equilibrium in her (neo)classic defense of the recent speculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But none of the justifications explained why inflation is globally stifled for the developed economies despite the rising-but-low rates. The observation remains that the Monetary Policy is losing grip over the rate of inflation. Prices are no longer as sensitive to the interest rates as they used to be, thus, explaining the recent surge in various financial forums pronouncing inflation dead, attributing it mainly to technological advancements. In times of prosperity, inflation is high due to the increased productivity and employment, which gives the workforce the ability to bargain for greater wages, that will push up the costs and then the prices. With improved technology and reduced labour intensity, the ability of the workers to demand greater wages during an upswing has declined. Additionally, the prophecy paradox, that embodies the self-fulfilling nature of expectations in economics, comes to play. The general level of expected inflation in the markets is low which is seen to be taking its effect on the actual figures, and though these expectations are being publicized as a reflective of the credibility of the Fed, they certainly don’t go in tandem with the economic or the fiscal cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the major setback has been taken by the theory of the Phillips curve, which describes the inverse relationship between inflation and unemployment via the cost-wage spiral. This relation was violated once back in the 70s when stagflation hit the American economy. It was chiefly blamed at the rising oil prices, when in fact it was the abolition of Bretton Woods by Nixon that took a toll on the economy. Though its collapse provided the US with a monetary policy that extended beyond the clasp of the Special Drawing Rights, it immediately resulted in inflation which was previously limited to the $35/ounce gold peg. In order to tackle the inflation, the government bought in price controls which reduced the profitability of businesses, and ended up in large scale layoffs. But this direct relation had helped Milton Friedman in developing a long run perspective to the theory, and concluding that in the long run, the Phillips curve is vertical. In the short-run, however, there is sufficient scope for monetary policy to smooth out fluctuations around the independent pathway of potential output by affecting cyclical unemployment and price levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The curve has currently flattened, and this relation is no longer as strong for the developed economies as it used to be, considering how unemployment is presently at 3.9% in the USA, below its natural rate that stands at 4%, but inflation has shown no signs of a revival. A similar pattern had been witnessed right before the tech bubble had burst. This flattening of the curve is possibly a structural problem, not amenable to macroeconomic measures and it reduces the capability of the Central Banks to reach their inflation targets. But if the theory still survives, it could only mean that the Fed anticipates a pending risk for the inflation to resurface, for which the rate hikes, under the alias of a ‘friendly normalisation’, are being pursued. Perhaps inflation is not dead, but dormant and potentially on a rise, although it is ‘inflation targeting’ that might be officially dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, this inflation-interest rate relation, which is hardly ever questioned, was never a strong one, to begin with. J.Stiglitz asserts &lt;em&gt;“this rudimentary method is based on a weak economic theory and little empirical evidence…and there is no reason to believe that, whatever the source of inflation, the best solution is to raise interest rates.”&lt;/em&gt; The Central Banks have been over-relying on the Monetary Policy for every minor inconvenience as if it is a panacea for the dearth of aggregate demand. And why not? It’s the easiest way out, 2008 stands witness. But that is if we remain unreasonably adamant on the “In the long run, we’re all dead” approach. While the Fiscal Policy, despite its implementation imperfections, attempts to systematically address the economic issues at their core, the monetary policy has been globally reduced to an interest fluctuation switch, whose volatility takes its toll on its own ability. It is an important but overexploited tool that was ideally supposed to address the Dual Mandate on both price stability and employment issues through a suitable policy mix, but there seems to be no coordination among the fiscal and the monetary policy. The past few centuries stand witness to the fact that no monetary system has stood firm for over 50 years, citing the changes that the monetary policy faced in 1913, 1933, 1945 and 1971. And considering its ageing ability to address inflation, people have already started coming up with alternatives to the existing system, the most prominent one being the Modern Monetary Theory (MMT).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a fringe economic model, MMT stems out of the monetary theory of Marx, which later seems to have influenced Keynes, and is nowadays gaining mainstream attention, such as being proposed for financing the Green New Deal by Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez. It basically states that a country with its own currency can simply pay off its debt by printing more currency. The idea would seem questionable even to a layman, but this is only true if the debt is denominated in the domestic currency, which though is not the case for most of the nations, it’s certainly applicable for the USA as an advantage of USD being the major global reserve currency. This theory is often criticised for its utter disregard for the size of the deficits and the impact on inflation, but it does address these issues by manipulating the revenue side. Additionally, being a brain-child of the left doesn’t imply that it will not be accepted by the right since it can just as easily help in financing tax cuts. Major investors such as Ray Dalio, who feed off of capitalism, have stated that something like MMT will inevitably be replacing the Central Banks. In fact, MMT appears to be the only way to elude the burgeoning debt and the declining credibility of the Fed. It will help finance the fiscal profligacy every US government has inherited from its fear of lobbyists, be it progressive or conservative. Either way, it might ameliorate the system after the hawks have devoured what’s left of their monetary policy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The US Federal Reserve, in its recent Open Market Operations Committee Meeting, chose an ambiguous stance by leaving the federal funds rate unchanged at the range of 2.25-2.5%, much to the dismay of the markets and the Government, who long awaited a rate cut. As the growth rates declined across Europe, China and US in Q1 2019, the Fed was expected to finally move away from the rate hikes, which were also offsetting the fiscal concessions provided by the US government.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Robots: Magic to Manic to Toxic</title>
      <link href="/Magic-Manic-Toxic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Robots: Magic to Manic to Toxic" />
      <published>2019-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Magic-Manic-Toxic</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Magic-Manic-Toxic">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How can mankind prevail in the face of such exponential and encompassing technological change?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each new development comes at a cost. We frequently witness the dawn of a new era at the expense of the old, such as the Iron Age following the Bronze, which itself followed the Stone Age. The advent of the Industrial Revolution wiped out the livelihood of millions, such as cobblers and weavers who were forced to adapt or be left behind, and this dynamic process continues today, only now at a much faster rate. In this era of ‘The New Machine Age’, we enter a dramatical phase where even highly skilled jobs are at risk, and where there will be increasing technology and potentially decreasing jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The realities of the new Machine Age are becoming clear and we can use them to chart the challenging yet abundant economy that we are creating. According to research at Oxford University, almost one out of every two jobs has a high risk of being automated by machines. Machine Learning, the most powerful branch of Artificial Intelligence, is the technology which is to be blamed for this alarming disruption. It basically permits machines to learn from data and mimic some of the routine jobs that we humans perform, but much more efficiently. And, evidently, this can prove game-changing or extremely problematic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent study from Forrester Research goes so far as to predict that 25 million jobs might disappear over the next decade. To put that in perspective, that is three times as many as jobs lost in the aftermath of the Financial Crisis. In fact, 87% of the lost manufacturing jobs have been eliminated as a result of improvements to our own productivity through automation. Automation is spreading to every production sector in every country around the globe. Output in the manufacturing sector in the US is actually growing, but we are losing jobs and lots of them. In fact, from 2000-2010, 5.7 million manufacturing jobs were lost to machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just the blue-collar jobs that are at risk, even those at the top of the ladder, including the highest-paid people, will be affected. What is clear that no matter whatever your job, at least some of it will be done by a robot in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is that the reason why visionaries like Mark Zuckerberg and Bill Gates are talking about government-funded minimum income levels? By the time today’s elementary school students are college-aged, we could be living in a robotic world largely unemployed and stuck in an ‘ungreat depression’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is supplemented by the dangers of technological advancement beyond automation and job replacement. Consider the tasks that are now done by a phone. Navigating a strange city? Impossible without Google Maps. Can’t decide where to take your next trip? MakeMyTrip will tell me. No time to answer all my texts? Siri will do it for me. These “artificial brains” are modifying quickly from knowing me to representing me to being me. In fact, they are starting to become an e-copy of us—and if that thought is not yet disturbing, imagine the power of this digital human amplified 100x in the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose we give an AI programme the goal to make humans smile. When the AI is weak, it causes humans to smile by performing normal amusing actions. However, when the AI is super intelligent, it realises there is a more effective way to achieve this goal: take control of the world and stick electrodes into the facial muscles of humans to cause constant, beaming grins. Of course, while such a scenario sounds very alarmistic, it does highlight a fundamental problem. AI is a genie inside a bottle, so the only solution is to find a way that when it gets out, it is on our side through shared values. This does not involve spelling out a long list of what we care about in computer code, rather an AI could use its ‘intelligence’ to learn what we value. Because, after all, the real worry isn’t enmity, but competence. A superintelligent AI can attain its goals, however for the common good of the world, we need to ensure that its goals are aligned with ours. For instance, humans don’t generally hate bees, but we’re more intelligent than they are – so if humans want to build a home in the place of a beehive, too bad for the bees. The beneficial AI movement is simply a way of avoiding placing humanity in the position of those bees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work that brings everyday surprise is designed for humans and not machines. And an area in which we are most certainly able to compete with and beat any machine conceivable is creativity. Machines have made very little progress in tackling novel situations. The fundamental limitation of Machine Learning is that it requires huge volumes of past data which we humans don’t require. We have the capability to connect seemingly disparate threads to find a solution to crisis situations or problems we have never seen before. The ability of the human mind to take strands from reality and weave them into something beautiful using a vivid imagination cannot be surpassed by bits of code, no matter how intelligent it is. Indeed, an AI programme has made music, but the capacities of such programmes have a critical limitation: they cannot do something new, which is the foundation of human creativity, they can only replicate and mutate the data that is given them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, it would seem that, with the right kind of limitations on what Machine Learning is used for and an investment in human beings, we can really herald a society where man and AI work together. First, we need to change our educational institutions to help foster more and more creativity, thereby preparing the jobs market for a situation where humans no longer do many mundane jobs. The efficiencies created by this division of labour between humans and AI will reap rewards that can only be imagined. Second, we need to align AI with our value systems and morals, using it as a purposeful instrument for human betterment rather than as a sterile but disastrously potent machine. With these two broad approaches, we humans can reach even greater heights of civilisation in the coming Age. After all, to quote Max Tegmark, President of the Future of Life Institute:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Everything we love about civilization is a product of intelligence, so amplifying our human intelligence with artificial intelligence has the potential of helping a civilization flourish like never before – as long as we manage to keep the technology beneficial.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>unnati.jain sailesh.buchasia</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">How can mankind prevail in the face of such exponential and encompassing technological change?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Fintech Effect: How Digital Innovators are Disrupting Banking</title>
      <link href="/The-Fintech-Effect" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fintech Effect: How Digital Innovators are Disrupting Banking" />
      <published>2019-05-03T02:33:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-03T02:33:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Fintech-Effect</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Fintech-Effect">&lt;p&gt;The world stands on the brink of a 4th industrial revolution that will
fundamentally alter the way everyone functions, which includes the complete
disruption of many industries and their business models. Banking is one such
industry which has experienced major turmoil when it comes to digital services
and mechanisation. Every transaction, be it online shopping, foreign currency
exchange, stock investments, or money transfers, is possible digitally at our
fingertips. At the intersection of finance and technology lies this altering
phenomenon, Fintech, which has been accelerating the pace of change at a
remarkable rate and is reshaping the industry’s status quo. ‘Fintech’ is a term
that has become the new trend in the media and in technology circles. Yet,
despite being widely discussed, many – including tech-savvy and clued-up
entrepreneurs – don’t quite have a handle on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While traditionally fintech was used for back-office functions to help banks
manage customer databases, facilitate transactions and record accounts, today it
has DIY modes where customers have a plethora of digital platforms at their
disposal, almost eliminating their dependence on a brick and mortar bank. With
24/7 device-sceptic access, virtually every transaction is now digitally
possible. The relevance of having several brick and mortar bank branches is
reducing as banking permeates all digital channels (cell phones, social and
online channels). According to some studies, in the European Union itself, more
than nine thousand bank branches were closed at the end of 2016 due to the wider
introduction of electronic payments and online/mobile banking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digital Disruption: What next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legacy financial institutions looking to become digitally-enabled encounter two
main problems. First, the business models and personal skills that have been
imbibed in the industry for decades have been disrupted by digital innovation,
and no longer hold the same degree of importance in the new banking ecosystem.
Second is “the innovator’s dilemma”. The innovator’s dilemma implies that when
companies adopt new technology and allocate the resources accordingly, they end
up disrupting the existing methods, something which they were already nurturing.
Hence, they might prefer to focus resources on existing methods to avoid
disruption, which, in turn, might make them uncompetitive in the long run.
Tackling this dilemma distinguishes successful firms and how they react to
change or ‘innovation’. For banks, attempts to create new models for the digital
age will wallow unless people and organisations are willing to disrupt
themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fintech affects or disrupts the financial sector in many ways which are beyond
our supposition. For instance, the mechanism which works behind the software of
chatbots is designed to capture natural language and human interactions through
machine learning and artificial intelligence. They assist banks to direct
customers to relevant departments more efficiently while handling queries.
Leading banks in Japan have chatbots that guide customers to information on its
website. Erica, the Bank of America’s chatbot provides investment advice too.
Customer emails containing transaction orders or details can be scanned and
executed within two minutes by robots which would otherwise take over 45
minutes. This process reduces costs, improves customer satisfaction and saves
time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next big development: a blockchain for digital transactions - cryptocurrency - is triumphing over the financial industry by providing consumers with a
speedier and cheaper way to carry on transactions. According to NASDAQ, the
greatest visible application of blockchain will be in how it moulds the payment
mechanism for the banks and users in order to dwindle away the transaction time.
In addition, with a unique trust system, blockchain offers a complete trading
platform for exchanges of securities which is achieved through transparency,
minimisation of risk, human error and transaction costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The importance of fintech will increase as the next few years will see the
disappearance of the Baby Boomer generation and the coming forth of the
Millennials or Gen Y (people born between 1980-1999). As they gain purchasing
power, they will cause drastic changes in client pattern, behaviour, decision
making, demographics and expectations. Their preference for a state-of-the-art
customer experience, high speed and convenience at the click of a button will
further accelerate the inculcation of fintech solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, digital disruption is not only about the positives. Cyber-crimes are
ever growing (malware, ransomware, phishing, etc.) along with digitisation. So,
stereotyped verification mechanisms are no longer enough to thwart fraudulent
attempts. The answer to this problem also lies in technology. More secure
protocols and extreme and extensive real-time, cross-channel fraud detection
systems are now available to protect the industry. There exists machine Learning
as well as artificial intelligence for disclosure of fraudulent activities. The
security softwares generate alarms on the plausibility of a fraud. Thereupon, it
is up to the investigators to figure out whether the transaction is a false
positive or an actual peril. The adoption of data aggregation floors, machine
learning steered statistical modelling and process automation can revamp
anti-money laundering activities by inculcating advanced efficiencies. Data
aggregation platforms can provide a 360-degree client view and facilitate
speedier transaction validation as already discussed. Further, machine learning
algorithms can leverage historical records to ascertain patterns and foresee the
happening of fraud and attacks, curtailing human endeavour by nearly half of
what it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In search of a safe and personal banking experience, as well as applications for
mobile devices, smartphones, and online payments, a new chapter of introducing
financial technologies in the financial services sector is being adopted. Today,
fintech covers everything, from chatbots to customer service, from machine
learning algorithms to blockchains for fraud analysis, from digital transactions
to biometrics. Retail banks have become a new player in providing all this to
their customers, forcing traditional banks to strategically invest in innovative
technologies. All of this will eventually lead to higher consumer retention.
While fintech, like any other technology, brings with it its set of disruptions,
the best is yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>sailesh.buchasia unnati.jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The world stands on the brink of a 4th industrial revolution that will fundamentally alter the way everyone functions, which includes the complete disruption of many industries and their business models. Banking is one such industry which has experienced major turmoil when it comes to digital services and mechanisation. Every transaction, be it online shopping, foreign currency exchange, stock investments, or money transfers, is possible digitally at our fingertips. At the intersection of finance and technology lies this altering phenomenon, Fintech, which has been accelerating the pace of change at a remarkable rate and is reshaping the industry’s status quo. ‘Fintech’ is a term that has become the new trend in the media and in technology circles. Yet, despite being widely discussed, many – including tech-savvy and clued-up entrepreneurs – don’t quite have a handle on it. While traditionally fintech was used for back-office functions to help banks manage customer databases, facilitate transactions and record accounts, today it has DIY modes where customers have a plethora of digital platforms at their disposal, almost eliminating their dependence on a brick and mortar bank. With 24/7 device-sceptic access, virtually every transaction is now digitally possible. The relevance of having several brick and mortar bank branches is reducing as banking permeates all digital channels (cell phones, social and online channels). According to some studies, in the European Union itself, more than nine thousand bank branches were closed at the end of 2016 due to the wider introduction of electronic payments and online/mobile banking. Digital Disruption: What next? Legacy financial institutions looking to become digitally-enabled encounter two main problems. First, the business models and personal skills that have been imbibed in the industry for decades have been disrupted by digital innovation, and no longer hold the same degree of importance in the new banking ecosystem. Second is “the innovator’s dilemma”. The innovator’s dilemma implies that when companies adopt new technology and allocate the resources accordingly, they end up disrupting the existing methods, something which they were already nurturing. Hence, they might prefer to focus resources on existing methods to avoid disruption, which, in turn, might make them uncompetitive in the long run. Tackling this dilemma distinguishes successful firms and how they react to change or ‘innovation’. For banks, attempts to create new models for the digital age will wallow unless people and organisations are willing to disrupt themselves. Fintech affects or disrupts the financial sector in many ways which are beyond our supposition. For instance, the mechanism which works behind the software of chatbots is designed to capture natural language and human interactions through machine learning and artificial intelligence. They assist banks to direct customers to relevant departments more efficiently while handling queries. Leading banks in Japan have chatbots that guide customers to information on its website. Erica, the Bank of America’s chatbot provides investment advice too. Customer emails containing transaction orders or details can be scanned and executed within two minutes by robots which would otherwise take over 45 minutes. This process reduces costs, improves customer satisfaction and saves time. The next big development: a blockchain for digital transactions - cryptocurrency - is triumphing over the financial industry by providing consumers with a speedier and cheaper way to carry on transactions. According to NASDAQ, the greatest visible application of blockchain will be in how it moulds the payment mechanism for the banks and users in order to dwindle away the transaction time. In addition, with a unique trust system, blockchain offers a complete trading platform for exchanges of securities which is achieved through transparency, minimisation of risk, human error and transaction costs. The importance of fintech will increase as the next few years will see the disappearance of the Baby Boomer generation and the coming forth of the Millennials or Gen Y (people born between 1980-1999). As they gain purchasing power, they will cause drastic changes in client pattern, behaviour, decision making, demographics and expectations. Their preference for a state-of-the-art customer experience, high speed and convenience at the click of a button will further accelerate the inculcation of fintech solutions. However, digital disruption is not only about the positives. Cyber-crimes are ever growing (malware, ransomware, phishing, etc.) along with digitisation. So, stereotyped verification mechanisms are no longer enough to thwart fraudulent attempts. The answer to this problem also lies in technology. More secure protocols and extreme and extensive real-time, cross-channel fraud detection systems are now available to protect the industry. There exists machine Learning as well as artificial intelligence for disclosure of fraudulent activities. The security softwares generate alarms on the plausibility of a fraud. Thereupon, it is up to the investigators to figure out whether the transaction is a false positive or an actual peril. The adoption of data aggregation floors, machine learning steered statistical modelling and process automation can revamp anti-money laundering activities by inculcating advanced efficiencies. Data aggregation platforms can provide a 360-degree client view and facilitate speedier transaction validation as already discussed. Further, machine learning algorithms can leverage historical records to ascertain patterns and foresee the happening of fraud and attacks, curtailing human endeavour by nearly half of what it was. In search of a safe and personal banking experience, as well as applications for mobile devices, smartphones, and online payments, a new chapter of introducing financial technologies in the financial services sector is being adopted. Today, fintech covers everything, from chatbots to customer service, from machine learning algorithms to blockchains for fraud analysis, from digital transactions to biometrics. Retail banks have become a new player in providing all this to their customers, forcing traditional banks to strategically invest in innovative technologies. All of this will eventually lead to higher consumer retention. While fintech, like any other technology, brings with it its set of disruptions, the best is yet to come.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">United in Pay, Divided in Dues</title>
      <link href="/United-in-pay" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="United in Pay, Divided in Dues" />
      <published>2019-05-03T02:14:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-03T02:14:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/United-in-pay</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/United-in-pay">&lt;p&gt;India’s Jet Airways may have shut down all operations, but they are not the only
ones with their international business up in flames due to a financial crisis.
The United Nations has been jostling with its latest set of money problems as
well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have not been living under a rock for the past couple of weeks, you must
have already come across numerous articles like these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dmicdc.com/about-DMICDC&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//united-in-pay-1.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost every publication on the Internet that you could think of has been
reeling from this news and successfully copy-pasting news from one another.
Whichever side you look at, whatever your source is, it does not make a
difference. There have been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=moYojoQsedU&quot;&gt;YouTube
videos&lt;/a&gt;, Facebook posts, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5hJzKSJCtn8&quot;&gt;TV
monologues&lt;/a&gt; and private rants about
it. The same thing, boxed up and packaged differently, again and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Ok! The United Nations owes India money, lots of money. Now get over it”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with the discussion is that it is pointed in the wrong direction and
the whole narrative is messed up. To be honest, the United Nations is not really
at fault here. When you have a situation like this, news consumers tend to
simplify the news in their terms and react to it in the most primitive way
possible: by losing their minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dmicdc.com/about-DMICDC&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//united-in-pay-2.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, let’s get down to business. The United Nations is under a financial
crisis of unusual proportions. It is facing severe shortages in its Regular
Budget compensation, as well as its Peacekeeping Budget, which is the main
reason why they are finding it tough to repay their dues to the
Police-Contributing Countries (PCCs) and Troop-Contributing Countries (TCCs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of the beginning of April 2019, the United Nations is yet to complete $256
million in total payments, with the likes of India, Bangladesh, Nepal, Pakistan
and Rwanda each being &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/defence/un-owes-india-usd-38-million-for-peacekeeping-operations-unsg-report/articleshow/68904063.cms&quot;&gt;owed $23-38
million&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This situation has a direct link with the state of the United Nations’ cash
balance, which has fallen by $735 million since the beginning of the decade. It
currently stands at an abysmal -$323 million (yes, the minus sign is a negative
balance).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How could such a dangerous cash crunch bite the UN at this point of time? To
understand things, we have to get a better understanding of the way the UN gets
its money to function. It is a bit complex, but if you know basic maths and
possess an above-average attention span, then you will definitely get a grip of
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it works like this. The United Nations decides the amount that each country
should pay to the Regular Budget, based on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/ny.gnp.mktp.cd&quot;&gt;Gross National Income
(GNI)&lt;/a&gt; of the respective
country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It then makes a series of adjustments based on the amount of external debt of
the country, whether the country has a very low per-capita GNI and if it belongs
to the list of Least Developed Countries or not. If so, the contributions by the
country will be capped at 0.01% of the total budget. Also, every country must
pay at least 0.001% of the budget, called the minimum pay adjustment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and lastly, if a country’s share exceeds 22%, it will be brought down to and
capped at 22% of the total budget amount. The United States whose estimated
share is 23.069% is the only country that is getting a discount, in having to
pay only 22%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a great infographic from &lt;a href=&quot;https://qz.com/author/ashendrukqz/&quot;&gt;Amanda
Shendruk&lt;/a&gt; of Quartz.com, who sums it up
perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shohan Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">India’s Jet Airways may have shut down all operations, but they are not the only ones with their international business up in flames due to a financial crisis. The United Nations has been jostling with its latest set of money problems as well. If you have not been living under a rock for the past couple of weeks, you must have already come across numerous articles like these. Almost every publication on the Internet that you could think of has been reeling from this news and successfully copy-pasting news from one another. Whichever side you look at, whatever your source is, it does not make a difference. There have been YouTube videos, Facebook posts, TV monologues and private rants about it. The same thing, boxed up and packaged differently, again and again. “Ok! The United Nations owes India money, lots of money. Now get over it” The problem with the discussion is that it is pointed in the wrong direction and the whole narrative is messed up. To be honest, the United Nations is not really at fault here. When you have a situation like this, news consumers tend to simplify the news in their terms and react to it in the most primitive way possible: by losing their minds. Alright, let’s get down to business. The United Nations is under a financial crisis of unusual proportions. It is facing severe shortages in its Regular Budget compensation, as well as its Peacekeeping Budget, which is the main reason why they are finding it tough to repay their dues to the Police-Contributing Countries (PCCs) and Troop-Contributing Countries (TCCs). As of the beginning of April 2019, the United Nations is yet to complete $256 million in total payments, with the likes of India, Bangladesh, Nepal, Pakistan and Rwanda each being owed $23-38 million. This situation has a direct link with the state of the United Nations’ cash balance, which has fallen by $735 million since the beginning of the decade. It currently stands at an abysmal -$323 million (yes, the minus sign is a negative balance). How could such a dangerous cash crunch bite the UN at this point of time? To understand things, we have to get a better understanding of the way the UN gets its money to function. It is a bit complex, but if you know basic maths and possess an above-average attention span, then you will definitely get a grip of it. So, it works like this. The United Nations decides the amount that each country should pay to the Regular Budget, based on the Gross National Income (GNI) of the respective country. It then makes a series of adjustments based on the amount of external debt of the country, whether the country has a very low per-capita GNI and if it belongs to the list of Least Developed Countries or not. If so, the contributions by the country will be capped at 0.01% of the total budget. Also, every country must pay at least 0.001% of the budget, called the minimum pay adjustment. Oh, and lastly, if a country’s share exceeds 22%, it will be brought down to and capped at 22% of the total budget amount. The United States whose estimated share is 23.069% is the only country that is getting a discount, in having to pay only 22%. Here is a great infographic from Amanda Shendruk of Quartz.com, who sums it up perfectly.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Exposing the Irrational Voter, Mathematically!</title>
      <link href="/Exposing-the-Irrational-Voter" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exposing the Irrational Voter, Mathematically!" />
      <published>2019-04-26T01:45:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-26T01:45:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Exposing-the-Irrational-Voter</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Exposing-the-Irrational-Voter">&lt;p&gt;The Indian elections are right around the corner and the mood is currently in
full swing. Check the papers and you’ll barely find any real estate left for
anything else (but you can always check back with &lt;a href=&quot;http://thepangean.com&quot;&gt;The
Pangean&lt;/a&gt; for more). The juries are out and so are the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloombergquint.com/bq-blue-exclusive/elections-2019-a-manifesto-for-political-manifestos&quot;&gt;manifestos&lt;/a&gt;.
The line between celebrities and candidates gets blurrier by the day and
election campaigns are &lt;a href=&quot;https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/city/kolkata/for-mimi-chakraborty-its-all-work-and-no-sleep-before-poll-drill-starts/articleshow/68434360.cms&quot;&gt;quickly turning into promotional
tours&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One has to feel sorry for the manifestos, which the &lt;em&gt;majority&lt;/em&gt; of voters will
probably have only a glance of at most. Studies at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S002205310800080X?via%3Dihub&quot;&gt;frontiers of decision
theory&lt;/a&gt;
have shown that when people do not pay attention to candidate policy choices,
uninformed voters end up making decisions based on personalities. This seems to
explain most of the name-calling and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MkqIEWY2-aY&quot;&gt;on-stage
singing&lt;/a&gt; that candidates have
resorted to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the midst of all this, three main talking points have emerged: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiainfoline.com/article/general-blog/rising-unemployment-and-the-future-of-indian-youth-118112200298_1.html&quot;&gt;youth
unemployment&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fairobserver.com/region/central_south_asia/indian-farmer-suicides-india-south-asian-world-news-latest-32349/&quot;&gt;farmer’s
perils&lt;/a&gt;
and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2018/06/27/india-ranked-worlds-most-dangerous-place-for-women-reigniting-debate-about-womens-safety/?noredirect=on&amp;amp;utm_term=.933d533d9a10&quot;&gt;safety of
women&lt;/a&gt;.
It is no doubt that these topics will be sticking out as the major drivers of
the 2019 Indian election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a look at some data that will give us some insight into the State of the
Nation. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cmie.com/kommon/bin/sr.php?kall=warticle&amp;amp;dt=2019-01-08%2009:28:37&amp;amp;msec=666&quot;&gt;Centre for Monitoring Indian
Economy&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cmie.com/kommon/bin/sr.php?kall=warticle&amp;amp;dt=2019-01-08%2009:28:37&amp;amp;msec=666&quot;&gt;CMIE&lt;/a&gt;)
estimated that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thehindu.com/opinion/lead/surveying-indias-unemployment-numbers/article26218615.ece&quot;&gt;11 million
jobs&lt;/a&gt;
were lost in 2018 – pushing the unemployment rate to 7.38%. A leaked NSSO report
pegged the unemployment rate at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.business-standard.com/article/economy-policy/unemployment-rate-at-four-decade-high-nsso-survey-compared-past-figures-119020100042_1.html&quot;&gt;6.1%&lt;/a&gt;,
the highest in over four decades. Things do not look so good for our youth at
work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about the farmers, the bedrock of our society? Well, this is where
things go further downhill. According to Wholesale Price Index
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://tradingeconomics.com/india/producer-prices-change&quot;&gt;WPI&lt;/a&gt;) data for the
month of December released by the Ministry of Commerce and Industry, the WPI
sub-component for primary food articles has been negative for six consecutive
months beginning July 2018. This is a direct indication of the sliding prices
that farmers have been facing for their produce, which has led to innumerable
suicides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women’s safety is also experiencing issues that India cannot seem to get away
from that have been lingering for far too long and are only getting worse.
According to a recent poll of 548 experts by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://poll2018.trust.org/country/?id=india&quot;&gt;Thomson Reuters
Foundation&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“India ranked 1st among the world’s most dangerous countries for women.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No progress here, ladies and gentlemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The situation is dire and the immediate need for change is crystal clear. It is
also understood that this summer the onus is on the people to effect change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But can we &lt;em&gt;trust&lt;/em&gt; the voters? How rational are they when it comes to making
decisions? How rational are &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where our rant comes to an end and the &lt;em&gt;dissection&lt;/em&gt; begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us play a little game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elections are only about promises and promises do not hold up most of the time,
so we reduce them to a matter of &lt;em&gt;probability&lt;/em&gt;. Now, let’s see how you and your
choices fare in our mock election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let there be two political parties, A and B, standing in the elections. Party A
promises to reduce unemployment by 20%, with a 100% chance of fulfilling his
promise. Whereas, Party B promises to reduce unemployment by 35%, with a 15 out
of 16 chance of fulfilling his promise. To put it neatly,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;20% unemployment drop, with certainty (100% Guarantee).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;35% unemployment reduction, with 15/16 chance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go on. Take your pick. Is it party A or party B? Who would you bank on for the
country’s sake?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, here’s a second case to choose from.  Party A promises a 20% reduction in
unemployment, only now with a 16% chance of fulfilling his promise. Whereas,
Party B promises 35% fall, with a 15% chance. Restating it,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;20% unemployment drop, with a 16% chance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;35% unemployment reduction, with a 15% chance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, whom did you pick? If you happened to pick Party A in Case 1, then you are
like the majority, who prefer certainty over chance. For those who chose Party B
in the first case, you were ready to take the risk for the greater reward. But
there is nothing wrong with either choice, the real game starts with Case 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, what about Case 2?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, here’s the bombshell. Case 2 is equal to Case 1 with a one-sixth chance.
That is, Case 2 is the same situation as Case 1, only with a 16% probability.
The change between the party’s probability of fulfilling promises in both cases
was proportional and thus, renders both cases to be the absolute same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if the problem never changed, did your choice of candidates change? From B to
A, or A to B?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you did not, then congratulations, you have
rational preferences. If you did, then there are more than a few things at work
here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us try another problem of this sort. Whether or not the government promised
to deposit &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businesstoday.in/current/economy-politics/bjp-never-promised-to-deposit-rs-15-lakh-in-people-bank-accounts-rajnath-singh/story/335629.html&quot;&gt;Rs. 15
Lakh&lt;/a&gt;
in everyone’s accounts, it is always possible another party will make a similar
promise in the run-up to the elections. Farmers are definitely in need of severe
financial help, so take Party A and Party B who make the respective
&lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/economy/agriculture/budget-2019-income-support-for-farmers-a-progressive-step-but-not-enough-to-mitigate-stress/articleshow/67802322.cms&quot;&gt;income-support&lt;/a&gt;
promises:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 11,000 a year, with an 11% chance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 11,000 a year, &lt;b&gt;guaranteed&lt;/b&gt; (100% chance).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance, and Rs 11,000 a year, with an 89%
chance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who gets the vote, in each case, this time around? Did you choose the same party
both times, or different parties? Choosing different parties is a sign of
incoherent decision-making. This is because Case 1 is once again of a similar
form as Case 2. There has been no significant change in the factors that should
influence your decision-making. Yet there will be more than a few instances of
people making unidentical choices for Cases 1 and 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time to do a bit of explaining. Consider these cases as lotteries. Both Party A
and Party B have an 89% chance of not fulfilling any promise in Case 1. But
wait? Didn’t Party B promise a 10% chance? So it gives us (100% -10%=) 90%
chance of empty-handed farmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, there is the existence of a lottery within a lottery; a &lt;strong&gt;compound&lt;/strong&gt;
lottery, so to speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lottery within is actually a 10 out of 11 chance of receiving Rs 15000 and 1
out of 11 chance of getting Rs 0. So when it is nested inside the outer lottery
of Party B, we get&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;11% x [( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)]   + 89% x Rs 0&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is essentially,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance and Rs 0, with a 90% chance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know, things are getting discombobulated in your head, but stay with me.
Eventually, what we are left with is a much detailed way to re-write and
represent Cases 1 and 2 as &lt;em&gt;nested&lt;/em&gt; probabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: 11% x &lt;em&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;Rs 11,000&lt;/span&gt; +   &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;89% x Rs 0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;11% x [&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)&lt;/span&gt;]   +  &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;89% x Rs 0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: 11% x &lt;em&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;Rs 11,000&lt;/span&gt; +   &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;89% x Rs 11,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;11% x [&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)&lt;/span&gt;]   + &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;89% x Rs 11,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parts marked in &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;Red&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; are the actual &lt;em&gt;determinants&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; factors
when it comes to decision-making between the two parties. The segments marked in
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;Blue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; are offered by &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; parties and thus, should not be a determining
factor in rational choosing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you ended up choosing A in Case 1 and B in Case 2 (or vice versa), you
have just chosen two different answers for the same problem. Do you see it now?
That is where rational preferences are violated and we can now find our
&lt;em&gt;irrational voter&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all this, we come to the origins of the problem. The lack of coherence
empirically observed above is called the &lt;strong&gt;Allais Paradox&lt;/strong&gt;, and has been the
talk of game theorists and psychologists for years. First published in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://wolfweb.unr.edu/homepage/pingle/Teaching/BADM%20791/Week%206%20Decision%20Making%20Under%20Uncertainty/Allais%20Paradox%201953.pdf&quot;&gt;1953&lt;/a&gt;,
in the &lt;em&gt;Econometrica&lt;/em&gt; journal by French economist Maurice Allais, the Allais
Paradox was observed among subjects who, when presented with choices such as the
ones above, made snap decisions that were proven to be incoherent upon further
study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although not everyone got it wrong, a significant number of people made the
error which prompted him to wonder whether there was more than just rationality
behind human choices. So the Allais Paradox started off as more of a standout
against conventional rationality theory, than as the rationality test that it
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/zJZvoiwydJ5zvzTHK/the-allais-paradox&quot;&gt;has evolved to
today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maurice Allais did end up &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/economic-sciences/1988/summary/&quot;&gt;winning the 1988 Nobel Prize in
Economics&lt;/a&gt;
but it was not until 20 years after it was first published, that the Allais
Paradox was brought back to the mainstream by Daniel Kahneman. In a way, the
Allais Paradox was what got Nobel laureate Daniel Kahneman (2002 Nobel laureate)
into economics. He along with Amos Tversky, were two young psychologists back in
the 1970s who came across this paradox and were so intrigued by the study of
human approach towards uncertainty that they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1207/S15427579JPFM0402_01&quot;&gt;opened up new
dimensions&lt;/a&gt; in
the world of economics and &lt;a href=&quot;http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/economics/laureates/2002/&quot;&gt;decision-making under
uncertainty&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maurice Allais had made one of the foremost and yet perplexing dives into human
rationality and for that, today, the world is in a better position to understand
human behaviour and decision-making. And while we are on the topic of making
decisions, we get back to the decision of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This election may be driven by 3 &lt;em&gt;central&lt;/em&gt; issues: unemployment, farmers and
women’s protection. But at the end of the day, it is the people who &lt;em&gt;drive&lt;/em&gt;
elections. Yet what we often overlook is what drives the &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt; and their
&lt;em&gt;choices&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we as smart as we think we are? Does being &lt;em&gt;irrational&lt;/em&gt; only mean being
‘unreasonable’ or ‘baseless’ as the Dictionary says? Or is there more to this
than meets the eye &lt;em&gt;or brain&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On that note, we ask you to think twice before calling someone else irrational.
Oh, and yes, don’t forget to think twice before voting. Happy elections!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*31st May, 2019 marks the 108th Birth Anniversary of French physicist and
economist Maurice Allais, best known for his contributions to the neoclassical
synthesis and the Allais Paradox.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shohan Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Indian elections are right around the corner and the mood is currently in full swing. Check the papers and you’ll barely find any real estate left for anything else (but you can always check back with The Pangean for more). The juries are out and so are the manifestos. The line between celebrities and candidates gets blurrier by the day and election campaigns are quickly turning into promotional tours. One has to feel sorry for the manifestos, which the majority of voters will probably have only a glance of at most. Studies at the frontiers of decision theory have shown that when people do not pay attention to candidate policy choices, uninformed voters end up making decisions based on personalities. This seems to explain most of the name-calling and on-stage singing that candidates have resorted to. In the midst of all this, three main talking points have emerged: youth unemployment, farmer’s perils and the safety of women. It is no doubt that these topics will be sticking out as the major drivers of the 2019 Indian election. Here’s a look at some data that will give us some insight into the State of the Nation. The Centre for Monitoring Indian Economy (CMIE) estimated that 11 million jobs were lost in 2018 – pushing the unemployment rate to 7.38%. A leaked NSSO report pegged the unemployment rate at 6.1%, the highest in over four decades. Things do not look so good for our youth at work. But what about the farmers, the bedrock of our society? Well, this is where things go further downhill. According to Wholesale Price Index (WPI) data for the month of December released by the Ministry of Commerce and Industry, the WPI sub-component for primary food articles has been negative for six consecutive months beginning July 2018. This is a direct indication of the sliding prices that farmers have been facing for their produce, which has led to innumerable suicides. Women’s safety is also experiencing issues that India cannot seem to get away from that have been lingering for far too long and are only getting worse. According to a recent poll of 548 experts by the Thomson Reuters Foundation, “India ranked 1st among the world’s most dangerous countries for women.” No progress here, ladies and gentlemen. The situation is dire and the immediate need for change is crystal clear. It is also understood that this summer the onus is on the people to effect change. But can we trust the voters? How rational are they when it comes to making decisions? How rational are you? This is where our rant comes to an end and the dissection begins. Let us play a little game. Elections are only about promises and promises do not hold up most of the time, so we reduce them to a matter of probability. Now, let’s see how you and your choices fare in our mock election. Let there be two political parties, A and B, standing in the elections. Party A promises to reduce unemployment by 20%, with a 100% chance of fulfilling his promise. Whereas, Party B promises to reduce unemployment by 35%, with a 15 out of 16 chance of fulfilling his promise. To put it neatly, Case 1 A: 20% unemployment drop, with certainty (100% Guarantee). B: 35% unemployment reduction, with 15/16 chance. Go on. Take your pick. Is it party A or party B? Who would you bank on for the country’s sake? Ok, here’s a second case to choose from.  Party A promises a 20% reduction in unemployment, only now with a 16% chance of fulfilling his promise. Whereas, Party B promises 35% fall, with a 15% chance. Restating it, Case 2 A: 20% unemployment drop, with a 16% chance. B: 35% unemployment reduction, with a 15% chance. So, whom did you pick? If you happened to pick Party A in Case 1, then you are like the majority, who prefer certainty over chance. For those who chose Party B in the first case, you were ready to take the risk for the greater reward. But there is nothing wrong with either choice, the real game starts with Case 2. Now, what about Case 2? Well, here’s the bombshell. Case 2 is equal to Case 1 with a one-sixth chance. That is, Case 2 is the same situation as Case 1, only with a 16% probability. The change between the party’s probability of fulfilling promises in both cases was proportional and thus, renders both cases to be the absolute same. So if the problem never changed, did your choice of candidates change? From B to A, or A to B? If you did not, then congratulations, you have rational preferences. If you did, then there are more than a few things at work here. Let us try another problem of this sort. Whether or not the government promised to deposit Rs. 15 Lakh in everyone’s accounts, it is always possible another party will make a similar promise in the run-up to the elections. Farmers are definitely in need of severe financial help, so take Party A and Party B who make the respective income-support promises: Case 1 A: Rs 11,000 a year, with an 11% chance B: Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance Case 2 A: Rs 11,000 a year, guaranteed (100% chance). B: Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance, and Rs 11,000 a year, with an 89% chance Who gets the vote, in each case, this time around? Did you choose the same party both times, or different parties? Choosing different parties is a sign of incoherent decision-making. This is because Case 1 is once again of a similar form as Case 2. There has been no significant change in the factors that should influence your decision-making. Yet there will be more than a few instances of people making unidentical choices for Cases 1 and 2. Time to do a bit of explaining. Consider these cases as lotteries. Both Party A and Party B have an 89% chance of not fulfilling any promise in Case 1. But wait? Didn’t Party B promise a 10% chance? So it gives us (100% -10%=) 90% chance of empty-handed farmers. Here, there is the existence of a lottery within a lottery; a compound lottery, so to speak. The lottery within is actually a 10 out of 11 chance of receiving Rs 15000 and 1 out of 11 chance of getting Rs 0. So when it is nested inside the outer lottery of Party B, we get B: 11% x [( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)]   + 89% x Rs 0 Which is essentially, B: Rs 15,000 a year, with a 10% chance and Rs 0, with a 90% chance I know, things are getting discombobulated in your head, but stay with me. Eventually, what we are left with is a much detailed way to re-write and represent Cases 1 and 2 as nested probabilities. Case 1 A: 11% x Rs 11,000 +   89% x Rs 0 B: 11% x [( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)]   +  89% x Rs 0 Case 2 A: 11% x Rs 11,000 +   89% x Rs 11,000 B: 11% x [( 10/11 x Rs 15000)+(1/11 x Rs 0)]   + 89% x Rs 11,000 The parts marked in Red are the actual determinants and the only factors when it comes to decision-making between the two parties. The segments marked in Blue are offered by both parties and thus, should not be a determining factor in rational choosing. So if you ended up choosing A in Case 1 and B in Case 2 (or vice versa), you have just chosen two different answers for the same problem. Do you see it now? That is where rational preferences are violated and we can now find our irrational voter. After all this, we come to the origins of the problem. The lack of coherence empirically observed above is called the Allais Paradox, and has been the talk of game theorists and psychologists for years. First published in 1953, in the Econometrica journal by French economist Maurice Allais, the Allais Paradox was observed among subjects who, when presented with choices such as the ones above, made snap decisions that were proven to be incoherent upon further study. Although not everyone got it wrong, a significant number of people made the error which prompted him to wonder whether there was more than just rationality behind human choices. So the Allais Paradox started off as more of a standout against conventional rationality theory, than as the rationality test that it has evolved to today. Maurice Allais did end up winning the 1988 Nobel Prize in Economics but it was not until 20 years after it was first published, that the Allais Paradox was brought back to the mainstream by Daniel Kahneman. In a way, the Allais Paradox was what got Nobel laureate Daniel Kahneman (2002 Nobel laureate) into economics. He along with Amos Tversky, were two young psychologists back in the 1970s who came across this paradox and were so intrigued by the study of human approach towards uncertainty that they opened up new dimensions in the world of economics and decision-making under uncertainty. Maurice Allais had made one of the foremost and yet perplexing dives into human rationality and for that, today, the world is in a better position to understand human behaviour and decision-making. And while we are on the topic of making decisions, we get back to the decision of the year. This election may be driven by 3 central issues: unemployment, farmers and women’s protection. But at the end of the day, it is the people who drive elections. Yet what we often overlook is what drives the people and their choices. Are we as smart as we think we are? Does being irrational only mean being ‘unreasonable’ or ‘baseless’ as the Dictionary says? Or is there more to this than meets the eye or brain? On that note, we ask you to think twice before calling someone else irrational. Oh, and yes, don’t forget to think twice before voting. Happy elections! *31st May, 2019 marks the 108th Birth Anniversary of French physicist and economist Maurice Allais, best known for his contributions to the neoclassical synthesis and the Allais Paradox.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">CLO’s - The New Danger to Financial Markets?</title>
      <link href="/CLO" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CLO’s - The New Danger to  Financial Markets?" />
      <published>2019-04-25T14:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-25T14:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/CLO</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/CLO">&lt;p&gt;It’s funny to see the people who run financial markets so eagerly rushing into
committing the same mistake. Rushing for what? The same old, usual story. The
enticement of higher profits by undertaking higher risks provides the same high
to these investors as drugs do to teens. The global financial markets, which had
a near-death experience with CDOs just a decade ago, face a new product ready to
facilitate its total obliteration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The product in question this time is CLOs, or Collateralized Loan Obligations.
Believed to be a safer version of the infamous CDOs, or Collateralized Debt
Obligations, which was one of the main culprits of the 2008 Financial Crisis,
CLOs are already raising eyebrows all around the world. With the Governor of The
Bank of England Mark Carney and the former Fed Chairman Janet Yellen warning
about the potential risks, governments and the public are becoming wary.
However, it looks like these warnings are having no effect on banks and
institutional investors, for whom it was intended, as they continue buying CLOs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A CLO is very similar to a CDO which, as mentioned earlier, was the main reason
for the downfall of the financial markets in 2008. A CLO is basically a huge
collection of loans given out by a bank for sale to banks and institutional
investors in small tranches or groups. The benefit that an investor gains from
buying a CLO is that he gets to earn the entire interest from the loans in his
group or “tranche”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the amount of CLOs currently outstanding in the world crossing  $700
billion, and with $100 billion being added each year, the amount of CLOs has
already reached the levels of CDOs before the Financial Crisis of 2008. The
structuring of a CLO is the same as a CDO. The groups of CLOs are rated by
rating agencies on the basis of the overall creditworthiness and mortgaged
assets. The CLO groups are majorly rated into AA, BBB+, BBB- and so on. Within
each individual group, each specific tranche is also rated. Hence, in an AA
class group, there are tranches rated AA, BBB+, BBB- and so forth. The same goes
for the BBB+ class group and all the other groups which follow. The highest
tranche of the highest group is paid first, followed by all the tranches in the
highest group, which is followed by all the groups and their respective
tranches. Hence, the lowest class tranche of the lowest group is the riskiest,
and promises the highest return, whereas, the highest class tranche of the
highest group is the safest and promises least return. This allows investors to
invest in groups and tranches according to their risk appetite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way in which CLOs have differed from CDOs have been stricter banking
regulations and the type of loans which are being put into the groups. Instead
of having only housing loans, CLOs offer a wide variety of loans such as
automobiles, housing, retail and so on. Moreover, stricter regulations demand
that banks hold some proportion of each group of CLOs in order to ensure that to
earn a riskless profit, the banks are not just giving loans to any individual
they meet, which happened in the case of CDOs during the Financial Crisis of
2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proponents of CLOs point towards the double-digit returns, low default rates and
resilience to rising interest rates. With banks such as Credit Suisse, Nomura,
Barclays and JP Morgan Chase showing confidence in CLOs due to its high returns
and substantially low risks, the demand for CLOs is rising in international
markets. The industry is stressing the fact that CLOs are not as vulnerable to
rising interest rates as CDOs were a decade ago. They also stress the fact that
only 36 tranches among the 1500 plus CLOs rated by S&amp;amp;P Global Ratings have
defaulted since 1994.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are downfalls. Investors assume that the portfolios are safer as
they are better diversified. But, diversification of portfolios has led to them
being made of fewer and larger loans, which increases concentration risk. These
leveraged loans are highly sensitive to economic conditions, with many loans
defaulting as soon as the economic conditions take a downturn. The condition
will be particularly adverse for Japanese banks, which have bought 75% of AAA
tranches and one-third of all CLOs, finance their operations by borrowing from
international markets. Losses can lead to difficulties in continuing operations,
which in turn may lead to a liquidity squeeze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of a downturn, the CLOs pose a risk of creating adverse feedback
loops. Banks will be stuck with unsold loans clogging up inventories due to a
decrease in demand. Falling prices and tightening credit availability will cause
credit markets to seize up. Tighter credit will feed into the real economy
triggering losses, selling and price declines. Fears about the financial
positions of banks and investors will create havoc as depositors refuse to fund
banks and investors demand their money back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, it is clear that governments need to set in motion regulations and a
robust framework on how to go about dealing with CLOs. This is extremely
necessary as everyone today is accepting the fact that CLOs are a potentially
dangerous item capable of causing devastating chaos in the international
markets. Still, banks and institutional investors are pouring money into this
product with the hopes of higher returns from the higher risks they undertake.
It is clear that CLOs have the capability to topple the global financial markets
if it spirals out of control. Therefore, with the world talking of another
financial crisis, the question that needs to be answered is will it be the
phoenix of CDOs that proves to be the catalyst? The danger that currently
beholds us is that if we keep allowing investment junkies to get their
risk-fuelled fix, it will be the rest of us left to pick up the tab if the
international financial system enters rehab.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhishek Sancheti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It’s funny to see the people who run financial markets so eagerly rushing into committing the same mistake. Rushing for what? The same old, usual story. The enticement of higher profits by undertaking higher risks provides the same high to these investors as drugs do to teens. The global financial markets, which had a near-death experience with CDOs just a decade ago, face a new product ready to facilitate its total obliteration. The product in question this time is CLOs, or Collateralized Loan Obligations. Believed to be a safer version of the infamous CDOs, or Collateralized Debt Obligations, which was one of the main culprits of the 2008 Financial Crisis, CLOs are already raising eyebrows all around the world. With the Governor of The Bank of England Mark Carney and the former Fed Chairman Janet Yellen warning about the potential risks, governments and the public are becoming wary. However, it looks like these warnings are having no effect on banks and institutional investors, for whom it was intended, as they continue buying CLOs. A CLO is very similar to a CDO which, as mentioned earlier, was the main reason for the downfall of the financial markets in 2008. A CLO is basically a huge collection of loans given out by a bank for sale to banks and institutional investors in small tranches or groups. The benefit that an investor gains from buying a CLO is that he gets to earn the entire interest from the loans in his group or “tranche”. With the amount of CLOs currently outstanding in the world crossing  $700 billion, and with $100 billion being added each year, the amount of CLOs has already reached the levels of CDOs before the Financial Crisis of 2008. The structuring of a CLO is the same as a CDO. The groups of CLOs are rated by rating agencies on the basis of the overall creditworthiness and mortgaged assets. The CLO groups are majorly rated into AA, BBB+, BBB- and so on. Within each individual group, each specific tranche is also rated. Hence, in an AA class group, there are tranches rated AA, BBB+, BBB- and so forth. The same goes for the BBB+ class group and all the other groups which follow. The highest tranche of the highest group is paid first, followed by all the tranches in the highest group, which is followed by all the groups and their respective tranches. Hence, the lowest class tranche of the lowest group is the riskiest, and promises the highest return, whereas, the highest class tranche of the highest group is the safest and promises least return. This allows investors to invest in groups and tranches according to their risk appetite. The only way in which CLOs have differed from CDOs have been stricter banking regulations and the type of loans which are being put into the groups. Instead of having only housing loans, CLOs offer a wide variety of loans such as automobiles, housing, retail and so on. Moreover, stricter regulations demand that banks hold some proportion of each group of CLOs in order to ensure that to earn a riskless profit, the banks are not just giving loans to any individual they meet, which happened in the case of CDOs during the Financial Crisis of 2008. Proponents of CLOs point towards the double-digit returns, low default rates and resilience to rising interest rates. With banks such as Credit Suisse, Nomura, Barclays and JP Morgan Chase showing confidence in CLOs due to its high returns and substantially low risks, the demand for CLOs is rising in international markets. The industry is stressing the fact that CLOs are not as vulnerable to rising interest rates as CDOs were a decade ago. They also stress the fact that only 36 tranches among the 1500 plus CLOs rated by S&amp;amp;P Global Ratings have defaulted since 1994. However, there are downfalls. Investors assume that the portfolios are safer as they are better diversified. But, diversification of portfolios has led to them being made of fewer and larger loans, which increases concentration risk. These leveraged loans are highly sensitive to economic conditions, with many loans defaulting as soon as the economic conditions take a downturn. The condition will be particularly adverse for Japanese banks, which have bought 75% of AAA tranches and one-third of all CLOs, finance their operations by borrowing from international markets. Losses can lead to difficulties in continuing operations, which in turn may lead to a liquidity squeeze. In the case of a downturn, the CLOs pose a risk of creating adverse feedback loops. Banks will be stuck with unsold loans clogging up inventories due to a decrease in demand. Falling prices and tightening credit availability will cause credit markets to seize up. Tighter credit will feed into the real economy triggering losses, selling and price declines. Fears about the financial positions of banks and investors will create havoc as depositors refuse to fund banks and investors demand their money back. Hence, it is clear that governments need to set in motion regulations and a robust framework on how to go about dealing with CLOs. This is extremely necessary as everyone today is accepting the fact that CLOs are a potentially dangerous item capable of causing devastating chaos in the international markets. Still, banks and institutional investors are pouring money into this product with the hopes of higher returns from the higher risks they undertake. It is clear that CLOs have the capability to topple the global financial markets if it spirals out of control. Therefore, with the world talking of another financial crisis, the question that needs to be answered is will it be the phoenix of CDOs that proves to be the catalyst? The danger that currently beholds us is that if we keep allowing investment junkies to get their risk-fuelled fix, it will be the rest of us left to pick up the tab if the international financial system enters rehab.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Industrial Corridors in India: A New Vehicle for Industrialisation</title>
      <link href="/Industrial-Corridors-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Industrial Corridors in India: A New Vehicle for Industrialisation" />
      <published>2019-04-19T23:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-19T23:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Industrial-Corridors-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Industrial-Corridors-India">&lt;p&gt;According to a Briefing Paper prepared for the UK’s House of Commons, China’s
share as a percentage of world manufacturing is 20% and as a percentage of its
GDP, it is 27%. In contrast, for India, the corresponding figures stand dismally
at 4% and 16% respectively. The Report has taken manufacturing output in 2015 as
the basis, using 2005 exchange rates. The burgeoning services sector
contribution to India’s GDP during the last decade has gone past 60%, whereas
the contribution of manufacturing activity to GDP has remained virtually
stagnant. This clearly indicates that India has been quick to adopt
technological advances in the services sector, but has failed to encourage
manufacturing entrepreneurship. Over the years, a clear need has been felt to
boost manufacturing activity in India. Mass consumerization of Indian society
due to rising disposable income and increased rural electrification have led to
a rise in demand for electronic consumer goods. It is expected to reach ₹3.15
trillion in the year 2022. If quality domestic products are not available,
people will buy imported goods. All this has further added to the necessity of
manufacturing led industrialisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to boost domestic manufacturing, the Indian Government tried to emulate
the Chinese experience as China had immensely benefited from its SEZ (Special
Economic Zones) policy. On similar lines, India enacted the SEZ Act in 2005.
However, Indian SEZs lacked the all-important connectivity to ports and thus,
failed to augment manufacturing activity in the country. It is this realisation
that has resulted in the introduction of the concept of industrial corridors
that is modelled on similar corridors in Japan and China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is an Industrial Corridor?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An industrial corridor or economic corridor is a pathway comprising
manufacturing clusters, ancillary units and smart cities connected with rail,
road, air or sea links. The Indian government has envisaged five integrated
industrial corridors across the country in partnership with the respective State
governments. The National Industrial Corridor Development &amp;amp; Implementation Trust
(NICDIT) has been established as the apex body to oversee development of all
industrial corridors across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dmicdc.com/about-DMICDC&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Industrial_Corridors.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Source:&lt;/b&gt; http://www.dmicdc.com/about-DMICDC
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Industrial Corridor as Wheels of Progress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industrial corridors recognise the interdependence of various sectors of the
economy and offer effective integration between industry and infrastructure
leading to overall socio-economic development. Industrial corridors lead to the
creation of state-of-art infrastructure such as high-speed transportation
(rail/road) networks, ports with advanced cargo handling equipment, modern
airports, special economic regions/ industrial areas, logistic parks, etc. that
are focused on fulfilling the requirements of the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The late C.K. Prahalad, a renowned management expert, had said that over the
next three decades if India does not create new cities to accommodate a whopping
500 million people desirous of urban life, every existing city would become a
slum. The establishment of manufacturing zones along the industrial corridors
will prevent distress migration and provide people with job opportunities close
to their dwelling place. The new smart cities created will mark the beginning of
a new wave of urbanisation in India and reduce pressure on existing cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The buzz word connecting the various programmes PM of Modi’s Government - Make
in India, Digital India, and Skill India - is employment generation. Smart
cities and industrial corridors are no exceptions. The educational institutions,
roads, railways, airports, hospitals that will come up in these corridors is
expected to generate employment and raise the overall standard of living. The
government is targeting 100 million new jobs through industrial corridors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Way Forward&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘The wheels of progress’ are encountering a plethora of issues on their road to
success, however. Of all the issues, acquisition of land at a snail’s pace is
the single biggest concern owing to the Right to Fair Compensation and
Transparency in Land Acquisition, Rehabilitation and Resettlement Act, 2013. To
take an example, the $100-billion Delhi-Mumbai Industrial Corridor (DMIC) was
expected to be completed in three phases spread over nine years starting from
January 2008. However, owing to mostly land acquisition issues, the first phase
is likely to be completed by December 2019 and revised deadlines for the second
phase and third phase have already been shifted to 2027 and 2037. The
governments at both India’s Central and State levels need to work out a
comprehensive land acquisition policy and not approach this issue in a piecemeal
manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, as India lacks technological expertise, it is prudent to bring in
foreign direct investment through established foreign entities that have the
required skill. At the same time, it is also important to encourage Indian
investment in setting up ancillary units in the same sector. This will provide
for smooth backward integration by ensuring regular supply of raw materials and
forward integration by providing ready markets. For example, the Chennai to
Bengaluru defence production corridor in India’s southern States will pass
through towns such as Trichy, Coimbatore, Salem and Hosur and will connect
ordnance factories and defence public sector units to ancillary units (which are
small and medium scale industries in the said corridor). The supplies from these
units to factories and Public Sector Undertakings is an example of forward
integration and purchases by the latter is backward integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, in order to encourage FDI, the government needs to rationalise the tax
structure. India’s corporate tax rate is high in comparison to many ASEAN
countries and stands at 30%. It is 20% in Cambodia, Thailand and Vietnam.
Moreover, India also has very high import tariffs that make manufacturing of
products with imported components economically unviable or expensive as compared
to countries like Taiwan. To achieve success, the government should rationalise
the tariff structure, realising that it is export promotion not import
prevention that actually benefits an economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategy of industrial corridors is poised to develop a sound industrial
base, characterised by excellent infrastructure and uninhibited growth of
manufacturing. However, all this would remain only rhetoric if stumbling blocks
are not removed and issues plaguing industrial corridor projects are not
resolved. This requires a holistic approach and involvement of all the
government departments, stakeholders such as farmers from whom land is to be
acquired, manufacturers who would be setting units for production, transport
operators, etc. With the onset of election season in India, it would be naive to
assume anyone has the time to truly calibrate policy, but with a new Government
and new ambitions post elections, one can only hope that the Industrial
Corridors project will take on new heights.  &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">According to a Briefing Paper prepared for the UK’s House of Commons, China’s share as a percentage of world manufacturing is 20% and as a percentage of its GDP, it is 27%. In contrast, for India, the corresponding figures stand dismally at 4% and 16% respectively. The Report has taken manufacturing output in 2015 as the basis, using 2005 exchange rates. The burgeoning services sector contribution to India’s GDP during the last decade has gone past 60%, whereas the contribution of manufacturing activity to GDP has remained virtually stagnant. This clearly indicates that India has been quick to adopt technological advances in the services sector, but has failed to encourage manufacturing entrepreneurship. Over the years, a clear need has been felt to boost manufacturing activity in India. Mass consumerization of Indian society due to rising disposable income and increased rural electrification have led to a rise in demand for electronic consumer goods. It is expected to reach ₹3.15 trillion in the year 2022. If quality domestic products are not available, people will buy imported goods. All this has further added to the necessity of manufacturing led industrialisation. In order to boost domestic manufacturing, the Indian Government tried to emulate the Chinese experience as China had immensely benefited from its SEZ (Special Economic Zones) policy. On similar lines, India enacted the SEZ Act in 2005. However, Indian SEZs lacked the all-important connectivity to ports and thus, failed to augment manufacturing activity in the country. It is this realisation that has resulted in the introduction of the concept of industrial corridors that is modelled on similar corridors in Japan and China. What is an Industrial Corridor? An industrial corridor or economic corridor is a pathway comprising manufacturing clusters, ancillary units and smart cities connected with rail, road, air or sea links. The Indian government has envisaged five integrated industrial corridors across the country in partnership with the respective State governments. The National Industrial Corridor Development &amp;amp; Implementation Trust (NICDIT) has been established as the apex body to oversee development of all industrial corridors across the country. Source: http://www.dmicdc.com/about-DMICDC Industrial Corridor as Wheels of Progress Industrial corridors recognise the interdependence of various sectors of the economy and offer effective integration between industry and infrastructure leading to overall socio-economic development. Industrial corridors lead to the creation of state-of-art infrastructure such as high-speed transportation (rail/road) networks, ports with advanced cargo handling equipment, modern airports, special economic regions/ industrial areas, logistic parks, etc. that are focused on fulfilling the requirements of the industry. The late C.K. Prahalad, a renowned management expert, had said that over the next three decades if India does not create new cities to accommodate a whopping 500 million people desirous of urban life, every existing city would become a slum. The establishment of manufacturing zones along the industrial corridors will prevent distress migration and provide people with job opportunities close to their dwelling place. The new smart cities created will mark the beginning of a new wave of urbanisation in India and reduce pressure on existing cities. The buzz word connecting the various programmes PM of Modi’s Government - Make in India, Digital India, and Skill India - is employment generation. Smart cities and industrial corridors are no exceptions. The educational institutions, roads, railways, airports, hospitals that will come up in these corridors is expected to generate employment and raise the overall standard of living. The government is targeting 100 million new jobs through industrial corridors.   The Way Forward ‘The wheels of progress’ are encountering a plethora of issues on their road to success, however. Of all the issues, acquisition of land at a snail’s pace is the single biggest concern owing to the Right to Fair Compensation and Transparency in Land Acquisition, Rehabilitation and Resettlement Act, 2013. To take an example, the $100-billion Delhi-Mumbai Industrial Corridor (DMIC) was expected to be completed in three phases spread over nine years starting from January 2008. However, owing to mostly land acquisition issues, the first phase is likely to be completed by December 2019 and revised deadlines for the second phase and third phase have already been shifted to 2027 and 2037. The governments at both India’s Central and State levels need to work out a comprehensive land acquisition policy and not approach this issue in a piecemeal manner. Secondly, as India lacks technological expertise, it is prudent to bring in foreign direct investment through established foreign entities that have the required skill. At the same time, it is also important to encourage Indian investment in setting up ancillary units in the same sector. This will provide for smooth backward integration by ensuring regular supply of raw materials and forward integration by providing ready markets. For example, the Chennai to Bengaluru defence production corridor in India’s southern States will pass through towns such as Trichy, Coimbatore, Salem and Hosur and will connect ordnance factories and defence public sector units to ancillary units (which are small and medium scale industries in the said corridor). The supplies from these units to factories and Public Sector Undertakings is an example of forward integration and purchases by the latter is backward integration. Thirdly, in order to encourage FDI, the government needs to rationalise the tax structure. India’s corporate tax rate is high in comparison to many ASEAN countries and stands at 30%. It is 20% in Cambodia, Thailand and Vietnam. Moreover, India also has very high import tariffs that make manufacturing of products with imported components economically unviable or expensive as compared to countries like Taiwan. To achieve success, the government should rationalise the tariff structure, realising that it is export promotion not import prevention that actually benefits an economy. The strategy of industrial corridors is poised to develop a sound industrial base, characterised by excellent infrastructure and uninhibited growth of manufacturing. However, all this would remain only rhetoric if stumbling blocks are not removed and issues plaguing industrial corridor projects are not resolved. This requires a holistic approach and involvement of all the government departments, stakeholders such as farmers from whom land is to be acquired, manufacturers who would be setting units for production, transport operators, etc. With the onset of election season in India, it would be naive to assume anyone has the time to truly calibrate policy, but with a new Government and new ambitions post elections, one can only hope that the Industrial Corridors project will take on new heights.  </summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Bike-Sharing: Ending Soon?</title>
      <link href="/Bike-Sharing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bike-Sharing: Ending Soon?" />
      <published>2019-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Bike-Sharing</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Bike-Sharing">&lt;p&gt;In the past few years, what scholars term the ‘sharing economy’ has attracted tremendous attention and massive venture capital. Prominent platforms such as Airbnb  and Uber  are experiencing explosive growth, which has led to both virtues and detriments. Advocates of the sharing economy claim the system yields positive outcomes such as empowerment of ordinary people, efficiency in commerce and even lower carbon footprints. On the other hand, critics accuse it of promoting economic self-interest rather than sharing and decry it as being exploitative and predatory. Today, bike-sharing services are among the most prevalent start-up business models purportedly constituting the sharing economy. Comparable to other businesses of its kind however, bike-sharing companies have begun encountering issues ranging from regulatory hurdles to unethical business practices, vandalism and theft to uncooperative customers and communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharing remains a routine practice even today: families sharing the rewards of their labour, communities sharing access to resources and countries sharing intelligence, among other examples. While ‘sharing’ is as old as humankind, the ‘sharing economy’ in its current understanding is a fairly recent concept. However, despite its instant growth and enormous popularity among consumers, it is extremely perplexing to propose a universally applicable definition for ‘sharing economy’, especially one that reflects clarity whilst also addressing the variety of ways in which the term is used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The generic meaning of ‘sharing’ omits methods of exchange that involve a monetary connotation, which means schemes based on peer-to-peer (P2P) asset dealings should be excluded from the sharing economy. However, if we elucidate that access to an asset can be shared instead of the asset itself, the attachment of a monetary implication becomes irrelevant and activities based on peer-to-peer asset sharing should be included in the sharing economy. Due to its ambiguous definition, scholars today consider ‘sharing economy’ an umbrella term with a variety of meanings. It is, however, most appropriate to think of it as a marketplace that connects individuals on a peer-to-peer basis, enabling them to share assets that are otherwise underutilised and idling in exchange for a price. A sharing economy, thus, offers an economical and convenient alternative to actually purchasing the asset, since the cost of sharing is considerably lower than the cost incurred on owning the asset. Hence, this model can also be called a ‘collaborative economy’ or a ‘peer economy’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise of this ‘peer economy’ has been highly transformative over recent years. It has altered the way we commute, lodge, holiday and borrow, by employing ‘dead capital’ in more productive fashions. Accredited with altering the way we commute, among other examples, is the bike-sharing industry. It has received increasing spotlight in recent years for enlarging mobility options and lowering transportation costs for consumers. The bike-sharing industry has augmented the use of public transport, reduced traffic congestion and fuel consumption, delivered health benefits and improved environmental awareness among the public. It also acts as a resort to the ‘first mile-last mile’ problem of transit. Bixi, a bike-sharing company,  proudly professes that it has helped reduce over 3 million pounds of greenhouse gases in Montreal in 2009. Another such program that began in France in 2005 or so claims it has saved the equivalent of 18.6 million pounds of carbon dioxide pollution from the atmosphere in a year. In 2008, 28% of Vélib’s  customers, a bike-sharing company based out of Paris, stated they were less likely to use their personal vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the question is, is the bike-sharing industry truly a part of the sharing economy? Undertakings in the sharing economy are immensely diverse. TaskRabbit, an errands site, is considered a part of it but Mechanical Turk, Amazon’s online labour market, is not. Airbnb  is virtually synonymous with the sharing economy, but conventional bed and breakfasts are rarely included in it. Even though they serve similar agendas, public libraries, community centers and parks are not counted in the sharing economy. When Juliet Schor, Professor of Sociology at Boston College, presented these puzzles to a few scholars, they gave a pragmatic response rather than an analytical one: “self-definition by the platforms and the press defines who is in and who is out”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, most bike-sharing companies function as business-to-peer organisations rather than peer-to-peer organisations. This stands in violation of the ‘peer-to-peer sharing’ characteristic of a sharing economy that we established earlier in this article. Technically, an ideal model of the peer economy involves a company, customers and non-company owners of the physical asset providing customers a service, in this case, bikes. My view is that bike-sharing companies contravene &lt;em&gt;marketing ethics&lt;/em&gt; by advertising themselves as part of the sharing economy. These companies themselves own the physical asset. Furthermore, these bikes are neither underutilised assets, nor are they idling: they are perpetually available for customers. Therefore, the honest approach would be to label it a ‘bike-renting’ business rather than a ‘bike-sharing’ business, because bikes are actually rented out to consumers and not peer-shared. Take Uber  or Airbnb  as examples to compare bike-sharing with the true model of a sharing business. We find that genuine sharing-companies work as aggregators of vendors and partners who are simply connected to customers, in exchange for a commission for this straightforward networking service. On the contrary, bike-sharing companies act as vendors themselves, and instead of a commission, charge the entire price upon renting the bikes independently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of ethical conduct and positioning of these companies as a part of the sharing economy further deepens on evaluating their core strategy. Given the public affinity to the current wave of peer-sharing, bike-sharing companies, or perhaps more appropriately now, bike-renting companies, are attempting to build a consumer behaviour of routine and habitual renting, leveraging the sentiment of people who find peer-sharing trendy to be the ‘in thing’, or the only resort to the miseries of mankind. This has led to speculations of inflated company valuations, rendering a scar on the industry’s &lt;em&gt;financial ethics&lt;/em&gt;, besides forming a bubble waiting to burst as the demand dips after the initial euphoria is over and more players enter the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet another bane of the bike-sharing industry is its eagle-eye for big data and metadata, an agenda that endangers user privacy. Over the last few years, bike-sharing companies have received billions of dollars in funding, but have failed to generate consequential revenue. There is widespread concern as billions are being invested in loss-making bike-sharing companies that have no profit model. These companies consume cash just to build vast user networks in order to justify higher valuations in subsequent fundraising. Despite marginal returns, investors are constantly investing in these companies, with increased frequency and greater magnitude. The real objective for these investors is securing access to millions of ‘tech-savvy’ customers, and surprising enough is their ability to go to any extent to achieve this objective. In fact, Ofo  gave away rides for free when they launched in Chongqing, China. Users were merely required to register on the online app, and free rides they got. As a result of technological advancements and innovations, most bike-sharing companies today operate through online applications. External players like investors and content creators, are hungry for access to online user information from as many sources as possible, so as to build a massive customer network for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies like Chinese e-commerce giant Alibaba, whose financial affiliate, Ant Financial, is an investor for the bike-sharing company Ofo, are exploring opportunities to deliver other products and services to these digital customers they are monitoring on the aforementioned applications. “They are keen to access valuable data on users’ commuting habits and rental history”, says Zhou Wei, founder of China Creation Ventures. “These bike services are of high strategic importance to Alibaba and Tencent. It is an indispensable way to get data on frequent users”. Access to user data also provides information on a person’s credit history, social media conduct, and online shopping habits. Surveillance like this reveals our individual details to unidentified players who establish ‘&lt;em&gt;echo chambers&lt;/em&gt;’ and ‘&lt;em&gt;filter bubbles&lt;/em&gt;’ on our network so as to create custom content and influence our online buying and selling activities, news feeds and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another allegation that social activists and governments always shower bike-sharing companies with is the ‘bring-your-own-helmet’ practice, which helps these companies evade liability towards the safety of their customers. In a recent case, an 11-year old boy riding an Ofo  bike met with a fatal accident in Shanghai when he was hit by a bus. Road safety laws in China prohibit children under the age of 12 from riding bikes on public roads. However, bike-sharing companies have been flouting this law openly. Despite its lapse in allowing an 11-year old to rent their bike, Ofo simply expressed condolences over the mishap but failed to take responsibility for the event. As part of an example from outside China, we may note that only 20% of Hubway riders in Boston bike wear helmets. This means only &lt;strong&gt;two out of ten shared-bike riders riding in heavy traffic are likely to survive in the event of an accident&lt;/strong&gt;. Absence of helmets in bike-sharing services also conflicts with insurance laws, wherein injuries or fatalities may not be covered by insurance companies. The Hangzhou bike-sharing system in China is one of the very few systems of its kind to cover any injuries that riders sustain while using their bikes. The Cambridge Cycling Campaign has also raised concerns over the absence of lights in front of most shared-bikes in China. They are apprehensive over the legal permissibility of the commercial use of such bikes. During the dark, if streets lack sufficient lighting, riders can meet with accidents and the same argument on liability is repeated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding to the problem of traffic congestion, bike-sharing companies are also accused of using ‘bike visibility’ as a mode of marketing. They are heavily investing in a model that perpetually releases bikes into the market but abandons their maintenance and upkeep. In terms of ‘fleet size’, 17 of the world’s top 20 bike-sharing schemes are based out of China. Despite truncated demand, China currently has over 10 million shared-bikes on its streets, 1.5 million of which are active in Shanghai alone. The industry is engaging in cut-throat competition, with the winner title supposedly going to the company that has most bikes on the road. This has aggravated traffic congestion and hence reduced road-safety. Companies are attempting to make regional monopolies of their own: Ofo  operates 2.2 million bikes across China, Mobike,  about a million, and then there are over forty other startups expanding in different parts of the Mainland. “Piles of bikes dumped outside subway stations are now a common sight”, says Yang Fengchun, a professor at Peking University’s School of Government. This is happening due to the lack of docking facilities in urban cities. Bike-sharing companies are saving costs by not installing adequate docking stations. Even if the companies operate on a dock-less model, they have dusted their hands off the responsibility to manage bikes that clog public streets, parks, condominiums, sidewalks and office areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Non-cooperating communities also play a major role in the theft and vandalism of shared-bikes. In an interesting case recently, bike-sharing went on to symbolise inequality and discrimination for the economically backward black community residing in peripheral parts of San Francisco. The launch of the Ford GoBike  scheme became a scapegoat for people who were distressed due to the housing crisis and troubled by the problem of rising income inequalities. They identified the bike-sharing trend as an indulgence of rich techies, hipsters and young professionals, who used them to commute to popular coffee shops and high-end food joints. Bike-sharing has hence been criticised in localities that lack efficient and organised city services. In such an environment, the industry produces more adversaries than peers, thus encouraging unethical practices and inappropriate conduct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, several bike-sharing companies have had to seal operations from time to time. Wukong Bicycle  lost 90% of its bikes to theft and vandalism, hence having to end operations in June 2017. In a similar case in November 2017, Bluegogo  declared bankruptcy since most of its bikes had either been stolen or wrecked, leaving no other option for the company but to shut down operations. Outside China, the state of affairs is no better. Seattle ended its Pronto  scheme this March; a bike-sharing program in Melbourne also ended in failure when its demand dipped after the enforcement of a law that mandated wearing helmets while riding. Spain seems to have suffered the highest casualties: 65 of the 130 schemes that began in Spain back in 2010 have shut down, half of them concluding operations within three years of opening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, it is also important that we examine the morals of governments. Why are cities being designed only for cars? Why does urbanisation involve more automobiles and not more ‘thought-o-mobiles’? Is it not unfair to disregard people who perhaps choose to cycle due to financial constraints or health motivations? The world is tirelessly discussing climate change and the impact it will have on future generations. Governments themselves are pledging to relegate pollution in a variety of ways. One of these ways is to reduce motorised vehicles on the road. While governments do advocate the necessity of owning lesser cars and using them less often, they end up sponsoring hypocrisy by failing to provide and support alternative measures. The bike-sharing industry could have structured a new way of life by now, where the main mode of transport for citizens was a shared-bike. But, consistent with their neo-capitalistic propaganda, governments are busy building highways and expressways to facilitate motorised commute while resource allocation to boost bike-sharing barely seems existent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can cogently affirm that the bike-sharing industry is not a true manifestation of the sharing economy. In reality, it is modelled more on a rental service than a peer-sharing facility. Further, all evidence presented throw light on a spectrum of problems: several people have lost their jobs and perhaps still remain unemployed with bike-sharing companies having to shut down operations; land, plant and machinery have gone largely underutilised on account of the same; the industry has witnessed numerous regulatory hurdles that include infringement of current legislations and the imperative need for new and more comprehensive ones; the government has been unsuccessful in extracting benefits of the industry for the public; and finally, criminal activity by society has gone largely unpunished. The bike-sharing industry can hence be identified with more negatives than positives today. Bike-sharing companies, the society and governments, all have a role to play in its flawed model of business and sheer disregard for ethics. Though seemingly pacing ahead with consistent innovation and expansion, the bike-sharing industry has begun its gradual decline. It will soon meet its end lest all its stakeholders pedal to survive…&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shivang Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In the past few years, what scholars term the ‘sharing economy’ has attracted tremendous attention and massive venture capital. Prominent platforms such as Airbnb and Uber are experiencing explosive growth, which has led to both virtues and detriments. Advocates of the sharing economy claim the system yields positive outcomes such as empowerment of ordinary people, efficiency in commerce and even lower carbon footprints. On the other hand, critics accuse it of promoting economic self-interest rather than sharing and decry it as being exploitative and predatory. Today, bike-sharing services are among the most prevalent start-up business models purportedly constituting the sharing economy. Comparable to other businesses of its kind however, bike-sharing companies have begun encountering issues ranging from regulatory hurdles to unethical business practices, vandalism and theft to uncooperative customers and communities.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Apple’s China problems ft. Future Apple and the Coase Conjecture</title>
      <link href="/Apple-China-Problems" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Apple’s China problems ft. Future Apple and the Coase Conjecture" />
      <published>2019-03-28T02:03:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-28T02:03:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Apple-China-Problems</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Apple-China-Problems">&lt;p&gt;The Apple craze in China is officially over a decade old. During my days in
China, more often than not, I would take the early bus to Tianjin, along with 20
people glued to the glare of their phone screens. Take a walk across a busy
intersection on a weekday morning and you will find dozens of people marching to
work, busy on their smartphones. Not just any smartphones―the Apple iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/lb38KXlz1F2TllikTfKpV3QKflZ14w92D3AnAwq8xIDHYLYtaELdYAwVWzngy9CZL74x2d-m5T_5E5xvwu8CCnNjQQZdB_1EhYWv6BH0lrHxWevAoriAgQAx-uvdWf0jM9KdcirH&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/1509730264519.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why I did not specify which models are most popular is that the
iPhone craze in China is more about class than tech specs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“The people don’t bother which generation it is, as long as it’s an iPhone”--
Mobile store owner, Tianjin, China
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 4th Generation all the way to the latest models, the Chinese make a big
deal out of the iPhone, even if they are not the ones to show it. Despite this,
Apple’s returns for the holiday quarter have not been good. One may attribute
this to the slowing Chinese economy but there are other factors at play. Things
have turned so bad that Apple has had to scale down its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investors.com/news/apple-chinese-iphones-demand-revenue/&quot;&gt;revenue forecasts by an
estimated $5 billion- $9
billion&lt;/a&gt;.
The announcement (made way back in January) sent its stock
&lt;a href=&quot;https://finance.yahoo.com/quote/aapl/&quot;&gt;(AAPL)&lt;/a&gt; tumbling, falling by about 10
percentage points, though it has managed to recover since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The struggle for Apple in the Chinese market was real and people were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apnews.com/e0a2c907669c4821814763035b562c55&quot;&gt;simply
not buying iPhones&lt;/a&gt; as
they found the price tag too demanding. What seemed to be the problem? Was there
a new competitor on the block? If so, who was causing the disruption?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is pretty simple, it was Apple - yes, Apple from the Future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To break this down, we have to take a look at the Cupertino smartphone giant and
its position in the Chinese market. Yes, they make smartphones, but not just any
smartphone. They are makers of the most sought-after digital product in China.
No, not the BlackBerry. With an iPhone comes class, finesse, style, elegance,
efficiency, exclusivity and a burning hole in the pocket. This is where Apple
separates itself from the Huaweis and the Xiaomis of the market. To be honest,
Apple is a monopoly, with no competition in the foreseeable future. But wait,
our good friend Ronald Coase, a Nobel-winning economist, has something important
to say…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“[A]s soon as the consumers who are willing to pay the monopoly price make
their purchases, the monopolist has an incentive to lower his price and sell to
some of the remaining consumers. Immediately after the next round of sales, the
monopolist would find it worthwhile to lower his price yet again. This process
would continue until all buyers with reservation prices above marginal cost are
served. But rational consumers would anticipate this rapid fall of prices and
wait until the market price reaches its ultimate level before making any
purchases”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that went over your head, do not panic. What he means to say is that in a
market for a durable good (whose resale is not possible) with only one primary
seller (monopoly), once the first lot of goods is sold at a particular price,
the remaining goods are sold at a lower price. Now of the further remaining
goods, some are sold at an even lower price than before and those still
remaining shall be sold even cheaper and this goes on. If a rational buyer
anticipates this and waits for the price to keep falling, he can nab the good at
a much lower price than before. This is what we call the Coase Conjecture. In
effect, the Coase Conjecture holds that a monopolist faces competition from
future incarnations of himself, even though he is the only producer in the
market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if we take an iPhone (any generation) to be a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://bgr.com/2018/05/28/iphone-x-vs-iphone-7-case-screen-scratches/&quot;&gt;durable&lt;/a&gt;
good, as most of the Chinese market prefers it to be, and Apple as the
monopolist, there will be competition faced by Apple. From whom one may ask?
From the Apple of tomorrow, its future self. And as a result, Apple will be
forced to drive down prices to encourage purchases. Oh, look, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.notebookcheck.net/Apple-cuts-iPhone-8-and-XR-prices-in-China-by-20-percent.394146.0.html&quot;&gt;it’s already
taking
place&lt;/a&gt;.
Time to get yourself an iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/ZTgkOCzIQP3kJpWuDzoY5rOmUl3jCg11OTrIRKWgguK_Qc8JXos7VycoRldaD2_HHOTOFTtfklC5r8vT2j8JDSeOcyM1IPjIfgIDQmCm78DiUmHKLevdmnuwMw2le3Yx_MSrDOTk&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/gettyimages-93081350.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people in China know this well enough and this is why they keep sitting on
the iPhones, waiting for prices to drop. That, ladies and gentlemen, is exactly
how most of the Chinese middle class enjoys an excess of iPhones. Nevermind them
showing off models released six years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appears that there is little Apple can do to rid themselves of such a
predicament. They could try introducing a new spec of such a high quality that
people simply &lt;em&gt;have to have&lt;/em&gt; the new model. Or, as an alternative, they could
simply refuse to lower the price of new models for such a period of time that
people are practically forced into a purchase. But neither of these seem like
realistic solutions. The former will likely fail due to the notional loyalty to
&lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; iPhone. The latter will fall short also, as long as older models continue
to function. The question is then, what next for Apple in the Chinese market? Is
there an unexploited strategy waiting to lure the Chinese public into parting
with their hard earned cash, or is Apple destined to be a fashion item?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shohan Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Apple craze in China is officially over a decade old. During my days in China, more often than not, I would take the early bus to Tianjin, along with 20 people glued to the glare of their phone screens. Take a walk across a busy intersection on a weekday morning and you will find dozens of people marching to work, busy on their smartphones. Not just any smartphones―the Apple iPhone. The reason why I did not specify which models are most popular is that the iPhone craze in China is more about class than tech specs. “The people don’t bother which generation it is, as long as it’s an iPhone”-- Mobile store owner, Tianjin, China From 4th Generation all the way to the latest models, the Chinese make a big deal out of the iPhone, even if they are not the ones to show it. Despite this, Apple’s returns for the holiday quarter have not been good. One may attribute this to the slowing Chinese economy but there are other factors at play. Things have turned so bad that Apple has had to scale down its revenue forecasts by an estimated $5 billion- $9 billion. The announcement (made way back in January) sent its stock (AAPL) tumbling, falling by about 10 percentage points, though it has managed to recover since. The struggle for Apple in the Chinese market was real and people were simply not buying iPhones as they found the price tag too demanding. What seemed to be the problem? Was there a new competitor on the block? If so, who was causing the disruption? The answer is pretty simple, it was Apple - yes, Apple from the Future. To break this down, we have to take a look at the Cupertino smartphone giant and its position in the Chinese market. Yes, they make smartphones, but not just any smartphone. They are makers of the most sought-after digital product in China. No, not the BlackBerry. With an iPhone comes class, finesse, style, elegance, efficiency, exclusivity and a burning hole in the pocket. This is where Apple separates itself from the Huaweis and the Xiaomis of the market. To be honest, Apple is a monopoly, with no competition in the foreseeable future. But wait, our good friend Ronald Coase, a Nobel-winning economist, has something important to say… “[A]s soon as the consumers who are willing to pay the monopoly price make their purchases, the monopolist has an incentive to lower his price and sell to some of the remaining consumers. Immediately after the next round of sales, the monopolist would find it worthwhile to lower his price yet again. This process would continue until all buyers with reservation prices above marginal cost are served. But rational consumers would anticipate this rapid fall of prices and wait until the market price reaches its ultimate level before making any purchases” If that went over your head, do not panic. What he means to say is that in a market for a durable good (whose resale is not possible) with only one primary seller (monopoly), once the first lot of goods is sold at a particular price, the remaining goods are sold at a lower price. Now of the further remaining goods, some are sold at an even lower price than before and those still remaining shall be sold even cheaper and this goes on. If a rational buyer anticipates this and waits for the price to keep falling, he can nab the good at a much lower price than before. This is what we call the Coase Conjecture. In effect, the Coase Conjecture holds that a monopolist faces competition from future incarnations of himself, even though he is the only producer in the market. Now, if we take an iPhone (any generation) to be a durable good, as most of the Chinese market prefers it to be, and Apple as the monopolist, there will be competition faced by Apple. From whom one may ask? From the Apple of tomorrow, its future self. And as a result, Apple will be forced to drive down prices to encourage purchases. Oh, look, it’s already taking place. Time to get yourself an iPhone. The people in China know this well enough and this is why they keep sitting on the iPhones, waiting for prices to drop. That, ladies and gentlemen, is exactly how most of the Chinese middle class enjoys an excess of iPhones. Nevermind them showing off models released six years ago. It appears that there is little Apple can do to rid themselves of such a predicament. They could try introducing a new spec of such a high quality that people simply have to have the new model. Or, as an alternative, they could simply refuse to lower the price of new models for such a period of time that people are practically forced into a purchase. But neither of these seem like realistic solutions. The former will likely fail due to the notional loyalty to any iPhone. The latter will fall short also, as long as older models continue to function. The question is then, what next for Apple in the Chinese market? Is there an unexploited strategy waiting to lure the Chinese public into parting with their hard earned cash, or is Apple destined to be a fashion item?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Crimea and Iraq: A Lesson in Economic Sanctions</title>
      <link href="/Crimea-and-Iraq" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crimea and Iraq: A Lesson in Economic Sanctions" />
      <published>2019-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Crimea-and-Iraq</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Crimea-and-Iraq">&lt;p&gt;In an increasingly globalised world, nations are often called upon to intervene in situations thousands of miles from their own borders. This may be in the response to atrocities such as genocide, as happened in Rwanda in 1994. Or, it may be needed to prevent a hostile escalation, such as the one which occurred when Russia annexed Crimea in 2014. It is often the case that the oppressed group is far smaller than its attacker and therefore needs outside assistance. As a result, often through public pressure, countries are forced into action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to such events, the powers-that-be have several tools at their disposal. A more mellow approach could come in the form of a political warning such as a leader’s speech, in the hope that actual, costly action would not be required. The other extreme is military intervention. This, however, has obvious drawbacks such as huge financial costs, loss of life and the risk of civilian casualties. A commonly argued alternative comes in the form of economic sanctions, often seen as an effective, peaceful form of coercion with a lesser risk to human life. However, these beliefs are often unfounded, and evidence would suggest its utility as a form of coercion is minimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prevailing view is that economic sanctions provide the optimal middle-ground between a peaceful approach and military warfare. The former is often viewed as weak, ineffective and more often than not, pointless. Leaders who take this avenue are viewed to be doing so simply to please their audience, possibly responding to public calls for crisis response. Leaders’ statements often serve the purpose of audience appeasement, amid fear of a backlash to inaction. Of course, there are possible arguments in favour of this approach. A powerful country may be able to impose some authority merely through an ultimatum if their reputation precedes them. Furthermore, if successful, it provides a completely costless solution. The targeted country will concede with no cost to the demanding nation. The positives are there, it’s just a shame that words are rarely enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is economic sanctions. These too are a varied tool and can range from action against individuals, such as business leaders, or the political elite, or broader blanket-sanctions on nations as a whole. The underlying logic is that the sanctions will over time cripple a country into submission, forcing them to concede to demands. Although this may cost the sanctioning nation in lost trade, it is usually far cheaper than troop mobilisation or air warfare. However, in the modern world, this is much easier said than done. Most countries are no longer dependant on a single commodity or links to a handful of trading partners. To have any significant impact, sanctions often need to be multilateral, often requiring the support of not just several countries, but from international bodies such as the United Nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was one of the many stumbling blocks with the Crimean crisis. Sanctions primarily came from the United States and Europe. Although together they accounted for a substantial portion of Russia’s trade, they failed to gain the support of crucial Asian states, as a result failing to eradicate their trade links. Russia was able to ease any economic suffering by strengthening ties with China and North Korea. The costs to Russia needed to be severe enough that it would have little choice but to modify its behaviour. As Russia was able to partially circumvent the sanctions and relieve some of the damage, the chance of sanction success drastically decreased. Cooperation from North Korea and China would have resulted in much more severe economic damage, and therefore a higher chance of Russia modifying its behaviour and sanction success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second crucial factor when evaluating the probability of sanction success is the presence of domestic audience pressure. The leader in question, in this case Putin, needs to be accountable to his people, who should have the ability and motivation to remove him should the economy start to suffer. It is clear that a democratic audience has the opportunity, via elections, to remove a leader or force him into policy change. However, a common misconception is that this scenario only exists within a democracy. Work by Jessica Weeks demonstrates that this may also occur in dictatorships, albeit in a different fashion. In a country with a political make-up akin to Russia, a political elite may choose to overthrow a leader if they stand to benefit and have the capacity to do so. This may occur if the elite stand to gain more through a coup than maintaining the status quo, as may be the case during a sanctions-induced economic crisis. In Russia, this was not the case. No democratic audience exists, and Putin has established an elite whose fate is tied to his. So, Putin’s approval rating soared when the sanctions hit, creating an anti-western “rally around the flag” effect as the economic suffering was blamed on Europe and the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empirical studies have shown these two influences, multilateral sanctions, and audience pressure, to be the most important factors. But even then, the success rate is weak. The ground-breaking HSE study into sanction success found only a third of 120 cases to be a success. Even more damning is further work by Robert Pape which showed only 5 of these cases to be successful. In the Crimean case, the sanctions ultimately failed in their objective to remove Russia from Crimea, and given their generally appalling success rate it begs the question, why even bother?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strong answer is that sanctions can be ‘smart’ and limit civilian suffering. A common objection to military action is that they often result in accidental civilian casualties, and if we instead use economic sanctions this will reduce the likelihood of such consequences. But again, this has not always gone to plan. As was the case with Iraq.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a response to Iraq’s invasion of Kuwait in August 1990, the United Nations enforced economic sanctions. The initial aim was to pressure Iraq into withdrawing from Kuwait, and a demand to give up any weapons of mass destruction was soon added. Although the sanctions may have been relatively effective, more noticeable was the alarming impact on child mortality. The economic impacts were severe which, whilst admittedly being the aim, had devastating effects on innocent civilians, particularly children. Some estimates place the number of deaths attributable to sanctions between half-a-million and a million, although there is much controversy surrounding these claims. Further surveys by UNICEF in 1999 concluded that in certain areas, children under five were dying at more than twice the rate they were ten years before, clean water and medical supplies were particular issues. This sheds some harsh reality on the potential cost to civilian life under economic sanctions, to a degree comparable with warfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The saving grace for world leaders is that they may simply have no other choice. Threats are often deemed empty and fall on deaf ears. To save face, action is required, yet military action is often opposed by the public. As a result, some form of economic sanction is required. However, with a success rate between 5% and 36%, this seems futile. The next question, then, is how do we respond to such events? It would be wrong to stand by as a spectator, yet no response seems suitable. Of course, as many scholars have pointed out, long-term solutions provide the best answer. Preventing such disasters from ever occurring is the desired outcome. But until then, a preferable alternative to economic sanctions must be sought.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Stephen McAndrew</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In an increasingly globalised world, nations are often called upon to intervene in situations thousands of miles from their own borders. This may be in the response to atrocities such as genocide, as happened in Rwanda in 1994. Or, it may be needed to prevent a hostile escalation, such as the one which occurred when Russia annexed Crimea in 2014. It is often the case that the oppressed group is far smaller than its attacker and therefore needs outside assistance. As a result, often through public pressure, countries are forced into action.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
