<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/economics/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-01-06T14:35:41+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/economics/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Pubcast on the Indian Economy</title>
      <link href="/Pubcast-on-the-Indian-Econoomy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Pubcast on the Indian Economy" />
      <published>2019-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Pubcast-on-the-Indian-Econoomy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Pubcast-on-the-Indian-Econoomy">&lt;p&gt;The second of The Pangean’s pubcasts is with Mr Achyut Chandra, an MSME businessman engaged in the field of manufacturing printing and packaging solutions. Mr Chandra is the Chairman of the New Market Development Committee of the Federation of Corrugated Box Manufacturers’ Association of India, an umbrella organisation of box manufacturing organisations in India. He’s also the current Vice-President of the Corrugated Box Manufacturers’ Association of Eastern India and is an active member of the Bharat Chambers of Commerce. The pubcast with Mr Chandra is in two parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part I&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(0)&quot;&gt;00:00&lt;/a&gt;) - an on-ground overview of what is going wrong with the Indian economy, i.e. the current slowdown, and a brief overview of the state of the MSME sector, in particular&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part II&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(2246)&quot;&gt;37:26&lt;/a&gt;) - a vision for India’s economy, including a broad roadmap for future prosperity and for unleashing the potential of India’s small businesses&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;audio id=&quot;pubcast-2&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; controlsList=&quot;nodownload&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/Podcast2-final.mp3&quot;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    var aud = document.getElementById(&quot;pubcast-2&quot;);
    function setTime(x) {
      aud.currentTime = x;
    }

&lt;/script&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The second of The Pangean’s pubcasts is with Mr Achyut Chandra, an MSME businessman engaged in the field of manufacturing printing and packaging solutions. Mr Chandra is the Chairman of the New Market Development Committee of the Federation of Corrugated Box Manufacturers’ Association of India, an umbrella organisation of box manufacturing organisations in India. He’s also the current Vice-President of the Corrugated Box Manufacturers’ Association of Eastern India and is an active member of the Bharat Chambers of Commerce. The pubcast with Mr Chandra is in two parts: Part I (00:00) - an on-ground overview of what is going wrong with the Indian economy, i.e. the current slowdown, and a brief overview of the state of the MSME sector, in particular Part II (37:26) - a vision for India’s economy, including a broad roadmap for future prosperity and for unleashing the potential of India’s small businesses Your browser does not support the audio element.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Corruption - Cynicism or Pragmatism</title>
      <link href="/Cynicism-or-Pragmatism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Corruption - Cynicism or Pragmatism" />
      <published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Cynicism-or-Pragmatism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Cynicism-or-Pragmatism">&lt;p&gt;A couple of years back, post the implementation of certain paramount structural reforms, Nigerian social media platforms were bizarrely flooded with a rather idiosyncratic hashtag ‘BBOC’, or ‘BringBackOurCorruption’. The laws that were partially aimed at enabling transparency, accountability and a greater oversight of government revenue, with penalisation for infringement extended to incarceration, did not sit well with the public. The government had apparently stolen the ‘grease’ to their economic cycle, which eventually showed in the levels of inflation in the Nigerian economy as well as in a plummeting Nigerian Naira in international markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corruption is bad. There is a large consensus that corroborates its corrosive impact on society. Macro level studies, that have used country-level data to explore cross country variations in both governance and economic indicators, have managed to consistently establish a correlation between low-income countries and greater levels of bureaucratic corruption. But if we look beyond conventional wisdom, it doesn’t take a genius to figure out that while the former argument is purely moral in its reasoning, rather than rational, the latter is also weak in its inability to establish a coherent causational relation between the two variables involved. Rose-Ackerman (1996), through their works, further helped carve into stone the idea that corruption is detrimental to the health of an economy, leading to the rise of a school of thought that opposed the idea of corruption as a positive for the economy (something which was extensively worked upon by various scholars in the 1960’s). It was popularly believed that corruption ‘sands’ the wheels of the economy. One might never be able to debunk the moral argument against corruption, but as for the empirical data backing the second argument, one must note that for every poor and corrupt African nation, there is an equally corrupt but rich Asian nation, leading many to believe that corruption has got nothing to do with the level of growth in an economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If one had to defend corruption, it would be difficult, nearly impossible, to do so from an ethical perspective. Any possible argument in its defense would be highly situational. But when it comes to the economic perspective, one might become much more tolerant. It is then simply considered a ‘grease’ that ensures smoother functioning of the economy, like a tax you pay to cut through the bureaucratic red tape. Although corruption is popularly believed to be an aspect inherent to socialism, it arises out of a society’s need to come closer to its capitalistic features. In a free-market, demand and supply balance in a manner that ensures that all goods and services eventually reach their intrinsic value in the market, eliminating any arbitrage opportunities for an individual seller, given perfect knowledge. As soon as there is intervention, this cycle breaks down. This is an issue that was highlighted in Ludwig Von Mises’ Socialist Calculation Debate in the 1920’s. Mises argued for the inability of the socialist system to get through one of the fundamental economic problems: what to produce? The state makes that decision and sets the prices, but since there is a lack of market determination of the eventual prices, a seller may not be able to gauge the demand that exists for his product and may end up believing that the prices are not at par with the intrinsic value, that is what he deserves. In order to get closer to that figure, the seller may resort to hoarding a product or charging a little under-the-table fee, and it’s only fair. However the inability to estimate this intrinsic figure is also something that perpetuates corruption. A public servant in India may demand a bribe to get a service done because he feels that his salary is too low to compensate for his efforts. This behavioural aspect may not go away even if his salary is raised, not simply because it becomes habitual but because he tends to measure his reward relatively. Well, also because human wants are never ending (but this has nothing to do with the intrinsic aspect, here he will charge higher for as long as he can). In this example, even if the given behavioural aspect does go away, that is the employee is satisfied with the salary hike, he would be disincentivised from even showing up to work because he is getting a satisfactory remuneration for a job which has no stringent regulatory mechanism and is known to turn people lethargic. This example counter-intuitively explains how a bribe would proves to be much better for the economy than a salary hike for public servants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this perspective offers an analysis based on the degree of intervention, many believe that the existence of corruption is inherent to any developing economy, citing how all the major developed economies of the modern world went through phases of deep corruption and social unrest to get where they are. In fact, Leff, N.H. (1964) found empirical evidence that anti-corruption campaigns in developing nations, like the then-China, depress economic growth by slowing down investment levels. Another argument states that developing nations have a poorly drafted constitutional and policy framework. When they don’t, it is considered overambitious due to their inability to constantly keep up with redesigning policies, resulting in them falling victim to various perverse incentives. This paucity of appropriate laws and policies is an aspect that was hypothesised by Samuel Huntington in the 1960’s. He believed that in such cases the only way to drive growth and revive businesses stuck in legislative red tape is corruption. It becomes a mechanism to circumvent thoughtless regulations in developing nations and provides rationality to the rising income inequality in these economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The uncanny response of Nigeria, a barely developing nation, to the anti-corruption crackdown was exactly what Huntington attempted to explain. The reforms happening at a stage when a majority of the population is reliant on the informal economy was an evident policy mis-step that exacerbated the economy that was already bearing the wrath of low oil prices. This can perhaps help us generate a sound ethical justification because here, corruption is not an optional add-on to the system, it is the system itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A couple of years back, post the implementation of certain paramount structural reforms, Nigerian social media platforms were bizarrely flooded with a rather idiosyncratic hashtag ‘BBOC’, or ‘BringBackOurCorruption’. The laws that were partially aimed at enabling transparency, accountability and a greater oversight of government revenue, with penalisation for infringement extended to incarceration, did not sit well with the public. The government had apparently stolen the ‘grease’ to their economic cycle, which eventually showed in the levels of inflation in the Nigerian economy as well as in a plummeting Nigerian Naira in international markets.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Reasons Why Traditional Employment is Becoming Obsolete</title>
      <link href="/Traditional-Employment-is-Becoming-Obsolete" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reasons Why Traditional Employment is Becoming Obsolete" />
      <published>2019-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Traditional-Employment-is-Becoming-Obsolete</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Traditional-Employment-is-Becoming-Obsolete">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;gig economy&lt;/em&gt;: a term we are becoming more familiar with each passing day.
We are constantly reminded about the rise of the gig economy but only a few
understand the factors that are accelerating this process. In this article, I
will be breaking down some of these factors as simply as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.  Real Estate Prices have been going up&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economicshelp.org/blog/5709/housing/market/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//uk-house-prices.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economicshelp.org/blog/5709/housing/market/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.economicshelp.org/blog/5709/housing/market/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the late 90’s, real estate prices have seen a steady growth rate, with the
only drop being between 2008-2012 during the housing crisis, before increasing
again steadily. With the continual increases in prices, getting office spaces
for large companies is becoming less affordable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. The rise of co-working spaces&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like a new co-working space pops up every couple of months. It has been
estimated that there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://allwork.space/2019/05/coworking-is-the-new-normal-and-these-stats-prove-itt/&quot;&gt;35,000 flexible office spaces covering 521 million
square feet of real estate in the entire
world&lt;/a&gt; - a number that is growing very rapidly. With the increased competition,
co-working spaces are becoming more affordable with far more services becoming
available. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.  Commuting times are increasing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The increasing population density in cities is leading to overcrowding.
Transport infrastructures can no longer keep up with the increased load, leading
to bumper-to-bumper traffic jams and overcrowding of public transport where we
all feel like canned sardines. Besides discomfort, a lot of time is lost daily.
Because of this, more and more people are opting to work from home to get back
those additional hours which they used to waste earlier in travel. And what
better way to do it than to be a freelancer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. There are more entrepreneurs and startups than ever before&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the growth of the digital economy, it has become easier than ever to start
a new business. With access to large markets globally and a wealth of resources
to help push the business forward; starting a business is an enticing option. No
more 9-5 jobs, increased fulfilment, flexibility and so much more have turned
&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/tag/millennial/&quot;&gt;millennials&lt;/a&gt; away from the traditional
job market. With many of these startups being run from home with no additional
employees, most of these companies are more likely to hire a freelancer to
complete any work that is out of their scope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Almost everything can be done online&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New ways of working. A phrase thrown around in big companies all over the world.
With more tools and better connectivity, collaboration no longer requires the
team to be in the same country anymore, let alone a shared office space. Data
sharing and real-time updates have led to a far more seamless online
collaboration. Collaboration tools aside, online transactions are far easier,
safer and more secure than ever before. With the click of a button, money can be
transferred around the world instantaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Reduced barriers to a globalised workforce&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A marketing executive in Malaysia, a programmer in America and ales teams that
span across 10 countries. With the increase in available collaboration tools and
English becoming the global business language, working across borders is
becoming increasingly easier. With further improvements to the laws and
regulations, global-scale projects are becoming the norm. &lt;a href=&quot;https://singularityhub.com/2017/10/22/peak-globalization-is-the-path-to-a-sustainable-economy/&quot;&gt;With a whole host of
benefits to going
global&lt;/a&gt;,
companies are all gearing up for the workforce revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Better Freelancing platforms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, the increased availability of freelancing platforms which
are getting more effective at connecting employers to freelancers. Not only are
they better at connecting collaborators but they also provide a host of services
to make the collaboration as risk-free and hassle-free as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at these seven reasons, it is easy to see why companies are more likely
to downsize their operations and rely more heavily on freelance work. This helps
further develop the gig economy in a continuous growth cycle and someday the
traditional 9-5 job will just be a long-forgotten memory.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Avinash Naidu</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The gig economy: a term we are becoming more familiar with each passing day. We are constantly reminded about the rise of the gig economy but only a few understand the factors that are accelerating this process. In this article, I will be breaking down some of these factors as simply as possible. 1.  Real Estate Prices have been going up Source: https://www.economicshelp.org/blog/5709/housing/market/ Since the late 90’s, real estate prices have seen a steady growth rate, with the only drop being between 2008-2012 during the housing crisis, before increasing again steadily. With the continual increases in prices, getting office spaces for large companies is becoming less affordable. 2. The rise of co-working spaces It seems like a new co-working space pops up every couple of months. It has been estimated that there are 35,000 flexible office spaces covering 521 million square feet of real estate in the entire world - a number that is growing very rapidly. With the increased competition, co-working spaces are becoming more affordable with far more services becoming available.  3.  Commuting times are increasing The increasing population density in cities is leading to overcrowding. Transport infrastructures can no longer keep up with the increased load, leading to bumper-to-bumper traffic jams and overcrowding of public transport where we all feel like canned sardines. Besides discomfort, a lot of time is lost daily. Because of this, more and more people are opting to work from home to get back those additional hours which they used to waste earlier in travel. And what better way to do it than to be a freelancer.  4. There are more entrepreneurs and startups than ever before With the growth of the digital economy, it has become easier than ever to start a new business. With access to large markets globally and a wealth of resources to help push the business forward; starting a business is an enticing option. No more 9-5 jobs, increased fulfilment, flexibility and so much more have turned millennials away from the traditional job market. With many of these startups being run from home with no additional employees, most of these companies are more likely to hire a freelancer to complete any work that is out of their scope. 5. Almost everything can be done online New ways of working. A phrase thrown around in big companies all over the world. With more tools and better connectivity, collaboration no longer requires the team to be in the same country anymore, let alone a shared office space. Data sharing and real-time updates have led to a far more seamless online collaboration. Collaboration tools aside, online transactions are far easier, safer and more secure than ever before. With the click of a button, money can be transferred around the world instantaneously. 6. Reduced barriers to a globalised workforce A marketing executive in Malaysia, a programmer in America and ales teams that span across 10 countries. With the increase in available collaboration tools and English becoming the global business language, working across borders is becoming increasingly easier. With further improvements to the laws and regulations, global-scale projects are becoming the norm. With a whole host of benefits to going global, companies are all gearing up for the workforce revolution. 7. Better Freelancing platforms Last but not least, the increased availability of freelancing platforms which are getting more effective at connecting employers to freelancers. Not only are they better at connecting collaborators but they also provide a host of services to make the collaboration as risk-free and hassle-free as possible. Looking at these seven reasons, it is easy to see why companies are more likely to downsize their operations and rely more heavily on freelance work. This helps further develop the gig economy in a continuous growth cycle and someday the traditional 9-5 job will just be a long-forgotten memory.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Indian Economic Downturn: A Critique</title>
      <link href="/Indian-Economic-Downturn" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Indian Economic Downturn: A Critique" />
      <published>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Indian-Economic-Downturn</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Indian-Economic-Downturn">&lt;p&gt;The recent economic downturn in India has been the talk of the hour. The state of Indian economy is at its worst phase since the Modi Government came back to power in 2019. Having lost its coveted title of world’s fastest growing economy to China, India’s GDP growth rate has slipped to a six year low at 5% during the April-June quarter of 2019-20, putting the Reserve Bank of India’s projected GDP growth rate of 6.9% in grave danger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This decrease in the growth prospects of the Indian economy is largely due to the decline in manufacturing output and lack of consumption demand. This is clearly evidenced by the miserable state of Indian automobile sector, with an 18% dip in overall sales in July, 2019 alone. The worst hit was the passenger vehicles category, which saw a 35% decline in sales, followed by a decline in the sales of commercial vehicles by 25% and two-wheelers by 16%. Many automakers like Tata Motors and Ashok Leyland temporarily shut down their factories and suspended production so as to reduce excess inventories in a situation of weak demand. More than 300 dealerships have been closed and a mammoth of 230 thousand jobs have been lost in the sector. This heavy decline in sales has been caused due to a basket of factors, catalysed by upcoming changes related to environmental regulations and electric cars, and a lack of financing. India’s move to adopt new emission norms from April 1, 2020 has caused consumers to delay their consumption temporarily, partly because of the apprehension regarding validity of registration. A drop in rural demand is also evident from the reduced sale of tractors and two-wheelers in the country. In case of commercial vehicles, an increase in the freight carrying capacity of trucks has shrunk demand for new trucks. Further, an increase in the price of vehicles due to manufacturers having to comply with stringent safety regulations (airbags, anti-lock braking system and other crash norms) has weakened demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has tried to kick start the auto sector by taking steps such as lifting the ban on the purchase of vehicles by government departments, allowing additional 15% depreciation on vehicles acquired from mid-August till March 2020 to lower taxable profits and deferring the increase in one-time registration fee of vehicles until June 2020. However, many economists believe the downturn in auto sector to be cyclical caused by recent developments in the Indian economy which will eventually fade away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real problem comes in when people do not even have the money to buy things of everyday use like soaps, biscuits, tea, spices. The Fast Moving Consumer Goods (FMCG) market is in a lull with slowed down volume growth (number of packs sold) of companies like HUL, Daabur, Britannia during first quarter of the current financial year. On the other hand, the real estate sector is experiencing a downward trend in demand, with 1.28 million unsold houses as of March 2019, a 7% increase in the number from the previous year-end. This slowdown has affected more than 250 ancillaries that have forward and backward linkages with the housing sector, ranging from steel and cement to furnishings and paints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The underlying cause of the poor performance of the manufacturing sector is a fall in private consumption and investment. While turbulence in the world economy has impacted India’s exports, the slump in internal demand is a result of falling rural and urban wages. From having high double digit figures, growth rates of both rural and urban areas has plunged to dismal single digit figures, largely due to structural changes like demonetisation and GST in the country as well as a poor monsoon affecting the agricultural income in rural areas. This has resulted in stagnant per capita income (in real terms) and to keep the consumption expenditure at the same level, the household savings have declined, resulting in a subsequent decline in investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There exists a slow growth in retail loans such as home loans, vehicle loans and personal loans granted by banks and non-banking financial companies (NBFCs) during the first quarter of 2019-20. After the DHFL and IL&amp;amp;FS crisis, banks and mutual funds are reluctant to lend out to these institutions. This liquidity crunch of NBFCs has decreased their lending capacity. Borrowers too are apprehensive of their ability to repay loans in a period of decreasing real income and employee layoffs. Further, an inverted yield curve in the US, a symbol of long term lending rates being less than short term rates, is taken as an indicator of impending global recession. This is because banks borrow at short term rates and lend at long-term rates and the downward sloping curve means that the loans of these banks will become unprofitable, forcing banks to reduce their lending in the market, resulting in decreased economic activity globally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Modi Government has been quick in initiating a recovery process to bring back the economy on track and undoing the damage done by its Budget 2019. The government recently unveiled the mega plan to merge ten public sector banks into four, reducing the number of public sector banks to merely 12 in the country, as part of plans to create fewer and stronger global-sized lenders to boost economic growth. The Union Budget 2019 also talked about injecting ₹70 trillion for recapitalisation of public sector banks to increase credit offtake in the economy. The Reserve Bank of India has also cut the repo rate for the fourth time in a row in 2019 by 35 base points to peg it at 5.4% giving commercial banks a nudge to reduce their lending rates, thus passing on the benefit to customers and attracting them to borrow more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another smart move off late is certainly the transfer of surplus funds of the central bank, worth ₹176 trillion to the Indian government, which will not only reduce the government’s dependence on external borrowings to finance its fiscal deficit target of 3.3%, but also increase per capita income and job creation via increased government expenditure at a time of weakening private investment. However, this transfer will reduce the wide gap between estimated revenue and expenditure by merely ₹580 billion in this fiscal year, because an amount equivalent to ₹900 billion has already been proposed by the Budget 2019 and an interim dividend worth ₹280 billion has been transferred to the government in FY19. The government has further announced the rollback of enhanced surcharge on foreign portfolio Investments (FPIs) as well as exemption to startups and investors from paying an ‘angel tax’ so as to reverse the outflow of money from the Indian stock market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This current contraction in the Indian economy is neither wholly cyclical that is bound to eventually fade away nor is it wholly structural that will result in a massive recession. It is rather a combination of both, with lower per capita income, especially in rural areas, and low job growth being major structural issues plaguing the economy; and low consumer demand and liquidity crunch being the prime cyclical problems. The government has wisely used both monetary and fiscal measures to combat this slowdown, but there is still a lot that needs to be done like new infrastructure projects, affordable housing schemes, modified GST rates, better irrigation facilities and enhanced liquidity of NBFCs. In a time when the private sector is wary of investment, it is only the government that can nudge the economy out of the rock bottom.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sanjana Chandaliya</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The recent economic downturn in India has been the talk of the hour. The state of Indian economy is at its worst phase since the Modi Government came back to power in 2019. Having lost its coveted title of world’s fastest growing economy to China, India’s GDP growth rate has slipped to a six year low at 5% during the April-June quarter of 2019-20, putting the Reserve Bank of India’s projected GDP growth rate of 6.9% in grave danger.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Iceland’s Tourism Story</title>
      <link href="/Iceland-Tourism-Story" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Iceland’s Tourism Story" />
      <published>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Iceland-Tourism-Story</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Iceland-Tourism-Story">&lt;p&gt;Iceland, a small island nation, situated in the Northern Atlantic went from being the 4th richest nation during its economic rise to occupying the center stage role in the financial controversy of 2008. And now, it has become infamous among the economists as an example of “what countries shouldn’t do”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most astonishing part of its journey is that until the 1990’s, the country had very little economic growth, with fishing being its primary source of employment. In 1991, there was a significant shift in the power tectonics of the country and David Oddsson was elected as the new Prime Minister. His ascent to the country’s Prime Ministership changed the fate of the country forever. His Government had inherited an economy built on huge debts, lacking the means of paying them back. This was a result of immense accumulation of unproductive investments made by the earlier governments and to worsen the situation further, the nation’s inflation rate was as high as 20% (which was unbelievably high when compared to other western countries). The stocks of fish, then a major source of income for the economy, began to deplete at an increasing rate. Thus, it called for a change and people voted for it. And oh, what a change did their votes bring!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Government rolled out extensive liberalisation policies: the state-owned enterprises were privatised, taxes were slashed and that paved the way for the rise of the private sector in the country. Fortunately, the economy started to revive gradually, and inflation was brought under control. Thus, began an era of growth and it exploded in the 2000’s. Most significant of all was the deregulation of the finance industry which helped the banks to expand and grow at an unbridled speed. They started holding and managing billions of dollars. An exponential progression from the past. Shockingly, the banks dealt with an enormous amount of money, which was almost ten times the country’s GDP. By early 2007, the country had successfully emerged as the 4th richest nation in the world, and Reykjavik, the nation’s capital, had become a financial power hub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the rise curve was steep and the short term growth misled people to think that they were invincible. However, as swift the rise to power is, the harder is the fall from grace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When everything was going well for the country, the financial crisis of 2008, which affected almost every west-world country, took a massive toll on Iceland’s economy. As the global recession started, the value of &lt;em&gt;krona&lt;/em&gt;, the currency of Iceland, began to plummet and their banks failed the country. Because the banks dealt in enormous volume of money, it proved hard for the government to bail out the big players of the market. Amidst the chaos and tragedy, the country managed to find its way out of the recession far earlier than many of its partners-in-crime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we know, some countries grow off manufacturing and the others off services. Likewise, Iceland decided to grow off the latter. They captured a part of the already gigantic worldwide tourism industry and built up a feasible strategy for much-needed economic development. The country leveraged tourism effectively to bounce back from the worst financial crisis that the world has witnessed since the Great Depression of 1929.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iceland has a serene and pure natural beauty with plentiful waterfalls, lakes, glaciers, geysers: pretty much everything that could attract tourists from all over the world. It has one of the most spectacular natural environments in the world, the country is only a few flight hours away from the richest countries like the UK, the US and others. Accessibility and affordability are two major aspects that tourists look for when travelling. Iceland has been very focused on addressing these two primary concerns to boost its tourism sector. The issue of affordability needed no attention as the fall in the value of &lt;em&gt;krona&lt;/em&gt; made it cheaper for tourists to travel and avail various services in the country. To resolve the issue of accessibility, Iceland had Iceland Air, the national carrier, which by providing attractive fares to the flyers had grown in the trans-Atlantic area, and acted as a boon to the country. This well-reputed airline started more service routes and expanded to different parts of the world. A second airline based in Iceland, Wow Air, was soon launched. The two airlines carried more than half the visitors every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Crisis, word about Iceland spread across the world and grabbed the interest and attention of tourists. This has helped the Nordic nation tremendously in attracting foreign tourists. In one way, the event that crashed the economy had paved the path for its revival. By 2010, the tourism industry was growing by an enormous 20% per annum. As the industry grew, so did the hospitality sector. New hotels began to spring up. Car rentals expanded to carry people all across the pristine country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, Iceland’s real GDP started to grow at almost 7.5% by 2016. Tourism contributed about 10% to the GDP and 30% of the total export revenue of the country. Another central reason for the sudden boom in the tourism sector was immigration. The number of immigrants steadily rose into the country because of the labour shortage and economic boom in the country. They now make up for 32% of the total workforce employed in the tourism industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this is one side of the coin, let’s now look at the other side. The tourism industry is highly seasonal and therefore, can’t be expected to generate revenue and employment throughout the year. This largely curtails the period of growth making it difficult for those employed in the sector to find stable employment. Tourism is an industry where most of the people are low-wage workers with limited scope of growth. Tourism also hasn’t exactly been the go-to industry for those white-collared employees who were out of jobs after the crisis. Then there are the negative effects on the environment due to the excessive usage. As heavy infrastructure is needed to accommodate the exponential growth in tourist visits, they come at the expense of damaging the environment. It has reached a level that excess tourism has become a serious concern for the country. The tourism industry has its dark sides, such as illegal employment, paying workers below the minimum wage and human trafficking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this boom did not last for long. The tourism sector began to experience downfall since the third quarter of 2018. Since last December there has been a substantial fall in the number of tourists in the country. Since December 2018, Iceland started reporting negatives in the growth rate of incoming tourists. In April 2019, this had reached a level of negative 26%. There are many reasons for this sharp and sudden downfall. One of the first reasons is the collapse of Wow Air. Albeit being the second-largest airline of the nation, it had collapsed as it never saw profits and ran out of financials. Consequently, the growth estimates for 2019 were revised to -0.4% from the earlier 1.8%. Unemployment was predicted to reach 3.9% as against the earlier 3.1%. The collapse also meant that the thousands of tourists that were supposed to come were suddenly non-existent. Apart from Wow Air’s collapse, the fall of tourism can also be attributed to Iceland becoming expensive as a result of the appreciating &lt;em&gt;krona&lt;/em&gt; owing to increased GDP growth. If one were to make an intelligent guess, it can also be is simply that Iceland isn’t appealing to people anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it was noted earlier, the tourism boon had devastating effects on the environment. On the other hand, the country did not have the structural capacity to support the huge influx of tourists. Optimistically speaking, Iceland can utilise this period to rebuild itself to expand infrastructure and to restore the lost natural beauty. It can also utilise this time to make plans for revitalising the sector and transforming it into one that can sustain a huge number of tourists and think of a solution to provide year-long stable income stream to the workers involved in this business.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Iceland, a small island nation, situated in the Northern Atlantic went from being the 4th richest nation during its economic rise to occupying the center stage role in the financial controversy of 2008. And now, it has become infamous among the economists as an example of “what countries shouldn’t do”.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Canada’s Climate Combat</title>
      <link href="/Canada-Climate-Combat" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Canada’s Climate Combat" />
      <published>2019-08-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Canada-Climate-Combat</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Canada-Climate-Combat">&lt;p&gt;Global warming and climate change: the two terms widely occupying public discourse in recent times. Something that the millennials would call upon as the mistakes of the past, that scares all the youth reminding them of sci-fi movies which show the looming dark days of the future. &lt;em&gt;Inevitable&lt;/em&gt; as some of us would put it across as. Thus, it is no surprise that movements and protests to combat climate change are picking up in many parts of the globe, especially in first world countries, where the youth is more empowered with knowledge of the future. The world has gone berserk over the issue, and reactions all across the globe seems to be mixed. While the American Government is making news by dismissing climate change and global warming as a hoax and ditching climate pacts, her northern neighbour, Canada is doing the exact opposite. The Prime Minister of Canada announced that the country will create protected marine areas in the Arctic region of the country. This decision comes across as a delight to most around the globe, and here’s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Arctic is one of the worst affected regions in the world. Deterioration of climate has led to a rise in the water level, becoming ominous to indigenous animals. Over the past three decades, the Arctic Ocean has lost an area of sea ice equivalent to Germany, France and Spain combined (2,00,000 sq km approx.). Major power players like the USA, Russia, Canada and China have long been competing to get a hold of the Arctic to extract minerals and petroleum resources promised by the region. In the wake of all these happenings, Canada’s announcement to create Protected Marine Areas (PMA) comes as new found hope. Canada has announced two PMAs namely Tuvaijuittuq (which means ‘ice never melts’) Marine Protected Area and Tallurutiup Imanga, covering an area of 427,000 square kilometres. The federal government and Qikiqtani Inuit Association (QIA) have signed Inuit Impact Benefit Agreement (IIBA) to that effect. QIA is a non-profit society that is designated to safeguard the interests of the minority Inuit community (Eskimos) and has played a key role in pulling off the agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IIBA proposes a two-fold strategy. Firstly, it forbids any anthropogenic activity and the areas are entirely closed from deep-sea mining, oil and gas extraction, dumping, and fishing. Second, it targets at providing sustainable employment to the Inuit community. For this, the government is set to invest $143 million over the next 7 years. It includes the promotion of local arts and crafts, textiles, indigenous occupations and government jobs in research and data collection as well as investments in ship harbors and boating docks. Thus, one can see that the major beneficiary of this agreement is the Inuit community of northwestern Canada. Akeeagok, QIA president, said that by investing in Inuit, the government is paying the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main principles that Economics teaches us is that there is always a tradeoff, and so is there one between economic development and environmental sustainability. Development mostly succeeds at the expense of the environment and has a ravaging effect on it. Canada’s project, however, is an exception. The project protects 14% of the country’s total marine and coastal area, exceeding the original target of protecting 10% of the area by 2020. It also protects indigenous species like narwhal, polar bear, walrus, seal, beluga and the under-ice algae that form a very important base for the entire Arctic food web. Thus, the two notified PMAs will be pivotal biodiversity conservation regions. Further, the Canadian government is actively investing in research related projects so as to support the process to conserve PMAs. It has been announced that an investment of approximately 6 million will go into a scientific research on the impacts of potential oil spills, taken up under the country’s Coastal Environmental Baseline Program, which aims at identifying the long term changes in Canada’s coastal environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this policy is being criticised as a politically motivated move. One cannot dismiss these claims because they seem to be partially true. The Inuit community, on whose betterment the agreement primarily focuses, is afterall a minority group in the country who were the victims of discrimination for ages. Justin Trudeau, the incumbent PM of Canada is seeking re-election in October 2019. Thus, critics term the government’s decision as one to woo votes and win the confidence of the people. Apart from this, the agreement says that “no new human activities will be allowed to occur in the area for up to five years, with a few exceptions.” The question is if a 5-year ban on human activities would prove effective at all and whether the exceptions in the notified areas will be able to serve their true purpose. As it was noted earlier, the activities of the previous decades had deteriorated the condition of the area. While it is uncertain if the 5-year ban will be extended, this short span is not sufficient for a sustainable revival of the Arctic. Thus lies a risk of economic growth coming to a halt and simultaneously no significant development towards environmental restoration taking place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, one thing to be noted here is that prior to the announcement of PMAs, the Canadian government had announced that it would actively explore for oil and natural gas in the Arctic. It is estimated that the proposed area of PMAs contains 56 trillion cubic feet of natural gas and 8 billion barrels of oil. However, the government has banned all activities pertaining to the extraction of these resources. This shows the government’s integrity and sends the message that Canada is serious and determined to battle against climate change. At the end, no matter the motive, what counts is the result. The initiative is one which not only empowers a certain section of the country but also helps the world delay an impending climate crisis and take up arms to promote sustainable development. Yes, agreeing to the fact that PMAs are not a panacea to climate change, it is something to begin with. It will slow down global warming and mitigate the effects thereof. To ensure success, they must be taken up together with other measures to tackle global warming and climate change. PMAs should be notified by all countries that are a part of the Arctic region. Such countries should draw inspiration from Canada and ban maximum anthropogenic activities in the region. A ban on industrial and human affairs in the region will, most definitely, help revive and restore the lost biodiversity and reduce global warming. Thus, hoping for a better future.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Global warming and climate change: the two terms widely occupying public discourse in recent times. Something that the millennials would call upon as the mistakes of the past, that scares all the youth reminding them of sci-fi movies which show the looming dark days of the future. Inevitable as some of us would put it across as. Thus, it is no surprise that movements and protests to combat climate change are picking up in many parts of the globe, especially in first world countries, where the youth is more empowered with knowledge of the future. The world has gone berserk over the issue, and reactions all across the globe seems to be mixed. While the American Government is making news by dismissing climate change and global warming as a hoax and ditching climate pacts, her northern neighbour, Canada is doing the exact opposite. The Prime Minister of Canada announced that the country will create protected marine areas in the Arctic region of the country. This decision comes across as a delight to most around the globe, and here’s why.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Indian Startup Ecosystem: A Global Perspective</title>
      <link href="/A-Global-Perspective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Indian Startup Ecosystem: A Global Perspective" />
      <published>2019-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Global-Perspective</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Global-Perspective">&lt;p&gt;A proud moment for India was to have been ranked as the 5th most startup-friendly economy in the world, in 2019. This was based on five parameters: human capital investment, research and development, entrepreneurial infrastructure, technical workforce and policy dynamics. Despite losing the first four positions to the USA, UK, Canada and Israel, India has come a long way due to various government schemes such as Startup India, Make In India, Digital India, the setting up of the Biotechnology Industry Research Assistance Council (BIRAC) and many more which foster a culture of entrepreneurship and innovation in the country. However, India has lagged behind other countries in two aspects majorly; innovation and taxation. The persistent dearth of successful innovation and the recent ‘Angel tax issue’ have discouraged investors from providing funds to Indian entrepreneurs for the creation of their own startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As per Global Innovation Index 2019, India stood at the 52nd position out of a total of 129 countries for capacity and success in innovation. For a country that is the fifth leading startup- friendly economy globally, to rank so poorly in innovation is nothing short of a disgrace. This lack of innovation is clearly depicted by India’s relatively low expenditure on research and development. Although India stands at the 7th position when it comes to absolute money spent on R&amp;amp;D (after adjusting PPP) with a mammoth expenditure of $48.1 billion. However, this generally isn’t enough, given the large geographical area and population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relative figures show a different reality altogether. India’s expenditure on R&amp;amp;D continues to be as low as 0.8% of the GDP, much lower than countries like South Korea at 4.3%, Israel at 4.2% and Japan at 3.4%. The lack of quality research is evidenced by the fact that many of India’s startups are nothing but an emulation of successful global ideas fine-tuned to serve local needs. Talk about the American Uber and Indians have an Ola. Think about Spotify and we have the Indian version &lt;em&gt;Gaana&lt;/em&gt;. For Amazon, we have Indian competitors, Flipkart and Snapdeal. For Airbnb, we have OYO Rooms. We have the Indian Zomato and Swiggy as replacements of the middle-eastern Talabat. All these foreign startups were established before we Indians copied their ideas and made it our own. One cannot deny that India has become a startup hub with a total of 8625 startups in 2018 across various fields like edtech, traveltech, fintech, logistics and healthtech, yet it is even harder to disagree with the reality that the number of these startups formed out of original new ideas of Indians is laughably low. This is perhaps due to loopholes in the Indian education system that fails to provide the requisite infrastructure, skills and highly-qualified, research-oriented teaching faculty in universities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next lies the issue of the ‘Angel tax’ which has been tormenting the Indian startup ecosystem lately. Angel tax is an ‘income tax’ payable on capital raised by ‘unlisted’ companies via issue of shares, where income refers to the share price in excess of the fair market value of the shares sold. The investors providing funds to these companies also have to pay a ‘gift tax’ on the excess amount. The Angel tax was introduced in India in 2012 with the aim to curb money laundering by various small companies by imposing a high tax rate of 30.9% on all unlisted companies in the country, along with a tax on the investors. It all started when owners of small-scale companies started laundering their tax-evaded income by selling their shares to investors at a price above the fair market value. In reality, the investors got the money to be invested in the companies from the owners themselves and charged commission for helping the owners carry out the money laundering process smoothly. The Angel tax successfully curbed such malpractices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this started creating problems for startups (which are often unlisted companies), when honest angel investors who provided seed funding to these startups had to start paying an exorbitant tax on the excess amount, they began putting their money elsewhere. This gave entrepreneurs a hard time in finding that first cheque to kick start their business, thus, resulting in unnecessary road kills of many good ideas. However, there was a sigh of relief when Indian Finance Minister Nirmala Sitharaman announced in her 2019 Budget that startups and their investors, who will provide the requisite declarations on their returns, will not be subject to scrutiny under the Angel tax. The government also eased the norms for companies to qualify as startups by increasing the upper limit for the turnover of the tax exempt startups from ₹250 million to ₹1 billion. Furthermore, an entity will now be considered a startup for upto 10 years after its incorporation, as compared to 7 years earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India has definitely come a long way, but still has a lot to learn from how other countries have successfully implemented some out-of-the-box policies to create a vibrant startup ecosystem. The global startup economy has achieved great heights with a total economic value of nearly $3 trillion in 2019, a 20% increase in worth from the prior two periods. This growth is largely driven by high-tech startups in the fields of advanced manufacturing and robotics, blockchain, agritech and new food, and artificial intelligence. Meanwhile, sectors such as edtech, digital media, gaming and adTech have seen falling levels of investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some countries have outperformed others in terms of innovation, friendly government policies and entrepreneurial mindset. Israel is one such country which boasts of the highest venture capital investments as a percentage of GDP. The influx of highly educated Jewish immigrants in the 1990’s and the training of people in sophisticated technology, due to compulsory military service, has given a boost to technological research in this small Middle-Eastern country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has played an instrumental role in ensuring that this abundant human capital does not go to waste by providing adequate funding to convert their ideas into businesses. The Matching Grants Programme is one such government initiative that was launched with the aim to eliminate the financial risk associated with the ambiguity in the outcome of a research. The firms simply have to submit their R&amp;amp;D proposals to the chief scientist, and grants are awarded on a competitive basis, with 66% to 90% of the research costs covered. These grants act as high-risk loans, where successful projects repay the funding received via a deduction of a small percentage of annual sales whereas the government bears the costs of the unsuccessful projects. This policy played a major role in boosting the high-tech industry of Israel and made it the ‘Startup Nation’ that it is today. In India, the government does provide funds to startups to carry on R&amp;amp;D, but it does not bear the risk of failure of startup. With over 90% of Indian startups failing in the initial years due to lack of original ideas and innovation, a government policy mirroring Israel’s will inculcate a sense of confidence conducive to taking bolder risks by entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canada is also known for its startup hubs like Montreal, Vancouver and Toronto. Canada has successfully launched and implemented NextAI: the first global programme to build Canada’s Artificial Intelligence ecosystem. It not only provides funding to talented teams and individuals in AI ranging from $50,000 to an additional $150,000 to the top performers, but also provides them with education from AI experts, a network of like-minded innovators and corporate mentors, office space in AI-focused hubs, and easy access to visas to entrepreneurs from abroad. R&amp;amp;D on AI is non-existent in India and initiatives like NextAI must be undertaken in collaboration with educational institutions, the corporate sector and international governments to provide Indian researchers the required expertise and monetary support to kickstart such a programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In European countries, like the UK, private companies help individuals and firms in the paperwork of proving and estimating the costs of R&amp;amp;D for a meagre commission, a facility non-existent in India. This has great prospects in India because this Asian country requires every fund-raising request to go through 14 procedural stages against the global average of 4.3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the single most important aspect which Indians lack is the Israeli ‘chutzpah’, which literally translates to audacity and boldness. Entrepreneurs in countries like USA, UK, Canada, Japan and Germany are risk-takers who are not afraid to fail. Unlike India, where being practical and financially secure is given far more significance than the ability to dream big, failure is merely seen as a learning experience and a stepping stone to success in these counties. The Indian startup economy has not yet seen its full potential due to the timid and risk-averse nature of people, which is reiterated time and again, thus, creating a mental barrier in people. However, India is changing for the better, with a bold, young generation ready to take the risks of having their own businesses. India is treading the correct path. All it needs to do is learn from the best; whether that is innovative governmental policies or Chutzpah, and finally, implement it efficiently in their country.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sanjana Chandaliya</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A proud moment for India was to have been ranked as the 5th most startup-friendly economy in the world, in 2019. This was based on five parameters: human capital investment, research and development, entrepreneurial infrastructure, technical workforce and policy dynamics. Despite losing the first four positions to the USA, UK, Canada and Israel, India has come a long way due to various government schemes such as Startup India, Make In India, Digital India, the setting up of the Biotechnology Industry Research Assistance Council (BIRAC) and many more which foster a culture of entrepreneurship and innovation in the country. However, India has lagged behind other countries in two aspects majorly; innovation and taxation. The persistent dearth of successful innovation and the recent ‘Angel tax issue’ have discouraged investors from providing funds to Indian entrepreneurs for the creation of their own startups.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Capitalist Realism</title>
      <link href="/Capitalist-Realism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Capitalist Realism" />
      <published>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Capitalist-Realism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Capitalist-Realism">&lt;p&gt;The Mayan calendar had prophesied that the world would end in 2012. Various
scientists have predicted that life on Earth will end after an asteroid hits the
planet. All these forecasts seem more or less acceptable to the general
populace. But will communism ever be the next world order? Not a chance. If one
were to inspect carefully, it is easier for us to imagine the end of the world
than to think that an alternative to capitalism exists. It is precisely this
phenomenon that Mark Fisher wrote about in his book, &lt;em&gt;Capitalist Realism - Is
There No Alternative?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalist Realism is the acceptance that “not only is capitalism the only
viable political and economic system but also that it is now impossible even to
imagine a coherent alternative to it.” While there is an acceptance of the many
faults in capitalism, the ramifications of those faults are often neglected or
undermined. Capitalist realism exists because it has managed to become
irreplaceable to us and has killed any sort of hope for a new system to take its
place. The narrative says that though we may not live in a condition of perfect
‘Goodness’, we must be grateful that we are saved from the ultimate ‘Evil’. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalism is vehement in the criticism of any alternatives that may be present - while things may not be ideal, the alternatives are much worse. Here, it draws
power by painting contrasts between democracies and dictatorships, between civil
liberties and stark inequality - where one is shown to be a lesser evil, even if
reality may speak differently. The bombing of thousands of innocents in Syria is
justified, as long as it does not imitate the ruthless persecution or ethnic
cleansing that happened in countries like Rwanda. By characterising itself as a
hail-Mary from the disaster that any other alternative would lead to, capitalism
poses as a protector and gives way to capitalist realism - the foregone
conclusion that what persists is the best out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even for those who realise the problem, there is a severe lack of action. What
could be an explanation for this? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One idea theorised is that the repetition of history has saturated us. In the
time and age we are in, it seems that every action we take has already been
taken in the past. Imagine the despondency of a generation that has come after
history, “whose every move is anticipated, tracked, bought and sold before it
had even happened.” Every act of ours is an experienced cliche, already noted in
the accounts of the past. No protest is novel. The realisation is in itself a
cliche. When all our attempts to create history are old and uninspired, it
eventually leads to a detached witnessing of events instead of active
involvement and engagement. There is a saturation of history, which inspires a
sense of cultural and political exhaustion - almost sterility - into old and
young minds alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger threat of the indoctrination of capitalism is that it has penetrated
our unconscious. Our unconscious shapes our desires, hopes and aspirations. If
one introspects, he/she would realise that our ambitions are driven by a
capitalist narrative - the image of success for us is a rich, privileged
businessman, who enjoys a position of social, economic and political capital in
society. Even while mentally accepting that money is tokenistic and “cannot buy
happiness,” we fetishise money. This acceptance of capitalist aims by society as
a whole and the subsequent trickle down to an individual level further solidify
its existence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strengthening the Roots of Capitalism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is impossible to think of Stalin, Hitler or Mussolini succeeding without
propaganda - their rallies were charged with nationalist sentiment and were
publicised to the extent that the idea of a Great Reich was almost shoved down
people’s throats. But the way that capitalism promotes itself is more nuanced -
the anti-capitalist sentiment is co-opted into capitalism. In a majority of
Hollywood movies, the villain turns out to be the CEO of an evil corporation or
a wealthy fanatic in retirement. Capitalist realism, therefore, is dangerous as
it gets away with including critique within its structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We accept that capitalism has problems - but the way we perceive the solution to
these problems is problematic in itself. Poverty and income inequality are
accepted faults of capitalism. Ask yourself - can we have a world without
poverty? Can we have one where there is income equity? Can an egalitarian
society exist? The answer will be no. Sure, we are striving towards these goals,
but their actual achievement is &lt;em&gt;utopian&lt;/em&gt;. Capitalist realism allows the
acceptance of a state of crisis in a continuum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to challenge this idea is to identify how capitalist realism
escapes our notice on a day-to-day basis. Fisher gives three simple examples for
us to understand this: climate change, bureaucracy, and mental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalism is built on the idea of consumerism. A capitalist state aims to grow
and expand markets continuously. A system that wants to be on its feet
constantly, that is principally in support of bulldozing through time for
profits, can never simultaneously aim for sustenance and stability. This
dichotomy in the theory of capitalism itself is something that often gets
unnoticed. Instead of saying that institutionalised inequalities are a result of
consumerism, the narrative is spun on its head by saying that what we buy is
going to change the principle of the political theory. For example, we are told
to consume alternatives instead of questioning the practicality of usage and
reducing our consumption. Buying the right thing, from the right place is
projected as a long term solution - but it still feeds into a structure that
advocates for consumerism. Climate change can never be solved or dealt with in a
capitalist construct because expansion is the ultimate goal and usage of
resources is a way to achieve the ‘target’. We will always, despite our best
efforts, hold resources secondary to this manic need for material progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberal and neo-liberal societies, while criticising socialism and communism,
highlight the problem with giving excess power to bureaucratic structures.
Bureaucrats often exploit their power and it leads to corruption and
inefficiency in the economy. The winning pitch for capitalism to be accepted
originally was to promise that bureaucracy would vanish. Except, what is the
status quo like? Even in late capitalism, bureaucracy still exists. The
difference is that it is morphed into a different kind of bureaucracy - one that
is allowed to penetrate all forms of structures through things like demanding
memos and answering to superiors. This bureaucracy is enforced at all levels of
management, establishing its place in the micro-levels of the economy.
Capitalist realism further reinforces that we cannot ‘practically’ do without
this culture of constantly answering to someone and being monitored, making the
control of societies a self-enforcing reality. Essentially, capitalism has
failed to differentiate itself from its alternatives on this metric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalism, in its want to create overachievers and socially acceptable success
stories, has created ‘hustle culture’ - one that essentially relies on the idea
that &lt;em&gt;one mustn’t stop&lt;/em&gt;. If one chooses to listen to music instead of a podcast
on the way home, he/she is actively choosing to not add to his/her productivity.
If one does not succeed, the burden of the failure is wholly individualistic -
one must work harder or do things a particular way because regardless of the
kind of burdens one faces (for instance sociological burdens like racism),
anyone who strives enough &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; succeed. As a society, we have
pressurised people to the extent that mental health issues are on the rise among
young people - and no one ties it back to the inherent dysfunction in
capitalism. Instead of taking responsibility for this mass pressurisation, we
have privatised stress to be caused by individual chemical imbalances. By
placing the onus of a healthy state of mind exclusively on the individual
instead of accepting how society has failed him/her, we have allowed capitalist
realism to become our inevitable reality. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we establish capitalist realism’s claim to fame, one must wonder how it
sustains itself. Lacan argues that the concept of the ‘big Other’ in this
regard. The PR image that capitalism creates is sustained by those who are
willing to buy into this marketing. The Other is simply one who experiences life
differently even after knowing what the truth may be. The difference between
what one chooses to accept and what exists primarily sustains the ordinary
interactions we have daily. When the Other accepts reality as it is and chooses
to ignore the narrative that is set out, it creates an abnormality. When
Khrushchev’s speech in 1965 accepted the faults in the Soviet Union, it caused
an uproar. It was not as if people did not know of the kind of human rights
violations and corruption that was happening - the declaration just ensured that
‘the Other’ could not ignore it anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, unlike Khrushchev in the Soviet Union, there is no incentive for anyone
with legitimacy in the Other’s eye to inform the Other of the kind of abominable
structure it is living in. The persons considered by the Other as leaders enjoy
the power that they hold and acceptance of truth by the masses will threaten
their hold over being able to control narratives. Thus, when people who can make
a difference choose not to, it serves to further crystallise capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Playing the Blame Game&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with capitalism is accountability. While, in principle, corporations
are supposed to be the drivers of growth, they do not take responsibility as
they aren’t supposed to look after the welfare of every citizen operating within
the ambit of the care of the government. But the government does not take
responsibility either because it says that its role is minimised and unwanted.
So, any anger towards the system is directed towards an abstraction that is,
thus, unresponsive - someone did something wrong and we are now left with the
burden of cleaning up the mess. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to hold collective responsibility for issues that plague all of us -
like climate change needs to be addressed by each one of us to get any tangible
change. The genius of capitalism is especially evident here - it protects itself
while making individuals scapegoats. For any scandal that happens, we tend to
burden the individual and ask for a more ‘morally upright’ replacement. However,
countless examples of upright individuals succumbing to the pressures and power
of a particular appointment and ending up corrupt are a testament to the fact
that vices are engendered in and by the system - as long as the system persists,
these vices will continue to sustain themselves. Therefore, Žižek argues that
placing individual responsibility due to the need for “ethical immediacy” lets
the system shirk the responsibility of cleaning itself up. He uses the example
of the 2008 credit crisis, wherein the blame was put on those ‘horrible people’
who abused the system rather than on the system that encouraged this culture of
abuse itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the acceptance of the possibility of an alternative to capitalism, none
of these problems will be effectively tackled and capitalist realism will
continue to dominate - perhaps as an unconscious undertone, but with immense
power over our economic, social and political interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Road Ahead &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There may be a glimmer of hope for the world yet. Neoliberal capitalism is no
longer secure in its throne as the days of democratic socialism are on the
horizon. As the study of late capitalism and its critique increases, protesting
voices have emerged.  There is an increasing acceptance of left leaders like
Jeremy Corbyn, Alexandria Cortez, Bernie Sanders, and their policies in states
that have been the poster-children for capitalism. Healthcare for all, free
education and opportunity for the underprivileged are being accepted by a vast
majority of people - especially those who have been victims of capitalist
structures. The gravity of the stark income inequality is being acknowledged and
called out. Corporates and the wealthy are under increasing pressure and
scrutiny to pay higher taxes and fulfil any responsibility they have towards the
less privileged. While capitalist realism paints a bleak picture of us as a
civilisation, perhaps it is time for the sleeping phoenix to rise from the ashes
and take us to a better tomorrow. The cracks in the existing system are more
prominent and visible today than ever before - the responsibility of analysing
them and creating a new order is now on us to fulfil.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aanandi Arjun</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Mayan calendar had prophesied that the world would end in 2012. Various scientists have predicted that life on Earth will end after an asteroid hits the planet. All these forecasts seem more or less acceptable to the general populace. But will communism ever be the next world order? Not a chance. If one were to inspect carefully, it is easier for us to imagine the end of the world than to think that an alternative to capitalism exists. It is precisely this phenomenon that Mark Fisher wrote about in his book, Capitalist Realism - Is There No Alternative? Capitalist Realism is the acceptance that “not only is capitalism the only viable political and economic system but also that it is now impossible even to imagine a coherent alternative to it.” While there is an acceptance of the many faults in capitalism, the ramifications of those faults are often neglected or undermined. Capitalist realism exists because it has managed to become irreplaceable to us and has killed any sort of hope for a new system to take its place. The narrative says that though we may not live in a condition of perfect ‘Goodness’, we must be grateful that we are saved from the ultimate ‘Evil’.  Capitalism is vehement in the criticism of any alternatives that may be present - while things may not be ideal, the alternatives are much worse. Here, it draws power by painting contrasts between democracies and dictatorships, between civil liberties and stark inequality - where one is shown to be a lesser evil, even if reality may speak differently. The bombing of thousands of innocents in Syria is justified, as long as it does not imitate the ruthless persecution or ethnic cleansing that happened in countries like Rwanda. By characterising itself as a hail-Mary from the disaster that any other alternative would lead to, capitalism poses as a protector and gives way to capitalist realism - the foregone conclusion that what persists is the best out there. Even for those who realise the problem, there is a severe lack of action. What could be an explanation for this?  One idea theorised is that the repetition of history has saturated us. In the time and age we are in, it seems that every action we take has already been taken in the past. Imagine the despondency of a generation that has come after history, “whose every move is anticipated, tracked, bought and sold before it had even happened.” Every act of ours is an experienced cliche, already noted in the accounts of the past. No protest is novel. The realisation is in itself a cliche. When all our attempts to create history are old and uninspired, it eventually leads to a detached witnessing of events instead of active involvement and engagement. There is a saturation of history, which inspires a sense of cultural and political exhaustion - almost sterility - into old and young minds alike. The bigger threat of the indoctrination of capitalism is that it has penetrated our unconscious. Our unconscious shapes our desires, hopes and aspirations. If one introspects, he/she would realise that our ambitions are driven by a capitalist narrative - the image of success for us is a rich, privileged businessman, who enjoys a position of social, economic and political capital in society. Even while mentally accepting that money is tokenistic and “cannot buy happiness,” we fetishise money. This acceptance of capitalist aims by society as a whole and the subsequent trickle down to an individual level further solidify its existence.  Strengthening the Roots of Capitalism It is impossible to think of Stalin, Hitler or Mussolini succeeding without propaganda - their rallies were charged with nationalist sentiment and were publicised to the extent that the idea of a Great Reich was almost shoved down people’s throats. But the way that capitalism promotes itself is more nuanced - the anti-capitalist sentiment is co-opted into capitalism. In a majority of Hollywood movies, the villain turns out to be the CEO of an evil corporation or a wealthy fanatic in retirement. Capitalist realism, therefore, is dangerous as it gets away with including critique within its structure. We accept that capitalism has problems - but the way we perceive the solution to these problems is problematic in itself. Poverty and income inequality are accepted faults of capitalism. Ask yourself - can we have a world without poverty? Can we have one where there is income equity? Can an egalitarian society exist? The answer will be no. Sure, we are striving towards these goals, but their actual achievement is utopian. Capitalist realism allows the acceptance of a state of crisis in a continuum. The only way to challenge this idea is to identify how capitalist realism escapes our notice on a day-to-day basis. Fisher gives three simple examples for us to understand this: climate change, bureaucracy, and mental health. Capitalism is built on the idea of consumerism. A capitalist state aims to grow and expand markets continuously. A system that wants to be on its feet constantly, that is principally in support of bulldozing through time for profits, can never simultaneously aim for sustenance and stability. This dichotomy in the theory of capitalism itself is something that often gets unnoticed. Instead of saying that institutionalised inequalities are a result of consumerism, the narrative is spun on its head by saying that what we buy is going to change the principle of the political theory. For example, we are told to consume alternatives instead of questioning the practicality of usage and reducing our consumption. Buying the right thing, from the right place is projected as a long term solution - but it still feeds into a structure that advocates for consumerism. Climate change can never be solved or dealt with in a capitalist construct because expansion is the ultimate goal and usage of resources is a way to achieve the ‘target’. We will always, despite our best efforts, hold resources secondary to this manic need for material progress. Liberal and neo-liberal societies, while criticising socialism and communism, highlight the problem with giving excess power to bureaucratic structures. Bureaucrats often exploit their power and it leads to corruption and inefficiency in the economy. The winning pitch for capitalism to be accepted originally was to promise that bureaucracy would vanish. Except, what is the status quo like? Even in late capitalism, bureaucracy still exists. The difference is that it is morphed into a different kind of bureaucracy - one that is allowed to penetrate all forms of structures through things like demanding memos and answering to superiors. This bureaucracy is enforced at all levels of management, establishing its place in the micro-levels of the economy. Capitalist realism further reinforces that we cannot ‘practically’ do without this culture of constantly answering to someone and being monitored, making the control of societies a self-enforcing reality. Essentially, capitalism has failed to differentiate itself from its alternatives on this metric. Capitalism, in its want to create overachievers and socially acceptable success stories, has created ‘hustle culture’ - one that essentially relies on the idea that one mustn’t stop. If one chooses to listen to music instead of a podcast on the way home, he/she is actively choosing to not add to his/her productivity. If one does not succeed, the burden of the failure is wholly individualistic - one must work harder or do things a particular way because regardless of the kind of burdens one faces (for instance sociological burdens like racism), anyone who strives enough can and must succeed. As a society, we have pressurised people to the extent that mental health issues are on the rise among young people - and no one ties it back to the inherent dysfunction in capitalism. Instead of taking responsibility for this mass pressurisation, we have privatised stress to be caused by individual chemical imbalances. By placing the onus of a healthy state of mind exclusively on the individual instead of accepting how society has failed him/her, we have allowed capitalist realism to become our inevitable reality.  Once we establish capitalist realism’s claim to fame, one must wonder how it sustains itself. Lacan argues that the concept of the ‘big Other’ in this regard. The PR image that capitalism creates is sustained by those who are willing to buy into this marketing. The Other is simply one who experiences life differently even after knowing what the truth may be. The difference between what one chooses to accept and what exists primarily sustains the ordinary interactions we have daily. When the Other accepts reality as it is and chooses to ignore the narrative that is set out, it creates an abnormality. When Khrushchev’s speech in 1965 accepted the faults in the Soviet Union, it caused an uproar. It was not as if people did not know of the kind of human rights violations and corruption that was happening - the declaration just ensured that ‘the Other’ could not ignore it anymore. However, unlike Khrushchev in the Soviet Union, there is no incentive for anyone with legitimacy in the Other’s eye to inform the Other of the kind of abominable structure it is living in. The persons considered by the Other as leaders enjoy the power that they hold and acceptance of truth by the masses will threaten their hold over being able to control narratives. Thus, when people who can make a difference choose not to, it serves to further crystallise capitalism. Playing the Blame Game The problem with capitalism is accountability. While, in principle, corporations are supposed to be the drivers of growth, they do not take responsibility as they aren’t supposed to look after the welfare of every citizen operating within the ambit of the care of the government. But the government does not take responsibility either because it says that its role is minimised and unwanted. So, any anger towards the system is directed towards an abstraction that is, thus, unresponsive - someone did something wrong and we are now left with the burden of cleaning up the mess.  We need to hold collective responsibility for issues that plague all of us - like climate change needs to be addressed by each one of us to get any tangible change. The genius of capitalism is especially evident here - it protects itself while making individuals scapegoats. For any scandal that happens, we tend to burden the individual and ask for a more ‘morally upright’ replacement. However, countless examples of upright individuals succumbing to the pressures and power of a particular appointment and ending up corrupt are a testament to the fact that vices are engendered in and by the system - as long as the system persists, these vices will continue to sustain themselves. Therefore, Žižek argues that placing individual responsibility due to the need for “ethical immediacy” lets the system shirk the responsibility of cleaning itself up. He uses the example of the 2008 credit crisis, wherein the blame was put on those ‘horrible people’ who abused the system rather than on the system that encouraged this culture of abuse itself. Without the acceptance of the possibility of an alternative to capitalism, none of these problems will be effectively tackled and capitalist realism will continue to dominate - perhaps as an unconscious undertone, but with immense power over our economic, social and political interactions. The Road Ahead  There may be a glimmer of hope for the world yet. Neoliberal capitalism is no longer secure in its throne as the days of democratic socialism are on the horizon. As the study of late capitalism and its critique increases, protesting voices have emerged.  There is an increasing acceptance of left leaders like Jeremy Corbyn, Alexandria Cortez, Bernie Sanders, and their policies in states that have been the poster-children for capitalism. Healthcare for all, free education and opportunity for the underprivileged are being accepted by a vast majority of people - especially those who have been victims of capitalist structures. The gravity of the stark income inequality is being acknowledged and called out. Corporates and the wealthy are under increasing pressure and scrutiny to pay higher taxes and fulfil any responsibility they have towards the less privileged. While capitalist realism paints a bleak picture of us as a civilisation, perhaps it is time for the sleeping phoenix to rise from the ashes and take us to a better tomorrow. The cracks in the existing system are more prominent and visible today than ever before - the responsibility of analysing them and creating a new order is now on us to fulfil.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Building the Abode of Gods…From Scratch</title>
      <link href="/Building-the-Abode-of-Gods" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building the Abode of Gods...From Scratch" />
      <published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Building-the-Abode-of-Gods</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Building-the-Abode-of-Gods">&lt;p&gt;In 2014, a southern state of India, Andhra Pradesh, was bifurcated to form the separate state of Telangana. Economically speaking, Andhra Pradesh was left with literally nothing. It did not have a major metropolitan city. Nor did it have the financials to develop one. Overnight after bifurcation, the state was deep down in debt. It had lost its capital and major source of revenue, the high-tech city of Hyderabad. Section 5(1) of the Andhra Pradesh Reorganization Act, 2014 mandates that Hyderabad will be a common capital for a period not exceeding ten years (i.e. till 2024). However, the geographical location of the city made it inconvenient for the new Andhra Pradesh government to govern from Hyderabad. Now, without a capital, how does a government function and make plans for the state? After all, state capitals are centers for administrative activities and policy formulations. Most importantly, a capital gives the state a sense of identity. Thus began plans for the construction of a new, world-class capital city of ‘&lt;em&gt;Amaravati&lt;/em&gt;’- the Abode of the Gods. The ambition as grand as the name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2014 Assembly elections, N Chandrababu Naidu of India’s Telugu Desam Party became the Chief Minister of the state. Soon, the government set up committees to finalise the area for capital construction. Amaravati was chosen by the end of 2014. There are many reasons for this selection. First, the proposed region is at the centre and is equidistant from every corner of the state. The second reason is the availability of water. The proposed capital city is situated on the banks of the river Krishna. It also has a barrage constructed which could hold up to 1 TMC of water. The third is the ease of connectivity. Amaravati is not more than 400 km from Hyderabad, Chennai and Bengaluru, capital cities of states that neighbour Andhra Pradesh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon deciding the capital, the government constituted the Andhra Pradesh Capital Region Development Authority (APCRDA) in 2014 for planning, supervising, executing, financing and developing the capital region of Andhra Pradesh. Its tasks include finalising designs, calling for tenders and administering capital construction. Right from the beginning, the state drew its inspiration from Singapore to build a world-class city. Mr Naidu always talked about how Singapore too had developed from scratch and Andhra Pradesh was in the same position. APCRDA even signed an MoU with the Singapore government for the development of a master plan for Amaravati, which was finalised recently in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting thing to be noted here is that land for the capital was pooled rather than acquired. This was done to avoid the financial burden that would arise in the form of compensations against land acquisitions. Under this land pooling scheme, the landowners (mostly farmers) who surrendered their lands to the government would get a portion of the developed plots in the capital city after a period of 10 years. A huge 33,000 acres (133.5 square kilometers) was pooled for the construction of the capital city. It is a commendable achievement because the land was pooled in a very short period, that too without a single court case. Mr Naidu played a key role in assuring the fearful farmers that they would lose nothing by sacrificing their lands. To attract investments into the capital (and the state), the Andhra Pradesh government introduced a slew of measures. It eased its industrial policy by introducing a ‘single window clearance’ for industries, under which one can easily obtain all the necessary approvals for the setting up of a business, and avoid red tape thereof. Not only did this place Andhra Pradesh at the number 1 spot in the ‘Ease of Doing Business’ index of India but also helped the state in signing a $500 million deal with the World Bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a city from scratch is an uphill task. For a state with finances like Andhra Pradesh, it is an economic nightmare. The state is so deep in a financial crisis that a recent White Paper released by the government stated that the state has to go for an overdraft almost every month! Yet, there seems to be non-cooperation from India’s central government. When the  Andhra Pradesh Reorganization Bill was up for discussion in the Rajya Sabha, the upper house of the Indian Parliament, the then Prime Minister Dr Manmohan Singh said “for the purpose of central assistance, Special Category Status (SCS) will be extended to the State of Andhra Pradesh for a period of five years. This will put the state finances on a firmer footing.” What SCS means is that the state would get preferential treatment in the transfer of funds from the central government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, SCS money never seems to come. It is estimated that construction of the new capital would require a massive sum of ₹330 billion. Out of this, a mere ₹25 billion has been allocated by India’s central government, and only ₹10.5 billion has been released till date. The administrative help from the Indian central government has been delayed too. One example of the central government’s neglect is worth mentioning here. Emirates, a world-renowned airline, sought to fly from Andhra Pradesh and establish a training facility there. It requested the state to provide the requisite land. As aviation is regulated by the central government according to India’s Constitution, this required the centre’s approval. Unfortunately, that approval never came.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given all these troubles, wouldn’t it have been more feasible for Andhra Pradesh to select an already existing city rather than build a capital from scratch? All this said, building a new capital boosts aggregate demand. A huge amount of money is invested and employment opportunities are generated. However, the government needs to take appropriate steps to invite private investment into the state. Given the high fiscal deficit of the state, 4.5% of the GSDP or Gross State Domestic Product, it is imperative that the state goes hand-in-hand with the private sector because a further increase in fiscal deficit would put the state in a financially critical position. Infrastructural development needs huge investments with a generally long gestation period. It would be burdensome for the crippled economy of Andhra Pradesh to finance such investments. Private investments would ensure that there is no stoppage in the fund flow and the projects are completed duly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the erstwhile Andhra Pradesh, excessive economic centralisation took place in and around Hyderabad. Even today, a lion’s share of Telangana’s (the newly formed state) revenue is generated by Hyderabad. It is because all major developmental activities were planned in Hyderabad and less emphasis was placed on the development of other cities and towns. Bearing this experience in mind, the new Andhra Pradesh should be diversified in its development trajectory. Single-city centric development will cost the state dearly (like it did during its bifurcation). The capital should be restricted to administrative uses. Necessary infrastructure should be built in other cities to transform them into major centres in the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, Visakhapatnam, or Vizag, in its anglicised form, is a happening port city with a notable presence of the software industry. It has the potential to emerge as a major IT hub and the government should take steps to harness the said potential. Rayalaseema, the southern part of Andhra Pradesh, receives scarce rainfall and is not as feasible for agriculture as the other regions are. On the other hand, southern India is not a manufacturing power in the country. Andhra Pradesh could fill this gap by developing the Rayalaseema region into a major industrial and manufacturing hub. Like the existing Sri City Special Economic Zone (SEZ), a rising industrial hub in the southern part of the state, more of such initiatives can be taken up for the same purpose. The lawmakers should learn from their earlier experiences. They should make plans in such a way that development is spread throughout the state rather than being concentrated in Amaravati. Andhra Pradesh should not repeat its mistakes. And using its scarce funds to create a grand city of Amaravati would be doing so, in fact, one could say it’s already doing so.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In 2014, a southern state of India, Andhra Pradesh, was bifurcated to form the separate state of Telangana. Economically speaking, Andhra Pradesh was left with literally nothing. It did not have a major metropolitan city. Nor did it have the financials to develop one. Overnight after bifurcation, the state was deep down in debt. It had lost its capital and major source of revenue, the high-tech city of Hyderabad. Section 5(1) of the Andhra Pradesh Reorganization Act, 2014 mandates that Hyderabad will be a common capital for a period not exceeding ten years (i.e. till 2024). However, the geographical location of the city made it inconvenient for the new Andhra Pradesh government to govern from Hyderabad. Now, without a capital, how does a government function and make plans for the state? After all, state capitals are centers for administrative activities and policy formulations. Most importantly, a capital gives the state a sense of identity. Thus began plans for the construction of a new, world-class capital city of ‘Amaravati’- the Abode of the Gods. The ambition as grand as the name.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Crypto-Crazed Millennials on a Saving Spree</title>
      <link href="/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Crypto-Crazed Millennials on a Saving Spree" />
      <published>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Crypto-Crazed-Millennials-on-a-Saving-Spree">&lt;p&gt;The global financial markets recently completed the longest-ever bull run at the remarkable stretch of a decade. A slow and steady boom rose in March 2009 from the ashes of The Great Recession of 2008. This, however, was not enough to heal the scars that the recession and the dot com bubble had left on the minds of the then-young millennial. While the pre-teen millennials witnessed their parents go through a financial crunch, the older ones stepped right into a slough of joblessness. This has contributed to their unnaturally high sensitivity to losses. As a result, even the near-zero federal funds rate (which directs the global rates) has not been enough to channelise their funds towards the financial markets. This is a major concern for the global economy, especially when you factor in the fact that the millennials are at the cusp of surpassing the Boomers as the largest living adult generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some millennials, burdened by low-income jobs and debt obligations, living from paycheck to paycheck, are genuinely unable to finance stock purchases, the statistics tell us how even better-off millennials are straying away from investing and are preferring to save instead. Unfortunately, their risk-averse tendencies are miscalculated and are costing them precious returns, since the S&amp;amp;P 500 (adjusted for inflation and dividends reinvested) averaged a 7.92% return between 2007 to 2017, while the money market bank accounts averaged a 0.3% return during the same period. Nearly 42% of millennials are conservative investors, as opposed to 38% of GenXers and 23% of the Boomers. They are unwilling to fully embrace the financial markets, and when they do, it is only through a safer, less costly mechanism such as that of an Exchange Traded Fund (ETF), which is a type of fund that holds multiple underlying assets rather than a single stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is worth noting is that their caution seems selective. Millennials’ risk-aversion appears to be more about scepticism when one realises how they have stayed away only from what they personally saw fail - the stock markets. They are still the ones responsible for inflating the crypto-market, despite its lack of intrinsic value or any ‘faith’ backing. The only argument in defense of their wild investment choice is perhaps the sophisticated distributed ledger technology used in the asset which makes the case for fostering technological innovation in the stock markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the politically correct environment, with encouragement from Hollywood, has put capitalism out of style for many. The ones still willing to invest have raised the bar over mere profitability when making an investment decision. Company ethics and transparency are a primary consideration for millennials when they choose to invest, and these additional filters reduce the overall amount invested. The rate of investment for women is in an even poorer state. The Harris Poll survey revealed that a staggering 79% of women do not invest at all, with 70% of them stating that the process is confusing to them, while 60% of them believing how they felt investing was ‘an old-white man’s game’. Clearly, the Millennials need a better education when it comes to managing their finances and getting over &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; impression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger picture is clear: Millennials are savers and not investors. 71% of Millennial workers are saving for retirement, and begin saving at the median age of 24, which puts the GenX’s median saving age of 30 to shame. And while they rely on the banks for saving, they try to keep away from availing any of the other services. A three year study from Scratch, an in-house unit of Viacom, as a part of the &lt;em&gt;Millennial Disruption Study&lt;/em&gt;, found that not only were banks among the ‘Most Hated’ brands, but a third of this demographic cohort believed that they’d be better off without them. This is a major concern for banks, who are now resorting to appeasement techniques. Providing special discounts on credit card bills and easing out the enrollment mechanism for loans are a few examples. This has also partially fueled the rise of fintech in the formal banking system and is encouraging the development of such technologies. Developing a system with a user-friendly interface and greater transparency by incorporation of Artificial Intelligence (AI) and machine learning is an obvious solution to this issue. For instance,  a ZeroHedge survey revealed that one in three Millennials would rather invest in Bitcoin than in the stock market, simply because of the unconventional and futuristic technology involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that in traditional economics, the West had never been considered the saver’s economy, and this pattern is shifting for the better. The situation is quite akin to the rise in savings post the hyperinflationary periods in Germany after World War I, which incidentally was also a result of the psychological impact of the crisis. At the macro level, greater savings would imply lesser dependence on foreign investment. Lesser inflow of USD denominated investment in the USA implies lesser demand for the dollar. The consequent decline in appreciation of the USD is great for recovering the Current Account Deficit, which has been a primary long-term concern for the nation. But this advantage is dwarfed when growth concerns step in, as slowdowns are the projected case for the next few years. Additionally, with the rise of protectionist, right-wing governments around the globe, millennials are increasingly inclining towards what they think is socialism, which implies increased disinterest towards the financial markets. And that is a terrible prospect for growth. Hence, even though this demographic cohort has been through quite a lot at an impressionable age, they must put their concerns aside and take up a more rational approach. They have made a wise decision to save, considering the depleting ability of the burgeoning federal balance sheet to finance their post-retirement expenses. But they must learn to be comfortable with the idea of some risk.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The global financial markets recently completed the longest-ever bull run at the remarkable stretch of a decade. A slow and steady boom rose in March 2009 from the ashes of The Great Recession of 2008. This, however, was not enough to heal the scars that the recession and the dot com bubble had left on the minds of the then-young millennial. While the pre-teen millennials witnessed their parents go through a financial crunch, the older ones stepped right into a slough of joblessness. This has contributed to their unnaturally high sensitivity to losses. As a result, even the near-zero federal funds rate (which directs the global rates) has not been enough to channelise their funds towards the financial markets. This is a major concern for the global economy, especially when you factor in the fact that the millennials are at the cusp of surpassing the Boomers as the largest living adult generation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
