<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/economics/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-06-16T10:19:52+01:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/economics/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Post-COVID World Economy</title>
      <link href="/The-Post-COVID-World-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Post-COVID World Economy" />
      <published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Post-COVID-World-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Post-COVID-World-Economy">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The history of the world economy demonstrates a trend of economic shocks emerging in every generation. The World Health Organisation (WHO) declared COVID-19 as a global pandemic on March 11, 2020; and since then, almost every human endeavour has been disrupted.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The impact on the global economy is particularly worrying. We witnessed global supply chains being severely disrupted and strained, financial markets unsettled, resulting in a cross-border economic disaster. Border closures and lockdowns shattered the core sustaining pillars of modern world economies, with the economic shock due to these measures still being weighed across the globe. The ramifications of these disruptions are more far-reaching than anticipated, and the legacies of COVID-19 will shape global growth for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Even though economies are recovering at different paces throughout the world, the world economy is well on the way to recovery from a slump the likes of which none of its 7.7 billion inhabitants has seen in their lifetimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The new paradigms enforced in the COVID-19 era have led to an unprecedented acceleration in automation and digitisation of operations whilst highlighting the importance of upskilling the workforce. Turbulent labour markets provide additional challenges to professionals as the pace of technology adoption remains unabated while automation, in tandem with the COVID-19 recession, is creating a 'double-disruption' scenario for the labour force. There is more inequality between and within countries, and governments are playing a larger role in the lives of citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Looking at historical precedents, the World Economic Forum postulates that the pandemic is about three times as bad as the global financial crisis of 2008 in terms of GDP decline on an annual basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2020/09/an-economist-explains-what-covid-19-has-done-to-the-global-economy/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/IHS-Markit-gdp-growth.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Economists surmise that adopting a circular economy would be the best way for the world's economy to recover, whilst enabling the transition to an essentially low-carbon economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The pandemic also catalysed the rise of the digital economy, with the influx of digital behaviour such as remote working and learning, telemedicine, and delivery services. Due to this rapid digitisation, other structural changes can also be anticipated, including regionalisation of supply chains and a further explosion of cross-border data flows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The future of work has arrived faster, along with its myriad challenges such as worker vulnerability, income polarisation, more gig work, and the need for workers to adapt to occupational transitions multiplied in potential. This acceleration is the result not only of technological advances and recession, but also of new considerations for health and safety, and economies and labour markets will take time to recover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The quantum of the amplification of these trends and the realities of this crisis have also triggered a reconsideration of several beliefs, with implicit and long-lasting effects on the economy and society and attitudes about efficiency versus resilience, the future of capitalism, densification of economic activity and peoples’ lifestyles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The pandemic has also accelerated some of the key geopolitical trends that will shape our next world order - de-globalisation and nationalism, for instance, along with debilitating China’s hegemony in the supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While the quantitative disruptions in the economy, structured finance and credit facilities are quite explicit, the more permanent changes are perhaps the ones considered from humanitarian perspectives. The most prominent qualities that were on display during this time of distress were the adaptability and versatility of people, which caused the cataclysmic shift of buying patterns to the online medium and helped to keep it afloat while intensifying the focus on the triple bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Over the past two decades, in advancing economies, the onus of security has generally shifted from institutions to individuals. Healthcare systems are being tested and often found wanting, while benefits from paid sick leave to universal basic income are getting reviewed. There is potential for a long-term shift in how institutions offer support, through safety nets, and a more inclusive social contract.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;History bears witness that choices made during crises can shape the world for decades to come. What remains critical is the need for collective action to build economies that deliver inclusive economic growth, prosperity, and safety for all.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Maanya Oberoi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The history of the world economy demonstrates a trend of economic shocks emerging in every generation. The World Health Organisation (WHO) declared COVID-19 as a global pandemic on March 11, 2020; and since then, almost every human endeavour has been disrupted.&amp;nbsp; The impact on the global economy is particularly worrying. We witnessed global supply chains being severely disrupted and strained, financial markets unsettled, resulting in a cross-border economic disaster. Border closures and lockdowns shattered the core sustaining pillars of modern world economies, with the economic shock due to these measures still being weighed across the globe. The ramifications of these disruptions are more far-reaching than anticipated, and the legacies of COVID-19 will shape global growth for years to come. Even though economies are recovering at different paces throughout the world, the world economy is well on the way to recovery from a slump the likes of which none of its 7.7 billion inhabitants has seen in their lifetimes. The new paradigms enforced in the COVID-19 era have led to an unprecedented acceleration in automation and digitisation of operations whilst highlighting the importance of upskilling the workforce. Turbulent labour markets provide additional challenges to professionals as the pace of technology adoption remains unabated while automation, in tandem with the COVID-19 recession, is creating a 'double-disruption' scenario for the labour force. There is more inequality between and within countries, and governments are playing a larger role in the lives of citizens. Looking at historical precedents, the World Economic Forum postulates that the pandemic is about three times as bad as the global financial crisis of 2008 in terms of GDP decline on an annual basis. Economists surmise that adopting a circular economy would be the best way for the world's economy to recover, whilst enabling the transition to an essentially low-carbon economy. The pandemic also catalysed the rise of the digital economy, with the influx of digital behaviour such as remote working and learning, telemedicine, and delivery services. Due to this rapid digitisation, other structural changes can also be anticipated, including regionalisation of supply chains and a further explosion of cross-border data flows. The future of work has arrived faster, along with its myriad challenges such as worker vulnerability, income polarisation, more gig work, and the need for workers to adapt to occupational transitions multiplied in potential. This acceleration is the result not only of technological advances and recession, but also of new considerations for health and safety, and economies and labour markets will take time to recover. The quantum of the amplification of these trends and the realities of this crisis have also triggered a reconsideration of several beliefs, with implicit and long-lasting effects on the economy and society and attitudes about efficiency versus resilience, the future of capitalism, densification of economic activity and peoples’ lifestyles. The pandemic has also accelerated some of the key geopolitical trends that will shape our next world order - de-globalisation and nationalism, for instance, along with debilitating China’s hegemony in the supply chain. While the quantitative disruptions in the economy, structured finance and credit facilities are quite explicit, the more permanent changes are perhaps the ones considered from humanitarian perspectives. The most prominent qualities that were on display during this time of distress were the adaptability and versatility of people, which caused the cataclysmic shift of buying patterns to the online medium and helped to keep it afloat while intensifying the focus on the triple bottom line. Over the past two decades, in advancing economies, the onus of security has generally shifted from institutions to individuals. Healthcare systems are being tested and often found wanting, while benefits from paid sick leave to universal basic income are getting reviewed. There is potential for a long-term shift in how institutions offer support, through safety nets, and a more inclusive social contract. History bears witness that choices made during crises can shape the world for decades to come. What remains critical is the need for collective action to build economies that deliver inclusive economic growth, prosperity, and safety for all.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Digital Yuan: The Start of the End for the US Dollar?</title>
      <link href="/Digital-Yuan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Digital Yuan: The Start of the End for the US Dollar?" />
      <published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Digital-Yuan</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Digital-Yuan">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Crypto currency mania has gripped the world, as increasing acceptance of blockchain technology by major financial institutions has propelled the likes of Bitcoin into the mainstream. Whether you believe in crypto or not, the emergence of crypto currencies threatens to usurp fiat money. The Chinese government has identified the threat early, and has taken significant steps to ensure they have a meaningful head start on digitising their commercial sector and money supply. China’s long anticipated and recently released digital Yuan threatens to undermine the US dollar’s (USD) supremacy as we know it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;China’s digital Yuan project is the first of its kind for any major global economy. It is a version of normal Chinese currency, deployed on a blockchain; the highly encrypted and secure online ledger technology that underpins digital coins like Bitcoin and Ethereum. The People’s Bank of China (PBOC) has led work on the digital Yuan project, which is classified as a central bank digital currency (CBDC) that aims to replace some of the cash in circulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;China has been trialling the digital currency since late 2020, and in 11 different regions since April, including in major cities such as Suzhou and Shenzhen, where the digital Yuan has been used for transport, food and retail. The digital Yuan bypasses the need for central banks in transaction processes, eliminating service fees and speeding up transaction times. China has plans for international use of the digital Yuan by 2024 or 2025, and has already established partnerships with the UAE, Hong Kong, and Thailand to promote international use of CBDCs. Given the vast extent of China’s bilateral trade relations globally, and the increasing likelihood of China overtaking the US as the world's largest economy, the internalisation of the digital Yuan is seeming inevitable.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decline of the Dollar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The emergence of the digital Yuan coincides with a difficult period for the US dollar. The US dollar has become increasingly fragile of late, perhaps mirroring America’s decline within the international system, with its status as the ultimate reserve currency looking increasingly likely to be challenged in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The US dollar has seen a steady fall since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic. It is down about 10-12% relative to America’s major trading partners. Some have even suggested that the dollar will decline in value by 35% by the end of 2021. Ongoing political instability in the US has had a detrimental effect on global trust in the US dollar. The debasing of the US dollar through massive US government debt and central bank stimulus raises the question of the dollar’s long-term viability as the ultimate reserve currency.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To demonstrate this effect, we can look at the declining market of the US-China bilateral trade. The US imports from China dropped by $87.3 billion in 2019 from 2018, and continue to drop annually. The Chinese need for the US dollar is declining. The use of the US dollar in China-Russia transactions has declined from 90% in 2015 to less than 50% in the first quarter of 2020. At a rate of 10% annual decline, it will not be long before the US dollar is no longer used at all in China’s transactions. This vacuum left by the USD will allow for the growth of other currencies such as the digital Yuan. As more countries decide not to use the US dollar, the use of alternative currency reserves will increase. Given China’s extensive trade relations, the digital Yuan is well positioned to take over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;China not Attempting to Replace USD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While it appears that the US dollar and digital Yuan are moving in opposite directions, Chinese officials have claimed that the development of the digital Yuan is not intended to ‘replace the USD’ as the ultimate reserve currency. Deputy governor of the PBOC Li Bo claimed that “efforts to create the digital Yuan are aimed at domestic use,” while Governor of the PBOC, Zhou Xiachuan, echoed that Beijing is not aiming to immediately take on the USD as a currency reserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Regardless of China’s intentions for the digital Yuan, the reality is that the growth of the new digital currency will likely further contribute to the weakening and destabilisation of the USD. Much like when China developed paper currency in the 7th century during the Tang dynasty, China is today leading the way in a key transitional phase of the global financial system. The CBDC space certainly has potential to be a key battleground in the larger US-China struggle for global hegemony. Perhaps it is time for the US central bank to explore the implementation of a CBDC project more urgently. Should they fail to do so, there is a pressing possibility for the USD to get left behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;-Noam Konyn&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Noam Konyn is a graduate of the University of Bristol. He is currently pursuing an MA Government Specialisation in diplomacy and conflict at Interdisciplinary Centre Herzliya, Israel. He has previously worked in Elminda, a brain health medical device company in Tel Aviv, Israel.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Guest</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Crypto currency mania has gripped the world, as increasing acceptance of blockchain technology by major financial institutions has propelled the likes of Bitcoin into the mainstream. Whether you believe in crypto or not, the emergence of crypto currencies threatens to usurp fiat money. The Chinese government has identified the threat early, and has taken significant steps to ensure they have a meaningful head start on digitising their commercial sector and money supply. China’s long anticipated and recently released digital Yuan threatens to undermine the US dollar’s (USD) supremacy as we know it. China’s digital Yuan project is the first of its kind for any major global economy. It is a version of normal Chinese currency, deployed on a blockchain; the highly encrypted and secure online ledger technology that underpins digital coins like Bitcoin and Ethereum. The People’s Bank of China (PBOC) has led work on the digital Yuan project, which is classified as a central bank digital currency (CBDC) that aims to replace some of the cash in circulation. China has been trialling the digital currency since late 2020, and in 11 different regions since April, including in major cities such as Suzhou and Shenzhen, where the digital Yuan has been used for transport, food and retail. The digital Yuan bypasses the need for central banks in transaction processes, eliminating service fees and speeding up transaction times. China has plans for international use of the digital Yuan by 2024 or 2025, and has already established partnerships with the UAE, Hong Kong, and Thailand to promote international use of CBDCs. Given the vast extent of China’s bilateral trade relations globally, and the increasing likelihood of China overtaking the US as the world's largest economy, the internalisation of the digital Yuan is seeming inevitable.&amp;nbsp; Decline of the Dollar The emergence of the digital Yuan coincides with a difficult period for the US dollar. The US dollar has become increasingly fragile of late, perhaps mirroring America’s decline within the international system, with its status as the ultimate reserve currency looking increasingly likely to be challenged in the long term. The US dollar has seen a steady fall since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic. It is down about 10-12% relative to America’s major trading partners. Some have even suggested that the dollar will decline in value by 35% by the end of 2021. Ongoing political instability in the US has had a detrimental effect on global trust in the US dollar. The debasing of the US dollar through massive US government debt and central bank stimulus raises the question of the dollar’s long-term viability as the ultimate reserve currency.&amp;nbsp; To demonstrate this effect, we can look at the declining market of the US-China bilateral trade. The US imports from China dropped by $87.3 billion in 2019 from 2018, and continue to drop annually. The Chinese need for the US dollar is declining. The use of the US dollar in China-Russia transactions has declined from 90% in 2015 to less than 50% in the first quarter of 2020. At a rate of 10% annual decline, it will not be long before the US dollar is no longer used at all in China’s transactions. This vacuum left by the USD will allow for the growth of other currencies such as the digital Yuan. As more countries decide not to use the US dollar, the use of alternative currency reserves will increase. Given China’s extensive trade relations, the digital Yuan is well positioned to take over. China not Attempting to Replace USD While it appears that the US dollar and digital Yuan are moving in opposite directions, Chinese officials have claimed that the development of the digital Yuan is not intended to ‘replace the USD’ as the ultimate reserve currency. Deputy governor of the PBOC Li Bo claimed that “efforts to create the digital Yuan are aimed at domestic use,” while Governor of the PBOC, Zhou Xiachuan, echoed that Beijing is not aiming to immediately take on the USD as a currency reserve. Regardless of China’s intentions for the digital Yuan, the reality is that the growth of the new digital currency will likely further contribute to the weakening and destabilisation of the USD. Much like when China developed paper currency in the 7th century during the Tang dynasty, China is today leading the way in a key transitional phase of the global financial system. The CBDC space certainly has potential to be a key battleground in the larger US-China struggle for global hegemony. Perhaps it is time for the US central bank to explore the implementation of a CBDC project more urgently. Should they fail to do so, there is a pressing possibility for the USD to get left behind. -Noam Konyn Noam Konyn is a graduate of the University of Bristol. He is currently pursuing an MA Government Specialisation in diplomacy and conflict at Interdisciplinary Centre Herzliya, Israel. He has previously worked in Elminda, a brain health medical device company in Tel Aviv, Israel.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Indian Pharma Industry: Present and Future</title>
      <link href="/The-Indian-Pharma-Industry" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Indian Pharma Industry: Present and Future" />
      <published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-05-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Indian-Pharma-Industry</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Indian-Pharma-Industry">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;On March 11, 2020, the World Health Organisation (WHO) declared the coronavirus, SARS-CoV-2 to be a pandemic. More than a year after the outbreak, over three million people have lost their lives with approximately 152 million cases across the globe. The pandemic has managed to cause a complete upheaval in people’s lifestyle along with businesses running losses and workers losing their jobs. Amidst this scenario, it is the pharmaceutical industry that has taken centre stage in the fight against this menace, assisting world governments in fulfilling their population's needs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The global pharmaceutical industry in 2019 achieved a market value of approximately $1,217 billion with a compound annual growth rate of 6.7%. This value is expected to decline to $1,209 billion in 2020 owing to the COVID-19 outbreak.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The pharmaceutical (or pharma) industry can be defined as a “&lt;em&gt;complex system of processes, operations, and organisations involved in the discovery, development, and manufacturing of drugs&lt;/em&gt;”. Firms functioning in the industry are responsible for research and development (R&amp;amp;D) activities, development and manufacturing of active pharmaceutical ingredients and manufacturing of drugs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In 2019, Germany occupied the top position in the pharma industry with a 14.5% share in the export of drugs and medicines. It was followed by Switzerland and Netherlands with a share of 12.2% and 7.9% respectively. Among other countries, Denmark, Netherlands and Italy are the fastest growing exporters of drugs and medicines since 2015. However, three countries have witnessed a decline in the exported drugs and medicines sales in the last five years. These are, namely, the United Kingdom (26.7%), Ireland (18.9%) and the United States (6.1%).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In recent years, growth patterns in developed economies have observed a flat trend which has induced firms to shift their focus to emerging markets, thus finding new sources of revenue and profitability. The same has been witnessed for the pharmaceutical industry. The pharmaceutical emerging markets, or 'pharmerging' markets hold the potential of an extraordinary growth story.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In 2016, emerging markets accounted for over 30% of the development in pharma markets. This shift has been attributed to the economic and demographic development in these economies with a rise in health expectancy, access to healthcare services and improved funding for the healthcare sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another major factor is the sharp decline in firms’ revenue as a result of the expiration of patents. This is known as the patent cliff, which is now affecting several branded drugs that have been in the market for years. The shift towards the use of generic drugs worldwide, increasing availability of biosimilar drugs, a significant differential in manufacturing costs and prices, and change in disease patterns in emerging countries are some of the other major reasons for the shift being observed in the pharmaceutical industry. These factors have induced the emerging economies into becoming the key drivers of the global pharmaceutical market.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Among the emerging markets, five countries namely China, Brazil, Russia, India and South Africa are the ones in domination with their role becoming increasingly important in the coming decade.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pharmaceutical Industry in India&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the last fifty years, India’s pharmaceutical industry has grown by leaps and bounds. From having a 5% share of the total medicine consumption in India in 1969, Indian pharma holds an 85% share of the same in 2020. Today, India is not only able to meet its domestic needs but has also established itself as a leader in the global pharma landscape and is known as the ‘pharmacy of the world’. The industry today is recognised for the quality and cost-effectiveness of its products. Widely known as the ‘archetype of affordable healthcare’, the Indian industry has had a significant contribution towards the improvement of public health outcomes, both within India and across the globe.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;With a market size of $41 billion in 2018-19 and a market growth rate of 10-12%, the Indian pharma industry exported $16.3 billion worth of bulk drugs, intermediates, drug formulations, herbal products, surgical equipment and other goods in 2019-20. Particularly, the industry contributes more than 20% by volume to the global generics market and 62% of the global demand for vaccines. Fourteenth largest in the world in terms of value and 3rd largest in terms of volume, the industry is expected to grow to $100 billion by 2025.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Within India, the industry plays an important role in India’s economic growth and is recognised as one of the top sectors attracting foreign direct investment (FDI) and reducing the trade deficit. The sector attracted a total of $16.54 billion worth of FDI inflow between April 2000 and June 2020. The sector’s importance is further underlined due to the amount of trade surplus generated with exports accounting for $20.7 billion and imports at $2.31 billion in the year 2020. The industry generates employment for over 2.7 million people, directly or indirectly.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COVID-19 and Opportunity for India in Post-Pandemic World&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The outbreak of the virus has challenged healthcare systems around the globe. From the United States, a country that undertakes the highest expenditure on its healthcare system, to the sophisticated European healthcare systems, each country is struggling to contain the spread. Despite the plethora of measures undertaken by countries, the massive inpouring of coronavirus infected patients has exceeded the existing infrastructure and resources in several countries, with the disease causing huge loss of life and human suffering. Additionally, there is a shortage of essential equipment, medicinal supplies and even medicines. The pandemic has also brought forth the existing inequalities in access to healthcare globally.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Amidst these challenges, the global pharmaceutical markets are facing major discontinuities. For instance, there have been concerns regarding global over-dependence on China for active pharmaceutical ingredients (API), particularly in India, the US and Europe. As a result, in the past few months, several countries have been experiencing disruption in the pharma supply chain. The pandemic has also reinforced issues like re-shoring, nearshoring and shortening supply chains.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Indian pharmaceutical industry has been a key contributor in improving the healthcare outcomes in the country with the pandemic presenting several opportunities and challenges for the industry. The growing distrust in China comes as an opportunity for India even so the economy will be facing increased competition from countries like Vietnam and Malaysia.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To utilise the post-pandemic potential to the fullest, the industry has to build on its strength along with taking a giant leap towards innovation. The introduction of new capabilities is necessary to bring efficiencies to facilitate the industry to move up the value chain. A two-fold approach can be adopted to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;First, India needs to explore opportunities in complex generics, biosimilars, vaccines and preventives and other complex products. Having attained leadership in the generic market globally, India now needs to consolidate its position in other markets to move up the value chain. Focusing on complex products for this matter will help to achieve long-term sustained growth for the sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;These complex generics involve a comparatively more difficult production process, face less competition and involve higher margins. Similarly, biosimilars can play an equally important role in expanding India’s pharma sector. Domestically, India is leading in the world when it comes to launching biosimilars, however, only a few Indian companies are able to infiltrate US and European markets due to the non-alignment of India's regulatory guidelines with the regulations in these markets. In addition to the generics market, India has also established itself as a strong contender in the global vaccines market, with the country supplying 60% of the world's vaccine requirements. The step further is thus to develop new and complex vaccines, especially in times like these.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The second approach should be with respect to innovation. India needs to set up an environment conducive to innovation by bringing together academia, pharma companies, entrepreneurs and medical institutions. A look at the global scenario reveals that there is a concentration of research and development activities in the US and Europe, reflecting their dominance in innovation. India also does not compare well with its counterpart China which has twice the number of R&amp;amp;D sites and innovation centres. Therefore, there exists tremendous scope for India to establish itself as a global innovation hub.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In conclusion, the increasing shift of pharmaceutical firms from western economies to emerging economies presents India with a golden opportunity to enhance its pharma production along with emerging as a strong contender in the R&amp;amp;D sector. Even though the pandemic has resulted in innumerable challenges to the economy and the pharma industry in particular, it has also presented the industry with an opportunity to rise to the occasion and establish itself as a leading global player. Whether the country is able to perform on this front remains to be seen!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rajsi Sah</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On March 11, 2020, the World Health Organisation (WHO) declared the coronavirus, SARS-CoV-2 to be a pandemic. More than a year after the outbreak, over three million people have lost their lives with approximately 152 million cases across the globe. The pandemic has managed to cause a complete upheaval in people’s lifestyle along with businesses running losses and workers losing their jobs. Amidst this scenario, it is the pharmaceutical industry that has taken centre stage in the fight against this menace, assisting world governments in fulfilling their population's needs.&amp;nbsp; The global pharmaceutical industry in 2019 achieved a market value of approximately $1,217 billion with a compound annual growth rate of 6.7%. This value is expected to decline to $1,209 billion in 2020 owing to the COVID-19 outbreak.&amp;nbsp; The pharmaceutical (or pharma) industry can be defined as a “complex system of processes, operations, and organisations involved in the discovery, development, and manufacturing of drugs”. Firms functioning in the industry are responsible for research and development (R&amp;amp;D) activities, development and manufacturing of active pharmaceutical ingredients and manufacturing of drugs.&amp;nbsp; In 2019, Germany occupied the top position in the pharma industry with a 14.5% share in the export of drugs and medicines. It was followed by Switzerland and Netherlands with a share of 12.2% and 7.9% respectively. Among other countries, Denmark, Netherlands and Italy are the fastest growing exporters of drugs and medicines since 2015. However, three countries have witnessed a decline in the exported drugs and medicines sales in the last five years. These are, namely, the United Kingdom (26.7%), Ireland (18.9%) and the United States (6.1%).&amp;nbsp; In recent years, growth patterns in developed economies have observed a flat trend which has induced firms to shift their focus to emerging markets, thus finding new sources of revenue and profitability. The same has been witnessed for the pharmaceutical industry. The pharmaceutical emerging markets, or 'pharmerging' markets hold the potential of an extraordinary growth story.&amp;nbsp; In 2016, emerging markets accounted for over 30% of the development in pharma markets. This shift has been attributed to the economic and demographic development in these economies with a rise in health expectancy, access to healthcare services and improved funding for the healthcare sector.&amp;nbsp; Another major factor is the sharp decline in firms’ revenue as a result of the expiration of patents. This is known as the patent cliff, which is now affecting several branded drugs that have been in the market for years. The shift towards the use of generic drugs worldwide, increasing availability of biosimilar drugs, a significant differential in manufacturing costs and prices, and change in disease patterns in emerging countries are some of the other major reasons for the shift being observed in the pharmaceutical industry. These factors have induced the emerging economies into becoming the key drivers of the global pharmaceutical market.&amp;nbsp; Among the emerging markets, five countries namely China, Brazil, Russia, India and South Africa are the ones in domination with their role becoming increasingly important in the coming decade.&amp;nbsp; Pharmaceutical Industry in India In the last fifty years, India’s pharmaceutical industry has grown by leaps and bounds. From having a 5% share of the total medicine consumption in India in 1969, Indian pharma holds an 85% share of the same in 2020. Today, India is not only able to meet its domestic needs but has also established itself as a leader in the global pharma landscape and is known as the ‘pharmacy of the world’. The industry today is recognised for the quality and cost-effectiveness of its products. Widely known as the ‘archetype of affordable healthcare’, the Indian industry has had a significant contribution towards the improvement of public health outcomes, both within India and across the globe.&amp;nbsp; With a market size of $41 billion in 2018-19 and a market growth rate of 10-12%, the Indian pharma industry exported $16.3 billion worth of bulk drugs, intermediates, drug formulations, herbal products, surgical equipment and other goods in 2019-20. Particularly, the industry contributes more than 20% by volume to the global generics market and 62% of the global demand for vaccines. Fourteenth largest in the world in terms of value and 3rd largest in terms of volume, the industry is expected to grow to $100 billion by 2025.&amp;nbsp; Within India, the industry plays an important role in India’s economic growth and is recognised as one of the top sectors attracting foreign direct investment (FDI) and reducing the trade deficit. The sector attracted a total of $16.54 billion worth of FDI inflow between April 2000 and June 2020. The sector’s importance is further underlined due to the amount of trade surplus generated with exports accounting for $20.7 billion and imports at $2.31 billion in the year 2020. The industry generates employment for over 2.7 million people, directly or indirectly.&amp;nbsp; COVID-19 and Opportunity for India in Post-Pandemic World The outbreak of the virus has challenged healthcare systems around the globe. From the United States, a country that undertakes the highest expenditure on its healthcare system, to the sophisticated European healthcare systems, each country is struggling to contain the spread. Despite the plethora of measures undertaken by countries, the massive inpouring of coronavirus infected patients has exceeded the existing infrastructure and resources in several countries, with the disease causing huge loss of life and human suffering. Additionally, there is a shortage of essential equipment, medicinal supplies and even medicines. The pandemic has also brought forth the existing inequalities in access to healthcare globally.&amp;nbsp; Amidst these challenges, the global pharmaceutical markets are facing major discontinuities. For instance, there have been concerns regarding global over-dependence on China for active pharmaceutical ingredients (API), particularly in India, the US and Europe. As a result, in the past few months, several countries have been experiencing disruption in the pharma supply chain. The pandemic has also reinforced issues like re-shoring, nearshoring and shortening supply chains.&amp;nbsp; The Indian pharmaceutical industry has been a key contributor in improving the healthcare outcomes in the country with the pandemic presenting several opportunities and challenges for the industry. The growing distrust in China comes as an opportunity for India even so the economy will be facing increased competition from countries like Vietnam and Malaysia.&amp;nbsp; To utilise the post-pandemic potential to the fullest, the industry has to build on its strength along with taking a giant leap towards innovation. The introduction of new capabilities is necessary to bring efficiencies to facilitate the industry to move up the value chain. A two-fold approach can be adopted to achieve this. First, India needs to explore opportunities in complex generics, biosimilars, vaccines and preventives and other complex products. Having attained leadership in the generic market globally, India now needs to consolidate its position in other markets to move up the value chain. Focusing on complex products for this matter will help to achieve long-term sustained growth for the sector.&amp;nbsp; These complex generics involve a comparatively more difficult production process, face less competition and involve higher margins. Similarly, biosimilars can play an equally important role in expanding India’s pharma sector. Domestically, India is leading in the world when it comes to launching biosimilars, however, only a few Indian companies are able to infiltrate US and European markets due to the non-alignment of India's regulatory guidelines with the regulations in these markets. In addition to the generics market, India has also established itself as a strong contender in the global vaccines market, with the country supplying 60% of the world's vaccine requirements. The step further is thus to develop new and complex vaccines, especially in times like these.&amp;nbsp; The second approach should be with respect to innovation. India needs to set up an environment conducive to innovation by bringing together academia, pharma companies, entrepreneurs and medical institutions. A look at the global scenario reveals that there is a concentration of research and development activities in the US and Europe, reflecting their dominance in innovation. India also does not compare well with its counterpart China which has twice the number of R&amp;amp;D sites and innovation centres. Therefore, there exists tremendous scope for India to establish itself as a global innovation hub.&amp;nbsp; In conclusion, the increasing shift of pharmaceutical firms from western economies to emerging economies presents India with a golden opportunity to enhance its pharma production along with emerging as a strong contender in the R&amp;amp;D sector. Even though the pandemic has resulted in innumerable challenges to the economy and the pharma industry in particular, it has also presented the industry with an opportunity to rise to the occasion and establish itself as a leading global player. Whether the country is able to perform on this front remains to be seen!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Medical Tourism: An Oar to the Indian Economy</title>
      <link href="/Medical-Tourism-An-Oar-to-the-Indian-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Medical Tourism: An Oar to the Indian Economy" />
      <published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Medical-Tourism-An-Oar-to-the-Indian-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Medical-Tourism-An-Oar-to-the-Indian-Economy">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Tourism is an important and rapidly growing industry of the Indian economy. This industry contributes to around 8-9% of India’s total GDP and creates millions of employment opportunities. Being home to various cultures, our country attracts tourists throughout the year. With an efficient and well-established infrastructure in terms of communication, transportation and a tourist-friendly visa policy, the number of tourists has seen a growth with each passing year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Apart from this, medical tourism has witnessed considerable growth and success in the Indian economy. Indian medical tourism sector is estimated to be worth 3 billion US dollars and is growing at a speedy rate with each passing year. The top ten source countries contributing to India’s medical tourism include Bangladesh, Afghanistan, Iraq, Maldives, Oman, Yemen, Uzbekistan, Kenya, Nigeria and Tanzania.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Apart from Chennai, Mumbai and Delhi, various other cities have seen an increase in the number of patients from various countries. Medical tourism in India is largely promoted by the government and fueled by the corporate boom in medical care. There are a number of reasons contributing to this industry, the two major reasons being affordability and accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What seeds medical tourism?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Globalisation brings with it a plethora of opportunities for consumers to choose from and for countries to expand their scope of development. Apart from evolution, it also provides an opportunity for countries to collaborate their resources and provide the best in terms of education and health to the citizens of the world. One such brilliant example is India’s efficient medical facilities that are made available to the citizens at an affordable price.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India offers a complete posy of healthcare facilities available at an affordable and attractive price which is less than 40% than any developed western country without any compromise on the quality and care. Adding to this the travel, accommodation and insurance are also made available at a very reasonable rate.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While the cost of living in India is 66.54% lower than in the USA and the rent in India is 85% lower than in the USA which is another major reason why people fly to India for treatments that require staying at the place of treatment for a long period of time. People across the globe consider themselves as global citizens, thus ensure exploring the best opportunities across the world and India’s personalised touch of care in the form of Atithi-Devo-Bhava plays a crucial role in the recent growth of medical tourism in the country.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The accessibility and comfort are also the reasons why India is favourable for treatments and attracts patients from across the globe. To begin with, the medical visa norms of the country are very simplified and easy to gain access to, this ensures hassle-free travel, treatment and stay for the patient as well as the attendant.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The medical visa assures multiple entries and longer stays, the recent development of e-medical visa that was launched by the Union Government has been viewed as a key element in boosting medical tourism in India. Alongside, India is home to multiple cuisines and offers organically prepared food that speeds up the process of getting healthier also attracts people for getting treated with the least disturbance to their comfort zone. India also ensures no language barrier as it is claimed to be the second-largest English speaking country in the world. Lean or no waiting for surgeries as compared to long waiting for even simple surgeries in the western countries also pegs the way for tourists visiting India for medicinal purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India has always been a hub of genius brains that can excel in all the fields. Technology and medicine have been going hand-in-hand lately. India has shown the fastest adoption of recent medical technology when compared to its developing counterparts. With more than 500 accredited healthcare providers, India offers a variety of options at different locations in the country to choose from as per the visitor’s convenience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Indian doctors, medicinal research, treatment and technology has been found to be at par with the western standard so much so that over 12% of doctors practising in the UK and US are from India. Staffed by expert professional and healthcare providers who are efficient in the use of the latest methods of treatments using the required technology along with modern infrastructure boosts the number of visitors each year that visit the diverse nation for medical treatment.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the Home Front&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The metropolitan cities continue to be the top listers when asked for the preferred city for treatment. To begin with, Chennai is known as the medical capital of the country as it attracts 40% of medical tourists annually for its high-quality treatment and world-class natural medicinal treatments. It attracts patients seeking bone marrow transplant, cardiac bypass, eye surgery, hip replacement and alternative treatments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Next in line is Mumbai, the business capital of India is also a hub of commendable medical facilities housed inside efficient infrastructure with numerous super-speciality hospitals, Research and Diagnostic Centre for Orthopaedic and weight-loss surgeries. Mumbai attracts a large number of patients seeking cosmetic surgery and Ayurveda treatment. Coming up next is the National Capital Territory of Delhi, it is home to several well-equipped private hospitals that offer special packages to foreign patients for general surgeries, eye surgery, heart care and neuro-surgeries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The upward trend in medical tourism is a piece of good news for the domestic citizens as well. With more and more people travelling to India for medical benefits it speeds up the pace of infrastructural development in the health sector. The development is not limited to building better hospitals that are equipped with the latest technology and staffing healthcare professional that are well versed with the most efficient treatments, or preparing medical students that can give birth to unique treatments with their genius but also providing these world-class to its very own citizens in their own country at the best price possible.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with healthcare facilities, medical tourism plays a key role in keeping the hospitality industry running and enhancing its presence in the world. The advent of the novel coronavirus and India’s excellent plan to control the mass damage has fetched it another brownie point for the citizens to trust the Indian healthcare system. Our effective vaccination drive, which is inaugurated by bringing into use the vaccines made at home (India) and the Prime Minister’s drive to help other nations in need is a commendable combination of the personal touch added to the treatment, &lt;em&gt;atithi-devo-bhava &lt;/em&gt;(guest is equivalent to God), our history of extending arms in times of crisis and most importantly, the genius brain of our scientists and doctors!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Tourism is an important and rapidly growing industry of the Indian economy. This industry contributes to around 8-9% of India’s total GDP and creates millions of employment opportunities. Being home to various cultures, our country attracts tourists throughout the year. With an efficient and well-established infrastructure in terms of communication, transportation and a tourist-friendly visa policy, the number of tourists has seen a growth with each passing year.&amp;nbsp; Apart from this, medical tourism has witnessed considerable growth and success in the Indian economy. Indian medical tourism sector is estimated to be worth 3 billion US dollars and is growing at a speedy rate with each passing year. The top ten source countries contributing to India’s medical tourism include Bangladesh, Afghanistan, Iraq, Maldives, Oman, Yemen, Uzbekistan, Kenya, Nigeria and Tanzania.&amp;nbsp; Apart from Chennai, Mumbai and Delhi, various other cities have seen an increase in the number of patients from various countries. Medical tourism in India is largely promoted by the government and fueled by the corporate boom in medical care. There are a number of reasons contributing to this industry, the two major reasons being affordability and accessibility. What seeds medical tourism? Globalisation brings with it a plethora of opportunities for consumers to choose from and for countries to expand their scope of development. Apart from evolution, it also provides an opportunity for countries to collaborate their resources and provide the best in terms of education and health to the citizens of the world. One such brilliant example is India’s efficient medical facilities that are made available to the citizens at an affordable price.&amp;nbsp; India offers a complete posy of healthcare facilities available at an affordable and attractive price which is less than 40% than any developed western country without any compromise on the quality and care. Adding to this the travel, accommodation and insurance are also made available at a very reasonable rate.&amp;nbsp; While the cost of living in India is 66.54% lower than in the USA and the rent in India is 85% lower than in the USA which is another major reason why people fly to India for treatments that require staying at the place of treatment for a long period of time. People across the globe consider themselves as global citizens, thus ensure exploring the best opportunities across the world and India’s personalised touch of care in the form of Atithi-Devo-Bhava plays a crucial role in the recent growth of medical tourism in the country.&amp;nbsp; The accessibility and comfort are also the reasons why India is favourable for treatments and attracts patients from across the globe. To begin with, the medical visa norms of the country are very simplified and easy to gain access to, this ensures hassle-free travel, treatment and stay for the patient as well as the attendant.&amp;nbsp; The medical visa assures multiple entries and longer stays, the recent development of e-medical visa that was launched by the Union Government has been viewed as a key element in boosting medical tourism in India. Alongside, India is home to multiple cuisines and offers organically prepared food that speeds up the process of getting healthier also attracts people for getting treated with the least disturbance to their comfort zone. India also ensures no language barrier as it is claimed to be the second-largest English speaking country in the world. Lean or no waiting for surgeries as compared to long waiting for even simple surgeries in the western countries also pegs the way for tourists visiting India for medicinal purposes. India has always been a hub of genius brains that can excel in all the fields. Technology and medicine have been going hand-in-hand lately. India has shown the fastest adoption of recent medical technology when compared to its developing counterparts. With more than 500 accredited healthcare providers, India offers a variety of options at different locations in the country to choose from as per the visitor’s convenience.&amp;nbsp; Indian doctors, medicinal research, treatment and technology has been found to be at par with the western standard so much so that over 12% of doctors practising in the UK and US are from India. Staffed by expert professional and healthcare providers who are efficient in the use of the latest methods of treatments using the required technology along with modern infrastructure boosts the number of visitors each year that visit the diverse nation for medical treatment.&amp;nbsp; On the Home Front The metropolitan cities continue to be the top listers when asked for the preferred city for treatment. To begin with, Chennai is known as the medical capital of the country as it attracts 40% of medical tourists annually for its high-quality treatment and world-class natural medicinal treatments. It attracts patients seeking bone marrow transplant, cardiac bypass, eye surgery, hip replacement and alternative treatments.&amp;nbsp; Next in line is Mumbai, the business capital of India is also a hub of commendable medical facilities housed inside efficient infrastructure with numerous super-speciality hospitals, Research and Diagnostic Centre for Orthopaedic and weight-loss surgeries. Mumbai attracts a large number of patients seeking cosmetic surgery and Ayurveda treatment. Coming up next is the National Capital Territory of Delhi, it is home to several well-equipped private hospitals that offer special packages to foreign patients for general surgeries, eye surgery, heart care and neuro-surgeries.&amp;nbsp; The upward trend in medical tourism is a piece of good news for the domestic citizens as well. With more and more people travelling to India for medical benefits it speeds up the pace of infrastructural development in the health sector. The development is not limited to building better hospitals that are equipped with the latest technology and staffing healthcare professional that are well versed with the most efficient treatments, or preparing medical students that can give birth to unique treatments with their genius but also providing these world-class to its very own citizens in their own country at the best price possible.&amp;nbsp; Along with healthcare facilities, medical tourism plays a key role in keeping the hospitality industry running and enhancing its presence in the world. The advent of the novel coronavirus and India’s excellent plan to control the mass damage has fetched it another brownie point for the citizens to trust the Indian healthcare system. Our effective vaccination drive, which is inaugurated by bringing into use the vaccines made at home (India) and the Prime Minister’s drive to help other nations in need is a commendable combination of the personal touch added to the treatment, atithi-devo-bhava (guest is equivalent to God), our history of extending arms in times of crisis and most importantly, the genius brain of our scientists and doctors!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Sinews of an Industrialised Economy</title>
      <link href="/The-Sinews-of-an-Industrialised-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Sinews of an Industrialised Economy" />
      <published>2021-04-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-04-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Sinews-of-an-Industrialised-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Sinews-of-an-Industrialised-Economy">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The industrial sector, manufacturing, in particular, plays an important role in transforming a country from a low-income one, with agriculture dominating the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) composition, to a high-income, services-oriented country. The industrialisation of a country is a crucial phase in this transformation. Industrialisation is not only about a country becoming a manufacturing hub. There is a huge societal transformation that accompanies such industrialisation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Though the process of industrialisation is disruptive, it results in an increase in the income of the people. People become more refined in their behaviour, and education becomes a top priority in industrial society. Thus giving top priority to human investment. The state gains a monopoly over violence, the institutions of the state become more competent, and many other changes are observed. But the initiation of the process of industrialisation begins with the sectoral composition of the GDP moving from agriculture to industry, along with a similar shift in employment patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The transition from agriculture to an industrial economy is an important transformation that places a country on a high growth path. There is a tranche of changes that occur in different domains that facilitate a country in kick-starting its progression into a developed country.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;First, emerging as an industrial society increases the income of the people. There will be a guaranteed income flow for the average person in the society, unlike an agrarian economy where there is too much uncertainty in income generation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Second, with large scale migrations from rural to urban areas, whole new sectors emerge on the stage (e.g. daycare centres, dog walkers etc.) and the demand in the economy as a whole goes up.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Third, as people become more urban there is a deep social change that occurs, a change for good; this includes an increase in women's participation in the labour force, women becoming more independent and having a say in many things. Industrialisation can also be a factor that eases out the population pressure on society. Industrialisation also paves the way for education to become a major aspect in society. People hitherto employing their children on fields will send their kids to school because their income will suffice to support the family without the children having to work in the fields. But in all this, it is important to remember that industrialisation is a very disruptive activity. It, therefore, demands a strong state with strong enforcement mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The initial stages of industrialisation are, however, characterised by a population that has had only the experiences of a pre-industrial society. Literacy levels are generally low, most people are uneducated. This is where manufacturing comes into the picture. Manufacturing has the potential to absorb a large pool of labour. This is because of its fundamental characteristic of being dependent on labour for various reasons, despite the onset of technology.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;An increase in manufacturing also leads to a division of labour which increases mamifold the productivity of all sectors. To encourage manufacturing, however, there are a set of factors that need to be set in place. To discuss the factors that have to be put in place we may take the example of India, a textbook example of a country in the midst of the transformation from an agrarian society to an industrial one.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;First, India has reformed its archaic labour laws, which are a nightmare to anyone starting an industry. While regulation is desirable anytime, Indian labour laws are a case of over-regulation and need reform.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Second, India has to bring about land reforms. The Land Acquisition Bill, which was introduced in the Indian Parliament in 2014, was withdrawn due to a lack of political will. It is high time now that India passes that bill and makes land acquisitions easier.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, a consistent effort must be made to transition from an agricultural economy to an industrial economy. For this, a two-fold approach may be recommended. The Indian government should take all necessary steps to encourage industry, especially manufacturing; at the same time, it must improve the urban facilities of the country so as to accommodate the migration that occurs in the process of urbanisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the context of transforming India into an industrial economy, looking at China may offer some lessons. China began its reform process with agriculture by moving from the commune-based system to the household responsibility system, and by revising agricultural prices upwards by more than 20%, the results were for everyone to see. The agricultural growth rate jumped to 7.1% per annum during 1978-84, up from 2.5% during the pre-reform period of 1966-1977. This was followed by a dramatic reduction of poverty from 33% to 15% in the reform period between 1978 and 1984. Farm income in China grew by almost 14% per annum. It is high growth in farm incomes that boosted demand for manufacturing goods produced by town and village enterprises, kick-starting the manufacturing revolution in China.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In this context, Indian farm reforms are a welcome first step; though, a lot more could be done. India also has the necessary requirements in place. For instance, the Make in India scheme encourages the setting up of industries in India. It is imperative to back it up with other necessary steps. Initiatives like Skill India can be used for this purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Today, the Indian industry is complaining that rural demand is collapsing. One reason for that is the consistent reduction in rural population in India since the 1991 economic reforms. Another reason for this outcome is that India never had any major reforms with respect to its labour laws, land laws and agriculture laws; and farmers’ incomes have remained very low. However, it is also important to note that industry is not a substitute for agriculture, rather they are complementary to one another. Both these sectors are so intertwined that it is not possible to increase the growth of one sector without the improvement of the other sector. Industrialisation is also important to increase farm incomes in the country. This is because industrialisation moves people from farms to industries, thus consolidating the land holdings and thereby increasing productivity in the agriculture sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the long term, it is also imperative that India plan to address the issues of education and employment. There is a two-way correlation between industrialisation and education. In education, India seriously lacks skills-based education as the primary focus is always scoring marks rather than problem-solving and skills enhancement. To address this issue the government can partner with the industry to tailor the curriculum to suit the needs of the industry. The focus should shift to develop problem-solving skills. The government can also ask companies to spend their CSR amount on skills development programs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The elasticity of employment generation has been constantly falling and has come down to near zero in the last decade. This shows the grave danger that is in store in regards to job creation. In India, more often than not, entrepreneurs focus on price controls to cut down costs rather than on efficiency. In many cases, producers compete on the basis of price rather than efficiency. This should also change and for that, the government should incentivise firms to focus on efficiency rather than prices. India should act fast to take advantage of the changing scenario on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The economic reforms of 1991 have transformed the lives of the Indian people in many ways. The reforms led to new aspirations among the people, as the expectation was that the Indian economy would grow and India was going to be the next big thing on the world stage. Since the 1991 economic reforms were not adequately followed up, India has witnessed jobless growth for most of the period of its golden economic period of 2003-2008. Despite this, the Indian economy remained among the fastest-growing large economies of the world. Yet, it might appear paradoxical that with respect to achievements in human development, India is ranked at 129 out of 189 countries, according to the human development report 2019.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manufacturing has been the engine of modern economic growth, be it in Britain and the USA of the 19th century or Russia of the 20th century or China of the 21st century. India’s first plans to industrialise go as far back in time as the 1950's. The second Five-Year Plan spoke at lengths about the need for industrialisation and outlined the steps for the same. Unfortunately, India failed to industrialise. The Nehruvian model that the Indian state adopted subsequently proved disastrous for the country. Today, the time frame for India to take off and reap benefits of its demographic dividend is too small. India should act fast. Else, the future might be bleaker than we imagine today.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The industrial sector, manufacturing, in particular, plays an important role in transforming a country from a low-income one, with agriculture dominating the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) composition, to a high-income, services-oriented country. The industrialisation of a country is a crucial phase in this transformation. Industrialisation is not only about a country becoming a manufacturing hub. There is a huge societal transformation that accompanies such industrialisation.&amp;nbsp; Though the process of industrialisation is disruptive, it results in an increase in the income of the people. People become more refined in their behaviour, and education becomes a top priority in industrial society. Thus giving top priority to human investment. The state gains a monopoly over violence, the institutions of the state become more competent, and many other changes are observed. But the initiation of the process of industrialisation begins with the sectoral composition of the GDP moving from agriculture to industry, along with a similar shift in employment patterns. The transition from agriculture to an industrial economy is an important transformation that places a country on a high growth path. There is a tranche of changes that occur in different domains that facilitate a country in kick-starting its progression into a developed country.&amp;nbsp; First, emerging as an industrial society increases the income of the people. There will be a guaranteed income flow for the average person in the society, unlike an agrarian economy where there is too much uncertainty in income generation.&amp;nbsp; Second, with large scale migrations from rural to urban areas, whole new sectors emerge on the stage (e.g. daycare centres, dog walkers etc.) and the demand in the economy as a whole goes up.&amp;nbsp; Third, as people become more urban there is a deep social change that occurs, a change for good; this includes an increase in women's participation in the labour force, women becoming more independent and having a say in many things. Industrialisation can also be a factor that eases out the population pressure on society. Industrialisation also paves the way for education to become a major aspect in society. People hitherto employing their children on fields will send their kids to school because their income will suffice to support the family without the children having to work in the fields. But in all this, it is important to remember that industrialisation is a very disruptive activity. It, therefore, demands a strong state with strong enforcement mechanisms. The initial stages of industrialisation are, however, characterised by a population that has had only the experiences of a pre-industrial society. Literacy levels are generally low, most people are uneducated. This is where manufacturing comes into the picture. Manufacturing has the potential to absorb a large pool of labour. This is because of its fundamental characteristic of being dependent on labour for various reasons, despite the onset of technology.&amp;nbsp; An increase in manufacturing also leads to a division of labour which increases mamifold the productivity of all sectors. To encourage manufacturing, however, there are a set of factors that need to be set in place. To discuss the factors that have to be put in place we may take the example of India, a textbook example of a country in the midst of the transformation from an agrarian society to an industrial one.&amp;nbsp; First, India has reformed its archaic labour laws, which are a nightmare to anyone starting an industry. While regulation is desirable anytime, Indian labour laws are a case of over-regulation and need reform.&amp;nbsp; Second, India has to bring about land reforms. The Land Acquisition Bill, which was introduced in the Indian Parliament in 2014, was withdrawn due to a lack of political will. It is high time now that India passes that bill and makes land acquisitions easier.&amp;nbsp; However, a consistent effort must be made to transition from an agricultural economy to an industrial economy. For this, a two-fold approach may be recommended. The Indian government should take all necessary steps to encourage industry, especially manufacturing; at the same time, it must improve the urban facilities of the country so as to accommodate the migration that occurs in the process of urbanisation. In the context of transforming India into an industrial economy, looking at China may offer some lessons. China began its reform process with agriculture by moving from the commune-based system to the household responsibility system, and by revising agricultural prices upwards by more than 20%, the results were for everyone to see. The agricultural growth rate jumped to 7.1% per annum during 1978-84, up from 2.5% during the pre-reform period of 1966-1977. This was followed by a dramatic reduction of poverty from 33% to 15% in the reform period between 1978 and 1984. Farm income in China grew by almost 14% per annum. It is high growth in farm incomes that boosted demand for manufacturing goods produced by town and village enterprises, kick-starting the manufacturing revolution in China.&amp;nbsp; In this context, Indian farm reforms are a welcome first step; though, a lot more could be done. India also has the necessary requirements in place. For instance, the Make in India scheme encourages the setting up of industries in India. It is imperative to back it up with other necessary steps. Initiatives like Skill India can be used for this purpose. Today, the Indian industry is complaining that rural demand is collapsing. One reason for that is the consistent reduction in rural population in India since the 1991 economic reforms. Another reason for this outcome is that India never had any major reforms with respect to its labour laws, land laws and agriculture laws; and farmers’ incomes have remained very low. However, it is also important to note that industry is not a substitute for agriculture, rather they are complementary to one another. Both these sectors are so intertwined that it is not possible to increase the growth of one sector without the improvement of the other sector. Industrialisation is also important to increase farm incomes in the country. This is because industrialisation moves people from farms to industries, thus consolidating the land holdings and thereby increasing productivity in the agriculture sector. In the long term, it is also imperative that India plan to address the issues of education and employment. There is a two-way correlation between industrialisation and education. In education, India seriously lacks skills-based education as the primary focus is always scoring marks rather than problem-solving and skills enhancement. To address this issue the government can partner with the industry to tailor the curriculum to suit the needs of the industry. The focus should shift to develop problem-solving skills. The government can also ask companies to spend their CSR amount on skills development programs.&amp;nbsp; The elasticity of employment generation has been constantly falling and has come down to near zero in the last decade. This shows the grave danger that is in store in regards to job creation. In India, more often than not, entrepreneurs focus on price controls to cut down costs rather than on efficiency. In many cases, producers compete on the basis of price rather than efficiency. This should also change and for that, the government should incentivise firms to focus on efficiency rather than prices. India should act fast to take advantage of the changing scenario on the world stage. The economic reforms of 1991 have transformed the lives of the Indian people in many ways. The reforms led to new aspirations among the people, as the expectation was that the Indian economy would grow and India was going to be the next big thing on the world stage. Since the 1991 economic reforms were not adequately followed up, India has witnessed jobless growth for most of the period of its golden economic period of 2003-2008. Despite this, the Indian economy remained among the fastest-growing large economies of the world. Yet, it might appear paradoxical that with respect to achievements in human development, India is ranked at 129 out of 189 countries, according to the human development report 2019.&amp;nbsp; Manufacturing has been the engine of modern economic growth, be it in Britain and the USA of the 19th century or Russia of the 20th century or China of the 21st century. India’s first plans to industrialise go as far back in time as the 1950's. The second Five-Year Plan spoke at lengths about the need for industrialisation and outlined the steps for the same. Unfortunately, India failed to industrialise. The Nehruvian model that the Indian state adopted subsequently proved disastrous for the country. Today, the time frame for India to take off and reap benefits of its demographic dividend is too small. India should act fast. Else, the future might be bleaker than we imagine today.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Strike of the Tax Cobra</title>
      <link href="/The-Strike-of-the-Tax-Cobra" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Strike of the Tax Cobra " />
      <published>2021-04-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-04-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Strike-of-the-Tax-Cobra</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Strike-of-the-Tax-Cobra">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There is diametric collinearity between humans and perishable commodities, both of them face an end, that is, both of them die. Ideas, on the other hand, are perennial. Of course with the advent of new ideas, the old ones may become obsolete, but they never die down, they’re there to stay.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A ton of macroeconomic growth theories are based on the foundation of ideas, economists like Solow and Romer are there to testify. One may think that all ideas come in the snap of a finger, like a light bulb over your head, capable of revolutionising, like some sort of a miracle, but that’s obviously not how it works in the real world. Because the real world is a lasagna of problems that exist in multiple layers. And no, they cannot be solved in a snap.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Hence, researchers and experts are perpetually working to give birth to or discover new ideas that help solve a pinch of the problems of this world we live in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Economists too are constantly working with the government to roll out new policies and strategies each consecutive year that make the economy run efficiently and satisfactorily, like a butter knife spreading butter on a slice of bread. Except, policies do not always pan out the way they were expected to. And this isn't where I talk about the policies giving an alternate outcome of what was expected, but the entirely opposite outcome, which worsens the problem at hand.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This brings me to talk about ‘The Cobra Effect’, which in literal terms means a policy or a strategy, made for the greater good, that leafs to certain unforeseen post-implementation consequences that don't just make the policy or strategy redundant, but also backfire well enough to compel the government to not just repeal the said policy/strategy but also make another move in the positive direction, a well-analysed one keeping the after-effects of it in mind.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A simple example to illustrate the idea better could be none other than road safety in India. With the massive population of India and its mortality rate existing in a spectrum of causes, road accidents are a major one. Imagine a handful of sand and then imagine the rate at which it slips out of your clenched fists. That’s the rate at which people riding on two-wheelers and cars face road accidents in India. To prevent this, the government decided to roll out a rule that car drivers would be fined a penalty amount in case they are seen driving without a seatbelt. &lt;em&gt;What did this do?&lt;/em&gt; This made the car drivers wear a seatbelt to prevent incurring the fine, but also made them counter-incentivised to now drive more recklessly thereby increasing their own risk to injury but also passersby’s and pedestrians’ risk to a road accident. Hence, this move didn’t just give an alternate outcome, but a diametrically opposite one to what was expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Digressing a little from the Cobra Effect, let us look at a topic that is very essentially affecting India as we speak, something that is also very politicised and very heavily debated upon across news platforms and social media, the ‘Goods and Services Tax’ or GST - a tax system formulated and applied and amended a total of 950 times, to aid the ease of doing business and to eliminate corruption by levying the tax on the value added to a good at every stage till it reaches the consumer. In a move to reduce costs incurred by producers and retailers by making far-reaching changes in the tax system, GST has surely brought about its own set of concerns, ones that are inherently opposed to its intended outcome.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To understand the negative implications of GST, let's look at a few reasons behind the recent protest by the Indian traders’ associations against it. Although we have been told our entire lives that making mistakes is okay, the same does not hold true when it comes to small businesses making mistakes while filing their returns. It is a huge irony to what some people, playing on the acronym, call it a 'Good and Simple Tax'. With the three categories under GST, namely - Central GST (CGST), State GST (SGST) and Inter-state GST (IGST), the government portal for GST allows no trading firm to review their purchase returns once filed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In multiple instances, firms mistakenly enter the IGST returns under CGST and SGST, or vice versa, and the only mechanism that the government then provides is to either cease your Input Tax Credit (ITC) for that particular transaction by sending a mismatch notice or claim your mistakenly filed returns under “assessment” and not refund the excess amount. This has effected a blow on the export industry who was already badly affected by the e-way bill amendment to GST.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The e-way bill was introduced so goods can be transported inter-state with ease, except the reality is that its the most strenuous process for any business, considering the government’s mandates of filling in all details, including vehicle numbers, specific goods’ names, and so on, on the online portal post. Moreover, a truck carrying a consignment with an expired e-way bill or an erroneous e-way bill is penalised 200% of the tax value.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The space that GST has allowed for natural human errors or even software errors is extremely narrow. What is making things even more difficult for such traders is that the grunt of the glitches in the online GST portal is also faced by these traders, and not the government. This makes it legit for the traders’ body to then claim that GST is begetting &lt;em&gt;'tax terrorism' &lt;/em&gt;in India and giving arbitrary powers to the government.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The worst hit by the entire situation are the ones that GST claimed to make better off, the Small and Medium Enterprises (SME). The cost of purchasing the software and hiring tax professionals, like chartered accountants, has made these firms incur more operational and overhead costs than anticipated. Moreover, since the new rule is that all businesses with a turnover exceeding Rupees 20 lakhs need to pay GST, another rule for the SMEs dictates that business with a turnover of up to ₹7.5 million can opt for the composition scheme and pay only 1% tax on turnover in exchange of GST and enjoy lesser compliances. &lt;em&gt;Sounds like a simple decision, doesn’t it? &lt;/em&gt;Except, it isn’t, since there is the catch to this - the businesses that opt for this will not be able to claim any Input Tax Credit (ITC), hence leaving these SMEs in a dilemma to choose between a deep-sea and a cliff.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;All in all, my view is that GST most definitely has a Cobra Effect on the Indian economy as it fails to fulfil the one thing it promised - good governance and ease of doing business. Of course, there are ways to change that by listening to the genuine demands of traders, entrepreneurs and various other industries and making compliances in a manner that in order to eliminate a few bads, we do not end up destroying the innocents. Because all they have got as humans are their ideas and their perishables.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There is diametric collinearity between humans and perishable commodities, both of them face an end, that is, both of them die. Ideas, on the other hand, are perennial. Of course with the advent of new ideas, the old ones may become obsolete, but they never die down, they’re there to stay.&amp;nbsp; A ton of macroeconomic growth theories are based on the foundation of ideas, economists like Solow and Romer are there to testify. One may think that all ideas come in the snap of a finger, like a light bulb over your head, capable of revolutionising, like some sort of a miracle, but that’s obviously not how it works in the real world. Because the real world is a lasagna of problems that exist in multiple layers. And no, they cannot be solved in a snap.&amp;nbsp; Hence, researchers and experts are perpetually working to give birth to or discover new ideas that help solve a pinch of the problems of this world we live in. Economists too are constantly working with the government to roll out new policies and strategies each consecutive year that make the economy run efficiently and satisfactorily, like a butter knife spreading butter on a slice of bread. Except, policies do not always pan out the way they were expected to. And this isn't where I talk about the policies giving an alternate outcome of what was expected, but the entirely opposite outcome, which worsens the problem at hand.&amp;nbsp; This brings me to talk about ‘The Cobra Effect’, which in literal terms means a policy or a strategy, made for the greater good, that leafs to certain unforeseen post-implementation consequences that don't just make the policy or strategy redundant, but also backfire well enough to compel the government to not just repeal the said policy/strategy but also make another move in the positive direction, a well-analysed one keeping the after-effects of it in mind.&amp;nbsp; A simple example to illustrate the idea better could be none other than road safety in India. With the massive population of India and its mortality rate existing in a spectrum of causes, road accidents are a major one. Imagine a handful of sand and then imagine the rate at which it slips out of your clenched fists. That’s the rate at which people riding on two-wheelers and cars face road accidents in India. To prevent this, the government decided to roll out a rule that car drivers would be fined a penalty amount in case they are seen driving without a seatbelt. What did this do? This made the car drivers wear a seatbelt to prevent incurring the fine, but also made them counter-incentivised to now drive more recklessly thereby increasing their own risk to injury but also passersby’s and pedestrians’ risk to a road accident. Hence, this move didn’t just give an alternate outcome, but a diametrically opposite one to what was expected. Digressing a little from the Cobra Effect, let us look at a topic that is very essentially affecting India as we speak, something that is also very politicised and very heavily debated upon across news platforms and social media, the ‘Goods and Services Tax’ or GST - a tax system formulated and applied and amended a total of 950 times, to aid the ease of doing business and to eliminate corruption by levying the tax on the value added to a good at every stage till it reaches the consumer. In a move to reduce costs incurred by producers and retailers by making far-reaching changes in the tax system, GST has surely brought about its own set of concerns, ones that are inherently opposed to its intended outcome.&amp;nbsp; To understand the negative implications of GST, let's look at a few reasons behind the recent protest by the Indian traders’ associations against it. Although we have been told our entire lives that making mistakes is okay, the same does not hold true when it comes to small businesses making mistakes while filing their returns. It is a huge irony to what some people, playing on the acronym, call it a 'Good and Simple Tax'. With the three categories under GST, namely - Central GST (CGST), State GST (SGST) and Inter-state GST (IGST), the government portal for GST allows no trading firm to review their purchase returns once filed.&amp;nbsp; In multiple instances, firms mistakenly enter the IGST returns under CGST and SGST, or vice versa, and the only mechanism that the government then provides is to either cease your Input Tax Credit (ITC) for that particular transaction by sending a mismatch notice or claim your mistakenly filed returns under “assessment” and not refund the excess amount. This has effected a blow on the export industry who was already badly affected by the e-way bill amendment to GST.&amp;nbsp; The e-way bill was introduced so goods can be transported inter-state with ease, except the reality is that its the most strenuous process for any business, considering the government’s mandates of filling in all details, including vehicle numbers, specific goods’ names, and so on, on the online portal post. Moreover, a truck carrying a consignment with an expired e-way bill or an erroneous e-way bill is penalised 200% of the tax value.&amp;nbsp; The space that GST has allowed for natural human errors or even software errors is extremely narrow. What is making things even more difficult for such traders is that the grunt of the glitches in the online GST portal is also faced by these traders, and not the government. This makes it legit for the traders’ body to then claim that GST is begetting 'tax terrorism' in India and giving arbitrary powers to the government.&amp;nbsp; The worst hit by the entire situation are the ones that GST claimed to make better off, the Small and Medium Enterprises (SME). The cost of purchasing the software and hiring tax professionals, like chartered accountants, has made these firms incur more operational and overhead costs than anticipated. Moreover, since the new rule is that all businesses with a turnover exceeding Rupees 20 lakhs need to pay GST, another rule for the SMEs dictates that business with a turnover of up to ₹7.5 million can opt for the composition scheme and pay only 1% tax on turnover in exchange of GST and enjoy lesser compliances. Sounds like a simple decision, doesn’t it? Except, it isn’t, since there is the catch to this - the businesses that opt for this will not be able to claim any Input Tax Credit (ITC), hence leaving these SMEs in a dilemma to choose between a deep-sea and a cliff.&amp;nbsp; All in all, my view is that GST most definitely has a Cobra Effect on the Indian economy as it fails to fulfil the one thing it promised - good governance and ease of doing business. Of course, there are ways to change that by listening to the genuine demands of traders, entrepreneurs and various other industries and making compliances in a manner that in order to eliminate a few bads, we do not end up destroying the innocents. Because all they have got as humans are their ideas and their perishables.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why India as a Superpower is a Distant Reality Part II</title>
      <link href="/Why-India-as-a-Superpower-is-a-Distant-Reality-Part-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why India as a Superpower is a Distant Reality Part II" />
      <published>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-India-as-a-Superpower-is-a-Distant-Reality-Part-II</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-India-as-a-Superpower-is-a-Distant-Reality-Part-II">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This article is the final part of the two-part series discussing the perils in the path of India becoming a superpower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Judicial Reforms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Law enforcement and the judicial system are the pillars on which the effectiveness of justice delivery depends. We have looked at the problems bugging India’s law enforcement in the first part of the article. Here we discuss the judiciary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The primary problem with the Indian judiciary is the pendency of cases. At the time of this writing, a total of 37,206,322 are&lt;a href=&quot;https://njdg.ecourts.gov.in/njdgnew/?p=main/pend_dashboard&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://njdg.ecourts.gov.in/njdgnew/?p=main/pend_dashboard&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pending&lt;/a&gt; before the District and subordinate courts in India. Another 5,660,908 cases, of which 87.54% are cases more than a year old, are pending before the High Courts in India. The result is one of an overburdened and sub-optimal judiciary. Some estimates put the time taken to resolve all the pending cases before the Indian Courts close to 300 years! So, what is the way forward?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;One suggestion is to establish appellate courts to expedite the pending cases. Courts of appeals at the district level, state level and national level can help reduce the burden on the courts. The Supreme Court of India also acts as an appellate Court, apart from acting as the Constitutional Court (which the Court can do under Article 133 and 134 of the Indian Constitution in civil and criminal matters respectively). This puts additional burden on the Supreme Court, and it is in fact plagued by a huge workload. To reduce this burden, the appellate work of the Supreme Court may be separated by setting up a Supreme Appellate Court, and its benches could be set up across the country. Apart from this, cognitive technologies could be incorporated into the dispute resolution mechanism (in civil cases). For instance, the biggest litigants today are the various governments in India. Government officials, who decide not to appeal an adverse order, often run the risk of having to justify why they did not pursue the matter more vigorously. Incorporating cognitive technologies can help these officials analyse the chances of a successful appeal better. They can also help the judges in the decision-making process, which could lead to faster decisions and thus, could dispose of a case quickly. But most important of all, the lower rung of courts should be strengthened by filling the vacancies, establishing new posts and developing the infrastructure; for, most of the cases are filed at the lower level and most of the disputes are settled there itself.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another problem with the courts today is the lack of accountability. The introduction of the collegium system in 1998 means that the judges across all the Indian courts are appointed by the higher courts but not the political executive. This is clearly against the principle of checks and balances. The Government of India tried to establish a National Judicial Appoints Committee in 2014. Despite the Parliament of India clearing it, the Supreme Court struck it down saying it violated ‘the basic structure’ doctrine. Collegium, therefore, can only be abolished if all the members of Parliament come together and stand up to the highest court of the land and force its hand. They should do it because it is in the best interest of the country. The Supreme Court should also exercise restraint when it wades into the duties of the executive and legislature and uphold the doctrine of separation of powers. This judicial activism, which has sometimes worked well to deliver justice, has also harmed the Indian economy (from the cancelation of 2G spectrum auctions, the cancellation of coal licences to the recent staying of the farm laws enacted by the Indian Parliament).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;After all is said and done, the judiciary, for all its failures, provides places for discussion and debate. IT acts as a forum for a certain amount of churn. Reforming the judiciary, therefore, is in the best interest of India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social indicators should be improved&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;We Indians are constantly obsessed with ranks. “India is the world’s fastest growing economy,” “India is the world’s third largest economy” we exclaim. But economic growth is not everything, we forget. A look at the social indicators of the country paints a much darker picture. India lags behind its neighbours in human development and social development indicators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;By comparing India with its neighbours, we can analyse the situation. The infant mortality rate, the number of infant deaths per 1,000 births, is 32 in India while it was 27 in Bangladesh in 2017. As of 2015, India’s life expectancy is 68.35, lagging behind Sri Lanka, Bangladesh, Nepal and Bhutan. Between 2003 and 2015 Bangladesh was successful in bringing down the open-defecation rate from 43% to 1%, while India is still struggling with it. Back in 2010 only, infant immunization for DPT and measles in Bangladesh, Sri Lanka and Nepal was about 80%, while India stood somewhere around 65%. In terms of sanitation facilities too, India’s neighbours outperform, though the situation is improving in India. The first&amp;nbsp; phase of the National Family Health Survey (NFHS) released in December 2020 indicates that India could be seeing an increase in child undernutrition. Child undernutrition, measured using three indicators namely stunting, wasting and underweight, has grown in many of the states in the latest NFHS. A rise in the all-India figures would mean that India is reversing the gains it had achieved since 1998-1999. Of all, the problem of stunting is serious in that it affects the cognitive abilities of the children and it could take up to three generations to undo the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It is not that the Indian government is not capable of delivering things. It had successfully carried out the polio vaccination programme and eradicated polio. More recently, it succeeded in getting the people to wear masks to combat the COVID-19 pandemic and proved false the many estimates which predicted 200-300 million deaths due to the pandemic. To improve the social indicators, the government can start by educating people through spreading information via cell phones when someone calls the other. Most importantly, NGOs in India are doing a commendable job in tackling various social problems in India. Government can very well incorporate them and work alongside them to change things where India’s performance lacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There are many other areas which need complete overhaul or effective management. For instance, from modernization of military equipment to facing the challenge of low diplomatic corps, India’s external security faces many challenges. India faces major national security challenges from a more authoritative China and an unstable Pakistan. Another area is that of data collection. Data collection faces huge problems and the depth of the problem is drastic. Often, due to lack of coordination among the various government departments, same data is collected by different departments and, sometimes, the departments arrive at different conclusions! To make cross-state comparisons, one often has to move mountains to gather and then interpret data. It is important to have standardised data collection mechanisms and data interpretations platforms so as to formulate policies that are relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Finally, the problems are huge. And they should be fixed if India has any hopes of playing an important role globally. India faces a (funny?) paradox. On the one hand, various governments in India are among the largest employment providers in the country and on the other practically every department is understaffed. This tells us that we need more personnel, but in the right places. India should also invest in creating a knowledge base for all relevant and necessary functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India is a pre-industrial economy living through an information age. Often, the state has to play a strong role in an industrial economy, but has to take a back seat in the information economy. How the Indian state sets about resolving this paradox also determines India’s future. If we look at history, the most resistance to change comes from villages; and they tend to become violent to resist change. This also presents India with unique challenges. However, the biggest of the problems is in realising all that we have discussed are not any of these. It is that these policies present huge political risks. In a country where the political representation is so heavily skewed towards rural India, whose population is about 30%-40%, the political priorities are also skewed towards rural India and their problems. India needs a leader who focuses on not winning the next election, but on doing the right thing, to get what we have discussed done. That leader may not come to power, but he/she/the will forever changed the fate of the country for the better.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This article is the final part of the two-part series discussing the perils in the path of India becoming a superpower. Judicial Reforms Law enforcement and the judicial system are the pillars on which the effectiveness of justice delivery depends. We have looked at the problems bugging India’s law enforcement in the first part of the article. Here we discuss the judiciary. The primary problem with the Indian judiciary is the pendency of cases. At the time of this writing, a total of 37,206,322 are pending before the District and subordinate courts in India. Another 5,660,908 cases, of which 87.54% are cases more than a year old, are pending before the High Courts in India. The result is one of an overburdened and sub-optimal judiciary. Some estimates put the time taken to resolve all the pending cases before the Indian Courts close to 300 years! So, what is the way forward?&amp;nbsp; One suggestion is to establish appellate courts to expedite the pending cases. Courts of appeals at the district level, state level and national level can help reduce the burden on the courts. The Supreme Court of India also acts as an appellate Court, apart from acting as the Constitutional Court (which the Court can do under Article 133 and 134 of the Indian Constitution in civil and criminal matters respectively). This puts additional burden on the Supreme Court, and it is in fact plagued by a huge workload. To reduce this burden, the appellate work of the Supreme Court may be separated by setting up a Supreme Appellate Court, and its benches could be set up across the country. Apart from this, cognitive technologies could be incorporated into the dispute resolution mechanism (in civil cases). For instance, the biggest litigants today are the various governments in India. Government officials, who decide not to appeal an adverse order, often run the risk of having to justify why they did not pursue the matter more vigorously. Incorporating cognitive technologies can help these officials analyse the chances of a successful appeal better. They can also help the judges in the decision-making process, which could lead to faster decisions and thus, could dispose of a case quickly. But most important of all, the lower rung of courts should be strengthened by filling the vacancies, establishing new posts and developing the infrastructure; for, most of the cases are filed at the lower level and most of the disputes are settled there itself.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Another problem with the courts today is the lack of accountability. The introduction of the collegium system in 1998 means that the judges across all the Indian courts are appointed by the higher courts but not the political executive. This is clearly against the principle of checks and balances. The Government of India tried to establish a National Judicial Appoints Committee in 2014. Despite the Parliament of India clearing it, the Supreme Court struck it down saying it violated ‘the basic structure’ doctrine. Collegium, therefore, can only be abolished if all the members of Parliament come together and stand up to the highest court of the land and force its hand. They should do it because it is in the best interest of the country. The Supreme Court should also exercise restraint when it wades into the duties of the executive and legislature and uphold the doctrine of separation of powers. This judicial activism, which has sometimes worked well to deliver justice, has also harmed the Indian economy (from the cancelation of 2G spectrum auctions, the cancellation of coal licences to the recent staying of the farm laws enacted by the Indian Parliament). After all is said and done, the judiciary, for all its failures, provides places for discussion and debate. IT acts as a forum for a certain amount of churn. Reforming the judiciary, therefore, is in the best interest of India. Social indicators should be improved We Indians are constantly obsessed with ranks. “India is the world’s fastest growing economy,” “India is the world’s third largest economy” we exclaim. But economic growth is not everything, we forget. A look at the social indicators of the country paints a much darker picture. India lags behind its neighbours in human development and social development indicators. By comparing India with its neighbours, we can analyse the situation. The infant mortality rate, the number of infant deaths per 1,000 births, is 32 in India while it was 27 in Bangladesh in 2017. As of 2015, India’s life expectancy is 68.35, lagging behind Sri Lanka, Bangladesh, Nepal and Bhutan. Between 2003 and 2015 Bangladesh was successful in bringing down the open-defecation rate from 43% to 1%, while India is still struggling with it. Back in 2010 only, infant immunization for DPT and measles in Bangladesh, Sri Lanka and Nepal was about 80%, while India stood somewhere around 65%. In terms of sanitation facilities too, India’s neighbours outperform, though the situation is improving in India. The first&amp;nbsp; phase of the National Family Health Survey (NFHS) released in December 2020 indicates that India could be seeing an increase in child undernutrition. Child undernutrition, measured using three indicators namely stunting, wasting and underweight, has grown in many of the states in the latest NFHS. A rise in the all-India figures would mean that India is reversing the gains it had achieved since 1998-1999. Of all, the problem of stunting is serious in that it affects the cognitive abilities of the children and it could take up to three generations to undo the problem. It is not that the Indian government is not capable of delivering things. It had successfully carried out the polio vaccination programme and eradicated polio. More recently, it succeeded in getting the people to wear masks to combat the COVID-19 pandemic and proved false the many estimates which predicted 200-300 million deaths due to the pandemic. To improve the social indicators, the government can start by educating people through spreading information via cell phones when someone calls the other. Most importantly, NGOs in India are doing a commendable job in tackling various social problems in India. Government can very well incorporate them and work alongside them to change things where India’s performance lacks. There are many other areas which need complete overhaul or effective management. For instance, from modernization of military equipment to facing the challenge of low diplomatic corps, India’s external security faces many challenges. India faces major national security challenges from a more authoritative China and an unstable Pakistan. Another area is that of data collection. Data collection faces huge problems and the depth of the problem is drastic. Often, due to lack of coordination among the various government departments, same data is collected by different departments and, sometimes, the departments arrive at different conclusions! To make cross-state comparisons, one often has to move mountains to gather and then interpret data. It is important to have standardised data collection mechanisms and data interpretations platforms so as to formulate policies that are relevant. Finally, the problems are huge. And they should be fixed if India has any hopes of playing an important role globally. India faces a (funny?) paradox. On the one hand, various governments in India are among the largest employment providers in the country and on the other practically every department is understaffed. This tells us that we need more personnel, but in the right places. India should also invest in creating a knowledge base for all relevant and necessary functions. India is a pre-industrial economy living through an information age. Often, the state has to play a strong role in an industrial economy, but has to take a back seat in the information economy. How the Indian state sets about resolving this paradox also determines India’s future. If we look at history, the most resistance to change comes from villages; and they tend to become violent to resist change. This also presents India with unique challenges. However, the biggest of the problems is in realising all that we have discussed are not any of these. It is that these policies present huge political risks. In a country where the political representation is so heavily skewed towards rural India, whose population is about 30%-40%, the political priorities are also skewed towards rural India and their problems. India needs a leader who focuses on not winning the next election, but on doing the right thing, to get what we have discussed done. That leader may not come to power, but he/she/the will forever changed the fate of the country for the better.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Will the Bills Bear Fruit?!</title>
      <link href="/Will-the-Bills-Bear-Fruit" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Will the Bills Bear Fruit?!" />
      <published>2021-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Will-the-Bills-Bear-Fruit</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Will-the-Bills-Bear-Fruit">&lt;p&gt;The past year was certainly filled with uncertainty at every point! The pandemic affected lives and livelihoods in the most unexpected manner and the entire world was in a state of despair. Most of us are very hopeful that 2021 will be different. As we start this year full of hope and joy, there are many who welcomed it in the most unforeseen manner. The ongoing farmers' protest in and around Delhi, India is in full swing. The farmers are determined and have been protesting for over 60 days now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Indian government passed three farm bills in September 2020. The bills claim to revolutionise the agriculture sector and related services. They also aim to double the income of farmers with the help of new rules and regulations. Even after these promises, the farmers are reluctant and want the government to withdraw the bills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The bills are as follows:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-&amp;nbsp; 	The Farmers’ Produce Trade and Commerce (Promotion and Facilitation) Bill, 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-&amp;nbsp; 	The Farmers (Empowerment and Protection) Agreement of Price Assurance and Farm Services Bill, 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-&amp;nbsp; 	The Essential Commodities (Amendment) Bill, 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the existing system, farmers were supposed to sell their produce in registered Agricultural Produce Market Committee (APMC) markets (&lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt;). As the first bill comes into effect, it will allow the farmers to sell their produce outside of these APMC markets. This gives free entry to private corporations in the market and to directly deal with the farmers. Even though this sounds good, as farmers will now have autonomy regarding where to sell their produce, it won’t be as beneficial as it claims to be. Reports show that 85% of the farmers fall in the category of marginal or small farmers who own less than 2 hectares of land. These farmers will now have to face competition in the open market as government regulations will be reduced. Since most of them are marginal farmers, big corporates will certainly try to exploit them during transactions. Thus, these farmers will be worse off in the revolutionised era. The corporations will find it easy to buy produce at minimum prices, thereby increasing their profits. Without government intervention, it will be easy for corporations to use unfair practices during trade. The effects of the bills on farmers are manifold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second bill allows farmers to enter into contract farming with agribusiness firms, wholesale vendors or large retailers at pre-agreed prices. Even though this move helps the big farmers as they won’t be regulated by a third party, the marginal farmers won’t be gaining much out of the scheme. No regulation from the government's end also gives an edge to the firms in negotiations. Farmers are seeing this bill as an opportunity for agribusiness firms and retailers to expand themselves and dominate the market. They would definitely earn more profits without the imposition of rules. Thus, the bill is more beneficial for the corporations rather than the farmers, especially the small farmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third bill removes many commodities like pulses, cereals, onions, etc. from the essential commodities list. This allows firms and retailers to hoard these commodities for longer periods. This essentially gives them the power to manipulate pricing and dominate the farmers during trade and transactions. This also means that the minimum support price (MSP) won’t be given for these commodities. This leaves the farmers with little or no incentive to continue the production of the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above explanation gives us an idea that the three bills don’t directly benefit the farmers much. They are simply easing the regulation that existed in the agricultural sector. It gives a free entry to private players who in turn will exploit the marginal and poor farmers for their personal gains. As soon as the government steps out, the negotiating power of the farmers also reduces. They will be more vulnerable and the removal of MSP from certain commodities makes it even worse for them. As mentioned before, 85% of the farmers are small and thus are barely making any profits. These bills do not incentivise them in any way. The demands of the farmers still remain the same and unheard. Improved infrastructure and farming supplements at subsidised prices would benefit them way more than the privatisation which these bills indirectly aim at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protest has prolonged since September and the Indian government&amp;nbsp; has ignored it all along. The maximum population of our country is involved in agriculture and thus makes it a vital part of our economy. These disruptions directly affect the flow of business cycles as well. The bills have been painting a very rosy picture which doesn’t really fit the frame. The only people who will make money after the implementation will be the rich retailers and firm owners. The exploitation will increase without government intervention and thus farmers will have to struggle more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are currently witnessing the largest protest ever held and that conveys the urgency of the issue. It directly hits the poor who will most likely lose out on their meagre incomes once these laws come into play. The consequences are cyclic and the propensity of loss increases on this side. Welfare has always been a priority for our state. We have managed to follow a mixed economic model, which has proved&amp;nbsp; beneficial for all sectors. Privatisation might be the next step towards the reform but not at the cost of farmers losing out on their livelihoods. The need of the hour is to make them more self-reliant and provide them with farming supplements at cheaper rates. Reforms are only helpful when everyone is capable of making the best out of the available opportunities!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The past year was certainly filled with uncertainty at every point! The pandemic affected lives and livelihoods in the most unexpected manner and the entire world was in a state of despair. Most of us are very hopeful that 2021 will be different. As we start this year full of hope and joy, there are many who welcomed it in the most unforeseen manner. The ongoing farmers' protest in and around Delhi, India is in full swing. The farmers are determined and have been protesting for over 60 days now. The Indian government passed three farm bills in September 2020. The bills claim to revolutionise the agriculture sector and related services. They also aim to double the income of farmers with the help of new rules and regulations. Even after these promises, the farmers are reluctant and want the government to withdraw the bills. The bills are as follows: -&amp;nbsp; The Farmers’ Produce Trade and Commerce (Promotion and Facilitation) Bill, 2020 -&amp;nbsp; The Farmers (Empowerment and Protection) Agreement of Price Assurance and Farm Services Bill, 2020 -&amp;nbsp; The Essential Commodities (Amendment) Bill, 2020 In the existing system, farmers were supposed to sell their produce in registered Agricultural Produce Market Committee (APMC) markets (mandis). As the first bill comes into effect, it will allow the farmers to sell their produce outside of these APMC markets. This gives free entry to private corporations in the market and to directly deal with the farmers. Even though this sounds good, as farmers will now have autonomy regarding where to sell their produce, it won’t be as beneficial as it claims to be. Reports show that 85% of the farmers fall in the category of marginal or small farmers who own less than 2 hectares of land. These farmers will now have to face competition in the open market as government regulations will be reduced. Since most of them are marginal farmers, big corporates will certainly try to exploit them during transactions. Thus, these farmers will be worse off in the revolutionised era. The corporations will find it easy to buy produce at minimum prices, thereby increasing their profits. Without government intervention, it will be easy for corporations to use unfair practices during trade. The effects of the bills on farmers are manifold. The second bill allows farmers to enter into contract farming with agribusiness firms, wholesale vendors or large retailers at pre-agreed prices. Even though this move helps the big farmers as they won’t be regulated by a third party, the marginal farmers won’t be gaining much out of the scheme. No regulation from the government's end also gives an edge to the firms in negotiations. Farmers are seeing this bill as an opportunity for agribusiness firms and retailers to expand themselves and dominate the market. They would definitely earn more profits without the imposition of rules. Thus, the bill is more beneficial for the corporations rather than the farmers, especially the small farmers. The third bill removes many commodities like pulses, cereals, onions, etc. from the essential commodities list. This allows firms and retailers to hoard these commodities for longer periods. This essentially gives them the power to manipulate pricing and dominate the farmers during trade and transactions. This also means that the minimum support price (MSP) won’t be given for these commodities. This leaves the farmers with little or no incentive to continue the production of the same. The above explanation gives us an idea that the three bills don’t directly benefit the farmers much. They are simply easing the regulation that existed in the agricultural sector. It gives a free entry to private players who in turn will exploit the marginal and poor farmers for their personal gains. As soon as the government steps out, the negotiating power of the farmers also reduces. They will be more vulnerable and the removal of MSP from certain commodities makes it even worse for them. As mentioned before, 85% of the farmers are small and thus are barely making any profits. These bills do not incentivise them in any way. The demands of the farmers still remain the same and unheard. Improved infrastructure and farming supplements at subsidised prices would benefit them way more than the privatisation which these bills indirectly aim at. The protest has prolonged since September and the Indian government&amp;nbsp; has ignored it all along. The maximum population of our country is involved in agriculture and thus makes it a vital part of our economy. These disruptions directly affect the flow of business cycles as well. The bills have been painting a very rosy picture which doesn’t really fit the frame. The only people who will make money after the implementation will be the rich retailers and firm owners. The exploitation will increase without government intervention and thus farmers will have to struggle more than ever. We are currently witnessing the largest protest ever held and that conveys the urgency of the issue. It directly hits the poor who will most likely lose out on their meagre incomes once these laws come into play. The consequences are cyclic and the propensity of loss increases on this side. Welfare has always been a priority for our state. We have managed to follow a mixed economic model, which has proved&amp;nbsp; beneficial for all sectors. Privatisation might be the next step towards the reform but not at the cost of farmers losing out on their livelihoods. The need of the hour is to make them more self-reliant and provide them with farming supplements at cheaper rates. Reforms are only helpful when everyone is capable of making the best out of the available opportunities!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why India as a Superpower is a Distant Reality Part I</title>
      <link href="/Why-India-as-a-Superpower-is-a-Distant-Reality-Part-I" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why India as a Superpower is a Distant Reality Part I" />
      <published>2021-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-India-as-a-Superpower-is-a-Distant-Reality-Part-I</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-India-as-a-Superpower-is-a-Distant-Reality-Part-I">&lt;p&gt;The changing geopolitical structure of the contemporary world will expect India to play a larger role in world affairs. Coupling this with the call made by Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi to make India a $5 trillion economy, we are looking at a scenario where India is a potential superpower candidate in the 21st century. And Indians have always believed, owing to the rich civilisational heritage the country had in the past, that they deserve to lead the world – becoming the &lt;em&gt;viswaguru &lt;/em&gt;('lord of the world')&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; For this, India must present its world view and leverage its soft power to influence the world. At the same time, it is important for the country to get its ducks in a row; for, without resolving its domestic problems, we can forget about leading the world. In this article, I try to highlight some crucial problems that need immediate attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Law and Order&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first major roadblock pertains to law and order in India. With the Indian police, the issues pertain to distrust, understaffing, accountability and inefficiency. First, there is a lot of distrust towards the police among the public. A 2018&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lokniti.org/media/upload_files/Report%20Police%20Survey.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lokniti.org/media/upload_files/Report%20Police%20Survey.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt; found that less than 25% of Indians trust the police. This distrust can be attributed to the prevalent corruption in the police departments, the police-politician nexus and the abuse of power by the police. In the Indian Corruption&lt;a href=&quot;https://transparencyindia.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/11/India-Corruption-Survey-2019.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://transparencyindia.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/11/India-Corruption-Survey-2019.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Survey&lt;/a&gt; 2019, the police department was found to be the second most corrupt department in the country.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second issue is the understaffing of the police force. As recently as in 2017, 30% of all the sanctioned posts were vacant in the country. The police-to-population ratio, therefore, is low in the country and makes the Indian police force one of the weakest in the world. From delays in investigation, increased response time and an increased toll on the mental health of the police, this issue births many other problems which leads to grave consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third issue is accountability. Many-a-times there is no action taken against a police officer when a complaint is lodged against them for various reasons. Often times, higher officials tend to overlook such complaints due to political pressure or for being complicit with the accused. There is no other mechanism available to lodge complaints against the police. Lack of accountability also includes the cases of fake encounters and deaths in police custody (a Google search shows that as recently as last year, two custodial deaths took place in Telangana, India).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fourth problem is that of inefficiency. The educational qualifications for a constable, the lowest cadre in the police – who account for almost 85% of the police force, is passing class 10 or 12 in many states. But the responsibilities of constables are wide-ranging. They are expected to exercise their judgement in intelligence gathering, assist with investigations and maintain public contact. It is often the case that these constables are insensitive and rude to the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not that there are no solutions. There have been many committees which made several recommendations, only to find the politicians to dump them in the dustbin. In 2006, the Supreme Court of India issued seven directions to reform the police force. Though states have implemented some of them, in practice they have been rendered useless. There are four things that have to be done. First, an increase in the size of the police force 6-10 times than the current number. Second, investment in police training which should focus on getting the police personnel to clearly understand the law of the land and also be sensitive to the public. Third, giving a greater degree of autonomy to the police.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To reduce the police’s dependence on politicians, the Supreme Court recommended the setting up of a Police Establishment Board in every state that will decide postings, transfers and promotions for officers below the rank of Deputy Superintendent of Police, and make recommendations to the state government for officers of higher ranks. The fourth recommendation is to make the police accountable. For this, the Supreme Court recommended constituting Police Complaints Authorities at the state and district levels to inquire into allegations of serious misconduct and abuse of power by police personnel. Police reforms are the most important area to focus on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Education&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Education, particularly primary education, is one area where India has failed enormously. While it succeeded in building prominent universities like IITs and IISCs, it is unable to provide primary education to everyone. The primary school system in India also focuses more on getting done with the syllabus and scoring marks in the exam. Problem-solving doesn’t come automatically to us because we are not equipped with the necessary tools in the classroom. Students are made to, encouraged in some cases, to mug up answers rather than think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pratham &lt;/em&gt;surveys frequently indicate how school students, mainly from government schools, fail at basic math and writing their name in English. However, the idea that government schools cannot produce results but only the private sector can, is false. My own experience tells me how corporate state board schools operate. In most of the cases, teachers do not have a Bachelors of Education degree. The management often sets unrealistic targets for the teachers to complete the syllabus and leave no time for the students for other extracurricular activities. Students are segregated based on their ability to score marks and the slow-learners (euphemism for those students that can’t score well) are put in one section and are hardly cared for. Private schools can also be pretty bad. If one looks at the school system in Sri Lanka, one can find that government schools can also achieve success and all it needs is initiative on the part of political leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a simple solution. Invest in primary education heavily. Both in terms of infrastructure building and teacher training. In many instances, it was found that government school teachers in some states could not even get the basics right. Also, the new education policy revealed by the Indian government assumes that there is manoeuvre for the teachers to engage in skills-based education. This is a classic example of a third'world country looking for first-world solutions. Teachers in many government schools, who are highly qualified, are unable to do this, let alone the private schools. This is why investing in teacher training is crucial to get Indian education on to the right track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked to propose solutions to any social problems, often the first solution that comes up is to create awareness. By investing in primary education and educating the people, that goal can be successfully accomplished. Also, education is the most important tool for social mobility. Neglecting it does not make sense. Third, caste politics and this sense of belonging to the same caste can be countered by educating your people. Caste politics depends on a patronage system. The moment we ensure basic things are available to everyone, it acts as a deterrent to caste politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Urban Cities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India is undergoing rapid urbanisation. Since 2009, the rate of urbanisation in the country has been around 30%. With such a high rate of urbanisation, Indian urban areas are becoming increasingly crowded and haphazard. For all the talk about how &lt;em&gt;asli Bharat gaaon mein basta hein &lt;/em&gt;('real India lives in villages'), we must not forget that it is cities that are the centres of economic activity and result in economies of scale for the firms operating in them. However, with rapid urbanisation new challenges have emerged in city management in India. First and foremost is the problem of pollution. Indian cities are one of the most polluted in the world. The national capital Delhi regularly figures in the list of most polluted cities, mostly in the top ten spots. The second problem is that most of the cities that exist today are naturally formed and they were not planned. This in itself led to problems like a lack of proper sanitation systems, waste disposal systems, the inability to regulate traffic efficiently, illegal constructions and many more. The third problem is that there are many departments to regulate various aspects of the cities and due to lack of coordination among them there is inefficient planning and land use. Often, these departments are also zones of rampant corruption. The fourth and other important problem is lack of availability of funds. In most of the cases, the cities have very poor budgetary allocations and the revenue they get in the form of taxes is also low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To solve the funding problems, governments can consider transferring the revenue they get from public transport to the city development authorities. About 50% of the expenditure incurred by the city administrations is on administrative expenditures like salary, pensions, operation and maintenance of offices, and property, among other things. One solution is to cut personnel wherever it is possible by moving the services online. Certain departments, like water and sanitation, can be clubbed so as to cut staff. It is important to recognise that the bottom-up approach is best and hence there should be a transfer of greater funds to the local bodies. Creating a strong bond market and leveraging the land-based instruments can also be considered to raise revenue.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equally important is the concentration on city planning. As was mentioned earlier, many of the top Indian cities were not planned and the consequences of that are for everyone to see. Many state governments and local bodies do have planning departments and planning officials. The problem is either they are under-equipped or the staff has no proper knowledge regarding urban planning. It is therefore also important to invest in and encourage people to pursue degrees in urban planning.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from the three areas, which need the Indian state's immediate attention, there are three more which I think have high importance in facilitating India onto the superpower path. I will discuss those in the next part.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The changing geopolitical structure of the contemporary world will expect India to play a larger role in world affairs. Coupling this with the call made by Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi to make India a $5 trillion economy, we are looking at a scenario where India is a potential superpower candidate in the 21st century. And Indians have always believed, owing to the rich civilisational heritage the country had in the past, that they deserve to lead the world – becoming the viswaguru ('lord of the world'). For this, India must present its world view and leverage its soft power to influence the world. At the same time, it is important for the country to get its ducks in a row; for, without resolving its domestic problems, we can forget about leading the world. In this article, I try to highlight some crucial problems that need immediate attention. Law and Order The first major roadblock pertains to law and order in India. With the Indian police, the issues pertain to distrust, understaffing, accountability and inefficiency. First, there is a lot of distrust towards the police among the public. A 2018 survey found that less than 25% of Indians trust the police. This distrust can be attributed to the prevalent corruption in the police departments, the police-politician nexus and the abuse of power by the police. In the Indian Corruption Survey 2019, the police department was found to be the second most corrupt department in the country.&amp;nbsp; The second issue is the understaffing of the police force. As recently as in 2017, 30% of all the sanctioned posts were vacant in the country. The police-to-population ratio, therefore, is low in the country and makes the Indian police force one of the weakest in the world. From delays in investigation, increased response time and an increased toll on the mental health of the police, this issue births many other problems which leads to grave consequences. The third issue is accountability. Many-a-times there is no action taken against a police officer when a complaint is lodged against them for various reasons. Often times, higher officials tend to overlook such complaints due to political pressure or for being complicit with the accused. There is no other mechanism available to lodge complaints against the police. Lack of accountability also includes the cases of fake encounters and deaths in police custody (a Google search shows that as recently as last year, two custodial deaths took place in Telangana, India).&amp;nbsp; The fourth problem is that of inefficiency. The educational qualifications for a constable, the lowest cadre in the police – who account for almost 85% of the police force, is passing class 10 or 12 in many states. But the responsibilities of constables are wide-ranging. They are expected to exercise their judgement in intelligence gathering, assist with investigations and maintain public contact. It is often the case that these constables are insensitive and rude to the public. It is not that there are no solutions. There have been many committees which made several recommendations, only to find the politicians to dump them in the dustbin. In 2006, the Supreme Court of India issued seven directions to reform the police force. Though states have implemented some of them, in practice they have been rendered useless. There are four things that have to be done. First, an increase in the size of the police force 6-10 times than the current number. Second, investment in police training which should focus on getting the police personnel to clearly understand the law of the land and also be sensitive to the public. Third, giving a greater degree of autonomy to the police.&amp;nbsp; To reduce the police’s dependence on politicians, the Supreme Court recommended the setting up of a Police Establishment Board in every state that will decide postings, transfers and promotions for officers below the rank of Deputy Superintendent of Police, and make recommendations to the state government for officers of higher ranks. The fourth recommendation is to make the police accountable. For this, the Supreme Court recommended constituting Police Complaints Authorities at the state and district levels to inquire into allegations of serious misconduct and abuse of power by police personnel. Police reforms are the most important area to focus on. Education Education, particularly primary education, is one area where India has failed enormously. While it succeeded in building prominent universities like IITs and IISCs, it is unable to provide primary education to everyone. The primary school system in India also focuses more on getting done with the syllabus and scoring marks in the exam. Problem-solving doesn’t come automatically to us because we are not equipped with the necessary tools in the classroom. Students are made to, encouraged in some cases, to mug up answers rather than think. Pratham surveys frequently indicate how school students, mainly from government schools, fail at basic math and writing their name in English. However, the idea that government schools cannot produce results but only the private sector can, is false. My own experience tells me how corporate state board schools operate. In most of the cases, teachers do not have a Bachelors of Education degree. The management often sets unrealistic targets for the teachers to complete the syllabus and leave no time for the students for other extracurricular activities. Students are segregated based on their ability to score marks and the slow-learners (euphemism for those students that can’t score well) are put in one section and are hardly cared for. Private schools can also be pretty bad. If one looks at the school system in Sri Lanka, one can find that government schools can also achieve success and all it needs is initiative on the part of political leadership. There is a simple solution. Invest in primary education heavily. Both in terms of infrastructure building and teacher training. In many instances, it was found that government school teachers in some states could not even get the basics right. Also, the new education policy revealed by the Indian government assumes that there is manoeuvre for the teachers to engage in skills-based education. This is a classic example of a third'world country looking for first-world solutions. Teachers in many government schools, who are highly qualified, are unable to do this, let alone the private schools. This is why investing in teacher training is crucial to get Indian education on to the right track. When asked to propose solutions to any social problems, often the first solution that comes up is to create awareness. By investing in primary education and educating the people, that goal can be successfully accomplished. Also, education is the most important tool for social mobility. Neglecting it does not make sense. Third, caste politics and this sense of belonging to the same caste can be countered by educating your people. Caste politics depends on a patronage system. The moment we ensure basic things are available to everyone, it acts as a deterrent to caste politics. Urban Cities India is undergoing rapid urbanisation. Since 2009, the rate of urbanisation in the country has been around 30%. With such a high rate of urbanisation, Indian urban areas are becoming increasingly crowded and haphazard. For all the talk about how asli Bharat gaaon mein basta hein ('real India lives in villages'), we must not forget that it is cities that are the centres of economic activity and result in economies of scale for the firms operating in them. However, with rapid urbanisation new challenges have emerged in city management in India. First and foremost is the problem of pollution. Indian cities are one of the most polluted in the world. The national capital Delhi regularly figures in the list of most polluted cities, mostly in the top ten spots. The second problem is that most of the cities that exist today are naturally formed and they were not planned. This in itself led to problems like a lack of proper sanitation systems, waste disposal systems, the inability to regulate traffic efficiently, illegal constructions and many more. The third problem is that there are many departments to regulate various aspects of the cities and due to lack of coordination among them there is inefficient planning and land use. Often, these departments are also zones of rampant corruption. The fourth and other important problem is lack of availability of funds. In most of the cases, the cities have very poor budgetary allocations and the revenue they get in the form of taxes is also low. To solve the funding problems, governments can consider transferring the revenue they get from public transport to the city development authorities. About 50% of the expenditure incurred by the city administrations is on administrative expenditures like salary, pensions, operation and maintenance of offices, and property, among other things. One solution is to cut personnel wherever it is possible by moving the services online. Certain departments, like water and sanitation, can be clubbed so as to cut staff. It is important to recognise that the bottom-up approach is best and hence there should be a transfer of greater funds to the local bodies. Creating a strong bond market and leveraging the land-based instruments can also be considered to raise revenue.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Equally important is the concentration on city planning. As was mentioned earlier, many of the top Indian cities were not planned and the consequences of that are for everyone to see. Many state governments and local bodies do have planning departments and planning officials. The problem is either they are under-equipped or the staff has no proper knowledge regarding urban planning. It is therefore also important to invest in and encourage people to pursue degrees in urban planning.&amp;nbsp; Apart from the three areas, which need the Indian state's immediate attention, there are three more which I think have high importance in facilitating India onto the superpower path. I will discuss those in the next part.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Beat The Casinos</title>
      <link href="/Beat-The-Casinos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beat The Casinos" />
      <published>2021-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Beat-The-Casinos</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Beat-The-Casinos">&lt;p&gt;Being a huge &lt;em&gt;Hangover&lt;/em&gt; fan, there is something that I have always wanted to do in my life and that is, gambling all night at a casino in Las Vegas for once. Within the walls of the 51 licensed casinos of the Las Vegas Strip, there are 2,879 gaming tables collectively bringing in $3.1 billion in revenue annually, or over a million dollars in each table. In addition, there are some 38,864 slot machines bringing in another $3.4 billion dollars. A single large Las Vegas casino, like the Bellagio, makes more than some small countries, annually.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is because the casino business model is pretty much bulletproof. Overall, the odds are always in the casino’s favour. If this weren’t true, casinos would fail - so these floors just print money. MGM International, for example, one of the world’s largest multinational gaming companies, has about 2.5 million square feet of casino floor worldwide meaning it makes, on average, $1,038 per square foot. With the money their casinos bring in, they could line every inch of every foot of their casino floor worldwide with a brand-new iPad and still have money left over. This is all to say, casinos make a lot of money, but to do so, they need a lot more money coming through their doors. You see, the casino business model all revolves around risk. With every game they have, the odds are in their favour, but doesn’t mean the house will always win. Their advantage varies from game to game - in Roulette, it is about 5.25%, in Poker, it is about 3.35%, and in Blackjack, it is about 0.5%.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, given how tight these margins are, there’s natural variability, so casinos can come out behind or lose money on a given table on a given night but overall, with enough tables and enough nights, they average out these odds. However, in order to do so, they need an immense amount of money running through their casinos. Blackjack, for example, is one of the games with the lowest house edge so if the casino wants to earn $1 billion in a given year from the game, they would need $200 billion changing hands within their doors each year. That’s pretty much the entire GDP of New Zealand. When you have such a rapid throughput of money, very slight changes in the odds can make a huge variation in the gaming company’s earnings. If, for example, the house edge in the Blackjack changed from 0.5% to 0.4%, they would lose $200 million, assuming $200 billion in annual play. This is why making sure these odds stay in their favour is so important to the casinos. It could quite literally be the difference between millions of dollars in profit or filing for bankruptcy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite what the movie culture might portray, a casino’s biggest problem is not robbers or hackers or even technically cheaters, because each of those is relatively easy to prevent and detect. Rather, their biggest problem is people who are able to turn the odds in their favour without robbing, hacking or even cheating. Cheating in a casino is generally illegal, however, it’s possible for a player to consistently win without cheating. The best-known example of this is card counting, a type of advantage play used in the Blackjack family of games which is not illegal and in some cases is even legally protected. This play technique takes the basic principles of the game of Blackjack and uses them against the casino, and these principles are fairly simple.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start a game, each player bets an amount of money and then six decks of cards are shuffled together to form what’s called the Shoe. Each player is dealt two cards face-up while the dealer gets one face-up and one face-down card. The goal for all the participants is simple, it’s to get their cards to total as close to 21 without going above 21. Starting from the left, each player will either decide to stick with the total they have or to take another card to add to it. Of course, the player doesn’t know what the next card will be worth in between one to 11, so it’s a gamble on whether it’ll make the total go over 21 – in which case their bet is lost.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The higher the original sum, the riskier it is to take another card but there is in fact a mathematically optimal choice for every scenario called the 'basic strategy'. Once every player is done taking cards, the dealer reveals the face-down card and automatically if their total is below 17, they take additional cards until it isn’t over 17. If it's 17 or higher, they leave it as it is. There are then 3 scenarios. If the dealer goes above 21, all players’ bets are doubled, as long as they didn’t go above 21 first. If the player’s total is higher than the dealer’s then the player's bet is doubled, however, if the player's total is lower, they lose their bet.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this explanation skipped over plenty of smaller rules and less likely edge-cases, but it is these fundamental elements of game-play that tie into why card counting works. Now, without getting too much into the math, on average, in Blackjack, higher value cards benefit the player, while the lower value cards benefit the dealers. While the explanation for the higher cards is more complex, lower card benefit is based on the fact that the dealer is required to take additional cards when their total is less than 17 and so a greater density of lower cards makes it less likely that they will go over 21 – in which case each player’s bet is doubled. Therefore, if you know that a bunch of low cards are coming, you know that the odds are against you and so you should reduce your bet or not play but the question is how do you know what’s coming in a randomly shuffled deck. Well, you perform the process of elimination or even more simply you count the cards you see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are hundreds of different forms of card counting that work in hundreds of different ways, but all are more or less based on what’s known as the 'Hi-Lo' system. With this, each card is assigned a value. Cards ranging from two to six are assigned 'one', cards from seven to nine are assigned 'zero', and card 10 and ace and all the face cards are assigned 'minus one'. This is based on the fact that every time a high-value card is dealt there are fewer of them left in the deck, which means the odds get worse for the player considering that high-value cards are better for them and vice versa. With every card a player sees, they add up its assigned value. So, if there are three players and they are dealt the cards in &lt;em&gt;figure 1&lt;/em&gt;, the running count would be two.&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/cardlayouteuan.png&quot; /&gt;Figure 1: Cards dealt to three players and their running count - Euan Decourt, 23/01/2020&lt;/div&gt;As the play goes on and they get deeper into the deck, the running count will generally increase in one direction or the other giving the player more confidence on where the odds stand. So, for example, if the running count equals 20, the player would know that the odds are greatly in their favour and therefore that they should bet big on the next round as they have a greater than 50% chance of winning. This is how people can reliably make money in Blackjack. If a player changes their bet by a factor of 15 depending on the odds, and the dealer waits until they’re through five of the six decks before shuffling, a player, following a perfect Blackjack strategy, could earn an advantage of about 1.182% over the house. That means that if assuming a table completes a round of play every minute and an average bet is around $200, a card counter could profit on average about $110 an hour - enough that some people can and do make a living by sitting at Blackjack tables, counting cards. However, how simple and reliable this advantage play method is, casinos go to great lengths to stop it which is very, very difficult. That’s because the advantage is all in the mind—there’s no good way to fully prove that a person is counting cards. Sometimes, people are just lucky and it is quite a bad look for casinos to kick people out just because they are winning. That’s why instead of trying to prove it, most casinos implement rules to try and stop card counting from working as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that, generally, the running count will get further into positive or negative the further into the game one goes because the card counter would have seen more cards that are now in the discard pile, and therefore cannot be dealt. While a few rounds in the running count might be in the single digits positive or negative, further on, it will get into the double digits which gives the counter great confidence whether they should bet big or not. It is towards the end of the Shoes, when card counters really make their money, so to make it less profitable, casinos can just have their dealers shuffle earlier on. If they shuffle 4 decks deep into a six-deck show rather than five, that decreases the player’s advantage from 1.182 to just 0.568%. However, shuffling earlier and more often also cuts into the casino’s profits because, anytime the dealer is shuffling the non-advantaged players aren’t playing and losing money, which is how the casino makes its money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another option for casinos is to increase the number of decks they shuffle together to make a show. Back before card-counting first became a widespread issue for casinos, they would play Blackjack with just a single deck of cards but if they did this today, it would only be a matter of minutes before a card counter would have high confidence about the odds. Therefore, they typically now play with six decks shuffled together, which increases the time it takes to get to high confidence and since time is money for a card counter, this decreases their profits. Some casinos take this a step further by using a continuous shuffling machine. With no discard piles, there is no increase or decrease in the beneficial cards in the shoe, so card counting is completely ineffective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these methods deal with stopping or reducing a player’s ability to actually know what the odds are at a given moment, the other method involves stopping a player’s ability to respond to this knowledge by changing the size of their bets. Essentially, if a dealer or a pit boss suspects someone might be counting cards, they’ll change the rules on them and require flat betting which means making a player choose one bet size for all rounds and not allowing them to change the bet in future rounds when the count is in their favour. However, that poses the question, how do you spot a card counter? Well, one of the signs is if a player changes their bet from 100 to 1000 right before a series of wins or as the Shoe is close to finish, that’s a good sign that they know what the odds are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end, the casinos aren’t much affected by card counters as they make a very small proportion of all the players and they consider it as a cost of running the business. Till this time these games continue to exist, players will always try to find new ways to shift the odds in their favour and this causes a never-ending cycle, but what we must know is that if we use basic math we can outwit some of these casinos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about Blackjack, click &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.blackjackapprenticeship.com/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Being a huge Hangover fan, there is something that I have always wanted to do in my life and that is, gambling all night at a casino in Las Vegas for once. Within the walls of the 51 licensed casinos of the Las Vegas Strip, there are 2,879 gaming tables collectively bringing in $3.1 billion in revenue annually, or over a million dollars in each table. In addition, there are some 38,864 slot machines bringing in another $3.4 billion dollars. A single large Las Vegas casino, like the Bellagio, makes more than some small countries, annually.&amp;nbsp; This is because the casino business model is pretty much bulletproof. Overall, the odds are always in the casino’s favour. If this weren’t true, casinos would fail - so these floors just print money. MGM International, for example, one of the world’s largest multinational gaming companies, has about 2.5 million square feet of casino floor worldwide meaning it makes, on average, $1,038 per square foot. With the money their casinos bring in, they could line every inch of every foot of their casino floor worldwide with a brand-new iPad and still have money left over. This is all to say, casinos make a lot of money, but to do so, they need a lot more money coming through their doors. You see, the casino business model all revolves around risk. With every game they have, the odds are in their favour, but doesn’t mean the house will always win. Their advantage varies from game to game - in Roulette, it is about 5.25%, in Poker, it is about 3.35%, and in Blackjack, it is about 0.5%.&amp;nbsp; Of course, given how tight these margins are, there’s natural variability, so casinos can come out behind or lose money on a given table on a given night but overall, with enough tables and enough nights, they average out these odds. However, in order to do so, they need an immense amount of money running through their casinos. Blackjack, for example, is one of the games with the lowest house edge so if the casino wants to earn $1 billion in a given year from the game, they would need $200 billion changing hands within their doors each year. That’s pretty much the entire GDP of New Zealand. When you have such a rapid throughput of money, very slight changes in the odds can make a huge variation in the gaming company’s earnings. If, for example, the house edge in the Blackjack changed from 0.5% to 0.4%, they would lose $200 million, assuming $200 billion in annual play. This is why making sure these odds stay in their favour is so important to the casinos. It could quite literally be the difference between millions of dollars in profit or filing for bankruptcy.&amp;nbsp; Despite what the movie culture might portray, a casino’s biggest problem is not robbers or hackers or even technically cheaters, because each of those is relatively easy to prevent and detect. Rather, their biggest problem is people who are able to turn the odds in their favour without robbing, hacking or even cheating. Cheating in a casino is generally illegal, however, it’s possible for a player to consistently win without cheating. The best-known example of this is card counting, a type of advantage play used in the Blackjack family of games which is not illegal and in some cases is even legally protected. This play technique takes the basic principles of the game of Blackjack and uses them against the casino, and these principles are fairly simple.&amp;nbsp; To start a game, each player bets an amount of money and then six decks of cards are shuffled together to form what’s called the Shoe. Each player is dealt two cards face-up while the dealer gets one face-up and one face-down card. The goal for all the participants is simple, it’s to get their cards to total as close to 21 without going above 21. Starting from the left, each player will either decide to stick with the total they have or to take another card to add to it. Of course, the player doesn’t know what the next card will be worth in between one to 11, so it’s a gamble on whether it’ll make the total go over 21 – in which case their bet is lost.&amp;nbsp; The higher the original sum, the riskier it is to take another card but there is in fact a mathematically optimal choice for every scenario called the 'basic strategy'. Once every player is done taking cards, the dealer reveals the face-down card and automatically if their total is below 17, they take additional cards until it isn’t over 17. If it's 17 or higher, they leave it as it is. There are then 3 scenarios. If the dealer goes above 21, all players’ bets are doubled, as long as they didn’t go above 21 first. If the player’s total is higher than the dealer’s then the player's bet is doubled, however, if the player's total is lower, they lose their bet.&amp;nbsp; Of course, this explanation skipped over plenty of smaller rules and less likely edge-cases, but it is these fundamental elements of game-play that tie into why card counting works. Now, without getting too much into the math, on average, in Blackjack, higher value cards benefit the player, while the lower value cards benefit the dealers. While the explanation for the higher cards is more complex, lower card benefit is based on the fact that the dealer is required to take additional cards when their total is less than 17 and so a greater density of lower cards makes it less likely that they will go over 21 – in which case each player’s bet is doubled. Therefore, if you know that a bunch of low cards are coming, you know that the odds are against you and so you should reduce your bet or not play but the question is how do you know what’s coming in a randomly shuffled deck. Well, you perform the process of elimination or even more simply you count the cards you see. There are hundreds of different forms of card counting that work in hundreds of different ways, but all are more or less based on what’s known as the 'Hi-Lo' system. With this, each card is assigned a value. Cards ranging from two to six are assigned 'one', cards from seven to nine are assigned 'zero', and card 10 and ace and all the face cards are assigned 'minus one'. This is based on the fact that every time a high-value card is dealt there are fewer of them left in the deck, which means the odds get worse for the player considering that high-value cards are better for them and vice versa. With every card a player sees, they add up its assigned value. So, if there are three players and they are dealt the cards in figure 1, the running count would be two.Figure 1: Cards dealt to three players and their running count - Euan Decourt, 23/01/2020As the play goes on and they get deeper into the deck, the running count will generally increase in one direction or the other giving the player more confidence on where the odds stand. So, for example, if the running count equals 20, the player would know that the odds are greatly in their favour and therefore that they should bet big on the next round as they have a greater than 50% chance of winning. This is how people can reliably make money in Blackjack. If a player changes their bet by a factor of 15 depending on the odds, and the dealer waits until they’re through five of the six decks before shuffling, a player, following a perfect Blackjack strategy, could earn an advantage of about 1.182% over the house. That means that if assuming a table completes a round of play every minute and an average bet is around $200, a card counter could profit on average about $110 an hour - enough that some people can and do make a living by sitting at Blackjack tables, counting cards. However, how simple and reliable this advantage play method is, casinos go to great lengths to stop it which is very, very difficult. That’s because the advantage is all in the mind—there’s no good way to fully prove that a person is counting cards. Sometimes, people are just lucky and it is quite a bad look for casinos to kick people out just because they are winning. That’s why instead of trying to prove it, most casinos implement rules to try and stop card counting from working as well.&amp;nbsp; Remember that, generally, the running count will get further into positive or negative the further into the game one goes because the card counter would have seen more cards that are now in the discard pile, and therefore cannot be dealt. While a few rounds in the running count might be in the single digits positive or negative, further on, it will get into the double digits which gives the counter great confidence whether they should bet big or not. It is towards the end of the Shoes, when card counters really make their money, so to make it less profitable, casinos can just have their dealers shuffle earlier on. If they shuffle 4 decks deep into a six-deck show rather than five, that decreases the player’s advantage from 1.182 to just 0.568%. However, shuffling earlier and more often also cuts into the casino’s profits because, anytime the dealer is shuffling the non-advantaged players aren’t playing and losing money, which is how the casino makes its money. Another option for casinos is to increase the number of decks they shuffle together to make a show. Back before card-counting first became a widespread issue for casinos, they would play Blackjack with just a single deck of cards but if they did this today, it would only be a matter of minutes before a card counter would have high confidence about the odds. Therefore, they typically now play with six decks shuffled together, which increases the time it takes to get to high confidence and since time is money for a card counter, this decreases their profits. Some casinos take this a step further by using a continuous shuffling machine. With no discard piles, there is no increase or decrease in the beneficial cards in the shoe, so card counting is completely ineffective. While these methods deal with stopping or reducing a player’s ability to actually know what the odds are at a given moment, the other method involves stopping a player’s ability to respond to this knowledge by changing the size of their bets. Essentially, if a dealer or a pit boss suspects someone might be counting cards, they’ll change the rules on them and require flat betting which means making a player choose one bet size for all rounds and not allowing them to change the bet in future rounds when the count is in their favour. However, that poses the question, how do you spot a card counter? Well, one of the signs is if a player changes their bet from 100 to 1000 right before a series of wins or as the Shoe is close to finish, that’s a good sign that they know what the odds are. At the end, the casinos aren’t much affected by card counters as they make a very small proportion of all the players and they consider it as a cost of running the business. Till this time these games continue to exist, players will always try to find new ways to shift the odds in their favour and this causes a never-ending cycle, but what we must know is that if we use basic math we can outwit some of these casinos. If you want to learn more about Blackjack, click here.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
