<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/football/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-10-19T18:57:15+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/football/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How Can England Make the Most of Their Upcoming Golden Generation?</title>
      <link href="/England-Golden-Generation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Can England Make the Most of Their Upcoming Golden Generation?" />
      <published>2019-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/England-Golden-Generation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/England-Golden-Generation">&lt;p&gt;English football has been going through a resurgence in recent years. Along with the likes of Liverpool flying the flag high for England, the national team has excelled at various levels as the World Champion U20 and U17 teams were followed by the senior side achieving their best finish at a World Cup for 28 years. It’s evident that the raw talent coming through the ranks is something special, but now the attention turns to whether the England national team can harness this potential and produce a side good enough to compete for major honours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;English Excellence - Young Players on the Rise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Goalkeepers&lt;/em&gt;: Mark Travers, Dean Henderson, Aaron Ramsdale&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Centre-backs&lt;/em&gt;: Joe Gomez, Fikayo Tomori, Axel Tuanzebe, Rob Holding, Ben Godfrey, Marc Guehi&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fullbacks&lt;/em&gt;: Aaron Wan-Bissaka, Trent Alexander-Arnold, Ben Chillwell, Ryan Sessegnon, Reece James, Jamal Lewis, Max Aarons, James Justin, Ainsley Maitland-Niles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Central midfielders&lt;/em&gt;: Declan Rice, Morgan Gibbs-White, Ruben Loftus-Cheek, Hamza Choudhury, Joe Willock, Lewis Cook, Oliver Skipp&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Attacking midfielders&lt;/em&gt;: Phil Foden, Mason Mount, James Maddison, Angel Gomes, Emile Smith-Rowe, Todd Cantwell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wingers&lt;/em&gt;: Ademola Lookman, Jadon Sancho, Reiss Nelson, Callum Hudson-Odoi, Harvey Barnes, Dwight McNeil, Bukayo Saka&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Strikers&lt;/em&gt;: Eddie Nketiah, Tammy Abraham, Rhian Brewster, Mason Greenwood&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As these players’ abilities is not in doubt, continued hunger to be the best and staving off injuries while maximising gametime for their clubs will be the pivotal factors as to whether these young players are able to sustain long-term success. Complacency in major tournaments has been an issue for England teams in the past, and it was also manifest during the recent U21 European Championships in which many of the players mentioned above were involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;England can look at how recent World Cup winners were able to make the most of their talented generations and try and replicate certain aspects of their successes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spain (Euro 2008 &amp;amp; 2012, World Cup 2010 winners)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spain were widely considered perennial underachievers on the international stage before their triumph in 2008, as they had produced talented players, such as Raúl, Fernando Hierro and Emiliano Butragueño, but hadn’t won a major honour since 1964.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you think of the all-conquering Spain team, technically outstanding players such as Xavi, Andrés Iniesta and Cesc Fàbregas immediately spring to mind. It was no coincidence that Spain produced such an array of small, talented midfielders that Santi Cazorla and Juan Mata could barely get any game time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spain worked from the ground up to establish a footballing culture centred around players that were comfortable on the ball and could dominate possession. This philosophy set them apart from other contenders at the time as they suffocated possession, making their opponents have to drastically change their gameplans. Such was this team’s influence that there has been a rise in ‘Spanish style’ English midfielders, such as Phil Foden, who differ from the stereotypical English midfielder. The use of St. George’s Park National Football Centre in 2012 would have hopefully got some of the current youngsters to grow together following a similar footballing philosophy which may now be applied to the senior team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Germany (World Cup 2014 winners)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst it’s hard to argue that a nation with 4 World Cups and 3 European Championships has one single golden generation, the group that propelled Germany to 2014 glory are certainly a good example of a close-knit group of players that all progressed lineally. Key players like Mats Hummels, Mesut Özil, Sami Khedira, Manuel Neuer, Jerome Boateng, Toni Kroos and Thomas Müller were all born between 1986 and 1989 and had grown up playing together from a young age for both club and country. Five of the aforementioned players started the U21s Euro 2009 final where they got a taste of victory as they trounced England 4-0. All were subsequently involved in the 2010 World Cup where the youngsters impressed on their way to the semi-finals, putting 4 past both England and Argentina in the knockout stages before succumbing to eventual winners Spain. Although they fell short, this was a resounding success for this young team as Thomas Müller won the Golden Boot and Mesut Özil and Sami Khedira both earned moves to Real Madrid off the back of the tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only did this generation’s experience hold them in good stead for their 2014 World Cup win, but a group of players born from 1983-1985 had preceded the 2010 class by reaching the semis of the 2006 World Cup. Phillip Lahm, Per Mertesacker, Lukas Podolski and Bastian Schweinsteiger were all 22 years or younger during this tournament and played starring roles which they used to build on their international careers. Lahm and Mertesacker retired from international football immediately after their 2014 World Cup triumph in Brazil whilst Podolski and Schweinsteiger did so a few years later with the quartet accumulating 468 caps between them. That level of experience is invaluable when trying to win major honours and England can try and emulate this template to some degree. Jordan Henderson, Raheem Sterling, Dele Alli, John Stones, Harry Kane et al. have already experienced tournament football with England and can use their experiences, both positive and negative, to try and guide the new crop of U23 talent in the same way the Germans did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;France (World Cup 2018 winners)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that England can take away from France’s World Cup 2018 winning side is how manager Didier Deschamps didn’t just cram all the most talented players into the starting XI, but rather opted for the most balanced team. After starting mercurial winger Ousmane Dembele in their World Cup opener against Australia, Deschamps eventually settled on a team with target man Olivier Giroud favoured over a more prolific striker like Alexandre Lacazette whilst box-to-box midfielder Blaise Matuidi started on the left side of midfield over more creative players like Dembele, Thomas Lemar and Nabil Fekir. This new lineup was very well balanced, complimenting star players Paul Pogba, Antoine Griezmann and Kylian Mbappe. Deschamps was famously called “the water carrier” during his playing days by Eric Cantona, and just as he allowed the likes of Zinedine Zidane to flourish, he found the winning formula for France as manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, after France’s disastrous, mutinous 2010 World Cup campaign, the French Football Federation prioritised good squad harmony. Despite mediocre showing in the subsequent 2 tournaments, the FFF were happy with the job Deschamps had done having replaced Laurent Blanc. It should be noted that neither Franck Ribery (retired) nor Karim Benzema played for France after 2015 and despite being arguably the nation’s two most talented players, the team thrived. Benzema was still an elite centre-forward but after his blackmail scandal involving French teammate Mathieu Valbuena, the Real Madrid striker wasn’t considered for selection again. Both him and Ribery had careers riddled with controversy and could have disrupted the excellent squad chemistry and morale in the French dressing room. Due to their triumph in Russia, no one involved in French football will have any regrets over their omissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;England 2000-2010&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;England’s previous ‘golden generation’ were notorious underachievers. Despite boasting players who were world-class for their clubs such as Rio Ferdinand, David Beckham and Wayne Rooney to name but a few, they consistently flattered to deceive on the international stage, never advancing past the quarter-finals of a major tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, this side provides an excellent example of how not to maximise the potential of a golden generation and what Southgate and co. should look to avoid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the obvious downfalls was Sven-Göran Eriksson putting out an XI of all the most ‘talented’ players and the team that looks the best on paper, but not the best team in reality. Steven Gerrard and Frank Lampard infamously struggled to play together in midfield in a 4-4-2 formation with neither player’s quality being fully utilised. Lampard and Gerrard often played alongside the likes of Javier Mascherano and Claude Makelele at club level, allowing the English duo more freedom but English holding midfielders such as Gareth Barry, Michael Carrick and Owen Hargreaves started intermittently so there was no real chemistry that could be built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shoehorning players out of position was also a theme for this England team with Paul Scholes and Steven Gerrard often deployed wide left, and whilst this worked for France when they moved Matuidi wide, Matuidi is naturally left-footed and France played a 4-2-3-1 / 4-3-3 hybrid, an entirely different system than the 4-4-2 used by Sven-Göran Eriksson. When you add in Frank Lampard, England had 3 elite centre-midfielders yet their midfield never seemed to really stand out as a collective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another issue was that, due to fierce club rivalries, there was some tension between England’s stars. Rio Ferdinand stated that once he and then close friend Lampard went their separate ways after leaving West Ham, they stopped speaking to each other due to the ferocity of the Chelsea-Manchester United rivalry with both clubs regularly vying for titles. Whilst selecting players who play for rival clubs isn’t a barrier to international success, as Spain showed with a team largely comprised of Barcelona and Real Madrid players, it’s essential that Southgate’s England don’t let petty rivalries bring down their morale and derail their potential success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Current England (2018 - present)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arguably the most significant feature of Southgate’s reign is that he has harmonised the England setup so that club rivalries do not infringe on the national team’s unity. It is no longer the case that England players only spend time with their clubmates on national duty and, as many English pundits, fans and players have noted since the 2018 World Cup, there is a real sense of togetherness now with England’s senior team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although man-for-man the current England XI can’t compete with Eriksson’s 2000’s team, it does seem as though the current England set up will help England’s talented next generation to succeed in a way that Eriksson’s didn’t. The FA should now be aware of what to avoid and what to do when assembling a team for contention. England have the talent, now it’s time to use it correctly.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samuel Hogan</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">English football has been going through a resurgence in recent years. Along with the likes of Liverpool flying the flag high for England, the national team has excelled at various levels as the World Champion U20 and U17 teams were followed by the senior side achieving their best finish at a World Cup for 28 years. It’s evident that the raw talent coming through the ranks is something special, but now the attention turns to whether the England national team can harness this potential and produce a side good enough to compete for major honours.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How Will Arsenal’s New Signings Fit In?</title>
      <link href="/How-Will-Arsenals-New-Signings-Fit-In" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Will Arsenal’s New Signings Fit In?" />
      <published>2019-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/How-Will-Arsenals-New-Signings-Fit-In</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/How-Will-Arsenals-New-Signings-Fit-In">&lt;p&gt;Since the appointment of ex-Arsenal midfielder Edu as the club’s technical
director last month, the Gunners have accelerated their transfer plans after
initially making slow progress towards agreeing deals for the likes of Wilfried
Zaha and Kieran Tierney. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the little-heralded signing of Brazillian youngster Gabriel Martinelli,
the window really kicked off with the double announcement of Dani Ceballos on
loan from Real Madrid and the signing of £27 million William Saliba (who was
subsequently loaned back to Saint Étienne) on July 25th. This was soon trumped
by the surprise signing of Nicolas Pépé from Lille, with Arsenal defying the
reports of their £45 million transfer budget by securing the £72 million Ivorian
forward on a 5 year deal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, deadline day saw the defence bolstered by the £25 million signing of
left-back Kieran Tierney from Celtic and the shock arrival of veteran
centre-back David Luiz from London rivals Chelsea for £8M on a two year deal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Unai Emery now having added quality at his disposal, the question is how
each of the new boys will fit in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;William Saliba&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick mention of someone Arsenal fans won’t get to see for a while; teenage
defender William Saliba whose former club Saint-Etienne insisted on having him
loaned back to them this season. Despite not having played a game for the club,
he has already endeared himself to the Arsenal faithful after he reportedly
snubbed interest from North London rivals Tottenham before opting to join the
Gunners. Once Arsenal fans do get to see him in action, they will see an
accomplished modern centre-back, capable of surging forward from the back whilst
also being a dependable defender, especially in 1v1 situations. His rangy stride
and 6’3 frame make him a physically excellent prospect and when looking at the
market for the likes of Harry Maguire, £28 million could be a bargain for an 18
year old that was starting for the fourth best team in France.  Saliba, along
with Rob Holding and Calum Chambers, looks set to be the future of Arsenal’s
central defence as Sokratis and David Luiz advance into their 30s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gabriel Martinelli&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The signing of 18 year old Brazillian winger Gabriel Martinelli has
understandably been forgotten about by many after the 5 higher profile signings
that followed. Signed from Brazillian side Ituano for a reported fee of £6
million, Martinelli made his debut in a short cameo against Newcastle last
weekend and, with the sale of Alex Iwobi to Everton, could be in for some
minutes as a rotation player this season. With Pépé and Henrikh Mkhitaryan now
the only established wingers at the club there’s a route to the first team for
Martinelli, but he’ll face fierce competition from fellow teenage wingers Reiss
Nelson, Emile Smith-Rowe and Bukayo Saka. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dani Ceballos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talented midfielder Dani Ceballos played a crucial role in Spain’s triumph at
the European U21 Championship in Italy this summer, and he will now embark on a
short stint in North London before he likely cements himself as a Real Madrid
regular for years to come. A player as gifted as Ceballos is seldom available on
loan and Arsenal should thank the likes of Luka Modric and Toni Kroos for
blocking his path to regular minutes at the Bernabeu, allowing Arsenal to
acquire a player who will slot right into their first XI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Ceballos being the only addition to Arsenal’s midfield this summer, it
would be natural to think he would be tasked with replacing the void left by
Aaron Ramsey’s departure to Juventus. However, Ceballos is more similar to a few
of Ramsey’s former midfield partners: Jack Wilshere and fellow Spaniard Santi
Cazorla. Wilshere and Cazorla both averaged over 2 dribbles a game throughout
their Arsenal careers, but since their departures in 2018 no Arsenal midfielder
averaged more than Mattéo Guendouzi’s 0.7 dribbles a game last season. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ceballos averaged 2.7 dribbles per game in his last league season of regular
football at Real Betis in the 2016/17 season and should contribute to some much
needed technical support in the centre of the park, giving Arsenal a ball
carrying outlet from deep to evade pressure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-01.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-02.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-03.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ceballos’ immense skill set and versatility means he is capable as a deep-lying
playmaker, a tireless box-to-box CM, or in the number 10 role. Given Ramsey’s
departure and Özil’s recent off-the-pitch adversities, Emery is likely to deploy
Ceballos as the furthest forward midfielder. The 23-year old’s outstanding
performance on his home debut against Burnley earned him rave reviews and the
MOTM award, showcasing his masterful ability as he began the game behind the
striker but switched to a deeper role later in the game. Wherever he plays, the
former Real Betis man is a superb addition to Arsenal’s midfield for this
season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nicolas Pépé&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£72 million man Nicolas Pépé is the most hyped up of Arsenal’s summer signings
for good reason; the Ivorian was one of only two players in the top 5 European
leagues to score at least 20 times and record over 10 assists, with the other
being Lionel Messi. Only Pierre-Emerick Aubameyang (22) and Alexandre Lacazette
(13) managed more than 6 league goals for Arsenal last season so Pépé’s arrival
should easen the load for the pair while forming a potent 3-pronged attack to
try to match those at Liverpool and Man City. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though playing in a weaker league last year, Pépé regularly got into goal
scoring positions and had no hesitation in pulling the trigger, averaging 3.1
shots a game from wide, which is a welcome attribute to a team that had less
shots than Crystal Palace and Southampton last season. Pépé will add value as a
ball carrier and an outlet in the final third, fitting a profile Arsenal have
been missing since the departures of Alex Oxlade-Chamberlain, Theo Walcott and
Alexis Sánchez. Pépé’s dribbling stats last season were comparable to those of
Chamberlain’s and Sánchez’s during their time at the Emirates, and if he can
combine that with Walcott and Sánchez’s goal tallies then Arsenal have found a
real gem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are, however, questions as to how he will fit into Arsenal’s front line
with the likes of Lacazette, Aubameyang and Özil. Based on Unai Emery’s
pragmatic approach last season, it seems unlikely the 4 will line up together
often, especially away from home. Pépé should nevertheless be a fixture on the
team sheet along with Aubameyang due to their counter attacking potential. With
Pépé being a right sided player and Aubameyang, Özil and Lacazette usually
playing centrally it seems difficult to play them all without one of them being
out of position. Özil prefers to operate on the right rather than the left which
could cause Pépé to be forced to the left in pursuit of playing the two
centre-forwards in their natural positions. Needless to say, this would not be
an ideal situation for a player new to the Premier League so it’ll be up to
Emery to manage his team rotations and come up with a fluid attack to get the
best out of all his star forwards. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-11.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-12.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-13.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kieran Tierney&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most important Arsenal signings were made on deadline day as the
Gunners brought in some much needed defensive reinforcements. 22-year-old
Tierney has already captained Celtic and Scotland, fulfilling the criteria of
being a leader, a quality that many pundits, such as Gary Neville, have long
been saying Arsenal miss. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When he recovers from his hernia operation, Tierney will be tasked with fighting
off competition from fellow left-backs Nacho Monreal and Sead Kolašinac to make
the position his own. Tierney predominantly featured in a back 4 at Celtic but
has also played on the left of a back 3 for Scotland, with Liverpool’s Andy
Robertson playing as a wing back ahead of him. Whilst this may just have been a
way to shoehorn two of Scotland’s best players into the same XI, it could be an
option for Arsenal going forward with Sead Kolašinac lining up alongside
Tierney. Nacho Monreal has been deployed in a similar way over the last few
years and the benefit of this would be adding another ball playing centre-half
to bring the ball out from the back, as well as ideally having improved
defensive security with 5 defenders playing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should Tierney start in a back 4, he should act as a good counter balance to
Hector Bellerin on the opposite flank, with the Scot being the more reserved,
technically proficient of the pair whilst Bellerin utilises his athleticism to
make off ball runs and try and get in behind the opposition’s defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-21.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;David Luiz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By crossing the divide between West and North London David Luiz followed the
path that several players have trodden in the last 20 years, and if he can
emulate the very reasonable Arsenal career of William Gallas then by all
accounts he should be considered a success. Whilst Gallas was 3 years younger
than Luiz when he left Stamford Bridge for the Emirates, he was a reliable (on
the pitch, at least) performer for the club, playing 142 times for Arsenal and
being named club captain after just one season at the club ahead of established
veterans such as Jens Lehmann and Gilberto Silva. Luiz will likely form an
experienced central defensive partnership with Sokratis, replacing Laurent
Koscielny after the Frenchman’s 9 year residency at the club came to an end. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-31.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luiz entered the Premier League the same year Koscielny did, with both rightly
considered error-prone during their formative years in England before becoming
quality centre-backs. Both are proactive defenders who defend on the front-foot,
frequently stepping up to intercept dangerous passes. They are also both adept
at bringing the ball out of defence and into midfield. However, Luiz is a much
more accomplished passer, completing more through balls than any other Premier
League player last season. If Luiz can replicate that form this season, Pépé and
Aubameyang will thoroughly enjoy themselves in behind opposition backlines.
Luiz’s fine passing repertoire may be best served in a back 3, like in the
2016/17 season where he made the PFA Team of the Year, where he can venture
forward into midfield whilst still having two central defenders to cover for
him. Seeing the Brazillian in an Arsenal shirt will take some getting used to,
but, at £8 million, he could prove to be one of the most astute signings of the
summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal’s window surpassed most people’s expectations and, though nothing is
certain in football, right now has to be tentatively considered a success.
Sanllehi and co. added 5 players ranging from 18-24 years of age along with a 32
year old with years of Premier League experience. Arsenal now have a good mix of
youngsters who can grow together in the next few years whilst also having
several seasoned veterans. The departures of Ramsey, Iwobi, Koscielny and Danny
Welbeck appear to have been well replaced whilst lowering the average squad age
as Arsenal begin a new era. Having said that, we can only review how good a
transfer window has been after seeing how the signings actually perform on the
pitch. There was lots of optimism following Arsenal’s 2016 window in which they
spent around £90 million on Shkodran Mustafi, Granit Xhaka, Lucas Pérez and Rob
Holding though the first 3 have all disappointed to varying degrees. It’s now up
to the team to prove the new signings have brought them back to the level where
Arsenal strive to be. However, fans do have reason for optimism as it seems that
after a few tumultuous years with Sven Mislintat and Ivan Gazidis at the helm,
the new management regime are capable of putting together a squad that looks set
to contend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*pictures are from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot;&gt;www.buildlineup.com&lt;/a&gt; and stats are from
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.whoscored.com&quot;&gt;www.whoscored.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samuel Hogan</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Since the appointment of ex-Arsenal midfielder Edu as the club’s technical director last month, the Gunners have accelerated their transfer plans after initially making slow progress towards agreeing deals for the likes of Wilfried Zaha and Kieran Tierney.  After the little-heralded signing of Brazillian youngster Gabriel Martinelli, the window really kicked off with the double announcement of Dani Ceballos on loan from Real Madrid and the signing of £27 million William Saliba (who was subsequently loaned back to Saint Étienne) on July 25th. This was soon trumped by the surprise signing of Nicolas Pépé from Lille, with Arsenal defying the reports of their £45 million transfer budget by securing the £72 million Ivorian forward on a 5 year deal.  Finally, deadline day saw the defence bolstered by the £25 million signing of left-back Kieran Tierney from Celtic and the shock arrival of veteran centre-back David Luiz from London rivals Chelsea for £8M on a two year deal.  With Unai Emery now having added quality at his disposal, the question is how each of the new boys will fit in. William Saliba A quick mention of someone Arsenal fans won’t get to see for a while; teenage defender William Saliba whose former club Saint-Etienne insisted on having him loaned back to them this season. Despite not having played a game for the club, he has already endeared himself to the Arsenal faithful after he reportedly snubbed interest from North London rivals Tottenham before opting to join the Gunners. Once Arsenal fans do get to see him in action, they will see an accomplished modern centre-back, capable of surging forward from the back whilst also being a dependable defender, especially in 1v1 situations. His rangy stride and 6’3 frame make him a physically excellent prospect and when looking at the market for the likes of Harry Maguire, £28 million could be a bargain for an 18 year old that was starting for the fourth best team in France.  Saliba, along with Rob Holding and Calum Chambers, looks set to be the future of Arsenal’s central defence as Sokratis and David Luiz advance into their 30s.  Gabriel Martinelli The signing of 18 year old Brazillian winger Gabriel Martinelli has understandably been forgotten about by many after the 5 higher profile signings that followed. Signed from Brazillian side Ituano for a reported fee of £6 million, Martinelli made his debut in a short cameo against Newcastle last weekend and, with the sale of Alex Iwobi to Everton, could be in for some minutes as a rotation player this season. With Pépé and Henrikh Mkhitaryan now the only established wingers at the club there’s a route to the first team for Martinelli, but he’ll face fierce competition from fellow teenage wingers Reiss Nelson, Emile Smith-Rowe and Bukayo Saka.  Dani Ceballos Talented midfielder Dani Ceballos played a crucial role in Spain’s triumph at the European U21 Championship in Italy this summer, and he will now embark on a short stint in North London before he likely cements himself as a Real Madrid regular for years to come. A player as gifted as Ceballos is seldom available on loan and Arsenal should thank the likes of Luka Modric and Toni Kroos for blocking his path to regular minutes at the Bernabeu, allowing Arsenal to acquire a player who will slot right into their first XI. With Ceballos being the only addition to Arsenal’s midfield this summer, it would be natural to think he would be tasked with replacing the void left by Aaron Ramsey’s departure to Juventus. However, Ceballos is more similar to a few of Ramsey’s former midfield partners: Jack Wilshere and fellow Spaniard Santi Cazorla. Wilshere and Cazorla both averaged over 2 dribbles a game throughout their Arsenal careers, but since their departures in 2018 no Arsenal midfielder averaged more than Mattéo Guendouzi’s 0.7 dribbles a game last season.  Ceballos averaged 2.7 dribbles per game in his last league season of regular football at Real Betis in the 2016/17 season and should contribute to some much needed technical support in the centre of the park, giving Arsenal a ball carrying outlet from deep to evade pressure.  Ceballos’ immense skill set and versatility means he is capable as a deep-lying playmaker, a tireless box-to-box CM, or in the number 10 role. Given Ramsey’s departure and Özil’s recent off-the-pitch adversities, Emery is likely to deploy Ceballos as the furthest forward midfielder. The 23-year old’s outstanding performance on his home debut against Burnley earned him rave reviews and the MOTM award, showcasing his masterful ability as he began the game behind the striker but switched to a deeper role later in the game. Wherever he plays, the former Real Betis man is a superb addition to Arsenal’s midfield for this season. Nicolas Pépé £72 million man Nicolas Pépé is the most hyped up of Arsenal’s summer signings for good reason; the Ivorian was one of only two players in the top 5 European leagues to score at least 20 times and record over 10 assists, with the other being Lionel Messi. Only Pierre-Emerick Aubameyang (22) and Alexandre Lacazette (13) managed more than 6 league goals for Arsenal last season so Pépé’s arrival should easen the load for the pair while forming a potent 3-pronged attack to try to match those at Liverpool and Man City.  Though playing in a weaker league last year, Pépé regularly got into goal scoring positions and had no hesitation in pulling the trigger, averaging 3.1 shots a game from wide, which is a welcome attribute to a team that had less shots than Crystal Palace and Southampton last season. Pépé will add value as a ball carrier and an outlet in the final third, fitting a profile Arsenal have been missing since the departures of Alex Oxlade-Chamberlain, Theo Walcott and Alexis Sánchez. Pépé’s dribbling stats last season were comparable to those of Chamberlain’s and Sánchez’s during their time at the Emirates, and if he can combine that with Walcott and Sánchez’s goal tallies then Arsenal have found a real gem. There are, however, questions as to how he will fit into Arsenal’s front line with the likes of Lacazette, Aubameyang and Özil. Based on Unai Emery’s pragmatic approach last season, it seems unlikely the 4 will line up together often, especially away from home. Pépé should nevertheless be a fixture on the team sheet along with Aubameyang due to their counter attacking potential. With Pépé being a right sided player and Aubameyang, Özil and Lacazette usually playing centrally it seems difficult to play them all without one of them being out of position. Özil prefers to operate on the right rather than the left which could cause Pépé to be forced to the left in pursuit of playing the two centre-forwards in their natural positions. Needless to say, this would not be an ideal situation for a player new to the Premier League so it’ll be up to Emery to manage his team rotations and come up with a fluid attack to get the best out of all his star forwards.  Kieran Tierney Perhaps the most important Arsenal signings were made on deadline day as the Gunners brought in some much needed defensive reinforcements. 22-year-old Tierney has already captained Celtic and Scotland, fulfilling the criteria of being a leader, a quality that many pundits, such as Gary Neville, have long been saying Arsenal miss.  When he recovers from his hernia operation, Tierney will be tasked with fighting off competition from fellow left-backs Nacho Monreal and Sead Kolašinac to make the position his own. Tierney predominantly featured in a back 4 at Celtic but has also played on the left of a back 3 for Scotland, with Liverpool’s Andy Robertson playing as a wing back ahead of him. Whilst this may just have been a way to shoehorn two of Scotland’s best players into the same XI, it could be an option for Arsenal going forward with Sead Kolašinac lining up alongside Tierney. Nacho Monreal has been deployed in a similar way over the last few years and the benefit of this would be adding another ball playing centre-half to bring the ball out from the back, as well as ideally having improved defensive security with 5 defenders playing.  Should Tierney start in a back 4, he should act as a good counter balance to Hector Bellerin on the opposite flank, with the Scot being the more reserved, technically proficient of the pair whilst Bellerin utilises his athleticism to make off ball runs and try and get in behind the opposition’s defence.  David Luiz By crossing the divide between West and North London David Luiz followed the path that several players have trodden in the last 20 years, and if he can emulate the very reasonable Arsenal career of William Gallas then by all accounts he should be considered a success. Whilst Gallas was 3 years younger than Luiz when he left Stamford Bridge for the Emirates, he was a reliable (on the pitch, at least) performer for the club, playing 142 times for Arsenal and being named club captain after just one season at the club ahead of established veterans such as Jens Lehmann and Gilberto Silva. Luiz will likely form an experienced central defensive partnership with Sokratis, replacing Laurent Koscielny after the Frenchman’s 9 year residency at the club came to an end.  Luiz entered the Premier League the same year Koscielny did, with both rightly considered error-prone during their formative years in England before becoming quality centre-backs. Both are proactive defenders who defend on the front-foot, frequently stepping up to intercept dangerous passes. They are also both adept at bringing the ball out of defence and into midfield. However, Luiz is a much more accomplished passer, completing more through balls than any other Premier League player last season. If Luiz can replicate that form this season, Pépé and Aubameyang will thoroughly enjoy themselves in behind opposition backlines. Luiz’s fine passing repertoire may be best served in a back 3, like in the 2016/17 season where he made the PFA Team of the Year, where he can venture forward into midfield whilst still having two central defenders to cover for him. Seeing the Brazillian in an Arsenal shirt will take some getting used to, but, at £8 million, he could prove to be one of the most astute signings of the summer. Summary Arsenal’s window surpassed most people’s expectations and, though nothing is certain in football, right now has to be tentatively considered a success. Sanllehi and co. added 5 players ranging from 18-24 years of age along with a 32 year old with years of Premier League experience. Arsenal now have a good mix of youngsters who can grow together in the next few years whilst also having several seasoned veterans. The departures of Ramsey, Iwobi, Koscielny and Danny Welbeck appear to have been well replaced whilst lowering the average squad age as Arsenal begin a new era. Having said that, we can only review how good a transfer window has been after seeing how the signings actually perform on the pitch. There was lots of optimism following Arsenal’s 2016 window in which they spent around £90 million on Shkodran Mustafi, Granit Xhaka, Lucas Pérez and Rob Holding though the first 3 have all disappointed to varying degrees. It’s now up to the team to prove the new signings have brought them back to the level where Arsenal strive to be. However, fans do have reason for optimism as it seems that after a few tumultuous years with Sven Mislintat and Ivan Gazidis at the helm, the new management regime are capable of putting together a squad that looks set to contend. *pictures are from www.buildlineup.com and stats are from www.whoscored.com</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What’s Gone Wrong at Arsenal? Evaluating The Post-Wenger Regime</title>
      <link href="/Evaluating-The-Post-Wenger-Regime" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What’s Gone Wrong at Arsenal? Evaluating The Post-Wenger Regime" />
      <published>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Evaluating-The-Post-Wenger-Regime</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Evaluating-The-Post-Wenger-Regime">&lt;p&gt;When Arsenal’s legendary manager Arsène Wenger left north London 14 months ago, it was widely thought that this was what was needed for the Gunners to progress as a club after a disappointing few years under Le Professeur’s control. Despite Wenger shouldering almost all the blame for Arsenal’s recent shortcomings, improvement since he left has been extremely minimal at best, with the club in a similar situation to that which they were in under the Frenchman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When determining what is preventing Arsenal from progressing as a club, it is now clear that there can no longer be a single scapegoat and accountability must be shared across different departments of the club. Wenger had an almost autocratic reign for 2 decades and it was going to take more than 1 man to replace him. Have Arsenal hired the right men?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The natural place to start is with Wenger’s direct successor, Unai Emery. When Arsenal announced the appointment of the Spaniard, the press release described his role as ‘head coach’, perhaps indicating that he wouldn’t have the same influence on matters such as transfers as his predecessor did and his role would be more focused towards on-pitch matters. From a results point of view, Emery improved Arsenal’s points total and league position by 7 points and 1 place respectively, although it wasn’t hard to improve on a season in which Arsenal lost a staggering 11 away league games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 2 difficult games to open the season, Arsenal had a strong first few months in terms of results, although the performances weren’t on par and stars Aaron Ramsey and Mesut Özil were noticeably less influential than they were during the Wenger years. As of yet, Emery has failed to maximise Özil’s ability. Since he moved to north London in 2013, the German world champion has regularly topped the stats for assists and chances created as he operated as the fulcrum of Wenger’s side, however there was a sharp decline in his output last season. Whilst Özil himself must shoulder most of the blame, he was sometimes bypassed by Emery’s system which saw a more direct way of chance creation. This was often through long passes to Pierre-Emerick Aubameyang and Alexandre Lacazette up front or through Bosnian wing-back Sead Kolašinac getting in behind the back-line, though his end product was often found wanting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the reliance on Kolašinac as an attacking outlet caused problems at the back as Arsenal’s left side of the defence was often left exposed by his attacking charges. This contributed to a season where Arsenal conceded just as many league goals as they had the season prior, ending up with a worse defensive record than the likes of Newcastle and Everton despite Emery’s reputation as a pragmatic, defensive minded coach. After years of attractive attacking football under Wenger, it did seem as though a lot of the Arsenal fanbase were more than prepared to trade that off for a more conservative style if it yielded better results. Diego Simeone and Massimiliano Allegri were often (optimistically) touted as possible Wenger replacements, both men having league titles from the top 5 European leagues and multiple Champions League finals under their belts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it was Unai Emery who eventually filled Wenger’s boots. The Spaniard came with a reputation as a Europa League specialist and as impressive as his 3 successive tournament victories with Sevilla were, they themselves are a sign of what an uninspiring appointment he was. Sevilla only had the chance to participate in the Europa League by virtue of not being good enough to get into the last 16 of the Champions League. Emery’s Sevilla won the Europa League in 2014 but finished 5th in La Liga, missing out on Champions League qualification and allowing them to win the Europa League the following year. That 2015 triumph guaranteed them qualification for the following season’s Champions League due to a new rule whereby the Europa League winners automatically qualified for Europe’s premier club competition the next season. However, Sevilla could only scrape 3rd in Group D, dropping down back into the EL and winning the competition again, beating Liverpool in the final. Emery was firmly established as a quality second tier manager, cemented further by a mediocre spell with a star-studded Paris Saint Germain team, making him a questionable choice. He was a known quantity; he wouldn’t be a disaster, but neither would he get more out of the squad than expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a transfer policy that doesn’t seem to be prioritising youth, the club have signed experienced players such as Aubameyang, Sokratis, Henrikh Mkhitaryan and Stefan Lichsteiner in recent years. Arsenal are currently stagnating with little sign of improvement unless drastic changes are made. Having said all of that, the outlook on Arsenal as a whole would be vastly different if the club had managed to secure a top 4 place over a heavily criticised Maurizio Sarri-led Chelsea or Tottenham, who were distracted by their European run but still managed to stumble over the finishing line. In the end, Arsenal finished just 1 point behind Chelsea and 2 behind Tottenham. Arsenal’s failure to win any of their 4 games against Brighton, Leicester, Wolves and Crystal Palace in the final run-in proved to be the sticking point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having seemingly prioritised the Europa League, Emery’s chance at salvaging the season went up in smoke as he was outclassed by Sarri and Chelsea in a humiliating defeat to the London rivals in Baku. With Unai Emery at the helm Arsenal are seemingly treading water and for that reason serious questions have to be asked about whether he is the man to take the club forward or whether a change is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all of Emery’s faults, the majority of the blame has to lie within the higher echelons of the club. If we rewind a year (give or take), back to when it was announced Arsène Wenger’s tenure in north London would be coming to an end, Chief Executive Ivan Gazidis and Head of Recruitment Sven Mislintat were primed to be the figureheads of Arsenal’s rebuilding process. Gazidis made himself vocal around this time and spearheaded the search for a new manager, reportedly considering former Arsenal captain Mikel Arteta before settling on Emery. However, he departed for A.C Milan in September 2018, a puzzling decision that was soon followed by Mislintat leaving after barely 12 months in his role, having recruited the likes of Aubameyang, Matteo Guendouzi, Lucas Torreira and Bernd Leno.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal felt Gazidis was so influential that he couldn’t be replaced by one man, thus Vinai Venkatesham and Raul Sanllehi were brought in. The pair featured in a lengthy interview conducted on Arsenal’s social media platforms, a PR exercise in which they looked to assert their positions as the key directors at the club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mislintat, meanwhile, has been replaced by former Arsenal midfielder, Edu. The invincible left his role as general coordinator of the Brazilian national team following their Copa America triumph, being brought in as Arsenal’s first ever technical director with less than a month of the transfer window left. Arsenal’s window, so far, has been disappointing; pursuits of the likes of Kieran Tierney, William Saliba and Wilfried Zaha have been unsuccessful as of now. Once news broke that Arsenal reportedly had a transfer budget of just £45 million, expectations were lowered. With the season fast approaching, Edu will have to quickly re-accustom himself to his old surroundings and set off bargain hunting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal owner Stan Kroenke has been extensively criticised for his frugality which, along with Arsenal’s high wage bill and their inability to maximise their assets, has led to this paltry budget. In recent years, the club has let key players such as Mesut Özil, Alexis Sanchez, Aaron Ramsey, Danny Welbeck, Jack Wilshere and Santi Cazorla run their contracts down to the final 6 months, with the latter four having left for free meaning Arsenal did not receive any money to help with finding replacements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite those inconveniences, the most crippling examples of poor asset management came with Arsenal’s 2 star players as they swapped Alexis Sanchez for (then 29 year old) Manchester United flop Henrikh Mkhitaryan in an attempt to extract some kind of value for the Chilean, reportedly giving Mkhitaryan a 4 year, £180,000 a week contract. Meanwhile, Arsenal retained the services of Özil for the small price of £350,000 a week over 4 years, with the club desperately trying to dump him just 18 months later. Furthermore, with big contract extensions reportedly being lined up for 30-year old Aubameyang and 28-year-old Lacazette, the club must decide whether they want to risk a situation where they again overpay players as they exit their prime. Conversely, the alternative could be to have a repeat of the Sanchez and Ramsey situations if they choose to let the attackers run down the remainder of their contracts, which expire in 2021 and 2022 respectively. It is a somewhat unenviable position for Arsenal management to be in as it must also be considered that any decision to sell either of these two fan favourites will be widely lambasted by the Arsenal faithful, not to mention the impact selling a star player would have on the team’s success. Signings such as 18-year-old forward Gabriel Martinelli represent the player profile that Arsenal should be targeting; young players with potential to improve and be sold for profit. This was the approach Arsenal took following their move to the Emirates Stadium when funds were restricted. Players such as Cesc Fabregas, Emmanuel Adebayor, Robin Van Persie and Alex Song put in years of good service before recouping high transfer fees. Arsenal are currently not in a position to contend for the Premier League or Champions League but could be in 5-8 years if they are patient and have a long-term plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a club has undergone such drastic change in such a short period of time, it is important that it has a clear vision about how to achieve its goals. When a club’s Chief Executive and Head of Recruitment leave in the same season, it makes said club look like an aimless mess. Arsenal’s transfer plans look to be uncreative to say the least. When former Borussia Dortmund scout Sven Mislintat was at the club, Arsenal signed 3 former players that he knew from his time at the German club in Aubameyang, Mkhitaryan and Sokratis. Interestingly, despite this, he was reportedly ‘dismayed’ when Unai Emery requested the signing of one of his former players, Denis Suarez, with the German leaving shortly after. There seems to be a worrying pattern here with several former Emery players such as Ever Banega, Christopher Nkunku and Thomas Meunier also being linked with a move to the Emirates. Furthermore, widely reported targets Kieran Tierney and Wilfried Zaha come with a premium added to their price due to their home grown statuses which isn’t optimal for a club with limited funds. The future looks bleak and will continue to look so until the club commits to a full scale rebuild where they prioritise the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal should be hiring a young manager that has a clear footballing philosophy with the potential to win major honours; Julian Nagelsmann and Mikel Arteta are possible options. The club must come to terms with the fact that the current squad is not close to being good enough to challenge for the league title and youngsters like Reiss Nelson, Hector Bellerin, Ainsley Maitland-Niles, Alex Iwobi, Guendouzi and Torreira should be considered the key to future success, along with any signings that have potential to grow into quality players. This is likely to be a slow process, but, due to the mess the club has gotten itself into, it is a necessary one.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samuel Hogan</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">When Arsenal’s legendary manager Arsène Wenger left north London 14 months ago, it was widely thought that this was what was needed for the Gunners to progress as a club after a disappointing few years under Le Professeur’s control. Despite Wenger shouldering almost all the blame for Arsenal’s recent shortcomings, improvement since he left has been extremely minimal at best, with the club in a similar situation to that which they were in under the Frenchman.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Scrutinising Pep Guardiola’s Record in the Champions League</title>
      <link href="/Scrutinising-Pep-Guardiola" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scrutinising Pep Guardiola’s Record in the Champions League" />
      <published>2019-06-26T16:13:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-26T16:13:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Scrutinising-Pep-Guardiola</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Scrutinising-Pep-Guardiola">&lt;p&gt;A Pep Guardiola managed team failed to reach the UEFA Champions League Final for
the 7th season in a row since his famed F.C Barcelona squad won the competition
in 2011. Following this, Guardiola has faced inevitable criticism questioning
whether he will be able to win another Champions League and, more specifically,
whether he can win the trophy without having a Lionel Messi-led team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When scrutinising Pep’s European record, it is worth noting how some of his
contemporaries and other managerial greats have fared in the biggest competition
in club football. Sir Alex Ferguson, often described as the greatest manager of
all time, has won the same number of Champions League titles as Guardiola
despite the former Manchester United manager having competed in 9 more editions
of the competition. Furthermore, along with fellow European football leaders
such as Carlo Ancelotti, José Mourinho and Louis Van Gaal, the Scot has a lower
win rate in the competition than Guardiola.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Manager&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;UEFA Champions League Finals &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;win&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;loss&lt;/span&gt; record (year)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL semi-finals reached&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL quarter-finals reached&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Number of seasons managed in CL&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL win percentage (%)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Luis Enrique&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;73&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jupp Heynckes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2 -1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;98&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zinedine Zidane&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pep Guardiola&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;09&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Louis Van Gaal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;95&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;96&lt;/span&gt;, 10)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;60&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diego Simeone&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carlo Ancelotti&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3-1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;03&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;05&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;07&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;55&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sir Alex Ferguson&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;99&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;08&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;09&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;José Mourinho&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;04&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;53&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jürgen Klopp&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3*&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arsène Wenger&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;06&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of this, only two managers have won more UEFA Champions League winners
medals than Pep since the competition’s inception in 1992: Ancelotti and
Zinedine Zidane. It is a sign that Guardiola has set himself impossibly high
standards as a result of his star-studded and revolutionary Barcelona team
capturing two CL titles in his first three seasons at a major club. Not only a
victim of his own success, Guardiola was also faced with the unenviable task of
having to take over at a Bayern Munich team that had just won the treble
(Bundesliga, Champions League and DFB Pokal). The Catalan native therefore had
sky high expectations and no room for error, with anything less than a repeat of
the Bavarians’ success to be deemed regression and failure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After cruising through the 2013/14 group stages and dispatching of Manchester
United and Arsenal, Pep’s Bayern ran into a devastating counter attacking force
that exposed a weakness in his system. At the time, Real Madrid were relatively
starved of European success and chasing ‘La Decima’. After a semi-final first
leg in which Bayern had 72% possession but succumbed to a Karim Benzema goal,
the German outfit were “accused of valuing possession football ahead of the
penetrative sort” per The Guardian, a criticism in reference to their
‘tika-taka’ football that would follow Pep throughout his career. Bayern were
trounced on their own turf in the return leg, with a 4-0 loss summed up by a
breath-taking counter attacking goal where the Bayern midfield were bypassed and
the central defensive partnership of Jerome Boateng and Dante cut wide open by
the clinical play of Benzema, Gareth Bale and Cristiano Ronaldo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse was to come the following year when Bayern, domestically dominant as ever,
again exited at the semi-final stage, this time at the hands of Guardiola’s
former team. Even though Barcelona boasted the talents of Messi along with
Neymar Jr. and Luis Suárez in a 3-pronged attack, Pep set his Bayern team out to
play a suicidal high line that allowed Neymar and Suárez ample space behind the
defence, with the likes of Andres Iniesta, Sergio Busquets and Messi able to
pick out their runs. Despite this, Bayern were kept in the game by goalkeeper
Manuel Neuer but following two moments of Messi magic, Neymar exposed this
tactical error to clinch the 3-0 win with his breakaway goal putting the 2nd leg
out of reach for Guardiola’s side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More disappointment was to come in Guardiola’s 3rd and final season in Bavaria
as Bayern were once again unable to advance past the semi-final stage, this time
losing to Atletico Madrid on away goals. Over the 2 legs, Bayern had 74%
possession and outshot the Spanish side 53-18 with familiar criticism levelled
at Pep with regards to his team’s one dimensional, possession reliant style
being vulnerable to defensively strong teams that were proficient at counter
attacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manchester City’s appointment of Guardiola in June 2016 was made with the
understanding that he had experienced winning club football’s ultimate prize.
But in his first three seasons at the club, the Spaniard is yet to reach the
semi-final round of the competition, let alone the final. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his first season, City were surprisingly dumped out of the Champions League
on away goals by a youthful AS Monaco team. Monaco’s exuberant team, which
included Kylian Mbappé, Thomas Lemar as well as current City stars Bernardo
Silva and Benjamin Mendy, were able to capitalise on City’s frailties and score
6 goals across the two legs. Whilst this exit was disappointing considering
Monaco’s inexperience and Pep’s pedigree, it was somewhat understandable due to
an unbalanced squad with ageing fullbacks. Willy Caballero, Bacary Sagna, Gael
Clichy, Pablo Zabaleta and Aleksandar Kolarov, who have all since left the club,
were all clearly past their prime and this fact was consistently exposed by the
young French side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improvements were expected following a spending spree which included over £120
million spent to address the problematic full back position. In spite of these
costly additions, City were overwhelmed by a high tempo Liverpool game plan at
Anfield in the 17/18 season and again failed to reach the semis of Europe’s
premier club competition this year after losing out on away goals to Tottenham
Hotspur. Whilst Pep wasn’t blameless for this exit following an underwhelming
performance in the first leg where City struggled to impose themselves and Leroy
Sane was confined to the bench for 89 minutes in a bewildering tactical
decision, it seems harsh to place too much blame on him for the second leg. City
largely dominated and won 4-3 on the night, with the three Tottenham goals
stemming from two errors from the usually reliable Aymeric Laporte and a
fortuitous Fernando Llorente arm/hip finish. Furthermore, whilst Llorente’s goal
could have been ruled out for handball, Raheem Sterling’s dramatic ‘winner’ was
ruled out by the newly introduced Video Assistant Referee (VAR) system, meaning
that without VAR intervention and following the rules from every previous year
of Pep’s UCL career, City would have surely advanced. This is now the third
season in a row Guardiola has failed to reach the Champions League semi-finals,
having succeeded in doing so in his first 7 seasons in the competition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Controversial official decisions have to be mentioned when evaluating Pep’s
Champions League career with the Catalan being on both sides of questionable
decisions. In 2009, there was an infamous Champions League semi-final 2nd leg
between Barcelona and Chelsea in which the west London side thought they were
unfairly denied 4 penalty shouts before Iniesta sent Barca to the final with
their only shot on target. Additionally, in 2011, there was more controversy as
Arsenal star Robin Van Persie was given a ludicrous red card for kicking the
ball away 1 second after the referee had blown his whistle. Arsenal were leading
Barcelona 3-2 on aggregate at this stage before losing 4-3 as Barca went on to
win Pep’s second Champions League. Guardiola’s Barca nearly benefited from
questionable officiating again in the 2010 semi-final 2nd leg as Thiago Motta
was given a harsh red card, though Barca were bitten by the same hand that fed
them as the goal from Bojan that would have sent them through to the final in
Madrid was incorrectly ruled out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only do the fine margins of refereeing decisions affect perceptions of Pep’s
success, but more general plays can greatly alter managerial legacies. A
plethora of things can happen on a pitch to tilt the result of a match one way
or another, with the manager having no control over them. For example, if John
Terry converts his infamous penalty in Moscow 2008, Sir Alex Ferguson has only
one Champions League final win to his name. Does the fact that Terry slipped
mean we should see Ferguson as a better manager? Of course not, it was simply
luck in the same way that Frank Lampard and Didier Drogba each hitting the
woodwork in extra time that night was. The list goes on: Guardiola would only
have 1 Champions League if Iniesta’s last gasp shot in 2009 was a few inches
higher, Jupp Heynckes would likely have 3 CLs if Arjen Robben scored his penalty
in the 2012 final. Even in this year’s edition, finalists Liverpool would have
been knocked out at the first hurdle had Napoli’s Arkadiusz Milik not fired
straight at Alisson in the final minute of the group stage. Managers have no
control over these moments and it is imperceptive to solely look at the end
results rather than use critical thinking to evaluate the process of a match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pep’s Champions League legacy is complex with many different factors having to
be considered. He has almost exclusively had super-teams at his disposal and
whilst he has heavily influenced European football’s ethos in the past decade,
he has underperformed on multiple occasions. Nevertheless, criticising a manager
that has reached 7 semi-finals in 10 years seems harsh considering the Champions
League is notoriously hard to win, with there being no team able to retain the
trophy from 1992-2017 (Real Madrid retained the trophy in the 2017 season).
Guardiola set impossibly high standards for himself in his first 3 European
campaigns and whilst there is no shame in failing to meet or exceed those
expectations, his Champions League record in his 3 seasons at Manchester City
have undoubtedly been a disappointment (especially considering the £500M that
has been spent on transfers). If he wants to put the scrutiny to bed, it is time
for Pep to join the exclusive list of managers to win the UEFA Champions League
with multiple clubs.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samuel Hogan</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A Pep Guardiola managed team failed to reach the UEFA Champions League Final for the 7th season in a row since his famed F.C Barcelona squad won the competition in 2011. Following this, Guardiola has faced inevitable criticism questioning whether he will be able to win another Champions League and, more specifically, whether he can win the trophy without having a Lionel Messi-led team. When scrutinising Pep’s European record, it is worth noting how some of his contemporaries and other managerial greats have fared in the biggest competition in club football. Sir Alex Ferguson, often described as the greatest manager of all time, has won the same number of Champions League titles as Guardiola despite the former Manchester United manager having competed in 9 more editions of the competition. Furthermore, along with fellow European football leaders such as Carlo Ancelotti, José Mourinho and Louis Van Gaal, the Scot has a lower win rate in the competition than Guardiola. Manager UEFA Champions League Finals win/loss record (year) CL semi-finals reached CL quarter-finals reached Number of seasons managed in CL CL win percentage (%) Luis Enrique 1-0 (15) 1 3 3 73 Jupp Heynckes 2 -1 (98, 12, 13) 4 4 4 70 Zinedine Zidane 3-0 (16, 17, 18) 3 3 4 70 Pep Guardiola 2-0 (09, 11) 7 9 10 61 Louis Van Gaal 1-2 (95, 96, 10) 5 6 10 60 Diego Simeone 0-2 (14, 16) 3 4 6 56 Carlo Ancelotti 3-1 (03, 05, 07, 14) 8 12 17 55 Sir Alex Ferguson 2-2 (99, 08, 09, 11) 7 12 19 54 José Mourinho 2-0 (04, 10) 8 8 16 53 Jürgen Klopp 0-2 (13, 18) 3* 4 6 51 Arsène Wenger 0-1 (06) 3 7 20 47 On top of this, only two managers have won more UEFA Champions League winners medals than Pep since the competition’s inception in 1992: Ancelotti and Zinedine Zidane. It is a sign that Guardiola has set himself impossibly high standards as a result of his star-studded and revolutionary Barcelona team capturing two CL titles in his first three seasons at a major club. Not only a victim of his own success, Guardiola was also faced with the unenviable task of having to take over at a Bayern Munich team that had just won the treble (Bundesliga, Champions League and DFB Pokal). The Catalan native therefore had sky high expectations and no room for error, with anything less than a repeat of the Bavarians’ success to be deemed regression and failure.  After cruising through the 2013/14 group stages and dispatching of Manchester United and Arsenal, Pep’s Bayern ran into a devastating counter attacking force that exposed a weakness in his system. At the time, Real Madrid were relatively starved of European success and chasing ‘La Decima’. After a semi-final first leg in which Bayern had 72% possession but succumbed to a Karim Benzema goal, the German outfit were “accused of valuing possession football ahead of the penetrative sort” per The Guardian, a criticism in reference to their ‘tika-taka’ football that would follow Pep throughout his career. Bayern were trounced on their own turf in the return leg, with a 4-0 loss summed up by a breath-taking counter attacking goal where the Bayern midfield were bypassed and the central defensive partnership of Jerome Boateng and Dante cut wide open by the clinical play of Benzema, Gareth Bale and Cristiano Ronaldo. Worse was to come the following year when Bayern, domestically dominant as ever, again exited at the semi-final stage, this time at the hands of Guardiola’s former team. Even though Barcelona boasted the talents of Messi along with Neymar Jr. and Luis Suárez in a 3-pronged attack, Pep set his Bayern team out to play a suicidal high line that allowed Neymar and Suárez ample space behind the defence, with the likes of Andres Iniesta, Sergio Busquets and Messi able to pick out their runs. Despite this, Bayern were kept in the game by goalkeeper Manuel Neuer but following two moments of Messi magic, Neymar exposed this tactical error to clinch the 3-0 win with his breakaway goal putting the 2nd leg out of reach for Guardiola’s side. More disappointment was to come in Guardiola’s 3rd and final season in Bavaria as Bayern were once again unable to advance past the semi-final stage, this time losing to Atletico Madrid on away goals. Over the 2 legs, Bayern had 74% possession and outshot the Spanish side 53-18 with familiar criticism levelled at Pep with regards to his team’s one dimensional, possession reliant style being vulnerable to defensively strong teams that were proficient at counter attacking. Manchester City’s appointment of Guardiola in June 2016 was made with the understanding that he had experienced winning club football’s ultimate prize. But in his first three seasons at the club, the Spaniard is yet to reach the semi-final round of the competition, let alone the final.  In his first season, City were surprisingly dumped out of the Champions League on away goals by a youthful AS Monaco team. Monaco’s exuberant team, which included Kylian Mbappé, Thomas Lemar as well as current City stars Bernardo Silva and Benjamin Mendy, were able to capitalise on City’s frailties and score 6 goals across the two legs. Whilst this exit was disappointing considering Monaco’s inexperience and Pep’s pedigree, it was somewhat understandable due to an unbalanced squad with ageing fullbacks. Willy Caballero, Bacary Sagna, Gael Clichy, Pablo Zabaleta and Aleksandar Kolarov, who have all since left the club, were all clearly past their prime and this fact was consistently exposed by the young French side. Improvements were expected following a spending spree which included over £120 million spent to address the problematic full back position. In spite of these costly additions, City were overwhelmed by a high tempo Liverpool game plan at Anfield in the 17/18 season and again failed to reach the semis of Europe’s premier club competition this year after losing out on away goals to Tottenham Hotspur. Whilst Pep wasn’t blameless for this exit following an underwhelming performance in the first leg where City struggled to impose themselves and Leroy Sane was confined to the bench for 89 minutes in a bewildering tactical decision, it seems harsh to place too much blame on him for the second leg. City largely dominated and won 4-3 on the night, with the three Tottenham goals stemming from two errors from the usually reliable Aymeric Laporte and a fortuitous Fernando Llorente arm/hip finish. Furthermore, whilst Llorente’s goal could have been ruled out for handball, Raheem Sterling’s dramatic ‘winner’ was ruled out by the newly introduced Video Assistant Referee (VAR) system, meaning that without VAR intervention and following the rules from every previous year of Pep’s UCL career, City would have surely advanced. This is now the third season in a row Guardiola has failed to reach the Champions League semi-finals, having succeeded in doing so in his first 7 seasons in the competition.  Controversial official decisions have to be mentioned when evaluating Pep’s Champions League career with the Catalan being on both sides of questionable decisions. In 2009, there was an infamous Champions League semi-final 2nd leg between Barcelona and Chelsea in which the west London side thought they were unfairly denied 4 penalty shouts before Iniesta sent Barca to the final with their only shot on target. Additionally, in 2011, there was more controversy as Arsenal star Robin Van Persie was given a ludicrous red card for kicking the ball away 1 second after the referee had blown his whistle. Arsenal were leading Barcelona 3-2 on aggregate at this stage before losing 4-3 as Barca went on to win Pep’s second Champions League. Guardiola’s Barca nearly benefited from questionable officiating again in the 2010 semi-final 2nd leg as Thiago Motta was given a harsh red card, though Barca were bitten by the same hand that fed them as the goal from Bojan that would have sent them through to the final in Madrid was incorrectly ruled out. Not only do the fine margins of refereeing decisions affect perceptions of Pep’s success, but more general plays can greatly alter managerial legacies. A plethora of things can happen on a pitch to tilt the result of a match one way or another, with the manager having no control over them. For example, if John Terry converts his infamous penalty in Moscow 2008, Sir Alex Ferguson has only one Champions League final win to his name. Does the fact that Terry slipped mean we should see Ferguson as a better manager? Of course not, it was simply luck in the same way that Frank Lampard and Didier Drogba each hitting the woodwork in extra time that night was. The list goes on: Guardiola would only have 1 Champions League if Iniesta’s last gasp shot in 2009 was a few inches higher, Jupp Heynckes would likely have 3 CLs if Arjen Robben scored his penalty in the 2012 final. Even in this year’s edition, finalists Liverpool would have been knocked out at the first hurdle had Napoli’s Arkadiusz Milik not fired straight at Alisson in the final minute of the group stage. Managers have no control over these moments and it is imperceptive to solely look at the end results rather than use critical thinking to evaluate the process of a match. Pep’s Champions League legacy is complex with many different factors having to be considered. He has almost exclusively had super-teams at his disposal and whilst he has heavily influenced European football’s ethos in the past decade, he has underperformed on multiple occasions. Nevertheless, criticising a manager that has reached 7 semi-finals in 10 years seems harsh considering the Champions League is notoriously hard to win, with there being no team able to retain the trophy from 1992-2017 (Real Madrid retained the trophy in the 2017 season). Guardiola set impossibly high standards for himself in his first 3 European campaigns and whilst there is no shame in failing to meet or exceed those expectations, his Champions League record in his 3 seasons at Manchester City have undoubtedly been a disappointment (especially considering the £500M that has been spent on transfers). If he wants to put the scrutiny to bed, it is time for Pep to join the exclusive list of managers to win the UEFA Champions League with multiple clubs.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Champions League Final Preview</title>
      <link href="/CL-Final-Preview" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Champions League Final Preview" />
      <published>2019-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/CL-Final-Preview</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/CL-Final-Preview">&lt;p&gt;Saturday 1st June, 2019, will live long in the memory of the millions of people who witness the spectacle of football. The Wanda Metropolitano stadium in Madrid will host the Champions League final as Tottenham and Liverpool come face-to-face for the third and final time this season in what promises to be an exceptional match. Liverpool prevailed 2-1 both times in the previous meetings between the two teams this season, and the evidence suggests that the final will be a hard-fought, tense, tactical encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pochettino’s Legacy and Klopp’s Final Troubles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tottenham are undoubtedly the underdogs but the narrative surrounding Mauricio Pochettino ahead of his first major European final is wholly favourable. If Tottenham prevail on Saturday, Pochettino will be lauded for his principal role in masterminding the North London club to the greatest prize in club football. In any case, Pochettino’s immense coaching qualities are unequivocal; it is no wonder that some of the world’s richest and most successful clubs, such as Juventus, Manchester United and Real Madrid have attempted to lure the Argentine away from N17. Spurs are on the brink of an unforgettable achievement and Pochettino will be a Tottenham legend regardless of the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Pochettino has previously faced criticism from fans and pundits for repeatedly asserting that he is not interested in winning the FA or League Cup and for never having won a major trophy in his managerial career, there is no question that the philosophy and attitude he has inculcated at the club has led to the greatest period of sustained success since the 1950s and 60s. Tottenham’s squad is too thin to compete on all four fronts, therefore it is no wonder that Pochettino has focused on the two most significant club competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to Pochettino, Tottenham’s history of having only won two major trophies since 1991 (2 League Cups) underlied the club’s reputation for ‘bottling’ and being a ‘nearly’ team. There is a strong sense in and around the club that Pochettino’s meticulous management, combined with mindful investment from chairman Daniel Levy to introduce dazzling new training facilities and stadium, has led to the instillment of a winning mentality that had been lacking at Tottenham for too long. The 47 year-old Argentine has indicated that a result in Tottenham’s favour could spell the end of his 5 year stay at Tottenham; he recently stated it is unlikely he will be able to repeat a victory of this magnitude for the club and is therefore open to moving on and seeking a new challenge elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harry Kane’s role in the game as well as whether Tottenham can handle the big game pressure and the inexperience of winning finals will be crucial. The latest word from the Spurs camp is that Mauricio Pochettino and his staff will delay telling their players the starting line-up until Saturday afternoon in order to give themselves the more time to assess the fitness of the England captain. Surprising though it may seem, some of Spurs’ best performances this season have occurred without their star striker. It has been argued that this could be due to other players in the squad upping their game in order to account for the loss of Kane’s supreme talent. Nevertheless, everyone can agree that having Kane fit for the final gives Spurs a huge boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pochettino’s equivalent on Saturday evening will be none other than Jürgen Klopp. Klopp has already experienced managing a Champions League final in 2013 and 2018; the former saw his Borussia Dortmund side suffer a 2-1 defeat to Bayern Munich after a late Arjen Robben goal eventually penetrated Dortmund, who had been astutely tactically organised until the 80th minute mark when they were caught out of position as they began to take more risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the time since, Klopp has lost 5 successive cup finals, leading to questions over his big game management. There is a tendency for Klopp’s sides to lose their shape towards the end of games if they are eagerly attempting to score late in the game. If Spurs are to pull off an upset, they must recognise that in the few games Liverpool have lost this season - such as against Manchester City, Barcelona, Chelsea and Napoli - the Reds have typically conceded goals beyond the 80th minute mark. Nonetheless, the context and reality of Klopp guiding his teams to such a large number of cup finals is testament to his eminent coaching abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparisons can be drawn between Liverpool’s and Spurs’ recent histories. Klopp is bidding to win his first trophy as Liverpool manager, and he has ably reintroduced the consistency needed for success at Anfield. Before his arrival, the Scousers were to failing to compete in the major competitions. It is easy to see why Liverpool are favourites among bookmakers to become Champions of Europe for the sixth time in their history; Klopp has turned Liverpool into a leading European powerhouse once again: the upturn in performances over the last two seasons has been astounding, culminating in reaching two successive Champions League finals and finishing second with 97 points and 1 loss (to champions Manchester City) - no mean feats. The German recently described his current team as the best squad he has worked with in his managerial career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New signings Virgil Van Dijk, Fabinho, Alisson and Shaqiri have all played their part in Liverpool’s excellence and they are subsequently a well-rounded elite team wholly capable of competing among the very best. In the same time period that Liverpool made these formidable signings, Tottenham chose not to spend a single penny across 2 transfer windows. Furthermore, although the pressure on Liverpool to win is greater than their adversary, the Reds have shown many times over that they are able to perform masterfully under pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May the best team win.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ali Abdi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Saturday 1st June, 2019, will live long in the memory of the millions of people who witness the spectacle of football. The Wanda Metropolitano stadium in Madrid will host the Champions League final as Tottenham and Liverpool come face-to-face for the third and final time this season in what promises to be an exceptional match. Liverpool prevailed 2-1 both times in the previous meetings between the two teams this season, and the evidence suggests that the final will be a hard-fought, tense, tactical encounter.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Champions League Quarter-Final Round Up</title>
      <link href="/CL-QF" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Champions League Quarter-Final Round Up" />
      <published>2019-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/CL-QF</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/CL-QF">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pochettino outclasses Pep despite the odds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manchester City were narrowly defeated against a defiant Tottenham side in an enthralling Champions League quarter-final match that will live long in the memory of the competition’s illustrious history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first leg finished 1-0 to Spurs after Heung-Min Son’s late strike gave the home side the advantage heading into the second leg at the Etihad stadium; some will argue that the South Korean’s sole goal should have been saved by Ederson as it was close to his body but the sheer power off Son’s left boot managed to dumbfound the Brazilian goalkeeper. Perhaps the biggest turning point of the tie was Lloris’ early penalty save from Aguero, as from then on City’s opportunities were limited by a formidable Spurs defence who were successfully able to deny the Citizens from scoring a vital away goal. The first leg of the tie was a highly entertaining clash between two sides at the peak of their powers, but nobody expected the second leg to be as engrossing as it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Citizens needed to win by more than one goal at their home stadium to ensure going through to the semi-finals and despite the first leg defeat, City were still favourites to proceed to the next round, largely based on their impressive domestic successes and superior squad. Therefore, when Raheem Sterling scored in the 4th minute of the second leg to equal the aggregate score, many thought it would be a routine win for City, but these postulations were withdrawn after Heung-Min Son scored twice in quick succession to give Spurs the advantage. Astonishingly, Bernardo Silva’s deflected shot made it 2-2 within 11 minutes, and City, via Raheem Sterling again, added another before the interval to make it 3-2 on the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expectedly, City began the second half putting immense pressure on the away side and their efforts eventually came to fruition after Sergio Aguero’s powerful near-post finish put City 4-2 up on 59 minutes. Spurs replied through Fernando Llorente, who became the unexpected hero after the ball bounced off his body into the net from a corner kick. In the end, the mesmerising game finished 4-3 to the Premier League champions, but it wasn’t enough as Spurs went through on away goals. The final few minutes of the tie saw Raheem Sterling score only for it to be ruled out for offside after VAR was consulted and City celebrations had already taken place in vain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After losing their talisman, Harry Kane, through a recurrent ankle injury in the first leg, few people expected Tottenham to beat Pep Guardiola’s prestigious team but Heung-Min Son stepped up to the plate in Kane’s absence, as he has numerous times this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result brings into question whether Pochettino is the better overall manager than Pep. Their rivalry stems from their time in Spain, as Espanyol and Barcelona managers respectively. Although Pep’s achievements in the game are unrivalled and has the superior record over the Argentine, Pochettino has had the lesser squad and defeated Pep in a quarter final despite not having made a signing since January 2018 and missing key players such as Harry Kane and Harry Winks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Messi shines again as Barcelona are into the semi-finals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barcelona were 4-0 aggregate winners against a hopeless Manchester United side as the Catalan giants made light work of the Red Devils. After a 1-0 first leg defeat in which the Mancunians failed to provide any serious threat, United were made to pay for costly mistakes in the second leg as Leo Messi capitalised twice to give Barcelona a 3-0 aggregate advantage within 20 minutes of the second leg, all but ending the tie and sending Barcelona through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result marks Manchester United’s largest ever aggregate defeat in a two-legged European tie, while Barcelona will go on to face Liverpool in the last four of the competition, who will surely provide a sterner test than their English counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks, it has become clear that Manchester United’s initial upsurge in form after Ole Gunnar Solskjaer’s appointment in December was only a short term reaction to the mood being lifted around the club. Since the unlikely comeback at the Parc des Princes in the competition’s round of sixteen stage, United have lost 6 of their last 8 matches in all competitions. The two games they did win (2-1 victories vs Watford and West Ham respectively) were unmerited by way of being the lesser side on both occasions. It still remains to be seen whether Solskjaer has the tactical know-how to match the enormity of the task being asked of him, which begs the question: why were United so hasty to appoint him as permanent manager, and why did they offer a three year contract, rather than a one-year rolling contract?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Astounding Ajax&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile in Turin, Juventus were humbled by defeat against Dutch champions Ajax in a game in which the Italian heavyweights were strong favourites. Ajax stunned football fans with their accomplished displays against Real Madrid in the last round, and they continued to silence doubters by producing another set of proficient performances against Juventus. Ajax played Juventus off the park in both legs of the tie and if there is a stat that exemplifies the Dutch team’s dominance it is that Ajax scored three goals over the two legs, while Juventus only managed a measly three shots on target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ajax’s 3-2 aggregate win does not begin to tell the story of just how commanding they were over the Italian champions. However, if there can be any criticism pointed towards Ajax, it is that they are often wasteful in front of goal despite creating numerous chances. This may be partly due to not playing a recognised striker, as their front three is a combination of attacking midfielders and wingers, who are typically more involved in the build-up of goals rather than the finishing of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Juventus were wholly uninspiring and lacklustre for a team that was tipped as a potential winner of the competition and Max Allegri’s job has now been called into question as reputable Italian newspapers report that his time at the club could be up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Liverpool ease past Porto&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Porto were thumped 6-1 on aggregate by Liverpool as the Scousers comfortably swept aside the Portuguese champions to go on to the semi-finals. In truth, the scoreline does not truly reflect the nature of the game, in which Liverpool were made to defend for large parts to hang onto their lead. However, the result does reassert Liverpool’s defensive solidity and attacking prowess; the team is exceptional at both ends of the pitch. Liverpool defeated Porto by the same margin last season in the 16 round of the competition on their way to reaching the final and they will hope to do the same this year, although their next opponents will be Barcelona in a mouth-watering tie that promises to captivate audiences across the world as two European heavyweights go head-to-head for a place in this year’s final in Madrid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jurgen Klopp has not yet lost a two-legged European tie during his stint at Liverpool and his side are now faced with a tough task of keeping this record intact against a Barcelona side who have only lost three games in all competitions this season. Luis Suarez and Philippé Coutinho will return to meet their former employers for the first time since leaving Anfield, which will host the second leg of the tie on 7th May at 20:00 BST.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ali Abdi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Pochettino outclasses Pep despite the odds</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">MOURINHO OUT: What it Means for the Devils Going Forward and Again, Mourinho.</title>
      <link href="/MOURINHO-OUT-or-not-What-it-Means-for-the-Devils-Going-Forward-and-Again-Mourinho" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MOURINHO OUT: What it Means for the Devils Going Forward and Again, Mourinho." />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/MOURINHO-OUT-or-not-What-it-Means-for-the-Devils-Going-Forward-and-Again-Mourinho</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/MOURINHO-OUT-or-not-What-it-Means-for-the-Devils-Going-Forward-and-Again-Mourinho">&lt;p&gt;It was their worst start to any championship season in as many as 28 years. For a team considered to be a giant in world club football, only 10 wins out of 20 games is, to say the least, terrible. Anti-positional, even. It had the potential to be a major surprise initially. But nevertheless, it was always on the cards. Jose Mourinho, much-celebrated manager, was fired. The management had finally taken the leap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The news, which came out early December 18th following an almost-devastating 3-1 loss to Jurgen Klopp’s Liverpool at Anfield, was christened by a not-so-coincidental Instagram post by Paul Pogba, whose feud with Mourinho over the last season has been no secret to a sane person. Not to say, this garnered huge reactions across all social media, but that’s another story. For another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most United fans cannot stop smiling ear-to-ear with the news, some feel it’s all a bit too late with the Red Devils &lt;a href=&quot;https://bleacherreport.com/articles/2812956-epl-results-saturdays-week-20-scores-updated-2019-premier-league-table&quot;&gt;currently placed 6th&lt;/a&gt; in the Premier League, six points behind 5th-placed Arsenal and a gargantuan nineteen points behind table-toppers Liverpool, all combining to make a Champions League spot for next year seem very, very unlikely. However things aren’t all gloomy for Manchester United as they did manage to qualify for the knockout stage of this year’s Champions League. What’s more, they have a long two-month break (holiday?) before their game against French rivals Paris Saint Germain. This affords the interim manager Ole Gunnar Solskjaer a fighting chance to get the boys back and running before the all-important clash. It however will be no easy task, as post Sir Alex Ferguson, United have had as many as four managers (including Jose Mourinho), every single one of whom have failed to deliver the bounties or even as much as have any real impact on the club. Norwegian Ole ‘Gunnar’ Solskjaer is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://bleacherreport.com/articles/2812956-epl-results-saturdays-week-20-scores-updated-2019-premier-league-table&quot;&gt;former United forward&lt;/a&gt;, netting 126 goals in 366 appearances for the club. His exploits also earned him the rather scary nickname of ‘baby-faced-Assassin’. In retrospect, it is also an oxymoron, so you never know. He is expected to run the show at Old Trafford for now, until the board can appoint a successor to Mourinho’s three year ‘reign-of-terror’. The current favorites’ to replace him would be Spurs’ manager Mauricio Pochettino and former Madrid superstar Zinedine Zidane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to United’s actual players, we saw a flickering shade of the Reds of yore in their first game post the Mourinho ‘era’ with their resounding 5-1 win over Cardiff this weekend immediately followed by 3–1 and 4-1 wins over Huddersfield and Bournemouth respectively just a few days later. With Mourinho ousted and gone, it’s a massive opportunity for United’s big signings Sanchez, Pogba and the effervescent Lukaku to step up and regain some lost pride for the club. Moreover, they would always have the services of the younger guns like Rashford, Lingard and Martial. In a recent interview, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.football365.com/news/lingard-explains-what-ole-has-done-for-pogba&quot;&gt;Lingard talked&lt;/a&gt; about Pogba and Solskjaer. He said, “I can definitely, definitely see the Paul I used to know. Ole has given him the license to be free and play his game and do what all of us know he can.” So, if we go by what Lingard has to say, the future bodes well for the Devils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as José Mourinho goes, the hope of another Premier League managerial job seems slim given his consecutive failures at United and a poor last season at Chelsea which saw them spiraling to lose nine out of their last sixteen League games. There are a few Madrid rumors in the air but it all seems pretty bleak as one of ESPN’s pundits puts it, going on to say, “At this point, Mourinho is a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.espn.in/video/clip?id=25564591&quot;&gt;damaged brand&lt;/a&gt;.” However, with all due respect to Mourinho, he is still one of the greatest managers the world has ever seen, with as many as a whopping twenty-five major honors. So maybe, just maybe, his story doesn’t end here. Who knows, perhaps international management is on the cards as well as he could very likely be the potential successor to Portugal’s Fernando Santos. Only time will tell, whatever that is. As for now his 22.5 million pound payout should keep him fed for a while.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Andrew Mark</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It was their worst start to any championship season in as many as 28 years. For a team considered to be a giant in world club football, only 10 wins out of 20 games is, to say the least, terrible. Anti-positional, even. It had the potential to be a major surprise initially. But nevertheless, it was always on the cards. Jose Mourinho, much-celebrated manager, was fired. The management had finally taken the leap.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
