<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/olly.bowes/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-10-31T21:54:25+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/olly.bowes/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Picture of Dorian Gray – Final Thoughts from the Composer’s Desk</title>
      <link href="/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray-2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Picture of Dorian Gray – Final Thoughts from the Composer’s Desk" />
      <published>2019-03-07T03:30:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-07T03:30:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray-2</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray-2">&lt;p&gt;It strikes me that whenever I announced to people that I had set about writing
an opera, I never actually received that reaction I expected. I was certain I’d
be met with derision – “What makes you think YOU can write one, Bowes?” Up to
the point that I began working on &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt;, I had only really written choral
music and a few songs. My only forays into purely instrumental music consisted
of a piano quintet I concocted for my A-level coursework, an arrangement of a
school song (&lt;em&gt;Bedford by the River&lt;/em&gt; – won a cash prize for it, to be fair), and
a frankly ridiculous setting of the &lt;em&gt;Requiem Mass&lt;/em&gt;, which I hope will never be
performed in its current state. Yet, the reaction, especially when I told
everyone of the subject-matter of this opera, Wilde’s seminal novella &lt;em&gt;The
Picture of Dorian Gray&lt;/em&gt;, was unanimously positive. A few more knowledgeable
friends asked whether it had been done before, to which I ask: how many versions
of &lt;em&gt;Faust&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Romeo and Juliet&lt;/em&gt; are there? Answer: frankly too many, not that I
wouldn’t consider doing a &lt;em&gt;Faust&lt;/em&gt;-related one at some point – indeed, one can
see &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt; itself as a Faustian tale. Nevertheless, the reception to the idea
was that I ought to push on, and so I did. Thus, I have reached the end of the
compositional process (barring edits after the fact) and I have more than enough
time to sit and worry about the show. Which I do – all too often, in fact. And
which also led me to write this pair of articles for &lt;em&gt;The Pangean&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray&quot;&gt;last
article&lt;/a&gt;, I had reflected on
the music of the first Act, but I came to realize after its publication that I
had failed to actually discuss compositional process, which I suppose is far
more interesting than simply taking you, arm-in-arm, on a promenade through what
you will, in just a matter of months, be able to hear for yourself. Therefore,
while I will still move chronologically through the final Act, wouldn’t you
rather hear about how I did the composing, rather than what composing I did?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all honesty, I have not been composing for long enough to have entirely
unified a process. Different pieces require different things from me. Some
pieces can go from just the little scribblings in a notebook straight into my
computer, where I will transform them from the idea into an actual functioning
piece. Others, such as the song-cycle I am currently working on, &lt;em&gt;Crow&lt;/em&gt;, needed
to be mapped out in full-score on paper first, and in ink – it felt particularly
necessary for &lt;em&gt;Crow&lt;/em&gt;, as it lent a sparseness to the writing that was very
helpful (although, I must say that it has been an absolute b*tch to write up on
my computer.) These are the two ends of a sliding scale upon which &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt; sat
somewhere in the middle. Or, in fact, off of either end. Some scenes, such as
the theatre scene in Act One went straight from my brain into the computer, as
the nature of the scurrying accompaniment made it a real bore to hand-write,
without the joy of copy-and-paste and editing after the fact. Others, such as
the entire last scene, were almost entirely drafted on paper first and then
written up – although I admit that at least part of the reason for hand-writing
the entire last scene was that my laptop was on the blink and I was 3,000 miles
from home. But, it keeps the romantic notion of the composer scribbling away
with pen and ink alive, so I’ve got to keep up appearances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so we come to the last Act. Although much of this was drafted last, the
prelude to the first scene was, in fact, finished long before most of Act One,
as it gave me, frankly, a nice compositional break from the Prologue. My
librettist Jamie and I had to come up with some way to symbolise several years
of debauchery that the audience missed by swanning out for their interval drinks
in the bar. I assume that the debauched years will be lived through in the minds
of our performers during this interval; it would be nicely ‘method’ of them. But
how to illustrate it in music? I gave the audience a brief, slow moment in which
to mourn Basil and Sybil, both brutally killed at the end of the first Act,
before setting about the musical debauchery. Decadence and wild abandon are
often achieved in music through the use of rowdy dances. Ravel was a master of
this, especially in the finale of &lt;em&gt;La Valse&lt;/em&gt;, or consider Stravinsky’s &lt;em&gt;Rite of
Spring&lt;/em&gt; – the poor girl dances herself to death at the end. But, as those of you
who know me can testify, I am no dancer. So how should I go after the same
effects? It’s actually fairly obvious: the thing that makes a dance a dance is
the rhythm, with which I have very little issue (getting the legs to do what
they’re told on the other hand…). Therefore, I took one of the rhythmic motifs
that described the den of iniquity that was the theatre in Act One, and laid it
underneath a pulsating Yoruba-inspired cross-rhythm from a pair of drums to
create a heady mix of open fifths and driving rhythms that symbolises Dorian’s
embracing of Harry’s lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the segue into the first scene, which itself takes place in an opium
den, takes its influences from Debussy’s use of the quartal harmony to lend an
air of intentionally fake orientalism, with added xylophonic twinkling. This is
undercut by the following chorus ‘number’ – Dorian, his mind full of a romantic
poems, hallucinates that the other patrons of this establishment all begin
singing, in French, about the beauty of Venice, at odds with both the Chinese-y
music of the den, as well as with the general dinginess of London at the end of
the 19th century. And, as a unifying feature of this scene, the music is still
Debussy-inspired. With a French poem, especially by a poet such as Théophile
Gautier, one can’t not look to Debussy, I feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Sur une gamme chromatique, &lt;br /&gt;

Le sein de perles ruisselant, &lt;br /&gt;

La Vénus de l’Adriatique, &lt;br /&gt;

Sort de l’eau son corps rose et blanc.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remainder of the first scene is dominated by the one appearance of Sybil’s
brother James, who rages like a bull in a china-shop while attempting to pursue
Dorian. His aria was one for which I did the most planning – James had to be
able to arrive on the scene and make enough of an impact to make him feel like a
threat for the remainder of the show, despite not having been seen in the
previous acts. Thus, he demanded a full-on show-stopper of an aria. What makes
music sound angry? It’s much the same as that which makes music sound debauched,
as both violent anger and wild abandon stray from the comfortable emotional
spectrum. Thus, I focused on rhythm again. I wrote out his words, some of the
most violent I have read in Wilde, and began to speak them to myself over and
over again. Individual lines became something of a rapid chant, savagely
thumping away, until I was able to write down specific rhythms I had associated
with them. The aria became very caballetic, with compound rhythms driving
underneath the singer’s howling. And then I worked out the melody. It’s not
greatly complicated, just arpeggiating through the chords underneath. Far more
important is the tessitura: James was, in my head, a Bass, albeit one with a
very solid top range, and this aria is one that exploits it, as I push the
singer to the upper extreme, bellowing away in righteous fury, while the
orchestra churns away tempestuously around him, until he disappears into the
night to hunt his sister’s ‘killer’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second scene, the last scene to be written, and not appearing in the
novella, we return to Lord Henry’s house. Yet the house has a much darker aspect
than when we had seen it in the first Act. For one thing, it is about three in
the morning. But, more importantly, Henry’s wife has made a decision that will
cast a pall on the man for the rest of the show. To give a sense of this
foreboding, I searched back through her brief appearance in Act One for melodies
associated with Lady Victoria, finally picking the languorous downwardly
meandering tune she uses to describe her enjoyment of pianists to manipulate
into a mournful prelude to the scene, descending through the strings in a canon,
before a quote from Tchaikovsky’s &lt;em&gt;Eugene Onegin&lt;/em&gt; foreshadows the fateful letter
that she has written for Harry. Harry’s music, on the other hand, is much
brighter and jolly – he’s drunk, and he sings in a drunkenly twisted patter,
while Victoria drums up the courage to tell him she is leaving. When she finally
pours forth all her upset, we move from twisted patter into a driving
baroque-esque raging, reminiscent of Handel’s more overtly furious moments, most
particularly Dejanira’s aria, &lt;em&gt;Where Shall I Fly&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;Hercules,&lt;/em&gt; in which the
overwrought Dejanira is driven mad by guilt, having caused the death of her
god-like husband. But, for me, there was a deeper meaning behind the baroque
façade that I had Victoria put up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jamie and I discussed this scene at great length, deliberating over how to stop
Victoria from seeming like a shrewish, nagging wife, and more like the bright,
free woman she ought to be. Neither of us understand women (or, in my case,
people in general) as well as we’d like to think, I suspect, but I truly believe
we have drawn here a very human event: Victoria pretends, in her baroque raging,
that her divorce is for all sorts of moral and societal reasons, citing Harry’s
insalubrious behaviour as more than enough reason for her to leave him. Yet, she
ultimately confesses that this is a pretence. She married him because that
behaviour, fuelled as it was by his Byronic intelligence, was highly attractive.
However, he has now ceased being Byronic, and is simply being indulgent and
destructive whilst ignoring her as a wife. All the romance has gone from his
behaviour. It’s a far more interesting character that Jamie has drawn through
this dichotomy than what could have been there: a shrew reprimanding a wastrel
for his wastefulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We finally return to Dorian, still suffering shock from his encounter with James
Vane, on retreat in the country. We find him alone in the grounds of the Duchess
of Monmouth’s house, musing on the events of the previous few days. For this
scene, we took full advantage of the non-linear storytelling we had introduced
with the appearance of Sybil at the end of Act One. There is, in Wilde’s
original, a scintillating scene of witty repartee between Harry and several
other pillars of society after a dinner hosted by the Duchess. However, in
streamlining the show, we feared we would lose this in order to focus more
clearly on Dorian himself. That is, we feared until one of us realised we could
just do another pseudo-flashback, as Dorian recalls the events of the previous
evening. Therefore, we have another moment of lighthearted patter from Harry,
who is joined by the chorus – I felt I was channelling all of my love for &lt;em&gt;Die
Fledermaus&lt;/em&gt; or even the great Victorian partnership of Gilbert and Sullivan,
trying to create some feeling of effervescence in the midst of the terror that
is consuming Dorian here. This continues into the next big chorus moment, after
the flashback, when these society lords and ladies enter the field in which
Dorian has been sitting in order to go shooting, singing words by Rudyard
Kipling, from his &lt;em&gt;Verses on Games&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Peace upon Earth, Goodwill to men” &lt;br /&gt;

So greet we Christmas Day! &lt;br /&gt;

Oh, Christian, load your gun and then &lt;br /&gt;

Oh, Christian, out and slay.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This joyful entrance is set to a reharmonisation of Sullivan’s tune Noel, known
to most of us as &lt;em&gt;It Came Upon A Midnight Clear.&lt;/em&gt; At the same time, something of
RVW’s &lt;em&gt;Antiphon&lt;/em&gt; or Bruckner’s &lt;em&gt;Te Deum&lt;/em&gt; was never far from my mind, in terms of
the orchestration. It may have become obvious to you that I am always thinking
of other things to relate my music to. It is a problem I run into occasionally –
am I being influenced, which is fine: music does not exist in a vacuum; or am I
simply copying? Quoting things is fine, especially in such a long work as this
(there are many quotes in &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt;, most of which I have not pointed out, but
all of which make me irrationally, self-indulgently happy), but copying is not
just plagiaristic but, personally, pointless – even if my original thought, at
the inception of this opera, was that “I wish Britten had written a Dorian
Gray.” Hopefully, my style has become distinct enough from just “a kid copying
Britten”. Hopefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving on, there is so much to point to in the final scene. Therefore, I will
keep my comments limited to two particular moments. In this last scene, we see
Dorian and Harry finally alone in Dorian’s living room. Dorian is by now
incredibly stressed – Vane hunted him all the way to the Duchess’ estate, and,
in trying to creep up on him, was shot by one of the Lords on their morning
shoot – which Dorian took as a terribly ill omen. Returning to London, Harry has
been keeping tabs on his young protégé, making sure the fear and stress doesn’t
get to him. Therefore, he ups the levels of inane babble. The treatment of his
final moment of inane babble is possibly one of my favourite bits of composition
I’ve done to date. I say my composition, but actually, Harry’s last aria is
founded entirely upon a piece by Alexander Scriabin, who, although I mention him
very infrequently, is one of my favourite composers, if only for his absolutely
insane theories about the end of the world (and attempts to bring said end
about) and his pretence at having synaesthesia, which he tried to use to create
a light-organ or ‘&lt;em&gt;clavier à lumières&lt;/em&gt;’ with which to compose for the
colour-spectrum―which is, I think you’ll agree, fairly bonkers. Nevertheless, I
got it into my head to use this moment at the end of the piece to highlight
musically a big change in Dorian: before we meet Dorian in the Prologue, we hear
him from offstage, playing a snippet from Schumann’s &lt;em&gt;Waldszenen&lt;/em&gt;, a very calm,
nature-themed work for the piano – a piece of innocence, if you will. But now,
at the end of the evening, many years later for the two remaining characters,
Dorian returns to the piano to ignore Harry’s inanities, and plays Scriabin’s
&lt;em&gt;Nocturne&lt;/em&gt; for the left hand. This highlights a change in Dorian in several
ways. Firstly, it is significantly more technically and harmonically challenging
than the Schumann, in part because it is specifically for the left hand, but
also because of Scriabin’s tense, dense harmonic language, which is
significantly more discordant and much less innocent than Schumann’s. Moreover,
Schumann published &lt;em&gt;Waldszenen&lt;/em&gt; in 1849, whereas the &lt;em&gt;Nocturne&lt;/em&gt; was composed in
1894; there is nearly half a century of musical development, pushing the
boundaries of tonality and taste, between the two, indicative of the passage of
time within the show, perhaps, and certainly indicative again of the corruption
of Dorian’s innocence over that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we come to the grand collapse that is the ending. I shan’t spoil the
last few pages by discussing exactly how the show closes, because that would
undoubtedly be a travesty. What I would like to discuss is the allegorical use
of the story of &lt;em&gt;Belshazzar&lt;/em&gt; in the closing moments. In my first plan of the
end, I had refused the idea of an off-stage chorus as too ‘operatic’ for an
intimate close to this show, much too close to the end of &lt;em&gt;Don Giovanni&lt;/em&gt; or the
countless other shows that copied that dramatic close, with the lecher dragged
into hell by an immaterial chorus. However, one chat with Jamie transformed my
conception entirely: I was not overly keen on my first draft’s ending, and he
wrote some new words to close the show – they were splendid. In a tangent to
Dorian’s flashback or his vision of Sybil, Jamie brought up an off-stage chorus,
symbolic perhaps of Dorian’s frantic brain or of heavenly judgement (I’m
inclined to think one particular way, but others may disagree), singing the
&lt;em&gt;“writing on the wall”&lt;/em&gt; that appeared at &lt;em&gt;Belshazzar’s Feast&lt;/em&gt;: “&lt;em&gt;Mene Mene Tekel
Upharsin&lt;/em&gt;” or, as Jamie put it, “&lt;em&gt;Thou art in the balances, and art found
wanting.&lt;/em&gt;” Dorian, in his desperate bid to redeem himself after his years of
immorality, cannot help but hear these words, directly paralleling the
condemnation that is his own portrait hanging upon the wall. Thus, in
composition, I had to avoid not just the links to Don Giovanni but also to
Walton’s own &lt;em&gt;Belshazzar’s Feast&lt;/em&gt;, again a favourite work of mine. Fortunately,
context saved me here, as the chorus slowly makes itself known, crescendoing slowly to become just about audible on-stage, before making a final fortissimo
statement and leaving Dorian to contemplate his fate – with little over a minute
left of the opera.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Olly Bowes</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It strikes me that whenever I announced to people that I had set about writing an opera, I never actually received that reaction I expected. I was certain I’d be met with derision – “What makes you think YOU can write one, Bowes?” Up to the point that I began working on Dorian, I had only really written choral music and a few songs. My only forays into purely instrumental music consisted of a piano quintet I concocted for my A-level coursework, an arrangement of a school song (Bedford by the River – won a cash prize for it, to be fair), and a frankly ridiculous setting of the Requiem Mass, which I hope will never be performed in its current state. Yet, the reaction, especially when I told everyone of the subject-matter of this opera, Wilde’s seminal novella The Picture of Dorian Gray, was unanimously positive. A few more knowledgeable friends asked whether it had been done before, to which I ask: how many versions of Faust or Romeo and Juliet are there? Answer: frankly too many, not that I wouldn’t consider doing a Faust-related one at some point – indeed, one can see Dorian itself as a Faustian tale. Nevertheless, the reception to the idea was that I ought to push on, and so I did. Thus, I have reached the end of the compositional process (barring edits after the fact) and I have more than enough time to sit and worry about the show. Which I do – all too often, in fact. And which also led me to write this pair of articles for The Pangean. At the end of my last article, I had reflected on the music of the first Act, but I came to realize after its publication that I had failed to actually discuss compositional process, which I suppose is far more interesting than simply taking you, arm-in-arm, on a promenade through what you will, in just a matter of months, be able to hear for yourself. Therefore, while I will still move chronologically through the final Act, wouldn’t you rather hear about how I did the composing, rather than what composing I did? In all honesty, I have not been composing for long enough to have entirely unified a process. Different pieces require different things from me. Some pieces can go from just the little scribblings in a notebook straight into my computer, where I will transform them from the idea into an actual functioning piece. Others, such as the song-cycle I am currently working on, Crow, needed to be mapped out in full-score on paper first, and in ink – it felt particularly necessary for Crow, as it lent a sparseness to the writing that was very helpful (although, I must say that it has been an absolute b*tch to write up on my computer.) These are the two ends of a sliding scale upon which Dorian sat somewhere in the middle. Or, in fact, off of either end. Some scenes, such as the theatre scene in Act One went straight from my brain into the computer, as the nature of the scurrying accompaniment made it a real bore to hand-write, without the joy of copy-and-paste and editing after the fact. Others, such as the entire last scene, were almost entirely drafted on paper first and then written up – although I admit that at least part of the reason for hand-writing the entire last scene was that my laptop was on the blink and I was 3,000 miles from home. But, it keeps the romantic notion of the composer scribbling away with pen and ink alive, so I’ve got to keep up appearances. And so we come to the last Act. Although much of this was drafted last, the prelude to the first scene was, in fact, finished long before most of Act One, as it gave me, frankly, a nice compositional break from the Prologue. My librettist Jamie and I had to come up with some way to symbolise several years of debauchery that the audience missed by swanning out for their interval drinks in the bar. I assume that the debauched years will be lived through in the minds of our performers during this interval; it would be nicely ‘method’ of them. But how to illustrate it in music? I gave the audience a brief, slow moment in which to mourn Basil and Sybil, both brutally killed at the end of the first Act, before setting about the musical debauchery. Decadence and wild abandon are often achieved in music through the use of rowdy dances. Ravel was a master of this, especially in the finale of La Valse, or consider Stravinsky’s Rite of Spring – the poor girl dances herself to death at the end. But, as those of you who know me can testify, I am no dancer. So how should I go after the same effects? It’s actually fairly obvious: the thing that makes a dance a dance is the rhythm, with which I have very little issue (getting the legs to do what they’re told on the other hand…). Therefore, I took one of the rhythmic motifs that described the den of iniquity that was the theatre in Act One, and laid it underneath a pulsating Yoruba-inspired cross-rhythm from a pair of drums to create a heady mix of open fifths and driving rhythms that symbolises Dorian’s embracing of Harry’s lessons. Similarly, the segue into the first scene, which itself takes place in an opium den, takes its influences from Debussy’s use of the quartal harmony to lend an air of intentionally fake orientalism, with added xylophonic twinkling. This is undercut by the following chorus ‘number’ – Dorian, his mind full of a romantic poems, hallucinates that the other patrons of this establishment all begin singing, in French, about the beauty of Venice, at odds with both the Chinese-y music of the den, as well as with the general dinginess of London at the end of the 19th century. And, as a unifying feature of this scene, the music is still Debussy-inspired. With a French poem, especially by a poet such as Théophile Gautier, one can’t not look to Debussy, I feel. “Sur une gamme chromatique, Le sein de perles ruisselant, La Vénus de l’Adriatique, Sort de l’eau son corps rose et blanc.” The remainder of the first scene is dominated by the one appearance of Sybil’s brother James, who rages like a bull in a china-shop while attempting to pursue Dorian. His aria was one for which I did the most planning – James had to be able to arrive on the scene and make enough of an impact to make him feel like a threat for the remainder of the show, despite not having been seen in the previous acts. Thus, he demanded a full-on show-stopper of an aria. What makes music sound angry? It’s much the same as that which makes music sound debauched, as both violent anger and wild abandon stray from the comfortable emotional spectrum. Thus, I focused on rhythm again. I wrote out his words, some of the most violent I have read in Wilde, and began to speak them to myself over and over again. Individual lines became something of a rapid chant, savagely thumping away, until I was able to write down specific rhythms I had associated with them. The aria became very caballetic, with compound rhythms driving underneath the singer’s howling. And then I worked out the melody. It’s not greatly complicated, just arpeggiating through the chords underneath. Far more important is the tessitura: James was, in my head, a Bass, albeit one with a very solid top range, and this aria is one that exploits it, as I push the singer to the upper extreme, bellowing away in righteous fury, while the orchestra churns away tempestuously around him, until he disappears into the night to hunt his sister’s ‘killer’. In the second scene, the last scene to be written, and not appearing in the novella, we return to Lord Henry’s house. Yet the house has a much darker aspect than when we had seen it in the first Act. For one thing, it is about three in the morning. But, more importantly, Henry’s wife has made a decision that will cast a pall on the man for the rest of the show. To give a sense of this foreboding, I searched back through her brief appearance in Act One for melodies associated with Lady Victoria, finally picking the languorous downwardly meandering tune she uses to describe her enjoyment of pianists to manipulate into a mournful prelude to the scene, descending through the strings in a canon, before a quote from Tchaikovsky’s Eugene Onegin foreshadows the fateful letter that she has written for Harry. Harry’s music, on the other hand, is much brighter and jolly – he’s drunk, and he sings in a drunkenly twisted patter, while Victoria drums up the courage to tell him she is leaving. When she finally pours forth all her upset, we move from twisted patter into a driving baroque-esque raging, reminiscent of Handel’s more overtly furious moments, most particularly Dejanira’s aria, Where Shall I Fly from Hercules, in which the overwrought Dejanira is driven mad by guilt, having caused the death of her god-like husband. But, for me, there was a deeper meaning behind the baroque façade that I had Victoria put up. Jamie and I discussed this scene at great length, deliberating over how to stop Victoria from seeming like a shrewish, nagging wife, and more like the bright, free woman she ought to be. Neither of us understand women (or, in my case, people in general) as well as we’d like to think, I suspect, but I truly believe we have drawn here a very human event: Victoria pretends, in her baroque raging, that her divorce is for all sorts of moral and societal reasons, citing Harry’s insalubrious behaviour as more than enough reason for her to leave him. Yet, she ultimately confesses that this is a pretence. She married him because that behaviour, fuelled as it was by his Byronic intelligence, was highly attractive. However, he has now ceased being Byronic, and is simply being indulgent and destructive whilst ignoring her as a wife. All the romance has gone from his behaviour. It’s a far more interesting character that Jamie has drawn through this dichotomy than what could have been there: a shrew reprimanding a wastrel for his wastefulness. We finally return to Dorian, still suffering shock from his encounter with James Vane, on retreat in the country. We find him alone in the grounds of the Duchess of Monmouth’s house, musing on the events of the previous few days. For this scene, we took full advantage of the non-linear storytelling we had introduced with the appearance of Sybil at the end of Act One. There is, in Wilde’s original, a scintillating scene of witty repartee between Harry and several other pillars of society after a dinner hosted by the Duchess. However, in streamlining the show, we feared we would lose this in order to focus more clearly on Dorian himself. That is, we feared until one of us realised we could just do another pseudo-flashback, as Dorian recalls the events of the previous evening. Therefore, we have another moment of lighthearted patter from Harry, who is joined by the chorus – I felt I was channelling all of my love for Die Fledermaus or even the great Victorian partnership of Gilbert and Sullivan, trying to create some feeling of effervescence in the midst of the terror that is consuming Dorian here. This continues into the next big chorus moment, after the flashback, when these society lords and ladies enter the field in which Dorian has been sitting in order to go shooting, singing words by Rudyard Kipling, from his Verses on Games: “Peace upon Earth, Goodwill to men” So greet we Christmas Day! Oh, Christian, load your gun and then Oh, Christian, out and slay.” This joyful entrance is set to a reharmonisation of Sullivan’s tune Noel, known to most of us as It Came Upon A Midnight Clear. At the same time, something of RVW’s Antiphon or Bruckner’s Te Deum was never far from my mind, in terms of the orchestration. It may have become obvious to you that I am always thinking of other things to relate my music to. It is a problem I run into occasionally – am I being influenced, which is fine: music does not exist in a vacuum; or am I simply copying? Quoting things is fine, especially in such a long work as this (there are many quotes in Dorian, most of which I have not pointed out, but all of which make me irrationally, self-indulgently happy), but copying is not just plagiaristic but, personally, pointless – even if my original thought, at the inception of this opera, was that “I wish Britten had written a Dorian Gray.” Hopefully, my style has become distinct enough from just “a kid copying Britten”. Hopefully. Moving on, there is so much to point to in the final scene. Therefore, I will keep my comments limited to two particular moments. In this last scene, we see Dorian and Harry finally alone in Dorian’s living room. Dorian is by now incredibly stressed – Vane hunted him all the way to the Duchess’ estate, and, in trying to creep up on him, was shot by one of the Lords on their morning shoot – which Dorian took as a terribly ill omen. Returning to London, Harry has been keeping tabs on his young protégé, making sure the fear and stress doesn’t get to him. Therefore, he ups the levels of inane babble. The treatment of his final moment of inane babble is possibly one of my favourite bits of composition I’ve done to date. I say my composition, but actually, Harry’s last aria is founded entirely upon a piece by Alexander Scriabin, who, although I mention him very infrequently, is one of my favourite composers, if only for his absolutely insane theories about the end of the world (and attempts to bring said end about) and his pretence at having synaesthesia, which he tried to use to create a light-organ or ‘clavier à lumières’ with which to compose for the colour-spectrum―which is, I think you’ll agree, fairly bonkers. Nevertheless, I got it into my head to use this moment at the end of the piece to highlight musically a big change in Dorian: before we meet Dorian in the Prologue, we hear him from offstage, playing a snippet from Schumann’s Waldszenen, a very calm, nature-themed work for the piano – a piece of innocence, if you will. But now, at the end of the evening, many years later for the two remaining characters, Dorian returns to the piano to ignore Harry’s inanities, and plays Scriabin’s Nocturne for the left hand. This highlights a change in Dorian in several ways. Firstly, it is significantly more technically and harmonically challenging than the Schumann, in part because it is specifically for the left hand, but also because of Scriabin’s tense, dense harmonic language, which is significantly more discordant and much less innocent than Schumann’s. Moreover, Schumann published Waldszenen in 1849, whereas the Nocturne was composed in 1894; there is nearly half a century of musical development, pushing the boundaries of tonality and taste, between the two, indicative of the passage of time within the show, perhaps, and certainly indicative again of the corruption of Dorian’s innocence over that time. Finally, we come to the grand collapse that is the ending. I shan’t spoil the last few pages by discussing exactly how the show closes, because that would undoubtedly be a travesty. What I would like to discuss is the allegorical use of the story of Belshazzar in the closing moments. In my first plan of the end, I had refused the idea of an off-stage chorus as too ‘operatic’ for an intimate close to this show, much too close to the end of Don Giovanni or the countless other shows that copied that dramatic close, with the lecher dragged into hell by an immaterial chorus. However, one chat with Jamie transformed my conception entirely: I was not overly keen on my first draft’s ending, and he wrote some new words to close the show – they were splendid. In a tangent to Dorian’s flashback or his vision of Sybil, Jamie brought up an off-stage chorus, symbolic perhaps of Dorian’s frantic brain or of heavenly judgement (I’m inclined to think one particular way, but others may disagree), singing the “writing on the wall” that appeared at Belshazzar’s Feast: “Mene Mene Tekel Upharsin” or, as Jamie put it, “Thou art in the balances, and art found wanting.” Dorian, in his desperate bid to redeem himself after his years of immorality, cannot help but hear these words, directly paralleling the condemnation that is his own portrait hanging upon the wall. Thus, in composition, I had to avoid not just the links to Don Giovanni but also to Walton’s own Belshazzar’s Feast, again a favourite work of mine. Fortunately, context saved me here, as the chorus slowly makes itself known, crescendoing slowly to become just about audible on-stage, before making a final fortissimo statement and leaving Dorian to contemplate his fate – with little over a minute left of the opera.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Picture of Dorian Gray</title>
      <link href="/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Picture of Dorian Gray" />
      <published>2019-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray">&lt;p&gt;Several years ago, in quite another place, I began work upon the largest
compositional process I have ever undergone. I seemed to get it into my head as
I prepared to spend a year waving my hands at the poor, unfortunate singers of
St Mark’s Anglican Church, Florence, that I was far enough developed as a
composer that I could write for myself an opera. Not only that, but that I could
distil on my own one of the great works of Victorian literature, Oscar Wilde’s
&lt;em&gt;The Picture of Dorian Gray&lt;/em&gt; into a stage-show that would combine the sparkle of
&lt;em&gt;Die Fledermaus&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Figaro&lt;/em&gt; with the grim horror of one of Britten’s darker
dramas, &lt;em&gt;The Turn of the Screw&lt;/em&gt; or perhaps &lt;em&gt;Owen Wingrave&lt;/em&gt;. I was mistaken. It
took a chance encounter with one Jamie Fox, who had had similar ideas of taking
some time out in that magnificent Tuscan city, to turn my fantasy of an opera
into a more cohesive reality. Over several Negroni-fuelled evenings, and many
more ale-fuelled ones since our return to the UK, we translated Wilde’s
effervescent and yet shockingly terror-filled novella into a two-and-a-half act
show that now, slightly over three years later, has not only reached its
completion, but is, even as we speak, being prepared to be brandished before the
public by the wonderful people at &lt;em&gt;LoveOpera&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, no small part of me is turned towards retrospection: three years ago,
almost to the day of writing, I was asked by Jay Wolfe of &lt;em&gt;The Wolfian&lt;/em&gt; to write
a small article on the subject of setting about composing something of this
magnitude. I did my best – I had, at that point, only just finished &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt;’s
Prologue (the –and-a-half act) and had only vague ideas what the rest of the
opera had in store for me. Nevertheless, I now look back upon that article and
see that there is a compositional thread that stayed with me throughout the
process, even from the pre-Foxian beginnings. I knew then as I know now that
Wilde’s novella brought together the myriad elements of philosophy, dark humour,
and gothic horror. Musically, that meant each of these strands had to be
individually emphasised without any single one dominating the general effect of
the music. Of course, this was no easy task. But I did find a solution, if I can
really claim to have one. I studied closely how the likes of Henry Purcell,
Benjamin Britten, Claude Debussy, and Richard Wagner musically synthesised
various themes in their operas. I also made it a point to follow the man
himself: Oscar Wilde, taking note of how he balanced these themes to create such
a fine piece of art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that there is a fortunate divide between the Prologue of the work and the
two Acts. It is a divide that I touched on in my previous article: much of the
dialogue of the Prologue, taken from the first two chapters of Wilde’s work,
consists of Basil, the painter, philosophising with his friend Lord Henry, the
prime corruptive influence upon young Dorian before the boy actually arrives to
kick-start the drama. This leads to moments of the Prologue that feel somewhat
slower than the rest of the show, a turgid calm before a hopefully more driving
roller-coaster of a storm. And I believe this is as it should be, but I may well
be wrong – I shall have to see after I hear from the audiences in July and
September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as the previous article focussed so heavily upon the Prologue, on
account of the fact that neither of the other two acts actually yet existed, I
feel it may be much more suitable for us now to turn ourselves to a brief
musical guided tour, as it were, through at least some of the show. Therefore,
some introductions must be made:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt; has a main cast of six – it was quite a task to reduce down the large,
high-society focused drama into six characters, but what else is a chorus for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The characters are, in order of appearance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basil Hallward, (tenor) - the artist who holds Dorian as his muse,
unfortunately;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Henry “Harry” Wotton, (baritone) - a modern-day Mephistopheles with a
heart, somewhere deep down in there;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dorian himself, (mezzo-soprano) - I had this idea when watching Mozart’s
&lt;em&gt;Marriage of Figaro&lt;/em&gt; and realising Dorian and the teenage sex-pest Cherubino,
also a trouser-role, are not so very different if you gave the latter money and
immortality;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lady Victoria Wotton, (soprano) - aside from a few witty flashes in the novella,
Henry’s wife is reduced to acting off-screen, as it were. Jamie and I changed
that, as you will see;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sybil Vane, (soprano) – Poor Sybil. To fall in love with an as-yet not fully
corrupted Dorian, only to so quickly jilted after one bad night on the stage;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James Vane, (bass) – Sybil’s brother arrives in the 2nd Act, and will avenge his
sister… or, at least, he’ll try his utmost, raging best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behind these six there comes a host of minor characters that make up our show’s
chorus: the society lords and ladies, the audience of a run-down theatre, the
whores and opium fiends that make up the rich tapestry that is Victorian London
in Oscar’s (and our) minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so Act one begins, with Dorian, now in possession of Basil’s masterful
portrait of him, sitting alone in Lord Henry’s living-room, awaiting his friend.
It is here that I can illustrate the first influence of any of the composers
mentioned in my previous article: the act opens with a harp gesture (Fig. 1)
that is at once a textural back-cloth for the scene, and also acts as a
leitmotif, to borrow from Richard Wagner’s vocabulary. The theme, extended by
the strings and later the flute, can be said, therefore to be a genius loci – it
represents the building, musically, suggesting the luxurious, lavish
surroundings of the Wottons’ town-house. When, therefore, it reappears to
introduce use to Dorian’s own house, in both acts one and two, it possibly tells
us something about Dorian’s own following of Henry’s teachings – indeed, this
ability to manipulate melodies is an incredibly useful tool, compositionally, as
melodies are often indelibly linked with the emotion, location or character
alongside which they first appear. Thus, the twisting of a motif by introducing
it to a new context can suggest many things to an audience – watch out for it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/Dorian1.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 1&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we hear Henry’s own leitmotif, languorous triplets in the horns, except
this time it isn’t Henry, but his wife, whom neither we nor Dorian are expecting
to see. She has some interesting things to say on the subject of Wagner, too: “I
like Wagner’s music more than anyone’s. It is so loud that one can talk the
whole time without other people hearing what you say!” (I must say, I hope no
one uses &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt; to gossip under!) Nevertheless, as Victoria is here only for
some witty repartee and to avoid her husband at this point in the drama, when
Henry does finally show up she departs in short order – it’s not the healthiest
of relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry’s real entrance is accompanied by a different sort of music, though. He’s
a little drunk, and announces himself with a lop-sided little fanfare, before
launching in a duettino of banter with Dorian, which again manipulates his own
triplet motif into some fast-paced patter, as Dorian tells us that he has fallen
in rapturously love with an actress, “a rather commonplace debut” as Henry puts
it, named Sybil Vane. This confession leads to the first overtly romantic music
of the evening, as Dorian narrates how he came across his new sweetheart in a
sequence that is, structurally, a reflection of the early-Verdian style of
cantabile-cabaletta, but turned entirely on its head: in Verdi, or indeed,
Donizetti or Bellini, a cantabile-cabaletta consists of (as the name suggests) a
slow, more relaxed section that is very ‘sing-able’ followed by a more
barnstorming or pyrotechnic section. However, here Dorian sings them the wrong
way ‘round: first a fast, rhythmically twisting section (Fig. 2) describing her
beauty, and then two slower sections discussing first her acting ability and
then how lost he is in the romance of it all (Fig. 3), before the scene peters
out, and we transition to the next night, at the theatre&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/Dorian2.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/Dorian3.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 3&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, the theatre scene. This was a lot of fun to devise – I recall Jamie
gesticulating wildly as he explained to me that this was to be no great work of
Shakespearean spectacle, but a farcical experience, with a wooden, nervous
Juliet and a stout, middle-aged Romeo with a bit too much gut and far too much
Brian Blessed. And in the midst of it all sits Dorian, trying desperately to
convince Henry and Basil that Sybil is, in truth, a wonderful actress and well
worth his love. Therefore, I put my comedy hat on, and have tried to construct a
woeful imitation of Gilbert and Sullivan as an overture to this
play-within-a-play. There is no emotional core to this moment, no attempt to tug
at the heart-strings as one would expect from an overture to a performance of
&lt;em&gt;Romeo and Juliet&lt;/em&gt;. It’s just dross. As is the acting that follows it, but for
that I had to get more creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/Dorian4.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 4&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I set up a sense of scurrying tension within the on-stage audience by way
of a tiny fragment of melody that, when repeated over and over, becomes an
ostinato-texture which, much like the harp motif of Fig. 1, serves as a backdrop
for the entire scene. Over this, both our trio and the on-stage audience mutter
between each other until the curtain comes up and we see a sequence of three
scenes from the play, each successively worse: steadily, we progress from thin,
dull orchestration and bad singing, add in meandering, meaningless chromaticism
and unstable harmonies, and finally top it all off with some bombastic as the
crowd get steadily more unimpressed with the performance (Fig. 4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I write quite good ‘bad’ music, sometimes…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, Basil and Henry resolve to leave before the end of the show and
leave Dorian behind to talk to poor Sybil. Poor Sybil who is, in point of fact,
much more vivacious in real life than she ever was on stage, and so very much in
love with Dorian, as illustrated by her motif, which is itself an extension of
Dorian and the portrait’s own melody (Fig. 5, showing Dorian’s melody on top,
and Sybil’s extension below it), before flourishing into a much more lush
romantic gesture, and finally a re-hashing of one of Dorian’s own earlier
cantabile sections. She is so consumed by what could kindly be called her
infatuation or, worse, obsession with Dorian that she does not create her own
music, merely adopts his. And yet, in his refusal, Dorian himself mimics Henry’s
own more impassioned music from the Prologue; neither of them is, in truth, free
from obsessive thoughts about another person, or the ideals that they represent.
Unfortunately for Sybil, Dorian’s ideals lead him to abandon her, storm out,
have a wild night on the town before returning to his house, alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/Dorian5.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 5&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To cap the act off, Jamie and I had a bit of a predicament: the novella contains
a long time-skip before a certain climactic scene that we both wanted to include
as the finale of Act One. Whilst this reads incredibly well on paper – as the
years pass, Dorian becomes more and more corrupt until he goes beyond the pale –
this does not work near so well on a stage, where the audience is best served by
having a cohesive narrative, at least according to critics as far back as
Aristotle and the classical unities (of action, time and place). Thus, we
conflated several scenes from the book in order to make this finale to Act One
as impactful as can be. As Dorian recovers from his hangover, portrayed by slow,
chromatic triplet descents, his torpor is interrupted by the arrival of Basil,
who has bad news. This is the first change, as Wilde has Henry come to Dorian’s
house to deliver this particular news – that Sybil has committed suicide. Basil
is, therefore, able to finally act more overtly and lovingly towards his muse.
This also sets up a further conflation, as there are two scenes of Basil, in his
moralising fashion, trying to help Dorian. In the one, he asks to see the
portrait and is rebuffed, and on the other, many years later, Dorian crosses a
line. Basil is never seen again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we conflated these three scenes into one, I introduced, musically, one last
thing: the poor soprano playing Sybil would otherwise have only two scenes, and,
feeling sorry for her, I wrote her voice into the scene. Dorian, so affected by
the news of her death, can almost hear her calling out to him, turning a duet
into a trio, and having the final action of the scene, and indeed of the first
half of the Opera, become the deaths of two of &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt;’s principals (Game of
Thrones style). I don’t believe I know of another opera where both the tenor and
the soprano are killed before we make it half-way. That ought to make an impact
– and hopefully leave the audience as eager to see the conclusion of the drama
as you may well be to read the final instalment of this little-guided tour
through my opera!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Olly Bowes</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Several years ago, in quite another place, I began work upon the largest compositional process I have ever undergone. I seemed to get it into my head as I prepared to spend a year waving my hands at the poor, unfortunate singers of St Mark’s Anglican Church, Florence, that I was far enough developed as a composer that I could write for myself an opera. Not only that, but that I could distil on my own one of the great works of Victorian literature, Oscar Wilde’s The Picture of Dorian Gray into a stage-show that would combine the sparkle of Die Fledermaus or Figaro with the grim horror of one of Britten’s darker dramas, The Turn of the Screw or perhaps Owen Wingrave. I was mistaken. It took a chance encounter with one Jamie Fox, who had had similar ideas of taking some time out in that magnificent Tuscan city, to turn my fantasy of an opera into a more cohesive reality. Over several Negroni-fuelled evenings, and many more ale-fuelled ones since our return to the UK, we translated Wilde’s effervescent and yet shockingly terror-filled novella into a two-and-a-half act show that now, slightly over three years later, has not only reached its completion, but is, even as we speak, being prepared to be brandished before the public by the wonderful people at LoveOpera.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Cynical Circus</title>
      <link href="/A-Cynical-Circus" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Cynical Circus" />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Cynical-Circus</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Cynical-Circus">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Greatest Showman Betrays Barnum’s Legacy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Greatest Showman&lt;/em&gt; has swept across the cinematic landscape, garnering praise from almost every audience-member (young and old), whilst being generally panned by any critic going. Most were swift to point blame at the score, whose music, I agree, is largely an unchanging series of generic music-theatre-lite pop songs punctuated by a couple of ballads to swell the emotions, all backed by RnB-style beats to make it seem accessible for all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, while I don’t actually have too many issues with the score outside of its genericness (there are even a few that really caught my attention!), the idea of being ‘accessible for all’ pervades this show in an extremely insidious manner. It’s almost as if the composers Benj Pasek and Justin Paul (&lt;em&gt;James and the Giant Peach, Dear Evan Hansen&lt;/em&gt;) embraced the idea of making this score so generic to better reel in their paying audience—and there’s the rub with the entire film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right from the end of the opening song (“The Greatest Show” – one of the few that stands out as being genuinely individual as it introduces Barnum’s Circus in an eye- and ear-catching festival of light and sound), we are introduced to characters whose every purpose is to force the audience to either pity or love them – usually both. The boy, Barnum’s younger self, suffers abuse from all sides – his father shoves him about; his father’s rich client, unfortunately the father of the girl, Charity, slaps the lad out of hand. Charity and Barnum are ultimately left to explore their young love in secret in the most frustratingly clichéd and tedious songs of the film (“A Million Dreams”), wherein the pair grow up apart, writing letters as she (as per) goes off to finishing-school and he grows up on the streets, an American Oliver, eventually becoming respectable… somehow? The teenaged Barnum over-hears someone calling for people to work on the railway, and then suddenly we see middle-aged Hugh Jackman asking for Charity’s hand – and, shock-horror, the father is not pleased. But off they go anyway, declaring that “however big, however small / let me be a part of it all.” Adorable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so are their children, who are just too perfect: one ballet-dances and the other plays with her dollhouse – both agonisingly cute, setting off a quiet, childlike reprise of “A Million Dreams”. So, in a sequence that ought to be about family struggling against poverty, we miss every chance offered to have some angst over their inability to live the life Barnum wants to give them – which ought to be the driving factor for him to found the Circus in the first place! Instead, the writers, Jenny Bicks and Bill Condon (&lt;em&gt;Men in Trees, Chicago&lt;/em&gt;), allow the family to get by on being cute and seemingly glitter their way through poverty. Compared to &lt;em&gt;Oliver!&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;Fiddler&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;In The Heights&lt;/em&gt;, the struggle against poverty that ought to be central to the film is entirely lacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is worse, though, than the manipulation of the audience with cute children and a sob-story past, is the exploitation of the characters in Barnum’s Circus; not by Barnum himself, but by the writers. Barnum himself was fairly charitable towards his ‘freaks’, practicing ‘profitable philanthropy’ – making both himself and their-selves richer by dint of the public’s fascination with them. But every character we see in his Circus is not real. They are all, without fault, amalgams of several historical persons, simplified and made to seem less exploited by Barnum and more empowered. Charles, the dwarf, one of the few allowed to keep his own name, was not in his twenties when he joined Barnum. He was four – and within a year he was drinking and smoking to entertain the audience. Insidiously, the producers are making money by exploiting not just the ‘freaks’, but the age of #MeToo and of #blacklivesmatter, following the current trend of films that provide empowerment, without truly empowering the audience itself. They are mining the feel-good factor itself in a very obvious and distasteful manner through the generic score and through the freedom and empowerment that Barnum appears to offer his ‘freaks’ (even that term is taken and made empowering) And that is to say nothing of the ‘White Man’s Burden’ that goes unaddressed in this film; Hugh Jackman empowering all these people by showing them how they can make money off of other people’s macabre fascination with them? It struck me as a great white elephant in the room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we come to my pet-hate from this film? Oh, Ms Bicks, what did you do to Jenny Lind? You’ve destroyed her defining feature: her voice. In terms of singing, the Swedish Nightingale is reduced to a pop-music mezzo rather than a sparkling operatic soprano. Accent-wise, she is bizarrely British. And narratively? They construct an affair between Lind and Barnum to try and provoke some familial angst at a point in the story where there is already enough circus-based angst, and where we could have had some real familial angst as Barnum historically fell into debt again after Lind’s tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That all being said, there are positives: the performances are stellar. Hugh Jackman is masterful as Barnum. Zac Efron rises above a poorly-constructed amalgam role designed to give some class-tension, and is an excellent foil to Jackman. Paul Sparks as Bennett, the nasty newspaper critic, oddly provides a final moral to the piece that doesn’t feel false. Similarly, the choreography is amazing: “The Other Side” duet is mesmeric in its staging. The dancing in general is fantastic, especially during the Circus performances and in “A Million Dreams”. And the cinematography is broadly very good – a misstep with a CGI elephant notwithstanding. The use of colour I find particularly notable to separate the circus from the outside world, reminding one of Baz Luhrmann’s &lt;em&gt;Moulin Rouge&lt;/em&gt; in its carnival pomp. Ultimately, however, &lt;em&gt;The Greatest Showman&lt;/em&gt; is simply a well-made spectacle that looks good but feels terribly, terribly wrong.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Olly Bowes</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Greatest Showman Betrays Barnum’s Legacy</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
