<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/featured/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-11-24T19:00:30+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/featured/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Highs and Lows</title>
      <link href="/Highs-and-Lows" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Highs and Lows" />
      <published>2019-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Highs-and-Lows</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Highs-and-Lows">&lt;p&gt;What questions do I bring forth today? What mundane instances caught my eye and left me high and dry? What search brought on a flurry of more searches? Well, today’s going to be a little different. In the past few weeks, I’ve found a multitude of things that I want to talk, write and think about, and I shall, soon enough, but today, I’m switching my tandem just a tad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, life’s been more Rocky Road and less Blueberry Swirl. Submerged under a mountainous pile of assignments - some pending and most, already doomed - a couple of really strenuous friendships and a moderately significant heartbreak, the painting seemed all too grey. And while that’s my favourite colour, I don’t prefer it in shades of life. And hence, I did what most suggest you do in times of need: sit, reflect, meditate, or better yet, run away to the hills or the beaches. So, I chose the latter and ran away - to older hills, for a couple of days, met a couple of new people, stayed in a hostel - even strayed away from social media. Phew, right? But, why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, it was just procrastination with a beautiful view and some good food and wine. But that isn’t the case for most, is it? An &lt;em&gt;Eat, Pray, Love&lt;/em&gt; escape is not warranted for all. I overheard a fellow dorm-mate say he had earned enough money to buy a big house, but he didn’t want to share it with anyone, so he packed his bags and lo and behold- has been travelling for the last 2 years. His joy and reflection almost made me feel guilty. I didn’t have a good enough reason, nothing as inspirational, nothing with foreshadow per se. Mostly just running away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people travel to challenge themselves - to run amok places one shouldn’t be able to, to jump off of cliffs, to rage in the adrenaline. Some travel with a specific goal. The goal being to learn something: a new dialect, a new cuisine, a different culture or to develop a deeper appreciation for faith or spirituality. Some do it with others to build stronger relationships, to strengthen their bonds. &lt;em&gt;Virtuoso&lt;/em&gt;, a popular travel magazine, named ‘Multigenerational Travel’ as the top trend of 2018. One may even move around to find new people to create new friendships, new bonds. Traveling seems like a gift that keeps giving. It expands your perspective, as seen in several eudaimonic travel experience researches. It helps us appreciate our lives, a little more than usual. It also is the reason you can come home and excuse a picture of your room, on your Instagram, with a gif - home sweet home. On note of that, it also makes you InstaPopular (but that’d be very shallow of me to add, so excuse me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you may think why is this girl jabbering on and on about one trip and how travel is the boon of our existence? Truthfully? I am not so sure. All I had in my head when I started this off was why is it that people suggest traveling when one is sad, or not having the best time. I understand a change of view may bring a change of heart, or how looking at others’ challenges may bring in a better perspective for your own, or how just taking a break must feel amazing. Hell, there’s so much to see, why must there be a reason to feast your eyes? I’m only looking for this socialised understanding’s bare roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year millions of people leave all that they have, in order to see the world; some in joy, some out of worry, some because there’s no other option. If you’ve watched &lt;em&gt;Parts Unknown&lt;/em&gt;, I’m sure Bourdain made you feel all kinds of joy. I distinctly remember him saying in an episode shot in Tangier, Morocco: “I’ve always wanted to get as far away as possible from the place that I was born. Far both geographically and spiritually. To leave it behind.” While this might seem contrary to the inherent human desire to fit into a tribe, to have a close community, it does reflect a state of being less understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a thousand and one songs - all talking about how one wants to fly away, zoom into sunsets, never to be back - leave it all behind. And while, I’d say most people would love to open their hair, wear 90’s glasses, drive a Camaro along the LA coast, I’m not sure the romanticisation of going away is healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, no part of me can say that I didn’t have a good time. I understand and recognise my privilege at being able to plan a trip to a place and visit it all in about 24 hours. I feel lucky to have seen all that I did and experience all that I experienced. What expunges my certainty of how good all this is - how to let go of the nuisances in your life just by going to a scenic place? I can’t say that when I sat there, listening to a fellow person play the ukulele, sipping my blessed coffee, staring at snow-capped mountains - that I didn’t forget all there was to forget. Sure, I did. But, for how long? And honestly, if I were to forget it all anyway, wouldn’t that be worse? Pathway to repression? Not Disney perfect, albeit Disney recommended. Suppression, the conscious forcing of unwanted thoughts, memories, or feelings out of conscious awareness, more apropos than repression in this scenario, leads to bottling up of feelings and emotions and inability to deal with misgivings in the long run. If used in the right fashion, it may be beneficial, but everytime one is given the chance to run away instead of dealing with something, they miss out on learning. Not to mention, suppression requires that we focus our mind on a negative emotion. By suppressing a feeling of anger, we start worrying about feeling angry, which attaches us to the emotion and heats up our mind and costs us extra energy. A cycle that maybe never ending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I’m not saying don’t go around the world and explore, I implore that you don’t run away from something to look at these otherworldly scenes. I suggest that you deal with all the uglies at hand and then go around looking for beauty. To be what you really want to be, you need to accustom yourself to the steps underneath. Well, that’s all I got today. Thanks for coming to my TED Talk.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">What questions do I bring forth today? What mundane instances caught my eye and left me high and dry? What search brought on a flurry of more searches? Well, today’s going to be a little different. In the past few weeks, I’ve found a multitude of things that I want to talk, write and think about, and I shall, soon enough, but today, I’m switching my tandem just a tad.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What Even is Happening?</title>
      <link href="/What-Even-is-Happening" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Even is Happening?" />
      <published>2019-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-Even-is-Happening</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-Even-is-Happening">&lt;p&gt;Hello, I’m Harshita and I’m addicted to this phenomenon called ‘web surfing’,
which sounds like the closest adventure sport I could ever be into and oh well.
Today, I bring to you a new question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, perhaps not as new as I’d like it to be. About an hour or two ago, on a
podcast I heard a 15-year-old say and I quote, “… in previous eras, they had
wars with guns and gas, and in ours, we war with our own self.” To give you more
context, she reinstated what we all can see but perhaps are unable to
acknowledge- we’re all in an epidemic, one which is not as visible as we think
it to be- mental health issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With more than 10 million posts on Instagram with the hashtag ‘mental_health’
and about ten times more of blogs on Tumblr, it’d be wrong of me to say we don’t
talk about it enough. I know that we do, hell, we more than just talk about it.
And yet, it’s an epidemic with no foreseeable solution. I can sit here and go on
and on about how maybe we are more aware of these mental issues now because
people are more knowledgeable of the same, maybe because the stigma is being
fought against, perhaps, we just are more courageous than the ones who came
before us. What I can’t give up on are the words by my 15-year-old muse, is she
right in believing that just as every era is to go through one huge
debilitation, we’ve been destined to fall into the chasm of mental health chaos?
Would it be wrong of me to assume that there are more factors than just
awareness that are making us all a little more troubled than ever?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t give you a solid number for the amount of times I’ve said ‘Same!’
when someone around me said, ‘I can’t live this life no more’ or, ‘Ugh! I’m so
depressed’ or something akin to it. I know I’ve uttered the words ‘I want to
die’ on multiple accounts, once because I couldn’t bear the heat. Albeit the
fact that I know it’s asinine to have claimed the same, it is difficult not to
do the same. I could tell you it’s because it’s ingrained, because I’ve been
conditioned and been rewarded quite positively or, perhaps, because everyone
around me does it and if Bandura had anything to say for it, he’d agree. All
around us- in the spaces we most frequent, there’s a strong prevalence of (and I
say this off of my personal disposition) romanticisation of mental illness.
Somehow our move to ‘delete the stigma’ has drastically changed towards a trend
to ‘romanticise the stigma’. While it’s not something that one should be ashamed
of, it also isn’t something one should aspire for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it that on Tumblr, #Thinspo is always trending, why is it that not
sleeping and being perpetually tired has become a way of popular culture? How
did self-inflicted scars come to be called art? When did the ‘Sad Girls Club’
become the new ideal, often propagated by the VSCO girls or the new e-girls?
What about #proana? I remember reading &lt;em&gt;Looking for Alaska&lt;/em&gt; and being astounded
by how easily the teenage girl said, and oh, ‘with delight of a kid on a
Christmas morning’- “Y’all smoke to enjoy it. I smoke to die.” If you’ve ever
gone down the Instagram explore page, you’ve definitely been acquainted with Sir
R.M. Drake and his well-fonted, honey-coloured quotes such as that of, ‘We
desire to keep the pain close, close enough to destroy us.’  Upon learning more,
I found out about how a popular jewellery brand conceived a new line of
necklaces with the words- ‘depression’, ‘anxiety’ and ‘bipolar’ inscribed on
them. Twitter has multiple accounts such as that of &lt;em&gt;So Sad Today&lt;/em&gt;. I guess what
I’m trying to allude to is- The Sad Online Culture. You can’t tell me you’ve
never seen a post where someone is staring into the distance, the picture tuned
to darker shades, and a caption with something negative/sad. There is a new
culture of equalling beauty to tragedy. Pain, melancholy are seen as artsy. It’s
not to say I don’t like my fair share of Lana Del Rey or I don’t appreciate all
the API trimmed sappy content Instagram throws at me. In fact, if you’ve got
time- you really ought to check out this feminist philosophy called &lt;a href=&quot;https://believermag.com/in-conversation-with-mira-gonzalez/&quot;&gt;Sad Girl
Theory&lt;/a&gt;, penned by
artist Audrey Wollen, who, by the way, goes by ’&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/audreywollen/?hl=en&quot;&gt;Tragic
Queen&lt;/a&gt;‘ on Instagram. There’s the
complicated concept of creativity and mental illness, but that requires a long,
let’s get cookies and milk/wine (whatever’s your poison), sit down. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Withstanding all that I’ve mentioned above, I’m still well aware of how social
media has allowed mental health issues to become more widely known and accepted,
how they have allowed us all to share personal stories and accounts of many a
psychological disorder. They’re often seen as support systems to encourage and
inform others of one’s own personal experiences and yet, it also comprises an
entire added bonus of trivialising these disorders. Sites that allow anonymous
posting end up becoming group therapy sessions with no therapist to take charge
of the situation. This is where one may find people suffering the same way that
they are but it is highly likely that instead of improving their situation, it
ends up becoming a constant, painful cycle of reinforcement. All of this leads
to people expressing their emotions and hardships which end up looking like an
effort to romanticise the ordeals. It is noteworthy, however, to know that one
might just be unaware that one is romanticising something. People feel that they
are merely sharing their thoughts and feelings. For the vulnerable mind, these
online spaces become communities that seemingly provide the ideal solution:
support, understanding, acceptance. To be accepted by this community, it is
almost as if one has to advertise one’s suffering. Thus, subconsciously a choice
is made- to suffer, to fit in and get acceptance. “Adaptability is what makes us
both wonderful and terrible. We can easily forget what’s healthy- can adapt to
really unhealthy environments quickly. And it so often feels somehow right even
when it’s not,” said Whitlock. This is not a ‘you’ or ‘me’ situation, this is a
complete trajectory of a ‘we’ situation. More often than not, we invest in this
world, consciously or not- and help it prosper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might have made a lot of foes for saying all that I have, but once in a while,
one’s bound to have a curious case of ‘What even is happening?’ I don’t come
here with ways to live one’s life, I only come here with questions.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Hello, I’m Harshita and I’m addicted to this phenomenon called ‘web surfing’, which sounds like the closest adventure sport I could ever be into and oh well. Today, I bring to you a new question. Okay, perhaps not as new as I’d like it to be. About an hour or two ago, on a podcast I heard a 15-year-old say and I quote, “… in previous eras, they had wars with guns and gas, and in ours, we war with our own self.” To give you more context, she reinstated what we all can see but perhaps are unable to acknowledge- we’re all in an epidemic, one which is not as visible as we think it to be- mental health issues. With more than 10 million posts on Instagram with the hashtag ‘mental_health’ and about ten times more of blogs on Tumblr, it’d be wrong of me to say we don’t talk about it enough. I know that we do, hell, we more than just talk about it. And yet, it’s an epidemic with no foreseeable solution. I can sit here and go on and on about how maybe we are more aware of these mental issues now because people are more knowledgeable of the same, maybe because the stigma is being fought against, perhaps, we just are more courageous than the ones who came before us. What I can’t give up on are the words by my 15-year-old muse, is she right in believing that just as every era is to go through one huge debilitation, we’ve been destined to fall into the chasm of mental health chaos? Would it be wrong of me to assume that there are more factors than just awareness that are making us all a little more troubled than ever? I couldn’t give you a solid number for the amount of times I’ve said ‘Same!’ when someone around me said, ‘I can’t live this life no more’ or, ‘Ugh! I’m so depressed’ or something akin to it. I know I’ve uttered the words ‘I want to die’ on multiple accounts, once because I couldn’t bear the heat. Albeit the fact that I know it’s asinine to have claimed the same, it is difficult not to do the same. I could tell you it’s because it’s ingrained, because I’ve been conditioned and been rewarded quite positively or, perhaps, because everyone around me does it and if Bandura had anything to say for it, he’d agree. All around us- in the spaces we most frequent, there’s a strong prevalence of (and I say this off of my personal disposition) romanticisation of mental illness. Somehow our move to ‘delete the stigma’ has drastically changed towards a trend to ‘romanticise the stigma’. While it’s not something that one should be ashamed of, it also isn’t something one should aspire for. Why is it that on Tumblr, #Thinspo is always trending, why is it that not sleeping and being perpetually tired has become a way of popular culture? How did self-inflicted scars come to be called art? When did the ‘Sad Girls Club’ become the new ideal, often propagated by the VSCO girls or the new e-girls? What about #proana? I remember reading Looking for Alaska and being astounded by how easily the teenage girl said, and oh, ‘with delight of a kid on a Christmas morning’- “Y’all smoke to enjoy it. I smoke to die.” If you’ve ever gone down the Instagram explore page, you’ve definitely been acquainted with Sir R.M. Drake and his well-fonted, honey-coloured quotes such as that of, ‘We desire to keep the pain close, close enough to destroy us.’  Upon learning more, I found out about how a popular jewellery brand conceived a new line of necklaces with the words- ‘depression’, ‘anxiety’ and ‘bipolar’ inscribed on them. Twitter has multiple accounts such as that of So Sad Today. I guess what I’m trying to allude to is- The Sad Online Culture. You can’t tell me you’ve never seen a post where someone is staring into the distance, the picture tuned to darker shades, and a caption with something negative/sad. There is a new culture of equalling beauty to tragedy. Pain, melancholy are seen as artsy. It’s not to say I don’t like my fair share of Lana Del Rey or I don’t appreciate all the API trimmed sappy content Instagram throws at me. In fact, if you’ve got time- you really ought to check out this feminist philosophy called Sad Girl Theory, penned by artist Audrey Wollen, who, by the way, goes by ’Tragic Queen‘ on Instagram. There’s the complicated concept of creativity and mental illness, but that requires a long, let’s get cookies and milk/wine (whatever’s your poison), sit down.  Withstanding all that I’ve mentioned above, I’m still well aware of how social media has allowed mental health issues to become more widely known and accepted, how they have allowed us all to share personal stories and accounts of many a psychological disorder. They’re often seen as support systems to encourage and inform others of one’s own personal experiences and yet, it also comprises an entire added bonus of trivialising these disorders. Sites that allow anonymous posting end up becoming group therapy sessions with no therapist to take charge of the situation. This is where one may find people suffering the same way that they are but it is highly likely that instead of improving their situation, it ends up becoming a constant, painful cycle of reinforcement. All of this leads to people expressing their emotions and hardships which end up looking like an effort to romanticise the ordeals. It is noteworthy, however, to know that one might just be unaware that one is romanticising something. People feel that they are merely sharing their thoughts and feelings. For the vulnerable mind, these online spaces become communities that seemingly provide the ideal solution: support, understanding, acceptance. To be accepted by this community, it is almost as if one has to advertise one’s suffering. Thus, subconsciously a choice is made- to suffer, to fit in and get acceptance. “Adaptability is what makes us both wonderful and terrible. We can easily forget what’s healthy- can adapt to really unhealthy environments quickly. And it so often feels somehow right even when it’s not,” said Whitlock. This is not a ‘you’ or ‘me’ situation, this is a complete trajectory of a ‘we’ situation. More often than not, we invest in this world, consciously or not- and help it prosper. I might have made a lot of foes for saying all that I have, but once in a while, one’s bound to have a curious case of ‘What even is happening?’ I don’t come here with ways to live one’s life, I only come here with questions.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Test</title>
      <link href="/test" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Test" />
      <published>2018-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2018-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/test</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/test">&lt;p&gt;This is test page&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kheeran Naidu</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="test" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This is test page</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Caption Image</title>
      <link href="/photo-caption" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Caption Image" />
      <published>2018-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2018-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/photo-caption</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/photo-caption">&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Mario-Draghi.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display:inline; text-align: left; width:40%&quot; /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//&quot; style=&quot;display:inline; margin-left:10%; text-align: left; width:40%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Mario-Draghi.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; Italy &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; La Sapienza University, Massachusetts Institute of Technology&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kheeran Naidu</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="test" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">&amp;lt;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
