<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/featured/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-06-23T22:13:13+01:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/featured/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A 23 on The Test</title>
      <link href="/A-23-on-The-Test" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A 23 on The Test" />
      <published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/A-23-on-The-Test</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-23-on-The-Test">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It is not often that one gets to do what one enjoys the most, and I do. I get to announce to the world my life and web history. Unfortunately, the latter is almost always more exciting than the former and that is completely on me.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As an emotionally stunted child who wore the ugliest orange-brown clothes, I wondered which vehicle would zoom me out of my very own, personally customised hell. Turns out, it all begins with writing the lyrics of &lt;em&gt;Turning Page&lt;/em&gt; (from &lt;em&gt;Twilight&lt;/em&gt;, duh) in a yellow, Winnie-the-Pooh diary. That and more, enveloped between multiple pages about overbearing mothers and underwhelming crushes can pave you the perfect path. My road to this pleasured life - wherein one learns to write like a jilted lover who married Freud’s second cousin, while may not have been easy, but it surely has been interesting to talk about. I may think I am all snark and sass, but underneath it all, I believe I am just an underdeveloped adult (read: kid) who barely has any control over herself and her relationships. Seldom have I ever given thought to who I would be if not me (not that I know who I am to begin with). A narcissistic go-getter? A quiet soul that fills everyone around them with peace? A bubbly know-it-all? Who!? Hold up, what if I am all of these or worse, none of them? What if I am just an unseasoned cardboard? Ah, the suspense.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Narcissism, come to think of it, is a word quite widely used and abused. Have you not called your ex one when he forgot your birthday? Or when your best friend buys that pair of jeans you had chosen for yourself? Often, the term is shrouded with the veil of self-love, and is even explained as vanity. But to be able to completely comprehend what it means, maybe we ought to step into the shoes of a narcissist. But first, should we test ourselves? How narcissistic are we? I have managed to find us all a risqué, not-all-that-legit &lt;a href=&quot;https://openpsychometrics.org/tests/NPI/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;test&lt;/a&gt;. If you tell me your scores, I will tell you mine (wink, wink), and then we can open a club!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The word ‘narcissism’ commonly describes someone who is excessively self-absorbed, selfish and egotistical, self-enhancing, arrogant, and shameless; but it is also used to explain individuals who are headstrong and may as well be used in a positive connotation. You see, before the Pandemic of Foreverland, they trended the idea of ‘Narcissism Epidemic’. It was based on the foundation of the ‘ME! ME! ME!’ life that many of us (us being Millennials and Gen Z) are leading. The social media influencers amidst us, have both literally and figuratively made a living out of just talking about and being concerned about oneself. From ‘OOTDs’ to ‘My Skincare Routine’- we’ve all been witnesses to the magic. I will watch Zendaya, or Harry Styles put on sunscreen any day, any time, no questions asked. And that may just be me with a keen level of fascination - but to each of them, the artists, they have to live with the idea of being famous for being ‘them’. This ‘Me’ culture quite vividly personifies the definition of Narcissism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This is not to say - any and every celebrity is a narcissist, just the ones who do not care about anyone else but them, such as Trump- (Melania, of course. Since the other Trump is irrelevant). It has been found that narcissistic traits afflict almost 10% of people in their 20s, compared to the 3% of people in their 60s, suggesting that as we grow older, our personalities are more settled and well-formed. I must say, this proves me right about how babies are just cute li’l narcissistic tiny-humans. All they care about is their milk and toys, the ‘me’ time never ends for them (oh the absolute joy!). I wonder if my suggestion of being a narcissist is also narcissistic. I wonder if we have made it so that anything but downgrading oneself beyond humility is how you prove you are not a narcissist. I wonder if only at the DSM’s criteria can we lay down the damage of narcissism and anything else is just immaculate fake news. The personality disorder of Narcissism is not something I’ve delved into, maybe due to the inconsistencies it may bring to our lives (self-fulfilling prophecy is real, people) or perhaps because no collection of symptoms is worth the trauma of self-diagnosis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Authority, self-sufficiency - a belief that one has achieved everything on their own, superiority, exhibitionism, exploitative-ness, vanity, and entitlement: these are the factoids used by the aforementioned risqué test, all quite all-encompassing, all traits of serial killers and great actors. All not all that bad sounding. Hitherto, the true problem that underlies narcissistic traits is not that they are problematic but that they are unrealistic. However much one is to believe otherwise, the belief in one’s own extraordinariness will sooner or later come to an end. Disillusionment is at bay. Now, one may choose to cross the bay, or stay stagnant and enjoy life while giving others’ plight - it's obviously a fair choice.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;You see, with a topic such as this, I can go on and on - hell, who am I kidding, I can go on and on about the most mundane of things - but today is special. I type all this knowing I might not get to do this again for some time now. Each time that I have penned down my thoughts, I have thought about how maybe it's just me and my editor who get a good chuckle out of these. Each time I tell myself my editor probably does not chuckle at all. Each time I am glad for the opportunity, upset about my own expectations and ecstatic over having been able to transfer my head-junk on paper. Narcissistic or not, I’m glad to be here.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Disclaimer- I did score a 23 on the test, and if you did, too- please let’s form a Club! We can name it “Harshita’s”.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="featured" />
      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is not often that one gets to do what one enjoys the most, and I do. I get to announce to the world my life and web history. Unfortunately, the latter is almost always more exciting than the former and that is completely on me.&amp;nbsp; As an emotionally stunted child who wore the ugliest orange-brown clothes, I wondered which vehicle would zoom me out of my very own, personally customised hell. Turns out, it all begins with writing the lyrics of Turning Page (from Twilight, duh) in a yellow, Winnie-the-Pooh diary. That and more, enveloped between multiple pages about overbearing mothers and underwhelming crushes can pave you the perfect path. My road to this pleasured life - wherein one learns to write like a jilted lover who married Freud’s second cousin, while may not have been easy, but it surely has been interesting to talk about. I may think I am all snark and sass, but underneath it all, I believe I am just an underdeveloped adult (read: kid) who barely has any control over herself and her relationships. Seldom have I ever given thought to who I would be if not me (not that I know who I am to begin with). A narcissistic go-getter? A quiet soul that fills everyone around them with peace? A bubbly know-it-all? Who!? Hold up, what if I am all of these or worse, none of them? What if I am just an unseasoned cardboard? Ah, the suspense.&amp;nbsp; Narcissism, come to think of it, is a word quite widely used and abused. Have you not called your ex one when he forgot your birthday? Or when your best friend buys that pair of jeans you had chosen for yourself? Often, the term is shrouded with the veil of self-love, and is even explained as vanity. But to be able to completely comprehend what it means, maybe we ought to step into the shoes of a narcissist. But first, should we test ourselves? How narcissistic are we? I have managed to find us all a risqué, not-all-that-legit test. If you tell me your scores, I will tell you mine (wink, wink), and then we can open a club! The word ‘narcissism’ commonly describes someone who is excessively self-absorbed, selfish and egotistical, self-enhancing, arrogant, and shameless; but it is also used to explain individuals who are headstrong and may as well be used in a positive connotation. You see, before the Pandemic of Foreverland, they trended the idea of ‘Narcissism Epidemic’. It was based on the foundation of the ‘ME! ME! ME!’ life that many of us (us being Millennials and Gen Z) are leading. The social media influencers amidst us, have both literally and figuratively made a living out of just talking about and being concerned about oneself. From ‘OOTDs’ to ‘My Skincare Routine’- we’ve all been witnesses to the magic. I will watch Zendaya, or Harry Styles put on sunscreen any day, any time, no questions asked. And that may just be me with a keen level of fascination - but to each of them, the artists, they have to live with the idea of being famous for being ‘them’. This ‘Me’ culture quite vividly personifies the definition of Narcissism.&amp;nbsp; This is not to say - any and every celebrity is a narcissist, just the ones who do not care about anyone else but them, such as Trump- (Melania, of course. Since the other Trump is irrelevant). It has been found that narcissistic traits afflict almost 10% of people in their 20s, compared to the 3% of people in their 60s, suggesting that as we grow older, our personalities are more settled and well-formed. I must say, this proves me right about how babies are just cute li’l narcissistic tiny-humans. All they care about is their milk and toys, the ‘me’ time never ends for them (oh the absolute joy!). I wonder if my suggestion of being a narcissist is also narcissistic. I wonder if we have made it so that anything but downgrading oneself beyond humility is how you prove you are not a narcissist. I wonder if only at the DSM’s criteria can we lay down the damage of narcissism and anything else is just immaculate fake news. The personality disorder of Narcissism is not something I’ve delved into, maybe due to the inconsistencies it may bring to our lives (self-fulfilling prophecy is real, people) or perhaps because no collection of symptoms is worth the trauma of self-diagnosis.&amp;nbsp; Authority, self-sufficiency - a belief that one has achieved everything on their own, superiority, exhibitionism, exploitative-ness, vanity, and entitlement: these are the factoids used by the aforementioned risqué test, all quite all-encompassing, all traits of serial killers and great actors. All not all that bad sounding. Hitherto, the true problem that underlies narcissistic traits is not that they are problematic but that they are unrealistic. However much one is to believe otherwise, the belief in one’s own extraordinariness will sooner or later come to an end. Disillusionment is at bay. Now, one may choose to cross the bay, or stay stagnant and enjoy life while giving others’ plight - it's obviously a fair choice.&amp;nbsp; You see, with a topic such as this, I can go on and on - hell, who am I kidding, I can go on and on about the most mundane of things - but today is special. I type all this knowing I might not get to do this again for some time now. Each time that I have penned down my thoughts, I have thought about how maybe it's just me and my editor who get a good chuckle out of these. Each time I tell myself my editor probably does not chuckle at all. Each time I am glad for the opportunity, upset about my own expectations and ecstatic over having been able to transfer my head-junk on paper. Narcissistic or not, I’m glad to be here.&amp;nbsp; Disclaimer- I did score a 23 on the test, and if you did, too- please let’s form a Club! We can name it “Harshita’s”.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Specter of Blood Cotton</title>
      <link href="/The-Specter-of-Blood-Cotton" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Specter of Blood Cotton" />
      <published>2021-04-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-04-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Specter-of-Blood-Cotton</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Specter-of-Blood-Cotton">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-center&quot;&gt;&quot;Being an Uyghur is a Crime&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li class=&quot;ql-align-right&quot;&gt;Mihrigal Tursun&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-right&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;(detained at an Uyghur camp for the third time in 2015)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Mid-March witnessed an unprecedented boycott of a number of western brands including H&amp;amp;M and Nike all over China. This can be best described as cotton-sourcing juxtaposed against political gamesmanship. The incident traces its origins to the Xinjiang region of China, infamous for systematic allegations of exploiting forced Uyghur labour and dubbed as the tip of the iceberg concealing a larger problem of forced detention and China’s severe ill-treatment of its minorities. However, this recent upsurge has great economic and political ramifications in the supply chains of multinational fashion retailers such as Adidas, Lacoste, H&amp;amp;M, Ralph Lauren and Tommy Hilfiger.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In January 2016, the Trump administration had banned all cotton imports from Xinjiang as well as consumer items manufactured in the area. The administration reiterated the US stance of declaring the existence of genocide in the Xinjiang region. This was a significant shift as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.workersrights.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Workers Rights Consortium&lt;/a&gt; estimated that the material imported from Xinjiang was used in the manufacture of 1.5 billion garments that were manufactured by American brands and retailers. The question arises as to why the issue has gained the spotlight in March 2021 when it has long been a publicly contested subject in the international arena.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Many observers have attributed this to the widening of political differences between China and the Western Nations in the aftermath of the pandemic. The tensions further escalated on March 22 when Britain, Canada and the European Union imposed sanction on China for its abominable treatment towards the Uyghurs. Soon there was a circulation of September 2020 screenshots of an H&amp;amp;M statement that cited &quot;deep concerns&quot; regarding forced labour in Xinjiang along with the confirmation that the organisation had stopped buying cotton from Xinjiang cultivators. China denied all such claims and in retaliation, the products of the protesting brands were removed from China’s e-commerce platforms including&amp;nbsp; JD.COM&amp;nbsp; and Alibaba Group’s Tmall.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Not all brands chose to raise their voice. Hugo Boss, the German brand being a notable dissenter posting on its website: &quot;We will continue to purchase and support Xinjiang cotton.&quot; However, later they claimed it to be unauthorized and it was deleted.&amp;nbsp; The foreign brands have repeatedly faced challenges regarding selling off their products to the 1.4 billion strong Chinese customer base and simultaneously adhering to the global customer’s demand for adherence to certain ethical norms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The exploitation of the Uyghur minority however demands a greater exposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Dehumanization of the Uyghur Community&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In its 2020 report, the &lt;em&gt;BBC&lt;/em&gt; had revealed that China is forcing hundreds and thousands of Uyghurs into manual labour in the cotton fields at Xinjiang, which produces a fifth of the world’s cotton. The Uyghurs are a Muslim minority that ethnically and culturally identify with Central Asian communities. They even speak in a language similar to that of Turkish. They have been detained in camps and allegedly subjected to torture, forced labour, sexual, psychological abuse, and forced sterilisation attempts. China has veiled such atrocities under the garb of such camps being ‘re-education’ sites aimed at salvaging the Uyghurs out of poverty.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The mass migration of the Han Chinese (ethnic majority) to the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region (XUAR) has birthed a threat perception among the Uyghurs that their culture and livelihood are under threat by the ethnic majority. The crackdown upon this community can be traced to the Anti-Han and separatist movements that arose in the 1990's, spiralling into violence in 2009 when 200 people were killed in clashes at Xinjiang. The Chinese state laid the blame on the Uyghurs’ demand for a separate state. Since 2015, a million Uyghurs have been detained in camps in complete adherence to Xi Jinping’s goal of national ideology.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The justifications have been based on the ground of threats of extremism directed at Chinese national integration and unity. The Chinese government maintains its actions are justified by citing the extremist and terrorist activities linked to the Uyghurs in the Baren Township riot, 1997 Urumqi bus bombings, 2014 Urumqi attack, 2011 Holtan attacks and the 2015 Aksu colliery attack, among others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The China Cables, a collection of secret government documents leaked by Uyghurs in exile, had earlier revealed that the detention camps were run as high-security prisons marked by the autocratic disciplining of Uyghurs. A report by the China scholar Adrian Zenz revealed that Uyghur women who had more children than the legally permitted number were forced to receive intrauterine devices and injected with syringes that stopped their menstrual cycle, resulting in a massive decline of the population growth, with growth rates falling by 84% in the two largest Uyghur districts between 2015 and 2018.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Gang rapes, sexual torture, forcible co-habitation of Uyghur homes by government workers are common under the ‘Pair up and Become a Family’ policy with the aim of promoting ‘ethnic unity’. The extensive use of surveillance technology includes intelligent monitoring systems, police checkpoints and drones, and the Ministry of Public Security has invested in the Skynet and Sharp Eyes Project for video camera facial recognition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;When President Xi Jinping declared that all practising religions in China should be Chinese in orientation, the crackdowns rose to unprecedented scales, resulting in the complete eradication of Uyghur culture. Wearing headscarves, veils and other Islamic dress in the region is completely forbidden which led to a 2014 protest in Alakaga, Xinjiang, when 25 women were detained for wearing headscarves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The attack on Islamic religion is evidenced by the systematic destruction of mosques, Muslim shrines and cemeteries, with &lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt; stating that over one-third of the mosques and religious sites in China suffered ‘significant structural damage’. There has been a complete breakdown of fundamental rights such as freedom of speech and expression, with the Uyghur economist Ilham Tohti being sentenced to life imprisonment in 2014, and the disappearance of Rahile Dawut, an Uyghur anthropologist. The cultural assimilation and integration of the Uyghurs is encouraged by promoting marriages between the Uyghurs and the Han Chinese through schemes such as the ‘Incentive Measures Encouraging Uighur-Chinese Intermarriage’ scheme which includes a cash reward of $1,450 per annum for the first five years of marriage.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The International Reaction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;22 countries have sent a joint letter to the United Nations Human Rights Council (UNHRC) condemning the mass detention of Uyghurs. The European Union had in March 2021 sanctioned Zhu Hailun, the proponent of the indoctrination program. The United States Customs and Border Protection had issued five Withhold Release Orders (WRO) on products produced by state-sponsored forced labour such as hair products made in the industrial park at Xinjiang and cotton produced by the Yili Zhouwan Garment Manufacturing Company and Baoding LYSZD Trade and Business Company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It has to be noted that Pakistani Prime Minister Imran Khan, a vocal critic of Islamophobia has maintained silence on Uyghur persecution, stating that he didn’t &quot;know much about&quot; the scale of Uyghur mistreatment and stating that China had helped them when &quot;they were at the rock bottom&quot;. The 57 country Organization of Islamic Cooperation (OIC) has, however, mentioned &quot;disturbing reports&quot; of China’s crackdown on Muslims, but has backtracked on its publication.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The process of Sinicization is perhaps best amplified in the words: &quot;You people are not Turks. Uighurs are Chinese. You are one of us, Chinese&quot; as recalled by Mohammed, an Uyghur from Southern Xinjiang, who had been detained for seven months in June 2018, held in a camp with his hands chained together in a room with 35 others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The tale of Blood Cotton haunts the collective conscience of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="featured" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">&quot;Being an Uyghur is a Crime&quot; Mihrigal Tursun&amp;nbsp; (detained at an Uyghur camp for the third time in 2015) Mid-March witnessed an unprecedented boycott of a number of western brands including H&amp;amp;M and Nike all over China. This can be best described as cotton-sourcing juxtaposed against political gamesmanship. The incident traces its origins to the Xinjiang region of China, infamous for systematic allegations of exploiting forced Uyghur labour and dubbed as the tip of the iceberg concealing a larger problem of forced detention and China’s severe ill-treatment of its minorities. However, this recent upsurge has great economic and political ramifications in the supply chains of multinational fashion retailers such as Adidas, Lacoste, H&amp;amp;M, Ralph Lauren and Tommy Hilfiger.&amp;nbsp; In January 2016, the Trump administration had banned all cotton imports from Xinjiang as well as consumer items manufactured in the area. The administration reiterated the US stance of declaring the existence of genocide in the Xinjiang region. This was a significant shift as the Workers Rights Consortium estimated that the material imported from Xinjiang was used in the manufacture of 1.5 billion garments that were manufactured by American brands and retailers. The question arises as to why the issue has gained the spotlight in March 2021 when it has long been a publicly contested subject in the international arena.&amp;nbsp; Many observers have attributed this to the widening of political differences between China and the Western Nations in the aftermath of the pandemic. The tensions further escalated on March 22 when Britain, Canada and the European Union imposed sanction on China for its abominable treatment towards the Uyghurs. Soon there was a circulation of September 2020 screenshots of an H&amp;amp;M statement that cited &quot;deep concerns&quot; regarding forced labour in Xinjiang along with the confirmation that the organisation had stopped buying cotton from Xinjiang cultivators. China denied all such claims and in retaliation, the products of the protesting brands were removed from China’s e-commerce platforms including&amp;nbsp; JD.COM&amp;nbsp; and Alibaba Group’s Tmall.&amp;nbsp; Not all brands chose to raise their voice. Hugo Boss, the German brand being a notable dissenter posting on its website: &quot;We will continue to purchase and support Xinjiang cotton.&quot; However, later they claimed it to be unauthorized and it was deleted.&amp;nbsp; The foreign brands have repeatedly faced challenges regarding selling off their products to the 1.4 billion strong Chinese customer base and simultaneously adhering to the global customer’s demand for adherence to certain ethical norms. The exploitation of the Uyghur minority however demands a greater exposition. The Dehumanization of the Uyghur Community In its 2020 report, the BBC had revealed that China is forcing hundreds and thousands of Uyghurs into manual labour in the cotton fields at Xinjiang, which produces a fifth of the world’s cotton. The Uyghurs are a Muslim minority that ethnically and culturally identify with Central Asian communities. They even speak in a language similar to that of Turkish. They have been detained in camps and allegedly subjected to torture, forced labour, sexual, psychological abuse, and forced sterilisation attempts. China has veiled such atrocities under the garb of such camps being ‘re-education’ sites aimed at salvaging the Uyghurs out of poverty.&amp;nbsp; The mass migration of the Han Chinese (ethnic majority) to the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region (XUAR) has birthed a threat perception among the Uyghurs that their culture and livelihood are under threat by the ethnic majority. The crackdown upon this community can be traced to the Anti-Han and separatist movements that arose in the 1990's, spiralling into violence in 2009 when 200 people were killed in clashes at Xinjiang. The Chinese state laid the blame on the Uyghurs’ demand for a separate state. Since 2015, a million Uyghurs have been detained in camps in complete adherence to Xi Jinping’s goal of national ideology.&amp;nbsp; The justifications have been based on the ground of threats of extremism directed at Chinese national integration and unity. The Chinese government maintains its actions are justified by citing the extremist and terrorist activities linked to the Uyghurs in the Baren Township riot, 1997 Urumqi bus bombings, 2014 Urumqi attack, 2011 Holtan attacks and the 2015 Aksu colliery attack, among others. The China Cables, a collection of secret government documents leaked by Uyghurs in exile, had earlier revealed that the detention camps were run as high-security prisons marked by the autocratic disciplining of Uyghurs. A report by the China scholar Adrian Zenz revealed that Uyghur women who had more children than the legally permitted number were forced to receive intrauterine devices and injected with syringes that stopped their menstrual cycle, resulting in a massive decline of the population growth, with growth rates falling by 84% in the two largest Uyghur districts between 2015 and 2018.&amp;nbsp; Gang rapes, sexual torture, forcible co-habitation of Uyghur homes by government workers are common under the ‘Pair up and Become a Family’ policy with the aim of promoting ‘ethnic unity’. The extensive use of surveillance technology includes intelligent monitoring systems, police checkpoints and drones, and the Ministry of Public Security has invested in the Skynet and Sharp Eyes Project for video camera facial recognition. When President Xi Jinping declared that all practising religions in China should be Chinese in orientation, the crackdowns rose to unprecedented scales, resulting in the complete eradication of Uyghur culture. Wearing headscarves, veils and other Islamic dress in the region is completely forbidden which led to a 2014 protest in Alakaga, Xinjiang, when 25 women were detained for wearing headscarves. The attack on Islamic religion is evidenced by the systematic destruction of mosques, Muslim shrines and cemeteries, with The Guardian stating that over one-third of the mosques and religious sites in China suffered ‘significant structural damage’. There has been a complete breakdown of fundamental rights such as freedom of speech and expression, with the Uyghur economist Ilham Tohti being sentenced to life imprisonment in 2014, and the disappearance of Rahile Dawut, an Uyghur anthropologist. The cultural assimilation and integration of the Uyghurs is encouraged by promoting marriages between the Uyghurs and the Han Chinese through schemes such as the ‘Incentive Measures Encouraging Uighur-Chinese Intermarriage’ scheme which includes a cash reward of $1,450 per annum for the first five years of marriage.&amp;nbsp; The International Reaction 22 countries have sent a joint letter to the United Nations Human Rights Council (UNHRC) condemning the mass detention of Uyghurs. The European Union had in March 2021 sanctioned Zhu Hailun, the proponent of the indoctrination program. The United States Customs and Border Protection had issued five Withhold Release Orders (WRO) on products produced by state-sponsored forced labour such as hair products made in the industrial park at Xinjiang and cotton produced by the Yili Zhouwan Garment Manufacturing Company and Baoding LYSZD Trade and Business Company. It has to be noted that Pakistani Prime Minister Imran Khan, a vocal critic of Islamophobia has maintained silence on Uyghur persecution, stating that he didn’t &quot;know much about&quot; the scale of Uyghur mistreatment and stating that China had helped them when &quot;they were at the rock bottom&quot;. The 57 country Organization of Islamic Cooperation (OIC) has, however, mentioned &quot;disturbing reports&quot; of China’s crackdown on Muslims, but has backtracked on its publication.&amp;nbsp; The process of Sinicization is perhaps best amplified in the words: &quot;You people are not Turks. Uighurs are Chinese. You are one of us, Chinese&quot; as recalled by Mohammed, an Uyghur from Southern Xinjiang, who had been detained for seven months in June 2018, held in a camp with his hands chained together in a room with 35 others. The tale of Blood Cotton haunts the collective conscience of the world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Tale of Two Pandemics</title>
      <link href="/A-Tale-of-Two-Pandemics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Tale of Two Pandemics" />
      <published>2021-03-31T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-03-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Tale-of-Two-Pandemics</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Tale-of-Two-Pandemics">&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, the COVID-19 pandemic has claimed millions of lives, plunged the world economy into a deep crisis, and laid bare the contradictions and injustices that have resulted from a decade of austerity, privatisation and financialisation. Events of such epochal significance often invite comparisons with the past, and with regards to the circumstances in which it emerged and the economic and social disruption which it has caused, COVID-19 can be compared to the Black Death which swept Europe, Asia and North Africa from 1347 to 1351, killing a third of Europe’s population. This article will examine how the devastating spread of both COVID-19 and the Black Death was catalysed by ecological conditions in which disease flourished, analysing how both diseases profoundly altered the economic systems that had given rise to them, and how in both cases, elites sought to protect their precarious positions by utilising coercive State control over dissident populations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The System Grinds to a Halt&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both the Black Death and COVID-19 exposed the flaws in the global, interconnected systems of trade and commerce from which they emerged. The Pax Mongolica, which followed the Mongol conquests of Eurasia and ensured relatively peaceful commerce and communication between West and East, would eventually introduce the plague into Europe. Historian William MacNeill writes that Pax Mongolica had&lt;em&gt; “created a territorially vast human web that linked the Mongol headquarters at Karakorum with Kazan and Astrakhan on the Volga, with Caffa in the Crimea, with Khanbaliq in China and with innumerable other caravanserais in between.” &lt;/em&gt;Pax Mongolica lowered the transactional and protective costs of overland trade, guaranteeing the safety of merchants to travel in the regions controlled by the Mongols, and ensuring that Western countries gained commercial and territorial concessions. The free exchange of goods, ideas and technologies from the Far East to Europe also aided the specialisation of the Italian City States, who expanded their trade in the Black Sea region as a result of Mongolian protection.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the spread of the Black Death followed the aforementioned period of sustained urban and commercial growth, significantly accelerated by an ecological breakdown. A group of Norwegian and Swiss researchers discovered a causal link between warm springs and wet summers in the Karakoram mountain ranges on the borders of China and India and the outbreak of the Black Death, as plague-carrying rodents had fled, forcing fleas to latch onto new hosts. The same system which saw Mongol domination over trade routes in Eurasia and the Silk Road, exchanging goods, raw materials and men, soon became the vector for this deadly bacterial infection, as it spread from Central Asia to Europe, introduced to Europe by Genoese merchants from their trading port in Caffa in the Black Sea during 1347. It is estimated that in the next three years, 20 million Europeans died from the Black Death, in addition to 60 million Chinese people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 too has emerged from a system of global markets and exchange of information, technology and people, driven by ecological conditions conducive to transferring diseases from animals to humans. Rob Wallace and others &lt;a href=&quot;https://monthlyreview.org/2020/05/01/covid-19-and-circuits-of-capital/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;argue&lt;/a&gt; that: &lt;em&gt;“the entirety of the production line is organised around practices that accelerate the evolution of pathogen virulence and subsequent transmission.” &lt;/em&gt;The character of the modern agribusiness system, replete with monocultures and methods of cutting costs that result in multiple livestock species congregating in the same place, such as in a wet market in Wuhan, creates a fertile breeding ground for viruses. The swine and bird influenza outbreaks also had their origins in this agricultural system. Thomas Gillespie, a &amp;nbsp;professor in Emory University’s department of environmental sciences, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2020/mar/18/tip-of-the-iceberg-is-our-destruction-of-nature-responsible-for-covid-19-aoe&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;told&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;The Guardian &lt;/em&gt;that &lt;em&gt;“Wet markets make a perfect storm for cross-species transmission of pathogens,”&lt;/em&gt; adding: &lt;em&gt;“Whenever you have novel interactions with a range of species in one place, whether that is in a natural environment like a forest or a wet market, you can have a spillover event.”&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the “just in time” supply chains that govern food production, with production calculated to meet market demand rather than human need, crashed in the aftermath of COVID-19. Demand shocks led to price hikes and shortages, and lockdowns severely hampered global supply chains, making the logistics for transporting grain supplies extremely difficult. Dairy farmers in Wisconsin, Minnesota and Georgia were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/thesalt/2020/04/03/826006362/food-shortages-nope-too-much-food-in-the-wrong-places&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;forced to throw away thousands of gallons of milk&lt;/a&gt;, and in Florida, vegetable farmers were forced to abandon fields of harvest-ready produce owing to the acceleration of an acute crisis of overproduction. As with the Black Death and feudalism, COVID-19 did not cause the crises of capitalism, but came into being partly as a consequence of them, demonstrating the volatility and uncertainty of global capitalist markets. In the cases of both the Black Death and COVID-19, environmental conditions hastened the spread of diseases whose devastating impacts threatened to bring the existing economic systems to a standstill.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Elites Consolidate Power&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Black Death struck at the heart of the feudal mode of production, undermining the manorial system and dramatically reducing the Lords’ authority over peasants. Feudalism had been steadily declining prior to the outbreak of the plague, as a lack of virgin land to expand into, coupled with the absorption of agricultural surpluses by lords had lowered the productivity of labour and brought the system to its limits. The income of the feudal aristocracy is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marxist.com/black-death-pandemic-changed-world.htm&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;estimated&lt;/a&gt; to have fallen by over 20% between 1347 and 1353. The plague acted as a powerful external shock to the system, engendering cataclysmic changes in the economy and increasing the autonomy, productivity and militancy of the peasantry. For example, owing to the dramatic decline in population that the plague caused, the amount of readily available land increased, allowing peasants to free themselves from the threat of expulsion that had once loomed over them, bargaining for higher wages and lower rents. In the century following the Black Death, rent revenue fell at rates of up to 70% throughout Europe, particularly in regions of Normandy and Flanders. In England, wages doubled over the same period.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As is currently the case in the countries reeling from the impact of COVID-19&lt;strong&gt;,&lt;/strong&gt; the blows that the Black Death caused to the predominant political and economic system were followed by a frantic consolidation of power by the elites. In 1349, Edward III introduced a Statute of Labourers, a failed attempt to fix wages at their pre-plague levels, which stated: “If any...take more wages than were wont to be paid, he shall be committed to gaol.” The following year, the Archbishop of Canterbury denounced the “greed” of peasants who dared to charge extra money for their services. The punitive Poll Tax of 1377, levied in part to finance a war against France, sparked the peasants’ revolt, the memory of which echoed in the riots against the poll tax imposed by Margeret Thatcher centuries later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the attempts to entrench authority and quell dissent in the aftermath of the Black Death involved restricting the autonomy and competitiveness of a new class of independent peasants, the post-COVID world will likely incur the utilisation of modern technologies and bureaucracies to stifle protest and coerce labour. For example, Hungarian Prime Minister Viktor Orban used the COVID crisis as a pretext to pass a controversial Parliamentary bill allowing him to rule by decree with minimal oversight, and Philippines President Rodrigo Duterte awarded himself emergency powers to carry out press censorship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the transformation and digitisation of work, coupled with the potential for the retrenchment of surveillance and expansion of the power of&amp;nbsp; Big Tech, pose a significant threat to the freedom of a now-disposable working class. Both the Black Death and COVID-19 accelerated technological developments which constrained the power of a militant workforce. In the aftermath of the Black Death, rising labour costs saw the purchase of improved tools, machinery, fertiliser and other methods of production replacing expensive labour, as capital-intensive industries emerged, stimulating textile industries in Holland and England. The proliferation of online work and the shift away from offices in professional labour as a result of COVID could potentially give employers access to cheaper labour in overseas markets, as employees become easier to replace. This increased labour market flexibility may also be used to stifle dissent and trade union activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world’s billionaires have made record profits in the aftermath of COVID-19, as Swiss Bank UBS reported that they had increased their wealth by 27.5% between April and July 2020. The collective wealth of America’s 651 billionaires increased by $1 trillion during the pandemic, &lt;a href=&quot;https://americansfortaxfairness.org/wp-content/uploads/12-9-20-National-Billionaires-Report-Press-Release-1T-4T-FINAL-1.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;according&lt;/a&gt; to The Institute for Policy Studies. Owing to the collapse of small businesses as a result of lockdowns and a spike in demand for online retailers like Amazon, the comparative ease with which big business could weather the storm of economic turmoil has facilitated a concentration of wealth not seen since the Vanderbilts, Rockefellers and Carnegies amassed vast fortunes at the end of the 19th century. Global tech companies whose business models are predicated on accruing vast amounts of venture capital and mining consumer data, and as such depend on establishing monopolies to function, have also largely emerged unscathed. In a similar way to how the Black Death catalysed the emergence of a bureaucratic class of merchants on whom the weakened feudal monarchy became increasingly dependent, COVID-19 may propel the modern technocrats of Silicon Valley to even greater heights than are currently conceivable.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Black Death, and the response to it by political elites, provides an instructive historical case study in how the spread of disease can radically alter the balance of power within a society, drastically revolutionising the productive forces and paving the way for radical change. The response to the Black Death by landlords and feudal aristocrats, which took the form of coercive labour controls and wage reductions, led directly to the peasants’ revolt. The aftermath of COVID-19 has already seen vast corporate payouts and a concentration of wealth alongside a marked upsurge in evictions, homelessness and extreme poverty. To prevent the emergence of ruthless State-monopoly capitalism, it is imperative to learn the lessons of history, which can provide blueprints for building a new society in the shell of the old. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="featured" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Over the past year, the COVID-19 pandemic has claimed millions of lives, plunged the world economy into a deep crisis, and laid bare the contradictions and injustices that have resulted from a decade of austerity, privatisation and financialisation. Events of such epochal significance often invite comparisons with the past, and with regards to the circumstances in which it emerged and the economic and social disruption which it has caused, COVID-19 can be compared to the Black Death which swept Europe, Asia and North Africa from 1347 to 1351, killing a third of Europe’s population. This article will examine how the devastating spread of both COVID-19 and the Black Death was catalysed by ecological conditions in which disease flourished, analysing how both diseases profoundly altered the economic systems that had given rise to them, and how in both cases, elites sought to protect their precarious positions by utilising coercive State control over dissident populations.&amp;nbsp; The System Grinds to a Halt Both the Black Death and COVID-19 exposed the flaws in the global, interconnected systems of trade and commerce from which they emerged. The Pax Mongolica, which followed the Mongol conquests of Eurasia and ensured relatively peaceful commerce and communication between West and East, would eventually introduce the plague into Europe. Historian William MacNeill writes that Pax Mongolica had “created a territorially vast human web that linked the Mongol headquarters at Karakorum with Kazan and Astrakhan on the Volga, with Caffa in the Crimea, with Khanbaliq in China and with innumerable other caravanserais in between.” Pax Mongolica lowered the transactional and protective costs of overland trade, guaranteeing the safety of merchants to travel in the regions controlled by the Mongols, and ensuring that Western countries gained commercial and territorial concessions. The free exchange of goods, ideas and technologies from the Far East to Europe also aided the specialisation of the Italian City States, who expanded their trade in the Black Sea region as a result of Mongolian protection.&amp;nbsp; However, the spread of the Black Death followed the aforementioned period of sustained urban and commercial growth, significantly accelerated by an ecological breakdown. A group of Norwegian and Swiss researchers discovered a causal link between warm springs and wet summers in the Karakoram mountain ranges on the borders of China and India and the outbreak of the Black Death, as plague-carrying rodents had fled, forcing fleas to latch onto new hosts. The same system which saw Mongol domination over trade routes in Eurasia and the Silk Road, exchanging goods, raw materials and men, soon became the vector for this deadly bacterial infection, as it spread from Central Asia to Europe, introduced to Europe by Genoese merchants from their trading port in Caffa in the Black Sea during 1347. It is estimated that in the next three years, 20 million Europeans died from the Black Death, in addition to 60 million Chinese people. COVID-19 too has emerged from a system of global markets and exchange of information, technology and people, driven by ecological conditions conducive to transferring diseases from animals to humans. Rob Wallace and others argue that: “the entirety of the production line is organised around practices that accelerate the evolution of pathogen virulence and subsequent transmission.” The character of the modern agribusiness system, replete with monocultures and methods of cutting costs that result in multiple livestock species congregating in the same place, such as in a wet market in Wuhan, creates a fertile breeding ground for viruses. The swine and bird influenza outbreaks also had their origins in this agricultural system. Thomas Gillespie, a &amp;nbsp;professor in Emory University’s department of environmental sciences, told The Guardian that “Wet markets make a perfect storm for cross-species transmission of pathogens,” adding: “Whenever you have novel interactions with a range of species in one place, whether that is in a natural environment like a forest or a wet market, you can have a spillover event.”&amp;nbsp; Moreover, the “just in time” supply chains that govern food production, with production calculated to meet market demand rather than human need, crashed in the aftermath of COVID-19. Demand shocks led to price hikes and shortages, and lockdowns severely hampered global supply chains, making the logistics for transporting grain supplies extremely difficult. Dairy farmers in Wisconsin, Minnesota and Georgia were forced to throw away thousands of gallons of milk, and in Florida, vegetable farmers were forced to abandon fields of harvest-ready produce owing to the acceleration of an acute crisis of overproduction. As with the Black Death and feudalism, COVID-19 did not cause the crises of capitalism, but came into being partly as a consequence of them, demonstrating the volatility and uncertainty of global capitalist markets. In the cases of both the Black Death and COVID-19, environmental conditions hastened the spread of diseases whose devastating impacts threatened to bring the existing economic systems to a standstill.&amp;nbsp; The Elites Consolidate Power The Black Death struck at the heart of the feudal mode of production, undermining the manorial system and dramatically reducing the Lords’ authority over peasants. Feudalism had been steadily declining prior to the outbreak of the plague, as a lack of virgin land to expand into, coupled with the absorption of agricultural surpluses by lords had lowered the productivity of labour and brought the system to its limits. The income of the feudal aristocracy is estimated to have fallen by over 20% between 1347 and 1353. The plague acted as a powerful external shock to the system, engendering cataclysmic changes in the economy and increasing the autonomy, productivity and militancy of the peasantry. For example, owing to the dramatic decline in population that the plague caused, the amount of readily available land increased, allowing peasants to free themselves from the threat of expulsion that had once loomed over them, bargaining for higher wages and lower rents. In the century following the Black Death, rent revenue fell at rates of up to 70% throughout Europe, particularly in regions of Normandy and Flanders. In England, wages doubled over the same period.&amp;nbsp; As is currently the case in the countries reeling from the impact of COVID-19, the blows that the Black Death caused to the predominant political and economic system were followed by a frantic consolidation of power by the elites. In 1349, Edward III introduced a Statute of Labourers, a failed attempt to fix wages at their pre-plague levels, which stated: “If any...take more wages than were wont to be paid, he shall be committed to gaol.” The following year, the Archbishop of Canterbury denounced the “greed” of peasants who dared to charge extra money for their services. The punitive Poll Tax of 1377, levied in part to finance a war against France, sparked the peasants’ revolt, the memory of which echoed in the riots against the poll tax imposed by Margeret Thatcher centuries later. While the attempts to entrench authority and quell dissent in the aftermath of the Black Death involved restricting the autonomy and competitiveness of a new class of independent peasants, the post-COVID world will likely incur the utilisation of modern technologies and bureaucracies to stifle protest and coerce labour. For example, Hungarian Prime Minister Viktor Orban used the COVID crisis as a pretext to pass a controversial Parliamentary bill allowing him to rule by decree with minimal oversight, and Philippines President Rodrigo Duterte awarded himself emergency powers to carry out press censorship. Furthermore, the transformation and digitisation of work, coupled with the potential for the retrenchment of surveillance and expansion of the power of&amp;nbsp; Big Tech, pose a significant threat to the freedom of a now-disposable working class. Both the Black Death and COVID-19 accelerated technological developments which constrained the power of a militant workforce. In the aftermath of the Black Death, rising labour costs saw the purchase of improved tools, machinery, fertiliser and other methods of production replacing expensive labour, as capital-intensive industries emerged, stimulating textile industries in Holland and England. The proliferation of online work and the shift away from offices in professional labour as a result of COVID could potentially give employers access to cheaper labour in overseas markets, as employees become easier to replace. This increased labour market flexibility may also be used to stifle dissent and trade union activity. The world’s billionaires have made record profits in the aftermath of COVID-19, as Swiss Bank UBS reported that they had increased their wealth by 27.5% between April and July 2020. The collective wealth of America’s 651 billionaires increased by $1 trillion during the pandemic, according to The Institute for Policy Studies. Owing to the collapse of small businesses as a result of lockdowns and a spike in demand for online retailers like Amazon, the comparative ease with which big business could weather the storm of economic turmoil has facilitated a concentration of wealth not seen since the Vanderbilts, Rockefellers and Carnegies amassed vast fortunes at the end of the 19th century. Global tech companies whose business models are predicated on accruing vast amounts of venture capital and mining consumer data, and as such depend on establishing monopolies to function, have also largely emerged unscathed. In a similar way to how the Black Death catalysed the emergence of a bureaucratic class of merchants on whom the weakened feudal monarchy became increasingly dependent, COVID-19 may propel the modern technocrats of Silicon Valley to even greater heights than are currently conceivable.&amp;nbsp; The Black Death, and the response to it by political elites, provides an instructive historical case study in how the spread of disease can radically alter the balance of power within a society, drastically revolutionising the productive forces and paving the way for radical change. The response to the Black Death by landlords and feudal aristocrats, which took the form of coercive labour controls and wage reductions, led directly to the peasants’ revolt. The aftermath of COVID-19 has already seen vast corporate payouts and a concentration of wealth alongside a marked upsurge in evictions, homelessness and extreme poverty. To prevent the emergence of ruthless State-monopoly capitalism, it is imperative to learn the lessons of history, which can provide blueprints for building a new society in the shell of the old.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">“I don’t belong here”</title>
      <link href="/Dont-Belong-Here" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“I don’t belong here”" />
      <published>2020-07-09T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Dont-Belong-Here</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Dont-Belong-Here">&lt;p&gt;With the latest lockdown extension, I am back to dilly-dallying and fraught musings. While I watch &lt;em&gt;House of Cards&lt;/em&gt; for the third time, I wonder how one can be so smart and manipulative and yet, question themselves. How the mind that makes us perform all the good, is also the one that makes us question each action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these times where we put ourselves to uses more than we can avail, where multiple to-do lists loom over our heads, it is easy to maintain a fail-safe, procrastinate, and be stressed. But there is another issue on the other side of the spectrum that we do not usually talk about. A fear, if I may call it that, of how we are being able to perform these tasks, and with suave too. The other day, I had just washed my hands of paint and stopped to see what I had painted. I actually liked it. On any other day, I just sit there and count flaws, but I did not. I could not. And, thus, I called it my lucky day, took a picture of it, and off went my Snapchat. Ah, a happy day. A happy day that brought in new questions. After my usual tip-dip-trip to Google, I found that there prevails a phenomenon that affects many - the ‘Impostor Syndrome’. It is a persistent feeling that causes someone to doubt their accomplishments despite evidence and fear they may be exposed as a fraud. It caught my interest and also managed to make me redirect my thought process on multiple occasions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many times have we felt like we did not belong with the ones who excel, that we did not deserve the appreciation, that we had somehow managed to fool everyone around us? I sure have. Even on a day that I am sure I had prepared more than I needed to and did well in the task, I give about 70% of the credit to luck. Other times, when I do not score well, the very first thought in my head is, “See? You are not as smart as you’d like to believe you are.” Some have described their experience with impostor syndrome as a feeling of being trapped in a situation where you are well out of your depth and have no way out. People affected by this syndrome show a common behaviour: they are often remarkably successful, overachieving on a regular basis and are considered experts by others, but deep down they feel like frauds, scared of being unmasked anytime. It may seem hard to believe, but there is a huge discrepancy between the false image they own of themselves and what others see, they live an internal conflict. Psychologists Clance and Imes first described the impostor phenomenon in 1978; Kolligian and Sternberg in 2000 suggested that we should categorise this mental fraudulence experience as a category in personality disorder or pervasive mental disorder for it is known not as a symptom but a self-perception or self-referral ideation with cognitive and emotional-affective components. However, until today, the syndrome has not been acknowledged psychiatrically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The syndrome mind-trap prevents people from believing in themselves to the detriment of us all. Reading the cases (and oh, the famous!), the way it has been portrayed, I wondered if it was just low self-esteem or not having plenty of self-confidence. But self-doubt and low self-confidence levels are seen to be symptoms of impostor syndrome, and at its core, it is said to be a self-assessment problem. I’d say there are three ways to muster the syndrome, “Hello, I’m fake”; “Hello, I’m just lucky”; and my favourite, “Hello, this thing!? Oh, it’s nothing.” Now, you cannot tell me you haven’t uttered any of these, just like I can’t tell you having said any (or all) of this implies that you have the syndrome. Blimey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon looking up literature on the phenomenon, I was surprised to find that most of it revolved around women, while research has shown that there is no certain gender effect, seemingly people don’t believe so, and well, who are we to fault, but society? More on that, someday. The most important factor that influences this syndrome is found to be the connection link between family variables, personality variables, destructive beliefs, and the unpleasant consequences of progress. The family and child-rearing method along with the attribution styles really make the play. As a child, we are often taught not to be over-confident, or well, too self-serving. While, how you are brought up plays a huge role, let me just say, that is not the only factor. Your personality, your own disposition, and its marriage to how well your esteem was nurtured are what make the magic happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst all the research about who is feeling what and why they did manage to find out certain types to this syndrome. Valerie Young suggested five types: The Perfectionist who piles up their own expectations and does most of them and still feels like a failure. The Experts feel the need to know every piece of information and, are always wanting to improve their skills, however, they continue to question it. The Soloist is someone who feels the need to do everything on their own and if they want for help, they count it as a failure. The Superwoman/man pushes themselves to work harder than those around them to prove that they are not imposters. And lastly, The Great Mind, or the Natural Genius, their problem is that if they have to struggle or work hard to accomplish something, they think it means they are not good enough. I suppose it says something about me that even putting myself in one of these boxes, is making me mildly anxious. Ha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is interesting is that when individuals with this phenomenon face a competitive situation; they show two reactions: they either become negligent and make up excuses for doing the given task or spend excessive energy doing it. What should not come as a surprise is how strongly it is associated with psychological distress- depression and anxiety and is heavily linked to burnout too. Holding yourself to impossible standards, trying to control your environment and comparing yourself to others: these three are the silent triggers. They lead to self-assessment standards that are unreachable, making you feel like you will never measure up and that you don’t deserve what you have. Time and again, these feelings may flutter by, but are they only bad? Is there any good to it? I mean, at the end of the day, it does involve self-talk, and reflection, however negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Hermione (Emma Watson, to the uncultured), herself, has it, I would say there must be something to it. Amidst the 30 or so famous names that &lt;em&gt;InStyle&lt;/em&gt; shows me on a slideshow, with even Meryl Streep making a cameo, there is much to how one feels the fear. Just the statements made by someone who inhabits it can let you know. Most times, fear is considered weak, however, this could very well be a strength in its own right. The ones affected see flaws in their work where others do not and self-medicate against it by aiming for perfection, and when has perfection ever been less than (I apologise) perfect. Studies have shown that people perform at higher levels when they are worried about being (or seeming) incompetent. There is a paradoxical similarity between the self-views of people who are really competent and the self-views of those who are not. Would you say that feeling like a fraud when you should not is probably not as bad as not feeling like a fraud when you should?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people experience moments of doubt, and that is normal. The important part is said to be not to let that doubt control your actions and, well, to appease you, still, I have Bertrand Russell, telling us all- &lt;em&gt;“The whole problem with the world is that fools and fanatics are always so certain of themselves, and wiser people so full of doubts.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">With the latest lockdown extension, I am back to dilly-dallying and fraught musings. While I watch House of Cards for the third time, I wonder how one can be so smart and manipulative and yet, question themselves. How the mind that makes us perform all the good, is also the one that makes us question each action.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Dear Pandemic Diary</title>
      <link href="/Dear-Pandemic-Diary" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Dear Pandemic Diary" />
      <published>2020-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Dear-Pandemic-Diary</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Dear-Pandemic-Diary">&lt;p&gt;Last time I was here, I was asking if you would like that Corona (the beer, folks) with lime or without, today, I might take a dozen bottles with or without you. I apologise in advance; this may seem like an untoward journal entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the pandemic is upon us, and God, is it upon us - I wonder to myself, is this regression to teen years going to bring me down, or the virus? While I don’t have to wake up at 5 am, listen to VH1 till 6:30 and move to school by 6:40 anymore, I have to deal with chaos that nobody ever told me about. No school lessons taught me how to be home and keep sane; hiding under the table definitely doesn’t work. Crisis intervention only tells me so much that I might truly have to be infected in order to utilise my knowledge. I wish I could run back to my 3rd grade moral lessons and really be the person that they proposed we be - the sane, calm, adjusted one that obviously had nothing but respect and compassion for everyone. It would make life easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we speak of the pandemic, many don’t realise that while the certainty of having the virus is difficult to deal with (and that may as well be an understatement), the uncertainty it brings with itself is the silent killer that may lead us to a Noah’s Ark situation. The aforementioned teen regression that I speak of? Well, people my age and around my age have had to come back home from being away for college or their respective jobs plainly because, “better be sick with family than without.” And people who were home already, have lost their autonomy and are back to being home with the ‘others’ deciding what is to be done. My teenage hormones, albeit crazy, perhaps, were the only thing that led me to the slightly retained sanity I used to encompass, till, well, a few days ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having reread that paragraph, I understand if I might sound ungrateful, believe me, I’m not. I assure you, I’m aware of my privilege of being safe and healthy, of having resources to maintain that, of being able to share my thoughts and being able to help myself and others while I’m at it. I suppose all I’m trying to suggest here is how while ‘inside and isolated’ may drive us crazy, figuratively speaking - doing both while you’re in a toxic household or with someone who may be riddled with their own issues - may, literally speaking, make you crazy. Personally, having had to deal with a symptomatic-to-hypochondriac mother has been driving me up the walls, the paranoia that surfaces is so strong, that any denial will be harshly rejected, and that’s my reality to live with now. Upon asking my near and dear ones, I’m now able to recount several cases of unhealthy relationships, malfunctioning behaviour and what one may call unsettling dependency. My sample is too small, and perhaps not as generalisable - I mean it is, after all, purposive and convenient (Okay, I’m going to stop now). But, what may be concluded is that there’s a danger lurking, and we’re not aware of it or, well, not wanting to be aware of it. May as well dump it in that subconscious, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The curse on mental health that social isolation is, is not unknown; there are plenty of people with flared anxieties or triggered depression - and then, there are people who may not even be aware of what they’re going through and end up more hurt than ever. As a future mental health professional, I can sit here and count out hundreds of flaws in self-isolation and social distancing, but the science behind it is not unknown and it definitely is better of the two evils. I can’t give an informed solution, as someone once told me: mental health is like fingerprints, different for everybody (and definitely, incriminating!). I only ask everyone to be more receptive to the idea of keeping your thoughts open and look for more sources of help (and try to be one, too).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were to intimate yourself with my thoughts - I don’t suppose the fear of COVID-19 is as high as having to figure out how to placate my mother, submit two assignments and attend 3 classes and write 2 research papers, while simultaneously completing my to-dos of ‘productive work during quarantine.’ Every time I watch the news, I worry that maybe the numbers that rise up everyday are just becoming statistics to me and my brain, and my empathy and fear will be drained out by my need to do chores and completing tasks and just proving that I’m ‘productive’. Or perhaps, it’s the other way round, maybe that is good, denial till faced with the issue - a (good?) coping mechanism. I wouldn’t know; if you do please, page me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only think of today as possibly weighed by my worries and the silliness that pertains to “whoa, today was busy”. Maybe, you can do one better and ask your near and dear ones how their day was. And yourself, it’s important that you ask yourself about your day. My day was mopping, Humanism and the utter joy followed after finding recent, high Impact Factor research papers. Well, it’s yet to be over, but you know I’ll keep you posted.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="repost" />
      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Last time I was here, I was asking if you would like that Corona (the beer, folks) with lime or without, today, I might take a dozen bottles with or without you. I apologise in advance; this may seem like an untoward journal entry.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Beer, anyone? Levity in a Time of Crisis</title>
      <link href="/Beer-anyone-Levity-in-a-Time-of-Crisis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beer, anyone? Levity in a Time of Crisis" />
      <published>2020-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Beer-anyone-Levity-in-a-Time-of-Crisis</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Beer-anyone-Levity-in-a-Time-of-Crisis">&lt;p&gt;If one were to tell me that I’d be receiving an impromptu holiday which may last anywhere between 10 days to the end of time (my personal time, friends) - I’d be elated, ecstatic, even. However, the very backing of the same would be resulting in deaths around the world and would be the reason for self-quarantining? Not as idealistic. While COVID-19 is no secret, and there is plenty known as well as unknown about this global pandemic, what has increasingly caught on like wildfire is the machinery related to the meme-making and the subsequent jokes that have flown in. While everyone is apprehensive about the unknown, the at-homeness has led to coping with the situation in any fashion we can. But, why humour? And what version of it is deemed appropriate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it that something that was born along one side of the world and has followed around the entirety of it has led to a strong sense of levity, at this dire time? What room do we have in our heads that makes us condone a business supposedly so corroded? And if not supposedly as corroded as it is supposed to be- what conception of this humour makes the cut?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From making fun of Trump and his infallible speeches (and more importantly, wigs) to now, suggesting how Bollywood star Ranveer Singh dresses like Coronavirus - believe you me, the latter tickled me about as much as it shocked me. The memes have hit like the plague, itself (no pun, intended) - quite unavoidable and with no cure. Just this morning, Snapchat informed me that a proficient actress was being ‘cancelled’ for making less of this pandemic. If she is at fault, aren’t we all? If Tom Hanks can tweet out that he’s lost 216 bouts of rummy with his wife due to the posited isolation of his positive-to-the-virus-self, we laugh, don’t we? It is ‘absolutely amazing’ how well he’s handling the issue at hand. However, if another individual so much as suggest that this pandemic is God’s gift to students- Ma’am, you have a #cancelled on your hands. I, a mere human, only ask for the boundary - where to build the wall, you know? (Please forgive me.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do what I can do best, right about now. I ask. People, Google, one and all. My friend tells me memes are the medicine to this pandemic, at least until you test positive, while a research published in ​Harvard Business Review explains that “laughter relieves stress and boredom, boosts engagement and well-being, and spurs not only creativity and collaboration but also analytic precision and productivity.” It’s the manna from heaven, my friends. All that has troubled us: stress, boredom- cured. One article went ahead and suggested that humour can be and is, very well a form of self-care when experiencing burnout and compassion fatigue. Finding a humorous angle together can serve as a doorway to a deeper connection with other individuals, acting as a buffer. Could it be that a sense of belonging is what we seek, it is this that makes these jokes and memes as popular as they are - our need for affiliation! ​Malchiodi, one of the greatest researchers of ‘the funnies’ has vastly discussed the positive mental and physical results of laughter and/or humour. “Since the late 1980s, a number of studies support the idea that laughter stimulates the immune system and counteracts the effects of stress ​hormones, although results are mixed about exactly how,” she said. “In brief, there’s agreement that it’s another way to arrive at the relaxation response.” ​We’ve got it, people - an explanation as to why there has been a surge in the circulation of COVID-19 memes, parodies and videos aiming to get a laugh out of people. It could be that for certain people, making light of things is more of a coping mechanism than it is a chance at fame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and what fame to give up, too. Please afford me another moment of pondering and I shall be done. In the extensive research that this phenomenon took - what became extremely apparent to me was the cultural difference. While Singapore is busy with how other countries are copying their way of work, or may I suggest, homework; the USA was busy with toilet paper memes (or, better yet, buttcoin, the new currency crowned after the infamous bitcoin.) India, out here, is confused about which issue to put higher up on the hierarchy - the failure of it as a democracy, the communal riots, the pandemic that is barely being considered as one or just the sheer amount of Whatsapp forwards that suggest you drink ‘gau mutra’ (cow urine) and get vaccinated towards Corona. Hitherto, the reigning queen, (and this I say with much bias) has to be the Corona Beer memes and the expected aversion to the same by the sages of the world. The economy is down the drain for most countries, the population - more so. But, I really do think Corona with/without lime deserves better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly enough, and this may be of interest to one and all, the place where Rapunzel isolated herself? Corona. In more ways than one, the world is coming full circle- and while it may be really difficult to go through, it is nonetheless entertaining to watch the unfolding. Just this morning, another friend and I had a long conversation about the conspiracy theories involved with the awakening of COVID-19. Oh, and if you weren’t aware CoronaVirus Disorder- 2019 getting abbreviated has very much to do with the memes, you can ask WHO, they’d attest. While I’m no meme connoisseur, conspiracy theories really get me going but that’s for another day, another time, another beer. Done with my rambling, I warrant my answer to my aforementioned question - why humour? Why this very coping mechanism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I think? It is non-violent resistance to any form of oppression. A successful one at that. It facilitates a culture of resistance, tries to bring levity, sure - but with it, interest and awareness. It’s the pink colour to cough syrups - the pretty packaging to venomous bottles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as ​at a personal level, self-irony and joking about one’s own shortcomings are considered to have the greatest impact on self-liberation through humour, dare I suggest that may be true at the social level, irrespective of cultural and individual differences? Now, what does mere me know? While I ride back home in an airplane where no individual is without a mask or sanitizer - while I go home because my mother would rather I be sick with her than without - while there’s panic and apprehension on almost possible levels of conscious awareness, I wonder if you’d like that Corona with lime or without.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">If one were to tell me that I’d be receiving an impromptu holiday which may last anywhere between 10 days to the end of time (my personal time, friends) - I’d be elated, ecstatic, even. However, the very backing of the same would be resulting in deaths around the world and would be the reason for self-quarantining? Not as idealistic. While COVID-19 is no secret, and there is plenty known as well as unknown about this global pandemic, what has increasingly caught on like wildfire is the machinery related to the meme-making and the subsequent jokes that have flown in. While everyone is apprehensive about the unknown, the at-homeness has led to coping with the situation in any fashion we can. But, why humour? And what version of it is deemed appropriate?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Are You Bored Enough?</title>
      <link href="/Are-You-Bored-Enough" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are You Bored Enough?" />
      <published>2020-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Are-You-Bored-Enough</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Are-You-Bored-Enough">&lt;p&gt;A happy new year, yeah, um, happy? From what I’ve been told, we’re unsubscribing from Jan’20, so, I hope for a good, uneven eleven-month’d year ahead. There has been a huge lapse on my end: I’ve been unable to pen down anything for the longest time. Not because I’m lacking the resources, definitely not the time―what it is, may only be described as dissatisfaction. Dissatisfaction in everything that, I, as an individual of a certain age- living in the country that I live in, belonging to the state I belong to, have had to see. The ghastly past few days and the subsequent coming days, all of it seems too much to bear and I’ve decided I am not to write on it. The awareness that this entire fascist regime (or, situation) in India deserves is beyond anything I can measure, and I can’t remotely do it justice, in no specific way. My bias holds too high and is nowhere near close to being over, not anytime soon. Hence, I’ll use this as a ‘breath of fresh air,’ with how polluted the air I breathe is. In more ways than one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I type this, I’ve Billie crooning in my ears about how she’s so bored, and well, let’s run with it, shall we? Billie deserves her answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bored? Boredom? Equivalent to disinterest? Or, is it a conditioned, negative feeling that shrouds us upon being unproductive? I’ve often felt awful after a day spent watching Netflix. But does that mean I was bored? I wouldn’t say so. But has the binge been productive? I wouldn’t say that, either. So, I go surfing, web surfing and find out what this damned concept entails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several authors from Pascal to Schopenhauer, from Kierkegaard to our very favourite Nietzsche, and Baudelaire, and Dostoevsky―everyone seems to have dropped a cent on this everyday phenomenon. Well, is it an everyday phenomenon all? It almost seems like the closer we get to the present day, the more destructive boredom becomes, compelling creative types—from writers and artists to rock musicians (Slash!!)—to reflect on this theme. Nevertheless, it remains a difficult psychological state to define, more so today, than ever. Kierkegaard equates boredom with the devil and defines it thus: “The demonic is that which is without content, boring.” According to Dostoevsky, boredom is “a bestial and indefinable affliction.” One of the present-day researchers, Elizabeth Goodstein, labels it “experience without qualities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure I agree. I mean, she’s clearly influenced by Robert Musil’s &lt;em&gt;The Man Without Qualities&lt;/em&gt;. The book is simply a diagnosis of everyday life and thrives on the concept of boredom. If one were to read Lars Svendsen’s (pretty much the father of boredom, and one who serves quite a heavy read) &lt;em&gt;A Philosophy of Boredom&lt;/em&gt;, one’ll find out that boredom is a social construction of the era that began in the middle of the 18th century. ‘Interesting’ as a concept came to light simultaneously with that of boredom. It was not up to then accepted practice to classify things as being either “boring” or “interesting.” Understandably, such a classification contrasted ‘boring’ with ‘interesting’. That which was interesting was attractive. To be interesting meant not being boring (I’d suggest you read that over a couple of times, I definitely did.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can definitely claim that boredom is a state of discomfort. The most common terms I can substitute it with may be uninteresting, a growth flowered by disinterest and detachment. It is often understood as a catch-all term. It may be understood in its simplicity, termed ‘simple boredom’, a product of temporarily unavoidable and predictable circumstances (being stuck in a bad date? A sad lecture? An awful movie?) as well as ‘existential boredom’ wherein underlies an unrelieved sense of isolation, emptiness, alienation and even helplessness. The main relationship between these two conditions is probably the loose use of the term ‘boredom’. Another close related concept, ‘chronic boredom’, is, one could guess, more like simple boredom, albeit not temporary. If simple boredom is the result of the circumstances we find ourselves in, chronic boredom is a symptom of a lower than normal level in the system of the neurotransmitter dopamine. The notion of chronic boredom is something that is especially the preserve of psychologists. It is measured in a famous test called the Boredom Proneness Scale (BPS) that was devised in 1986 by the now-retired psychologist Norman D Sundberg. Now that you know types of boredom and how fellow psychology enthusiasts are measuring the same, do you still have an unclear picture? Because I sure do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What of a nuanced concept such as this is so difficult to understand? In his book &lt;em&gt;The Will to Meaning&lt;/em&gt;, Viktor Frankl recorded that contemporary man suffered from a deep sense of loss of meaning; a state that he diagnosed as “existential vacuum.” This sense of loss of meaning characterises post-traditional man who cannot make up his mind as to what he wants and what he must do, since tradition no longer dictates what is necessary. If this way is the right way, boredom appears to be the polar opposite of what Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi has famously termed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brainpickings.org/2012/02/27/purpose-work-love/#flow&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;flow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;—a state of intense focus one enters whilst absorbed in an enthralling task, when one loses track of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen, if someone were to ask me to spend any more than 10 minutes by myself, with nothing else to think of, I’d go insane, and that brings me to the question: are we as a generation more or less bored than the ones who came before us? Now, every day brings a new article about how to stop the demon of lassitude, or a new invention designed to keep us from ever being at loose ends again. Come to think of it, phones got smart, and so did we, with easy access to more information and entertainment than ever before. Now, every moment one spends being bored—while riding an elevator, or waiting at the doctor’s office, or biding time until your date returns from the restroom—is a moment one doesn’t spend reading a book, skimming the news, or catching up on social media. What I may be suggesting is that, being bored in 2020, might just be a slap in the face of technology. Never again will we have nothing to do. This should be a good thing… Right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What in the world goes on in our brains when we get bored? Not just physically, but psychologically? And pray tell, what would go on in our brains if we were to never get bored?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers such as Mashuq Ally have led to a whirlwind romance between authors and the idea of boredom. It has been suggested that something super repetitive that doesn’t need one’s brain to be engaged, that’s when one ignites a network in their brain, one called the ‘default mode’. Neuroscientists have claimed that the default mode is when one does their most original thinking: problem-solving, imagination, empathy, all reside in the house of original thinking. The mind is told to be working as somewhat of a time traveling machine. One goes back and thinks of things that have already conspired and makes sense of them and then extracts lessons from them. They call it autobiographical planning. The unthinking mind-wandering that happens when one is bored takes all the information that has ever entered the brain and makes use of it in innovative ways. In other words: being bored is the difference between being good at &lt;em&gt;Jeopardy!&lt;/em&gt; and being someone who actually &lt;em&gt;uses&lt;/em&gt; the knowledge that one has learned to come up with solutions to fix problems (both of the personal and societal kind).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, boredom is good!? However, boredom too, like other fruits of modernity, has its geography. Despite the fact that no one is safe against boredom, the luxury of being bored is not equally accessible to all societies and strata. And that’s just that. The amount of information we feed ourselves, in this tech driven world, is absurd. No number of hard drives could ever retain all the information I gather from Instagram, or heck, a Buzzfeed video binge. So, why wouldn’t the idea of feeding ourselves more and more information and then never actually doing anything with it seem just perfect? Isn’t that what we’ve been taught ever since we were a kid? I have an art degree and I only have my mum’s concern towards my boredom to thank for it. I mean, I could leave social media, give away my joys in boredom, all so I could self-regulate my thoughts, use the knowledge I’ve previously gained and make the most of it, but wouldn’t that make me Joe from &lt;em&gt;You&lt;/em&gt; and I don’t reckon he was liked by many. Sketchy Joe is no good, friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a culture obsessed with productivity, boredom seems like a sin, not to mention impossible when so much of the everyday stimuli we take for granted—email, ads, Instagram, Netflix, YouTube (God, I can go on, and on and on)―is bent on robbing us of our attention. But sitting back and doing nothing is, ironically, exactly what you need to do in order to get more done. We were so scared of being bored at all that we failed to appreciate the frightening repercussions of not being bored enough. And I only have Billie to thank for this insight. So, next up (on my playlist and search engine): &lt;em&gt;Where do we go when we fall asleep?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A happy new year, yeah, um, happy? From what I’ve been told, we’re unsubscribing from Jan’20, so, I hope for a good, uneven eleven-month’d year ahead. There has been a huge lapse on my end: I’ve been unable to pen down anything for the longest time. Not because I’m lacking the resources, definitely not the time―what it is, may only be described as dissatisfaction. Dissatisfaction in everything that, I, as an individual of a certain age- living in the country that I live in, belonging to the state I belong to, have had to see. The ghastly past few days and the subsequent coming days, all of it seems too much to bear and I’ve decided I am not to write on it. The awareness that this entire fascist regime (or, situation) in India deserves is beyond anything I can measure, and I can’t remotely do it justice, in no specific way. My bias holds too high and is nowhere near close to being over, not anytime soon. Hence, I’ll use this as a ‘breath of fresh air,’ with how polluted the air I breathe is. In more ways than one.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Here’s to Feeling Good All The Time!</title>
      <link href="/Here-s-to-Feeling-Good-All-the-Time" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Here’s to Feeling Good All The Time!" />
      <published>2019-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Here-s-to-Feeling-Good-All-the-Time</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Here-s-to-Feeling-Good-All-the-Time">&lt;p&gt;If you were to walk through my door today, I’d only welcome you with a question: Are you happy? I’m no Dr. Phil, it’s not so much as to check on your well-being (well, not completely), it is mostly to comprehend how happiness became the most important thing ever. Personally, I’ve come to a conclusion. Happiness is overrated and way too popular. Happiness is that jock in high school that everybody crushes on, but no one knows how to talk to. I can put a million researches here explaining how it all works: the biology, physiology, and all of the rest. But, why are we so attracted to the concept? What is this constant desire to be happy? And, pressure!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several aspects of our lives revolve around trying to be happy, wanting to be happy. God! take a shot every time you read happy. Or maybe do that every time you see a sunny post on Instagram giving you lessons on how to be more joyous. Believe you me, you’re about to be very intoxicated. We’re now living in a world where even several social media platforms have changed their algorithm so as to promote a more positive content. We’ve all, in a way, turned into Sisyphus, continuously pushing for joy and happiness, but in return only to find it rolling back on nearing the top. This push seems like it’s going to last us a lifetime, and the irony is not lost on any of us. Out of all the ‘feels’ one could feel- why stick to one and work for it so hard that we forget to feel the rest of the lot?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever heard of ‘struggle porn’? It has been trending in the business world for a long time- it alludes to how romanticised entrepreneurs make struggle out to be. Well, I think, what we have in our hands is- ‘happiness porn’. I’m not here to tell you that feeling good is bad—friend, feeling good is always great, but by putting this impractical expectation on oneself we are actually hurting our manifesting powers more than we are helping them. This constant need to feel a certain way restricts our way to ascertain what we’re feeling all together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re almost, in most ways, taught to judge our feelings as wrong. There are negative feelings and positive ones, but right or wrong? I don’t think so. It’s like being in a battle with yourself, which is causing resistance, which is really the only obstacle that stands between you and the realisation of your feelings. Therefore, feeling bad is not the problem, feeling bad about feeling bad definitely is. Quite an inception. One distinction I have to make is that the opposite of happiness is not sadness, it couldn’t be. Its apathy. It is the opposite of every feeling- not feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feeling good is good, this is a belief that is so intuitive to be almost axiomatic, and there is now substantial data to support it. Yet, most of us do know that perpetual joy is not a practical goal. Recent research is actually starting to suggest that it may actually be a harmful one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Galen_Bodenhausen&quot;&gt;Bodenhausen&lt;/a&gt; and&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/scientific-contributions/79839499_Geoffrey_P_Kramer&quot;&gt; Kramer&lt;/a&gt; (pretty credible names, wouldn’t you say?) stated that “happiness is a kind of a safety signal, indicating that there is no current need for problem solving…..Unhappy people will think more deeply about their social environment (in an effort to solve their problems), whereas happy people can contentedly coast on cruise control, not bothering to think very deeply about surrounding events unless they impinge directly on their well-being”—basically suggesting you’re better off solving things when you’re not obliterated with absolute joy. Serious focus may not be pleasant, but it may be the optimal mood for certain tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that might be troubling? People who are in a good mood are more likely to jump to conclusions about others and less likely to consciously correct any stereotypical notions they harbour. There you go people, want to be in 2020 still harbouring stereotypes? In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/222401249_On_being_happy_and_gullible_Mood_effects_on_skepticism_and_the_detection_of_deception&quot;&gt;2008 study&lt;/a&gt;, nearly 120 students were induced to feel amused, neutral, or sad (by watching a comedy video, a nature documentary, or a film clip about cancer). Then, they watched interrogation videos where other students lied or told the truth about stealing a movie ticket (yeah, they were very thorough). It was seen that the negative-mood group was better at detecting deception than the neutral or positive groups, correctly identifying the liars more often. So, you better keep your Kanye West on when trying to check if people are trying to pull one over you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon talking to a friend this morning about this ‘high school jock’, she expressed that feeling sad is when she feels the most creative. Feeling FOMO may actually foster a more proactive approach. What I’m trying to imply is that all of the rest feelings we’re constantly combating? They ain’t so bad! Instead, let’s look into how, when we express high levels of happiness, research suggests, we are &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.obhdp.2016.05.006&quot;&gt;perceived as more naive&lt;/a&gt; and are more likely to be targets of exploitation than when we express moderate happiness. This obviously explains why we wait for people to be in a good mood before we ask them for money, hoping that they won’t be as critical and careful in considering our request. Listen, the evolutionary psychologists have made a living off of telling us just what I’m trying to say- that other, less-blissful feelings serve a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are people who have an irrational aversion to being happy, they’re said to suffer from something called ‘cherophobia’, another term could be ‘hedonophobia’, which is defined as the fear of pleasure. This is not what yours truly is drawing upon, not at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you remember the very, very famous movie (that may be credited for the increased tourism in India) -* Eat, Pray, Love*? There was an entire monologue by Elizabeth, herself- “Happiness is the consequence of personal effort. You fight for it, strive for it, insist upon it, and sometimes even travel around the world looking for it, you have to participate relentlessly in the manifestations of your own blessings. And once you have achieved a state of happiness, you must make a mighty effort to keep swimming upward into that happiness forever, to stay afloat on top of it. If you don’t, you will leak away your innate contentment.” This chips at a person’s ability to ever feel okay about loneliness or personal failure. It reads to you that nothing except complete and absolute happiness is all one warrants. Downright absurd, right? People might set very high standards for their own happiness as a function of this view- they may think they should be happy all the time, or extremely happy, and that can set people up to feel disappointed with themselves, that they fall short- and that could have these self-defeating effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our world focuses on happiness and treats unhappiness as an unnecessary or useless feeling. In a 2017 article titled, “The Secret of Happiness, Feeling Good or Feeling Right,” published in the &lt;em&gt;Journal of Experimental Psychology General&lt;/em&gt;, 2,324 university students in eight countries were studied. The researchers found that people may be happier when they feel the emotions they desire, regardless of whether those desired emotions were pleasant or unpleasant. In other words, feeling our feelings is important, more so than whether they are positive or negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure I can use the word happy anymore, especially if you’ve been taking those shots this entire time. All I have to say is that if you were to play &lt;em&gt;Seinfeld&lt;/em&gt;’s S05E04 at 11:46:47, you will hear Kramer say, “here’s to feeling good all the time!” And let’s just remember, that’s not all there is to life.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">If you were to walk through my door today, I’d only welcome you with a question: Are you happy? I’m no Dr. Phil, it’s not so much as to check on your well-being (well, not completely), it is mostly to comprehend how happiness became the most important thing ever. Personally, I’ve come to a conclusion. Happiness is overrated and way too popular. Happiness is that jock in high school that everybody crushes on, but no one knows how to talk to. I can put a million researches here explaining how it all works: the biology, physiology, and all of the rest. But, why are we so attracted to the concept? What is this constant desire to be happy? And, pressure!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Highs and Lows</title>
      <link href="/Highs-and-Lows" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Highs and Lows" />
      <published>2019-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Highs-and-Lows</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Highs-and-Lows">&lt;p&gt;What questions do I bring forth today? What mundane instances caught my eye and left me high and dry? What search brought on a flurry of more searches? Well, today’s going to be a little different. In the past few weeks, I’ve found a multitude of things that I want to talk, write and think about, and I shall, soon enough, but today, I’m switching my tandem just a tad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, life’s been more Rocky Road and less Blueberry Swirl. Submerged under a mountainous pile of assignments - some pending and most, already doomed - a couple of really strenuous friendships and a moderately significant heartbreak, the painting seemed all too grey. And while that’s my favourite colour, I don’t prefer it in shades of life. And hence, I did what most suggest you do in times of need: sit, reflect, meditate, or better yet, run away to the hills or the beaches. So, I chose the latter and ran away - to older hills, for a couple of days, met a couple of new people, stayed in a hostel - even strayed away from social media. Phew, right? But, why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, it was just procrastination with a beautiful view and some good food and wine. But that isn’t the case for most, is it? An &lt;em&gt;Eat, Pray, Love&lt;/em&gt; escape is not warranted for all. I overheard a fellow dorm-mate say he had earned enough money to buy a big house, but he didn’t want to share it with anyone, so he packed his bags and lo and behold- has been travelling for the last 2 years. His joy and reflection almost made me feel guilty. I didn’t have a good enough reason, nothing as inspirational, nothing with foreshadow per se. Mostly just running away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people travel to challenge themselves - to run amok places one shouldn’t be able to, to jump off of cliffs, to rage in the adrenaline. Some travel with a specific goal. The goal being to learn something: a new dialect, a new cuisine, a different culture or to develop a deeper appreciation for faith or spirituality. Some do it with others to build stronger relationships, to strengthen their bonds. &lt;em&gt;Virtuoso&lt;/em&gt;, a popular travel magazine, named ‘Multigenerational Travel’ as the top trend of 2018. One may even move around to find new people to create new friendships, new bonds. Traveling seems like a gift that keeps giving. It expands your perspective, as seen in several eudaimonic travel experience researches. It helps us appreciate our lives, a little more than usual. It also is the reason you can come home and excuse a picture of your room, on your Instagram, with a gif - home sweet home. On note of that, it also makes you InstaPopular (but that’d be very shallow of me to add, so excuse me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you may think why is this girl jabbering on and on about one trip and how travel is the boon of our existence? Truthfully? I am not so sure. All I had in my head when I started this off was why is it that people suggest traveling when one is sad, or not having the best time. I understand a change of view may bring a change of heart, or how looking at others’ challenges may bring in a better perspective for your own, or how just taking a break must feel amazing. Hell, there’s so much to see, why must there be a reason to feast your eyes? I’m only looking for this socialised understanding’s bare roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year millions of people leave all that they have, in order to see the world; some in joy, some out of worry, some because there’s no other option. If you’ve watched &lt;em&gt;Parts Unknown&lt;/em&gt;, I’m sure Bourdain made you feel all kinds of joy. I distinctly remember him saying in an episode shot in Tangier, Morocco: “I’ve always wanted to get as far away as possible from the place that I was born. Far both geographically and spiritually. To leave it behind.” While this might seem contrary to the inherent human desire to fit into a tribe, to have a close community, it does reflect a state of being less understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a thousand and one songs - all talking about how one wants to fly away, zoom into sunsets, never to be back - leave it all behind. And while, I’d say most people would love to open their hair, wear 90’s glasses, drive a Camaro along the LA coast, I’m not sure the romanticisation of going away is healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, no part of me can say that I didn’t have a good time. I understand and recognise my privilege at being able to plan a trip to a place and visit it all in about 24 hours. I feel lucky to have seen all that I did and experience all that I experienced. What expunges my certainty of how good all this is - how to let go of the nuisances in your life just by going to a scenic place? I can’t say that when I sat there, listening to a fellow person play the ukulele, sipping my blessed coffee, staring at snow-capped mountains - that I didn’t forget all there was to forget. Sure, I did. But, for how long? And honestly, if I were to forget it all anyway, wouldn’t that be worse? Pathway to repression? Not Disney perfect, albeit Disney recommended. Suppression, the conscious forcing of unwanted thoughts, memories, or feelings out of conscious awareness, more apropos than repression in this scenario, leads to bottling up of feelings and emotions and inability to deal with misgivings in the long run. If used in the right fashion, it may be beneficial, but everytime one is given the chance to run away instead of dealing with something, they miss out on learning. Not to mention, suppression requires that we focus our mind on a negative emotion. By suppressing a feeling of anger, we start worrying about feeling angry, which attaches us to the emotion and heats up our mind and costs us extra energy. A cycle that maybe never ending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I’m not saying don’t go around the world and explore, I implore that you don’t run away from something to look at these otherworldly scenes. I suggest that you deal with all the uglies at hand and then go around looking for beauty. To be what you really want to be, you need to accustom yourself to the steps underneath. Well, that’s all I got today. Thanks for coming to my TED Talk.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">What questions do I bring forth today? What mundane instances caught my eye and left me high and dry? What search brought on a flurry of more searches? Well, today’s going to be a little different. In the past few weeks, I’ve found a multitude of things that I want to talk, write and think about, and I shall, soon enough, but today, I’m switching my tandem just a tad.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
