<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/poorvi.gupta/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-09-21T16:28:11+01:00</updated>
  <id>/author/poorvi.gupta/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Clean Sheet and a Cleaner Mind</title>
      <link href="/A-Clean-Sheet-and-a-Cleaner-Mind" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Clean Sheet and a Cleaner Mind" />
      <published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-07-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Clean-Sheet-and-a-Cleaner-Mind</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Clean-Sheet-and-a-Cleaner-Mind">&lt;p&gt;The months of June and July provided a shade from the exhaustion of the lockdown in the guise of various sporting events, ironically, despite being the hottest months of the year. They brought with them a momentary respite and distraction from the overbearing pandemic and the disconcerting healthcare crisis around the world. The much anticipated Euro Cup 2020 was the highlight of this summer, with new records being made and new players and teams taking the centre stage after what seemed like a long wait.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those two hours at night, people across the world would leave their chores, rush through dinner or complete assignments in haste so that they could give their undivided attention to the game. For those few hours, they would forget about their surroundings and become one with the spirit of the game and diffuse with the energy in the room.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It almost works like alchemy, the allure of sports. As someone who started watching football not so long ago, I have come to two deductions. Firstly, the 20 long years of my life wherein I did not take out enough time for sports have been wasted on the endorphins I could have brimmed with. Secondly, sports, especially football is a festival of emotions for which you do not need expert knowledge or an undying allegiance to a team to enjoy but simply a fervour to follow it through till the end.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to appreciate this game for what it is - a collection of moments that are so fleeting that you have no time to waste on temporal matters but focus wholeheartedly on the game. You sit down in front of a big screen with a tub of popcorn and a cold beverage (pro tip: avoid hot drinks in and around a room where a feisty match is on the go) and for the next two hours you forget about the deadlines, or a fight with your partner, or your family’s daily dysfunctionality, and even maybe that you're amid a pandemic and that life has come to a standstill for the most part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those two hours, you do not take it one day at a time, you do not take deep breaths and think about how the pieces of your life will fall into place, but you dive deep as all the bets are off. You feel like you’re going through a ridge of crests and troughs, but you don't mind the troughs because those little moments, good or bad, is what sums up the experience of this sport into something wholesome. It is somehow okay even through the lows because you risked it all when you started to watch the game- accepting its outcome for the sheer journey of it all. It is sufficient to say that it is therapeutic to see those players make their lives’ commitment and devotion come alive in a matter of seconds.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey of a spectator is anything but linear for the period of a football match - it is chaotic and intense. To think of the journey of the players - out on the field, flowing, flying, heaving and yearning has to be an enigmatic experience - one that we can only speculate, assess and discuss but never actualise.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final of the Euros was a pivotal event for both Italy and England. Italy went from plummeting to their bottom in 2018 when they did not even qualify for the World Cup to successfully lifting the championship trophy of Euro Cup 2020. Historical giants of the footballing world not qualifying for the World Cup of 2018 was as close to sacrilege for their team and Italy's fans as it could've been.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Italy lost its zeal, some players retired and some just left due to the backlash that they faced from their fans and their counterparts. Italy went through their worst phase brought about by a lack of driven players, direction, ideology, and dismal management. Until they found their way back to their calling, led by their manager Roberto Mancini who turned their trajectory by 180 degrees, back toward their ascent. With his tactics and shrewd man-management, he ignited the dying fire and passion in those players, manifested in their unmatched grit and determination during the Euro 2020 season.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When no one expected anything from Italy, they changed the face of the game, their retired players came back to fight and they proved to be the dark horses of the season. It was a historic and beautiful victory for Italy, finally after all their hard work. It was a classic case of rising from the ashes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As important as this victory was for Italy, it was also a watershed game for England who made it to the finals for the first time in 60 years, since the Cup commenced their games in 1960. For a team who hadn't even made it to the finals before, this was a glorious moment for them to 'bring it home’ as the world chanted on. England had reached the semi-finals and quarter-finals in the previous years but never made it past that, losing quite a few games during the penalty shoot-outs in those instances. Thus, one can imagine how terribly fraught this moment must have been for the players badged with the three lions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happened during the penalty shoot out was unfortunate for England due to their history with penalties and the pressure of the moment, but what happened after the match was even more pitiful - the backlash and violence at the stadium by the English fans, who publicly booed the Italian national anthem first and then caused a ruckus with policemen and other supporters in a post-match rage. Racist slurs were hurled at the three players who missed the penalty shootout. Bukayo Saka, 19 (one of the youngest players on the England squad), Marcus Rashford and Jadon Sancho were the three players who were subjected to unfairly carrying on the burden of England’s defeat and faced the brunt of the English audience’s racist and insensitive reaction. It goes on to show the ignorance and bias still entrenched in people’s minds about race. Makes you wonder if all the acceptance is just a perfunctory act.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is by no means justified to have to face the kind of abuse that these players did, even if they missed the penalty. It is easy to rebuke sportspersons for missing a shot but what the spectators don't realise is the trepidation that is induced by these heavy moments of &lt;em&gt;do or die&lt;/em&gt;, where one shot of yours will decide the fate of not just your team but your entire country. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://believeperform.com/the-effect-of-anxiety-on-world-cup-penalty-shootouts/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt;, such moments in a penalty shootout may lead to footballers experiencing symptoms of anxiety. Some commonly occurring symptoms are increases in muscle tension affecting coordination and an increase in heart rate and sweating. Psychologically, anxiety can cause concentration changes such as loss of awareness due to mental tension or poor selective perception. The weakening physiological and attentional changes that occur are the factors that can lead to ‘choking’ in the moment. Imagine your stage fright or nervousness in a new social situation and multiply that by a hundred and maybe then you'll begin to fathom the mental state of a person in such a situation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rashford faced a deluge of slander on his Instagram and people went so far ahead as to even destroy his mural in his own home country, a country wherein he excelled not just in football but even outside the field. This is a man who has done so much good for society and even received The Most Excellent Order of the British Empire award for his efforts to tackle food poverty among vulnerable children, especially during the pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not that it matters that he did all of this, even if he hadn’t, there is no cop-out for the abuse. But this is to say how racial abuse still affects one’s life. Wherever you reach, however much you do, the so-called ‘privileged’ race, class, or gender will always find ways to bring you down. The xenophobic and rowdy behaviour of the English fans was abhorrent in ways ineffable. Even though these racist remarks were received with intolerance and chide from many people across the world, who stood with these players through staunch social media support and protests near Rashford’s mural, we are still far from the response these players and many others deserve from the world football community and association. This is just one case that came to light because of the enormity of the game's scale, but such petty racism is still prevalent in every corner of this world's football fields. To not let another Rashford, Saka or Sancho feel this disparaged and harassed, the world needs to put their foot down and refuse to tolerate such immature cowards in the guise of bullies. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The months of June and July provided a shade from the exhaustion of the lockdown in the guise of various sporting events, ironically, despite being the hottest months of the year. They brought with them a momentary respite and distraction from the overbearing pandemic and the disconcerting healthcare crisis around the world. The much anticipated Euro Cup 2020 was the highlight of this summer, with new records being made and new players and teams taking the centre stage after what seemed like a long wait.&amp;nbsp; For those two hours at night, people across the world would leave their chores, rush through dinner or complete assignments in haste so that they could give their undivided attention to the game. For those few hours, they would forget about their surroundings and become one with the spirit of the game and diffuse with the energy in the room.&amp;nbsp; It almost works like alchemy, the allure of sports. As someone who started watching football not so long ago, I have come to two deductions. Firstly, the 20 long years of my life wherein I did not take out enough time for sports have been wasted on the endorphins I could have brimmed with. Secondly, sports, especially football is a festival of emotions for which you do not need expert knowledge or an undying allegiance to a team to enjoy but simply a fervour to follow it through till the end.&amp;nbsp; You need to appreciate this game for what it is - a collection of moments that are so fleeting that you have no time to waste on temporal matters but focus wholeheartedly on the game. You sit down in front of a big screen with a tub of popcorn and a cold beverage (pro tip: avoid hot drinks in and around a room where a feisty match is on the go) and for the next two hours you forget about the deadlines, or a fight with your partner, or your family’s daily dysfunctionality, and even maybe that you're amid a pandemic and that life has come to a standstill for the most part. For those two hours, you do not take it one day at a time, you do not take deep breaths and think about how the pieces of your life will fall into place, but you dive deep as all the bets are off. You feel like you’re going through a ridge of crests and troughs, but you don't mind the troughs because those little moments, good or bad, is what sums up the experience of this sport into something wholesome. It is somehow okay even through the lows because you risked it all when you started to watch the game- accepting its outcome for the sheer journey of it all. It is sufficient to say that it is therapeutic to see those players make their lives’ commitment and devotion come alive in a matter of seconds.&amp;nbsp; The journey of a spectator is anything but linear for the period of a football match - it is chaotic and intense. To think of the journey of the players - out on the field, flowing, flying, heaving and yearning has to be an enigmatic experience - one that we can only speculate, assess and discuss but never actualise.&amp;nbsp; The final of the Euros was a pivotal event for both Italy and England. Italy went from plummeting to their bottom in 2018 when they did not even qualify for the World Cup to successfully lifting the championship trophy of Euro Cup 2020. Historical giants of the footballing world not qualifying for the World Cup of 2018 was as close to sacrilege for their team and Italy's fans as it could've been.&amp;nbsp; Italy lost its zeal, some players retired and some just left due to the backlash that they faced from their fans and their counterparts. Italy went through their worst phase brought about by a lack of driven players, direction, ideology, and dismal management. Until they found their way back to their calling, led by their manager Roberto Mancini who turned their trajectory by 180 degrees, back toward their ascent. With his tactics and shrewd man-management, he ignited the dying fire and passion in those players, manifested in their unmatched grit and determination during the Euro 2020 season.&amp;nbsp; When no one expected anything from Italy, they changed the face of the game, their retired players came back to fight and they proved to be the dark horses of the season. It was a historic and beautiful victory for Italy, finally after all their hard work. It was a classic case of rising from the ashes.&amp;nbsp; As important as this victory was for Italy, it was also a watershed game for England who made it to the finals for the first time in 60 years, since the Cup commenced their games in 1960. For a team who hadn't even made it to the finals before, this was a glorious moment for them to 'bring it home’ as the world chanted on. England had reached the semi-finals and quarter-finals in the previous years but never made it past that, losing quite a few games during the penalty shoot-outs in those instances. Thus, one can imagine how terribly fraught this moment must have been for the players badged with the three lions.&amp;nbsp; What happened during the penalty shoot out was unfortunate for England due to their history with penalties and the pressure of the moment, but what happened after the match was even more pitiful - the backlash and violence at the stadium by the English fans, who publicly booed the Italian national anthem first and then caused a ruckus with policemen and other supporters in a post-match rage. Racist slurs were hurled at the three players who missed the penalty shootout. Bukayo Saka, 19 (one of the youngest players on the England squad), Marcus Rashford and Jadon Sancho were the three players who were subjected to unfairly carrying on the burden of England’s defeat and faced the brunt of the English audience’s racist and insensitive reaction. It goes on to show the ignorance and bias still entrenched in people’s minds about race. Makes you wonder if all the acceptance is just a perfunctory act.&amp;nbsp; It is by no means justified to have to face the kind of abuse that these players did, even if they missed the penalty. It is easy to rebuke sportspersons for missing a shot but what the spectators don't realise is the trepidation that is induced by these heavy moments of do or die, where one shot of yours will decide the fate of not just your team but your entire country. According to research, such moments in a penalty shootout may lead to footballers experiencing symptoms of anxiety. Some commonly occurring symptoms are increases in muscle tension affecting coordination and an increase in heart rate and sweating. Psychologically, anxiety can cause concentration changes such as loss of awareness due to mental tension or poor selective perception. The weakening physiological and attentional changes that occur are the factors that can lead to ‘choking’ in the moment. Imagine your stage fright or nervousness in a new social situation and multiply that by a hundred and maybe then you'll begin to fathom the mental state of a person in such a situation.&amp;nbsp; Rashford faced a deluge of slander on his Instagram and people went so far ahead as to even destroy his mural in his own home country, a country wherein he excelled not just in football but even outside the field. This is a man who has done so much good for society and even received The Most Excellent Order of the British Empire award for his efforts to tackle food poverty among vulnerable children, especially during the pandemic.&amp;nbsp; Not that it matters that he did all of this, even if he hadn’t, there is no cop-out for the abuse. But this is to say how racial abuse still affects one’s life. Wherever you reach, however much you do, the so-called ‘privileged’ race, class, or gender will always find ways to bring you down. The xenophobic and rowdy behaviour of the English fans was abhorrent in ways ineffable. Even though these racist remarks were received with intolerance and chide from many people across the world, who stood with these players through staunch social media support and protests near Rashford’s mural, we are still far from the response these players and many others deserve from the world football community and association. This is just one case that came to light because of the enormity of the game's scale, but such petty racism is still prevalent in every corner of this world's football fields. To not let another Rashford, Saka or Sancho feel this disparaged and harassed, the world needs to put their foot down and refuse to tolerate such immature cowards in the guise of bullies.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Work Hard, Pay Hard</title>
      <link href="/Work-Hard-Pay-Hard" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Work Hard, Pay Hard" />
      <published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Work-Hard-Pay-Hard</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Work-Hard-Pay-Hard">&lt;p&gt;On my way to university, I heard two women chatting beside me on the train and I couldn't help but eavesdrop at the horrors exchanged in their dialogue. They were engrossed in discussing or rather denouncing the daughter-in-law of one of their acquaintances for her values and time devoted to her family. From what I heard, they believed that she doesn't contribute much to the household chores as she continues to work after marriage (a heinous crime apparently) and comes home late. One of them said that this is bound to happen when women study too much.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This made me spiral into thinking about what most women, both married or unmarried, but mostly married, living with huge families and kids go through. They work from 9-5 or more I assume, complete their chores, handle their kids and still are not compensated enough for the same, be it the remuneration at their jobs in terms of money or the healthcare and safety provisions, and, on top of that, they are conveniently expected to undertake relentless unpaid work at home.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after all the effort that women put in every sphere of life, they still earn less respect and salary than their male counterparts for the same job, irrespective of their qualification and experience, contingent merely on their gender. &lt;em&gt;Because women are child-bearers and menstruators who expect the bare minimum of maternity and period leaves as an employee. Because women can't lead teams as capably as their male counterparts, since they aren't dominant by birth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This led me to realise that the gender-pay-gap is one of the most exploitative and discriminative features of our economic systems staring us in the face. One would expect a better system of rewards based on one’s merit and calibre, but even in the 21st century only six countries in the world, namely, Belgium, Denmark, France, Latvia, Luxembourg and Sweden grant men and women equal legal work rights, which is a concept as old as only a decade, according to a report by &lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even so, bringing about legal changes does not translate into effective actions. In Sweden, women still earn about 5% less than their male counterparts and, globally, women earn 79 cents for every dollar paid to a man - which might not sound like a huge gap in theory but again, this is just a statistic which might not even reflect the actual situation flailing about in our system. It might not even consider the many women who are employed in the informal sectors of developing countries or are labouring away in the agricultural-sector without reaping any significant benefits out of it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wage gap exists for women of all educational backgrounds - from high school graduates to women with advanced degrees. According to a report by the Economic Policy Institute, this gap ranges from three dollars for women having an education level of less than high school to twelve dollars for women with advanced degrees. This is the opposite of what one would expect and a strong argument against how gender-wage-gap stems from the lower education levels of women. The gap only widens as the level of education increases, which is testament to the fact that the more literate and intelligent the woman, the more of a threat she is made out to be.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this bias is not limited to merely the pecuniary aspect of the work culture; it is deeply embedded in how women are treated in offices, always put on a rung lower than men, listened to but never heard or appreciated. From bearing the ‘motherhood penalty’ to being biologically ‘complicated’, women around the world are stifled at every step of their way to success. A recent American study deduced the average by which women’s future wages fall—at 4% per child, and 10% for the highest-earning, most skilled white women.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women are considered assets as long as they do not ask for anything that lies outside the zone of anyone's convenience - be it providing maternity leaves or transportation for late work hours. And are also looked at like a nuisance for any lawsuits and uncomfortable conversations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the famous #MeToo movement, many companies and men in position suggested that hiring a woman nowadays can prove to be a risky investment because everything these days leads to lawsuits. Blaming the MeToo movement, many men claim that they are afraid to be alone with women in the workspace or hesitant to be around in their close vicinity - which is a complete rationalisation of the actions that are not okay in any workspace. And these men flagrantly choose to ignore that the issue doesn’t lie in women’s capability to live by the rules created by men but in men’s inability to treat them like human beings with boundaries that are to be respected.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zomato, a food-delivery service was one of the first major-league companies in India to grant paid period leaves - an action heavily slated by men. Even so, only bringing a policy in place doesn't seem enough to provoke a change because most women might be hesitant to take those leaves due to the pronounced stigma around menstruation and being considered weak and fragile for going through with it. Menstruation is not given enough medical importance, contingent on how potent its symptoms can be- from nausea and backache to stomach cramps that can invalidate any healthy and strong person. The hope is that with policies like these there is wider acceptance towards the gravity of this issue without it being used as a pretext for inequality or inferiority in the workplace.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though women are more substantially employed now, occupying more positions in the workspace than before especially in developed countries, the proportion of women in managerial and top executive positions still remains abysmally low and according to the Enterprise Survey by the World Bank, only 18% of businesses had a female CEO. On the other hand in legislatures, the proportion of women is approximately 24%. Women, in their entirety, comprise less than one-fourth of the major domains of the working world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue is not just gender-based discrimination but also discrimination against occupations that are majorly dominated by women. Professions of nurses, teachers, secretaries, child-care workers are found to be respected less and paid less too. According to a report by &lt;em&gt;The Economist&lt;/em&gt;, Primary teachers in the OECD countries earn 81% of the average for graduate jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This issue leads to a polarity in the jobs pursued by men and women and thus demotivates and intimidates women to take up jobs in the field of law and litigation, engineering and the police force. It is found that only 3.5% of women are firefighters, which is one of the most heavily male-dominated industries next to male technicians and mechanics who dominate 99.19% of the industry. Even something as universal as religion is dominated by men, according to &lt;em&gt;the Insider&lt;/em&gt;, only 17.6% of the clergy is female. And I am pretty sure this is not pertinent only to America but most of the world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, an important solution to gender-wage-gap is the migration of genders from female-dominated sectors to the male-dominated sectors and vice-versa. As important as it is for women to pursue fields that are considered too ambitious for them, it is equally imperative for men to be accepted in industries that are primarily governed by women. It is also important for the parental-care axle to shift from mothers, who drop out of the workforce or shift to less-intensive jobs to take care of their children to fathers, with a higher emphasis on the implementation of paternity leaves.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While discussing gender-based discrimination, to not consider the prejudice faced by trans people and other non-binary genders in the workplace would be unjust to the cause of equal wages for all. Trans people have even lesser representation and provisions to fall back on than women in the workplace and face persistent abuse and hiring-discrimination throughout the world, but more so in third-world and developing countries. Let alone provisions in the workplace, third-world countries like Kenya, Uganda, Senegal and Haiti do not even have basic anti-discriminatory laws for trans people. The transgender social acceptance rate, according to a report by Kimberly Tower is -2 whereas, in countries like India, Nepal and Argentina, it is positive yet wretchedly low, that is, 3, 2 and 1.5 respectively. Thus, there is still a long way to go for other genders to have equal remuneration and dignity as our &lt;em&gt;patriarchal lords&lt;/em&gt; in the workplace.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These statistics and facts only substantiate the actuality of domination of men in most sectors of the world, which leads to the gender-wage-gap. This majority that men enjoy in legislation, business or the sciences, is what propagates ideas, policies and products fabricated by men, which more often than not are not gender-friendly. Representation is salient as it leads to better targeted economic and social policies which will help bridge this widening gap and actualise acceptance - thus ameliorating the social and economic status of minority genders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On my way to university, I heard two women chatting beside me on the train and I couldn't help but eavesdrop at the horrors exchanged in their dialogue. They were engrossed in discussing or rather denouncing the daughter-in-law of one of their acquaintances for her values and time devoted to her family. From what I heard, they believed that she doesn't contribute much to the household chores as she continues to work after marriage (a heinous crime apparently) and comes home late. One of them said that this is bound to happen when women study too much.&amp;nbsp; This made me spiral into thinking about what most women, both married or unmarried, but mostly married, living with huge families and kids go through. They work from 9-5 or more I assume, complete their chores, handle their kids and still are not compensated enough for the same, be it the remuneration at their jobs in terms of money or the healthcare and safety provisions, and, on top of that, they are conveniently expected to undertake relentless unpaid work at home.&amp;nbsp; Even after all the effort that women put in every sphere of life, they still earn less respect and salary than their male counterparts for the same job, irrespective of their qualification and experience, contingent merely on their gender. Because women are child-bearers and menstruators who expect the bare minimum of maternity and period leaves as an employee. Because women can't lead teams as capably as their male counterparts, since they aren't dominant by birth.&amp;nbsp; This led me to realise that the gender-pay-gap is one of the most exploitative and discriminative features of our economic systems staring us in the face. One would expect a better system of rewards based on one’s merit and calibre, but even in the 21st century only six countries in the world, namely, Belgium, Denmark, France, Latvia, Luxembourg and Sweden grant men and women equal legal work rights, which is a concept as old as only a decade, according to a report by The Guardian.&amp;nbsp; Even so, bringing about legal changes does not translate into effective actions. In Sweden, women still earn about 5% less than their male counterparts and, globally, women earn 79 cents for every dollar paid to a man - which might not sound like a huge gap in theory but again, this is just a statistic which might not even reflect the actual situation flailing about in our system. It might not even consider the many women who are employed in the informal sectors of developing countries or are labouring away in the agricultural-sector without reaping any significant benefits out of it.&amp;nbsp; The wage gap exists for women of all educational backgrounds - from high school graduates to women with advanced degrees. According to a report by the Economic Policy Institute, this gap ranges from three dollars for women having an education level of less than high school to twelve dollars for women with advanced degrees. This is the opposite of what one would expect and a strong argument against how gender-wage-gap stems from the lower education levels of women. The gap only widens as the level of education increases, which is testament to the fact that the more literate and intelligent the woman, the more of a threat she is made out to be.&amp;nbsp; However, this bias is not limited to merely the pecuniary aspect of the work culture; it is deeply embedded in how women are treated in offices, always put on a rung lower than men, listened to but never heard or appreciated. From bearing the ‘motherhood penalty’ to being biologically ‘complicated’, women around the world are stifled at every step of their way to success. A recent American study deduced the average by which women’s future wages fall—at 4% per child, and 10% for the highest-earning, most skilled white women.&amp;nbsp; Women are considered assets as long as they do not ask for anything that lies outside the zone of anyone's convenience - be it providing maternity leaves or transportation for late work hours. And are also looked at like a nuisance for any lawsuits and uncomfortable conversations.&amp;nbsp; After the famous #MeToo movement, many companies and men in position suggested that hiring a woman nowadays can prove to be a risky investment because everything these days leads to lawsuits. Blaming the MeToo movement, many men claim that they are afraid to be alone with women in the workspace or hesitant to be around in their close vicinity - which is a complete rationalisation of the actions that are not okay in any workspace. And these men flagrantly choose to ignore that the issue doesn’t lie in women’s capability to live by the rules created by men but in men’s inability to treat them like human beings with boundaries that are to be respected.&amp;nbsp; Zomato, a food-delivery service was one of the first major-league companies in India to grant paid period leaves - an action heavily slated by men. Even so, only bringing a policy in place doesn't seem enough to provoke a change because most women might be hesitant to take those leaves due to the pronounced stigma around menstruation and being considered weak and fragile for going through with it. Menstruation is not given enough medical importance, contingent on how potent its symptoms can be- from nausea and backache to stomach cramps that can invalidate any healthy and strong person. The hope is that with policies like these there is wider acceptance towards the gravity of this issue without it being used as a pretext for inequality or inferiority in the workplace.&amp;nbsp; Even though women are more substantially employed now, occupying more positions in the workspace than before especially in developed countries, the proportion of women in managerial and top executive positions still remains abysmally low and according to the Enterprise Survey by the World Bank, only 18% of businesses had a female CEO. On the other hand in legislatures, the proportion of women is approximately 24%. Women, in their entirety, comprise less than one-fourth of the major domains of the working world.&amp;nbsp; The issue is not just gender-based discrimination but also discrimination against occupations that are majorly dominated by women. Professions of nurses, teachers, secretaries, child-care workers are found to be respected less and paid less too. According to a report by The Economist, Primary teachers in the OECD countries earn 81% of the average for graduate jobs. This issue leads to a polarity in the jobs pursued by men and women and thus demotivates and intimidates women to take up jobs in the field of law and litigation, engineering and the police force. It is found that only 3.5% of women are firefighters, which is one of the most heavily male-dominated industries next to male technicians and mechanics who dominate 99.19% of the industry. Even something as universal as religion is dominated by men, according to the Insider, only 17.6% of the clergy is female. And I am pretty sure this is not pertinent only to America but most of the world.&amp;nbsp; Thus, an important solution to gender-wage-gap is the migration of genders from female-dominated sectors to the male-dominated sectors and vice-versa. As important as it is for women to pursue fields that are considered too ambitious for them, it is equally imperative for men to be accepted in industries that are primarily governed by women. It is also important for the parental-care axle to shift from mothers, who drop out of the workforce or shift to less-intensive jobs to take care of their children to fathers, with a higher emphasis on the implementation of paternity leaves.&amp;nbsp; While discussing gender-based discrimination, to not consider the prejudice faced by trans people and other non-binary genders in the workplace would be unjust to the cause of equal wages for all. Trans people have even lesser representation and provisions to fall back on than women in the workplace and face persistent abuse and hiring-discrimination throughout the world, but more so in third-world and developing countries. Let alone provisions in the workplace, third-world countries like Kenya, Uganda, Senegal and Haiti do not even have basic anti-discriminatory laws for trans people. The transgender social acceptance rate, according to a report by Kimberly Tower is -2 whereas, in countries like India, Nepal and Argentina, it is positive yet wretchedly low, that is, 3, 2 and 1.5 respectively. Thus, there is still a long way to go for other genders to have equal remuneration and dignity as our patriarchal lords in the workplace.&amp;nbsp; These statistics and facts only substantiate the actuality of domination of men in most sectors of the world, which leads to the gender-wage-gap. This majority that men enjoy in legislation, business or the sciences, is what propagates ideas, policies and products fabricated by men, which more often than not are not gender-friendly. Representation is salient as it leads to better targeted economic and social policies which will help bridge this widening gap and actualise acceptance - thus ameliorating the social and economic status of minority genders.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Retelling of Childhood</title>
      <link href="/A-Retelling-of-Childhood" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Retelling of Childhood" />
      <published>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Retelling-of-Childhood</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Retelling-of-Childhood">&lt;p&gt;All of us have grown up with stories and tales aplenty - that our parents, grandparents and older siblings used to read to us. I had a little corner in my chest of drawers where I kept my A-3 sized colourfully illustrated books about the &lt;em&gt;Little Mermaid, Beauty and the Beast, Thumbelina, Cinderella&lt;/em&gt; and many others. I would take out one copy of those thin, 15-paged books and ask someone to read them to me or even give it a go at reading myself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a kid, I was fascinated with that world and maybe still haven’t lost my touch with it - because who doesn’t enjoy a good Disney&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;movie and some hot chocolate to go with it? Disney&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;is one such institution that has cemented and eternalised the stories that were written hundreds of years ago for children, now told and retold through years, they have changed into a different form - liked by people of all age groups.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A while back, I came across the writer behind these beloved stories - Hans Christian Anderson. Even though he revolutionised the world of storytelling through his selected works like - &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;em&gt; The Snow Queen &lt;/em&gt;(now adapted into the Disney production of &lt;em&gt;Frozen&lt;/em&gt;) and&lt;em&gt; The Ugly Duckling &lt;/em&gt;- his work is criticised for being unfit for children. Now that his work, that dates back to 1835, has been adapted into so many plays, productions and movies, one would think that he used to write perfect fairy tales for a blissful childhood. However, the truth is a bit far from that. Anderson is known for his dark and bitter tales that were written for children but without any filters - just blatant truth and atrocities staring oneself in the face.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anderson was born and raised in Denmark in a poor family to a shoemaker father and an illiterate washerwoman mother. Still, he persisted with his education at the local school for the poor, and at night used to listen to the tales of the &lt;em&gt;Arabian Nights&lt;/em&gt; from his father. He had a rough go at childhood and had to move out and provide for himself at an early age - the pain of which is reflected in his early-written pieces. The first and original edition of his stories is unlike the retold versions of them in many ways. For starters, his stories were not as happy-go-lucky as we see them now to be. &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt;, a classic tale of love and redemption, was actually a disturbing and morbid tale about a mermaid who makes a diabolical bargain with a sea witch and suffers her tongue to be cut out and her tail to be lost, all for the love of a prince. Unfortunately, he completely fails to recognise the enormity of her sacrifice and love for him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Disney film adaption of this tale was morphed into a story about love which always unites, as Ariel and Eric get together in the end, and she leaves her world to be with him. Even though Anderson’s story was bitter, it was realistic because it told you that life doesn’t always give you what or whom you desire, and that it’s not okay to give up your life and the things that make you who you are for anyone - because that never ends well. It reflected that no sacrifice will get you eternal love but maybe patience, time and consent would. Even the tale of &lt;em&gt;Thumbelina&lt;/em&gt; was that of grave pain and a torturous existence, unlike the popular idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might not have understood that as a kid, but if something is repeatedly told, from a young age then it can have an impact on you in many ways. The debate around protecting kids from bad and traumatic things is acceptable and justified, but only as long as the truth is harmful to them. If not, even kids have a right to be exposed to the right and wrong of life, to disappointment and failure - so that they learn to take something from it instead of thinking of it as the end. A lot of Anderson’s stories were changed for this reason alone. Because his stories did not twist the truth into entangled sentences about a utopian world but told them things that everyone should know - the reality of this harsh world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only Anderson’s, but many of children’s tales and stories are moulded according to what adults deem right; in fact, some are banned or censored too. A children’s book by the name of &lt;em&gt;And Tango Makes Three&lt;/em&gt; written by Parnell and Richardson was published in 2005, after a real-life incident that occurred in the Central Park Zoo of New York, where two male, chinstrap penguins, Roy and Silo fell in love. The book tells the story of these two male penguins who&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;create a family together. With the help of the zookeeper, Mr Gramsay, Roy and Silo are given an egg which they help hatch. The female chick, that completes their family, is consequently named 'Tango' by the zookeepers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book wasn’t received well by many parents, because according to them, homosexuality in animals suggested homosexuality in humans as well. They argued that they weren’t able to explain to their kids as to why “&lt;em&gt;a male penguin has a baby with another male penguin instead of a mommy penguin&lt;/em&gt;”. After retaliation from parents across the world, the book was consequently banned in Singapore, Hong Kong and places across the United States, like Utah, Missouri and Massachusetts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ql-cursor&quot;&gt;﻿It is these ingrained notions and our discomfort with the truth that anything different from what we consider ‘normal’, we try to hide from kids instead of having a conversation with them which they might be completely open to.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;p&gt;The question that wavers in my mind is, ‘how much of reality is too much’ to be introduced to children? The reason those stories were changed is that it was considered unfit and inappropriate for a child’s brains. Which might be true from one vantage point, however, why must children be veiled from the realities of the world until a certain age only to be exposed to them suddenly at one go? What is really the right age to see the world in its face?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve always wondered how fair it is to concoct a picture of a world that only disappoints you when you grow up. One, it creates unreal expectations from the world and two, it teaches you things that should be shattered as a concept early on while growing up - be it a princess being saved by the valiant hero at the end, kissing someone without their consent (&lt;em&gt;The Sleeping Beauty&lt;/em&gt;) or having to be perfect for people to like you.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I go back and forth in my mind as to why we think of children as weak or want to shield them from the truth? According to many child psychologists, the impulse to protect kids from unpleasant facts is similar to the self-esteem fad practised by educators. The idea rests on the assumption, not backed by any evidence, that high self-esteem must lead to high academic achievement. Similarly, the instinct to protect children from anything unpleasant is simply out of one’s idea of what a child should and shouldn’t know.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But if one asks themselves, is this reality protecting your child from long-term pain or is just an area of discussion that you don’t want to deal with, or better answer, and so you choose what is convenient - that is, to digress, to lie and to manoeuvre. You leave your children to figure out the jarring and upsetting realities of life by themselves as they grow up. And more often than not, the sources through which your children consume all the things that were hidden from them during their nascent years are not the most reliable or truthful sources. Thus, as we grow up, we are ambushed with facts and to find answers to them we tend to rely on treacherous sources which skew our ideas all the more. Instead of nurturing our kids with righteousness and practicality from the beginning, we try to mask them from facts, for as long as possible - which might not help them as much as one would hope.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The thing about the ‘real’ world is that unlike fairytales, it’s flawed and filled with imperfections. Which is what drives life ahead, the little or large hiccups in the flow of life. From Anderson’s stories to the truth about sexuality, identity, religion and relationships - a lot is made inconspicuous for the kids so that the information dissemination is controlled according to the norms that we have constructed and reaches them in a palatable form. But the question remains: who gets to decide what is right or wrong for these kids? Are flowery stories with morals sieved through our model of heteronormativity, appropriate culture and paradigms of acceptable behaviour the way to go about raising our kids? Only to impel them later into a world where they stumble as they go through life deconstructing their thoughts and knowledge, indoctrinated throughout childhood and then rebuilding it in a frenzy of emotions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wonder if it would’ve been better, had my parents read me stories of women who didn’t enforce ideals of self-sacrifice to find the truest form of love or tales of women and people in general, who didn’t settle for anything less than what they deserved, did not change themselves only to be accepted by society, and stories that told that life’s utmost purpose was not to find a perfect partner but to find yourself. And in the process of that, you will meet people who will make life worthwhile. But not one of the stories told us, that it is very much okay, even if you don’t. Because in life, there is no blueprint or algorithm like in stories - all the milestones of life are supposed to make your journey easier and not all the more pressurizing. So the moral of this article is maybe that it is okay to chart your own path - because if you find yourself not fitting in with any of the existing stories, you can always write a new one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">All of us have grown up with stories and tales aplenty - that our parents, grandparents and older siblings used to read to us. I had a little corner in my chest of drawers where I kept my A-3 sized colourfully illustrated books about the Little Mermaid, Beauty and the Beast, Thumbelina, Cinderella and many others. I would take out one copy of those thin, 15-paged books and ask someone to read them to me or even give it a go at reading myself.&amp;nbsp; As a kid, I was fascinated with that world and maybe still haven’t lost my touch with it - because who doesn’t enjoy a good Disney movie and some hot chocolate to go with it? Disney is one such institution that has cemented and eternalised the stories that were written hundreds of years ago for children, now told and retold through years, they have changed into a different form - liked by people of all age groups.&amp;nbsp; A while back, I came across the writer behind these beloved stories - Hans Christian Anderson. Even though he revolutionised the world of storytelling through his selected works like - The Little Mermaid, The Snow Queen (now adapted into the Disney production of Frozen) and The Ugly Duckling - his work is criticised for being unfit for children. Now that his work, that dates back to 1835, has been adapted into so many plays, productions and movies, one would think that he used to write perfect fairy tales for a blissful childhood. However, the truth is a bit far from that. Anderson is known for his dark and bitter tales that were written for children but without any filters - just blatant truth and atrocities staring oneself in the face.&amp;nbsp; Anderson was born and raised in Denmark in a poor family to a shoemaker father and an illiterate washerwoman mother. Still, he persisted with his education at the local school for the poor, and at night used to listen to the tales of the Arabian Nights from his father. He had a rough go at childhood and had to move out and provide for himself at an early age - the pain of which is reflected in his early-written pieces. The first and original edition of his stories is unlike the retold versions of them in many ways. For starters, his stories were not as happy-go-lucky as we see them now to be. The Little Mermaid, a classic tale of love and redemption, was actually a disturbing and morbid tale about a mermaid who makes a diabolical bargain with a sea witch and suffers her tongue to be cut out and her tail to be lost, all for the love of a prince. Unfortunately, he completely fails to recognise the enormity of her sacrifice and love for him. The Disney film adaption of this tale was morphed into a story about love which always unites, as Ariel and Eric get together in the end, and she leaves her world to be with him. Even though Anderson’s story was bitter, it was realistic because it told you that life doesn’t always give you what or whom you desire, and that it’s not okay to give up your life and the things that make you who you are for anyone - because that never ends well. It reflected that no sacrifice will get you eternal love but maybe patience, time and consent would. Even the tale of Thumbelina was that of grave pain and a torturous existence, unlike the popular idea. I might not have understood that as a kid, but if something is repeatedly told, from a young age then it can have an impact on you in many ways. The debate around protecting kids from bad and traumatic things is acceptable and justified, but only as long as the truth is harmful to them. If not, even kids have a right to be exposed to the right and wrong of life, to disappointment and failure - so that they learn to take something from it instead of thinking of it as the end. A lot of Anderson’s stories were changed for this reason alone. Because his stories did not twist the truth into entangled sentences about a utopian world but told them things that everyone should know - the reality of this harsh world. Not only Anderson’s, but many of children’s tales and stories are moulded according to what adults deem right; in fact, some are banned or censored too. A children’s book by the name of And Tango Makes Three written by Parnell and Richardson was published in 2005, after a real-life incident that occurred in the Central Park Zoo of New York, where two male, chinstrap penguins, Roy and Silo fell in love. The book tells the story of these two male penguins who create a family together. With the help of the zookeeper, Mr Gramsay, Roy and Silo are given an egg which they help hatch. The female chick, that completes their family, is consequently named 'Tango' by the zookeepers.&amp;nbsp; This book wasn’t received well by many parents, because according to them, homosexuality in animals suggested homosexuality in humans as well. They argued that they weren’t able to explain to their kids as to why “a male penguin has a baby with another male penguin instead of a mommy penguin”. After retaliation from parents across the world, the book was consequently banned in Singapore, Hong Kong and places across the United States, like Utah, Missouri and Massachusetts. ﻿It is these ingrained notions and our discomfort with the truth that anything different from what we consider ‘normal’, we try to hide from kids instead of having a conversation with them which they might be completely open to.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;The question that wavers in my mind is, ‘how much of reality is too much’ to be introduced to children? The reason those stories were changed is that it was considered unfit and inappropriate for a child’s brains. Which might be true from one vantage point, however, why must children be veiled from the realities of the world until a certain age only to be exposed to them suddenly at one go? What is really the right age to see the world in its face?&amp;nbsp;I’ve always wondered how fair it is to concoct a picture of a world that only disappoints you when you grow up. One, it creates unreal expectations from the world and two, it teaches you things that should be shattered as a concept early on while growing up - be it a princess being saved by the valiant hero at the end, kissing someone without their consent (The Sleeping Beauty) or having to be perfect for people to like you.&amp;nbsp;I go back and forth in my mind as to why we think of children as weak or want to shield them from the truth? According to many child psychologists, the impulse to protect kids from unpleasant facts is similar to the self-esteem fad practised by educators. The idea rests on the assumption, not backed by any evidence, that high self-esteem must lead to high academic achievement. Similarly, the instinct to protect children from anything unpleasant is simply out of one’s idea of what a child should and shouldn’t know.&amp;nbsp;But if one asks themselves, is this reality protecting your child from long-term pain or is just an area of discussion that you don’t want to deal with, or better answer, and so you choose what is convenient - that is, to digress, to lie and to manoeuvre. You leave your children to figure out the jarring and upsetting realities of life by themselves as they grow up. And more often than not, the sources through which your children consume all the things that were hidden from them during their nascent years are not the most reliable or truthful sources. Thus, as we grow up, we are ambushed with facts and to find answers to them we tend to rely on treacherous sources which skew our ideas all the more. Instead of nurturing our kids with righteousness and practicality from the beginning, we try to mask them from facts, for as long as possible - which might not help them as much as one would hope.&amp;nbsp;The thing about the ‘real’ world is that unlike fairytales, it’s flawed and filled with imperfections. Which is what drives life ahead, the little or large hiccups in the flow of life. From Anderson’s stories to the truth about sexuality, identity, religion and relationships - a lot is made inconspicuous for the kids so that the information dissemination is controlled according to the norms that we have constructed and reaches them in a palatable form. But the question remains: who gets to decide what is right or wrong for these kids? Are flowery stories with morals sieved through our model of heteronormativity, appropriate culture and paradigms of acceptable behaviour the way to go about raising our kids? Only to impel them later into a world where they stumble as they go through life deconstructing their thoughts and knowledge, indoctrinated throughout childhood and then rebuilding it in a frenzy of emotions.I wonder if it would’ve been better, had my parents read me stories of women who didn’t enforce ideals of self-sacrifice to find the truest form of love or tales of women and people in general, who didn’t settle for anything less than what they deserved, did not change themselves only to be accepted by society, and stories that told that life’s utmost purpose was not to find a perfect partner but to find yourself. And in the process of that, you will meet people who will make life worthwhile. But not one of the stories told us, that it is very much okay, even if you don’t. Because in life, there is no blueprint or algorithm like in stories - all the milestones of life are supposed to make your journey easier and not all the more pressurizing. So the moral of this article is maybe that it is okay to chart your own path - because if you find yourself not fitting in with any of the existing stories, you can always write a new one.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Stranded by the Sea</title>
      <link href="/Stranded-by-the-Sea" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stranded by the Sea" />
      <published>2020-08-27T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Stranded-by-the-Sea</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Stranded-by-the-Sea">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;Refugee&lt;/em&gt; is a term we read and hear about often, on the internet or the news and dissect into it like any other topic that we came across on a particular day. Be it the Syrian refugee crisis, the Afghanistan refugee crisis, people displaced in the Middle East fleeing to Europe for desperate rehabilitation, the partition of India or the result of a civil war. These are all issues originating in different parts of the world, delineated by boundaries and separated based on geography or the cause or origin of conflict. However, even though conflicts might vary in terms of nature- political, economic or social - it’s corollary remains immutable across borders and religion, that is, displacement of people and wreckage of homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve fled your country (or have been chased out by the majority population/authoritarian government), it’s nearly impossible to come back. The unsafe and riotous situation in certain countries caused by wars or feud creates conditions that make it fatal to a come back to a place they once called home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rohingya are one such community, facing persecution and fleeing from one place to another since 58 years, circa 1962.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of the persecution of the Rohingyas can be traced back to the colonization of India by the British, which endured for over 200 years. Tracing back to the British colonial period in the 1800’s, many people from India and Bangladesh were brought to Myanmar to work in the British led administration, doubling the Muslim community in Myanmar. This decision was received with acrimony by the local Myanmar people. This stands as one of the root cause of the animosity against the Rohingyas. During the World Wars, this hostility further deepened its roots since the majority of the Muslim population supported the British whereas the Buddhist population was predisposed towards the Japanese. This incongruity, as a result of the disparity between The Allies and The Axis Powers, aggravated the situation for the Muslim population in Myanmar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The official status of “refugee” is something the Rohingya people have struggled with for years now. In 1962, military rule became the norm and law throughout Myanmar. As a result, the Muslim population in Rakhine State was overpowered by militants and the Buddhist majority, thus causing the refugees to flee to Bangladesh. Since then, from 1962 to 2017 a large number of Rohingya people have migrated to the neighbouring countries, especially Bangladesh, having faced oppression in their own country. In 1982, an official Myanmar announcement declared 135 nationally recognized ethnic groups and the Rohingya were not included in the list, leaving them stateless and without citizenship. Further, in 2012 riots were waged against the Rohingyas and 200 people were killed while leaving 15,000 homeless and displaced. The Myanmar government even prohibited them from participating in the national census and the voting procedure during the elections. These acts of negligence, violence and repression continued till 2017 causing more than 600,000 Rohingya people to flee the Rakhine State since their communities were destroyed. But that doesn’t mean that things are any safer for them now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, there are some 860,000 Rohingya people seeking refuge in Bangladesh and at least 1.3 million people — Rohingya refugees and Bangladeshi host communities — who rely on humanitarian assistance to meet their basic needs. More than half of them are children. These populations live in desperately overcrowded camps and communities, highly vulnerable to oncoming monsoon and cyclone seasons, violence, sexual harassment and unhygienic environment. These camps provide them with less than the meagre amenities, leaving them to live a life of ignorance, in a vicious cycle of poverty, violence and substandard living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) and Médecins Sans Frontières (MSF) (also known as Doctors without Borders) describes the Rohingya as one of the most persecuted people in the world. The world we live in prides itself on its safety and peacekeeping system at the international level. Since after the Second World War, many nations came together and pledged to save vulnerable people and nations in crises. Yet, their (Rohingyas) struggle and oppression has been one of the most under-reported humanitarian crises in the world. The international media and community have practically ignored the situation of these people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all of this because of one reason, deeply entrenched in our parochial minds: ethnic animosity and conflict on the grounds of religion and historical beliefs of territory and ownership. This practice has left the Rohingya people without a beacon of hope for a better future. It has normalized a humanitarian crisis of this gravity, leading us to believe that it’s okay to treat a community of people with mindless hostility and utter disregard for their lives. (Because they might’ve done something to deserve it)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having faced persecution even in the camps of Bangladesh’s Cox Bazaar (and Myanmar, of course) the Rohingya people have made attempts to reach Malaysia, Thailand, Indonesia and other countries for years now. Since they lack visas, travel documents and are subjected to strict restrictions, boats are often the only option left for them to undertake transnational crossing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to MSF, it is estimated that around 167 countries across the world have fully or partially closed their borders during COVID-19 pandemic and 57 states made no exception for people seeking asylum. Even though closing borders is an acceptable reaction to the pandemic, not providing a concession for people looking for a refugee status amidst these tough times, stranded by the sea and in between nations is unacceptable. Countries such as Italy and Malta closed their ports for refugees and are using the excuse of the pandemic to reject refugees from entering their land and water borders. Several hundred Rohingyas fleeing persecution at home and refugee camps in Bangladesh have been stranded for months after countries sealed their borders to block the spread of the coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have reported that their relatives are stranded by the sea and their traffickers, holding hundreds of Rohingya refugees, are demanding money to release them from boats that have been off Southeast Asia since February, trying to find a place to land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Material cupidity has yet again taken precedence over humanity in a situation of a deadly life-crisis. The refugees travelling on these boats could hardly gather the money and documents to take this journey across the sea, and now with the pandemic having engulfed the world, they’re stuck on these boats, suffering, starving and seething in pain, waiting to get across any border to find some refuge and shelter from these treacherous circumstances. On top of this, they are being exploited for money in a situation of utmost helplessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To think why these people landed in such a chronic crisis, which has persisted for over five decades now; to think why we as a community allow and tolerate a humanitarian crisis at such a cosmic level. It is because somewhere deep down, we all have our own set of ideas and beliefs tied by social norms of caste, creed and culture. Because we all have ingrained the idea of &lt;em&gt;Us vs Them&lt;/em&gt;, so concretely in our heads that it’s almost impossible to break down those walls around us. But if there’s something that this pandemic has taught us, it’s that we’re all in this together. No problem is a standalone issue - it’s always linked to a larger affliction and it’s not outside the ambit of possibility for it to find its way to you. If we don’t untangle this issue as a community and for the community, it’ll always remain unresolved and will surface time and again.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A Refugee is a term we read and hear about often, on the internet or the news and dissect into it like any other topic that we came across on a particular day. Be it the Syrian refugee crisis, the Afghanistan refugee crisis, people displaced in the Middle East fleeing to Europe for desperate rehabilitation, the partition of India or the result of a civil war. These are all issues originating in different parts of the world, delineated by boundaries and separated based on geography or the cause or origin of conflict. However, even though conflicts might vary in terms of nature- political, economic or social - it’s corollary remains immutable across borders and religion, that is, displacement of people and wreckage of homes.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Amongst The Living: Review of the TV Series ‘After Life’</title>
      <link href="/Amongst-The-Living" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amongst The Living: Review of the TV Series 'After Life'" />
      <published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Amongst-The-Living</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Amongst-The-Living">&lt;p&gt;There’s no earthly medicine, nor any amount of therapy or escape from the grief that engulfs you completely from head to toe after the demise of a loved one, especially a spouse. Someone you’ve spent more than half of your life with and expected to share the rest of your old and fragile years, sprawled under the sun with a classic and some iced-tea. Someone who becomes not just a habit but as ingrained in your mind as muscle memory - the way a writer’s fingertips move across a keyboard, gliding through without a mere thought - as necessary as breathing and as easy too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Losing that person, (if you’re lucky enough to find them in the first place), is something I thought could not be expressed or filmed, but Ricky Gervais’ character Tony in &lt;em&gt;After Life&lt;/em&gt; did just that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tony, after losing his wife whom he was married to for 25 years had forgone the will to live. He had unabashedly submitted to death and wasn’t afraid of anything that was to come his way. He didn’t think death was the hard part anymore; it was life that stung him every day. In simpler terms - he wanted to die, or at least he thought he did. After several attempts at it, he still found himself waking up each morning to a hollow life - most times for his beloved dog Brandy whom he thought he couldn’t leave alone and other times to watch the videotapes of his wife from their bygone life. His day started with the clips of Lisa (his wife) talking and laughing, and he succumbed to sleep with them too. I think dying wasn’t a part of his plan at all, or he would have done that a long time back, and we wouldn’t have a two-season-long series of &lt;em&gt;After Life&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, his pain was equivalent to the effect that made him attempt to kill himself. When the series commenced, his attitude could be described in his own words as - &lt;em&gt;“Here’s what’s what: humanity is a plague. We’re a disgusting, narcissistic, selfish parasite, and the world would be a better place without us.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ricky Gervais is probably the only person who can turn a macabre series about death and depression into a heartwarming and hilarious tale of love and redemption that friendship can offer. Written, directed and starred by this multi-talented actor (who also wrote the original version of &lt;em&gt;The Office&lt;/em&gt; UK), you will find yourself on an inundating journey of emotions throughout this show. He normalises mourning, grief and depression in an unprecedented way. He tells us it’s okay to be wrought up because, &lt;em&gt;“We’re all screwed up in one way or the other, that’s what makes us normal.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often after we lose a loved one, we’re sympathised with for a while, maybe for a couple of months, but after that, you’re expected to move on with your normal life. But is there an end-date to the grief that death taints your heart with? You can move on from a bad-hair-day or a lull in your career, but how do you fill a hole cratered by death?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, in my opinion, you don’t. And that is one of the reasons I fell in love with this beautiful yet realistic show. It doesn’t end with a colossal epiphany where you find that life is still beautiful and move on, back to being the person you were, because you cannot ever go back to that version of yourself that you were - in this case, what he was with his wife. That part of him might exist somewhere passively but it was put to sleep with the person who brought it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People aren’t whole or made up of a monolithic tenor; people are the sum of their parts. Sometimes it does so happen that you might lose an irreplaceable part of yourself, and so did Tony. But he didn’t “move on” from his wife, just because she was no more with him. Even though he knew he had lost that part of himself to her, he accepted it. They were very slow days but he got there. He learnt to live a life without forgoing Lisa. Why do we have to let go of the things and the memories left behind by the demised anyway? Tony definitely didn’t because he believes “love is everything”  and that he had experienced the purest form of it; a love which won’t ever feel the same way again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the 2 seasons, he struggles with an impertinence of character and apathy for life. Tony lives in a fictional town of Tambury and writes for the local newspaper, &lt;em&gt;The Tambury Gazette&lt;/em&gt;. He works with his brother-in-law, opposite to him in nature, who stood by him throughout his journey of dealing with something that can be vaguely referred to as &lt;em&gt;life&lt;/em&gt;, after Lisa. Their newspaper showcases stories of the local people and their quirky, crazy little tales- from an old man who had been posting his letters in a dog-poop box, to a 50-year-old man who identifies as an 8-year-old girl (which according to his wife was clearly a nervous breakdown). Tony hates his job, including meeting all these people and recording their inane and frothy stories. But towards the turn of Season 1, this formerly despised routine makes his life just a tad more bearable for him. He starts relating to these people, realising that they are all either lonely or going through something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The keenness with which Gervais has worked on his characters individually is laudable. Each role brings something to the table, has a unique personality and contributes to pacifying Tony’s seething soul. Tony, who hated any social interaction, comes out of this vortex with a few special relationships. Be it the candid postman Pat (who clearly doesn’t understand boundaries), his coworker Sandy who looks up to him and shares a sweet relationship with him, his infirm father whom he visits daily or his father’s nurse Emma with whom unfolds an inexplicable relationship towards the culmination of the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The portrayal of his unbiased friendship with a sex worker who goes by the name of Roxy whom he met across the street unfurls into a sweet friendship, where she cares and worries for him a lot. He tells her that he sees a reflection of his wife in her; that even Lisa couldn’t go to sleep until everyone around her was okay. These little anecdotes, entwined in his memory is what keeps him going and concurrently pains him too. But these moments reinforce my faith in his undying love for his wife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of Season 2, Tony turns a corner and thinks that the least he can do is be a better person for the people he loves, who have constantly been there for him to rely on. He introspects as to how selfish he has been, and that life necessarily doesn’t need to be about him. If he doesn’t want to live for himself anymore, he can live for others, because &lt;em&gt;“we’re not just here for ourselves”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this had a lot to do with Anne, a woman he met at the graveyard, sitting at a bench close by, whom he found himself visiting everyday and sharing the tiniest, most banal parts of his day. She dressed his wounds with her kind and wise words, and a shared experience of losing her husband. She made him realise that the only way to heal is to let go of his anger for the world, that he can’t ever feel better again without being his intrinsically good self. She told him once that, &lt;em&gt;“Good people do things for other people. That’s it. The end.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you choose to watch this show, I promise you will laugh deliriously, even whilst questioning his coal-like dark humour and cry when he cries for no reason at all when old memories come gushing to him. Even though the development of his character through the two seasons is commendable and leaves you with a sense of warmth in your heart, you will feel this show hitting you hard because of the sheer reality that it emanates even amidst a fictional setting. After all the sadness, despair and the caustic humour, at the end you will agree with the writer on one thing at least - that &lt;em&gt;“hope is everything”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think &lt;em&gt;after life&lt;/em&gt; should be a word attributed to the living instead of the dead, in that once people leave; it is us who grapple to make peace with the reality of it all, amongst the living, in our &lt;strong&gt;After Life&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There’s no earthly medicine, nor any amount of therapy or escape from the grief that engulfs you completely from head to toe after the demise of a loved one, especially a spouse. Someone you’ve spent more than half of your life with and expected to share the rest of your old and fragile years, sprawled under the sun with a classic and some iced-tea. Someone who becomes not just a habit but as ingrained in your mind as muscle memory - the way a writer’s fingertips move across a keyboard, gliding through without a mere thought - as necessary as breathing and as easy too.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Tale of Two Words: Climate Change</title>
      <link href="/A-Tale-of-Two-Words-Climate-Change" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Tale of Two Words: Climate Change" />
      <published>2020-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Tale-of-Two-Words-Climate-Change</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Tale-of-Two-Words-Climate-Change">&lt;p&gt;There are ample things in the world- a mix of ideas, notions and facts that we dust off as ostensible, a fabricated theory or in the words of the President of the ‘Great’ nation of America, a &lt;em&gt;hoax&lt;/em&gt;. And what tops this list is the acknowledgement (or lack thereof) of climate change across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you set out to find how deep the reality of climate change has (or has not) seeped into our being, you’d probably roam forever like &lt;em&gt;Diogenes of Sinope&lt;/em&gt;, holding up a lamp to people’s face, looking for a solution, a solace. Diogenes claimed that people were trapped in this make-believe world which they thought to be real and hitherto were living in a dream state. Although this is a myth which dates back to 445-365 BCE (number of years I can’t even count), it oddly makes sense even today. He stood for something that went above and beyond the bar of normality of our society; he challenged the society and thus was termed a ‘Socrates gone mad’. Mad or &lt;em&gt;radical-liberalist&lt;/em&gt; is a term I hear almost every time I try to explain to someone how exigent the issue of climate change is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our society has tainted climate change as a secondary issue, an elitist issue that the first world countries fight for because there are more pressing issues around the world that third-world nations are grappling with- like hunger, poverty, unemployment and lack of healthcare. And I agree that these issues are foundational and require a country’s full attention- but whilst you’re making developmental plans and ignoring climate change, the world is becoming more predisposed to calamities, disasters and diseases, global warming is increasing alarmingly and destroying this intricately knit web that is our earth, one grain at a time. And what good is this cupidity that we’re after when you don’t have a planet good enough to inhabit anymore?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The famous &lt;em&gt;’12 years left’&lt;/em&gt; statement isn’t a hoax, a notion or an arbitrary idea that someone woke up to. It’s based on empirical calculations by scientists around the world who claim that to avoid a scourge on humanity we have to be on a realistic path toward a carbon-free global economy by 2030. People take this to mean that we can live freely without any delimitation till 2030 and start alleviating our output of hazardous emissions after that. However, to keep the global temperature from rising more than 1.5 degrees, countries would have to cut their carbon dioxide emissions to almost net-zero by around 2050. And to reach that goal, CO2 emissions would have to start dropping &lt;em&gt;“well before 2030”&lt;/em&gt; so that it falls close to 45 per cent by around 2030. Even though such thorough studies have been conducted and there is no shortage of scientific evidence that we need to &lt;em&gt;stop&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;listen&lt;/em&gt; to these words of caution if we want a future of any kind, let alone a sustainable one, many nations continue to live in climate science denial. President Trump is one of those many, who went so far ahead to claim that climate change was invented by China to disable American industry. (According to the very diffident American President every move of China alludes to a clandestine act towards the United States)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People turn a blind eye toward climate change, thinking how much it could possibly affect them. But the fact is that no one has the resources or the faculty to shield themselves from the wrath of climate change. It is biased to no one and would wipe out whatever comes in its way. The recent California wildfires, hurricane Dorian in the US, the Australian bushfire, and unprecedented heat waves sweeping Verkhoyansk- a Siberian town in the arctic circle weren’t a startling enough wake-up call for the world, because we continue to resort to our exploitative methods. Two of the most catastrophic cyclones hit India in the last couple of months, Amphan in Kolkata and Nisarga in Mumbai which was the worst cyclone to have hit the city of Mumbai since 1891.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The financial costs of these calamities aside, loss of flora and fauna and a colossal number of deaths reflect how the world’s poorest and most vulnerable pay the heaviest price for the consequences of climate change, be it the underprivileged in developing countries or the oppressed in first-world nations. It’s not just these drastic tragedies, but the actual danger can be traced from the little changes happening across the world as well, ranging from scorching heat waves in the northern parts of India worsening every year to a hail storm as closely tantamount to snow as the subtropical and semi-arid city of Delhi would’ve ever seen. It was enjoyed by the residents of the city, indifferent to how unnatural it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Climate change is not a stand-alone issue; it’s chained and linked to other societal maladies like a domino effect, be it infrastructure, economy or politics. This cyclic motion continues until we exert force to stop it, or at least ease it down. We’re now witnessing how humanity is paying a price for its benightedness over the last 200 years, since after the Industrial Revolution- as we have been driven by capitalism and materialism instead of welfare and rehabilitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After traversing halfway through a deadly pandemic, increased calamity, crime, racism and right-wing oppression, it’s time to stop and accept the fallacy in our system and pay our dues for the prolonged procrastination on accepting and abating climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can agree that climate change is here to stay. After hundreds of years of exploitation of resources and massive technological advancements that have left us wanting a life of ease and luxuries at the cost of our environment, nature cannot disappear into thin air. But the first step towards having a sustainable future would be to understand the gravity of this issue and not let it hang entirely on the shoulders of the Gen-Z. In recent decades, we’ve had to fight our own battle for a healthy world that we will potentially live in, that our forebears have set on fire, left for us to extinguish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Greta Thunberg, a 17-year-old soul, who deserves to be studying and living her life to the fullest, can leave her hedonic lifestyle and take to revolting on the streets for the right to have a sustainable future, then why can’t we support her and thousands of others fighting for the earth? If she can chant these two simple words and make them her anthem then how hard is it for our aged leaders to comprehend that this world that they want to dominate is withering one day at a time, and if climate change is not tamed now then all there will be left to reign over will be a kingdom of embers?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There are ample things in the world- a mix of ideas, notions and facts that we dust off as ostensible, a fabricated theory or in the words of the President of the ‘Great’ nation of America, a hoax. And what tops this list is the acknowledgement (or lack thereof) of climate change across the globe.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lockdown Diaries and the Smell of Strange Perfume</title>
      <link href="/Lockdown-Diaries" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lockdown Diaries and the Smell of Strange Perfume" />
      <published>2020-06-02T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Lockdown-Diaries</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lockdown-Diaries">&lt;p&gt;Dear Diary (are you still supposed to write that or is it totally outdated?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t know how to start; the last time I wrote to myself was in the eighth grade, when I wished desperately for the English exam to end, lest my hand fall off and I live without one with an awkward story to tell for as long as the world sustains. It’s not as weird as I thought it would be, honestly. I do talk to myself all the time, at 3 AM, wavering between what I should’ve said to some people two years back and all the possible ways that the world might end in (Armageddon is not left unconsidered, by the way).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pretty sure this time is hard for every living person on the surface of this planet, and I’m not in this alone. Sometimes, my problems seem like a tiny little whine when I open the news and read about the horrible things happening around; people trying to survive, to get food and just breathe every day, hoping the sun doesn’t set, because if it does, there is another day of suffering waiting for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whereas as soon as I wake up, I wait eagerly for the dusk, creating a mental picture of the day ahead in my head, trying to bring a sense of organisation and calm to this commotion that life has become. It is almost like an annoying traffic jam, cars glued to the ground, an utterly piercing horn in the background that isn’t ready to subside and your foot on the pedal trying to move your car one bit at a time, as much as you can, to get out of this rut so that you can finally glide onto the highway, roll down your windows and let the cool autumn breeze embrace you until it touches your feet and you feel like all is okay in the world again. I feel as if these days I’m just waiting for this jam to clear, so that I can take in that air again as I rush my car through the freeway, and go anywhere I want, no restrictions, just the journey and the destination ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I just romanticise a pandemic? I’m afraid so. Reading a little too much of Mitch Albom, watching a string of Jane Austen classic movies and smelling books and teas doesn’t make you a &lt;em&gt;cool&lt;/em&gt; millennial, I’m sure. Just your average old-school -person, who loves cardigans and sighs when they look at &lt;em&gt;tiktoks&lt;/em&gt;, referring to it as ‘these kids’ when you’re a 20-year-old yourself (or more like an 80-year-old woman stuck in a 20-year-old’s body).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even though I enjoy my old-person traits most days, it’s certainly hard to keep up with it when you live in the year 2020, jailed amidst the four walls of your room. The internet and social media isn’t a respite because you cannot for the life of you comprehend the conundrum that is #quarantineandchill or the Dalgona coffee trend? (I mean it’s just coffee upside down). I know that I have all the time in the world to read all those books and literary wonders that I keep crying about when I didn’t have enough time or listen to Sam Cooke all day and Paul McCartney the next. And it was all about those books, songs and heartwarming movies but only for a good four weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the fifth week started to unfold, I missed the smell of freshly roasted coffee that came wafting from the cafes that I walked past, pulling me towards themselves as the moon does to the tides - just simple laws of gravity. And that’s just not it. I miss my entire commute to university every day - waking up early yet late, at 7 am (yes that was sadly late) and crying about it, while I rush to get ready and catch a ride to the metro-station as my hair is soaking wet and I drench the marble floors of my house as I sprint around, trying to find my glasses and earphones. I would gulp my cold coffee whole, while my mother gave me a sniggering look for skipping breakfast and yet would sneak in a sandwich wrapped in aluminium foil in my bag when I wasn’t looking. I miss the morning breeze that air-dried my hair in the auto-rickshaw, while I fiddled with my earphones and rummaged through my playlist for a morning boost of Mumford and Sons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would give up all of the social media, yes, Instagram and Snapchat and whatever new application the kids are using these days for a train ride to college, filled with strangers, all so hurried, so hasty, to reach somewhere, pushing and fumbling through the metro - I would find an uncanny sense of calm in it. This uncertainty and muddled life has made me realize how much I also miss studying or skipping the first-morning class to hang out in the cafeteria instead with a cup of steaming coffee and half-forgotten anecdotes from old nights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it just me or does anyone else also miss the yellow and red flowers strewn about on the streets in March? It is not easy for a memory hoarder to get through these tough times without lapsing into nostalgia every other minute. Not easy for a person who loves stray discourses on politics, life, love, career and books over a cup of tea to text people and still have that fiery enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not undermining my privilege, for I know these aren’t the issues that matter in the least right now. But I think writing them down makes me feel a tad better - like I’m ranting to someone as I would in the &lt;em&gt;old days&lt;/em&gt;, if I may.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And like a true old-soul, these past three months have made me realize how much I enjoy my own company rather than texting away or relying on social media to get through the day. And I don’t think less of anyone who does that; whatever one finds their peace in. But it’s hard to blend in sometimes for monochromes in this vibrant world, when all you want is to cook yourself nice, steaming-hot banana bread and curl into your bed with a sad PDF. (I miss the smell of books).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think all I want is a redo sometimes. I know I couldn’t change anything; I couldn’t stop the pandemic because that is beyond my corporeal control. However, if I do get a redo, as I imagine- &lt;em&gt;I see myself standing at the jostling platform of Rajiv Chowk Metro Station in Delhi- people brushing past and into each other. I might be looking at them indifferently, as my earphones pulse to the tunes of The Beach Boys. It looks like a tiresome day and I don’t pay heed to the stranger next to me, who smells like Fijian Water Lotus mist. If only I knew it was the last time I’d smell an unfamiliar perfume, I would’ve stepped a little lighter, would’ve breathed a little longer. I would’ve lingered for a slow second before stepping out the metro doors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waiting,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poorvi.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Dear Diary (are you still supposed to write that or is it totally outdated?)</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Racism in the Time of Corona</title>
      <link href="/Racism-in-the-Time-of-Corona" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Racism in the Time of Corona" />
      <published>2020-05-22T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Racism-in-the-Time-of-Corona</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Racism-in-the-Time-of-Corona">&lt;p&gt;Racial discrimination and prejudice aren’t novel for this world, unlike the COVID-19. Race and ethnicity have been the two major building blocks of our society. We can trace its origin back to the slavery of the Africans and African-Americans in the United States during the 18th century, the anti-Semitism that blew up in Germany during the Second World War or Islamophobia post 9/11; &lt;em&gt;new disease, old story.&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Society has always found it comforting and easy on their minds to deflect their insecurities and frustrations onto a group, a minority or a defined culture. This is what is generally referred to as the Scapegoat Theory, that is, the tendency to blame someone else for one’s problems, a process that often results in feelings of prejudice toward the group that one is blaming. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When struck with this unforeseen disease that no one thought would erupt and set alight the world, with no prospects of fizzling out any time soon, people turned to the old blame-game. The uncertainty, the fear, the anger and frustration, although no justification for such acts of racism, led to a huge rise in Sinophobia (or Anti-Chinese sentiment). It also led to xenophobia and violence against people of East Asian and Southeast Asian descent around the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coronavirus that originated in Wuhan, China has not only infected people physically but mentally and as stereotypically as it could. Draconian comments such as “wipe the Chinese people out” and “hope this virus gets all of them” etc. have been expressed throughout the world, apathetically. However, this discrimination isn’t a result of just the pandemic, or the lockdown frustration because that would be a fairly a simple explanation for the centuries of entrenched racism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Race Conflict Theory, the race came about as a tool to justify and maintain the economic and political power held by those of European descent ages ago. The prejudice that we hold against certain communities, is, by and large, an extension of the stereotypes we create with an implicit bias that comes into play while making judgments about them. And this chain of stereotype leading to prejudice creates discrimination-unequal treatment of different groups of people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The matter in question today is the virus and its origin in China that has led us to fabricate a stereotype and deplorable feelings towards the Chinese and Asian people. This includes incidents of Northeast-Indian students facing odious and hurtful remarks in colleges, more than 1,000 South Korean tourists being instructed to avoid public places and remain in isolation in their hotels, and even being rejected by hotels and forced to spend nights at the airport, a woman being called “coronavirus”, threatened, and spat on by youths in Schaerbeek and a French newspaper &lt;em&gt;Le Courrier Picard&lt;/em&gt; featuring an Asian woman wearing a mask on its front page on January 26, 2020 with a headline “Yellow Alert”. The paper also titled an editorial “A New Yellow Peril”. These instances are overlooked every day by most of us as they are not considered undignified or moralistically unrighteous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yellow, a term mindlessly anointed to the Asians isn’t new. Segregation based on colour has been a rite as archaic as the Old Testament itself. To think that Racism is not a 21st century paradigm would be a self-delude, a ‘Racism without Racists’, because even though the explicit views might have become less prominent due to their social condemnation and fewer people’s willingness to say them, doesn’t mean that this racism doesn’t exist. It has morphed into a more structural and anchored form of racism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has manifested some economic repercussions too, as nations are withdrawing their faith in China, particularly the United States, whose President Donald Trump has been ramping up his censure of Beijing and threatening new tariffs on China. The United States is considering retaliatory measures against China over the outbreak. A commentator from a US news channel even went so far ahead as to criticise the country for selling virus-infected bats in open-air marketplaces and have business and tourist travel between “that country” and the “civilized world”. These slurs and scorn are touching new bottoms of impropriety across the world, emanating their ideas of what is civilised, as we just saw. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this sentiment hasn’t been restricted to just the Chinese people. Sinophobia was an antechamber into a spur of punitive sentiment against many communities, like the Muslims and the Jews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Islamophobia reinforced its clutches in India after an incidence of Muslim gatherings organised by the Tablighi Jamaat that resulted in large increased cases in India, which has triggered Islamophobic reactions and increased communal tensions. Fabricated videos falsely claiming to show members of the missionary group spitting on police and others quickly went viral on social media, hospitals refused to treat Muslim patients which led to the deaths of at least two newborn babies, and the Indian media hopped onto the bandwagon of anti-Muslim stories and headlines like a moth to fire.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a country already beset with 70 years of friction between the Hindus and Muslims following the partition of the Indian subcontinent in 1947; gory wars, terrorist attacks and the recent CAA-NRC bill, this new information spread animosity across the country like a wildfire. Instead of dealing with the issue of the virus getting out of hand, due to unequivocal carelessness on the part of certain people, the quandary shifted seamlessly from the economic and social situation of the country to the incongruous matter of factitious religious sentiments. This hate-mongering has ignited the ember of aversion that is already extant in this nation, making hashtags like #CoronaVirusJihaad viral. It’s both shocking and commonplace at the same time for India to spew such hatred against the Muslims amidst a larger issue of a threatening pandemic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authoritarian societies tend to see the societal structure as people who are naturally superior (as they say), having the right to power over others (minorities). It’s a perpetual cyclical motion of various ideas that lead to something grave. A difference based on racial heritage, called ’Pluralism’ gives birth to this pattern which then leads to what sociology refers to as cultural ’Assimilation’ and further ’Segregation’. However, this cycle doesn’t cease until it reaches the point of ’Genocide’. This is a theory, but it cannot be discredited as purely abstract because history has given us enough &lt;em&gt;corpus delicti&lt;/em&gt; to believe that such a heinous crime can occur. The Holocaust and the Rwandan Genocide are testaments to the exacerbated results of racism and pluralism into something inconceivably ghastly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pandemic has shed light not only on the flaws of our societal structure but the general hierarchy of the Capitalist nature of the economic and political organisation that we follow in the 21st century, necessitating a huge change in both our attitudes and the way we function at large. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People’s prejudice has blinded them, making them ignorant of the fact that this virus is affecting everyone equally, affecting &lt;em&gt;‘them’&lt;/em&gt; as much as it is distressing any other person; that it is us against the malady and not each other. But hasn’t that always been the human folly? &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Racial discrimination and prejudice aren’t novel for this world, unlike the COVID-19. Race and ethnicity have been the two major building blocks of our society. We can trace its origin back to the slavery of the Africans and African-Americans in the United States during the 18th century, the anti-Semitism that blew up in Germany during the Second World War or Islamophobia post 9/11; new disease, old story.  </summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Puppets of Patriarchy</title>
      <link href="/Puppets-of-Patriarchy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Puppets of Patriarchy" />
      <published>2020-04-23T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Puppets-of-Patriarchy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Puppets-of-Patriarchy">&lt;p&gt;I wake up every morning as a woman in this society, a child of the upper-middle-class, privileged and comfortable in my warm bed. I have the option to choose the course of my day as I like, as do most of the women in my surroundings. However, a lot of us forget amidst the warmth of our mornings that our choices or rather the right to choose weren’t granted to us on a platter of silverware. It has been a long, arduous, gory fight since the beginning of time. From colossal watershed moments like wars and suffrage to societal acceptance, from voting rights and the combat against harassment to as minuscule a subject as walking freely on the streets in a pair of your favourite blue jeans. The world hasn’t been a wish-granting factory for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most men &lt;em&gt;used to, still do, and always will&lt;/em&gt; wake up every day in a society that doesn’t refer to them as ‘The Second Sex’. They don’t have to walk the face of the earth with gills to breathe with on land. And in those moments when you forget what the millions of women, forgotten and faded through history, gave up, the ones who asked &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; and refuted with a staunch &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;, take a swift sift through the past that screams for you to protect this privilege. Yes, it’s a privilege, even if it shouldn’t have been because respecting another human being and walking with them instead of trooping ahead should be as easy as shutting your eyes close and lapsing into sleep. Instead of morphing this system into a more accepting and wholesome one, it might just be easier in a parallel world, where we can go back 200,000 years in time and reset the trail of human life on earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is my statement to everyone who has ever questioned me as to why we need feminism anymore. To those who still foolishly think of it as a process with an end date, a time when everything will be idyllic and we’ll stop the ‘train of feminism’. To those who question the label that it has gained over the last few decades, mindless of the fact that it was them who pejoratively stamped in that way- both men and women. Men, who are scared and alarmed at the thought of a world where their kind doesn’t dominate and take precedence anymore but exists in an unruffled state with the environment with all people, all genders. And the women who have so long been repressed and rewired that they don’t think that openly breathing is an option anymore. And to everybody who thinks that feminism is a struggle against men,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I vehemently disagree, for these people are way off-target. For two reasons- because I reckon women aren’t in the least powerless, let alone tenuous in front of any gender. And secondly, for those who think that men aren’t subjugated in this society are starkly mistaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patriarchy is a friend to none, no gender; be it men, women or non-binary. It feeds and thrives on the politics of power and authority and throttles whatever comes in its way. Men who aren’t ‘masculine’ enough, women who are too ‘brazen’, ‘impure’ castes and races, and everyone who doesn’t fit inside their box; the icy-cold, suffocating box with pores impossible to permeate, into which it shoves all who refuse to conform to the beliefs of gender. Gender, which is just a socially constructed idea, gradually fabricated into a sheath of rules and norms, which in actuality is as abstract an idea as complex numbers, perhaps. Apart from the normal human physiology that describes a person’s sex, no science explains the attributes we innocently anoint to the ‘two’ genders. They say women are calm and understanding, whereas men are temperamental and impulsive. &lt;em&gt;Of pinks and blues, cooking and driving, dominant and submissive, on top, on the bottom, floral and solid;&lt;/em&gt; gender is a &lt;em&gt;role&lt;/em&gt; perfected intricately over years, contingent on patriarchy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judith Butler, a renowned gender theorist, contends that being female is not “natural” and that it appears natural only through repeated performances of gender; these performances in turn reproduce and define the traditional categories of gender. Maybe Shakespeare was right, maybe the world is a stage and we’re all mere players, nay, puppets of patriarchy. These roles assigned to us are bolstered into a cemented building, so tightly plastered that any attempt to subvert that structure is considered a convulsion of the society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stereotyping is the soul food of human civilisation, especially when it comes to gender. And a simple explanation for it could be the fact that it is easier on the brain to stereotype, in other words, a heuristic. When faced with a decision to be made quickly, our brain doesn’t have the time or resources to compare all the information before making a choice, and so people often rely on mental shortcuts known as representative heuristics. Stereotyping stems from these heuristics and when inculcated as a habit or unwittingly imbibed since an early age, can be spotted in children as young as six years old. If you take a neutral environment and raise two different sexes with the same treatment and knowledge, bereft of these norms, they will grow up to be free of gender stereotypes. The girl might not necessarily pick up the doll and the boy the copter, but if they do, it will be out of a liking, a choice and not a manoeuvred stereotype that the society has comfortably sunk into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patriarchal violence is not solely against women but nature as well, and when we stand up against the Satanic cousin that is patriarchy, tearing down this concrete-helix structure, we emerge loyal to the posterity and to the planet itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the foundation of ‘Eco-Feminism’, first ideated in the late 1970’s and early 1980’s. Eco-feminism is about connectedness and wholeness of the abstract and the actual. It asserts a special strength and integrity of every living thing. Vandana Shiva, a radical eco-feminist from India has changed the conception of this idea in her analysis of links between the degradation of women and the exploitation of nature in modern social setups. It highlights the gall of patriarchy to dominate and destroy not just ‘anything that isn’t masculine’ but the environment we’re living in. Both women and the environment are undervalued in our global system and economies and both are very essential elements of our world, if we are to see a changeover to a more inclusive and sustainable economy. Better use of the world’s female population would increase economic growth, reduce poverty, enhance societal well-being, and help ensure sustainable development in all countries since women have a smaller ecological footprint than men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fight hasn’t gotten any easier than it was before. It started with earning the rights and the place we deserved. And after a good 100 years, only six countries in the world give other genders absolute equal rights, the World Bank found out. And they ask what more do we need? Others do state those (hollow) rights in their constitution, but they don’t uphold them. So now it is about taking those values into everyday life and making them as real and tangible as possible. The fight now is to break down the barrier of being referred to as ‘The Second Sex’ and locomote to a non-ordinal world, where genders aren’t ranked, defined, suffocated, and bifurcated into pink and blue. Instead, they can breathe and identify themselves through the way that they feel and not necessarily their sex, manifesting through a rainbow of colours.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I wake up every morning as a woman in this society, a child of the upper-middle-class, privileged and comfortable in my warm bed. I have the option to choose the course of my day as I like, as do most of the women in my surroundings. However, a lot of us forget amidst the warmth of our mornings that our choices or rather the right to choose weren’t granted to us on a platter of silverware. It has been a long, arduous, gory fight since the beginning of time. From colossal watershed moments like wars and suffrage to societal acceptance, from voting rights and the combat against harassment to as minuscule a subject as walking freely on the streets in a pair of your favourite blue jeans. The world hasn’t been a wish-granting factory for us.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Walk with Me, Through Calcutta</title>
      <link href="/A-Walk-with-Me-through-Calcutta" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Walk with Me, Through Calcutta" />
      <published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Walk-with-Me-through-Calcutta</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Walk-with-Me-through-Calcutta">&lt;p&gt;It’s almost every day that one takes a stroll down the memory lane, but even more so during a heart-wrenching pandemic and lockdown. This is unexplored territory for most of us millennials, who have been living their teens and adulthood through the golden period of India, in terms of economy and culture both. We never had to face the horrors of the 1984 riots, the Emergency or the grotesque wars fought by India, post-Independence. I wonder if we’ll come out of this pandemic a bit more mature and stable, or just more reliant on the virtual world for sustenance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find myself one early morning after the lockdown, woken up by the sheer tirelessness at 6 am; only to witness a swathe of cotton candy shaped clouds and the Sun so calm, for it is March in Delhi. It was unlike anything I had witnessed before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a good half hour of staring at the silence clinging to the walls of my house, I make myself my ritualistic cup of lemon tea and cross another day off of my calendar, until this is all over.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I sit and blow on my tea for the thousandth time, I hear a voice from a recorder coming from my neighbour’s house. They were playing a famous Satyajit Ray song, that they do often but is usually drowned out by the jingling utensils of the neighbourhood and the hasty vehicles. I can faintly put any words together, but the calming music makes me get off my bed and lean against the wall to listen a little more clearly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I clamber on my couch, with my black laptop and fiddle through the folders to finally find the one I was rummaging for, named Kolkata or Calcutta, as most snobby Kolkatans would insist. I look at the pictures nostalgically and I’m back in the streets of the city of joy, where I can almost smell the salty fragrance of fish and the rust adorning Victoria Memorial’s old doors. For a good five years of my life, in fact, for as long as I can remember, I have dreamed of going to Kolkata. Maybe it was &lt;em&gt;Gitanjali&lt;/em&gt; by Rabindranath Tagore, Anupam Roy’s sweet sitar music, the movie &lt;em&gt;Piku&lt;/em&gt;, Kolkata’s iconic yellow taxis or my love for &lt;em&gt;Mishti Doi&lt;/em&gt; (sweet yogurt).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For someone hailing from Delhi, Kolkata hits you like the fresh respite of mint lemonade on a hot summer day. A lot more scanty and calmer than the fast-paced city of Delhi, Kolkata, for me, was a sight out of a Michelangelo painting, an architect’s candy land if you may. Wherever you look, across three-sixty degrees, beautiful colours adorn the old buildings; not one is left white. There is something about the buildings in that city - they’re as old as time, but they stand strong, bold and speak to you if you like all things old. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kolkata is one of the metropolitan cities of India, with the 7th largest population and a bustling cultural milieu, yet it feels as if time has not moved there. The city has heavy influences from its colonial past, which can be seen in the wide roads, intersections, pavements, and the touch of white on the big, stellar monuments and museums. There is a mix of old and modern Indo-Saracenic elements in Kolkata, but a huge part of it dates back to the late 19th century when it was the major cultural, economic and commercial capital of colonial India. From the old rusty doors on its buildings, the yellow taxis around the city, to the cramped markets and street vendors selling the famous street food called* Phuchka*, there are parts of Kolkata surviving still, as authentic to its culture as it could’ve been. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tradition of the &lt;em&gt;hand-pulled rickshaws &lt;/em&gt;is still going strong and extant in the tapered lanes of Kolkata’s &lt;em&gt;Bara Bazar&lt;/em&gt; (literally ‘big market’) where men labour all day long, pulling these rickshaws with people for survival. These rickshaws were introduced in Kolkata by the Chinese Traders around the 1900’s who inhabited the Bara Bazar area  primarily to carry goods. The present-day pullers are either third or fourth generation pullers carrying the colonial heritage with their heredity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government of Kolkata has tried time and again to eradicate this practice, which some consider vile and inhuman, by banning it throughout the city, however, the rickshaws can still be spotted across the town. They say it’s their heritage and legacy, and it’s the only work they know. Hence, Kolkata stands as the only city in India to still have hand-pulled rickshaws in a working environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When talking about a monopoly on things, Kolkata is also the city of the &lt;em&gt;Tram Car&lt;/em&gt;. These trams are the oldest operating electric tram system in Asia, which has been running since 1902. They are little yellow and blue carriages, usually in a pair of two that run on electricity from overhead lines and tracks laid down throughout the city; from right next to Park Street to the Fort William, their expanse is widely spread. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although these trams are old and rough around the edges, they are still chosen as a means of transportation by a significant number of lower-middle-class people, as it costs less than rupees ten to travel in this delightful little vehicle. Sitting in a tram takes you back to the 70’s and you can suddenly hear an old Hindi song playing in your head. They’re slow yet still efficient and environment-friendly and sit right in the heart of Kolkata’s culture, defining the city since time immemorial. And if you’re in Kolkata, I promise you can tell by the metallic tracks hugging the road and the muffled ringing of its bell that you’re near one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, undoubtedly, Kolkata’s culture is what it is known for across the globe. During the late 19th and 20th centuries, Kolkata gave birth to what later came to be known as the Bengal Renaissance. It is said to be initiated by the famous social-religious reformer, Raja Ram Mohan Roy, who led Kolkata to greatness, along with fellow reformers from this period - Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar, Swami Vivekananda, and many others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the British authority over India was incrementing every day, Bengal decided to step out from this period of darkness and towards the light. Reconsideration and reassessment transpired in the culture and philosophy of Kolkata, which is the very soul of a renaissance. This renaissance increased the importance of Kolkata by folds when it became the capital of colonial British India. Education, literacy, and civilisation flourished throughout the city which led to the birth of Kolkata’s literary realm, producing impressive pieces of literature and concurrently writers like the Nobel Prize-winning legend Rabindranath Tagore or Rashsundari Debi who is considered to be one of the first Indian women to write an autobiography and the first Bengali woman to have ever written anything. The Bengal renaissance not only brought literature and knowledge but reforms, technology, science, and enlightenment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise in Bengali culture during the time of colonialism is a watershed for Indian feminism because of the remnants that some of the women have left behind. Kolkata has witnessed women like Begum Rokeya, the author of the feminist utopian story &lt;em&gt;Sultana’s Dream&lt;/em&gt;, Nobel Peace Prize recipient Mother Teresa, Bina Das and Aruna Asaf Ali who laid a firm foundation of a feminist example for India’s posterity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the streets of Kolkata, I was not only staggered by its beautiful museums and churches but the art that lives in every corner of that city. Be it music, books or food, Kolkata aces the chart on every ground. It houses India’s largest library - The National Library of India, which provides a serene environment for any bibliophile, and &lt;em&gt;College Street, &lt;/em&gt;a mile of bookshops and bookstalls spilling over each other, where a large majority of publishers are situated. It became the heart of all-things-books after the &lt;em&gt;Kallol *movement, started around the beginning of the 20th century, witnessed the arrival of postmodernism. One of the greatest achievements of the &lt;/em&gt;Kallol* group was in establishing a new generation of writers and thinkers in Bengal, especially Kolkata. This also gave rise to Kolkata’s cinematic scene theatre and by extension, art films, known worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember seeing the oldest building in Kolkata situated in the centre of a jostling market called Lalbazar, lost and unmarked, shown to me by an old man, a lawyer, whom I met in my Uber-pool. It had red bricks and white pillars with curved white-painted windows. Before he left, he told me the best time to enjoy all that Kolkata has to offer is mid-October, during the period of Durga Pujo, a time of week-long festivities and food. The city lights up like a cluster of fireflies and rejoices with music authentic to the soul of Kolkata. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city lost its colossal importance after the capital of the Indian subcontinent was shifted from Calcutta (back then) to Delhi on December 12, 1911. However, it still strives to mesmerise its inhabitants and travellers from across the globe. It’s unlike any other city, soaked deeply in immense history and culture, which is reflected in every building, every pavement, and every bite of its delectable &lt;em&gt;roshogollas&lt;/em&gt;. The sweet Bengali music from the house adjacent to mine stops as the world wakes up and dives into the everyday hustle of life again. I close the window into my memory jar of Kolkata, rush to the kitchen and pour my nostalgia into a hearty Sunday treat of &lt;em&gt;Mishti Doi.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It’s almost every day that one takes a stroll down the memory lane, but even more so during a heart-wrenching pandemic and lockdown. This is unexplored territory for most of us millennials, who have been living their teens and adulthood through the golden period of India, in terms of economy and culture both. We never had to face the horrors of the 1984 riots, the Emergency or the grotesque wars fought by India, post-Independence. I wonder if we’ll come out of this pandemic a bit more mature and stable, or just more reliant on the virtual world for sustenance. </summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
