<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/poorvi.gupta/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-06-03T21:03:01+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/poorvi.gupta/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lockdown Diaries and the Smell of Strange Perfume</title>
      <link href="/Lockdown-Diaries" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lockdown Diaries and the Smell of Strange Perfume" />
      <published>2020-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Lockdown-Diaries</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lockdown-Diaries">&lt;p&gt;Dear Diary (are you still supposed to write that or is it totally outdated?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t know how to start; the last time I wrote to myself was in the eighth grade, when I wished desperately for the English exam to end, lest my hand fall off and I live without one with an awkward story to tell for as long as the world sustains. It’s not as weird as I thought it would be, honestly. I do talk to myself all the time, at 3 AM, wavering between what I should’ve said to some people two years back and all the possible ways that the world might end in (Armageddon is not left unconsidered, by the way).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pretty sure this time is hard for every living person on the surface of this planet, and I’m not in this alone. Sometimes, my problems seem like a tiny little whine when I open the news and read about the horrible things happening around; people trying to survive, to get food and just breathe every day, hoping the sun doesn’t set, because if it does, there is another day of suffering waiting for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whereas as soon as I wake up, I wait eagerly for the dusk, creating a mental picture of the day ahead in my head, trying to bring a sense of organisation and calm to this commotion that life has become. It is almost like an annoying traffic jam, cars glued to the ground, an utterly piercing horn in the background that isn’t ready to subside and your foot on the pedal trying to move your car one bit at a time, as much as you can, to get out of this rut so that you can finally glide onto the highway, roll down your windows and let the cool autumn breeze embrace you until it touches your feet and you feel like all is okay in the world again. I feel as if these days I’m just waiting for this jam to clear, so that I can take in that air again as I rush my car through the freeway, and go anywhere I want, no restrictions, just the journey and the destination ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I just romanticise a pandemic? I’m afraid so. Reading a little too much of Mitch Albom, watching a string of Jane Austen classic movies and smelling books and teas doesn’t make you a &lt;em&gt;cool&lt;/em&gt; millennial, I’m sure. Just your average old-school -person, who loves cardigans and sighs when they look at &lt;em&gt;tiktoks&lt;/em&gt;, referring to it as ‘these kids’ when you’re a 20-year-old yourself (or more like an 80-year-old woman stuck in a 20-year-old’s body).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even though I enjoy my old-person traits most days, it’s certainly hard to keep up with it when you live in the year 2020, jailed amidst the four walls of your room. The internet and social media isn’t a respite because you cannot for the life of you comprehend the conundrum that is #quarantineandchill or the Dalgona coffee trend? (I mean it’s just coffee upside down). I know that I have all the time in the world to read all those books and literary wonders that I keep crying about when I didn’t have enough time or listen to Sam Cooke all day and Paul McCartney the next. And it was all about those books, songs and heartwarming movies but only for a good four weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the fifth week started to unfold, I missed the smell of freshly roasted coffee that came wafting from the cafes that I walked past, pulling me towards themselves as the moon does to the tides - just simple laws of gravity. And that’s just not it. I miss my entire commute to university every day - waking up early yet late, at 7 am (yes that was sadly late) and crying about it, while I rush to get ready and catch a ride to the metro-station as my hair is soaking wet and I drench the marble floors of my house as I sprint around, trying to find my glasses and earphones. I would gulp my cold coffee whole, while my mother gave me a sniggering look for skipping breakfast and yet would sneak in a sandwich wrapped in aluminium foil in my bag when I wasn’t looking. I miss the morning breeze that air-dried my hair in the auto-rickshaw, while I fiddled with my earphones and rummaged through my playlist for a morning boost of Mumford and Sons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would give up all of the social media, yes, Instagram and Snapchat and whatever new application the kids are using these days for a train ride to college, filled with strangers, all so hurried, so hasty, to reach somewhere, pushing and fumbling through the metro - I would find an uncanny sense of calm in it. This uncertainty and muddled life has made me realize how much I also miss studying or skipping the first-morning class to hang out in the cafeteria instead with a cup of steaming coffee and half-forgotten anecdotes from old nights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it just me or does anyone else also miss the yellow and red flowers strewn about on the streets in March? It is not easy for a memory hoarder to get through these tough times without lapsing into nostalgia every other minute. Not easy for a person who loves stray discourses on politics, life, love, career and books over a cup of tea to text people and still have that fiery enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not undermining my privilege, for I know these aren’t the issues that matter in the least right now. But I think writing them down makes me feel a tad better - like I’m ranting to someone as I would in the &lt;em&gt;old days&lt;/em&gt;, if I may.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And like a true old-soul, these past three months have made me realize how much I enjoy my own company rather than texting away or relying on social media to get through the day. And I don’t think less of anyone who does that; whatever one finds their peace in. But it’s hard to blend in sometimes for monochromes in this vibrant world, when all you want is to cook yourself nice, steaming-hot banana bread and curl into your bed with a sad PDF. (I miss the smell of books).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think all I want is a redo sometimes. I know I couldn’t change anything; I couldn’t stop the pandemic because that is beyond my corporeal control. However, if I do get a redo, as I imagine- &lt;em&gt;I see myself standing at the jostling platform of Rajiv Chowk Metro Station in Delhi- people brushing past and into each other. I might be looking at them indifferently, as my earphones pulse to the tunes of The Beach Boys. It looks like a tiresome day and I don’t pay heed to the stranger next to me, who smells like Fijian Water Lotus mist. If only I knew it was the last time I’d smell an unfamiliar perfume, I would’ve stepped a little lighter, would’ve breathed a little longer. I would’ve lingered for a slow second before stepping out the metro doors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waiting,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poorvi.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Dear Diary (are you still supposed to write that or is it totally outdated?)</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Racism in the Time of Corona</title>
      <link href="/Racism-in-the-Time-of-Corona" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Racism in the Time of Corona" />
      <published>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Racism-in-the-Time-of-Corona</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Racism-in-the-Time-of-Corona">&lt;p&gt;Racial discrimination and prejudice aren’t novel for this world, unlike the COVID-19. Race and ethnicity have been the two major building blocks of our society. We can trace its origin back to the slavery of the Africans and African-Americans in the United States during the 18th century, the anti-Semitism that blew up in Germany during the Second World War or Islamophobia post 9/11; &lt;em&gt;new disease, old story.&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Society has always found it comforting and easy on their minds to deflect their insecurities and frustrations onto a group, a minority or a defined culture. This is what is generally referred to as the Scapegoat Theory, that is, the tendency to blame someone else for one’s problems, a process that often results in feelings of prejudice toward the group that one is blaming. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When struck with this unforeseen disease that no one thought would erupt and set alight the world, with no prospects of fizzling out any time soon, people turned to the old blame-game. The uncertainty, the fear, the anger and frustration, although no justification for such acts of racism, led to a huge rise in Sinophobia (or Anti-Chinese sentiment). It also led to xenophobia and violence against people of East Asian and Southeast Asian descent around the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coronavirus that originated in Wuhan, China has not only infected people physically but mentally and as stereotypically as it could. Draconian comments such as “wipe the Chinese people out” and “hope this virus gets all of them” etc. have been expressed throughout the world, apathetically. However, this discrimination isn’t a result of just the pandemic, or the lockdown frustration because that would be a fairly a simple explanation for the centuries of entrenched racism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Race Conflict Theory, the race came about as a tool to justify and maintain the economic and political power held by those of European descent ages ago. The prejudice that we hold against certain communities, is, by and large, an extension of the stereotypes we create with an implicit bias that comes into play while making judgments about them. And this chain of stereotype leading to prejudice creates discrimination-unequal treatment of different groups of people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The matter in question today is the virus and its origin in China that has led us to fabricate a stereotype and deplorable feelings towards the Chinese and Asian people. This includes incidents of Northeast-Indian students facing odious and hurtful remarks in colleges, more than 1,000 South Korean tourists being instructed to avoid public places and remain in isolation in their hotels, and even being rejected by hotels and forced to spend nights at the airport, a woman being called “coronavirus”, threatened, and spat on by youths in Schaerbeek and a French newspaper &lt;em&gt;Le Courrier Picard&lt;/em&gt; featuring an Asian woman wearing a mask on its front page on January 26, 2020 with a headline “Yellow Alert”. The paper also titled an editorial “A New Yellow Peril”. These instances are overlooked every day by most of us as they are not considered undignified or moralistically unrighteous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yellow, a term mindlessly anointed to the Asians isn’t new. Segregation based on colour has been a rite as archaic as the Old Testament itself. To think that Racism is not a 21st century paradigm would be a self-delude, a ‘Racism without Racists’, because even though the explicit views might have become less prominent due to their social condemnation and fewer people’s willingness to say them, doesn’t mean that this racism doesn’t exist. It has morphed into a more structural and anchored form of racism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has manifested some economic repercussions too, as nations are withdrawing their faith in China, particularly the United States, whose President Donald Trump has been ramping up his censure of Beijing and threatening new tariffs on China. The United States is considering retaliatory measures against China over the outbreak. A commentator from a US news channel even went so far ahead as to criticise the country for selling virus-infected bats in open-air marketplaces and have business and tourist travel between “that country” and the “civilized world”. These slurs and scorn are touching new bottoms of impropriety across the world, emanating their ideas of what is civilised, as we just saw. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this sentiment hasn’t been restricted to just the Chinese people. Sinophobia was an antechamber into a spur of punitive sentiment against many communities, like the Muslims and the Jews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Islamophobia reinforced its clutches in India after an incidence of Muslim gatherings organised by the Tablighi Jamaat that resulted in large increased cases in India, which has triggered Islamophobic reactions and increased communal tensions. Fabricated videos falsely claiming to show members of the missionary group spitting on police and others quickly went viral on social media, hospitals refused to treat Muslim patients which led to the deaths of at least two newborn babies, and the Indian media hopped onto the bandwagon of anti-Muslim stories and headlines like a moth to fire.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a country already beset with 70 years of friction between the Hindus and Muslims following the partition of the Indian subcontinent in 1947; gory wars, terrorist attacks and the recent CAA-NRC bill, this new information spread animosity across the country like a wildfire. Instead of dealing with the issue of the virus getting out of hand, due to unequivocal carelessness on the part of certain people, the quandary shifted seamlessly from the economic and social situation of the country to the incongruous matter of factitious religious sentiments. This hate-mongering has ignited the ember of aversion that is already extant in this nation, making hashtags like #CoronaVirusJihaad viral. It’s both shocking and commonplace at the same time for India to spew such hatred against the Muslims amidst a larger issue of a threatening pandemic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authoritarian societies tend to see the societal structure as people who are naturally superior (as they say), having the right to power over others (minorities). It’s a perpetual cyclical motion of various ideas that lead to something grave. A difference based on racial heritage, called ’Pluralism’ gives birth to this pattern which then leads to what sociology refers to as cultural ’Assimilation’ and further ’Segregation’. However, this cycle doesn’t cease until it reaches the point of ’Genocide’. This is a theory, but it cannot be discredited as purely abstract because history has given us enough &lt;em&gt;corpus delicti&lt;/em&gt; to believe that such a heinous crime can occur. The Holocaust and the Rwandan Genocide are testaments to the exacerbated results of racism and pluralism into something inconceivably ghastly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pandemic has shed light not only on the flaws of our societal structure but the general hierarchy of the Capitalist nature of the economic and political organisation that we follow in the 21st century, necessitating a huge change in both our attitudes and the way we function at large. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People’s prejudice has blinded them, making them ignorant of the fact that this virus is affecting everyone equally, affecting &lt;em&gt;‘them’&lt;/em&gt; as much as it is distressing any other person; that it is us against the malady and not each other. But hasn’t that always been the human folly? &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Racial discrimination and prejudice aren’t novel for this world, unlike the COVID-19. Race and ethnicity have been the two major building blocks of our society. We can trace its origin back to the slavery of the Africans and African-Americans in the United States during the 18th century, the anti-Semitism that blew up in Germany during the Second World War or Islamophobia post 9/11; new disease, old story.  </summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Puppets of Patriarchy</title>
      <link href="/Puppets-of-Patriarchy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Puppets of Patriarchy" />
      <published>2020-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Puppets-of-Patriarchy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Puppets-of-Patriarchy">&lt;p&gt;I wake up every morning as a woman in this society, a child of the upper-middle-class, privileged and comfortable in my warm bed. I have the option to choose the course of my day as I like, as do most of the women in my surroundings. However, a lot of us forget amidst the warmth of our mornings that our choices or rather the right to choose weren’t granted to us on a platter of silverware. It has been a long, arduous, gory fight since the beginning of time. From colossal watershed moments like wars and suffrage to societal acceptance, from voting rights and the combat against harassment to as minuscule a subject as walking freely on the streets in a pair of your favourite blue jeans. The world hasn’t been a wish-granting factory for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most men &lt;em&gt;used to, still do, and always will&lt;/em&gt; wake up every day in a society that doesn’t refer to them as ‘The Second Sex’. They don’t have to walk the face of the earth with gills to breathe with on land. And in those moments when you forget what the millions of women, forgotten and faded through history, gave up, the ones who asked &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; and refuted with a staunch &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;, take a swift sift through the past that screams for you to protect this privilege. Yes, it’s a privilege, even if it shouldn’t have been because respecting another human being and walking with them instead of trooping ahead should be as easy as shutting your eyes close and lapsing into sleep. Instead of morphing this system into a more accepting and wholesome one, it might just be easier in a parallel world, where we can go back 200,000 years in time and reset the trail of human life on earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is my statement to everyone who has ever questioned me as to why we need feminism anymore. To those who still foolishly think of it as a process with an end date, a time when everything will be idyllic and we’ll stop the ‘train of feminism’. To those who question the label that it has gained over the last few decades, mindless of the fact that it was them who pejoratively stamped in that way- both men and women. Men, who are scared and alarmed at the thought of a world where their kind doesn’t dominate and take precedence anymore but exists in an unruffled state with the environment with all people, all genders. And the women who have so long been repressed and rewired that they don’t think that openly breathing is an option anymore. And to everybody who thinks that feminism is a struggle against men,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I vehemently disagree, for these people are way off-target. For two reasons- because I reckon women aren’t in the least powerless, let alone tenuous in front of any gender. And secondly, for those who think that men aren’t subjugated in this society are starkly mistaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patriarchy is a friend to none, no gender; be it men, women or non-binary. It feeds and thrives on the politics of power and authority and throttles whatever comes in its way. Men who aren’t ‘masculine’ enough, women who are too ‘brazen’, ‘impure’ castes and races, and everyone who doesn’t fit inside their box; the icy-cold, suffocating box with pores impossible to permeate, into which it shoves all who refuse to conform to the beliefs of gender. Gender, which is just a socially constructed idea, gradually fabricated into a sheath of rules and norms, which in actuality is as abstract an idea as complex numbers, perhaps. Apart from the normal human physiology that describes a person’s sex, no science explains the attributes we innocently anoint to the ‘two’ genders. They say women are calm and understanding, whereas men are temperamental and impulsive. &lt;em&gt;Of pinks and blues, cooking and driving, dominant and submissive, on top, on the bottom, floral and solid;&lt;/em&gt; gender is a &lt;em&gt;role&lt;/em&gt; perfected intricately over years, contingent on patriarchy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judith Butler, a renowned gender theorist, contends that being female is not “natural” and that it appears natural only through repeated performances of gender; these performances in turn reproduce and define the traditional categories of gender. Maybe Shakespeare was right, maybe the world is a stage and we’re all mere players, nay, puppets of patriarchy. These roles assigned to us are bolstered into a cemented building, so tightly plastered that any attempt to subvert that structure is considered a convulsion of the society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stereotyping is the soul food of human civilisation, especially when it comes to gender. And a simple explanation for it could be the fact that it is easier on the brain to stereotype, in other words, a heuristic. When faced with a decision to be made quickly, our brain doesn’t have the time or resources to compare all the information before making a choice, and so people often rely on mental shortcuts known as representative heuristics. Stereotyping stems from these heuristics and when inculcated as a habit or unwittingly imbibed since an early age, can be spotted in children as young as six years old. If you take a neutral environment and raise two different sexes with the same treatment and knowledge, bereft of these norms, they will grow up to be free of gender stereotypes. The girl might not necessarily pick up the doll and the boy the copter, but if they do, it will be out of a liking, a choice and not a manoeuvred stereotype that the society has comfortably sunk into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patriarchal violence is not solely against women but nature as well, and when we stand up against the Satanic cousin that is patriarchy, tearing down this concrete-helix structure, we emerge loyal to the posterity and to the planet itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the foundation of ‘Eco-Feminism’, first ideated in the late 1970’s and early 1980’s. Eco-feminism is about connectedness and wholeness of the abstract and the actual. It asserts a special strength and integrity of every living thing. Vandana Shiva, a radical eco-feminist from India has changed the conception of this idea in her analysis of links between the degradation of women and the exploitation of nature in modern social setups. It highlights the gall of patriarchy to dominate and destroy not just ‘anything that isn’t masculine’ but the environment we’re living in. Both women and the environment are undervalued in our global system and economies and both are very essential elements of our world, if we are to see a changeover to a more inclusive and sustainable economy. Better use of the world’s female population would increase economic growth, reduce poverty, enhance societal well-being, and help ensure sustainable development in all countries since women have a smaller ecological footprint than men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fight hasn’t gotten any easier than it was before. It started with earning the rights and the place we deserved. And after a good 100 years, only six countries in the world give other genders absolute equal rights, the World Bank found out. And they ask what more do we need? Others do state those (hollow) rights in their constitution, but they don’t uphold them. So now it is about taking those values into everyday life and making them as real and tangible as possible. The fight now is to break down the barrier of being referred to as ‘The Second Sex’ and locomote to a non-ordinal world, where genders aren’t ranked, defined, suffocated, and bifurcated into pink and blue. Instead, they can breathe and identify themselves through the way that they feel and not necessarily their sex, manifesting through a rainbow of colours.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I wake up every morning as a woman in this society, a child of the upper-middle-class, privileged and comfortable in my warm bed. I have the option to choose the course of my day as I like, as do most of the women in my surroundings. However, a lot of us forget amidst the warmth of our mornings that our choices or rather the right to choose weren’t granted to us on a platter of silverware. It has been a long, arduous, gory fight since the beginning of time. From colossal watershed moments like wars and suffrage to societal acceptance, from voting rights and the combat against harassment to as minuscule a subject as walking freely on the streets in a pair of your favourite blue jeans. The world hasn’t been a wish-granting factory for us.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Walk with Me, Through Calcutta</title>
      <link href="/A-Walk-with-Me-through-Calcutta" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Walk with Me, Through Calcutta" />
      <published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Walk-with-Me-through-Calcutta</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Walk-with-Me-through-Calcutta">&lt;p&gt;It’s almost every day that one takes a stroll down the memory lane, but even more so during a heart-wrenching pandemic and lockdown. This is unexplored territory for most of us millennials, who have been living their teens and adulthood through the golden period of India, in terms of economy and culture both. We never had to face the horrors of the 1984 riots, the Emergency or the grotesque wars fought by India, post-Independence. I wonder if we’ll come out of this pandemic a bit more mature and stable, or just more reliant on the virtual world for sustenance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find myself one early morning after the lockdown, woken up by the sheer tirelessness at 6 am; only to witness a swathe of cotton candy shaped clouds and the Sun so calm, for it is March in Delhi. It was unlike anything I had witnessed before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a good half hour of staring at the silence clinging to the walls of my house, I make myself my ritualistic cup of lemon tea and cross another day off of my calendar, until this is all over.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I sit and blow on my tea for the thousandth time, I hear a voice from a recorder coming from my neighbour’s house. They were playing a famous Satyajit Ray song, that they do often but is usually drowned out by the jingling utensils of the neighbourhood and the hasty vehicles. I can faintly put any words together, but the calming music makes me get off my bed and lean against the wall to listen a little more clearly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I clamber on my couch, with my black laptop and fiddle through the folders to finally find the one I was rummaging for, named Kolkata or Calcutta, as most snobby Kolkatans would insist. I look at the pictures nostalgically and I’m back in the streets of the city of joy, where I can almost smell the salty fragrance of fish and the rust adorning Victoria Memorial’s old doors. For a good five years of my life, in fact, for as long as I can remember, I have dreamed of going to Kolkata. Maybe it was &lt;em&gt;Gitanjali&lt;/em&gt; by Rabindranath Tagore, Anupam Roy’s sweet sitar music, the movie &lt;em&gt;Piku&lt;/em&gt;, Kolkata’s iconic yellow taxis or my love for &lt;em&gt;Mishti Doi&lt;/em&gt; (sweet yogurt).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For someone hailing from Delhi, Kolkata hits you like the fresh respite of mint lemonade on a hot summer day. A lot more scanty and calmer than the fast-paced city of Delhi, Kolkata, for me, was a sight out of a Michelangelo painting, an architect’s candy land if you may. Wherever you look, across three-sixty degrees, beautiful colours adorn the old buildings; not one is left white. There is something about the buildings in that city - they’re as old as time, but they stand strong, bold and speak to you if you like all things old. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kolkata is one of the metropolitan cities of India, with the 7th largest population and a bustling cultural milieu, yet it feels as if time has not moved there. The city has heavy influences from its colonial past, which can be seen in the wide roads, intersections, pavements, and the touch of white on the big, stellar monuments and museums. There is a mix of old and modern Indo-Saracenic elements in Kolkata, but a huge part of it dates back to the late 19th century when it was the major cultural, economic and commercial capital of colonial India. From the old rusty doors on its buildings, the yellow taxis around the city, to the cramped markets and street vendors selling the famous street food called* Phuchka*, there are parts of Kolkata surviving still, as authentic to its culture as it could’ve been. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tradition of the &lt;em&gt;hand-pulled rickshaws &lt;/em&gt;is still going strong and extant in the tapered lanes of Kolkata’s &lt;em&gt;Bara Bazar&lt;/em&gt; (literally ‘big market’) where men labour all day long, pulling these rickshaws with people for survival. These rickshaws were introduced in Kolkata by the Chinese Traders around the 1900’s who inhabited the Bara Bazar area  primarily to carry goods. The present-day pullers are either third or fourth generation pullers carrying the colonial heritage with their heredity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government of Kolkata has tried time and again to eradicate this practice, which some consider vile and inhuman, by banning it throughout the city, however, the rickshaws can still be spotted across the town. They say it’s their heritage and legacy, and it’s the only work they know. Hence, Kolkata stands as the only city in India to still have hand-pulled rickshaws in a working environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When talking about a monopoly on things, Kolkata is also the city of the &lt;em&gt;Tram Car&lt;/em&gt;. These trams are the oldest operating electric tram system in Asia, which has been running since 1902. They are little yellow and blue carriages, usually in a pair of two that run on electricity from overhead lines and tracks laid down throughout the city; from right next to Park Street to the Fort William, their expanse is widely spread. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although these trams are old and rough around the edges, they are still chosen as a means of transportation by a significant number of lower-middle-class people, as it costs less than rupees ten to travel in this delightful little vehicle. Sitting in a tram takes you back to the 70’s and you can suddenly hear an old Hindi song playing in your head. They’re slow yet still efficient and environment-friendly and sit right in the heart of Kolkata’s culture, defining the city since time immemorial. And if you’re in Kolkata, I promise you can tell by the metallic tracks hugging the road and the muffled ringing of its bell that you’re near one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, undoubtedly, Kolkata’s culture is what it is known for across the globe. During the late 19th and 20th centuries, Kolkata gave birth to what later came to be known as the Bengal Renaissance. It is said to be initiated by the famous social-religious reformer, Raja Ram Mohan Roy, who led Kolkata to greatness, along with fellow reformers from this period - Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar, Swami Vivekananda, and many others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the British authority over India was incrementing every day, Bengal decided to step out from this period of darkness and towards the light. Reconsideration and reassessment transpired in the culture and philosophy of Kolkata, which is the very soul of a renaissance. This renaissance increased the importance of Kolkata by folds when it became the capital of colonial British India. Education, literacy, and civilisation flourished throughout the city which led to the birth of Kolkata’s literary realm, producing impressive pieces of literature and concurrently writers like the Nobel Prize-winning legend Rabindranath Tagore or Rashsundari Debi who is considered to be one of the first Indian women to write an autobiography and the first Bengali woman to have ever written anything. The Bengal renaissance not only brought literature and knowledge but reforms, technology, science, and enlightenment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise in Bengali culture during the time of colonialism is a watershed for Indian feminism because of the remnants that some of the women have left behind. Kolkata has witnessed women like Begum Rokeya, the author of the feminist utopian story &lt;em&gt;Sultana’s Dream&lt;/em&gt;, Nobel Peace Prize recipient Mother Teresa, Bina Das and Aruna Asaf Ali who laid a firm foundation of a feminist example for India’s posterity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the streets of Kolkata, I was not only staggered by its beautiful museums and churches but the art that lives in every corner of that city. Be it music, books or food, Kolkata aces the chart on every ground. It houses India’s largest library - The National Library of India, which provides a serene environment for any bibliophile, and &lt;em&gt;College Street, &lt;/em&gt;a mile of bookshops and bookstalls spilling over each other, where a large majority of publishers are situated. It became the heart of all-things-books after the &lt;em&gt;Kallol *movement, started around the beginning of the 20th century, witnessed the arrival of postmodernism. One of the greatest achievements of the &lt;/em&gt;Kallol* group was in establishing a new generation of writers and thinkers in Bengal, especially Kolkata. This also gave rise to Kolkata’s cinematic scene theatre and by extension, art films, known worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember seeing the oldest building in Kolkata situated in the centre of a jostling market called Lalbazar, lost and unmarked, shown to me by an old man, a lawyer, whom I met in my Uber-pool. It had red bricks and white pillars with curved white-painted windows. Before he left, he told me the best time to enjoy all that Kolkata has to offer is mid-October, during the period of Durga Pujo, a time of week-long festivities and food. The city lights up like a cluster of fireflies and rejoices with music authentic to the soul of Kolkata. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city lost its colossal importance after the capital of the Indian subcontinent was shifted from Calcutta (back then) to Delhi on December 12, 1911. However, it still strives to mesmerise its inhabitants and travellers from across the globe. It’s unlike any other city, soaked deeply in immense history and culture, which is reflected in every building, every pavement, and every bite of its delectable &lt;em&gt;roshogollas&lt;/em&gt;. The sweet Bengali music from the house adjacent to mine stops as the world wakes up and dives into the everyday hustle of life again. I close the window into my memory jar of Kolkata, rush to the kitchen and pour my nostalgia into a hearty Sunday treat of &lt;em&gt;Mishti Doi.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It’s almost every day that one takes a stroll down the memory lane, but even more so during a heart-wrenching pandemic and lockdown. This is unexplored territory for most of us millennials, who have been living their teens and adulthood through the golden period of India, in terms of economy and culture both. We never had to face the horrors of the 1984 riots, the Emergency or the grotesque wars fought by India, post-Independence. I wonder if we’ll come out of this pandemic a bit more mature and stable, or just more reliant on the virtual world for sustenance. </summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">HER: A Tale of Blurred Lines of Love</title>
      <link href="/HER-A-Tale-of-Blurred-Lines-of-Love" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="HER: A Tale of Blurred Lines of Love" />
      <published>2020-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/HER-A-Tale-of-Blurred-Lines-of-Love</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/HER-A-Tale-of-Blurred-Lines-of-Love">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Theodore Twombly:&lt;/em&gt; What are you doing? &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Samantha:&lt;/em&gt; I'm just sitting here, looking at the world and writing a new piece of music. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Theodore Twombly:&lt;/em&gt; Can I hear it? What's this one about?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Samantha:&lt;/em&gt; Well, I was thinking, we don't really have any photographs of us. And I thought this song could be like a photo that captures us at this moment in our life together.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Theodore Twombly:&lt;/em&gt; Aw, I like our photograph. I can see you in it.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Samantha:&lt;/em&gt; I am.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t watched this movie yet, you need to figure out the most mundane and ordinary day to sit and binge through this cinematic work of art because you’ll need a good two hours later to stare at the wall and think about it. &lt;em&gt;A little later in the week and in all the still and noiseless moments of your life too&lt;/em&gt;. But why are we talking about a six-year-old movie? Primarily because &lt;em&gt;Her&lt;/em&gt; is a movie that stands more relevant today than ever and it will remain so for the next century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story spins around a fairly simple and reclusive guy, Theodore Twombly who writes heartwarming letters for a living at a company called (BeautifulHandwrittenLetters.com)[BeautifulHandwrittenLetters.com], letters that’ll make you feel a tingling sensation in your back and curl your toes. He’s your everyday Joe with a sweet and simple appearance, but if you look closely, he has a broken heart from his ex-wife that he is seen trying to mend throughout the movie. &lt;em&gt;Her&lt;/em&gt; is set in an undisclosed time in the future, where technology has taken over the human life threefold than it does now, trickling down human interaction to its least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, it’s completely normal for us to meet somebody via the internet or social media, talk to them, laugh with them, and maybe even fall in love with them in the process. Meeting the old fashioned way isn’t what you get to see very often- a café, two corner booths and eyes meeting over the same order of Irish coffee from across the room. Instead, it starts with a follow request or a right swipe. If that’s our cultural identity, then it’s not going too far to say that you can fall in love with an operating system; as shown in this ensemble by Spike Jonze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you gulped a little too hard at that, then sit tight because this story is all about the struggle of the self, about thinning the boundaries of the real and the unreal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an adventure of the protagonist Theodore Twombly, who purchases a new operating system to better his life, exclusively designed for the personal needs of each individual. This operating system names herself Samantha, who is an ever-evolving device, learning from humans and picking up on their habits. He carries her around, shares the little and larger things about his day and most importantly- laughs wholeheartedly with her. He befriends her over their shared humour and easiness of being together which ultimately leads to falling in love with her, so much so that he isn’t afraid to accept it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might sound ridiculous to think of someone loving an inanimate object such as an OS but the intricacy with which Spike Jonze has written it and Joaquin Phoenix has flawlessly personified the character would take you on a roller coaster of emotions throughout the two hours of this movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A light banter over the phone becomes their everyday routine and Samantha feels more like a human with every passing minute, and so does their relationship. This delusion is conjured skillfully by the writer through the seclusion of characters from the world and the empathising nature of Theodore’s loneliness. The lightness in him and the calming effect of his presence gives a nice contrast to the brazenly out-there idea of the movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only point of human contact that Theodore has is his neighbour and college best friend, Amy who provides him with little bits of sanity now and then, as most of our friends do for us. Telling them your innermost thoughts that sound beyond normal in your head, somehow begin to gain a sense of sanity as you voice it out to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Amy tells him that she has become best friends with her OS since she left her husband, Theodore gathers the courage to say it out loud for the first time: that he is dating an operating system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He somewhere feels that this is insane but Amy senses that and sympathises with him telling him that, “Falling in love is kind of like a form of socially acceptable insanity”. This one line ties together the essence of the movie and the argument of what is acceptable and what isn’t. As long as you can accommodate and accept an idea in your head and heart, nothing is too far fetched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, you start to believe in their relationship and the genuineness of Samantha; which is the beauty of the screenplay and the one man tussle of Joaquin Phoenix, who carries us with him throughout the movie, never letting us go off the wagon even for a second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this misty canvas of emotions comes washing down when one day he wakes up and calls Samantha, only to find out that she’s not there at the other end of the line. He tries in vain to connect to her repeatedly but it’s as if she vanished from his phone, his life. And in that brief second, their entire relationship flashes before his eyes, he’s panting and almost subliminal. Even though she’s back in the next moment, he realizes how fleetingly real this relationship was. One minute it was everything, and the next there was no trace of it in the world- it fizzled into thin air. For a spectator, this instance was like a snap out of a daydream as a huge underlying reality of the story hits you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to that, Theodore’s ex-wife, whom he has always had unresolved feelings for, learns about his relationship with an operating system, Samantha, and blatantly tells him that he is crazy to pursue such a relationship just because he cannot handle ‘real emotions.’ She even goes on to say that he had always wanted a wife without the challenges of actually dealing with something real. Her reaction gives us an insight into Theodore’s deepest insecurities and a more clear view of why his relationship with Samantha worked out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He goes into a dour state of introspection and starts developing issues with Samantha. They fight, they cry and emotionalise, consummating the final step of their relationship and making it as human as it could have been. But the reality once slipped away, only drifts farther and farther in his mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What finally happens to Samantha and Theodore is something I’d leave up to you to comprehend for yourself. I’d urge you to go and watch the movie, for the feeling that it ends with is not something any writer can pen down in a review, let alone myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what I can comment on is the complex and mind-twisting path chosen by Spike Jonze to portray modern love, the paradox of solipsism and its untwined relationship with technology in the 21st century. It makes us question the boundaries of love? The line that separates the real and the unreal is no more clear to one. This movie toys with the questions we’re too afraid to ask ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is the tangled beauty of this story - it leaves you with an unfamiliar feeling in the pit of your stomach towards the end because we humans like to know the why and how of everything, and that is something that this movie does not promise.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Theodore Twombly: What are you doing? Samantha: I'm just sitting here, looking at the world and writing a new piece of music. Theodore Twombly: Can I hear it? What's this one about? Samantha: Well, I was thinking, we don't really have any photographs of us. And I thought this song could be like a photo that captures us at this moment in our life together. Theodore Twombly: Aw, I like our photograph. I can see you in it. Samantha: I am.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
