<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/nirikta.mukherjee/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-03-23T21:51:30+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/nirikta.mukherjee/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Retail Binge for the Mental Twinge</title>
      <link href="/Retail-Binge-for-the-Mental-Twinge" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Retail Binge for the Mental Twinge" />
      <published>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Retail-Binge-for-the-Mental-Twinge</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Retail-Binge-for-the-Mental-Twinge">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;They say, “When the going gets tough, the tough go shopping.” This is more commonly known as &lt;em&gt;Retail Therapy&lt;/em&gt;. It is a phenomenon where people shop to improve one’s disposition and raise spirits. People in distress often resort to this as a source of solace. A study published in the journal &lt;em&gt;Psychology and Marketing&lt;/em&gt; states that retail therapy has a lasting positive effect on mood. While its findings pointed out that these are impulsive purchases, the survey suggested that feelings of guilt or regret were not associated among the respondents.&amp;nbsp;The name in itself is ironic. Shopping is a concept deeply rooted in materialism. As its positive impact is temporary, it does not qualify as a ‘therapy’ in the medical sense. However, it is a fairly popular phrase used around the world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In a 2001 survey conducted by the European Union, it was found that 33% of the shoppers surveyed had a “high level of addiction to rash buying”. The study also revealed that ‘binge purchasing’ was most common among the Scottish youth. Another study of 1,000 American adults, conducted in 2013, detected that more than half of the respondents indulged in retail therapy. It also threw light on the gender aspect of the practice, stating that it is more common among women than men. It was found that 64.9% of women and 38.9% of men binge purchased while women mostly bought clothing, men indulged in ‘comfort food’. This was further reinforced by the Youngstown State University with similar male-female percentages, showing that relief from stress was the most common reason behind the practice. A more adverse extension of retail therapy is Oniomania or Compulsive Buying Disorder, which is an obsession with shopping, resulting in serious financial and mental consequences.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Whys behind the Comfort Buys&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While stress, anxiety and sadness are a part of daily life, they can be tackled through other means such as reaching out to others, practicing yoga, mindfulness and meditation, journaling, exercising and consulting experts in more severe cases. Despite there being these solutions, which on an average are cheaper than shopping, why do people indulge in purchasing things to boost their mood? To understand the causes behind retail therapy, the behavioral aspect of individuals needs to be analysed in a twofold manner. Even though, at first glance, these reasons seem simple — associated with daily life, a deeper analysis suggests that the root cause can be traced back to psychological theory.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Firstly, we examine the relatively straightforward causes.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;When everything goes wrong and nothing falls into place as you imagined it to, how do you feel? Out of control, right? Thus, one of the reasons people indulge in retail therapy is that shopping is a coping mechanism that helps people feel more in control. From deciding where to shop, to choosing what to purchase, it allows people to exercise autonomy and make decisions. In my personal opinion, shopping can also make one feel a sense of achievement. Utilising good offers and deals, applying coupons to get discounts and sometimes even getting goods for free certainly makes one feel happier as they ‘save’ along with fulfilling a guilty pleasure.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Secondly, retail therapy can be a useful mechanism for smooth transitions of life as it enables people to envisage their lives post such changes. For instance, people often shop excessively before they are going to live alone for the first time, shifting to a new house, getting married or having a baby. Shopping may ease anxiety by making people feel more in control by helping them to prepare themselves for such huge transitions through the process of ‘visualisation’, which is a process that boosts performance, confidence and reduces anxiety.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another way in which retail therapy boosts mood is through a pleasant gush of creativity. Specifically, clothing of various kinds of colors and textures, accessories like jewelry, footwear, bags, sunglasses, etc, home decor items may induce a positive breeze of art and aesthetics. For example, the arrival of a new outfit may stir your creative juices in thinking about what shoes, jewelry and bag to pair it up with. This may certainly bring about a calmness in a way similar to art therapy, a well-known method of healing and reducing stress.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Some people treat shopping, both online and offline as a source of refreshment from the humdrum of daily life. Being a mindless activity, it enables people to relax and take some time off from their sources of stress. This form may vary from window shopping to scrolling on an online website or going to a shopping-mall for a break.&amp;nbsp;Yet another reason behind binge-purchasing may be the need to ‘feel connected’. For instance, one may shop for a sweater with a snowman or bells, candies and wreaths for decoration during Christmas, to feel more socially connected to the festival. Or someone may shop for a beret before visiting Paris to feel a part of the culture of the fashion capital. Thus, retail therapy may help individuals to feel closer to society and culture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;An extensive scrutiny of the idea suggests that the root cause lies in Sigmund Freud’s Pleasure Principle of psychology. The principle claims that individuals instinctively seek immediate pleasure to avoid experiencing feelings of stress, pain and sadness. In the context of impulsive purchasing, the principle fits well, as it is only a short term coping mechanism rooted in instant relief from stress. As compared to the Freudian Reality Principle, the Pleasure Principle is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Present-Bias-Focus-on-the-Now-but-maybe-Not-Always&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;inability of individuals to defer immediate gratification of certain desires and wants that rationality and reality may disallow.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Sadness Cycle&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Even though retail therapy eases the anxiety and pain in people’s lives, such a positive impact may be short-lived. While retail therapy can be supported by psychological reasoning, Economics does not go hand-in-hand with the concept due to its assumption of rationality among all individuals. From the point of view of rationality, the problems of running out of budget and debts arise due to limited financial resources. Impulsive overspending may lead people to become even more anxious and distressed due to the inability of paying bills and lacking a sound financial base, in the long run. A rough patch after having run out of budget may seem more dramatic and difficult to handle, due to a lack of finance to purchase something to feel better. In desperate times like these, individuals addicted to the method, may resort to desperate measures like taking loans from others or stealing. This might be complemented with feelings of guilt due to unrealistically high expenditure patterns.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Thus, retail therapy, to an obsessive degree can lead to reverse effects by introducing a cycle of stress and anxiety for an individual rather than helping one fight the tough times.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The ‘Viral’ Remedy&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;With the Coronavirus pandemic hitting the world, people across the globe felt paralysed due to being restricted homes all the time. While this altered the work culture among people, the norms of schooling among students and put a halt to dining out, it had an impact on the shoppers. Research suggests that elements appealing to an individual’s senses, like aroma, music, a creative arrangement of products in a store, temperature contribute to the experience of shoppers. Unfortunately, with the lockdown implemented across the world, this ‘sensory’ experience was no longer available. As a result of this, one would expect sales to fall. However, the online retail industry led to a different turn of events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to &lt;em&gt;Forbes&lt;/em&gt;, as of March 2020, several online retail categories experienced a 74% year over year increase in sales, as compared to March 2018. Some of the top categories that saw a surge in the sale are home goods like furniture and home decor items and athletic and loungewear. While it may be argued that these categories resonate more with individuals in the current scenario due to the need to stay home, it must be noted that none of these items are essentials. Thus, it can be suggested that individuals binge purchased during the pandemic to escape the fears and stress of the situation and its uncertainty, thereby serving as a recent instance of retail therapy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The impact of retail therapy on an individual’s life depends upon the degree of engagement. On one hand, retail therapy in the form of window shopping, purchasing with adherence to one’s budget or buying pre-planned things can help to reduce stress and sadness both in the short term and long run. On the other hand, if the simple habit intensifies to become an addiction, it results in adverse problems which in turn brings more distress, thereby defeating the purpose of the ‘therapy’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Nirikta Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">They say, “When the going gets tough, the tough go shopping.” This is more commonly known as Retail Therapy. It is a phenomenon where people shop to improve one’s disposition and raise spirits. People in distress often resort to this as a source of solace. A study published in the journal Psychology and Marketing states that retail therapy has a lasting positive effect on mood. While its findings pointed out that these are impulsive purchases, the survey suggested that feelings of guilt or regret were not associated among the respondents.&amp;nbsp;The name in itself is ironic. Shopping is a concept deeply rooted in materialism. As its positive impact is temporary, it does not qualify as a ‘therapy’ in the medical sense. However, it is a fairly popular phrase used around the world.&amp;nbsp; In a 2001 survey conducted by the European Union, it was found that 33% of the shoppers surveyed had a “high level of addiction to rash buying”. The study also revealed that ‘binge purchasing’ was most common among the Scottish youth. Another study of 1,000 American adults, conducted in 2013, detected that more than half of the respondents indulged in retail therapy. It also threw light on the gender aspect of the practice, stating that it is more common among women than men. It was found that 64.9% of women and 38.9% of men binge purchased while women mostly bought clothing, men indulged in ‘comfort food’. This was further reinforced by the Youngstown State University with similar male-female percentages, showing that relief from stress was the most common reason behind the practice. A more adverse extension of retail therapy is Oniomania or Compulsive Buying Disorder, which is an obsession with shopping, resulting in serious financial and mental consequences.&amp;nbsp; The Whys behind the Comfort Buys&amp;nbsp; While stress, anxiety and sadness are a part of daily life, they can be tackled through other means such as reaching out to others, practicing yoga, mindfulness and meditation, journaling, exercising and consulting experts in more severe cases. Despite there being these solutions, which on an average are cheaper than shopping, why do people indulge in purchasing things to boost their mood? To understand the causes behind retail therapy, the behavioral aspect of individuals needs to be analysed in a twofold manner. Even though, at first glance, these reasons seem simple — associated with daily life, a deeper analysis suggests that the root cause can be traced back to psychological theory.&amp;nbsp; Firstly, we examine the relatively straightforward causes.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;When everything goes wrong and nothing falls into place as you imagined it to, how do you feel? Out of control, right? Thus, one of the reasons people indulge in retail therapy is that shopping is a coping mechanism that helps people feel more in control. From deciding where to shop, to choosing what to purchase, it allows people to exercise autonomy and make decisions. In my personal opinion, shopping can also make one feel a sense of achievement. Utilising good offers and deals, applying coupons to get discounts and sometimes even getting goods for free certainly makes one feel happier as they ‘save’ along with fulfilling a guilty pleasure.&amp;nbsp; Secondly, retail therapy can be a useful mechanism for smooth transitions of life as it enables people to envisage their lives post such changes. For instance, people often shop excessively before they are going to live alone for the first time, shifting to a new house, getting married or having a baby. Shopping may ease anxiety by making people feel more in control by helping them to prepare themselves for such huge transitions through the process of ‘visualisation’, which is a process that boosts performance, confidence and reduces anxiety.&amp;nbsp; Another way in which retail therapy boosts mood is through a pleasant gush of creativity. Specifically, clothing of various kinds of colors and textures, accessories like jewelry, footwear, bags, sunglasses, etc, home decor items may induce a positive breeze of art and aesthetics. For example, the arrival of a new outfit may stir your creative juices in thinking about what shoes, jewelry and bag to pair it up with. This may certainly bring about a calmness in a way similar to art therapy, a well-known method of healing and reducing stress.&amp;nbsp; Some people treat shopping, both online and offline as a source of refreshment from the humdrum of daily life. Being a mindless activity, it enables people to relax and take some time off from their sources of stress. This form may vary from window shopping to scrolling on an online website or going to a shopping-mall for a break.&amp;nbsp;Yet another reason behind binge-purchasing may be the need to ‘feel connected’. For instance, one may shop for a sweater with a snowman or bells, candies and wreaths for decoration during Christmas, to feel more socially connected to the festival. Or someone may shop for a beret before visiting Paris to feel a part of the culture of the fashion capital. Thus, retail therapy may help individuals to feel closer to society and culture.&amp;nbsp; An extensive scrutiny of the idea suggests that the root cause lies in Sigmund Freud’s Pleasure Principle of psychology. The principle claims that individuals instinctively seek immediate pleasure to avoid experiencing feelings of stress, pain and sadness. In the context of impulsive purchasing, the principle fits well, as it is only a short term coping mechanism rooted in instant relief from stress. As compared to the Freudian Reality Principle, the Pleasure Principle is the inability of individuals to defer immediate gratification of certain desires and wants that rationality and reality may disallow.&amp;nbsp; The Sadness Cycle&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Even though retail therapy eases the anxiety and pain in people’s lives, such a positive impact may be short-lived. While retail therapy can be supported by psychological reasoning, Economics does not go hand-in-hand with the concept due to its assumption of rationality among all individuals. From the point of view of rationality, the problems of running out of budget and debts arise due to limited financial resources. Impulsive overspending may lead people to become even more anxious and distressed due to the inability of paying bills and lacking a sound financial base, in the long run. A rough patch after having run out of budget may seem more dramatic and difficult to handle, due to a lack of finance to purchase something to feel better. In desperate times like these, individuals addicted to the method, may resort to desperate measures like taking loans from others or stealing. This might be complemented with feelings of guilt due to unrealistically high expenditure patterns.&amp;nbsp; Thus, retail therapy, to an obsessive degree can lead to reverse effects by introducing a cycle of stress and anxiety for an individual rather than helping one fight the tough times.&amp;nbsp; The ‘Viral’ Remedy&amp;nbsp; With the Coronavirus pandemic hitting the world, people across the globe felt paralysed due to being restricted homes all the time. While this altered the work culture among people, the norms of schooling among students and put a halt to dining out, it had an impact on the shoppers. Research suggests that elements appealing to an individual’s senses, like aroma, music, a creative arrangement of products in a store, temperature contribute to the experience of shoppers. Unfortunately, with the lockdown implemented across the world, this ‘sensory’ experience was no longer available. As a result of this, one would expect sales to fall. However, the online retail industry led to a different turn of events. According to Forbes, as of March 2020, several online retail categories experienced a 74% year over year increase in sales, as compared to March 2018. Some of the top categories that saw a surge in the sale are home goods like furniture and home decor items and athletic and loungewear. While it may be argued that these categories resonate more with individuals in the current scenario due to the need to stay home, it must be noted that none of these items are essentials. Thus, it can be suggested that individuals binge purchased during the pandemic to escape the fears and stress of the situation and its uncertainty, thereby serving as a recent instance of retail therapy.&amp;nbsp; The impact of retail therapy on an individual’s life depends upon the degree of engagement. On one hand, retail therapy in the form of window shopping, purchasing with adherence to one’s budget or buying pre-planned things can help to reduce stress and sadness both in the short term and long run. On the other hand, if the simple habit intensifies to become an addiction, it results in adverse problems which in turn brings more distress, thereby defeating the purpose of the ‘therapy’.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Weaponised Words: A Tale of Hate Speech</title>
      <link href="/Weaponised-Words-A-Tale-of-Hate-Speech" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Weaponised Words: A Tale of Hate Speech" />
      <published>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Weaponised-Words-A-Tale-of-Hate-Speech</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Weaponised-Words-A-Tale-of-Hate-Speech">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&quot;There is a fine line between free speech and hate speech. Free speech encourages debate whereas hate speech incites violence&quot; -&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Newton Lee,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/work/quotes/24289059&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Counterterrorism and Cybersecurity: Total Information Awareness&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quotation is a constant reminder of how easily hate speech overlaps with the idea of freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp;Over the past few months, the challenge of separating hate speech from the Indian citizen’s right to ‘Freedom of Expression’ has increased tremendously. Recently, several citizens including journalists, political party leaders and activists have been charged with hate speech, inflammatory speech and sedition. On one hand, offended plaintiffs file complaints due to hurt caused to their sentiments by the comments of the accused people. On the other hand, the defendants perceive it as a violation of their right to Freedom of Speech.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the light of recent incidents in India, a crucial question arises.&amp;nbsp;Should hate speech be incorporated as a part of Freedom of Speech, or should hate speech be legally regulated?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to scrutinise the idea of ‘free, hate speech’, it is important to distinguish between the two ideas of hate speech and free speech.&amp;nbsp;'Freedom of Expression or Speech' is a principle supporting the idea of an individual or a community articulating their opinions and ideas freely. It ensures such freedom “without the fear of retaliation, censorship, or legal sanction.” On the other hand, hate speech is clearly defined by the &lt;em&gt;Cambridge Dictionary&lt;/em&gt; as a &quot;public speech that expresses hate or encourages violence towards a person or a group based on something such as race, religion, sex, or sexual orientation”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get a sense of how hate speech is treated by legislation, we must take a look at a few examples. While hate speech is not a legal term in some countries, victims of hate speech may seek redressal under civil law, criminal law, or both in other nations. For instance, in the United States, hate speech is constitutionally protected. On the contrary, de jure, freedom of expression is promised in North Korea but there is no de facto right to free speech as asserted by Amnesty International, a human rights group.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In India, hate speech is regulated. While ‘Freedom of Speech and Expression’ is a fundamental right of the Indian Constitution, under Article 19(2) &quot;reasonable restrictions&quot; can be imposed on this right. This is in order to protect &quot;the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of the State, friendly relations with foreign States, public order, decency or morality, or in relation to contempt of court, defamation or incitement to an offence&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hurdle of Hate&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hate speech is a threat to humankind because words have the power to influence people to take action. It causes instability and agitation across the society. It can lead to reduced motivation, lower tolerance, emotional trauma or in extreme cases, depression.&amp;nbsp;Raising this concern, Joyce Arthur, a Canadian activist, in an article titled 'Should Hate Speech be a Crime?' underlines the importance of hate speech legislation. She elucidates that hate speech needs to be regulated as it has a huge impact on people’s dignity and human rights. Hate speech is often derogatory to the sentiments of a particular caste, creed, sex or religion as it is often rooted in stereotypes, prejudices and personal experiences which may be an inaccurate perception of the group or community as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A product of hate speech is hate crime&lt;/strong&gt;. Hate crimes are dangerous as they jeopardise amity in society, instigate precarity among communities, and foster a sense of animosity in the democracy.&amp;nbsp;In the technological era, hate speech over social media causes a tremendous amount of intolerance and violence leading to hate crimes. For instance, the perpetrator of the 2019 New Zealand mosque shootings killed 49 Muslims at prayer and sought to broadcast the attack on YouTube. In Germany, a correlation was observed between anti-refugee Facebook posts by the Alternative for Germany party and increasing attacks on refugees. In India, the recent case of Delhi violence due to hate speech and rumors on social media is also another instance.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hate Speech in India&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While 2020 has been a relatively inactive year for India in terms of business and functioning of institutions, the story is very different when it comes to hate speech laws. Starting from January 2020, there have been 10+ cases involving charges for sedition and hate speech.&amp;nbsp;Among journalists, Arnab Goswami, Amish Devgan and Vinod Dua are a few who&amp;nbsp; have faced FIRs or First Information Reports against them. On one hand, Amish Devgan was accused of injuring religious sentiments on his show. On the other hand, Goswami and Dua faced charges for criticising the State in different forms. FIRs against Goswami have been filed in relation to his questioning opposition leader Sonia Gandhi regarding mob lynching in the Palghar district of Western India. And Dua has been charged with sedition for a Youtube broadcast wherein he said that the State failed to implement the lockdown.&amp;nbsp;Sharjeel Imam, an Indian activist, has been charged with sedition, hate speech and promoting religious antagonism for his speeches against the Citizenship Amendment Act.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These diverse cases point out that it is also challenging and important to define specifically what can be categorized as hate speech.&amp;nbsp;A striking point has been stated in one of the articles in &lt;em&gt;Indian Express&lt;/em&gt;. It says that out of the ten hate speech cases that were scrutinised, including the ones mentioned above, the cases where the State and the petitioner contended on the same side, relief was provided. However, in six cases, where the State was accused, no relief was granted to the petitioner. A ‘telling pattern’ of this sort indicates a fresh challenge of violation of the right to equality before the law.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of this is the regulation of hate speech over social media. While trolling is only the tip of the iceberg, Facebook has recently faced challenges concerning hate speech rules. The &lt;em&gt;Wall Street Journal&lt;/em&gt; has accused Facebook of having failed to apply hate speech regulations on content posted by a BJP leader from the state of Telangana. Three other party leaders’ posts have also been overlooked.&amp;nbsp;A great initiative to combat such challenges is Facebook’s Oversight Board. The Oversight Board is an entity vested with the power to moderate and make independent decisions regarding content over social media sites like Facebook and Instagram. Its purpose is the protection of Facebook users. Hate speech and cases related to ‘political bias’ are within the purview of the board.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Watershed Verdicts&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1962 Indian Supreme Court judgement in &lt;em&gt;Kedar Nath Singh vs State of Bihar&lt;/em&gt; is a landmark judgement concerning the right to Freedom of Expression. The defendant faced charges of sedition and inciting public mischief due to a criticism of the then ruling party, the Indian National Congress in his speech. The defendant argued that the provisions on sedition in the Indian Penal Code (IPC) violated the right to Freedom of Expression under Article 19(1)(a) of the Indian Constitution.&amp;nbsp;The Court asserted that these were not under the purview of “reasonable restrictions” under Article 19(2). It explained that the phrase “Government established by law” under section 124A is different from the criticism of a political party or political leaders.&amp;nbsp;Yet sedition continues to be criminalised under the IPC. However, its provision has been narrowed down to only criminalise expression that intends to jeopardize public order and peace through violence, thereby protecting the right to freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another remarkable judgement in the field of online free speech is &lt;em&gt;Shreya Singhal vs Union of India (UOI).&lt;/em&gt; Two women were arrested under Section 66A of the Information Technology Act, 2000 for ‘posting allegedly offensive comments on Facebook’. As per the section, any person who sends “grossly offensive information” or information “to cause insult, injury or ill will” can be punished. These women filed a petition arguing that Section 66A was constitutionally invalid on the grounds of violation of the right to freedom of speech.&amp;nbsp;In 2015, the Supreme Court declared Section 66A to be unconstitutional and it was struck down. This was because Section 66A was not recognized as a “reasonable restriction” under Article 19(2). Thus, this was a turning point for online free speech.&amp;nbsp;These landmark judgements are useful to cite in cases relating to hate speech and freedom of expression for stronger established arguments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above-mentioned arguments and instances indicate that hate speech needs to be tackled through a balanced approach. While the right to freedom of expression needs to be upheld, hate speech intending to cause violence, disturb public order and promote unrest can prove to be detrimental for humankind.&amp;nbsp;A study by the Pew Research Center reveals that 67% and 27% of people in the United States and Asia-Pacific, respectively, agree with free hate speech. Nonetheless, as the saying goes, “Hate begets more hate”, hate speech causes a vicious cycle of hatred that has no end.&amp;nbsp;Thus, to balance respectful and considerate free speech without hampering the true essence of the Freedom of Expression, regulation of hate speech and uniform implementation of such rules is the need of the hour.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Nirikta Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">&quot;There is a fine line between free speech and hate speech. Free speech encourages debate whereas hate speech incites violence&quot; - Newton Lee, Counterterrorism and Cybersecurity: Total Information Awareness This quotation is a constant reminder of how easily hate speech overlaps with the idea of freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp;Over the past few months, the challenge of separating hate speech from the Indian citizen’s right to ‘Freedom of Expression’ has increased tremendously. Recently, several citizens including journalists, political party leaders and activists have been charged with hate speech, inflammatory speech and sedition. On one hand, offended plaintiffs file complaints due to hurt caused to their sentiments by the comments of the accused people. On the other hand, the defendants perceive it as a violation of their right to Freedom of Speech.&amp;nbsp; In the light of recent incidents in India, a crucial question arises.&amp;nbsp;Should hate speech be incorporated as a part of Freedom of Speech, or should hate speech be legally regulated?&amp;nbsp; In order to scrutinise the idea of ‘free, hate speech’, it is important to distinguish between the two ideas of hate speech and free speech.&amp;nbsp;'Freedom of Expression or Speech' is a principle supporting the idea of an individual or a community articulating their opinions and ideas freely. It ensures such freedom “without the fear of retaliation, censorship, or legal sanction.” On the other hand, hate speech is clearly defined by the Cambridge Dictionary as a &quot;public speech that expresses hate or encourages violence towards a person or a group based on something such as race, religion, sex, or sexual orientation”. To get a sense of how hate speech is treated by legislation, we must take a look at a few examples. While hate speech is not a legal term in some countries, victims of hate speech may seek redressal under civil law, criminal law, or both in other nations. For instance, in the United States, hate speech is constitutionally protected. On the contrary, de jure, freedom of expression is promised in North Korea but there is no de facto right to free speech as asserted by Amnesty International, a human rights group.&amp;nbsp; In India, hate speech is regulated. While ‘Freedom of Speech and Expression’ is a fundamental right of the Indian Constitution, under Article 19(2) &quot;reasonable restrictions&quot; can be imposed on this right. This is in order to protect &quot;the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of the State, friendly relations with foreign States, public order, decency or morality, or in relation to contempt of court, defamation or incitement to an offence&quot;. Hurdle of Hate&amp;nbsp; Hate speech is a threat to humankind because words have the power to influence people to take action. It causes instability and agitation across the society. It can lead to reduced motivation, lower tolerance, emotional trauma or in extreme cases, depression.&amp;nbsp;Raising this concern, Joyce Arthur, a Canadian activist, in an article titled 'Should Hate Speech be a Crime?' underlines the importance of hate speech legislation. She elucidates that hate speech needs to be regulated as it has a huge impact on people’s dignity and human rights. Hate speech is often derogatory to the sentiments of a particular caste, creed, sex or religion as it is often rooted in stereotypes, prejudices and personal experiences which may be an inaccurate perception of the group or community as a whole. A product of hate speech is hate crime. Hate crimes are dangerous as they jeopardise amity in society, instigate precarity among communities, and foster a sense of animosity in the democracy.&amp;nbsp;In the technological era, hate speech over social media causes a tremendous amount of intolerance and violence leading to hate crimes. For instance, the perpetrator of the 2019 New Zealand mosque shootings killed 49 Muslims at prayer and sought to broadcast the attack on YouTube. In Germany, a correlation was observed between anti-refugee Facebook posts by the Alternative for Germany party and increasing attacks on refugees. In India, the recent case of Delhi violence due to hate speech and rumors on social media is also another instance.&amp;nbsp; Hate Speech in India&amp;nbsp; While 2020 has been a relatively inactive year for India in terms of business and functioning of institutions, the story is very different when it comes to hate speech laws. Starting from January 2020, there have been 10+ cases involving charges for sedition and hate speech.&amp;nbsp;Among journalists, Arnab Goswami, Amish Devgan and Vinod Dua are a few who&amp;nbsp; have faced FIRs or First Information Reports against them. On one hand, Amish Devgan was accused of injuring religious sentiments on his show. On the other hand, Goswami and Dua faced charges for criticising the State in different forms. FIRs against Goswami have been filed in relation to his questioning opposition leader Sonia Gandhi regarding mob lynching in the Palghar district of Western India. And Dua has been charged with sedition for a Youtube broadcast wherein he said that the State failed to implement the lockdown.&amp;nbsp;Sharjeel Imam, an Indian activist, has been charged with sedition, hate speech and promoting religious antagonism for his speeches against the Citizenship Amendment Act.&amp;nbsp; These diverse cases point out that it is also challenging and important to define specifically what can be categorized as hate speech.&amp;nbsp;A striking point has been stated in one of the articles in Indian Express. It says that out of the ten hate speech cases that were scrutinised, including the ones mentioned above, the cases where the State and the petitioner contended on the same side, relief was provided. However, in six cases, where the State was accused, no relief was granted to the petitioner. A ‘telling pattern’ of this sort indicates a fresh challenge of violation of the right to equality before the law.&amp;nbsp; Another aspect of this is the regulation of hate speech over social media. While trolling is only the tip of the iceberg, Facebook has recently faced challenges concerning hate speech rules. The Wall Street Journal has accused Facebook of having failed to apply hate speech regulations on content posted by a BJP leader from the state of Telangana. Three other party leaders’ posts have also been overlooked.&amp;nbsp;A great initiative to combat such challenges is Facebook’s Oversight Board. The Oversight Board is an entity vested with the power to moderate and make independent decisions regarding content over social media sites like Facebook and Instagram. Its purpose is the protection of Facebook users. Hate speech and cases related to ‘political bias’ are within the purview of the board.&amp;nbsp; Watershed Verdicts&amp;nbsp; The 1962 Indian Supreme Court judgement in Kedar Nath Singh vs State of Bihar is a landmark judgement concerning the right to Freedom of Expression. The defendant faced charges of sedition and inciting public mischief due to a criticism of the then ruling party, the Indian National Congress in his speech. The defendant argued that the provisions on sedition in the Indian Penal Code (IPC) violated the right to Freedom of Expression under Article 19(1)(a) of the Indian Constitution.&amp;nbsp;The Court asserted that these were not under the purview of “reasonable restrictions” under Article 19(2). It explained that the phrase “Government established by law” under section 124A is different from the criticism of a political party or political leaders.&amp;nbsp;Yet sedition continues to be criminalised under the IPC. However, its provision has been narrowed down to only criminalise expression that intends to jeopardize public order and peace through violence, thereby protecting the right to freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp; Another remarkable judgement in the field of online free speech is Shreya Singhal vs Union of India (UOI). Two women were arrested under Section 66A of the Information Technology Act, 2000 for ‘posting allegedly offensive comments on Facebook’. As per the section, any person who sends “grossly offensive information” or information “to cause insult, injury or ill will” can be punished. These women filed a petition arguing that Section 66A was constitutionally invalid on the grounds of violation of the right to freedom of speech.&amp;nbsp;In 2015, the Supreme Court declared Section 66A to be unconstitutional and it was struck down. This was because Section 66A was not recognized as a “reasonable restriction” under Article 19(2). Thus, this was a turning point for online free speech.&amp;nbsp;These landmark judgements are useful to cite in cases relating to hate speech and freedom of expression for stronger established arguments.&amp;nbsp; The above-mentioned arguments and instances indicate that hate speech needs to be tackled through a balanced approach. While the right to freedom of expression needs to be upheld, hate speech intending to cause violence, disturb public order and promote unrest can prove to be detrimental for humankind.&amp;nbsp;A study by the Pew Research Center reveals that 67% and 27% of people in the United States and Asia-Pacific, respectively, agree with free hate speech. Nonetheless, as the saying goes, “Hate begets more hate”, hate speech causes a vicious cycle of hatred that has no end.&amp;nbsp;Thus, to balance respectful and considerate free speech without hampering the true essence of the Freedom of Expression, regulation of hate speech and uniform implementation of such rules is the need of the hour.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
