<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/devyani.arora/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-04-14T18:42:48+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/devyani.arora/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Sexism and the City</title>
      <link href="/Sexism-and-the-City" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sexism and the City" />
      <published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Sexism-and-the-City</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Sexism-and-the-City">&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that this big bad world is biased towards the people with both the X and Y chromosomes, thanks to the patriarchy that has upheld the ideas of male superiority. These biases further suggest that women are inferior because of their sex. Thus, any expression upholding these biases can be termed as — ‘sexist.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sexism can affect anyone, however, there have been few men on the receiving end. It affects men and boys when they don’t conform to gender roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this article, we will restrict the ambit of our discussion to only the University level in India. Sexist attitudes are not just limited to boys rating girls on a scale of 0-10 based on their physical appearances. It has transcended into limiting the opportunities for women, imposing draconian rules and observing traditions that are misogynistic and chauvinist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often consider academia as the citadel of everything fair and progressive. However, we don’t live in a utopian world. Just like other institutions that have these notions of male superiority deep-rooted in their practices and norms, so does education. Many people benefit from these power dynamics in the status quo, and thus, have no incentive to change it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a stark imbalance in the male to female ratio in many courses such as law, management, and STEM disciplines. Considered the holy grail of education and achievement, Indian Institutes of Technology (IITs), suffer from the worst gender imbalance with only 9.3% of females. This gap further increases with progression in these careers, with an utter lack of women in leadership positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see this trend across central universities in India. Out of 46 central universities, only 5 have women placed as the heads of the institutions. Even in India’s most liberal universities, like Jawaharlal Nehru University (JNU), no women has ever been the head of the institute. The selection committees are dominated by men, who give little weightage to women candidates as many view women as someone who has stolen a job a man was entitled to do. This perception has risen from the cultural view that men are the bread-earners of the family while women are the homemakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In colleges with extreme gender disproportion, the environment becomes testosterone-driven, leading to women students being subjected to sexual innuendos and sexist remarks. Language and communication make people recognise or demean their contribution to society. Our language shapes our thoughts, and the way we think influences our actions. Gender-discriminatory language reinforces sexist attitudes and behaviours. Thus, female students become conditioned to accept subtle sexism and lewd remarks as the norm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sexism in Indian universities isn’t just limited to leadership positions but encompasses norms that affect the day-to-day lives of many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many colleges across India, dress codes are imposed on women. For example, The Government Medical College, Kerala issued a dress code for its female students instructing them not to wear jeans, leggings, short tops or noisy ornaments. Many girls’ hostels also follow curfews, thus increasing the red tape for them to step out. Many institutions like Jamia Milia University, IITs and the University of Delhi have come under the light in the past for such rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such draconian measures show how expecting equality remains a far-off dream for girls. These rules concretise the notion that the price for the safety of women is curbing their freedom rather than bringing a systemic change in the attitude of men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Symbiosis Center for Media and Communication (SCMC) Pune is widely recognised for its option of ‘film and television’ specialisation as a part of its three-year undergraduate program. In her article for &lt;em&gt;The Print&lt;/em&gt;, Vaishnavi Suresh, an SCMC alumnus highlights the rampant sexism in the coveted institution. Being a media college, the students spend a large amount of time in classes watching films. Vaishnavi, however, notes how the students barely had any female filmmakers as role models. In an incident where some people from her class suggested they study a female filmmaker, the professor shot down their requests and instead taught them about another male filmmaker. She also noted how by the time they came to their 3rd year, only 2 women out of her batch were still invested in the camera by practising photography or videography. She cites the reason for this to be the “reality of the industry drilled into them constantly.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A college that prides itself on being liberal lacks showing its students that women could be role models too. Having female role models is important for breaking the stereotype of men being better than women to propagate for a more inclusive world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016, while the #MeToo movement was still in its nascent stage, the students of Women Centred Practices at Tata Institute of Social Sciences (TISS), Mumbai organised a ‘Gender Sensitisation Week’ in their campus. Amidst the gender sensitisation week, a signed comment was noticed on a banner that was put up for people to anonymously share accounts of sexist instances on campus. It read, “Sexism is an accusation, sluts level against dissenting voices for recognising that a slut is a slut.” Instances like these make one realise that the notion of some campuses being ‘more sensitive and liberal than the rest of the world’, is nothing but a facade. People still trivialise sexual harassment, use the word ‘slut’ as a derogatory term and push aside voices of dissent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2019, a few pre-university colleges in Bengaluru set higher cut-off marks for girls for admission into the courses. On inquiring about the reason behind this move, the Vice-Chancellor of Christ PU College, Fr Abraham VM, commented - “Girls are smart, and this is not a new trend. If there is no higher cut-off, the college will have only girls. The higher cut-off is to bring in gender balance.” Subsequently, the cut-off for science stream in Christ college was fixed at 93.92% for girls and 91.04% for boys. This move begs the question that in a society where historically almost every classroom has been dominated by men, why do we fear if women step into those shoes. It seems like a move to &lt;em&gt;punish&lt;/em&gt; women for breaking the glass ceiling despite being on the worse off end of the access to opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the most famous sexist tradition would be the regressive Virgin Tree ‘Pooja’ on Valentine’s Day at Hindu College (University of Delhi). The Pooja is a customary tradition wherein the boys’ hostel decorates a ‘virgin tree’ on campus with condoms and posters of an actress naming her the Damdami Mai. This actress, seen as a sex symbol, is ‘worshipped’ on Valentine’s Day and according to legend, the people partaking in this practice lose their virginity in the coming six months or at least get into a relationship. In a university space, where we regard sexuality-related conversations as a taboo, they often term such a celebration as ‘liberatory.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The V-Day pooja, which has been taking place since 1953, is ridden in a Brahmanical and casteist notion of prayer and reward. Highly offensive and misogynistic, the pooja follows a hollow notion of ‘sex-positivity’ while overlooking homosexual relationships. The celebration reinforces the existing patriarchal structures which have ingrained insecurity in the minds of young women by reducing their value to just the pleasure of and determined by an external male gaze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;College is the first encounter of the young adults with reality by giving them a peek into the larger world out there. It introduces us to the workings of the ‘real world’ and underpins many of our perspectives and expectations in a social context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sexist practices create a climate of fear and insecurity by producing feelings of worthlessness, self-censorship, and changes in behaviour. This further leads to the deterioration of people’s mental health and makes them acceptable to violence, as they now think they &lt;em&gt;deserve&lt;/em&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When students are exposed to these ideas in college, it either normalises these ideas for many by ingraining notions of male superiority. Or it makes people recognise and fight the problem. The wave of social consciousness and woke culture have made the youth today more liberal than their predecessors, leading to more inclusive spaces for women and homosexuals in institutions. They, however, remain a minority faction and their wokeness hasn’t led to a ripple effect big enough to shake down sexism on a bigger level. The boy’s hostel at Hindu College plans to host the Virgin Tree Pooja in 2021, many girls’ hostels continue to follow the archaic dress codes and curfews, and conversations among men will continue to be casually sexist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All over the world, people have celebrated 46 International Women’s Days and 6 Zero Discrimination Days and will celebrate many more, but until we abolish all discriminatory and sexist practices, we won’t be celebrating these days in their true essence.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It’s no secret that this big bad world is biased towards the people with both the X and Y chromosomes, thanks to the patriarchy that has upheld the ideas of male superiority. These biases further suggest that women are inferior because of their sex. Thus, any expression upholding these biases can be termed as — ‘sexist.’</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Beware, You’re Being Watched!</title>
      <link href="/Beware-You-re-Being-Watched" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beware, You’re Being Watched!" />
      <published>2020-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Beware-You-re-Being-Watched</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Beware-You-re-Being-Watched">&lt;p&gt;The Netflix show &lt;em&gt;You&lt;/em&gt; has made its way to one of the most talked-about television shows on social media. It revolves around the creepy but hot stalker who spies on women using telescopes and by physically following them. If you think this merely happens in fiction, wait till the end of this article. Before we begin, this article isn’t about a particular political party acting as the villain, though all of them may be considered so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the increased use of technology by criminals, government surveillance is inevitable. In almost every nation, a certain proportion of the population is under the scanner of intelligence agencies. However, the potential mass-scale tracking of the data of all citizens has sparked a grave debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s surveillance systems have access to 100% of all internet activity, with broad surveillance capability based on IP, email addresses, URLs, HTTP, Telenet, or webmail, and even through abroad and blind searches across all traffic in the internet pipe using keywords and key-phrases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Central Monitoring System (CMS), launched in 2013, is the surveillance project which allows the Indian government to monitor online and telephonic data of citizens. Unlike its American counterpart PRISM, there is no legal recourse for a citizen whose personal details are being misused or leaked from the central or regional database. CMS does not even have any judicial oversight.In India, most orders are signed by either the Central or State Home Secretary. This causes a conflict of interest, as the executive branch is both undertaking law enforcement and providing oversight on its work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pursuit of internet monitoring started following the leak of the Amar Singh tapes, with instructions for ensuring the privacy of communications. This mandated all ISPs (Internet Service Providers) to have designated nodal officers for communicating and receiving the intimations for interceptions. Since the government controlled the LIMs (Lawful Intercept and Monitoring Systems), it directly sent software commands and sucked out whatever information is needed from the internet pipe with no intimation to anyone. The lack of a privacy law made it easier for the government to undertake such radical steps. The Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 and the Information Technology Act, 2008, allowed the government to monitor, intercept, and even block online conversations and websites. The addition of the CMS significantly widened the number of sources and could simplify access to these records. In 2019, the government went even further with this pursuit of privacy, like passing the Data Protection Bill and forming the NATGRID.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Intelligence Grid (NATGRID) aims to allow investigation and law enforcement agencies to access real-time information from data stored with agencies such as the Income Tax Department, banks, insurance companies, Indian Railways, credit card transactions, and more. It is meant to connect public and private databases for ten central intelligence agencies. State agencies, however, will not be allowed access to the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NATGRID was first introduced post the 26/11 Mumbai terror attacks by the then Home Minister Mr P Chidambaram. After 10 years of delay, on September 12, 2019, Home Minister Amit Shah announced that the NATGRID would be functional by the end of 2019. Along with the Crime and Criminal Tracking Network System (CCTNS), which will integrate the Central and State crime data, NATGRID will give a suspect’s ‘360-degree’ profile. This system could prevent or detect incidents like the 26/11 attacks, claims the Home Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been many concerns regarding the dangers of misuse of this system. The unified pooling of vital information from different resources is vulnerable to cyber attacks or espionage from foreign intelligence agencies. Given the recent WhatsApp data breach, this apprehension needs to be addressed by having proper checks and balances in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, who is watching the notorious &lt;em&gt;chowkidars&lt;/em&gt; (watchmen)? Also, if someone violated your privacy, but you never knew about it, did it even happen? This is where the Data Protection Bill, 2019, becomes important. It is India’s first step towards a privacy framework and sets a framework to govern personal data. The bill is meant to ensure that Indian citizens have control of their data. The bill seeks to localise the storage of data and to set up the Data Protection Authority of India. However, under the bill, not only will your sensitive personal information be stored but also information about you and your online habits. It is a potential avenue for the invasion of privacy because it can reveal many personal aspects. Companies, governments, and political parties can further use these to find the most convincing ways to advertise to you online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has exempted its agencies from the rules that govern the processing of personal data citing national security, public order and friendly relations with foreign states. 24x7 surveillance acts as a major threat to businesses. Businesses are formed on the foundations of security and trust: from the purchase of an item on an e-commerce site to a company’s research mechanisms and technologies. Central databases make attacking a company based on such confidential information easier. All one would have to do to go one-up on you is to attack these databases. It was because of this the USA decided not to impose blanket surveillance. Their idea is “while we may live in a society without human rights, we cannot be in one without functional markets”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, it allows the government to manipulate the data patterns and wrongly accuse innocent citizens of being criminals. With NATGRID and the Data Protection Bill, the government shall have access to all data. In a world where the government claims that peaceful protests by the students are a threat to national security and anyone can be labelled a terrorist without evidence, the exemptions in the Data Protection Bill become important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government can access private data or government agency data on grounds of sovereignty or public order. This has dangerous implications. While the Indian Constitution recognises the right to privacy, there are very few laws governing government surveillance. Due to this, there is very little legislative oversight, leading to little judicial decision-making regarding surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Acton had famously prophesied that “power tends to corrupt and absolute power corrupts absolutely”. This peril is more acute when the power is used covertly. Efforts to maintain accountability over intelligence agencies are frequently troublesome. All things considered, intelligence agencies comprise human beings, with their capabilities being circumscribed by human flaws, frailties and defects. Thus, safeguards are unavoidable and unnecessary, unfortunately, or rather, suspiciously, the Indian government seems blissfully unaware of that necessity, betraying its desire to be the stalker in people’s homes.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Netflix show You has made its way to one of the most talked-about television shows on social media. It revolves around the creepy but hot stalker who spies on women using telescopes and by physically following them. If you think this merely happens in fiction, wait till the end of this article. Before we begin, this article isn’t about a particular political party acting as the villain, though all of them may be considered so.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Women are Under-represented? Not News.</title>
      <link href="/Women-are-Under-represented-Not-News" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Women are Under-represented? Not News." />
      <published>2020-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Women-are-Under-represented-Not-News</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Women-are-Under-represented-Not-News">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I only go to a movie if it satisfies three basic requirements. One, it has to have at least two women in it, who, two, talk to each other about, three, something besides a man.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1985, a new edition of the comic strip &lt;em&gt;Dykes to Watch Out For&lt;/em&gt;, called ‘The Rule’, first introduced the ‘Bechdel Test’ to the film industry. The writers portrayed the character as avoiding cinema with an extreme male bias, with the character in the script claiming that she hasn’t been able to watch a movie since the 1979 space horror film &lt;em&gt;Alien&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a society where patriarchy has been the dominating narrative, it’s no surprise that women’s representation in the film industry (or any industry, for that matter) is lacking. Looking at statistics from the past few years, women play only about 37% of roles on television (2015). In films, the percentage of speaking roles for women drops to 28% (2012). Women make up a mere 16% of directors, writers, producers, and editors (2013).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many are unaware that gender stereotypes are not just linked to the costumes but are intrinsic to a character’s conversations, actions and traits. To understand how grave the situation is, the Test proves to be helpful. The Bechdel Test is a convenient way to gauge the active presence of female characters in films and just how well-rounded and complete those roles are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On listening to what it takes for the movies to pass the test, one might think: “This seems easy, I bet most movies pass it.” And that’s what I expected. But on researching more on the topic, the number of popular movies that couldn’t pass this simple test turned out to be astonishing. At the 2014 Academy Awards, only three out of the eight nominees for Best Picture passed the Bechdel Test: &lt;em&gt;Boyhood&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Theory of Everything&lt;/em&gt;. Corresponding to research by Duke University in 2017, over 40% of all the films in the US failed the test. The team used data from the bechdeltest.com website, a user-compiled database of over 7,000 movies where volunteers rate films based on the Bechdel criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These results show the under-representation of women’s complex lives in the film industry. The Bechdel Test’s demands set a low bar for the filmmakers to meet and they start a conversation about gender inequality in film. The test has brought to light the importance of shifting the focus from men to the other things in a woman’s life: career goals, friendships, inner troubles, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the test comes with its own set of problems. A film passing the test doesn’t mean the movie automatically becomes one that the feminists support. The Bechdel Test can be a misleading gauge of ‘feminism’ in movies. Films with a strong female lead don’t provide a supporting female character who holds enough importance to converse with the lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many movies that pass the test, do so based on a ‘technicality’: in some inconsequential scene, the women have a small conversation about something other than men, therefore fulfilling the criteria. For example, &lt;em&gt;Gravity&lt;/em&gt; featuring a female astronaut doesn’t pass the test. However, &lt;em&gt;Legally Blonde&lt;/em&gt; does because Elle and her friend talk about their dogs in a scene or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female characters have followed the same tropes. The movies make women damsels in distress or a ‘manic pixie dream girl.’ They also sexualise women, forcing them to wear tight-fitting clothes and heels throughout the movie. Adjectives about physical attributes like beautiful, gorgeous and pretty are used to describe the female characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another common trope used is called ‘fridging’ wherein the female characters are injured, raped, killed, or depowered, sometimes to stimulate ‘protective’ traits in men, and often as a plot device intended to move a male character’s story arc forward. &lt;em&gt;Women in Refrigerators&lt;/em&gt;, a website created in 1999 by a group of feminist comic-book fans lists examples of this trope. It refers to an incident in &lt;em&gt;Green Lantern #54&lt;/em&gt; (1994), in which, the title hero, Kyle Rayner, comes home to his apartment to find that his girlfriend had been killed and stuffed into a refrigerator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, however, is not the sole test. The ‘Mako Mori Test’ requires that: The film must feature at least one female character, who has her narrative arc that does not depend on supporting a man’s story. Likewise, the ‘DuVernay Test’ determines a film’s racial diversity. It checks if the minorities have realised lives rather than serving as scenery in the stories of the whites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these tests prove to be like the Bechdel Test as they provide data about representation but cannot provide a coherent picture if the film is feminist enough. Some critics argue that the problem lies in the disagreement about what it means to be a ‘feminist film.’ Because of this, forming a one-size-fits-all test for judging feminism has been difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female representation worsens across intersectionality. Under the broader umbrella of female characters, there are even fewer black females, Latina females, Lesbians or Transgenders. Hollywood executives have knocked dark-skinned women to the side in favour of those with European features and pale complexions. ‘Colourism’ isn’t, however, unique to the black community. In the Bollywood film industry, too, the starring roles go to lighter-skinned actors. Many of them also endorse fairness creams and other similar products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the 2018 USC Annenberg Inclusion Initiative study, out of the top 100 films in 2017, 43 films didn’t include any African-American female character. Sixty-five films were missing Asian or Asian-American female characters, and 64 didn’t include a Latina character. Ninety-four didn’t feature characters with disabilities and LGBTQ characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representation is significant for all communities. However, more than representation, it’s accurate representation that is important. Accurate and well-rounded representation allows people to see a world outside of themselves, fostering critical thinking and empathy with those who are different. The stereotypes don’t allow for the representation to portray the full picture of the complexities of the surrounding people. Because of the aspirational value that pop culture holds, it becomes a cunning, persuasive and pervasive educator. As an educator, it has the power to shape views and opinions about how people look at themselves and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representation in the film industry, however, isn’t just limited to on-screen representation but also extends to those who are working behind the camera. Figures published by &lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt; have revealed that only 22% of the crew involved in making 2,000 of the biggest grossing films over the past 20 years were women. Further, the report revealed a split in responsibilities: women made up a majority only in costume and wardrobe departments and casting. These departments have been perceived as feminine workplaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue deepens when you take into consideration the wage gap between the actors and actresses. &lt;em&gt;Forbes’&lt;/em&gt; analysis of American acting salaries in 2013 determined that the top-paid actors for that year made 2½ times as much money as the top-paid actresses. This means that Hollywood’s best-compensated actresses made just 40 cents for every dollar that the best-compensated men made. Women who have spoken about the issue explain the reason for not demanding higher pay as “they worry about seeming difficult or spoiled.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her 2018 Oscar speech, Frances McDormand suggested an ‘inclusion rider’, a clause in contracts meant to stipulate that 50% of a film crew had to be female. If A-list actors put this clause into practice, the film industry could portray the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Film producers and showrunners have, however, started to take charge. In 2015, the film professionals started the “Bechdel Bill” campaign, who pledged that 80% of their films will pass the test. CW also incorporated the Bechdel Test in two of its shows: &lt;em&gt;Crazy Ex-Girlfriend&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Jane the Virgin&lt;/em&gt;. Despite both shows not passing the test, the move was symbolic as the network constructed a space in which discourse could take place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This discourse can challenge Hollywood to do more than settle for the status quo and to question the absences of many types of people from the movie-making process. These people could potentially enrich our entertainment in countless ways, both on the screen and behind the lens. A post &lt;em&gt;#&lt;/em&gt;MeToo and #TimesUp world has the potential to hold Hollywood accountable and challenge the oppressive structure to demand a more inclusive industry that isn’t hegemonised by cis-white-men.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“I only go to a movie if it satisfies three basic requirements. One, it has to have at least two women in it, who, two, talk to each other about, three, something besides a man.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Sikhs in Canada: A Thorn in India’s Side</title>
      <link href="/Sikhs-in-Canada" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sikhs in Canada: A Thorn in India's Side" />
      <published>2019-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Sikhs-in-Canada</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Sikhs-in-Canada">&lt;p&gt;For many families in Punjab, shifting to Canada and being a permanent resident is the objective. Families want their sons to settle there and their daughters to marry the rich non-resident Indians. ‘&lt;em&gt;Caneda&lt;/em&gt;’ is a household term and a second home for these Punjabis. The rate of migration is such that Punjabis in Canada form roughly 2% of the total population, with a majority of them being Sikh. Punjabi is the third-most spoken language in Canada, after English and French. For the rest of us in India, it only seems fair to imagine a day when &lt;em&gt;Caneda&lt;/em&gt;’s Prime Minister is also a Sikh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the broader picture of Indo-Canadian relations shows a little more animosity between the two countries. The two countries share various complementarities, like their democratic character and association with the Commonwealth. Despite this and both countries recognising the economic potential in their bilateral ties, the relationship has been rather tense on the political front and thus has not prospered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major factor for this has been the activities of the Khalistan supporters in Canada. Canada’s criticism of India has also been responsible for denting India’s interest in engaging with Canada as a strategic partner. These criticisms have involved past events such as the military action in Amritsar’s Golden Temple and the 1984 riots. Relations reached one of their lowest points in 1985, when Sikh extremists blew up Air India Flight 182 as it left Vancouver Airport for India, killing all 329 passengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides these issues, the current political scenario of Canada has also caused some concern for India. Because of the prominent involvement of Sikhs in Canada’s politics and the regionalisation of Indo-Canadian politics, issues affecting the Sikh diaspora have often become a part of the political discourse in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While moderates view India favourably and oppose secessionist sentiments, the fundamentalist groups, such as the Babbar Khalsa, vehemently advocate for the Khalistan cause. Events like the 1984 riots and the Golden Temple incident have been frequently introduced in Canada’s provincial legislatures, often in the form of petitions. In 2010, for instance, Liberal MPs Sukh Dhaliwal and Andrew Kania introduced a petition in the House of Commons asking Canada to consider the 1984 riots as an act of genocide and discuss the issue with India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Justin Trudeau has often been caught in the crossfire between pandering to the Sikh population in his country and maintaining peaceful relations with India. Canadian politicians tread a fine line when attempting to involve themselves in the Sikh community, ensuring that people do not see them advocating for separatist causes inadvertently. The Sikhs in Canada form a voting bloc for Trudeau. In April 2019, his government removed a reference to Sikh extremism from a report that had earlier termed Sikh terrorism as one of the five threats facing Canada. He even attended a Khalsa Day parade organized by a radical Gurudwara in Toronto in 2017 where people waved Khalistani flags and put images of Sikh separatist leaders and militants on display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canada cannot curtail the right to freedom of speech and expression of its Sikh citizens, but New Delhi wants Trudeau to distance himself from Sikh separatists, publicly. PM Narendra Modi clarified that India would not tolerate any attempts to undermine India’s sovereignty and unity in his press conference with Trudeau. Punjab’s Chief Minister, Amarinder Singh has publicly accused Trudeau’s ministers of having sympathies with Canadian Sikh extremists and secessionists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;18 Sikhs were voted into the 338-seat lower house of the Canadian Parliament in the 2019 Federal Elections. However, only 13 candidates from the Sikh community were elected to the 543-seat Lok Sabha in the 17th General Elections in India. Sikhs form approximately 2% of the population both in Canada and India, but their representation in politics is unmatched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of these 18 Sikhs is the leader of the National Democratic Party (NDP), Jagmeet Singh. A former criminal lawyer, Singh created political history in Canada when he made his debut in the House of Commons as the first non-white leader of a major opposition party in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pre-election polls showed he was the most popular of the three party leaders. Singh is your poster woke boy with swag. Recognised in Canadian media for his fashion sense and style, Singh identifies as a progressive and a social democrat. He supports a progressive tax system and a $15 per hour minimum wage. He strongly advocates for equality, and supports LGBTQ rights. He also wants to save the planet by reducing the carbon emissions levels of Canada to 30% of 2005 levels by 2025.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Canada’s highly decentralised federation, forming the government at the provincial level makes the NDP an influential political force. Being led federally by a “visible minority” makes it a prominent symbol of the maturity of Canada’s multiculturalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Democratic Party, despite winning only 24 seats in the 2019 General Elections, has become one of the most talked-about parties. We can attribute two key factors to this popularity: (i) Singh’s speech in the democratic debate and (ii) the Liberal Party emerged as a minority party in the elections. Despite the Liberal Party staying a minority party in the House of Commons, forming a coalition with the NDP to govern, as the majority party, had been a general suggestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Canadian media refer to Singh as the “kingmaker” in the legislative. The Liberal Party would need NDP’s votes on issues where the NDP and Liberals are more aligned than the Conservatives are, to pass any bill. For India, its interest in Singh is not one of pride that an Indian rose to become the leader of a major political party in a powerful Western state. Instead, the power Singh holds having entered the Canadian parliament has become a matter of concern for India. He has had a history of defending militants fighting for a separate Sikh homeland and lobbying for labeling a 1984 pogrom against Sikhs in India a ‘genocide’ by the government of Ontario. While he has not offered unqualified support to the Khalistan cause and remains vague on the issue, he has criticised India for Operation Blue Star. Singh will now have a far more consequential platform to continue his activism concerning attempting to seek justice for several violent episodes in India’s past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, India denied Jagmeet Singh a visa to visit because he was “misusing the pretext of human rights to pursue his insidious agenda of disturbing the social fabric of India and undermining the peace, harmony and territorial integrity of India.” For a provincial politician, this is notable. But as the leader of a major political party with a seat in the country’s main legislative body, this suspicion towards Singh by a friendly country is of more substantial potential consequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India has dealt with a partition once before and thus has little tolerance for movements that could threaten further division of the state. This and the fact that India comprises culturally distinct regions make its current integrity reliant on a compact of pluralism. Khalistan seems to have more significant traction in the Sikh diaspora than it does in Punjab. Because of which India seems more concerned about diaspora movements that agitate for its creation than internal movements. Thus, India is sensitive towards anything that it perceives as a threat to its unity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Singh is leading a deeply divided party that is facing severe fundraising deficits and a significant number of experienced MPs who won’t be seeking re-election. If he wishes to use his new platform to bring light to the injustices of India in the 1980’s, Singh would have to wait until he has dealt with the more direct concerns of his party first. The primary focus of the realities of Singh’s role at home may just save New Delhi from having to be overly concerned with him for the time being.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For many families in Punjab, shifting to Canada and being a permanent resident is the objective. Families want their sons to settle there and their daughters to marry the rich non-resident Indians. ‘Caneda’ is a household term and a second home for these Punjabis. The rate of migration is such that Punjabis in Canada form roughly 2% of the total population, with a majority of them being Sikh. Punjabi is the third-most spoken language in Canada, after English and French. For the rest of us in India, it only seems fair to imagine a day when Caneda’s Prime Minister is also a Sikh.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Nakba of Israel and Palestine</title>
      <link href="/The-Nakba-of-Israel-and-Palestine" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Nakba of Israel and Palestine" />
      <published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Nakba-of-Israel-and-Palestine</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Nakba-of-Israel-and-Palestine">&lt;p&gt;In 2014, Rihanna, Zayn Malik, and Coldplay found themselves in the media limelight for posting pro-Palestinian tweets. As #freePalestine and #freedomforpalestine started trending, their popularity in Israel fell. We can attribute this to the conflict between Israel and Palestine. The Israel-Palestinian conflict is one of the world’s longest-running and most controversial conflicts. Today, over 7 million Palestinians identify themselves as refugees, with Israelis continuing to settle in the territory that Palestinians claim as their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Torn between the Jewish Zionist movement and the Palestinian nationalist movement lies a piece of land and millions of people. Whom does this land belong to? Is there more to this conflict than a piece of land? What has this conflict led to? Is there a way out of this labyrinth of suffering? Within Israeli and Palestinian societies, the conflict has generated a wide variety of opinions. A hallmark of the conflict has been the level of violence conducted by rebel armies, paramilitary groups, terror cells and individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conflict has its roots in history. In the 1900’s, the area which is now known as Israel and Palestine was under Ottoman rule. The Ottoman Empire was religiously diverse with Muslims, Christians, and Jews living together. This happily ever after was hindered when Muslims in the area started developing a sense of not just being Arabs but also having a distinct national identity: Palestinian. Concurrently, the Zionism movement started emerging in Europe. They believed Judaism was not just a religion but also a national identity and so, Jews deserved a home in their ancestral land. Their idea was similar to how the French live in France and the Indians live in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As both groups started working towards developing this area as their homeland, the peace they had been living in vanished forever. Between 1896 and 1948, millions of Jews migrated to British-controlled Palestine, with many fleeing the Holocaust in Germany. Palestinians regarded this as another form of European colonisation. As more Jews settled into farming communes, tension rose between Jews and Arabs, with both sides committing acts of violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jewish population in British Palestine and violence between the two groups continued to rise. And so, in 1947, the United Nations (UN) approved a plan to divide the land into two areas, with distinct borders, to form Israel and Palestine. The plan was meant to give the Jews a state and to establish Palestinian independence. It declared Jerusalem a ‘special international zone’ , owing to its religious importance, whose administration was to be controlled by the UN. Jerusalem has a place of importance in three vital religions: Islam, Christianity and Judaism. Because of this, both countries consider Jerusalem as their capital. But the map largely looked like a jigsaw puzzle. An average Palestinian citizen who lived in West Bank had no idea about what would be happening in Gaza (and still doesn’t).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formation of a Jewish majority state in the Middle East didn’t sit well with the rest of the Arab countries. They saw the UN’s plan as another way of the Europeans stealing their land. Many of the Arab states came together and declared war on Israel, in 1948, to establish a unified Arab Palestine. Despite being a new-born country, Israel defeated them and proved its military might. In doing so, Israel pushed past its borders and took control of a significant portion of Palestine. The war forced hundreds of Palestinians to flee their homes and become refugees in the surrounding Arab countries, making them stateless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1967, a six-day war took place between Israel and the Arab nations. Again, Israel won. Not only did it annex the whole of Palestine but also territories from Egypt, Syria and Jordan. Israel got the right to govern the Palestinians. In the decades that followed, the Arab countries made peace with Israel. This allowed them to get their Israeli annexed territories back. The broader Israeli-Arab conflict now morphed into a more specific Israeli-Palestinian conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the rise of the Palestinian Liberation Organization (PLO) in 1964, the founder, Yasser Arafat, used military tactics including attacks on Israeli civilians. The PLO oversaw guerrilla groups on the one hand and used non-violent approaches on the other. Meanwhile, the Israeli started moving into West Bank and East Jerusalem, establishing Israeli settlements. They undertook this for three main reasons: (i) religious reasons so that people could live close to Jerusalem, (ii) to claim the land as Israeli territory and (iii) cheap housing. As more civilians settled into Palestinian territories, the military followed. This led to increased checkpoints for Palestinians and forced Palestinians off their land. In effect, it blurred the boundaries of any future Palestinian state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the 1980’s, the frustration among Palestinians grew, and they launched the First Intifada (meaning uprising). This began by boycotting Israeli products and services, and refusing to pay taxes or working jobs in Israel. However, when the Israeli military cracked down on the protestors, violence ensued. The Intifada led to the rise of Hamas in Gaza, an extremist group dedicated to Israel’s destruction, which considered the PLO too compromise-minded. Till date, Hamas has garnered support not just because of its military strength but because of the social welfare projects undertaken by it in Gaza. They have built schools, mosques and clinics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1993, the PLO accepted Israel’s right to exist and in exchange wanted Israel to recognize it as the legitimate representative of Palestinians. That was the beginning of real peace negotiations between the two sides. Leaders from both sides signed the American-brokered Oslo Accords. This allowed Palestinians more freedom to govern themselves. Hard-liners on both sides, however, were not happy with the terms of the peace process and ensued violence to sabotage this process. After signing the second round of the Oslo Accords, the far-right Israeli groups shot Israeli PM Yitzhak Rabin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US has been pro-Israel since the Cold War. US politicians view the pro-Israel propaganda as a method to garner support from their citizens by appealing to their anti-Muslim sentiments. This, however, has larger implications. The domino effect of the US supporting Israel is that the US’ allies have started to support Israel too. A good example is India. India aligned itself with Palestine after the partition in 1948, but since it has aligned with the US now, they have forced India to support Israel. In 2018, the USA shifted its embassy from Tel Aviv to Jerusalem in Israel, internationally recognizing Jerusalem as the capital of Israel. As a consequence, other countries such as Guatemala and Paraguay also shifted their embassies to Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crux of this conflict remains the same till date. Both parties want a country to exert their distinct identity, and none will compromise with the other. Caught in the crossfire between the two governments and extremist groups, it’s the voices and lives of the citizens that are being compromised. Everyone who identifies as either a Palestinian or an Israeli knows at least one person who lost their life because of this conflict. Most Jews see the Palestinians’ demand for an independent state as just. Most Palestinians prefer a two-state solution. Both Israelis and Palestinians are afraid of the people in charge on the other side. The people can’t trust their information sources because they know it’s fueled with propaganda. The settlements resemble regular suburbs from any part of the world, with people trying to live peacefully in a place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Palestinian governance is divided between the Palestinian Authority and Hamas. The Israeli government is skeptical of Hamas and its goal of Israel’s destruction. As violence continues, there seems to be little political will for peace. Any successful peace initiative would need resolving the issues: West Bank settlements, Israeli security, Palestinian refugees and their right to return, Jerusalem, mutual recognition and water rights. However, there are three major hurdles: (i) Israeli settlements continue expanding, (ii) the PLO, and Hamas cannot negotiate jointly and (iii) everyone is unsure regarding how to get the talks started. The truth of the matter is the governments aren’t solving the conflict anymore, they are just managing it. Israel constructed walls and checkpoints after the second Intifada, leaving Palestinians to believe they have no future as a people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent Israeli elections have not given a clear mandate but Likud party’s chief, incumbent Prime Minister, Benjamin Netanyahu is likely to head a coalition government. It remains to be seen whether there would be any change in attitude of leaders on both sides of the fence. For this to happen, it is necessary that both parties trust each other, and explore the possibility of coexistence and the legitimacy of each other’s historical narrative. The United Nations should come out of the shadow of the US and mediate a solution for the welfare of the people in this war torn area.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In 2014, Rihanna, Zayn Malik, and Coldplay found themselves in the media limelight for posting pro-Palestinian tweets. As #freePalestine and #freedomforpalestine started trending, their popularity in Israel fell. We can attribute this to the conflict between Israel and Palestine. The Israel-Palestinian conflict is one of the world’s longest-running and most controversial conflicts. Today, over 7 million Palestinians identify themselves as refugees, with Israelis continuing to settle in the territory that Palestinians claim as their own.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Heartbeat Bill: An Infringement Upon the Right to Choose</title>
      <link href="/Heartbeat-Bill" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Heartbeat Bill: An Infringement Upon the Right to Choose" />
      <published>2019-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Heartbeat-Bill</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Heartbeat-Bill">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;American Horror Story&lt;/em&gt; is no longer a mere fictional television show, it is a reality for women in the United States. A country, put on a pedestal for its liberal laws and democratic attitude, has taken a turn with the rise of the extreme right-wing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2010, new state laws have been passed in various parts of the US, making abortions physically inaccessible to women. These laws have reduced the number of abortion clinics in several states to one, due to frequent and unnecessary changes in the restrictions placed on them. The clinics that cannot afford such changes end up shutting down altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the US Supreme Court ruled on &lt;em&gt;Roe v. Wade&lt;/em&gt;, it did not specify when abortions were legal. They vaguely decided to make it unconstitutional to outlaw them until the foetus is ‘viable’. Since scientists had not determined when that was, states exploited this ambiguity and passed specific week bans like (i) when a foetal heartbeat can be detected, (ii) when the foetus can experience the pain of the procedure and (iii) when the foetus has developed into a person. This sparked the pro-life vs pro-choice debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2019, a law was passed, in Alabama, making abortions practically illegal for women. The sole exceptions made are if the mother’s life is at severe risk or if the abortion is carried out before six weeks into the pregnancy. The six-week rule is impractical as most women find out about their pregnancies only after those six weeks. The lack of other exceptions also implies that a woman who is HIV positive or has been impregnated by rape or incest would not be allowed to terminate her pregnancy. Moreover, a doctor carrying out this procedure could face 99 years in prison, so if he/she was to be prosecuted under this law in 2019, he would get out in 2118. The rapist, however, can get out after three months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pro-life activists support this legislation out of the belief that it addresses an important human rights issue: the right to life of the foetus. The bill, however, is not about protecting an unborn child, but about control over a woman’s body. Most importantly, it acts as an infringement on a woman’s right to life itself. In fact the High Court at Calcutta, in India, a country ostensibly more backward than the United States, brilliantly explains why a practical blanket ban on abortions is truly the infringement of a woman’s right to life, and not the foetus’, in the case of &lt;em&gt;Suparna Debnath v. State of West Bengal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, The Honourable Acting Chief Justice of the Court, Mr Justice Somadder explained that a woman’s “sufferings include the sufferings of her child, whose compromised existence is inextricably linked with the mother. The role of the State in this regard is crucial; both for the well-being of the mother and that of her child.” Mr Justice Somadder added that the reasoning behind this proposition was that “[t]he mother’s personal life and liberty….is inextricably linked with that of the unborn child and will continue even after she gives birth to the child.” Therefore, any person who professes to care about the right to life of the foetus has to care about the right to life of its mother, for the foetus’ existence is, by all means, dependent on its mother. So, if one does not prioritise the woman’s life on the issue of abortion in certain circumstances or understand that the issue is a priori about a woman’s right to life, one only masquerades as ‘pro-life’, when, in fact, they only wish to have dominion over a woman’s body. And this is verily the case with the supporters of the proposed Alabama law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ban is a classic case of a problem-solution mismatch. A government that has failed to strengthen its gun laws, to protect children from mass shootings and has separated immigrant families, is now pretending to care about ‘young and innocent lives’. Currently, Alabama has an F in its status of women’s health and has the highest infant mortality rate. If it were pro-children, the government of Alabama would be working towards increasing the standard of living in the state through measures such as improving the status of women’s health, lowering the infant mortality rates and allocating more resources towards public schools. Instead of adopting policies that keeps people trapped in poverty for generations, because of being forced to support another human being without having the means to do so, the government should to provide comprehensive sex education, free birth control and contraception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, many a time there is a substantial risk that a child, if born, would suffer from deformities and diseases. Their treatment not only takes a financial toll but also a mental toll on the parents. Often, parents cannot afford the treatment. Such a birth especially hurts when the child ends up dying only a few years later. The effects on a woman’s physical and mental health, strength, and life because of carrying a specially-abled child full term is an avoidable cost. A woman’s suffering is not only limited to her pain and agony. As explained above, it is interlinked to her child’s suffering too, as the child’s right to life is parasitic. This, however, does not go to say that the parents loved their child any less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A popular justification for anti-abortion laws has been: ‘protecting women’s health’. However, abortion is no danger to their health. Abortion, carried out by a doctor, has a mortality rate of 0.00073%, which is the lowest of all medical procedures. The law will drive women to now undertake unsafe abortions. As defined by the WHO, “unsafe abortion is a procedure for terminating an unintended pregnancy carried out either by persons lacking the necessary skills or in an environment that does not conform to minimal medical standards or both.” These abortions are the third leading cause of maternal deaths worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many pro-lifers argue that a woman who doesn’t wish to raise the child can give the child up for adoption. However, there are certain problems attached to this. Firstly, there are already too many kids waiting to be adopted, trapped in America’s faulty foster care system. The system comes with its own set of problems: assault by foster parents, lack of access to basic amenities. Secondly, women often do not know whether their baby will be cared for and must live in the perpetual guilt of negative possibilities. It is due to this that women are unable to give a baby up for adoption, a baby they carried to full term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The domino effect of the Alabama bill has already spread to multiple states, some following suit and some still considering it. Beyond this, the bill and the conservative judges in the Supreme Court will now have the power to overturn &lt;em&gt;Roe v. Wade&lt;/em&gt; making abortion illegal all over the country. But America isn’t the only country affected by these laws. In 2017, President Trump reinstated and expanded a policy called the ‘global gag rule’. This rule states, that any overseas organisation which receives US global health funding, cannot even mention abortion as part of their counselling or education programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Kaiser Family Foundation poll of 1,492 Americans, 67% say abortion should be legalised in all or most cases. Women who live in places where abortions are illegal are known to be arrested by police in cases of miscarriage, due to the police believing it to be a conscious attempt to abort. Recently, in Alabama, a pregnant woman who got shot in the stomach was arrested by the police, under similar justifications. From grassroots to the global level, a trend has followed suit, wherein women are being subjected to harsher realities. A voice against these draconian abortion laws made anywhere in the world, be it Ireland or the USA, should be raised by all, irrespective of gender. These regressive laws have no place in any progressive society.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">American Horror Story is no longer a mere fictional television show, it is a reality for women in the United States. A country, put on a pedestal for its liberal laws and democratic attitude, has taken a turn with the rise of the extreme right-wing.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
