<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/devyani.arora/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-08-03T23:47:34+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/devyani.arora/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Rainbows for Sale: How the Corporates and Politicians are Capitalising on the Pride Movement</title>
      <link href="/Rainbows-for-Sale" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rainbows for Sale: How the Corporates and Politicians are Capitalising on the Pride Movement" />
      <published>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Rainbows-for-Sale</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Rainbows-for-Sale">&lt;p&gt;The world is experiencing a paradigm shift with the society’s mindset evolving towards becoming more inclusive and accepting of minorities. With woke culture becoming ‘trendy’, it isn’t out of the ordinary to see corporations and politicians jumping on the bandwagon and coming to support the marginalised. They proclaim themselves to be LGBTQIA+ friendly, feminist and believe black and Dalit lives matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With each passing day in June, Pride flags and rainbows are everywhere and increasing— company logos, Instagram bios, clothing lines, and tweets from politicians and companies. This trend of companies and politicians has been observed previously during past Pride Months, and whenever the movement achieved milestones like Section 377 being decriminalised in India or the US legalising same-sex marriage. However, is their allyship and activism constant or a perfectly timed tokenistic act? Are their supporting words and rainbow display pictures translating into tangible acts, or are they just trying to garner profit and goodwill by capitalising on the LGBTQ movement?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the LGBTQ movement gets incorporated into the market economy, products dipped in pride colours dominate the generation of a market specifically focused on them. The corporates are leaving no stone unturned to tick off all points on their corporate social responsibility checklist – sponsoring pride events, manufacturing pride-themed merchandise and creating advertisements revolving around the queer. Companies are capitalising on the ‘queer awareness’ wave to increase their sales, thereby increasing profits earned by them. With a growing acceptance of the LGBTQ, ‘pink money’ is now becoming a way to boost the economy. This rainbow (or pink) brand of capitalism, however, is accessible by only those affluent, liberal, upper-middle-class people who have gained enough purchasing power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These public displays of acceptance allow companies and politicians to ‘pinkwash’ their image to be perceived as progressive and tolerant. Pinkwashing refers to the marketing and political strategies used by corporates to promote products, people or entities by portraying themselves as allies. This allows the corporates to not only target the queer but also their allies, thereby creating goodwill for themselves amongst a vast audience. Breast Cancer Action originally coined this term to call out corporates, who used the pink breast cancer ribbon as a PR stunt while creating products that directly contributed to breast cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier, advertisements representing the LGBTQ community were restricted to LGBTQ organisations and LGBTQ-owned businesses directly targeting the community. We can attribute this to other businesses’ cautiousness to advertise in the gay press due to fear of backlash from the majority. A breakthrough for queer representation in advertising came with the 1994 IKEA ad, which showed a gay couple purchasing furniture. They did it to normalise depictions of LGBTQ identities. However, the ad was accused of creating a brand of ‘homonormativity’ - a concept complementary to heteronormativity with the assumption that all individuals fall into two complementary categories as males and females, and that they behave as per their gendered ‘norms’. Homonormativity upholds heteronormative presumptions and institutions by assimilating the heteronormative norms into the LGBTQ culture, thereby assuming that gay couples are just like everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the corporates and politicians remain busy soaking their products and policies in rainbows, the LGBTQ continues to face problems like discrimination, unemployment, and lack of healthcare. In recent years, Barclays Bank, an institution complicit in driving up food prices globally, has been sponsoring pride in London. Barclays Bank also holds a 4.25% shareholding in BAE systems, which also has a presence in the pride march to showcase itself as an LGBTQ friendly employer. On the flip side, however, as of 2016, BAE Systems has provided arms to nations such as United Arab Emirates, India, Pakistan, and Qatar, which are known to commit homophobic and transphobic human rights violations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The corporates, however, aren’t the only ones capitalising on the LGBTQ movement. In 2005, Israel started promoting itself as a gay-friendly tourist destination to portray itself as a progressive country and shift attention away from its regime of occupation and apartheid oppressing Palestine, regardless of sexuality. A secondary motive of the same was to reiterate the Islamophobic myth: Palestinians are backward, homophobic, misogynistic and uncivilised. The ‘gay-friendly’ destination, however, hasn’t spared queer Palestinians from the marginalisation and discrimination at the hands of the Israeli regime. Additionally, Israel’s far-right government has been known to align itself with the likes of Donald Trump, Jair Bolsonaro, Viktor Orbán - world leaders known for their homophobic, racist and intolerant opinions. Because of the religious law, same-sex marriage and adoption by gay couples is also banned in Israel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar example can be seen back in Kashmir. On one hand, the right-wing fascists denounce the Kashmiris’ right to self-determination and celebrate their freedoms being taken by abrogation of Article 370, lockdowns, and information blackouts. But on the other hand, ‘non-political’ student organisations like the Kashmiri Youth Movement that have previously supported the right-wing, call for a Pride march in Kashmir to celebrate International Pride Month. Not only do these propagandist acts cast a rainbow smokescreen to conceal the damage done to the minorities by their policies, but they also undermine the efforts of various organisations towards queer rights. As with Israel, these methods act as a reiteration of Hindu superiority. The Hindu nationalists try to cast a light on the supposed dismal life of LGBTQ in the Muslim-majority state. This can further be used to justify violent pogroms in the Muslim-majority areas. While the government is busy pinkwashing its image using Kashmir, it is turning a blind eye towards the people protesting the Transgender Rights Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By appropriating the voices of the queer, these pink washers are creating an ‘us v/s them’ narrative. However, movements that aim at fighting oppressive structures must do so unconditionally and not at the expense of other marginalised groups. As the queer community includes people from all races and economic backgrounds, queer liberation can’t be achieved without racial, economic, and all other forms of justice. Going by this principle, anti-pinkwashing activists have been pushing Palestinian rights to the forefront of Pride events across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her 2007 book, &lt;em&gt;Terrorist Assemblages&lt;/em&gt;, Jasbir K Puar explains this as ‘homonationalism’. After 9/11, LGBTQ rights became a way for the West to demonstrate its civilisation and humanity in contrast to the barbarism and homophobia in the Middle East. However, this easy-to-buy narrative is untrue as prisoners continued to be tortured by the American government at Guantanamo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of all entities guilty of pinkwashing, few have taken additional steps to tangibly contribute to the movement. Companies like Coca Cola and Hyatt have gone beyond the tokenistic post on social media by making their health insurance trans-inclusive. Hyatt was also the first major hotel company to offer domestic partnership benefits to queer couples. Thus, a company’s LGBTQ friendliness must not be judged by how good they are at marketing, but by their intent to foster a safe and equal workplace, thereby leading to the creation of a more inclusive society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many hold the opinion that expecting corporations to always work selflessly for the minorities is placing too much onus on them, for they are at least ‘trying’, and backing of such powerful organisations is required to take the movement forward. To some extent, this is true. With corporate involvement, the LGBTQ community accrues the marginal benefit of integrating into the mainstream and of further normalising being queer. But as more and more corporations join the movement with their rainbow-dipped products, the Pride movement includes only those who have the purchasing power to buy those products. Additionally, by trivialising the movement to make it an elitist one, the corporates are creating a brand of pride movement antithetical to what it originally stands for. At the heart of the LGBTQ movement lies its motive of liberating the oppressed queer community from the age-old societal stigma. But the assimilation by the capitalists creates a false sense of acceptance for the community, leaving little scope for them to question the status quo. For society expects the queer to take a moral high ground and accept whatever minimal representation they’re being offered by the ones in power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pinkwashing can be done by the LGBTQ community itself too. After the 2016 Orlando gay club shooting, many Republicans - including gay people - used the tragedy to describe all Muslims as homophobic and terrorists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the particularity of its meaning, pinkwashing refers to the exploitation of marginalised sexual identities to promote deceptive agendas. To fight this, appropriated movements must be reclaimed and reoriented towards collective social change. Individuals must not be swept away by organisations’ pseudo-activism aimed at grabbing headlines. Instead, these appropriators must be called out and held accountable for their actions, because Pride is a protest and they are late to the party. As an alternate, grassroots methods of awareness like education, fundraisers, and activism have proved to be more successful in fostering an equal environment for the queer community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As ally involvement in Pride events increases, a responsible analysis is vital to decide the face of the movement – will it be about the queer, whose lived experiences bind them together in solidarity, or the pinkwashed corporations and politicians?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The world is experiencing a paradigm shift with the society’s mindset evolving towards becoming more inclusive and accepting of minorities. With woke culture becoming ‘trendy’, it isn’t out of the ordinary to see corporations and politicians jumping on the bandwagon and coming to support the marginalised. They proclaim themselves to be LGBTQIA+ friendly, feminist and believe black and Dalit lives matter.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Error 404: Democracy Unachievable in your Region</title>
      <link href="/Democracy-Unachievable-in-your-Region" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Error 404: Democracy Unachievable in your Region" />
      <published>2020-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Democracy-Unachievable-in-your-Region</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Democracy-Unachievable-in-your-Region">&lt;p&gt;For Hong Kong, the year 2019 has been a monumental one. In April last year, the citizens of Hong Kong took to the streets to protest against the controversial extradition bill. This bill could have potentially undermined the judicial independence of Hong Kong and silenced the dissidents by exposing the Hongkongers to unfair trials by Beijing. In September, after 5 months of protests, the bill was withdrawn. However, this has led to a bigger uprising: one against Beijing as Hong Kong now demands full democracy and an inquiry into the police’s actions. With this, the protests continue. However, as the entire world got caught up by COVID-19, the protestors withdrew from the streets to escape the virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An opportunist Beijing swooped in during this period with the National People’s Congress (NPC) approving to impose a highly contentious national security law in Hong Kong on May 28, 2020. The legislation seeks to ban secession, subversion of state power, terrorism, foreign intervention, and allow mainland China’s state security agencies to operate in Hong Kong. This essentially means that the harshest criticism of China and the ruling party will be criminalised. Detailed legislation, however, still needs to be drafted and enacted, which could be done within the next few months. Critics fear it threatens the political and civil freedoms enjoyed by the semi-autonomous territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hong Kong’s government has signalled support for the legislature and said it would cooperate with China to enforce the laws in Hong Kong. Carrie Lam, Hong Kong’s Chief Executive, has also made a public statement reiterating China’s stance saying that the law will only target a handful of people involved in terrorism or subversion. On the other hand, the Hongkongers have retaliated with a series of protests despite fears of coronavirus. On a forum popular with protestors, LIHKG (often referred to as the Hong Kong version of Reddit), users have called for a ‘hundred-day war’, calling it the last opportunity to protest before the law comes into force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Pompeo, US Secretary of State, condemned the legislation by calling it a ‘disastrous proposal’. He also stated that Hong Kong is no longer autonomous from China and threatened to revoke the special status it enjoys in trade with the USA. In a joint statement, Australia, Canada, the UK and the US have expressed their ‘deep concern’ regarding the law. They have also called on Beijing to work with the Hong Kong government and people to find a “mutually acceptable accommodation”. Taiwan, Japan and Germany are also standing in solidarity with Hong Kong and have called for China to not undermine Hong Kong’s freedoms. As these countries line up in support of Hong Kong, Beijing is getting more suspicious that these foreign efforts aim to exploit its domestic weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hong Kong was handed over to China in 1997 by the United Kingdom after 150 years of colonisation. As a part of China, it operates under the ‘one country, two systems’ principle ensuring Hong Kong enjoys independence in its legislature, judiciary and economy. Set to expire in 2047, the arrangement allows Hong Kong to enjoy autonomy and freedom of speech and assembly. These freedoms, however, don’t exist in mainland China. To aid this, a document called the Basic Law – Hong Kong’s mini-constitution - was drafted which ensured Hong Kong its freedom and set out a structure for governance of the territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Article 23 of the Basic Law already calls for Hong Kong to enact national security laws to prohibit “treason, secession, sedition [and] subversion” against the Chinese government. While the article already exists as a part of the Basic Law, it has never been enacted. In 2003, a similar attempt was made by Hong Kong’s first Chief Executive, Tung Chee-hwa but was abandoned post mass protests. The next three successors never attempted to repeat this out of fear of protests, despite repeated warnings from China stating that they were obliged to do so. This time, however, China plans to enact the law without Hong Kong’s approval by pursuing an ‘unconstitutional’ method. The laws will be enacted through a provision that bypasses Hong Kong’s legislature and therefore, public debate and consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The draconian legislation comes when China is already under the scrutiny of the international community after the coronavirus outbreak. It is said to be China’s way of tightening its grip on Hong Kong after a year of pro-democracy protests. Seeing how the legislation eerily echoes the mainland’s current legal framework, it is safe to believe that the drafted legislation will not be compatible with international human rights obligations binding on Hong Kong. Provisions regarding anti-terrorism and sedition under existing laws are already inconsistent with global standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hong Kong has acted as a haven for dissent with its freedom of speech and assembly. The legislation, however, seeks to attack these freedoms and silence the loudest voice against China. Many are afraid that China will set up its institutions in Hong Kong under the garb of ‘national security’ that could introduce China’s law enforcement to the city. This could further affect the judicial system of Hong Kong. According to Professor Johannes Chan, a scholar at the University of Hong Kong, the security law poses a major problem. “Almost all trials involving national security are conducted behind closed doors. It [is] never clear what exactly the allegations and the evidence are, and the term national security is so vague that it could cover almost anything,” said the Professor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legislation, additionally, bans all “activities of foreign forces” interfering in Hong Kong’s affairs. People also worry that this could affect Hong Kong’s attractiveness as a business and economic powerhouse. This is a troubling aspect for an economy already struggling with tourism in the past year because of protests and COVID-19. This, however, isn’t the first step taken by China to counter the rising pro-democracy narrative in Hong Kong. In February 2020, China announced Xia Baolong, the man known for the clampdown on Christian churches in the Zhejiang province during 2014-15, as the head of the Hong Kong &amp;amp; Macau Office. China also revamped the reporting structure that crystalised the clear chain of command from Hong Kong to Beijing. Additionally, Luo Huining, known for executing Xi Jinping’s anti-corruption campaign, was appointed to head the Chinese Liaison Office in Hong Kong. “They’ve got two guys who are not familiar with Hong Kong issues, and who have governed provinces in China in a heavy-handed way and think they can do the same in Hong Kong,” said Kwok, who has a law degree from King’s College, University of London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, on June 4, 2020, Hong Kong’s legislature passed a contentious bill that makes insulting the Chinese national anthem, illegal. Anyone who shall intentionally insult the anthem will face up to 3 years in prison plus fines worth at least $6,000. The bill was introduced by Beijing last year in response to the Hong Kong soccer fans booing at the anthem at the 2015 FIFA matches. Post the bill being passed, students at the Hong Kong University held a silent protest at the Pillar of Shame, a sculpture commemorating the victims of the Tiananmen crackdown. With a foggy future ahead, Hongkongers tread on a narrow road to democracy with no destination in sight. More clashes between the two parties are to be expected in the future, but it’s going to take a long time before either party backs down. Hong Kong’s pro-democracy fire will not burn out anytime soon. In a world where the global community blames China for the coronavirus outbreak and the USA further imposes tariffs on Chinese goods, China will do all it can to retain its power and reputation.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For Hong Kong, the year 2019 has been a monumental one. In April last year, the citizens of Hong Kong took to the streets to protest against the controversial extradition bill. This bill could have potentially undermined the judicial independence of Hong Kong and silenced the dissidents by exposing the Hongkongers to unfair trials by Beijing. In September, after 5 months of protests, the bill was withdrawn. However, this has led to a bigger uprising: one against Beijing as Hong Kong now demands full democracy and an inquiry into the police’s actions. With this, the protests continue. However, as the entire world got caught up by COVID-19, the protestors withdrew from the streets to escape the virus.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">No Longer Forgotten</title>
      <link href="/No-Longer-Forgotten" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No Longer Forgotten" />
      <published>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/No-Longer-Forgotten</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/No-Longer-Forgotten">&lt;p&gt;Despite witnessing one of the bloodiest wars and being the only region in the world divided by the Cold War, the Korean Peninsula and its history, until recently, has failed to make its way into the mainstream. It’s only in the last 20 years that the peninsula has gained the world’s attention: the notorious Northern part has become infamous for its nuclear weapons while the South is taking over the world with its Hallyu wave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 36 years of the ruthless Japanese colonisation, the Korean Peninsula was liberated on August 15, 1945. It was a joyous occasion for the peninsula, for the Koreans were now independent, and the pain and humiliation of the Japanese invasion were over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Second World War ended and Japan surrendered, the Korean peninsula fell into the hands of the winners of the World War, i.e. the Allied powers. While the Soviet Union spread its communist propaganda in the North, the US vouched for democracy in the South. The peninsula was divided along the 38th parallel in 1948 due to these ideological differences, forming two nations, the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea (DPRK) in the North and the Republic of Korea (ROK) in the South. For the rest of the world, they might be North and South Korea, but both believe they are the only legitimate Korea. Initially, blessed with more heavy industries, the communist DPRK’s economy rose, while the South struggled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the next two years, North and South Korea were heavily militarised with the help of the Soviet Union and the US, respectively. While the US and the Soviet Union had been regarded as key reasons in the peninsula’s division, the military troops acted as deterrents and prevented war between the two Koreas. However, as the troops started withdrawing, it left the Koreas on their own, making the prospects of war more imminent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 1950, North Korea invaded South Korea swiftly overtaking much of the country. The South Korean army was unprepared and inadequately equipped to face a sudden attack. In September, however, the UN force, led by the US, launched a counter-attack and advanced into the North. China, then, sent in troops to aid the North, shifting the balance of the war. In 1953, the fighting ended with an armistice that approximately restored the original boundaries between North and South Korea. This armistice inaugurated an official ceasefire but did not lead to a peace treaty, and so, the two are still at a cold war against each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the war, a buffer zone called the demilitarised zone (DMZ) was set up along the 38th parallel to prevent another war from taking place and to prevent people from reuniting or escaping. Since the war didn’t end officially, the US kept its bases in South Korea and there are about 23,500 personnel stationed there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//north-south-korea-divide.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The peninsula that was once ‘one’ was now divided on ideological differences. In the years after the war, the two Koreas competed for legitimacy and international recognition abroad. DPRK and ROK continued to view each other as potential threats and propaganda against each other was rampant in the peninsula. The inter-Korean relations, however, worsened with the increasing provocations by the North. In 1968, North Korean commandos attacked the South Korean Blue House. In 1976, North Korean soldiers killed two US Army officers in the truce village of Panmunjom. Later, in 1987, two North Koreans bombed a Korean airliner carrying over 100 passengers to hinder the 1988 Olympic Games that were scheduled to be held in Seoul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;South Korea’s first democratically elected President, Roh Tae-woo launched a diplomatic initiative known as ‘Nordpolitik’, proposing the development of a ‘Korean Community’. As part of the policy, South Korea established diplomatic relations with the Soviet Union and China. Additionally, it led to direct inter-Korean trade and started inter-Korean sports exchanges. In 1991, both countries signed the Agreement on Reconciliation, Non-Aggression, Exchanges, and Cooperation and the Joint Declaration of the Denuclearisation of the Korean Peninsula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1998, the ‘Sunshine Policy’, or as it is formally known, the ‘Comprehensive Engagement Policy towards North Korea’ was announced by the then President of South Korea, Rho Moo-hyun. The policy aimed at loosening containment on North Korea, embracing North Korea, and eventually making the North Korean government denuclearise itself. The objectives of the Sunshine Policy were more specific and substantial than any of the previous policies towards North Korea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sunshine Policy prompted a reduction of military tension and improved inter-Korean relations. It led to increased economic and cultural interactions between not only the leaders but also the people. These regular interactions created a sense of safety and stability in the Korean peninsula and rekindled the prospect of unification. The policy also led to the spread of South Korea’s soft power in North Korea, shaking their faith in their communist government. South Korean Choco Pies and Dramas spread like wildfire, and people started getting and consuming these illegally. Soon it started changing the way North Koreans viewed South Korea as they realised that the South wasn’t the poor, struggling country their leaders had them believe. Instead, they were the ones living in a poor, struggling country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of the policy, a breakthrough in the inter-Korean relations came at the start of the century with the first Inter-Korean Summit of 2000 as the leaders of both countries met in Pyongyang (capital of North Korea). The summit resulted in a joint peace declaration, with Kim Jong-Il and Kim Dae-Jung agreeing to promote unification and humanitarian and economic cooperation. The meeting resulted in a series of reunions of families separated by the Korean War, as well as a joint factory park in the North’s border town of Kaesong in 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policy, however, was riddled with criticism. Despite its benefits, the policy failed to change North Korea’s behaviour. Many accuse the policy not only of being ineffectual but also immoral, giving North Korea access to money to develop nuclear weapons, instead of the humanitarian purpose it was supposed to serve. Some conservatives believed that the policy weakened the US-South Korea alliance. By continuing to help the North with financial aid even after 9/11, South Korea offended the US, which had placed North Korea on its ‘Axis of Evil.’ This stopped the ROK-US relations from advancing further, thus, blocking the South Korean economy’s potential to grow during the early 2000’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, North Korea conducted its first nuclear test and with the worsening international sentiment towards North Korea, the South decided to hold an inter-Korean summit. This led to the second meeting in 2007 between President Roh Moo-hyun of the Republic of Korea and Kim Jong-il of the DPRK, in Pyongyang. The summit culminated in an eight-point agreement as the two leaders pledged to promote and expand joint economic, military and family reunion projects. The declaration also expressed its willingness to replace the existing armistice agreement with a permanent peace regime. But the agreement didn’t lead to concrete results as the North continued to carry out a series of nuclear and missile tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lee Myung-bak’s presidency (2008-13) heralded a major change in inter-Korean relations as he decided to abandon the Sunshine policy (in 2010) and take a more hard-line stance against the North. Upon taking office, the Lee administration curtailed aid to the North. As a result of the shooting of a South Korean tourist in a restricted zone of Mt Geumgang in 2008, they ordered a suspension of tourism in the area. Inter-Korean relations continued to deteriorate in 2009, with North Korea nullifying the past inter-Korean agreements. South Korea retaliated by condemning nuclear and missile tests by the North.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tension between the two remained high as North Korea attacked South Korea almost 20 times post the attack in 2009. Peace in the Korean Peninsula seemed impossible to reach in the following years and it was only in 2018 that the situation took a turn for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As South Korean President Moon Jae-In revived the Sunshine Policy in 2017, North Korean leader Kim Jong-Un proposed to send a delegation to the upcoming Winter Olympics in South Korea in his New Year address for 2018. This olive branch led to the Seoul-Pyongyang hotline being reopened, a K-pop concert in North Korea, and propaganda no longer being broadcasted on both sides. At the Winter Olympics, North and South Korea marched together in the opening ceremony and fielded a united women’s ice hockey team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 27, 2018, North Korean leader Kim Jong-Un met with South Korean President Moon Jae-In in the Demilitarised Zone at Panmunjom. It was a historical moment as this summit marked the first time a North Korean leader entered South Korean territory since the Korean War. Their discussions centred on the denuclearisation of the Korean peninsula and a peace settlement. The summit ended with both countries pledging to work towards complete denuclearisation of the Korean Peninsula and to declare an official end to the Korean War within a year. Moon and Kim also pledged to reconnect east and west coast roads and railroad tracks and reopen the inter-Korean Kaesong Industrial Complex (KIC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, many US and ROK experts are sceptical because North Korea didn’t disclose the composition and/or size of its nuclear material or warhead stocks and facilities. They also didn’t agree upon what constitutes ‘denuclearisation’, nor did they agree upon a timeline or verification measures for dismantlement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post the summit, North Korea adjusted its time zone to match the South’s, and South and North Korea fully restored their military communication line on the Western part of the peninsula. In November 2018, a South Korean train crossed the DMZ border with North Korea marking the first time a South Korean train entered North Korean territory since 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jenny Town, the assistant director of the US-Korea Institute at the Johns Hopkins School of Advanced International Studies, explained North Korea’s behaviour by saying, “Kim Jong-un is trying to repair the relations that have deteriorated over the last few years while they developed nuclear weapons.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August 2019, South Korea’s President, Moon Jae-In vowed to achieve the unification of the Korean peninsula by 2045, a century after the liberation of the peninsula. However, despite the proclamations and friendly summits, reunification seems a distant dream. DPRK has given a formal commitment to unification, but it likely does not want unity. Reunification would come at the cost of NK’s demise, with the North Korean elite being implicated in human rights abuses and corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cultural gap between the two countries has been widening, and a cultural shock and unrest for North Koreans would be inevitable. Like any other developed capitalist country, South Korea is fast-paced and fosters a competitive environment. South Korea is also a highly globalised country with English being used by many. North Korea, on the other hand, is a poor isolated country, where food has been scarce and praising the Supreme Leader has been abundant. North Korean defectors have historically struggled to assimilate. They usually suffer from depression and cannot find work, leading to a few of them returning to the North. On a nation-wide level, it will become more difficult to balance out these differences and to allow for assimilation of the two cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of such differences, people don’t identify with each other despite being ’Koreans’. The older people, who’ve grown up in the peak of ‘the sunshine era’, support reunification in a more historical and humanitarian context. The younger, who grew up in the more conservative era have grown indifferent to their ‘brothers’. According to a 2017 survey conducted by the Korean Institute for National Unification, 14% of South Koreans in their 20s, and around 63% over-50, wanted reunification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are economic problems to consider too in this ordeal. DPRK’s GDP is less than 1% of ROK, which is the world’s 11th biggest economy. The South Korean population believes their hands are already full of domestic problems of unemployment among the youth, an ageing population, sluggish growth, and corruption scandals involving the nation’s highest office to take an additional burden of absorbing the North Korean economy too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the nuclear program deters South Korea and American intervention. DPRK, a small, half-country, built these elite weapons for the sole purpose of standing tall against its enemies and routinely asserts that the United States pursues a ‘hostile policy’ towards it. In 2018, Kim Jong-un stated that he would abandon his nuclear weapons only if the US agreed to formally end the Korean War and promised not to invade his country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korea’s marriage of convenience with China acts as another hurdle in unification. American influence has been increasing in East Asia over the past few years, with North Korea remaining the only country that hasn’t succumbed to the US yet. Unification of the Korean Peninsula would lead to a further increase in the US’ influence in the region. Until, however, China changes its threat evaluation of the US, North Korea is relatively secure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the North Korean commoners, however, reunification remains the only hope for access to a better life. The only other way is by risking their lives and crossing the border, thus, defecting. While the rich and elite enjoy the current state, it’s the people belonging to lower classes who want this unification, especially the youth. With the growing access to South Korean and Chinese media, they are becoming more cognizant of the opportunities that lie outside of the DPRK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, on May 3, 2020, North and South Korea exchanged gunfire around the South’s guard post. Despite the South Korean military believing the gunshots by North Korea to be accidental, it is still unclear if that is the case or if a bigger strategy is at play post-Kim Jong-Un’s much-awaited appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, a deescalation of military troops from the demilitarised line and nuclear weapons from both sides would be a prerequisite for any peace talks to take place. This, however, is just the starting point. The road to unification is long. The gap between the two sides would need to be balanced out by exposing the people to each other’s cultures and lifestyles gradually. Nevertheless, unification is becoming necessary with each passing day as North Korea continues to control the rights and lives of its people. It is important to do it sooner rather than later, for the gap between the countries will only widen, increasing the cost of unification and making the South Koreans believe it to be unnecessary.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Despite witnessing one of the bloodiest wars and being the only region in the world divided by the Cold War, the Korean Peninsula and its history, until recently, has failed to make its way into the mainstream. It’s only in the last 20 years that the peninsula has gained the world’s attention: the notorious Northern part has become infamous for its nuclear weapons while the South is taking over the world with its Hallyu wave.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">An Insight into the World’s Favourite Hermit State</title>
      <link href="/Hermit-State" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Insight into the World’s Favourite Hermit State" />
      <published>2020-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Hermit-State</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Hermit-State">&lt;p&gt;A K-Drama that I was watching recently revolved around a North Korean soldier. The drama was great, but what stayed with me post bingeing it was the intrigue for North Korea: a country that calls itself the greatest nation in the world while its people suffer from the worst human rights violations; a country that calls itself a democracy with a 100% voter turnout in any election but has the world’s most authoritarian regime; a country built on the ideology of ‘self-reliance’ but heavily dependent on aid from the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On typing ‘North Korea’ in the search bar on Google, you note that the search results are dominated by nuclear weapons and North Korea’s relationship with the US and South Korea. Most of the articles paint them as enemies. However, this is where the problem lies - we equate the North Korean people with its government. While the leader and the high-ranking officials propagate an ideology and a culture that benefits them, the common man bears it. This is a country where there is no scope for upward mobility. Defecting is the only way that allows them the taste of a better life. However, in doing so, they are exposed to the racist world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian Myers notes that an international network on Google Earth is working on identifying structures visible in aerial photographs in North Korea. Yet, the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea (DPRK) remains a mystery to many. He attributes this to people’s view of DPRK via the lens of economics and nuclear weapons, and not via its propaganda and people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korea is effectively a totalitarian state run by a dynastic line of dictators. Its cultural and political ideology is based on devotion to leader Kim Il-Sung, whose eternal Presidential authority is written into the Constitution. Three branches constitute the government– executive, legislative and judiciary. The Premier and the Supreme Leader (Kim Jong-un) control the executive branch. The legislative branch is a congress, called the Supreme People’s Assembly, occupied by unopposed candidates from the Workers’ Party of Korea. They, however, rarely meet and have historically passed nearly all proposed laws without debate. The judicial branch is known for secretive trials headed by judges appointed by the SPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a gulag posing as a nation. Everything there is about the great leader: books, newspaper articles, songs and TV programs. The flowers are named after him, and mountains are carved with his slogans. In line with this, only ‘state-approved’ content is produced, as books, newspaper articles, songs and TV programs are all censored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korea calls itself a communist country, which it is not, it is also not the last bastion of Confucian patriarchy, as they often characterise it. Rather, it’s guided by a paranoid ideology of race-based nationalism, holding that Koreans are purer than all others. In his book, &lt;em&gt;The Cleanest Race: How North Koreans See Themselves and Why It Matters&lt;/em&gt;, Brian Myers notes that the nation’s race-based ideology has its roots in Japanese fascism. He states the government’s criteria for national identity paints its citizens as innocent and morally virtuous but militarily weak. Thus, they require Kim Il-Sung’s guidance and protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The country harbours a population of 25 million, with a low rate of population growth. The population of this ‘mighty’ and ‘prosperous’ is starving. The Soviet Union originally supported North Korea. However, the collapse of the USSR led to DPRK not receiving aid, making food production plummet in the early 1990’s. This, coupled with natural disasters, led to the infamous 1990 famine. In the years since, aid from the US and other countries has helped improve the situation. However, most North Koreans still don’t have access to food with necessary nutrients, subsiding on crops like rice, cabbages, and radish. In poorer regions, boiled grass and ground tree bark serve as food alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korean society is based on a social caste system called–‘songbun’, used to allocate government assistance like housing and rations. The loyalty to the North Korean government is the key factor in determining the ranks of the people, and any real or perceived slight against the government can lead to the demotion of an entire family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With no source of outside information, the North Koreans have been ignorant. And in this ignorance lies their safety. It’s a common myth that everyone in North Korea is brainwashed. A considerable number of people are brainwashed, as many committed suicides after the death of Kim Il-Sung as they didn’t know what to do without their leader. But the majority knows the nation is not as prosperous as it shows itself to be and thus, have defected. The fear of punishment has motivated the supposed admiration of the Supreme Leader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Juche’ ideology has shaped the lifestyle of these people. Every household in North Korea is supposed to display the portraits of the eternal leaders, Kim Il-Sung and Kim Jong-Il. There are strict rules and fines associated with dusting the pictures regularly, and their placement for maximum respect. As a symbol of the North Korean identity, all citizens wear a red lapel pin with portraits of the eternal leaders on themselves 24/7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korea observes an 11-year school for the children. In the formative years, the children are taught the legends of their eternal leader. Subjects like Science and Mathematics are paid less attention compared to North Korean history. Many defectors note that growing up they were taught to believe their great leader was a god working tirelessly for their benefit. The idea of their leader being a god was so deeply entrenched that they used to think he could even hear their thoughts, making them afraid of even thinking negatively about the eternal leader. The students have been simply told what to think, and they obey. In their world, critical thinking isn’t allowed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 10 and a 3-year military enlistment is compulsory for all men and women, respectively, after they’ve completed their high school. The government assigns jobs to its people, based on industry needs and location, which they’re supposed to do without fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government claims to provide free healthcare to all its citizens. However, reports say it spends less per citizen than almost any other country in the world. The country has a low standard of care, with nearly all regions suffering shortages of medical equipment and medication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public executions are also a common practice in the world’s favourite hermit state. In fact, too common. A defector revealed that her mother was publicly executed for watching a Hollywood movie. It is mandatory for every North Korean, 12 and above, to witness the public execution. Only the Great Leader has absolute human rights; all others are his vassals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way of escaping this regime, other than taking the government’s permission, is by defecting and illegally crossing the border. The most common strategy is to cross the border in northeast China before fleeing to a third country. This third country generally becomes South Korea, the country that is supposed to be their enemy, welcomes them with open arms. If, however, the defectors are caught in China; they are deported back where they often face harsh interrogations and years of punishment or even death in political prison camps. Post the 1990 famine, the number of defectors increased owing to the poor conditions. The number of defectors since then has only been increasing, the reason now being–freedom. To deal with this increase, the DPRK government now punishes 3 generations of the family, if even one member defects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the larger question remains—how does such a country still exist in the 21st century? We can attribute two major reasons for this. First, every conversation in North Korea is overheard, and the propagation of any ideology against the nation leads to immediate persecution. There is also a travel ban in North Korea with permission required from the government for even inter-state transport, hindering collectivisation. The fear of torture and starvation for their entire family has become a deterrent that has forced people to simply follow the government without dissent. Second, if North Korea falls, it will create a massive humanitarian and refugee crisis, a civil war, an insurgency that could have nuclear weapons and a state divided between the ideological difference of South Korea and China. Because of the looming threat of these scenarios, no country has ever done anything more than sanctioning North Korea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future in North Korea seems bleak. In an isolated world, these people are simply getting by each day trying to survive. However, amidst the tyranny, the people have created a world for themselves where they support one another. Many defectors note that while the country was poor, and the people were starving, but, they were warm to one another and cared for each other. Unlike its southern counterpart, where capitalism has induced stress and chasing materialistic needs, the Northern peninsula maintains a lifestyle where they are content even if they’re getting a small surplus. The more well off a person is, the more stressed out they are for instead of thinking about survival, they have time to overthink.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A K-Drama that I was watching recently revolved around a North Korean soldier. The drama was great, but what stayed with me post bingeing it was the intrigue for North Korea: a country that calls itself the greatest nation in the world while its people suffer from the worst human rights violations; a country that calls itself a democracy with a 100% voter turnout in any election but has the world’s most authoritarian regime; a country built on the ideology of ‘self-reliance’ but heavily dependent on aid from the international community.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Sexism and the City</title>
      <link href="/Sexism-and-the-City" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sexism and the City" />
      <published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Sexism-and-the-City</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Sexism-and-the-City">&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that this big bad world is biased towards the people with both the X and Y chromosomes, thanks to the patriarchy that has upheld the ideas of male superiority. These biases further suggest that women are inferior because of their sex. Thus, any expression upholding these biases can be termed as — ‘sexist.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sexism can affect anyone, however, there have been few men on the receiving end. It affects men and boys when they don’t conform to gender roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this article, we will restrict the ambit of our discussion to only the University level in India. Sexist attitudes are not just limited to boys rating girls on a scale of 0-10 based on their physical appearances. It has transcended into limiting the opportunities for women, imposing draconian rules and observing traditions that are misogynistic and chauvinist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often consider academia as the citadel of everything fair and progressive. However, we don’t live in a utopian world. Just like other institutions that have these notions of male superiority deep-rooted in their practices and norms, so does education. Many people benefit from these power dynamics in the status quo, and thus, have no incentive to change it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a stark imbalance in the male to female ratio in many courses such as law, management, and STEM disciplines. Considered the holy grail of education and achievement, Indian Institutes of Technology (IITs), suffer from the worst gender imbalance with only 9.3% of females. This gap further increases with progression in these careers, with an utter lack of women in leadership positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see this trend across central universities in India. Out of 46 central universities, only 5 have women placed as the heads of the institutions. Even in India’s most liberal universities, like Jawaharlal Nehru University (JNU), no women has ever been the head of the institute. The selection committees are dominated by men, who give little weightage to women candidates as many view women as someone who has stolen a job a man was entitled to do. This perception has risen from the cultural view that men are the bread-earners of the family while women are the homemakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In colleges with extreme gender disproportion, the environment becomes testosterone-driven, leading to women students being subjected to sexual innuendos and sexist remarks. Language and communication make people recognise or demean their contribution to society. Our language shapes our thoughts, and the way we think influences our actions. Gender-discriminatory language reinforces sexist attitudes and behaviours. Thus, female students become conditioned to accept subtle sexism and lewd remarks as the norm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sexism in Indian universities isn’t just limited to leadership positions but encompasses norms that affect the day-to-day lives of many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many colleges across India, dress codes are imposed on women. For example, The Government Medical College, Kerala issued a dress code for its female students instructing them not to wear jeans, leggings, short tops or noisy ornaments. Many girls’ hostels also follow curfews, thus increasing the red tape for them to step out. Many institutions like Jamia Milia University, IITs and the University of Delhi have come under the light in the past for such rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such draconian measures show how expecting equality remains a far-off dream for girls. These rules concretise the notion that the price for the safety of women is curbing their freedom rather than bringing a systemic change in the attitude of men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Symbiosis Center for Media and Communication (SCMC) Pune is widely recognised for its option of ‘film and television’ specialisation as a part of its three-year undergraduate program. In her article for &lt;em&gt;The Print&lt;/em&gt;, Vaishnavi Suresh, an SCMC alumnus highlights the rampant sexism in the coveted institution. Being a media college, the students spend a large amount of time in classes watching films. Vaishnavi, however, notes how the students barely had any female filmmakers as role models. In an incident where some people from her class suggested they study a female filmmaker, the professor shot down their requests and instead taught them about another male filmmaker. She also noted how by the time they came to their 3rd year, only 2 women out of her batch were still invested in the camera by practising photography or videography. She cites the reason for this to be the “reality of the industry drilled into them constantly.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A college that prides itself on being liberal lacks showing its students that women could be role models too. Having female role models is important for breaking the stereotype of men being better than women to propagate for a more inclusive world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016, while the #MeToo movement was still in its nascent stage, the students of Women Centred Practices at Tata Institute of Social Sciences (TISS), Mumbai organised a ‘Gender Sensitisation Week’ in their campus. Amidst the gender sensitisation week, a signed comment was noticed on a banner that was put up for people to anonymously share accounts of sexist instances on campus. It read, “Sexism is an accusation, sluts level against dissenting voices for recognising that a slut is a slut.” Instances like these make one realise that the notion of some campuses being ‘more sensitive and liberal than the rest of the world’, is nothing but a facade. People still trivialise sexual harassment, use the word ‘slut’ as a derogatory term and push aside voices of dissent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2019, a few pre-university colleges in Bengaluru set higher cut-off marks for girls for admission into the courses. On inquiring about the reason behind this move, the Vice-Chancellor of Christ PU College, Fr Abraham VM, commented - “Girls are smart, and this is not a new trend. If there is no higher cut-off, the college will have only girls. The higher cut-off is to bring in gender balance.” Subsequently, the cut-off for science stream in Christ college was fixed at 93.92% for girls and 91.04% for boys. This move begs the question that in a society where historically almost every classroom has been dominated by men, why do we fear if women step into those shoes. It seems like a move to &lt;em&gt;punish&lt;/em&gt; women for breaking the glass ceiling despite being on the worse off end of the access to opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the most famous sexist tradition would be the regressive Virgin Tree ‘Pooja’ on Valentine’s Day at Hindu College (University of Delhi). The Pooja is a customary tradition wherein the boys’ hostel decorates a ‘virgin tree’ on campus with condoms and posters of an actress naming her the Damdami Mai. This actress, seen as a sex symbol, is ‘worshipped’ on Valentine’s Day and according to legend, the people partaking in this practice lose their virginity in the coming six months or at least get into a relationship. In a university space, where we regard sexuality-related conversations as a taboo, they often term such a celebration as ‘liberatory.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The V-Day pooja, which has been taking place since 1953, is ridden in a Brahmanical and casteist notion of prayer and reward. Highly offensive and misogynistic, the pooja follows a hollow notion of ‘sex-positivity’ while overlooking homosexual relationships. The celebration reinforces the existing patriarchal structures which have ingrained insecurity in the minds of young women by reducing their value to just the pleasure of and determined by an external male gaze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;College is the first encounter of the young adults with reality by giving them a peek into the larger world out there. It introduces us to the workings of the ‘real world’ and underpins many of our perspectives and expectations in a social context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sexist practices create a climate of fear and insecurity by producing feelings of worthlessness, self-censorship, and changes in behaviour. This further leads to the deterioration of people’s mental health and makes them acceptable to violence, as they now think they &lt;em&gt;deserve&lt;/em&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When students are exposed to these ideas in college, it either normalises these ideas for many by ingraining notions of male superiority. Or it makes people recognise and fight the problem. The wave of social consciousness and woke culture have made the youth today more liberal than their predecessors, leading to more inclusive spaces for women and homosexuals in institutions. They, however, remain a minority faction and their wokeness hasn’t led to a ripple effect big enough to shake down sexism on a bigger level. The boy’s hostel at Hindu College plans to host the Virgin Tree Pooja in 2021, many girls’ hostels continue to follow the archaic dress codes and curfews, and conversations among men will continue to be casually sexist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All over the world, people have celebrated 46 International Women’s Days and 6 Zero Discrimination Days and will celebrate many more, but until we abolish all discriminatory and sexist practices, we won’t be celebrating these days in their true essence.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It’s no secret that this big bad world is biased towards the people with both the X and Y chromosomes, thanks to the patriarchy that has upheld the ideas of male superiority. These biases further suggest that women are inferior because of their sex. Thus, any expression upholding these biases can be termed as — ‘sexist.’</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Beware, You’re Being Watched!</title>
      <link href="/Beware-You-re-Being-Watched" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beware, You’re Being Watched!" />
      <published>2020-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Beware-You-re-Being-Watched</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Beware-You-re-Being-Watched">&lt;p&gt;The Netflix show &lt;em&gt;You&lt;/em&gt; has made its way to one of the most talked-about television shows on social media. It revolves around the creepy but hot stalker who spies on women using telescopes and by physically following them. If you think this merely happens in fiction, wait till the end of this article. Before we begin, this article isn’t about a particular political party acting as the villain, though all of them may be considered so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the increased use of technology by criminals, government surveillance is inevitable. In almost every nation, a certain proportion of the population is under the scanner of intelligence agencies. However, the potential mass-scale tracking of the data of all citizens has sparked a grave debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s surveillance systems have access to 100% of all internet activity, with broad surveillance capability based on IP, email addresses, URLs, HTTP, Telenet, or webmail, and even through abroad and blind searches across all traffic in the internet pipe using keywords and key-phrases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Central Monitoring System (CMS), launched in 2013, is the surveillance project which allows the Indian government to monitor online and telephonic data of citizens. Unlike its American counterpart PRISM, there is no legal recourse for a citizen whose personal details are being misused or leaked from the central or regional database. CMS does not even have any judicial oversight.In India, most orders are signed by either the Central or State Home Secretary. This causes a conflict of interest, as the executive branch is both undertaking law enforcement and providing oversight on its work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pursuit of internet monitoring started following the leak of the Amar Singh tapes, with instructions for ensuring the privacy of communications. This mandated all ISPs (Internet Service Providers) to have designated nodal officers for communicating and receiving the intimations for interceptions. Since the government controlled the LIMs (Lawful Intercept and Monitoring Systems), it directly sent software commands and sucked out whatever information is needed from the internet pipe with no intimation to anyone. The lack of a privacy law made it easier for the government to undertake such radical steps. The Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 and the Information Technology Act, 2008, allowed the government to monitor, intercept, and even block online conversations and websites. The addition of the CMS significantly widened the number of sources and could simplify access to these records. In 2019, the government went even further with this pursuit of privacy, like passing the Data Protection Bill and forming the NATGRID.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Intelligence Grid (NATGRID) aims to allow investigation and law enforcement agencies to access real-time information from data stored with agencies such as the Income Tax Department, banks, insurance companies, Indian Railways, credit card transactions, and more. It is meant to connect public and private databases for ten central intelligence agencies. State agencies, however, will not be allowed access to the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NATGRID was first introduced post the 26/11 Mumbai terror attacks by the then Home Minister Mr P Chidambaram. After 10 years of delay, on September 12, 2019, Home Minister Amit Shah announced that the NATGRID would be functional by the end of 2019. Along with the Crime and Criminal Tracking Network System (CCTNS), which will integrate the Central and State crime data, NATGRID will give a suspect’s ‘360-degree’ profile. This system could prevent or detect incidents like the 26/11 attacks, claims the Home Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been many concerns regarding the dangers of misuse of this system. The unified pooling of vital information from different resources is vulnerable to cyber attacks or espionage from foreign intelligence agencies. Given the recent WhatsApp data breach, this apprehension needs to be addressed by having proper checks and balances in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, who is watching the notorious &lt;em&gt;chowkidars&lt;/em&gt; (watchmen)? Also, if someone violated your privacy, but you never knew about it, did it even happen? This is where the Data Protection Bill, 2019, becomes important. It is India’s first step towards a privacy framework and sets a framework to govern personal data. The bill is meant to ensure that Indian citizens have control of their data. The bill seeks to localise the storage of data and to set up the Data Protection Authority of India. However, under the bill, not only will your sensitive personal information be stored but also information about you and your online habits. It is a potential avenue for the invasion of privacy because it can reveal many personal aspects. Companies, governments, and political parties can further use these to find the most convincing ways to advertise to you online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has exempted its agencies from the rules that govern the processing of personal data citing national security, public order and friendly relations with foreign states. 24x7 surveillance acts as a major threat to businesses. Businesses are formed on the foundations of security and trust: from the purchase of an item on an e-commerce site to a company’s research mechanisms and technologies. Central databases make attacking a company based on such confidential information easier. All one would have to do to go one-up on you is to attack these databases. It was because of this the USA decided not to impose blanket surveillance. Their idea is “while we may live in a society without human rights, we cannot be in one without functional markets”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, it allows the government to manipulate the data patterns and wrongly accuse innocent citizens of being criminals. With NATGRID and the Data Protection Bill, the government shall have access to all data. In a world where the government claims that peaceful protests by the students are a threat to national security and anyone can be labelled a terrorist without evidence, the exemptions in the Data Protection Bill become important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government can access private data or government agency data on grounds of sovereignty or public order. This has dangerous implications. While the Indian Constitution recognises the right to privacy, there are very few laws governing government surveillance. Due to this, there is very little legislative oversight, leading to little judicial decision-making regarding surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Acton had famously prophesied that “power tends to corrupt and absolute power corrupts absolutely”. This peril is more acute when the power is used covertly. Efforts to maintain accountability over intelligence agencies are frequently troublesome. All things considered, intelligence agencies comprise human beings, with their capabilities being circumscribed by human flaws, frailties and defects. Thus, safeguards are unavoidable and unnecessary, unfortunately, or rather, suspiciously, the Indian government seems blissfully unaware of that necessity, betraying its desire to be the stalker in people’s homes.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Netflix show You has made its way to one of the most talked-about television shows on social media. It revolves around the creepy but hot stalker who spies on women using telescopes and by physically following them. If you think this merely happens in fiction, wait till the end of this article. Before we begin, this article isn’t about a particular political party acting as the villain, though all of them may be considered so.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Women are Under-represented? Not News.</title>
      <link href="/Women-are-Under-represented-Not-News" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Women are Under-represented? Not News." />
      <published>2020-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Women-are-Under-represented-Not-News</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Women-are-Under-represented-Not-News">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I only go to a movie if it satisfies three basic requirements. One, it has to have at least two women in it, who, two, talk to each other about, three, something besides a man.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1985, a new edition of the comic strip &lt;em&gt;Dykes to Watch Out For&lt;/em&gt;, called ‘The Rule’, first introduced the ‘Bechdel Test’ to the film industry. The writers portrayed the character as avoiding cinema with an extreme male bias, with the character in the script claiming that she hasn’t been able to watch a movie since the 1979 space horror film &lt;em&gt;Alien&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a society where patriarchy has been the dominating narrative, it’s no surprise that women’s representation in the film industry (or any industry, for that matter) is lacking. Looking at statistics from the past few years, women play only about 37% of roles on television (2015). In films, the percentage of speaking roles for women drops to 28% (2012). Women make up a mere 16% of directors, writers, producers, and editors (2013).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many are unaware that gender stereotypes are not just linked to the costumes but are intrinsic to a character’s conversations, actions and traits. To understand how grave the situation is, the Test proves to be helpful. The Bechdel Test is a convenient way to gauge the active presence of female characters in films and just how well-rounded and complete those roles are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On listening to what it takes for the movies to pass the test, one might think: “This seems easy, I bet most movies pass it.” And that’s what I expected. But on researching more on the topic, the number of popular movies that couldn’t pass this simple test turned out to be astonishing. At the 2014 Academy Awards, only three out of the eight nominees for Best Picture passed the Bechdel Test: &lt;em&gt;Boyhood&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Theory of Everything&lt;/em&gt;. Corresponding to research by Duke University in 2017, over 40% of all the films in the US failed the test. The team used data from the bechdeltest.com website, a user-compiled database of over 7,000 movies where volunteers rate films based on the Bechdel criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These results show the under-representation of women’s complex lives in the film industry. The Bechdel Test’s demands set a low bar for the filmmakers to meet and they start a conversation about gender inequality in film. The test has brought to light the importance of shifting the focus from men to the other things in a woman’s life: career goals, friendships, inner troubles, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the test comes with its own set of problems. A film passing the test doesn’t mean the movie automatically becomes one that the feminists support. The Bechdel Test can be a misleading gauge of ‘feminism’ in movies. Films with a strong female lead don’t provide a supporting female character who holds enough importance to converse with the lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many movies that pass the test, do so based on a ‘technicality’: in some inconsequential scene, the women have a small conversation about something other than men, therefore fulfilling the criteria. For example, &lt;em&gt;Gravity&lt;/em&gt; featuring a female astronaut doesn’t pass the test. However, &lt;em&gt;Legally Blonde&lt;/em&gt; does because Elle and her friend talk about their dogs in a scene or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female characters have followed the same tropes. The movies make women damsels in distress or a ‘manic pixie dream girl.’ They also sexualise women, forcing them to wear tight-fitting clothes and heels throughout the movie. Adjectives about physical attributes like beautiful, gorgeous and pretty are used to describe the female characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another common trope used is called ‘fridging’ wherein the female characters are injured, raped, killed, or depowered, sometimes to stimulate ‘protective’ traits in men, and often as a plot device intended to move a male character’s story arc forward. &lt;em&gt;Women in Refrigerators&lt;/em&gt;, a website created in 1999 by a group of feminist comic-book fans lists examples of this trope. It refers to an incident in &lt;em&gt;Green Lantern #54&lt;/em&gt; (1994), in which, the title hero, Kyle Rayner, comes home to his apartment to find that his girlfriend had been killed and stuffed into a refrigerator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, however, is not the sole test. The ‘Mako Mori Test’ requires that: The film must feature at least one female character, who has her narrative arc that does not depend on supporting a man’s story. Likewise, the ‘DuVernay Test’ determines a film’s racial diversity. It checks if the minorities have realised lives rather than serving as scenery in the stories of the whites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these tests prove to be like the Bechdel Test as they provide data about representation but cannot provide a coherent picture if the film is feminist enough. Some critics argue that the problem lies in the disagreement about what it means to be a ‘feminist film.’ Because of this, forming a one-size-fits-all test for judging feminism has been difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female representation worsens across intersectionality. Under the broader umbrella of female characters, there are even fewer black females, Latina females, Lesbians or Transgenders. Hollywood executives have knocked dark-skinned women to the side in favour of those with European features and pale complexions. ‘Colourism’ isn’t, however, unique to the black community. In the Bollywood film industry, too, the starring roles go to lighter-skinned actors. Many of them also endorse fairness creams and other similar products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the 2018 USC Annenberg Inclusion Initiative study, out of the top 100 films in 2017, 43 films didn’t include any African-American female character. Sixty-five films were missing Asian or Asian-American female characters, and 64 didn’t include a Latina character. Ninety-four didn’t feature characters with disabilities and LGBTQ characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representation is significant for all communities. However, more than representation, it’s accurate representation that is important. Accurate and well-rounded representation allows people to see a world outside of themselves, fostering critical thinking and empathy with those who are different. The stereotypes don’t allow for the representation to portray the full picture of the complexities of the surrounding people. Because of the aspirational value that pop culture holds, it becomes a cunning, persuasive and pervasive educator. As an educator, it has the power to shape views and opinions about how people look at themselves and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representation in the film industry, however, isn’t just limited to on-screen representation but also extends to those who are working behind the camera. Figures published by &lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt; have revealed that only 22% of the crew involved in making 2,000 of the biggest grossing films over the past 20 years were women. Further, the report revealed a split in responsibilities: women made up a majority only in costume and wardrobe departments and casting. These departments have been perceived as feminine workplaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue deepens when you take into consideration the wage gap between the actors and actresses. &lt;em&gt;Forbes’&lt;/em&gt; analysis of American acting salaries in 2013 determined that the top-paid actors for that year made 2½ times as much money as the top-paid actresses. This means that Hollywood’s best-compensated actresses made just 40 cents for every dollar that the best-compensated men made. Women who have spoken about the issue explain the reason for not demanding higher pay as “they worry about seeming difficult or spoiled.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her 2018 Oscar speech, Frances McDormand suggested an ‘inclusion rider’, a clause in contracts meant to stipulate that 50% of a film crew had to be female. If A-list actors put this clause into practice, the film industry could portray the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Film producers and showrunners have, however, started to take charge. In 2015, the film professionals started the “Bechdel Bill” campaign, who pledged that 80% of their films will pass the test. CW also incorporated the Bechdel Test in two of its shows: &lt;em&gt;Crazy Ex-Girlfriend&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Jane the Virgin&lt;/em&gt;. Despite both shows not passing the test, the move was symbolic as the network constructed a space in which discourse could take place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This discourse can challenge Hollywood to do more than settle for the status quo and to question the absences of many types of people from the movie-making process. These people could potentially enrich our entertainment in countless ways, both on the screen and behind the lens. A post &lt;em&gt;#&lt;/em&gt;MeToo and #TimesUp world has the potential to hold Hollywood accountable and challenge the oppressive structure to demand a more inclusive industry that isn’t hegemonised by cis-white-men.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“I only go to a movie if it satisfies three basic requirements. One, it has to have at least two women in it, who, two, talk to each other about, three, something besides a man.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Sikhs in Canada: A Thorn in India’s Side</title>
      <link href="/Sikhs-in-Canada" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sikhs in Canada: A Thorn in India's Side" />
      <published>2019-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Sikhs-in-Canada</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Sikhs-in-Canada">&lt;p&gt;For many families in Punjab, shifting to Canada and being a permanent resident is the objective. Families want their sons to settle there and their daughters to marry the rich non-resident Indians. ‘&lt;em&gt;Caneda&lt;/em&gt;’ is a household term and a second home for these Punjabis. The rate of migration is such that Punjabis in Canada form roughly 2% of the total population, with a majority of them being Sikh. Punjabi is the third-most spoken language in Canada, after English and French. For the rest of us in India, it only seems fair to imagine a day when &lt;em&gt;Caneda&lt;/em&gt;’s Prime Minister is also a Sikh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the broader picture of Indo-Canadian relations shows a little more animosity between the two countries. The two countries share various complementarities, like their democratic character and association with the Commonwealth. Despite this and both countries recognising the economic potential in their bilateral ties, the relationship has been rather tense on the political front and thus has not prospered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major factor for this has been the activities of the Khalistan supporters in Canada. Canada’s criticism of India has also been responsible for denting India’s interest in engaging with Canada as a strategic partner. These criticisms have involved past events such as the military action in Amritsar’s Golden Temple and the 1984 riots. Relations reached one of their lowest points in 1985, when Sikh extremists blew up Air India Flight 182 as it left Vancouver Airport for India, killing all 329 passengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides these issues, the current political scenario of Canada has also caused some concern for India. Because of the prominent involvement of Sikhs in Canada’s politics and the regionalisation of Indo-Canadian politics, issues affecting the Sikh diaspora have often become a part of the political discourse in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While moderates view India favourably and oppose secessionist sentiments, the fundamentalist groups, such as the Babbar Khalsa, vehemently advocate for the Khalistan cause. Events like the 1984 riots and the Golden Temple incident have been frequently introduced in Canada’s provincial legislatures, often in the form of petitions. In 2010, for instance, Liberal MPs Sukh Dhaliwal and Andrew Kania introduced a petition in the House of Commons asking Canada to consider the 1984 riots as an act of genocide and discuss the issue with India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Justin Trudeau has often been caught in the crossfire between pandering to the Sikh population in his country and maintaining peaceful relations with India. Canadian politicians tread a fine line when attempting to involve themselves in the Sikh community, ensuring that people do not see them advocating for separatist causes inadvertently. The Sikhs in Canada form a voting bloc for Trudeau. In April 2019, his government removed a reference to Sikh extremism from a report that had earlier termed Sikh terrorism as one of the five threats facing Canada. He even attended a Khalsa Day parade organized by a radical Gurudwara in Toronto in 2017 where people waved Khalistani flags and put images of Sikh separatist leaders and militants on display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canada cannot curtail the right to freedom of speech and expression of its Sikh citizens, but New Delhi wants Trudeau to distance himself from Sikh separatists, publicly. PM Narendra Modi clarified that India would not tolerate any attempts to undermine India’s sovereignty and unity in his press conference with Trudeau. Punjab’s Chief Minister, Amarinder Singh has publicly accused Trudeau’s ministers of having sympathies with Canadian Sikh extremists and secessionists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;18 Sikhs were voted into the 338-seat lower house of the Canadian Parliament in the 2019 Federal Elections. However, only 13 candidates from the Sikh community were elected to the 543-seat Lok Sabha in the 17th General Elections in India. Sikhs form approximately 2% of the population both in Canada and India, but their representation in politics is unmatched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of these 18 Sikhs is the leader of the National Democratic Party (NDP), Jagmeet Singh. A former criminal lawyer, Singh created political history in Canada when he made his debut in the House of Commons as the first non-white leader of a major opposition party in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pre-election polls showed he was the most popular of the three party leaders. Singh is your poster woke boy with swag. Recognised in Canadian media for his fashion sense and style, Singh identifies as a progressive and a social democrat. He supports a progressive tax system and a $15 per hour minimum wage. He strongly advocates for equality, and supports LGBTQ rights. He also wants to save the planet by reducing the carbon emissions levels of Canada to 30% of 2005 levels by 2025.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Canada’s highly decentralised federation, forming the government at the provincial level makes the NDP an influential political force. Being led federally by a “visible minority” makes it a prominent symbol of the maturity of Canada’s multiculturalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Democratic Party, despite winning only 24 seats in the 2019 General Elections, has become one of the most talked-about parties. We can attribute two key factors to this popularity: (i) Singh’s speech in the democratic debate and (ii) the Liberal Party emerged as a minority party in the elections. Despite the Liberal Party staying a minority party in the House of Commons, forming a coalition with the NDP to govern, as the majority party, had been a general suggestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Canadian media refer to Singh as the “kingmaker” in the legislative. The Liberal Party would need NDP’s votes on issues where the NDP and Liberals are more aligned than the Conservatives are, to pass any bill. For India, its interest in Singh is not one of pride that an Indian rose to become the leader of a major political party in a powerful Western state. Instead, the power Singh holds having entered the Canadian parliament has become a matter of concern for India. He has had a history of defending militants fighting for a separate Sikh homeland and lobbying for labeling a 1984 pogrom against Sikhs in India a ‘genocide’ by the government of Ontario. While he has not offered unqualified support to the Khalistan cause and remains vague on the issue, he has criticised India for Operation Blue Star. Singh will now have a far more consequential platform to continue his activism concerning attempting to seek justice for several violent episodes in India’s past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, India denied Jagmeet Singh a visa to visit because he was “misusing the pretext of human rights to pursue his insidious agenda of disturbing the social fabric of India and undermining the peace, harmony and territorial integrity of India.” For a provincial politician, this is notable. But as the leader of a major political party with a seat in the country’s main legislative body, this suspicion towards Singh by a friendly country is of more substantial potential consequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India has dealt with a partition once before and thus has little tolerance for movements that could threaten further division of the state. This and the fact that India comprises culturally distinct regions make its current integrity reliant on a compact of pluralism. Khalistan seems to have more significant traction in the Sikh diaspora than it does in Punjab. Because of which India seems more concerned about diaspora movements that agitate for its creation than internal movements. Thus, India is sensitive towards anything that it perceives as a threat to its unity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Singh is leading a deeply divided party that is facing severe fundraising deficits and a significant number of experienced MPs who won’t be seeking re-election. If he wishes to use his new platform to bring light to the injustices of India in the 1980’s, Singh would have to wait until he has dealt with the more direct concerns of his party first. The primary focus of the realities of Singh’s role at home may just save New Delhi from having to be overly concerned with him for the time being.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For many families in Punjab, shifting to Canada and being a permanent resident is the objective. Families want their sons to settle there and their daughters to marry the rich non-resident Indians. ‘Caneda’ is a household term and a second home for these Punjabis. The rate of migration is such that Punjabis in Canada form roughly 2% of the total population, with a majority of them being Sikh. Punjabi is the third-most spoken language in Canada, after English and French. For the rest of us in India, it only seems fair to imagine a day when Caneda’s Prime Minister is also a Sikh.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Nakba of Israel and Palestine</title>
      <link href="/The-Nakba-of-Israel-and-Palestine" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Nakba of Israel and Palestine" />
      <published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Nakba-of-Israel-and-Palestine</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Nakba-of-Israel-and-Palestine">&lt;p&gt;In 2014, Rihanna, Zayn Malik, and Coldplay found themselves in the media limelight for posting pro-Palestinian tweets. As #freePalestine and #freedomforpalestine started trending, their popularity in Israel fell. We can attribute this to the conflict between Israel and Palestine. The Israel-Palestinian conflict is one of the world’s longest-running and most controversial conflicts. Today, over 7 million Palestinians identify themselves as refugees, with Israelis continuing to settle in the territory that Palestinians claim as their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Torn between the Jewish Zionist movement and the Palestinian nationalist movement lies a piece of land and millions of people. Whom does this land belong to? Is there more to this conflict than a piece of land? What has this conflict led to? Is there a way out of this labyrinth of suffering? Within Israeli and Palestinian societies, the conflict has generated a wide variety of opinions. A hallmark of the conflict has been the level of violence conducted by rebel armies, paramilitary groups, terror cells and individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conflict has its roots in history. In the 1900’s, the area which is now known as Israel and Palestine was under Ottoman rule. The Ottoman Empire was religiously diverse with Muslims, Christians, and Jews living together. This happily ever after was hindered when Muslims in the area started developing a sense of not just being Arabs but also having a distinct national identity: Palestinian. Concurrently, the Zionism movement started emerging in Europe. They believed Judaism was not just a religion but also a national identity and so, Jews deserved a home in their ancestral land. Their idea was similar to how the French live in France and the Indians live in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As both groups started working towards developing this area as their homeland, the peace they had been living in vanished forever. Between 1896 and 1948, millions of Jews migrated to British-controlled Palestine, with many fleeing the Holocaust in Germany. Palestinians regarded this as another form of European colonisation. As more Jews settled into farming communes, tension rose between Jews and Arabs, with both sides committing acts of violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jewish population in British Palestine and violence between the two groups continued to rise. And so, in 1947, the United Nations (UN) approved a plan to divide the land into two areas, with distinct borders, to form Israel and Palestine. The plan was meant to give the Jews a state and to establish Palestinian independence. It declared Jerusalem a ‘special international zone’ , owing to its religious importance, whose administration was to be controlled by the UN. Jerusalem has a place of importance in three vital religions: Islam, Christianity and Judaism. Because of this, both countries consider Jerusalem as their capital. But the map largely looked like a jigsaw puzzle. An average Palestinian citizen who lived in West Bank had no idea about what would be happening in Gaza (and still doesn’t).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formation of a Jewish majority state in the Middle East didn’t sit well with the rest of the Arab countries. They saw the UN’s plan as another way of the Europeans stealing their land. Many of the Arab states came together and declared war on Israel, in 1948, to establish a unified Arab Palestine. Despite being a new-born country, Israel defeated them and proved its military might. In doing so, Israel pushed past its borders and took control of a significant portion of Palestine. The war forced hundreds of Palestinians to flee their homes and become refugees in the surrounding Arab countries, making them stateless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1967, a six-day war took place between Israel and the Arab nations. Again, Israel won. Not only did it annex the whole of Palestine but also territories from Egypt, Syria and Jordan. Israel got the right to govern the Palestinians. In the decades that followed, the Arab countries made peace with Israel. This allowed them to get their Israeli annexed territories back. The broader Israeli-Arab conflict now morphed into a more specific Israeli-Palestinian conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the rise of the Palestinian Liberation Organization (PLO) in 1964, the founder, Yasser Arafat, used military tactics including attacks on Israeli civilians. The PLO oversaw guerrilla groups on the one hand and used non-violent approaches on the other. Meanwhile, the Israeli started moving into West Bank and East Jerusalem, establishing Israeli settlements. They undertook this for three main reasons: (i) religious reasons so that people could live close to Jerusalem, (ii) to claim the land as Israeli territory and (iii) cheap housing. As more civilians settled into Palestinian territories, the military followed. This led to increased checkpoints for Palestinians and forced Palestinians off their land. In effect, it blurred the boundaries of any future Palestinian state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the 1980’s, the frustration among Palestinians grew, and they launched the First Intifada (meaning uprising). This began by boycotting Israeli products and services, and refusing to pay taxes or working jobs in Israel. However, when the Israeli military cracked down on the protestors, violence ensued. The Intifada led to the rise of Hamas in Gaza, an extremist group dedicated to Israel’s destruction, which considered the PLO too compromise-minded. Till date, Hamas has garnered support not just because of its military strength but because of the social welfare projects undertaken by it in Gaza. They have built schools, mosques and clinics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1993, the PLO accepted Israel’s right to exist and in exchange wanted Israel to recognize it as the legitimate representative of Palestinians. That was the beginning of real peace negotiations between the two sides. Leaders from both sides signed the American-brokered Oslo Accords. This allowed Palestinians more freedom to govern themselves. Hard-liners on both sides, however, were not happy with the terms of the peace process and ensued violence to sabotage this process. After signing the second round of the Oslo Accords, the far-right Israeli groups shot Israeli PM Yitzhak Rabin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US has been pro-Israel since the Cold War. US politicians view the pro-Israel propaganda as a method to garner support from their citizens by appealing to their anti-Muslim sentiments. This, however, has larger implications. The domino effect of the US supporting Israel is that the US’ allies have started to support Israel too. A good example is India. India aligned itself with Palestine after the partition in 1948, but since it has aligned with the US now, they have forced India to support Israel. In 2018, the USA shifted its embassy from Tel Aviv to Jerusalem in Israel, internationally recognizing Jerusalem as the capital of Israel. As a consequence, other countries such as Guatemala and Paraguay also shifted their embassies to Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crux of this conflict remains the same till date. Both parties want a country to exert their distinct identity, and none will compromise with the other. Caught in the crossfire between the two governments and extremist groups, it’s the voices and lives of the citizens that are being compromised. Everyone who identifies as either a Palestinian or an Israeli knows at least one person who lost their life because of this conflict. Most Jews see the Palestinians’ demand for an independent state as just. Most Palestinians prefer a two-state solution. Both Israelis and Palestinians are afraid of the people in charge on the other side. The people can’t trust their information sources because they know it’s fueled with propaganda. The settlements resemble regular suburbs from any part of the world, with people trying to live peacefully in a place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Palestinian governance is divided between the Palestinian Authority and Hamas. The Israeli government is skeptical of Hamas and its goal of Israel’s destruction. As violence continues, there seems to be little political will for peace. Any successful peace initiative would need resolving the issues: West Bank settlements, Israeli security, Palestinian refugees and their right to return, Jerusalem, mutual recognition and water rights. However, there are three major hurdles: (i) Israeli settlements continue expanding, (ii) the PLO, and Hamas cannot negotiate jointly and (iii) everyone is unsure regarding how to get the talks started. The truth of the matter is the governments aren’t solving the conflict anymore, they are just managing it. Israel constructed walls and checkpoints after the second Intifada, leaving Palestinians to believe they have no future as a people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent Israeli elections have not given a clear mandate but Likud party’s chief, incumbent Prime Minister, Benjamin Netanyahu is likely to head a coalition government. It remains to be seen whether there would be any change in attitude of leaders on both sides of the fence. For this to happen, it is necessary that both parties trust each other, and explore the possibility of coexistence and the legitimacy of each other’s historical narrative. The United Nations should come out of the shadow of the US and mediate a solution for the welfare of the people in this war torn area.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In 2014, Rihanna, Zayn Malik, and Coldplay found themselves in the media limelight for posting pro-Palestinian tweets. As #freePalestine and #freedomforpalestine started trending, their popularity in Israel fell. We can attribute this to the conflict between Israel and Palestine. The Israel-Palestinian conflict is one of the world’s longest-running and most controversial conflicts. Today, over 7 million Palestinians identify themselves as refugees, with Israelis continuing to settle in the territory that Palestinians claim as their own.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Heartbeat Bill: An Infringement Upon the Right to Choose</title>
      <link href="/Heartbeat-Bill" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Heartbeat Bill: An Infringement Upon the Right to Choose" />
      <published>2019-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Heartbeat-Bill</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Heartbeat-Bill">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;American Horror Story&lt;/em&gt; is no longer a mere fictional television show, it is a reality for women in the United States. A country, put on a pedestal for its liberal laws and democratic attitude, has taken a turn with the rise of the extreme right-wing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2010, new state laws have been passed in various parts of the US, making abortions physically inaccessible to women. These laws have reduced the number of abortion clinics in several states to one, due to frequent and unnecessary changes in the restrictions placed on them. The clinics that cannot afford such changes end up shutting down altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the US Supreme Court ruled on &lt;em&gt;Roe v. Wade&lt;/em&gt;, it did not specify when abortions were legal. They vaguely decided to make it unconstitutional to outlaw them until the foetus is ‘viable’. Since scientists had not determined when that was, states exploited this ambiguity and passed specific week bans like (i) when a foetal heartbeat can be detected, (ii) when the foetus can experience the pain of the procedure and (iii) when the foetus has developed into a person. This sparked the pro-life vs pro-choice debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2019, a law was passed, in Alabama, making abortions practically illegal for women. The sole exceptions made are if the mother’s life is at severe risk or if the abortion is carried out before six weeks into the pregnancy. The six-week rule is impractical as most women find out about their pregnancies only after those six weeks. The lack of other exceptions also implies that a woman who is HIV positive or has been impregnated by rape or incest would not be allowed to terminate her pregnancy. Moreover, a doctor carrying out this procedure could face 99 years in prison, so if he/she was to be prosecuted under this law in 2019, he would get out in 2118. The rapist, however, can get out after three months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pro-life activists support this legislation out of the belief that it addresses an important human rights issue: the right to life of the foetus. The bill, however, is not about protecting an unborn child, but about control over a woman’s body. Most importantly, it acts as an infringement on a woman’s right to life itself. In fact the High Court at Calcutta, in India, a country ostensibly more backward than the United States, brilliantly explains why a practical blanket ban on abortions is truly the infringement of a woman’s right to life, and not the foetus’, in the case of &lt;em&gt;Suparna Debnath v. State of West Bengal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, The Honourable Acting Chief Justice of the Court, Mr Justice Somadder explained that a woman’s “sufferings include the sufferings of her child, whose compromised existence is inextricably linked with the mother. The role of the State in this regard is crucial; both for the well-being of the mother and that of her child.” Mr Justice Somadder added that the reasoning behind this proposition was that “[t]he mother’s personal life and liberty….is inextricably linked with that of the unborn child and will continue even after she gives birth to the child.” Therefore, any person who professes to care about the right to life of the foetus has to care about the right to life of its mother, for the foetus’ existence is, by all means, dependent on its mother. So, if one does not prioritise the woman’s life on the issue of abortion in certain circumstances or understand that the issue is a priori about a woman’s right to life, one only masquerades as ‘pro-life’, when, in fact, they only wish to have dominion over a woman’s body. And this is verily the case with the supporters of the proposed Alabama law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ban is a classic case of a problem-solution mismatch. A government that has failed to strengthen its gun laws, to protect children from mass shootings and has separated immigrant families, is now pretending to care about ‘young and innocent lives’. Currently, Alabama has an F in its status of women’s health and has the highest infant mortality rate. If it were pro-children, the government of Alabama would be working towards increasing the standard of living in the state through measures such as improving the status of women’s health, lowering the infant mortality rates and allocating more resources towards public schools. Instead of adopting policies that keeps people trapped in poverty for generations, because of being forced to support another human being without having the means to do so, the government should to provide comprehensive sex education, free birth control and contraception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, many a time there is a substantial risk that a child, if born, would suffer from deformities and diseases. Their treatment not only takes a financial toll but also a mental toll on the parents. Often, parents cannot afford the treatment. Such a birth especially hurts when the child ends up dying only a few years later. The effects on a woman’s physical and mental health, strength, and life because of carrying a specially-abled child full term is an avoidable cost. A woman’s suffering is not only limited to her pain and agony. As explained above, it is interlinked to her child’s suffering too, as the child’s right to life is parasitic. This, however, does not go to say that the parents loved their child any less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A popular justification for anti-abortion laws has been: ‘protecting women’s health’. However, abortion is no danger to their health. Abortion, carried out by a doctor, has a mortality rate of 0.00073%, which is the lowest of all medical procedures. The law will drive women to now undertake unsafe abortions. As defined by the WHO, “unsafe abortion is a procedure for terminating an unintended pregnancy carried out either by persons lacking the necessary skills or in an environment that does not conform to minimal medical standards or both.” These abortions are the third leading cause of maternal deaths worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many pro-lifers argue that a woman who doesn’t wish to raise the child can give the child up for adoption. However, there are certain problems attached to this. Firstly, there are already too many kids waiting to be adopted, trapped in America’s faulty foster care system. The system comes with its own set of problems: assault by foster parents, lack of access to basic amenities. Secondly, women often do not know whether their baby will be cared for and must live in the perpetual guilt of negative possibilities. It is due to this that women are unable to give a baby up for adoption, a baby they carried to full term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The domino effect of the Alabama bill has already spread to multiple states, some following suit and some still considering it. Beyond this, the bill and the conservative judges in the Supreme Court will now have the power to overturn &lt;em&gt;Roe v. Wade&lt;/em&gt; making abortion illegal all over the country. But America isn’t the only country affected by these laws. In 2017, President Trump reinstated and expanded a policy called the ‘global gag rule’. This rule states, that any overseas organisation which receives US global health funding, cannot even mention abortion as part of their counselling or education programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Kaiser Family Foundation poll of 1,492 Americans, 67% say abortion should be legalised in all or most cases. Women who live in places where abortions are illegal are known to be arrested by police in cases of miscarriage, due to the police believing it to be a conscious attempt to abort. Recently, in Alabama, a pregnant woman who got shot in the stomach was arrested by the police, under similar justifications. From grassroots to the global level, a trend has followed suit, wherein women are being subjected to harsher realities. A voice against these draconian abortion laws made anywhere in the world, be it Ireland or the USA, should be raised by all, irrespective of gender. These regressive laws have no place in any progressive society.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">American Horror Story is no longer a mere fictional television show, it is a reality for women in the United States. A country, put on a pedestal for its liberal laws and democratic attitude, has taken a turn with the rise of the extreme right-wing.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
