<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/sam.tanberg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-12-19T23:49:25+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/sam.tanberg/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">From Friday Night Lights to National Champion, What’s Next for Trevor Lawrence?</title>
      <link href="/From-Friday-Night-Lights-to-National-Champion" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Friday Night Lights to National Champion, What’s Next for Trevor Lawrence?" />
      <published>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/From-Friday-Night-Lights-to-National-Champion</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/From-Friday-Night-Lights-to-National-Champion">&lt;p&gt;Just a little over a year ago, a quarterback in Cartersville, Georgia was the #2 overall ranked high school QB in the nation. A couple weeks later, that same quarterback broke the record for career touchdown passes in Georgia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you might not have known his name a year ago, you most definitely know it now. Trevor Lawrence has proved, as a 19-year-old freshman, that the Clemson Tigers have a new sheriff in town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although he did not come into the season as the starting QB, Lawrence took over the job only 3 weeks into the season. He immediately lit up the scoreboards and stats sheets with 5 passing touchdowns in his first two games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leading the Clemson Tigers to an undefeated, CFP Championship winning season, Lawrence quickly proved that he is ready for college football. He is the first true freshman quarterback to win the CFP National Championship in over 30 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some analysts say that Lawrence is already showing NFL level talent despite only being in his freshman year. He had a 30 touchdown season with only 4 interceptions. Along with the big arm, his accuracy was dead-on all season with a completion rate of 65.2 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This young man still has 2 maybe 3 years left in his college career. Also, Clemson have multiple true freshman threats at receiver helping Lawrence out. Coach Dabo Swinney said all season that this team was special, and they proved it in the playoffs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can only wonder what will happen to Trevor Lawrence once his college career is over. Does he have the skills to make it to the NFL? Or will he be another bust like many of the other college quarterback superstars in recent history?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back on what Trevor Lawrence has done so far, it’s difficult to see him becoming a bust. As previously mentioned, he held the number 2 spot among the nation’s high school quarterbacks in his senior year. Because of this many people knew he would be good but were not sure exactly how he would fare in college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He proved that he was ready for a college defense, as he embarrassed the Syracuse defense in his first start with a 97.6 quarterback rating and a 194 passing yard game. And with at least two more years of growth, a coach and teammates with 100% confidence behind him (as well as a brand-new ring) Lawrence’s prime is yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sports-reference.com/cfb/&quot;&gt;https://www.sports-reference.com/cfb/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sam Tanberg</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="american-football" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Just a little over a year ago, a quarterback in Cartersville, Georgia was the #2 overall ranked high school QB in the nation. A couple weeks later, that same quarterback broke the record for career touchdown passes in Georgia.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Is Hollywood the Perfect Fit for Superstar Bryce Harper?</title>
      <link href="/Is-Hollywood-the-Perfect-Fit-for-Superstar-Bryce-Harper" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Hollywood the Perfect Fit for Superstar Bryce Harper?" />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Is-Hollywood-the-Perfect-Fit-for-Superstar-Bryce-Harper</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Is-Hollywood-the-Perfect-Fit-for-Superstar-Bryce-Harper">&lt;p&gt;The end of baseball season is the time when all diehard fans settle on watching football for a few months. A long 152 days until baseball rolls back around. But that time in the offseason is one of the most important for a franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The offseason is when general managers, scouts, and other team personnel come together to talk about the future of their organization. Trades and new contracts are the most important part of the offseason for a general manager. And with every MLB team having one or more superstars, it has been a wild offseason for trading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest buzz that has been circling around MLB is where Bryce Harper is going to be cleating up to start the 2019 season. As one of the star names in professional baseball, and arguably the biggest free agent this offseason, everyone is hoping that their general manager is keeping an eye out for the 26-year-old phenom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Can the Dodgers make the best case for Harper?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harper, who is now a free agent after an 8-year contract with the Washington Nationals, is looking for a new city to call home. Being a 7-time All-Star with only 8 seasons under his belt makes it obvious that he will have an immediate impact on any team that he joins. Many teams in the MLB are making trades and moves to adjust their lineup for someone like Harper, but none have made a splash like the Los Angeles Dodgers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With back to back World Series appearances, the Dodgers have been making their mark on the MLB in recent years. But in mid-December, the Dodgers traded two powerhouse outfields to the Cincinnati Reds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3-time All-Star, 2-time Gold Glover, and 2-time Silver Slugger, Matt Kemp is a known face for Los Angeles. He played his first 9 seasons with the Dodgers and made it to the All-Star Game last season with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yasiel Puig is another big name for Los Angeles as he has geared up for the Dodgers in all 6 of his professional seasons. In that time he has had an All-Star selection and was runner up for the Rookie of the Year award.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Puig and Kemp are outfielders, so it is obvious that the Dodgers’ staff  are trying to open the outfield up. Whether they are doing so for Harper or not is not clear yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dodgers are desperately looking for an opportunity to get that World Series Ring in October, and maybe Harper is the man they need leading the charge.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sam Tanberg</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="baseball" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The end of baseball season is the time when all diehard fans settle on watching football for a few months. A long 152 days until baseball rolls back around. But that time in the offseason is one of the most important for a franchise.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
