<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/business-finance/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-06-28T23:19:28+01:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/business-finance/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What is Your Ideal Brand Doing for Your ‘Pride’?</title>
      <link href="/What-is-Your-Ideal-Brand-Doing-for-Your-Pride" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Your Ideal Brand Doing for Your ‘Pride’?" />
      <published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/What-is-Your-Ideal-Brand-Doing-for-Your-Pride</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-is-Your-Ideal-Brand-Doing-for-Your-Pride">&lt;p&gt;Each year, in the summertime, Pride collections emerge like a swarm of vividly coloured locusts. They envelop every storefront and Instagram feed in June, promising solidarity for LGBTQ+ communities. In 2021, we are yet again observing the second virtual celebration of pride month. Numerous brands have leveraged pride marketing to increase visibility and lend support to others within the LGBTQ+ community who are still exploring their identities. However, brands tend to forget the existence of the community as soon as July rolls on. It makes us question, is this just another marketing gimmick?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is customary for Pride-themed merchandise to spike during June, a practice known as rainbow capitalism, is often criticised and compared to pinkwashing. Nevertheless, there is still tremendous value that can come from rocking rainbows during this time of the year. Like ‘empowerment campaigns’, several brands climb the trend wagon in Pride month, with no concern for the cause. Pride marketing is empathetic, where aiming ‘just for sales’ will misfire and attract more backlash from the audience and hurt the entity's image in the long term. Therefore, brands should not use Pride month to ramp up the sales but instead use their platform to show support and disperse awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, Burger King's Pride month initiative was very thoughtful and won many hearts. Their tagline stated, &quot;&lt;em&gt;The pride is on you. The parade is on us&lt;/em&gt;&quot;, along with their delivery vehicles transformed. The campaign persisted till July 5. This year, diverse brands showcased their support to the community beyond rainbow washing and making the most out of pride marketing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Popular brands like Fossil, Apple, Reebok and others often dedicate enormous resources during Pride month to LGBTQ+ non-profit organisations (among them,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thetrevorproject.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Trevor Project&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.glsen.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GLSEN&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;and different groups), which means you could be helping others gain access to valuable resources, too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To honour Pride month, Fossil launched its all-new limited-edition Pride collection to celebrate the spirit of love, equality and the very essence of individuality. The proceeds from this collection will benefit The Trevor Project — the world’s most significant suicide prevention and crisis intervention organisation for LGBTQ+ young adults.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of Apple, it has released two new Apple Watch Pride bands this year and a new Pride watch face for users. The brand also supports many LGBTQ+ advocacy organisations, including&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://encircletogether.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Encircle&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;(which offers safe spaces for LGBTQ+ youth, young adults and families), the&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://transequality.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Center for Transgender Equality&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;(committed to social justice advocacy for transgender humans), and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To add on, Reebok’s newest collection celebrating the LGBTQ+ community features a vibrant assortment of Pride-inspired footwear and apparel. The items were designed by Colorful Soles, the brand’s LGBTQ+ employee community, which also partnered with the legendary House of Ninja (spotlighted in the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reviewed.com/streaming/features/black-history-documentaries-stream-now&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;iconic documentary&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Paris is Burning&lt;/em&gt;). Moreover, Reebok is donating $75,000 to the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://srlp.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sylvia Rivera Law Project&lt;/a&gt;, which advocates for affirming access to social, health and legal services for persons of all gender identities and expressions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Into the bargain, loads of fashion and beauty brands create Pride-inspired products that not only help you look great but also feel good as they support organisations that empower and uplift LGBTQ+ communities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give some instances, the Gap Collective Pride collection includes T-shirts, hoodies, socks and more for all ages. The brand is donating $50,000 this season to the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.glaad.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD)&lt;/a&gt;, an LGBTQ media advocacy organization.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Levi's is flaunting the Pride collection &quot;All Pronouns. All Love&quot; by emphasising respect for people's pronouns. They have the inscribed phrase &quot;they/them, she/her, he/him, we&quot; on their collections, which is gender-neutral. It will be donating 100% of the profits to OutRight Action International.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NYX's limited-edition collection comprises a wide makeup range that will bring a colourful ultra-metallic sheen. It will also donate $100,000 to Pride efforts globally and contribute towards the LA LGBT Center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other brands are also making their Pride-themed offerings and donations a year-round initiative, including Happy Socks, donating 10% of the sales from its rainbow-coloured socks to InterPride throughout the year, and Pink, which has expanded its offerings with its gender-inclusive Pink for All collection that debuted earlier this year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next door, LEGO has launched a limited-edition&amp;nbsp;LGBTQ themed set. This is the first LGBTQ set with 11 monochromatic figures, each with an assigned colour and 346 pieces creating a rainbow cascade.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, TGI Fridays have introduced a decadent, delicious dessert. This dessert is six layers of rainbow-coloured vanilla cake piled high with vanilla icing and sprinkles and is available for home delivery and in-store locations. Part of the profits generated from the sales will be donated to support GLSEN&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many music platforms in India, like music streaming service Jio Saavan and Spotify, and music channel VH1 are also celebrating Pride Month.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike other brands, Skittles took a bold move of launching limited-edition&amp;nbsp;Skittles Pride Packs&amp;nbsp;that come in grey packaging rather than rainbow washing. Even the candies inside are grey with delicious strawberries, orange, grape, apple, and lemon. For every pack sold, $1 will be donated to GLAAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shira Kogan, Director of Corporate Development at The Trevor Project, said &lt;em&gt;&quot;We are thrilled to see so many companies and brands stepping up to support Pride this year.&quot;&lt;/em&gt; Well, it is true that brands have the power and platform to influence others. These brands can tell stories to empower the LGBTQ+ community through marketing campaigns or a separate product line. Together they can create a world where the LGBTQ+ community is championed, celebrated and protected.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is that consumers of Pride gear are becoming more aware and are making an effort to shop where proceeds will make the most significant impact, including shopping at small, queer-owned businesses. For example, consumers are taking note when companies only feature underrepresented groups during their respective history or heritage months, says Ali Fazal, Vice President of Marketing at influencer marketing platform&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://grin.co/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GRIN&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;&quot;(If) the only time they see LGBT people represented is during Pride Month, it's clear that what you're doing is not a long-term evolution for your company and your marketing.&quot;&lt;/em&gt; says Fazal.&lt;em&gt;&quot;You're just trying to capitalize upon the seasonality of that month.&quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let's be honest: Most major brands have not maintained a consistent enough relationship with LGBTQ+ communities to survive Pride month without some level of scrutiny. More often than not, ‘rainbow washing’ — that is, the act of deploying Pride-themed versions of their products and marketing it without substantially engaging queer communities — tends to be the minimal-effort route that multiple brands take and majority of consumers recognise these attempts as inauthentic almost immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it's never too late to start developing real bonds with LGBTQ+ consumers. One of the most effective ways to show support is through charitable efforts, and Pride offers brands ample opportunities to turn their specialised products into the support that resonates beyond June.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a recent analysis, queer consumers who tend to maintain higher median household incomes, are more likely than other marginalised groups to actively seek and patronise the companies that engage with their collective community in a sustained fashion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, some brands understand the lasting power of giving back. It is important to remember the message one leaves out there can help lay the foundation of change. We need to understand that equality is not a once-a-month fight, but year-round support is necessary — not just for Pride month, but all the social causes we rise for. Together we can create a world, which is fairer for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samakshi Garg</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Each year, in the summertime, Pride collections emerge like a swarm of vividly coloured locusts. They envelop every storefront and Instagram feed in June, promising solidarity for LGBTQ+ communities. In 2021, we are yet again observing the second virtual celebration of pride month. Numerous brands have leveraged pride marketing to increase visibility and lend support to others within the LGBTQ+ community who are still exploring their identities. However, brands tend to forget the existence of the community as soon as July rolls on. It makes us question, is this just another marketing gimmick? While it is customary for Pride-themed merchandise to spike during June, a practice known as rainbow capitalism, is often criticised and compared to pinkwashing. Nevertheless, there is still tremendous value that can come from rocking rainbows during this time of the year. Like ‘empowerment campaigns’, several brands climb the trend wagon in Pride month, with no concern for the cause. Pride marketing is empathetic, where aiming ‘just for sales’ will misfire and attract more backlash from the audience and hurt the entity's image in the long term. Therefore, brands should not use Pride month to ramp up the sales but instead use their platform to show support and disperse awareness. In 2020, Burger King's Pride month initiative was very thoughtful and won many hearts. Their tagline stated, &quot;The pride is on you. The parade is on us&quot;, along with their delivery vehicles transformed. The campaign persisted till July 5. This year, diverse brands showcased their support to the community beyond rainbow washing and making the most out of pride marketing.&amp;nbsp; Popular brands like Fossil, Apple, Reebok and others often dedicate enormous resources during Pride month to LGBTQ+ non-profit organisations (among them,&amp;nbsp;The Trevor Project,&amp;nbsp;GLSEN&amp;nbsp;and different groups), which means you could be helping others gain access to valuable resources, too.&amp;nbsp; To honour Pride month, Fossil launched its all-new limited-edition Pride collection to celebrate the spirit of love, equality and the very essence of individuality. The proceeds from this collection will benefit The Trevor Project — the world’s most significant suicide prevention and crisis intervention organisation for LGBTQ+ young adults.&amp;nbsp; In the case of Apple, it has released two new Apple Watch Pride bands this year and a new Pride watch face for users. The brand also supports many LGBTQ+ advocacy organisations, including&amp;nbsp;Encircle&amp;nbsp;(which offers safe spaces for LGBTQ+ youth, young adults and families), the&amp;nbsp;National Center for Transgender Equality&amp;nbsp;(committed to social justice advocacy for transgender humans), and others. To add on, Reebok’s newest collection celebrating the LGBTQ+ community features a vibrant assortment of Pride-inspired footwear and apparel. The items were designed by Colorful Soles, the brand’s LGBTQ+ employee community, which also partnered with the legendary House of Ninja (spotlighted in the&amp;nbsp;iconic documentary,&amp;nbsp;Paris is Burning). Moreover, Reebok is donating $75,000 to the&amp;nbsp;Sylvia Rivera Law Project, which advocates for affirming access to social, health and legal services for persons of all gender identities and expressions.&amp;nbsp; Into the bargain, loads of fashion and beauty brands create Pride-inspired products that not only help you look great but also feel good as they support organisations that empower and uplift LGBTQ+ communities.&amp;nbsp; To give some instances, the Gap Collective Pride collection includes T-shirts, hoodies, socks and more for all ages. The brand is donating $50,000 this season to the&amp;nbsp;Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD), an LGBTQ media advocacy organization.&amp;nbsp; Levi's is flaunting the Pride collection &quot;All Pronouns. All Love&quot; by emphasising respect for people's pronouns. They have the inscribed phrase &quot;they/them, she/her, he/him, we&quot; on their collections, which is gender-neutral. It will be donating 100% of the profits to OutRight Action International.&amp;nbsp; NYX's limited-edition collection comprises a wide makeup range that will bring a colourful ultra-metallic sheen. It will also donate $100,000 to Pride efforts globally and contribute towards the LA LGBT Center. Other brands are also making their Pride-themed offerings and donations a year-round initiative, including Happy Socks, donating 10% of the sales from its rainbow-coloured socks to InterPride throughout the year, and Pink, which has expanded its offerings with its gender-inclusive Pink for All collection that debuted earlier this year.&amp;nbsp; Next door, LEGO has launched a limited-edition&amp;nbsp;LGBTQ themed set. This is the first LGBTQ set with 11 monochromatic figures, each with an assigned colour and 346 pieces creating a rainbow cascade.&amp;nbsp; Meanwhile, TGI Fridays have introduced a decadent, delicious dessert. This dessert is six layers of rainbow-coloured vanilla cake piled high with vanilla icing and sprinkles and is available for home delivery and in-store locations. Part of the profits generated from the sales will be donated to support GLSEN.&amp;nbsp; Many music platforms in India, like music streaming service Jio Saavan and Spotify, and music channel VH1 are also celebrating Pride Month.&amp;nbsp; Unlike other brands, Skittles took a bold move of launching limited-edition&amp;nbsp;Skittles Pride Packs&amp;nbsp;that come in grey packaging rather than rainbow washing. Even the candies inside are grey with delicious strawberries, orange, grape, apple, and lemon. For every pack sold, $1 will be donated to GLAAD. Shira Kogan, Director of Corporate Development at The Trevor Project, said &quot;We are thrilled to see so many companies and brands stepping up to support Pride this year.&quot; Well, it is true that brands have the power and platform to influence others. These brands can tell stories to empower the LGBTQ+ community through marketing campaigns or a separate product line. Together they can create a world where the LGBTQ+ community is championed, celebrated and protected.&amp;nbsp; The result is that consumers of Pride gear are becoming more aware and are making an effort to shop where proceeds will make the most significant impact, including shopping at small, queer-owned businesses. For example, consumers are taking note when companies only feature underrepresented groups during their respective history or heritage months, says Ali Fazal, Vice President of Marketing at influencer marketing platform&amp;nbsp;GRIN. &quot;(If) the only time they see LGBT people represented is during Pride Month, it's clear that what you're doing is not a long-term evolution for your company and your marketing.&quot; says Fazal.&quot;You're just trying to capitalize upon the seasonality of that month.&quot; Now let's be honest: Most major brands have not maintained a consistent enough relationship with LGBTQ+ communities to survive Pride month without some level of scrutiny. More often than not, ‘rainbow washing’ — that is, the act of deploying Pride-themed versions of their products and marketing it without substantially engaging queer communities — tends to be the minimal-effort route that multiple brands take and majority of consumers recognise these attempts as inauthentic almost immediately. But it's never too late to start developing real bonds with LGBTQ+ consumers. One of the most effective ways to show support is through charitable efforts, and Pride offers brands ample opportunities to turn their specialised products into the support that resonates beyond June.&amp;nbsp; According to a recent analysis, queer consumers who tend to maintain higher median household incomes, are more likely than other marginalised groups to actively seek and patronise the companies that engage with their collective community in a sustained fashion. Fortunately, some brands understand the lasting power of giving back. It is important to remember the message one leaves out there can help lay the foundation of change. We need to understand that equality is not a once-a-month fight, but year-round support is necessary — not just for Pride month, but all the social causes we rise for. Together we can create a world, which is fairer for everyone.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Coach - The Success Story</title>
      <link href="/Coach-The-Success-Story" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coach - The Success Story" />
      <published>2021-06-16T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Coach-The-Success-Story</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Coach-The-Success-Story">&lt;p&gt;'Classic American Style', the style embodied by Coach, has defined its soul and essence for over 80 years now. In these 80 years, the brand transitioned from a small family business based in a New York loft to an international company with worldwide sales of $600 million in 2001. Today, Coach, Inc has carved a niche for itself as one of the leading modern luxury lifestyle brands providing various merchandise characterised by authenticity and distinctiveness that define its consumers' way of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1941, the company started with just six leather workers who produced small leather goods like wallets and billfolds. Five years later, Miles Cahn, a New Yorker and his wife joined the company. He saw that the leather used in baseball gloves became soft and supple with wear and abrasion. So he devised a way of processing the leather, which made it wear-and-tear resistant and long-lasting. At the same time, his wife started producing women's handbags with such innovative techniques that marked the brand's entry into manufacturing, designing and marketing of leather goods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From its inception, Coach adopted a business strategy of producing timeless and elegant pieces which would not be affected by the vagaries of fashion. As a result, its goods were identified with artistic craftsmanship and sophisticated designs rather than being fashionable. Despite staying away from fashion fads, what built the brand reputation and set it apart from its competitors was that it offered sturdy and functional handbags of supreme quality that could last for an average of 15 years.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, Coach provided lifetime repairs and replacement services for its products without any additional costs. This helped in its unique positioning in the luxury market as an 'accessible luxury brand'. Coach's products were known for their exquisite quality but were priced lower than other designer products. It attracted people from both the higher and middle end of the wealth spectrum by adopting a mid-premium pricing strategy. This strategy allowed the brand to maintain its exclusivity and, at the same time, kept its door open for further sales.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things were going well for the brand until the 1990's. Then, it encountered a bottleneck in development that restricted it from building a unique brand image when every brand was adopting aggressive advertising and promotional policies. This was also the era of ushering in new competitor brands like Michael Kors and Kate Spade, which completely transformed the market scene. Michael Kors had a similar brand position as Coach, but it found that affordable luxury was a rage in China. As a result, Kors diversified its product line and customised its products to suit the Chinese demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kate Spade targeted millennials by designing chic and contemporary accessories. However, Coach was not ready to handle such cut-throat competition, due to which it lost almost 30% of its market share. So Coach introduced its first non-leather product, silk scarves, to soften the blow to its earnings. However, this proved disastrous since the equestrian designs on the scarves looked like a cheaper version of the Hermes scarves. This left the company more miserable than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to plummeting sales, Coach had launched discount stores and factory outlet stores, which boosted its performance quickly, but did not address the real product issues that eventually diluted the brand image. This was at the beginning of 2008.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coach's 'affordable luxury' position, which elevated the brand from niche to powerhouse, was no longer influential because of the negative influence of the competitors and customers on the market environment. According to a survey taken in 2009, only 30% of the customers had a positive feeling for Coach. Consumers felt that it was no longer fashionable and that there were better alternatives available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the brand had lagged behind its competitors in the 'trendiness' dimension because it targeted older women who prioritise quality over fashion. As a result, the brand became regarded as a brand for the masses attracted to gaudy handbags. Coach was also responsible for the rising phenomenon of 'the death of the designer bags'. Since it kept its prices lower to attract a larger audience, nearly every rich woman had one of its bags which tarnished its exclusive image. For a luxury brand, if a product is not precious and scarce enough, there is no meaning in associating with the brand.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company carried on its operations in losses for a few years till it could continue no further.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2014, Victor Luis took the reins as CEO and hired the new creative head Stuart Vevers. They carried out a series of successful revolutions to revive the company and rejuvenate its image to rebuild a high-end brand and win customers' favour. He repositioned the brand as a smaller, healthier retailer, putting the onus on quality and not on mass-market quantity and rebranded Coach to be 'Modern Luxury' which meant that the brand was inclusive and more approachable.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luis allocated a significant chunk of the brand's budget on opening up new plush flagship stores in various fashion capitals and spruced up their store milieu to provide a better shopping experience. Stuart brought fresh blood to the organisation and revamped the brand's image by infusing traditional designs with his innovative ones which helped attract millennials. In addition, Coach diversified the product lines and started making ready-to-wear collections. Although clothing was a small part of Coach's revenue, its influence on the brand went far beyond the dollar terms, for it helped to develop the 'halo effect', that is, it helped to reshape the brand's aura, which gave a whole new lease of life to the entire product line.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 2015, the US had started evolving as a fan economy, and social media had gained tremendous popularity. The new generation of consumers loved to use social media to catch up with trends and follow the celebrities they loved. A survey in 2015 found that 33% of the consumers were lured by social media promotions to splurge on big brands.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Coach decided to resuscitate its online presence and hired Selena Gomez, the US pop singer, to represent the brand from 2016. She was the highest-paid celebrity on Instagram, and Coach took advantage of her social media power to appeal to the millennials. For example, when Coach announced the launch of a new handbag in collaboration with Selena, it sold out within a month. In 2017, Coach acquired Kate Spade to tap into a broader millennial-driven customer base and develop into a luxury lifestyle brand.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This acquisition pushed Coach in a better position to compete with Michael Kors. After four years of efforts, Coach has finally rebranded as a modern luxury brand thanks to the series of radical initiatives launched by Victor Luis and several incomparable products rebuilt by Stuart Vevers. By this time, Coach became the biggest story in the retail sector riding the handbag fascination. It helped propel sales into billions.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, Coach represents a unique combination of magic and logic, representing rich cultural heritage and a truly aspirational and distinctive American style. The brand maintains the highest standard for materials and artistry. Its labour is committed to carefully upholding the principles of quality and integrity that defines the company. The strategy of moving beyond tangible products to own a larger share of customers' minds has proved to be an excellent defence against the volatile market and consumers' changing needs. The brand seeks to establish long-term relationships with customers based on loyalty and satisfaction, which also helps in the automatic adoption of new products upon release.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The products are made from genuine leather and undergo strict research checking before being launched in the consumer market. Coach has a strong distribution network and has adopted both direct and indirect channels to distribute products. The company shares fashion runway videos via streaming platforms like YouTube to create a positive buzz.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brand believes in celebrity endorsements and advertises its products using Bohemian imagery in magazines and billboards.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coach has also adopted a promotional pricing strategy wherein it offers incentives, and on the arrival of new stock, the company puts the older stock for a clearance sale. It has an official website that handles sales and caters to customers' queries in more than 20 countries. However, their website does not have visualisation apps and suitable size guides. They need to keep it updated and try to list all their products on their online shop. Besides this, Coach actively engages in corporate social responsibility by supporting organisations that provide women's education.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coach should now focus on expansion, especially in emerging prosperous economies like Latin America, Japan and India. It needs to ship to more countries, especially those that do not levy consumer taxes on foreign online shopping. It has become a famous brand among men who are willing to spend liberal amounts on fashion products.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It needs to live up to their expectations and meet their demands. It should also improve the technological content of its products to prevent counterfeiting of its products. Apart from this, the brand should invest more in eye-catching and stimulating commercials and print advertisements. Coach needs to reinvigorate its brand image and keep up with new trends without losing the original touch.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhinav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">'Classic American Style', the style embodied by Coach, has defined its soul and essence for over 80 years now. In these 80 years, the brand transitioned from a small family business based in a New York loft to an international company with worldwide sales of $600 million in 2001. Today, Coach, Inc has carved a niche for itself as one of the leading modern luxury lifestyle brands providing various merchandise characterised by authenticity and distinctiveness that define its consumers' way of life. In 1941, the company started with just six leather workers who produced small leather goods like wallets and billfolds. Five years later, Miles Cahn, a New Yorker and his wife joined the company. He saw that the leather used in baseball gloves became soft and supple with wear and abrasion. So he devised a way of processing the leather, which made it wear-and-tear resistant and long-lasting. At the same time, his wife started producing women's handbags with such innovative techniques that marked the brand's entry into manufacturing, designing and marketing of leather goods. From its inception, Coach adopted a business strategy of producing timeless and elegant pieces which would not be affected by the vagaries of fashion. As a result, its goods were identified with artistic craftsmanship and sophisticated designs rather than being fashionable. Despite staying away from fashion fads, what built the brand reputation and set it apart from its competitors was that it offered sturdy and functional handbags of supreme quality that could last for an average of 15 years.&amp;nbsp; In addition, Coach provided lifetime repairs and replacement services for its products without any additional costs. This helped in its unique positioning in the luxury market as an 'accessible luxury brand'. Coach's products were known for their exquisite quality but were priced lower than other designer products. It attracted people from both the higher and middle end of the wealth spectrum by adopting a mid-premium pricing strategy. This strategy allowed the brand to maintain its exclusivity and, at the same time, kept its door open for further sales.&amp;nbsp; Things were going well for the brand until the 1990's. Then, it encountered a bottleneck in development that restricted it from building a unique brand image when every brand was adopting aggressive advertising and promotional policies. This was also the era of ushering in new competitor brands like Michael Kors and Kate Spade, which completely transformed the market scene. Michael Kors had a similar brand position as Coach, but it found that affordable luxury was a rage in China. As a result, Kors diversified its product line and customised its products to suit the Chinese demand. Kate Spade targeted millennials by designing chic and contemporary accessories. However, Coach was not ready to handle such cut-throat competition, due to which it lost almost 30% of its market share. So Coach introduced its first non-leather product, silk scarves, to soften the blow to its earnings. However, this proved disastrous since the equestrian designs on the scarves looked like a cheaper version of the Hermes scarves. This left the company more miserable than ever. Due to plummeting sales, Coach had launched discount stores and factory outlet stores, which boosted its performance quickly, but did not address the real product issues that eventually diluted the brand image. This was at the beginning of 2008.&amp;nbsp; Coach's 'affordable luxury' position, which elevated the brand from niche to powerhouse, was no longer influential because of the negative influence of the competitors and customers on the market environment. According to a survey taken in 2009, only 30% of the customers had a positive feeling for Coach. Consumers felt that it was no longer fashionable and that there were better alternatives available. Furthermore, the brand had lagged behind its competitors in the 'trendiness' dimension because it targeted older women who prioritise quality over fashion. As a result, the brand became regarded as a brand for the masses attracted to gaudy handbags. Coach was also responsible for the rising phenomenon of 'the death of the designer bags'. Since it kept its prices lower to attract a larger audience, nearly every rich woman had one of its bags which tarnished its exclusive image. For a luxury brand, if a product is not precious and scarce enough, there is no meaning in associating with the brand.&amp;nbsp; The company carried on its operations in losses for a few years till it could continue no further.&amp;nbsp; In 2014, Victor Luis took the reins as CEO and hired the new creative head Stuart Vevers. They carried out a series of successful revolutions to revive the company and rejuvenate its image to rebuild a high-end brand and win customers' favour. He repositioned the brand as a smaller, healthier retailer, putting the onus on quality and not on mass-market quantity and rebranded Coach to be 'Modern Luxury' which meant that the brand was inclusive and more approachable.&amp;nbsp; Luis allocated a significant chunk of the brand's budget on opening up new plush flagship stores in various fashion capitals and spruced up their store milieu to provide a better shopping experience. Stuart brought fresh blood to the organisation and revamped the brand's image by infusing traditional designs with his innovative ones which helped attract millennials. In addition, Coach diversified the product lines and started making ready-to-wear collections. Although clothing was a small part of Coach's revenue, its influence on the brand went far beyond the dollar terms, for it helped to develop the 'halo effect', that is, it helped to reshape the brand's aura, which gave a whole new lease of life to the entire product line.&amp;nbsp; By 2015, the US had started evolving as a fan economy, and social media had gained tremendous popularity. The new generation of consumers loved to use social media to catch up with trends and follow the celebrities they loved. A survey in 2015 found that 33% of the consumers were lured by social media promotions to splurge on big brands.&amp;nbsp; So Coach decided to resuscitate its online presence and hired Selena Gomez, the US pop singer, to represent the brand from 2016. She was the highest-paid celebrity on Instagram, and Coach took advantage of her social media power to appeal to the millennials. For example, when Coach announced the launch of a new handbag in collaboration with Selena, it sold out within a month. In 2017, Coach acquired Kate Spade to tap into a broader millennial-driven customer base and develop into a luxury lifestyle brand.&amp;nbsp; This acquisition pushed Coach in a better position to compete with Michael Kors. After four years of efforts, Coach has finally rebranded as a modern luxury brand thanks to the series of radical initiatives launched by Victor Luis and several incomparable products rebuilt by Stuart Vevers. By this time, Coach became the biggest story in the retail sector riding the handbag fascination. It helped propel sales into billions.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Today, Coach represents a unique combination of magic and logic, representing rich cultural heritage and a truly aspirational and distinctive American style. The brand maintains the highest standard for materials and artistry. Its labour is committed to carefully upholding the principles of quality and integrity that defines the company. The strategy of moving beyond tangible products to own a larger share of customers' minds has proved to be an excellent defence against the volatile market and consumers' changing needs. The brand seeks to establish long-term relationships with customers based on loyalty and satisfaction, which also helps in the automatic adoption of new products upon release.&amp;nbsp; The products are made from genuine leather and undergo strict research checking before being launched in the consumer market. Coach has a strong distribution network and has adopted both direct and indirect channels to distribute products. The company shares fashion runway videos via streaming platforms like YouTube to create a positive buzz.&amp;nbsp; The brand believes in celebrity endorsements and advertises its products using Bohemian imagery in magazines and billboards.&amp;nbsp; Coach has also adopted a promotional pricing strategy wherein it offers incentives, and on the arrival of new stock, the company puts the older stock for a clearance sale. It has an official website that handles sales and caters to customers' queries in more than 20 countries. However, their website does not have visualisation apps and suitable size guides. They need to keep it updated and try to list all their products on their online shop. Besides this, Coach actively engages in corporate social responsibility by supporting organisations that provide women's education.&amp;nbsp; Coach should now focus on expansion, especially in emerging prosperous economies like Latin America, Japan and India. It needs to ship to more countries, especially those that do not levy consumer taxes on foreign online shopping. It has become a famous brand among men who are willing to spend liberal amounts on fashion products.&amp;nbsp; It needs to live up to their expectations and meet their demands. It should also improve the technological content of its products to prevent counterfeiting of its products. Apart from this, the brand should invest more in eye-catching and stimulating commercials and print advertisements. Coach needs to reinvigorate its brand image and keep up with new trends without losing the original touch.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Decoding Cryptic Cryptos</title>
      <link href="/Decoding-Cryptic-Cryptos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Decoding Cryptic Cryptos" />
      <published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Decoding-Cryptic-Cryptos</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Decoding-Cryptic-Cryptos">&lt;p&gt;Cryptocurrencies have yet again gone through one of the many roller coaster rides in the past few months. They can synonymously be used for volatility – they are that highly erratic. In this article, we will try to decode the entire episode and present it to you from scratch.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin with, cryptocurrency is a digital asset or a form that is secured by cryptography. Cryptography refers to the process of converting legible information into an almost uncrackable code. The first-ever cryptocurrency, Bitcoin, was introduced in 2009 by a mysterious individual (or a group of people) with the pseudonym Satoshi Nakamoto. The creator's objective was to eliminate the intermediaries (eg, banks) in the backdrop of the 2008 debacle, also known as The Great Recession. Therefore, it did not want any third party's involvement, which raises the transaction cost (by way of transaction fees) and risk via exposure to mortgage lending. Additionally, the value of fiat currency is dependent on money circulation in the economy, which can fluctuate depending on the monetary authority. These interventions, per se, are not wrong; however, the component of uncertainty and dependence on third-party necessitated the absence of intermediaries in the eyes of Nakamoto.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next big question arises: if no intermediary involvement is present, then who develops and verifies these digital currencies? Through the process of mining, these digital coins are created and verified by way of blockchain networks. Simply put, blockchains are digital ledgers where the transactional data are stored in an encrypted, decentralised format such that no person can own, control or manipulate the particulars.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mining is a laborious procedure involving solving complex computational puzzles. Nonetheless, it still appeals to various individuals (known as miners) because of its reward in terms of ownership of the new crypto tokens. Initially, mining could be done with basic devices. When crypto participants and engagement increased, the activity became further complicated. It can no longer be solved by basic computers and instead requires supercomputers. Cryptos have a fixed supply; hence, unlike government-backed fiat money, their supply cannot go up suddenly. The disadvantageous element of this process is the carbon footprint it accounts for.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A University of Cambridge study has stated that mining of the largest cryptocurrency by market capitalisation – Bitcoins, consumes more than 120 Terawatt Hours (Twh) each year, using more electricity annually than countries like Malaysia or Sweden. Furthermore, studies claim that mining should follow the adoption rate of other broadly adopted technologies, and Bitcoin could alone produce enough carbon dioxide emissions to push global warming above 2°C within less than three decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It goes without saying that other much smaller cryptocurrencies have a far lower energy footprint due to their much smaller scale. However, if scaled up, they are equally carbon-heavy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, proponents of cryptos say that mining is increasingly being done with electricity generated from renewable sources. Nevertheless, environmentalists continue to decry mining since miners will keep up consuming coal (it is the cheapest source) for electricity generation, thus giving us its ecological aftermath.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from environment lovers, government and monetary officials view these digital assets as potential threats due to their operation outside government control, which can potentially overturn an economy if not supervised.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several risks are associated with cryptocurrencies. Firstly, a high degree of market manipulation due to the lack of backing by any tangible assets questions their intrinsic value, marking their price discovery in uncharted territory.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, asymmetrical information raises the likelihood of money laundering, hacking, cyber extortion, and more, damaging consumer protection and systemic stability.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some risks are familiar with other financial products; however, crypto's information opacity disrupts the adjustment. For example, as per a &lt;em&gt;Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Journal &lt;/em&gt;finding, Hamas, the Palestinian militant group, saw a spike in Bitcoin donations during the violence between Israel and Palestine in mid-May. Hamas, which rules the Gaza Strip, is designated as a terrorist entity by the US, the European Union (EU) and other Western nations and has sanctions imposed upon it. Nonetheless, its funding remained unaffected due to anonymous digital transactions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In another such instance, according to the analytics firm Elliptic, DarkSide, a hacking group, shut down a critical US oil pipeline in May and collected over $90 million in hard-to-trace Bitcoin from 47 victims. That hack ended after Colonial Pipeline paid nearly $5 million as ransom to regain control of systems needed to supply gasoline to the Eastern US.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these complications, cryptocurrencies are seeing huge public acceptance. There are multiple reasons for broader acceptance of these digital assets, owing to their higher yields on the back of low-interest rates, hedging against inflation, or their growing acceptance by corporate leaders. For example, digital assets are pretty popular in Argentina as a way for locals to hedge against cyclical economic crises, including repeat currency devaluations, defaults and hyperinflation, with the recent imposition of foreign exchange controls and now a three-year recession made worse by the pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The massive monthly rally of cryptos in early 2021 and the big sell-off in mid-May, as per market observers, was caused by Elon Musk's tweets. The American electric car maker, Tesla, announced in its February, 2021 filing to the market regulator that it had bought $1.5 billion worth of Bitcoins and would soon start accepting the digital currency for payments. A few weeks back, its CEO Musk hinted as much by adding '#bitcoin' to his Twitter bio. Followers and the general public went into a frenzy, and the market price surged. However, the plunge in crypto prices in mid-May was sparked when the Tesla chief tweeted the company’s u-turn on Bitcoin acceptance and criticised it for the environmental hazard posed by aggressive power mining.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk has a track record of influencing the market price of asset classes. Back in 2018, Musk and Tesla, each paid $20 million to the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) to settle fraud charges for tweeting about a potential buyout of the car-making company, leading to a spike in share prices followed by a fall when the buyout could not be negotiated. Many regulators are worried about the concentration of social power among a few individuals and organisations to influence prices of various asset classes, which can hamper price stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another key reason for slumping prices of crypto in the early morning of May 19 in Wall Street was attributed to China, after the country barred its financial institutions from dealing in cryptocurrencies.&amp;nbsp;China accounts for more than 70% of all bitcoin mining in the world. Due to its cheap energy, the country's Inner Mongolia Autonomous region accounts for around 8% globally, a more significant share than the US. The move is part of the government's target of achieving carbon neutrality by 2060.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China had such a ban in 2017, but the 2021 ban has a broader scope. The ban prohibits institutions from accepting or settling payments in crypto or providing exchange services to convert crypto to fiat currencies, including the Chinese yuan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In India, are cryptocurrency banned? No, they are not 100% legal, so it is all right for us to trade in crypto exchanges like WazirX or CoinDCX. However, they are not legal tender of money, so you cannot purchase any goods or services and make payments in these digitised currencies. Back in 2018, the Indian central bank had issued a circular to refrain financial institutions from having any relation with any crypto assets or crypto organisations; however, the ban was lifted by an Indian Supreme Court decision in the very same year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court in March 2020 said the central bank could notify cryptocurrencies as ‘other similar instruments’ under the definition of the term 'currency' in the Indian Foreign Exchange Management Act (FEMA). Therefore, the trading in crypto can fall within the purview of the central bank. In May 2021, the central bank came out with a circular reiterating its commitment to upholding the Court's decision. However, it did ask institutions and other entities to carry out due diligence processes in line with customer protection and economic stability as per the FEMA Act. The Indian Finance Minister in her 2021-22 budget hinted that the government would take a ‘calibrated approach’ towards digital assets. Hence, some regulation or oversight by the government is expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will get to know whether these computerised assets are the future of payments in years to come. However, administrations need to acknowledge the public involvement and bridge the loopholes these instruments carry with themselves as soon as possible.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Cryptocurrencies have yet again gone through one of the many roller coaster rides in the past few months. They can synonymously be used for volatility – they are that highly erratic. In this article, we will try to decode the entire episode and present it to you from scratch.&amp;nbsp; To begin with, cryptocurrency is a digital asset or a form that is secured by cryptography. Cryptography refers to the process of converting legible information into an almost uncrackable code. The first-ever cryptocurrency, Bitcoin, was introduced in 2009 by a mysterious individual (or a group of people) with the pseudonym Satoshi Nakamoto. The creator's objective was to eliminate the intermediaries (eg, banks) in the backdrop of the 2008 debacle, also known as The Great Recession. Therefore, it did not want any third party's involvement, which raises the transaction cost (by way of transaction fees) and risk via exposure to mortgage lending. Additionally, the value of fiat currency is dependent on money circulation in the economy, which can fluctuate depending on the monetary authority. These interventions, per se, are not wrong; however, the component of uncertainty and dependence on third-party necessitated the absence of intermediaries in the eyes of Nakamoto.&amp;nbsp; The next big question arises: if no intermediary involvement is present, then who develops and verifies these digital currencies? Through the process of mining, these digital coins are created and verified by way of blockchain networks. Simply put, blockchains are digital ledgers where the transactional data are stored in an encrypted, decentralised format such that no person can own, control or manipulate the particulars.&amp;nbsp; Mining is a laborious procedure involving solving complex computational puzzles. Nonetheless, it still appeals to various individuals (known as miners) because of its reward in terms of ownership of the new crypto tokens. Initially, mining could be done with basic devices. When crypto participants and engagement increased, the activity became further complicated. It can no longer be solved by basic computers and instead requires supercomputers. Cryptos have a fixed supply; hence, unlike government-backed fiat money, their supply cannot go up suddenly. The disadvantageous element of this process is the carbon footprint it accounts for.&amp;nbsp; A University of Cambridge study has stated that mining of the largest cryptocurrency by market capitalisation – Bitcoins, consumes more than 120 Terawatt Hours (Twh) each year, using more electricity annually than countries like Malaysia or Sweden. Furthermore, studies claim that mining should follow the adoption rate of other broadly adopted technologies, and Bitcoin could alone produce enough carbon dioxide emissions to push global warming above 2°C within less than three decades. It goes without saying that other much smaller cryptocurrencies have a far lower energy footprint due to their much smaller scale. However, if scaled up, they are equally carbon-heavy.&amp;nbsp; However, proponents of cryptos say that mining is increasingly being done with electricity generated from renewable sources. Nevertheless, environmentalists continue to decry mining since miners will keep up consuming coal (it is the cheapest source) for electricity generation, thus giving us its ecological aftermath.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Apart from environment lovers, government and monetary officials view these digital assets as potential threats due to their operation outside government control, which can potentially overturn an economy if not supervised.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Several risks are associated with cryptocurrencies. Firstly, a high degree of market manipulation due to the lack of backing by any tangible assets questions their intrinsic value, marking their price discovery in uncharted territory.&amp;nbsp; Secondly, asymmetrical information raises the likelihood of money laundering, hacking, cyber extortion, and more, damaging consumer protection and systemic stability.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Some risks are familiar with other financial products; however, crypto's information opacity disrupts the adjustment. For example, as per a Wall Street Journal finding, Hamas, the Palestinian militant group, saw a spike in Bitcoin donations during the violence between Israel and Palestine in mid-May. Hamas, which rules the Gaza Strip, is designated as a terrorist entity by the US, the European Union (EU) and other Western nations and has sanctions imposed upon it. Nonetheless, its funding remained unaffected due to anonymous digital transactions.&amp;nbsp; In another such instance, according to the analytics firm Elliptic, DarkSide, a hacking group, shut down a critical US oil pipeline in May and collected over $90 million in hard-to-trace Bitcoin from 47 victims. That hack ended after Colonial Pipeline paid nearly $5 million as ransom to regain control of systems needed to supply gasoline to the Eastern US.&amp;nbsp; Despite these complications, cryptocurrencies are seeing huge public acceptance. There are multiple reasons for broader acceptance of these digital assets, owing to their higher yields on the back of low-interest rates, hedging against inflation, or their growing acceptance by corporate leaders. For example, digital assets are pretty popular in Argentina as a way for locals to hedge against cyclical economic crises, including repeat currency devaluations, defaults and hyperinflation, with the recent imposition of foreign exchange controls and now a three-year recession made worse by the pandemic.&amp;nbsp; The massive monthly rally of cryptos in early 2021 and the big sell-off in mid-May, as per market observers, was caused by Elon Musk's tweets. The American electric car maker, Tesla, announced in its February, 2021 filing to the market regulator that it had bought $1.5 billion worth of Bitcoins and would soon start accepting the digital currency for payments. A few weeks back, its CEO Musk hinted as much by adding '#bitcoin' to his Twitter bio. Followers and the general public went into a frenzy, and the market price surged. However, the plunge in crypto prices in mid-May was sparked when the Tesla chief tweeted the company’s u-turn on Bitcoin acceptance and criticised it for the environmental hazard posed by aggressive power mining.&amp;nbsp; Elon Musk has a track record of influencing the market price of asset classes. Back in 2018, Musk and Tesla, each paid $20 million to the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) to settle fraud charges for tweeting about a potential buyout of the car-making company, leading to a spike in share prices followed by a fall when the buyout could not be negotiated. Many regulators are worried about the concentration of social power among a few individuals and organisations to influence prices of various asset classes, which can hamper price stability. Another key reason for slumping prices of crypto in the early morning of May 19 in Wall Street was attributed to China, after the country barred its financial institutions from dealing in cryptocurrencies.&amp;nbsp;China accounts for more than 70% of all bitcoin mining in the world. Due to its cheap energy, the country's Inner Mongolia Autonomous region accounts for around 8% globally, a more significant share than the US. The move is part of the government's target of achieving carbon neutrality by 2060. China had such a ban in 2017, but the 2021 ban has a broader scope. The ban prohibits institutions from accepting or settling payments in crypto or providing exchange services to convert crypto to fiat currencies, including the Chinese yuan.&amp;nbsp; In India, are cryptocurrency banned? No, they are not 100% legal, so it is all right for us to trade in crypto exchanges like WazirX or CoinDCX. However, they are not legal tender of money, so you cannot purchase any goods or services and make payments in these digitised currencies. Back in 2018, the Indian central bank had issued a circular to refrain financial institutions from having any relation with any crypto assets or crypto organisations; however, the ban was lifted by an Indian Supreme Court decision in the very same year. The Supreme Court in March 2020 said the central bank could notify cryptocurrencies as ‘other similar instruments’ under the definition of the term 'currency' in the Indian Foreign Exchange Management Act (FEMA). Therefore, the trading in crypto can fall within the purview of the central bank. In May 2021, the central bank came out with a circular reiterating its commitment to upholding the Court's decision. However, it did ask institutions and other entities to carry out due diligence processes in line with customer protection and economic stability as per the FEMA Act. The Indian Finance Minister in her 2021-22 budget hinted that the government would take a ‘calibrated approach’ towards digital assets. Hence, some regulation or oversight by the government is expected. We will get to know whether these computerised assets are the future of payments in years to come. However, administrations need to acknowledge the public involvement and bridge the loopholes these instruments carry with themselves as soon as possible.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Unlimited Vacation: A Relief or A Stressor?</title>
      <link href="/Unlimited-Vacation-A-Relief-or-A-Stressor" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unlimited Vacation: A Relief or A Stressor?" />
      <published>2021-06-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Unlimited-Vacation-A-Relief-or-A-Stressor</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Unlimited-Vacation-A-Relief-or-A-Stressor">&lt;p&gt;Last year around March, most of the countries went into a lockdown. Everything, including education and work, shifted to an online mode and the phrase 'work from home' (WFH) became popular.&amp;nbsp; It felt like a relief at first, as working from home in the comfort of pyjamas seemed like a dream come true. After a few months, the internet got flooded with articles claiming how WFH increases stress among young adults as the boundaries between professional and personal lives get blurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meetings and zoom calls picked up the pace and continued even after the office hours. The nine-to-five rule was discarded by this new normal of working, which demanded people work round the clock. Work-life balance seemed like a distant reality as both were accessible throughout the day. All these factors acted as stressors for the working adults. Vacation and leaves were not the best options as everyone was stuck at home with no other place to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many employees might have thought about the 'No-Vacation Policy' followed by many organisations during these times. The policy was first initiated by Netflix several years ago. It promotes unlimited vacation for its employees. There won't be any check on the number of days a person has taken off in a year. In the beginning, it was seen as a 'controversial policy' which won't stay in place for long. People argued in favour of as well as against the policy. Several diverse viewpoints came forward, but none of them could prove themselves as the absolute right. Even after all this time, Netflix has continued with the policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emerging startups and other companies have also started to follow the 'No Vacation Policy'. In the US, 1% of all the companies have abandoned the existing vacation and leave policies. Employees are trusted to complete their work and tasks at scheduled times and given the freedom to take leaves and go for holidays at their convenience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The critics of the policy claim that 'no rules and regulations' might not work in the firm's best interests. They believe that the employees will take advantage of it and not turn up for important meetings or meet deadlines. Thus, it will impact the output and efficiency of any company in a negative manner. Human behaviour is unpredictable and varies from person to person. Not all employees will behave similarly. Some might avail themselves of working while being on vacation while others might never take a holiday because they do not want others to think they work less!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advocates of the policy have given various arguments in its defence. They believe that the foundation of any such approach is based on mutual trust between the employees and the employer. With freedom comes responsibility! Every employee will be responsible for fulfilling their work on time and keeping other members in the loop with their vacation plans. Team leaders will have the responsibility to set examples for their employees to maintain a perfect work-life balance. They also believe that the existing holiday calendar doesn't serve all employees. Not every employee in Netflix celebrates Christmas or Hanukkah, thus giving them the freedom to take off is justified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the US, 35% of the workforce is millennials. Their way of doing things and perceiving the world is way too different from the previous generation. They don't want to prioritise work at the cost of personal life. They want a flexible work-life that allows them to live and enjoy as per their convenience. They believe that there's no point in working hard if one does not have enough time to enjoy and relax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from this, the millennials have a strong opinion on equality among the genders. Demand for paternity leaves has been a priority for the employees in the past few years. The no vacation policy works in favour of the millennial way of thinking. It allows them to maintain a work-life balance that suits their needs. Working parents now have the liberty to spend more time with their kids and family. The concept of period leave does not come up in these organisations because one has the freedom to take an off whenever they want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hustle culture has increased productivity but at the cost of mental health. Young adults suffer from anxiety, stress and even depression because of the overly competitive atmosphere at the workplace. Half of Millennials, along with 75% of Gen-Zers, have left a job for mental health reasons. WHO (World Health Organisation) has classified 'burnout' as an occupational phenomenon. The race to be better and more productive never ends. People end up working extra to achieve the next target or deadline. Leisure and relaxation are not encouraged in hustle culture. It is believed that working all the time without breaks is entirely normal and every individual should aspire to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With increased awareness of mental health, companies are taking measures to reduce the burden on the employees. In some ways, the no vacation policy will lead to reduced stress. The reason being, it allows people to work at their own pace. Employees have the liberty to take leaves whenever they are stressed. They can rejuvenate themselves and get back to work at their convenience. This helps increase efficiency as employees work with a fresh and relaxed mind. Each individual has a different way to cope with stress, and thus the policy gives them the freedom to choose what they want to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than this, there are other aspects as well which make this policy favourable for all! New startups can recruit people from far off cities. The approach makes it possible for these people to work from wherever they are. These companies are giving more weightage to the amount and quality of work rather than the place and time at which they are done. This also encourages diversity in the workplace, as people from different cities join and work in one team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An unlimited vacation policy might allow people to work at their own pace and in the comfort of their own home. It could also help them to think better, which would reflect in the quality of work. Not everyone will agree, but then every human behaves and perceives differently! This policy tries to accommodate all the employees under one frame. It gives freedom but not at the cost of work. Work has to be prioritised, but the time and place should depend on the employee and his preferences. After all, it harms no one to relax a bit and sing, &quot;&lt;em&gt;A-a-aye, I'm on vacation, every single day 'cause I love my occupation!&lt;/em&gt;&quot;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Last year around March, most of the countries went into a lockdown. Everything, including education and work, shifted to an online mode and the phrase 'work from home' (WFH) became popular.&amp;nbsp; It felt like a relief at first, as working from home in the comfort of pyjamas seemed like a dream come true. After a few months, the internet got flooded with articles claiming how WFH increases stress among young adults as the boundaries between professional and personal lives get blurred. Meetings and zoom calls picked up the pace and continued even after the office hours. The nine-to-five rule was discarded by this new normal of working, which demanded people work round the clock. Work-life balance seemed like a distant reality as both were accessible throughout the day. All these factors acted as stressors for the working adults. Vacation and leaves were not the best options as everyone was stuck at home with no other place to go. Many employees might have thought about the 'No-Vacation Policy' followed by many organisations during these times. The policy was first initiated by Netflix several years ago. It promotes unlimited vacation for its employees. There won't be any check on the number of days a person has taken off in a year. In the beginning, it was seen as a 'controversial policy' which won't stay in place for long. People argued in favour of as well as against the policy. Several diverse viewpoints came forward, but none of them could prove themselves as the absolute right. Even after all this time, Netflix has continued with the policy. Emerging startups and other companies have also started to follow the 'No Vacation Policy'. In the US, 1% of all the companies have abandoned the existing vacation and leave policies. Employees are trusted to complete their work and tasks at scheduled times and given the freedom to take leaves and go for holidays at their convenience. The critics of the policy claim that 'no rules and regulations' might not work in the firm's best interests. They believe that the employees will take advantage of it and not turn up for important meetings or meet deadlines. Thus, it will impact the output and efficiency of any company in a negative manner. Human behaviour is unpredictable and varies from person to person. Not all employees will behave similarly. Some might avail themselves of working while being on vacation while others might never take a holiday because they do not want others to think they work less! The advocates of the policy have given various arguments in its defence. They believe that the foundation of any such approach is based on mutual trust between the employees and the employer. With freedom comes responsibility! Every employee will be responsible for fulfilling their work on time and keeping other members in the loop with their vacation plans. Team leaders will have the responsibility to set examples for their employees to maintain a perfect work-life balance. They also believe that the existing holiday calendar doesn't serve all employees. Not every employee in Netflix celebrates Christmas or Hanukkah, thus giving them the freedom to take off is justified. In the US, 35% of the workforce is millennials. Their way of doing things and perceiving the world is way too different from the previous generation. They don't want to prioritise work at the cost of personal life. They want a flexible work-life that allows them to live and enjoy as per their convenience. They believe that there's no point in working hard if one does not have enough time to enjoy and relax. Apart from this, the millennials have a strong opinion on equality among the genders. Demand for paternity leaves has been a priority for the employees in the past few years. The no vacation policy works in favour of the millennial way of thinking. It allows them to maintain a work-life balance that suits their needs. Working parents now have the liberty to spend more time with their kids and family. The concept of period leave does not come up in these organisations because one has the freedom to take an off whenever they want. The hustle culture has increased productivity but at the cost of mental health. Young adults suffer from anxiety, stress and even depression because of the overly competitive atmosphere at the workplace. Half of Millennials, along with 75% of Gen-Zers, have left a job for mental health reasons. WHO (World Health Organisation) has classified 'burnout' as an occupational phenomenon. The race to be better and more productive never ends. People end up working extra to achieve the next target or deadline. Leisure and relaxation are not encouraged in hustle culture. It is believed that working all the time without breaks is entirely normal and every individual should aspire to do that. With increased awareness of mental health, companies are taking measures to reduce the burden on the employees. In some ways, the no vacation policy will lead to reduced stress. The reason being, it allows people to work at their own pace. Employees have the liberty to take leaves whenever they are stressed. They can rejuvenate themselves and get back to work at their convenience. This helps increase efficiency as employees work with a fresh and relaxed mind. Each individual has a different way to cope with stress, and thus the policy gives them the freedom to choose what they want to do. Other than this, there are other aspects as well which make this policy favourable for all! New startups can recruit people from far off cities. The approach makes it possible for these people to work from wherever they are. These companies are giving more weightage to the amount and quality of work rather than the place and time at which they are done. This also encourages diversity in the workplace, as people from different cities join and work in one team. An unlimited vacation policy might allow people to work at their own pace and in the comfort of their own home. It could also help them to think better, which would reflect in the quality of work. Not everyone will agree, but then every human behaves and perceives differently! This policy tries to accommodate all the employees under one frame. It gives freedom but not at the cost of work. Work has to be prioritised, but the time and place should depend on the employee and his preferences. After all, it harms no one to relax a bit and sing, &quot;A-a-aye, I'm on vacation, every single day 'cause I love my occupation!&quot;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Tyranny of Trends</title>
      <link href="/The-Tyranny-of-Trends" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Tyranny of Trends" />
      <published>2021-06-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Tyranny-of-Trends</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Tyranny-of-Trends">&lt;p&gt;Where does your clothing go when it's not needed anymore?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every second, a truck full of clothes is burned or dumped in a landfill. Every year, 92 million tonnes of fast fashion items are thrown away. Every year, 79 trillion litres of water is consumed by the fashion industry. Consequently, every year, more than $500 billion of value is lost due to clothing underutilisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were just a few of the many facts illustrating the case of ‘TYRANNY OF TRENDS’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With new trends taking over the market everyday, fast fashion is blooming like never before, leading to excessive carbon emissions, imprudent waste generation, giving birth to a new water crisis and to top it all, the lack of recycling is worsening the existing situation of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is imperative for the world to know that it takes more than just a piece of cloth and a few designers to design the trendsetting high-on-bling clothes that influencers wear, the head-turning long trails that brides want to wear or the gorgeous Italian-cut tuxedos that men wish to wear. The essence of sustainability lies in finding plausible alternatives to the existing resources being used because soon there will be a time when we won’t be left with any. It’s high time that we buckle up and start working in the direction to find new resources in order to keep the existing ones available for generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we wrap our heads around finding implementable solutions to the problem of fast fashion, let’s get into the nitty gritties of the concept of fast fashion. As a consequence of the fickle trends, which seem to change while you are reading this article, there exists a never ending demand for affordable, high-in-fashion garments to fulfil the quest of the masses to be in-trend. Which in turn compels and gives fashion brands and garment manufacturers a new avenue to mint money by producing cheap, in-trend fashion to keep up with the demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast fashion is a by-product of trends, so let's take a look at how this frenzy around trends is created? Saying that trends come and go like seasons would be wrong in this day and age as these trends are way more volatile to be able to stay for a full season. The real question is how are these trends set in the first place, compelling people to be in trend all the time. The following are a few ways in which trends are introduced to the world:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Runway Trends - Many-a-times certain runway looks created by designers catch the eyes of people and the next thing we know is every other brand starts incorporating those elements in their collection to be able to fill their pockets by pushing trends and fast fashion forward.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Celebrities - Trends are fuelled by celebrities the minute they are spotted wearing something which no one has seen before. People who idolise celebrities are always on a hunt for similar pieces eventually paving a way for a new trend to enter.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Social media and influencers -&amp;nbsp; The impact social media has on one’s life is immense so much so that everyone wants to follow and replicate the well-fabricated lives portrayed by influencers on their well-curated handles. To top it all, designers and brands approach influencers just as they approach celebrities to make new trends enter the market.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main problem which fast fashion brings with itself is the problem of disposal. Once a piece of clothing goes out of trend, both the consumers and the fashion labels do not think twice before dumping huge heaps of clothes which no longer continues to quench their thirst for trends so much so that every second, enough clothes&amp;nbsp;to fill a garbage truck full are either burned or sent to a landfill. Extortion of environmental resources, excessive waste generation, carbon emissions are all consequences of a choice that we have opted for, a choice to simply wear clothes for a shorter span of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the aforementioned heinous consequences of fast fashion pose one question to mankind, should we stop buying clothes at all? The answer is NO! You can still stand out and manage to be a trendsetter just by being a little mindful of your actions and choices.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most efficient way of tackling the problem at hand is by adopting sustainable fashion in order to achieve a circular fashion economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circular fashion economy proposes a progressive system of circulating a piece of clothing in the economy till the time its maximum value gets exhausted and the cycle is completed by safely disposing off the no-longer-in-use piece back to the environment.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sustainability is a two-way stream, brands and consumers are the two main players who can pave the way for circular and sustainable fashion. Before looking at how long is the road ahead, let’s see how far we have come on this long journey of achieving sustainability in its true sense. On the manufacturer’s side we have brands like H&amp;amp;M, which is now planning to deviate from the well-trodden path of fast fashion to reduce their environmental footprint by introducing sustainable collections made of organic cotton and recycled polyester.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a brand which has now stepped up its game in circular fashion by accepting and recycling unwanted garments from customers, H&amp;amp;M has set a benchmark for brands in the similar line. Levi’s, on the other hand, has been trying to reduce the notorious amounts of water required to make a pair of jeans by 96% which is a huge step towards making judicial use of existing resources. Like H&amp;amp;M and Levi’s there are many more brands which are working in the same direction but there is still a lot to be done. On the other hand, consumers of fashion can adopt the following steps with a motive to convert their vision for the fashion industry into reality:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Keep and wear the clothes for a longer span of time.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Think twice before dumping clothes which no longer please you. Instead, upcycle, alter, repair or donate them.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Buy sustainable fashion, go for upcycled, thrifted pieces.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bigger question is, can sustainability and profitability ever go hand-in-hand? It’s the demand which can make or break a brand’s fate. With more and more consumers becoming environmentally conscious, the demand for sustainable fashion has hiked up over the course of the years, which has led to brands supplying more and more sustainable garments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aware and conscious customers, especially Gen Z and millennials are ready to buy sustainable clothing even if they have to shell out more money for it, which makes it profitable for brands to go sustainable. And the ones whose pockets are holding them back from supporting the cause, they tend to take another route by turning to thrift stores which are sustainable and pocket friendly too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These small measures are just a few steps on the ladder towards achieving our goal of a sustainable and circular fashion economy which is all about covering one full circle from growing, designing, wearing, thrifting to finally passing the cloth to the biosphere by safely composting it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Agrawal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Where does your clothing go when it's not needed anymore? Every second, a truck full of clothes is burned or dumped in a landfill. Every year, 92 million tonnes of fast fashion items are thrown away. Every year, 79 trillion litres of water is consumed by the fashion industry. Consequently, every year, more than $500 billion of value is lost due to clothing underutilisation. These were just a few of the many facts illustrating the case of ‘TYRANNY OF TRENDS’. With new trends taking over the market everyday, fast fashion is blooming like never before, leading to excessive carbon emissions, imprudent waste generation, giving birth to a new water crisis and to top it all, the lack of recycling is worsening the existing situation of climate change. It is imperative for the world to know that it takes more than just a piece of cloth and a few designers to design the trendsetting high-on-bling clothes that influencers wear, the head-turning long trails that brides want to wear or the gorgeous Italian-cut tuxedos that men wish to wear. The essence of sustainability lies in finding plausible alternatives to the existing resources being used because soon there will be a time when we won’t be left with any. It’s high time that we buckle up and start working in the direction to find new resources in order to keep the existing ones available for generations to come. Before we wrap our heads around finding implementable solutions to the problem of fast fashion, let’s get into the nitty gritties of the concept of fast fashion. As a consequence of the fickle trends, which seem to change while you are reading this article, there exists a never ending demand for affordable, high-in-fashion garments to fulfil the quest of the masses to be in-trend. Which in turn compels and gives fashion brands and garment manufacturers a new avenue to mint money by producing cheap, in-trend fashion to keep up with the demand. Fast fashion is a by-product of trends, so let's take a look at how this frenzy around trends is created? Saying that trends come and go like seasons would be wrong in this day and age as these trends are way more volatile to be able to stay for a full season. The real question is how are these trends set in the first place, compelling people to be in trend all the time. The following are a few ways in which trends are introduced to the world: Runway Trends - Many-a-times certain runway looks created by designers catch the eyes of people and the next thing we know is every other brand starts incorporating those elements in their collection to be able to fill their pockets by pushing trends and fast fashion forward. Celebrities - Trends are fuelled by celebrities the minute they are spotted wearing something which no one has seen before. People who idolise celebrities are always on a hunt for similar pieces eventually paving a way for a new trend to enter.&amp;nbsp; Social media and influencers -&amp;nbsp; The impact social media has on one’s life is immense so much so that everyone wants to follow and replicate the well-fabricated lives portrayed by influencers on their well-curated handles. To top it all, designers and brands approach influencers just as they approach celebrities to make new trends enter the market. The main problem which fast fashion brings with itself is the problem of disposal. Once a piece of clothing goes out of trend, both the consumers and the fashion labels do not think twice before dumping huge heaps of clothes which no longer continues to quench their thirst for trends so much so that every second, enough clothes&amp;nbsp;to fill a garbage truck full are either burned or sent to a landfill. Extortion of environmental resources, excessive waste generation, carbon emissions are all consequences of a choice that we have opted for, a choice to simply wear clothes for a shorter span of time. All the aforementioned heinous consequences of fast fashion pose one question to mankind, should we stop buying clothes at all? The answer is NO! You can still stand out and manage to be a trendsetter just by being a little mindful of your actions and choices.&amp;nbsp; The most efficient way of tackling the problem at hand is by adopting sustainable fashion in order to achieve a circular fashion economy.&amp;nbsp; Circular fashion economy proposes a progressive system of circulating a piece of clothing in the economy till the time its maximum value gets exhausted and the cycle is completed by safely disposing off the no-longer-in-use piece back to the environment.&amp;nbsp; Sustainability is a two-way stream, brands and consumers are the two main players who can pave the way for circular and sustainable fashion. Before looking at how long is the road ahead, let’s see how far we have come on this long journey of achieving sustainability in its true sense. On the manufacturer’s side we have brands like H&amp;amp;M, which is now planning to deviate from the well-trodden path of fast fashion to reduce their environmental footprint by introducing sustainable collections made of organic cotton and recycled polyester.&amp;nbsp; As a brand which has now stepped up its game in circular fashion by accepting and recycling unwanted garments from customers, H&amp;amp;M has set a benchmark for brands in the similar line. Levi’s, on the other hand, has been trying to reduce the notorious amounts of water required to make a pair of jeans by 96% which is a huge step towards making judicial use of existing resources. Like H&amp;amp;M and Levi’s there are many more brands which are working in the same direction but there is still a lot to be done. On the other hand, consumers of fashion can adopt the following steps with a motive to convert their vision for the fashion industry into reality: Keep and wear the clothes for a longer span of time.Think twice before dumping clothes which no longer please you. Instead, upcycle, alter, repair or donate them.&amp;nbsp;Buy sustainable fashion, go for upcycled, thrifted pieces. The bigger question is, can sustainability and profitability ever go hand-in-hand? It’s the demand which can make or break a brand’s fate. With more and more consumers becoming environmentally conscious, the demand for sustainable fashion has hiked up over the course of the years, which has led to brands supplying more and more sustainable garments.&amp;nbsp; Aware and conscious customers, especially Gen Z and millennials are ready to buy sustainable clothing even if they have to shell out more money for it, which makes it profitable for brands to go sustainable. And the ones whose pockets are holding them back from supporting the cause, they tend to take another route by turning to thrift stores which are sustainable and pocket friendly too.&amp;nbsp; These small measures are just a few steps on the ladder towards achieving our goal of a sustainable and circular fashion economy which is all about covering one full circle from growing, designing, wearing, thrifting to finally passing the cloth to the biosphere by safely composting it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Louis Vuitton - A Luxury Mecca</title>
      <link href="/Louis-Vuitton-A-Luxury-Mecca" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Louis Vuitton - A Luxury Mecca" />
      <published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Louis-Vuitton-A-Luxury-Mecca</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Louis-Vuitton-A-Luxury-Mecca">&lt;p&gt;When one thinks of Louis Vuitton, the first thing that comes to mind is an expensive luxury brand of supreme quality. LV is a true definition of aristocracy and elegance and kindles a utopian dream, a tantalising illusion. It is the best seller in the top range of luxury brands which produces high-quality, fashionable products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Established in France in 1854, Louis Vuitton started as a retailer for travelling bags. It opened the first store in Oxford Street, London. Louis Vuitton Moët Hennessy, usually abbreviated as LVMH, was the conglomerate founded in 1987 owing to a merger between Moët Hennessy and Louis Vuitton. Its headquarter is in Paris, France. Bernard Arnault, the President, owns 48% of LVMH. Today, the brand has a strong presence in categories like leather goods, handbags, ready-to-wear garments, jewellery and other accessories.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the very beginning, Louis Vuitton has attracted the support of customers who primarily belong to the upper echelons of society. The brand's mission is to represent the most refined qualities of the occidental art of living around the world. It firmly believes that fashion must follow the customer or die. Thus, it has stepped up its value proposition over time to provide a bespoke experience to its clientele, which adds to its dynamism. Louis Vuitton is one of the few fashion brands that started avant-garde fashion without compromising on traditional values. It won't be an exaggeration to say that LV is the holy grail of those seeking luxury.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current rise of Louis Vuitton is not a coincidence but instead can be attributed to an effective business model. It has always tried to counter mass production with limited edition series. This means that not everyone will have the same bags, and customers, therefore, get to enjoy fantastic exclusivity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Limited editions help to create an instant buzz. Because of the scarcity, waiting lists become longer and longer, and the products become even more desirable. The brand has worked in collaboration with various artists who have created their limited edition lines. This series helps the brand in connecting with new and younger audiences. Louis Vuitton uses the principle of special order, which allows the consumer to order merchandise tailored exactly for him and his preferences.&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;LV maintains and controls its distribution and sales.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it were to allow a large chain store, it undoubtedly would garner more sales in the short run. However, it would damage the brand image and its rarity due to it being easily available. Production efficiency is another crucial factor of LV's thriving business model. The production is completed through teamwork, and the employees are trained to be autonomous and multi-skilled so that the problems related to the product can be solved timely with their knowledge and experience. The whole production process is done in-house, including the manufacturing of raw material, which guarantees superior quality. This is not only rare in the industry, but it also requires a huge financial outlay. LV perpetuates the image of handmade quality. The brand is a true example of superior craftsmanship in an age of cheap mass production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The success of Louis Vuitton's business model can also be accredited to its first-mover advantage in Japan. Louis Vuitton entered Japan in 1977 and saw the Japanese economic boom. The company realised that Japanese consumers demonstrated a fascination with and passion for luxury.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Japanese culture of expressing social status through luxury goods together with the beauty conscious women demanding quality products helped ignite the rage of luxury shopping in Japan. LV began to collaborate with Japanese designers and combined fashionable elements with its heritage to offer fine quality products. This helped nurture an addiction of the Japanese to luxury and enhanced brand loyalty to help sustain profitability. With the company strategies becoming immensely successful, LV became the industry mogul in the Japanese luxury market and acquired a 28% share in the nation's market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louis Vuitton has successfully distinguished itself from other competitors by following a unique marketing strategy that is not utilised by most of its peer luxury brands. It has established a unique brand character that has created a high-standard barrier for others to compete. The LV monogram is high on recognition, and thus, people prefer to carry the monogrammed merchandise since it is associated with fame and reputation. This highlights the great importance that the brand attaches to a consumer's psychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LV does not have a second line to sell products that have a lower cost than the mainline. It only sells high-priced products and ignores those consumers who cannot purchase the high-priced items in the mainline. Although this could be called a haughty attitude, there is a logical reason according to the theory 'Product-out or Lord's business', which means the company would produce the item in limited quantity to satiate the desire of the buyers for prestige.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The high price that the brand commands is not only justified by its superior quality but also by a high degree of exclusivity. While looking at LV history, one can see that not once in 166 years its prices were reduced. “Why LV is never on sales” is a frequently asked question. This is because the brand knows the adverse effects of price reduction. For instance, the customers would wait until the brand goes on sale, which would reduce its exclusivity. Thus, it fixes the price to stimulate customers' demand at once and prevents them from postponing their purchasing habits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louis Vuitton pursues excellence that goes far beyond the supreme quality of its products. It encompasses the layout and location of its stores. It opens these stores only in the most prime locations since it would make the customers feel proud while buying the products. Louis Vuitton shops are distinctive and unique, which offer an experience in itself. It has always rejected mass advertising. It accentuates publicity in newspapers and magazines that last longer than 15-30 seconds of normal television advertisements. It produces catalogues, which, unlike other free ones, carry a charge. These catalogues contain immense information and sell out completely, which is only possible due to Louis Vuitton's unique stature. LV provides its customers with the opportunity to have their damaged products repaired. This helps to develop trust and brand loyalty and sustains the strength of the brand. This strategy has rarely been found adopted by any other brand in the industry.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the fashion industry is still experiencing the colossal ramifications of COVID-19, Louis Vuitton surprisingly has raised prices by a few percentage points over the last year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The affordable mask, which is the new life-saving accessory, just got its extravagant counterpart, that is, the LV mask. Clearly, it is not for the masses but a luxury layer of pandemic protection added by the aristocrats. The fashion house announced Wuhan, a culturally rich Chinese city, as the first stop for its new global travelling exhibition. This shows the rise of China as the new luxury hub post COVID.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been an intriguing change in consumer behaviour in the Chinese markets post lockdown. Many wealthy Chinese consumers are switching their spending from international travel to luxury purchases. During the lockdown, their pent-up spending desires are now being unleashed, a concept that is popularly known as revenge shopping. LV has been able to weather the lockdown thanks to the ever-growing consumer appetite for dresses and monogrammed bags. It is interesting to note that not all brands can afford to raise prices in such times. The ability to charge a higher price during such a crisis is a manifestation of brand power.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louis Vuitton was one of the first brands to reset and streamline its business model to face the challenges posed by the pandemic-led lockdown. Realising the troubles caused by the brick-and-mortar closures and tourism plunge, the brand turned its focus to the digital realm and reinvigorated its online presence. The brand undertook a 360-degree marketing and advertising campaign to remind the customers of the traditional and intrinsic value of its products. For its Spring 2021 collection, Louis Vuitton launched an animated film, followed by live touring runway shows. The brand took over 100 million impressions on its social media posts for the event. LV has begun a partnership with a video game company producing a collection of outfits inspired by one of the company's online games to instil a desire of developing unique virtual personas in the minds of the young audience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest threat that Louis Vuitton faces today is counterfeiting. This new epidemic for the brand has diluted the brand essence and its market share. LV can overcome this menace by making its supply chain transparent and monitoring the movement of its products right from manufacturing to the promotion and beyond. Educating the consumers to recognise the difference between legitimate products and fakes by providing a visual guide will also help curb counterfeiting.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brand now needs to channelise its energies in new directions by expanding into kids clothing or household paraphernalia, where it can take advantage of its pre-established image of superior craftsmanship and command higher margins. It can increase its market size by either investing in emerging wealthy markets like South America and the Indian subcontinent.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LV needs to make itself more attractive to the millennials and generation z by incubating innovative marketing and branding strategies. The brand needs to recalibrate its operations by going green, which would serve as a hedge against rising costs and contribute to sustainability. It needs to show a sense of responsibility and empathy in this hour of crisis for the consumers to embrace it. Revamping the brand image and retaining an insatiable desire for innovation is required to ultimately remind the public that brands like H&amp;amp;M and Zara do not have the elegance and class which Louis Vuitton commands and how it feels a class apart to own a genuine LV product.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Abhinav Gupta&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abhinav Gupta is a first year Bachelor of Commerce (Honours) student in Shaheed Bhagat Singh College, Delhi University. Inquisitive by nature, he loves to explore and learn new things.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhinav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">When one thinks of Louis Vuitton, the first thing that comes to mind is an expensive luxury brand of supreme quality. LV is a true definition of aristocracy and elegance and kindles a utopian dream, a tantalising illusion. It is the best seller in the top range of luxury brands which produces high-quality, fashionable products. Established in France in 1854, Louis Vuitton started as a retailer for travelling bags. It opened the first store in Oxford Street, London. Louis Vuitton Moët Hennessy, usually abbreviated as LVMH, was the conglomerate founded in 1987 owing to a merger between Moët Hennessy and Louis Vuitton. Its headquarter is in Paris, France. Bernard Arnault, the President, owns 48% of LVMH. Today, the brand has a strong presence in categories like leather goods, handbags, ready-to-wear garments, jewellery and other accessories.&amp;nbsp; Since the very beginning, Louis Vuitton has attracted the support of customers who primarily belong to the upper echelons of society. The brand's mission is to represent the most refined qualities of the occidental art of living around the world. It firmly believes that fashion must follow the customer or die. Thus, it has stepped up its value proposition over time to provide a bespoke experience to its clientele, which adds to its dynamism. Louis Vuitton is one of the few fashion brands that started avant-garde fashion without compromising on traditional values. It won't be an exaggeration to say that LV is the holy grail of those seeking luxury.&amp;nbsp; The current rise of Louis Vuitton is not a coincidence but instead can be attributed to an effective business model. It has always tried to counter mass production with limited edition series. This means that not everyone will have the same bags, and customers, therefore, get to enjoy fantastic exclusivity.&amp;nbsp; Limited editions help to create an instant buzz. Because of the scarcity, waiting lists become longer and longer, and the products become even more desirable. The brand has worked in collaboration with various artists who have created their limited edition lines. This series helps the brand in connecting with new and younger audiences. Louis Vuitton uses the principle of special order, which allows the consumer to order merchandise tailored exactly for him and his preferences.&amp;nbsp;LV maintains and controls its distribution and sales.&amp;nbsp; If it were to allow a large chain store, it undoubtedly would garner more sales in the short run. However, it would damage the brand image and its rarity due to it being easily available. Production efficiency is another crucial factor of LV's thriving business model. The production is completed through teamwork, and the employees are trained to be autonomous and multi-skilled so that the problems related to the product can be solved timely with their knowledge and experience. The whole production process is done in-house, including the manufacturing of raw material, which guarantees superior quality. This is not only rare in the industry, but it also requires a huge financial outlay. LV perpetuates the image of handmade quality. The brand is a true example of superior craftsmanship in an age of cheap mass production. The success of Louis Vuitton's business model can also be accredited to its first-mover advantage in Japan. Louis Vuitton entered Japan in 1977 and saw the Japanese economic boom. The company realised that Japanese consumers demonstrated a fascination with and passion for luxury.&amp;nbsp; The Japanese culture of expressing social status through luxury goods together with the beauty conscious women demanding quality products helped ignite the rage of luxury shopping in Japan. LV began to collaborate with Japanese designers and combined fashionable elements with its heritage to offer fine quality products. This helped nurture an addiction of the Japanese to luxury and enhanced brand loyalty to help sustain profitability. With the company strategies becoming immensely successful, LV became the industry mogul in the Japanese luxury market and acquired a 28% share in the nation's market. Louis Vuitton has successfully distinguished itself from other competitors by following a unique marketing strategy that is not utilised by most of its peer luxury brands. It has established a unique brand character that has created a high-standard barrier for others to compete. The LV monogram is high on recognition, and thus, people prefer to carry the monogrammed merchandise since it is associated with fame and reputation. This highlights the great importance that the brand attaches to a consumer's psychology. LV does not have a second line to sell products that have a lower cost than the mainline. It only sells high-priced products and ignores those consumers who cannot purchase the high-priced items in the mainline. Although this could be called a haughty attitude, there is a logical reason according to the theory 'Product-out or Lord's business', which means the company would produce the item in limited quantity to satiate the desire of the buyers for prestige.&amp;nbsp; The high price that the brand commands is not only justified by its superior quality but also by a high degree of exclusivity. While looking at LV history, one can see that not once in 166 years its prices were reduced. “Why LV is never on sales” is a frequently asked question. This is because the brand knows the adverse effects of price reduction. For instance, the customers would wait until the brand goes on sale, which would reduce its exclusivity. Thus, it fixes the price to stimulate customers' demand at once and prevents them from postponing their purchasing habits.&amp;nbsp; Louis Vuitton pursues excellence that goes far beyond the supreme quality of its products. It encompasses the layout and location of its stores. It opens these stores only in the most prime locations since it would make the customers feel proud while buying the products. Louis Vuitton shops are distinctive and unique, which offer an experience in itself. It has always rejected mass advertising. It accentuates publicity in newspapers and magazines that last longer than 15-30 seconds of normal television advertisements. It produces catalogues, which, unlike other free ones, carry a charge. These catalogues contain immense information and sell out completely, which is only possible due to Louis Vuitton's unique stature. LV provides its customers with the opportunity to have their damaged products repaired. This helps to develop trust and brand loyalty and sustains the strength of the brand. This strategy has rarely been found adopted by any other brand in the industry.&amp;nbsp; While the fashion industry is still experiencing the colossal ramifications of COVID-19, Louis Vuitton surprisingly has raised prices by a few percentage points over the last year.&amp;nbsp; The affordable mask, which is the new life-saving accessory, just got its extravagant counterpart, that is, the LV mask. Clearly, it is not for the masses but a luxury layer of pandemic protection added by the aristocrats. The fashion house announced Wuhan, a culturally rich Chinese city, as the first stop for its new global travelling exhibition. This shows the rise of China as the new luxury hub post COVID.&amp;nbsp; There has been an intriguing change in consumer behaviour in the Chinese markets post lockdown. Many wealthy Chinese consumers are switching their spending from international travel to luxury purchases. During the lockdown, their pent-up spending desires are now being unleashed, a concept that is popularly known as revenge shopping. LV has been able to weather the lockdown thanks to the ever-growing consumer appetite for dresses and monogrammed bags. It is interesting to note that not all brands can afford to raise prices in such times. The ability to charge a higher price during such a crisis is a manifestation of brand power.&amp;nbsp; Louis Vuitton was one of the first brands to reset and streamline its business model to face the challenges posed by the pandemic-led lockdown. Realising the troubles caused by the brick-and-mortar closures and tourism plunge, the brand turned its focus to the digital realm and reinvigorated its online presence. The brand undertook a 360-degree marketing and advertising campaign to remind the customers of the traditional and intrinsic value of its products. For its Spring 2021 collection, Louis Vuitton launched an animated film, followed by live touring runway shows. The brand took over 100 million impressions on its social media posts for the event. LV has begun a partnership with a video game company producing a collection of outfits inspired by one of the company's online games to instil a desire of developing unique virtual personas in the minds of the young audience.&amp;nbsp; The biggest threat that Louis Vuitton faces today is counterfeiting. This new epidemic for the brand has diluted the brand essence and its market share. LV can overcome this menace by making its supply chain transparent and monitoring the movement of its products right from manufacturing to the promotion and beyond. Educating the consumers to recognise the difference between legitimate products and fakes by providing a visual guide will also help curb counterfeiting.&amp;nbsp; The brand now needs to channelise its energies in new directions by expanding into kids clothing or household paraphernalia, where it can take advantage of its pre-established image of superior craftsmanship and command higher margins. It can increase its market size by either investing in emerging wealthy markets like South America and the Indian subcontinent.&amp;nbsp; LV needs to make itself more attractive to the millennials and generation z by incubating innovative marketing and branding strategies. The brand needs to recalibrate its operations by going green, which would serve as a hedge against rising costs and contribute to sustainability. It needs to show a sense of responsibility and empathy in this hour of crisis for the consumers to embrace it. Revamping the brand image and retaining an insatiable desire for innovation is required to ultimately remind the public that brands like H&amp;amp;M and Zara do not have the elegance and class which Louis Vuitton commands and how it feels a class apart to own a genuine LV product.&amp;nbsp; -Abhinav Gupta Abhinav Gupta is a first year Bachelor of Commerce (Honours) student in Shaheed Bhagat Singh College, Delhi University. Inquisitive by nature, he loves to explore and learn new things.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Taxing Verdict for the Indian Tax Man</title>
      <link href="/A-Taxing-Verdict-for-the-Indian-Tax-Man" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Taxing Verdict for the Indian Tax Man" />
      <published>2021-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Taxing-Verdict-for-the-Indian-Tax-Man</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Taxing-Verdict-for-the-Indian-Tax-Man">&lt;p&gt;The Permanent Court of Arbitration at the Hague, in its arbitral ruling, has once again dealt a blow to the Government of India by ruling in favour of the gas and oil exploration company, Cairn Energy Plc over tax disputes. The verdict comes post the September 25, 2020 victory of Vodafone International Holdings BV against the Indian government over the same dispute relating to the retrospective tax amendment in 2012.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2006-07, Cairn UK, as part of an internal rearrangement process, transferred shares of Cairn India Holdings to Cairn India. Later, in 2011, the Edinburgh-headquartered organisation sold its Cairn India stake to the mining conglomerate Vedanta. In January 2014, the Indian income tax authorities, in view of the retroactive amended income tax law, alleged that the gas exploration firm made capital gains of ₹245.03 billion in the rearrangement process and hence was liable to pay a tax of ₹102.47 billion to the authorities. The company’s interpretation of Indian laws on capital gains differed, and consequently, it refused to pay the amount. In response, the authorities stopped the sale of the 10% stake to Vedanta and froze dividend pay-out to UK based parent company.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2015, Cairn initiated an international arbitration proceeding against the Indian authorities under article 9 of the Agreement between the Government of the Republic of India and the Government of Great Britain and Northern Ireland for Promotion and Protection of Investments (India-UK BIT). Countries enter into treaties, especially tax treaties, to prevent double taxation of corporations’ incomes earned by foreign investments, so as to promote a healthy business relationship and trade between two countries in this growing globalised world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose behind the said BIT provision was also the same, i.e. ensuring protection of the investors of the contracting state against any disruption/harassment of business in the territory of the host state. (See, Fair and Equitable Treatment – UNCTAD Series on Issues in International Investment Agreement II).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A final assessment order was slapped on the oil corporation in 2016, which included interest amounting to ₹188 billion, in addition to the principal tax amount.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three-member international arbitration tribunal, including a nominee of the Indian government, unanimously ruled in favour of the exploration organisation, and ordered the Indian administration to compensate the former for the total harm suffered including interest and the costs of arbitration. In its judgment, the arbitration panel said, “&lt;em&gt;Tax demand against the claimants (Cairn Energy Plc and Cairn UK Holdings Limited) in respect of AY (assessment year) 2007-08 is inconsistent with the treaty and the claimants are relieved from any obligation to pay it and [the tribunal] orders the respondent (Indian government) to neutralise the continuing effect of the demand by permanently withdrawing the demand.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sovereign country has the power to impose tax from a retrospective date. Nonetheless, such an action when a past transaction, which was not liable to taxation as on that date, is taxed under the aegis of a retrospective amendment, it is naturally seen to be unjust and discriminatory. Officials usually defend the amendments by stating that such moves are brought into effect to correct earlier flaws that defeated the purpose of the legislation in the first place.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be interesting to observe India’s follow-up on the issue. The government has until this month to challenge the award in a higher court in Singapore. By February end, Cairn’s CEO &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?rlz=1C1RXQR_enIN928IN928&amp;amp;sxsrf=ALeKk03IPhQp-AiVjX-3f-BE1qS7-EiNXw:1614752810068&amp;amp;q=Simon+Thomson&amp;amp;stick=H4sIAAAAAAAAAOPgE-LUz9U3sDCxtCxX4gIx85LzcgqNtBSzk63084vSE_MyqxJLMvPzUDhWyan5i1h5gzNz8_MUQjLyc4vz83awMgIATPkbn08AAAA&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjgi5P9vpPvAhWTXSsKHSlvCAoQmxMoATApegQIIRAD&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Simon Thomson&lt;/a&gt; in his conversation with the Ministry of&amp;nbsp; Finance conveyed the corporation’s desire for a speedy resolution that is in the interest of all stakeholders involved. The government has hinted that the only possible solution for both parties to avoid further litigation is for the former to agree to the government’s&amp;nbsp;'&lt;a href=&quot;https://indianexpress.com/article/explained/direct-tax-vivad-se-vishwas-bill-how-govt-aims-to-reduce-direct-tax-litigation-6254981/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Vivad se Vishwas&lt;/a&gt;' (From Litigation to Trust) &amp;nbsp;tax amnesty. This scheme, announced in the Indian Budget 2020, provides speedy resolution for tax disputes in the forms of certain compensation between individuals and the tax department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The oil discovery company aims to enforce the award under international arbitration rules, and can use this judgment to approach courts in countries like the UK, USA to seize any overseas property owned by India, to recover the money if the award is not honoured. If it does happen, India would not be the first country to face seizure of its international assets from an energy company. In 2019, US Oil firm ConocoPhillips, under international arbitration law, seized Venezuela’s overseas assets to execute an arbitration award of more than $8 billion. Cairn is reportedly identifying India’s overseas assets, including bank accounts and even Air India planes or Indian ships, that could be seized in the absence of a settlement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also worthwhile to note that if the Indian government accepts the award, then this move would be welcomed by the business corporations. India's reputation has taken a severe beating as a result of these cases. The BJP government has, in the past, denounced the introduction of a retrospective tax amendment by the previous Congress government as &quot;tax terrorism&quot;. Prime Minister Narendra Modi had promised to bring an end to &quot;tax terror&quot; after coming to power in 2014. However, the opposite happened when the government carried on with the case.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a government struggling to find revenue and seeking to boost its economy post-COVID-19, it is essential for the government to reduce compliance troubles and stumbling blocks such as retrospective taxation, lest it finds itself seriously damaging its potential post economic liberalisation.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Permanent Court of Arbitration at the Hague, in its arbitral ruling, has once again dealt a blow to the Government of India by ruling in favour of the gas and oil exploration company, Cairn Energy Plc over tax disputes. The verdict comes post the September 25, 2020 victory of Vodafone International Holdings BV against the Indian government over the same dispute relating to the retrospective tax amendment in 2012.&amp;nbsp; In 2006-07, Cairn UK, as part of an internal rearrangement process, transferred shares of Cairn India Holdings to Cairn India. Later, in 2011, the Edinburgh-headquartered organisation sold its Cairn India stake to the mining conglomerate Vedanta. In January 2014, the Indian income tax authorities, in view of the retroactive amended income tax law, alleged that the gas exploration firm made capital gains of ₹245.03 billion in the rearrangement process and hence was liable to pay a tax of ₹102.47 billion to the authorities. The company’s interpretation of Indian laws on capital gains differed, and consequently, it refused to pay the amount. In response, the authorities stopped the sale of the 10% stake to Vedanta and froze dividend pay-out to UK based parent company.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; In 2015, Cairn initiated an international arbitration proceeding against the Indian authorities under article 9 of the Agreement between the Government of the Republic of India and the Government of Great Britain and Northern Ireland for Promotion and Protection of Investments (India-UK BIT). Countries enter into treaties, especially tax treaties, to prevent double taxation of corporations’ incomes earned by foreign investments, so as to promote a healthy business relationship and trade between two countries in this growing globalised world. The purpose behind the said BIT provision was also the same, i.e. ensuring protection of the investors of the contracting state against any disruption/harassment of business in the territory of the host state. (See, Fair and Equitable Treatment – UNCTAD Series on Issues in International Investment Agreement II). A final assessment order was slapped on the oil corporation in 2016, which included interest amounting to ₹188 billion, in addition to the principal tax amount.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The three-member international arbitration tribunal, including a nominee of the Indian government, unanimously ruled in favour of the exploration organisation, and ordered the Indian administration to compensate the former for the total harm suffered including interest and the costs of arbitration. In its judgment, the arbitration panel said, “Tax demand against the claimants (Cairn Energy Plc and Cairn UK Holdings Limited) in respect of AY (assessment year) 2007-08 is inconsistent with the treaty and the claimants are relieved from any obligation to pay it and [the tribunal] orders the respondent (Indian government) to neutralise the continuing effect of the demand by permanently withdrawing the demand.” A sovereign country has the power to impose tax from a retrospective date. Nonetheless, such an action when a past transaction, which was not liable to taxation as on that date, is taxed under the aegis of a retrospective amendment, it is naturally seen to be unjust and discriminatory. Officials usually defend the amendments by stating that such moves are brought into effect to correct earlier flaws that defeated the purpose of the legislation in the first place.&amp;nbsp; It would be interesting to observe India’s follow-up on the issue. The government has until this month to challenge the award in a higher court in Singapore. By February end, Cairn’s CEO Simon Thomson in his conversation with the Ministry of&amp;nbsp; Finance conveyed the corporation’s desire for a speedy resolution that is in the interest of all stakeholders involved. The government has hinted that the only possible solution for both parties to avoid further litigation is for the former to agree to the government’s&amp;nbsp;'Vivad se Vishwas' (From Litigation to Trust) &amp;nbsp;tax amnesty. This scheme, announced in the Indian Budget 2020, provides speedy resolution for tax disputes in the forms of certain compensation between individuals and the tax department. The oil discovery company aims to enforce the award under international arbitration rules, and can use this judgment to approach courts in countries like the UK, USA to seize any overseas property owned by India, to recover the money if the award is not honoured. If it does happen, India would not be the first country to face seizure of its international assets from an energy company. In 2019, US Oil firm ConocoPhillips, under international arbitration law, seized Venezuela’s overseas assets to execute an arbitration award of more than $8 billion. Cairn is reportedly identifying India’s overseas assets, including bank accounts and even Air India planes or Indian ships, that could be seized in the absence of a settlement. It is also worthwhile to note that if the Indian government accepts the award, then this move would be welcomed by the business corporations. India's reputation has taken a severe beating as a result of these cases. The BJP government has, in the past, denounced the introduction of a retrospective tax amendment by the previous Congress government as &quot;tax terrorism&quot;. Prime Minister Narendra Modi had promised to bring an end to &quot;tax terror&quot; after coming to power in 2014. However, the opposite happened when the government carried on with the case.&amp;nbsp; For a government struggling to find revenue and seeking to boost its economy post-COVID-19, it is essential for the government to reduce compliance troubles and stumbling blocks such as retrospective taxation, lest it finds itself seriously damaging its potential post economic liberalisation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A High ROE can be Misleading!</title>
      <link href="/A-High-ROE-can-be-Misleading" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A High ROE can be Misleading!" />
      <published>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-High-ROE-can-be-Misleading</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-High-ROE-can-be-Misleading">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Investment is most intelligent when it’s most businesslike&lt;/em&gt;”- Benjamin Graham.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Benjamin Graham and Warren Buffet have emphasised on the need for the investor to only invest in companies whose business they duly understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how do we do that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer lies in an obsession with numbers. Plain odd numbers that mean something to a blank eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like the Greeks had an obsession with Golden Ratio, investors are the same with Financial ratios. Ratios are shortcuts and who doesn’t like them? Especially when “more time means more money”, seems real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One such important ratio that makes the kitty of the most important financial ratios to consider for an Investor is the “Return on Equity (ROE)” Ratio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And both these gentlemen mentioned above love this ratio. They do warn you on single-factor investing and urge you to consider other key factors but that’s in line with every valuation metric that comes with a “&lt;em&gt;yes, but…&lt;/em&gt;”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why do they love it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because it’s businesslike. It showcases the business owner’s ability to employ equity into money-making ventures. It measures profitability. It gives a raw sense of what the company is doing with its equity and how efficient it is in engineering its cash to generate more cash. More earnings mean higher valuations and higher valuation would mean capital appreciation for stakeholders. It’s simple math.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, as all math do,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It starts with a simple formula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Return on Equity (ROE) = Net Income/Shareholder’s equity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toggle to the company’s P&amp;amp;L statement and pick up the bottom-line item, ‘Net Income’ and divide it by the total shareholder’s equity present on the balance sheet and that’s how easily you can calculate the ROE of your desired company. The rule of thumb is, the higher the ROE, the more the company is efficient in its operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too excited to already switch tabs? Wait!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where the trouble begins.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplicity by which ROE can be calculated should already make you apprehensive about its god-like relevance. Good things don’t come easy, right? Well, let’s dig deeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s multiply and divide the above equation, once by the ‘Total Sales’ and again by ‘Total Assets’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;ROE= (Net Income/Total Sales) * (Total Sales/Total Assets) * (Total Assets/Shareholders Equity)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Total Sales cancel Total Sales and Total Assets cancel Total Assets but for now, let’s analyse each portion individually. Reframing the above equation, we have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;ROE= Net Profit Margin * Total Asset Turnover Ratio * Financial Leverage&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we have is something known as the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;DuPont Formula&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; which breaks down ROE into 3 key drivers, all of which independently relate to the ROE and can help back-test the components of the formula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Net Profit Margin is indicative of how well the company is in managing and financing its operations per unit of sales. A higher Net Profit Margin would eventually mean more earnings for the company and higher ROE. Asset turnover ratio means how efficiently the company is using its assets to drive sales. A higher Total Asset Turnover Ratio would mean that the company is deploying its assets correctly to target higher sales per unit of the asset owned. Hence, a higher ROE. Lastly, Financial Leverage is the extent to which the company uses debt in relation to equity to finance its assets. In brief, higher leverage would mean greater financial risk but substituted by higher Return on Equity (ROE).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An ideal firm should have a high Net Profit Margin, high Asset Turnover Ratio but use less leverage to reach there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out, however, that a company cannot grow earnings faster than its current ROE without raising additional cash. Now raising cash comes at a cost and cuts through the firm’s profits. If the company decides to raise money by way of debt, the interest gets paid as an expense and if it decides to raise equity, Earnings-per-share (EPS) goes down, which in turn affects investor sentiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, ROE is the limiter to a firm’s growth. It’s a gauge against the excessive heating up of the company. That is why ROE forms an integral part of the investor analysis but here comes the catch. When something holds such importance within stakeholders' minds and the management knows it, will not all companies tend to magnify ROE to seem better on the stock exchange?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, but soon you’ll know higher ROE numbers are no shortcut for diligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manipulating the ROE numbers isn’t an ordeal. There are numerous ways by which this can be done and that make higher ROE’s a subject for debate. This is where the trouble gets bigger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Share Buybacks:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember the ROE equation? A simple math student would tell how to increase its value. Either increase the Net Earnings (Numerator) or decrease Total Shareholders Equity (Denominator). An ideal and natural practice for companies would be to focus on increasing the numerator by increasing the Asset Turnover Ratio that drives sales with no additional asset cost or by increasing the Net profit Margin by efficiently managing operations. Both these practices done in tandem would result in a significantly higher ROE. But not all companies resort to this technique. Some adopt a latter technique and decrease shareholder’s equity by rolling out share buyback schemes. When they do say they use the retained earnings to buy stock and thus decrease the shareholder equity which in turn magnifies the firm’s ability to turn equity investments into profits (ROE).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;High Leverage:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to decrease shareholder equity is to tweak the company’s capital structure by playing around with the Debt/Equity ratio. Companies issue debt to raise capital and then use that to generate profits. Indeed, the finance cost will increase for a given capital requirement but that would only be a fraction of total debt and not enough to offset the decrease in shareholder’s equity. Higher Net Profits would boost ROE higher, but that has hidden risks related to insolvency and inability to survive during economic downturns. Because debt is an obligation to pay back with interest, it is neutral to the company’s bad run. Companies that issue large debt run the risks of overleveraging in the form of high-interest payments and greater chances of default. These companies may rely heavily on debt and hence have an Inflated and misleading ROE figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Off-balance sheet items and write-downs:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of Off-balance sheet items has been in talks ever since &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sir David Tweedie&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; was the chairman of the IASB. He joked that he wanted to fly in an aircraft that actually existed on an airline’s balance sheet. That is to say that it’s not on operating lease or any such way that the companies adopt to evade showing huge assets in their balance sheets. By doing this, they forgo depreciation expense and incur impairment charges when they right down assets, which in turn decreases Shareholders' equity on the balance sheet. This keeps equity investors in an obscure environment by hiding the true amount of capital invested in the business. This is further treated maliciously by the management to offset natural ROE figures and make them appear more inflated and following a growth trend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another problem with the ROE calculations is the ‘E’ part in it. The “Net Earnings” line item is such an entry that can easily be tricked and especially when the management bonus is linked to hitting ROE targets, they can have a strong interest in artificially boosting it. Further, it does not take into account risks associated with income generation and is subject to a wide variety of accounting conventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the number is so susceptible to management intervention and unchallenging to intrude and alter, higher ROE can be misleading. If not anything this is what companies did in the wake of the 2008 Financial Crisis and during the ongoing Covid-19 Pandemic. Since the market was undervalued on both occasions, companies came in with various offers to interest investors and appear good on paper. This rigorous attempt was also done to avoid a dent in the ROE history of the company. An ROE that’s greater than the return available from a lower risk investment motivates the Investor to see interesting but false prospects building within the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While companies do all this to fuel their investor's confidence, misinformed investors are caught in a tyranny of financial malpractices, unwinding which is a luxury for a common Investor. Investors can’t know whether that ROE number is reliable or pumped to perfection. One company might have a significantly higher ROE than a competitor simply because it’s more aggressively exploiting uninformed investors rather than being superior in terms of profitability. ROE lacks the necessary meticulous conscientiousness to buttress intelligent investment decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though every single ratio has a caveat. ROE is the dumbest of all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll leave you with one thought, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If such a flawed financial metric catches the attention of mass-market participants, then there should be a profitable arbitrage strategy that exploits that anomaly?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Mehul Goyal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Investment is most intelligent when it’s most businesslike”- Benjamin Graham. Both Benjamin Graham and Warren Buffet have emphasised on the need for the investor to only invest in companies whose business they duly understand. But how do we do that? The answer lies in an obsession with numbers. Plain odd numbers that mean something to a blank eye. Just like the Greeks had an obsession with Golden Ratio, investors are the same with Financial ratios. Ratios are shortcuts and who doesn’t like them? Especially when “more time means more money”, seems real. One such important ratio that makes the kitty of the most important financial ratios to consider for an Investor is the “Return on Equity (ROE)” Ratio. And both these gentlemen mentioned above love this ratio. They do warn you on single-factor investing and urge you to consider other key factors but that’s in line with every valuation metric that comes with a “yes, but…”.&amp;nbsp; But why do they love it? Because it’s businesslike. It showcases the business owner’s ability to employ equity into money-making ventures. It measures profitability. It gives a raw sense of what the company is doing with its equity and how efficient it is in engineering its cash to generate more cash. More earnings mean higher valuations and higher valuation would mean capital appreciation for stakeholders. It’s simple math. But, as all math do, It starts with a simple formula. Return on Equity (ROE) = Net Income/Shareholder’s equity. Toggle to the company’s P&amp;amp;L statement and pick up the bottom-line item, ‘Net Income’ and divide it by the total shareholder’s equity present on the balance sheet and that’s how easily you can calculate the ROE of your desired company. The rule of thumb is, the higher the ROE, the more the company is efficient in its operations. Too excited to already switch tabs? Wait! This is where the trouble begins.&amp;nbsp; The simplicity by which ROE can be calculated should already make you apprehensive about its god-like relevance. Good things don’t come easy, right? Well, let’s dig deeper. Let’s multiply and divide the above equation, once by the ‘Total Sales’ and again by ‘Total Assets’. ROE= (Net Income/Total Sales) * (Total Sales/Total Assets) * (Total Assets/Shareholders Equity) Total Sales cancel Total Sales and Total Assets cancel Total Assets but for now, let’s analyse each portion individually. Reframing the above equation, we have: ROE= Net Profit Margin * Total Asset Turnover Ratio * Financial Leverage What we have is something known as the DuPont Formula which breaks down ROE into 3 key drivers, all of which independently relate to the ROE and can help back-test the components of the formula. The Net Profit Margin is indicative of how well the company is in managing and financing its operations per unit of sales. A higher Net Profit Margin would eventually mean more earnings for the company and higher ROE. Asset turnover ratio means how efficiently the company is using its assets to drive sales. A higher Total Asset Turnover Ratio would mean that the company is deploying its assets correctly to target higher sales per unit of the asset owned. Hence, a higher ROE. Lastly, Financial Leverage is the extent to which the company uses debt in relation to equity to finance its assets. In brief, higher leverage would mean greater financial risk but substituted by higher Return on Equity (ROE). An ideal firm should have a high Net Profit Margin, high Asset Turnover Ratio but use less leverage to reach there. It turns out, however, that a company cannot grow earnings faster than its current ROE without raising additional cash. Now raising cash comes at a cost and cuts through the firm’s profits. If the company decides to raise money by way of debt, the interest gets paid as an expense and if it decides to raise equity, Earnings-per-share (EPS) goes down, which in turn affects investor sentiment. So, ROE is the limiter to a firm’s growth. It’s a gauge against the excessive heating up of the company. That is why ROE forms an integral part of the investor analysis but here comes the catch. When something holds such importance within stakeholders' minds and the management knows it, will not all companies tend to magnify ROE to seem better on the stock exchange?&amp;nbsp; Yes, but soon you’ll know higher ROE numbers are no shortcut for diligence. Manipulating the ROE numbers isn’t an ordeal. There are numerous ways by which this can be done and that make higher ROE’s a subject for debate. This is where the trouble gets bigger. Share Buybacks: Remember the ROE equation? A simple math student would tell how to increase its value. Either increase the Net Earnings (Numerator) or decrease Total Shareholders Equity (Denominator). An ideal and natural practice for companies would be to focus on increasing the numerator by increasing the Asset Turnover Ratio that drives sales with no additional asset cost or by increasing the Net profit Margin by efficiently managing operations. Both these practices done in tandem would result in a significantly higher ROE. But not all companies resort to this technique. Some adopt a latter technique and decrease shareholder’s equity by rolling out share buyback schemes. When they do say they use the retained earnings to buy stock and thus decrease the shareholder equity which in turn magnifies the firm’s ability to turn equity investments into profits (ROE). High Leverage: Another way to decrease shareholder equity is to tweak the company’s capital structure by playing around with the Debt/Equity ratio. Companies issue debt to raise capital and then use that to generate profits. Indeed, the finance cost will increase for a given capital requirement but that would only be a fraction of total debt and not enough to offset the decrease in shareholder’s equity. Higher Net Profits would boost ROE higher, but that has hidden risks related to insolvency and inability to survive during economic downturns. Because debt is an obligation to pay back with interest, it is neutral to the company’s bad run. Companies that issue large debt run the risks of overleveraging in the form of high-interest payments and greater chances of default. These companies may rely heavily on debt and hence have an Inflated and misleading ROE figure. Off-balance sheet items and write-downs: The concept of Off-balance sheet items has been in talks ever since Sir David Tweedie was the chairman of the IASB. He joked that he wanted to fly in an aircraft that actually existed on an airline’s balance sheet. That is to say that it’s not on operating lease or any such way that the companies adopt to evade showing huge assets in their balance sheets. By doing this, they forgo depreciation expense and incur impairment charges when they right down assets, which in turn decreases Shareholders' equity on the balance sheet. This keeps equity investors in an obscure environment by hiding the true amount of capital invested in the business. This is further treated maliciously by the management to offset natural ROE figures and make them appear more inflated and following a growth trend. Another problem with the ROE calculations is the ‘E’ part in it. The “Net Earnings” line item is such an entry that can easily be tricked and especially when the management bonus is linked to hitting ROE targets, they can have a strong interest in artificially boosting it. Further, it does not take into account risks associated with income generation and is subject to a wide variety of accounting conventions. Conclusion: Since the number is so susceptible to management intervention and unchallenging to intrude and alter, higher ROE can be misleading. If not anything this is what companies did in the wake of the 2008 Financial Crisis and during the ongoing Covid-19 Pandemic. Since the market was undervalued on both occasions, companies came in with various offers to interest investors and appear good on paper. This rigorous attempt was also done to avoid a dent in the ROE history of the company. An ROE that’s greater than the return available from a lower risk investment motivates the Investor to see interesting but false prospects building within the company. While companies do all this to fuel their investor's confidence, misinformed investors are caught in a tyranny of financial malpractices, unwinding which is a luxury for a common Investor. Investors can’t know whether that ROE number is reliable or pumped to perfection. One company might have a significantly higher ROE than a competitor simply because it’s more aggressively exploiting uninformed investors rather than being superior in terms of profitability. ROE lacks the necessary meticulous conscientiousness to buttress intelligent investment decisions. Though every single ratio has a caveat. ROE is the dumbest of all. I’ll leave you with one thought, though. If such a flawed financial metric catches the attention of mass-market participants, then there should be a profitable arbitrage strategy that exploits that anomaly?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Emergence of Sexbots and the Sentience Stumper</title>
      <link href="/The-Emergence-of-Sexbots-and-the-Sentience-Stumper" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Emergence of Sexbots and the Sentience Stumper" />
      <published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Emergence-of-Sexbots-and-the-Sentience-Stumper</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Emergence-of-Sexbots-and-the-Sentience-Stumper">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 1: Immersion into The SexTech Industry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What comes to your mind when you overhear the word ‘SexTech’? Sex robots and virtual mates? Sex toys and adult websites? These are only a portion of the SexTech industry. Basically, SexTech is any technology that has been curated to enhance the human sexual experience and disrupts the way sex is viewed, accessed and relished like never before. However, the industry is still marginalised, yet the market is buzzing with the rising voice of IoB technology. The industry is currently estimated at $30 billion and is forecasted to become one of the fastest-growing industries in the next few years, hitting $122.6 billion by 2026.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you remember that Saudi Arabia gave citizenship to a robot known as Sophia in 2017? She became the world’s first robot citizen. Since then, the robotics industry has advanced in other fields as well where artificial humans can be used in productive ways. The success of silicone sex dolls for sexual gratification has set a clear path for the role of robotics in the future of sex. Public polls and indirect measures insinuate that there would be a market for sex robots. We cannot determine how big the market will be. It could be a niche for fetishists, a new paraphilia, or societal norms could alter to allow their use to become widespread.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 2: Dealing with Artificial Love Servants&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The regular customers of the old world of artificial love servants will pay around $20 for such an object - not encompassing shipping and transport. For this, they would get, for example, an inflatable or mannequin-like sex partner, as referred to in earlier decades and centuries. If they dig deeper into their pockets and shell out $500 to $1,500, they have arrived in the modern world. For this, they can acquire a lifelike sex doll with silicone skin and a metal skeleton that can display a gamut of emotions they’re programmed with. They can smile, cry, even do a good approximation of an orgasm face and can produce ever-better mimicries of personhood.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, the sale of robots developed for sexual motives is fast approaching. Several companies such as Realbotix, Android Love Dolls, True Companion and the Sex Bot have begun to take shipping orders. In the world of human-machine intimacy, Harmony by RealDoll is among the most evolved sex robots which can blink, move its head, have a tête-à-tête, and comes with self-learning software that remembers earlier encounters to offer better companionship.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the advancements treading at this rate, we can expect bots to become more developed, sophisticated and human-like. Moreover, the industry experts are exploring the new domain of immersive sex content and virtual reality pornography.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 3: Intimate Droids for Dotage&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is it like to form an emotional bond with a robot? We turn to moral philosophers, scientists and sex workers to compare the differences between human relationships and what robots offer. Indeed, robots cannot feel love or tenderness. The best that robots can do is to ‘fake it’ but, the anthropomorphic features might be enough for some people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The robotic sex dolls are popularly joked about as fetish objects for lonesome beings. But some people believe that the potential of these dolls extends far beyond mere masturbatory succour. The use of sex robots in some therapies may help with sexual healing. For example, it may be beneficial to use a robot in aiding people with sexual dysfunction or social anxiety about sex. For all the adults who are entitled to sex life, robots have also been proposed as a means of appeasement for the differently-abled and the elderly. Although, this idea poses complex ethical issues, particularly with the elderly in care homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 4: Perverted or Practical in the battle against Sex Crimes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some believe that expressing disordered or criminal sexual desires with a sex robot would bring users to the point where they would not have the desire to harm fellow humans. Alternatively, many others believe that this would encourage recidivism, reinforce illicit sexual practices, and make them more admissible. Allowing people to live out their darkest fantasies with sex robots can have a detrimental effect on society and stir up more danger for the vulnerable. But the arrival of sex robots has a distinguished opinion. Inventors like Santos argue that they can potentially replace prostitutes, reduce sex trafficking, and help lonely rejects, while critics say they objectify women and normalize sexism as well as rape culture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts say that the increasingly life-like robots raise complex issues that should be considered by policymakers and the public- including whether the use of such products should be stimulated to curb prostitution and sex trafficking, for sex offenders, or people with disabilities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 5: Connecting the Dots&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could sexual intimacy with robots lead to pronounced social isolation? The majority of experts provide strong arguments that sex robots could lead to some form of a social void. It is contrary to what the manufactures of sex robots tell us. The CEO of RealBotix said that he has been making sex dolls for many years, especially to alleviate the vacuum of those who, for whatever reason, have problems relating to human intimacy. The public survey data shows mixed opinions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously this year, Women of SexTech held a virtual event to discuss the impact of COVID-19 on the industry. The keynote speaker was Cindy Gallop, founder of the MakeLoveNotPorn company, who claimed in her speech that months of lockdown showed us that human relationships are irreplaceable. Technology is just a means to enhance the human experience. Gallop also stated that “&lt;em&gt;it is only when things break down that new tech and ideas emerge&lt;/em&gt;.” The social isolation has created an utter context for SexTech to thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, nearly every facet of society today - public health organisations, school-based sex education, financial institutions, investment and venture capital, major social media companies- still forbid this very reality. At best, it’s considered an indulgence. At worst, sexual wellness and technology are routinely grouped along with pornography, illegal drugs, weapons, and gambling. Therefore, it operates underground in the gloom. Honestly, investors are apprehensive, which means they sometimes do not understand the problems to be solved. Or they answer to more conservative institutions that won’t invest in 'vice.' Stigma keeps them away from SexTech.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samakshi Garg</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Part 1: Immersion into The SexTech Industry What comes to your mind when you overhear the word ‘SexTech’? Sex robots and virtual mates? Sex toys and adult websites? These are only a portion of the SexTech industry. Basically, SexTech is any technology that has been curated to enhance the human sexual experience and disrupts the way sex is viewed, accessed and relished like never before. However, the industry is still marginalised, yet the market is buzzing with the rising voice of IoB technology. The industry is currently estimated at $30 billion and is forecasted to become one of the fastest-growing industries in the next few years, hitting $122.6 billion by 2026.&amp;nbsp; Do you remember that Saudi Arabia gave citizenship to a robot known as Sophia in 2017? She became the world’s first robot citizen. Since then, the robotics industry has advanced in other fields as well where artificial humans can be used in productive ways. The success of silicone sex dolls for sexual gratification has set a clear path for the role of robotics in the future of sex. Public polls and indirect measures insinuate that there would be a market for sex robots. We cannot determine how big the market will be. It could be a niche for fetishists, a new paraphilia, or societal norms could alter to allow their use to become widespread.&amp;nbsp; Part 2: Dealing with Artificial Love Servants The regular customers of the old world of artificial love servants will pay around $20 for such an object - not encompassing shipping and transport. For this, they would get, for example, an inflatable or mannequin-like sex partner, as referred to in earlier decades and centuries. If they dig deeper into their pockets and shell out $500 to $1,500, they have arrived in the modern world. For this, they can acquire a lifelike sex doll with silicone skin and a metal skeleton that can display a gamut of emotions they’re programmed with. They can smile, cry, even do a good approximation of an orgasm face and can produce ever-better mimicries of personhood.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Nowadays, the sale of robots developed for sexual motives is fast approaching. Several companies such as Realbotix, Android Love Dolls, True Companion and the Sex Bot have begun to take shipping orders. In the world of human-machine intimacy, Harmony by RealDoll is among the most evolved sex robots which can blink, move its head, have a tête-à-tête, and comes with self-learning software that remembers earlier encounters to offer better companionship.&amp;nbsp; With the advancements treading at this rate, we can expect bots to become more developed, sophisticated and human-like. Moreover, the industry experts are exploring the new domain of immersive sex content and virtual reality pornography.&amp;nbsp; Part 3: Intimate Droids for Dotage What is it like to form an emotional bond with a robot? We turn to moral philosophers, scientists and sex workers to compare the differences between human relationships and what robots offer. Indeed, robots cannot feel love or tenderness. The best that robots can do is to ‘fake it’ but, the anthropomorphic features might be enough for some people. The robotic sex dolls are popularly joked about as fetish objects for lonesome beings. But some people believe that the potential of these dolls extends far beyond mere masturbatory succour. The use of sex robots in some therapies may help with sexual healing. For example, it may be beneficial to use a robot in aiding people with sexual dysfunction or social anxiety about sex. For all the adults who are entitled to sex life, robots have also been proposed as a means of appeasement for the differently-abled and the elderly. Although, this idea poses complex ethical issues, particularly with the elderly in care homes. Part 4: Perverted or Practical in the battle against Sex Crimes Some believe that expressing disordered or criminal sexual desires with a sex robot would bring users to the point where they would not have the desire to harm fellow humans. Alternatively, many others believe that this would encourage recidivism, reinforce illicit sexual practices, and make them more admissible. Allowing people to live out their darkest fantasies with sex robots can have a detrimental effect on society and stir up more danger for the vulnerable. But the arrival of sex robots has a distinguished opinion. Inventors like Santos argue that they can potentially replace prostitutes, reduce sex trafficking, and help lonely rejects, while critics say they objectify women and normalize sexism as well as rape culture.&amp;nbsp; Experts say that the increasingly life-like robots raise complex issues that should be considered by policymakers and the public- including whether the use of such products should be stimulated to curb prostitution and sex trafficking, for sex offenders, or people with disabilities.&amp;nbsp; Part 5: Connecting the Dots Could sexual intimacy with robots lead to pronounced social isolation? The majority of experts provide strong arguments that sex robots could lead to some form of a social void. It is contrary to what the manufactures of sex robots tell us. The CEO of RealBotix said that he has been making sex dolls for many years, especially to alleviate the vacuum of those who, for whatever reason, have problems relating to human intimacy. The public survey data shows mixed opinions.&amp;nbsp; Previously this year, Women of SexTech held a virtual event to discuss the impact of COVID-19 on the industry. The keynote speaker was Cindy Gallop, founder of the MakeLoveNotPorn company, who claimed in her speech that months of lockdown showed us that human relationships are irreplaceable. Technology is just a means to enhance the human experience. Gallop also stated that “it is only when things break down that new tech and ideas emerge.” The social isolation has created an utter context for SexTech to thrive. Unfortunately, nearly every facet of society today - public health organisations, school-based sex education, financial institutions, investment and venture capital, major social media companies- still forbid this very reality. At best, it’s considered an indulgence. At worst, sexual wellness and technology are routinely grouped along with pornography, illegal drugs, weapons, and gambling. Therefore, it operates underground in the gloom. Honestly, investors are apprehensive, which means they sometimes do not understand the problems to be solved. Or they answer to more conservative institutions that won’t invest in 'vice.' Stigma keeps them away from SexTech.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Big Daddy’s Gamble: the Indian Securities Regulator Challenges India’s Oligarch</title>
      <link href="/Big-Daddy-s-Gamble-the-Indian-Securities-Regulator-Challenges-India-s-Oligarch" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Big Daddy’s Gamble: the Indian Securities Regulator Challenges India's Oligarch" />
      <published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Big-Daddy-s-Gamble-the-Indian-Securities-Regulator-Challenges-India-s-Oligarch</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Big-Daddy-s-Gamble-the-Indian-Securities-Regulator-Challenges-India-s-Oligarch">&lt;p&gt;On January 1, 2021, the Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI) slapped a fine on the largest company in India by market capitalisation, i.e. Reliance Industries Limited (RIL), and its Chairman and Managing Director Mukesh Ambani of ₹250 million and ₹150 million respectively, along with two other entities, for manipulative trading in the shares of the erstwhile Reliance Petroleum Limited (RPL) in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what activity did RIL engage in to receive a penalty from the market regulator?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reliance Petroleum Limited (RPL) was a refinery, partly owned by RIL, which later got merged with the latter in 2009. However, the conglomerate got itself under the radar of the watchdog for the transaction that occurred between the company and its agents in November, 2007, in the cash and futures segment of the secondary market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RIL had decided to sell off its 4.1% stake in RPL. According to SEBI, in order to make undue gains from the sale, the former had entered into an agreement with 12 agents, who booked large short positions of the refinery’s shares in the futures market. Short positions refer to a situation when a trader sells the security first with the intention of repurchasing it later at a lower price, hence the steeper the decline, greater is the profit for the trader. Following this, in the last ten minutes of the trading session of November 29, 2007, RIL sold close to 20 million RPL shares. This large scale selling triggered mass panic and within a moment’s notice, the stock price collapsed.&amp;nbsp; Interestingly, it also happened to be the same day that the futures contracts were meant to pay-out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, SEBI contends that RIL and the agents colluded together in a bid to make a profit estimated to be around ₹44.7 billion off of this transaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selling of securities by promoters in the capital markets in order to raise cash is a widely accepted practice, however, this act of secretive plotting that can distort the natural price discovery system in the market and cheat investors via non-transparent mechanisms is impermissible and against the objectives of the SEBI or any securities regulator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SEBI’s adjudicating officer B J Dilip said, “&lt;em&gt;any manipulation in the volume or price of securities always erodes investor confidence in the market when investors find themselves at the receiving end of market manipulators&lt;/em&gt;.” He further added, “&lt;em&gt;In the instant case, the general investors were not aware that the entity behind the above F&amp;amp;O segment transactions was RIL. The execution of the... fraudulent trades affected the price of the RPL securities in both cash and F&amp;amp;O [Futures and Options] segments and harmed the interests of other investors&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SEBI order states that Mukesh Ambani as the Managing Director of RIL was equally involved in the malpractice. Apart from the conglomerate and its chairman, SEBI also imposed penalties of ₹2 million and ₹1 million on Navi Mumbai SEZ Pvt Ltd and Mumbai SEZ Ltd respectively, both promoted by Anand Jain, a former member of the Reliance Group, for providing margin payments for the agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In March 2017, the market watchdog had ordered RIL and other entities to disgorge ₹4.47 billion in the RPL’s case, against which the latter appealed in the Securities Appellate Tribunal (SAT). The verdict announced by the tribunal in November 2020 was against the appellant. However, the petrochemicals to telecommunication multinational corporation said that it would appeal against the Tribunal’s ruling in the Indian Supreme Court.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not the first time that RIL and a government entity were at loggerheads. In 2014, the Indian market regulator had imposed a fine of ₹1.3 million on the corporation for non-disclosure of a key earnings ratio, which would have impacted investors’ evaluation on the shares. In 2018, the RIL-led consortium of BP Plc and Niko Resources won an award against the Indian government in international arbitration. The case related to a dispute over a penalty of $1.55 billion slapped by the Indian government on the petrochemical companies for allegedly drawing gas from the Oil and Natural Gas Corporation or ONGC’s (a state-owned oil and gas concern) block in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SEBI was established with the purpose of protecting investors and the development and regulation of capital markets in India. Over the years, it has evolved to meet its objective and has always taken a strong stance against any form of malpractice. However, it is essential that in order to mitigate any future wrongdoing, it penalises defaulters such that cost in fulfilling the punishment supersedes the gain.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On January 1, 2021, the Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI) slapped a fine on the largest company in India by market capitalisation, i.e. Reliance Industries Limited (RIL), and its Chairman and Managing Director Mukesh Ambani of ₹250 million and ₹150 million respectively, along with two other entities, for manipulative trading in the shares of the erstwhile Reliance Petroleum Limited (RPL) in 2007. So, what activity did RIL engage in to receive a penalty from the market regulator?&amp;nbsp; Reliance Petroleum Limited (RPL) was a refinery, partly owned by RIL, which later got merged with the latter in 2009. However, the conglomerate got itself under the radar of the watchdog for the transaction that occurred between the company and its agents in November, 2007, in the cash and futures segment of the secondary market. RIL had decided to sell off its 4.1% stake in RPL. According to SEBI, in order to make undue gains from the sale, the former had entered into an agreement with 12 agents, who booked large short positions of the refinery’s shares in the futures market. Short positions refer to a situation when a trader sells the security first with the intention of repurchasing it later at a lower price, hence the steeper the decline, greater is the profit for the trader. Following this, in the last ten minutes of the trading session of November 29, 2007, RIL sold close to 20 million RPL shares. This large scale selling triggered mass panic and within a moment’s notice, the stock price collapsed.&amp;nbsp; Interestingly, it also happened to be the same day that the futures contracts were meant to pay-out. So, SEBI contends that RIL and the agents colluded together in a bid to make a profit estimated to be around ₹44.7 billion off of this transaction. Selling of securities by promoters in the capital markets in order to raise cash is a widely accepted practice, however, this act of secretive plotting that can distort the natural price discovery system in the market and cheat investors via non-transparent mechanisms is impermissible and against the objectives of the SEBI or any securities regulator. SEBI’s adjudicating officer B J Dilip said, “any manipulation in the volume or price of securities always erodes investor confidence in the market when investors find themselves at the receiving end of market manipulators.” He further added, “In the instant case, the general investors were not aware that the entity behind the above F&amp;amp;O segment transactions was RIL. The execution of the... fraudulent trades affected the price of the RPL securities in both cash and F&amp;amp;O [Futures and Options] segments and harmed the interests of other investors.” The SEBI order states that Mukesh Ambani as the Managing Director of RIL was equally involved in the malpractice. Apart from the conglomerate and its chairman, SEBI also imposed penalties of ₹2 million and ₹1 million on Navi Mumbai SEZ Pvt Ltd and Mumbai SEZ Ltd respectively, both promoted by Anand Jain, a former member of the Reliance Group, for providing margin payments for the agents. In March 2017, the market watchdog had ordered RIL and other entities to disgorge ₹4.47 billion in the RPL’s case, against which the latter appealed in the Securities Appellate Tribunal (SAT). The verdict announced by the tribunal in November 2020 was against the appellant. However, the petrochemicals to telecommunication multinational corporation said that it would appeal against the Tribunal’s ruling in the Indian Supreme Court.&amp;nbsp; This is not the first time that RIL and a government entity were at loggerheads. In 2014, the Indian market regulator had imposed a fine of ₹1.3 million on the corporation for non-disclosure of a key earnings ratio, which would have impacted investors’ evaluation on the shares. In 2018, the RIL-led consortium of BP Plc and Niko Resources won an award against the Indian government in international arbitration. The case related to a dispute over a penalty of $1.55 billion slapped by the Indian government on the petrochemical companies for allegedly drawing gas from the Oil and Natural Gas Corporation or ONGC’s (a state-owned oil and gas concern) block in 2016. SEBI was established with the purpose of protecting investors and the development and regulation of capital markets in India. Over the years, it has evolved to meet its objective and has always taken a strong stance against any form of malpractice. However, it is essential that in order to mitigate any future wrongdoing, it penalises defaulters such that cost in fulfilling the punishment supersedes the gain.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
