<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/business-finance/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-08-11T16:49:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/business-finance/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Vision 20/20</title>
      <link href="/Vision-2020" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vision 20/20" />
      <published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Vision-2020</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Vision-2020">&lt;p&gt;In recent times, when Venture Capitalists (VC) are ruling the startup arena by providing piles of money to any idea that comes through their doors and making them cash burning machines, there are still companies that are keeping it low-key and building ‘cash cows’. Info Edge is one such company. The humble parent of four famous offspring: Naukri, Jeevansathi, Shiksha, and 99acres. From being one of the earliest internet firms in India which made the classifieds appearing in newspapers digital, to being valued at more than $4 billion today, it has come a long way. Sanjeev Bikhchandani founded Naukri, the job search portal, in 1995 when he observed while waiting for an interview that candidates are always circling classifieds in newspapers. Since then there has been no looking back for him. They have expanded into matrimonial (Jeevansathi), housing (99acres), and education (Shiksha) - making its presence in the four most important decisions in any person’s life. What made these startups different from the current startups, which spend so much on customer acquisition that they don’t have enough left for their own survival?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Info Edge, it seems, has mastered the maths of running online classifieds in India. Industry observers attribute this success to the fact that customers don’t pay anything to use these platforms, except for Jeevansathi. From listings of jobs, real estate, and education, the company earns most of its revenue from businesses, advertisements, listing fees, and subscription products. This is in sharp contrast to the likes of OLX and Quikr, where a customer has the option to buy a paid listing, but the vast majority of users don’t pay to have their products listed; consequently, they have also burnt through millions of dollars to acquire new customers. However, Info Edge founders do not believe in this philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The country’s largest employment website, Naukri, boasts about 67 million résumés and currently has 500,000 job listings on its platform. More than 60% of its revenue comes from the fees it charges from employers for access to its huge résumé database. 99acres, another successful venture of the Info Edge brand was founded in 2005 and is also a leader in its category. As of December 31, 2019, the site had total listings of 1,004,378 properties. It competes with Magicbricks, Commonfloor, and Housing. However, between 2013 and 2016, VC funding was abundantly available, triggering a mushrooming of players in the real estate sector. Backed by the likes of NewsCorp, SoftBank, and Tiger Global Management, startups such as Proptiger, Commonfloor, Housing, Quikr, OLX, Indiahomes, and Indiaproperty started giving 99Acres a tough fight. However, 99acres has held its ground. Jeevansathi is the third-largest matrimonial site in India, after Bharat Matrimony and Shaadi. Online spending on the business is likely to grow to ₹11-12 billion by 2023-24 from ₹7-8 billion in 2020-21. This is expected to give a huge boost to Info Edge’s matrimonial website. Shiksha, the portal providing information on careers, examinations, colleges, and courses is facing stiff competition as there are a lot many major players in the EdTech sector. With the likes of Byju’s, it has become tough for Shiksha to make a strong presence in the Indian EdTech sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bikhchandani had seen potential in classifieds websites when there were just around 14,000 internet accounts in the country and a few thousand users comparing that to the around 500 million users in India now, second only to China’s more than 800 million. It became the early mover in the internet economy, taking many essentials online as India’s population started discovering the joys of a virtually connected world. But as an early mover, Bikhchandani knows the downside of the treadmill. He is aware of the need to continuously make innovations in the fast-changing technological world. For that, Info Edge will leverage its advantage of two decades’ worth of data, using artificial intelligence, data analytics, and machine learning to drive informed change through improved user experiences and new products. Also, Info Edge will continue its 12-year-long practice of investing in ‘ideas’ with the ₹1 billion ‘Info Edge Venture Fund’, launched in January, to fund early-stage startups across categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be the first fund by Info Edge, but the company has already invested ₹1.03 billion in 16 startups, including the likes of Zomato and PolicyBazaar. Overall the company has 21 active investments worth ₹1.108 billion at the end of 2020-21. In fact, one of its most successful bets has been restaurant aggregator and food delivery platform Zomato. Bikhchandani, a foodie, had been using Foodiebay (rebranded as Zomato only in 2010). A subsequent conversation with founder Deepinder Goyal set the tone for a business association, and Bikhchandani made an initial investment of ₹40.5 million. Its investment till date is ₹1.52 billion with about 22.7% stake. Zomato has already successfully acquired Uber’s food delivery business in India, Uber Eats. Moreover, PolicyBazaar is expected to receive investment from Google in its bid to expand its digital presence in India. Additionally, the insurance aggregator is also expected to raise $500 million from its Initial Public Offering (IPO) sometime next year. So the prospects of Info Edge cashing out big are right around the corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While making investments, Bikhchandani not only focuses on the business model but also takes into consideration the commitment, capability, and integrity of founders, and good governance. The importance of these qualities can be understood when fiascos like WeWork and Wirecard occur. Of course, some of the newer business models ask for cash burn to gain market share which is not how Bikhchandani runs his companies. He has always advised startups to get ‘customer money’ before ‘investor money’. Maybe some of the larger funds can learn from this strategy instead of blindly burning cash.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Amrit Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In recent times, when Venture Capitalists (VC) are ruling the startup arena by providing piles of money to any idea that comes through their doors and making them cash burning machines, there are still companies that are keeping it low-key and building ‘cash cows’. Info Edge is one such company. The humble parent of four famous offspring: Naukri, Jeevansathi, Shiksha, and 99acres. From being one of the earliest internet firms in India which made the classifieds appearing in newspapers digital, to being valued at more than $4 billion today, it has come a long way. Sanjeev Bikhchandani founded Naukri, the job search portal, in 1995 when he observed while waiting for an interview that candidates are always circling classifieds in newspapers. Since then there has been no looking back for him. They have expanded into matrimonial (Jeevansathi), housing (99acres), and education (Shiksha) - making its presence in the four most important decisions in any person’s life. What made these startups different from the current startups, which spend so much on customer acquisition that they don’t have enough left for their own survival?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">JioMart: The Disruptor?</title>
      <link href="/JioMart" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JioMart: The Disruptor?" />
      <published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/JioMart</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/JioMart">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Don’t find customers for your products, find products for your customers”&lt;/em&gt;, they say, and truly, those who have always thought about their consumers, are the ones whose products have been the most successful. I would not be wrong in saying that the economic development of any country starts and ends with the consumers of that country. Any consumer-related business can rise to great heights if the creators of that business model cater to the needs of the consumers and provide them with efficient services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving along these lines, Mukesh Ambani has now become the fourth richest in the Forbes Global Rich List 2020 as Reliance Industries’ market capitalisation, including the partly paid shares, topped the ₹13 trillion mark. With the recent rise in the e-commerce sector, Reliance Industries has aimed to extend its reach here, which is in contrast with its previous approach wherein they limited themselves to the oil refinery and petroleum sector. To put this in context, we have to take a look at the facts to see why Reliance Industries is where it is today. In the last few years, the launch of Reliance Jio Infocomm Ltd has been able to attract customers even from other rivals such as Vodafone-Idea, Airtel and other telecom operators in India, with its cheap data plans, free calls, and other exciting features. Due to this, it now has the largest user base in India. The launch of Jio was game-changing for India because it redefined the limits of internet usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With its e-commerce platform JioMart, Reliance plans to cause a similar disruption that Jio caused in the telecom sector. The aim is to “completely transform”  India’s unorganised retail market of mostly mom-and-pop stores, which account for nearly 90% of the nation’s retail industry. Through this online-offline model, JioMart won’t sell products to the customers directly but instead, it would link the online buyers with offline retailers in their locality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reliance estimates that through this platform it would be able to link 30 million offline retailers with 200 million households. The digital platform, unlike other foreign competitors, would link producers, traders, small merchants, consumer brands, and consumers under a common shed. Hence, JioMart is a strategically planned holistic model that aims to usher in opportunities not only to Reliance Industries but also to other people directly linked to the same industry. Moreover, at a time when other ventures of Reliance in the grocery segment such as Reliance Retail and Reliance Fresh, which have a strong offline presence over the country, are doing quite well, we can expect this online platform to be a ‘cash cow’ for the giant. To make them completely digitised, JioMart claims to integrate local &lt;em&gt;kirana&lt;/em&gt; (corner) stores and provide them with Points of Sale (PoS) terminals, educate them about inventory management skills, supply chain management, and Goods and Service Tax (GST) compliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analysts and experts are of the view that Facebook’s recent investment in Jio could help JioMart grow. The deal is expected to bear fruits for both the giants. On one side, Jio would gain from the technological expertise that Facebook brings to the table. At the same time, the payments made on the platform through WhatsApp Pay would help the messaging app to overcome the regulatory issues it has been facing. Moreover, Reliance being an already established brand in India would increase the customer base of the Facebook-owned company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to market the online retail platform, Jio has been sending invites to all its users to avail the preliminary discounts. Furthermore, it claims that all its listed products are sold at 5% below the Maximum Retail Price (MRP), this feature is quite similar to DMart’s model that made it quite successful overnight. Additionally, it is still offering the cash-on-delivery option that a lot of existing competitors have stopped. Claims have also been made that JioMart delivers 400,000 orders in a single day which is significantly higher than other grocery home delivery companies. Hence, if JioMart continues working in the same direction, it is bound to give a tough competition to its counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the launch of JioMart, rivals such as Amazon, have started taking steps to maintain their foothold. Amazon has signed a deal with Kishore Biyani’s Future Group to deliver its products. It has also started to broaden the options it provides and has resorted to selective discounting. Amazon has also launched ‘Local Shops’ which has enabled 5,000 offline retailers to set up shop online and has established 10 new warehouses to expand their storage capacity. Additionally, Flipkart said that it would reapply for a food retail license in India. Most importantly, Flipkart has bought Walmart India’s wholesale business in July and is expected to launch a digital marketplace, Flipkart Wholesale in August. So, these already established online platforms have identified the threat being posed by JioMart, and have buckled themselves up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At present, all that we can expect is that with the launch of JioMart, competitive intensity is likely to increase and nothing can be said about who will win the race. Everything is completely dependent upon who would be able to gain the eyes of more consumers and attract them easily with their lucrative offers, but it also seems to be a stiff competition since both JioMart and other established e-commerce websites are leaving no stone unturned. So, whether established e-commerce platforms retain their place or JioMart takes over is what remains to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Cherry Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Don’t find customers for your products, find products for your customers”, they say, and truly, those who have always thought about their consumers, are the ones whose products have been the most successful. I would not be wrong in saying that the economic development of any country starts and ends with the consumers of that country. Any consumer-related business can rise to great heights if the creators of that business model cater to the needs of the consumers and provide them with efficient services.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Elyments: A Step Towards ‘Atma Nirbhar’ Tech</title>
      <link href="/Elyments" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Elyments: A Step Towards ‘Atma Nirbhar’ Tech" />
      <published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Elyments</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Elyments">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Friends, we have been hearing since the last century that the 21st century belongs to India. This is not our dream, rather a responsibility for all of us.”&lt;/em&gt;  These were the words of the Indian Prime Minister when the ‘Atma Nirbhar’ COVID-19 stimulus package was introduced. The PM seems to be determined to make this dream a reality and has successfully commenced India’s venture in the tech world. Indian Vice President Venkaiah Naidu launched India’s first social media app &lt;em&gt;Elyments&lt;/em&gt; on July 5, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After implementing a ban on Chinese apps, the Indian government decided to set its foot in the tech market and secure a powerful position. The app offers various features of video/voice call, instant messaging as well as social networking. It has encouraged the ‘Make in India’ initiative as it employed 1000 Information Technology (IT) professionals who created the app in a very short period. The aim was to boost confidence and faith in the campaign among fellow citizens. It has been downloaded more than 5 million times since its launch which is huge, considering it’s only been a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the app is being known as the “super app” because of the numerous features it has to offer, it does leave us with a few questions to ponder upon. The success is still undetermined and data security is a big concern among the users. Questions were frequently raised regarding data security in the case of Aadhaar and thus, it makes it difficult for us to trust this app as well. The developers have guaranteed safety and assurance that all data will be stored with the Indian servers itself. No data will be transferred to any third party without the user’s consent. A considerable amount of effort has been made just to ensure data safety and that no lapses are being experienced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competition in this field is tough, with tech giants like Facebook and WhatsApp being the rivals. It becomes more important for the government to offer something new to the consumers. It won’t be a cakewalk for Elyments to secure its position as a strong player. The moment it fails to do so, the investments will boil down to zero making it difficult for the government to establish India in the tech space. The success of an app is determined by its active user base, which isn’t much in the case of Elyments. Developers should prioritise maximum sign-ups in the coming days. I feel the government is seriously lacking in the aspect of marketing the product that they have created. Strategising their moves and giving adequate attention to the required areas will definitely help it grow at a steady and smooth pace. Amid the Indo-Sino standoff, Elyments suffered a cyberattack and successfully recovered from it, which shows that it is capable of competing at a global level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these times of COVID-19 pandemic, when the economy is paying a heavy cost due to it, a failed attempt will be faced with major backlash, and people would not hesitate to highlight it as a waste of the taxpayer’s money. Further, this one failure will allow the rivals to regain control, thus making it even more difficult to enter the circle again. On the bright side, if it turns out to be a success, it will boost the economy and open up the gateway to ‘Made in India’ tech. This beginning will ensure a promising future for our young minds and a strong foothold of India in this domain. The vision of Atma Nirbhar Bharat will become a reality and the faith will be restored. Furthermore, there have never been any doubts regarding the brainpower that India possesses in terms of IT. Being the manufacturer of CEOs for tech companies around the world, it is time for India to focus on a homegrown giant and take over the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Friends, we have been hearing since the last century that the 21st century belongs to India. This is not our dream, rather a responsibility for all of us.” These were the words of the Indian Prime Minister when the ‘Atma Nirbhar’ COVID-19 stimulus package was introduced. The PM seems to be determined to make this dream a reality and has successfully commenced India’s venture in the tech world. Indian Vice President Venkaiah Naidu launched India’s first social media app Elyments on July 5, 2020.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Businesses are Flying!</title>
      <link href="/Businesses-are-Flying" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Businesses are Flying!" />
      <published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Businesses-are-Flying</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Businesses-are-Flying">&lt;p&gt;Airports are incredibly complex and challenging businesses but, in many cases, they are businesses that make money. Many airports are owned by the government but still, they are often operated as businesses – just businesses that are publicly owned. The majority of airports make their money through what they earn from passenger-carrying commercial flights using their facilities. Some airports are cargo focused and fund their operation through cargo flights but airports such as Paris’s Charles De Gaulle Airport and London’s Heathrow Airport rely almost entirely on passenger flights. While the amount of cargo going through these airports is significant, the number of dedicated cargo flights is low in proportion to the airport’s daily flights. The question is: how do they generate profits and what goes on behind the scenes that enable them to run their operations effectively and, at the same time, efficiently? For this study, I am going to be looking at the most famous airport in the world – the London Heathrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heathrow makes its money off of the 78 million passengers flying through each year. Heathrow is the busiest airport in the world that is fully privately owned - the UK government owns no stake in it and so it is perhaps the best example of an airport built to turn a profit. It costs $1,485,650,000 per year to run Heathrow airport. This includes costs like $494,000,000, which Heathrow pays in salaries to its 6,500 employees. Almost 76,000 people actually work at Heathrow but only those 6,500 actually work for Heathrow. The company that runs Heathrow, Heathrow Airport Holdings, is only responsible for the oversight and administration of the airport, within Heathrow’s walls though, there are hundreds of other companies operating. Those 70,000 other people work for the airlines, the baggage handling companies, the air traffic control company, the restaurants, the rental car companies, the bus company, and all the other different employers at the airport. There are, of course, plenty of other costs involved in running the airport from the $232 million dollars per year in maintenance to the $113 million yearly utility bill for water, electricity, internet, gas, and more. But overall that number of $1.5 billion is what it costs to run the sixth busiest airport in the world. That’s more than it costs to run the entire 1.3 million people country of Swaziland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a per passenger basis, it costs approximately $19 to run the Heathrow. Essentially that means Heathrow needs to make $19 from each passenger that passes through its doors in order to break even. Obviously, some passengers are more profitable than others. Arriving passengers generally just get off the plane, go through customs, and leave immediately without making any purchases. Whereas, connecting and departing passengers generally have more time to shop at the airport. Retail is incredibly important to the profitability of any airport. This is part of the reason why it’s in the airport’s best interest to make the security and check-in procedure as quickly as possible so the passengers have more time to shop. Heathrow makes money through retail by taking a cut out of every sale made. On average, through restaurants the airport earns 95 cents per passenger, retail stores earn them $5.15 per passenger, the parking lots add to another $2.03, then all the other smaller sources of retail revenue such as rental car companies and VIP lounges account for another $3.04. Rather uniquely, Heathrow also operates the express train from the airport to Paddington Station which makes them another $2.15 per passenger. All in all, the airport makes $13.32 from passengers through purchases on top of their actual airplane ticket, and it’s worth pointing out that this doesn’t mean that passengers spend $13.32 - this means that Heathrow makes $13.32 per passenger. This is their cut, the actual spending at the airport per passenger is much higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you may think that this amount of retail revenue per passenger is high and you would be right, it is. In fact, it’s one of the highest retail revenues per passenger of any airport worldwide. In comparison, Washington Dulles Airport makes $5.68 per passenger, Auckland Airport makes $7.71, and Paris’ Charles De Gaulle Airport makes $10.92 per passenger from retail. Heathrow is an expert in making passengers spend. They use all sorts of tricks and tactics to increase passenger spending. For example, in Terminal 3, to get from security and to all the gates, all passengers have to walk through duty-free which increases sales enormously. Heathrow also doesn’t display the gate for flights until 45-90 minutes before departure. Because of this, passengers wait in a central area where all the shops and restaurants are located. Being one of the very few airports with non-stop service to all six continents, Heathrow also has the advantage of being an airport focused on long-haul service. These flights tend to carry the wealthiest passengers and while, worldwide, passengers arrive at an average of 2 hours and 17 minutes before their flight, Heathrow passengers arrive 2 hours and 51 minutes before. This means they have more time to shop at the airport. As mentioned, though the airport needs to make $19 per passenger but retail only earns them just over $13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of it comes from flights. Each plane that lands at Heathrow pays the airport an average of $9,500. That goes to paying for things like gate space, a check-in area, and the runway time itself. On departure, airlines are charged again, this time per passenger. For each passenger flying to a destination outside of Europe, the airline is charged a base of $58 but this charge is reduced to $44 if a passenger connects through Heathrow rather than originating or to $39 if the aircraft is parked at a remote stand rather than a gate. It’s worth noting that these are the published prices. In reality, many airlines with a significant number of flights at Heathrow have an agreement with the airport that reduces their costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaking it down, what those numbers mean is that Heathrow gets, on average, $29 of the cost of every passenger’s ticket. As you can see that means that Heathrow makes a fair bit more than it costs to run the airport. The company mostly uses this operating profit to pay off debt from prior projects and to pay taxes so, in the end, they are only truly making about $8.20 off of each of their passengers, but what these numbers also mean is that, by design, Heathrow is incentivised to attract long-haul flights. The airport is currently at capacity. Their maximum number of flights per day is 657, and they currently have 650. They really have no more capacity which means one of the only ways for them to grow financially is to bring in larger planes. This is no doubt that part of the reason why Heathrow is so poorly connected to the country is that it is in the UK. The airport only has flights to eight airports in the UK which means the airport has exactly the same number of destinations in the UK as it has in China. The reality is that Heathrow is a commercial company while most UK residents would likely want to see domestic flights to their largest airport, it just doesn’t make commercial sense to operate short and cheap flights. It’s not only less lucrative for the airport, but it’s also more costly for the passenger than flying to other smaller airports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, not every airport is like Heathrow. Not every airport is a commercial company, and that’s just because, in many cases, running an airport the way the public wants it to be run is bad business. About two-thirds of all airports worldwide lose money. In many cases that’s because they are government-run and just not that focused on making money. However, the entire focus of the authorities should not be on making the airports profitable. Because of the fact that ultimately, it’s the passengers who would be paying more for their travel and this would cause less travel and mobility, thus, hindering opportunities for people and lesser growth opportunity for the airport itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Airports are incredibly complex and challenging businesses but, in many cases, they are businesses that make money. Many airports are owned by the government but still, they are often operated as businesses – just businesses that are publicly owned. The majority of airports make their money through what they earn from passenger-carrying commercial flights using their facilities. Some airports are cargo focused and fund their operation through cargo flights but airports such as Paris’s Charles De Gaulle Airport and London’s Heathrow Airport rely almost entirely on passenger flights. While the amount of cargo going through these airports is significant, the number of dedicated cargo flights is low in proportion to the airport’s daily flights. The question is: how do they generate profits and what goes on behind the scenes that enable them to run their operations effectively and, at the same time, efficiently? For this study, I am going to be looking at the most famous airport in the world – the London Heathrow.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Icarus Paradox: Why Successful Ventures Fail?</title>
      <link href="/Icarus-Paradox" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Icarus Paradox: Why Successful Ventures Fail?" />
      <published>2020-08-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Icarus-Paradox</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Icarus-Paradox">&lt;p&gt;Though most people deem pride as transgression, some appraise it as a trait that can be capitalised upon. Research teams at the University of Montreal and UC Santa Barbara’s Center for Evolutionary Psychology (CEP) suggest that pride is an evolutionary by-product of the trait of self-preservation. Because of the frequent lethal reversals that our ancestors faced, they needed their fellow band members to value them enough during hardships to pull them through. Therefore, in making choices, humans had to weigh their self-interest over the approval of others, so that when they needed help, others would value them enough to give it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though we have come a long way, &lt;em&gt;hubris&lt;/em&gt; is still not hard to come across. Irrespective of the peculiarity of its radix, pride is not limited to individuals - organisations also emanate it. The anomaly, however, is that organisational hubris is just a compendium of the egos of individuals who comprise it, but people in an organisation struggle to keep their individual pride in parity with the organisational one. Therefore, in theory, there is no comprehensible line distinguishing individual pride from organisational pride, as one is a concoction of the other. The practical aspect, however, differentiates between the magnitude and gravity of the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vanity is believed to be the root of all sin by cultures across the globe. While the widely followed Abrahamic religions talk about the spiritual descent of Lucifer into Satan as a result of his pride, the Greeks present the tale of Icarus. Icarus was the son of Daedalus - a famous Greek inventor. While in captivity, Daedalus crafted two pairs of wings which would enable him and his son to escape certain execution. Before taking off, Daedalus specifically instructed his son not to fly too high. Ignoring the words of his father, Icarus soared too near to the clouds, which ultimately led to his wings failing him. The boy plummeted to his death in the sea because his pride clouded his judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Danny Miller coined the term ‘Icarus Paradox’ in 1990. The term, alluding to the Greek tale, refers to the phenomenon of businesses suddenly failing after a period of success, where this failure is brought about by the very elements that led to their initial uprise. Miller noted that it’s the victories of the past that conceit a successful organisation, lulling them into complacency. The very values that usher companies upwards in the pecking order - such as tried-and-true business strategies, dauntless and self-assured management, and the overall combination of all these elements - may be rendered blunt and platitudinous, ultimately leading to business catastrophes. Managers tend to make injudicious decisions, as they cling onto the past success of their manoeuvres and fail to factor in the revamp in the external business environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most successful firms owe their fortune to a unique competitive algorithm which guides the formulation and execution of their policies. It helps it gain momentum and reach a higher pedestal, but cloaks its dynamism and its ability to acclimatise because the management’s confidence in this winning formula is bolstered. Eventually, the firm ends up focusing only on refining and extending these strategies, products and values. Activities/policies that do not conform to the paradigm are neglected or even discouraged. This may be profitable in the short run as companies continue to specialise and improve in a certain product or strategy, leading to higher efficiency, sales and growth as they develop a competitive advantage in a particular area. However, its viability is leached away in the long run, as the stereotypical aspect ingrained in their corporate culture barres them from keeping up with the threats of new competitors, changing consumer demands, newly developed business models and changes in the external environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Standard economic theory explains the high rate of failures as an inevitable result of companies taking rational risks in the face of peaky situations. The rewards of a few successes outweigh losses incurred from many failures in the long run. Executives know this and accept the risk. Anyhow, this theory absolves them from blame as they simply obey rationality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lovallo and Kahneman from the &lt;em&gt;Harvard Business Review&lt;/em&gt;, however, argue that most failures are actually the results of flawed decision making. While predicting the outcomes of potentially risky projects, executives easily fall victim to what psychologists call the ‘planning fallacy’. They make decisions based on delusional optimism instead of rational computation of gains, losses, and probabilities, dwelling in situations of hypothetical success while overlooking potential problems. Consequently, they are overly optimistic and pursue opportunities that are unlikely to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A prime example of the paradox at work would be Tesco’s experimental venture into the US market – Fresh &amp;amp; Easy. Tesco opened the chain in 2007- right before the economic recession which took a severe toll on consumer spending. Tesco also did not anticipate the upshot in the popularity of online grocery shopping. Additionally, Tesco’s research segment misconstrued the spending habits of their consumer base. While their Metro stores in the UK were popular, there was not enough demand in the US as the population was not accustomed to grab-and-go meals. Most of the Americans would usually order take out or cook their own meals - as purchasing such meals would be comparatively costlier than grocery shopping. Lastly, an elementary point of distinction was the statistics indicating that most people in the US buy their groceries once a week, with bulk and diversity of purchase being the key takeaways. Conversely, Europeans tend to make more frequent, but smaller trips to the grocery stores. After they took a hit of approximately £1.2bn ($1.8bn), Tesco’s net profit slithered down by 96%, compelling them to abandon the US market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, Tesco’s confidence in bringing its successful concept of ready meals to the US market contributed heavily to its failure. The intensive marketing required to change people’s daily consumption proclivities takes time and money, neither of which Tesco invested enough of. Tesco was also confident enough to continue to hang on for over 5 years despite indications of possible failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above example highlights &lt;em&gt;hubris&lt;/em&gt; in its raw essence, which can be used as a base for conceptual bifurcation, creating multiple subdivisions rooted in the same basic concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Humans have a natural tendency to amplify their own talents, which leads a lot of executives to believe that they transcend the rest in ability and output. This is further reinforced by the tendency to misperceive causes of certain events and attribute success to their abilities when it might have been out of pure luck.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People also display keenness to take credit for positive outcomes and ascribe undesirable ones to external factors. A study of letters to shareholders in annual reports, for example, found that managers tend to attribute favourable outcomes to variables under their control, like corporate strategy or R&amp;amp;D (research and development) programs, while inimical ones were more likely to be attributed to uncontrollable external factors like the weather or inflation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A company’s values unify its people. Strong, meaningful credos can help inculcate employee loyalty, strengthen the bonds between a company and its customers, attract like-minded partners, and hold together a company’s far-flung operations. However, as companies mature, these values may morph into commandments- which contribute more towards suppressing novelty and flexibility, rather than inspiring moral conduct.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A peculiar observation made in business process analysis is that, as more investment is made in information technology, worker productivity may go down instead of going up. This observation has been firmly supported by empirical evidence from the 1970’s to the early 1990’s. Prior to the upward jolt in IT investment, the expected return on investment in terms of productivity was 3-4%. The aberration, however, was that with IT, the normal return on investment was only 1% from the 1970’s to the early 1990’s. Thus, the investment in IT - done for performance enhancement - led to contradictory outcomes that threatened to pick the organisation apart. This is known as the ‘paradox of information technology’- a concept encapsulated by the Icarus paradox.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it may seem easy to deal with, the paradox is a trap that is too hard to escape, with companies like Lehman Brothers, Xerox, Atari, Digital Equipment, Tupperware and Revlon on the victim list. Also, a lot of unforeseen complications arise upon the initial implementation of solutions. The key is an optimum blend of flexibility, innovation, and diversification, which needs to be instilled in the bedrock of the organisational structure of business entities.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aryaman Dhiman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Though most people deem pride as transgression, some appraise it as a trait that can be capitalised upon. Research teams at the University of Montreal and UC Santa Barbara’s Center for Evolutionary Psychology (CEP) suggest that pride is an evolutionary by-product of the trait of self-preservation. Because of the frequent lethal reversals that our ancestors faced, they needed their fellow band members to value them enough during hardships to pull them through. Therefore, in making choices, humans had to weigh their self-interest over the approval of others, so that when they needed help, others would value them enough to give it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Online Delivery: Adjusting to The New Normal</title>
      <link href="/Online-Delivery" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Online Delivery: Adjusting to The New Normal" />
      <published>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Online-Delivery</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Online-Delivery">&lt;p&gt;Imagine the times when in-store aisles were optimised for foot traffic and retail therapy, featuring better product discovery, impulse purchases and time spent in-store. The coronavirus pandemic has changed that almost overnight. Six months ago, on-demand home delivery was far from mainstream - a luxury for those willing to pay extra for delivery services and convenience, skewing towards young professionals in big cities. Now everyone is willing to order everything from household staples to ice cream on-demand. Stores, which were struggling for customer growth and retention are scrambling for more fulfilment capacity. Demand boom, which the experts believe is likely to persist even after the pandemic ends, makes it worthwhile to analyse the future of online marketplaces, and what opportunities this brings for the suppliers, the consumers, and the platform itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This market inversion has led to a growth of online delivery marketplaces, with even bigger market players in other segments pivoting their business strategies around home delivery. Delivery service marketplaces have inverted from demand-constrained to supply-constrained almost overnight, but new entrants in the delivery space have reportedly struggled with profits, reporting a boost in sales but thin margins. They claim that it is not terribly profitable, and it probably gets unprofitable with more orders. While many restaurants and supermarkets prefer the lower costs and hassle of having customers collect orders at stores, others see it as a threat to their existing customer relationships that could have been better taken care of, had the customers walked into the store. Online delivery was never a core part of these supplier’s revenue and made up only a small chunk of the total orders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issues and challenges that marketplaces face today are logistical and reputational, arising from increased demand and customer awareness rather than challenges arising from low consumer penetration and slim demand for services. Consumers are holding brands and companies to a higher standard than previously, favouring those perceived as doing more for society. Pre-crisis, a common complaint on the platforms was that drivers weren’t receiving enough orders. Now, those same drivers are overwhelmed with demand, and platforms have to figure out how to build product solutions to help stores balance their delivery loads. There have been inventory stockouts, closed stores, and supply chain disruptions due to COVID-19 — all while the customer service team has been inundated with order volume. That’s consistent with the experience of all mid-sized delivery platforms, and even that of Amazon. These platforms have had to switch their focus overnight and develop expertise around the new supply-side constraints. The bigger problem here is that many suppliers didn’t have the infrastructure set up to make delivery work at scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among all vociferous trumpets about ‘the demise of commuting’, ‘the death of retail’, and ‘the collapse of globalisation’, many executives have come to assume that everything will change accordingly when the recipe for survival is supposed to be a thorough transformation. The economic crisis does not necessarily spell the end of entire industries or companies but it does weed out business models that fail to pivot towards the new reality characterised by shorter value chains, remote work, social distancing, consumer introspection, and enhanced usage of technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, now is the time for marketplaces to help their suppliers invest in infrastructure and technology, and indulge in business practices that will enable them to compete in a world in which having a delivery sales presence is essential. Now is the time for them to shift their focus from customer acquisition and retention to investment in metrics for supporting retailer operations. Platforms can be a part of the supplier side transition which, in fact, is happening organically. With in-person retail restricted or outright eliminated, suppliers have been reimagining their store layouts and operations around online fulfilment and omnichannel retail, simultaneously leveraging marketplace platforms, a self-managed online presence, and traditional in-person sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can identify and share best practices around staffing and delivery processes, and provide technology solutions to help small businesses optimise their operations around delivery, with, for example, cloud-based inventory logs and modern point-of-sale systems. Marketplace platforms have vision into the whole market, which enables them to predict demand — an advantage they should use to the benefit of their suppliers. This could be helpful in forecasting when to schedule extra drivers on an hour-by-hour basis, and staffing driver teams in direct proportion to order volume. This can also increase capital efficiency by helping stores match inventory levels to predict future demand. Platforms can lower their tax rates to increase supplier participation — especially among chains and other established supplier networks. Food delivery marketplaces’ supplier-weighted cost structure may have worked when restaurants saw having a small stream of delivery orders as a promotional subsidy for in-person traffic — but it isn’t working in the current, in-person demand constrained marketplace environment. Likewise, some fees should be shifted over to the consumers, since they’re now the ‘long’ side of the market. In particular, it might make sense to institute per-order delivery fees, to encourage consumers to place large delivery orders instead of more frequent small ones, as well as to make it more valuable for a retailer to take an additional order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before COVID-19, a delivery service’s performance was mostly determined by convenience, speed and price. Now, by contrast, safety, availability and breadth of selection are the new priorities. Customers are placing bigger orders and are comfortable with longer lead times with ‘acceptable’ estimated time of arrival windows widening. Platforms also have the leeway to shift customer service efforts to prioritise responsiveness to retailers and allocate developer resources towards solving suppliers’ operational problems. All these solutions will help keep in place, exactly the right products on the supplier’s shelves. These improvements will benefit both parties but would require information sharing and communication on the part of the platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When suppliers make the best or most effective use of marketplace transactions, the consumer experience on the platform improves too — often due to increased availability, selection and price options. Overall, this results in much higher conversion rates: a customer with three stores and 1,000 items to choose from spends 67% more per session than a customer facing just one store with 300 items. Orders are processed more smoothly, and with fewer errors that will help translate fleeting customer relations into stronger consumer engagement post-crisis. Better and more optimised choices lead to more bargaining power in the hands of the customers, thereby increasing satisfaction and chances of application reuse. Bars and restaurants will eventually reopen and consumers will become comfortable shopping for goods in-person again but the supplier networks that marketplace platforms build will remain. When platforms invest in suppliers as partners, those suppliers will come out of the crisis stronger, improving the customer experience in the long run. It’s a three-way win — for suppliers, platforms and consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As worried consumers move to shop more online, choosing online platforms is an easy decision — with a click of the button, they can buy almost anything. But for sellers, doing business with them is a less straightforward proposition. Although partnering opens up access to more customers and offers operational efficiencies, brands risk leveraging power in favour of the platforms. Thus, they face an unavoidable dilemma — form the partnership and risk ceding profits, or eschew the partnership and forgo the operational cost savings and access to new customers. A big threat to these established brands is consumers’ increased willingness to experiment with different offerings during the crisis. Research suggests that consumers react badly even when the bad news extends beyond the company to its supply chain. They are more likely to believe that a company’s product is inferior in quality when there is a supply chain mishap, even when the product quality has nothing to do with the supply chain problem. They assume a product has decreased in quality whether the supply chain problems are related to an economic issue (like consistently low profits), a social issue (like racial discrimination in the hiring process), or an environmental issue (like polluting). Brands must, therefore, realise that pivots must be a lateral extension of the firm’s existing capabilities, cementing — not undermining — its strategic intent.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Mehul Goyal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Imagine the times when in-store aisles were optimised for foot traffic and retail therapy, featuring better product discovery, impulse purchases and time spent in-store. The coronavirus pandemic has changed that almost overnight. Six months ago, on-demand home delivery was far from mainstream - a luxury for those willing to pay extra for delivery services and convenience, skewing towards young professionals in big cities. Now everyone is willing to order everything from household staples to ice cream on-demand. Stores, which were struggling for customer growth and retention are scrambling for more fulfilment capacity. Demand boom, which the experts believe is likely to persist even after the pandemic ends, makes it worthwhile to analyse the future of online marketplaces, and what opportunities this brings for the suppliers, the consumers, and the platform itself.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lost Vision: The Many Failures of Masayoshi Son</title>
      <link href="/Lost-Vision" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lost Vision: The Many Failures of Masayoshi Son" />
      <published>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Lost-Vision</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lost-Vision">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;45 minutes, $45 billion, $1 billion per minute&lt;/em&gt;”, this is how SoftBank’s Chief Executive Officer Masayoshi Son, described his meeting with Saudi Arabia’s Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman. After this meeting, the Public Investment Fund of Saudi Arabia (PIF) became the largest investor in SoftBank’s outrageous $93 billion technology investment fund, the Vision Fund. This fund was unlike any other fund that anyone had ever seen before - &lt;em&gt;bigger, bolder, and better&lt;/em&gt;. The CEO’s exuberance was even highlighted in the size of the fund which was introduced. With this particular fund, Son wanted to make a presence in tech companies working in artificial intelligence, robotics and the Internet of Things. The fund did fulfil its purpose by giving the company a major share in some of the world’s ‘up and coming’ startups like OYO, Paytm, WeWork, Didi, Uber, Ola, Flipkart, along with 83 others. However, at what cost?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masayoshi Son has always been famous for his gut-led investment style, and it seems that he invests in people rather than in companies. One such person in whom Son invested was Alibaba founder, Jack Ma. Son himself said that Ma had no business plan, but he had “strong eyes”. However unconventional that might sound, it did turn out to be the most profitable investment of SoftBank till date. The investment in Alibaba, $20 million in 2000, turned into $60 billion when the company went public in September 2014. Masa expects every person in whom he invests to become the next Jack Ma. This strategy seemed to be working for the company as it reported a 62% return in the mid of 2019, after making 71 investments for a total of $64.2 billion, and the ride was supposed to be smooth from this point. On the flip side, the company has started facing hurdles and the return on the fund is negative 6%, compared with 62% just a year ago. The fund has lost more for the company than it has earned for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Son’s weakness for charismatic and flashy founders led him to invest in WeWork’s Adam Neumann. Through a combination of glamour and millennial charm, Adam was able to sell WeWrok to Son. It wasn’t even a tech company. Although Son was impressed, the company failed to impress financial analysts. People couldn’t understand the business model of WeWork and were reluctant to invest in it. Even after these speculations, the company decided to go public and as a result of this, their valuation came down to $3 billion from $47 billion in just a year. WeWork’s struggling finances, huge losses, hard-partying culture, and the CEO’s antics sank the ship. Eventually, SoftBank had to step in and buy the company. It came up with a $9.5 billion ‘rescue package’ and took over 80% of the shares. This takeover added dead weight to the company’s balance sheet as the onus to make the real estate firm profitable lay on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another such investment that might come to haunt SoftBank in the near future would be OYO. Son invested $1.5 billion in the company and asked the 26-year old founder, Ritesh Agarwal, to make it the world’s largest hotel operator by room count. The business model that worked so well in India wasn’t an obvious fit for the US and European markets, which already had well established, quality hotel chains. In a hasty attempt to expand outside India, OYO faced many logistical and technological challenges. These included double booking of rooms, failing to keep track of the keys, and reducing the rent of the landlords to mere pennies and taking days to fix these glitches. All these failures left the consumers as well as the vendors highly unsatisfied. OYO’s figures haven’t been impressive either, the company had revenue of $951 million for the fiscal year ending in March 2019, while losses surged six-fold to $335 million year-on-year. Furthermore, the young founder has further borrowed $2 billion, to buy out some investors. The loan has been personally guaranteed by Son, in a bizarre deal. The cash-pumping strategy has hampered the company’s natural course and put it on a path to become what many experts believe ‘the next WeWork’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the ongoing pandemic, tech companies have faced the most brutal brunt of the lockdowns across the globe. These unicorns have had to let go of people, lose consumers and face burgeoning costs. Uber, another major investment of SoftBank, has been one of the hardest hit. It had merely recovered from the saga of its poor-performing IPO that it had to face the impact of the virus. This has further added to the tensions of the Son-led company. The current scenario has dimmed the hopes of the CEO who was hoping for a $108 billion Vision Fund part-two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to tackle the mounting problems, the company has had to sell shares in Alibaba, its most valuable holding, to raise $11.5 billion. SoftBank is also likely to sell stock in its Japanese telecom unit SoftBank Corp and T-Mobile US Inc. Furthermore, the Japanese company also plans to spend up to ¥500 billion to buy back shares through March 2021, on top of an existing repurchase plan of the same size. That has helped to stabilise SoftBank shares giving them a boost of more than 75% from their low in March. The massive buyback remains the only good news for the shares. The company did not announce any dividend for the first time in its history this year and it has no plans to announce one next year as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separately, SoftBank said Jack Ma will step down as a director. Additionally, three new directors have been nominated. Son’s increasingly risky bets over the past few years coincided with departures from its board of some of its most outspoken members. With no famous outside directors left on SoftBank’s board, it’s not clear who is going to hold Son responsible anymore. It remains to be seen how that bodes for the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Undoubtedly, the Vision Fund has made massive losses for the company, it can still be argued that Masayoshi Son has faced worse after he made $70 billion in losses after the dot-com bubble burst and bounced back even stronger. However, to ensure that there is a comeback this time as well, the company needs to make some strategic changes. Instead of investing huge sums of money in these startups in their early stages and making them cash-burning machineries, they should let them grow according to their organic speed. The kind of ‘growth at all costs’ that comes with an asterisk with such large investments is what ruins a good company with a good business plan. Moreover, focussing on profitability rather than on growth solely would help in making the situation better for the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesson to learn here is that money can’t always buy success. The cheques that Son was blindly cutting for the companies were harming them more than they were helping. He was actually creating bigger and bigger bubbles, which came back to burst right in his face. Although, the enthusiastic CEO has reiterated several times during the past few months that he has learnt his lesson. It remains to be seen as to what he actually does to turn the situation around. Maybe, his self-confidence and stubbornness will help the company after all.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Amrit Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“45 minutes, $45 billion, $1 billion per minute”, this is how SoftBank’s Chief Executive Officer Masayoshi Son, described his meeting with Saudi Arabia’s Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman. After this meeting, the Public Investment Fund of Saudi Arabia (PIF) became the largest investor in SoftBank’s outrageous $93 billion technology investment fund, the Vision Fund. This fund was unlike any other fund that anyone had ever seen before - bigger, bolder, and better. The CEO’s exuberance was even highlighted in the size of the fund which was introduced. With this particular fund, Son wanted to make a presence in tech companies working in artificial intelligence, robotics and the Internet of Things. The fund did fulfil its purpose by giving the company a major share in some of the world’s ‘up and coming’ startups like OYO, Paytm, WeWork, Didi, Uber, Ola, Flipkart, along with 83 others. However, at what cost?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why are Gold Prices Soaring in the Midst of a Pandemic?</title>
      <link href="/Why-are-Gold-Prices-Soaring-in-the-Midst-of-a-Pandemic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why are Gold Prices Soaring in the Midst of a Pandemic?" />
      <published>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-are-Gold-Prices-Soaring-in-the-Midst-of-a-Pandemic</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-are-Gold-Prices-Soaring-in-the-Midst-of-a-Pandemic">&lt;p&gt;Want to invest your money and you are neither an equity person nor a mutual fund person and interest on fixed deposits is too low for you, what should you do? Of course, you should go and buy gold! Most people buy gold for making jewellery. It is also a place of investment for many. The precious metal has long been used by investors to hedge themselves against inflation. Considered a safe haven by those who don’t want to risk their savings in the stock market, it has always given positive returns to investors. Losing in the glittery metal market is far less likely but in the midst of a pandemic, every sort of investment seems to be too ‘dangerous’, so why are people still buying gold?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever there has been any economic crisis, people tend to stay away from the stock market because market crashes are highly unpredictable. We all know about the 2007-08 financial crisis, and how in every country there was reluctance in investing in the stock market. However, people who still had savings went right to the commodity exchange and bought gold. This was clearly visible from the fact that the rally in gold continued from 2007 to 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what we are witnessing in this current scenario with the coronavirus spreading all over the world and lockdown of economies leading to bankruptcy for many companies, people are pulling out their money from stocks and other financial instruments and buying bullion to park their money in safe investments. Exchange-Traded Funds (ETFs) have been piling up on gold reserves as well, which has more than made up for the domestic lack of demand. Demand for gold comes from another significant set of investors who tend to invest in real estate. The sector itself being in limbo due to the pandemic has forced such investors to invest in the yellow metal. Additionally, the metal is benefitting from the ultra-loose monetary policies being pursued by bankers and expectation that such a stance will tend to continue in the long run. Rising fiscal deficits and increasing debts are also contributing to the rising shift to gold. The fiscal policies adopted and the printing of more currency have led to inflation and have been the contributing factors in the current rally in gold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, central banks around the globe are regularly keeping a check on the economy and are providing liquidity. During the past few months, central banks too, have been buying gold and increasing their gold reserves in order to face any unforeseen circumstances. Central banks of China, Russia and India were the biggest buyers of gold in 2019, and many countries are still adding more to their coffers. This rally is expected to continue until we see any stability in the stock market and people feel safe to buy stocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gold prices have gone through the ceiling in the past few weeks and every banker has his/her own perception regarding the future price movement. All in all, it remains to be seen whether gold prices will continue to rise, or will gold lose its steam. However, the metal has yet again proven its mettle in trying times, when every other investment fails to provide returns, it keeps its investors happy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rachit Kumar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Want to invest your money and you are neither an equity person nor a mutual fund person and interest on fixed deposits is too low for you, what should you do? Of course, you should go and buy gold! Most people buy gold for making jewellery. It is also a place of investment for many. The precious metal has long been used by investors to hedge themselves against inflation. Considered a safe haven by those who don’t want to risk their savings in the stock market, it has always given positive returns to investors. Losing in the glittery metal market is far less likely but in the midst of a pandemic, every sort of investment seems to be too ‘dangerous’, so why are people still buying gold?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">When The Faithful Prince Backfired!</title>
      <link href="/When-The-Faithful-Prince-Backfired" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When The Faithful Prince Backfired!" />
      <published>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/When-The-Faithful-Prince-Backfired</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/When-The-Faithful-Prince-Backfired">&lt;p&gt;Remember, four years ago when the entire business world was shocked to hear the allegations made against the ‘not so clean’ Tata &amp;amp; Sons? In today’s highly competitive and capitalistic world, where business rivalry is a routine affair among the giants, there are a few players who prefer to keep it clean. The Tata group is one of them and has maintained its reputation as one of the most honest corporate entities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ratan Tata, former Chairman of the Tata group is one of the most powerful businessmen in India and one of the most influential in the world. He owns less than 1% of the assets of the group in his own name. He ended up being in the headlines related to a controversy. It all started after the Tata group appointed Cyrus Mistry as the 6th Chairman of Tata Sons in 2012. He had been on the board of Tata Sons since August 2006. Mistry is the son of Pallonji Mistry who was the owner of Shapoorji Pallonji Group till 2012 (presently headed by Shapoor Mistry). The Mistrys are the largest individual shareholders in Tata Sons with 18.4%, which is equally divided between the two sons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On October 24, 2016, Mistry was removed from his post as the Chairman during a board meeting. According to sources, Mr Tata gave him a chance to resign voluntarily, which Mistry denied. The severity of bitterness among the two was made obvious after he was ousted from all the other boards as well. At that point in time, the Mistrys were crippled and the future course was unknown. Ratan Tata was reinstated as the Interim Chairman for about four months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tata Sons stated that a trust deficit with Cyrus Mistry was the major reason for his removal. They also claimed that the members of the board had lost their confidence in Mistry and thus took a collective decision to replace him as the Chairman. On the other hand, Mistry claimed the removal to be illegal and a staged coup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since no concrete reasoning has been given out for the removal, many possible reasons have been floating across. Legacy problems within the Tata group, and differences between Mr Tata and Mr Mistry are also seen as the alleged reasons for Cyrus being ousted. Additionally, Mistry wanted to get rid of certain ventures which proved to be unsuccessful. These included Tata Steel’s European business, Tata Nano, and telecoms. Mr Tata refused these advances and these led to certain conflicts. Mistry made some decisions without consulting the board and Ratan Tata himself. Unsurprisingly, these decisions were not well received by all. Tata group also suffered some losses under Mistry’s reign. At times, he even overlooked the existing ventures and was prioritising new businesses. This was not acceptable to Mr Tata as the existing ventures had some emotional sentiment attached to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mistry filed a case against the Tata Sons with the National Company Law Tribunal (NCLT) in December 2016. He stated that even after 8 weeks, he does not have any concrete reason backing the move, and hence he chose to go the legal way. This whole situation has adversely affected the position of the Pallonjis as a minority shareholder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mistry’s challenge was turned down by the NCLT. After this, he went to the National Company Law Appellate Tribunal (NCLAT) in regard to the NCLT dismissal. His appeal with the tribunal was admitted in August 2018. The appeal was restored later and judgment was passed by the NCLAT in December 2019. The judgment and order reinstated Mistry as the Chairman of Tata Sons and restored his position on all the boards. This order was challenged by the Tata Son’s in the Indian Supreme Court. The Supreme Court put a stay order on the NCLAT’s judgment after it refused to modify the same. Even after various hearings, both the parties are nowhere near satisfied and the conflict is ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tata Sons did what they felt was needed for the group’s benefit. This move was not well reasoned by them and the consequences being faced are dreadful. Even the Mistrys are facing uncertainty at their end! This move has not only defamed Cyrus Mistry but has also raised questions on Tata’s working and management. Even though the NCLAT’s judgment was in Mistry’s favour, he believes it’s not enough. His demands for rights in a corporate democracy for a minority shareholder still remain untackled! This forces us to think more about shareholders and how authority should be controlled within the working of business houses in order to maintain the ideals of corporate democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t believe that majority dominance should play a role in the business culture. Decisions being taken affect all the investors equally and thus their approval should be necessary. A democratic process that includes debate and deliberation regarding every big step should be given importance. In this particular feud, both sides had made similar mistakes of taking decisions on an individual level. Be it Cyrus taking company matters and policies in his own hands or Mr Tata scrapping his ideas and at last ousting him without justification. These examples prove how seniority plays an important role in corporate functioning. This also means that views and opinions of other board members who are usually the minority shareholders are negated or delegitimised. Power dynamics need to be minimised in order to protect minority rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interests of a company should be prioritised while taking crucial decisions. Is it safe to assume that all minority shareholders genuinely care about the company as a whole? Personal interests and gains have always been prioritised by individuals. Keeping this in mind, it is important to make sure these rights are not misused and the interests of a company are always taken care of. Does this justify the ousting of Mistry? Oops! We ended up being in a dilemma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These situations are not favourable to any of the parties involved but they do unfold the power play within corporate houses. The Tata group which was known for its values and ideals is facing severe repercussions. It is time to rethink and stand up for minority rights not only within national boundaries but also within the corporate world and make sure they are not tampered with. The ambiguity of this whole situation can be sensed in every article present in my search history and thus it makes it difficult to land upon a conclusion which satisfies all the parties involved.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Remember, four years ago when the entire business world was shocked to hear the allegations made against the ‘not so clean’ Tata &amp;amp; Sons? In today’s highly competitive and capitalistic world, where business rivalry is a routine affair among the giants, there are a few players who prefer to keep it clean. The Tata group is one of them and has maintained its reputation as one of the most honest corporate entities.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Green Bonds: A New Revolution towards Sustainable Finance in India?</title>
      <link href="/A-New-Revolution-towards-Sustainable-Finance-in-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Green Bonds: A New Revolution towards Sustainable Finance in India?" />
      <published>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-New-Revolution-towards-Sustainable-Finance-in-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-New-Revolution-towards-Sustainable-Finance-in-India">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;We need bold action on climate change, our generation may not be able to solve all the problems related to climate change, but we can do our part to leave a better planet for the next generation&lt;/em&gt;”, said Kristalina Georgieva, World Bank Group and Interim Chief Executive Officer. Climate change has caused an unprecedented risk to the growth of societies and economies. According to a recent report by Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), it has been estimated that around $6-7 trillion of annual investment is globally required to achieve the objective of moving the world economy towards a ‘greener economy’. To get the entire globe out of this trap, we need to make substantial investments that fund projects focussing on creating low carbon economies, clean energy, water transportation, etc. Only with such effective measures shall we be able to build a climate-resilient economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many countries around the world have been pursuing a shift towards a more sustainable environment. Recently, the European Union launched the Next Generation EU (NGEU) fund to tackle the coronavirus pandemic. The deal puts the issue of climate change at the forefront. According to the deal document, a total of 30% of the expenditure of the €1.82 trillion will be used to reach the climate targets in conformity to the objectives of the Paris agreements. It also has a provision that rules that the European Commission should publish a report on climate expenditure annually. In order to ensure that such legislations bear fruitful results, it is important to provide investors with alternative options of investments, with higher returns and which also give them a feeling of having satisfied their responsibility towards the environment. This is where ‘Green Bonds’ come into the picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the current status and impetus given to green finance globally, we can not only give credit to institutions that have introduced green bonds but also to the dynamic shift witnessed in the corporate bond market wherein we have more socially responsible investors who want to invest their money in the funding of those projects that would lead to a positive impact on the society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite knowing the unmeasured potential of green finance all over the world, the total number of green bonds issued was only around 3% as a percentage of the total corporate bonds issued. This reveals the percentage of untapped potential of the green bond market which should be effectively realised to create a sustainable environment. So, how are these bonds currently being exploited in India?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Indian Green Bond Market and the Road Ahead.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a time when governments across the world are emphasising on creating low carbon economies, India is not lagging behind in showing its efforts in the same direction. Indian financial institutions such as the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) and the Securities Exchange Board of India (SEBI) are effectively trying to promote green bonds in the country. India is aiming to build 175 gigawatts of renewable energy capacity by 2022. Thus, the financing needs of the renewable energy sector can effectively be addressed by the issuance of green bonds in our country. In the last few years Indian investors, banking institutions, and the government have played a crucial role in developing sustainable finance. They have recognised it as a fundamental tool towards financing the nation’s renewable energy targets through developing strategies for sustainable economic growth and effective policy framework for judicious utilisation of all-natural resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green bonds in India were introduced in 2015 when Yes Bank issued the first series of green bonds in the country for financing projects of ₹10 billion followed by ₹6 billion issuances of green bonds by CLP India. In order to regulate these issuances, SEBI issued the green bond guidelines on lines of the green bond principles issued by the Institute of Cost and Management Accountants (ICMA). By 2018, the Indian green bond market had risen to ₹500 billion. This clearly indicates that India has an enormous capacity for the development of sustainable finance which just needs to be unlocked with appropriate policies and measures. According to Climate Transparency’s &lt;em&gt;Brown to Green&lt;/em&gt; report, wherein a study was conducted among the G20 countries measuring the Green Bond Issuance as a share of the country’s overall debt, India was ranked 5th, hence, Indian financial institutions and investors should realise that the green bond market has a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the enormous potential, the market is yet to overcome several barriers such as greenwashing, false claims of environmental compliance, etc. Additionally, there exist mismatches between long-term green investment and short-term interests of the investors which tend to make the market less efficient. Exorbitant currency hedging costs because of the high volatility of the Indian rupee, poor sovereign rating, and low tenure of the green bonds pose a hurdle in the path of creating a highly advanced green bond market. Moreover, we need to realise that till date the green bonds that have been issued in India have only been offered by highly established finance companies, whereas internationally, other organisations such as local governments, climate change organisations, and other corporate firms are all coming together to address this issue by diversifying the green bond market in their countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On analysing the above situation of green finance in the country, we can clearly conclude that India’s full potential still needs to be explored because currently there exists a shortage of supply as well as the demand for green bonds in the market because of various constraints. In order to increase the efficiency of this particular market, the government and the authorities need to formulate relevant policies and implement them. For starters, the short-term interests of investors as well as issuers, need to be removed by educating them that the advancement of the market in the country not only will fund the necessary environmental projects but also would allow issuers to generate a positive public reputation. Since the main reason for the lack of demand of green bonds in our country is the investors’ perception that they are not competitive enough to give them high financial returns, the governmental agencies need to step up by guaranteeing a fixed rate of return which is marginally higher than other investments so that large institutional investors and retail investors would heavily invest under this domain. Other measures such as reducing foreign exchange hedging costs will attract investors from overseas to invest in clean energy projects of India. RBI, SEBI, Indian Renewable Energy Development Agency Ltd. (IREDA), and the Ministry of Finance can play an important role in the nascent stage development of Green Finance in the country by creating more rupee denominated bonds such as the IFC-Yes Bank Green Masala Bond of 2015. Launching credited and standardised Indian green bonds that would reduce the stigma of the attached risk with green bonds can completely flip the situation upside-down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, in order to attract domestic demand, the government should provide tax incentives to individuals for investment in such bonds. The development of sustainable stock exchanges just like the Shanghai Stock Exchange did is essential for continued growth. It has a special index to monitor the green finance situation in the country. Efforts of the government and other institutions have borne positive results. According to the Indian Economic Survey 2019-20, India has become the second-largest market for green bonds after China with $10.3 billion transactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government support and a dedicated policy at hand are necessarily required to scale up the level of green bonds market in the country. An enhanced policy framework is required in action to upgrade the current situation of the green finance market in the country. This can also be done by educating investors, and removing information asymmetry between issuers and investors. An increase in investor confidence could give a new shape to the outlook of sustainable finance in our country. Only enhanced collective participation of issuers, corporate firms, financial institutions, policymakers, and regulators will give the fundamental push to the boundary of the green bond market, and would further give rise to other such opportunities in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, green bonds can be seen as the interlinking bridge connecting sustainable finance with funding quintessential environmental projects. Growth in the green bonds in India would set a precedent for other theme-based bonds such as social bonds, water bonds, and sustainability bonds that raise finance for specific developmental purposes.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Cherry Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“We need bold action on climate change, our generation may not be able to solve all the problems related to climate change, but we can do our part to leave a better planet for the next generation”, said Kristalina Georgieva, World Bank Group and Interim Chief Executive Officer. Climate change has caused an unprecedented risk to the growth of societies and economies. According to a recent report by Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), it has been estimated that around $6-7 trillion of annual investment is globally required to achieve the objective of moving the world economy towards a ‘greener economy’. To get the entire globe out of this trap, we need to make substantial investments that fund projects focussing on creating low carbon economies, clean energy, water transportation, etc. Only with such effective measures shall we be able to build a climate-resilient economy.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
