<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/business-finance/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-12-18T10:56:48+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/business-finance/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Understanding the SPAC Phenomenon</title>
      <link href="/Understanding-the-SPAC-Phenomenon" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding the SPAC Phenomenon" />
      <published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Understanding-the-SPAC-Phenomenon</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-the-SPAC-Phenomenon">&lt;p&gt;Special Purpose Acquisition Companies, or SPACs, have been in the limelight lately, be it on Wall Street, in corporate boardrooms, or in the media. Even celebrities and public figures like the famous singer-songwriter, Ciara, and the former US speaker of the House, Paul Ryan, are jumping on the bandwagon. Hell, even former President Donald Trump has launched his own media network, including a social media platform called 'TRUTH Social' in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/10/22/trump-social-media-spac-digital-world-acquisition-corp-surges-another-100percent.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;SPAC merger&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand the quickly booming industry, take a look at the following figures: &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2021/07/spacs-what-you-need-to-know&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;in 2019&lt;/a&gt;, 59 SPACs were created, with $13 billion invested; in 2020, 247 were created, with $80 billion invested; and in the first quarter alone of 2021, 295 were created, with $96 billion invested.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But what exactly is a SPAC, and why is everyone talking about it?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, a special purpose acquisition company (SPAC) is a sort of shell company formed for the sole purpose of raising investment capital through an IPO. Such an arrangement allows investors to contribute money towards a fund, which is later used to acquire or merge with one or more unspecified businesses wanting to go public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though SPACs are an active part of contemporary discourse, SPACs were fraudulent when they first appeared as blank-check corporations, in the 1980's. However, with the introduction of much-needed regulation for SPACs, for example, barrage on the use of the proceeds of blank-check IPOs until the mergers were complete, blank-check corporations could be successfully rebranded as SPACs, as we now know them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An important feature of modern SPACs is the option for investors to withdraw from a deal after the sponsor identifies a target, which is to say, if investors don’t like the deal, they can choose to pull out, redeeming their shares for cash plus interest.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sponsors of SPACs usually have two years to find a company to merge with/acquire and intimate the market on which industry they’re targeting. And when it comes to which industry they usually target, then as per recent trends, the hot areas seem to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/21502700/spac-explained-meaning-special-purpose-acquisition-company&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;EVs and Technology&lt;/a&gt; (consumer tech, biotech etc).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What makes SPACs better than traditional IPOs?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I were to define SPACs with utmost precision, I’d say a SPAC is an IPO for ‘nothing’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is because, with a SPAC, the IPO is already done, you’re just left to negotiate with the SPAC that might acquire you, which makes the process a lot faster. You’re not even required to arrange for a roadshow, for the pool of funds is already available! Apart from greater speed, SPACs also provide higher valuations, lower fees, less dilution, more certainty and transparency, and fewer regulatory demands than traditional IPOs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most private companies go public years after the commencement of their operations, that is, when they achieve stability, thus depriving investors of an opportunity to experience the gains from their growth spurts. Many investors are interested in being part of a company’s journey but they’ve been frustrated because of being unable to access these companies as they’ve stayed private longer. And this is where SPACs come to the rescue! They usually enable investors to help a business grow from rags to riches, and reap the resulting rewards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the flip side though, some investors may be apprehensive of buying shares of a company going public through a SPAC because the amount of due diligence required for that may be lesser than a regular IPO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A parallel between VCs and SPACs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A SPAC isn’t just a medium for a company to go public, it’s a medium for a company to raise new capital to deploy toward some business objective. So if we look at SPACs as an instrument of capital allocation rather than that of a go-public mechanism, they start to look a lot like venture capital firms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major criticism of the SPAC boom is that companies going public through SPACs are often initially low quality, because they have yet to generate any revenue. This is largely common in VC firm investments, which require dealing with the uncertainty of the value of future cash flows, that might be more than a decade away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, just like VCs, SPACs enable investors to partake in the rewards arising out of helping a business grow from scratch, instead of an already stable base, in the case of most traditional IPOs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the SPAC market mirrors the venture capital market very closely in the sense that investors have to pitch companies to take their money. So it’s no wonder that while SPACs may compete against each other for targets, they also compete with VC firms as companies choose the best path for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The stakeholders in a SPAC&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three main stakeholder groups in a SPAC, namely, sponsors, investors, and targets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sponsors&lt;/strong&gt;: The SPAC process is initiated by the sponsors. They invest risk capital in the form of nonrefundable payments to accountants, bankers, and lawyers. Since SPACs don’t own any assets, it’s the sponsors that are the main attraction point. In essence, to investors, a SPAC is only as credible as its sponsors. If sponsors fail to create an arrangement within the deadline, the SPAC must be dissolved and all funds returned. The sponsors lose not only their risk capital but also all the time they invested. But if they succeed, they earn sponsors’ shares in the resulting company, often worth as much as 20% of the equity raised from original investors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investors:&lt;/strong&gt; The investors in SPACs (mainly institutional investors and highly specialized hedge funds) receive two classes of securities: common stock (typically at $10 per share) and warrants that allow them to buy shares at a specified price (typically $11.50 per share) in the future. While warrants are considered to be incentives to subscribe, the greater the number of warrants issued, the higher the perceived risk of the SPAC. After the announcement of the target, the original investors choose to move forward with the deal or withdraw.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SPAC mergers often involve parallel funding by institutional investors, known as 'private investment in public equity' or PIPE. While the institutional investors in PIPE (mutual funds, family offices, private equity firms, pension funds, strategic investors) provide the company that’s merging some additional funds (locked up for six months), they get a chunk of the new company in return. Sponsors use PIPEs to represent a vote of confidence, increase the funding, and guarantee a minimum amount of cash should the original investors choose to pull out of the deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Targets: &lt;/strong&gt;Most SPAC targets at this stage consider several options like pursuing a traditional IPO, approaching venture capital firms, raising additional capital, or selling the business to another company or a private equity firm. Due to the multiple benefits that SPACs offer, they can be an attractive alternative to the above-mentioned options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SPACs seem amazing! What’s the catch?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite all the glitter, SPACs aren’t gold. They &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/6eb655a2-21f5-4313-b287-964a63dd88b3&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;have a dubious reputation when it comes to fraud&lt;/a&gt;. Take, for example, the infamous case of Akazoo, the Greek streaming company listed on the markets in 2019. A short-seller named Gabriel Grego did some digging and asserted that the subscriber figures Akazoo provided were falsified. The company’s board launched an investigation, “eventually concluding that the company’s previous management had ‘participated in a sophisticated scheme to falsify Akazoo’s books and records,’” including the documents that had been given to the acquiring SPAC, according to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/6eb655a2-21f5-4313-b287-964a63dd88b3&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Financial Times&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another analysis by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/6eb655a2-21f5-4313-b287-964a63dd88b3&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Financial Times&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of the SPACs from 2015 and 2019 found that the majority of the SPACs trade below their original price of $10 a share. And these aren’t very reassuring, or confidence-inspiring stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The bottom line&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of ways the events can unfold in this rapidly evolving story - the two most famous contenders being the SPAC boom emerging as a safe and sustainable bet or it ending in a bubble burst.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All we can do is wait, and watch how these SPACs unpack.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Eeshita Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Special Purpose Acquisition Companies, or SPACs, have been in the limelight lately, be it on Wall Street, in corporate boardrooms, or in the media. Even celebrities and public figures like the famous singer-songwriter, Ciara, and the former US speaker of the House, Paul Ryan, are jumping on the bandwagon. Hell, even former President Donald Trump has launched his own media network, including a social media platform called 'TRUTH Social' in a SPAC merger.&amp;nbsp; To understand the quickly booming industry, take a look at the following figures: in 2019, 59 SPACs were created, with $13 billion invested; in 2020, 247 were created, with $80 billion invested; and in the first quarter alone of 2021, 295 were created, with $96 billion invested.&amp;nbsp; But what exactly is a SPAC, and why is everyone talking about it? To put it simply, a special purpose acquisition company (SPAC) is a sort of shell company formed for the sole purpose of raising investment capital through an IPO. Such an arrangement allows investors to contribute money towards a fund, which is later used to acquire or merge with one or more unspecified businesses wanting to go public. Even though SPACs are an active part of contemporary discourse, SPACs were fraudulent when they first appeared as blank-check corporations, in the 1980's. However, with the introduction of much-needed regulation for SPACs, for example, barrage on the use of the proceeds of blank-check IPOs until the mergers were complete, blank-check corporations could be successfully rebranded as SPACs, as we now know them. An important feature of modern SPACs is the option for investors to withdraw from a deal after the sponsor identifies a target, which is to say, if investors don’t like the deal, they can choose to pull out, redeeming their shares for cash plus interest.&amp;nbsp; The sponsors of SPACs usually have two years to find a company to merge with/acquire and intimate the market on which industry they’re targeting. And when it comes to which industry they usually target, then as per recent trends, the hot areas seem to be EVs and Technology (consumer tech, biotech etc).&amp;nbsp; What makes SPACs better than traditional IPOs? If I were to define SPACs with utmost precision, I’d say a SPAC is an IPO for ‘nothing’.&amp;nbsp; This is because, with a SPAC, the IPO is already done, you’re just left to negotiate with the SPAC that might acquire you, which makes the process a lot faster. You’re not even required to arrange for a roadshow, for the pool of funds is already available! Apart from greater speed, SPACs also provide higher valuations, lower fees, less dilution, more certainty and transparency, and fewer regulatory demands than traditional IPOs. Most private companies go public years after the commencement of their operations, that is, when they achieve stability, thus depriving investors of an opportunity to experience the gains from their growth spurts. Many investors are interested in being part of a company’s journey but they’ve been frustrated because of being unable to access these companies as they’ve stayed private longer. And this is where SPACs come to the rescue! They usually enable investors to help a business grow from rags to riches, and reap the resulting rewards. On the flip side though, some investors may be apprehensive of buying shares of a company going public through a SPAC because the amount of due diligence required for that may be lesser than a regular IPO. A parallel between VCs and SPACs A SPAC isn’t just a medium for a company to go public, it’s a medium for a company to raise new capital to deploy toward some business objective. So if we look at SPACs as an instrument of capital allocation rather than that of a go-public mechanism, they start to look a lot like venture capital firms. A major criticism of the SPAC boom is that companies going public through SPACs are often initially low quality, because they have yet to generate any revenue. This is largely common in VC firm investments, which require dealing with the uncertainty of the value of future cash flows, that might be more than a decade away. Moreover, just like VCs, SPACs enable investors to partake in the rewards arising out of helping a business grow from scratch, instead of an already stable base, in the case of most traditional IPOs. Lastly, the SPAC market mirrors the venture capital market very closely in the sense that investors have to pitch companies to take their money. So it’s no wonder that while SPACs may compete against each other for targets, they also compete with VC firms as companies choose the best path for themselves. The stakeholders in a SPAC There are three main stakeholder groups in a SPAC, namely, sponsors, investors, and targets: Sponsors: The SPAC process is initiated by the sponsors. They invest risk capital in the form of nonrefundable payments to accountants, bankers, and lawyers. Since SPACs don’t own any assets, it’s the sponsors that are the main attraction point. In essence, to investors, a SPAC is only as credible as its sponsors. If sponsors fail to create an arrangement within the deadline, the SPAC must be dissolved and all funds returned. The sponsors lose not only their risk capital but also all the time they invested. But if they succeed, they earn sponsors’ shares in the resulting company, often worth as much as 20% of the equity raised from original investors. Investors: The investors in SPACs (mainly institutional investors and highly specialized hedge funds) receive two classes of securities: common stock (typically at $10 per share) and warrants that allow them to buy shares at a specified price (typically $11.50 per share) in the future. While warrants are considered to be incentives to subscribe, the greater the number of warrants issued, the higher the perceived risk of the SPAC. After the announcement of the target, the original investors choose to move forward with the deal or withdraw.&amp;nbsp; SPAC mergers often involve parallel funding by institutional investors, known as 'private investment in public equity' or PIPE. While the institutional investors in PIPE (mutual funds, family offices, private equity firms, pension funds, strategic investors) provide the company that’s merging some additional funds (locked up for six months), they get a chunk of the new company in return. Sponsors use PIPEs to represent a vote of confidence, increase the funding, and guarantee a minimum amount of cash should the original investors choose to pull out of the deal. Targets: Most SPAC targets at this stage consider several options like pursuing a traditional IPO, approaching venture capital firms, raising additional capital, or selling the business to another company or a private equity firm. Due to the multiple benefits that SPACs offer, they can be an attractive alternative to the above-mentioned options. SPACs seem amazing! What’s the catch? Despite all the glitter, SPACs aren’t gold. They have a dubious reputation when it comes to fraud. Take, for example, the infamous case of Akazoo, the Greek streaming company listed on the markets in 2019. A short-seller named Gabriel Grego did some digging and asserted that the subscriber figures Akazoo provided were falsified. The company’s board launched an investigation, “eventually concluding that the company’s previous management had ‘participated in a sophisticated scheme to falsify Akazoo’s books and records,’” including the documents that had been given to the acquiring SPAC, according to the Financial Times. Another analysis by the Financial Times of the SPACs from 2015 and 2019 found that the majority of the SPACs trade below their original price of $10 a share. And these aren’t very reassuring, or confidence-inspiring stories. The bottom line There are a lot of ways the events can unfold in this rapidly evolving story - the two most famous contenders being the SPAC boom emerging as a safe and sustainable bet or it ending in a bubble burst.&amp;nbsp; All we can do is wait, and watch how these SPACs unpack.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Wall Street’s New Leviathan</title>
      <link href="/Wall-Street-s-New-Leviathan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wall Street’s New Leviathan" />
      <published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Wall-Street-s-New-Leviathan</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Wall-Street-s-New-Leviathan">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Thou art Peter, and upon this rock I will build my church.”&lt;/em&gt; (Matthew 16:18)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chances are high you’ll find a person who knows about this Peter, the bedrock of Christianity – it is the religion with the greatest number of adherents, after all. About two millennia later, the modern-day Peter has emerged, albeit less popular.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Americans pride themselves on being intelligent people, the folks who are good at everything – from fast food to babysitting world peace. Even if we were to believe these claims, one thing they’re &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; good at is answering a simple question – ‘&lt;em&gt;How much is too much?&lt;/em&gt;’&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This unanswered question has hurt the States time and again, and yet, answering it is &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; an ex-post job and not ex-ante. A decade after Wall Street fell victim to its own greed, regulations and investment trends of people who grew up through this collapse have shifted all headwinds to the buy-side, making them the new apex predators of what the country chooses to call capitalism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the buy-side firms are becoming as large as pre-crash investment banks, one particular name stands apart from the rest – literally and figuratively. It controls $9.5 trillion worth of assets and chances are, you have not heard of this firm - BlackRock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The firm and its asset growth are the true embodiment of the word exponential. Compared to the century-old financial behemoths such as Deutsche Bank, Goldman Sachs and Morgan Stanley, BlackRock was founded in 1988, a meagre three-decade-old company.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Founder Larry Fink was the man behind the infamous Mortgage-Backed Securities (MBS) market, which led to the 2008 crisis and subsequently his fall at Wall Street’s bulge bracket. Investment company First Boston used this as an opportunity and made him start an asset management firm: BlackRock, with an emphasis on risk management as their ace in the hole.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with a humble $5 million credit line from Blackstone, Fink and BlackRock quadrupled their assets within the year, a pace that continues till date - the firm adds a trillion to its asset base every year or so, which is the equivalent of saying it adds the &lt;em&gt;total&lt;/em&gt; asset base of leading asset management firms till date, to its balance sheet every year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BlackRock is like a Swiss-Army knife. As you’d expect, it is difficult to find a sector where the firm is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in. Currently, it is an institutional investor, money manager, consultant and private equity firm. It effectively is involved on all sides of the table in most industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A funny example is that of the environment. In 2017, announcements were made to support ESG practices within owned firms and improve the investment landscape in sustainable practices with new products. Two years later, BlackRock was a major shareholder in every big oil company and in seven of the leading producers of the other black rock – coal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this became public knowledge, protests were staged outside of BlackRock‘s France division, leading Fink to announce an exit from coal and fossil fuel assets. Alongside, revelations were made of letters to the boards of companies to improve sustainability and gender diversity practices or risk losing business with BlackRock.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other times, it simply has stakes in leading competitors – Apple and Microsoft, Deutsche Bank, JP Morgan Chase and Wells Fargo, just to name a few. It simply cannot lose money unless the entire sector goes bust.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can figure out other conflicts as well – a company goes to raise debt and BlackRock, a major shareholder, is already out to be a buyer of this debt. BlackRock is an advisor to most firms it’s an investor in. The ownership structure should ring a few alarms as well – Vanguard, another asset manager and a direct competitor of BlackRock, is its biggest shareholder. Many institutions that BlackRock invests in, are shareholders of BlackRock themselves.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is another part of BlackRock’s business that took flight in 1999 and is dubbed as “&lt;em&gt;a tech start-up&lt;/em&gt;” by CEO Fink – Aladdin, the risk management system. One would be damned if their start-up was managing risk for $21.6 trillion worth of assets including those of the Federal Reserve Board and the European Central Bank. BlackRock’s internal ‘Tech 2025’ plan aims to make Aladdin the standard, and perhaps the only used risk management platform in the industry. But that’s a monopoly for another time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, BlackRock is begging to be labelled as the present-day Illuminati, but that isn’t the case. However, it is a marionettist in its own right, and here is where things get murky. Back in the mid-to-late 00’s, Goldman Sachs was well known for hiring prominent policymakers who would go on to be part of America’s cabinet and ensure nothing went too awry for Wall Street.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 2008, one would expect that things would change and the blurred lines between White House and Wall Street would be redrawn but that’s the exact opposite of what happened. Who do you call when a set of financial products is threatening to, or rather, causing the biggest financial crisis in almost a century? Of course, it’s the creator!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the MBS markets were rearranging the food chain by the minute, one was eyeing the newly vacated spot of the apex predator – BlackRock. The Federal Reserve called in Fink and his team to manage the mess and has been a loyal customer ever since – be it Aladdin’s risk management, or an appropriate response to the coronavirus pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the pandemic hit, the Fed announced that it will purchase assets other than Treasury bonds as well – Corporate Bonds and Exchange Traded Funds (ETFs). Who else do we know as a major firm dealing in Corporate Bonds and ETFs? Do the math. The funds the Fed poured money in were a hit among retail investors and no prizes for guessing the issuer of the funds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are conversant with US law, you must have thought at least once about how BlackRock is not under the purview of ‘too big to fail’ or why the Dodd-Frank reform, which has riddled the powerhouses of the sell-side with multiple regulations on risk-taking, is not handicapping their earning potential?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is the same as that with Goldman – it has multiple former executives in Washington and multiple former Washington policymakers reside at the 52nd Street in Manhattan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This cosy revolving door is not just limited from Manhattan to Washington rather extends to Ottawa and Mexico City. For example, PEMEX, Mexico’s state-owned oil company was opened to private investment, and BlackRock quickly jumped in. Then it acquired a loss-making, scandalous private equity firm in the country, I Cuadrada, and a month down the line, Sierra Oil, a year-old portfolio company of the former, which had not had a project in its short life was awarded two major exploration contracts as the sole bidder.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BlackRock also holds the distinction of being the first global asset manager which has set up an onshore shop in China. There are multiple examples, from private to public sectors where the private firm has played on both sides of the court to benefit itself, earning the title of a white-collar mafia. Europe has dealt a stricter hand with criticism of the European Commission for awarding BlackRock a contract with a significant conflict of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the common person was never directly under attack from this leviathan but as it extends its power, it now faces a direct confrontation with the people – housing. The American Dream has always consisted of owning a place you can call home, however, that soon might not be the case as BlackRock and multiple other funds are outbidding individuals or paying the entire amount upfront with no inspection. These bids are too sweet for developers to pass.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you thought this was excessive, mega-funds are buying out entire neighbourhoods for a few factors above the listed prices and immediately putting them out on exorbitant rents. A new monopoly is unfolding before us and one can only hope America finds an answer to its age-old dilemma sooner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“For what does it profit a man to gain the whole world and forfeit his soul?”&lt;/em&gt; (Mark 8:36)&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aaradhya Daga</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Thou art Peter, and upon this rock I will build my church.” (Matthew 16:18) Chances are high you’ll find a person who knows about this Peter, the bedrock of Christianity – it is the religion with the greatest number of adherents, after all. About two millennia later, the modern-day Peter has emerged, albeit less popular.&amp;nbsp; Americans pride themselves on being intelligent people, the folks who are good at everything – from fast food to babysitting world peace. Even if we were to believe these claims, one thing they’re not good at is answering a simple question – ‘How much is too much?’&amp;nbsp; This unanswered question has hurt the States time and again, and yet, answering it is still an ex-post job and not ex-ante. A decade after Wall Street fell victim to its own greed, regulations and investment trends of people who grew up through this collapse have shifted all headwinds to the buy-side, making them the new apex predators of what the country chooses to call capitalism.&amp;nbsp; While the buy-side firms are becoming as large as pre-crash investment banks, one particular name stands apart from the rest – literally and figuratively. It controls $9.5 trillion worth of assets and chances are, you have not heard of this firm - BlackRock. The firm and its asset growth are the true embodiment of the word exponential. Compared to the century-old financial behemoths such as Deutsche Bank, Goldman Sachs and Morgan Stanley, BlackRock was founded in 1988, a meagre three-decade-old company.&amp;nbsp; Founder Larry Fink was the man behind the infamous Mortgage-Backed Securities (MBS) market, which led to the 2008 crisis and subsequently his fall at Wall Street’s bulge bracket. Investment company First Boston used this as an opportunity and made him start an asset management firm: BlackRock, with an emphasis on risk management as their ace in the hole.&amp;nbsp; Starting with a humble $5 million credit line from Blackstone, Fink and BlackRock quadrupled their assets within the year, a pace that continues till date - the firm adds a trillion to its asset base every year or so, which is the equivalent of saying it adds the total asset base of leading asset management firms till date, to its balance sheet every year.&amp;nbsp; BlackRock is like a Swiss-Army knife. As you’d expect, it is difficult to find a sector where the firm is not in. Currently, it is an institutional investor, money manager, consultant and private equity firm. It effectively is involved on all sides of the table in most industries. A funny example is that of the environment. In 2017, announcements were made to support ESG practices within owned firms and improve the investment landscape in sustainable practices with new products. Two years later, BlackRock was a major shareholder in every big oil company and in seven of the leading producers of the other black rock – coal.&amp;nbsp; When this became public knowledge, protests were staged outside of BlackRock‘s France division, leading Fink to announce an exit from coal and fossil fuel assets. Alongside, revelations were made of letters to the boards of companies to improve sustainability and gender diversity practices or risk losing business with BlackRock.&amp;nbsp; Other times, it simply has stakes in leading competitors – Apple and Microsoft, Deutsche Bank, JP Morgan Chase and Wells Fargo, just to name a few. It simply cannot lose money unless the entire sector goes bust.&amp;nbsp; You can figure out other conflicts as well – a company goes to raise debt and BlackRock, a major shareholder, is already out to be a buyer of this debt. BlackRock is an advisor to most firms it’s an investor in. The ownership structure should ring a few alarms as well – Vanguard, another asset manager and a direct competitor of BlackRock, is its biggest shareholder. Many institutions that BlackRock invests in, are shareholders of BlackRock themselves.&amp;nbsp; There is another part of BlackRock’s business that took flight in 1999 and is dubbed as “a tech start-up” by CEO Fink – Aladdin, the risk management system. One would be damned if their start-up was managing risk for $21.6 trillion worth of assets including those of the Federal Reserve Board and the European Central Bank. BlackRock’s internal ‘Tech 2025’ plan aims to make Aladdin the standard, and perhaps the only used risk management platform in the industry. But that’s a monopoly for another time. At this point, BlackRock is begging to be labelled as the present-day Illuminati, but that isn’t the case. However, it is a marionettist in its own right, and here is where things get murky. Back in the mid-to-late 00’s, Goldman Sachs was well known for hiring prominent policymakers who would go on to be part of America’s cabinet and ensure nothing went too awry for Wall Street. After 2008, one would expect that things would change and the blurred lines between White House and Wall Street would be redrawn but that’s the exact opposite of what happened. Who do you call when a set of financial products is threatening to, or rather, causing the biggest financial crisis in almost a century? Of course, it’s the creator! When the MBS markets were rearranging the food chain by the minute, one was eyeing the newly vacated spot of the apex predator – BlackRock. The Federal Reserve called in Fink and his team to manage the mess and has been a loyal customer ever since – be it Aladdin’s risk management, or an appropriate response to the coronavirus pandemic.&amp;nbsp; As the pandemic hit, the Fed announced that it will purchase assets other than Treasury bonds as well – Corporate Bonds and Exchange Traded Funds (ETFs). Who else do we know as a major firm dealing in Corporate Bonds and ETFs? Do the math. The funds the Fed poured money in were a hit among retail investors and no prizes for guessing the issuer of the funds. If you are conversant with US law, you must have thought at least once about how BlackRock is not under the purview of ‘too big to fail’ or why the Dodd-Frank reform, which has riddled the powerhouses of the sell-side with multiple regulations on risk-taking, is not handicapping their earning potential? The answer is the same as that with Goldman – it has multiple former executives in Washington and multiple former Washington policymakers reside at the 52nd Street in Manhattan.&amp;nbsp; This cosy revolving door is not just limited from Manhattan to Washington rather extends to Ottawa and Mexico City. For example, PEMEX, Mexico’s state-owned oil company was opened to private investment, and BlackRock quickly jumped in. Then it acquired a loss-making, scandalous private equity firm in the country, I Cuadrada, and a month down the line, Sierra Oil, a year-old portfolio company of the former, which had not had a project in its short life was awarded two major exploration contracts as the sole bidder.&amp;nbsp; BlackRock also holds the distinction of being the first global asset manager which has set up an onshore shop in China. There are multiple examples, from private to public sectors where the private firm has played on both sides of the court to benefit itself, earning the title of a white-collar mafia. Europe has dealt a stricter hand with criticism of the European Commission for awarding BlackRock a contract with a significant conflict of interest. While the common person was never directly under attack from this leviathan but as it extends its power, it now faces a direct confrontation with the people – housing. The American Dream has always consisted of owning a place you can call home, however, that soon might not be the case as BlackRock and multiple other funds are outbidding individuals or paying the entire amount upfront with no inspection. These bids are too sweet for developers to pass.&amp;nbsp; If you thought this was excessive, mega-funds are buying out entire neighbourhoods for a few factors above the listed prices and immediately putting them out on exorbitant rents. A new monopoly is unfolding before us and one can only hope America finds an answer to its age-old dilemma sooner. “For what does it profit a man to gain the whole world and forfeit his soul?” (Mark 8:36)</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Evergrande: A Cave-in of Real Estate?</title>
      <link href="/Evergrande" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evergrande: A Cave-in of Real Estate?" />
      <published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Evergrande</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Evergrande">&lt;p&gt;The year 2020 was the worst year for economic growth since World War II - all economies came to a standstill with the raging spread of the virus. However, China, the country where the first outbreak of COVID-19 was reported, was the only major economy in the world to report a positive GDP growth in that year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to November 2021, the second-largest economy seems to be in a precarious situation with various credit rating firms cutting down on its growth forecasts owing to glaring uncertainties in the nation.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my last article, I covered &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;China's crackdown on its tech sector&lt;/a&gt;. Now the ball has come rolling to its real estate sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evergrande Group, China's second-largest property developer and the world’s most indebted real estate firm with liabilities amounting to $300 billion, informed bondholders in early September about its inability to honour its interest obligation. (For context, Russia's state debt &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.themoscowtimes.com/2021/02/24/russias-government-debt-rose-40-in-2020-a73044&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;in 2020 was $257 billion&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evergrande was founded by Mr Xu Jiayin, who was once the country’s richest man, in 1996, and was in the bottled water business. Later the company expanded into several areas, including pig farming, owning a football club, wealth management and the electric car segment. However, it was its real estate business for which it was widely known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, it recorded a gross profit of nearly $19 billion and in the year before that, it was on the Fortune Global 500 list. The company owns 2% of all newly-constructed real estate in China and employs about 200,000 people directly and helps in sustaining more than 3.8 million jobs indirectly every year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The possible collapse of an organisation this big can be brushed aside as a one-time occurrence, however, one cannot turn a blind eye when many such firms in that line of business are on the same path: Chinese luxury developer Fantasia Holding Group and the Sinic Holdings group have also announced a default on their debt repayment obligations in mid-October.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cause of worry intensifies when one observes that around 30% of China’s Gross Domestic Product (GDP) is related to its real estate sector. Therefore, the fall of real estate companies can leave a dent not only in the Chinese economy but the global economy as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The State Of Real Estate In China&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the late 1980's, China started moving from public housing to the commercial property model. Post-1994, The central government decentralised the goals and interests of the policymakers - passing the responsibility of social welfare services to local administration but with taxes to be submitted back to them.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The imbalance of funds led provincial governments to create state-owned shell companies called Local Government Financing Vehicles (LGFV). They gave these LGFV free valuable lands which were then used to take out loans that the administration themselves could not. Consequently, this made the administration seem healthier because their debt was now hidden while at the same time they met quotas set by Beijing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, land became the backbone of local economies.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, steep discounts and low-interest rates were offered to citizens as an act of welfare. Strict regulation by the government on how much money leaves the country left citizens with limited investment options - stock markets became synonymous with volatility and risk and housing gained the reputation of safe and profitable investments in the country. Housing prices were also such that they fell only once in the two decades that followed the Asian Financial Crisis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the aforementioned reasons, real estate is one of the most loved sectors of the economy with homeownership in China being the highest in the world, i.e. around 90%. It has become the country's leading pillar of economic growth with a contribution of around 15-30% to the GDP. In the COVID-19 period alone, the sector has grown by 4.9%.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, an unusual trend is seen in the country. The boom in real estate is coming at a cost: high vacancy rates in cities due to the vast majority of home purchases being second/third homes. In 2018, 87% of new home buyers already owned at least one flat.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the societal norm in China is such that male marriages demand homeownership. Decades of the one-child policy have resulted in an imbalance between males and females with scales tipping in favour of the latter. As a result, female families have become awfully picky, with the groom's homeownership being one of the prerequisites. As per a study, home prices are higher in cities of disproportionate male-to-female ratios.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In cities like Shenzhen, Beijing, Shanghai - it takes nearly 40 years worth of an accumulated average income to afford a home. Thus the vast majority of homes are purchased even before the construction has begun, sometimes years in advance.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With overhead demand, some developers undertake techniques such as selling batches of properties in glitzy online events or through raffles-off in lotteries where thousands of apartments are often sold out in minutes, giving the winners mere hours to submit down payments or lose the opportunity.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What all these instances, numbers and facts point towards is that of a speculative market, i.e. the assumption that prices would only go up.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However the demographic of the country suggests otherwise. In the next ten years, the country’s over-55 cohort will increase in size by 120 million, but by the end of the century, the overall population will be cut in half. The majority of present home buyers are precisely from this segment which China would soon lose. In addition, with age, home requirements keep differing.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was reasonable to anticipate a decade ago that the rapid urbanisation demand would be met by bringing in more than enough migrants to effectively cancel out the effects of ageing. Nonetheless, the statistics prove otherwise with the migration rate falling below the country’s 60% urbanisation rate. Moreover, such exorbitant home prices act as a further deterrent to the very people that were to be attracted by the construction of so many homes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the demand-supply misproportion is haunting the real estate space.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coming Back&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the context of speculative and overpriced real estate being understood, what consequences are in store, given the defaults of Evergrande and other real estate firms?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trigger for this fall is attributed to new guidelines, known as The Red Lines, introduced by the government in August 2020 for property developers. The rule requires the ratio of liabilities-to-assets of developers and their net debt-to-equity ratio to be below 70% and 100% respectively whilst requiring real estate firms to maintain the cash-to-short term debt ratio at a minimum of 100%.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any borrower failing to meet these requirements would be restricted from raising more funds, practically cutting off developers from taking on more debts. This means a complete alteration in the nature of the real estate business, which relies heavily on borrowing for its capital requirements.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crackdown on developers is in line with China’s supremo Xi Jinping's slogan of ‘Common Prosperity’, where the estate market is being regulated so as to puncture the property bubble and make housing more affordable. Some also see this as an example of the government taking on influential private businessmen under the guise of the ‘common prosperity’ programme to fight income inequality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This rule is about-turn, the government previously encouraged developers to take on huge debt through the heavily state-controlled financial sector to develop new properties. In the past, they have even bailed out troubled business entities thereby leading to the indiscriminate allocation of resources to the sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per an analyst, “&lt;em&gt;A regime shift is occurring without necessarily the markets fully comprehending the enormous underlying change to the structure of the economy.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many have called the Evergrande fiasco China’s own ‘Lehman moment', alluding to the failure of the US bank Lehman Brothers, which precipitated the 2008 financial crisis. Some observers believe that the current crisis was a long time coming owing to the company's unsustainable business model.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2012, Andrew Left of Citron Research argued that Evergrande was insolvent and that the company was engaged in aggressive accounting practices to cover up its troubles.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was said that the company held properties that it could not sell on its balance sheet as inventory, thus avoiding the booking of losses. The company was also accused of running a Ponzi scheme as it relied on the constant inflow of funds to prop up a business model that is fundamentally unsustainable. Interestingly, Evergrande has over the years consistently reported strong profits and has showcased a strong balance sheet with sufficient liquid assets.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A letter leaked last year by &lt;em&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/em&gt; showed Evergrande’s executives seeking financial assistance from the Chinese government by admitting their inability to meet their debt obligations to banks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per a &lt;em&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/em&gt; report, the administration is potentially going ahead with the restructuring of debt. The company has sold off various units at a discounted price to meet funding requirements. The organisation's deal with state-owned Yuexiu Property to sell a 51% stake in its property services unit has also been put on hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markets are closely observing the Chinese economic environment owing to growing uncertainties. Various countries are concerned about a possible slowdown resulting from the rebalancing of the economy away from the property sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China is the biggest steel importer and a drop in construction activities would affect the global steel prices. The IMF has estimated that a fall of 1% in demand from China would decrease global GDP by 25%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chinese administration has sent a clear signal: the only expectation one should have is unpredictability and nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The year 2020 was the worst year for economic growth since World War II - all economies came to a standstill with the raging spread of the virus. However, China, the country where the first outbreak of COVID-19 was reported, was the only major economy in the world to report a positive GDP growth in that year. Fast forward to November 2021, the second-largest economy seems to be in a precarious situation with various credit rating firms cutting down on its growth forecasts owing to glaring uncertainties in the nation.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; In my last article, I covered China's crackdown on its tech sector. Now the ball has come rolling to its real estate sector.&amp;nbsp; Evergrande Group, China's second-largest property developer and the world’s most indebted real estate firm with liabilities amounting to $300 billion, informed bondholders in early September about its inability to honour its interest obligation. (For context, Russia's state debt in 2020 was $257 billion.) Evergrande was founded by Mr Xu Jiayin, who was once the country’s richest man, in 1996, and was in the bottled water business. Later the company expanded into several areas, including pig farming, owning a football club, wealth management and the electric car segment. However, it was its real estate business for which it was widely known. In 2020, it recorded a gross profit of nearly $19 billion and in the year before that, it was on the Fortune Global 500 list. The company owns 2% of all newly-constructed real estate in China and employs about 200,000 people directly and helps in sustaining more than 3.8 million jobs indirectly every year. The possible collapse of an organisation this big can be brushed aside as a one-time occurrence, however, one cannot turn a blind eye when many such firms in that line of business are on the same path: Chinese luxury developer Fantasia Holding Group and the Sinic Holdings group have also announced a default on their debt repayment obligations in mid-October. The cause of worry intensifies when one observes that around 30% of China’s Gross Domestic Product (GDP) is related to its real estate sector. Therefore, the fall of real estate companies can leave a dent not only in the Chinese economy but the global economy as well.&amp;nbsp; The State Of Real Estate In China&amp;nbsp; In the late 1980's, China started moving from public housing to the commercial property model. Post-1994, The central government decentralised the goals and interests of the policymakers - passing the responsibility of social welfare services to local administration but with taxes to be submitted back to them.&amp;nbsp; The imbalance of funds led provincial governments to create state-owned shell companies called Local Government Financing Vehicles (LGFV). They gave these LGFV free valuable lands which were then used to take out loans that the administration themselves could not. Consequently, this made the administration seem healthier because their debt was now hidden while at the same time they met quotas set by Beijing.&amp;nbsp; As a result, land became the backbone of local economies.&amp;nbsp; Additionally, steep discounts and low-interest rates were offered to citizens as an act of welfare. Strict regulation by the government on how much money leaves the country left citizens with limited investment options - stock markets became synonymous with volatility and risk and housing gained the reputation of safe and profitable investments in the country. Housing prices were also such that they fell only once in the two decades that followed the Asian Financial Crisis.&amp;nbsp; Due to the aforementioned reasons, real estate is one of the most loved sectors of the economy with homeownership in China being the highest in the world, i.e. around 90%. It has become the country's leading pillar of economic growth with a contribution of around 15-30% to the GDP. In the COVID-19 period alone, the sector has grown by 4.9%.&amp;nbsp; However, an unusual trend is seen in the country. The boom in real estate is coming at a cost: high vacancy rates in cities due to the vast majority of home purchases being second/third homes. In 2018, 87% of new home buyers already owned at least one flat.&amp;nbsp; Additionally, the societal norm in China is such that male marriages demand homeownership. Decades of the one-child policy have resulted in an imbalance between males and females with scales tipping in favour of the latter. As a result, female families have become awfully picky, with the groom's homeownership being one of the prerequisites. As per a study, home prices are higher in cities of disproportionate male-to-female ratios.&amp;nbsp; In cities like Shenzhen, Beijing, Shanghai - it takes nearly 40 years worth of an accumulated average income to afford a home. Thus the vast majority of homes are purchased even before the construction has begun, sometimes years in advance.&amp;nbsp; With overhead demand, some developers undertake techniques such as selling batches of properties in glitzy online events or through raffles-off in lotteries where thousands of apartments are often sold out in minutes, giving the winners mere hours to submit down payments or lose the opportunity.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; What all these instances, numbers and facts point towards is that of a speculative market, i.e. the assumption that prices would only go up.&amp;nbsp; However the demographic of the country suggests otherwise. In the next ten years, the country’s over-55 cohort will increase in size by 120 million, but by the end of the century, the overall population will be cut in half. The majority of present home buyers are precisely from this segment which China would soon lose. In addition, with age, home requirements keep differing.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; It was reasonable to anticipate a decade ago that the rapid urbanisation demand would be met by bringing in more than enough migrants to effectively cancel out the effects of ageing. Nonetheless, the statistics prove otherwise with the migration rate falling below the country’s 60% urbanisation rate. Moreover, such exorbitant home prices act as a further deterrent to the very people that were to be attracted by the construction of so many homes.&amp;nbsp; Thus, the demand-supply misproportion is haunting the real estate space.&amp;nbsp; Coming Back With the context of speculative and overpriced real estate being understood, what consequences are in store, given the defaults of Evergrande and other real estate firms?&amp;nbsp; The trigger for this fall is attributed to new guidelines, known as The Red Lines, introduced by the government in August 2020 for property developers. The rule requires the ratio of liabilities-to-assets of developers and their net debt-to-equity ratio to be below 70% and 100% respectively whilst requiring real estate firms to maintain the cash-to-short term debt ratio at a minimum of 100%.&amp;nbsp; Any borrower failing to meet these requirements would be restricted from raising more funds, practically cutting off developers from taking on more debts. This means a complete alteration in the nature of the real estate business, which relies heavily on borrowing for its capital requirements.&amp;nbsp; The crackdown on developers is in line with China’s supremo Xi Jinping's slogan of ‘Common Prosperity’, where the estate market is being regulated so as to puncture the property bubble and make housing more affordable. Some also see this as an example of the government taking on influential private businessmen under the guise of the ‘common prosperity’ programme to fight income inequality. This rule is about-turn, the government previously encouraged developers to take on huge debt through the heavily state-controlled financial sector to develop new properties. In the past, they have even bailed out troubled business entities thereby leading to the indiscriminate allocation of resources to the sector.&amp;nbsp; As per an analyst, “A regime shift is occurring without necessarily the markets fully comprehending the enormous underlying change to the structure of the economy.” Many have called the Evergrande fiasco China’s own ‘Lehman moment', alluding to the failure of the US bank Lehman Brothers, which precipitated the 2008 financial crisis. Some observers believe that the current crisis was a long time coming owing to the company's unsustainable business model.&amp;nbsp; In 2012, Andrew Left of Citron Research argued that Evergrande was insolvent and that the company was engaged in aggressive accounting practices to cover up its troubles.&amp;nbsp; It was said that the company held properties that it could not sell on its balance sheet as inventory, thus avoiding the booking of losses. The company was also accused of running a Ponzi scheme as it relied on the constant inflow of funds to prop up a business model that is fundamentally unsustainable. Interestingly, Evergrande has over the years consistently reported strong profits and has showcased a strong balance sheet with sufficient liquid assets.&amp;nbsp; A letter leaked last year by Bloomberg showed Evergrande’s executives seeking financial assistance from the Chinese government by admitting their inability to meet their debt obligations to banks.&amp;nbsp; As per a Bloomberg report, the administration is potentially going ahead with the restructuring of debt. The company has sold off various units at a discounted price to meet funding requirements. The organisation's deal with state-owned Yuexiu Property to sell a 51% stake in its property services unit has also been put on hold. Markets are closely observing the Chinese economic environment owing to growing uncertainties. Various countries are concerned about a possible slowdown resulting from the rebalancing of the economy away from the property sector.&amp;nbsp; China is the biggest steel importer and a drop in construction activities would affect the global steel prices. The IMF has estimated that a fall of 1% in demand from China would decrease global GDP by 25%. The Chinese administration has sent a clear signal: the only expectation one should have is unpredictability and nothing more.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The PMC Bank Fiasco</title>
      <link href="/The-PMC-Bank-Fiasco" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The PMC Bank Fiasco" />
      <published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-PMC-Bank-Fiasco</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-PMC-Bank-Fiasco">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With great power come greater scams. &lt;/em&gt;This is evidently a mantra for India. Politicians getting named in large scams and then using their power to sway the decisions of government bodies has become a typical sight in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Punjab and Maharashtra Co-operative (PMC) bank fiasco is not the first time a major scam has been unearthed which has left a financial institution and its depositors in complete shambles. Call it misgovernance or blindsight of the management - borrowing from one bank to repay another bank has become a common&amp;nbsp;practice&amp;nbsp;in India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fraud to the tune of ₹6,500 billion was found in the books of the PMC bank, all of which were loans extended to only a single borrower: Housing Development and Infrastructure Limited (HDIL). This amount was way beyond the statutory limit set by the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) for lending to a single entity. Yet the senior management kept quiet on the matter until they were thrown under the bus by the managing director in his confession letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relations between the Wadhawan group and the PMC bank have prevailed since the 1980's, wherein the former had saved the latter from the brink of a financial collapse quite a few times by infusing capital and keeping a majority of their deposits with the establishment. Thus, aiding the PMC bank to maintain the liquidity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But every&amp;nbsp;good story&amp;nbsp;has an end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As HDIL’s business started to grow, and their capital requirements grew multifold, the group started to transact with larger banks in order to meet their needs. This hindered the profitability of the cooperative bank as the majority of the institution’s revenue was attributed to transactions in the Wadhawan group’s accounts. Hence, upon request the group started banking with PMC again after a short span of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018-19, the bank had reported a profit of ₹996.9 million in its annual report. The bank showed 3.76% of advances (₹8,3830 million) as gross non-performing assets (NPAs), which was fair as compared to public sector banks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, things started to go awry when a few projects undertaken by HDIL were shelved, and this resulted in a liquidity crunch. Consequently, the bank started defaulting on all the loans it had taken from other banks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, due to the past repayment record of the group, the bank continued to treat the loan as a standard loan. But when the loan amount snowballed to more than 73% of the bank’s total exposure, the issue came into the limelight and a strict moratorium was put upon the bank by the RBI. Hence, it's clear that the bank gave false monetary reports to cover its dangerous loan mess and the alleged collusion with HDIL and other firms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To prevent panic and loss of public confidence, all the depositors were barred from withdrawing more than ₹1,000, but later the withdrawal limit was capped at ₹100,000 per depositor until further notice. In addition to the complaint that was filed with the authorities, the board of directors were suspended and the Wadhawan family members were arrested. The Enforcement Directorate, India's economic offences investigator, even seized movable and immovable assets of approximately&amp;nbsp; ₹40 billion in connection with the case.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole case was nothing but another instance of corporate misgovernance and partial treatment to a particular lender by the senior management of banks, just like in the case of the Punjab National Bank scam.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fiasco could have been prevented had the institution increased its collateral against the loans disbursed and classified the Wadhawan group’s account as a NPA at the right time. The central bank should have learned its lesson post the PNB scam, and could have increased its due diligence on public sector banks by placing stricter checks and reporting standards on these financial institutions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In July 2021, the RBI approved the bid of Centrum Financial Services (CFS) and BharatPe to jointly take over the crisis driven cooperative bank, thereby providing some respite to its depositors. The president of BharatPe group said, “One thing was clear in our discussion with RBI that the interest of depositors is supreme”, further emphasising on the management's future intent.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RBI was initially reluctant in giving an in-principle nod to the two institutions to set up a small finance bank (SFB), however, it has finally given the licence and has even gone on to provide a lot of other statutory reliefs to the new entity to be jointly formed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are different points of view on the RBI's decision to pick Centrum-BharatPe for the takeover of one of the largest cooperative banks in India. A section of the bank’s depositors are unhappy with the decision, as they preferred an established commercial bank to take over the entity rather than a new licensee with no direct experience of running a regular bank.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CFS and BharatPe are set to infuse ₹5 billion each into the new entity when starting over and will increase the capital up to ₹30 billion in due course. Additionally, they also have the option to restructure the liability and convert them into capital instruments, take support from the Depositor Insurance and Credit Guarantee Corporation (DICGC) for repayment of insured deposits up to ₹50,000, phase withdrawal plans for individuals with higher deposits or convert the same into tier 1 or tier 2 capital.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The joint venture is likely to form a good synergy between BharatPe and Centrum Financial Services. While the former is an establishment specialising in fintech with a strong footprint in the digital lending and Unified Payment Interface (UPI) industry, the latter is a non-banking lender with strong holdings and a good history in providing credit to small-mid size firms. Together they can bring innovation and renewed vigour to a fallen institution.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new entity is to be operational in 120 days post the principal nod given by the central banking authority, and only post this, will the RBI draft a scheme on amalgamation of the two entities with PMC Bank. The plan will then be sent to the government for approval and official notification. Under Section 45 of the Banking Regulation Act, only a bank can be merged with another, therefore, the process of handover will start only once the SFB (Small Finance Bank) is created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from that, the subsidiaries of Centrum namely Centrum Housing Finance and Centrum Microcredit are in the same business as the small finance bank to be set up by them. Hence, this poses a hurdle for Centrum, as one cannot have separate entities doing the same business. Either it will have to sell its majority stake or merge the subsidiaries; or not enter the microcredit and home loan business from the SFB set up, which would mean giving up a major business opportunity for the new joint venture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RBI has now called for sweeping changes in the Banking Regulation Act, and will be actively looking into the regulation of cooperative banks to avoid such a future debacle. But the problem doesn't stop there, the problem only begins here. India massively lacks transparency in the financial sector and this often puts a lot of wrongdoings away from the eyes of the public and regulatory bodies. There are more important questions that this mess raises. The first being, will the public institutions continue to show vigilance only after the chaos unfolds or will they ever learn to step in the moment the lines are crossed?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samyak Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">With great power come greater scams. This is evidently a mantra for India. Politicians getting named in large scams and then using their power to sway the decisions of government bodies has become a typical sight in the country. The Punjab and Maharashtra Co-operative (PMC) bank fiasco is not the first time a major scam has been unearthed which has left a financial institution and its depositors in complete shambles. Call it misgovernance or blindsight of the management - borrowing from one bank to repay another bank has become a common&amp;nbsp;practice&amp;nbsp;in India. A fraud to the tune of ₹6,500 billion was found in the books of the PMC bank, all of which were loans extended to only a single borrower: Housing Development and Infrastructure Limited (HDIL). This amount was way beyond the statutory limit set by the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) for lending to a single entity. Yet the senior management kept quiet on the matter until they were thrown under the bus by the managing director in his confession letter. Relations between the Wadhawan group and the PMC bank have prevailed since the 1980's, wherein the former had saved the latter from the brink of a financial collapse quite a few times by infusing capital and keeping a majority of their deposits with the establishment. Thus, aiding the PMC bank to maintain the liquidity.&amp;nbsp; But every&amp;nbsp;good story&amp;nbsp;has an end. As HDIL’s business started to grow, and their capital requirements grew multifold, the group started to transact with larger banks in order to meet their needs. This hindered the profitability of the cooperative bank as the majority of the institution’s revenue was attributed to transactions in the Wadhawan group’s accounts. Hence, upon request the group started banking with PMC again after a short span of time. In 2018-19, the bank had reported a profit of ₹996.9 million in its annual report. The bank showed 3.76% of advances (₹8,3830 million) as gross non-performing assets (NPAs), which was fair as compared to public sector banks. However, things started to go awry when a few projects undertaken by HDIL were shelved, and this resulted in a liquidity crunch. Consequently, the bank started defaulting on all the loans it had taken from other banks.&amp;nbsp; Initially, due to the past repayment record of the group, the bank continued to treat the loan as a standard loan. But when the loan amount snowballed to more than 73% of the bank’s total exposure, the issue came into the limelight and a strict moratorium was put upon the bank by the RBI. Hence, it's clear that the bank gave false monetary reports to cover its dangerous loan mess and the alleged collusion with HDIL and other firms. To prevent panic and loss of public confidence, all the depositors were barred from withdrawing more than ₹1,000, but later the withdrawal limit was capped at ₹100,000 per depositor until further notice. In addition to the complaint that was filed with the authorities, the board of directors were suspended and the Wadhawan family members were arrested. The Enforcement Directorate, India's economic offences investigator, even seized movable and immovable assets of approximately&amp;nbsp; ₹40 billion in connection with the case.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; This whole case was nothing but another instance of corporate misgovernance and partial treatment to a particular lender by the senior management of banks, just like in the case of the Punjab National Bank scam.&amp;nbsp; This fiasco could have been prevented had the institution increased its collateral against the loans disbursed and classified the Wadhawan group’s account as a NPA at the right time. The central bank should have learned its lesson post the PNB scam, and could have increased its due diligence on public sector banks by placing stricter checks and reporting standards on these financial institutions.&amp;nbsp; In July 2021, the RBI approved the bid of Centrum Financial Services (CFS) and BharatPe to jointly take over the crisis driven cooperative bank, thereby providing some respite to its depositors. The president of BharatPe group said, “One thing was clear in our discussion with RBI that the interest of depositors is supreme”, further emphasising on the management's future intent.&amp;nbsp; The RBI was initially reluctant in giving an in-principle nod to the two institutions to set up a small finance bank (SFB), however, it has finally given the licence and has even gone on to provide a lot of other statutory reliefs to the new entity to be jointly formed.&amp;nbsp; There are different points of view on the RBI's decision to pick Centrum-BharatPe for the takeover of one of the largest cooperative banks in India. A section of the bank’s depositors are unhappy with the decision, as they preferred an established commercial bank to take over the entity rather than a new licensee with no direct experience of running a regular bank.&amp;nbsp; CFS and BharatPe are set to infuse ₹5 billion each into the new entity when starting over and will increase the capital up to ₹30 billion in due course. Additionally, they also have the option to restructure the liability and convert them into capital instruments, take support from the Depositor Insurance and Credit Guarantee Corporation (DICGC) for repayment of insured deposits up to ₹50,000, phase withdrawal plans for individuals with higher deposits or convert the same into tier 1 or tier 2 capital.&amp;nbsp; The joint venture is likely to form a good synergy between BharatPe and Centrum Financial Services. While the former is an establishment specialising in fintech with a strong footprint in the digital lending and Unified Payment Interface (UPI) industry, the latter is a non-banking lender with strong holdings and a good history in providing credit to small-mid size firms. Together they can bring innovation and renewed vigour to a fallen institution.&amp;nbsp; The new entity is to be operational in 120 days post the principal nod given by the central banking authority, and only post this, will the RBI draft a scheme on amalgamation of the two entities with PMC Bank. The plan will then be sent to the government for approval and official notification. Under Section 45 of the Banking Regulation Act, only a bank can be merged with another, therefore, the process of handover will start only once the SFB (Small Finance Bank) is created. Apart from that, the subsidiaries of Centrum namely Centrum Housing Finance and Centrum Microcredit are in the same business as the small finance bank to be set up by them. Hence, this poses a hurdle for Centrum, as one cannot have separate entities doing the same business. Either it will have to sell its majority stake or merge the subsidiaries; or not enter the microcredit and home loan business from the SFB set up, which would mean giving up a major business opportunity for the new joint venture. The RBI has now called for sweeping changes in the Banking Regulation Act, and will be actively looking into the regulation of cooperative banks to avoid such a future debacle. But the problem doesn't stop there, the problem only begins here. India massively lacks transparency in the financial sector and this often puts a lot of wrongdoings away from the eyes of the public and regulatory bodies. There are more important questions that this mess raises. The first being, will the public institutions continue to show vigilance only after the chaos unfolds or will they ever learn to step in the moment the lines are crossed?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Pace of EV Adoption in India</title>
      <link href="/Pace-of-EV-Adoption-in-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pace of EV Adoption in India" />
      <published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Pace-of-EV-Adoption-in-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Pace-of-EV-Adoption-in-India">&lt;p&gt;Over the past ten years, the automobile sector has been gravitating towards electrification. Electrification is essentially the replacement of conventionally used Internal Combustion Engine (ICE) vehicles with more powerful, simpler, smarter and greener Electric Vehicles (EV).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EVs came into being before its ICE counterparts but due to lack of infrastructure, high upfront costs and absence of incentives, they could not gain the deserved spotlight. So, are we to believe that the right time has come to think about the electrification of our cars?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand the situation better, let us look at why it is imperative for India to adopt electric mobility. The Indian automobile market has earned the distinction of being a unique market; the Indian auto and ancillary market is among the largest in the world and constitutes 9% of the country’s GDP. 84% of vehicles sold domestically are either two or three Wheelers (2W/3Ws) and therefore, it is imperative for the nation to adapt to electrification now.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EV adoption in India is more than just a technological upgradation in the automotive sector. There are varying reasons which make it essential for the fifth largest economy to pace up the process of electrification.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extensive and often reckless use of ICE vehicles paired with exorbitant industrial pollution has worsened the nation’s Air Quality Index (AQI), making it the third most polluted country in the world. Moreover, considering the macroeconomic factors, India imports $100 billion worth of crude oil to quench its industrial and retail demand (which is mostly generated by operational ICE vehicles).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that the intent is clear, let’s see how long is the road ahead of our goal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electric mobility targets can only be achieved with joint efforts of all the players in the EV ecosystem. Government incentives, appropriate charging infrastructures, battery costs and manufacturing coupled with Original Equipment Manufacturers (OEMs) transitioning from ICE to EV can help in&amp;nbsp; ramping up the process of electrification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last decade, Indian policymakers have been extensively promoting adoption of electric vehicles, mostly under the umbrella of the National Mission for Electric Mobility (The EV Mission) led by the Department of Heavy Industries (DHI).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction of schemes like FAME II (Faster Adoption and Manufacturing of Hybrid &amp;amp; Electric Vehicles) and Production Linked Incentive (PLI) coupled with GST incentives are pushed to achieve adoption targets, localisation of key components with an aim to foster electric adoption in both private and public transportation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FAME II aims to provide direct financial benefits to EV manufacturers which would benefit in reducing the cost of acquisition for end-customers. As a mechanism, OEMs first pass on the subsidy support to the end-customer by way of decreased purchase price, and later claim the amount from the DHI.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a mismatch between the market demand and the policy’s vision, as since inception, FAME II has only been able to achieve less than 10% of its target of supporting one million electric two-wheelers, half a million of 3Ws, 55,000 four-wheelers and 7,000 buses by 2022. To tackle the same, new amendments were introduced in June 2021 to reduce the overall vehicle cost and revamp the EV adoption scenario in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per the new amendments, the subsidy offered has been revised from ₹10,000 to ₹15,000 per kWh per electric 2W vehicle, thereby increasing the demand incentive by 50%. Maximum cap on subsidies offered has also increased from 20% to 40% of the cost of E-2W, which drastically bridged the Total Cost of Ownership (TCO) gap between conventional ICE and electric two wheelers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electric charging infrastructure in the country is at a very nascent stage and the charging grid is more like a mandate to support the operational leg of the electrification process. Therefore, it is important for India to have the required charging infrastructure to accelerate the process.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India needs about 400 thousand charging stations to meet the requirement for two million&amp;nbsp;electric vehicles&amp;nbsp;that could potentially move on its roads by 2026. Currently, it has about 18 hundred charging stations, most of which are slow chargers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest players in this segment is Tata Power which owns a network of over 500 public chargers in 100+ cities across India, and has recently tied up with HPCL to further expand its network.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To support the forecasted electricity demand that EV adoption is expected to bring with itself, it is a must for the nation to develop grids which are capable of handling the multitudinous increase in load. India relying on its coal dependent grid is said to be one of the most inefficient ones in the world, thus giving a reason for the nation to shift the composition of the grid towards renewables to truly address the pollution problem.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one of his announcements, the Union Power and New and Renewable Energy Minister Raj Kumar Singh disclosed the country’s plans to set up around 14 gigawatt-hour (GWh) grid-scale battery storage system at the world’s largest renewable energy park at Khavda in Gujarat. This is in addition to the plan to invite bids for the largest global tender for setting up a 13GWh grid-scale battery storage system in Ladakh. This strategic push is to make India’s grid-scale battery storage programme the largest in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is encouraging to see the government's action in this regard but there still lays a long road ahead for the nation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another gap which needs to be bridged to achieve EV adoption is the TCO (Total Cost Ownership) disparity between ICE and EVs. TCO is the sum of upfront and operational costs which a customer has to incur through the life of the vehicle. With batteries constituting 35% of the vehicle cost, it is one of the major drivers of EV’s upfront costs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With inefficient indigenous cell technology and limited access to battery raw materials like Lithium and Cobalt, India is yet to become a leading player in the EV battery industry. Local players like Exicom Power, Amar Raja Batteries, Tata Power have plans to turn this around.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electric 2W are smaller vehicles and are easier to electrify, hence they require smaller and simpler batteries and are much closer to economic parity. Li-ion battery based e-rickshaws form a major portion of electric 3W base in the country and have in fact achieved TCO parity and are benefitting from the lower charging costs and time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there still exists a wide gap between TCO parity of electric 4W and buses with their ICE counterparts, mostly due to large battery sizes requirements and lack of complementary infrastructure.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tesla in its recent pitch to the government was successful in lowering import duties on EVs which would eventually make electric vehicles more affordable for the Indian masses. However, the administration is in favor of high import duties as it wishes to encourage domestic production. Therefore, it's too early to show such excitement as only time can vouch for its implementation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the 2W segment being the frontrunner followed by 3W in the ICE-EV shift in India and 4W premium and commercial vehicles yet to achieve the value for money proposition, a lot more has to be done by the government on many fronts such as OEMs transitioning to electric mobility, customers considering EVs over ICE vehicles and other players in the EV segment actively working to achieve India’s goal of becoming a 100% electric vehicle nation by 2030.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Agrawal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Over the past ten years, the automobile sector has been gravitating towards electrification. Electrification is essentially the replacement of conventionally used Internal Combustion Engine (ICE) vehicles with more powerful, simpler, smarter and greener Electric Vehicles (EV).&amp;nbsp; EVs came into being before its ICE counterparts but due to lack of infrastructure, high upfront costs and absence of incentives, they could not gain the deserved spotlight. So, are we to believe that the right time has come to think about the electrification of our cars?&amp;nbsp; To understand the situation better, let us look at why it is imperative for India to adopt electric mobility. The Indian automobile market has earned the distinction of being a unique market; the Indian auto and ancillary market is among the largest in the world and constitutes 9% of the country’s GDP. 84% of vehicles sold domestically are either two or three Wheelers (2W/3Ws) and therefore, it is imperative for the nation to adapt to electrification now.&amp;nbsp; EV adoption in India is more than just a technological upgradation in the automotive sector. There are varying reasons which make it essential for the fifth largest economy to pace up the process of electrification.&amp;nbsp; Extensive and often reckless use of ICE vehicles paired with exorbitant industrial pollution has worsened the nation’s Air Quality Index (AQI), making it the third most polluted country in the world. Moreover, considering the macroeconomic factors, India imports $100 billion worth of crude oil to quench its industrial and retail demand (which is mostly generated by operational ICE vehicles).&amp;nbsp; Now that the intent is clear, let’s see how long is the road ahead of our goal.&amp;nbsp; Electric mobility targets can only be achieved with joint efforts of all the players in the EV ecosystem. Government incentives, appropriate charging infrastructures, battery costs and manufacturing coupled with Original Equipment Manufacturers (OEMs) transitioning from ICE to EV can help in&amp;nbsp; ramping up the process of electrification. Over the last decade, Indian policymakers have been extensively promoting adoption of electric vehicles, mostly under the umbrella of the National Mission for Electric Mobility (The EV Mission) led by the Department of Heavy Industries (DHI).&amp;nbsp; Introduction of schemes like FAME II (Faster Adoption and Manufacturing of Hybrid &amp;amp; Electric Vehicles) and Production Linked Incentive (PLI) coupled with GST incentives are pushed to achieve adoption targets, localisation of key components with an aim to foster electric adoption in both private and public transportation.&amp;nbsp; FAME II aims to provide direct financial benefits to EV manufacturers which would benefit in reducing the cost of acquisition for end-customers. As a mechanism, OEMs first pass on the subsidy support to the end-customer by way of decreased purchase price, and later claim the amount from the DHI.&amp;nbsp; There was a mismatch between the market demand and the policy’s vision, as since inception, FAME II has only been able to achieve less than 10% of its target of supporting one million electric two-wheelers, half a million of 3Ws, 55,000 four-wheelers and 7,000 buses by 2022. To tackle the same, new amendments were introduced in June 2021 to reduce the overall vehicle cost and revamp the EV adoption scenario in the country. As per the new amendments, the subsidy offered has been revised from ₹10,000 to ₹15,000 per kWh per electric 2W vehicle, thereby increasing the demand incentive by 50%. Maximum cap on subsidies offered has also increased from 20% to 40% of the cost of E-2W, which drastically bridged the Total Cost of Ownership (TCO) gap between conventional ICE and electric two wheelers.&amp;nbsp; Electric charging infrastructure in the country is at a very nascent stage and the charging grid is more like a mandate to support the operational leg of the electrification process. Therefore, it is important for India to have the required charging infrastructure to accelerate the process.&amp;nbsp; India needs about 400 thousand charging stations to meet the requirement for two million&amp;nbsp;electric vehicles&amp;nbsp;that could potentially move on its roads by 2026. Currently, it has about 18 hundred charging stations, most of which are slow chargers.&amp;nbsp; One of the biggest players in this segment is Tata Power which owns a network of over 500 public chargers in 100+ cities across India, and has recently tied up with HPCL to further expand its network.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; To support the forecasted electricity demand that EV adoption is expected to bring with itself, it is a must for the nation to develop grids which are capable of handling the multitudinous increase in load. India relying on its coal dependent grid is said to be one of the most inefficient ones in the world, thus giving a reason for the nation to shift the composition of the grid towards renewables to truly address the pollution problem.&amp;nbsp; In one of his announcements, the Union Power and New and Renewable Energy Minister Raj Kumar Singh disclosed the country’s plans to set up around 14 gigawatt-hour (GWh) grid-scale battery storage system at the world’s largest renewable energy park at Khavda in Gujarat. This is in addition to the plan to invite bids for the largest global tender for setting up a 13GWh grid-scale battery storage system in Ladakh. This strategic push is to make India’s grid-scale battery storage programme the largest in the world. It is encouraging to see the government's action in this regard but there still lays a long road ahead for the nation.&amp;nbsp; Another gap which needs to be bridged to achieve EV adoption is the TCO (Total Cost Ownership) disparity between ICE and EVs. TCO is the sum of upfront and operational costs which a customer has to incur through the life of the vehicle. With batteries constituting 35% of the vehicle cost, it is one of the major drivers of EV’s upfront costs.&amp;nbsp; With inefficient indigenous cell technology and limited access to battery raw materials like Lithium and Cobalt, India is yet to become a leading player in the EV battery industry. Local players like Exicom Power, Amar Raja Batteries, Tata Power have plans to turn this around.&amp;nbsp; Electric 2W are smaller vehicles and are easier to electrify, hence they require smaller and simpler batteries and are much closer to economic parity. Li-ion battery based e-rickshaws form a major portion of electric 3W base in the country and have in fact achieved TCO parity and are benefitting from the lower charging costs and time.&amp;nbsp; However, there still exists a wide gap between TCO parity of electric 4W and buses with their ICE counterparts, mostly due to large battery sizes requirements and lack of complementary infrastructure.&amp;nbsp; Tesla in its recent pitch to the government was successful in lowering import duties on EVs which would eventually make electric vehicles more affordable for the Indian masses. However, the administration is in favor of high import duties as it wishes to encourage domestic production. Therefore, it's too early to show such excitement as only time can vouch for its implementation.&amp;nbsp; With the 2W segment being the frontrunner followed by 3W in the ICE-EV shift in India and 4W premium and commercial vehicles yet to achieve the value for money proposition, a lot more has to be done by the government on many fronts such as OEMs transitioning to electric mobility, customers considering EVs over ICE vehicles and other players in the EV segment actively working to achieve India’s goal of becoming a 100% electric vehicle nation by 2030.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Is Ambani or Tata the Ratan the Answer We’ve Been Looking For?</title>
      <link href="/Is-Ambani-or-Tata-the-Ratan-the-Answer-We-ve-Been-Looking-For" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Ambani or Tata the Ratan the Answer We've Been Looking For?" />
      <published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Is-Ambani-or-Tata-the-Ratan-the-Answer-We-ve-Been-Looking-For</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Is-Ambani-or-Tata-the-Ratan-the-Answer-We-ve-Been-Looking-For">&lt;p&gt;The dynamics of the power and influence that the Ambanis and the Tatas hold in the Indian market has evolved considerably in the past few decades. While some may argue that the Reliance group has surpassed the Tata conglomerate, here’s a take on why that’s not even marginally correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preconceived notions, pertaining to money and wealth, are the main reason behind such false assumptions. Mukesh Ambani is indeed the richest man in India with a net worth of $91 billion, while Shri Ratan Tata’s worth is estimated at $1 billion. Based on these statistics alone, people jump to conclusions that the richer party, in this case the Ambanis, is superior to the other side, the Tatas. But is monetary wealth enough of a metric to label which group possesses the higher ground?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ambanis are known for their affluent nature and have never shied away from displaying their prosperity. From throwing weddings of the century, hosting private Beyoncé concerts to living in a 27-storey sky palace, ‘Antilia’, they’ve often caused social media uproar and made headlines.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In stark contrast, Tatas live a relatively humble life with 66% of their company stake held by charitable organisations such as the Sir Ratan Tata Trust, Sir Dorabji Tata Trust, Tata Education Trust to name a few. Their primary goal was, and has always been, the financial and social empowerment of the entire nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To delve further into the details of this ill-conceived and strikingly biased opinion, one must start to understand the elementary difference between a businessman and an industrialist. The former is more concerned with maximising their own profits while, the latter makes it their concern to consider the best interests of the society at large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Booming Businessman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dhirubhai Ambani and his rise to fortune is a true rags-to-riches story. His success in taking his company public in 1977, expanding from textiles to other sectors such as petrochemicals, which in-turn led to the formation of what we know today as ‘Reliance Industries’, was largely owed to his sharp business acumen, excellent entrepreneurial skills and great oratorship. He was what we refer to as a ‘one in a million’ case wherein a high school dropout, with no significant education, made it big!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the major reasons behind his success was the value and vitality he placed on the quality of service that was associated with the Ambani name. He prioritised his promise to the shareholders, declared regular dividends and held annual meetings to strengthen mutual trustworthiness.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After his death in 2002, the company was divided between his two sons, Mukesh and Anil. While the former inherited his father’s business instincts, the same seemed to have been lost in the case of the latter. Mukesh Ambani expanded the spectrum covered under Reliance Industries far beyond expectations, and one of his most remarkable achievements was the launch of Reliance Jio in 2016. Not only was Jio a real game changer, but it also sparked a price war in the super-competitive telecom market in India, and gave otherwise unparalleled companies like Airtel a run for its money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reliance was the first Indian company to be included in the Fortune 500 companies list. The consolidated efforts of two generations, branching from Vimal to Jio, resulted in an increase in annual revenue from ₹700 million at the time its IPO was first launched, to over ₹750 billion in the year 2002.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today RIL is an oil-to-telecom conglomerate with a valuation of about ₹6.10 trillion. It is the first company to have a market capitalisation of ₹9 trillion on the Bombay Stock Exchange (BSE). Out of this, about 48% stake is personally controlled by Mukesh Ambani, and while Reliance did purchase some gas companies in the US and occasionally in Europe, it largely remains an Indian entity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Business must serve a larger societal purpose.” – &lt;/em&gt;Mukesh Ambani&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above statement is quite ironic as the Ambanis, like most business families, donate only a small fraction of their wealth. To substantiate, in 2018, Ambani donated a seemingly grand amount of ₹4.02 billion, which in reality amounted only to 0.1% of his net worth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the world came to a standstill during the pandemic, Reliance Jio continued its successful operations based on the philosophy that the show must go on. Not only did it see a 15.5% growth in net profit to ₹34.89 billion in the fourth quarter of 2020-21, but also an additional increase of 5.2 million customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At such times of crisis, despite having enjoyed phenomenal growth and profits, Mukesh Ambani pledged to donate only ₹50 million to Maharashtra Chief Minister’s Relief Fund as monetary contributions whereas Mr. Ratan Tata, Tata Sons and Tata Trusts collectively pledged a total of ₹15 billion for combating the coronavirus pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The International Industrialist&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey of the trailblazers began in 1868, when Jamsetji Tata invested ₹21,000 in his own trading business. However, his sight was set on the textile business. Following his newfound objective, he returned from England equipped with knowledge and moved out of Mumbai to Nagpur which was comparatively economical.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What made Tatas the true tycoons was the care they extended to their workers and the importance they laid on the welfare of the society. These measures resonated among the masses with the same level of loyalty and appreciation reciprocated by them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jamsetji Tata had four major goals in life: an iron and steel company, a world class educational institution, a hydroelectric power plant and a five star hotel. However, in his lifetime he could only manage to accomplish the task of building the Taj hotel in Mumbai, which serves as a symbol of his glorious march into the future till date. The rest of his dreams were realised by his son Dorabji Tata.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This proud legacy was carried on by JRD Tata, under whom the Tata Group grew from $100 million to over $5 billion, establishing itself as a conglomerate of 95 companies including Tata Tea, Tata Motors &amp;amp; TCS.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, The Tata Group has products and services in 150 countries spread over 6 continents, with a ₹6.11 trillion valuation, $100 billion in revenues, i.e., over ₹11 trillion of market capitalisation and 29 publicly listed companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite such a remarkable feat it's quite intriguing as to why the Tatas are not the richest businessmen in India, though the Tata Group is India’s numero uno conglomerate.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Tatas have done much to introduce industrial capitalism in India in place of the old mercantile and petty capitalism. As the companies progressed, they socialised the business by transferring much of the ownership to charitable trusts.” &lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;- &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Professor Gras of Harvard Business School.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Staying true to this promise, Shri Ratan Tata’s personal stake in Tata industries is less than 1%.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike other business tycoons, he donates a big chunk of his wealth to several trusts, the largest being the Sir Dorabji Tata Trust (28%), followed by the Sir Ratan Tata Trust (23.5%).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Bigger of the Big Fish&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response to when asked why he was not the richest man in the world, Ratan Tata said, &lt;em&gt;“Ambanis are businessmen and the Tatas are industrialists.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This difference in outlook represents a bigger value difference between the two behemoths and their line of thinking. While both the groups create livelihood for millions and represent big parts of India, one chooses to add to the bottom of the pyramid in his own capacity, while one leaves the bigger machinery to its own devices.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is moot to discuss who is doing “more”, but if not for his philanthropic nature, Ratan Tata could easily be one of the richest people in the world, let alone India, making it clear without an iota of doubt that Mukesh Ambani may be the richest man in India but the Tata Conglomerate reigns supreme over Reliance Industries.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Raisa Azad</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The dynamics of the power and influence that the Ambanis and the Tatas hold in the Indian market has evolved considerably in the past few decades. While some may argue that the Reliance group has surpassed the Tata conglomerate, here’s a take on why that’s not even marginally correct. Preconceived notions, pertaining to money and wealth, are the main reason behind such false assumptions. Mukesh Ambani is indeed the richest man in India with a net worth of $91 billion, while Shri Ratan Tata’s worth is estimated at $1 billion. Based on these statistics alone, people jump to conclusions that the richer party, in this case the Ambanis, is superior to the other side, the Tatas. But is monetary wealth enough of a metric to label which group possesses the higher ground? The Ambanis are known for their affluent nature and have never shied away from displaying their prosperity. From throwing weddings of the century, hosting private Beyoncé concerts to living in a 27-storey sky palace, ‘Antilia’, they’ve often caused social media uproar and made headlines.&amp;nbsp; In stark contrast, Tatas live a relatively humble life with 66% of their company stake held by charitable organisations such as the Sir Ratan Tata Trust, Sir Dorabji Tata Trust, Tata Education Trust to name a few. Their primary goal was, and has always been, the financial and social empowerment of the entire nation. To delve further into the details of this ill-conceived and strikingly biased opinion, one must start to understand the elementary difference between a businessman and an industrialist. The former is more concerned with maximising their own profits while, the latter makes it their concern to consider the best interests of the society at large. The Booming Businessman Dhirubhai Ambani and his rise to fortune is a true rags-to-riches story. His success in taking his company public in 1977, expanding from textiles to other sectors such as petrochemicals, which in-turn led to the formation of what we know today as ‘Reliance Industries’, was largely owed to his sharp business acumen, excellent entrepreneurial skills and great oratorship. He was what we refer to as a ‘one in a million’ case wherein a high school dropout, with no significant education, made it big!&amp;nbsp; One of the major reasons behind his success was the value and vitality he placed on the quality of service that was associated with the Ambani name. He prioritised his promise to the shareholders, declared regular dividends and held annual meetings to strengthen mutual trustworthiness.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; After his death in 2002, the company was divided between his two sons, Mukesh and Anil. While the former inherited his father’s business instincts, the same seemed to have been lost in the case of the latter. Mukesh Ambani expanded the spectrum covered under Reliance Industries far beyond expectations, and one of his most remarkable achievements was the launch of Reliance Jio in 2016. Not only was Jio a real game changer, but it also sparked a price war in the super-competitive telecom market in India, and gave otherwise unparalleled companies like Airtel a run for its money. Reliance was the first Indian company to be included in the Fortune 500 companies list. The consolidated efforts of two generations, branching from Vimal to Jio, resulted in an increase in annual revenue from ₹700 million at the time its IPO was first launched, to over ₹750 billion in the year 2002.&amp;nbsp; Today RIL is an oil-to-telecom conglomerate with a valuation of about ₹6.10 trillion. It is the first company to have a market capitalisation of ₹9 trillion on the Bombay Stock Exchange (BSE). Out of this, about 48% stake is personally controlled by Mukesh Ambani, and while Reliance did purchase some gas companies in the US and occasionally in Europe, it largely remains an Indian entity. “Business must serve a larger societal purpose.” – Mukesh Ambani The above statement is quite ironic as the Ambanis, like most business families, donate only a small fraction of their wealth. To substantiate, in 2018, Ambani donated a seemingly grand amount of ₹4.02 billion, which in reality amounted only to 0.1% of his net worth.&amp;nbsp; While the world came to a standstill during the pandemic, Reliance Jio continued its successful operations based on the philosophy that the show must go on. Not only did it see a 15.5% growth in net profit to ₹34.89 billion in the fourth quarter of 2020-21, but also an additional increase of 5.2 million customers. At such times of crisis, despite having enjoyed phenomenal growth and profits, Mukesh Ambani pledged to donate only ₹50 million to Maharashtra Chief Minister’s Relief Fund as monetary contributions whereas Mr. Ratan Tata, Tata Sons and Tata Trusts collectively pledged a total of ₹15 billion for combating the coronavirus pandemic. The International Industrialist&amp;nbsp; The journey of the trailblazers began in 1868, when Jamsetji Tata invested ₹21,000 in his own trading business. However, his sight was set on the textile business. Following his newfound objective, he returned from England equipped with knowledge and moved out of Mumbai to Nagpur which was comparatively economical.&amp;nbsp; What made Tatas the true tycoons was the care they extended to their workers and the importance they laid on the welfare of the society. These measures resonated among the masses with the same level of loyalty and appreciation reciprocated by them. Jamsetji Tata had four major goals in life: an iron and steel company, a world class educational institution, a hydroelectric power plant and a five star hotel. However, in his lifetime he could only manage to accomplish the task of building the Taj hotel in Mumbai, which serves as a symbol of his glorious march into the future till date. The rest of his dreams were realised by his son Dorabji Tata.&amp;nbsp; This proud legacy was carried on by JRD Tata, under whom the Tata Group grew from $100 million to over $5 billion, establishing itself as a conglomerate of 95 companies including Tata Tea, Tata Motors &amp;amp; TCS.&amp;nbsp; Currently, The Tata Group has products and services in 150 countries spread over 6 continents, with a ₹6.11 trillion valuation, $100 billion in revenues, i.e., over ₹11 trillion of market capitalisation and 29 publicly listed companies. Despite such a remarkable feat it's quite intriguing as to why the Tatas are not the richest businessmen in India, though the Tata Group is India’s numero uno conglomerate.&amp;nbsp; “Tatas have done much to introduce industrial capitalism in India in place of the old mercantile and petty capitalism. As the companies progressed, they socialised the business by transferring much of the ownership to charitable trusts.” - Professor Gras of Harvard Business School. Staying true to this promise, Shri Ratan Tata’s personal stake in Tata industries is less than 1%.&amp;nbsp; Unlike other business tycoons, he donates a big chunk of his wealth to several trusts, the largest being the Sir Dorabji Tata Trust (28%), followed by the Sir Ratan Tata Trust (23.5%). The Bigger of the Big Fish In response to when asked why he was not the richest man in the world, Ratan Tata said, “Ambanis are businessmen and the Tatas are industrialists.” This difference in outlook represents a bigger value difference between the two behemoths and their line of thinking. While both the groups create livelihood for millions and represent big parts of India, one chooses to add to the bottom of the pyramid in his own capacity, while one leaves the bigger machinery to its own devices.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; It is moot to discuss who is doing “more”, but if not for his philanthropic nature, Ratan Tata could easily be one of the richest people in the world, let alone India, making it clear without an iota of doubt that Mukesh Ambani may be the richest man in India but the Tata Conglomerate reigns supreme over Reliance Industries.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Power Play: China’s Command &amp;amp; Control</title>
      <link href="/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Power Play: China's Command &amp; Control" />
      <published>2021-09-21T02:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-21T02:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control">&lt;p&gt;In November 2020, I authored an article on China’s move of&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Derailing-of-the-World-s-Biggest-IPO&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt; scuttling Ant Group Co.’s blockbuster $37 billion listing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Little did we know that it was just the beginning of an excessive clampdown on the country's technological sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To continue with the story of e-commerce giant Alibaba, the country’s authorities imposed a record fine - $2.8 billion in 2021, after an investigation that found it had abused its dominant market position for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China’s unprecedented crackdown on its tech industry has cost several companies and their investors hundreds of billions of dollars. Tencent alone has &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/markets/stocks/news/market-darling-tencent-turns-into-worlds-worst-stock-bet-with-170-billion-wipeout/articleshow/84853892.cms&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;had $170 billion shaved off its value&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; For context, that’s more than ten Byju’s, India’s biggest startup, which is valued at $16.5 billion.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The July Roundup by Goldman Sachs Group Inc shows that since November, the country’s regulators have taken more than 50 actual or reported actions on areas spanning antitrust, finance, data security and social equality, i.e. more than one move a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, China has assiduously built up its tech sector, and has borrowed an industrial and internet model from the West. Arguably it was a resounding success, then why is it now trying to strangle the golden goose it had once cradled?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.natlawreview.com/article/china-issues-data-security-law&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;adopted a new cybersecurity law in June&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which builds on the foundation of the 2017 Cyber Security Law, that started tightening the control of data flow. However, since the measure was vaguely worded, it remained unclear how it would be implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around the same time, the Chinese economy was rebounding from its bout with COVID-19, lifting the nation's&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/06/10/didi-chuxing-files-for-ipo-booked-6point4-billion-revenue-in-q1.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/06/10/didi-chuxing-files-for-ipo-booked-6point4-billion-revenue-in-q1.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;ride, hailing giant Didi Global&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s revenue with it as the US stock market continued to be in a bull run. Didi's long venture investors, including Softbank’s Vision Fund, urged seizing the moment to take the company public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company made its debut at $14 on the New York Stock Exchange on the last day of June 2021, raising $4.4 billion - the biggest stock sale by a Chinese company since the 2014 listing of Alibaba Group Holding Ltd.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its shares briefly topped $18 in the first days of trading, before China’s cyber security watchdog - Cyberspace Administration of China (CAC) stunned investors on July 2 by launching a data-security probe into Didi and blocking its China business from adding new users.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crackdown worsened on July 9, when 25 more Didi apps - including ones used by drivers - were ordered to be removed from app stores, potentially crippling the company’s operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this was not enough, the administration further extended its clampdown on other sectors in&amp;nbsp; July. On July 22, the government &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/tech/startups/china-strengthens-protection-for-food-delivery-workers-in-setback-for-meituan-alibaba/articleshow/84755202.cms&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;announced new worker protection rules&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, under which online food platforms must cover minimum wage and insurance benefits. This gutted the share price of delivery giants such as Meituan and its rival, Alibaba's Ele.me; which had drawn severe criticism on social media for their treatment of riders and guaranteed time-bound delivery which has compelled riders to undertake dangerous routes, risking their lives.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the following day, Beijing effectively torpedoed a multibillion-dollar industry - after-school tutoring - with a single administrative order. The new rules banned companies that teach the K-12 school curriculum from going public and registering themselves as non-profits. The shares of the three largest US-listed Chinese edtech firms - TAL Education, New Oriental and Gaotu Techedu, fell by 65-70% on the announcement, and the founders of the latter two companies went from billionaires to millionaires almost instantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The corporate intervention that has hammered internet stocks is now driving investors to sectors still in Beijing’s good graces, such as high-tech manufacturing and renewable energy. Indexes for new energy stocks, semiconductor makers and electric vehicle companies, outperformed the market from 4% to 18% since the beginning of July.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Broadly, Beijing is concerned about four pillars of stability: banking, antitrust regulation, data security and social equality. For example, social equality being at the heart of the ban of for-profit after-school tutors or rights concerning gig economy workers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some market participants believe China is trying to direct capital and human resources from internet companies into sectors that will help the country become more self-reliant. A portfolio manager at M&amp;amp;G Investments, Singapore, tracking the Chinese economy said, “&lt;em&gt;They are trying to reach a new equilibrium because it seems capital flows were not in line with long-term, top- down priorities.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts believe the government’s latest initiatives are motivated by a bigger ambition to realign the relationship between private business and the state, with a goal of ensuring companies do more to serve the Communist Party’s economic, social and national security concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it is worth noticing that Huawei, which should fall under the purview of the state on every possible reason in law, is entirely untouched.&amp;nbsp; As per some observers, the reason for the telecom giant being solidly backed by Beijing is due to the mutual benefit of both parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China’s vision for a domestic adversary as opposed to a Silicon Valley has benefited the private companies for years from lax regulatory oversight. However, leaders now worry that the tech giants have become too big and could be using personal and corporate digital records as leverage to build &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/china-blocked-jack-mas-ant-ipo-after-an-investigation-revealed-who-stood-to-gain-11613491292?mod=searchresults_pos10&amp;amp;page=1&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;alternative power centers&lt;/a&gt; in the one-party state.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, the government has often demanded data from private firms, and could sometimes enforce its wishes, especially for hunting down criminal suspects and silencing dissent but the tech companies have pushed back on requests to share and centralise their statistics.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, Beijing now wishes to undo these through their complex cyber security laws and regulations which would make it harder for companies to resist data sharing requests.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chinese regulators have formally made the data localisation requirement a prerequisite for foreign institutions trying to get a foothold in China, enabling the government to have more authority over the records. Western companies have long complained such “data localisation” requirements could stifle innovation in their global operations or enable Chinese authorities to steal their proprietary information.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US electric car maker &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/market-data/quotes/TSLA&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Tesla&lt;/a&gt; Inc has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/tesla-to-store-china-data-locally-in-new-data-center-11622015001?mod=article_inline&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pledged&lt;/a&gt; to build more data centers in China and to keep information generated by the vehicles it sells there, within Chinese borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Less invasive private-sector data collection anywhere is a good thing,” says analyst Ryan Fedasiuk at Georgetown University’s Center for Security and Emerging Technology. “But China’s push for data privacy strikes me as yet another move to strengthen the role of the government and the party vis-à-vis tech companies.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the EU rules, the Chinese version lacks restrictions on government entities when it comes to gathering information on people’s call logs, contact lists, location and other data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, these laws should also be seen against the backdrop of high tensions between US-China relations, which has sharpened President Xi’s focus on security and self-sufficiency. Beijing prohibits foreign ownership of larger sections of the Chinese economy, especially the profitable parts involving digital technology and data, and hence the companies follow a concept of&amp;nbsp; Variable-Interest-Entity or VIE, where the companies selling shares in foreign markets (including Hong Kong) can do so only quasi-legally at best. The workaround for VIE was the transparency that would come with foreign ownership and control which could reveal more about the state of the economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under a 2020 law signed by then-President, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/topics/person/donald-trump&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Donald Trump&lt;/a&gt;, Chinese companies would have to share their audit working papers with the US regulators. Failure to do so would lead to delisting of companies from US exchanges.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For China, that could risk allowing key data, such as detailed information about Chinese consumers and government agencies that may be included in the papers, to end up in the hands of a foreign government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both the second largest economy in the world and West see tech as a possible disrupter, however, it’s the Chinese who seem to be turbocharging a move towards the real tech, where they are ready to destroy the ‘pre-tender’ that exists today.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In November 2020, I authored an article on China’s move of scuttling Ant Group Co.’s blockbuster $37 billion listing. Little did we know that it was just the beginning of an excessive clampdown on the country's technological sector.&amp;nbsp; To continue with the story of e-commerce giant Alibaba, the country’s authorities imposed a record fine - $2.8 billion in 2021, after an investigation that found it had abused its dominant market position for years. China’s unprecedented crackdown on its tech industry has cost several companies and their investors hundreds of billions of dollars. Tencent alone has had $170 billion shaved off its value. For context, that’s more than ten Byju’s, India’s biggest startup, which is valued at $16.5 billion.&amp;nbsp; The July Roundup by Goldman Sachs Group Inc shows that since November, the country’s regulators have taken more than 50 actual or reported actions on areas spanning antitrust, finance, data security and social equality, i.e. more than one move a week. For decades, China has assiduously built up its tech sector, and has borrowed an industrial and internet model from the West. Arguably it was a resounding success, then why is it now trying to strangle the golden goose it had once cradled?&amp;nbsp; China adopted a new cybersecurity law in June, which builds on the foundation of the 2017 Cyber Security Law, that started tightening the control of data flow. However, since the measure was vaguely worded, it remained unclear how it would be implemented. Around the same time, the Chinese economy was rebounding from its bout with COVID-19, lifting the nation's ride, hailing giant Didi Global’s revenue with it as the US stock market continued to be in a bull run. Didi's long venture investors, including Softbank’s Vision Fund, urged seizing the moment to take the company public. The company made its debut at $14 on the New York Stock Exchange on the last day of June 2021, raising $4.4 billion - the biggest stock sale by a Chinese company since the 2014 listing of Alibaba Group Holding Ltd.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Its shares briefly topped $18 in the first days of trading, before China’s cyber security watchdog - Cyberspace Administration of China (CAC) stunned investors on July 2 by launching a data-security probe into Didi and blocking its China business from adding new users.&amp;nbsp; The crackdown worsened on July 9, when 25 more Didi apps - including ones used by drivers - were ordered to be removed from app stores, potentially crippling the company’s operations. If this was not enough, the administration further extended its clampdown on other sectors in&amp;nbsp; July. On July 22, the government announced new worker protection rules, under which online food platforms must cover minimum wage and insurance benefits. This gutted the share price of delivery giants such as Meituan and its rival, Alibaba's Ele.me; which had drawn severe criticism on social media for their treatment of riders and guaranteed time-bound delivery which has compelled riders to undertake dangerous routes, risking their lives.&amp;nbsp; On the following day, Beijing effectively torpedoed a multibillion-dollar industry - after-school tutoring - with a single administrative order. The new rules banned companies that teach the K-12 school curriculum from going public and registering themselves as non-profits. The shares of the three largest US-listed Chinese edtech firms - TAL Education, New Oriental and Gaotu Techedu, fell by 65-70% on the announcement, and the founders of the latter two companies went from billionaires to millionaires almost instantly. The corporate intervention that has hammered internet stocks is now driving investors to sectors still in Beijing’s good graces, such as high-tech manufacturing and renewable energy. Indexes for new energy stocks, semiconductor makers and electric vehicle companies, outperformed the market from 4% to 18% since the beginning of July.&amp;nbsp; Broadly, Beijing is concerned about four pillars of stability: banking, antitrust regulation, data security and social equality. For example, social equality being at the heart of the ban of for-profit after-school tutors or rights concerning gig economy workers.&amp;nbsp; Some market participants believe China is trying to direct capital and human resources from internet companies into sectors that will help the country become more self-reliant. A portfolio manager at M&amp;amp;G Investments, Singapore, tracking the Chinese economy said, “They are trying to reach a new equilibrium because it seems capital flows were not in line with long-term, top- down priorities.” Analysts believe the government’s latest initiatives are motivated by a bigger ambition to realign the relationship between private business and the state, with a goal of ensuring companies do more to serve the Communist Party’s economic, social and national security concerns. However, it is worth noticing that Huawei, which should fall under the purview of the state on every possible reason in law, is entirely untouched.&amp;nbsp; As per some observers, the reason for the telecom giant being solidly backed by Beijing is due to the mutual benefit of both parties. China’s vision for a domestic adversary as opposed to a Silicon Valley has benefited the private companies for years from lax regulatory oversight. However, leaders now worry that the tech giants have become too big and could be using personal and corporate digital records as leverage to build alternative power centers in the one-party state.&amp;nbsp; In the past, the government has often demanded data from private firms, and could sometimes enforce its wishes, especially for hunting down criminal suspects and silencing dissent but the tech companies have pushed back on requests to share and centralise their statistics.&amp;nbsp; Nonetheless, Beijing now wishes to undo these through their complex cyber security laws and regulations which would make it harder for companies to resist data sharing requests.&amp;nbsp; Chinese regulators have formally made the data localisation requirement a prerequisite for foreign institutions trying to get a foothold in China, enabling the government to have more authority over the records. Western companies have long complained such “data localisation” requirements could stifle innovation in their global operations or enable Chinese authorities to steal their proprietary information.&amp;nbsp; US electric car maker Tesla Inc has pledged to build more data centers in China and to keep information generated by the vehicles it sells there, within Chinese borders. “Less invasive private-sector data collection anywhere is a good thing,” says analyst Ryan Fedasiuk at Georgetown University’s Center for Security and Emerging Technology. “But China’s push for data privacy strikes me as yet another move to strengthen the role of the government and the party vis-à-vis tech companies.” Unlike the EU rules, the Chinese version lacks restrictions on government entities when it comes to gathering information on people’s call logs, contact lists, location and other data. Meanwhile, these laws should also be seen against the backdrop of high tensions between US-China relations, which has sharpened President Xi’s focus on security and self-sufficiency. Beijing prohibits foreign ownership of larger sections of the Chinese economy, especially the profitable parts involving digital technology and data, and hence the companies follow a concept of&amp;nbsp; Variable-Interest-Entity or VIE, where the companies selling shares in foreign markets (including Hong Kong) can do so only quasi-legally at best. The workaround for VIE was the transparency that would come with foreign ownership and control which could reveal more about the state of the economy.&amp;nbsp; Under a 2020 law signed by then-President, Donald Trump, Chinese companies would have to share their audit working papers with the US regulators. Failure to do so would lead to delisting of companies from US exchanges.&amp;nbsp; For China, that could risk allowing key data, such as detailed information about Chinese consumers and government agencies that may be included in the papers, to end up in the hands of a foreign government. Both the second largest economy in the world and West see tech as a possible disrupter, however, it’s the Chinese who seem to be turbocharging a move towards the real tech, where they are ready to destroy the ‘pre-tender’ that exists today.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Combating the Menace of Counterfeits</title>
      <link href="/Combating-the-Menace-of-Counterfeits" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Combating the Menace of Counterfeits" />
      <published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Combating-the-Menace-of-Counterfeits</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Combating-the-Menace-of-Counterfeits">&lt;p&gt;How often do you see a dubious Hermes scarf or a pair of Prada shoes on sale in the street markets?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Counterfeiting is regarded as one of the ‘oldest crimes in history’. The origins of pirated brands of luxury articles can be traced back to 27 AD when a wine merchant named Gaul feigned expensive Roman wines and sold cheaper wine to earn huge profits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of counterfeit products has proliferated enormously, by about 10,000% in the last two decades, to be precise, contributing to the sheer volume, sophistication, and increasing ‘globalisation’ of the counterfeit market.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The International Anti-Counterfeiting Coalition (2012) estimates that counterfeiting is a $600 billion problem representing a sizable and growing percentage of all world trade. Fuelled by consumer demand, this counterfeit market has increasingly been putting an acute burden on companies as they grapple with the intricate challenges of protecting intellectual property rights and safeguarding the integrity of their products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are various interpretations of counterfeiting as a concept. Some researchers say that counterfeiting involves imitating product attributes to make them indistinguishable from the original and selling them at a lower price. At the same time, others say that it is the production of copies that are identically-packaged, including trademarks and labelling, to make it seem like a genuine article.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Counterfeiting can essentially be defined as the forgery of a product whose unique characteristics are protected as intellectual property rights.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the consumer’s perspective, counterfeiting has two forms, that is, deceptive and non-deceptive. Under deceptive counterfeiting, the consumer is a victim of a sham since he/she is not aware of purchasing a fake product. Non-deceptive counterfeiting identifies consumers as active and enthusiastic players in counterfeiting transactions. This form of counterfeiting is commonplace in the luxury brand markets, where consumers are often able to discern the ersatz products based on the differences in price, quality, and distribution channels.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumer complicity with counterfeits has attracted vibrant controversy over the years. Price difference is the chief advantage of forged goods since they give consumers the same prestige without making them pay a hefty amount. A significant relationship has been established between the place of origin, consumers’ ethnocentrism, and psychographic variables. Buyers of these substitute goods are usually characterised by low-income levels and, sometimes, low self-esteem.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brand visibility is equally recognised as a substantial decisional factor in buying intention. Brands that are globally more conspicuous and have ‘loud logos’ are more susceptible to piracy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another dimension of counterfeit consumption consists of the mood and situational context of the buyer. For instance, consumers are likely to purchase pirated goods while abroad or on a holiday since these goods can provide an authentic experience to tourist consumers. Tourists visiting Morocco constitute a vital segment of the counterfeit market. Moroccan hawkers are well known amongst European tourists for carrying a wide range of phoney labels such as Chanel, Fendi, and&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Louis Vuitton. A fake Levi’s shirt, for example, is sold for less than one-tenth of the price of the genuine brand.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The existence of the counterfeiting phenomenon may also be associated with consumers’ ethical and lawful cues. A consumer’s ethical awareness is measured along two axes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is his or her own judgement. This refers to the feeling of pride or culpability arising from the use of cheap knock-offs. A majority of buyers do not perceive any harm and feel less accountable for counterfeit-buying behaviour. Consumers are willing to jettison avowed ethical principles for low prices and other product attributes. Their hedonic motivations far outweigh their ethical concerns.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many times, ethical constraints may be directly linked to legal punishments. Some buyers hold a lax attitude about legal protection of intellectual property and indulge in counterfeiting transactions despite unscrupulous and illegal underpinnings. For them, breaking the relevant law heightens a sense of pleasure and adventure. As the product attributes’ salience increases and becomes progressively alluring, buyers also become ready to take risks related to dissatisfaction with the product as well as legal violations and sometimes, health risks too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second axis comprises societal judgment. The ‘status-seeking’ paradigm is often applied to explain the motivation of proletariats to purchase rip-offs since they seek to imitate consumption standards of their wealthy counterparts to communicate a desired self-image and provide a self-concept reinforcement, a visible proof that the consumer can afford premium prices. These consumers construct an identity wherein they perceive themselves as savvy individuals.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social influence can have both a negative or positive stimulus in consumer purchasing intentions and conformity motives. ‘Without a brand, nobody looks at you in the street’-&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This general consumer opinion throws light on the fact that consumers are more interested in the social necessity of luxury than the luxury in itself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, Chinese society has traditionally focused on social behaviour over the personal, which explains the extreme sensitivity of Chinese consumers towards the attention and reaction of others.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the backdrop of a Confucian society, Chinese consumers behave irrationally while purchasing luxury brands because these brands are something similar to ‘must haves’ for them to gratify vanity. However, due to highly uneven wealth distribution and the consequent burgeoning gap between the rich and poor, the desire for these brands with exorbitant price tags remains unfulfilled. This contributes to a dissonance whereby consumers at lower levels of the wealth spectrum resort to replicas for manifesting their desired status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While China, North Korea, and Taiwan have been acknowledged as the famous ‘made in’ for counterfeit products, there has been a shifting pattern to regions and countries hitherto unfocused as hubs for distributing fake brands. An example of such a region is the Middle East and North Africa region (MENA), which is flourishing in the international trading scenario and concomitantly shifting astronomical volumes of counterfeit goods to Europe, exploiting the contiguous and porous borders with the continent.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of dummy products seized at the European Union Border rose from 10 million in 1990 to 41 million in 2016 with a total worth of $780 million. Should the growth of this illicit trade remain constant, according to the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, total losses for industries of original goods should be profoundly debilitating. The US industries would be the most drastically impacted with a possible loss of more than 75 million jobs per year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers seem to value quality in their intention to purchase counterfeit items. If the quality of replicas is fairly perceived in terms of relative quality, consumers’ disposition to purchase increases manifolds. This suggests a critical challenge for companies. A strong brand is a ‘moving target’ for counterfeiters, especially when it appears to serve ‘social adjustive’ rather than ‘value adjustive’ functions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marketing communications should emphasise product credibility and ethical credentials, as well as the pitfalls of buying dummies and the hidden human costs of a counterfeit economy which would act as a negative enforcer for this type of purchasing behaviour. Communication campaigns should be aimed at increasing consumer awareness of the superior quality and the value delivered by authentic brands.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public education and enlightenment could be the key to fight the demand for counterfeits. Companies should adopt marketing strategies with sensitivity to the operating environments of consumers in developing countries. Some companies have begun adopting a product adaptation strategy as opposed to a product standardisation strategy to act as a countervailing factor on behavioural intentions towards purchasing rip-offs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High performance, durability and low health risk should also be a part of a company’s promotional message. Brands should improve a consumer’s product usage experience which refers to cognitions, fantasies, and sensations evoked by brand-related stimuli. They should keep design high on their agenda whilst developing new products. The more distinctive the design is, the more difficult it becomes to imitate it, especially using low-scale technology.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all its ramifications, counterfeiting strikes a massive blow to the most valuable asset of an enterprise, that is, the brand image. The symbolism of a strong brand image lies in how it underpins the brand's strength in the market. Companies cannot overcome this obstacle alone. Counterfeiters are imaginative, flexible and above all, pursue continuous adaptation to the market much like leading innovative companies do.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a public policy dimension to this issue. Governments have an imperative role in protecting all property rights and curbing the flow of imitations along with multilateral agencies like WTO.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, in an effort to crack down on counterfeit trade, raids in New York alone resulted in a seizure of over $200 million worth of bogus brands and about 34% of national intellectual property. Moreover, in many developing countries, anti-counterfeiting legislations exist but have glaring lacunae which are never resolved.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, tackling counterfeiting is not an exclusive preserve of any single entity (government, business, or para-governmental agencies) but a shared obligation. There is a lot at stake for manufacturers, consumers, and the industrial nations if the peril is not effectively checked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The underlying issue with counterfeiting is not so much about consumer protection from potential risk implications per se. The real issue is much more convoluted. It is about creating a fair and safe environment for the main actors in global trade and society.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from the dire consequences for corporates and genuine item innovation and economic welfare, counterfeit production also escalates illegal practices in the unorganised sector where workers are denied their fundamental rights, and there is little or no attention paid to social or environmental concerns. Equally grave are the skyrocketing social problems which&amp;nbsp; include drug trafficking, terrorism, and human and capital insecurity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, Morocco’s counterfeiting industry has been linked to organised criminal clans who smuggle these goods and re-export them to Europe. The demand for counterfeit goods shows little or no sign of abatement. Instead, it appears likely to increase remarkably in tandem with the growth of the country’s tourism industry.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essentially, the fight against counterfeiting is a legal battle to promote marketplace righteousness and a conflict for the mind of the consumer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhinav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">How often do you see a dubious Hermes scarf or a pair of Prada shoes on sale in the street markets?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Counterfeiting is regarded as one of the ‘oldest crimes in history’. The origins of pirated brands of luxury articles can be traced back to 27 AD when a wine merchant named Gaul feigned expensive Roman wines and sold cheaper wine to earn huge profits.&amp;nbsp; The use of counterfeit products has proliferated enormously, by about 10,000% in the last two decades, to be precise, contributing to the sheer volume, sophistication, and increasing ‘globalisation’ of the counterfeit market.&amp;nbsp; The International Anti-Counterfeiting Coalition (2012) estimates that counterfeiting is a $600 billion problem representing a sizable and growing percentage of all world trade. Fuelled by consumer demand, this counterfeit market has increasingly been putting an acute burden on companies as they grapple with the intricate challenges of protecting intellectual property rights and safeguarding the integrity of their products. There are various interpretations of counterfeiting as a concept. Some researchers say that counterfeiting involves imitating product attributes to make them indistinguishable from the original and selling them at a lower price. At the same time, others say that it is the production of copies that are identically-packaged, including trademarks and labelling, to make it seem like a genuine article.&amp;nbsp; Counterfeiting can essentially be defined as the forgery of a product whose unique characteristics are protected as intellectual property rights.&amp;nbsp; From the consumer’s perspective, counterfeiting has two forms, that is, deceptive and non-deceptive. Under deceptive counterfeiting, the consumer is a victim of a sham since he/she is not aware of purchasing a fake product. Non-deceptive counterfeiting identifies consumers as active and enthusiastic players in counterfeiting transactions. This form of counterfeiting is commonplace in the luxury brand markets, where consumers are often able to discern the ersatz products based on the differences in price, quality, and distribution channels.&amp;nbsp; Consumer complicity with counterfeits has attracted vibrant controversy over the years. Price difference is the chief advantage of forged goods since they give consumers the same prestige without making them pay a hefty amount. A significant relationship has been established between the place of origin, consumers’ ethnocentrism, and psychographic variables. Buyers of these substitute goods are usually characterised by low-income levels and, sometimes, low self-esteem.&amp;nbsp; Brand visibility is equally recognised as a substantial decisional factor in buying intention. Brands that are globally more conspicuous and have ‘loud logos’ are more susceptible to piracy.&amp;nbsp; Another dimension of counterfeit consumption consists of the mood and situational context of the buyer. For instance, consumers are likely to purchase pirated goods while abroad or on a holiday since these goods can provide an authentic experience to tourist consumers. Tourists visiting Morocco constitute a vital segment of the counterfeit market. Moroccan hawkers are well known amongst European tourists for carrying a wide range of phoney labels such as Chanel, Fendi, and Louis Vuitton. A fake Levi’s shirt, for example, is sold for less than one-tenth of the price of the genuine brand.&amp;nbsp; The existence of the counterfeiting phenomenon may also be associated with consumers’ ethical and lawful cues. A consumer’s ethical awareness is measured along two axes.&amp;nbsp; The first is his or her own judgement. This refers to the feeling of pride or culpability arising from the use of cheap knock-offs. A majority of buyers do not perceive any harm and feel less accountable for counterfeit-buying behaviour. Consumers are willing to jettison avowed ethical principles for low prices and other product attributes. Their hedonic motivations far outweigh their ethical concerns.&amp;nbsp; Many times, ethical constraints may be directly linked to legal punishments. Some buyers hold a lax attitude about legal protection of intellectual property and indulge in counterfeiting transactions despite unscrupulous and illegal underpinnings. For them, breaking the relevant law heightens a sense of pleasure and adventure. As the product attributes’ salience increases and becomes progressively alluring, buyers also become ready to take risks related to dissatisfaction with the product as well as legal violations and sometimes, health risks too. The second axis comprises societal judgment. The ‘status-seeking’ paradigm is often applied to explain the motivation of proletariats to purchase rip-offs since they seek to imitate consumption standards of their wealthy counterparts to communicate a desired self-image and provide a self-concept reinforcement, a visible proof that the consumer can afford premium prices. These consumers construct an identity wherein they perceive themselves as savvy individuals.&amp;nbsp; Social influence can have both a negative or positive stimulus in consumer purchasing intentions and conformity motives. ‘Without a brand, nobody looks at you in the street’-&amp;nbsp; This general consumer opinion throws light on the fact that consumers are more interested in the social necessity of luxury than the luxury in itself.&amp;nbsp; For instance, Chinese society has traditionally focused on social behaviour over the personal, which explains the extreme sensitivity of Chinese consumers towards the attention and reaction of others.&amp;nbsp; In the backdrop of a Confucian society, Chinese consumers behave irrationally while purchasing luxury brands because these brands are something similar to ‘must haves’ for them to gratify vanity. However, due to highly uneven wealth distribution and the consequent burgeoning gap between the rich and poor, the desire for these brands with exorbitant price tags remains unfulfilled. This contributes to a dissonance whereby consumers at lower levels of the wealth spectrum resort to replicas for manifesting their desired status. While China, North Korea, and Taiwan have been acknowledged as the famous ‘made in’ for counterfeit products, there has been a shifting pattern to regions and countries hitherto unfocused as hubs for distributing fake brands. An example of such a region is the Middle East and North Africa region (MENA), which is flourishing in the international trading scenario and concomitantly shifting astronomical volumes of counterfeit goods to Europe, exploiting the contiguous and porous borders with the continent.&amp;nbsp; The number of dummy products seized at the European Union Border rose from 10 million in 1990 to 41 million in 2016 with a total worth of $780 million. Should the growth of this illicit trade remain constant, according to the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, total losses for industries of original goods should be profoundly debilitating. The US industries would be the most drastically impacted with a possible loss of more than 75 million jobs per year.&amp;nbsp; Consumers seem to value quality in their intention to purchase counterfeit items. If the quality of replicas is fairly perceived in terms of relative quality, consumers’ disposition to purchase increases manifolds. This suggests a critical challenge for companies. A strong brand is a ‘moving target’ for counterfeiters, especially when it appears to serve ‘social adjustive’ rather than ‘value adjustive’ functions.&amp;nbsp; Marketing communications should emphasise product credibility and ethical credentials, as well as the pitfalls of buying dummies and the hidden human costs of a counterfeit economy which would act as a negative enforcer for this type of purchasing behaviour. Communication campaigns should be aimed at increasing consumer awareness of the superior quality and the value delivered by authentic brands.&amp;nbsp; Public education and enlightenment could be the key to fight the demand for counterfeits. Companies should adopt marketing strategies with sensitivity to the operating environments of consumers in developing countries. Some companies have begun adopting a product adaptation strategy as opposed to a product standardisation strategy to act as a countervailing factor on behavioural intentions towards purchasing rip-offs.&amp;nbsp; High performance, durability and low health risk should also be a part of a company’s promotional message. Brands should improve a consumer’s product usage experience which refers to cognitions, fantasies, and sensations evoked by brand-related stimuli. They should keep design high on their agenda whilst developing new products. The more distinctive the design is, the more difficult it becomes to imitate it, especially using low-scale technology.&amp;nbsp; In all its ramifications, counterfeiting strikes a massive blow to the most valuable asset of an enterprise, that is, the brand image. The symbolism of a strong brand image lies in how it underpins the brand's strength in the market. Companies cannot overcome this obstacle alone. Counterfeiters are imaginative, flexible and above all, pursue continuous adaptation to the market much like leading innovative companies do.&amp;nbsp; There is a public policy dimension to this issue. Governments have an imperative role in protecting all property rights and curbing the flow of imitations along with multilateral agencies like WTO.&amp;nbsp; For instance, in an effort to crack down on counterfeit trade, raids in New York alone resulted in a seizure of over $200 million worth of bogus brands and about 34% of national intellectual property. Moreover, in many developing countries, anti-counterfeiting legislations exist but have glaring lacunae which are never resolved.&amp;nbsp; However, tackling counterfeiting is not an exclusive preserve of any single entity (government, business, or para-governmental agencies) but a shared obligation. There is a lot at stake for manufacturers, consumers, and the industrial nations if the peril is not effectively checked. The underlying issue with counterfeiting is not so much about consumer protection from potential risk implications per se. The real issue is much more convoluted. It is about creating a fair and safe environment for the main actors in global trade and society.&amp;nbsp; Apart from the dire consequences for corporates and genuine item innovation and economic welfare, counterfeit production also escalates illegal practices in the unorganised sector where workers are denied their fundamental rights, and there is little or no attention paid to social or environmental concerns. Equally grave are the skyrocketing social problems which&amp;nbsp; include drug trafficking, terrorism, and human and capital insecurity.&amp;nbsp; For instance, Morocco’s counterfeiting industry has been linked to organised criminal clans who smuggle these goods and re-export them to Europe. The demand for counterfeit goods shows little or no sign of abatement. Instead, it appears likely to increase remarkably in tandem with the growth of the country’s tourism industry.&amp;nbsp; Essentially, the fight against counterfeiting is a legal battle to promote marketplace righteousness and a conflict for the mind of the consumer.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Combating the Menace of Counterfeits</title>
      <link href="/Combating-the-Menace-of-Counterfeits" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Combating the Menace of Counterfeits" />
      <published>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Combating-the-Menace-of-Counterfeits</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Combating-the-Menace-of-Counterfeits">&lt;p&gt;How often do you see a dubious Hermes scarf or a pair of Prada shoes on sale in the street markets?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Counterfeiting is regarded as one of the ‘oldest crimes in history’. The origins of pirated brands of luxury articles can be traced back to 27 AD when a wine merchant named Gaul feigned expensive Roman wines and sold cheaper wine to earn huge profits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of counterfeit products has proliferated enormously, by about 10,000% in the last two decades, to be precise, contributing to the sheer volume, sophistication, and increasing ‘globalisation’ of the counterfeit market.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The International Anti-Counterfeiting Coalition (2012) estimates that counterfeiting is a $600 billion problem representing a sizable and growing percentage of all world trade. Fuelled by consumer demand, this counterfeit market has increasingly been putting an acute burden on companies as they grapple with the intricate challenges of protecting intellectual property rights and safeguarding the integrity of their products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are various interpretations of counterfeiting as a concept. Some researchers say that counterfeiting involves imitating product attributes to make them indistinguishable from the original and selling them at a lower price. At the same time, others say that it is the production of copies that are identically-packaged, including trademarks and labelling, to make it seem like a genuine article.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Counterfeiting can essentially be defined as the forgery of a product whose unique characteristics are protected as intellectual property rights.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the consumer’s perspective, counterfeiting has two forms, that is, deceptive and non-deceptive. Under deceptive counterfeiting, the consumer is a victim of a sham since he/she is not aware of purchasing a fake product. Non-deceptive counterfeiting identifies consumers as active and enthusiastic players in counterfeiting transactions. This form of counterfeiting is commonplace in the luxury brand markets, where consumers are often able to discern the ersatz products based on the differences in price, quality, and distribution channels.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumer complicity with counterfeits has attracted vibrant controversy over the years. Price difference is the chief advantage of forged goods since they give consumers the same prestige without making them pay a hefty amount. A significant relationship has been established between the place of origin, consumers’ ethnocentrism, and psychographic variables. Buyers of these substitute goods are usually characterised by low-income levels and, sometimes, low self-esteem.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brand visibility is equally recognised as a substantial decisional factor in buying intention. Brands that are globally more conspicuous and have ‘loud logos’ are more susceptible to piracy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another dimension of counterfeit consumption consists of the mood and situational context of the buyer. For instance, consumers are likely to purchase pirated goods while abroad or on a holiday since these goods can provide an authentic experience to tourist consumers. Tourists visiting Morocco constitute a vital segment of the counterfeit market. Moroccan hawkers are well known amongst European tourists for carrying a wide range of phoney labels such as Chanel, Fendi, and&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Louis Vuitton. A fake Levi’s shirt, for example, is sold for less than one-tenth of the price of the genuine brand.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The existence of the counterfeiting phenomenon may also be associated with consumers’ ethical and lawful cues. A consumer’s ethical awareness is measured along two axes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is his or her own judgement. This refers to the feeling of pride or culpability arising from the use of cheap knock-offs. A majority of buyers do not perceive any harm and feel less accountable for counterfeit-buying behaviour. Consumers are willing to jettison avowed ethical principles for low prices and other product attributes. Their hedonic motivations far outweigh their ethical concerns.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many times, ethical constraints may be directly linked to legal punishments. Some buyers hold a lax attitude about legal protection of intellectual property and indulge in counterfeiting transactions despite unscrupulous and illegal underpinnings. For them, breaking the relevant law heightens a sense of pleasure and adventure. As the product attributes’ salience increases and becomes progressively alluring, buyers also become ready to take risks related to dissatisfaction with the product as well as legal violations and sometimes, health risks too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second axis comprises societal judgment. The ‘status-seeking’ paradigm is often applied to explain the motivation of proletariats to purchase rip-offs since they seek to imitate consumption standards of their wealthy counterparts to communicate a desired self-image and provide a self-concept reinforcement, a visible proof that the consumer can afford premium prices. These consumers construct an identity wherein they perceive themselves as savvy individuals.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social influence can have both a negative or positive stimulus in consumer purchasing intentions and conformity motives. ‘Without a brand, nobody looks at you in the street’-&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This general consumer opinion throws light on the fact that consumers are more interested in the social necessity of luxury than the luxury in itself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, Chinese society has traditionally focused on social behaviour over the personal, which explains the extreme sensitivity of Chinese consumers towards the attention and reaction of others.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the backdrop of a Confucian society, Chinese consumers behave irrationally while purchasing luxury brands because these brands are something similar to ‘must haves’ for them to gratify vanity. However, due to highly uneven wealth distribution and the consequent burgeoning gap between the rich and poor, the desire for these brands with exorbitant price tags remains unfulfilled. This contributes to a dissonance whereby consumers at lower levels of the wealth spectrum resort to replicas for manifesting their desired status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While China, North Korea, and Taiwan have been acknowledged as the famous ‘made in’ for counterfeit products, there has been a shifting pattern to regions and countries hitherto unfocused as hubs for distributing fake brands. An example of such a region is the Middle East and North Africa region (MENA), which is flourishing in the international trading scenario and concomitantly shifting astronomical volumes of counterfeit goods to Europe, exploiting the contiguous and porous borders with the continent.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of dummy products seized at the European Union Border rose from 10 million in 1990 to 41 million in 2016 with a total worth of $780 million. Should the growth of this illicit trade remain constant, according to the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, total losses for industries of original goods should be profoundly debilitating. The US industries would be the most drastically impacted with a possible loss of more than 75 million jobs per year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers seem to value quality in their intention to purchase counterfeit items. If the quality of replicas is fairly perceived in terms of relative quality, consumers’ disposition to purchase increases manifolds. This suggests a critical challenge for companies. A strong brand is a ‘moving target’ for counterfeiters, especially when it appears to serve ‘social adjustive’ rather than ‘value adjustive’ functions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marketing communications should emphasise product credibility and ethical credentials, as well as the pitfalls of buying dummies and the hidden human costs of a counterfeit economy which would act as a negative enforcer for this type of purchasing behaviour. Communication campaigns should be aimed at increasing consumer awareness of the superior quality and the value delivered by authentic brands.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public education and enlightenment could be the key to fight the demand for counterfeits. Companies should adopt marketing strategies with sensitivity to the operating environments of consumers in developing countries. Some companies have begun adopting a product adaptation strategy as opposed to a product standardisation strategy to act as a countervailing factor on behavioural intentions towards purchasing rip-offs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High performance, durability and low health risk should also be a part of a company’s promotional message. Brands should improve a consumer’s product usage experience which refers to cognitions, fantasies, and sensations evoked by brand-related stimuli. They should keep design high on their agenda whilst developing new products. The more distinctive the design is, the more difficult it becomes to imitate it, especially using low-scale technology.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all its ramifications, counterfeiting strikes a massive blow to the most valuable asset of an enterprise, that is, the brand image. The symbolism of a strong brand image lies in how it underpins the brand's strength in the market. Companies cannot overcome this obstacle alone. Counterfeiters are imaginative, flexible and above all, pursue continuous adaptation to the market much like leading innovative companies do.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a public policy dimension to this issue. Governments have an imperative role in protecting all property rights and curbing the flow of imitations along with multilateral agencies like WTO.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, in an effort to crack down on counterfeit trade, raids in New York alone resulted in a seizure of over $200 million worth of bogus brands and about 34% of national intellectual property. Moreover, in many developing countries, anti-counterfeiting legislations exist but have glaring lacunae which are never resolved.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, tackling counterfeiting is not an exclusive preserve of any single entity (government, business, or para-governmental agencies) but a shared obligation. There is a lot at stake for manufacturers, consumers, and the industrial nations if the peril is not effectively checked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The underlying issue with counterfeiting is not so much about consumer protection from potential risk implications per se. The real issue is much more convoluted. It is about creating a fair and safe environment for the main actors in global trade and society.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from the dire consequences for corporates and genuine item innovation and economic welfare, counterfeit production also escalates illegal practices in the unorganised sector where workers are denied their fundamental rights, and there is little or no attention paid to social or environmental concerns. Equally grave are the skyrocketing social problems which&amp;nbsp; include drug trafficking, terrorism, and human and capital insecurity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, Morocco’s counterfeiting industry has been linked to organised criminal clans who smuggle these goods and re-export them to Europe. The demand for counterfeit goods shows little or no sign of abatement. Instead, it appears likely to increase remarkably in tandem with the growth of the country’s tourism industry.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essentially, the fight against counterfeiting is a legal battle to promote marketplace righteousness and a conflict for the mind of the consumer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhinav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">How often do you see a dubious Hermes scarf or a pair of Prada shoes on sale in the street markets?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Counterfeiting is regarded as one of the ‘oldest crimes in history’. The origins of pirated brands of luxury articles can be traced back to 27 AD when a wine merchant named Gaul feigned expensive Roman wines and sold cheaper wine to earn huge profits.&amp;nbsp; The use of counterfeit products has proliferated enormously, by about 10,000% in the last two decades, to be precise, contributing to the sheer volume, sophistication, and increasing ‘globalisation’ of the counterfeit market.&amp;nbsp; The International Anti-Counterfeiting Coalition (2012) estimates that counterfeiting is a $600 billion problem representing a sizable and growing percentage of all world trade. Fuelled by consumer demand, this counterfeit market has increasingly been putting an acute burden on companies as they grapple with the intricate challenges of protecting intellectual property rights and safeguarding the integrity of their products. There are various interpretations of counterfeiting as a concept. Some researchers say that counterfeiting involves imitating product attributes to make them indistinguishable from the original and selling them at a lower price. At the same time, others say that it is the production of copies that are identically-packaged, including trademarks and labelling, to make it seem like a genuine article.&amp;nbsp; Counterfeiting can essentially be defined as the forgery of a product whose unique characteristics are protected as intellectual property rights.&amp;nbsp; From the consumer’s perspective, counterfeiting has two forms, that is, deceptive and non-deceptive. Under deceptive counterfeiting, the consumer is a victim of a sham since he/she is not aware of purchasing a fake product. Non-deceptive counterfeiting identifies consumers as active and enthusiastic players in counterfeiting transactions. This form of counterfeiting is commonplace in the luxury brand markets, where consumers are often able to discern the ersatz products based on the differences in price, quality, and distribution channels.&amp;nbsp; Consumer complicity with counterfeits has attracted vibrant controversy over the years. Price difference is the chief advantage of forged goods since they give consumers the same prestige without making them pay a hefty amount. A significant relationship has been established between the place of origin, consumers’ ethnocentrism, and psychographic variables. Buyers of these substitute goods are usually characterised by low-income levels and, sometimes, low self-esteem.&amp;nbsp; Brand visibility is equally recognised as a substantial decisional factor in buying intention. Brands that are globally more conspicuous and have ‘loud logos’ are more susceptible to piracy.&amp;nbsp; Another dimension of counterfeit consumption consists of the mood and situational context of the buyer. For instance, consumers are likely to purchase pirated goods while abroad or on a holiday since these goods can provide an authentic experience to tourist consumers. Tourists visiting Morocco constitute a vital segment of the counterfeit market. Moroccan hawkers are well known amongst European tourists for carrying a wide range of phoney labels such as Chanel, Fendi, and Louis Vuitton. A fake Levi’s shirt, for example, is sold for less than one-tenth of the price of the genuine brand.&amp;nbsp; The existence of the counterfeiting phenomenon may also be associated with consumers’ ethical and lawful cues. A consumer’s ethical awareness is measured along two axes.&amp;nbsp; The first is his or her own judgement. This refers to the feeling of pride or culpability arising from the use of cheap knock-offs. A majority of buyers do not perceive any harm and feel less accountable for counterfeit-buying behaviour. Consumers are willing to jettison avowed ethical principles for low prices and other product attributes. Their hedonic motivations far outweigh their ethical concerns.&amp;nbsp; Many times, ethical constraints may be directly linked to legal punishments. Some buyers hold a lax attitude about legal protection of intellectual property and indulge in counterfeiting transactions despite unscrupulous and illegal underpinnings. For them, breaking the relevant law heightens a sense of pleasure and adventure. As the product attributes’ salience increases and becomes progressively alluring, buyers also become ready to take risks related to dissatisfaction with the product as well as legal violations and sometimes, health risks too. The second axis comprises societal judgment. The ‘status-seeking’ paradigm is often applied to explain the motivation of proletariats to purchase rip-offs since they seek to imitate consumption standards of their wealthy counterparts to communicate a desired self-image and provide a self-concept reinforcement, a visible proof that the consumer can afford premium prices. These consumers construct an identity wherein they perceive themselves as savvy individuals.&amp;nbsp; Social influence can have both a negative or positive stimulus in consumer purchasing intentions and conformity motives. ‘Without a brand, nobody looks at you in the street’-&amp;nbsp; This general consumer opinion throws light on the fact that consumers are more interested in the social necessity of luxury than the luxury in itself.&amp;nbsp; For instance, Chinese society has traditionally focused on social behaviour over the personal, which explains the extreme sensitivity of Chinese consumers towards the attention and reaction of others.&amp;nbsp; In the backdrop of a Confucian society, Chinese consumers behave irrationally while purchasing luxury brands because these brands are something similar to ‘must haves’ for them to gratify vanity. However, due to highly uneven wealth distribution and the consequent burgeoning gap between the rich and poor, the desire for these brands with exorbitant price tags remains unfulfilled. This contributes to a dissonance whereby consumers at lower levels of the wealth spectrum resort to replicas for manifesting their desired status. While China, North Korea, and Taiwan have been acknowledged as the famous ‘made in’ for counterfeit products, there has been a shifting pattern to regions and countries hitherto unfocused as hubs for distributing fake brands. An example of such a region is the Middle East and North Africa region (MENA), which is flourishing in the international trading scenario and concomitantly shifting astronomical volumes of counterfeit goods to Europe, exploiting the contiguous and porous borders with the continent.&amp;nbsp; The number of dummy products seized at the European Union Border rose from 10 million in 1990 to 41 million in 2016 with a total worth of $780 million. Should the growth of this illicit trade remain constant, according to the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, total losses for industries of original goods should be profoundly debilitating. The US industries would be the most drastically impacted with a possible loss of more than 75 million jobs per year.&amp;nbsp; Consumers seem to value quality in their intention to purchase counterfeit items. If the quality of replicas is fairly perceived in terms of relative quality, consumers’ disposition to purchase increases manifolds. This suggests a critical challenge for companies. A strong brand is a ‘moving target’ for counterfeiters, especially when it appears to serve ‘social adjustive’ rather than ‘value adjustive’ functions.&amp;nbsp; Marketing communications should emphasise product credibility and ethical credentials, as well as the pitfalls of buying dummies and the hidden human costs of a counterfeit economy which would act as a negative enforcer for this type of purchasing behaviour. Communication campaigns should be aimed at increasing consumer awareness of the superior quality and the value delivered by authentic brands.&amp;nbsp; Public education and enlightenment could be the key to fight the demand for counterfeits. Companies should adopt marketing strategies with sensitivity to the operating environments of consumers in developing countries. Some companies have begun adopting a product adaptation strategy as opposed to a product standardisation strategy to act as a countervailing factor on behavioural intentions towards purchasing rip-offs.&amp;nbsp; High performance, durability and low health risk should also be a part of a company’s promotional message. Brands should improve a consumer’s product usage experience which refers to cognitions, fantasies, and sensations evoked by brand-related stimuli. They should keep design high on their agenda whilst developing new products. The more distinctive the design is, the more difficult it becomes to imitate it, especially using low-scale technology.&amp;nbsp; In all its ramifications, counterfeiting strikes a massive blow to the most valuable asset of an enterprise, that is, the brand image. The symbolism of a strong brand image lies in how it underpins the brand's strength in the market. Companies cannot overcome this obstacle alone. Counterfeiters are imaginative, flexible and above all, pursue continuous adaptation to the market much like leading innovative companies do.&amp;nbsp; There is a public policy dimension to this issue. Governments have an imperative role in protecting all property rights and curbing the flow of imitations along with multilateral agencies like WTO.&amp;nbsp; For instance, in an effort to crack down on counterfeit trade, raids in New York alone resulted in a seizure of over $200 million worth of bogus brands and about 34% of national intellectual property. Moreover, in many developing countries, anti-counterfeiting legislations exist but have glaring lacunae which are never resolved.&amp;nbsp; However, tackling counterfeiting is not an exclusive preserve of any single entity (government, business, or para-governmental agencies) but a shared obligation. There is a lot at stake for manufacturers, consumers, and the industrial nations if the peril is not effectively checked. The underlying issue with counterfeiting is not so much about consumer protection from potential risk implications per se. The real issue is much more convoluted. It is about creating a fair and safe environment for the main actors in global trade and society.&amp;nbsp; Apart from the dire consequences for corporates and genuine item innovation and economic welfare, counterfeit production also escalates illegal practices in the unorganised sector where workers are denied their fundamental rights, and there is little or no attention paid to social or environmental concerns. Equally grave are the skyrocketing social problems which&amp;nbsp; include drug trafficking, terrorism, and human and capital insecurity.&amp;nbsp; For instance, Morocco’s counterfeiting industry has been linked to organised criminal clans who smuggle these goods and re-export them to Europe. The demand for counterfeit goods shows little or no sign of abatement. Instead, it appears likely to increase remarkably in tandem with the growth of the country’s tourism industry.&amp;nbsp; Essentially, the fight against counterfeiting is a legal battle to promote marketplace righteousness and a conflict for the mind of the consumer.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Financial Crime in a Disrupted Global Environment</title>
      <link href="/Financial-Crime-in-a-Disrupted-Global-Environment" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Financial Crime in a Disrupted Global Environment" />
      <published>2021-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Financial-Crime-in-a-Disrupted-Global-Environment</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Financial-Crime-in-a-Disrupted-Global-Environment">&lt;p&gt;Albert Einstein famously said: “&lt;em&gt;In the midst of every crisis, lies great opportunity,&lt;/em&gt;” and criminals got a little too inspired by the sentiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Since time immemorial, the financial services sector has been at the receiving end of various risks ranging in magnitudes. In contemporary times, there is perhaps nothing as disconcerting as the risk of financial crimes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Financial crimes have an impact on large and small entities alike and include a broad spectrum of violations, including internet phishing, money laundering, identity fraud, terrorist financing, and tax evasion. This trillion-dollar threat has profound repercussions, and combating it is an unenviable task for all participants in the global financial economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Furthermore, COVID-19 has brought the world to the forefront of the fight against financial crime and led institutions to turbocharge what had generally been a glacial stroll towards remote working, the paramount concern remains to ensure safe access to data. Around the world, many have seized the opportunity presented by the crisis to exploit the antecedent vulnerabilities of an already distressed financial system, leading to even common concerns being exacerbated by extraordinary circumstances.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;On a micro level, there are broadly two types of financial crime. Firstly, activities that dishonestly generate wealth for those engaged in the act in question. For instance, exploitation of insider information or acquisition of another person’s property by deceit, done with the intention of securing a material benefit. Secondly, there are activities where there is no direct involvement of such dishonest gain but rather protection or facilitation of such unethical rewards. An example of such an act can be someone who attempts to launder the criminal proceeds of another offence in order to place the revenue beyond the reach of the law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Anecdotal evidence suggests a rise in financial crime, including money laundering and rogue trading, during the pandemic. Opportunities for perpetrating cyber-enabled crimes have also increased, and data shows an exponential surge in cyber attacks over baseline levels.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Not even the most extreme scenarios would ever have envisaged a global lockdown with such high levels of online activity over such a period and subject to such high degree of uncertainty, as in the present time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mckinsey.com/business-functions/risk-and-resilience/our-insights/financial-crime-and-fraud-in-the-age-of-cybersecurity&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2021-08-15-Financial-Crime-in-a-Disrupted-Global-Environment_image1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Translating the financial threat into quantitative terms, the United Nations estimates that the annual cost of money laundering and associated crimes is $1.4-3.5 trillion, out of which banks are only able to put a stop to less than a percent. Regulators have fined the world’s biggest banks more than $320 billion for breaches to date.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Each of the world's largest banks spends $1 billion annually on financial crime operations, with most of this amount being allocated to compliance rather than actively targeting the aforementioned criminal activities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This considerable spending corresponds to an ever more growing onus on institutions to know precisely who their benefactors are and where their money is coming from. This situation also imposes enormous ramifications on cyber resilience capabilities at financial institutions and third-party technology service providers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The industry has been making progress towards adopting a common cyber lexicon, implementing a robust cybersecurity framework, and enhancing international cooperation. Banks and financial institutions are employing new technologies and approaches to detect financial crime, which is highly appreciated by regulators and consumers alike.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Banks can now automate and improve their Know Your Customer (KYC) and Suspicious Activity Reporting (SAR) processes using Robotic Process Automation (RPA), Artificial Intelligence, and other newer technologies; they can use these nextgen technologies and capabilities to review scenarios and spot money laundering, insider trading and other illicit activities via identifying suspicious behaviour, reducing the number of false positives and improving the response time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Nonetheless, before they can use these technologies effectively, institutions need to upgrade their data and advanced behavioural analytics capabilities to lay a stronger foundation for success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mckinsey.com/business-functions/risk-and-resilience/our-insights/financial-crime-and-fraud-in-the-age-of-cybersecurity&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2021-08-15-Financial-Crime-in-a-Disrupted-Global-Environment_image2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To assess other facets of financial crime, it is essential to monitor the growth in the payments space, which is primarily driven not only by a renewed focus on customer-centricity but also by offering a plethora of novel payment options, including digital wallets, cross-border payments, cryptocurrencies and other financial technologies which reduce payment friction and support transactions through the use of blockchain. These payment methods have brought forth new financial crime risks that existing regulations and infrastructure are not equipped to address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Owing to the new wave of digital transformation, vulnerabilities manifest in tandem with advancements in technologies. These are explicitly apparent in cross-border transactions and between multiple economies governed by a varied spectrum of lax to stringent regulatory requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Anyhow, the baseline expectations of regulators are that institutions must ensure market integrity, effective customer due diligence processes, and ongoing monitoring, specifically concerning counter-financing of terrorism (CFT), and anti-money laundering (AML) norms.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As a consequence, the financial crime compliance dimension is on the cusp of transformation. There is increasing recognition of the need to innovate towards a more agile, efficient, and resilient approach to compliance of financial crime regulations and proactive targeting of criminal behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The offshoring of activities in financial services, either to captives or by outsourcing them to third parties, has also witnessed a turbulent trend during the pandemic. Many organisations offshore their AML and related financial crime prevention processes like transaction monitoring, alert management, and customer due diligence to managed service partners in emerging markets.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The critical criteria for choosing a location for offshoring remains political stability, availability of competent labour and technology at low costs. However, offshoring hubs such as India have revealed pitfalls in offshoring/outsourcing models, owing to the stringent lockdowns that have prompted institutions to consider bringing their financial crime functions back in-house while aggressively pursuing their use of digital tools to reduce manual effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Moreover, while offshoring may be cost-effective, it is often suboptimal for achieving the objective of preventing financial crime, partly due to the additional risks of complex and intransparent offshore structures, dispersed responsibilities, and lack of power to enforce technical control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Bank for International settlements (BIS) suggests that firms can reduce risks by taking steps to draw up clear outsourcing policies, and establishing effective risk management programmes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Despite all the challenges mentioned above, the pandemic has presented an opportunity for criminals to commit extraordinary amounts of financial crime; as regulatory pressures continue to mount and new entrants render the marketplace more competitive. There is a newfound prerequisite of the agility context of this industry.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Luckily, there seems to be newfound cognisance that a reactive response to crime and compliance requirements is not the way of the future, as it is costly and suboptimal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There needs to be a proactive approach to detect, prevent and mitigate threats using enhanced data and analytics capabilities. The integration of fraud and cybersecurity operations is a crucial step, given their interrelation. To maintain a competitive advantage, financial crime officers need to pursue strategic investments in offshoring and outsourcing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Consequently, if this world presents criminals an opportunity amidst the crisis, it provides crime regulators with a more significant opportunity to improve and uplift themselves to emerge victorious.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Maanya Oberoi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Albert Einstein famously said: “In the midst of every crisis, lies great opportunity,” and criminals got a little too inspired by the sentiment. Since time immemorial, the financial services sector has been at the receiving end of various risks ranging in magnitudes. In contemporary times, there is perhaps nothing as disconcerting as the risk of financial crimes.&amp;nbsp; Financial crimes have an impact on large and small entities alike and include a broad spectrum of violations, including internet phishing, money laundering, identity fraud, terrorist financing, and tax evasion. This trillion-dollar threat has profound repercussions, and combating it is an unenviable task for all participants in the global financial economy.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, COVID-19 has brought the world to the forefront of the fight against financial crime and led institutions to turbocharge what had generally been a glacial stroll towards remote working, the paramount concern remains to ensure safe access to data. Around the world, many have seized the opportunity presented by the crisis to exploit the antecedent vulnerabilities of an already distressed financial system, leading to even common concerns being exacerbated by extraordinary circumstances.&amp;nbsp; On a micro level, there are broadly two types of financial crime. Firstly, activities that dishonestly generate wealth for those engaged in the act in question. For instance, exploitation of insider information or acquisition of another person’s property by deceit, done with the intention of securing a material benefit. Secondly, there are activities where there is no direct involvement of such dishonest gain but rather protection or facilitation of such unethical rewards. An example of such an act can be someone who attempts to launder the criminal proceeds of another offence in order to place the revenue beyond the reach of the law. Anecdotal evidence suggests a rise in financial crime, including money laundering and rogue trading, during the pandemic. Opportunities for perpetrating cyber-enabled crimes have also increased, and data shows an exponential surge in cyber attacks over baseline levels.&amp;nbsp; Not even the most extreme scenarios would ever have envisaged a global lockdown with such high levels of online activity over such a period and subject to such high degree of uncertainty, as in the present time.&amp;nbsp; Translating the financial threat into quantitative terms, the United Nations estimates that the annual cost of money laundering and associated crimes is $1.4-3.5 trillion, out of which banks are only able to put a stop to less than a percent. Regulators have fined the world’s biggest banks more than $320 billion for breaches to date.&amp;nbsp; Each of the world's largest banks spends $1 billion annually on financial crime operations, with most of this amount being allocated to compliance rather than actively targeting the aforementioned criminal activities.&amp;nbsp; This considerable spending corresponds to an ever more growing onus on institutions to know precisely who their benefactors are and where their money is coming from. This situation also imposes enormous ramifications on cyber resilience capabilities at financial institutions and third-party technology service providers.&amp;nbsp; The industry has been making progress towards adopting a common cyber lexicon, implementing a robust cybersecurity framework, and enhancing international cooperation. Banks and financial institutions are employing new technologies and approaches to detect financial crime, which is highly appreciated by regulators and consumers alike.&amp;nbsp; Banks can now automate and improve their Know Your Customer (KYC) and Suspicious Activity Reporting (SAR) processes using Robotic Process Automation (RPA), Artificial Intelligence, and other newer technologies; they can use these nextgen technologies and capabilities to review scenarios and spot money laundering, insider trading and other illicit activities via identifying suspicious behaviour, reducing the number of false positives and improving the response time.&amp;nbsp; Nonetheless, before they can use these technologies effectively, institutions need to upgrade their data and advanced behavioural analytics capabilities to lay a stronger foundation for success. To assess other facets of financial crime, it is essential to monitor the growth in the payments space, which is primarily driven not only by a renewed focus on customer-centricity but also by offering a plethora of novel payment options, including digital wallets, cross-border payments, cryptocurrencies and other financial technologies which reduce payment friction and support transactions through the use of blockchain. These payment methods have brought forth new financial crime risks that existing regulations and infrastructure are not equipped to address. Owing to the new wave of digital transformation, vulnerabilities manifest in tandem with advancements in technologies. These are explicitly apparent in cross-border transactions and between multiple economies governed by a varied spectrum of lax to stringent regulatory requirements. Anyhow, the baseline expectations of regulators are that institutions must ensure market integrity, effective customer due diligence processes, and ongoing monitoring, specifically concerning counter-financing of terrorism (CFT), and anti-money laundering (AML) norms.&amp;nbsp; As a consequence, the financial crime compliance dimension is on the cusp of transformation. There is increasing recognition of the need to innovate towards a more agile, efficient, and resilient approach to compliance of financial crime regulations and proactive targeting of criminal behaviour. The offshoring of activities in financial services, either to captives or by outsourcing them to third parties, has also witnessed a turbulent trend during the pandemic. Many organisations offshore their AML and related financial crime prevention processes like transaction monitoring, alert management, and customer due diligence to managed service partners in emerging markets.&amp;nbsp; The critical criteria for choosing a location for offshoring remains political stability, availability of competent labour and technology at low costs. However, offshoring hubs such as India have revealed pitfalls in offshoring/outsourcing models, owing to the stringent lockdowns that have prompted institutions to consider bringing their financial crime functions back in-house while aggressively pursuing their use of digital tools to reduce manual effort. Moreover, while offshoring may be cost-effective, it is often suboptimal for achieving the objective of preventing financial crime, partly due to the additional risks of complex and intransparent offshore structures, dispersed responsibilities, and lack of power to enforce technical control. The Bank for International settlements (BIS) suggests that firms can reduce risks by taking steps to draw up clear outsourcing policies, and establishing effective risk management programmes.&amp;nbsp; Despite all the challenges mentioned above, the pandemic has presented an opportunity for criminals to commit extraordinary amounts of financial crime; as regulatory pressures continue to mount and new entrants render the marketplace more competitive. There is a newfound prerequisite of the agility context of this industry.&amp;nbsp; Luckily, there seems to be newfound cognisance that a reactive response to crime and compliance requirements is not the way of the future, as it is costly and suboptimal. There needs to be a proactive approach to detect, prevent and mitigate threats using enhanced data and analytics capabilities. The integration of fraud and cybersecurity operations is a crucial step, given their interrelation. To maintain a competitive advantage, financial crime officers need to pursue strategic investments in offshoring and outsourcing. Consequently, if this world presents criminals an opportunity amidst the crisis, it provides crime regulators with a more significant opportunity to improve and uplift themselves to emerge victorious.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
