<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/business-finance/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2022-02-02T23:35:06+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/business-finance/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The American Recipe for a Food Crisis</title>
      <link href="/The-American-Recipe-for-a-Food-Crisis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The American Recipe for a Food Crisis" />
      <published>2022-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-American-Recipe-for-a-Food-Crisis</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-American-Recipe-for-a-Food-Crisis">&lt;p&gt;You might have heard about corporations profiting from sexism, homophobia, physical insecurities, poverty, and even, you! But have you ever wondered how these organisations feed off hunger?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article attempts to capture the Hunger Industrial Complex (a mechanism by which huge, capitalist organisations systemically perpetuate hunger in order to reap profits, all while maintaining the facade of ‘anti-hunger proponents’) through the story of the US.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chronology is simple. People are hungry. They can’t afford food. (Primarily because while the federal minimum wage in the US has been stuck at $7.25, the cost of groceries has &lt;a href=&quot;https://politicsofpoverty.oxfamamerica.org/what-is-the-anti-hunger-industrial-complex/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gone up by 25% &lt;/a&gt;in the past decade.) Anti-hunger groups bank on charities from huge corporations to feed the hungry. These corporations shell out millions for the ‘noble cause’, while ensuring they turn a deaf ear to their employees demanding a wage hike, which would eliminate the need for food banks in the first place. People are hungry, again, the next day!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand the complexities better, we need to visit the three main actors in the process: The Donors, The Anti-Hunger Groups and Food Banks, and The Government, and trace their complicity and contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's first visit the big corporations vis-a-vis the benefactors or &lt;em&gt;donors&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;to food banks through the lens of Walmart. As the largest employer in the US with nearly 1.6 million workers, Walmart has faced criticism for years over low wages, wage theft, and keeping workers on part-time schedules to shirk off employee security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;You can’t pay your bills, rent and buy groceries on $12 an hour. I don’t think anywhere in the United States, you can do that. No way&lt;/em&gt;,” said Mendy Hughes, 46, who has worked as a cashier for Walmart in Arkansas, for 11 years. Anna Turner, who had worked at Walmart in California for more than eight years before being fired for complaining about COVID-19 mismanagement in the workplace, noted that she made less than $15 an hour and was never hired for full-time hours, even though the department was chronically understaffed. “&lt;em&gt;They would always cut our hours so we couldn’t get full-time and health benefits&lt;/em&gt;,” said Turner. (Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/business/2021/oct/28/walmart-pay-hourly-low-wages-working-conditions&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, even the Food Stamp Program that the US government has in place to provide food-purchasing assistance to low- and no-income people connects back to Walmart making money! Americans spend about &lt;a href=&quot;http://online.wsj.com/news/articles/SB10001424052702303843104579168011245171266?mod=djemITP_h&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;18% of all food stamp dollars&lt;/a&gt; at Walmart, which gives Walmart all the more incentive to force its employees to rely on food stamps.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So basically, Walmart is encouraging its employees to get food stamps, or go to food banks, because they don’t pay them enough wages in the first place. And surprisingly, the atrocities are legal as the federal minimum wage in the US, as mentioned before, is $7.25!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, Walmart’s not the only culprit, there are so many more corporations playing this game. In 2012, Arby’s (one of the biggest fast-foo&lt;a href=&quot;https://civileats.com/2013/09/05/the-anti-hunger-industrial-complex/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;d chains of America)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://civileats.com/2013/09/05/the-anti-hunger-industrial-complex/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;raised $2.7 million&lt;/a&gt; for the hunger cause, most of which &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arbysfoundation.org/Fundraiser.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;went to Share Our Strength&lt;/a&gt;, an organisation aiming to end childhood hunger. Ironically, all this while, Arby’s employees were protesting the fact that they didn’t earn enough to feed their children.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now another question arises, why would these companies rather make huge donations than pay their employees a little more?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two facets to the answer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the ‘Maths’ of it. It wouldn’t require much calculation to figure that paying a ‘little’ more to millions of employees, every month, compounds to a much greater price than shelling out a good chunk of bucks every now and then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the ‘PR’ of it. Donations and charities facilitate corporations to ‘greenwash’ their damaged reputations and boost their CSR (Corporate Social Responsibility) contribution in ways pay hikes could never accomplish. Charities make these corporations look like ‘hunger fighters’ instead of ‘hunger causers’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could still, for a minute, understand corporate complicity. But what about the food banks? What about anti-hunger groups?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s visit these one by one.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A&lt;em&gt; food bank &lt;/em&gt;is a non-profit, charitable organisation that distributes food to those without the resources to evade their hunger, through intermediaries like food pantries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past few decades, food banks have become an integral and accepted part of America’s hunger response. According to a comprehensive government survey completed in 2002, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Food_bank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;over 90% of food banks were established in the US after 1981&lt;/a&gt;. In the early 1980's, President Reagan’s administration cut back several welfare programmes, which, combined with unemployment and a budding recession, led to a rapid rise in hunger relief activities. The “emergency food system”, supposedly a temporary measure, slowly became a rather permanent industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While some believe food banks to be an example of active, caring citizenship, others express concern that the rise of food banks may corrode political support and incentive for welfare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next on the list are &lt;em&gt;anti-hunger groups.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are organisations attempting to alleviate hunger through long-term solutions, anti-hunger programmes, etc. Anti-hunger groups usually tie up with food banks to further their cause.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many groups see their role as ensuring that no kid misses a meal, rather than reducing the growing economic inequality (the underlying cause of hunger in the US). Their approach is not hunger elimination, but hunger maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings us to a pertinent question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anti-hunger groups are feeding people. But why aren’t they fighting hunger?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One would expect anti-hunger groups to be lobbying for the signage of the living wage bill, or rallying against the violation of employees' rights at the hands of corporations like Walmart and Amazon. But it’s not that simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps their lack of attention is grounded in the fact that many anti-hunger organisations find their roots in these greedy corporations. Look at these numbers: &lt;a href=&quot;https://civileats.com/2013/09/05/the-anti-hunger-industrial-complex/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;One in every four&lt;/a&gt; food bank board members works at a Fortune 1000 company.&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Walmart staff sit on the boards of about &lt;a href=&quot;https://civileats.com/2013/09/05/the-anti-hunger-industrial-complex/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;one of every eight &lt;/a&gt;food banks.&amp;nbsp; And they are actively stopping anti-hunger organisations from engaging in public policy activism that threatens their business interest.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, anti-hunger groups and food banks are not the bad guys, they just seem to be trapped in an intricate system of exploitative capitalism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last actor is the &lt;em&gt;Government.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each year, the USDA (United States Department of Agriculture) spends roughly half a billion dollars in buying produce from farmers, and donates them to food banks. However, if only they spent these resources in increasing social safety net programmes instead, the impact would be truly durable. But that’s an impossible feat to achieve given the lobbying power of the corporate giants in the halls of American Congress.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To synthesise, there’s nothing the food banks can do, and there’s nothing the government or corporations want to do. So what’s the bottom line?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bottom Line&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The anti-hunger movement needs to focus on anti-hunger efforts, not on charity but on the root causes of food insecurity, improving public health, and reducing income inequality. It needs anti-hunger groups to serve a broader agenda than just temporarily fading out hunger for the day, through federal programmes and charitable organisations. It needs to exact a much higher price from corporations in the form of greater social responsibility. It needs to urge the government to bring systemic changes, especially in the form of increased wages and benefits, policy reforms, etc. But most importantly, we need to familiarise ourselves with these systemic disadvantages and blockages, identify them, and uproot them, because, at the end of the day, no one deserves to be hungry.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Eeshita Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      
        <category term="humanity" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">You might have heard about corporations profiting from sexism, homophobia, physical insecurities, poverty, and even, you! But have you ever wondered how these organisations feed off hunger? This article attempts to capture the Hunger Industrial Complex (a mechanism by which huge, capitalist organisations systemically perpetuate hunger in order to reap profits, all while maintaining the facade of ‘anti-hunger proponents’) through the story of the US.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The chronology is simple. People are hungry. They can’t afford food. (Primarily because while the federal minimum wage in the US has been stuck at $7.25, the cost of groceries has gone up by 25% in the past decade.) Anti-hunger groups bank on charities from huge corporations to feed the hungry. These corporations shell out millions for the ‘noble cause’, while ensuring they turn a deaf ear to their employees demanding a wage hike, which would eliminate the need for food banks in the first place. People are hungry, again, the next day! To understand the complexities better, we need to visit the three main actors in the process: The Donors, The Anti-Hunger Groups and Food Banks, and The Government, and trace their complicity and contributions. Let's first visit the big corporations vis-a-vis the benefactors or donors to food banks through the lens of Walmart. As the largest employer in the US with nearly 1.6 million workers, Walmart has faced criticism for years over low wages, wage theft, and keeping workers on part-time schedules to shirk off employee security. “You can’t pay your bills, rent and buy groceries on $12 an hour. I don’t think anywhere in the United States, you can do that. No way,” said Mendy Hughes, 46, who has worked as a cashier for Walmart in Arkansas, for 11 years. Anna Turner, who had worked at Walmart in California for more than eight years before being fired for complaining about COVID-19 mismanagement in the workplace, noted that she made less than $15 an hour and was never hired for full-time hours, even though the department was chronically understaffed. “They would always cut our hours so we couldn’t get full-time and health benefits,” said Turner. (Source: The Guardian)&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Moreover, even the Food Stamp Program that the US government has in place to provide food-purchasing assistance to low- and no-income people connects back to Walmart making money! Americans spend about 18% of all food stamp dollars at Walmart, which gives Walmart all the more incentive to force its employees to rely on food stamps.&amp;nbsp; So basically, Walmart is encouraging its employees to get food stamps, or go to food banks, because they don’t pay them enough wages in the first place. And surprisingly, the atrocities are legal as the federal minimum wage in the US, as mentioned before, is $7.25! Unsurprisingly, Walmart’s not the only culprit, there are so many more corporations playing this game. In 2012, Arby’s (one of the biggest fast-food chains of America) raised $2.7 million for the hunger cause, most of which went to Share Our Strength, an organisation aiming to end childhood hunger. Ironically, all this while, Arby’s employees were protesting the fact that they didn’t earn enough to feed their children.&amp;nbsp; Now another question arises, why would these companies rather make huge donations than pay their employees a little more? There are two facets to the answer.&amp;nbsp; First, the ‘Maths’ of it. It wouldn’t require much calculation to figure that paying a ‘little’ more to millions of employees, every month, compounds to a much greater price than shelling out a good chunk of bucks every now and then. Second, the ‘PR’ of it. Donations and charities facilitate corporations to ‘greenwash’ their damaged reputations and boost their CSR (Corporate Social Responsibility) contribution in ways pay hikes could never accomplish. Charities make these corporations look like ‘hunger fighters’ instead of ‘hunger causers’. I could still, for a minute, understand corporate complicity. But what about the food banks? What about anti-hunger groups? Let’s visit these one by one.&amp;nbsp; A food bank is a non-profit, charitable organisation that distributes food to those without the resources to evade their hunger, through intermediaries like food pantries.&amp;nbsp; In the past few decades, food banks have become an integral and accepted part of America’s hunger response. According to a comprehensive government survey completed in 2002, over 90% of food banks were established in the US after 1981. In the early 1980's, President Reagan’s administration cut back several welfare programmes, which, combined with unemployment and a budding recession, led to a rapid rise in hunger relief activities. The “emergency food system”, supposedly a temporary measure, slowly became a rather permanent industry. While some believe food banks to be an example of active, caring citizenship, others express concern that the rise of food banks may corrode political support and incentive for welfare. Next on the list are anti-hunger groups. These are organisations attempting to alleviate hunger through long-term solutions, anti-hunger programmes, etc. Anti-hunger groups usually tie up with food banks to further their cause.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Many groups see their role as ensuring that no kid misses a meal, rather than reducing the growing economic inequality (the underlying cause of hunger in the US). Their approach is not hunger elimination, but hunger maintenance. This brings us to a pertinent question. Anti-hunger groups are feeding people. But why aren’t they fighting hunger? One would expect anti-hunger groups to be lobbying for the signage of the living wage bill, or rallying against the violation of employees' rights at the hands of corporations like Walmart and Amazon. But it’s not that simple. Perhaps their lack of attention is grounded in the fact that many anti-hunger organisations find their roots in these greedy corporations. Look at these numbers: One in every four food bank board members works at a Fortune 1000 company. Walmart staff sit on the boards of about one of every eight food banks.&amp;nbsp; And they are actively stopping anti-hunger organisations from engaging in public policy activism that threatens their business interest.&amp;nbsp; So, anti-hunger groups and food banks are not the bad guys, they just seem to be trapped in an intricate system of exploitative capitalism.&amp;nbsp; The last actor is the Government. Each year, the USDA (United States Department of Agriculture) spends roughly half a billion dollars in buying produce from farmers, and donates them to food banks. However, if only they spent these resources in increasing social safety net programmes instead, the impact would be truly durable. But that’s an impossible feat to achieve given the lobbying power of the corporate giants in the halls of American Congress.&amp;nbsp; To synthesise, there’s nothing the food banks can do, and there’s nothing the government or corporations want to do. So what’s the bottom line? Bottom Line The anti-hunger movement needs to focus on anti-hunger efforts, not on charity but on the root causes of food insecurity, improving public health, and reducing income inequality. It needs anti-hunger groups to serve a broader agenda than just temporarily fading out hunger for the day, through federal programmes and charitable organisations. It needs to exact a much higher price from corporations in the form of greater social responsibility. It needs to urge the government to bring systemic changes, especially in the form of increased wages and benefits, policy reforms, etc. But most importantly, we need to familiarise ourselves with these systemic disadvantages and blockages, identify them, and uproot them, because, at the end of the day, no one deserves to be hungry.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Water Supply &amp;amp; Sanitation: Private vs Public Sector</title>
      <link href="/Water-Supply-Sanitation-Private-vs-Public-Sector" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Water Supply &amp; Sanitation: Private vs Public Sector" />
      <published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Water-Supply-Sanitation-Private-vs-Public-Sector</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Water-Supply-Sanitation-Private-vs-Public-Sector">&lt;p&gt;Today, about 2.6 billion people live without basic sanitation and nearly 1.1 billion live without access to safe drinking water. Around 13% of the world population still defecates in the open. The&amp;nbsp; diarrhoeal diseases that result from poor sanitation kill more than five million children every year and 9% of these deaths happen to be of children aged less than five years. Up to 50% of malnutrition is attributable to poor water, sanitation and hygiene, as are many neglected tropical diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Death and disease due to inadequate sanitation not only burdens a country's healthcare system, it also causes a huge emotional and financial cost to families. Children drop out of school and fail to reach their potential, especially young girls. Moreover, research shows how poor sanitation has a substantial impact on the economy as well. Countries with poor access to sanitation are losing significant proportions of their GDP – in India, this figure is over 5%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It thus stands to reason that we need better sanitation for a better economy, a better society and a better world. The question is: how do we achieve that? Moreover, which sector should cater to Water Supply and Sanitation (WSS)? Private or Public?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economists champion public sector involvement in cases of market failures and unequal distribution of economic outcomes. The prime justification for public provision of WSS is market failures such as natural monopoly, externalities, and public good characteristics. A sole profit-oriented producer of a good with declining long-term average cost will restrict output to monopoly level, thereby leading to a social welfare loss. Thus, government intervention is essential to restore efficiency. Moreover, the positive externalities gained from use of WSS further strengthens this argument. It is the responsibility of the government to not just focus on efficiency (the primary focus of profit-oriented enterprises) but also to make sure that distribution is provided to all, without any disparity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, experiences from the past have shown that public-owned utilities have not always been successful both in developed and developing nations. This has been especially so in the latter case owing to various non-market failures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public WSS services have remained lacking on grounds of efficiency. Large proportions of the population have little or no access to public WSS services, while the remaining who receive it often face issues of poor quality, characterised by frequent breakdowns and unreliable supply.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simultaneously, these water utilities barely have enough to cover operational costs, leaving no surplus available to finance the expansion of networks, eventually leading to a downward spiral in customer service. This results in the consumer's reluctance to pay higher tariffs ultimately leading to a deterioration of assets and squandering of financial resources. This descending cycle attracts political interference and furthers the velocity of the fall.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, divergence of personal gains of employees from the social goals and absence of reliable measures to hold such officials accountable further exacerbates the deplorable functioning of such organisations. These organisations become hotbeds of corruption and maladministration. Hence, there have been growing views in favour of privatisation for increased competition and better efficiency. Furthermore, WSS does fulfil the prerequisite of a private good by being rivalrous in nature, and the additional benefits associated with its consumption generates a stronger incentive for individuals to pay higher for obtaining better quality services.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The private sector has long played a role in the water sector, particularly in the industrialised economies. Historically, water supplies in many cities of the US were provided by private players until the government reverted the ownership to itself. The WSS services are entirely provided by the private sector in countries such as the UK, France, Philippines, etc.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Owing to the principal role of Water and Sanitation, such countries do have in place mechanisms where the government has oversight over the private sector. It accomplishes this through models which outsource management and supply of WSS while retaining public ownership, or by providing concessions against contracts, or through the presence of a regulatory agency. The only exception is France where there exists no sort of supervision by the administration. Private sector involvement in such a key area of the economy presents numerous risks for the former, such as commercial, financial, technical, legal and political risks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commercial risks involve the fear that the private investors may not be able to recoup their investment and make a profit, while technical risks pertain to insufficient knowledge about the state of installations resulting in operational failures. Legal risks occur as a result of contractual disputes, while financial risks relate to currency devaluations and convertibility of local to foreign currency, especially when foreign borrowings are used to finance services. Political risks stem from governments' changing policy in the course of implementation of the contract or due to their reluctance in charging higher tariffs.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example to illustrate the risks posed could be seen in the case of Argentina. Water privatisation in Argentina began in 1992, where certain concessions were awarded by the administration to private companies. Post 2001, all concessions were terminated under the leadership of a different government on the basis that the contracts were not fulfilled by the providing company. The private companies conceded to their failure in meeting the targets, but argued that a freeze in tariffs at the time of the devaluation of the Peso during the Argentine economic crisis violated the contract, and thus, made it impossible for them to achieve the set targets. In July 2010, the International Centre for the Settlement of Investment Disputes (ICSID) ruled in favour of the private concessionaires and entitled them to compensation. Thus, there were losses faced by both the private companies and the government, with no winners in such a fight.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Private sector participation (in such areas) has generally been touted as the solution to the pressing need of huge capital investments in the water sector. However, the ability of the private sector to actually invest in water infrastructure is doubtful. As per the Global Water Partnership, estimates of the total investment needs for new water infrastructure amounted to $180 billion per year for the period of 2000–2005. However, according to historical data, total private investment in WSS has averaged $3.3 billion per year, i.e. only about 1.8% of the annual investment needs of developing countries. In Asia, the annual average private investment of $1.9 billion in water (World Bank PPI database) accounts for 7.9% of the total financing needs of the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another claimed basis for involvement of private players is increased competition so as to improve the overall efficiency. However, the investment level in the distribution networks is massive relative to the size of the market, which obscures the potential for direct product market competition in developing countries. The entry to this market is often done on contractual basis from governments but factors like political risks, long payback periods, huge sunk costs and high degree of non-transparency while awarding the contracts deter private sector participation. Additionally, there has not been any substantial data to evidently prove the productive efficiency of the private sector in sanitation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, one of the most important arguments in favour of private sector participation is the expansion in the scope of services due to the huge resources it brings with it. However, this theoretical abundance is difficult to translate into actions in the developing economies for the following reasons: 1) On the demand side, the unwillingness of the consumers to pay cost-recovering tariffs (maybe due to unawareness of the benefits of WSS); and 2) on the supply side, neglect of the poor by profit-oriented firms which pursue only the wealthy section to recoup their large investments. Moreover, rural areas have scattered populations that often present technical, organisational, and financial sustainability issues, thus proving to be unviable for private companies. As per data, private investments have appeared to have benefited the relatively wealthier countries due to the lower risks associated with them in ways such as market friendly policy and institutional environments, high household incomes, effective regulatory mechanisms, etc.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To illustrate, in the period 1990–2005, of the total&amp;nbsp; investment of $46.2 billion in WSS, the upper middle, lower middle and the lowest income nations captured 56%, 43% and 1% respectively.&amp;nbsp; Thus, one can conclude that provision of water supply and sanitation is not a game of either-or, rather an affair where the nation needs to create an enabling environment that can harness innovation and good governance for achieving success.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      
        <category term="humanity" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Today, about 2.6 billion people live without basic sanitation and nearly 1.1 billion live without access to safe drinking water. Around 13% of the world population still defecates in the open. The&amp;nbsp; diarrhoeal diseases that result from poor sanitation kill more than five million children every year and 9% of these deaths happen to be of children aged less than five years. Up to 50% of malnutrition is attributable to poor water, sanitation and hygiene, as are many neglected tropical diseases. Death and disease due to inadequate sanitation not only burdens a country's healthcare system, it also causes a huge emotional and financial cost to families. Children drop out of school and fail to reach their potential, especially young girls. Moreover, research shows how poor sanitation has a substantial impact on the economy as well. Countries with poor access to sanitation are losing significant proportions of their GDP – in India, this figure is over 5%. It thus stands to reason that we need better sanitation for a better economy, a better society and a better world. The question is: how do we achieve that? Moreover, which sector should cater to Water Supply and Sanitation (WSS)? Private or Public? Economists champion public sector involvement in cases of market failures and unequal distribution of economic outcomes. The prime justification for public provision of WSS is market failures such as natural monopoly, externalities, and public good characteristics. A sole profit-oriented producer of a good with declining long-term average cost will restrict output to monopoly level, thereby leading to a social welfare loss. Thus, government intervention is essential to restore efficiency. Moreover, the positive externalities gained from use of WSS further strengthens this argument. It is the responsibility of the government to not just focus on efficiency (the primary focus of profit-oriented enterprises) but also to make sure that distribution is provided to all, without any disparity.&amp;nbsp; However, experiences from the past have shown that public-owned utilities have not always been successful both in developed and developing nations. This has been especially so in the latter case owing to various non-market failures. Public WSS services have remained lacking on grounds of efficiency. Large proportions of the population have little or no access to public WSS services, while the remaining who receive it often face issues of poor quality, characterised by frequent breakdowns and unreliable supply.&amp;nbsp; Simultaneously, these water utilities barely have enough to cover operational costs, leaving no surplus available to finance the expansion of networks, eventually leading to a downward spiral in customer service. This results in the consumer's reluctance to pay higher tariffs ultimately leading to a deterioration of assets and squandering of financial resources. This descending cycle attracts political interference and furthers the velocity of the fall.&amp;nbsp; Secondly, divergence of personal gains of employees from the social goals and absence of reliable measures to hold such officials accountable further exacerbates the deplorable functioning of such organisations. These organisations become hotbeds of corruption and maladministration. Hence, there have been growing views in favour of privatisation for increased competition and better efficiency. Furthermore, WSS does fulfil the prerequisite of a private good by being rivalrous in nature, and the additional benefits associated with its consumption generates a stronger incentive for individuals to pay higher for obtaining better quality services.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The private sector has long played a role in the water sector, particularly in the industrialised economies. Historically, water supplies in many cities of the US were provided by private players until the government reverted the ownership to itself. The WSS services are entirely provided by the private sector in countries such as the UK, France, Philippines, etc.&amp;nbsp; Owing to the principal role of Water and Sanitation, such countries do have in place mechanisms where the government has oversight over the private sector. It accomplishes this through models which outsource management and supply of WSS while retaining public ownership, or by providing concessions against contracts, or through the presence of a regulatory agency. The only exception is France where there exists no sort of supervision by the administration. Private sector involvement in such a key area of the economy presents numerous risks for the former, such as commercial, financial, technical, legal and political risks.&amp;nbsp; Commercial risks involve the fear that the private investors may not be able to recoup their investment and make a profit, while technical risks pertain to insufficient knowledge about the state of installations resulting in operational failures. Legal risks occur as a result of contractual disputes, while financial risks relate to currency devaluations and convertibility of local to foreign currency, especially when foreign borrowings are used to finance services. Political risks stem from governments' changing policy in the course of implementation of the contract or due to their reluctance in charging higher tariffs.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; An example to illustrate the risks posed could be seen in the case of Argentina. Water privatisation in Argentina began in 1992, where certain concessions were awarded by the administration to private companies. Post 2001, all concessions were terminated under the leadership of a different government on the basis that the contracts were not fulfilled by the providing company. The private companies conceded to their failure in meeting the targets, but argued that a freeze in tariffs at the time of the devaluation of the Peso during the Argentine economic crisis violated the contract, and thus, made it impossible for them to achieve the set targets. In July 2010, the International Centre for the Settlement of Investment Disputes (ICSID) ruled in favour of the private concessionaires and entitled them to compensation. Thus, there were losses faced by both the private companies and the government, with no winners in such a fight.&amp;nbsp; Private sector participation (in such areas) has generally been touted as the solution to the pressing need of huge capital investments in the water sector. However, the ability of the private sector to actually invest in water infrastructure is doubtful. As per the Global Water Partnership, estimates of the total investment needs for new water infrastructure amounted to $180 billion per year for the period of 2000–2005. However, according to historical data, total private investment in WSS has averaged $3.3 billion per year, i.e. only about 1.8% of the annual investment needs of developing countries. In Asia, the annual average private investment of $1.9 billion in water (World Bank PPI database) accounts for 7.9% of the total financing needs of the region. Another claimed basis for involvement of private players is increased competition so as to improve the overall efficiency. However, the investment level in the distribution networks is massive relative to the size of the market, which obscures the potential for direct product market competition in developing countries. The entry to this market is often done on contractual basis from governments but factors like political risks, long payback periods, huge sunk costs and high degree of non-transparency while awarding the contracts deter private sector participation. Additionally, there has not been any substantial data to evidently prove the productive efficiency of the private sector in sanitation.&amp;nbsp; Lastly, one of the most important arguments in favour of private sector participation is the expansion in the scope of services due to the huge resources it brings with it. However, this theoretical abundance is difficult to translate into actions in the developing economies for the following reasons: 1) On the demand side, the unwillingness of the consumers to pay cost-recovering tariffs (maybe due to unawareness of the benefits of WSS); and 2) on the supply side, neglect of the poor by profit-oriented firms which pursue only the wealthy section to recoup their large investments. Moreover, rural areas have scattered populations that often present technical, organisational, and financial sustainability issues, thus proving to be unviable for private companies. As per data, private investments have appeared to have benefited the relatively wealthier countries due to the lower risks associated with them in ways such as market friendly policy and institutional environments, high household incomes, effective regulatory mechanisms, etc.&amp;nbsp; To illustrate, in the period 1990–2005, of the total&amp;nbsp; investment of $46.2 billion in WSS, the upper middle, lower middle and the lowest income nations captured 56%, 43% and 1% respectively.&amp;nbsp; Thus, one can conclude that provision of water supply and sanitation is not a game of either-or, rather an affair where the nation needs to create an enabling environment that can harness innovation and good governance for achieving success.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Capitalising on the Pandemic</title>
      <link href="/Capitalising-on-the-Pandemic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Capitalising on the Pandemic" />
      <published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Capitalising-on-the-Pandemic</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Capitalising-on-the-Pandemic">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Post the first wave of COVID-19, people across the world were hoping to have access to vaccination. On December 31, 2020, the Pfizer/BioNTech vaccine received emergency validation from the World Health Organisation (WHO). It was the first vaccine which was made available for public use. Since then, multiple vaccines have been made available for use across nations. Oxford/AstraZeneca, Moderna and Sputnik are some of the most common vaccines which are being used as of today.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;All major producers observed a huge surge in sales and revenues. AstraZeneca was the only manufacturer to witness a decrease in its profits compared to their gains in 2020. They claim that they have ‘no regrets’ associated with the falling share of profits on their vaccine, as it is benefiting people and preventing hospitalisation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, the not-for-profit vaccine schemes washed out within a year. The new contracts signed by big pharmas were all &lt;em&gt;for profit&lt;/em&gt;. All major vaccine producers are now banking on this pandemic, which doesn’t seem to be ending anytime soon. The latest Omicron variant has increased the demands for booster doses which will increase demands from all nations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In May 2021, Pfizer stated that, “they brought in $3.5 billion in revenue during the first three months of the year”. Although they never disclosed their profit numbers, they reiterated their previous predictions that the profit margins on the vaccine would be in the top 20% range. Unlike others, this was just one vaccine giant willing to talk about numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As the gains continue to soar high for the pharmaceuticals, some of the poorest nations remain largely unvaccinated. According to some reports, vaccine producers like Pfizer, BioNtech and Moderna are using their monopolies to earn huge profits by signing favourable contracts. Most of their dealings are with rich governments while only less than 1% of their vaccine supplies are being delivered to the low income countries. Large parts of the African population still remain unvaccinated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As per the reports, by August 2020, the USA had secured 800 billion doses of at least six different vaccines in the process of development. This was followed by the UK, the world’s highest per capita buyer with 340 million doses; approximately five doses for each citizen. The European Union nations which ordered doses as a group were not far behind and had acquired deals for around hundred million doses.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A United Nations press released on 16th April 2021 quoted Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus, Director-General of the World Health Organization (WHO); &lt;em&gt;“of the 832 million vaccine doses administered, 82 per cent have gone to high- or upper‑middle-income countries, while only 0.2 per cent have been sent to their low-income counterparts.&amp;nbsp; In high‑income countries alone, 1 in 4 people have been vaccinated, a ratio that drops precipitously to 1 in 500 in poorer countries”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As this data suggests, vaccine equity is a real challenge of our time. The world is failing to deal with it and will have to bear the consequences in no time. It also gives rise to a major debate on whether COVID-19 vaccines should be considered a public good.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;UNESCO’s&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.unesco.org/themes/ethics-science-and-technology/ibc&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; International Bioethics Committee (IBC)&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.unesco.org/themes/ethics-science-and-technology/comest#:~:text=The%20World%20Commission%20on%20the,up%20by%20UNESCO%20in%201998.&amp;amp;text=The%20Commission%20is%20mandated%20to,extend%20beyond%20purely%20economic%20considerations.&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;World Commission on the Ethics of Scientific Knowledge and Technology (COMEST)&lt;/a&gt; have asked for a reevaluation of the current vaccination strategies, urging that vaccines should be treated as a global public good. They should be equitably available to all nations and not only those capable of placing the highest bids.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Experts from the scientific community and other organisations have been reiterating the importance of &lt;em&gt;vaccines for all&lt;/em&gt;. They believe that in order to prevent the rapid spread of newer variants, immunisation plays a major role, but a minimum of 60-70% of the world population needs to be vaccinated for that. The vaccines are capable of ensuring less severity of disease along with lower rates of hospitalisation, while also reducing chances of virus mutations and spread in short periods of time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India and South Africa have initiated talks about waiving off the intellectual property rights of the big pharmas. This move is backed by several countries and international organisations who support the principle that every&lt;em&gt; country should have the right to produce their own vaccines during a pandemic&lt;/em&gt;. However, the pharmaceuticals industry along with some high income nations are not in favour of this proposal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It is believed that this would allow nations to produce vaccines as per their own demand. The so-called Nobel Pharma doesn't seem to agree with this idea and claims that due to shortage of raw materials it would take years to produce vaccines from scratch. Analysing the situation, it won’t be wrong to assume that vaccines are being seen as liquid gold and the major pharmaceutical companies are leaving no stone unturned in their quest to increase revenues.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A similar inequality exists in my country, i.e. India.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India’s vaccination drive started in January 2021 prior to the fatal second wave. The drug regulatory body of India approved the use of Covaxin, a home-grown vaccine manufactured by Bharat Biotech, and Covishield (Oxford/AstraZeneca), manufactured by the Serum Institute of India (SII). They have been producing nearly 100 million doses each month since January 2021.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Considering the huge inequality, vaccines are provided free of cost through central and state government collaborations. These doses are available at government-run dispensaries, hospitals and institutions have turned into vaccination centres to assist the ongoing efforts of the government.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Despite the strategies in place, the vaccination drive has been hampered multiple times due to shortage of supply of doses in the first initial months and other pragmatic reasons such as hesitance regarding immunisation, far off distance of vaccination centres from villages, etc. The government cannot shrug off its responsibility by providing doses free of cost and not ensuring equitable distribution of the public good.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The administration has to further strengthen its outreach to ensure availability of vaccines to the most vulnerable sections of the society residing in far off areas of rural India. In order to prevent the horrors of an upcoming third wave, immunisation among the adult population is essential.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The latest Omicron variant of Coronavirus was first detected in South Africa. It's only been two months and the cases have been rising exponentially across the globe. The only way to reduce severity and fatalities in the coming few weeks is mass scale vaccination.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;What started out as a pandemic has taken the form of an endemic! It is a global health crisis which needs to be dealt with in a unified manner. It's about time that big pharma and first world nations understand their collective responsibility to provide for the lower income nations. The mutations are not limited to continents and thus, a mutual effort is required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Capitalising on a pandemic, which can be termed as a humanitarian crisis, isn’t a wise decision. Protecting global health should be prioritised at all costs. Vaccine as a global public good would do more good to humanity in the long run rather than the short lived profits of big pharmas.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Here's to hoping for a safe and healthy year ahead!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      
        <category term="humanity" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Post the first wave of COVID-19, people across the world were hoping to have access to vaccination. On December 31, 2020, the Pfizer/BioNTech vaccine received emergency validation from the World Health Organisation (WHO). It was the first vaccine which was made available for public use. Since then, multiple vaccines have been made available for use across nations. Oxford/AstraZeneca, Moderna and Sputnik are some of the most common vaccines which are being used as of today.&amp;nbsp; All major producers observed a huge surge in sales and revenues. AstraZeneca was the only manufacturer to witness a decrease in its profits compared to their gains in 2020. They claim that they have ‘no regrets’ associated with the falling share of profits on their vaccine, as it is benefiting people and preventing hospitalisation.&amp;nbsp; However, the not-for-profit vaccine schemes washed out within a year. The new contracts signed by big pharmas were all for profit. All major vaccine producers are now banking on this pandemic, which doesn’t seem to be ending anytime soon. The latest Omicron variant has increased the demands for booster doses which will increase demands from all nations.&amp;nbsp; In May 2021, Pfizer stated that, “they brought in $3.5 billion in revenue during the first three months of the year”. Although they never disclosed their profit numbers, they reiterated their previous predictions that the profit margins on the vaccine would be in the top 20% range. Unlike others, this was just one vaccine giant willing to talk about numbers. As the gains continue to soar high for the pharmaceuticals, some of the poorest nations remain largely unvaccinated. According to some reports, vaccine producers like Pfizer, BioNtech and Moderna are using their monopolies to earn huge profits by signing favourable contracts. Most of their dealings are with rich governments while only less than 1% of their vaccine supplies are being delivered to the low income countries. Large parts of the African population still remain unvaccinated. As per the reports, by August 2020, the USA had secured 800 billion doses of at least six different vaccines in the process of development. This was followed by the UK, the world’s highest per capita buyer with 340 million doses; approximately five doses for each citizen. The European Union nations which ordered doses as a group were not far behind and had acquired deals for around hundred million doses.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; A United Nations press released on 16th April 2021 quoted Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus, Director-General of the World Health Organization (WHO); “of the 832 million vaccine doses administered, 82 per cent have gone to high- or upper‑middle-income countries, while only 0.2 per cent have been sent to their low-income counterparts.&amp;nbsp; In high‑income countries alone, 1 in 4 people have been vaccinated, a ratio that drops precipitously to 1 in 500 in poorer countries”. As this data suggests, vaccine equity is a real challenge of our time. The world is failing to deal with it and will have to bear the consequences in no time. It also gives rise to a major debate on whether COVID-19 vaccines should be considered a public good.&amp;nbsp; UNESCO’s International Bioethics Committee (IBC) and the World Commission on the Ethics of Scientific Knowledge and Technology (COMEST) have asked for a reevaluation of the current vaccination strategies, urging that vaccines should be treated as a global public good. They should be equitably available to all nations and not only those capable of placing the highest bids.&amp;nbsp; Experts from the scientific community and other organisations have been reiterating the importance of vaccines for all. They believe that in order to prevent the rapid spread of newer variants, immunisation plays a major role, but a minimum of 60-70% of the world population needs to be vaccinated for that. The vaccines are capable of ensuring less severity of disease along with lower rates of hospitalisation, while also reducing chances of virus mutations and spread in short periods of time.&amp;nbsp; India and South Africa have initiated talks about waiving off the intellectual property rights of the big pharmas. This move is backed by several countries and international organisations who support the principle that every country should have the right to produce their own vaccines during a pandemic. However, the pharmaceuticals industry along with some high income nations are not in favour of this proposal.&amp;nbsp; It is believed that this would allow nations to produce vaccines as per their own demand. The so-called Nobel Pharma doesn't seem to agree with this idea and claims that due to shortage of raw materials it would take years to produce vaccines from scratch. Analysing the situation, it won’t be wrong to assume that vaccines are being seen as liquid gold and the major pharmaceutical companies are leaving no stone unturned in their quest to increase revenues.&amp;nbsp; A similar inequality exists in my country, i.e. India.&amp;nbsp; India’s vaccination drive started in January 2021 prior to the fatal second wave. The drug regulatory body of India approved the use of Covaxin, a home-grown vaccine manufactured by Bharat Biotech, and Covishield (Oxford/AstraZeneca), manufactured by the Serum Institute of India (SII). They have been producing nearly 100 million doses each month since January 2021.&amp;nbsp; Considering the huge inequality, vaccines are provided free of cost through central and state government collaborations. These doses are available at government-run dispensaries, hospitals and institutions have turned into vaccination centres to assist the ongoing efforts of the government.&amp;nbsp; Despite the strategies in place, the vaccination drive has been hampered multiple times due to shortage of supply of doses in the first initial months and other pragmatic reasons such as hesitance regarding immunisation, far off distance of vaccination centres from villages, etc. The government cannot shrug off its responsibility by providing doses free of cost and not ensuring equitable distribution of the public good.&amp;nbsp; The administration has to further strengthen its outreach to ensure availability of vaccines to the most vulnerable sections of the society residing in far off areas of rural India. In order to prevent the horrors of an upcoming third wave, immunisation among the adult population is essential.&amp;nbsp; The latest Omicron variant of Coronavirus was first detected in South Africa. It's only been two months and the cases have been rising exponentially across the globe. The only way to reduce severity and fatalities in the coming few weeks is mass scale vaccination.&amp;nbsp; What started out as a pandemic has taken the form of an endemic! It is a global health crisis which needs to be dealt with in a unified manner. It's about time that big pharma and first world nations understand their collective responsibility to provide for the lower income nations. The mutations are not limited to continents and thus, a mutual effort is required. Capitalising on a pandemic, which can be termed as a humanitarian crisis, isn’t a wise decision. Protecting global health should be prioritised at all costs. Vaccine as a global public good would do more good to humanity in the long run rather than the short lived profits of big pharmas.&amp;nbsp; Here's to hoping for a safe and healthy year ahead!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Understanding the SPAC Phenomenon</title>
      <link href="/Understanding-the-SPAC-Phenomenon" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding the SPAC Phenomenon" />
      <published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Understanding-the-SPAC-Phenomenon</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-the-SPAC-Phenomenon">&lt;p&gt;Special Purpose Acquisition Companies, or SPACs, have been in the limelight lately, be it on Wall Street, in corporate boardrooms, or in the media. Even celebrities and public figures like the famous singer-songwriter, Ciara, and the former US speaker of the House, Paul Ryan, are jumping on the bandwagon. Hell, even former President Donald Trump has launched his own media network, including a social media platform called 'TRUTH Social' in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/10/22/trump-social-media-spac-digital-world-acquisition-corp-surges-another-100percent.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;SPAC merger&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand the quickly booming industry, take a look at the following figures: &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2021/07/spacs-what-you-need-to-know&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;in 2019&lt;/a&gt;, 59 SPACs were created, with $13 billion invested; in 2020, 247 were created, with $80 billion invested; and in the first quarter alone of 2021, 295 were created, with $96 billion invested.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But what exactly is a SPAC, and why is everyone talking about it?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, a special purpose acquisition company (SPAC) is a sort of shell company formed for the sole purpose of raising investment capital through an IPO. Such an arrangement allows investors to contribute money towards a fund, which is later used to acquire or merge with one or more unspecified businesses wanting to go public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though SPACs are an active part of contemporary discourse, SPACs were fraudulent when they first appeared as blank-check corporations, in the 1980's. However, with the introduction of much-needed regulation for SPACs, for example, barrage on the use of the proceeds of blank-check IPOs until the mergers were complete, blank-check corporations could be successfully rebranded as SPACs, as we now know them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An important feature of modern SPACs is the option for investors to withdraw from a deal after the sponsor identifies a target, which is to say, if investors don’t like the deal, they can choose to pull out, redeeming their shares for cash plus interest.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sponsors of SPACs usually have two years to find a company to merge with/acquire and intimate the market on which industry they’re targeting. And when it comes to which industry they usually target, then as per recent trends, the hot areas seem to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/21502700/spac-explained-meaning-special-purpose-acquisition-company&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;EVs and Technology&lt;/a&gt; (consumer tech, biotech etc).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What makes SPACs better than traditional IPOs?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I were to define SPACs with utmost precision, I’d say a SPAC is an IPO for ‘nothing’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is because, with a SPAC, the IPO is already done, you’re just left to negotiate with the SPAC that might acquire you, which makes the process a lot faster. You’re not even required to arrange for a roadshow, for the pool of funds is already available! Apart from greater speed, SPACs also provide higher valuations, lower fees, less dilution, more certainty and transparency, and fewer regulatory demands than traditional IPOs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most private companies go public years after the commencement of their operations, that is, when they achieve stability, thus depriving investors of an opportunity to experience the gains from their growth spurts. Many investors are interested in being part of a company’s journey but they’ve been frustrated because of being unable to access these companies as they’ve stayed private longer. And this is where SPACs come to the rescue! They usually enable investors to help a business grow from rags to riches, and reap the resulting rewards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the flip side though, some investors may be apprehensive of buying shares of a company going public through a SPAC because the amount of due diligence required for that may be lesser than a regular IPO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A parallel between VCs and SPACs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A SPAC isn’t just a medium for a company to go public, it’s a medium for a company to raise new capital to deploy toward some business objective. So if we look at SPACs as an instrument of capital allocation rather than that of a go-public mechanism, they start to look a lot like venture capital firms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major criticism of the SPAC boom is that companies going public through SPACs are often initially low quality, because they have yet to generate any revenue. This is largely common in VC firm investments, which require dealing with the uncertainty of the value of future cash flows, that might be more than a decade away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, just like VCs, SPACs enable investors to partake in the rewards arising out of helping a business grow from scratch, instead of an already stable base, in the case of most traditional IPOs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the SPAC market mirrors the venture capital market very closely in the sense that investors have to pitch companies to take their money. So it’s no wonder that while SPACs may compete against each other for targets, they also compete with VC firms as companies choose the best path for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The stakeholders in a SPAC&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three main stakeholder groups in a SPAC, namely, sponsors, investors, and targets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sponsors&lt;/strong&gt;: The SPAC process is initiated by the sponsors. They invest risk capital in the form of nonrefundable payments to accountants, bankers, and lawyers. Since SPACs don’t own any assets, it’s the sponsors that are the main attraction point. In essence, to investors, a SPAC is only as credible as its sponsors. If sponsors fail to create an arrangement within the deadline, the SPAC must be dissolved and all funds returned. The sponsors lose not only their risk capital but also all the time they invested. But if they succeed, they earn sponsors’ shares in the resulting company, often worth as much as 20% of the equity raised from original investors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investors:&lt;/strong&gt; The investors in SPACs (mainly institutional investors and highly specialized hedge funds) receive two classes of securities: common stock (typically at $10 per share) and warrants that allow them to buy shares at a specified price (typically $11.50 per share) in the future. While warrants are considered to be incentives to subscribe, the greater the number of warrants issued, the higher the perceived risk of the SPAC. After the announcement of the target, the original investors choose to move forward with the deal or withdraw.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SPAC mergers often involve parallel funding by institutional investors, known as 'private investment in public equity' or PIPE. While the institutional investors in PIPE (mutual funds, family offices, private equity firms, pension funds, strategic investors) provide the company that’s merging some additional funds (locked up for six months), they get a chunk of the new company in return. Sponsors use PIPEs to represent a vote of confidence, increase the funding, and guarantee a minimum amount of cash should the original investors choose to pull out of the deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Targets: &lt;/strong&gt;Most SPAC targets at this stage consider several options like pursuing a traditional IPO, approaching venture capital firms, raising additional capital, or selling the business to another company or a private equity firm. Due to the multiple benefits that SPACs offer, they can be an attractive alternative to the above-mentioned options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SPACs seem amazing! What’s the catch?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite all the glitter, SPACs aren’t gold. They &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/6eb655a2-21f5-4313-b287-964a63dd88b3&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;have a dubious reputation when it comes to fraud&lt;/a&gt;. Take, for example, the infamous case of Akazoo, the Greek streaming company listed on the markets in 2019. A short-seller named Gabriel Grego did some digging and asserted that the subscriber figures Akazoo provided were falsified. The company’s board launched an investigation, “eventually concluding that the company’s previous management had ‘participated in a sophisticated scheme to falsify Akazoo’s books and records,’” including the documents that had been given to the acquiring SPAC, according to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/6eb655a2-21f5-4313-b287-964a63dd88b3&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Financial Times&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another analysis by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/6eb655a2-21f5-4313-b287-964a63dd88b3&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Financial Times&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of the SPACs from 2015 and 2019 found that the majority of the SPACs trade below their original price of $10 a share. And these aren’t very reassuring, or confidence-inspiring stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The bottom line&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of ways the events can unfold in this rapidly evolving story - the two most famous contenders being the SPAC boom emerging as a safe and sustainable bet or it ending in a bubble burst.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All we can do is wait, and watch how these SPACs unpack.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Eeshita Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Special Purpose Acquisition Companies, or SPACs, have been in the limelight lately, be it on Wall Street, in corporate boardrooms, or in the media. Even celebrities and public figures like the famous singer-songwriter, Ciara, and the former US speaker of the House, Paul Ryan, are jumping on the bandwagon. Hell, even former President Donald Trump has launched his own media network, including a social media platform called 'TRUTH Social' in a SPAC merger.&amp;nbsp; To understand the quickly booming industry, take a look at the following figures: in 2019, 59 SPACs were created, with $13 billion invested; in 2020, 247 were created, with $80 billion invested; and in the first quarter alone of 2021, 295 were created, with $96 billion invested.&amp;nbsp; But what exactly is a SPAC, and why is everyone talking about it? To put it simply, a special purpose acquisition company (SPAC) is a sort of shell company formed for the sole purpose of raising investment capital through an IPO. Such an arrangement allows investors to contribute money towards a fund, which is later used to acquire or merge with one or more unspecified businesses wanting to go public. Even though SPACs are an active part of contemporary discourse, SPACs were fraudulent when they first appeared as blank-check corporations, in the 1980's. However, with the introduction of much-needed regulation for SPACs, for example, barrage on the use of the proceeds of blank-check IPOs until the mergers were complete, blank-check corporations could be successfully rebranded as SPACs, as we now know them. An important feature of modern SPACs is the option for investors to withdraw from a deal after the sponsor identifies a target, which is to say, if investors don’t like the deal, they can choose to pull out, redeeming their shares for cash plus interest.&amp;nbsp; The sponsors of SPACs usually have two years to find a company to merge with/acquire and intimate the market on which industry they’re targeting. And when it comes to which industry they usually target, then as per recent trends, the hot areas seem to be EVs and Technology (consumer tech, biotech etc).&amp;nbsp; What makes SPACs better than traditional IPOs? If I were to define SPACs with utmost precision, I’d say a SPAC is an IPO for ‘nothing’.&amp;nbsp; This is because, with a SPAC, the IPO is already done, you’re just left to negotiate with the SPAC that might acquire you, which makes the process a lot faster. You’re not even required to arrange for a roadshow, for the pool of funds is already available! Apart from greater speed, SPACs also provide higher valuations, lower fees, less dilution, more certainty and transparency, and fewer regulatory demands than traditional IPOs. Most private companies go public years after the commencement of their operations, that is, when they achieve stability, thus depriving investors of an opportunity to experience the gains from their growth spurts. Many investors are interested in being part of a company’s journey but they’ve been frustrated because of being unable to access these companies as they’ve stayed private longer. And this is where SPACs come to the rescue! They usually enable investors to help a business grow from rags to riches, and reap the resulting rewards. On the flip side though, some investors may be apprehensive of buying shares of a company going public through a SPAC because the amount of due diligence required for that may be lesser than a regular IPO. A parallel between VCs and SPACs A SPAC isn’t just a medium for a company to go public, it’s a medium for a company to raise new capital to deploy toward some business objective. So if we look at SPACs as an instrument of capital allocation rather than that of a go-public mechanism, they start to look a lot like venture capital firms. A major criticism of the SPAC boom is that companies going public through SPACs are often initially low quality, because they have yet to generate any revenue. This is largely common in VC firm investments, which require dealing with the uncertainty of the value of future cash flows, that might be more than a decade away. Moreover, just like VCs, SPACs enable investors to partake in the rewards arising out of helping a business grow from scratch, instead of an already stable base, in the case of most traditional IPOs. Lastly, the SPAC market mirrors the venture capital market very closely in the sense that investors have to pitch companies to take their money. So it’s no wonder that while SPACs may compete against each other for targets, they also compete with VC firms as companies choose the best path for themselves. The stakeholders in a SPAC There are three main stakeholder groups in a SPAC, namely, sponsors, investors, and targets: Sponsors: The SPAC process is initiated by the sponsors. They invest risk capital in the form of nonrefundable payments to accountants, bankers, and lawyers. Since SPACs don’t own any assets, it’s the sponsors that are the main attraction point. In essence, to investors, a SPAC is only as credible as its sponsors. If sponsors fail to create an arrangement within the deadline, the SPAC must be dissolved and all funds returned. The sponsors lose not only their risk capital but also all the time they invested. But if they succeed, they earn sponsors’ shares in the resulting company, often worth as much as 20% of the equity raised from original investors. Investors: The investors in SPACs (mainly institutional investors and highly specialized hedge funds) receive two classes of securities: common stock (typically at $10 per share) and warrants that allow them to buy shares at a specified price (typically $11.50 per share) in the future. While warrants are considered to be incentives to subscribe, the greater the number of warrants issued, the higher the perceived risk of the SPAC. After the announcement of the target, the original investors choose to move forward with the deal or withdraw.&amp;nbsp; SPAC mergers often involve parallel funding by institutional investors, known as 'private investment in public equity' or PIPE. While the institutional investors in PIPE (mutual funds, family offices, private equity firms, pension funds, strategic investors) provide the company that’s merging some additional funds (locked up for six months), they get a chunk of the new company in return. Sponsors use PIPEs to represent a vote of confidence, increase the funding, and guarantee a minimum amount of cash should the original investors choose to pull out of the deal. Targets: Most SPAC targets at this stage consider several options like pursuing a traditional IPO, approaching venture capital firms, raising additional capital, or selling the business to another company or a private equity firm. Due to the multiple benefits that SPACs offer, they can be an attractive alternative to the above-mentioned options. SPACs seem amazing! What’s the catch? Despite all the glitter, SPACs aren’t gold. They have a dubious reputation when it comes to fraud. Take, for example, the infamous case of Akazoo, the Greek streaming company listed on the markets in 2019. A short-seller named Gabriel Grego did some digging and asserted that the subscriber figures Akazoo provided were falsified. The company’s board launched an investigation, “eventually concluding that the company’s previous management had ‘participated in a sophisticated scheme to falsify Akazoo’s books and records,’” including the documents that had been given to the acquiring SPAC, according to the Financial Times. Another analysis by the Financial Times of the SPACs from 2015 and 2019 found that the majority of the SPACs trade below their original price of $10 a share. And these aren’t very reassuring, or confidence-inspiring stories. The bottom line There are a lot of ways the events can unfold in this rapidly evolving story - the two most famous contenders being the SPAC boom emerging as a safe and sustainable bet or it ending in a bubble burst.&amp;nbsp; All we can do is wait, and watch how these SPACs unpack.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Wall Street’s New Leviathan</title>
      <link href="/Wall-Street-s-New-Leviathan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wall Street’s New Leviathan" />
      <published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Wall-Street-s-New-Leviathan</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Wall-Street-s-New-Leviathan">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Thou art Peter, and upon this rock I will build my church.”&lt;/em&gt; (Matthew 16:18)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chances are high you’ll find a person who knows about this Peter, the bedrock of Christianity – it is the religion with the greatest number of adherents, after all. About two millennia later, the modern-day Peter has emerged, albeit less popular.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Americans pride themselves on being intelligent people, the folks who are good at everything – from fast food to babysitting world peace. Even if we were to believe these claims, one thing they’re &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; good at is answering a simple question – ‘&lt;em&gt;How much is too much?&lt;/em&gt;’&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This unanswered question has hurt the States time and again, and yet, answering it is &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; an ex-post job and not ex-ante. A decade after Wall Street fell victim to its own greed, regulations and investment trends of people who grew up through this collapse have shifted all headwinds to the buy-side, making them the new apex predators of what the country chooses to call capitalism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the buy-side firms are becoming as large as pre-crash investment banks, one particular name stands apart from the rest – literally and figuratively. It controls $9.5 trillion worth of assets and chances are, you have not heard of this firm - BlackRock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The firm and its asset growth are the true embodiment of the word exponential. Compared to the century-old financial behemoths such as Deutsche Bank, Goldman Sachs and Morgan Stanley, BlackRock was founded in 1988, a meagre three-decade-old company.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Founder Larry Fink was the man behind the infamous Mortgage-Backed Securities (MBS) market, which led to the 2008 crisis and subsequently his fall at Wall Street’s bulge bracket. Investment company First Boston used this as an opportunity and made him start an asset management firm: BlackRock, with an emphasis on risk management as their ace in the hole.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with a humble $5 million credit line from Blackstone, Fink and BlackRock quadrupled their assets within the year, a pace that continues till date - the firm adds a trillion to its asset base every year or so, which is the equivalent of saying it adds the &lt;em&gt;total&lt;/em&gt; asset base of leading asset management firms till date, to its balance sheet every year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BlackRock is like a Swiss-Army knife. As you’d expect, it is difficult to find a sector where the firm is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in. Currently, it is an institutional investor, money manager, consultant and private equity firm. It effectively is involved on all sides of the table in most industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A funny example is that of the environment. In 2017, announcements were made to support ESG practices within owned firms and improve the investment landscape in sustainable practices with new products. Two years later, BlackRock was a major shareholder in every big oil company and in seven of the leading producers of the other black rock – coal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this became public knowledge, protests were staged outside of BlackRock‘s France division, leading Fink to announce an exit from coal and fossil fuel assets. Alongside, revelations were made of letters to the boards of companies to improve sustainability and gender diversity practices or risk losing business with BlackRock.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other times, it simply has stakes in leading competitors – Apple and Microsoft, Deutsche Bank, JP Morgan Chase and Wells Fargo, just to name a few. It simply cannot lose money unless the entire sector goes bust.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can figure out other conflicts as well – a company goes to raise debt and BlackRock, a major shareholder, is already out to be a buyer of this debt. BlackRock is an advisor to most firms it’s an investor in. The ownership structure should ring a few alarms as well – Vanguard, another asset manager and a direct competitor of BlackRock, is its biggest shareholder. Many institutions that BlackRock invests in, are shareholders of BlackRock themselves.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is another part of BlackRock’s business that took flight in 1999 and is dubbed as “&lt;em&gt;a tech start-up&lt;/em&gt;” by CEO Fink – Aladdin, the risk management system. One would be damned if their start-up was managing risk for $21.6 trillion worth of assets including those of the Federal Reserve Board and the European Central Bank. BlackRock’s internal ‘Tech 2025’ plan aims to make Aladdin the standard, and perhaps the only used risk management platform in the industry. But that’s a monopoly for another time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, BlackRock is begging to be labelled as the present-day Illuminati, but that isn’t the case. However, it is a marionettist in its own right, and here is where things get murky. Back in the mid-to-late 00’s, Goldman Sachs was well known for hiring prominent policymakers who would go on to be part of America’s cabinet and ensure nothing went too awry for Wall Street.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 2008, one would expect that things would change and the blurred lines between White House and Wall Street would be redrawn but that’s the exact opposite of what happened. Who do you call when a set of financial products is threatening to, or rather, causing the biggest financial crisis in almost a century? Of course, it’s the creator!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the MBS markets were rearranging the food chain by the minute, one was eyeing the newly vacated spot of the apex predator – BlackRock. The Federal Reserve called in Fink and his team to manage the mess and has been a loyal customer ever since – be it Aladdin’s risk management, or an appropriate response to the coronavirus pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the pandemic hit, the Fed announced that it will purchase assets other than Treasury bonds as well – Corporate Bonds and Exchange Traded Funds (ETFs). Who else do we know as a major firm dealing in Corporate Bonds and ETFs? Do the math. The funds the Fed poured money in were a hit among retail investors and no prizes for guessing the issuer of the funds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are conversant with US law, you must have thought at least once about how BlackRock is not under the purview of ‘too big to fail’ or why the Dodd-Frank reform, which has riddled the powerhouses of the sell-side with multiple regulations on risk-taking, is not handicapping their earning potential?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is the same as that with Goldman – it has multiple former executives in Washington and multiple former Washington policymakers reside at the 52nd Street in Manhattan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This cosy revolving door is not just limited from Manhattan to Washington rather extends to Ottawa and Mexico City. For example, PEMEX, Mexico’s state-owned oil company was opened to private investment, and BlackRock quickly jumped in. Then it acquired a loss-making, scandalous private equity firm in the country, I Cuadrada, and a month down the line, Sierra Oil, a year-old portfolio company of the former, which had not had a project in its short life was awarded two major exploration contracts as the sole bidder.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BlackRock also holds the distinction of being the first global asset manager which has set up an onshore shop in China. There are multiple examples, from private to public sectors where the private firm has played on both sides of the court to benefit itself, earning the title of a white-collar mafia. Europe has dealt a stricter hand with criticism of the European Commission for awarding BlackRock a contract with a significant conflict of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the common person was never directly under attack from this leviathan but as it extends its power, it now faces a direct confrontation with the people – housing. The American Dream has always consisted of owning a place you can call home, however, that soon might not be the case as BlackRock and multiple other funds are outbidding individuals or paying the entire amount upfront with no inspection. These bids are too sweet for developers to pass.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you thought this was excessive, mega-funds are buying out entire neighbourhoods for a few factors above the listed prices and immediately putting them out on exorbitant rents. A new monopoly is unfolding before us and one can only hope America finds an answer to its age-old dilemma sooner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“For what does it profit a man to gain the whole world and forfeit his soul?”&lt;/em&gt; (Mark 8:36)&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aaradhya Daga</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Thou art Peter, and upon this rock I will build my church.” (Matthew 16:18) Chances are high you’ll find a person who knows about this Peter, the bedrock of Christianity – it is the religion with the greatest number of adherents, after all. About two millennia later, the modern-day Peter has emerged, albeit less popular.&amp;nbsp; Americans pride themselves on being intelligent people, the folks who are good at everything – from fast food to babysitting world peace. Even if we were to believe these claims, one thing they’re not good at is answering a simple question – ‘How much is too much?’&amp;nbsp; This unanswered question has hurt the States time and again, and yet, answering it is still an ex-post job and not ex-ante. A decade after Wall Street fell victim to its own greed, regulations and investment trends of people who grew up through this collapse have shifted all headwinds to the buy-side, making them the new apex predators of what the country chooses to call capitalism.&amp;nbsp; While the buy-side firms are becoming as large as pre-crash investment banks, one particular name stands apart from the rest – literally and figuratively. It controls $9.5 trillion worth of assets and chances are, you have not heard of this firm - BlackRock. The firm and its asset growth are the true embodiment of the word exponential. Compared to the century-old financial behemoths such as Deutsche Bank, Goldman Sachs and Morgan Stanley, BlackRock was founded in 1988, a meagre three-decade-old company.&amp;nbsp; Founder Larry Fink was the man behind the infamous Mortgage-Backed Securities (MBS) market, which led to the 2008 crisis and subsequently his fall at Wall Street’s bulge bracket. Investment company First Boston used this as an opportunity and made him start an asset management firm: BlackRock, with an emphasis on risk management as their ace in the hole.&amp;nbsp; Starting with a humble $5 million credit line from Blackstone, Fink and BlackRock quadrupled their assets within the year, a pace that continues till date - the firm adds a trillion to its asset base every year or so, which is the equivalent of saying it adds the total asset base of leading asset management firms till date, to its balance sheet every year.&amp;nbsp; BlackRock is like a Swiss-Army knife. As you’d expect, it is difficult to find a sector where the firm is not in. Currently, it is an institutional investor, money manager, consultant and private equity firm. It effectively is involved on all sides of the table in most industries. A funny example is that of the environment. In 2017, announcements were made to support ESG practices within owned firms and improve the investment landscape in sustainable practices with new products. Two years later, BlackRock was a major shareholder in every big oil company and in seven of the leading producers of the other black rock – coal.&amp;nbsp; When this became public knowledge, protests were staged outside of BlackRock‘s France division, leading Fink to announce an exit from coal and fossil fuel assets. Alongside, revelations were made of letters to the boards of companies to improve sustainability and gender diversity practices or risk losing business with BlackRock.&amp;nbsp; Other times, it simply has stakes in leading competitors – Apple and Microsoft, Deutsche Bank, JP Morgan Chase and Wells Fargo, just to name a few. It simply cannot lose money unless the entire sector goes bust.&amp;nbsp; You can figure out other conflicts as well – a company goes to raise debt and BlackRock, a major shareholder, is already out to be a buyer of this debt. BlackRock is an advisor to most firms it’s an investor in. The ownership structure should ring a few alarms as well – Vanguard, another asset manager and a direct competitor of BlackRock, is its biggest shareholder. Many institutions that BlackRock invests in, are shareholders of BlackRock themselves.&amp;nbsp; There is another part of BlackRock’s business that took flight in 1999 and is dubbed as “a tech start-up” by CEO Fink – Aladdin, the risk management system. One would be damned if their start-up was managing risk for $21.6 trillion worth of assets including those of the Federal Reserve Board and the European Central Bank. BlackRock’s internal ‘Tech 2025’ plan aims to make Aladdin the standard, and perhaps the only used risk management platform in the industry. But that’s a monopoly for another time. At this point, BlackRock is begging to be labelled as the present-day Illuminati, but that isn’t the case. However, it is a marionettist in its own right, and here is where things get murky. Back in the mid-to-late 00’s, Goldman Sachs was well known for hiring prominent policymakers who would go on to be part of America’s cabinet and ensure nothing went too awry for Wall Street. After 2008, one would expect that things would change and the blurred lines between White House and Wall Street would be redrawn but that’s the exact opposite of what happened. Who do you call when a set of financial products is threatening to, or rather, causing the biggest financial crisis in almost a century? Of course, it’s the creator! When the MBS markets were rearranging the food chain by the minute, one was eyeing the newly vacated spot of the apex predator – BlackRock. The Federal Reserve called in Fink and his team to manage the mess and has been a loyal customer ever since – be it Aladdin’s risk management, or an appropriate response to the coronavirus pandemic.&amp;nbsp; As the pandemic hit, the Fed announced that it will purchase assets other than Treasury bonds as well – Corporate Bonds and Exchange Traded Funds (ETFs). Who else do we know as a major firm dealing in Corporate Bonds and ETFs? Do the math. The funds the Fed poured money in were a hit among retail investors and no prizes for guessing the issuer of the funds. If you are conversant with US law, you must have thought at least once about how BlackRock is not under the purview of ‘too big to fail’ or why the Dodd-Frank reform, which has riddled the powerhouses of the sell-side with multiple regulations on risk-taking, is not handicapping their earning potential? The answer is the same as that with Goldman – it has multiple former executives in Washington and multiple former Washington policymakers reside at the 52nd Street in Manhattan.&amp;nbsp; This cosy revolving door is not just limited from Manhattan to Washington rather extends to Ottawa and Mexico City. For example, PEMEX, Mexico’s state-owned oil company was opened to private investment, and BlackRock quickly jumped in. Then it acquired a loss-making, scandalous private equity firm in the country, I Cuadrada, and a month down the line, Sierra Oil, a year-old portfolio company of the former, which had not had a project in its short life was awarded two major exploration contracts as the sole bidder.&amp;nbsp; BlackRock also holds the distinction of being the first global asset manager which has set up an onshore shop in China. There are multiple examples, from private to public sectors where the private firm has played on both sides of the court to benefit itself, earning the title of a white-collar mafia. Europe has dealt a stricter hand with criticism of the European Commission for awarding BlackRock a contract with a significant conflict of interest. While the common person was never directly under attack from this leviathan but as it extends its power, it now faces a direct confrontation with the people – housing. The American Dream has always consisted of owning a place you can call home, however, that soon might not be the case as BlackRock and multiple other funds are outbidding individuals or paying the entire amount upfront with no inspection. These bids are too sweet for developers to pass.&amp;nbsp; If you thought this was excessive, mega-funds are buying out entire neighbourhoods for a few factors above the listed prices and immediately putting them out on exorbitant rents. A new monopoly is unfolding before us and one can only hope America finds an answer to its age-old dilemma sooner. “For what does it profit a man to gain the whole world and forfeit his soul?” (Mark 8:36)</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Evergrande: A Cave-in of Real Estate?</title>
      <link href="/Evergrande" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evergrande: A Cave-in of Real Estate?" />
      <published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Evergrande</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Evergrande">&lt;p&gt;The year 2020 was the worst year for economic growth since World War II - all economies came to a standstill with the raging spread of the virus. However, China, the country where the first outbreak of COVID-19 was reported, was the only major economy in the world to report a positive GDP growth in that year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to November 2021, the second-largest economy seems to be in a precarious situation with various credit rating firms cutting down on its growth forecasts owing to glaring uncertainties in the nation.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my last article, I covered &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;China's crackdown on its tech sector&lt;/a&gt;. Now the ball has come rolling to its real estate sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evergrande Group, China's second-largest property developer and the world’s most indebted real estate firm with liabilities amounting to $300 billion, informed bondholders in early September about its inability to honour its interest obligation. (For context, Russia's state debt &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.themoscowtimes.com/2021/02/24/russias-government-debt-rose-40-in-2020-a73044&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;in 2020 was $257 billion&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evergrande was founded by Mr Xu Jiayin, who was once the country’s richest man, in 1996, and was in the bottled water business. Later the company expanded into several areas, including pig farming, owning a football club, wealth management and the electric car segment. However, it was its real estate business for which it was widely known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, it recorded a gross profit of nearly $19 billion and in the year before that, it was on the Fortune Global 500 list. The company owns 2% of all newly-constructed real estate in China and employs about 200,000 people directly and helps in sustaining more than 3.8 million jobs indirectly every year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The possible collapse of an organisation this big can be brushed aside as a one-time occurrence, however, one cannot turn a blind eye when many such firms in that line of business are on the same path: Chinese luxury developer Fantasia Holding Group and the Sinic Holdings group have also announced a default on their debt repayment obligations in mid-October.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cause of worry intensifies when one observes that around 30% of China’s Gross Domestic Product (GDP) is related to its real estate sector. Therefore, the fall of real estate companies can leave a dent not only in the Chinese economy but the global economy as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The State Of Real Estate In China&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the late 1980's, China started moving from public housing to the commercial property model. Post-1994, The central government decentralised the goals and interests of the policymakers - passing the responsibility of social welfare services to local administration but with taxes to be submitted back to them.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The imbalance of funds led provincial governments to create state-owned shell companies called Local Government Financing Vehicles (LGFV). They gave these LGFV free valuable lands which were then used to take out loans that the administration themselves could not. Consequently, this made the administration seem healthier because their debt was now hidden while at the same time they met quotas set by Beijing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, land became the backbone of local economies.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, steep discounts and low-interest rates were offered to citizens as an act of welfare. Strict regulation by the government on how much money leaves the country left citizens with limited investment options - stock markets became synonymous with volatility and risk and housing gained the reputation of safe and profitable investments in the country. Housing prices were also such that they fell only once in the two decades that followed the Asian Financial Crisis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the aforementioned reasons, real estate is one of the most loved sectors of the economy with homeownership in China being the highest in the world, i.e. around 90%. It has become the country's leading pillar of economic growth with a contribution of around 15-30% to the GDP. In the COVID-19 period alone, the sector has grown by 4.9%.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, an unusual trend is seen in the country. The boom in real estate is coming at a cost: high vacancy rates in cities due to the vast majority of home purchases being second/third homes. In 2018, 87% of new home buyers already owned at least one flat.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the societal norm in China is such that male marriages demand homeownership. Decades of the one-child policy have resulted in an imbalance between males and females with scales tipping in favour of the latter. As a result, female families have become awfully picky, with the groom's homeownership being one of the prerequisites. As per a study, home prices are higher in cities of disproportionate male-to-female ratios.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In cities like Shenzhen, Beijing, Shanghai - it takes nearly 40 years worth of an accumulated average income to afford a home. Thus the vast majority of homes are purchased even before the construction has begun, sometimes years in advance.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With overhead demand, some developers undertake techniques such as selling batches of properties in glitzy online events or through raffles-off in lotteries where thousands of apartments are often sold out in minutes, giving the winners mere hours to submit down payments or lose the opportunity.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What all these instances, numbers and facts point towards is that of a speculative market, i.e. the assumption that prices would only go up.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However the demographic of the country suggests otherwise. In the next ten years, the country’s over-55 cohort will increase in size by 120 million, but by the end of the century, the overall population will be cut in half. The majority of present home buyers are precisely from this segment which China would soon lose. In addition, with age, home requirements keep differing.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was reasonable to anticipate a decade ago that the rapid urbanisation demand would be met by bringing in more than enough migrants to effectively cancel out the effects of ageing. Nonetheless, the statistics prove otherwise with the migration rate falling below the country’s 60% urbanisation rate. Moreover, such exorbitant home prices act as a further deterrent to the very people that were to be attracted by the construction of so many homes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the demand-supply misproportion is haunting the real estate space.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coming Back&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the context of speculative and overpriced real estate being understood, what consequences are in store, given the defaults of Evergrande and other real estate firms?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trigger for this fall is attributed to new guidelines, known as The Red Lines, introduced by the government in August 2020 for property developers. The rule requires the ratio of liabilities-to-assets of developers and their net debt-to-equity ratio to be below 70% and 100% respectively whilst requiring real estate firms to maintain the cash-to-short term debt ratio at a minimum of 100%.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any borrower failing to meet these requirements would be restricted from raising more funds, practically cutting off developers from taking on more debts. This means a complete alteration in the nature of the real estate business, which relies heavily on borrowing for its capital requirements.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crackdown on developers is in line with China’s supremo Xi Jinping's slogan of ‘Common Prosperity’, where the estate market is being regulated so as to puncture the property bubble and make housing more affordable. Some also see this as an example of the government taking on influential private businessmen under the guise of the ‘common prosperity’ programme to fight income inequality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This rule is about-turn, the government previously encouraged developers to take on huge debt through the heavily state-controlled financial sector to develop new properties. In the past, they have even bailed out troubled business entities thereby leading to the indiscriminate allocation of resources to the sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per an analyst, “&lt;em&gt;A regime shift is occurring without necessarily the markets fully comprehending the enormous underlying change to the structure of the economy.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many have called the Evergrande fiasco China’s own ‘Lehman moment', alluding to the failure of the US bank Lehman Brothers, which precipitated the 2008 financial crisis. Some observers believe that the current crisis was a long time coming owing to the company's unsustainable business model.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2012, Andrew Left of Citron Research argued that Evergrande was insolvent and that the company was engaged in aggressive accounting practices to cover up its troubles.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was said that the company held properties that it could not sell on its balance sheet as inventory, thus avoiding the booking of losses. The company was also accused of running a Ponzi scheme as it relied on the constant inflow of funds to prop up a business model that is fundamentally unsustainable. Interestingly, Evergrande has over the years consistently reported strong profits and has showcased a strong balance sheet with sufficient liquid assets.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A letter leaked last year by &lt;em&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/em&gt; showed Evergrande’s executives seeking financial assistance from the Chinese government by admitting their inability to meet their debt obligations to banks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per a &lt;em&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/em&gt; report, the administration is potentially going ahead with the restructuring of debt. The company has sold off various units at a discounted price to meet funding requirements. The organisation's deal with state-owned Yuexiu Property to sell a 51% stake in its property services unit has also been put on hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markets are closely observing the Chinese economic environment owing to growing uncertainties. Various countries are concerned about a possible slowdown resulting from the rebalancing of the economy away from the property sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China is the biggest steel importer and a drop in construction activities would affect the global steel prices. The IMF has estimated that a fall of 1% in demand from China would decrease global GDP by 25%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chinese administration has sent a clear signal: the only expectation one should have is unpredictability and nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The year 2020 was the worst year for economic growth since World War II - all economies came to a standstill with the raging spread of the virus. However, China, the country where the first outbreak of COVID-19 was reported, was the only major economy in the world to report a positive GDP growth in that year. Fast forward to November 2021, the second-largest economy seems to be in a precarious situation with various credit rating firms cutting down on its growth forecasts owing to glaring uncertainties in the nation.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; In my last article, I covered China's crackdown on its tech sector. Now the ball has come rolling to its real estate sector.&amp;nbsp; Evergrande Group, China's second-largest property developer and the world’s most indebted real estate firm with liabilities amounting to $300 billion, informed bondholders in early September about its inability to honour its interest obligation. (For context, Russia's state debt in 2020 was $257 billion.) Evergrande was founded by Mr Xu Jiayin, who was once the country’s richest man, in 1996, and was in the bottled water business. Later the company expanded into several areas, including pig farming, owning a football club, wealth management and the electric car segment. However, it was its real estate business for which it was widely known. In 2020, it recorded a gross profit of nearly $19 billion and in the year before that, it was on the Fortune Global 500 list. The company owns 2% of all newly-constructed real estate in China and employs about 200,000 people directly and helps in sustaining more than 3.8 million jobs indirectly every year. The possible collapse of an organisation this big can be brushed aside as a one-time occurrence, however, one cannot turn a blind eye when many such firms in that line of business are on the same path: Chinese luxury developer Fantasia Holding Group and the Sinic Holdings group have also announced a default on their debt repayment obligations in mid-October. The cause of worry intensifies when one observes that around 30% of China’s Gross Domestic Product (GDP) is related to its real estate sector. Therefore, the fall of real estate companies can leave a dent not only in the Chinese economy but the global economy as well.&amp;nbsp; The State Of Real Estate In China&amp;nbsp; In the late 1980's, China started moving from public housing to the commercial property model. Post-1994, The central government decentralised the goals and interests of the policymakers - passing the responsibility of social welfare services to local administration but with taxes to be submitted back to them.&amp;nbsp; The imbalance of funds led provincial governments to create state-owned shell companies called Local Government Financing Vehicles (LGFV). They gave these LGFV free valuable lands which were then used to take out loans that the administration themselves could not. Consequently, this made the administration seem healthier because their debt was now hidden while at the same time they met quotas set by Beijing.&amp;nbsp; As a result, land became the backbone of local economies.&amp;nbsp; Additionally, steep discounts and low-interest rates were offered to citizens as an act of welfare. Strict regulation by the government on how much money leaves the country left citizens with limited investment options - stock markets became synonymous with volatility and risk and housing gained the reputation of safe and profitable investments in the country. Housing prices were also such that they fell only once in the two decades that followed the Asian Financial Crisis.&amp;nbsp; Due to the aforementioned reasons, real estate is one of the most loved sectors of the economy with homeownership in China being the highest in the world, i.e. around 90%. It has become the country's leading pillar of economic growth with a contribution of around 15-30% to the GDP. In the COVID-19 period alone, the sector has grown by 4.9%.&amp;nbsp; However, an unusual trend is seen in the country. The boom in real estate is coming at a cost: high vacancy rates in cities due to the vast majority of home purchases being second/third homes. In 2018, 87% of new home buyers already owned at least one flat.&amp;nbsp; Additionally, the societal norm in China is such that male marriages demand homeownership. Decades of the one-child policy have resulted in an imbalance between males and females with scales tipping in favour of the latter. As a result, female families have become awfully picky, with the groom's homeownership being one of the prerequisites. As per a study, home prices are higher in cities of disproportionate male-to-female ratios.&amp;nbsp; In cities like Shenzhen, Beijing, Shanghai - it takes nearly 40 years worth of an accumulated average income to afford a home. Thus the vast majority of homes are purchased even before the construction has begun, sometimes years in advance.&amp;nbsp; With overhead demand, some developers undertake techniques such as selling batches of properties in glitzy online events or through raffles-off in lotteries where thousands of apartments are often sold out in minutes, giving the winners mere hours to submit down payments or lose the opportunity.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; What all these instances, numbers and facts point towards is that of a speculative market, i.e. the assumption that prices would only go up.&amp;nbsp; However the demographic of the country suggests otherwise. In the next ten years, the country’s over-55 cohort will increase in size by 120 million, but by the end of the century, the overall population will be cut in half. The majority of present home buyers are precisely from this segment which China would soon lose. In addition, with age, home requirements keep differing.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; It was reasonable to anticipate a decade ago that the rapid urbanisation demand would be met by bringing in more than enough migrants to effectively cancel out the effects of ageing. Nonetheless, the statistics prove otherwise with the migration rate falling below the country’s 60% urbanisation rate. Moreover, such exorbitant home prices act as a further deterrent to the very people that were to be attracted by the construction of so many homes.&amp;nbsp; Thus, the demand-supply misproportion is haunting the real estate space.&amp;nbsp; Coming Back With the context of speculative and overpriced real estate being understood, what consequences are in store, given the defaults of Evergrande and other real estate firms?&amp;nbsp; The trigger for this fall is attributed to new guidelines, known as The Red Lines, introduced by the government in August 2020 for property developers. The rule requires the ratio of liabilities-to-assets of developers and their net debt-to-equity ratio to be below 70% and 100% respectively whilst requiring real estate firms to maintain the cash-to-short term debt ratio at a minimum of 100%.&amp;nbsp; Any borrower failing to meet these requirements would be restricted from raising more funds, practically cutting off developers from taking on more debts. This means a complete alteration in the nature of the real estate business, which relies heavily on borrowing for its capital requirements.&amp;nbsp; The crackdown on developers is in line with China’s supremo Xi Jinping's slogan of ‘Common Prosperity’, where the estate market is being regulated so as to puncture the property bubble and make housing more affordable. Some also see this as an example of the government taking on influential private businessmen under the guise of the ‘common prosperity’ programme to fight income inequality. This rule is about-turn, the government previously encouraged developers to take on huge debt through the heavily state-controlled financial sector to develop new properties. In the past, they have even bailed out troubled business entities thereby leading to the indiscriminate allocation of resources to the sector.&amp;nbsp; As per an analyst, “A regime shift is occurring without necessarily the markets fully comprehending the enormous underlying change to the structure of the economy.” Many have called the Evergrande fiasco China’s own ‘Lehman moment', alluding to the failure of the US bank Lehman Brothers, which precipitated the 2008 financial crisis. Some observers believe that the current crisis was a long time coming owing to the company's unsustainable business model.&amp;nbsp; In 2012, Andrew Left of Citron Research argued that Evergrande was insolvent and that the company was engaged in aggressive accounting practices to cover up its troubles.&amp;nbsp; It was said that the company held properties that it could not sell on its balance sheet as inventory, thus avoiding the booking of losses. The company was also accused of running a Ponzi scheme as it relied on the constant inflow of funds to prop up a business model that is fundamentally unsustainable. Interestingly, Evergrande has over the years consistently reported strong profits and has showcased a strong balance sheet with sufficient liquid assets.&amp;nbsp; A letter leaked last year by Bloomberg showed Evergrande’s executives seeking financial assistance from the Chinese government by admitting their inability to meet their debt obligations to banks.&amp;nbsp; As per a Bloomberg report, the administration is potentially going ahead with the restructuring of debt. The company has sold off various units at a discounted price to meet funding requirements. The organisation's deal with state-owned Yuexiu Property to sell a 51% stake in its property services unit has also been put on hold. Markets are closely observing the Chinese economic environment owing to growing uncertainties. Various countries are concerned about a possible slowdown resulting from the rebalancing of the economy away from the property sector.&amp;nbsp; China is the biggest steel importer and a drop in construction activities would affect the global steel prices. The IMF has estimated that a fall of 1% in demand from China would decrease global GDP by 25%. The Chinese administration has sent a clear signal: the only expectation one should have is unpredictability and nothing more.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The PMC Bank Fiasco</title>
      <link href="/The-PMC-Bank-Fiasco" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The PMC Bank Fiasco" />
      <published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-PMC-Bank-Fiasco</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-PMC-Bank-Fiasco">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With great power come greater scams. &lt;/em&gt;This is evidently a mantra for India. Politicians getting named in large scams and then using their power to sway the decisions of government bodies has become a typical sight in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Punjab and Maharashtra Co-operative (PMC) bank fiasco is not the first time a major scam has been unearthed which has left a financial institution and its depositors in complete shambles. Call it misgovernance or blindsight of the management - borrowing from one bank to repay another bank has become a common&amp;nbsp;practice&amp;nbsp;in India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fraud to the tune of ₹6,500 billion was found in the books of the PMC bank, all of which were loans extended to only a single borrower: Housing Development and Infrastructure Limited (HDIL). This amount was way beyond the statutory limit set by the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) for lending to a single entity. Yet the senior management kept quiet on the matter until they were thrown under the bus by the managing director in his confession letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relations between the Wadhawan group and the PMC bank have prevailed since the 1980's, wherein the former had saved the latter from the brink of a financial collapse quite a few times by infusing capital and keeping a majority of their deposits with the establishment. Thus, aiding the PMC bank to maintain the liquidity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But every&amp;nbsp;good story&amp;nbsp;has an end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As HDIL’s business started to grow, and their capital requirements grew multifold, the group started to transact with larger banks in order to meet their needs. This hindered the profitability of the cooperative bank as the majority of the institution’s revenue was attributed to transactions in the Wadhawan group’s accounts. Hence, upon request the group started banking with PMC again after a short span of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018-19, the bank had reported a profit of ₹996.9 million in its annual report. The bank showed 3.76% of advances (₹8,3830 million) as gross non-performing assets (NPAs), which was fair as compared to public sector banks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, things started to go awry when a few projects undertaken by HDIL were shelved, and this resulted in a liquidity crunch. Consequently, the bank started defaulting on all the loans it had taken from other banks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, due to the past repayment record of the group, the bank continued to treat the loan as a standard loan. But when the loan amount snowballed to more than 73% of the bank’s total exposure, the issue came into the limelight and a strict moratorium was put upon the bank by the RBI. Hence, it's clear that the bank gave false monetary reports to cover its dangerous loan mess and the alleged collusion with HDIL and other firms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To prevent panic and loss of public confidence, all the depositors were barred from withdrawing more than ₹1,000, but later the withdrawal limit was capped at ₹100,000 per depositor until further notice. In addition to the complaint that was filed with the authorities, the board of directors were suspended and the Wadhawan family members were arrested. The Enforcement Directorate, India's economic offences investigator, even seized movable and immovable assets of approximately&amp;nbsp; ₹40 billion in connection with the case.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole case was nothing but another instance of corporate misgovernance and partial treatment to a particular lender by the senior management of banks, just like in the case of the Punjab National Bank scam.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fiasco could have been prevented had the institution increased its collateral against the loans disbursed and classified the Wadhawan group’s account as a NPA at the right time. The central bank should have learned its lesson post the PNB scam, and could have increased its due diligence on public sector banks by placing stricter checks and reporting standards on these financial institutions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In July 2021, the RBI approved the bid of Centrum Financial Services (CFS) and BharatPe to jointly take over the crisis driven cooperative bank, thereby providing some respite to its depositors. The president of BharatPe group said, “One thing was clear in our discussion with RBI that the interest of depositors is supreme”, further emphasising on the management's future intent.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RBI was initially reluctant in giving an in-principle nod to the two institutions to set up a small finance bank (SFB), however, it has finally given the licence and has even gone on to provide a lot of other statutory reliefs to the new entity to be jointly formed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are different points of view on the RBI's decision to pick Centrum-BharatPe for the takeover of one of the largest cooperative banks in India. A section of the bank’s depositors are unhappy with the decision, as they preferred an established commercial bank to take over the entity rather than a new licensee with no direct experience of running a regular bank.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CFS and BharatPe are set to infuse ₹5 billion each into the new entity when starting over and will increase the capital up to ₹30 billion in due course. Additionally, they also have the option to restructure the liability and convert them into capital instruments, take support from the Depositor Insurance and Credit Guarantee Corporation (DICGC) for repayment of insured deposits up to ₹50,000, phase withdrawal plans for individuals with higher deposits or convert the same into tier 1 or tier 2 capital.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The joint venture is likely to form a good synergy between BharatPe and Centrum Financial Services. While the former is an establishment specialising in fintech with a strong footprint in the digital lending and Unified Payment Interface (UPI) industry, the latter is a non-banking lender with strong holdings and a good history in providing credit to small-mid size firms. Together they can bring innovation and renewed vigour to a fallen institution.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new entity is to be operational in 120 days post the principal nod given by the central banking authority, and only post this, will the RBI draft a scheme on amalgamation of the two entities with PMC Bank. The plan will then be sent to the government for approval and official notification. Under Section 45 of the Banking Regulation Act, only a bank can be merged with another, therefore, the process of handover will start only once the SFB (Small Finance Bank) is created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from that, the subsidiaries of Centrum namely Centrum Housing Finance and Centrum Microcredit are in the same business as the small finance bank to be set up by them. Hence, this poses a hurdle for Centrum, as one cannot have separate entities doing the same business. Either it will have to sell its majority stake or merge the subsidiaries; or not enter the microcredit and home loan business from the SFB set up, which would mean giving up a major business opportunity for the new joint venture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RBI has now called for sweeping changes in the Banking Regulation Act, and will be actively looking into the regulation of cooperative banks to avoid such a future debacle. But the problem doesn't stop there, the problem only begins here. India massively lacks transparency in the financial sector and this often puts a lot of wrongdoings away from the eyes of the public and regulatory bodies. There are more important questions that this mess raises. The first being, will the public institutions continue to show vigilance only after the chaos unfolds or will they ever learn to step in the moment the lines are crossed?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samyak Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">With great power come greater scams. This is evidently a mantra for India. Politicians getting named in large scams and then using their power to sway the decisions of government bodies has become a typical sight in the country. The Punjab and Maharashtra Co-operative (PMC) bank fiasco is not the first time a major scam has been unearthed which has left a financial institution and its depositors in complete shambles. Call it misgovernance or blindsight of the management - borrowing from one bank to repay another bank has become a common&amp;nbsp;practice&amp;nbsp;in India. A fraud to the tune of ₹6,500 billion was found in the books of the PMC bank, all of which were loans extended to only a single borrower: Housing Development and Infrastructure Limited (HDIL). This amount was way beyond the statutory limit set by the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) for lending to a single entity. Yet the senior management kept quiet on the matter until they were thrown under the bus by the managing director in his confession letter. Relations between the Wadhawan group and the PMC bank have prevailed since the 1980's, wherein the former had saved the latter from the brink of a financial collapse quite a few times by infusing capital and keeping a majority of their deposits with the establishment. Thus, aiding the PMC bank to maintain the liquidity.&amp;nbsp; But every&amp;nbsp;good story&amp;nbsp;has an end. As HDIL’s business started to grow, and their capital requirements grew multifold, the group started to transact with larger banks in order to meet their needs. This hindered the profitability of the cooperative bank as the majority of the institution’s revenue was attributed to transactions in the Wadhawan group’s accounts. Hence, upon request the group started banking with PMC again after a short span of time. In 2018-19, the bank had reported a profit of ₹996.9 million in its annual report. The bank showed 3.76% of advances (₹8,3830 million) as gross non-performing assets (NPAs), which was fair as compared to public sector banks. However, things started to go awry when a few projects undertaken by HDIL were shelved, and this resulted in a liquidity crunch. Consequently, the bank started defaulting on all the loans it had taken from other banks.&amp;nbsp; Initially, due to the past repayment record of the group, the bank continued to treat the loan as a standard loan. But when the loan amount snowballed to more than 73% of the bank’s total exposure, the issue came into the limelight and a strict moratorium was put upon the bank by the RBI. Hence, it's clear that the bank gave false monetary reports to cover its dangerous loan mess and the alleged collusion with HDIL and other firms. To prevent panic and loss of public confidence, all the depositors were barred from withdrawing more than ₹1,000, but later the withdrawal limit was capped at ₹100,000 per depositor until further notice. In addition to the complaint that was filed with the authorities, the board of directors were suspended and the Wadhawan family members were arrested. The Enforcement Directorate, India's economic offences investigator, even seized movable and immovable assets of approximately&amp;nbsp; ₹40 billion in connection with the case.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; This whole case was nothing but another instance of corporate misgovernance and partial treatment to a particular lender by the senior management of banks, just like in the case of the Punjab National Bank scam.&amp;nbsp; This fiasco could have been prevented had the institution increased its collateral against the loans disbursed and classified the Wadhawan group’s account as a NPA at the right time. The central bank should have learned its lesson post the PNB scam, and could have increased its due diligence on public sector banks by placing stricter checks and reporting standards on these financial institutions.&amp;nbsp; In July 2021, the RBI approved the bid of Centrum Financial Services (CFS) and BharatPe to jointly take over the crisis driven cooperative bank, thereby providing some respite to its depositors. The president of BharatPe group said, “One thing was clear in our discussion with RBI that the interest of depositors is supreme”, further emphasising on the management's future intent.&amp;nbsp; The RBI was initially reluctant in giving an in-principle nod to the two institutions to set up a small finance bank (SFB), however, it has finally given the licence and has even gone on to provide a lot of other statutory reliefs to the new entity to be jointly formed.&amp;nbsp; There are different points of view on the RBI's decision to pick Centrum-BharatPe for the takeover of one of the largest cooperative banks in India. A section of the bank’s depositors are unhappy with the decision, as they preferred an established commercial bank to take over the entity rather than a new licensee with no direct experience of running a regular bank.&amp;nbsp; CFS and BharatPe are set to infuse ₹5 billion each into the new entity when starting over and will increase the capital up to ₹30 billion in due course. Additionally, they also have the option to restructure the liability and convert them into capital instruments, take support from the Depositor Insurance and Credit Guarantee Corporation (DICGC) for repayment of insured deposits up to ₹50,000, phase withdrawal plans for individuals with higher deposits or convert the same into tier 1 or tier 2 capital.&amp;nbsp; The joint venture is likely to form a good synergy between BharatPe and Centrum Financial Services. While the former is an establishment specialising in fintech with a strong footprint in the digital lending and Unified Payment Interface (UPI) industry, the latter is a non-banking lender with strong holdings and a good history in providing credit to small-mid size firms. Together they can bring innovation and renewed vigour to a fallen institution.&amp;nbsp; The new entity is to be operational in 120 days post the principal nod given by the central banking authority, and only post this, will the RBI draft a scheme on amalgamation of the two entities with PMC Bank. The plan will then be sent to the government for approval and official notification. Under Section 45 of the Banking Regulation Act, only a bank can be merged with another, therefore, the process of handover will start only once the SFB (Small Finance Bank) is created. Apart from that, the subsidiaries of Centrum namely Centrum Housing Finance and Centrum Microcredit are in the same business as the small finance bank to be set up by them. Hence, this poses a hurdle for Centrum, as one cannot have separate entities doing the same business. Either it will have to sell its majority stake or merge the subsidiaries; or not enter the microcredit and home loan business from the SFB set up, which would mean giving up a major business opportunity for the new joint venture. The RBI has now called for sweeping changes in the Banking Regulation Act, and will be actively looking into the regulation of cooperative banks to avoid such a future debacle. But the problem doesn't stop there, the problem only begins here. India massively lacks transparency in the financial sector and this often puts a lot of wrongdoings away from the eyes of the public and regulatory bodies. There are more important questions that this mess raises. The first being, will the public institutions continue to show vigilance only after the chaos unfolds or will they ever learn to step in the moment the lines are crossed?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Pace of EV Adoption in India</title>
      <link href="/Pace-of-EV-Adoption-in-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pace of EV Adoption in India" />
      <published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Pace-of-EV-Adoption-in-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Pace-of-EV-Adoption-in-India">&lt;p&gt;Over the past ten years, the automobile sector has been gravitating towards electrification. Electrification is essentially the replacement of conventionally used Internal Combustion Engine (ICE) vehicles with more powerful, simpler, smarter and greener Electric Vehicles (EV).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EVs came into being before its ICE counterparts but due to lack of infrastructure, high upfront costs and absence of incentives, they could not gain the deserved spotlight. So, are we to believe that the right time has come to think about the electrification of our cars?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand the situation better, let us look at why it is imperative for India to adopt electric mobility. The Indian automobile market has earned the distinction of being a unique market; the Indian auto and ancillary market is among the largest in the world and constitutes 9% of the country’s GDP. 84% of vehicles sold domestically are either two or three Wheelers (2W/3Ws) and therefore, it is imperative for the nation to adapt to electrification now.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EV adoption in India is more than just a technological upgradation in the automotive sector. There are varying reasons which make it essential for the fifth largest economy to pace up the process of electrification.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extensive and often reckless use of ICE vehicles paired with exorbitant industrial pollution has worsened the nation’s Air Quality Index (AQI), making it the third most polluted country in the world. Moreover, considering the macroeconomic factors, India imports $100 billion worth of crude oil to quench its industrial and retail demand (which is mostly generated by operational ICE vehicles).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that the intent is clear, let’s see how long is the road ahead of our goal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electric mobility targets can only be achieved with joint efforts of all the players in the EV ecosystem. Government incentives, appropriate charging infrastructures, battery costs and manufacturing coupled with Original Equipment Manufacturers (OEMs) transitioning from ICE to EV can help in&amp;nbsp; ramping up the process of electrification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last decade, Indian policymakers have been extensively promoting adoption of electric vehicles, mostly under the umbrella of the National Mission for Electric Mobility (The EV Mission) led by the Department of Heavy Industries (DHI).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction of schemes like FAME II (Faster Adoption and Manufacturing of Hybrid &amp;amp; Electric Vehicles) and Production Linked Incentive (PLI) coupled with GST incentives are pushed to achieve adoption targets, localisation of key components with an aim to foster electric adoption in both private and public transportation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FAME II aims to provide direct financial benefits to EV manufacturers which would benefit in reducing the cost of acquisition for end-customers. As a mechanism, OEMs first pass on the subsidy support to the end-customer by way of decreased purchase price, and later claim the amount from the DHI.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a mismatch between the market demand and the policy’s vision, as since inception, FAME II has only been able to achieve less than 10% of its target of supporting one million electric two-wheelers, half a million of 3Ws, 55,000 four-wheelers and 7,000 buses by 2022. To tackle the same, new amendments were introduced in June 2021 to reduce the overall vehicle cost and revamp the EV adoption scenario in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per the new amendments, the subsidy offered has been revised from ₹10,000 to ₹15,000 per kWh per electric 2W vehicle, thereby increasing the demand incentive by 50%. Maximum cap on subsidies offered has also increased from 20% to 40% of the cost of E-2W, which drastically bridged the Total Cost of Ownership (TCO) gap between conventional ICE and electric two wheelers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electric charging infrastructure in the country is at a very nascent stage and the charging grid is more like a mandate to support the operational leg of the electrification process. Therefore, it is important for India to have the required charging infrastructure to accelerate the process.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India needs about 400 thousand charging stations to meet the requirement for two million&amp;nbsp;electric vehicles&amp;nbsp;that could potentially move on its roads by 2026. Currently, it has about 18 hundred charging stations, most of which are slow chargers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest players in this segment is Tata Power which owns a network of over 500 public chargers in 100+ cities across India, and has recently tied up with HPCL to further expand its network.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To support the forecasted electricity demand that EV adoption is expected to bring with itself, it is a must for the nation to develop grids which are capable of handling the multitudinous increase in load. India relying on its coal dependent grid is said to be one of the most inefficient ones in the world, thus giving a reason for the nation to shift the composition of the grid towards renewables to truly address the pollution problem.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one of his announcements, the Union Power and New and Renewable Energy Minister Raj Kumar Singh disclosed the country’s plans to set up around 14 gigawatt-hour (GWh) grid-scale battery storage system at the world’s largest renewable energy park at Khavda in Gujarat. This is in addition to the plan to invite bids for the largest global tender for setting up a 13GWh grid-scale battery storage system in Ladakh. This strategic push is to make India’s grid-scale battery storage programme the largest in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is encouraging to see the government's action in this regard but there still lays a long road ahead for the nation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another gap which needs to be bridged to achieve EV adoption is the TCO (Total Cost Ownership) disparity between ICE and EVs. TCO is the sum of upfront and operational costs which a customer has to incur through the life of the vehicle. With batteries constituting 35% of the vehicle cost, it is one of the major drivers of EV’s upfront costs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With inefficient indigenous cell technology and limited access to battery raw materials like Lithium and Cobalt, India is yet to become a leading player in the EV battery industry. Local players like Exicom Power, Amar Raja Batteries, Tata Power have plans to turn this around.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electric 2W are smaller vehicles and are easier to electrify, hence they require smaller and simpler batteries and are much closer to economic parity. Li-ion battery based e-rickshaws form a major portion of electric 3W base in the country and have in fact achieved TCO parity and are benefitting from the lower charging costs and time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there still exists a wide gap between TCO parity of electric 4W and buses with their ICE counterparts, mostly due to large battery sizes requirements and lack of complementary infrastructure.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tesla in its recent pitch to the government was successful in lowering import duties on EVs which would eventually make electric vehicles more affordable for the Indian masses. However, the administration is in favor of high import duties as it wishes to encourage domestic production. Therefore, it's too early to show such excitement as only time can vouch for its implementation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the 2W segment being the frontrunner followed by 3W in the ICE-EV shift in India and 4W premium and commercial vehicles yet to achieve the value for money proposition, a lot more has to be done by the government on many fronts such as OEMs transitioning to electric mobility, customers considering EVs over ICE vehicles and other players in the EV segment actively working to achieve India’s goal of becoming a 100% electric vehicle nation by 2030.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Agrawal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Over the past ten years, the automobile sector has been gravitating towards electrification. Electrification is essentially the replacement of conventionally used Internal Combustion Engine (ICE) vehicles with more powerful, simpler, smarter and greener Electric Vehicles (EV).&amp;nbsp; EVs came into being before its ICE counterparts but due to lack of infrastructure, high upfront costs and absence of incentives, they could not gain the deserved spotlight. So, are we to believe that the right time has come to think about the electrification of our cars?&amp;nbsp; To understand the situation better, let us look at why it is imperative for India to adopt electric mobility. The Indian automobile market has earned the distinction of being a unique market; the Indian auto and ancillary market is among the largest in the world and constitutes 9% of the country’s GDP. 84% of vehicles sold domestically are either two or three Wheelers (2W/3Ws) and therefore, it is imperative for the nation to adapt to electrification now.&amp;nbsp; EV adoption in India is more than just a technological upgradation in the automotive sector. There are varying reasons which make it essential for the fifth largest economy to pace up the process of electrification.&amp;nbsp; Extensive and often reckless use of ICE vehicles paired with exorbitant industrial pollution has worsened the nation’s Air Quality Index (AQI), making it the third most polluted country in the world. Moreover, considering the macroeconomic factors, India imports $100 billion worth of crude oil to quench its industrial and retail demand (which is mostly generated by operational ICE vehicles).&amp;nbsp; Now that the intent is clear, let’s see how long is the road ahead of our goal.&amp;nbsp; Electric mobility targets can only be achieved with joint efforts of all the players in the EV ecosystem. Government incentives, appropriate charging infrastructures, battery costs and manufacturing coupled with Original Equipment Manufacturers (OEMs) transitioning from ICE to EV can help in&amp;nbsp; ramping up the process of electrification. Over the last decade, Indian policymakers have been extensively promoting adoption of electric vehicles, mostly under the umbrella of the National Mission for Electric Mobility (The EV Mission) led by the Department of Heavy Industries (DHI).&amp;nbsp; Introduction of schemes like FAME II (Faster Adoption and Manufacturing of Hybrid &amp;amp; Electric Vehicles) and Production Linked Incentive (PLI) coupled with GST incentives are pushed to achieve adoption targets, localisation of key components with an aim to foster electric adoption in both private and public transportation.&amp;nbsp; FAME II aims to provide direct financial benefits to EV manufacturers which would benefit in reducing the cost of acquisition for end-customers. As a mechanism, OEMs first pass on the subsidy support to the end-customer by way of decreased purchase price, and later claim the amount from the DHI.&amp;nbsp; There was a mismatch between the market demand and the policy’s vision, as since inception, FAME II has only been able to achieve less than 10% of its target of supporting one million electric two-wheelers, half a million of 3Ws, 55,000 four-wheelers and 7,000 buses by 2022. To tackle the same, new amendments were introduced in June 2021 to reduce the overall vehicle cost and revamp the EV adoption scenario in the country. As per the new amendments, the subsidy offered has been revised from ₹10,000 to ₹15,000 per kWh per electric 2W vehicle, thereby increasing the demand incentive by 50%. Maximum cap on subsidies offered has also increased from 20% to 40% of the cost of E-2W, which drastically bridged the Total Cost of Ownership (TCO) gap between conventional ICE and electric two wheelers.&amp;nbsp; Electric charging infrastructure in the country is at a very nascent stage and the charging grid is more like a mandate to support the operational leg of the electrification process. Therefore, it is important for India to have the required charging infrastructure to accelerate the process.&amp;nbsp; India needs about 400 thousand charging stations to meet the requirement for two million&amp;nbsp;electric vehicles&amp;nbsp;that could potentially move on its roads by 2026. Currently, it has about 18 hundred charging stations, most of which are slow chargers.&amp;nbsp; One of the biggest players in this segment is Tata Power which owns a network of over 500 public chargers in 100+ cities across India, and has recently tied up with HPCL to further expand its network.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; To support the forecasted electricity demand that EV adoption is expected to bring with itself, it is a must for the nation to develop grids which are capable of handling the multitudinous increase in load. India relying on its coal dependent grid is said to be one of the most inefficient ones in the world, thus giving a reason for the nation to shift the composition of the grid towards renewables to truly address the pollution problem.&amp;nbsp; In one of his announcements, the Union Power and New and Renewable Energy Minister Raj Kumar Singh disclosed the country’s plans to set up around 14 gigawatt-hour (GWh) grid-scale battery storage system at the world’s largest renewable energy park at Khavda in Gujarat. This is in addition to the plan to invite bids for the largest global tender for setting up a 13GWh grid-scale battery storage system in Ladakh. This strategic push is to make India’s grid-scale battery storage programme the largest in the world. It is encouraging to see the government's action in this regard but there still lays a long road ahead for the nation.&amp;nbsp; Another gap which needs to be bridged to achieve EV adoption is the TCO (Total Cost Ownership) disparity between ICE and EVs. TCO is the sum of upfront and operational costs which a customer has to incur through the life of the vehicle. With batteries constituting 35% of the vehicle cost, it is one of the major drivers of EV’s upfront costs.&amp;nbsp; With inefficient indigenous cell technology and limited access to battery raw materials like Lithium and Cobalt, India is yet to become a leading player in the EV battery industry. Local players like Exicom Power, Amar Raja Batteries, Tata Power have plans to turn this around.&amp;nbsp; Electric 2W are smaller vehicles and are easier to electrify, hence they require smaller and simpler batteries and are much closer to economic parity. Li-ion battery based e-rickshaws form a major portion of electric 3W base in the country and have in fact achieved TCO parity and are benefitting from the lower charging costs and time.&amp;nbsp; However, there still exists a wide gap between TCO parity of electric 4W and buses with their ICE counterparts, mostly due to large battery sizes requirements and lack of complementary infrastructure.&amp;nbsp; Tesla in its recent pitch to the government was successful in lowering import duties on EVs which would eventually make electric vehicles more affordable for the Indian masses. However, the administration is in favor of high import duties as it wishes to encourage domestic production. Therefore, it's too early to show such excitement as only time can vouch for its implementation.&amp;nbsp; With the 2W segment being the frontrunner followed by 3W in the ICE-EV shift in India and 4W premium and commercial vehicles yet to achieve the value for money proposition, a lot more has to be done by the government on many fronts such as OEMs transitioning to electric mobility, customers considering EVs over ICE vehicles and other players in the EV segment actively working to achieve India’s goal of becoming a 100% electric vehicle nation by 2030.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Is Ambani or Tata the Ratan the Answer We’ve Been Looking For?</title>
      <link href="/Is-Ambani-or-Tata-the-Ratan-the-Answer-We-ve-Been-Looking-For" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Ambani or Tata the Ratan the Answer We've Been Looking For?" />
      <published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Is-Ambani-or-Tata-the-Ratan-the-Answer-We-ve-Been-Looking-For</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Is-Ambani-or-Tata-the-Ratan-the-Answer-We-ve-Been-Looking-For">&lt;p&gt;The dynamics of the power and influence that the Ambanis and the Tatas hold in the Indian market has evolved considerably in the past few decades. While some may argue that the Reliance group has surpassed the Tata conglomerate, here’s a take on why that’s not even marginally correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preconceived notions, pertaining to money and wealth, are the main reason behind such false assumptions. Mukesh Ambani is indeed the richest man in India with a net worth of $91 billion, while Shri Ratan Tata’s worth is estimated at $1 billion. Based on these statistics alone, people jump to conclusions that the richer party, in this case the Ambanis, is superior to the other side, the Tatas. But is monetary wealth enough of a metric to label which group possesses the higher ground?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ambanis are known for their affluent nature and have never shied away from displaying their prosperity. From throwing weddings of the century, hosting private Beyoncé concerts to living in a 27-storey sky palace, ‘Antilia’, they’ve often caused social media uproar and made headlines.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In stark contrast, Tatas live a relatively humble life with 66% of their company stake held by charitable organisations such as the Sir Ratan Tata Trust, Sir Dorabji Tata Trust, Tata Education Trust to name a few. Their primary goal was, and has always been, the financial and social empowerment of the entire nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To delve further into the details of this ill-conceived and strikingly biased opinion, one must start to understand the elementary difference between a businessman and an industrialist. The former is more concerned with maximising their own profits while, the latter makes it their concern to consider the best interests of the society at large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Booming Businessman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dhirubhai Ambani and his rise to fortune is a true rags-to-riches story. His success in taking his company public in 1977, expanding from textiles to other sectors such as petrochemicals, which in-turn led to the formation of what we know today as ‘Reliance Industries’, was largely owed to his sharp business acumen, excellent entrepreneurial skills and great oratorship. He was what we refer to as a ‘one in a million’ case wherein a high school dropout, with no significant education, made it big!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the major reasons behind his success was the value and vitality he placed on the quality of service that was associated with the Ambani name. He prioritised his promise to the shareholders, declared regular dividends and held annual meetings to strengthen mutual trustworthiness.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After his death in 2002, the company was divided between his two sons, Mukesh and Anil. While the former inherited his father’s business instincts, the same seemed to have been lost in the case of the latter. Mukesh Ambani expanded the spectrum covered under Reliance Industries far beyond expectations, and one of his most remarkable achievements was the launch of Reliance Jio in 2016. Not only was Jio a real game changer, but it also sparked a price war in the super-competitive telecom market in India, and gave otherwise unparalleled companies like Airtel a run for its money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reliance was the first Indian company to be included in the Fortune 500 companies list. The consolidated efforts of two generations, branching from Vimal to Jio, resulted in an increase in annual revenue from ₹700 million at the time its IPO was first launched, to over ₹750 billion in the year 2002.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today RIL is an oil-to-telecom conglomerate with a valuation of about ₹6.10 trillion. It is the first company to have a market capitalisation of ₹9 trillion on the Bombay Stock Exchange (BSE). Out of this, about 48% stake is personally controlled by Mukesh Ambani, and while Reliance did purchase some gas companies in the US and occasionally in Europe, it largely remains an Indian entity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Business must serve a larger societal purpose.” – &lt;/em&gt;Mukesh Ambani&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above statement is quite ironic as the Ambanis, like most business families, donate only a small fraction of their wealth. To substantiate, in 2018, Ambani donated a seemingly grand amount of ₹4.02 billion, which in reality amounted only to 0.1% of his net worth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the world came to a standstill during the pandemic, Reliance Jio continued its successful operations based on the philosophy that the show must go on. Not only did it see a 15.5% growth in net profit to ₹34.89 billion in the fourth quarter of 2020-21, but also an additional increase of 5.2 million customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At such times of crisis, despite having enjoyed phenomenal growth and profits, Mukesh Ambani pledged to donate only ₹50 million to Maharashtra Chief Minister’s Relief Fund as monetary contributions whereas Mr. Ratan Tata, Tata Sons and Tata Trusts collectively pledged a total of ₹15 billion for combating the coronavirus pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The International Industrialist&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey of the trailblazers began in 1868, when Jamsetji Tata invested ₹21,000 in his own trading business. However, his sight was set on the textile business. Following his newfound objective, he returned from England equipped with knowledge and moved out of Mumbai to Nagpur which was comparatively economical.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What made Tatas the true tycoons was the care they extended to their workers and the importance they laid on the welfare of the society. These measures resonated among the masses with the same level of loyalty and appreciation reciprocated by them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jamsetji Tata had four major goals in life: an iron and steel company, a world class educational institution, a hydroelectric power plant and a five star hotel. However, in his lifetime he could only manage to accomplish the task of building the Taj hotel in Mumbai, which serves as a symbol of his glorious march into the future till date. The rest of his dreams were realised by his son Dorabji Tata.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This proud legacy was carried on by JRD Tata, under whom the Tata Group grew from $100 million to over $5 billion, establishing itself as a conglomerate of 95 companies including Tata Tea, Tata Motors &amp;amp; TCS.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, The Tata Group has products and services in 150 countries spread over 6 continents, with a ₹6.11 trillion valuation, $100 billion in revenues, i.e., over ₹11 trillion of market capitalisation and 29 publicly listed companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite such a remarkable feat it's quite intriguing as to why the Tatas are not the richest businessmen in India, though the Tata Group is India’s numero uno conglomerate.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Tatas have done much to introduce industrial capitalism in India in place of the old mercantile and petty capitalism. As the companies progressed, they socialised the business by transferring much of the ownership to charitable trusts.” &lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;- &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Professor Gras of Harvard Business School.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Staying true to this promise, Shri Ratan Tata’s personal stake in Tata industries is less than 1%.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike other business tycoons, he donates a big chunk of his wealth to several trusts, the largest being the Sir Dorabji Tata Trust (28%), followed by the Sir Ratan Tata Trust (23.5%).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Bigger of the Big Fish&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response to when asked why he was not the richest man in the world, Ratan Tata said, &lt;em&gt;“Ambanis are businessmen and the Tatas are industrialists.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This difference in outlook represents a bigger value difference between the two behemoths and their line of thinking. While both the groups create livelihood for millions and represent big parts of India, one chooses to add to the bottom of the pyramid in his own capacity, while one leaves the bigger machinery to its own devices.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is moot to discuss who is doing “more”, but if not for his philanthropic nature, Ratan Tata could easily be one of the richest people in the world, let alone India, making it clear without an iota of doubt that Mukesh Ambani may be the richest man in India but the Tata Conglomerate reigns supreme over Reliance Industries.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Raisa Azad</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The dynamics of the power and influence that the Ambanis and the Tatas hold in the Indian market has evolved considerably in the past few decades. While some may argue that the Reliance group has surpassed the Tata conglomerate, here’s a take on why that’s not even marginally correct. Preconceived notions, pertaining to money and wealth, are the main reason behind such false assumptions. Mukesh Ambani is indeed the richest man in India with a net worth of $91 billion, while Shri Ratan Tata’s worth is estimated at $1 billion. Based on these statistics alone, people jump to conclusions that the richer party, in this case the Ambanis, is superior to the other side, the Tatas. But is monetary wealth enough of a metric to label which group possesses the higher ground? The Ambanis are known for their affluent nature and have never shied away from displaying their prosperity. From throwing weddings of the century, hosting private Beyoncé concerts to living in a 27-storey sky palace, ‘Antilia’, they’ve often caused social media uproar and made headlines.&amp;nbsp; In stark contrast, Tatas live a relatively humble life with 66% of their company stake held by charitable organisations such as the Sir Ratan Tata Trust, Sir Dorabji Tata Trust, Tata Education Trust to name a few. Their primary goal was, and has always been, the financial and social empowerment of the entire nation. To delve further into the details of this ill-conceived and strikingly biased opinion, one must start to understand the elementary difference between a businessman and an industrialist. The former is more concerned with maximising their own profits while, the latter makes it their concern to consider the best interests of the society at large. The Booming Businessman Dhirubhai Ambani and his rise to fortune is a true rags-to-riches story. His success in taking his company public in 1977, expanding from textiles to other sectors such as petrochemicals, which in-turn led to the formation of what we know today as ‘Reliance Industries’, was largely owed to his sharp business acumen, excellent entrepreneurial skills and great oratorship. He was what we refer to as a ‘one in a million’ case wherein a high school dropout, with no significant education, made it big!&amp;nbsp; One of the major reasons behind his success was the value and vitality he placed on the quality of service that was associated with the Ambani name. He prioritised his promise to the shareholders, declared regular dividends and held annual meetings to strengthen mutual trustworthiness.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; After his death in 2002, the company was divided between his two sons, Mukesh and Anil. While the former inherited his father’s business instincts, the same seemed to have been lost in the case of the latter. Mukesh Ambani expanded the spectrum covered under Reliance Industries far beyond expectations, and one of his most remarkable achievements was the launch of Reliance Jio in 2016. Not only was Jio a real game changer, but it also sparked a price war in the super-competitive telecom market in India, and gave otherwise unparalleled companies like Airtel a run for its money. Reliance was the first Indian company to be included in the Fortune 500 companies list. The consolidated efforts of two generations, branching from Vimal to Jio, resulted in an increase in annual revenue from ₹700 million at the time its IPO was first launched, to over ₹750 billion in the year 2002.&amp;nbsp; Today RIL is an oil-to-telecom conglomerate with a valuation of about ₹6.10 trillion. It is the first company to have a market capitalisation of ₹9 trillion on the Bombay Stock Exchange (BSE). Out of this, about 48% stake is personally controlled by Mukesh Ambani, and while Reliance did purchase some gas companies in the US and occasionally in Europe, it largely remains an Indian entity. “Business must serve a larger societal purpose.” – Mukesh Ambani The above statement is quite ironic as the Ambanis, like most business families, donate only a small fraction of their wealth. To substantiate, in 2018, Ambani donated a seemingly grand amount of ₹4.02 billion, which in reality amounted only to 0.1% of his net worth.&amp;nbsp; While the world came to a standstill during the pandemic, Reliance Jio continued its successful operations based on the philosophy that the show must go on. Not only did it see a 15.5% growth in net profit to ₹34.89 billion in the fourth quarter of 2020-21, but also an additional increase of 5.2 million customers. At such times of crisis, despite having enjoyed phenomenal growth and profits, Mukesh Ambani pledged to donate only ₹50 million to Maharashtra Chief Minister’s Relief Fund as monetary contributions whereas Mr. Ratan Tata, Tata Sons and Tata Trusts collectively pledged a total of ₹15 billion for combating the coronavirus pandemic. The International Industrialist&amp;nbsp; The journey of the trailblazers began in 1868, when Jamsetji Tata invested ₹21,000 in his own trading business. However, his sight was set on the textile business. Following his newfound objective, he returned from England equipped with knowledge and moved out of Mumbai to Nagpur which was comparatively economical.&amp;nbsp; What made Tatas the true tycoons was the care they extended to their workers and the importance they laid on the welfare of the society. These measures resonated among the masses with the same level of loyalty and appreciation reciprocated by them. Jamsetji Tata had four major goals in life: an iron and steel company, a world class educational institution, a hydroelectric power plant and a five star hotel. However, in his lifetime he could only manage to accomplish the task of building the Taj hotel in Mumbai, which serves as a symbol of his glorious march into the future till date. The rest of his dreams were realised by his son Dorabji Tata.&amp;nbsp; This proud legacy was carried on by JRD Tata, under whom the Tata Group grew from $100 million to over $5 billion, establishing itself as a conglomerate of 95 companies including Tata Tea, Tata Motors &amp;amp; TCS.&amp;nbsp; Currently, The Tata Group has products and services in 150 countries spread over 6 continents, with a ₹6.11 trillion valuation, $100 billion in revenues, i.e., over ₹11 trillion of market capitalisation and 29 publicly listed companies. Despite such a remarkable feat it's quite intriguing as to why the Tatas are not the richest businessmen in India, though the Tata Group is India’s numero uno conglomerate.&amp;nbsp; “Tatas have done much to introduce industrial capitalism in India in place of the old mercantile and petty capitalism. As the companies progressed, they socialised the business by transferring much of the ownership to charitable trusts.” - Professor Gras of Harvard Business School. Staying true to this promise, Shri Ratan Tata’s personal stake in Tata industries is less than 1%.&amp;nbsp; Unlike other business tycoons, he donates a big chunk of his wealth to several trusts, the largest being the Sir Dorabji Tata Trust (28%), followed by the Sir Ratan Tata Trust (23.5%). The Bigger of the Big Fish In response to when asked why he was not the richest man in the world, Ratan Tata said, “Ambanis are businessmen and the Tatas are industrialists.” This difference in outlook represents a bigger value difference between the two behemoths and their line of thinking. While both the groups create livelihood for millions and represent big parts of India, one chooses to add to the bottom of the pyramid in his own capacity, while one leaves the bigger machinery to its own devices.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; It is moot to discuss who is doing “more”, but if not for his philanthropic nature, Ratan Tata could easily be one of the richest people in the world, let alone India, making it clear without an iota of doubt that Mukesh Ambani may be the richest man in India but the Tata Conglomerate reigns supreme over Reliance Industries.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Power Play: China’s Command &amp;amp; Control</title>
      <link href="/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Power Play: China's Command &amp; Control" />
      <published>2021-09-21T02:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-21T02:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control">&lt;p&gt;In November 2020, I authored an article on China’s move of&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Derailing-of-the-World-s-Biggest-IPO&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt; scuttling Ant Group Co.’s blockbuster $37 billion listing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Little did we know that it was just the beginning of an excessive clampdown on the country's technological sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To continue with the story of e-commerce giant Alibaba, the country’s authorities imposed a record fine - $2.8 billion in 2021, after an investigation that found it had abused its dominant market position for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China’s unprecedented crackdown on its tech industry has cost several companies and their investors hundreds of billions of dollars. Tencent alone has &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/markets/stocks/news/market-darling-tencent-turns-into-worlds-worst-stock-bet-with-170-billion-wipeout/articleshow/84853892.cms&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;had $170 billion shaved off its value&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; For context, that’s more than ten Byju’s, India’s biggest startup, which is valued at $16.5 billion.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The July Roundup by Goldman Sachs Group Inc shows that since November, the country’s regulators have taken more than 50 actual or reported actions on areas spanning antitrust, finance, data security and social equality, i.e. more than one move a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, China has assiduously built up its tech sector, and has borrowed an industrial and internet model from the West. Arguably it was a resounding success, then why is it now trying to strangle the golden goose it had once cradled?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.natlawreview.com/article/china-issues-data-security-law&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;adopted a new cybersecurity law in June&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which builds on the foundation of the 2017 Cyber Security Law, that started tightening the control of data flow. However, since the measure was vaguely worded, it remained unclear how it would be implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around the same time, the Chinese economy was rebounding from its bout with COVID-19, lifting the nation's&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/06/10/didi-chuxing-files-for-ipo-booked-6point4-billion-revenue-in-q1.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/06/10/didi-chuxing-files-for-ipo-booked-6point4-billion-revenue-in-q1.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;ride, hailing giant Didi Global&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s revenue with it as the US stock market continued to be in a bull run. Didi's long venture investors, including Softbank’s Vision Fund, urged seizing the moment to take the company public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company made its debut at $14 on the New York Stock Exchange on the last day of June 2021, raising $4.4 billion - the biggest stock sale by a Chinese company since the 2014 listing of Alibaba Group Holding Ltd.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its shares briefly topped $18 in the first days of trading, before China’s cyber security watchdog - Cyberspace Administration of China (CAC) stunned investors on July 2 by launching a data-security probe into Didi and blocking its China business from adding new users.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crackdown worsened on July 9, when 25 more Didi apps - including ones used by drivers - were ordered to be removed from app stores, potentially crippling the company’s operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this was not enough, the administration further extended its clampdown on other sectors in&amp;nbsp; July. On July 22, the government &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/tech/startups/china-strengthens-protection-for-food-delivery-workers-in-setback-for-meituan-alibaba/articleshow/84755202.cms&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;announced new worker protection rules&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, under which online food platforms must cover minimum wage and insurance benefits. This gutted the share price of delivery giants such as Meituan and its rival, Alibaba's Ele.me; which had drawn severe criticism on social media for their treatment of riders and guaranteed time-bound delivery which has compelled riders to undertake dangerous routes, risking their lives.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the following day, Beijing effectively torpedoed a multibillion-dollar industry - after-school tutoring - with a single administrative order. The new rules banned companies that teach the K-12 school curriculum from going public and registering themselves as non-profits. The shares of the three largest US-listed Chinese edtech firms - TAL Education, New Oriental and Gaotu Techedu, fell by 65-70% on the announcement, and the founders of the latter two companies went from billionaires to millionaires almost instantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The corporate intervention that has hammered internet stocks is now driving investors to sectors still in Beijing’s good graces, such as high-tech manufacturing and renewable energy. Indexes for new energy stocks, semiconductor makers and electric vehicle companies, outperformed the market from 4% to 18% since the beginning of July.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Broadly, Beijing is concerned about four pillars of stability: banking, antitrust regulation, data security and social equality. For example, social equality being at the heart of the ban of for-profit after-school tutors or rights concerning gig economy workers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some market participants believe China is trying to direct capital and human resources from internet companies into sectors that will help the country become more self-reliant. A portfolio manager at M&amp;amp;G Investments, Singapore, tracking the Chinese economy said, “&lt;em&gt;They are trying to reach a new equilibrium because it seems capital flows were not in line with long-term, top- down priorities.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts believe the government’s latest initiatives are motivated by a bigger ambition to realign the relationship between private business and the state, with a goal of ensuring companies do more to serve the Communist Party’s economic, social and national security concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it is worth noticing that Huawei, which should fall under the purview of the state on every possible reason in law, is entirely untouched.&amp;nbsp; As per some observers, the reason for the telecom giant being solidly backed by Beijing is due to the mutual benefit of both parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China’s vision for a domestic adversary as opposed to a Silicon Valley has benefited the private companies for years from lax regulatory oversight. However, leaders now worry that the tech giants have become too big and could be using personal and corporate digital records as leverage to build &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/china-blocked-jack-mas-ant-ipo-after-an-investigation-revealed-who-stood-to-gain-11613491292?mod=searchresults_pos10&amp;amp;page=1&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;alternative power centers&lt;/a&gt; in the one-party state.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, the government has often demanded data from private firms, and could sometimes enforce its wishes, especially for hunting down criminal suspects and silencing dissent but the tech companies have pushed back on requests to share and centralise their statistics.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, Beijing now wishes to undo these through their complex cyber security laws and regulations which would make it harder for companies to resist data sharing requests.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chinese regulators have formally made the data localisation requirement a prerequisite for foreign institutions trying to get a foothold in China, enabling the government to have more authority over the records. Western companies have long complained such “data localisation” requirements could stifle innovation in their global operations or enable Chinese authorities to steal their proprietary information.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US electric car maker &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/market-data/quotes/TSLA&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Tesla&lt;/a&gt; Inc has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/tesla-to-store-china-data-locally-in-new-data-center-11622015001?mod=article_inline&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pledged&lt;/a&gt; to build more data centers in China and to keep information generated by the vehicles it sells there, within Chinese borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Less invasive private-sector data collection anywhere is a good thing,” says analyst Ryan Fedasiuk at Georgetown University’s Center for Security and Emerging Technology. “But China’s push for data privacy strikes me as yet another move to strengthen the role of the government and the party vis-à-vis tech companies.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the EU rules, the Chinese version lacks restrictions on government entities when it comes to gathering information on people’s call logs, contact lists, location and other data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, these laws should also be seen against the backdrop of high tensions between US-China relations, which has sharpened President Xi’s focus on security and self-sufficiency. Beijing prohibits foreign ownership of larger sections of the Chinese economy, especially the profitable parts involving digital technology and data, and hence the companies follow a concept of&amp;nbsp; Variable-Interest-Entity or VIE, where the companies selling shares in foreign markets (including Hong Kong) can do so only quasi-legally at best. The workaround for VIE was the transparency that would come with foreign ownership and control which could reveal more about the state of the economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under a 2020 law signed by then-President, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/topics/person/donald-trump&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Donald Trump&lt;/a&gt;, Chinese companies would have to share their audit working papers with the US regulators. Failure to do so would lead to delisting of companies from US exchanges.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For China, that could risk allowing key data, such as detailed information about Chinese consumers and government agencies that may be included in the papers, to end up in the hands of a foreign government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both the second largest economy in the world and West see tech as a possible disrupter, however, it’s the Chinese who seem to be turbocharging a move towards the real tech, where they are ready to destroy the ‘pre-tender’ that exists today.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In November 2020, I authored an article on China’s move of scuttling Ant Group Co.’s blockbuster $37 billion listing. Little did we know that it was just the beginning of an excessive clampdown on the country's technological sector.&amp;nbsp; To continue with the story of e-commerce giant Alibaba, the country’s authorities imposed a record fine - $2.8 billion in 2021, after an investigation that found it had abused its dominant market position for years. China’s unprecedented crackdown on its tech industry has cost several companies and their investors hundreds of billions of dollars. Tencent alone has had $170 billion shaved off its value. For context, that’s more than ten Byju’s, India’s biggest startup, which is valued at $16.5 billion.&amp;nbsp; The July Roundup by Goldman Sachs Group Inc shows that since November, the country’s regulators have taken more than 50 actual or reported actions on areas spanning antitrust, finance, data security and social equality, i.e. more than one move a week. For decades, China has assiduously built up its tech sector, and has borrowed an industrial and internet model from the West. Arguably it was a resounding success, then why is it now trying to strangle the golden goose it had once cradled?&amp;nbsp; China adopted a new cybersecurity law in June, which builds on the foundation of the 2017 Cyber Security Law, that started tightening the control of data flow. However, since the measure was vaguely worded, it remained unclear how it would be implemented. Around the same time, the Chinese economy was rebounding from its bout with COVID-19, lifting the nation's ride, hailing giant Didi Global’s revenue with it as the US stock market continued to be in a bull run. Didi's long venture investors, including Softbank’s Vision Fund, urged seizing the moment to take the company public. The company made its debut at $14 on the New York Stock Exchange on the last day of June 2021, raising $4.4 billion - the biggest stock sale by a Chinese company since the 2014 listing of Alibaba Group Holding Ltd.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Its shares briefly topped $18 in the first days of trading, before China’s cyber security watchdog - Cyberspace Administration of China (CAC) stunned investors on July 2 by launching a data-security probe into Didi and blocking its China business from adding new users.&amp;nbsp; The crackdown worsened on July 9, when 25 more Didi apps - including ones used by drivers - were ordered to be removed from app stores, potentially crippling the company’s operations. If this was not enough, the administration further extended its clampdown on other sectors in&amp;nbsp; July. On July 22, the government announced new worker protection rules, under which online food platforms must cover minimum wage and insurance benefits. This gutted the share price of delivery giants such as Meituan and its rival, Alibaba's Ele.me; which had drawn severe criticism on social media for their treatment of riders and guaranteed time-bound delivery which has compelled riders to undertake dangerous routes, risking their lives.&amp;nbsp; On the following day, Beijing effectively torpedoed a multibillion-dollar industry - after-school tutoring - with a single administrative order. The new rules banned companies that teach the K-12 school curriculum from going public and registering themselves as non-profits. The shares of the three largest US-listed Chinese edtech firms - TAL Education, New Oriental and Gaotu Techedu, fell by 65-70% on the announcement, and the founders of the latter two companies went from billionaires to millionaires almost instantly. The corporate intervention that has hammered internet stocks is now driving investors to sectors still in Beijing’s good graces, such as high-tech manufacturing and renewable energy. Indexes for new energy stocks, semiconductor makers and electric vehicle companies, outperformed the market from 4% to 18% since the beginning of July.&amp;nbsp; Broadly, Beijing is concerned about four pillars of stability: banking, antitrust regulation, data security and social equality. For example, social equality being at the heart of the ban of for-profit after-school tutors or rights concerning gig economy workers.&amp;nbsp; Some market participants believe China is trying to direct capital and human resources from internet companies into sectors that will help the country become more self-reliant. A portfolio manager at M&amp;amp;G Investments, Singapore, tracking the Chinese economy said, “They are trying to reach a new equilibrium because it seems capital flows were not in line with long-term, top- down priorities.” Analysts believe the government’s latest initiatives are motivated by a bigger ambition to realign the relationship between private business and the state, with a goal of ensuring companies do more to serve the Communist Party’s economic, social and national security concerns. However, it is worth noticing that Huawei, which should fall under the purview of the state on every possible reason in law, is entirely untouched.&amp;nbsp; As per some observers, the reason for the telecom giant being solidly backed by Beijing is due to the mutual benefit of both parties. China’s vision for a domestic adversary as opposed to a Silicon Valley has benefited the private companies for years from lax regulatory oversight. However, leaders now worry that the tech giants have become too big and could be using personal and corporate digital records as leverage to build alternative power centers in the one-party state.&amp;nbsp; In the past, the government has often demanded data from private firms, and could sometimes enforce its wishes, especially for hunting down criminal suspects and silencing dissent but the tech companies have pushed back on requests to share and centralise their statistics.&amp;nbsp; Nonetheless, Beijing now wishes to undo these through their complex cyber security laws and regulations which would make it harder for companies to resist data sharing requests.&amp;nbsp; Chinese regulators have formally made the data localisation requirement a prerequisite for foreign institutions trying to get a foothold in China, enabling the government to have more authority over the records. Western companies have long complained such “data localisation” requirements could stifle innovation in their global operations or enable Chinese authorities to steal their proprietary information.&amp;nbsp; US electric car maker Tesla Inc has pledged to build more data centers in China and to keep information generated by the vehicles it sells there, within Chinese borders. “Less invasive private-sector data collection anywhere is a good thing,” says analyst Ryan Fedasiuk at Georgetown University’s Center for Security and Emerging Technology. “But China’s push for data privacy strikes me as yet another move to strengthen the role of the government and the party vis-à-vis tech companies.” Unlike the EU rules, the Chinese version lacks restrictions on government entities when it comes to gathering information on people’s call logs, contact lists, location and other data. Meanwhile, these laws should also be seen against the backdrop of high tensions between US-China relations, which has sharpened President Xi’s focus on security and self-sufficiency. Beijing prohibits foreign ownership of larger sections of the Chinese economy, especially the profitable parts involving digital technology and data, and hence the companies follow a concept of&amp;nbsp; Variable-Interest-Entity or VIE, where the companies selling shares in foreign markets (including Hong Kong) can do so only quasi-legally at best. The workaround for VIE was the transparency that would come with foreign ownership and control which could reveal more about the state of the economy.&amp;nbsp; Under a 2020 law signed by then-President, Donald Trump, Chinese companies would have to share their audit working papers with the US regulators. Failure to do so would lead to delisting of companies from US exchanges.&amp;nbsp; For China, that could risk allowing key data, such as detailed information about Chinese consumers and government agencies that may be included in the papers, to end up in the hands of a foreign government. Both the second largest economy in the world and West see tech as a possible disrupter, however, it’s the Chinese who seem to be turbocharging a move towards the real tech, where they are ready to destroy the ‘pre-tender’ that exists today.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
