<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/business-finance/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-06-01T13:59:53+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/business-finance/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Louis Vuitton - A Luxury Mecca</title>
      <link href="/Louis-Vuitton-A-Luxury-Mecca" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Louis Vuitton - A Luxury Mecca" />
      <published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Louis-Vuitton-A-Luxury-Mecca</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Louis-Vuitton-A-Luxury-Mecca">&lt;p&gt;When one thinks of Louis Vuitton, the first thing that comes to mind is an expensive luxury brand of supreme quality. LV is a true definition of aristocracy and elegance and kindles a utopian dream, a tantalising illusion. It is the best seller in the top range of luxury brands which produces high-quality, fashionable products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Established in France in 1854, Louis Vuitton started as a retailer for travelling bags. It opened the first store in Oxford Street, London. Louis Vuitton Moët Hennessy, usually abbreviated as LVMH, was the conglomerate founded in 1987 owing to a merger between Moët Hennessy and Louis Vuitton. Its headquarter is in Paris, France. Bernard Arnault, the President, owns 48% of LVMH. Today, the brand has a strong presence in categories like leather goods, handbags, ready-to-wear garments, jewellery and other accessories.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the very beginning, Louis Vuitton has attracted the support of customers who primarily belong to the upper echelons of society. The brand's mission is to represent the most refined qualities of the occidental art of living around the world. It firmly believes that fashion must follow the customer or die. Thus, it has stepped up its value proposition over time to provide a bespoke experience to its clientele, which adds to its dynamism. Louis Vuitton is one of the few fashion brands that started avant-garde fashion without compromising on traditional values. It won't be an exaggeration to say that LV is the holy grail of those seeking luxury.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current rise of Louis Vuitton is not a coincidence but instead can be attributed to an effective business model. It has always tried to counter mass production with limited edition series. This means that not everyone will have the same bags, and customers, therefore, get to enjoy fantastic exclusivity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Limited editions help to create an instant buzz. Because of the scarcity, waiting lists become longer and longer, and the products become even more desirable. The brand has worked in collaboration with various artists who have created their limited edition lines. This series helps the brand in connecting with new and younger audiences. Louis Vuitton uses the principle of special order, which allows the consumer to order merchandise tailored exactly for him and his preferences.&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;LV maintains and controls its distribution and sales.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it were to allow a large chain store, it undoubtedly would garner more sales in the short run. However, it would damage the brand image and its rarity due to it being easily available. Production efficiency is another crucial factor of LV's thriving business model. The production is completed through teamwork, and the employees are trained to be autonomous and multi-skilled so that the problems related to the product can be solved timely with their knowledge and experience. The whole production process is done in-house, including the manufacturing of raw material, which guarantees superior quality. This is not only rare in the industry, but it also requires a huge financial outlay. LV perpetuates the image of handmade quality. The brand is a true example of superior craftsmanship in an age of cheap mass production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The success of Louis Vuitton's business model can also be accredited to its first-mover advantage in Japan. Louis Vuitton entered Japan in 1977 and saw the Japanese economic boom. The company realised that Japanese consumers demonstrated a fascination with and passion for luxury.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Japanese culture of expressing social status through luxury goods together with the beauty conscious women demanding quality products helped ignite the rage of luxury shopping in Japan. LV began to collaborate with Japanese designers and combined fashionable elements with its heritage to offer fine quality products. This helped nurture an addiction of the Japanese to luxury and enhanced brand loyalty to help sustain profitability. With the company strategies becoming immensely successful, LV became the industry mogul in the Japanese luxury market and acquired a 28% share in the nation's market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louis Vuitton has successfully distinguished itself from other competitors by following a unique marketing strategy that is not utilised by most of its peer luxury brands. It has established a unique brand character that has created a high-standard barrier for others to compete. The LV monogram is high on recognition, and thus, people prefer to carry the monogrammed merchandise since it is associated with fame and reputation. This highlights the great importance that the brand attaches to a consumer's psychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LV does not have a second line to sell products that have a lower cost than the mainline. It only sells high-priced products and ignores those consumers who cannot purchase the high-priced items in the mainline. Although this could be called a haughty attitude, there is a logical reason according to the theory 'Product-out or Lord's business', which means the company would produce the item in limited quantity to satiate the desire of the buyers for prestige.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The high price that the brand commands is not only justified by its superior quality but also by a high degree of exclusivity. While looking at LV history, one can see that not once in 166 years its prices were reduced. “Why LV is never on sales” is a frequently asked question. This is because the brand knows the adverse effects of price reduction. For instance, the customers would wait until the brand goes on sale, which would reduce its exclusivity. Thus, it fixes the price to stimulate customers' demand at once and prevents them from postponing their purchasing habits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louis Vuitton pursues excellence that goes far beyond the supreme quality of its products. It encompasses the layout and location of its stores. It opens these stores only in the most prime locations since it would make the customers feel proud while buying the products. Louis Vuitton shops are distinctive and unique, which offer an experience in itself. It has always rejected mass advertising. It accentuates publicity in newspapers and magazines that last longer than 15-30 seconds of normal television advertisements. It produces catalogues, which, unlike other free ones, carry a charge. These catalogues contain immense information and sell out completely, which is only possible due to Louis Vuitton's unique stature. LV provides its customers with the opportunity to have their damaged products repaired. This helps to develop trust and brand loyalty and sustains the strength of the brand. This strategy has rarely been found adopted by any other brand in the industry.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the fashion industry is still experiencing the colossal ramifications of COVID-19, Louis Vuitton surprisingly has raised prices by a few percentage points over the last year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The affordable mask, which is the new life-saving accessory, just got its extravagant counterpart, that is, the LV mask. Clearly, it is not for the masses but a luxury layer of pandemic protection added by the aristocrats. The fashion house announced Wuhan, a culturally rich Chinese city, as the first stop for its new global travelling exhibition. This shows the rise of China as the new luxury hub post COVID.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been an intriguing change in consumer behaviour in the Chinese markets post lockdown. Many wealthy Chinese consumers are switching their spending from international travel to luxury purchases. During the lockdown, their pent-up spending desires are now being unleashed, a concept that is popularly known as revenge shopping. LV has been able to weather the lockdown thanks to the ever-growing consumer appetite for dresses and monogrammed bags. It is interesting to note that not all brands can afford to raise prices in such times. The ability to charge a higher price during such a crisis is a manifestation of brand power.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louis Vuitton was one of the first brands to reset and streamline its business model to face the challenges posed by the pandemic-led lockdown. Realising the troubles caused by the brick-and-mortar closures and tourism plunge, the brand turned its focus to the digital realm and reinvigorated its online presence. The brand undertook a 360-degree marketing and advertising campaign to remind the customers of the traditional and intrinsic value of its products. For its Spring 2021 collection, Louis Vuitton launched an animated film, followed by live touring runway shows. The brand took over 100 million impressions on its social media posts for the event. LV has begun a partnership with a video game company producing a collection of outfits inspired by one of the company's online games to instil a desire of developing unique virtual personas in the minds of the young audience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest threat that Louis Vuitton faces today is counterfeiting. This new epidemic for the brand has diluted the brand essence and its market share. LV can overcome this menace by making its supply chain transparent and monitoring the movement of its products right from manufacturing to the promotion and beyond. Educating the consumers to recognise the difference between legitimate products and fakes by providing a visual guide will also help curb counterfeiting.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brand now needs to channelise its energies in new directions by expanding into kids clothing or household paraphernalia, where it can take advantage of its pre-established image of superior craftsmanship and command higher margins. It can increase its market size by either investing in emerging wealthy markets like South America and the Indian subcontinent.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LV needs to make itself more attractive to the millennials and generation z by incubating innovative marketing and branding strategies. The brand needs to recalibrate its operations by going green, which would serve as a hedge against rising costs and contribute to sustainability. It needs to show a sense of responsibility and empathy in this hour of crisis for the consumers to embrace it. Revamping the brand image and retaining an insatiable desire for innovation is required to ultimately remind the public that brands like H&amp;amp;M and Zara do not have the elegance and class which Louis Vuitton commands and how it feels a class apart to own a genuine LV product.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Abhinav Gupta&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abhinav Gupta is a first year Bachelor of Commerce (Honours) student in Shaheed Bhagat Singh College, Delhi University. Inquisitive by nature, he loves to explore and learn new things.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Guest</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">When one thinks of Louis Vuitton, the first thing that comes to mind is an expensive luxury brand of supreme quality. LV is a true definition of aristocracy and elegance and kindles a utopian dream, a tantalising illusion. It is the best seller in the top range of luxury brands which produces high-quality, fashionable products. Established in France in 1854, Louis Vuitton started as a retailer for travelling bags. It opened the first store in Oxford Street, London. Louis Vuitton Moët Hennessy, usually abbreviated as LVMH, was the conglomerate founded in 1987 owing to a merger between Moët Hennessy and Louis Vuitton. Its headquarter is in Paris, France. Bernard Arnault, the President, owns 48% of LVMH. Today, the brand has a strong presence in categories like leather goods, handbags, ready-to-wear garments, jewellery and other accessories.&amp;nbsp; Since the very beginning, Louis Vuitton has attracted the support of customers who primarily belong to the upper echelons of society. The brand's mission is to represent the most refined qualities of the occidental art of living around the world. It firmly believes that fashion must follow the customer or die. Thus, it has stepped up its value proposition over time to provide a bespoke experience to its clientele, which adds to its dynamism. Louis Vuitton is one of the few fashion brands that started avant-garde fashion without compromising on traditional values. It won't be an exaggeration to say that LV is the holy grail of those seeking luxury.&amp;nbsp; The current rise of Louis Vuitton is not a coincidence but instead can be attributed to an effective business model. It has always tried to counter mass production with limited edition series. This means that not everyone will have the same bags, and customers, therefore, get to enjoy fantastic exclusivity.&amp;nbsp; Limited editions help to create an instant buzz. Because of the scarcity, waiting lists become longer and longer, and the products become even more desirable. The brand has worked in collaboration with various artists who have created their limited edition lines. This series helps the brand in connecting with new and younger audiences. Louis Vuitton uses the principle of special order, which allows the consumer to order merchandise tailored exactly for him and his preferences.&amp;nbsp;LV maintains and controls its distribution and sales.&amp;nbsp; If it were to allow a large chain store, it undoubtedly would garner more sales in the short run. However, it would damage the brand image and its rarity due to it being easily available. Production efficiency is another crucial factor of LV's thriving business model. The production is completed through teamwork, and the employees are trained to be autonomous and multi-skilled so that the problems related to the product can be solved timely with their knowledge and experience. The whole production process is done in-house, including the manufacturing of raw material, which guarantees superior quality. This is not only rare in the industry, but it also requires a huge financial outlay. LV perpetuates the image of handmade quality. The brand is a true example of superior craftsmanship in an age of cheap mass production. The success of Louis Vuitton's business model can also be accredited to its first-mover advantage in Japan. Louis Vuitton entered Japan in 1977 and saw the Japanese economic boom. The company realised that Japanese consumers demonstrated a fascination with and passion for luxury.&amp;nbsp; The Japanese culture of expressing social status through luxury goods together with the beauty conscious women demanding quality products helped ignite the rage of luxury shopping in Japan. LV began to collaborate with Japanese designers and combined fashionable elements with its heritage to offer fine quality products. This helped nurture an addiction of the Japanese to luxury and enhanced brand loyalty to help sustain profitability. With the company strategies becoming immensely successful, LV became the industry mogul in the Japanese luxury market and acquired a 28% share in the nation's market. Louis Vuitton has successfully distinguished itself from other competitors by following a unique marketing strategy that is not utilised by most of its peer luxury brands. It has established a unique brand character that has created a high-standard barrier for others to compete. The LV monogram is high on recognition, and thus, people prefer to carry the monogrammed merchandise since it is associated with fame and reputation. This highlights the great importance that the brand attaches to a consumer's psychology. LV does not have a second line to sell products that have a lower cost than the mainline. It only sells high-priced products and ignores those consumers who cannot purchase the high-priced items in the mainline. Although this could be called a haughty attitude, there is a logical reason according to the theory 'Product-out or Lord's business', which means the company would produce the item in limited quantity to satiate the desire of the buyers for prestige.&amp;nbsp; The high price that the brand commands is not only justified by its superior quality but also by a high degree of exclusivity. While looking at LV history, one can see that not once in 166 years its prices were reduced. “Why LV is never on sales” is a frequently asked question. This is because the brand knows the adverse effects of price reduction. For instance, the customers would wait until the brand goes on sale, which would reduce its exclusivity. Thus, it fixes the price to stimulate customers' demand at once and prevents them from postponing their purchasing habits.&amp;nbsp; Louis Vuitton pursues excellence that goes far beyond the supreme quality of its products. It encompasses the layout and location of its stores. It opens these stores only in the most prime locations since it would make the customers feel proud while buying the products. Louis Vuitton shops are distinctive and unique, which offer an experience in itself. It has always rejected mass advertising. It accentuates publicity in newspapers and magazines that last longer than 15-30 seconds of normal television advertisements. It produces catalogues, which, unlike other free ones, carry a charge. These catalogues contain immense information and sell out completely, which is only possible due to Louis Vuitton's unique stature. LV provides its customers with the opportunity to have their damaged products repaired. This helps to develop trust and brand loyalty and sustains the strength of the brand. This strategy has rarely been found adopted by any other brand in the industry.&amp;nbsp; While the fashion industry is still experiencing the colossal ramifications of COVID-19, Louis Vuitton surprisingly has raised prices by a few percentage points over the last year.&amp;nbsp; The affordable mask, which is the new life-saving accessory, just got its extravagant counterpart, that is, the LV mask. Clearly, it is not for the masses but a luxury layer of pandemic protection added by the aristocrats. The fashion house announced Wuhan, a culturally rich Chinese city, as the first stop for its new global travelling exhibition. This shows the rise of China as the new luxury hub post COVID.&amp;nbsp; There has been an intriguing change in consumer behaviour in the Chinese markets post lockdown. Many wealthy Chinese consumers are switching their spending from international travel to luxury purchases. During the lockdown, their pent-up spending desires are now being unleashed, a concept that is popularly known as revenge shopping. LV has been able to weather the lockdown thanks to the ever-growing consumer appetite for dresses and monogrammed bags. It is interesting to note that not all brands can afford to raise prices in such times. The ability to charge a higher price during such a crisis is a manifestation of brand power.&amp;nbsp; Louis Vuitton was one of the first brands to reset and streamline its business model to face the challenges posed by the pandemic-led lockdown. Realising the troubles caused by the brick-and-mortar closures and tourism plunge, the brand turned its focus to the digital realm and reinvigorated its online presence. The brand undertook a 360-degree marketing and advertising campaign to remind the customers of the traditional and intrinsic value of its products. For its Spring 2021 collection, Louis Vuitton launched an animated film, followed by live touring runway shows. The brand took over 100 million impressions on its social media posts for the event. LV has begun a partnership with a video game company producing a collection of outfits inspired by one of the company's online games to instil a desire of developing unique virtual personas in the minds of the young audience.&amp;nbsp; The biggest threat that Louis Vuitton faces today is counterfeiting. This new epidemic for the brand has diluted the brand essence and its market share. LV can overcome this menace by making its supply chain transparent and monitoring the movement of its products right from manufacturing to the promotion and beyond. Educating the consumers to recognise the difference between legitimate products and fakes by providing a visual guide will also help curb counterfeiting.&amp;nbsp; The brand now needs to channelise its energies in new directions by expanding into kids clothing or household paraphernalia, where it can take advantage of its pre-established image of superior craftsmanship and command higher margins. It can increase its market size by either investing in emerging wealthy markets like South America and the Indian subcontinent.&amp;nbsp; LV needs to make itself more attractive to the millennials and generation z by incubating innovative marketing and branding strategies. The brand needs to recalibrate its operations by going green, which would serve as a hedge against rising costs and contribute to sustainability. It needs to show a sense of responsibility and empathy in this hour of crisis for the consumers to embrace it. Revamping the brand image and retaining an insatiable desire for innovation is required to ultimately remind the public that brands like H&amp;amp;M and Zara do not have the elegance and class which Louis Vuitton commands and how it feels a class apart to own a genuine LV product.&amp;nbsp; -Abhinav Gupta Abhinav Gupta is a first year Bachelor of Commerce (Honours) student in Shaheed Bhagat Singh College, Delhi University. Inquisitive by nature, he loves to explore and learn new things.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Taxing Verdict for the Indian Tax Man</title>
      <link href="/A-Taxing-Verdict-for-the-Indian-Tax-Man" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Taxing Verdict for the Indian Tax Man" />
      <published>2021-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Taxing-Verdict-for-the-Indian-Tax-Man</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Taxing-Verdict-for-the-Indian-Tax-Man">&lt;p&gt;The Permanent Court of Arbitration at the Hague, in its arbitral ruling, has once again dealt a blow to the Government of India by ruling in favour of the gas and oil exploration company, Cairn Energy Plc over tax disputes. The verdict comes post the September 25, 2020 victory of Vodafone International Holdings BV against the Indian government over the same dispute relating to the retrospective tax amendment in 2012.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2006-07, Cairn UK, as part of an internal rearrangement process, transferred shares of Cairn India Holdings to Cairn India. Later, in 2011, the Edinburgh-headquartered organisation sold its Cairn India stake to the mining conglomerate Vedanta. In January 2014, the Indian income tax authorities, in view of the retroactive amended income tax law, alleged that the gas exploration firm made capital gains of ₹245.03 billion in the rearrangement process and hence was liable to pay a tax of ₹102.47 billion to the authorities. The company’s interpretation of Indian laws on capital gains differed, and consequently, it refused to pay the amount. In response, the authorities stopped the sale of the 10% stake to Vedanta and froze dividend pay-out to UK based parent company.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2015, Cairn initiated an international arbitration proceeding against the Indian authorities under article 9 of the Agreement between the Government of the Republic of India and the Government of Great Britain and Northern Ireland for Promotion and Protection of Investments (India-UK BIT). Countries enter into treaties, especially tax treaties, to prevent double taxation of corporations’ incomes earned by foreign investments, so as to promote a healthy business relationship and trade between two countries in this growing globalised world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose behind the said BIT provision was also the same, i.e. ensuring protection of the investors of the contracting state against any disruption/harassment of business in the territory of the host state. (See, Fair and Equitable Treatment – UNCTAD Series on Issues in International Investment Agreement II).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A final assessment order was slapped on the oil corporation in 2016, which included interest amounting to ₹188 billion, in addition to the principal tax amount.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three-member international arbitration tribunal, including a nominee of the Indian government, unanimously ruled in favour of the exploration organisation, and ordered the Indian administration to compensate the former for the total harm suffered including interest and the costs of arbitration. In its judgment, the arbitration panel said, “&lt;em&gt;Tax demand against the claimants (Cairn Energy Plc and Cairn UK Holdings Limited) in respect of AY (assessment year) 2007-08 is inconsistent with the treaty and the claimants are relieved from any obligation to pay it and [the tribunal] orders the respondent (Indian government) to neutralise the continuing effect of the demand by permanently withdrawing the demand.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sovereign country has the power to impose tax from a retrospective date. Nonetheless, such an action when a past transaction, which was not liable to taxation as on that date, is taxed under the aegis of a retrospective amendment, it is naturally seen to be unjust and discriminatory. Officials usually defend the amendments by stating that such moves are brought into effect to correct earlier flaws that defeated the purpose of the legislation in the first place.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be interesting to observe India’s follow-up on the issue. The government has until this month to challenge the award in a higher court in Singapore. By February end, Cairn’s CEO &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?rlz=1C1RXQR_enIN928IN928&amp;amp;sxsrf=ALeKk03IPhQp-AiVjX-3f-BE1qS7-EiNXw:1614752810068&amp;amp;q=Simon+Thomson&amp;amp;stick=H4sIAAAAAAAAAOPgE-LUz9U3sDCxtCxX4gIx85LzcgqNtBSzk63084vSE_MyqxJLMvPzUDhWyan5i1h5gzNz8_MUQjLyc4vz83awMgIATPkbn08AAAA&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjgi5P9vpPvAhWTXSsKHSlvCAoQmxMoATApegQIIRAD&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Simon Thomson&lt;/a&gt; in his conversation with the Ministry of&amp;nbsp; Finance conveyed the corporation’s desire for a speedy resolution that is in the interest of all stakeholders involved. The government has hinted that the only possible solution for both parties to avoid further litigation is for the former to agree to the government’s&amp;nbsp;'&lt;a href=&quot;https://indianexpress.com/article/explained/direct-tax-vivad-se-vishwas-bill-how-govt-aims-to-reduce-direct-tax-litigation-6254981/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Vivad se Vishwas&lt;/a&gt;' (From Litigation to Trust) &amp;nbsp;tax amnesty. This scheme, announced in the Indian Budget 2020, provides speedy resolution for tax disputes in the forms of certain compensation between individuals and the tax department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The oil discovery company aims to enforce the award under international arbitration rules, and can use this judgment to approach courts in countries like the UK, USA to seize any overseas property owned by India, to recover the money if the award is not honoured. If it does happen, India would not be the first country to face seizure of its international assets from an energy company. In 2019, US Oil firm ConocoPhillips, under international arbitration law, seized Venezuela’s overseas assets to execute an arbitration award of more than $8 billion. Cairn is reportedly identifying India’s overseas assets, including bank accounts and even Air India planes or Indian ships, that could be seized in the absence of a settlement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also worthwhile to note that if the Indian government accepts the award, then this move would be welcomed by the business corporations. India's reputation has taken a severe beating as a result of these cases. The BJP government has, in the past, denounced the introduction of a retrospective tax amendment by the previous Congress government as &quot;tax terrorism&quot;. Prime Minister Narendra Modi had promised to bring an end to &quot;tax terror&quot; after coming to power in 2014. However, the opposite happened when the government carried on with the case.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a government struggling to find revenue and seeking to boost its economy post-COVID-19, it is essential for the government to reduce compliance troubles and stumbling blocks such as retrospective taxation, lest it finds itself seriously damaging its potential post economic liberalisation.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Permanent Court of Arbitration at the Hague, in its arbitral ruling, has once again dealt a blow to the Government of India by ruling in favour of the gas and oil exploration company, Cairn Energy Plc over tax disputes. The verdict comes post the September 25, 2020 victory of Vodafone International Holdings BV against the Indian government over the same dispute relating to the retrospective tax amendment in 2012.&amp;nbsp; In 2006-07, Cairn UK, as part of an internal rearrangement process, transferred shares of Cairn India Holdings to Cairn India. Later, in 2011, the Edinburgh-headquartered organisation sold its Cairn India stake to the mining conglomerate Vedanta. In January 2014, the Indian income tax authorities, in view of the retroactive amended income tax law, alleged that the gas exploration firm made capital gains of ₹245.03 billion in the rearrangement process and hence was liable to pay a tax of ₹102.47 billion to the authorities. The company’s interpretation of Indian laws on capital gains differed, and consequently, it refused to pay the amount. In response, the authorities stopped the sale of the 10% stake to Vedanta and froze dividend pay-out to UK based parent company.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; In 2015, Cairn initiated an international arbitration proceeding against the Indian authorities under article 9 of the Agreement between the Government of the Republic of India and the Government of Great Britain and Northern Ireland for Promotion and Protection of Investments (India-UK BIT). Countries enter into treaties, especially tax treaties, to prevent double taxation of corporations’ incomes earned by foreign investments, so as to promote a healthy business relationship and trade between two countries in this growing globalised world. The purpose behind the said BIT provision was also the same, i.e. ensuring protection of the investors of the contracting state against any disruption/harassment of business in the territory of the host state. (See, Fair and Equitable Treatment – UNCTAD Series on Issues in International Investment Agreement II). A final assessment order was slapped on the oil corporation in 2016, which included interest amounting to ₹188 billion, in addition to the principal tax amount.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The three-member international arbitration tribunal, including a nominee of the Indian government, unanimously ruled in favour of the exploration organisation, and ordered the Indian administration to compensate the former for the total harm suffered including interest and the costs of arbitration. In its judgment, the arbitration panel said, “Tax demand against the claimants (Cairn Energy Plc and Cairn UK Holdings Limited) in respect of AY (assessment year) 2007-08 is inconsistent with the treaty and the claimants are relieved from any obligation to pay it and [the tribunal] orders the respondent (Indian government) to neutralise the continuing effect of the demand by permanently withdrawing the demand.” A sovereign country has the power to impose tax from a retrospective date. Nonetheless, such an action when a past transaction, which was not liable to taxation as on that date, is taxed under the aegis of a retrospective amendment, it is naturally seen to be unjust and discriminatory. Officials usually defend the amendments by stating that such moves are brought into effect to correct earlier flaws that defeated the purpose of the legislation in the first place.&amp;nbsp; It would be interesting to observe India’s follow-up on the issue. The government has until this month to challenge the award in a higher court in Singapore. By February end, Cairn’s CEO Simon Thomson in his conversation with the Ministry of&amp;nbsp; Finance conveyed the corporation’s desire for a speedy resolution that is in the interest of all stakeholders involved. The government has hinted that the only possible solution for both parties to avoid further litigation is for the former to agree to the government’s&amp;nbsp;'Vivad se Vishwas' (From Litigation to Trust) &amp;nbsp;tax amnesty. This scheme, announced in the Indian Budget 2020, provides speedy resolution for tax disputes in the forms of certain compensation between individuals and the tax department. The oil discovery company aims to enforce the award under international arbitration rules, and can use this judgment to approach courts in countries like the UK, USA to seize any overseas property owned by India, to recover the money if the award is not honoured. If it does happen, India would not be the first country to face seizure of its international assets from an energy company. In 2019, US Oil firm ConocoPhillips, under international arbitration law, seized Venezuela’s overseas assets to execute an arbitration award of more than $8 billion. Cairn is reportedly identifying India’s overseas assets, including bank accounts and even Air India planes or Indian ships, that could be seized in the absence of a settlement. It is also worthwhile to note that if the Indian government accepts the award, then this move would be welcomed by the business corporations. India's reputation has taken a severe beating as a result of these cases. The BJP government has, in the past, denounced the introduction of a retrospective tax amendment by the previous Congress government as &quot;tax terrorism&quot;. Prime Minister Narendra Modi had promised to bring an end to &quot;tax terror&quot; after coming to power in 2014. However, the opposite happened when the government carried on with the case.&amp;nbsp; For a government struggling to find revenue and seeking to boost its economy post-COVID-19, it is essential for the government to reduce compliance troubles and stumbling blocks such as retrospective taxation, lest it finds itself seriously damaging its potential post economic liberalisation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A High ROE can be Misleading!</title>
      <link href="/A-High-ROE-can-be-Misleading" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A High ROE can be Misleading!" />
      <published>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-High-ROE-can-be-Misleading</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-High-ROE-can-be-Misleading">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Investment is most intelligent when it’s most businesslike&lt;/em&gt;”- Benjamin Graham.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Benjamin Graham and Warren Buffet have emphasised on the need for the investor to only invest in companies whose business they duly understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how do we do that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer lies in an obsession with numbers. Plain odd numbers that mean something to a blank eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like the Greeks had an obsession with Golden Ratio, investors are the same with Financial ratios. Ratios are shortcuts and who doesn’t like them? Especially when “more time means more money”, seems real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One such important ratio that makes the kitty of the most important financial ratios to consider for an Investor is the “Return on Equity (ROE)” Ratio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And both these gentlemen mentioned above love this ratio. They do warn you on single-factor investing and urge you to consider other key factors but that’s in line with every valuation metric that comes with a “&lt;em&gt;yes, but…&lt;/em&gt;”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why do they love it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because it’s businesslike. It showcases the business owner’s ability to employ equity into money-making ventures. It measures profitability. It gives a raw sense of what the company is doing with its equity and how efficient it is in engineering its cash to generate more cash. More earnings mean higher valuations and higher valuation would mean capital appreciation for stakeholders. It’s simple math.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, as all math do,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It starts with a simple formula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Return on Equity (ROE) = Net Income/Shareholder’s equity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toggle to the company’s P&amp;amp;L statement and pick up the bottom-line item, ‘Net Income’ and divide it by the total shareholder’s equity present on the balance sheet and that’s how easily you can calculate the ROE of your desired company. The rule of thumb is, the higher the ROE, the more the company is efficient in its operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too excited to already switch tabs? Wait!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where the trouble begins.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplicity by which ROE can be calculated should already make you apprehensive about its god-like relevance. Good things don’t come easy, right? Well, let’s dig deeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s multiply and divide the above equation, once by the ‘Total Sales’ and again by ‘Total Assets’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;ROE= (Net Income/Total Sales) * (Total Sales/Total Assets) * (Total Assets/Shareholders Equity)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Total Sales cancel Total Sales and Total Assets cancel Total Assets but for now, let’s analyse each portion individually. Reframing the above equation, we have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;ROE= Net Profit Margin * Total Asset Turnover Ratio * Financial Leverage&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we have is something known as the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;DuPont Formula&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; which breaks down ROE into 3 key drivers, all of which independently relate to the ROE and can help back-test the components of the formula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Net Profit Margin is indicative of how well the company is in managing and financing its operations per unit of sales. A higher Net Profit Margin would eventually mean more earnings for the company and higher ROE. Asset turnover ratio means how efficiently the company is using its assets to drive sales. A higher Total Asset Turnover Ratio would mean that the company is deploying its assets correctly to target higher sales per unit of the asset owned. Hence, a higher ROE. Lastly, Financial Leverage is the extent to which the company uses debt in relation to equity to finance its assets. In brief, higher leverage would mean greater financial risk but substituted by higher Return on Equity (ROE).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An ideal firm should have a high Net Profit Margin, high Asset Turnover Ratio but use less leverage to reach there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out, however, that a company cannot grow earnings faster than its current ROE without raising additional cash. Now raising cash comes at a cost and cuts through the firm’s profits. If the company decides to raise money by way of debt, the interest gets paid as an expense and if it decides to raise equity, Earnings-per-share (EPS) goes down, which in turn affects investor sentiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, ROE is the limiter to a firm’s growth. It’s a gauge against the excessive heating up of the company. That is why ROE forms an integral part of the investor analysis but here comes the catch. When something holds such importance within stakeholders' minds and the management knows it, will not all companies tend to magnify ROE to seem better on the stock exchange?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, but soon you’ll know higher ROE numbers are no shortcut for diligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manipulating the ROE numbers isn’t an ordeal. There are numerous ways by which this can be done and that make higher ROE’s a subject for debate. This is where the trouble gets bigger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Share Buybacks:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember the ROE equation? A simple math student would tell how to increase its value. Either increase the Net Earnings (Numerator) or decrease Total Shareholders Equity (Denominator). An ideal and natural practice for companies would be to focus on increasing the numerator by increasing the Asset Turnover Ratio that drives sales with no additional asset cost or by increasing the Net profit Margin by efficiently managing operations. Both these practices done in tandem would result in a significantly higher ROE. But not all companies resort to this technique. Some adopt a latter technique and decrease shareholder’s equity by rolling out share buyback schemes. When they do say they use the retained earnings to buy stock and thus decrease the shareholder equity which in turn magnifies the firm’s ability to turn equity investments into profits (ROE).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;High Leverage:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to decrease shareholder equity is to tweak the company’s capital structure by playing around with the Debt/Equity ratio. Companies issue debt to raise capital and then use that to generate profits. Indeed, the finance cost will increase for a given capital requirement but that would only be a fraction of total debt and not enough to offset the decrease in shareholder’s equity. Higher Net Profits would boost ROE higher, but that has hidden risks related to insolvency and inability to survive during economic downturns. Because debt is an obligation to pay back with interest, it is neutral to the company’s bad run. Companies that issue large debt run the risks of overleveraging in the form of high-interest payments and greater chances of default. These companies may rely heavily on debt and hence have an Inflated and misleading ROE figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Off-balance sheet items and write-downs:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of Off-balance sheet items has been in talks ever since &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sir David Tweedie&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; was the chairman of the IASB. He joked that he wanted to fly in an aircraft that actually existed on an airline’s balance sheet. That is to say that it’s not on operating lease or any such way that the companies adopt to evade showing huge assets in their balance sheets. By doing this, they forgo depreciation expense and incur impairment charges when they right down assets, which in turn decreases Shareholders' equity on the balance sheet. This keeps equity investors in an obscure environment by hiding the true amount of capital invested in the business. This is further treated maliciously by the management to offset natural ROE figures and make them appear more inflated and following a growth trend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another problem with the ROE calculations is the ‘E’ part in it. The “Net Earnings” line item is such an entry that can easily be tricked and especially when the management bonus is linked to hitting ROE targets, they can have a strong interest in artificially boosting it. Further, it does not take into account risks associated with income generation and is subject to a wide variety of accounting conventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the number is so susceptible to management intervention and unchallenging to intrude and alter, higher ROE can be misleading. If not anything this is what companies did in the wake of the 2008 Financial Crisis and during the ongoing Covid-19 Pandemic. Since the market was undervalued on both occasions, companies came in with various offers to interest investors and appear good on paper. This rigorous attempt was also done to avoid a dent in the ROE history of the company. An ROE that’s greater than the return available from a lower risk investment motivates the Investor to see interesting but false prospects building within the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While companies do all this to fuel their investor's confidence, misinformed investors are caught in a tyranny of financial malpractices, unwinding which is a luxury for a common Investor. Investors can’t know whether that ROE number is reliable or pumped to perfection. One company might have a significantly higher ROE than a competitor simply because it’s more aggressively exploiting uninformed investors rather than being superior in terms of profitability. ROE lacks the necessary meticulous conscientiousness to buttress intelligent investment decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though every single ratio has a caveat. ROE is the dumbest of all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll leave you with one thought, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If such a flawed financial metric catches the attention of mass-market participants, then there should be a profitable arbitrage strategy that exploits that anomaly?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Mehul Goyal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Investment is most intelligent when it’s most businesslike”- Benjamin Graham. Both Benjamin Graham and Warren Buffet have emphasised on the need for the investor to only invest in companies whose business they duly understand. But how do we do that? The answer lies in an obsession with numbers. Plain odd numbers that mean something to a blank eye. Just like the Greeks had an obsession with Golden Ratio, investors are the same with Financial ratios. Ratios are shortcuts and who doesn’t like them? Especially when “more time means more money”, seems real. One such important ratio that makes the kitty of the most important financial ratios to consider for an Investor is the “Return on Equity (ROE)” Ratio. And both these gentlemen mentioned above love this ratio. They do warn you on single-factor investing and urge you to consider other key factors but that’s in line with every valuation metric that comes with a “yes, but…”.&amp;nbsp; But why do they love it? Because it’s businesslike. It showcases the business owner’s ability to employ equity into money-making ventures. It measures profitability. It gives a raw sense of what the company is doing with its equity and how efficient it is in engineering its cash to generate more cash. More earnings mean higher valuations and higher valuation would mean capital appreciation for stakeholders. It’s simple math. But, as all math do, It starts with a simple formula. Return on Equity (ROE) = Net Income/Shareholder’s equity. Toggle to the company’s P&amp;amp;L statement and pick up the bottom-line item, ‘Net Income’ and divide it by the total shareholder’s equity present on the balance sheet and that’s how easily you can calculate the ROE of your desired company. The rule of thumb is, the higher the ROE, the more the company is efficient in its operations. Too excited to already switch tabs? Wait! This is where the trouble begins.&amp;nbsp; The simplicity by which ROE can be calculated should already make you apprehensive about its god-like relevance. Good things don’t come easy, right? Well, let’s dig deeper. Let’s multiply and divide the above equation, once by the ‘Total Sales’ and again by ‘Total Assets’. ROE= (Net Income/Total Sales) * (Total Sales/Total Assets) * (Total Assets/Shareholders Equity) Total Sales cancel Total Sales and Total Assets cancel Total Assets but for now, let’s analyse each portion individually. Reframing the above equation, we have: ROE= Net Profit Margin * Total Asset Turnover Ratio * Financial Leverage What we have is something known as the DuPont Formula which breaks down ROE into 3 key drivers, all of which independently relate to the ROE and can help back-test the components of the formula. The Net Profit Margin is indicative of how well the company is in managing and financing its operations per unit of sales. A higher Net Profit Margin would eventually mean more earnings for the company and higher ROE. Asset turnover ratio means how efficiently the company is using its assets to drive sales. A higher Total Asset Turnover Ratio would mean that the company is deploying its assets correctly to target higher sales per unit of the asset owned. Hence, a higher ROE. Lastly, Financial Leverage is the extent to which the company uses debt in relation to equity to finance its assets. In brief, higher leverage would mean greater financial risk but substituted by higher Return on Equity (ROE). An ideal firm should have a high Net Profit Margin, high Asset Turnover Ratio but use less leverage to reach there. It turns out, however, that a company cannot grow earnings faster than its current ROE without raising additional cash. Now raising cash comes at a cost and cuts through the firm’s profits. If the company decides to raise money by way of debt, the interest gets paid as an expense and if it decides to raise equity, Earnings-per-share (EPS) goes down, which in turn affects investor sentiment. So, ROE is the limiter to a firm’s growth. It’s a gauge against the excessive heating up of the company. That is why ROE forms an integral part of the investor analysis but here comes the catch. When something holds such importance within stakeholders' minds and the management knows it, will not all companies tend to magnify ROE to seem better on the stock exchange?&amp;nbsp; Yes, but soon you’ll know higher ROE numbers are no shortcut for diligence. Manipulating the ROE numbers isn’t an ordeal. There are numerous ways by which this can be done and that make higher ROE’s a subject for debate. This is where the trouble gets bigger. Share Buybacks: Remember the ROE equation? A simple math student would tell how to increase its value. Either increase the Net Earnings (Numerator) or decrease Total Shareholders Equity (Denominator). An ideal and natural practice for companies would be to focus on increasing the numerator by increasing the Asset Turnover Ratio that drives sales with no additional asset cost or by increasing the Net profit Margin by efficiently managing operations. Both these practices done in tandem would result in a significantly higher ROE. But not all companies resort to this technique. Some adopt a latter technique and decrease shareholder’s equity by rolling out share buyback schemes. When they do say they use the retained earnings to buy stock and thus decrease the shareholder equity which in turn magnifies the firm’s ability to turn equity investments into profits (ROE). High Leverage: Another way to decrease shareholder equity is to tweak the company’s capital structure by playing around with the Debt/Equity ratio. Companies issue debt to raise capital and then use that to generate profits. Indeed, the finance cost will increase for a given capital requirement but that would only be a fraction of total debt and not enough to offset the decrease in shareholder’s equity. Higher Net Profits would boost ROE higher, but that has hidden risks related to insolvency and inability to survive during economic downturns. Because debt is an obligation to pay back with interest, it is neutral to the company’s bad run. Companies that issue large debt run the risks of overleveraging in the form of high-interest payments and greater chances of default. These companies may rely heavily on debt and hence have an Inflated and misleading ROE figure. Off-balance sheet items and write-downs: The concept of Off-balance sheet items has been in talks ever since Sir David Tweedie was the chairman of the IASB. He joked that he wanted to fly in an aircraft that actually existed on an airline’s balance sheet. That is to say that it’s not on operating lease or any such way that the companies adopt to evade showing huge assets in their balance sheets. By doing this, they forgo depreciation expense and incur impairment charges when they right down assets, which in turn decreases Shareholders' equity on the balance sheet. This keeps equity investors in an obscure environment by hiding the true amount of capital invested in the business. This is further treated maliciously by the management to offset natural ROE figures and make them appear more inflated and following a growth trend. Another problem with the ROE calculations is the ‘E’ part in it. The “Net Earnings” line item is such an entry that can easily be tricked and especially when the management bonus is linked to hitting ROE targets, they can have a strong interest in artificially boosting it. Further, it does not take into account risks associated with income generation and is subject to a wide variety of accounting conventions. Conclusion: Since the number is so susceptible to management intervention and unchallenging to intrude and alter, higher ROE can be misleading. If not anything this is what companies did in the wake of the 2008 Financial Crisis and during the ongoing Covid-19 Pandemic. Since the market was undervalued on both occasions, companies came in with various offers to interest investors and appear good on paper. This rigorous attempt was also done to avoid a dent in the ROE history of the company. An ROE that’s greater than the return available from a lower risk investment motivates the Investor to see interesting but false prospects building within the company. While companies do all this to fuel their investor's confidence, misinformed investors are caught in a tyranny of financial malpractices, unwinding which is a luxury for a common Investor. Investors can’t know whether that ROE number is reliable or pumped to perfection. One company might have a significantly higher ROE than a competitor simply because it’s more aggressively exploiting uninformed investors rather than being superior in terms of profitability. ROE lacks the necessary meticulous conscientiousness to buttress intelligent investment decisions. Though every single ratio has a caveat. ROE is the dumbest of all. I’ll leave you with one thought, though. If such a flawed financial metric catches the attention of mass-market participants, then there should be a profitable arbitrage strategy that exploits that anomaly?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Emergence of Sexbots and the Sentience Stumper</title>
      <link href="/The-Emergence-of-Sexbots-and-the-Sentience-Stumper" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Emergence of Sexbots and the Sentience Stumper" />
      <published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Emergence-of-Sexbots-and-the-Sentience-Stumper</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Emergence-of-Sexbots-and-the-Sentience-Stumper">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 1: Immersion into The SexTech Industry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What comes to your mind when you overhear the word ‘SexTech’? Sex robots and virtual mates? Sex toys and adult websites? These are only a portion of the SexTech industry. Basically, SexTech is any technology that has been curated to enhance the human sexual experience and disrupts the way sex is viewed, accessed and relished like never before. However, the industry is still marginalised, yet the market is buzzing with the rising voice of IoB technology. The industry is currently estimated at $30 billion and is forecasted to become one of the fastest-growing industries in the next few years, hitting $122.6 billion by 2026.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you remember that Saudi Arabia gave citizenship to a robot known as Sophia in 2017? She became the world’s first robot citizen. Since then, the robotics industry has advanced in other fields as well where artificial humans can be used in productive ways. The success of silicone sex dolls for sexual gratification has set a clear path for the role of robotics in the future of sex. Public polls and indirect measures insinuate that there would be a market for sex robots. We cannot determine how big the market will be. It could be a niche for fetishists, a new paraphilia, or societal norms could alter to allow their use to become widespread.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 2: Dealing with Artificial Love Servants&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The regular customers of the old world of artificial love servants will pay around $20 for such an object - not encompassing shipping and transport. For this, they would get, for example, an inflatable or mannequin-like sex partner, as referred to in earlier decades and centuries. If they dig deeper into their pockets and shell out $500 to $1,500, they have arrived in the modern world. For this, they can acquire a lifelike sex doll with silicone skin and a metal skeleton that can display a gamut of emotions they’re programmed with. They can smile, cry, even do a good approximation of an orgasm face and can produce ever-better mimicries of personhood.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, the sale of robots developed for sexual motives is fast approaching. Several companies such as Realbotix, Android Love Dolls, True Companion and the Sex Bot have begun to take shipping orders. In the world of human-machine intimacy, Harmony by RealDoll is among the most evolved sex robots which can blink, move its head, have a tête-à-tête, and comes with self-learning software that remembers earlier encounters to offer better companionship.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the advancements treading at this rate, we can expect bots to become more developed, sophisticated and human-like. Moreover, the industry experts are exploring the new domain of immersive sex content and virtual reality pornography.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 3: Intimate Droids for Dotage&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is it like to form an emotional bond with a robot? We turn to moral philosophers, scientists and sex workers to compare the differences between human relationships and what robots offer. Indeed, robots cannot feel love or tenderness. The best that robots can do is to ‘fake it’ but, the anthropomorphic features might be enough for some people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The robotic sex dolls are popularly joked about as fetish objects for lonesome beings. But some people believe that the potential of these dolls extends far beyond mere masturbatory succour. The use of sex robots in some therapies may help with sexual healing. For example, it may be beneficial to use a robot in aiding people with sexual dysfunction or social anxiety about sex. For all the adults who are entitled to sex life, robots have also been proposed as a means of appeasement for the differently-abled and the elderly. Although, this idea poses complex ethical issues, particularly with the elderly in care homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 4: Perverted or Practical in the battle against Sex Crimes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some believe that expressing disordered or criminal sexual desires with a sex robot would bring users to the point where they would not have the desire to harm fellow humans. Alternatively, many others believe that this would encourage recidivism, reinforce illicit sexual practices, and make them more admissible. Allowing people to live out their darkest fantasies with sex robots can have a detrimental effect on society and stir up more danger for the vulnerable. But the arrival of sex robots has a distinguished opinion. Inventors like Santos argue that they can potentially replace prostitutes, reduce sex trafficking, and help lonely rejects, while critics say they objectify women and normalize sexism as well as rape culture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts say that the increasingly life-like robots raise complex issues that should be considered by policymakers and the public- including whether the use of such products should be stimulated to curb prostitution and sex trafficking, for sex offenders, or people with disabilities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 5: Connecting the Dots&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could sexual intimacy with robots lead to pronounced social isolation? The majority of experts provide strong arguments that sex robots could lead to some form of a social void. It is contrary to what the manufactures of sex robots tell us. The CEO of RealBotix said that he has been making sex dolls for many years, especially to alleviate the vacuum of those who, for whatever reason, have problems relating to human intimacy. The public survey data shows mixed opinions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously this year, Women of SexTech held a virtual event to discuss the impact of COVID-19 on the industry. The keynote speaker was Cindy Gallop, founder of the MakeLoveNotPorn company, who claimed in her speech that months of lockdown showed us that human relationships are irreplaceable. Technology is just a means to enhance the human experience. Gallop also stated that “&lt;em&gt;it is only when things break down that new tech and ideas emerge&lt;/em&gt;.” The social isolation has created an utter context for SexTech to thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, nearly every facet of society today - public health organisations, school-based sex education, financial institutions, investment and venture capital, major social media companies- still forbid this very reality. At best, it’s considered an indulgence. At worst, sexual wellness and technology are routinely grouped along with pornography, illegal drugs, weapons, and gambling. Therefore, it operates underground in the gloom. Honestly, investors are apprehensive, which means they sometimes do not understand the problems to be solved. Or they answer to more conservative institutions that won’t invest in 'vice.' Stigma keeps them away from SexTech.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samakshi Garg</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Part 1: Immersion into The SexTech Industry What comes to your mind when you overhear the word ‘SexTech’? Sex robots and virtual mates? Sex toys and adult websites? These are only a portion of the SexTech industry. Basically, SexTech is any technology that has been curated to enhance the human sexual experience and disrupts the way sex is viewed, accessed and relished like never before. However, the industry is still marginalised, yet the market is buzzing with the rising voice of IoB technology. The industry is currently estimated at $30 billion and is forecasted to become one of the fastest-growing industries in the next few years, hitting $122.6 billion by 2026.&amp;nbsp; Do you remember that Saudi Arabia gave citizenship to a robot known as Sophia in 2017? She became the world’s first robot citizen. Since then, the robotics industry has advanced in other fields as well where artificial humans can be used in productive ways. The success of silicone sex dolls for sexual gratification has set a clear path for the role of robotics in the future of sex. Public polls and indirect measures insinuate that there would be a market for sex robots. We cannot determine how big the market will be. It could be a niche for fetishists, a new paraphilia, or societal norms could alter to allow their use to become widespread.&amp;nbsp; Part 2: Dealing with Artificial Love Servants The regular customers of the old world of artificial love servants will pay around $20 for such an object - not encompassing shipping and transport. For this, they would get, for example, an inflatable or mannequin-like sex partner, as referred to in earlier decades and centuries. If they dig deeper into their pockets and shell out $500 to $1,500, they have arrived in the modern world. For this, they can acquire a lifelike sex doll with silicone skin and a metal skeleton that can display a gamut of emotions they’re programmed with. They can smile, cry, even do a good approximation of an orgasm face and can produce ever-better mimicries of personhood.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Nowadays, the sale of robots developed for sexual motives is fast approaching. Several companies such as Realbotix, Android Love Dolls, True Companion and the Sex Bot have begun to take shipping orders. In the world of human-machine intimacy, Harmony by RealDoll is among the most evolved sex robots which can blink, move its head, have a tête-à-tête, and comes with self-learning software that remembers earlier encounters to offer better companionship.&amp;nbsp; With the advancements treading at this rate, we can expect bots to become more developed, sophisticated and human-like. Moreover, the industry experts are exploring the new domain of immersive sex content and virtual reality pornography.&amp;nbsp; Part 3: Intimate Droids for Dotage What is it like to form an emotional bond with a robot? We turn to moral philosophers, scientists and sex workers to compare the differences between human relationships and what robots offer. Indeed, robots cannot feel love or tenderness. The best that robots can do is to ‘fake it’ but, the anthropomorphic features might be enough for some people. The robotic sex dolls are popularly joked about as fetish objects for lonesome beings. But some people believe that the potential of these dolls extends far beyond mere masturbatory succour. The use of sex robots in some therapies may help with sexual healing. For example, it may be beneficial to use a robot in aiding people with sexual dysfunction or social anxiety about sex. For all the adults who are entitled to sex life, robots have also been proposed as a means of appeasement for the differently-abled and the elderly. Although, this idea poses complex ethical issues, particularly with the elderly in care homes. Part 4: Perverted or Practical in the battle against Sex Crimes Some believe that expressing disordered or criminal sexual desires with a sex robot would bring users to the point where they would not have the desire to harm fellow humans. Alternatively, many others believe that this would encourage recidivism, reinforce illicit sexual practices, and make them more admissible. Allowing people to live out their darkest fantasies with sex robots can have a detrimental effect on society and stir up more danger for the vulnerable. But the arrival of sex robots has a distinguished opinion. Inventors like Santos argue that they can potentially replace prostitutes, reduce sex trafficking, and help lonely rejects, while critics say they objectify women and normalize sexism as well as rape culture.&amp;nbsp; Experts say that the increasingly life-like robots raise complex issues that should be considered by policymakers and the public- including whether the use of such products should be stimulated to curb prostitution and sex trafficking, for sex offenders, or people with disabilities.&amp;nbsp; Part 5: Connecting the Dots Could sexual intimacy with robots lead to pronounced social isolation? The majority of experts provide strong arguments that sex robots could lead to some form of a social void. It is contrary to what the manufactures of sex robots tell us. The CEO of RealBotix said that he has been making sex dolls for many years, especially to alleviate the vacuum of those who, for whatever reason, have problems relating to human intimacy. The public survey data shows mixed opinions.&amp;nbsp; Previously this year, Women of SexTech held a virtual event to discuss the impact of COVID-19 on the industry. The keynote speaker was Cindy Gallop, founder of the MakeLoveNotPorn company, who claimed in her speech that months of lockdown showed us that human relationships are irreplaceable. Technology is just a means to enhance the human experience. Gallop also stated that “it is only when things break down that new tech and ideas emerge.” The social isolation has created an utter context for SexTech to thrive. Unfortunately, nearly every facet of society today - public health organisations, school-based sex education, financial institutions, investment and venture capital, major social media companies- still forbid this very reality. At best, it’s considered an indulgence. At worst, sexual wellness and technology are routinely grouped along with pornography, illegal drugs, weapons, and gambling. Therefore, it operates underground in the gloom. Honestly, investors are apprehensive, which means they sometimes do not understand the problems to be solved. Or they answer to more conservative institutions that won’t invest in 'vice.' Stigma keeps them away from SexTech.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Big Daddy’s Gamble: the Indian Securities Regulator Challenges India’s Oligarch</title>
      <link href="/Big-Daddy-s-Gamble-the-Indian-Securities-Regulator-Challenges-India-s-Oligarch" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Big Daddy’s Gamble: the Indian Securities Regulator Challenges India's Oligarch" />
      <published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Big-Daddy-s-Gamble-the-Indian-Securities-Regulator-Challenges-India-s-Oligarch</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Big-Daddy-s-Gamble-the-Indian-Securities-Regulator-Challenges-India-s-Oligarch">&lt;p&gt;On January 1, 2021, the Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI) slapped a fine on the largest company in India by market capitalisation, i.e. Reliance Industries Limited (RIL), and its Chairman and Managing Director Mukesh Ambani of ₹250 million and ₹150 million respectively, along with two other entities, for manipulative trading in the shares of the erstwhile Reliance Petroleum Limited (RPL) in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what activity did RIL engage in to receive a penalty from the market regulator?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reliance Petroleum Limited (RPL) was a refinery, partly owned by RIL, which later got merged with the latter in 2009. However, the conglomerate got itself under the radar of the watchdog for the transaction that occurred between the company and its agents in November, 2007, in the cash and futures segment of the secondary market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RIL had decided to sell off its 4.1% stake in RPL. According to SEBI, in order to make undue gains from the sale, the former had entered into an agreement with 12 agents, who booked large short positions of the refinery’s shares in the futures market. Short positions refer to a situation when a trader sells the security first with the intention of repurchasing it later at a lower price, hence the steeper the decline, greater is the profit for the trader. Following this, in the last ten minutes of the trading session of November 29, 2007, RIL sold close to 20 million RPL shares. This large scale selling triggered mass panic and within a moment’s notice, the stock price collapsed.&amp;nbsp; Interestingly, it also happened to be the same day that the futures contracts were meant to pay-out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, SEBI contends that RIL and the agents colluded together in a bid to make a profit estimated to be around ₹44.7 billion off of this transaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selling of securities by promoters in the capital markets in order to raise cash is a widely accepted practice, however, this act of secretive plotting that can distort the natural price discovery system in the market and cheat investors via non-transparent mechanisms is impermissible and against the objectives of the SEBI or any securities regulator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SEBI’s adjudicating officer B J Dilip said, “&lt;em&gt;any manipulation in the volume or price of securities always erodes investor confidence in the market when investors find themselves at the receiving end of market manipulators&lt;/em&gt;.” He further added, “&lt;em&gt;In the instant case, the general investors were not aware that the entity behind the above F&amp;amp;O segment transactions was RIL. The execution of the... fraudulent trades affected the price of the RPL securities in both cash and F&amp;amp;O [Futures and Options] segments and harmed the interests of other investors&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SEBI order states that Mukesh Ambani as the Managing Director of RIL was equally involved in the malpractice. Apart from the conglomerate and its chairman, SEBI also imposed penalties of ₹2 million and ₹1 million on Navi Mumbai SEZ Pvt Ltd and Mumbai SEZ Ltd respectively, both promoted by Anand Jain, a former member of the Reliance Group, for providing margin payments for the agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In March 2017, the market watchdog had ordered RIL and other entities to disgorge ₹4.47 billion in the RPL’s case, against which the latter appealed in the Securities Appellate Tribunal (SAT). The verdict announced by the tribunal in November 2020 was against the appellant. However, the petrochemicals to telecommunication multinational corporation said that it would appeal against the Tribunal’s ruling in the Indian Supreme Court.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not the first time that RIL and a government entity were at loggerheads. In 2014, the Indian market regulator had imposed a fine of ₹1.3 million on the corporation for non-disclosure of a key earnings ratio, which would have impacted investors’ evaluation on the shares. In 2018, the RIL-led consortium of BP Plc and Niko Resources won an award against the Indian government in international arbitration. The case related to a dispute over a penalty of $1.55 billion slapped by the Indian government on the petrochemical companies for allegedly drawing gas from the Oil and Natural Gas Corporation or ONGC’s (a state-owned oil and gas concern) block in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SEBI was established with the purpose of protecting investors and the development and regulation of capital markets in India. Over the years, it has evolved to meet its objective and has always taken a strong stance against any form of malpractice. However, it is essential that in order to mitigate any future wrongdoing, it penalises defaulters such that cost in fulfilling the punishment supersedes the gain.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On January 1, 2021, the Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI) slapped a fine on the largest company in India by market capitalisation, i.e. Reliance Industries Limited (RIL), and its Chairman and Managing Director Mukesh Ambani of ₹250 million and ₹150 million respectively, along with two other entities, for manipulative trading in the shares of the erstwhile Reliance Petroleum Limited (RPL) in 2007. So, what activity did RIL engage in to receive a penalty from the market regulator?&amp;nbsp; Reliance Petroleum Limited (RPL) was a refinery, partly owned by RIL, which later got merged with the latter in 2009. However, the conglomerate got itself under the radar of the watchdog for the transaction that occurred between the company and its agents in November, 2007, in the cash and futures segment of the secondary market. RIL had decided to sell off its 4.1% stake in RPL. According to SEBI, in order to make undue gains from the sale, the former had entered into an agreement with 12 agents, who booked large short positions of the refinery’s shares in the futures market. Short positions refer to a situation when a trader sells the security first with the intention of repurchasing it later at a lower price, hence the steeper the decline, greater is the profit for the trader. Following this, in the last ten minutes of the trading session of November 29, 2007, RIL sold close to 20 million RPL shares. This large scale selling triggered mass panic and within a moment’s notice, the stock price collapsed.&amp;nbsp; Interestingly, it also happened to be the same day that the futures contracts were meant to pay-out. So, SEBI contends that RIL and the agents colluded together in a bid to make a profit estimated to be around ₹44.7 billion off of this transaction. Selling of securities by promoters in the capital markets in order to raise cash is a widely accepted practice, however, this act of secretive plotting that can distort the natural price discovery system in the market and cheat investors via non-transparent mechanisms is impermissible and against the objectives of the SEBI or any securities regulator. SEBI’s adjudicating officer B J Dilip said, “any manipulation in the volume or price of securities always erodes investor confidence in the market when investors find themselves at the receiving end of market manipulators.” He further added, “In the instant case, the general investors were not aware that the entity behind the above F&amp;amp;O segment transactions was RIL. The execution of the... fraudulent trades affected the price of the RPL securities in both cash and F&amp;amp;O [Futures and Options] segments and harmed the interests of other investors.” The SEBI order states that Mukesh Ambani as the Managing Director of RIL was equally involved in the malpractice. Apart from the conglomerate and its chairman, SEBI also imposed penalties of ₹2 million and ₹1 million on Navi Mumbai SEZ Pvt Ltd and Mumbai SEZ Ltd respectively, both promoted by Anand Jain, a former member of the Reliance Group, for providing margin payments for the agents. In March 2017, the market watchdog had ordered RIL and other entities to disgorge ₹4.47 billion in the RPL’s case, against which the latter appealed in the Securities Appellate Tribunal (SAT). The verdict announced by the tribunal in November 2020 was against the appellant. However, the petrochemicals to telecommunication multinational corporation said that it would appeal against the Tribunal’s ruling in the Indian Supreme Court.&amp;nbsp; This is not the first time that RIL and a government entity were at loggerheads. In 2014, the Indian market regulator had imposed a fine of ₹1.3 million on the corporation for non-disclosure of a key earnings ratio, which would have impacted investors’ evaluation on the shares. In 2018, the RIL-led consortium of BP Plc and Niko Resources won an award against the Indian government in international arbitration. The case related to a dispute over a penalty of $1.55 billion slapped by the Indian government on the petrochemical companies for allegedly drawing gas from the Oil and Natural Gas Corporation or ONGC’s (a state-owned oil and gas concern) block in 2016. SEBI was established with the purpose of protecting investors and the development and regulation of capital markets in India. Over the years, it has evolved to meet its objective and has always taken a strong stance against any form of malpractice. However, it is essential that in order to mitigate any future wrongdoing, it penalises defaulters such that cost in fulfilling the punishment supersedes the gain.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">11.11 - The Singles’ Date</title>
      <link href="/11-11-The-Singles-Date" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="11.11 - The Singles’ Date" />
      <published>2020-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/11-11-The-Singles-Date</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/11-11-The-Singles-Date">&lt;p&gt;China is one of the world’s biggest powerhouses in innovation and technology. While the country has its own set of laws, it has a holiday that not many people around the globe know about- the &lt;em&gt;Singles’ Day&lt;/em&gt;! It might sound peculiar, but it is a huge part of modern Chinese culture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Singles’ Day&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Double 11&lt;/em&gt;, originally called&lt;em&gt; Bachelors’ Day&lt;/em&gt;, is celebrated on November 11. It is a Chinese commercial holiday to celebrate being romantically unattached and paradoxically, turns out to be the largest physical retail and online shopping day of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Genesis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The narrative behind the Singles’ Day is pretty nice. It originated at Nanjing University in 1993. A group of lonely, yet positive students decided that instead of lamenting their lack of a significant other, they would celebrate being single. The reasoning? 11.11 looks like four, single sticks, strung together trying to make the most out of their time. The anti-Valentine’s Day celebration of singledom caught on and spread across universities throughout China, generally characterised by fun and harmless events. With the widespread use of social media, the day has become increasingly popular within contemporary Chinese culture and society.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alibaba’s Blockbuster Growth&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alibaba’s co-founder Jack Ma instituted the first Singles’ Day sale in 2009, laying the foundation for the highest-grossing shopping day of the year in the world. In 2012, the e-commerce company officially trademarked ‘Double 11’. Next in 2017, Alibaba’s mobile wallet app Alipay broke the record for the greatest number of transactions per second, whoa!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would not be Singles’ Day without Alibaba having some great deals available. This year, the company’s annual sales frenzy broke records again by raking in roughly $75 billion. The total includes an earlier three-day period that was added to boost post-pandemic sales. The company claimed that, compared to the same timeframe as last year, this year’s haul represents an increase of 26%. Chinese consumers, who already buy about 30% of the nation’s retail purchase online, have become more reliant on e-commerce.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, Alibaba also held a ‘Go Global 11.11 Pitch Fest’ aimed at small and medium-sized US brands, offering them a chance to be spotlighted during the event. Besides that, the company has been trying to involve more foreign brands globally. In 2019, Americans commanded the second-highest sales among importers, behind Japan but ahead of South Korea, Australia, and Germany.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Undoubtedly, Alibaba makes stupendous efforts to hype up Double 11 with its extravagant, rather over-the-top countdown gala. It featured appearances from celebrities such as Nicole Kidman, Kobe Bryant, Scarlett Johansson, Mariah Carey, Pharrell Williams, Miranda Kerr, Jessie J, Lionel Messi, and Taylor Swift in the preceding years. Pop star Katy Perry, who has performed at the event before, made an appearance at the company’s gala this season, albeit via a live stream, as travel restrictions on outside visitors remain in place in China.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though many other online platforms and stores take part in Singles’ Day, it is still closely tied to Alibaba.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crazy Sale&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For brands and retailers scrambling to recover from months of shuttered shops and consumers hunkered down indoors, the profitable Chinese shopper is a much-needed bright spot. It is estimated that the participation of luxury brands has doubled on Singles’ Day, as millions of Chinese who have been unable to travel overseas on shopping trips go online for what experts are dubbing ‘revenge spending’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, the buzz of Singles’ Day led the retailers worldwide to opt for special promotions to boost sales. &lt;em&gt;Uniqlo&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Foot Locker&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Best Buy&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Steam&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Target&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Alibaba&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Expedia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Topman&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Brooklinen&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Levi’s&lt;/em&gt;, and numerous other companies offered massive deals and discounts, orbiting the holiday. Three million workers, aided by 4,000 planes and ships got ready for the world’s biggest online sale in the current year- with ‘revenge spending’ tipping to be one of this year’s biggest trends.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A survey by market research firm &lt;em&gt;Oliver Wyman&lt;/em&gt; found out that 86% of Chinese consumers were willing to spend the same as or more than what they did during last year’s Singles’ Day. The remaining 14% of survey respondents said that they had spent less on Singles’ Day, because of the unprecedented times.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On The Outside&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Singles’ Day has become the most lucrative shopping holiday in several places outside China as well. The holiday has particularly grown in Southeast Asia, with customers in Indonesia, Singapore, Malaysia, Thailand, and Vietnam, who are the recipient of the huge discounts offered by Alibaba’s subsidiary Lazada. In the United Kingdom, Singles’ Day is marked on March 11. It was initiated by a group of internationally recognised dating experts to help singles embrace themselves. Furthermore, Swedish Electronic retailer &lt;em&gt;Elgiganten&lt;/em&gt; promoted a Singles’ Day campaign in Norway before implementing it in the other Nordic countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;MediaMarkt&lt;/em&gt;, a German Company, also promotes this day in its stores. Conversely, Belgian &lt;em&gt;MediaMarkt&lt;/em&gt; also participates but the reactions have been negative. It is because November 11 is the anniversary of the Armistice of 1918 that ended the First World War.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, awareness of Singles’ Day in New Zealand is still relatively low. According to a survey by &lt;em&gt;PriceSpy&lt;/em&gt;, around 73% of Kiwis have never heard of this day, with just 12% of Kiwis reporting to have brought something during the world’s biggest shopping bonanza.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Singles’ Day will continue to grow in importance for retailers outside of China, particularly in the United Kingdom, which last year grew their discounting assortment to mirror the United States. In the light of the pandemic and feel of 2020, upbeat marketing angles that touch on celebrating and treating yourself are drawing attention globally.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An Antidote to Valentine’s Day&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally on Singles’ Day, people buy things, take themselves out for dinner, watch movies, sheepishly ruin dates, hang out with their other single friends and delve into the gratifying embrace of self-love. This phenomenon of retail therapy has resulted in oodles of sales, easily surpassing Black Friday and Cyber Monday combined.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certainly, it is fun getting gifts on your birthday, Christmas and on other occasions- but how can people know what you actually want? On this day, you get to shop for yourself. I’m not just talking about buying yourself flowers or a decent meal. It is the day to show yourself some real love and appreciation. Go on, indulge. Splurge on those jeans you have been eying, or fancy wine club membership- you have earned it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Retailers all over the world are instigating exclusive, singles-oriented deals in Alibaba’s footsteps. Grab the benefit of special promotions- ticket for 1 to Fiji? Yes, please.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samakshi Garg</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">China is one of the world’s biggest powerhouses in innovation and technology. While the country has its own set of laws, it has a holiday that not many people around the globe know about- the Singles’ Day! It might sound peculiar, but it is a huge part of modern Chinese culture.&amp;nbsp; The Singles’ Day or Double 11, originally called Bachelors’ Day, is celebrated on November 11. It is a Chinese commercial holiday to celebrate being romantically unattached and paradoxically, turns out to be the largest physical retail and online shopping day of the year. Genesis The narrative behind the Singles’ Day is pretty nice. It originated at Nanjing University in 1993. A group of lonely, yet positive students decided that instead of lamenting their lack of a significant other, they would celebrate being single. The reasoning? 11.11 looks like four, single sticks, strung together trying to make the most out of their time. The anti-Valentine’s Day celebration of singledom caught on and spread across universities throughout China, generally characterised by fun and harmless events. With the widespread use of social media, the day has become increasingly popular within contemporary Chinese culture and society.&amp;nbsp; Alibaba’s Blockbuster Growth Alibaba’s co-founder Jack Ma instituted the first Singles’ Day sale in 2009, laying the foundation for the highest-grossing shopping day of the year in the world. In 2012, the e-commerce company officially trademarked ‘Double 11’. Next in 2017, Alibaba’s mobile wallet app Alipay broke the record for the greatest number of transactions per second, whoa!&amp;nbsp; It would not be Singles’ Day without Alibaba having some great deals available. This year, the company’s annual sales frenzy broke records again by raking in roughly $75 billion. The total includes an earlier three-day period that was added to boost post-pandemic sales. The company claimed that, compared to the same timeframe as last year, this year’s haul represents an increase of 26%. Chinese consumers, who already buy about 30% of the nation’s retail purchase online, have become more reliant on e-commerce.&amp;nbsp; This year, Alibaba also held a ‘Go Global 11.11 Pitch Fest’ aimed at small and medium-sized US brands, offering them a chance to be spotlighted during the event. Besides that, the company has been trying to involve more foreign brands globally. In 2019, Americans commanded the second-highest sales among importers, behind Japan but ahead of South Korea, Australia, and Germany.&amp;nbsp; Undoubtedly, Alibaba makes stupendous efforts to hype up Double 11 with its extravagant, rather over-the-top countdown gala. It featured appearances from celebrities such as Nicole Kidman, Kobe Bryant, Scarlett Johansson, Mariah Carey, Pharrell Williams, Miranda Kerr, Jessie J, Lionel Messi, and Taylor Swift in the preceding years. Pop star Katy Perry, who has performed at the event before, made an appearance at the company’s gala this season, albeit via a live stream, as travel restrictions on outside visitors remain in place in China.&amp;nbsp; Even though many other online platforms and stores take part in Singles’ Day, it is still closely tied to Alibaba.&amp;nbsp; Crazy Sale For brands and retailers scrambling to recover from months of shuttered shops and consumers hunkered down indoors, the profitable Chinese shopper is a much-needed bright spot. It is estimated that the participation of luxury brands has doubled on Singles’ Day, as millions of Chinese who have been unable to travel overseas on shopping trips go online for what experts are dubbing ‘revenge spending’.&amp;nbsp; Unsurprisingly, the buzz of Singles’ Day led the retailers worldwide to opt for special promotions to boost sales. Uniqlo, Foot Locker, Best Buy, Steam, Target, Alibaba, Expedia, Topman, Brooklinen, Levi’s, and numerous other companies offered massive deals and discounts, orbiting the holiday. Three million workers, aided by 4,000 planes and ships got ready for the world’s biggest online sale in the current year- with ‘revenge spending’ tipping to be one of this year’s biggest trends.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; A survey by market research firm Oliver Wyman found out that 86% of Chinese consumers were willing to spend the same as or more than what they did during last year’s Singles’ Day. The remaining 14% of survey respondents said that they had spent less on Singles’ Day, because of the unprecedented times.&amp;nbsp; On The Outside Singles’ Day has become the most lucrative shopping holiday in several places outside China as well. The holiday has particularly grown in Southeast Asia, with customers in Indonesia, Singapore, Malaysia, Thailand, and Vietnam, who are the recipient of the huge discounts offered by Alibaba’s subsidiary Lazada. In the United Kingdom, Singles’ Day is marked on March 11. It was initiated by a group of internationally recognised dating experts to help singles embrace themselves. Furthermore, Swedish Electronic retailer Elgiganten promoted a Singles’ Day campaign in Norway before implementing it in the other Nordic countries.&amp;nbsp; MediaMarkt, a German Company, also promotes this day in its stores. Conversely, Belgian MediaMarkt also participates but the reactions have been negative. It is because November 11 is the anniversary of the Armistice of 1918 that ended the First World War.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, awareness of Singles’ Day in New Zealand is still relatively low. According to a survey by PriceSpy, around 73% of Kiwis have never heard of this day, with just 12% of Kiwis reporting to have brought something during the world’s biggest shopping bonanza.&amp;nbsp; Singles’ Day will continue to grow in importance for retailers outside of China, particularly in the United Kingdom, which last year grew their discounting assortment to mirror the United States. In the light of the pandemic and feel of 2020, upbeat marketing angles that touch on celebrating and treating yourself are drawing attention globally.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; An Antidote to Valentine’s Day&amp;nbsp; Traditionally on Singles’ Day, people buy things, take themselves out for dinner, watch movies, sheepishly ruin dates, hang out with their other single friends and delve into the gratifying embrace of self-love. This phenomenon of retail therapy has resulted in oodles of sales, easily surpassing Black Friday and Cyber Monday combined.&amp;nbsp; Certainly, it is fun getting gifts on your birthday, Christmas and on other occasions- but how can people know what you actually want? On this day, you get to shop for yourself. I’m not just talking about buying yourself flowers or a decent meal. It is the day to show yourself some real love and appreciation. Go on, indulge. Splurge on those jeans you have been eying, or fancy wine club membership- you have earned it.&amp;nbsp; Retailers all over the world are instigating exclusive, singles-oriented deals in Alibaba’s footsteps. Grab the benefit of special promotions- ticket for 1 to Fiji? Yes, please.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Scams &amp;amp; Frauds: Serial Killers of the Economy</title>
      <link href="/Scams-Frauds-Serial-Killers-of-the-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scams &amp; Frauds: Serial Killers of the Economy" />
      <published>2020-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Scams-Frauds-Serial-Killers-of-the-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Scams-Frauds-Serial-Killers-of-the-Economy">&lt;p&gt;The Indian economy has been growing at an unprecedented rate in recent times. Various factors have culminated together to lead to such growth. No doubt, financial institutions are one of the most important aspects and thus referred to as the ‘backbones of the economy’. Banks, co-operatives, and other financial institutions look into the monetary affairs of a state, thus making their efficient functioning essential for an economy’s healthy growth. However, in recent times, these holy institutes have been marred by impious activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They do face errors and issues due to a number of reasons but it is of no serious concern until it is taken care of. There have been times when these issues and errors slipped out of hand and created chaos among the public. These major errors can also be termed as ‘banking frauds’. Banking frauds are referred to the illegal and unethical means used by one party to extract or misuse funds, assets or even property owned by a financial institution.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India has seen a spike in these frauds recently and the reasons are still unknown. The cases of Vijay Mallya and Nirav Modi are two major examples of such frauds. Mallya is accused of fraud and money laundering and owes an estimated ₹90 billion to 17 Indian banks. The Nirav Modi-PNB scam is one of the largest in India’s banking history. It involves undertaking an estimated amount of ₹110 billion from the Punjab National Bank, Brady House branch located in Mumbai. Both accused escaped the country and the cases are still under trial. The money has not been returned yet and thus the banks had to lose out on such a huge amount that belongs to their account holders in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frauds are usually done by individuals for petty self-gains but the involvement of people within the banks is definite. It is possible to plan and execute a crime so huge only when you play around with the loopholes existing in the policies and thereby messing the entire functioning of the system. This usually requires help from the people working within the institution and in most cases of frauds, employees are involved. The advent of technology can also be one reason which facilitates these frauds. Other reasons can be concentration of power at certain levels or giving leeway during legal procedures. Ideally, accounts with huge exposures and capital need to be checked frequently with the use of forensic due diligence infrastructure. The decision making regarding huge loans should be done by a committee rather than a single person. Monitoring the trail of money will also reduce the risk of laundering cases.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question still remains: how do these frauds impact the public or even the economy?&amp;nbsp; They cause a slowdown in the growth of the economy which weakens the economy and discourages foreign investments. The money being stolen or laundered in these cases is the public fund. The minute public loses trust in a bank, it leads to even greater losses for the banks, and the bank might even go bankrupt. Banks play an important and integral part of the monetary system. They affect the cash flow, money demand, and various other factors. The moment their functioning is disturbed by these frauds, it definitely trickles down to other areas as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frauds and scams can surely be avoided at various levels and it is important that even governments provide guidelines to minimise the risks. Strict action against the offenders should be taken to set a precedence for the public. It is a huge task to maintain transparency at every step but at the same time, banks should come forward and take responsibility and accountability for the mishaps. The trust between the public and these financial institutions has to be maintained for the smooth functioning of the economy. Banking institutions are vital and thus a step towards more secure functioning needs to be taken to avoid these circumstances. It is tedious but definitely not impossible. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Indian economy has been growing at an unprecedented rate in recent times. Various factors have culminated together to lead to such growth. No doubt, financial institutions are one of the most important aspects and thus referred to as the ‘backbones of the economy’. Banks, co-operatives, and other financial institutions look into the monetary affairs of a state, thus making their efficient functioning essential for an economy’s healthy growth. However, in recent times, these holy institutes have been marred by impious activities. They do face errors and issues due to a number of reasons but it is of no serious concern until it is taken care of. There have been times when these issues and errors slipped out of hand and created chaos among the public. These major errors can also be termed as ‘banking frauds’. Banking frauds are referred to the illegal and unethical means used by one party to extract or misuse funds, assets or even property owned by a financial institution.&amp;nbsp; India has seen a spike in these frauds recently and the reasons are still unknown. The cases of Vijay Mallya and Nirav Modi are two major examples of such frauds. Mallya is accused of fraud and money laundering and owes an estimated ₹90 billion to 17 Indian banks. The Nirav Modi-PNB scam is one of the largest in India’s banking history. It involves undertaking an estimated amount of ₹110 billion from the Punjab National Bank, Brady House branch located in Mumbai. Both accused escaped the country and the cases are still under trial. The money has not been returned yet and thus the banks had to lose out on such a huge amount that belongs to their account holders in the first place. Frauds are usually done by individuals for petty self-gains but the involvement of people within the banks is definite. It is possible to plan and execute a crime so huge only when you play around with the loopholes existing in the policies and thereby messing the entire functioning of the system. This usually requires help from the people working within the institution and in most cases of frauds, employees are involved. The advent of technology can also be one reason which facilitates these frauds. Other reasons can be concentration of power at certain levels or giving leeway during legal procedures. Ideally, accounts with huge exposures and capital need to be checked frequently with the use of forensic due diligence infrastructure. The decision making regarding huge loans should be done by a committee rather than a single person. Monitoring the trail of money will also reduce the risk of laundering cases.&amp;nbsp; The question still remains: how do these frauds impact the public or even the economy?&amp;nbsp; They cause a slowdown in the growth of the economy which weakens the economy and discourages foreign investments. The money being stolen or laundered in these cases is the public fund. The minute public loses trust in a bank, it leads to even greater losses for the banks, and the bank might even go bankrupt. Banks play an important and integral part of the monetary system. They affect the cash flow, money demand, and various other factors. The moment their functioning is disturbed by these frauds, it definitely trickles down to other areas as well.&amp;nbsp; Frauds and scams can surely be avoided at various levels and it is important that even governments provide guidelines to minimise the risks. Strict action against the offenders should be taken to set a precedence for the public. It is a huge task to maintain transparency at every step but at the same time, banks should come forward and take responsibility and accountability for the mishaps. The trust between the public and these financial institutions has to be maintained for the smooth functioning of the economy. Banking institutions are vital and thus a step towards more secure functioning needs to be taken to avoid these circumstances. It is tedious but definitely not impossible.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Economics of IPL</title>
      <link href="/Economics-of-IPL" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Economics of IPL" />
      <published>2020-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Economics-of-IPL</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Economics-of-IPL">&lt;p&gt;Cricket is something that is pious in India. Indians never fail to boast of the Indian cricket team and wear it as the most decorated belt. After a standby of more than five months, Board of Cricket Control in India's (BCCI) most awaited spectacle, the Indian Premier League (IPL), has been charming cricket crowds over the world from the latter half of September. In a world scarred by COVID-19, the 2020 version of IPL is being played in the UAE, without the gigantic groups that typically delude the stadiums. Be that as it may, fans need not stress as they will have the option to watch their favourite teams in the UAE from the peace and comfort of their homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all know with IPL, comes frenzied Indians along with a crazy IPL sentiment amongst all the cricket fans. As all the IPL teams are owned by business owners, it is imperative that they work on certain economics apart from providing leisure and fun-filled moments to the Indians.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of IPL was brought in by Lalit Modi who after watching the English Premier League (EPL) was inspired to do something on these lines in India. 10 years down the lane, IPL contributes upwards of 60% revenue to the BCCI in just a span of fewer than 2 months (53 days). The excess surplus which BCCI garners from IPL is further used for improving the game’s infrastructure and other heads. Hence, IPL has proved itself by hitting two arrows (economically and mentally) with just one concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all must have wondered that the IPL prize money for the ultimate winner is just ₹200 million (which has been further downsized by another ₹100 million in 2020) but Virat Kohli was bought for ₹170 million followed by Pat Cummins who was bought for ₹155 million. The main question, how can someone spend hundreds of millions on a single player but the prize money is just ₹20 million? This article will primarily deal with the economics of IPL and talk about how an IPL team earns revenue.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary source of money generation for an IPL team is its media rights. &lt;em&gt;Star India&lt;/em&gt; paid a whopping ₹163 billion for a five-year contract with relation to media rights. Every year, &lt;em&gt;Star India&lt;/em&gt; pays ₹32 billion to the BCCI. The broadcaster further sells the rights to different media companies geographically. The amount which the broadcaster gives to the BCCI is further distributed between the teams in a weighted average manner. The teams with higher ranking and higher viewership get a bigger chunk and vice versa. For some teams, media rights revenues account for more than 60% of their revenue. Therefore, media rights form a sizeable chunk of revenue earned by every team.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second most important source is sponsorship rights. The BCCI has signed a five-month sponsorship deal with gaming firm &lt;em&gt;Dream11&lt;/em&gt;, valued at ₹2.2 billion which is half of what &lt;em&gt;Vivo&lt;/em&gt; paid in 2019, but due to Indo-Chinese tensions, it had to back out. Other than that, &lt;em&gt;Cred&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Unacademy&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Tata Motors&lt;/em&gt; were roped in for official partners which paid BCCI to the tune of ₹1.2 billion. There are a plethora of sponsors like &lt;em&gt;Jio&lt;/em&gt;, the logo of which is seen on almost all the teams’ jerseys followed by &lt;em&gt;BKT&lt;/em&gt; which is present on six teams’ jerseys. The mechanism for this is, all the proceeds from the sponsors get collected in a central pool, which after deducting a certain cut for the BCCI, is equally distributed amongst all the teams. A part of this money is also contributed to the prize money as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now comes brand sponsorships, which also form an integral part of a team’s revenue. Groups tie-up with associations to advance brands that pay them exorbitant amounts of money. The advancement is done in two structures, through print media, and through advertorials. We can see a plethora of colourful logos on every team’s jersey with a few of them on the track pants and even on caps. For instance: principal sponsors of one of the teams are &lt;em&gt;Muthoot Group&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;India Cements,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Gulf Oil&lt;/em&gt;. These groups can ask any player of the team to advertise for them and the players have to adhere to it without any naysaying.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revenue generated from the sale of tickets for matches forms another major source of income for the IPL franchises. Each franchise is entitled to a minimum of 7 home matches. The ticket prices are fixed by team owners. A small portion of tickets are offered to sponsors and the BCCI, the rest goes into the team’s wallet. An IPL franchise gets to sell around 80% of the tickets for its home games while the rest is kept reserved for sponsors and BCCI. This is one of the few mediums of income where fans and franchises are directly involved in the financial transaction. This income may go through the roofs in high voltage matches when the stadium is jam-packed. Ticket revenue reportedly forms around 10% of revenue for IPL franchises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The penultimate source among other sources is revenue generated from merchandising. There is a lot of potential which is yet to be unleashed from merchandising. All the IPL teams have their own brand value, through more penetration and adoption of the teams’ merchandising, the brand quotient can drastically increase. Lastly, the most obvious source is the prize money which has been pegged at ₹100 million this year followed by ₹60 million for the runners-up and ₹40 million for the third and fourth-placed teams.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the world where people have transformed from citizens to netizens, IPL 2020 saw an increase in the participation of startups instead of conventional businesses. Despite &lt;em&gt;Dream11&lt;/em&gt; being the lead sponsor, BCCI lost around ₹13 billion this year. During 2019 IPL, BCCI amassed revenue of ₹50 billion compared to revenue of around ₹37 billion this year. This can be related to a lot of sponsors backing out due to slow business activity resulting in the new sponsors coming at a lower price. Another factor can be no jam-packed stadiums this time. Initially what stemmed off as an idea, has now held the nerves of all the Indians and the craze doesn’t stop here, it increases with every coming IPL.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aditya Khandelwal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Cricket is something that is pious in India. Indians never fail to boast of the Indian cricket team and wear it as the most decorated belt. After a standby of more than five months, Board of Cricket Control in India's (BCCI) most awaited spectacle, the Indian Premier League (IPL), has been charming cricket crowds over the world from the latter half of September. In a world scarred by COVID-19, the 2020 version of IPL is being played in the UAE, without the gigantic groups that typically delude the stadiums. Be that as it may, fans need not stress as they will have the option to watch their favourite teams in the UAE from the peace and comfort of their homes. We all know with IPL, comes frenzied Indians along with a crazy IPL sentiment amongst all the cricket fans. As all the IPL teams are owned by business owners, it is imperative that they work on certain economics apart from providing leisure and fun-filled moments to the Indians.&amp;nbsp; The concept of IPL was brought in by Lalit Modi who after watching the English Premier League (EPL) was inspired to do something on these lines in India. 10 years down the lane, IPL contributes upwards of 60% revenue to the BCCI in just a span of fewer than 2 months (53 days). The excess surplus which BCCI garners from IPL is further used for improving the game’s infrastructure and other heads. Hence, IPL has proved itself by hitting two arrows (economically and mentally) with just one concept. We all must have wondered that the IPL prize money for the ultimate winner is just ₹200 million (which has been further downsized by another ₹100 million in 2020) but Virat Kohli was bought for ₹170 million followed by Pat Cummins who was bought for ₹155 million. The main question, how can someone spend hundreds of millions on a single player but the prize money is just ₹20 million? This article will primarily deal with the economics of IPL and talk about how an IPL team earns revenue.&amp;nbsp; The primary source of money generation for an IPL team is its media rights. Star India paid a whopping ₹163 billion for a five-year contract with relation to media rights. Every year, Star India pays ₹32 billion to the BCCI. The broadcaster further sells the rights to different media companies geographically. The amount which the broadcaster gives to the BCCI is further distributed between the teams in a weighted average manner. The teams with higher ranking and higher viewership get a bigger chunk and vice versa. For some teams, media rights revenues account for more than 60% of their revenue. Therefore, media rights form a sizeable chunk of revenue earned by every team.&amp;nbsp; The second most important source is sponsorship rights. The BCCI has signed a five-month sponsorship deal with gaming firm Dream11, valued at ₹2.2 billion which is half of what Vivo paid in 2019, but due to Indo-Chinese tensions, it had to back out. Other than that, Cred, Unacademy and Tata Motors were roped in for official partners which paid BCCI to the tune of ₹1.2 billion. There are a plethora of sponsors like Jio, the logo of which is seen on almost all the teams’ jerseys followed by BKT which is present on six teams’ jerseys. The mechanism for this is, all the proceeds from the sponsors get collected in a central pool, which after deducting a certain cut for the BCCI, is equally distributed amongst all the teams. A part of this money is also contributed to the prize money as well.&amp;nbsp; Now comes brand sponsorships, which also form an integral part of a team’s revenue. Groups tie-up with associations to advance brands that pay them exorbitant amounts of money. The advancement is done in two structures, through print media, and through advertorials. We can see a plethora of colourful logos on every team’s jersey with a few of them on the track pants and even on caps. For instance: principal sponsors of one of the teams are Muthoot Group, India Cements, and Gulf Oil. These groups can ask any player of the team to advertise for them and the players have to adhere to it without any naysaying.&amp;nbsp; Revenue generated from the sale of tickets for matches forms another major source of income for the IPL franchises. Each franchise is entitled to a minimum of 7 home matches. The ticket prices are fixed by team owners. A small portion of tickets are offered to sponsors and the BCCI, the rest goes into the team’s wallet. An IPL franchise gets to sell around 80% of the tickets for its home games while the rest is kept reserved for sponsors and BCCI. This is one of the few mediums of income where fans and franchises are directly involved in the financial transaction. This income may go through the roofs in high voltage matches when the stadium is jam-packed. Ticket revenue reportedly forms around 10% of revenue for IPL franchises. The penultimate source among other sources is revenue generated from merchandising. There is a lot of potential which is yet to be unleashed from merchandising. All the IPL teams have their own brand value, through more penetration and adoption of the teams’ merchandising, the brand quotient can drastically increase. Lastly, the most obvious source is the prize money which has been pegged at ₹100 million this year followed by ₹60 million for the runners-up and ₹40 million for the third and fourth-placed teams.&amp;nbsp; In the world where people have transformed from citizens to netizens, IPL 2020 saw an increase in the participation of startups instead of conventional businesses. Despite Dream11 being the lead sponsor, BCCI lost around ₹13 billion this year. During 2019 IPL, BCCI amassed revenue of ₹50 billion compared to revenue of around ₹37 billion this year. This can be related to a lot of sponsors backing out due to slow business activity resulting in the new sponsors coming at a lower price. Another factor can be no jam-packed stadiums this time. Initially what stemmed off as an idea, has now held the nerves of all the Indians and the craze doesn’t stop here, it increases with every coming IPL.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Derailing of the World’s Biggest IPO</title>
      <link href="/Derailing-of-the-World-s-Biggest-IPO" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Derailing of the World’s Biggest IPO" />
      <published>2020-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Derailing-of-the-World-s-Biggest-IPO</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Derailing-of-the-World-s-Biggest-IPO">&lt;p&gt;The IPO of &lt;em&gt;Ant Group&lt;/em&gt;, the world's most valuable unicorn- or billion-dollar unlisted tech firm- was all set for a $37 billion dual listing in Hong Kong and Shanghai's STAR Market in the first week of November until news of a halt in its listing process hit the market just 48 hours before its trading debut on both stock exchanges.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simultaneous listing of &lt;em&gt;Ant Group&lt;/em&gt;, the financial service arm of the e-commerce giant &lt;em&gt;Alibaba&lt;/em&gt;, could have been the world's largest IPO. It would have surpassed the record set by oil giant &lt;em&gt;Saudi Aramco's&lt;/em&gt; $29.4 billion float last December. The company could have been worth more than many global banks after its share sale. So what turn of events lead to the suspension of the massive size IPO?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2003, Jack Ma, co-founder of &lt;em&gt;Alibaba&lt;/em&gt; created &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/alipay-and-the-world/finally-after-15-years-weve-found-alipay-s-very-first-buyer-jiao-zhengzhong-33d2c663d4f2&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a service called &lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alipay&lt;/em&gt;. It helped e-commerce take off. Under his leadership, he spun the service out in 2011 as a separate entity- &lt;em&gt;Ant Group&lt;/em&gt;, setting off a tiff with &lt;em&gt;Yahoo&lt;/em&gt;, which was then a major &lt;em&gt;Alibaba&lt;/em&gt; investor.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alipay&lt;/em&gt; became the largest player in China's $62 trillion third-party mobile payments market. It has more than 730 million monthly users, more than twice the population of the United States. &lt;em&gt;Ant &lt;/em&gt;says its systems processed 459,000 payments a second at the peak of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/11/11/technology/alibaba-singles-day.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Chinese shopping holiday&lt;/a&gt; in 2019 whereas &lt;em&gt;Visa&lt;/em&gt;, by contrast, says it can handle &lt;a href=&quot;https://usa.visa.com/dam/VCOM/download/corporate/media/visanet-technology/aboutvisafactsheet.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;65,000 transactions a second&lt;/a&gt;. Its wide range of functions include facilitating payments, granting loans, providing opportunities for investment and insurance, selling financial technology to enterprises, and much more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite being a fintech giant, the Shanghai stock exchange suspended the group’s IPO just 2 days before its trading debut, following which the company decided to halt the Hong Kong listing as well. The former stock exchange in a notice to the organisation stated that the company did not meet the “perquisites” owing to the changes in financial technology regulatory requirements.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new&lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2020/11/03/pulled-ant-group-ipo-costs-alibaba-nearly-60b-in-market-cap/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;s sent shock waves through&lt;/a&gt; the financial world, and other Chinese tech companies looking to raise capital. For months now, overseas exchanges have grown increasingly hostile towards Chinese firms, and exchanges within their home turf have offered solace. Retail investors alone bid a record of $3 trillion worth of institution’s shares in its twofold listing. However, this event is also a reminder of the challenges in their home country.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is believed that such scrutiny from regulators was to ensure the nation's financial stability and other related factors like privacy which is a concern all over the world. The fintech industry lies in a grey area, with not many regulations. The authorities were concerned about the increasing size and dominance of the company, and its possibility to jeopardize the country’s financial structure.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chinese foreign ministry spokesman Wang Wenbin said, &lt;em&gt;“The decision (of suspension of the IPO) is made by relevant exchange institutes based on laws to better safeguard capital market stability and protect investor rights and interests”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The loan segment forms a significant proportion of &lt;em&gt;Alipay&lt;/em&gt;’s business model where most of the credit risk is taken by banks, and hence the authorities were sceptical of this lending as it was done by an institution other than a bank. Hence, they wanted more involvement from the firm in the process and altered the requirement of maintaining capital reserve from 1% to almost 30%, which could effectively affect the group’s revenue stream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 weeks prior to the listing, China’s richest man, Jack Ma, who also is the largest shareholder of the fintech company made certain critical remarks about the regulatory framework not supporting fintech companies enough. Many also see it as a punishment for being so vocal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chinese government has always been a major participant in all aspects of the functioning of the nation. For years, the leadership has sought to facilitate the growth of its tech giants. Its internet restrictions also referred to as the 'Great Firewall', homegrown tech has been protected from foreign competitors and thus dominate the domestic market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take, for instance, &lt;em&gt;WeChat&lt;/em&gt;- the country’s alternative to social media sites like Facebook and Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this advantage to domestic firms comes at a cost, where they must never outgrow the regime’s grasp. The system has various measures to keep businesses in-check, such as the introduction of new laws and restrictions that it can impose on a whim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2017, &lt;em&gt;Tencent&lt;/em&gt; drew Beijing's ire after its &lt;em&gt;Honor of Kings&lt;/em&gt; gaming app was said to be too addictive and a few days later the government imposed sweeping reforms on the nations’ mobile gaming industry that included content and playing time restrictions. The most recent example could be the sudden imposition of restrictions on exporting ‘Artificial Intelligence’ technology, which immediately affected &lt;em&gt;ByteDance’s&lt;/em&gt; sale procedure to comply with the US’s threat to ban &lt;em&gt;TikTok&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This instance with &lt;em&gt;Ant Group&lt;/em&gt; should not be seen in isolation and more of such interferences could be expected in the future for tech firms. This could be a hurdle at a time when China faces extreme scrutiny over data privacy issues and aversion for coronavirus.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The IPO of Ant Group, the world's most valuable unicorn- or billion-dollar unlisted tech firm- was all set for a $37 billion dual listing in Hong Kong and Shanghai's STAR Market in the first week of November until news of a halt in its listing process hit the market just 48 hours before its trading debut on both stock exchanges.&amp;nbsp; Simultaneous listing of Ant Group, the financial service arm of the e-commerce giant Alibaba, could have been the world's largest IPO. It would have surpassed the record set by oil giant Saudi Aramco's $29.4 billion float last December. The company could have been worth more than many global banks after its share sale. So what turn of events lead to the suspension of the massive size IPO? In 2003, Jack Ma, co-founder of Alibaba created a service called Alipay. It helped e-commerce take off. Under his leadership, he spun the service out in 2011 as a separate entity- Ant Group, setting off a tiff with Yahoo, which was then a major Alibaba investor.&amp;nbsp; Alipay became the largest player in China's $62 trillion third-party mobile payments market. It has more than 730 million monthly users, more than twice the population of the United States. Ant says its systems processed 459,000 payments a second at the peak of a Chinese shopping holiday in 2019 whereas Visa, by contrast, says it can handle 65,000 transactions a second. Its wide range of functions include facilitating payments, granting loans, providing opportunities for investment and insurance, selling financial technology to enterprises, and much more. Despite being a fintech giant, the Shanghai stock exchange suspended the group’s IPO just 2 days before its trading debut, following which the company decided to halt the Hong Kong listing as well. The former stock exchange in a notice to the organisation stated that the company did not meet the “perquisites” owing to the changes in financial technology regulatory requirements.&amp;nbsp; The news sent shock waves through the financial world, and other Chinese tech companies looking to raise capital. For months now, overseas exchanges have grown increasingly hostile towards Chinese firms, and exchanges within their home turf have offered solace. Retail investors alone bid a record of $3 trillion worth of institution’s shares in its twofold listing. However, this event is also a reminder of the challenges in their home country.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; It is believed that such scrutiny from regulators was to ensure the nation's financial stability and other related factors like privacy which is a concern all over the world. The fintech industry lies in a grey area, with not many regulations. The authorities were concerned about the increasing size and dominance of the company, and its possibility to jeopardize the country’s financial structure.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Chinese foreign ministry spokesman Wang Wenbin said, “The decision (of suspension of the IPO) is made by relevant exchange institutes based on laws to better safeguard capital market stability and protect investor rights and interests”. The loan segment forms a significant proportion of Alipay’s business model where most of the credit risk is taken by banks, and hence the authorities were sceptical of this lending as it was done by an institution other than a bank. Hence, they wanted more involvement from the firm in the process and altered the requirement of maintaining capital reserve from 1% to almost 30%, which could effectively affect the group’s revenue stream. 2 weeks prior to the listing, China’s richest man, Jack Ma, who also is the largest shareholder of the fintech company made certain critical remarks about the regulatory framework not supporting fintech companies enough. Many also see it as a punishment for being so vocal.&amp;nbsp; The Chinese government has always been a major participant in all aspects of the functioning of the nation. For years, the leadership has sought to facilitate the growth of its tech giants. Its internet restrictions also referred to as the 'Great Firewall', homegrown tech has been protected from foreign competitors and thus dominate the domestic market. Take, for instance, WeChat- the country’s alternative to social media sites like Facebook and Twitter. However, this advantage to domestic firms comes at a cost, where they must never outgrow the regime’s grasp. The system has various measures to keep businesses in-check, such as the introduction of new laws and restrictions that it can impose on a whim. In 2017, Tencent drew Beijing's ire after its Honor of Kings gaming app was said to be too addictive and a few days later the government imposed sweeping reforms on the nations’ mobile gaming industry that included content and playing time restrictions. The most recent example could be the sudden imposition of restrictions on exporting ‘Artificial Intelligence’ technology, which immediately affected ByteDance’s sale procedure to comply with the US’s threat to ban TikTok.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; This instance with Ant Group should not be seen in isolation and more of such interferences could be expected in the future for tech firms. This could be a hurdle at a time when China faces extreme scrutiny over data privacy issues and aversion for coronavirus.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Teasing Bellies to Fill Pockets</title>
      <link href="/Teasing-Bellies-to-Fill-Pockets" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Teasing Bellies to Fill Pockets" />
      <published>2020-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Teasing-Bellies-to-Fill-Pockets</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Teasing-Bellies-to-Fill-Pockets">&lt;p&gt;All-you-can-eat (AYCE) restaurants charge a fixed price for access to food, and they allow customers to consume as much food as their heart desires at no extra charge. Simply put, consumers are charged a specified price regardless of how much food they consume. From “&lt;em&gt;Feast unlimited this Monday at Barbeque Nation; lunch at ₹399 and dinner at ₹499&lt;/em&gt;” to sell tandoori feasts in India, to “&lt;em&gt;$24.99 all you can eat buffets&lt;/em&gt;” in Las Vegas as a lure to bring hungry patrons into casinos, AYCE has its roots everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, managers may have several motivations for offering such flat-rate pricing. While some are driven by competitive pricing pressures that may lead to zero marginal cost of production, others seek to reduce costs such as labour by employing a smaller wait staff, made possible by the emphasis on self-service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have ever had an awful stomach after you thought you struck gold at the buffet, you might have just wondered how restaurants manage to keep up their bottom line while you think you seemingly rob them in broad daylight. As you can guess, it is definitely not a loss for the restaurants. They indeed make hefty profits from this scheme. Besides being an ingenious piece of marketing, such restaurants became so popular owing to their wide selection of food and to the freedom given to customers to choose their own portions. People skip their breakfast and lunch to have a buffet dinner. They come with the mentality that they are going to earn their value for money. But little do they know that they come out on the losing side of it, mostly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How then do buffets manage to create and maintain a winning environment whilst also keeping their customers elated?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To shed light on how this concept leaves restaurants with money requires an examination of some fundamental microeconomics, psychology and what magic a careful blend of both can do. The high-skilled and trained managers in the hotel industry have succeeded in hitting this sweet spot and manage to leverage customer satisfaction and generate profits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Law of Diminishing Marginal Utility&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A law inherent to every Econ 101 class. The crux is that the additional benefit we feel from consumption (be it of cake, cigarettes or coffee) decreases as we consume it. You won’t have the same satisfaction from the last bite you have as you have from the first time eating it (your fifth slice of pizza, although good, just doesn’t taste as good as the first). Additional utility (benefit) from the last slice of pizza will be less than that from the first and this goes on until you have a negative utility for each slice that you consume (nobody enjoys a 25th slice, probably). People go to the buffet with a set mentality of making the most of their money. They want to maximise their satisfaction i.e. eat till they drop. However, again with the prospect of an unlimited buffet, their greed takes over and once their satisfaction is maximum, it slowly becomes negative i.e. the satisfaction derived from the buffet initially rises, then becomes maximum, and then falls. This is nothing but the law of Diminishing Marginal Utility. This is why you see exasperated faces after a buffet when people overshoot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What this tells us is that no matter what the price paid for a buffet is, you can only continue eating until your satiation point is reached. We’ll see how restaurants are masters at taking you there, quickly and cheaply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sunk Costs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In economics and business decision-making, a sunk cost is one which is incurred and cannot be recovered. You’ve invested the money and nothing can be done to take it back. For this reason, sunk costs should not affect decision-making. If the money’s already gone then it should not be affecting our future decisions. But in reality, people let this influence them. People have a habit to chase their losses, unable to quit and move on. We see it predominantly among gamblers, always chasing a winning bet to recoup earlier mistakes. We also witness it in business, it’s the same reason that investors continue with a loss-making entity. They don’t see a world beyond their already sunk dollars. When we buy a ticket to a buffet, we also face the same dilemma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because a customer faces no marginal cost of consumption, conventional utility maximisation implies that he or she should continue to eat until the marginal utility of consumption reaches 0. Economic models of consumer behaviour commonly assume that the utility of consumption is unaffected by the price paid. Rather, the price affects consumption only through a budget constraint. So, in an AYCE setting, price should influence whether one chooses to eat at the restaurant, but it should not affect the amount of food one consumes. But various experiments and test results have proven that price determines the personal evaluation of certain food and indirectly affects consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Food and Brand Lab at Cornell University conducted an experiment to see how the price of a buffet influenced customers. They offered two groups of customers the same pizza buffet, and charged one group $4, while the other group was charged $8. The group who paid more was overwhelmingly more satisfied with the entire experience. We are driven by our personal conception of value for money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of revealing this is to demonstrate the sunk cost fallacy in an AYCE context. In an AYCE setting, price positively influences consumption. Additionally, consumption appears to be negatively related to individual evaluations of taste. In contrast to the standard utility model, this provides support to the notion that individuals consider price in evaluating their marginal utility of consumption, even when there is no marginal cost for additional consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more the buffet charges, the more you think the buffet is good. Hence, the buffet is charged more and you still think the buffet is good and within all this, restaurants jump in and book their profits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Concept of Bounded Rationality and the Bandwagon Effect&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bounded rationality is the idea that rationality is limited when individuals make decisions by the tractability of the decision problem, the cognitive limitations of the mind, and the time available to make the decision. It is similar to an inability to make a sagacious decision when bombarded with multitudes of options (as in a buffet) leading us unable to follow rational predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bandwagon effect is the tendency of an individual to acquire a particular style, behaviour or attitude because everyone else is doing it. It is a phenomenon whereby the rate of uptake of beliefs, ideas, fads and trends increases with respect to the proportion of others who have already done so. Usually, in a buffet, some items come out to be clear winners and almost everyone starts having more and more of the same, the customers recommend the same to the people they are having lunch/dinner with, who in turn again start having more of the product. This creates a bandwagon effect, people will quickly consume a few items thereby saving the restaurant’s cost on all others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When choices are abundant, rationality is limited, and people have a tendency to follow the bandwagon, the result is skewed option picking. Some dishes emerge to be the most wanted and are generally those that are in abundant supply. Usually, dishes that are cooked in large vessels with cheap ingredients. Hence the restaurant saves on the more expensive dishes and the cost is limited yet again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Economies of Scale&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economies of scale are cost advantages reaped by companies when production becomes efficient. Companies can achieve economies of scale by increasing production and lowering costs. The larger the business, the more the cost savings. Buffets are large production businesses. A restaurant buffet achieves economies of scale by producing in large quantities, spreading its costs over a larger number of dishes, even though it often demands a serious cut in food quality. Because of tight profit margins, the food quality becomes a second priority. However, this doesn’t matter, they have their footfall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to this, lesser personnel need to be deployed for a buffet. As a result, the restaurant makes large savings in employment costs. These overhead savings are one of the crucial areas in which buffets differ from traditional restaurants. That's because you are doing most of the work for them - and paying for the privilege. You serve yourself, and in some places, you might even get your drinks. This means there's next to no need for waiting staff. And since the menu relies heavily on a series of regular dishes which are prepared in advance, they can hire fewer and cheaper chefs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heck, at some buffets like Korean BBQ places, the customers are even doing the cooking as well as the serving!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you know the economics, you may have the power of defying these principles and &quot;beating the buffet’. Defy the diminishing marginal utility function. Be wise and judge your taste buds independent of price. Be rational and avoid the bandwagon. But buffet designers know this. While most people will be modest, some people will try to get &quot;all-they-can-eat&quot; and go for a ton of pieces of cottage cheese. Some don’t stop from piling it up vertically or going back for another plate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, buffets must cut corners in other ways to make sure they aren't losing out. They achieve this by teasing you in clever ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategic Layouts and Secret Nudges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buffets invest a lot of time into developing the right layout.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expensive items are cut into smaller pieces. Cheap, filling foods such as your salads, veggies, rice and noodles are served at the beginning, offering the consumer the opportunity to load up before the ‘luxury’ items. Relatively expensive offerings will be surrounded by four or five cheaper veggie side dishes, and pricier desserts like cakes will be surrounded by platters of fruit. Coupled with larger serving times for expensive items, buffets usually nudge you to take up the cheaper, more available, readily in flow food items. You can grab a ladle-full of rice and veggies any instant, but when it comes to those small pizza slices, you wait for your turn in line. They'll take longer to get on your plate, and most people don't like the pressure of holding up a line, so they tend to move quickly through. Also, pans with more expensive foods are generally less full — a subtle encouragement to take less, a nudge, while cheap ingredients will be served in giant, overflowing pans. Those are plenty for all, and people like that. They like to believe that must be the right choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest factors impacting your eating habits at a buffet is the cutlery you're given. You'll seldom see full-sized dinner plates or actual soup bowls. Instead, you'll be given small plates and even tiny dessert bowls to limit the amount of food you take. Restaurant suppliers know this, and buffets even purchase miniature tableware specially designed for buffets. This even includes purchasing silverware, which tends to be smaller — but not small enough you'd notice unless you already know their sneaky tricks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, buffets will keep extra sweet desserts, so clients are satisfied with lower portions. Complementary to this, buffets will usually have huge water and soft drink glasses. They need you to be full of soda that costs a penny. The more you drink, the less you eat, the more the restaurant saves. For a lot of buffets, things like vegetables, potatoes and rice are staple dishes. That's because they are both super cheap and extremely filling. Buffets entice you into indulging on salads before the meat because salad is cheaper and quickly fills plate space. &lt;em&gt;Psychology Today&lt;/em&gt; took a look at what's occurring in the buffet line, and they call this the &quot;fill the customer's belly cheaply&quot; metric. But remember, if you are truly there to make the most of your money, these items will only fill you up with nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its crudest level, the AYCE buffet restaurant manager’s primary job is simply to fill the customer’s stomach as cheaply and quickly as possible. Minimising waste by using computational data analytics to figure out the customers’ eating habits go a long way in cutting costs. Coupled with the power of using cheap ingredients to prepare worthwhile dishes, AYCE buffets tease your bellies to fill their pockets. But to satisfy customers and bring them back, buffet managers can’t stop there. They must create the perception of providing ample variety and high-quality food items. At the same time, they must manipulate customers’ choices and portion sizes, and ensure that food waste is minimised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With just a few tricks, such as using smaller plates, putting cheap items towards the front, and using drinks to off-set other costs, all-you-can-eat restaurants can accomplish the same goal as any other restaurant: get people in the door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, you may not want to take the &quot;all-you-can-eat&quot; part quite so literally. People can and have been banned from buffets for eating too much food. For instance, a Wisconsin man named Bill Wisth was not only banned but had the cops called on him for abusing his local buffet. So, before you go back for that fourth slice of pizza, ask yourself how much you might like the taste of jail food. Because the buffets there aren't nearly as good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, for a recap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did I teach you about buffet strategy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Grab a small-sized drink and a large-sized plate, start with your high-end entrée, skip veggies and carbs and yeah, ride your own bandwagon.”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Mehul Goyal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">All-you-can-eat (AYCE) restaurants charge a fixed price for access to food, and they allow customers to consume as much food as their heart desires at no extra charge. Simply put, consumers are charged a specified price regardless of how much food they consume. From “Feast unlimited this Monday at Barbeque Nation; lunch at ₹399 and dinner at ₹499” to sell tandoori feasts in India, to “$24.99 all you can eat buffets” in Las Vegas as a lure to bring hungry patrons into casinos, AYCE has its roots everywhere. In practice, managers may have several motivations for offering such flat-rate pricing. While some are driven by competitive pricing pressures that may lead to zero marginal cost of production, others seek to reduce costs such as labour by employing a smaller wait staff, made possible by the emphasis on self-service. If you have ever had an awful stomach after you thought you struck gold at the buffet, you might have just wondered how restaurants manage to keep up their bottom line while you think you seemingly rob them in broad daylight. As you can guess, it is definitely not a loss for the restaurants. They indeed make hefty profits from this scheme. Besides being an ingenious piece of marketing, such restaurants became so popular owing to their wide selection of food and to the freedom given to customers to choose their own portions. People skip their breakfast and lunch to have a buffet dinner. They come with the mentality that they are going to earn their value for money. But little do they know that they come out on the losing side of it, mostly. How then do buffets manage to create and maintain a winning environment whilst also keeping their customers elated? To shed light on how this concept leaves restaurants with money requires an examination of some fundamental microeconomics, psychology and what magic a careful blend of both can do. The high-skilled and trained managers in the hotel industry have succeeded in hitting this sweet spot and manage to leverage customer satisfaction and generate profits. Law of Diminishing Marginal Utility A law inherent to every Econ 101 class. The crux is that the additional benefit we feel from consumption (be it of cake, cigarettes or coffee) decreases as we consume it. You won’t have the same satisfaction from the last bite you have as you have from the first time eating it (your fifth slice of pizza, although good, just doesn’t taste as good as the first). Additional utility (benefit) from the last slice of pizza will be less than that from the first and this goes on until you have a negative utility for each slice that you consume (nobody enjoys a 25th slice, probably). People go to the buffet with a set mentality of making the most of their money. They want to maximise their satisfaction i.e. eat till they drop. However, again with the prospect of an unlimited buffet, their greed takes over and once their satisfaction is maximum, it slowly becomes negative i.e. the satisfaction derived from the buffet initially rises, then becomes maximum, and then falls. This is nothing but the law of Diminishing Marginal Utility. This is why you see exasperated faces after a buffet when people overshoot. What this tells us is that no matter what the price paid for a buffet is, you can only continue eating until your satiation point is reached. We’ll see how restaurants are masters at taking you there, quickly and cheaply. Sunk Costs In economics and business decision-making, a sunk cost is one which is incurred and cannot be recovered. You’ve invested the money and nothing can be done to take it back. For this reason, sunk costs should not affect decision-making. If the money’s already gone then it should not be affecting our future decisions. But in reality, people let this influence them. People have a habit to chase their losses, unable to quit and move on. We see it predominantly among gamblers, always chasing a winning bet to recoup earlier mistakes. We also witness it in business, it’s the same reason that investors continue with a loss-making entity. They don’t see a world beyond their already sunk dollars. When we buy a ticket to a buffet, we also face the same dilemma. Because a customer faces no marginal cost of consumption, conventional utility maximisation implies that he or she should continue to eat until the marginal utility of consumption reaches 0. Economic models of consumer behaviour commonly assume that the utility of consumption is unaffected by the price paid. Rather, the price affects consumption only through a budget constraint. So, in an AYCE setting, price should influence whether one chooses to eat at the restaurant, but it should not affect the amount of food one consumes. But various experiments and test results have proven that price determines the personal evaluation of certain food and indirectly affects consumption. The Food and Brand Lab at Cornell University conducted an experiment to see how the price of a buffet influenced customers. They offered two groups of customers the same pizza buffet, and charged one group $4, while the other group was charged $8. The group who paid more was overwhelmingly more satisfied with the entire experience. We are driven by our personal conception of value for money. The purpose of revealing this is to demonstrate the sunk cost fallacy in an AYCE context. In an AYCE setting, price positively influences consumption. Additionally, consumption appears to be negatively related to individual evaluations of taste. In contrast to the standard utility model, this provides support to the notion that individuals consider price in evaluating their marginal utility of consumption, even when there is no marginal cost for additional consumption. The more the buffet charges, the more you think the buffet is good. Hence, the buffet is charged more and you still think the buffet is good and within all this, restaurants jump in and book their profits. The Concept of Bounded Rationality and the Bandwagon Effect Bounded rationality is the idea that rationality is limited when individuals make decisions by the tractability of the decision problem, the cognitive limitations of the mind, and the time available to make the decision. It is similar to an inability to make a sagacious decision when bombarded with multitudes of options (as in a buffet) leading us unable to follow rational predictions. The bandwagon effect is the tendency of an individual to acquire a particular style, behaviour or attitude because everyone else is doing it. It is a phenomenon whereby the rate of uptake of beliefs, ideas, fads and trends increases with respect to the proportion of others who have already done so. Usually, in a buffet, some items come out to be clear winners and almost everyone starts having more and more of the same, the customers recommend the same to the people they are having lunch/dinner with, who in turn again start having more of the product. This creates a bandwagon effect, people will quickly consume a few items thereby saving the restaurant’s cost on all others. When choices are abundant, rationality is limited, and people have a tendency to follow the bandwagon, the result is skewed option picking. Some dishes emerge to be the most wanted and are generally those that are in abundant supply. Usually, dishes that are cooked in large vessels with cheap ingredients. Hence the restaurant saves on the more expensive dishes and the cost is limited yet again. Economies of Scale Economies of scale are cost advantages reaped by companies when production becomes efficient. Companies can achieve economies of scale by increasing production and lowering costs. The larger the business, the more the cost savings. Buffets are large production businesses. A restaurant buffet achieves economies of scale by producing in large quantities, spreading its costs over a larger number of dishes, even though it often demands a serious cut in food quality. Because of tight profit margins, the food quality becomes a second priority. However, this doesn’t matter, they have their footfall. In addition to this, lesser personnel need to be deployed for a buffet. As a result, the restaurant makes large savings in employment costs. These overhead savings are one of the crucial areas in which buffets differ from traditional restaurants. That's because you are doing most of the work for them - and paying for the privilege. You serve yourself, and in some places, you might even get your drinks. This means there's next to no need for waiting staff. And since the menu relies heavily on a series of regular dishes which are prepared in advance, they can hire fewer and cheaper chefs.&amp;nbsp; Heck, at some buffets like Korean BBQ places, the customers are even doing the cooking as well as the serving! Now that you know the economics, you may have the power of defying these principles and &quot;beating the buffet’. Defy the diminishing marginal utility function. Be wise and judge your taste buds independent of price. Be rational and avoid the bandwagon. But buffet designers know this. While most people will be modest, some people will try to get &quot;all-they-can-eat&quot; and go for a ton of pieces of cottage cheese. Some don’t stop from piling it up vertically or going back for another plate. So, buffets must cut corners in other ways to make sure they aren't losing out. They achieve this by teasing you in clever ways. Strategic Layouts and Secret Nudges Buffets invest a lot of time into developing the right layout.&amp;nbsp; Expensive items are cut into smaller pieces. Cheap, filling foods such as your salads, veggies, rice and noodles are served at the beginning, offering the consumer the opportunity to load up before the ‘luxury’ items. Relatively expensive offerings will be surrounded by four or five cheaper veggie side dishes, and pricier desserts like cakes will be surrounded by platters of fruit. Coupled with larger serving times for expensive items, buffets usually nudge you to take up the cheaper, more available, readily in flow food items. You can grab a ladle-full of rice and veggies any instant, but when it comes to those small pizza slices, you wait for your turn in line. They'll take longer to get on your plate, and most people don't like the pressure of holding up a line, so they tend to move quickly through. Also, pans with more expensive foods are generally less full — a subtle encouragement to take less, a nudge, while cheap ingredients will be served in giant, overflowing pans. Those are plenty for all, and people like that. They like to believe that must be the right choice. One of the biggest factors impacting your eating habits at a buffet is the cutlery you're given. You'll seldom see full-sized dinner plates or actual soup bowls. Instead, you'll be given small plates and even tiny dessert bowls to limit the amount of food you take. Restaurant suppliers know this, and buffets even purchase miniature tableware specially designed for buffets. This even includes purchasing silverware, which tends to be smaller — but not small enough you'd notice unless you already know their sneaky tricks. You're welcome. Generally, buffets will keep extra sweet desserts, so clients are satisfied with lower portions. Complementary to this, buffets will usually have huge water and soft drink glasses. They need you to be full of soda that costs a penny. The more you drink, the less you eat, the more the restaurant saves. For a lot of buffets, things like vegetables, potatoes and rice are staple dishes. That's because they are both super cheap and extremely filling. Buffets entice you into indulging on salads before the meat because salad is cheaper and quickly fills plate space. Psychology Today took a look at what's occurring in the buffet line, and they call this the &quot;fill the customer's belly cheaply&quot; metric. But remember, if you are truly there to make the most of your money, these items will only fill you up with nonsense. Conclusion At its crudest level, the AYCE buffet restaurant manager’s primary job is simply to fill the customer’s stomach as cheaply and quickly as possible. Minimising waste by using computational data analytics to figure out the customers’ eating habits go a long way in cutting costs. Coupled with the power of using cheap ingredients to prepare worthwhile dishes, AYCE buffets tease your bellies to fill their pockets. But to satisfy customers and bring them back, buffet managers can’t stop there. They must create the perception of providing ample variety and high-quality food items. At the same time, they must manipulate customers’ choices and portion sizes, and ensure that food waste is minimised. With just a few tricks, such as using smaller plates, putting cheap items towards the front, and using drinks to off-set other costs, all-you-can-eat restaurants can accomplish the same goal as any other restaurant: get people in the door. Finally, you may not want to take the &quot;all-you-can-eat&quot; part quite so literally. People can and have been banned from buffets for eating too much food. For instance, a Wisconsin man named Bill Wisth was not only banned but had the cops called on him for abusing his local buffet. So, before you go back for that fourth slice of pizza, ask yourself how much you might like the taste of jail food. Because the buffets there aren't nearly as good. So, for a recap. What did I teach you about buffet strategy? &quot;Grab a small-sized drink and a large-sized plate, start with your high-end entrée, skip veggies and carbs and yeah, ride your own bandwagon.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
