<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/business-finance/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-11-04T21:28:53+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/business-finance/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Do Meetings Have Any Agenda?</title>
      <link href="/Do-Meetings-Have-Any-Agenda" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do Meetings Have Any Agenda?" />
      <published>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Do-Meetings-Have-Any-Agenda</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Do-Meetings-Have-Any-Agenda">&lt;p&gt;It would take no expert on management to tell you that there's nothing more pissing off than a 'meeting'. To quote David Barry, “&lt;em&gt;Meetings are a highly addictive, self-indulgent activity that corporations and other large organisations engage in only because they cannot actually masturbate&lt;/em&gt;”. But the point, of course, is that despite a huge amount of management literature being spent on decrying the meeting, an American executive - according to research published in the &lt;em&gt;Harvard Business Review &lt;/em&gt;- spends, on average, 300,000 hours on meetings every year. This is astounding since Americans spend around 87,000 hours a year, on average, sleeping. The question is: Why? Why are meetings, at all, addictive, when we know that they are far from productive? Why on earth do we spend more time in meetings instead of getting some shut-eye? The answer requires us to take a deep dive into the nature of production and management in the modern office.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The act of making something has, throughout most of history, required an application of physical faculties. The work of a manager has been overseeing the labourer, ensuring that his toils are coordinated and oriented towards the goal of making something.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in a service-based economy, that is simply not possible in a traditional sense. The act of production is now a complex web of mental application. The product, even if made inside a factory, is ultimately an elusive entity that is mentioned in an invoice or a quarterly report. The excel entry called the product is tightly wound within the structure of the mental contrivance called the 'brand'. The brand is what captivates the modern Janus-like 'customer' who again is an email address or a delivery point. The 'market', even if physical, is ultimately a collection of data points, that may be manipulated through 'marketing' to get bigger entries on that column called 'revenue'. Of course, the aim of all this is an 'annual report' where a bunch of numbers indicate that there is 'profit', which is transmitted to the pantheon of gods called 'the shareholders'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, the whole idea of production and sale, the idea of a corporation, and its activity is merely a historical imitation of itself. There's no hum of a machine at work, no sound of the worker breaking for lunch after a gong, and no assembly line of men putting different parts together. What we have instead is the receipt of orders, the invoicing and billing, the handover of title through the handover of a bill of lading, the negotiation of a contract via a back-and-forth of emails, the power-point presentations, and so on. The very act of doing business by producing something and selling it for a profit has become a simulation, the corporate executive creates only an imitation of the real at his desk, typing away, caffeinated to the brim.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simulation of production represses some very basic needs that a person demands from their work: identity, individuality, a sense of purpose, a feeling of being part of something greater than oneself. And this is not some fancy philosophical takedown, but an assessment based on a very comprehensive body of psychological literature. For instance, a study by K C Madhav and others published in 2017 in the journal of &lt;em&gt;Preventive Medicine Reports&lt;/em&gt; on 3,201 American adults showed that people who spent more than six hours a day looking at a computer screen were highly likely to develop moderate to severe depression. Since the modern workplace requires at least eight hours of work behind a computer screen, we can only imagine how many are silently being pushed into despair by this dehumanising system. Furthermore, according to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cv-library.co.uk/recruitment-insight/brits-suffer-loneliness-workplace/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt; of 2,000 working professionals in the UK, around 53.6% of workers admit to feeling lonely, and around 44.4% attribute this to having nothing in common with their colleagues. Clearly, the modern workplace is antithetical to the basic human requirement of socialisation, which as we know, is a crucial component of neuronal health.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meeting, in such a scenario, and the addictive obsession with it is just a&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;“&lt;em&gt;return of the repressed&lt;/em&gt;” (to quote the French psychoanalyst Jacques Lacan). It is a desperate attempt at trying to introduce a feeling of reality and human connection which a simulation of production simply cannot provide. This point becomes even more apparent when we observe how the meeting becomes more and more vague in its mandate and execution. So many meetings are called ‘team-building exercises’, and they have no real discernible purpose, just a way for a manager to look at the people who send him all those emails and feel like he's looking at a factory floor. That apart, there are the ‘brainstorming sessions’, which are about as useful as non-alcoholic beers - with very little thinking happening over the glib and mindless chatter on a few talking points. Finally, there is the ‘feedback meeting’ which is, of course, hardly about genuine feedback.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sum, the modern meeting is an attempt at dealing with the neurosis of the modern corporation, which most thoroughly fails to actually solve the problem due to the fundamentally artificial setting of simulated production. The question, of course, is how do we actually end this neurosis, how do we give the modern professional his identity and a sense of community and purpose? Is there a way to actually imbue the meeting with meaning? I think it is worth looking at the original medicament to all problems relating to the human condition: religion. And not just any religion, but the oldest one in the world: Hinduism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the grandest meetings ever held in Hindu mythology was the ‘&lt;em&gt;Upanishads&lt;/em&gt;’. They were called by the mythical King Janaka to bring sages and wise men together to engage in great dialogues on philosophy. These dialogues continued for years. King Janaka's daughter, Lady Sita, would sit through these meetings. She would sit and listen intently as the mighty sage Yajnavalkya explained that every man was Brahma - the god of creation - for every man created his own world that was born from his own mind. Yajnavalkya would state, however, that every man or woman could be Brahman - the infinite godhead in Hinduism - and could go beyond his own world by expanding his mind to embrace the worlds of others.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day Lady Sita realised that as the sages talked, there was almost a magical force that ensured their throats were never parched and that they were always properly fed. She wandered into the royal kitchens to realise why this was so. Lady Sita saw her mother adeptly manage the kitchen to ensure a near-endless supply of food was always available. Lady Sita sat beside her mother, learning how to neatly slice vegetables. She expanded her mind. In other words, she journeyed from Brahma to Brahman because of a truly august meeting.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the story of Lady Sita and the Upanishadic meetings may seem too profound to be applicable to a shallow world, it gives us a lot to think about in terms of management theory. Lady Sita and sage Yajnavalkya tell us that a meeting has to become a sacred space - where the neuroses of the modern worker in the simulacra of production are confronted rather than avoided. They tell us that for a meeting to succeed, it has to go beyond just a desperate desire for human connection, serving as a springboard for greater thought and mind-expanding action. In practice, this is easier to implement than one may think, all we need do is ask the worker to expand his mind and truly see. We need to tell him that the sales report under discussion is far more than what appears to a Brahma like him. We need to tell him that the sales report represents the work of so many things coming together to create a Brahman greater than any one worker. In short, we need only remind the worker that the modern corporation now appears only a simulation of itself because the nature of the reality it controls is simply too vast.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A meeting where the manager reminds the modern worker that his typing and emailing on one desk moves mountains in actuality would be the true medicament to the worker's suffering. It would expand his mind to see his co-worker as a compatriot in going beyond their own world of emails and invoices to see the customer, the supplier, and the manufacturer. This would make workers learn from these people, thereby adding true accountability to the corporate process. Most importantly, it would make the worker human again, giving him the tools to fight off real problems like depression and nihilism.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It would take no expert on management to tell you that there's nothing more pissing off than a 'meeting'. To quote David Barry, “Meetings are a highly addictive, self-indulgent activity that corporations and other large organisations engage in only because they cannot actually masturbate”. But the point, of course, is that despite a huge amount of management literature being spent on decrying the meeting, an American executive - according to research published in the Harvard Business Review - spends, on average, 300,000 hours on meetings every year. This is astounding since Americans spend around 87,000 hours a year, on average, sleeping. The question is: Why? Why are meetings, at all, addictive, when we know that they are far from productive? Why on earth do we spend more time in meetings instead of getting some shut-eye? The answer requires us to take a deep dive into the nature of production and management in the modern office.&amp;nbsp; The act of making something has, throughout most of history, required an application of physical faculties. The work of a manager has been overseeing the labourer, ensuring that his toils are coordinated and oriented towards the goal of making something.&amp;nbsp; However, in a service-based economy, that is simply not possible in a traditional sense. The act of production is now a complex web of mental application. The product, even if made inside a factory, is ultimately an elusive entity that is mentioned in an invoice or a quarterly report. The excel entry called the product is tightly wound within the structure of the mental contrivance called the 'brand'. The brand is what captivates the modern Janus-like 'customer' who again is an email address or a delivery point. The 'market', even if physical, is ultimately a collection of data points, that may be manipulated through 'marketing' to get bigger entries on that column called 'revenue'. Of course, the aim of all this is an 'annual report' where a bunch of numbers indicate that there is 'profit', which is transmitted to the pantheon of gods called 'the shareholders'. In short, the whole idea of production and sale, the idea of a corporation, and its activity is merely a historical imitation of itself. There's no hum of a machine at work, no sound of the worker breaking for lunch after a gong, and no assembly line of men putting different parts together. What we have instead is the receipt of orders, the invoicing and billing, the handover of title through the handover of a bill of lading, the negotiation of a contract via a back-and-forth of emails, the power-point presentations, and so on. The very act of doing business by producing something and selling it for a profit has become a simulation, the corporate executive creates only an imitation of the real at his desk, typing away, caffeinated to the brim.&amp;nbsp; The simulation of production represses some very basic needs that a person demands from their work: identity, individuality, a sense of purpose, a feeling of being part of something greater than oneself. And this is not some fancy philosophical takedown, but an assessment based on a very comprehensive body of psychological literature. For instance, a study by K C Madhav and others published in 2017 in the journal of Preventive Medicine Reports on 3,201 American adults showed that people who spent more than six hours a day looking at a computer screen were highly likely to develop moderate to severe depression. Since the modern workplace requires at least eight hours of work behind a computer screen, we can only imagine how many are silently being pushed into despair by this dehumanising system. Furthermore, according to a survey of 2,000 working professionals in the UK, around 53.6% of workers admit to feeling lonely, and around 44.4% attribute this to having nothing in common with their colleagues. Clearly, the modern workplace is antithetical to the basic human requirement of socialisation, which as we know, is a crucial component of neuronal health.&amp;nbsp; The meeting, in such a scenario, and the addictive obsession with it is just a “return of the repressed” (to quote the French psychoanalyst Jacques Lacan). It is a desperate attempt at trying to introduce a feeling of reality and human connection which a simulation of production simply cannot provide. This point becomes even more apparent when we observe how the meeting becomes more and more vague in its mandate and execution. So many meetings are called ‘team-building exercises’, and they have no real discernible purpose, just a way for a manager to look at the people who send him all those emails and feel like he's looking at a factory floor. That apart, there are the ‘brainstorming sessions’, which are about as useful as non-alcoholic beers - with very little thinking happening over the glib and mindless chatter on a few talking points. Finally, there is the ‘feedback meeting’ which is, of course, hardly about genuine feedback.&amp;nbsp; In sum, the modern meeting is an attempt at dealing with the neurosis of the modern corporation, which most thoroughly fails to actually solve the problem due to the fundamentally artificial setting of simulated production. The question, of course, is how do we actually end this neurosis, how do we give the modern professional his identity and a sense of community and purpose? Is there a way to actually imbue the meeting with meaning? I think it is worth looking at the original medicament to all problems relating to the human condition: religion. And not just any religion, but the oldest one in the world: Hinduism.&amp;nbsp; One of the grandest meetings ever held in Hindu mythology was the ‘Upanishads’. They were called by the mythical King Janaka to bring sages and wise men together to engage in great dialogues on philosophy. These dialogues continued for years. King Janaka's daughter, Lady Sita, would sit through these meetings. She would sit and listen intently as the mighty sage Yajnavalkya explained that every man was Brahma - the god of creation - for every man created his own world that was born from his own mind. Yajnavalkya would state, however, that every man or woman could be Brahman - the infinite godhead in Hinduism - and could go beyond his own world by expanding his mind to embrace the worlds of others.&amp;nbsp; One day Lady Sita realised that as the sages talked, there was almost a magical force that ensured their throats were never parched and that they were always properly fed. She wandered into the royal kitchens to realise why this was so. Lady Sita saw her mother adeptly manage the kitchen to ensure a near-endless supply of food was always available. Lady Sita sat beside her mother, learning how to neatly slice vegetables. She expanded her mind. In other words, she journeyed from Brahma to Brahman because of a truly august meeting.&amp;nbsp; While the story of Lady Sita and the Upanishadic meetings may seem too profound to be applicable to a shallow world, it gives us a lot to think about in terms of management theory. Lady Sita and sage Yajnavalkya tell us that a meeting has to become a sacred space - where the neuroses of the modern worker in the simulacra of production are confronted rather than avoided. They tell us that for a meeting to succeed, it has to go beyond just a desperate desire for human connection, serving as a springboard for greater thought and mind-expanding action. In practice, this is easier to implement than one may think, all we need do is ask the worker to expand his mind and truly see. We need to tell him that the sales report under discussion is far more than what appears to a Brahma like him. We need to tell him that the sales report represents the work of so many things coming together to create a Brahman greater than any one worker. In short, we need only remind the worker that the modern corporation now appears only a simulation of itself because the nature of the reality it controls is simply too vast.&amp;nbsp; A meeting where the manager reminds the modern worker that his typing and emailing on one desk moves mountains in actuality would be the true medicament to the worker's suffering. It would expand his mind to see his co-worker as a compatriot in going beyond their own world of emails and invoices to see the customer, the supplier, and the manufacturer. This would make workers learn from these people, thereby adding true accountability to the corporate process. Most importantly, it would make the worker human again, giving him the tools to fight off real problems like depression and nihilism.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Amazon: The Deal Breaker?</title>
      <link href="/Amazon-The-Deal-Breaker" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amazon: The Deal Breaker?" />
      <published>2020-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Amazon-The-Deal-Breaker</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Amazon-The-Deal-Breaker">&lt;p&gt;The Reliance and Future Group deal has been in the headlines since a few days now. The recent development which involved Amazon sending a legal notice has spiced it up even more. We are all obsessed with conflicts especially when three multinational corporations are involved. To get a better understanding of the on-going feud, we need to look at the previous developments and understand what actually led to the present-day situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Future Group, owned by Kishore Biyani, had been facing a &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Past-Future-Future-Group&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;crisis&lt;/a&gt; for a few years. They were in huge debt and the reason might have been the diverse and over-ambitious investments made by the company. The group started out with a unique idea that gained success and their retail stores like Pantaloons and Big Bazaar became common household names. The greed to expand business in diverse areas might have turned out to be a big mistake. The group was burdened under debts but still continued to invest and make useless purchases. As the debt accumulated over time, the only option left was to sell their retail chains and shut down useless businesses. At the same time, online platforms like Amazon and Flipkart had already established themselves in the Indian market as retail giants. This increased the threat to all retail businesses as people were switching to e-commerce quicker than ever. Biyani saw this as an opportunity to extend his business to online platforms as well and thus decided to launch '&lt;em&gt;Retail 3.0&lt;/em&gt;'. It was too late to enter as the market had already been saturated and was now under the control of corporations like Amazon and Flipkart. Things didn’t work out for the group as planned. As of March 31, 2019, the combined debt of the Future Group was valued at ₹1.2 trillion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only viable option left for Biyani was to sell off the entire group. Reliance Industries Limited (RIL), which is looking to increase its presence in the retail business, acquired the retail and wholesale business as well as the logistics and warehousing business from the Future Group for a lump-sum aggregate consideration of ₹247 billion in 2020. Soon after the announcement was made public, Amazon jumped in between and turned the tables around. It not only slapped a legal notice but also approached the Singapore International Arbitration Centre (SIAC) claiming that the Future Group had breached the contract according to which Amazon owns a 49% stake in the Future Coupons Pvt Ltd, the parent company which owns all the retail stores, and thus has the first rights to refuse or acquire an even larger stake in the Future Group (after 3 years and before 10 years). Amazon has requested the SIAC to halt the deal between RIL and the Future Group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguments in defence of the deal state that pre-conditions that exist in the Amazon deal only come into effect after 2022, thus the allegations do not stand. Also, it is claimed that Future Coupons has nothing to do with the Ambani-Biyani deal, and hence, the legal notice doesn’t matter and won’t affect the deal for long. Well, we can’t really be sure of these points and thus have the avenue to make an opinion about the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deal was still awaiting completion by the authorities but now it seems to be kinda blurry! We know how prominent Amazon and RIL are in the Indian markets. They have expanded their businesses and the results have been profitable too. This deal definitely plays a crucial role considering the fact that the Future Group has a huge consumer base which will now benefit the new owner. Reliance Industries is owned by the richest Indian, Mukesh Ambani, and the company is in good shape and thus was looking forward to taking over the Future Group. It has plans to enter the e-commerce business via Jiomart. This will expand their business empire in the world of e-retail which will be beneficial in the long run. As we know, Amazon is the boss of e-commerce and won’t enjoy this new entrant in their arena. Thus, going ahead and flashing a legal notice which further halts the deal seems like a smart move to hamper the growth of RIL. We have grown up reading about business rivalries but we also know that profit is the only thing that matters at the end of the day. At this point in time, Amazon should be considerate of the fact that expansion within the subcontinent won’t be an easy task if they make RIL their rivals. The kind of control and authority RIL enjoys within the Indian markets is massive and thus the support will be of much help for expanding businesses. Amazon has the option to negotiate outside the courts and find a solution that satisfies the two parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever be the case, the Future Group has lost its shine and is now being juggled between two companies who only care about their profits and will prioritise their self-interests. Both Amazon and Reliance have been expanding their shares in the Indian markets. With or without the battle, both corporations are winning in a way that benefits them exclusively. The kind of power and authority they have is unbeatable so this case won’t really matter to them. For us, however, it is going to be an interesting battle to look forward to!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Reliance and Future Group deal has been in the headlines since a few days now. The recent development which involved Amazon sending a legal notice has spiced it up even more. We are all obsessed with conflicts especially when three multinational corporations are involved. To get a better understanding of the on-going feud, we need to look at the previous developments and understand what actually led to the present-day situation. Future Group, owned by Kishore Biyani, had been facing a crisis for a few years. They were in huge debt and the reason might have been the diverse and over-ambitious investments made by the company. The group started out with a unique idea that gained success and their retail stores like Pantaloons and Big Bazaar became common household names. The greed to expand business in diverse areas might have turned out to be a big mistake. The group was burdened under debts but still continued to invest and make useless purchases. As the debt accumulated over time, the only option left was to sell their retail chains and shut down useless businesses. At the same time, online platforms like Amazon and Flipkart had already established themselves in the Indian market as retail giants. This increased the threat to all retail businesses as people were switching to e-commerce quicker than ever. Biyani saw this as an opportunity to extend his business to online platforms as well and thus decided to launch 'Retail 3.0'. It was too late to enter as the market had already been saturated and was now under the control of corporations like Amazon and Flipkart. Things didn’t work out for the group as planned. As of March 31, 2019, the combined debt of the Future Group was valued at ₹1.2 trillion. The only viable option left for Biyani was to sell off the entire group. Reliance Industries Limited (RIL), which is looking to increase its presence in the retail business, acquired the retail and wholesale business as well as the logistics and warehousing business from the Future Group for a lump-sum aggregate consideration of ₹247 billion in 2020. Soon after the announcement was made public, Amazon jumped in between and turned the tables around. It not only slapped a legal notice but also approached the Singapore International Arbitration Centre (SIAC) claiming that the Future Group had breached the contract according to which Amazon owns a 49% stake in the Future Coupons Pvt Ltd, the parent company which owns all the retail stores, and thus has the first rights to refuse or acquire an even larger stake in the Future Group (after 3 years and before 10 years). Amazon has requested the SIAC to halt the deal between RIL and the Future Group. Arguments in defence of the deal state that pre-conditions that exist in the Amazon deal only come into effect after 2022, thus the allegations do not stand. Also, it is claimed that Future Coupons has nothing to do with the Ambani-Biyani deal, and hence, the legal notice doesn’t matter and won’t affect the deal for long. Well, we can’t really be sure of these points and thus have the avenue to make an opinion about the same. The deal was still awaiting completion by the authorities but now it seems to be kinda blurry! We know how prominent Amazon and RIL are in the Indian markets. They have expanded their businesses and the results have been profitable too. This deal definitely plays a crucial role considering the fact that the Future Group has a huge consumer base which will now benefit the new owner. Reliance Industries is owned by the richest Indian, Mukesh Ambani, and the company is in good shape and thus was looking forward to taking over the Future Group. It has plans to enter the e-commerce business via Jiomart. This will expand their business empire in the world of e-retail which will be beneficial in the long run. As we know, Amazon is the boss of e-commerce and won’t enjoy this new entrant in their arena. Thus, going ahead and flashing a legal notice which further halts the deal seems like a smart move to hamper the growth of RIL. We have grown up reading about business rivalries but we also know that profit is the only thing that matters at the end of the day. At this point in time, Amazon should be considerate of the fact that expansion within the subcontinent won’t be an easy task if they make RIL their rivals. The kind of control and authority RIL enjoys within the Indian markets is massive and thus the support will be of much help for expanding businesses. Amazon has the option to negotiate outside the courts and find a solution that satisfies the two parties. Whatever be the case, the Future Group has lost its shine and is now being juggled between two companies who only care about their profits and will prioritise their self-interests. Both Amazon and Reliance have been expanding their shares in the Indian markets. With or without the battle, both corporations are winning in a way that benefits them exclusively. The kind of power and authority they have is unbeatable so this case won’t really matter to them. For us, however, it is going to be an interesting battle to look forward to!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">COVID-19: RBI’s Take and What Now?</title>
      <link href="/RBI-Take-What-Now" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19: RBI’s Take and What Now?" />
      <published>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/RBI-Take-What-Now</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/RBI-Take-What-Now">&lt;p&gt;The Central bank of a nation is tasked with multiple responsibilities to maintain the dynamic, complex and entangled macroeconomic variables with the sole objective of economic development of the country. The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) follows the same pursuit of growth by working out the price and financial stability of the state. The gigantic wave of virus that swept the world in late 2019 and hit India in early 2020 has inevitably accelerated the socio-economic division, the footprint of which will be felt for years to come. With the advent of such unprecedented times, all eyes are turned to the Central bank and to the government for rescue from the ramifications of this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the late evening of March 24, 2020, Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi announced a 21-day complete lockdown which got extended for months due to the rising number of COVID-19 cases in the country. This declaration meant an absolute halt for businesses leading to complete disruption of market forces of demand and supply, money creation, etc. In short, it was a difficult affair for the economy. Nonetheless, the RBI sailed through it almost effortlessly, supporting the economy through the various tools:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) &lt;strong&gt;Rate cuts&lt;/strong&gt;: To incentivise investments and loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b) &lt;strong&gt;Liquidity Infusion&lt;/strong&gt;: Increasing the availability of funds in banks via various policy rates like CRR, Repo rate, Reverse Repo Rate, OMOs, and special windows for financial institutions to borrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;c) &lt;strong&gt;Regulatory Easing&lt;/strong&gt;: Via mechanisms like a moratorium, etc to support the borrowers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These steps resulted in a liquidity spree in the banking system, drawing concerns of inflationary pressure in an already high inflation economy (CPI inflation rate in July was 6.93%). In addition to this, the influx of dollars in the country through Foreign Direct Investments (FDIs) and Foreign Portfolio Investments (FPIs) fuelled the additional circulation of Indian currency in the economy. This, supported by collapsing net imports, led to the pile-up of RBIs forex kitty to an all-time high of $541billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In layman’s language, it looks like a rosy picture. However from an economist’s point of view, this means appreciation of the Indian rupee with respect to the mighty US dollar. Thus, putting exports at a disadvantage. It adds to the already concerning topic of inflation as now excess money will be spent on the imported items, increasing our dependence on imported goods. At the same time, we will be letting go of the opportunity of utilising the liquidity available in the system which could have been used to build productive capacities like infrastructure that will lead to the creation of employment, income and welfare of the nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, inflation will only occur when the monetary surplus in the banking system actually reaches the hands of the consumers via businesses and loans, but banks are averse in lending out due to skyrocketing Non-Performing Assets (NPAs). Hence the overflowing liquidity is limited within these financial intermediaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to an article published in &lt;em&gt;Business Today&lt;/em&gt;, despite the Central bank reducing the Reverse Repo Rate (RRR) from 4.9% to 3.35%, the number of deposits increased during the period of the pandemic. Unused funds in the financial system have further been increasing as businesses and firms are reluctant in taking loans for investments due to low production and capacity utilisation. Moreover, rising COVID-19 cases engulf the future with a blanket of uncertainty for businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The jump in the deposits with the RBI is a cause of worry as the excess money sitting idle with banks now requires the Central bank to pay interest on these deposits. Additionally, the money is never actually entering the productive sector for money creation, which was the prime motive of slashing the RRR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, governments too have a vital role in reviving the economy through its targeted expenditures. But the Union government’s fiscal deficit has soared to 109% of the budgeted target in just 5 months of the current financial year. State governments have been facing a shortage of funds owing to the shortfall of revenues due to sluggish economic activities and failure on part of the Union government to settle the compensation for Goods and Services Tax (GST). Hence, the governments’ bank stepped in to facilitate the reduction of that deficit by borrowing from the bond market. The Center has stuck to its borrowing plan of ₹12 trillion in 2020-21. The superfluity of funds in the financial system is managing to keep the yields in the bond market low, benefitting the borrowers in borrowing funds at low-interest rates. The Central government borrowed ₹7.66 trillion at a weighted rate of 5.82%, the lowest in 15 years, in the first half of the ongoing fiscal year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting the rate of economic expansion back on track is a daunting task and RBI has managed the situation quite decently, but the major chunk of work now lies on the government to use their borrowing for capital expenditure and revival of demand. Better demand sentiments would enable restoration of the market disruptions and lead to an expansion in the trade deficit which would perhaps reduce the balance of payment surplus and minimise the intervention by the Central bank to some extent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest projection by the US Federal Reserve to keep its interest rate near zero till 2023 would result in a sustained flow of foreign funds into countries like India. Therefore, the bankers’ bank needs to be watchful and avoid unnecessary currency appreciation which will not only affect exports but also other macroeconomic variables, thus risking the financial stability of the nation. The biggest challenge will perhaps come when pandemic recedes and activity picks back up but for now, the Reserve Bank needs to maintain a fine balance between the intertwined variables of inflation, bond yields, and currency market for the economic interest of India.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Central bank of a nation is tasked with multiple responsibilities to maintain the dynamic, complex and entangled macroeconomic variables with the sole objective of economic development of the country. The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) follows the same pursuit of growth by working out the price and financial stability of the state. The gigantic wave of virus that swept the world in late 2019 and hit India in early 2020 has inevitably accelerated the socio-economic division, the footprint of which will be felt for years to come. With the advent of such unprecedented times, all eyes are turned to the Central bank and to the government for rescue from the ramifications of this situation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Robot Tax to Fund Humans?: Analysing Future Prospects of Universal Basic Income</title>
      <link href="/A-Robot-Tax-to-Fund-Humans-Analysing-Future-Prospects-of-Universal-Basic-Income" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Robot Tax to Fund Humans?: Analysing Future Prospects of Universal Basic Income" />
      <published>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Robot-Tax-to-Fund-Humans---Analysing-Future-Prospects-of-Universal-Basic-Income</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Robot-Tax-to-Fund-Humans-Analysing-Future-Prospects-of-Universal-Basic-Income">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;There would be fewer and fewer jobs that the robot cannot do better.&lt;/em&gt;” &lt;em&gt;- &lt;/em&gt;Elon Musk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the world that we are very quickly creating, we are going to see more and more things that look like science fiction and fewer things that look like jobs. A recent study put lawyers and Artificial Intelligence (AI) against each other. Their task was to review non-disclosure agreements. It took AI 26 seconds to finish a task with 94% accuracy. The same task took the human manifestation 92 minutes with 85% accuracy. Hedge funds managed by AI gave an average return of 8% for which the humans could barely manage a 2%. AI could see in X-rays what an experienced doctor could not and was also better at predicting the risk an underlying disease poses to the patient. From supermarket checkout staff to truck drivers, everything is on the verge of getting automated. Thanks to human ingenuity, we no longer interact with the staff at &lt;em&gt;Blockbuster&lt;/em&gt;, rather we have &lt;em&gt;Netflix&lt;/em&gt; doing the work for us. &lt;em&gt;McKinsey&lt;/em&gt; has reported that whether it is repetitive low-skilled labour or high-skilled jobs, both are at risk of automation and as much as 30% of all jobs would be automated by 2030. The reality is that there is no clear limit to what AI can automate.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s no doubt that we are going to need lawyers and doctors in the future as there are some key things such as complex decision making and empathy that can’t be automated. Additionally, just because AI performs well in test settings doesn’t mean that it’s ready for the market just yet. We may need fewer humans to do the same amount of work and it’s not just AI we should be concerned about. The problem has gotten so bad that a new term has been coined- the ‘working poor’: people who earn below the poverty line despite actively working. What happens to these people when the basic entry-level jobs become obsolete in the face of reality?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Governments around the world need a narrative that helps people feel that they do belong and that they are being heard. One general solution to this is Universal Basic Income (UBI). That’s one of the ways through which governments can start rebuilding trust. What is it and what would the future of work look like with the implementation of&amp;nbsp; UBI?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Solution, how UBI can help?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though UBI may be the most ambitious policy of our times, it’s gaining popularity and momentum around the world fueled by the coronavirus pandemic and a whole legacy of unemployment and poverty that it is leaving behind. The idea of guaranteeing every person with a minimum living wage income is appealing. Andrew Yang, one of the former 2020 Democratic Presidential candidates, has based most of his campaign around the UBI. According to him, “&lt;em&gt;Technology is the oil of the 21st century&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly 200,000 people in South Korea's Gyeonggi province are a part of a radical experiment in UBI. They receive about $220 every three months. No questions asked. During the coronavirus pandemic, ‘Gyeonggi Pay’&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;was expanded to 13 million people in the province including new-borns to help people ride out the economic slowdown. There was one catch though, people had to spend the money only in their neighbourhoods to help stimulate the local economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The popularity of the local program during the pandemic has now drawn attention at the national level and there's another big reason. South Korea is one of the most automated countries in the world and about 15% of jobs in the country are projected to be automated by 2024. So some politicians, especially in the manufacturing hub of Gyeonggi, want to give all citizens about $430 every month to help prepare for a future with robots. The success of South Korea's experiment could change how other countries think about adopting their own UBI programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now people can’t decide what UBI is and what it should be. Though UBI in its raw sense is a fairly simple concept, its implementation has several ramifications. There are different schools of thought that pertain to evaluating UBI. While some see it in the setting where all other welfare schemes are scrapped and bureaucracy is eliminated, others demand UBI as an add-on to the existing welfare programs and want to keep UBI so high that work becomes optional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if we hand out enough free money and people just spend it on booze and stop working? Well, that is not true. According to a 2013 &lt;em&gt;World Bank&lt;/em&gt; study which specifically examined whether poor people waste their handouts on tobacco and alcohol if they receive it in the form of cash. The clear answer was, no they don't. The opposite is true. Other studies have shown that the richer you are, the more drugs and alcohol you consume. The lazy and drunk poor person is a stereotype rather than a reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A test run in Canada in the 1970’s showed that only 1% of the working population stopped working after UBI was rolled out and that too was attributed to child care reasons. On average, Canadians reduced their work time by less than 10% which was then dedicated to looking out for better jobs and going back to school. UBI aims to address that there are more motivations to work than to just cover up the necessities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if laziness and drugs are not a huge deal, why don’t our current welfare state programs solve poverty?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Many Strings Attached&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The existing welfare schemes have loopholes somewhere. Welfare or unemployment programmes often come with a lot of strings attached, taking part in courses, applying to a certain number of jobs every month, and taking any kind of job offer no matter if it is a good fit or what it pays. Besides the loss of personal freedom, these conditions are often a huge waste of time and only served to make the unemployment statistics seem less bad. Often your time would be much better spent looking for the right job, continuing education or starting a business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another unwanted side effect of many welfare programmes is that they trap people in poverty and promote passive behaviour. Imagine a benefit of $1000 every month. In a lot of programs, if you earn a single dollar extra, the whole thing is taken away. If you take a job which is paying $1200, you might not only lose your benefits but because of your taxes and other costs, you might end up having lesser money than before. So if you actively try to improve your situation and your total income is not rising or actually shrinking, welfare can create a ceiling that traps people in poverty and rewards passive behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A basic income can never be cut and therefore getting a job and additional income would always make your financial situation better. Work is always rewarded. Instead of a ceiling, it creates a floor from which people can lift themselves, and unlike unemployment benefits that run out over time, these payments are a stable flow of income.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even if UBI is the better model, is it economically feasible?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where does it come from?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although a Universal Basic Income contributes to the vitalisation of the consumer economy and increases small business revenue, it has its dark enemy: inflation. While demand props up and everything is rosy, prices inflate leaving everything just as it was before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the inflation problem and how to tackle it since the money is not being created by magic or printers, it needs to be transferred from somewhere. It is more of a shift of funds than the creation of new ones. Hence, no inflation. But how do we pay for it? There's no right answer here because the world is too diverse. How well-off the country is, what the local values are, are things like high taxes or cutting the defence budget politically acceptable or not? How much welfare state is already in place and is it effective? Each country has its own individual path to UBI. The easiest way to pay for UBI is to end all existing welfare and use the free funds to finance it. Not only would this make several government agencies disappear, which in itself saves money, it would also eliminate a lot of bureaucracy on the other hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, cutting them could leave many people worse off than before. If the goal is to have a foundation for everybody there still needs to be a program of some sort because just like countries, all people are not the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second way to finance UBI is by imposing higher taxes especially on the very wealthy and rich. The tax is to avenge the wealthy for reaping the most benefits of economic growth. The wealth gap is rapidly widening and many argue that it might be time to distribute the spoils more evenly to preserve social peace. Top percentiles get wealthier while the rest of the population stagnates. Inequality is increasingly getting skewed. There could be taxes on financial transactions, capital, land value, carbon or even robots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, UBI is not necessarily expensive. It can be balanced out with GDP growth as more spending stimulates the demand side of the economy. According to a recent study, a UBI of $1000 per month in the US could grow the GDP by 12% over eight years because it would enable poor people to spend more and increase overall demand. What about the people who do the dirty work? Who will work in the fields, crawl through sewers or lift bricks and stones? If you don't need to for survival, will people still do hard, boring and unfulfilling labour? UBI might give them enough leverage to demand better pay and working conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A study calculated that every extra dollar going to wage earners would add about $1.21 to the national economy, while every extra dollar going to high-income Americans would add only 39 cents. Making poor citizens better off could be a smart economic tactic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who demand enough UBI to cover all their costs and do no work, I have a problem. For me, the concept of work itself not being essential for survival is appalling. It would be unfair to portray work as just a chore. Work gives us something to do. It challenges us, it motivates us to improve, it forces us to engage. Many find friends or partners at work. We work for social status, wealth and for our place in the world. We're looking for something to do with our lives, and for many people work gives them meaning. Money alone wouldn't be enough to make people live a happy life. People need a differentiated and delineated purpose and simply giving people money without that purpose is a wrong solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other concerns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from this, there are other concerns associated with UBI too. If all welfare programs were exchanged for one single payment, this gives the government a lot of leverage. Individual programs are easier to attack or cut than a multitude. Populists might promise drastic changes to the UBI to get into power and a universal basic income does not tackle all problems when it comes to equality. For example, rents. While $1000 might be great in the countryside, it's not a lot for expensive metropolitan areas which could lead to poor people moving outwards and the difference between rich and poor becoming even more extreme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember the catch? South Korean people had to spend locally. That they can’t spend it in a McDonalds? Telling people where they can spend money sounds like an efficient way to boost local consumption but this policy has a loophole. Money is fungible and that what people can spend locally means they're saving on whatever other money they have. That other money was earlier being spent on non-local or non-eligible types of goods and services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one grave concern of governments using Universal Basic Income to practice political influence. The huge chunks of personal data collected about the preferences and choices of the consumer could lead to a massive data breach to achieve self-motivated interests. Although the South Korean government claims that it only analyses aggregate demand and not the individual data points, there’s still much obscurity. Governor Lee of the Gyeonggi&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;province is using the success of Gyeonggi Pay&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;as a pitch for the 2022 Presidential election and he's now leading in the polls. He plans to partly fund the UBI scheme through what he calls a ‘&lt;em&gt;Robot Tax&lt;/em&gt;’, essentially a levy on factories that have automated their production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, is UBI a good idea? The honest answer is that we don't know yet. There needs to be a lot more research and bigger test runs. We need to think about what kind of UBI we want and what we're prepared to give up to pay for it. The potential is huge. It might be the most promising model to sustainably eliminate poverty. It might seriously reduce the amount of desperation in the world and make us all much less stressed out. There would still be very rich and poor people but we could eliminate fear, suffering and existential panic for a significant part of the population. A recent pilot program in Finland found that UBI didn't help in getting people who were unemployed into jobs but it did make them happier and less stressed. About 50% of participants reported being healthier and having better overall well-being while the rest remained the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human nature has an inherent desire to be productive and to contribute something meaningful to the world. Sure, a lot of people do complain about their work and they dream of winning the lottery and never having to work again, perhaps these people may be happy for the first few months of not working but a few years down the road they may get the feeling of a life without purpose. When it comes to UBI, people often flippantly say that now everyone is free to pursue their passion but they forget the empathetic angle- everyone isn't them. There are also a lot many people in this world without passions or hobbies. It can be said that curiosity is the start of a passion. Follow the trail of what you're curious about and then develop that into a passion. Others still might even find that hard to do. So what happens to them? If technology does replace their jobs and they're unable to retrain, then what meaning will they find in life? That's personal to them and only they can solve that problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So automation is on the way. Advances in technology are too great to ignore. The people at the bottom of the workforce are going to start being replaced. UBI may be able to solve the issue of how everyone will be able to feed themselves in this future but what about that more burning question of purpose? Now that might be harder to solve.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Mehul Goyal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“There would be fewer and fewer jobs that the robot cannot do better.” - Elon Musk In the world that we are very quickly creating, we are going to see more and more things that look like science fiction and fewer things that look like jobs. A recent study put lawyers and Artificial Intelligence (AI) against each other. Their task was to review non-disclosure agreements. It took AI 26 seconds to finish a task with 94% accuracy. The same task took the human manifestation 92 minutes with 85% accuracy. Hedge funds managed by AI gave an average return of 8% for which the humans could barely manage a 2%. AI could see in X-rays what an experienced doctor could not and was also better at predicting the risk an underlying disease poses to the patient. From supermarket checkout staff to truck drivers, everything is on the verge of getting automated. Thanks to human ingenuity, we no longer interact with the staff at Blockbuster, rather we have Netflix doing the work for us. McKinsey has reported that whether it is repetitive low-skilled labour or high-skilled jobs, both are at risk of automation and as much as 30% of all jobs would be automated by 2030. The reality is that there is no clear limit to what AI can automate.&amp;nbsp; There’s no doubt that we are going to need lawyers and doctors in the future as there are some key things such as complex decision making and empathy that can’t be automated. Additionally, just because AI performs well in test settings doesn’t mean that it’s ready for the market just yet. We may need fewer humans to do the same amount of work and it’s not just AI we should be concerned about. The problem has gotten so bad that a new term has been coined- the ‘working poor’: people who earn below the poverty line despite actively working. What happens to these people when the basic entry-level jobs become obsolete in the face of reality? Governments around the world need a narrative that helps people feel that they do belong and that they are being heard. One general solution to this is Universal Basic Income (UBI). That’s one of the ways through which governments can start rebuilding trust. What is it and what would the future of work look like with the implementation of&amp;nbsp; UBI? The Solution, how UBI can help? Though UBI may be the most ambitious policy of our times, it’s gaining popularity and momentum around the world fueled by the coronavirus pandemic and a whole legacy of unemployment and poverty that it is leaving behind. The idea of guaranteeing every person with a minimum living wage income is appealing. Andrew Yang, one of the former 2020 Democratic Presidential candidates, has based most of his campaign around the UBI. According to him, “Technology is the oil of the 21st century”. Nearly 200,000 people in South Korea's Gyeonggi province are a part of a radical experiment in UBI. They receive about $220 every three months. No questions asked. During the coronavirus pandemic, ‘Gyeonggi Pay’ was expanded to 13 million people in the province including new-borns to help people ride out the economic slowdown. There was one catch though, people had to spend the money only in their neighbourhoods to help stimulate the local economy. The popularity of the local program during the pandemic has now drawn attention at the national level and there's another big reason. South Korea is one of the most automated countries in the world and about 15% of jobs in the country are projected to be automated by 2024. So some politicians, especially in the manufacturing hub of Gyeonggi, want to give all citizens about $430 every month to help prepare for a future with robots. The success of South Korea's experiment could change how other countries think about adopting their own UBI programs. Right now people can’t decide what UBI is and what it should be. Though UBI in its raw sense is a fairly simple concept, its implementation has several ramifications. There are different schools of thought that pertain to evaluating UBI. While some see it in the setting where all other welfare schemes are scrapped and bureaucracy is eliminated, others demand UBI as an add-on to the existing welfare programs and want to keep UBI so high that work becomes optional. But what if we hand out enough free money and people just spend it on booze and stop working? Well, that is not true. According to a 2013 World Bank study which specifically examined whether poor people waste their handouts on tobacco and alcohol if they receive it in the form of cash. The clear answer was, no they don't. The opposite is true. Other studies have shown that the richer you are, the more drugs and alcohol you consume. The lazy and drunk poor person is a stereotype rather than a reality. A test run in Canada in the 1970’s showed that only 1% of the working population stopped working after UBI was rolled out and that too was attributed to child care reasons. On average, Canadians reduced their work time by less than 10% which was then dedicated to looking out for better jobs and going back to school. UBI aims to address that there are more motivations to work than to just cover up the necessities.&amp;nbsp; But if laziness and drugs are not a huge deal, why don’t our current welfare state programs solve poverty? Many Strings Attached The existing welfare schemes have loopholes somewhere. Welfare or unemployment programmes often come with a lot of strings attached, taking part in courses, applying to a certain number of jobs every month, and taking any kind of job offer no matter if it is a good fit or what it pays. Besides the loss of personal freedom, these conditions are often a huge waste of time and only served to make the unemployment statistics seem less bad. Often your time would be much better spent looking for the right job, continuing education or starting a business. Another unwanted side effect of many welfare programmes is that they trap people in poverty and promote passive behaviour. Imagine a benefit of $1000 every month. In a lot of programs, if you earn a single dollar extra, the whole thing is taken away. If you take a job which is paying $1200, you might not only lose your benefits but because of your taxes and other costs, you might end up having lesser money than before. So if you actively try to improve your situation and your total income is not rising or actually shrinking, welfare can create a ceiling that traps people in poverty and rewards passive behaviour. A basic income can never be cut and therefore getting a job and additional income would always make your financial situation better. Work is always rewarded. Instead of a ceiling, it creates a floor from which people can lift themselves, and unlike unemployment benefits that run out over time, these payments are a stable flow of income.&amp;nbsp; But even if UBI is the better model, is it economically feasible? Where does it come from? Although a Universal Basic Income contributes to the vitalisation of the consumer economy and increases small business revenue, it has its dark enemy: inflation. While demand props up and everything is rosy, prices inflate leaving everything just as it was before. For the inflation problem and how to tackle it since the money is not being created by magic or printers, it needs to be transferred from somewhere. It is more of a shift of funds than the creation of new ones. Hence, no inflation. But how do we pay for it? There's no right answer here because the world is too diverse. How well-off the country is, what the local values are, are things like high taxes or cutting the defence budget politically acceptable or not? How much welfare state is already in place and is it effective? Each country has its own individual path to UBI. The easiest way to pay for UBI is to end all existing welfare and use the free funds to finance it. Not only would this make several government agencies disappear, which in itself saves money, it would also eliminate a lot of bureaucracy on the other hand. On the other hand, cutting them could leave many people worse off than before. If the goal is to have a foundation for everybody there still needs to be a program of some sort because just like countries, all people are not the same. The second way to finance UBI is by imposing higher taxes especially on the very wealthy and rich. The tax is to avenge the wealthy for reaping the most benefits of economic growth. The wealth gap is rapidly widening and many argue that it might be time to distribute the spoils more evenly to preserve social peace. Top percentiles get wealthier while the rest of the population stagnates. Inequality is increasingly getting skewed. There could be taxes on financial transactions, capital, land value, carbon or even robots. So, UBI is not necessarily expensive. It can be balanced out with GDP growth as more spending stimulates the demand side of the economy. According to a recent study, a UBI of $1000 per month in the US could grow the GDP by 12% over eight years because it would enable poor people to spend more and increase overall demand. What about the people who do the dirty work? Who will work in the fields, crawl through sewers or lift bricks and stones? If you don't need to for survival, will people still do hard, boring and unfulfilling labour? UBI might give them enough leverage to demand better pay and working conditions. A study calculated that every extra dollar going to wage earners would add about $1.21 to the national economy, while every extra dollar going to high-income Americans would add only 39 cents. Making poor citizens better off could be a smart economic tactic. For those who demand enough UBI to cover all their costs and do no work, I have a problem. For me, the concept of work itself not being essential for survival is appalling. It would be unfair to portray work as just a chore. Work gives us something to do. It challenges us, it motivates us to improve, it forces us to engage. Many find friends or partners at work. We work for social status, wealth and for our place in the world. We're looking for something to do with our lives, and for many people work gives them meaning. Money alone wouldn't be enough to make people live a happy life. People need a differentiated and delineated purpose and simply giving people money without that purpose is a wrong solution. Other concerns Apart from this, there are other concerns associated with UBI too. If all welfare programs were exchanged for one single payment, this gives the government a lot of leverage. Individual programs are easier to attack or cut than a multitude. Populists might promise drastic changes to the UBI to get into power and a universal basic income does not tackle all problems when it comes to equality. For example, rents. While $1000 might be great in the countryside, it's not a lot for expensive metropolitan areas which could lead to poor people moving outwards and the difference between rich and poor becoming even more extreme. Remember the catch? South Korean people had to spend locally. That they can’t spend it in a McDonalds? Telling people where they can spend money sounds like an efficient way to boost local consumption but this policy has a loophole. Money is fungible and that what people can spend locally means they're saving on whatever other money they have. That other money was earlier being spent on non-local or non-eligible types of goods and services. There is one grave concern of governments using Universal Basic Income to practice political influence. The huge chunks of personal data collected about the preferences and choices of the consumer could lead to a massive data breach to achieve self-motivated interests. Although the South Korean government claims that it only analyses aggregate demand and not the individual data points, there’s still much obscurity. Governor Lee of the Gyeonggi province is using the success of Gyeonggi Pay as a pitch for the 2022 Presidential election and he's now leading in the polls. He plans to partly fund the UBI scheme through what he calls a ‘Robot Tax’, essentially a levy on factories that have automated their production. Conclusion So, is UBI a good idea? The honest answer is that we don't know yet. There needs to be a lot more research and bigger test runs. We need to think about what kind of UBI we want and what we're prepared to give up to pay for it. The potential is huge. It might be the most promising model to sustainably eliminate poverty. It might seriously reduce the amount of desperation in the world and make us all much less stressed out. There would still be very rich and poor people but we could eliminate fear, suffering and existential panic for a significant part of the population. A recent pilot program in Finland found that UBI didn't help in getting people who were unemployed into jobs but it did make them happier and less stressed. About 50% of participants reported being healthier and having better overall well-being while the rest remained the same. Human nature has an inherent desire to be productive and to contribute something meaningful to the world. Sure, a lot of people do complain about their work and they dream of winning the lottery and never having to work again, perhaps these people may be happy for the first few months of not working but a few years down the road they may get the feeling of a life without purpose. When it comes to UBI, people often flippantly say that now everyone is free to pursue their passion but they forget the empathetic angle- everyone isn't them. There are also a lot many people in this world without passions or hobbies. It can be said that curiosity is the start of a passion. Follow the trail of what you're curious about and then develop that into a passion. Others still might even find that hard to do. So what happens to them? If technology does replace their jobs and they're unable to retrain, then what meaning will they find in life? That's personal to them and only they can solve that problem. So automation is on the way. Advances in technology are too great to ignore. The people at the bottom of the workforce are going to start being replaced. UBI may be able to solve the issue of how everyone will be able to feed themselves in this future but what about that more burning question of purpose? Now that might be harder to solve.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Promoting Free Trade in South Asia: SAFTA and Beyond</title>
      <link href="/Promoting-Free-Trade-in-South-Asia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Promoting Free Trade in South Asia: SAFTA and Beyond" />
      <published>2020-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Promoting-Free-Trade-in-South-Asia</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Promoting-Free-Trade-in-South-Asia">&lt;p&gt;South Asia experienced rapid GDP growth in the 1980’s, averaging around 6 % per annum across the region. This has attracted much global attention to the region. In addition to policy and institutional reforms that have been instrumental in tackling unemployment and poverty, market integration and regional cooperation have also been key to rapid growth and development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the 1990’s, South Asian countries have made efforts to enhance their trade and investment flows with the larger objective of poverty alleviation and economic development. Historically, changes in the trade policies of the region have been driven by the unilateral liberalisation of individual countries. However, preferential trade agreements were initiated after the formation of the South Asian Association for Regional Cooperation (SAARC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South Asian Preferential Trade Agreement (SAPTA) was signed by SAARC in 1995 as a step towards strengthening regional trade. However, SAPTA was not successful in enhancing trade among the member nations because its product coverage and tariff concessions were too limited. Thus, the South Asian Free Trade Agreement (SAFTA) was introduced. It aimed towards eventually bringing tariffs down to zero. SAFTA was signed on January 6, 2004, during the 12th SAARC Summit, held at Islamabad. The tariff liberalisation began to be implemented only in July 2006. In accordance with the first phase of the agreement, India, Pakistan, and Srilanka reduced their tariffs to 20% while Bangladesh, Bhutan and Maldives reduced their tariffs to nearly 30%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The introduction of SAFTA provided many opportunities to SAARC countries, but at the same time, it posed a few challenges. This was mainly because the agreement would have a significant impact on the welfare of member nations and on domestic producers. Critics say that SAFTA was unsuccessful in changing the existing trade patterns among South Asian countries to the extent that was initially proclaimed. Though SAFTA was introduced to counter the problems posed by SAPTA, it is considered to be an extension of the previous agreement. The only changes seemed to be the inclusion of trade facilitation elements and the switching of the trade liberalisation process from a positive list to a negative list approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main purpose of introducing the SAFTA was to encourage trade and also increase economic cooperation among the SAARC countries by reducing the tariffs and non-tariff barriers (NTBs) as well as by bringing transparency and equity among the nations. There was also a special preference to the Least Development Countries (LDCs) among the SAARC nations. SAFTA was also viewed as a South Asian Counterpart of the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA). By the end of 2013, the total exports by the member states under SAFTA had reached close to $3 billion. The question that arises is regarding the success of SAFTA over the years in achieving the goals that it set out for itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outcomes and Beyond&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality of the implementation of SAFTA was far different from the expectations that it had established. SAFTA’s main objective was to enable smooth movement of goods across borders with low tariffs, similar to what the European Union had been able to achieve. However, the governments of South Asia were not able to streamline their relations often due to conflicts between two or more nations. For example, the conflict between India and Pakistan has prevented many SAARC summits from taking place, thereby hindering the objectives of regional cooperation. A 2006 article in &lt;em&gt;Economic and Political Weekly&lt;/em&gt; titled ‘Does SAFTA have a Future?’ by Dushni Weerakoon and Jayanthi Thennakoon stated that nearly 53% of import trade amongst South Asian countries was excluded from the trade liberalisation as required under SAFTA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tariff Liberalisation Program (TLP) that was adopted under this agreement provided a clear system of tariff reduction. Non-LDCs were required to reduce existing tariffs to 0-5% within five years post-implementation, whereas LDCs were required to reduce tariffs to 30% within two years and to 0-5% within eight years. However, this system was criticised as it could potentially lead to the back-loading of tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TLP also excludes those goods which come under the sensitive list given by the member countries. This limits the range of goods available for trade. However, on the positive side, SAFTA puts a limit on the maximum number of sensitive goods that a country can list. This provision was not included in previous regional trade agreements such as the India-Sri Lanka Free Trade Agreement and the India-Pakistan Free Trade Agreement. Some features even hinted at turning a new page for trade policy, such as the provision of compensation for revenue losses that small countries were expected to face in the event of tariff reductions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also draw a comparison between the ASEAN Free Trade Area (AFTA) and the South Asian Free Trade Area (SAFTA). Under AFTA, between 1992-2017, exports increased from 21 to 27%. However, under SAFTA, this figure was very low. During the period that SAFTA came into effect, around 6-7% of the South Asian country’s exports were intra-regional exports. However, in recent years, this has declined to around 5%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Examining the Reasons for SAFTA’s Unsuccessful Run&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Asian Development Bank estimates that even after 35 years of SAARC’s establishment, it has not been able to significantly affect intra-regional trade. Many economists are of the view that SAFTA’s ineffectiveness could be attributed to the fact that it maintains a sensitive list which allows the exclusion of goods from the trade liberalisation process. The problem lies in the fact that these sensitive goods account for 6-45% of intra-regional imports in South Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The World Bank’s report titled &lt;em&gt;A Glass Half Full: The Promise of Regional Trade in South Asia&lt;/em&gt; (2018) examines SAFTA’s ineffectiveness in more depth. It is estimated that SAFTA’s proper application could have increased South Asian regional trade by more than $2 billion. However, SAFTA’s trade remains the lowest in the world among all other Regional Trade Agreements (RTAs) because South Asian countries are keener on trading with the US or the European Union. While intra-EU trade has a 70% success rate and the intra-NAFTA trade has a 50% success rate, the intra-SAARC trade has a meagre 5% success rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another notable finding is that within this region, there is a tendency of introducing para-tariffs that are levied on imports and not on domestic production. In Bangladesh, it is known as Supplementary Duty, whereas in Sri Lanka it is known as Ports and Airports Development Levy. These para-tariffs increase protection for domestic producers but also increase non-transparency between nations which hinders the process of free trade. This is a point of concern as these para-tariffs are not under the purview of SAFTA negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to a World Bank report, trade in South Asia can triple from its current volume of $23 billion to $67 billion. Considering this untapped potential, SAARC nations need to come together to address these issues. This will not only promote economic liberalisation by providing a higher variety of goods at lower prices, expanded markets and job creation, but will also take these nations to new heights of development. SAARC nations should also take a proactive role in implementing lower tariffs, lesser Non-Tariff Barriers to Trade (NTBs) and a common external tariff. Other initiatives such as creating a South Asian economic corridor and resolving disputes between countries in the region will go a long way in facilitating regional cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India plays an especially large role in turning around the fate of SAFTA. India is the dominant trading partner for most South Asian countries. About 90% of the foreign trade of countries such as Bangladesh, Nepal and Srilanka is achieved through bilateral trade relations with India. Thus, the creation of a free trade area is heavily reliant on India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, we can say that at the macro level, many initiatives are being taken to enable trade among South Asian countries and to limit trade with other regional unions for the collective prosperity of South Asia. However, the much anticipated SAFTA has fallen short of expectations. Factors such as simplifying the tariff structure, easing foreign exchange controls, transit facilities for the landlocked countries and easier banking facilities for import financing can help to build confidence among the SAARC nations. Apart from focusing solely on securing SAARC objectives, South Asian nations should also pay attention to bilateralism and sub-regionalism within South Asia. In 2014, Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi at the 18th SAARC Summit focussed on the need for relationships of South Asian countries to shift beyond SAARC. There is also a need for the launch of another free trade agreement that counters the issues of the SAFTA trade agreement to achieve the objective of establishing a South Asian Union. It is yet to be seen whether a new trade agreement is launched or not and if it is, how successfully does it tackle the issues of SAFTA or does it become an extension of SAFTA, just like the latter became of SAPTA.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Cherry Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">South Asia experienced rapid GDP growth in the 1980’s, averaging around 6 % per annum across the region. This has attracted much global attention to the region. In addition to policy and institutional reforms that have been instrumental in tackling unemployment and poverty, market integration and regional cooperation have also been key to rapid growth and development.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">EdTech: The New Normal of Learning?</title>
      <link href="/EdTech" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EdTech: The New Normal of Learning?" />
      <published>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/EdTech</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/EdTech">&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 has impacted every area of our lives and left us with no choice but to find new alternatives. Schooling and education were no exception. Parents, teachers and students felt nothing but helpless as everything came to a standstill. Schools and universities were shut and the situation was uncertain. While it was convenient for adults to adapt to the new normal and work from home, teachers and students had a hard time figuring out a way to keep the learning going. Edtech, the practice of using technology in education, has been around for quite some years but it was never considered a substitute to classroom teaching. Parents have always preferred live learning as the best possible method. However, times changed and we ended up in a situation that required us to learn virtually and adopt edtech. It has been six months and the edtech sector has flourished more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise was huge and pretty visible as the sector dominated the market numbers. The edtech sector in India is currently estimated to be valued at $735 million and a growth of 150% is expected in 2020. A number of edtech startups have completed their long-term goals within these six months of lockdown. The users have increased manifold and the businesses are soaring high. The consumer base of these upcoming disruptors in the education arena, not only consists of students but also working professionals. Lockdown increased the time people had on their hands which they utilised by enhancing and developing their skill sets. These innovative startups have included various courses which attract not only students but also adults who are currently working. Employers have also encouraged their employees to learn new skills via these courses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edtech has evolved over the years and has come a long way. It started with video-based learning which has now evolved into an interactive platform that adapts to the different needs of every learner. Students used to interact with peers and teachers which made learning more wholesome. Until recently, interactive virtual learning wasn’t a thing. But today, every edtech platform has various features that enhance the learning to make it more interactive and complete. Parents have started to rely on them as it makes learning fun and makes the concepts easy to understand. Moreover, allowing the students to learn at their own pace has proved to be another reason for their huge success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millions of people have signed up in the past few months and this massive growth has led to increased hiring and new opportunities. The increased consumer base demanded an increased workforce to deal with the complaints and enhance the learning experience for its users. Unlike Facebook and other social media platforms, these learning platforms offer paid services to its customers. Even besides all this, the growth is consistent. The reason being, most parents are willing to spend on their child’s education in the hope of a better future for them. Thus, paid subscriptions to e-learning was seen as an investment and was a big hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the edtech boom sustain post this lockdown period? It has been six months and most of us have adapted to this new normal of wearing masks and following social distancing at all points of time. The easing of lockdown has begun and people are getting back to work. Eventually schools, colleges and universities will open up for students, and in no time classroom teaching will overtake these virtual platforms. We cannot really predict how it is going to turn out for these companies in the near future, but it is highly likely that the growth might increase even in the post-COVID-19 period. First, the New Education Policy (NEP) will be implemented and the use of technology in learning will finally catch up with the outdated curriculums of schools. With the government’s plans to introduce coding for students, it is likely that parents would trust online tutors more than they would trust school teachers. The simple reason being that these edtech startups have the resources to onboard experienced coders and teachers in this field and many of these platforms already offer fundamental courses on coding. Second, with the growing demand for skills like Artificial Intelligence (AI) and machine learning in every field, it seems like technology in education is here to stay. The edtech market will not die out soon as we are expecting a merger between online and offline learning in the entire education system. There are certain problems that might impact its growth as a whole, issues of internet connectivity in suburban and rural areas might be a problem for many. All these problems demand unique solutions that the developers need to think about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edtech is like any other service which makes our lives easier. It aids us by providing a simpler way of learning and understanding things. We don’t know as of now whether it can possibly replace our classroom learning, however, it can definitely be integrated with the existing system to make our approach more holistic. The burden now lies on the developers to attract maximum users and provide unique features to ensure sustainability. While the choice remains on the students and the parents if they choose to trust this form of education in the coming decades.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">COVID-19 has impacted every area of our lives and left us with no choice but to find new alternatives. Schooling and education were no exception. Parents, teachers and students felt nothing but helpless as everything came to a standstill. Schools and universities were shut and the situation was uncertain. While it was convenient for adults to adapt to the new normal and work from home, teachers and students had a hard time figuring out a way to keep the learning going. Edtech, the practice of using technology in education, has been around for quite some years but it was never considered a substitute to classroom teaching. Parents have always preferred live learning as the best possible method. However, times changed and we ended up in a situation that required us to learn virtually and adopt edtech. It has been six months and the edtech sector has flourished more than ever.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Spirituality and Marketing: An Amalgam</title>
      <link href="/Spirituality-and-Marketing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spirituality and Marketing: An Amalgam" />
      <published>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Spirituality-and-Marketing</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Spirituality-and-Marketing">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Amalgam&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religion is a highly inappropriate topic for the workplace, and only has an institutional connotation that manifests into the practice of rituals, adhering to dogmas and attending services. Spirituality, on the other hand, deals with life’s deeper motivations and an emotional connection to God and is a highly appropriate subject for discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that the world is smitten by the spirituality bug and marketing academics are oblivious of this development. Spirituality is increasingly impacting the beliefs and behaviours of consumers around the world. A &lt;em&gt;USA Weekend&lt;/em&gt; poll conducted in July 1998 revealed that 47% of Americans viewed spirituality as the most important element of their happiness. They care deeply about ecology and saving the planet, about relationships, peace, social justice, along with authenticity, self-actualisation, spirituality, and self-expression. They tend to be both inner-directed and socially concerned; they want to be activists, volunteers, and contributors to good causes. It’s 2020 and there is a massive influx of spiritual information, currently crowding the pages of popular newspapers, television programmes, and the glossiest mainstream magazines. Meditation classes are offered at the United Nations, Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi uses visualisations and relaxation techniques to inspire the world, while political matters of spiritual and religious importance are the frequent subjects of public questioning and curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies have increasingly begun to use marketing as a spiritual practice to delve into a deeper wisdom, product offerings, and how they can help clients solve their problems. No jargon, no gimmicks, no trickery, just a deeper ‘wisdom’ in their marketing. Companies have started to use collaborative methods to co-vision with what the customer wants and help them see beyond their limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The root of spiritual marketing is clarity - the unwavering perception of how to do self-promotion. If you are clear about what you want and what you offer, your prospective customers will instantly know whether or not you offer what they need. A deep appreciation for a clear pricing strategy because consumers know the rule, &lt;em&gt;“if you have to ask how much, you probably can’t afford it”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies have realised that spirituality is the human response to God’s gracious call to a one-on-one relationship with Him. Therefore, companies encourage customers to trust the transfer of their (profitable) divine goals and perceptions. What follows is a spiritual bond between the two parties where neither can survive without the other, built on a dynamic system of data projections from both sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Big Fat Business&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only has mainstream spirituality gained popularity, but it has also become a big business. New age spirituality is a multi-billion-dollar industry, and some of the most popular contemporary spiritual teachers and gurus are among the wealthiest people in the world. Right from &lt;em&gt;“You can deprive the body, but the soul needs chocolate”&lt;/em&gt; to ‘Yoga-inspired athletic wear’ line of products, established companies and secular corporate firms are increasingly using spiritual appeals to identify and bond with consumers. It is one of the fast-growing industries. India’s estimated spiritual and religious market is over $30 billion. Studies have found that women comprise two-thirds of the active spiritual market consumers, particularly high income, educated, and middle-aged females but the men and youth market is also growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali  and Art of Living’s line of body care products and brands have created a niche for themselves in the market. The ageing of consumers in the western and Indian societies, coupled with their level of affluence, now permits them and the business community the luxury of seeking more meaning in their lives. Organisations like these are widening their reach in the production and distribution of these consumer goods. Furthermore some of these have entered into backward integration to source raw material as well. Once sold only at their &lt;em&gt;ashrams&lt;/em&gt; or particular outlets, today they can be found online or in supermarkets or even in &lt;em&gt;kirana&lt;/em&gt; stores. While FMCG companies need to invest a lot of time, effort, and money in branding and advertising their products, these spiritual gurus already have a huge number of devotees as their loyal consumer base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s to no surprise that such companies come up with unique, targeted and sound vocabulary and phraseology: “oneness”, “loving ourselves”, “we deserve”, “meditation”, “letting go”, “touching the void” among many others. Such marketing campaigns give an exotic edge, help unfurl competitive advantages, pep-up the spiritual image of the company, and facilitate the psychological transfer of ethics. Having a deep connection with clients and the community is what makes these business marketing techniques work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Magical World with Less Documentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the paucity of research on the topic of spirituality, bountiful opportunities and several interesting issues could be researched. For example, does the incidence of spirituality match with global macro-economic trends and how would these trends impact consumer behaviour and marketing practices? What is the relationship between rising incomes and economic development with the propagation of spiritually inspired ideas? Is spirituality increasingly used as a means of identity preservation and as a reaction to deterritorialisation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explain these dynamics in the marketplace would require both strong qualitative and quantitative research. Scales that measure spirituality may be engineered by incorporating spiritual variables comprising both beliefs and practices. The need is to comprehensively conceptualise the concept of spirituality and delimit its boundaries so that its conflation with the concept of religion is not misunderstood and fairly appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authentic spirituality is non-conceptual, and this presents a serious dilemma for spirituality in marketing for most of what attracts people is conceptual. Therefore, most authentic companies strike a balance between marketing and propagating non-conceptual bias, so that there is enough conceptualisation to hook people, but not too much to badly interfere with the marketing process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Said more simply, companies are all doing something inside themselves that is creating their outer results. Their inner state of being is creating their business or lack of it. Their inner spirit is doing their marketing. To paraphrase the famous Swiss psychologist Carl Jung, &lt;em&gt;“Until you make the unconscious conscious, it will direct your life and you will call it fate”.&lt;/em&gt; If you don’t consciously select where you want to go, you go where your unconscious wants you to go. Companies are having a great time skewing our unconscious minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of today, spirituality in marketing is still a slippery construct, and only a systematic segmentation program of inquiry will provide meaningful and actionable insights. It’s a mystery yet, but if the business invests in its spiritual aspect, it will reap many unanticipated rewards, both financially and by gaining joy and bliss in doing their own business.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Mehul Goyal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Amalgam</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Stocks Rallying Again? Time to invest?</title>
      <link href="/Stocks-Rallying-Again" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stocks Rallying Again? Time to invest?" />
      <published>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Stocks-Rallying-Again</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Stocks-Rallying-Again">&lt;p&gt;Speculation: the word around which the life of most of the people trading in the stock market revolves. Every trade involved in the stock market is merely a bet speculating upon the prices of stocks going up or down. Stock markets around the world crashed in the month of March due to a panic caused by the spread of COVID-19, bears conquered the indices like Dow Jones, S&amp;amp;P500, Shanghai Index, Nikkei225 and Nifty50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus outbreak got worse day-by-day and even now cases are rising every day although if you see the popular stock market indices, they are again back to the point where they were before March lows. A rally is bringing the indices back to their pre-March levels. Are the economies getting better? No. Have we recovered from the virus? No. Is GDP growth recovering? NO, instead most of the nations have announced contraction in GDP and are further expecting it to contract till 2021. Why have stocks been moving up again then? Let’s find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many countries worldwide went under complete lockdown. People tried looking for sources of income during this time and as the stock market never sleeps people turned to stocks to earn something in their free time. Everyone became a trader. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Robinhood-Misleads-Gen-Z&quot;&gt;Robinhood&lt;/a&gt; trading app, the most popular stock trading app in the US that charges zero commission, saw a rise in new account openings during the lockdown. The revenues of Robinhood have doubled in a quarter which clearly shows that retail participation has risen and is continuing to rise as we speak. Retailers with no knowledge of stocks, futures and options are trading just for the sake of earning some extra income during their free time and are buying stocks like grocery items, which is one of the main reasons for the rally of stock indices. All market indicators show that the market is overbought and a second wave of crash is due. Big retailers on seeing a big fall in the market start selling stocks to average out their price, and when they enter the market after a fall, it helps the market to regain again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the big question arises: where do we invest our money right now? Seeing a crash due in the market again, and positive signs not being visible in the short term for the economy, it is best to have a diversified portfolio. Over the years, the investment that is the most promising is gold but becoming wealthy through gold is almost unheard of. Seeing the current scenario one must have around 15-20% of his/her investment in gold, paper gold is preferred as you don’t have to keep it safe and don’t have to worry about it. Around 30% of the portfolio should be in mutual funds (Systematic Investment Plan) and 25% should be allocated to equities that too in ‘blue-chip’ stocks because right now profitability of companies is not important, the most important thing is survival and these companies have a huge amount of capital backing. If you want higher returns then you can switch to mid-caps and small-caps too, but your risk increases as well. 10% should be invested in very safe investments like fixed deposits for safe and a minimum guaranteed return. The remaining portfolio can be kept as cash-in-hand, and then one can wait for dips and add stocks of their choice. This portfolio investment has been advised for people who want to take moderate risk with decent returns. If you wish, you can go for high risk by allocating more to equities and if you want less risk then decrease your dependence on equities. Therefore, investing in such turbulent times depends totally on a person’s risk appetite and the depth of his pockets. No one can predict the movement of markets in such unprecedented times. It would be better to have a well-diversified portfolio and not expose yourself too much to a particular type of investment.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rachit Kumar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Speculation: the word around which the life of most of the people trading in the stock market revolves. Every trade involved in the stock market is merely a bet speculating upon the prices of stocks going up or down. Stock markets around the world crashed in the month of March due to a panic caused by the spread of COVID-19, bears conquered the indices like Dow Jones, S&amp;amp;P500, Shanghai Index, Nikkei225 and Nifty50.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Past and Future of the Future Group</title>
      <link href="/Past-Future-Future-Group" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Past and Future of the Future Group" />
      <published>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Past-Future-Future-Group</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Past-Future-Future-Group">&lt;p&gt;Kishore Biyani, the retail maverick of India, was the man who took the retail industry by storm. He realised the potential of retail, which oligarchs like the Ambanis and Birlas could not appreciate, and therefore came up with household names like Pantaloons, FBB and Big Bazaar. He is often referred to as the Sam Walton (the owner of Walmart) of India. However, recently, Reliance Industries (RIL) bought Biyani’s Future Group for a whopping ₹247 billion. Let’s understand why Mr Biyani had to sell off his dream, but for starters, let’s get acquainted with his story of rags-to-riches before getting onto the bad part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kishore Biyani, the current pin-up kid of the Indian retail industry, has assumed numerous jobs, however in the long run, he settled to turn into an inventive retailer. In contrast with numerous others of his class, Kishore wasn’t brought into the world with the proverbial silver spoon in his mouth and has, without any help, ascended the halls of India’s business elite. Nevertheless, coming from a family of businessmen, business flowed in his blood. He always knew that he would end up becoming a businessman because of his mindset and his ability to understand the customer. In order to understand the real world and to interpret the consumer’s nerve, he was often seen spending time visiting various shops rather than studying. His career actually started when he neared the end of his graduation by joining his family business Bansi Silk Mills, which traded fabrics. Though he used to go to his office, he wasn’t getting the kick which he wanted. He was unable to feel the enthusiasm and opportunity and was feeling quieted by the organisation’s moderate business culture and used to leave within 2 or 3 hours. He was totally against the manner in which the organisation worked and felt that their demeanour and approach towards the business wasn’t right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While he was meeting his friends, he noticed them wearing ‘stonewashed’ fabric, he promptly acted on this new information and contacted a few mill owners and sold it to the garment dealers. Kishore had tasted blood and now he wanted more! He frantically began to search for something new, something other than what’s expected. He launched his own brand of fabric for men’s trousers called, WBB – White, Brown, and Blue. In 1987, he started his own garment manufacturing company, Manz Wear Private Ltd, which he sold under the brand name Pantaloons (he chose the name Pantaloons because it gave the feel of an Italian Fashion House and secondly because it was closer to &lt;em&gt;patloon&lt;/em&gt;, an Urdu word for trouser). During the preliminary stages, Biyani went through a difficult phase as banks didn’t want to extend him loans, family and friends were also sceptical about the business. But &lt;em&gt;“it was fun”&lt;/em&gt; for him as he steered through the rough phase like a sailor with unbridled confidence and faith in himself. In 1992, he entered the stock market to fuel the car. After raising money, he went on a spree to open Pantaloons stores pan India along with some marketing campaigns and by the end of 1994 Pantaloons laid eggs worth ₹6 million annually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After tasting initial success with Pantaloons, he forayed into the supermarket business with the brand name Big Bazaar, wooing its core customers into large self-service supermarkets and leveraging his own supply and logistics chain to offer across-the-board discounts on maximum retail prices. Big Bazaar was formed on three pillars of Kishore’s ideology- Food, Fashion, and FMCG. You went to get a few vegetables, yet you needed to go through walkways of kurtas and dresses, and were enticed to purchase them. For budget clothing, Biyani launched the FBB design brand. Future Groups Home Center stores were also launched to force people to redesign their homes with the Future Group. The group also forayed into the tech retail sector with the e-zone varying media item stores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the offset of the story, everything seems spick and span but on the inside, the finances weren’t going great. He produced a few films between 2002 and 2003 which turned out to be huge flops. While he was growing at break-neck speed and success seemed to be touching his feet, all the acquisitions and the more than frequent opening up of stores, took him into bucket loads of debt. In fact, in 2012 he sold his flagship Pantaloons retail format to Aditya Birla Group for an estimated ₹16 billion at a time when the group had accumulated a consolidated debt of ₹78.50 billion. In 2014, Future Group acquired the south-based Nilgiris chain of markets for ₹3 billion. In 2011, Foodhall, an upmarket food store, found in luxurious shopping malls, was conceptualised by Biyani’s elder daughter, Avni Biyani. In 2016, a couple of years after Walmart and Bharti Airtel  headed out in different directions and failed to set up retail stores as was agreed under their deal, the Future Group took a plunge and purchased the Bharti Airtel’s Easyday chain of supermarkets. A year ago, it trimmed more than 100 Easyday stores, in an endeavour to cut costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is imperative to think that Mr Biyani tried to put his hands in almost everything from insurance to fashion. But the fact is that it was the fashion outlets which outdid every other business he had. Had he stuck to what he was good at, he would not have had to see these days. It’s not that he shouldn’t have diversified but at a steady pace rather than foraying into every other segment at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazon, which had announced an Indian war chest of $5.54 billion, and Flipkart, which further got strengthened after its buyout by Walmart, were wooing customers across all retail segments. Biyani tried to stick with his core competence customers: the middle-income Indians who preferred to shop in physical stores. Sadly, the customer had tasted the best of both worlds, and were swiftly moving online. Future Group tried but missed the e-commerce opportunity largely because of the promoter’s scepticism of making money on selling goods online. In 2017, the Future Retail also unveiled its ‘Retail 3.0’ platform that would enable tech to merge with offline retail. But it was too late as players were already established and people were happy buying from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, we can say the speed of expansion, acquisition of several retail assets — both regional and national, a chase to build more private labels and in-house manufacturing capabilities have left the company burdened with debt, and caused rating downgrades across the group’s listed entities. As of September 30, 2019, the combined debt of Future Group’s listed companies increased to ₹127 billion from ₹109 billion as of March 31, 2019. His debt woes were further exacerbated by the lockdown, wherein businesses were stalled but he had to keep servicing his debt. Finally, RIL acquired the retail and wholesale business, and the logistics and warehousing business from the Future Group for a lump-sum aggregate consideration of ₹247 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot can be said about Mr Biyani but he believed in the ‘Indian Dream’; he always wanted to help the Indian dream fly high and wanted to ensure that the &lt;em&gt;‘Sone Ki Chidiya’&lt;/em&gt; (Golden Bird) soared once again. We’re left with one question: will Biyani bounce back? Too early to tell. He is a brand and I’m optimistic enough that he’ll come back sooner and much stronger!!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aditya Khandelwal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Kishore Biyani, the retail maverick of India, was the man who took the retail industry by storm. He realised the potential of retail, which oligarchs like the Ambanis and Birlas could not appreciate, and therefore came up with household names like Pantaloons, FBB and Big Bazaar. He is often referred to as the Sam Walton (the owner of Walmart) of India. However, recently, Reliance Industries (RIL) bought Biyani’s Future Group for a whopping ₹247 billion. Let’s understand why Mr Biyani had to sell off his dream, but for starters, let’s get acquainted with his story of rags-to-riches before getting onto the bad part.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Wirecard: The Financial Collapse of the Century</title>
      <link href="/Wirecard-The-Financial-Collapse-of-the-Century" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wirecard: The Financial Collapse of the Century" />
      <published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Wirecard-The-Financial-Collapse-of-the-Century</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Wirecard-The-Financial-Collapse-of-the-Century">&lt;p&gt;The finance industry already grappling with the effects of COVID-19, faced yet another shock with one of the biggest financial scandals in the world coming to the limelight - the Wirecard scandal. Wirecard, a Munich-based payment processing company, once seen as a darling of investors with a market capitalisation of over $28 billion at its peak, filed for bankruptcy on June 25, 2020, after disclosing a $2.1 billion hole in its balance sheet. But what went wrong with the company?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fintech company incorporated in 1999, joined the Frankfurt stock exchange in 2005 and ascended to the ranking of Germany’s 30 leading companies, also known as the DAX Index. It claimed to have subsidiaries across the globe, with payments being processed for more than 200,000 merchants and clients including major European supermarket chains and airlines. It attracted notable investors such as SoftBank. Wirecard was like any other payment processing company that facilitated transactions between consumers and merchants, and earned a certain percentage per transaction. However what set the company apart from its competitors was its rapid expansion in Asia for the reason that it marketed itself as the leader in this system, claiming to have superior technology and highly capitalising on the shift to a cashless society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2008, the first allegations of accounting irregularities against the firm came to light and in the wake of the attack, the company appointed Ernst &amp;amp; Young (EY), one of the largest accounting enterprises in the world, to conduct a special audit on these claims. EY soon then became the Chief Auditor of the organisation for the next 10 years, signing off the firm’s balance sheet. As allegations against the firm of inflating its operational numbers in Asia continued to surface over the years, a pattern emerged with how the company dealt with these criticisms. They would aggressively deny any wrongdoings and announce that it was an attempt to manipulate their stock prices. However, the stock prices kept rising, undeterred by any negative news coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As claims of malpractice mounted, BaFin- the German financial regulator, during its probe focussed more on the accusers rather than the claims against the enterprise. Various analysts believe that authorities’ protection stemmed as it was a huge moment to see a European home-grown company competing against tech titans of Silicon Valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2019, the regulator announced an unprecedented 2-month ban on short-selling of the company’s shares due to its stock price plummeting below €100, citing its importance to the economy and serious threats to market confidence. Some also point to Germany’s corporate culture being wary of foreign speculators, since many allegations were brought forward by the British newspaper &lt;em&gt;Financial Times&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;FT&lt;/em&gt;). However, the regulators denied all allegations against the organisation and even filed a criminal investigation against &lt;em&gt;FT&lt;/em&gt; for colluding with short-sellers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wirecard mainly functioned by buying shell companies that acted as third party payment processors for the organisation. In return, these companies paid them a commission. However, instead of funds flowing into their Munich bank, it was all transferred to escrow accounts. These are special accounts where multiple parties can use them, hence convincing the public that large sums of money existed in them and were used by its subsidiaries. These accounts held more than $2 billion, all of Wirecard’s profit of more than a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, &lt;em&gt;FT&lt;/em&gt; published an article after being alerted by a whistle-blower, that the organisation was cooking accounting books, hiking up its sales and profit numbers of Asia and Pacific operations. Hence, to put an end to these allegations, the company, in 2019, hired Klynveld Peat Marwick Goerdeler (KPMG) to conduct a special audit. The audit report stated that it could not verify the authenticity of these escrow accounts. As more events unfolded, the company stated that all of the money was stored in the Philippines, and not in these escrow accounts. When EY went to examine these claims from the Philippines bank, the former was notified that the documents submitted by the company were all spurious and money never really entered their financial system, thus the $2.1 billion never existed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This announcement led to the arrest of Markus Braun, CEO and CTO of Wirecard since 2002, on June 23, 2020, on suspicion of inflating the value of the company through feigning business with third parties. Two days later, the company filed for insolvency, making it the biggest accounting scandal in post-war German history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The disclosure of malpractice of such a magnitude has eroded the trust in the country’s authorities, giving a heavy blow to Germany’s reputation as a financial centre - impacting its businesses and the confidence of market participants. This revelation has increased the scrutiny of not only accounting firms, especially EY, for failing to inspect the legitimacy of such an account, but also on regulators for their inadequacy. Various critics argued that Germany’s regulatory system is neither equipped to handle large scale processing enterprises like Wirecard nor does it have the power to oversee the investigation of potential malpractices. This highlights the need for transparency in financial systems and various regulatory reforms such as incentives for whistleblowers, a better framework for fintech companies, etc. With the expansion of inquiry, more details are yet to come, nonetheless, investigators worldwide are trying to comprehend how the company used the loopholes to present itself as a profitable business for more than a decade.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The finance industry already grappling with the effects of COVID-19, faced yet another shock with one of the biggest financial scandals in the world coming to the limelight - the Wirecard scandal. Wirecard, a Munich-based payment processing company, once seen as a darling of investors with a market capitalisation of over $28 billion at its peak, filed for bankruptcy on June 25, 2020, after disclosing a $2.1 billion hole in its balance sheet. But what went wrong with the company?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
