<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/business-finance/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-08-04T12:45:21+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/business-finance/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Online Delivery: Adjusting to The New Normal</title>
      <link href="/Online-Delivery" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Online Delivery: Adjusting to The New Normal" />
      <published>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Online-Delivery</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Online-Delivery">&lt;p&gt;Imagine the times when in-store aisles were optimised for foot traffic and retail therapy, featuring better product discovery, impulse purchases and time spent in-store. The coronavirus pandemic has changed that almost overnight. Six months ago, on-demand home delivery was far from mainstream - a luxury for those willing to pay extra for delivery services and convenience, skewing towards young professionals in big cities. Now everyone is willing to order everything from household staples to ice cream on-demand. Stores, which were struggling for customer growth and retention are scrambling for more fulfilment capacity. Demand boom, which the experts believe is likely to persist even after the pandemic ends, makes it worthwhile to analyse the future of online marketplaces, and what opportunities this brings for the suppliers, the consumers, and the platform itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This market inversion has led to a growth of online delivery marketplaces, with even bigger market players in other segments pivoting their business strategies around home delivery. Delivery service marketplaces have inverted from demand-constrained to supply-constrained almost overnight, but new entrants in the delivery space have reportedly struggled with profits, reporting a boost in sales but thin margins. They claim that it is not terribly profitable, and it probably gets unprofitable with more orders. While many restaurants and supermarkets prefer the lower costs and hassle of having customers collect orders at stores, others see it as a threat to their existing customer relationships that could have been better taken care of, had the customers walked into the store. Online delivery was never a core part of these supplier’s revenue and made up only a small chunk of the total orders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issues and challenges that marketplaces face today are logistical and reputational, arising from increased demand and customer awareness rather than challenges arising from low consumer penetration and slim demand for services. Consumers are holding brands and companies to a higher standard than previously, favouring those perceived as doing more for society. Pre-crisis, a common complaint on the platforms was that drivers weren’t receiving enough orders. Now, those same drivers are overwhelmed with demand, and platforms have to figure out how to build product solutions to help stores balance their delivery loads. There have been inventory stockouts, closed stores, and supply chain disruptions due to COVID-19 — all while the customer service team has been inundated with order volume. That’s consistent with the experience of all mid-sized delivery platforms, and even that of Amazon. These platforms have had to switch their focus overnight and develop expertise around the new supply-side constraints. The bigger problem here is that many suppliers didn’t have the infrastructure set up to make delivery work at scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among all vociferous trumpets about ‘the demise of commuting’, ‘the death of retail’, and ‘the collapse of globalisation’, many executives have come to assume that everything will change accordingly when the recipe for survival is supposed to be a thorough transformation. The economic crisis does not necessarily spell the end of entire industries or companies but it does weed out business models that fail to pivot towards the new reality characterised by shorter value chains, remote work, social distancing, consumer introspection, and enhanced usage of technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, now is the time for marketplaces to help their suppliers invest in infrastructure and technology, and indulge in business practices that will enable them to compete in a world in which having a delivery sales presence is essential. Now is the time for them to shift their focus from customer acquisition and retention to investment in metrics for supporting retailer operations. Platforms can be a part of the supplier side transition which, in fact, is happening organically. With in-person retail restricted or outright eliminated, suppliers have been reimagining their store layouts and operations around online fulfilment and omnichannel retail, simultaneously leveraging marketplace platforms, a self-managed online presence, and traditional in-person sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can identify and share best practices around staffing and delivery processes, and provide technology solutions to help small businesses optimise their operations around delivery, with, for example, cloud-based inventory logs and modern point-of-sale systems. Marketplace platforms have vision into the whole market, which enables them to predict demand — an advantage they should use to the benefit of their suppliers. This could be helpful in forecasting when to schedule extra drivers on an hour-by-hour basis, and staffing driver teams in direct proportion to order volume. This can also increase capital efficiency by helping stores match inventory levels to predict future demand. Platforms can lower their tax rates to increase supplier participation — especially among chains and other established supplier networks. Food delivery marketplaces’ supplier-weighted cost structure may have worked when restaurants saw having a small stream of delivery orders as a promotional subsidy for in-person traffic — but it isn’t working in the current, in-person demand constrained marketplace environment. Likewise, some fees should be shifted over to the consumers, since they’re now the ‘long’ side of the market. In particular, it might make sense to institute per-order delivery fees, to encourage consumers to place large delivery orders instead of more frequent small ones, as well as to make it more valuable for a retailer to take an additional order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before COVID-19, a delivery service’s performance was mostly determined by convenience, speed and price. Now, by contrast, safety, availability and breadth of selection are the new priorities. Customers are placing bigger orders and are comfortable with longer lead times with ‘acceptable’ estimated time of arrival windows widening. Platforms also have the leeway to shift customer service efforts to prioritise responsiveness to retailers and allocate developer resources towards solving suppliers’ operational problems. All these solutions will help keep in place, exactly the right products on the supplier’s shelves. These improvements will benefit both parties but would require information sharing and communication on the part of the platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When suppliers make the best or most effective use of marketplace transactions, the consumer experience on the platform improves too — often due to increased availability, selection and price options. Overall, this results in much higher conversion rates: a customer with three stores and 1,000 items to choose from spends 67% more per session than a customer facing just one store with 300 items. Orders are processed more smoothly, and with fewer errors that will help translate fleeting customer relations into stronger consumer engagement post-crisis. Better and more optimised choices lead to more bargaining power in the hands of the customers, thereby increasing satisfaction and chances of application reuse. Bars and restaurants will eventually reopen and consumers will become comfortable shopping for goods in-person again but the supplier networks that marketplace platforms build will remain. When platforms invest in suppliers as partners, those suppliers will come out of the crisis stronger, improving the customer experience in the long run. It’s a three-way win — for suppliers, platforms and consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As worried consumers move to shop more online, choosing online platforms is an easy decision — with a click of the button, they can buy almost anything. But for sellers, doing business with them is a less straightforward proposition. Although partnering opens up access to more customers and offers operational efficiencies, brands risk leveraging power in favour of the platforms. Thus, they face an unavoidable dilemma — form the partnership and risk ceding profits, or eschew the partnership and forgo the operational cost savings and access to new customers. A big threat to these established brands is consumers’ increased willingness to experiment with different offerings during the crisis. Research suggests that consumers react badly even when the bad news extends beyond the company to its supply chain. They are more likely to believe that a company’s product is inferior in quality when there is a supply chain mishap, even when the product quality has nothing to do with the supply chain problem. They assume a product has decreased in quality whether the supply chain problems are related to an economic issue (like consistently low profits), a social issue (like racial discrimination in the hiring process), or an environmental issue (like polluting). Brands must, therefore, realise that pivots must be a lateral extension of the firm’s existing capabilities, cementing — not undermining — its strategic intent.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Mehul Goyal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Imagine the times when in-store aisles were optimised for foot traffic and retail therapy, featuring better product discovery, impulse purchases and time spent in-store. The coronavirus pandemic has changed that almost overnight. Six months ago, on-demand home delivery was far from mainstream - a luxury for those willing to pay extra for delivery services and convenience, skewing towards young professionals in big cities. Now everyone is willing to order everything from household staples to ice cream on-demand. Stores, which were struggling for customer growth and retention are scrambling for more fulfilment capacity. Demand boom, which the experts believe is likely to persist even after the pandemic ends, makes it worthwhile to analyse the future of online marketplaces, and what opportunities this brings for the suppliers, the consumers, and the platform itself.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why are Gold Prices Soaring in the Midst of a Pandemic?</title>
      <link href="/Why-are-Gold-Prices-Soaring-in-the-Midst-of-a-Pandemic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why are Gold Prices Soaring in the Midst of a Pandemic?" />
      <published>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-are-Gold-Prices-Soaring-in-the-Midst-of-a-Pandemic</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-are-Gold-Prices-Soaring-in-the-Midst-of-a-Pandemic">&lt;p&gt;Want to invest your money and you are neither an equity person nor a mutual fund person and interest on fixed deposits is too low for you, what should you do? Of course, you should go and buy gold! Most people buy gold for making jewellery. It is also a place of investment for many. The precious metal has long been used by investors to hedge themselves against inflation. Considered a safe haven by those who don’t want to risk their savings in the stock market, it has always given positive returns to investors. Losing in the glittery metal market is far less likely but in the midst of a pandemic, every sort of investment seems to be too ‘dangerous’, so why are people still buying gold?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever there has been any economic crisis, people tend to stay away from the stock market because market crashes are highly unpredictable. We all know about the 2007-08 financial crisis, and how in every country there was reluctance in investing in the stock market. However, people who still had savings went right to the commodity exchange and bought gold. This was clearly visible from the fact that the rally in gold continued from 2007 to 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what we are witnessing in this current scenario with the coronavirus spreading all over the world and lockdown of economies leading to bankruptcy for many companies, people are pulling out their money from stocks and other financial instruments and buying bullion to park their money in safe investments. Exchange-Traded Funds (ETFs) have been piling up on gold reserves as well, which has more than made up for the domestic lack of demand. Demand for gold comes from another significant set of investors who tend to invest in real estate. The sector itself being in limbo due to the pandemic has forced such investors to invest in the yellow metal. Additionally, the metal is benefitting from the ultra-loose monetary policies being pursued by bankers and expectation that such a stance will tend to continue in the long run. Rising fiscal deficits and increasing debts are also contributing to the rising shift to gold. The fiscal policies adopted and the printing of more currency have led to inflation and have been the contributing factors in the current rally in gold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, central banks around the globe are regularly keeping a check on the economy and are providing liquidity. During the past few months, central banks too, have been buying gold and increasing their gold reserves in order to face any unforeseen circumstances. Central banks of China, Russia and India were the biggest buyers of gold in 2019, and many countries are still adding more to their coffers. This rally is expected to continue until we see any stability in the stock market and people feel safe to buy stocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gold prices have gone through the ceiling in the past few weeks and every banker has his/her own perception regarding the future price movement. All in all, it remains to be seen whether gold prices will continue to rise, or will gold lose its steam. However, the metal has yet again proven its mettle in trying times, when every other investment fails to provide returns, it keeps its investors happy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rachit Kumar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Want to invest your money and you are neither an equity person nor a mutual fund person and interest on fixed deposits is too low for you, what should you do? Of course, you should go and buy gold! Most people buy gold for making jewellery. It is also a place of investment for many. The precious metal has long been used by investors to hedge themselves against inflation. Considered a safe haven by those who don’t want to risk their savings in the stock market, it has always given positive returns to investors. Losing in the glittery metal market is far less likely but in the midst of a pandemic, every sort of investment seems to be too ‘dangerous’, so why are people still buying gold?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">When The Faithful Prince Backfired!</title>
      <link href="/When-The-Faithful-Prince-Backfired" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When The Faithful Prince Backfired!" />
      <published>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/When-The-Faithful-Prince-Backfired</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/When-The-Faithful-Prince-Backfired">&lt;p&gt;Remember, four years ago when the entire business world was shocked to hear the allegations made against the ‘not so clean’ Tata &amp;amp; Sons? In today’s highly competitive and capitalistic world, where business rivalry is a routine affair among the giants, there are a few players who prefer to keep it clean. The Tata group is one of them and has maintained its reputation as one of the most honest corporate entities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ratan Tata, former Chairman of the Tata group is one of the most powerful businessmen in India and one of the most influential in the world. He owns less than 1% of the assets of the group in his own name. He ended up being in the headlines related to a controversy. It all started after the Tata group appointed Cyrus Mistry as the 6th Chairman of Tata Sons in 2012. He had been on the board of Tata Sons since August 2006. Mistry is the son of Pallonji Mistry who was the owner of Shapoorji Pallonji Group till 2012 (presently headed by Shapoor Mistry). The Mistrys are the largest individual shareholders in Tata Sons with 18.4%, which is equally divided between the two sons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On October 24, 2016, Mistry was removed from his post as the Chairman during a board meeting. According to sources, Mr Tata gave him a chance to resign voluntarily, which Mistry denied. The severity of bitterness among the two was made obvious after he was ousted from all the other boards as well. At that point in time, the Mistrys were crippled and the future course was unknown. Ratan Tata was reinstated as the Interim Chairman for about four months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tata Sons stated that a trust deficit with Cyrus Mistry was the major reason for his removal. They also claimed that the members of the board had lost their confidence in Mistry and thus took a collective decision to replace him as the Chairman. On the other hand, Mistry claimed the removal to be illegal and a staged coup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since no concrete reasoning has been given out for the removal, many possible reasons have been floating across. Legacy problems within the Tata group, and differences between Mr Tata and Mr Mistry are also seen as the alleged reasons for Cyrus being ousted. Additionally, Mistry wanted to get rid of certain ventures which proved to be unsuccessful. These included Tata Steel’s European business, Tata Nano, and telecoms. Mr Tata refused these advances and these led to certain conflicts. Mistry made some decisions without consulting the board and Ratan Tata himself. Unsurprisingly, these decisions were not well received by all. Tata group also suffered some losses under Mistry’s reign. At times, he even overlooked the existing ventures and was prioritising new businesses. This was not acceptable to Mr Tata as the existing ventures had some emotional sentiment attached to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mistry filed a case against the Tata Sons with the National Company Law Tribunal (NCLT) in December 2016. He stated that even after 8 weeks, he does not have any concrete reason backing the move, and hence he chose to go the legal way. This whole situation has adversely affected the position of the Pallonjis as a minority shareholder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mistry’s challenge was turned down by the NCLT. After this, he went to the National Company Law Appellate Tribunal (NCLAT) in regard to the NCLT dismissal. His appeal with the tribunal was admitted in August 2018. The appeal was restored later and judgment was passed by the NCLAT in December 2019. The judgment and order reinstated Mistry as the Chairman of Tata Sons and restored his position on all the boards. This order was challenged by the Tata Son’s in the Indian Supreme Court. The Supreme Court put a stay order on the NCLAT’s judgment after it refused to modify the same. Even after various hearings, both the parties are nowhere near satisfied and the conflict is ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tata Sons did what they felt was needed for the group’s benefit. This move was not well reasoned by them and the consequences being faced are dreadful. Even the Mistrys are facing uncertainty at their end! This move has not only defamed Cyrus Mistry but has also raised questions on Tata’s working and management. Even though the NCLAT’s judgment was in Mistry’s favour, he believes it’s not enough. His demands for rights in a corporate democracy for a minority shareholder still remain untackled! This forces us to think more about shareholders and how authority should be controlled within the working of business houses in order to maintain the ideals of corporate democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t believe that majority dominance should play a role in the business culture. Decisions being taken affect all the investors equally and thus their approval should be necessary. A democratic process that includes debate and deliberation regarding every big step should be given importance. In this particular feud, both sides had made similar mistakes of taking decisions on an individual level. Be it Cyrus taking company matters and policies in his own hands or Mr Tata scrapping his ideas and at last ousting him without justification. These examples prove how seniority plays an important role in corporate functioning. This also means that views and opinions of other board members who are usually the minority shareholders are negated or delegitimised. Power dynamics need to be minimised in order to protect minority rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interests of a company should be prioritised while taking crucial decisions. Is it safe to assume that all minority shareholders genuinely care about the company as a whole? Personal interests and gains have always been prioritised by individuals. Keeping this in mind, it is important to make sure these rights are not misused and the interests of a company are always taken care of. Does this justify the ousting of Mistry? Oops! We ended up being in a dilemma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These situations are not favourable to any of the parties involved but they do unfold the power play within corporate houses. The Tata group which was known for its values and ideals is facing severe repercussions. It is time to rethink and stand up for minority rights not only within national boundaries but also within the corporate world and make sure they are not tampered with. The ambiguity of this whole situation can be sensed in every article present in my search history and thus it makes it difficult to land upon a conclusion which satisfies all the parties involved.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Remember, four years ago when the entire business world was shocked to hear the allegations made against the ‘not so clean’ Tata &amp;amp; Sons? In today’s highly competitive and capitalistic world, where business rivalry is a routine affair among the giants, there are a few players who prefer to keep it clean. The Tata group is one of them and has maintained its reputation as one of the most honest corporate entities.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Green Bonds: A New Revolution towards Sustainable Finance in India?</title>
      <link href="/A-New-Revolution-towards-Sustainable-Finance-in-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Green Bonds: A New Revolution towards Sustainable Finance in India?" />
      <published>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-New-Revolution-towards-Sustainable-Finance-in-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-New-Revolution-towards-Sustainable-Finance-in-India">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;We need bold action on climate change, our generation may not be able to solve all the problems related to climate change, but we can do our part to leave a better planet for the next generation&lt;/em&gt;”, said Kristalina Georgieva, World Bank Group and Interim Chief Executive Officer. Climate change has caused an unprecedented risk to the growth of societies and economies. According to a recent report by Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), it has been estimated that around $6-7 trillion of annual investment is globally required to achieve the objective of moving the world economy towards a ‘greener economy’. To get the entire globe out of this trap, we need to make substantial investments that fund projects focussing on creating low carbon economies, clean energy, water transportation, etc. Only with such effective measures shall we be able to build a climate-resilient economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many countries around the world have been pursuing a shift towards a more sustainable environment. Recently, the European Union launched the Next Generation EU (NGEU) fund to tackle the coronavirus pandemic. The deal puts the issue of climate change at the forefront. According to the deal document, a total of 30% of the expenditure of the €1.82 trillion will be used to reach the climate targets in conformity to the objectives of the Paris agreements. It also has a provision that rules that the European Commission should publish a report on climate expenditure annually. In order to ensure that such legislations bear fruitful results, it is important to provide investors with alternative options of investments, with higher returns and which also give them a feeling of having satisfied their responsibility towards the environment. This is where ‘Green Bonds’ come into the picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the current status and impetus given to green finance globally, we can not only give credit to institutions that have introduced green bonds but also to the dynamic shift witnessed in the corporate bond market wherein we have more socially responsible investors who want to invest their money in the funding of those projects that would lead to a positive impact on the society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite knowing the unmeasured potential of green finance all over the world, the total number of green bonds issued was only around 3% as a percentage of the total corporate bonds issued. This reveals the percentage of untapped potential of the green bond market which should be effectively realised to create a sustainable environment. So, how are these bonds currently being exploited in India?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Indian Green Bond Market and the Road Ahead.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a time when governments across the world are emphasising on creating low carbon economies, India is not lagging behind in showing its efforts in the same direction. Indian financial institutions such as the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) and the Securities Exchange Board of India (SEBI) are effectively trying to promote green bonds in the country. India is aiming to build 175 gigawatts of renewable energy capacity by 2022. Thus, the financing needs of the renewable energy sector can effectively be addressed by the issuance of green bonds in our country. In the last few years Indian investors, banking institutions, and the government have played a crucial role in developing sustainable finance. They have recognised it as a fundamental tool towards financing the nation’s renewable energy targets through developing strategies for sustainable economic growth and effective policy framework for judicious utilisation of all-natural resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green bonds in India were introduced in 2015 when Yes Bank issued the first series of green bonds in the country for financing projects of ₹10 billion followed by ₹6 billion issuances of green bonds by CLP India. In order to regulate these issuances, SEBI issued the green bond guidelines on lines of the green bond principles issued by the Institute of Cost and Management Accountants (ICMA). By 2018, the Indian green bond market had risen to ₹500 billion. This clearly indicates that India has an enormous capacity for the development of sustainable finance which just needs to be unlocked with appropriate policies and measures. According to Climate Transparency’s &lt;em&gt;Brown to Green&lt;/em&gt; report, wherein a study was conducted among the G20 countries measuring the Green Bond Issuance as a share of the country’s overall debt, India was ranked 5th, hence, Indian financial institutions and investors should realise that the green bond market has a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the enormous potential, the market is yet to overcome several barriers such as greenwashing, false claims of environmental compliance, etc. Additionally, there exist mismatches between long-term green investment and short-term interests of the investors which tend to make the market less efficient. Exorbitant currency hedging costs because of the high volatility of the Indian rupee, poor sovereign rating, and low tenure of the green bonds pose a hurdle in the path of creating a highly advanced green bond market. Moreover, we need to realise that till date the green bonds that have been issued in India have only been offered by highly established finance companies, whereas internationally, other organisations such as local governments, climate change organisations, and other corporate firms are all coming together to address this issue by diversifying the green bond market in their countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On analysing the above situation of green finance in the country, we can clearly conclude that India’s full potential still needs to be explored because currently there exists a shortage of supply as well as the demand for green bonds in the market because of various constraints. In order to increase the efficiency of this particular market, the government and the authorities need to formulate relevant policies and implement them. For starters, the short-term interests of investors as well as issuers, need to be removed by educating them that the advancement of the market in the country not only will fund the necessary environmental projects but also would allow issuers to generate a positive public reputation. Since the main reason for the lack of demand of green bonds in our country is the investors’ perception that they are not competitive enough to give them high financial returns, the governmental agencies need to step up by guaranteeing a fixed rate of return which is marginally higher than other investments so that large institutional investors and retail investors would heavily invest under this domain. Other measures such as reducing foreign exchange hedging costs will attract investors from overseas to invest in clean energy projects of India. RBI, SEBI, Indian Renewable Energy Development Agency Ltd. (IREDA), and the Ministry of Finance can play an important role in the nascent stage development of Green Finance in the country by creating more rupee denominated bonds such as the IFC-Yes Bank Green Masala Bond of 2015. Launching credited and standardised Indian green bonds that would reduce the stigma of the attached risk with green bonds can completely flip the situation upside-down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, in order to attract domestic demand, the government should provide tax incentives to individuals for investment in such bonds. The development of sustainable stock exchanges just like the Shanghai Stock Exchange did is essential for continued growth. It has a special index to monitor the green finance situation in the country. Efforts of the government and other institutions have borne positive results. According to the Indian Economic Survey 2019-20, India has become the second-largest market for green bonds after China with $10.3 billion transactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government support and a dedicated policy at hand are necessarily required to scale up the level of green bonds market in the country. An enhanced policy framework is required in action to upgrade the current situation of the green finance market in the country. This can also be done by educating investors, and removing information asymmetry between issuers and investors. An increase in investor confidence could give a new shape to the outlook of sustainable finance in our country. Only enhanced collective participation of issuers, corporate firms, financial institutions, policymakers, and regulators will give the fundamental push to the boundary of the green bond market, and would further give rise to other such opportunities in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, green bonds can be seen as the interlinking bridge connecting sustainable finance with funding quintessential environmental projects. Growth in the green bonds in India would set a precedent for other theme-based bonds such as social bonds, water bonds, and sustainability bonds that raise finance for specific developmental purposes.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Cherry Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“We need bold action on climate change, our generation may not be able to solve all the problems related to climate change, but we can do our part to leave a better planet for the next generation”, said Kristalina Georgieva, World Bank Group and Interim Chief Executive Officer. Climate change has caused an unprecedented risk to the growth of societies and economies. According to a recent report by Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), it has been estimated that around $6-7 trillion of annual investment is globally required to achieve the objective of moving the world economy towards a ‘greener economy’. To get the entire globe out of this trap, we need to make substantial investments that fund projects focussing on creating low carbon economies, clean energy, water transportation, etc. Only with such effective measures shall we be able to build a climate-resilient economy.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
