<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/business-finance/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-10-14T18:31:58+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/business-finance/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Promoting Free Trade in South Asia: SAFTA and Beyond</title>
      <link href="/Promoting-Free-Trade-in-South-Asia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Promoting Free Trade in South Asia: SAFTA and Beyond" />
      <published>2020-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Promoting-Free-Trade-in-South-Asia</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Promoting-Free-Trade-in-South-Asia">&lt;p&gt;South Asia experienced rapid GDP growth in the 1980’s, averaging around 6 % per annum across the region. This has attracted much global attention to the region. In addition to policy and institutional reforms that have been instrumental in tackling unemployment and poverty, market integration and regional cooperation have also been key to rapid growth and development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the 1990’s, South Asian countries have made efforts to enhance their trade and investment flows with the larger objective of poverty alleviation and economic development. Historically, changes in the trade policies of the region have been driven by the unilateral liberalisation of individual countries. However, preferential trade agreements were initiated after the formation of the South Asian Association for Regional Cooperation (SAARC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South Asian Preferential Trade Agreement (SAPTA) was signed by SAARC in 1995 as a step towards strengthening regional trade. However, SAPTA was not successful in enhancing trade among the member nations because its product coverage and tariff concessions were too limited. Thus, the South Asian Free Trade Agreement (SAFTA) was introduced. It aimed towards eventually bringing tariffs down to zero. SAFTA was signed on January 6, 2004, during the 12th SAARC Summit, held at Islamabad. The tariff liberalisation began to be implemented only in July 2006. In accordance with the first phase of the agreement, India, Pakistan, and Srilanka reduced their tariffs to 20% while Bangladesh, Bhutan and Maldives reduced their tariffs to nearly 30%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The introduction of SAFTA provided many opportunities to SAARC countries, but at the same time, it posed a few challenges. This was mainly because the agreement would have a significant impact on the welfare of member nations and on domestic producers. Critics say that SAFTA was unsuccessful in changing the existing trade patterns among South Asian countries to the extent that was initially proclaimed. Though SAFTA was introduced to counter the problems posed by SAPTA, it is considered to be an extension of the previous agreement. The only changes seemed to be the inclusion of trade facilitation elements and the switching of the trade liberalisation process from a positive list to a negative list approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main purpose of introducing the SAFTA was to encourage trade and also increase economic cooperation among the SAARC countries by reducing the tariffs and non-tariff barriers (NTBs) as well as by bringing transparency and equity among the nations. There was also a special preference to the Least Development Countries (LDCs) among the SAARC nations. SAFTA was also viewed as a South Asian Counterpart of the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA). By the end of 2013, the total exports by the member states under SAFTA had reached close to $3 billion. The question that arises is regarding the success of SAFTA over the years in achieving the goals that it set out for itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outcomes and Beyond&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality of the implementation of SAFTA was far different from the expectations that it had established. SAFTA’s main objective was to enable smooth movement of goods across borders with low tariffs, similar to what the European Union had been able to achieve. However, the governments of South Asia were not able to streamline their relations often due to conflicts between two or more nations. For example, the conflict between India and Pakistan has prevented many SAARC summits from taking place, thereby hindering the objectives of regional cooperation. A 2006 article in &lt;em&gt;Economic and Political Weekly&lt;/em&gt; titled ‘Does SAFTA have a Future?’ by Dushni Weerakoon and Jayanthi Thennakoon stated that nearly 53% of import trade amongst South Asian countries was excluded from the trade liberalisation as required under SAFTA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tariff Liberalisation Program (TLP) that was adopted under this agreement provided a clear system of tariff reduction. Non-LDCs were required to reduce existing tariffs to 0-5% within five years post-implementation, whereas LDCs were required to reduce tariffs to 30% within two years and to 0-5% within eight years. However, this system was criticised as it could potentially lead to the back-loading of tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TLP also excludes those goods which come under the sensitive list given by the member countries. This limits the range of goods available for trade. However, on the positive side, SAFTA puts a limit on the maximum number of sensitive goods that a country can list. This provision was not included in previous regional trade agreements such as the India-Sri Lanka Free Trade Agreement and the India-Pakistan Free Trade Agreement. Some features even hinted at turning a new page for trade policy, such as the provision of compensation for revenue losses that small countries were expected to face in the event of tariff reductions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also draw a comparison between the ASEAN Free Trade Area (AFTA) and the South Asian Free Trade Area (SAFTA). Under AFTA, between 1992-2017, exports increased from 21 to 27%. However, under SAFTA, this figure was very low. During the period that SAFTA came into effect, around 6-7% of the South Asian country’s exports were intra-regional exports. However, in recent years, this has declined to around 5%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Examining the Reasons for SAFTA’s Unsuccessful Run&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Asian Development Bank estimates that even after 35 years of SAARC’s establishment, it has not been able to significantly affect intra-regional trade. Many economists are of the view that SAFTA’s ineffectiveness could be attributed to the fact that it maintains a sensitive list which allows the exclusion of goods from the trade liberalisation process. The problem lies in the fact that these sensitive goods account for 6-45% of intra-regional imports in South Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The World Bank’s report titled &lt;em&gt;A Glass Half Full: The Promise of Regional Trade in South Asia&lt;/em&gt; (2018) examines SAFTA’s ineffectiveness in more depth. It is estimated that SAFTA’s proper application could have increased South Asian regional trade by more than $2 billion. However, SAFTA’s trade remains the lowest in the world among all other Regional Trade Agreements (RTAs) because South Asian countries are keener on trading with the US or the European Union. While intra-EU trade has a 70% success rate and the intra-NAFTA trade has a 50% success rate, the intra-SAARC trade has a meagre 5% success rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another notable finding is that within this region, there is a tendency of introducing para-tariffs that are levied on imports and not on domestic production. In Bangladesh, it is known as Supplementary Duty, whereas in Sri Lanka it is known as Ports and Airports Development Levy. These para-tariffs increase protection for domestic producers but also increase non-transparency between nations which hinders the process of free trade. This is a point of concern as these para-tariffs are not under the purview of SAFTA negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to a World Bank report, trade in South Asia can triple from its current volume of $23 billion to $67 billion. Considering this untapped potential, SAARC nations need to come together to address these issues. This will not only promote economic liberalisation by providing a higher variety of goods at lower prices, expanded markets and job creation, but will also take these nations to new heights of development. SAARC nations should also take a proactive role in implementing lower tariffs, lesser Non-Tariff Barriers to Trade (NTBs) and a common external tariff. Other initiatives such as creating a South Asian economic corridor and resolving disputes between countries in the region will go a long way in facilitating regional cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India plays an especially large role in turning around the fate of SAFTA. India is the dominant trading partner for most South Asian countries. About 90% of the foreign trade of countries such as Bangladesh, Nepal and Srilanka is achieved through bilateral trade relations with India. Thus, the creation of a free trade area is heavily reliant on India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, we can say that at the macro level, many initiatives are being taken to enable trade among South Asian countries and to limit trade with other regional unions for the collective prosperity of South Asia. However, the much anticipated SAFTA has fallen short of expectations. Factors such as simplifying the tariff structure, easing foreign exchange controls, transit facilities for the landlocked countries and easier banking facilities for import financing can help to build confidence among the SAARC nations. Apart from focusing solely on securing SAARC objectives, South Asian nations should also pay attention to bilateralism and sub-regionalism within South Asia. In 2014, Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi at the 18th SAARC Summit focussed on the need for relationships of South Asian countries to shift beyond SAARC. There is also a need for the launch of another free trade agreement that counters the issues of the SAFTA trade agreement to achieve the objective of establishing a South Asian Union. It is yet to be seen whether a new trade agreement is launched or not and if it is, how successfully does it tackle the issues of SAFTA or does it become an extension of SAFTA, just like the latter became of SAPTA.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Cherry Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">South Asia experienced rapid GDP growth in the 1980’s, averaging around 6 % per annum across the region. This has attracted much global attention to the region. In addition to policy and institutional reforms that have been instrumental in tackling unemployment and poverty, market integration and regional cooperation have also been key to rapid growth and development.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">EdTech: The New Normal of Learning?</title>
      <link href="/EdTech" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EdTech: The New Normal of Learning?" />
      <published>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/EdTech</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/EdTech">&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 has impacted every area of our lives and left us with no choice but to find new alternatives. Schooling and education were no exception. Parents, teachers and students felt nothing but helpless as everything came to a standstill. Schools and universities were shut and the situation was uncertain. While it was convenient for adults to adapt to the new normal and work from home, teachers and students had a hard time figuring out a way to keep the learning going. Edtech, the practice of using technology in education, has been around for quite some years but it was never considered a substitute to classroom teaching. Parents have always preferred live learning as the best possible method. However, times changed and we ended up in a situation that required us to learn virtually and adopt edtech. It has been six months and the edtech sector has flourished more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise was huge and pretty visible as the sector dominated the market numbers. The edtech sector in India is currently estimated to be valued at $735 million and a growth of 150% is expected in 2020. A number of edtech startups have completed their long-term goals within these six months of lockdown. The users have increased manifold and the businesses are soaring high. The consumer base of these upcoming disruptors in the education arena, not only consists of students but also working professionals. Lockdown increased the time people had on their hands which they utilised by enhancing and developing their skill sets. These innovative startups have included various courses which attract not only students but also adults who are currently working. Employers have also encouraged their employees to learn new skills via these courses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edtech has evolved over the years and has come a long way. It started with video-based learning which has now evolved into an interactive platform that adapts to the different needs of every learner. Students used to interact with peers and teachers which made learning more wholesome. Until recently, interactive virtual learning wasn’t a thing. But today, every edtech platform has various features that enhance the learning to make it more interactive and complete. Parents have started to rely on them as it makes learning fun and makes the concepts easy to understand. Moreover, allowing the students to learn at their own pace has proved to be another reason for their huge success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millions of people have signed up in the past few months and this massive growth has led to increased hiring and new opportunities. The increased consumer base demanded an increased workforce to deal with the complaints and enhance the learning experience for its users. Unlike Facebook and other social media platforms, these learning platforms offer paid services to its customers. Even besides all this, the growth is consistent. The reason being, most parents are willing to spend on their child’s education in the hope of a better future for them. Thus, paid subscriptions to e-learning was seen as an investment and was a big hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the edtech boom sustain post this lockdown period? It has been six months and most of us have adapted to this new normal of wearing masks and following social distancing at all points of time. The easing of lockdown has begun and people are getting back to work. Eventually schools, colleges and universities will open up for students, and in no time classroom teaching will overtake these virtual platforms. We cannot really predict how it is going to turn out for these companies in the near future, but it is highly likely that the growth might increase even in the post-COVID-19 period. First, the New Education Policy (NEP) will be implemented and the use of technology in learning will finally catch up with the outdated curriculums of schools. With the government’s plans to introduce coding for students, it is likely that parents would trust online tutors more than they would trust school teachers. The simple reason being that these edtech startups have the resources to onboard experienced coders and teachers in this field and many of these platforms already offer fundamental courses on coding. Second, with the growing demand for skills like Artificial Intelligence (AI) and machine learning in every field, it seems like technology in education is here to stay. The edtech market will not die out soon as we are expecting a merger between online and offline learning in the entire education system. There are certain problems that might impact its growth as a whole, issues of internet connectivity in suburban and rural areas might be a problem for many. All these problems demand unique solutions that the developers need to think about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edtech is like any other service which makes our lives easier. It aids us by providing a simpler way of learning and understanding things. We don’t know as of now whether it can possibly replace our classroom learning, however, it can definitely be integrated with the existing system to make our approach more holistic. The burden now lies on the developers to attract maximum users and provide unique features to ensure sustainability. While the choice remains on the students and the parents if they choose to trust this form of education in the coming decades.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">COVID-19 has impacted every area of our lives and left us with no choice but to find new alternatives. Schooling and education were no exception. Parents, teachers and students felt nothing but helpless as everything came to a standstill. Schools and universities were shut and the situation was uncertain. While it was convenient for adults to adapt to the new normal and work from home, teachers and students had a hard time figuring out a way to keep the learning going. Edtech, the practice of using technology in education, has been around for quite some years but it was never considered a substitute to classroom teaching. Parents have always preferred live learning as the best possible method. However, times changed and we ended up in a situation that required us to learn virtually and adopt edtech. It has been six months and the edtech sector has flourished more than ever.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Spirituality and Marketing: An Amalgam</title>
      <link href="/Spirituality-and-Marketing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spirituality and Marketing: An Amalgam" />
      <published>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Spirituality-and-Marketing</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Spirituality-and-Marketing">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Amalgam&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religion is a highly inappropriate topic for the workplace, and only has an institutional connotation that manifests into the practice of rituals, adhering to dogmas and attending services. Spirituality, on the other hand, deals with life’s deeper motivations and an emotional connection to God and is a highly appropriate subject for discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that the world is smitten by the spirituality bug and marketing academics are oblivious of this development. Spirituality is increasingly impacting the beliefs and behaviours of consumers around the world. A &lt;em&gt;USA Weekend&lt;/em&gt; poll conducted in July 1998 revealed that 47% of Americans viewed spirituality as the most important element of their happiness. They care deeply about ecology and saving the planet, about relationships, peace, social justice, along with authenticity, self-actualisation, spirituality, and self-expression. They tend to be both inner-directed and socially concerned; they want to be activists, volunteers, and contributors to good causes. It’s 2020 and there is a massive influx of spiritual information, currently crowding the pages of popular newspapers, television programmes, and the glossiest mainstream magazines. Meditation classes are offered at the United Nations, Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi uses visualisations and relaxation techniques to inspire the world, while political matters of spiritual and religious importance are the frequent subjects of public questioning and curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies have increasingly begun to use marketing as a spiritual practice to delve into a deeper wisdom, product offerings, and how they can help clients solve their problems. No jargon, no gimmicks, no trickery, just a deeper ‘wisdom’ in their marketing. Companies have started to use collaborative methods to co-vision with what the customer wants and help them see beyond their limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The root of spiritual marketing is clarity - the unwavering perception of how to do self-promotion. If you are clear about what you want and what you offer, your prospective customers will instantly know whether or not you offer what they need. A deep appreciation for a clear pricing strategy because consumers know the rule, &lt;em&gt;“if you have to ask how much, you probably can’t afford it”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies have realised that spirituality is the human response to God’s gracious call to a one-on-one relationship with Him. Therefore, companies encourage customers to trust the transfer of their (profitable) divine goals and perceptions. What follows is a spiritual bond between the two parties where neither can survive without the other, built on a dynamic system of data projections from both sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Big Fat Business&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only has mainstream spirituality gained popularity, but it has also become a big business. New age spirituality is a multi-billion-dollar industry, and some of the most popular contemporary spiritual teachers and gurus are among the wealthiest people in the world. Right from &lt;em&gt;“You can deprive the body, but the soul needs chocolate”&lt;/em&gt; to ‘Yoga-inspired athletic wear’ line of products, established companies and secular corporate firms are increasingly using spiritual appeals to identify and bond with consumers. It is one of the fast-growing industries. India’s estimated spiritual and religious market is over $30 billion. Studies have found that women comprise two-thirds of the active spiritual market consumers, particularly high income, educated, and middle-aged females but the men and youth market is also growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali  and Art of Living’s line of body care products and brands have created a niche for themselves in the market. The ageing of consumers in the western and Indian societies, coupled with their level of affluence, now permits them and the business community the luxury of seeking more meaning in their lives. Organisations like these are widening their reach in the production and distribution of these consumer goods. Furthermore some of these have entered into backward integration to source raw material as well. Once sold only at their &lt;em&gt;ashrams&lt;/em&gt; or particular outlets, today they can be found online or in supermarkets or even in &lt;em&gt;kirana&lt;/em&gt; stores. While FMCG companies need to invest a lot of time, effort, and money in branding and advertising their products, these spiritual gurus already have a huge number of devotees as their loyal consumer base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s to no surprise that such companies come up with unique, targeted and sound vocabulary and phraseology: “oneness”, “loving ourselves”, “we deserve”, “meditation”, “letting go”, “touching the void” among many others. Such marketing campaigns give an exotic edge, help unfurl competitive advantages, pep-up the spiritual image of the company, and facilitate the psychological transfer of ethics. Having a deep connection with clients and the community is what makes these business marketing techniques work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Magical World with Less Documentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the paucity of research on the topic of spirituality, bountiful opportunities and several interesting issues could be researched. For example, does the incidence of spirituality match with global macro-economic trends and how would these trends impact consumer behaviour and marketing practices? What is the relationship between rising incomes and economic development with the propagation of spiritually inspired ideas? Is spirituality increasingly used as a means of identity preservation and as a reaction to deterritorialisation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explain these dynamics in the marketplace would require both strong qualitative and quantitative research. Scales that measure spirituality may be engineered by incorporating spiritual variables comprising both beliefs and practices. The need is to comprehensively conceptualise the concept of spirituality and delimit its boundaries so that its conflation with the concept of religion is not misunderstood and fairly appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authentic spirituality is non-conceptual, and this presents a serious dilemma for spirituality in marketing for most of what attracts people is conceptual. Therefore, most authentic companies strike a balance between marketing and propagating non-conceptual bias, so that there is enough conceptualisation to hook people, but not too much to badly interfere with the marketing process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Said more simply, companies are all doing something inside themselves that is creating their outer results. Their inner state of being is creating their business or lack of it. Their inner spirit is doing their marketing. To paraphrase the famous Swiss psychologist Carl Jung, &lt;em&gt;“Until you make the unconscious conscious, it will direct your life and you will call it fate”.&lt;/em&gt; If you don’t consciously select where you want to go, you go where your unconscious wants you to go. Companies are having a great time skewing our unconscious minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of today, spirituality in marketing is still a slippery construct, and only a systematic segmentation program of inquiry will provide meaningful and actionable insights. It’s a mystery yet, but if the business invests in its spiritual aspect, it will reap many unanticipated rewards, both financially and by gaining joy and bliss in doing their own business.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Mehul Goyal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Amalgam</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Stocks Rallying Again? Time to invest?</title>
      <link href="/Stocks-Rallying-Again" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stocks Rallying Again? Time to invest?" />
      <published>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Stocks-Rallying-Again</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Stocks-Rallying-Again">&lt;p&gt;Speculation: the word around which the life of most of the people trading in the stock market revolves. Every trade involved in the stock market is merely a bet speculating upon the prices of stocks going up or down. Stock markets around the world crashed in the month of March due to a panic caused by the spread of COVID-19, bears conquered the indices like Dow Jones, S&amp;amp;P500, Shanghai Index, Nikkei225 and Nifty50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus outbreak got worse day-by-day and even now cases are rising every day although if you see the popular stock market indices, they are again back to the point where they were before March lows. A rally is bringing the indices back to their pre-March levels. Are the economies getting better? No. Have we recovered from the virus? No. Is GDP growth recovering? NO, instead most of the nations have announced contraction in GDP and are further expecting it to contract till 2021. Why have stocks been moving up again then? Let’s find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many countries worldwide went under complete lockdown. People tried looking for sources of income during this time and as the stock market never sleeps people turned to stocks to earn something in their free time. Everyone became a trader. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Robinhood-Misleads-Gen-Z&quot;&gt;Robinhood&lt;/a&gt; trading app, the most popular stock trading app in the US that charges zero commission, saw a rise in new account openings during the lockdown. The revenues of Robinhood have doubled in a quarter which clearly shows that retail participation has risen and is continuing to rise as we speak. Retailers with no knowledge of stocks, futures and options are trading just for the sake of earning some extra income during their free time and are buying stocks like grocery items, which is one of the main reasons for the rally of stock indices. All market indicators show that the market is overbought and a second wave of crash is due. Big retailers on seeing a big fall in the market start selling stocks to average out their price, and when they enter the market after a fall, it helps the market to regain again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the big question arises: where do we invest our money right now? Seeing a crash due in the market again, and positive signs not being visible in the short term for the economy, it is best to have a diversified portfolio. Over the years, the investment that is the most promising is gold but becoming wealthy through gold is almost unheard of. Seeing the current scenario one must have around 15-20% of his/her investment in gold, paper gold is preferred as you don’t have to keep it safe and don’t have to worry about it. Around 30% of the portfolio should be in mutual funds (Systematic Investment Plan) and 25% should be allocated to equities that too in ‘blue-chip’ stocks because right now profitability of companies is not important, the most important thing is survival and these companies have a huge amount of capital backing. If you want higher returns then you can switch to mid-caps and small-caps too, but your risk increases as well. 10% should be invested in very safe investments like fixed deposits for safe and a minimum guaranteed return. The remaining portfolio can be kept as cash-in-hand, and then one can wait for dips and add stocks of their choice. This portfolio investment has been advised for people who want to take moderate risk with decent returns. If you wish, you can go for high risk by allocating more to equities and if you want less risk then decrease your dependence on equities. Therefore, investing in such turbulent times depends totally on a person’s risk appetite and the depth of his pockets. No one can predict the movement of markets in such unprecedented times. It would be better to have a well-diversified portfolio and not expose yourself too much to a particular type of investment.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rachit Kumar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Speculation: the word around which the life of most of the people trading in the stock market revolves. Every trade involved in the stock market is merely a bet speculating upon the prices of stocks going up or down. Stock markets around the world crashed in the month of March due to a panic caused by the spread of COVID-19, bears conquered the indices like Dow Jones, S&amp;amp;P500, Shanghai Index, Nikkei225 and Nifty50.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Past and Future of the Future Group</title>
      <link href="/Past-Future-Future-Group" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Past and Future of the Future Group" />
      <published>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Past-Future-Future-Group</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Past-Future-Future-Group">&lt;p&gt;Kishore Biyani, the retail maverick of India, was the man who took the retail industry by storm. He realised the potential of retail, which oligarchs like the Ambanis and Birlas could not appreciate, and therefore came up with household names like Pantaloons, FBB and Big Bazaar. He is often referred to as the Sam Walton (the owner of Walmart) of India. However, recently, Reliance Industries (RIL) bought Biyani’s Future Group for a whopping ₹247 billion. Let’s understand why Mr Biyani had to sell off his dream, but for starters, let’s get acquainted with his story of rags-to-riches before getting onto the bad part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kishore Biyani, the current pin-up kid of the Indian retail industry, has assumed numerous jobs, however in the long run, he settled to turn into an inventive retailer. In contrast with numerous others of his class, Kishore wasn’t brought into the world with the proverbial silver spoon in his mouth and has, without any help, ascended the halls of India’s business elite. Nevertheless, coming from a family of businessmen, business flowed in his blood. He always knew that he would end up becoming a businessman because of his mindset and his ability to understand the customer. In order to understand the real world and to interpret the consumer’s nerve, he was often seen spending time visiting various shops rather than studying. His career actually started when he neared the end of his graduation by joining his family business Bansi Silk Mills, which traded fabrics. Though he used to go to his office, he wasn’t getting the kick which he wanted. He was unable to feel the enthusiasm and opportunity and was feeling quieted by the organisation’s moderate business culture and used to leave within 2 or 3 hours. He was totally against the manner in which the organisation worked and felt that their demeanour and approach towards the business wasn’t right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While he was meeting his friends, he noticed them wearing ‘stonewashed’ fabric, he promptly acted on this new information and contacted a few mill owners and sold it to the garment dealers. Kishore had tasted blood and now he wanted more! He frantically began to search for something new, something other than what’s expected. He launched his own brand of fabric for men’s trousers called, WBB – White, Brown, and Blue. In 1987, he started his own garment manufacturing company, Manz Wear Private Ltd, which he sold under the brand name Pantaloons (he chose the name Pantaloons because it gave the feel of an Italian Fashion House and secondly because it was closer to &lt;em&gt;patloon&lt;/em&gt;, an Urdu word for trouser). During the preliminary stages, Biyani went through a difficult phase as banks didn’t want to extend him loans, family and friends were also sceptical about the business. But &lt;em&gt;“it was fun”&lt;/em&gt; for him as he steered through the rough phase like a sailor with unbridled confidence and faith in himself. In 1992, he entered the stock market to fuel the car. After raising money, he went on a spree to open Pantaloons stores pan India along with some marketing campaigns and by the end of 1994 Pantaloons laid eggs worth ₹6 million annually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After tasting initial success with Pantaloons, he forayed into the supermarket business with the brand name Big Bazaar, wooing its core customers into large self-service supermarkets and leveraging his own supply and logistics chain to offer across-the-board discounts on maximum retail prices. Big Bazaar was formed on three pillars of Kishore’s ideology- Food, Fashion, and FMCG. You went to get a few vegetables, yet you needed to go through walkways of kurtas and dresses, and were enticed to purchase them. For budget clothing, Biyani launched the FBB design brand. Future Groups Home Center stores were also launched to force people to redesign their homes with the Future Group. The group also forayed into the tech retail sector with the e-zone varying media item stores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the offset of the story, everything seems spick and span but on the inside, the finances weren’t going great. He produced a few films between 2002 and 2003 which turned out to be huge flops. While he was growing at break-neck speed and success seemed to be touching his feet, all the acquisitions and the more than frequent opening up of stores, took him into bucket loads of debt. In fact, in 2012 he sold his flagship Pantaloons retail format to Aditya Birla Group for an estimated ₹16 billion at a time when the group had accumulated a consolidated debt of ₹78.50 billion. In 2014, Future Group acquired the south-based Nilgiris chain of markets for ₹3 billion. In 2011, Foodhall, an upmarket food store, found in luxurious shopping malls, was conceptualised by Biyani’s elder daughter, Avni Biyani. In 2016, a couple of years after Walmart and Bharti Airtel  headed out in different directions and failed to set up retail stores as was agreed under their deal, the Future Group took a plunge and purchased the Bharti Airtel’s Easyday chain of supermarkets. A year ago, it trimmed more than 100 Easyday stores, in an endeavour to cut costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is imperative to think that Mr Biyani tried to put his hands in almost everything from insurance to fashion. But the fact is that it was the fashion outlets which outdid every other business he had. Had he stuck to what he was good at, he would not have had to see these days. It’s not that he shouldn’t have diversified but at a steady pace rather than foraying into every other segment at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazon, which had announced an Indian war chest of $5.54 billion, and Flipkart, which further got strengthened after its buyout by Walmart, were wooing customers across all retail segments. Biyani tried to stick with his core competence customers: the middle-income Indians who preferred to shop in physical stores. Sadly, the customer had tasted the best of both worlds, and were swiftly moving online. Future Group tried but missed the e-commerce opportunity largely because of the promoter’s scepticism of making money on selling goods online. In 2017, the Future Retail also unveiled its ‘Retail 3.0’ platform that would enable tech to merge with offline retail. But it was too late as players were already established and people were happy buying from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, we can say the speed of expansion, acquisition of several retail assets — both regional and national, a chase to build more private labels and in-house manufacturing capabilities have left the company burdened with debt, and caused rating downgrades across the group’s listed entities. As of September 30, 2019, the combined debt of Future Group’s listed companies increased to ₹127 billion from ₹109 billion as of March 31, 2019. His debt woes were further exacerbated by the lockdown, wherein businesses were stalled but he had to keep servicing his debt. Finally, RIL acquired the retail and wholesale business, and the logistics and warehousing business from the Future Group for a lump-sum aggregate consideration of ₹247 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot can be said about Mr Biyani but he believed in the ‘Indian Dream’; he always wanted to help the Indian dream fly high and wanted to ensure that the &lt;em&gt;‘Sone Ki Chidiya’&lt;/em&gt; (Golden Bird) soared once again. We’re left with one question: will Biyani bounce back? Too early to tell. He is a brand and I’m optimistic enough that he’ll come back sooner and much stronger!!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aditya Khandelwal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Kishore Biyani, the retail maverick of India, was the man who took the retail industry by storm. He realised the potential of retail, which oligarchs like the Ambanis and Birlas could not appreciate, and therefore came up with household names like Pantaloons, FBB and Big Bazaar. He is often referred to as the Sam Walton (the owner of Walmart) of India. However, recently, Reliance Industries (RIL) bought Biyani’s Future Group for a whopping ₹247 billion. Let’s understand why Mr Biyani had to sell off his dream, but for starters, let’s get acquainted with his story of rags-to-riches before getting onto the bad part.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Wirecard: The Financial Collapse of the Century</title>
      <link href="/Wirecard-The-Financial-Collapse-of-the-Century" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wirecard: The Financial Collapse of the Century" />
      <published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Wirecard-The-Financial-Collapse-of-the-Century</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Wirecard-The-Financial-Collapse-of-the-Century">&lt;p&gt;The finance industry already grappling with the effects of COVID-19, faced yet another shock with one of the biggest financial scandals in the world coming to the limelight - the Wirecard scandal. Wirecard, a Munich-based payment processing company, once seen as a darling of investors with a market capitalisation of over $28 billion at its peak, filed for bankruptcy on June 25, 2020, after disclosing a $2.1 billion hole in its balance sheet. But what went wrong with the company?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fintech company incorporated in 1999, joined the Frankfurt stock exchange in 2005 and ascended to the ranking of Germany’s 30 leading companies, also known as the DAX Index. It claimed to have subsidiaries across the globe, with payments being processed for more than 200,000 merchants and clients including major European supermarket chains and airlines. It attracted notable investors such as SoftBank. Wirecard was like any other payment processing company that facilitated transactions between consumers and merchants, and earned a certain percentage per transaction. However what set the company apart from its competitors was its rapid expansion in Asia for the reason that it marketed itself as the leader in this system, claiming to have superior technology and highly capitalising on the shift to a cashless society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2008, the first allegations of accounting irregularities against the firm came to light and in the wake of the attack, the company appointed Ernst &amp;amp; Young (EY), one of the largest accounting enterprises in the world, to conduct a special audit on these claims. EY soon then became the Chief Auditor of the organisation for the next 10 years, signing off the firm’s balance sheet. As allegations against the firm of inflating its operational numbers in Asia continued to surface over the years, a pattern emerged with how the company dealt with these criticisms. They would aggressively deny any wrongdoings and announce that it was an attempt to manipulate their stock prices. However, the stock prices kept rising, undeterred by any negative news coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As claims of malpractice mounted, BaFin- the German financial regulator, during its probe focussed more on the accusers rather than the claims against the enterprise. Various analysts believe that authorities’ protection stemmed as it was a huge moment to see a European home-grown company competing against tech titans of Silicon Valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2019, the regulator announced an unprecedented 2-month ban on short-selling of the company’s shares due to its stock price plummeting below €100, citing its importance to the economy and serious threats to market confidence. Some also point to Germany’s corporate culture being wary of foreign speculators, since many allegations were brought forward by the British newspaper &lt;em&gt;Financial Times&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;FT&lt;/em&gt;). However, the regulators denied all allegations against the organisation and even filed a criminal investigation against &lt;em&gt;FT&lt;/em&gt; for colluding with short-sellers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wirecard mainly functioned by buying shell companies that acted as third party payment processors for the organisation. In return, these companies paid them a commission. However, instead of funds flowing into their Munich bank, it was all transferred to escrow accounts. These are special accounts where multiple parties can use them, hence convincing the public that large sums of money existed in them and were used by its subsidiaries. These accounts held more than $2 billion, all of Wirecard’s profit of more than a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, &lt;em&gt;FT&lt;/em&gt; published an article after being alerted by a whistle-blower, that the organisation was cooking accounting books, hiking up its sales and profit numbers of Asia and Pacific operations. Hence, to put an end to these allegations, the company, in 2019, hired Klynveld Peat Marwick Goerdeler (KPMG) to conduct a special audit. The audit report stated that it could not verify the authenticity of these escrow accounts. As more events unfolded, the company stated that all of the money was stored in the Philippines, and not in these escrow accounts. When EY went to examine these claims from the Philippines bank, the former was notified that the documents submitted by the company were all spurious and money never really entered their financial system, thus the $2.1 billion never existed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This announcement led to the arrest of Markus Braun, CEO and CTO of Wirecard since 2002, on June 23, 2020, on suspicion of inflating the value of the company through feigning business with third parties. Two days later, the company filed for insolvency, making it the biggest accounting scandal in post-war German history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The disclosure of malpractice of such a magnitude has eroded the trust in the country’s authorities, giving a heavy blow to Germany’s reputation as a financial centre - impacting its businesses and the confidence of market participants. This revelation has increased the scrutiny of not only accounting firms, especially EY, for failing to inspect the legitimacy of such an account, but also on regulators for their inadequacy. Various critics argued that Germany’s regulatory system is neither equipped to handle large scale processing enterprises like Wirecard nor does it have the power to oversee the investigation of potential malpractices. This highlights the need for transparency in financial systems and various regulatory reforms such as incentives for whistleblowers, a better framework for fintech companies, etc. With the expansion of inquiry, more details are yet to come, nonetheless, investigators worldwide are trying to comprehend how the company used the loopholes to present itself as a profitable business for more than a decade.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The finance industry already grappling with the effects of COVID-19, faced yet another shock with one of the biggest financial scandals in the world coming to the limelight - the Wirecard scandal. Wirecard, a Munich-based payment processing company, once seen as a darling of investors with a market capitalisation of over $28 billion at its peak, filed for bankruptcy on June 25, 2020, after disclosing a $2.1 billion hole in its balance sheet. But what went wrong with the company?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Game of Oil</title>
      <link href="/The-Game-of-Oil" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Game of Oil" />
      <published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Game-of-Oil</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Game-of-Oil">&lt;p&gt;On April 21, 2020, the world witnessed an unprecedented swing in the financial markets since the COVID-19 pandemic broke out, and nothing else has been more jaw-dropping than the West Texas Intermediary (WTI) trading at negative $37.63 per barrel. That’s right, sellers are paying buyers to take the stuff off their hands! The main reason for this? Probably the coronavirus. This pandemic has ravaged global economies, bringing all industrial and economic activities to a halt. As billions of people were advised to stay put at their homes to slow the spread of disease, the physical demand for oil had dried up. And on top of it, airlines and industries weren’t helping much either. Thereby, we can say that the demand was close to nil. But coronavirus might have decreased the prices by a lot, though not to the extent of it trading at a staggering negative of $37, right? So, what caused it then?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst the coronavirus pandemic, came the unexpected oil price war between Russia and Saudi Arabia. Oil prices were already tumbling due to scarce demand. Taking into account the plummeting demand, the Organisation of the Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) nations decided to cut the production by 1.5 million barrels per day (BPD), on top of the existing cuts. However, to everyone’s surprise, Russia backed out of the deal. This move was a response to the declining share of OPEC+ countries (OPEC + Russia) to the US shale producers; supposing OPEC+ reduced their supply, US shale producers would step in and rope all the customers of OPEC+.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia’s response agitated the oil-rich nations and the repercussions involved an announcement to flood the market with oil by producing 12.3 million BPD. Thereby, almost all the nations went on the offensive and ramped up their production. The story seemed interesting until now, to see how the two countries fought with each other through crude oil. But as countries’ production ascended, the storage avenues started to fill at an unprecedented rate and this was when the real problem came to light. The prices dipped below zero not because of scarce demand and excess supply but due to ‘oil futures’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s understand the concept of ‘oil futures’. To put it simply, a future means deciding the price for a commodity now but delivery and payment at a future pre-determined date. Let’s say you have futures of crude oil worth $40 and the delivery is anytime between May 1 and May 31. You need to get rid of the futures contract by April 20, according to the rule by the New York Mercantile Exchange, otherwise, you end up taking the actual delivery of goods. As a futures dealer, you might have thought that as the price of crude oil will rally, it would be profitable to sell them at a discount on current market price and earn a hefty profit later on. But the situation turned upside down and there was no taker for the futures contract. And your heart started thumping heavily, suddenly you see the futures chart falling to zero and as the time started to come closer, the price decreased as there was anxious selling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re in a dilemma about your course of action: either you take actual delivery of crude oil or you sell it at a negative price, in either case, you suffer a heavy setback. Now, we cannot just think of storing the oil in our garden as it is a bare minimum requirement to buy at least 1,000 barrels, or if you’re thinking to store it in the shipping yard, we’d have to shell another set of dollars, but the shipping yard was almost full and on top of it, they were charging exorbitant prices for it. Therefore, it was better to tick off the former option. Being left with the latter, we try to sell it at the least possible price, just to get rid of it. Due to panic selling, the prices dipped below zero which thereby caused a once-in-a-lifetime moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we write, crude oil prices have registered three weekly gains in a row, amid efforts by top producers to cut production due to concerns about recovery from the damage caused by the coronavirus pandemic and resultant lockdowns. Saudia Arabia has a history of waging oil price wars that have created ruckus all around the country. Increasing or decreasing production of oil might seem like a pinch to the Saudis but the repercussion is that various companies are filing for bankruptcy. The oil price war is rather synonymous with an actual war: wherein valiant soldiers die. But in this case, hard-working businessmen are turning bankrupt, just because they have to give in to the conditions dictated by the big and mighty, which causes them to incur losses. This puts up a very important question: is it the time to decentralise this power?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aditya Khandelwal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On April 21, 2020, the world witnessed an unprecedented swing in the financial markets since the COVID-19 pandemic broke out, and nothing else has been more jaw-dropping than the West Texas Intermediary (WTI) trading at negative $37.63 per barrel. That’s right, sellers are paying buyers to take the stuff off their hands! The main reason for this? Probably the coronavirus. This pandemic has ravaged global economies, bringing all industrial and economic activities to a halt. As billions of people were advised to stay put at their homes to slow the spread of disease, the physical demand for oil had dried up. And on top of it, airlines and industries weren’t helping much either. Thereby, we can say that the demand was close to nil. But coronavirus might have decreased the prices by a lot, though not to the extent of it trading at a staggering negative of $37, right? So, what caused it then?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Era of Online Stock Trading: Robinhood Misleads Gen-Z</title>
      <link href="/Robinhood-Misleads-Gen-Z" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Era of Online Stock Trading: Robinhood Misleads Gen-Z" />
      <published>2020-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Robinhood-Misleads-Gen-Z</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Robinhood-Misleads-Gen-Z">&lt;p&gt;The novel coronavirus has led to a situation of crisis and has drastically impacted consumer behaviour and supply chains, thus creating an imbalance. While this disparity has proven to be a nightmare for most of the business houses, some of them are really making it big. As people adjust to this new normal, technology has been their friend in disguise to learn new skills and explore their areas of interest. App developers are among those few who are benefitting from this pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lockdown has also led to a surge in first-time investors/traders entering the stock market. Stocks with “zero equity value” and even penny stocks have doubled since April this year. This increase is mainly due to easy access to the process via stock market apps which have seen maximum sign-ups in the past few months. Robinhood - one such stock market app has been in the headlines for quite some time now. They gained 3,000,000 new users within the first 6 months of 2020, which is literally half of the new trading accounts created this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The company has become one of the fastest-growing tech startups in recent times. The ease of trading that the app provides, has turned into a cultural phenomenon, and Robinhood has climbed to the billion-dollar mark. With investors pouring in money, its valuation has reached $11.2 billion. The app has been a hit since its launch in 2013 and has been growing since then. It recorded 4.3 million DART’s (Daily Average Revenue Trades), surpassing all its competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This huge traffic of day traders has also been affecting the American stock market. This is being referred to as the “Robinhood Effect”. It is described as the irrational stock price changes in the market. This effect began when apps like Robinhood attempted to democratise investing by providing platforms that simplified the methods and thus people with no background or knowledge joined the trading world. Today, youth with minimum capital are playing around as shares have become affordable due to the current economic situation. According to research, users buying small inexpensive stocks are generating solid returns which gives them an incentive to stay. Thus, it seems like the hype is not going to die anytime soon for this huge army of day traders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app even offers the facility to buy fractional shares which lowers the risk. Robinhood doesn’t charge trading commissions, which further increases its popularity. These day traders are becoming known as the “risk-takers”. The accounts are mostly handled by youngsters who are stuck in their homes due to the norms of social distancing. They are ready to take immediate action and trade shares without much consideration. These investors are inexperienced and don’t have much prior knowledge. Not only are they indulging in basic trades but also in advanced level trading like futures and options. This behaviour has proven to be beneficial for the company but can cause serious losses to the traders. Many investors have shared their traumatic experiences which were mainly caused due to their uninformed choices. A 20-year-old college student from Nebraska killed himself as his balance dropped to negative $730,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consequences being faced are intense and the developers should take accountability for the same. Educating the newcomers and providing enough information should be an important aspect of the whole trading process. The new day traders who start playing with their capital end up bearing losses which can thereby lead to some detrimental conditions. Certain restrictions within the app will definitely ensure some responsibility by these individuals. Another problem being faced by the company is of technical glitches. These tech issues have increased with the rise in the number of users and sometimes, these also lead to losses due to the fluctuating nature of stocks. In order to solve these issues and have better customer service, Robinhood plans to expand its team. They have more than a hundred positions available in many American cities. This move will benefit the consumers and might also help the issue of unemployment at some level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While every firm has its own set of difficulties, dealing with them in a strategic manner is the best way out. Robinhood too has its own set of criticisms. Even in this capitalistic world, ethics still hold high regard and companies should take decisions after considering certain moral grounds. The idea of providing easy access to the stock market is ideal but it still has its own problems that need attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app has totally changed our outlook towards the stock market and trading. It has provided an avenue to millions of people to invest and has also led to certain prominent changes in the market which might be fruitful. But, at the same time, its harms are no less in terms of losses being suffered. The uncertainty of the stock market has also blurred my perspective on Robinhood’s future. It definitely hasn’t proven to be as generous as the animated character! Until then, the uncertainty will remain a constant source of anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The novel coronavirus has led to a situation of crisis and has drastically impacted consumer behaviour and supply chains, thus creating an imbalance. While this disparity has proven to be a nightmare for most of the business houses, some of them are really making it big. As people adjust to this new normal, technology has been their friend in disguise to learn new skills and explore their areas of interest. App developers are among those few who are benefitting from this pandemic.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Breaking Up Big Tech</title>
      <link href="/Breaking-Up-Big-Tech" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breaking Up Big Tech" />
      <published>2020-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Breaking-Up-Big-Tech</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Breaking-Up-Big-Tech">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“It’s about as likely as is Mexico paying for Trump’s wall”&lt;/em&gt;, commented an equity researcher in response to Elizabeth Warren’s proposal. Have Google and Facebook become too powerful in our economy, should they be broken up? Are they creating some sort of monopoly in the technology space? All these are questions that have been in our minds for quite some time now. A decade ago, Amazon, Google, Facebook, Apple, and other networking sites were not a part of our lives the way they are today. However, in recent times, the emergence of these e-commerce websites and search engines has immensely increased, with everything, from purchasing groceries to online classes, taking place through these established tech agents. The issue cropped up after the US Senator Elizabeth Warren proposed to break down these companies into smaller units. This is gaining quite some popularity on both sides of the US political divide. Even President Donald Trump has made comments disparaging big tech and called for the government to sue companies like Google and Facebook. Lawmakers back in the US are thinking to disintegrate these companies because they feel that these companies have absolutely dismantled the healthy competitive spirit in their respective domains and have completely violated the antitrust laws of the country. So, let’s start unfolding the various layers of this recently heated debate by getting down to the history of the antitrust laws of the USA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Brief History of the Antitrust Laws in the USA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States has a history of breaking up large companies. Back then the railroad, oil, steel and sugar industries formed monopolies because of the very few competitors they had. Thus, they became wealthier at the expense of the consumer. The most well-known example is that of Standard Oil which controlled the entire industry of oil due to which they could completely change the price of the product by changing the supply. The oil industry at that time was prone to natural monopolies because of the rarity of the products. At this juncture, the federal government was forced to bust many of these large businesses with the help of the newly created ‘Antitrust Laws’ to protect the interests of the consumers. The first of these was the Sherman Act, passed in 1890 which aimed at preventing mergers between companies that led to unfair competition in the market. Despite this Act’s approval in 1890, the next fifty years saw the formation of many monopolies. Also, the profits of  Standard Oil and the generous dividends encouraged investors to invest in monopolistic firms. Succeeding it in 1914, the Federal Trade Commission Act was passed to monitor and track unfair business practices that deter the spirit of competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very well-known example of this Act being used is that of Microsoft  which was believed to be the tech giant of its time and aimed at establishing dominance in the area of web browsing but then the federal government intervened and sued it for violating anti-monopoly laws and reached an agreement with it. One school of thought says that the antitrust case on Microsoft that time helped shape a path for big tech giants like Google and Amazon to emerge. However, some analysts are of the view that in today’s times these antitrust laws seem inapplicable to the tech giants because they are already a century old and they were created to protect the interests of the consumers differently, specifically we mean that they were built in an era where financial domination led to the creation of monopolies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Role of Big Tech and the Present Debate Related to It&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US economy has been on an upward trend which can to some extent be attributed to the tech sector. Nearly, half of the e-commerce goes through Amazon, more than 70% of all internet referral traffic goes through sites owned and operated by Google and Facebook. Instagram, today, has one billion active monthly users – two-thirds of whom visit the platform on a daily basis. More than two million businesses have bought ads there, many of which are intended to drive users to their websites to buy products. And Senator Elizabeth Warren feels that these companies have too much power over our economy, society and democracy. Presidential candidate Bernie Sanders has also clashed with Amazon on multiple occasions, and criticised Facebook and Google for destroying local media. He said that he will look into breaking up big tech companies. This proposal enjoys support from not just the majority of Democrats but in similar proportions of Republicans and Independents, claiming it to be a bipartisan issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent online poll, it has been shown that around 7 in 10 Americans say it’s a good idea to break up big tech companies when the content that they are showing is ranked depending on whether the company is making money or not. On these lines, it is being argued that the current landscape of technology has left consumers with little privacy even as their data is converted into vast corporate profit. These American big tech companies have mainly achieved the level of dominance by using two strategies- using mergers to limit competition and using the proprietary marketplace to limit competition. Take the example of Facebook, which purchased potential competitors such as Instagram and WhatsApp. Amazon used its extreme market power to force smaller competitors such as Diapers.com to sell its products at a discounted rate. Weak antitrust enforcement laws have led to the culminating dominance created by these tech companies in the last few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venture capitalists are also hesitant to fund new tech because they feel that either these start-ups would be purchased by these monopolists or else, they will completely crash. It is also claimed that with fewer tech companies entering the market, these large tech agents don’t have to compete in matters such as protecting our data privacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two sorts of measures that can be taken to break these monopolies, first by passing legislation that requires large tech platforms to be designated as ‘platform utilities’ (companies with annual global revenue of $25 billion or more that offer to the public an online marketplace, an exchange, or a platform connecting third parties would be termed as ‘platform utilities’) that would be broken apart from any participant on that platform, with them not being allowed to share data with any third parties. Also, they should be required to meet a standard of fair, reasonable and non-discriminatory dealing with third parties. Such measures would also ensure that the sovereignty of America is upheld and no third-country can influence its election results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will Breaking Up these Tech Giants Really Fix it Up?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experts from Wharton have challenged Warren’s proposals and said that breaking them up won’t actually provide a level playing field, but instead in the long term would again route down profits to other successful business ventures. I believe that the reason why this political debate has come up is completely valid but the solution that is being offered is not the most practical, this is because even in the past this has not worked. The breaking up of AT&amp;amp;T into eight companies unleashed competition for a time, lowering prices but as landlines gave way for wireless, the industry reconsolidated. Thus, the enforcement of antitrust laws will not solve the issues of high prices and privacy. For example, removing WhatsApp from Facebook won’t let Facebook collect any lesser data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consumers would also be at a loss because, if suppose, we disintegrate Google then we won’t be able to simultaneously use Google Drive and Google Chrome, imagine the number of complexities involved. Also, the Antitrust Doctrine has focused on two things, one is the conduct and the other is the structure. The Federal Trade Commission and Department of Justice should focus on the conduct and behaviour of big tech companies to make sure that they don’t use their market power to become anticompetitive. The size of these companies have enabled them to make big investments in future, if we try to break them up, we’re going to lose that. Also, even if antitrust laws would prevent mergers, we need to understand the chain reaction that would follow, which is when prices are lowered the wages will be lowered too, jobs would be cut, and product quality would also fall discouraging innovation. All of these changes would unknowingly harm the consumers in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s in Store for these Large Tech Giants?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we can not deny the fact that these large tech giants have created some sort of dominance in the society with their products, lucrative offers and better policies at hand to gain maximum profits and to drive out other competitors from the business, we should not deny the fact that they have always driven the economy on an upward trend, providing better opportunities for employees. We should also realise the fact that disintegrating them based on antitrust laws is not correct because globalisation and the ever-increasing world economy have called out for the retirement of the antitrust laws. Further, ultimately, we as consumers are also to be blamed because, in the end, it’s we who have given them the title of large tech giants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning, most of them started on a level playing field and now they have reached their present level due to a lot of effort. Instead of just relying on one individual’s statement and subsequently taking action against these tech giants is not justified, the regulators and politicians should ask the consumers how ‘bad’ they find the tech giants to be at present and then decide. We need to understand that instead of breaking them up, we should think of fixing up issues like data privacy. Moreover, we should look at the fact that even though an investigation can be carried on for years accusing them of many things but ultimately proving them in court with proofs would be another thing because they would also leave no stone unturned to prove themselves not guilty. With some forces standing against them and others supporting it, the future of these big tech companies remains uncertain and largely depends on what shall happen in the courts.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Cherry Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“It’s about as likely as is Mexico paying for Trump’s wall”, commented an equity researcher in response to Elizabeth Warren’s proposal. Have Google and Facebook become too powerful in our economy, should they be broken up? Are they creating some sort of monopoly in the technology space? All these are questions that have been in our minds for quite some time now. A decade ago, Amazon, Google, Facebook, Apple, and other networking sites were not a part of our lives the way they are today. However, in recent times, the emergence of these e-commerce websites and search engines has immensely increased, with everything, from purchasing groceries to online classes, taking place through these established tech agents. The issue cropped up after the US Senator Elizabeth Warren proposed to break down these companies into smaller units. This is gaining quite some popularity on both sides of the US political divide. Even President Donald Trump has made comments disparaging big tech and called for the government to sue companies like Google and Facebook. Lawmakers back in the US are thinking to disintegrate these companies because they feel that these companies have absolutely dismantled the healthy competitive spirit in their respective domains and have completely violated the antitrust laws of the country. So, let’s start unfolding the various layers of this recently heated debate by getting down to the history of the antitrust laws of the USA.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The IPL Business and the Sponsorship Conundrum</title>
      <link href="/IPL-Sponsorship-Conundrum" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The IPL Business and the Sponsorship Conundrum" />
      <published>2020-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/IPL-Sponsorship-Conundrum</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/IPL-Sponsorship-Conundrum">&lt;p&gt;Sports fans comprise one of the most passionate and powerful demographics in the world. From companies like Barilla, to the more well-known ones like Budweiser, all brands consistently bring their A-game to sports sponsorship activities. Sponsors are finding clever ways to bring fans closer to the game, the athletes, and thereby, to their brand. The sponsorship of events represents a significant and growing component of a firm’s overall investment in marketing and promotions. While the marketing literature suggests that sponsorships may be a potential communication tool, relatively little empirical research has been devoted to studying efficiency issues in sponsorships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coca-Cola and the Olympics, Rolex and the TED, and PepsiCo and NFL are some of the many long-standing sponsorships that have caught our eyes, have been stuck in our brains, and have managed to hire us as free mouths for applause. In the most memorable episode, during the 1992 Barcelona Olympics, sponsorship was used to fuel comparative advertising campaigns. VISA’s tagline was ‘The Olympics don’t take American Express’, with images of ticket windows being slammed shut in the faces of American Express cardholders. The $20 million that they had paid to the International Olympic Committee (IOC) for their official sponsorship ensured that they received no complaints about the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, American Express responded with more style, pointing out in its own advertisement campaigns that ‘To visit Spain, you don’t need a Visa’. Before UNICEF tied hands with football club Barcelona, it was just a Catalonian football club, but soon after, the football giant became the world’s favourite football club alongside UNICEF as ‘More than a club’. Nike’s close call with Michael Jordan in a commercial &lt;em&gt;“I’ve missed more than 9000 shots in my career….”&lt;/em&gt;, changed the brand forever. The sporting fraternity has seen it all, right from Coca-Cola’s  ‘Taste the feeling’  campaign during the Rio Olympic Games of 2016 with the #thatsgold campaign, to the Arsenal player Nicklas Bendtner proudly lowering his shorts while showcasing his underpants branded with Irish bookmaker Paddy Power’s logo when millions of spectators were glued to their TV sets. Sports has had a love affair with grandstanding sponsorships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months down the line Indian cricketers will compete with each other to prove their dominance and for this, they’ll take help from the foreigners too. This will take place as a festival of sorts. People will support their states instead of the country. And, we’ll get to witness a distorted form of the &lt;em&gt;‘Gentleman’s Game’&lt;/em&gt; in the form of an extravaganza. The Indian Premier League (IPL) is set to host its 13th edition in the United Arab Emirates (UAE) this year and the talks around sponsorships have already fuelled. The BCCI and the IPL make money via the auction of broadcasting rights, title and corporate sponsorship, ticket sales, auction of franchise rights, and official umpire sponsorship. Though the IPL has produced ghastly match-fixing incidents, terrible fights among cricketers on the field, mass level gambling, and whatnot, people can be seen binge-watching matches on their phone and simultaneously speculating the outcomes during the 42-day long tournament. Just like the IPL, the history of IPL’s title sponsorship is also muddled with a bit of controversy, confusion and drama. Besides this, the economics of IPL churns in millions and billions of rupees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2008, DLF, India’s largest real estate company, paid a hefty sum of ₹2 billion (around $36.25 million), to own the title rights for the first five years of the tournament. However, after the given period, DLF decided not to renew its contract. This forced Board of Control for Cricket in India (BCCI) to issue a new tender, with a base price of ₹3 billion. In 2013, PepsiCo was the new title sponsor until 2015 when it chose to terminate its contract amid rising concerns of match-fixing, and irregular and untimely blemishes on the face of the IPL. VIVO, the Chinese smartphone company was then roped in for the 2016 and 2017 season. The BCCI had a fresh deal with VIVO in 2018 that saw them earn ₹4.40 billion every year, but the Indo-China face-off across the Line of Actual Control (LAC) as well as the negative publicity of the smartphone brand, has forced VIVO to withdraw its name as IPL sponsor this season. Though VIVO will no longer be a sponsor this year, it has only sought for a one-year moratorium, keeping the door open for a 2021 return. So, the BCCI is in an eager search to find a new short-term replacement sponsor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst the rising cries and steadfast support for home-grown brands, it has been understood that e-commerce companies as well as educational e-portals are keen to get the IPL sponsorship. Others in the race include Patanjali Ayurveda and Jio, besides e-learning platforms Byju’s and Unacademy, and fantasy sports firm Dream11. Though 5 companies have given their Expression of Interest (EOI), Tata Sons are likely to win the race hands down against the others on the back of not only money power but also because of being the biggest home-grown brand. The homegrown FMCG brand, Patanjali was the first brand in the country to openly declare that they would be bidding for the title sponsorship of the IPL but the loudest of the suitors seems to have chickened out. Despite  Patanjali’s antics, the BCCI need not worry as the IPL 2020 is set to get a helping hand from one of the biggest and the most credible business houses of the country. It’s unsure, given the current scenario and sudden exit of VIVO, that the final bid would be anywhere close to what VIVO was offering but it will be interesting to see to what extent the BCCI will manage to cut its losses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For reference, the brand value of IPL stood at $6.8 billion in 2019 up 7% from 2018, according to consultancy firm Duff and Phelps. It is not clear what model the consultants have used to calculate gross value added from the cricketing extravaganza, and a lot depends on this, but cricket administrators have done well to commission such a study. There is a broader lesson here. The contribution of IPL is currently just a drop in the $3 trillion Indian economy, around 0.2%. One can assume from this fact that sports are still a very small part of the economy. Informal studies show that most rich nations have around 1.5-2% of their GDP coming from sports. Indian sports have a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another key question which is worthy of consideration is how do you calculate the Return on Investment (ROI) of sponsorship? It is probably the initiative that has the highest budget commitment, so it’s extremely important to ensure that the marketing dollars spent on sponsorship can be traced. There is no Bloomberg Terminal or NASDAQ exchange to provide external benchmarks of the value of sponsorship assets. And there are few accounting standards or valuation models that brands can use to determine the fair financial value of a team, stadium or athlete. There are a few ways to calculate ROI for sponsorship:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a. By taking into account the change in a brand’s share of ‘voice’ before and after the sports tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b. By measuring buyers’ purchase intent using tools like digital surveys or social media audits. Especially if a brand deals in high-value products and purchases such as automobiles, IPL sponsorships cannot immediately skyrocket their sales since generally, a large investment is needed for it. Of course, inquiries can go up, but an immediate ROI would not represent an accurate picture. Purchase intent surveys can help to understand the effectiveness of sponsorships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s very hard to measure the financial value of sponsorship investments. Chief Finacial Officers (CFOs) fairly argue that they lack the financial vocabulary and Key Performance Indicators (KPIs) to properly measure these complex investments that require a blend of art, science and commercialism to execute. The bigger issue marketers face as they defend their multi-million-dollar sponsorship budgets is that they fail to quantify and communicate how these investments create financial value beyond their equivalent media value. Until these problems are solved, CFOs will continue to treat sponsorship as a discretionary expense rather than a growth asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until then, the whole of India looks forward to seeing their beloved soap-opera that brings all the emotions on the table. Love, joy, happiness, tears, laughter, sadness, and lots of deceit and intrigue. The white ball going against the night sky like it’s a meteor headed somewhere, bits and pieces of outlandish stump mic conversations, embellished commentary voices, and glitzy song and dance will be a feast to watch. Now attach to it the dollars it deals in, it’s all the way more interesting.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Mehul Goyal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Sports fans comprise one of the most passionate and powerful demographics in the world. From companies like Barilla, to the more well-known ones like Budweiser, all brands consistently bring their A-game to sports sponsorship activities. Sponsors are finding clever ways to bring fans closer to the game, the athletes, and thereby, to their brand. The sponsorship of events represents a significant and growing component of a firm’s overall investment in marketing and promotions. While the marketing literature suggests that sponsorships may be a potential communication tool, relatively little empirical research has been devoted to studying efficiency issues in sponsorships.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
