<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/aritra.gupta/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-07-26T04:55:09+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/aritra.gupta/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Millennials and Meme Culture</title>
      <link href="/Millennials-and-Meme-Culture" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Millennials and Meme Culture" />
      <published>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Millennials-and-Meme-Culture</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Millennials-and-Meme-Culture">&lt;p&gt;Art has existed for about 30,000 years now. And although art has no practical utility, it is one of those things that puts humans at the apex of the food chain. At first, art was strictly an extension of the artist’s speculation, and slowly it branched out to imagination. It slowly evolved into a tool to form friendships and solidarities, establish authority, form groups, bands, tribes, civilisations, and societies. Societies as big as Russia were formed through art. And, unlike the other extension of human cognitive faculty, i.e. science, art has evolved on its own through vessels called artists. It has endured through time and adapted itself to epochal changes and cultural diversifications like a living, breathing organism. If there’s one thing on the planet that could come close to humans, it would be art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time and the intent behind it shape the adaptability of art. Art can be used as a mouthpiece for personal vexation, for political propaganda, as a romantic sonnet, a rebellious speech, or even as satire. The possibilities are endless and the means to propagate them have a few malleable forms. The very beginning of art was through illustrations, statuettes, and fictional stories. As our ancestors developed their faculties, so did art. It has since then taken several forms, namely illustration, text, sculpting, acting, dance, song, cinema and now, memes. Like innumerable developments in the field of art, memes too betray a thing or two about the period to which they are relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;em&gt;meme&lt;/em&gt; originally comes from the Greek word ‘&lt;em&gt;mimema&lt;/em&gt;’, meaning imitation. The term was coined by Richard Dawkins in his book &lt;em&gt;The Selfish Gene&lt;/em&gt; in 1976. Back then, however, the word didn’t gain a lot of recognition. A few decades later, after the emergence of the Internet, memes have surged to be an art form most characteristic of the millennials or Gen Y.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand how a meme is a form of art, we need to understand other art forms. The key idea behind any art is to freeze or compress a particular thought or vision, a whole infinity into a finite space. It confronts our consciousness with matters that we miss out on due to activities essential to survival. If rendered well enough, it takes hold of our spirits and colonises it with whatever it wanted to. Consuming art is a conscious effort and has always been, until the arrival of memes. Memes have gone astray from this principle of art. Memes are consumed in an unstudied manner, seldom requiring cognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memes are symbolic of millennials. They symbolise the hyperactive lifestyle of our generation. They betray the cultural degradation we are going through. A degradation that makes us ponder and say less and less and passively consume more and more. Our vocabulary is riddled with buzzwords which lose meaning with every passing day. Abundance has made us fall out of our practice of thinking. Time has shortened itself relatively, and we constantly seek to escape reality. On average, in a single day, a person goes through a hundred different thoughts, which are &lt;em&gt;not his own&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are losing the originality of thought, the creativity that we are born with. It is in the nature of words and of our human selves to make it difficult to say just about anything. It is momentous to experience the bittersweetness of struggling for words to express how we feel, to lose words just as they are clawing at the base of one’s throat. But with meme culture we lose that. My broken expression and my efforts give way to tagging my friends in memes and to what Buzzfeed tells me describes me and the culture of my generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The erosion of human cognition is alarming and evermore because of the manner of consumption. As mentioned before, memes are consumed quite absently not requiring a conscious effort. This leaves us unguarded, vulnerable to what the memes represent. And, as the practice of conscious thinking ebbs away, so does our consciousness towards life. We are gradually turning apathetic, normalising things that should evoke deep concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Phil Kaye tells us, “If you repeat something over and over again it loses its meaning.” The words ‘climate change’ turn into a category of memes you share, people’s mental traumas become a ‘&lt;em&gt;mood&lt;/em&gt;’ to us and bashing capitalist exploitation just something we do for the kick of feeling edgy. The outrageous loses the ability to outrage us anymore. We think we feel so much that we end up feeling very little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A generation distinguished by a mental health crisis, an existential crisis, a crisis of faith, and a crisis of belief requires, above all, empathy and a careful understanding of the self to counter all our crises. But with the emergence of memes, the probability of countering them is plummeting. Memes that represent cultures and societies, on both micro and macro levels, qualify as phenomenal and path-breaking. Memes have helped us understand our kind better, they’ve taken away the alienation we feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, memes have ended up normalising, without us realising, a lot that is worrisome. The apathy we feel towards ourselves and our actions is of grave concern. The manifestation of this apathy is seen in the increasing streak of nihilism in our generation. Memes are blurring the lines and lies constructed through fiction over the ages and slowly lifting our trust from certain systems of belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But enough about the villainy of memes. Memes are an extension of postmodernism. One can’t discount all of the good that memes have brought. They’ve made us aware of things we otherwise would have remained oblivious of: culture, people, politics, ideologies, sports, our favourite celebrities. Memes are reaching to form a global culture, unparalleled by any art form before. Millennials understand diversity better than any of our previous generations. Millennials are aware of and understand the climate crisis, the water crisis and in general the humanitarian crisis breathing heavily down our necks. With the hyperactivity and the pace of things, it is difficult to take time out to be aware, to seek information, but with memes, it is no longer an arduous task. The simplicity of it is probably its greatest feature. It psychologically functions on the need to remain simple. Perhaps why we keep returning to memes in the face of rising complexities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memes represent a milestone in the evolution of art, a point at which human art has transcended from a confrontation of our inner consciousness to an unguarded passive intake of what lies before one. For better or for worse, meme culture has a sinister ability to both reveal and shape the people who consume it the most, namely the Millennials.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Art has existed for about 30,000 years now. And although art has no practical utility, it is one of those things that puts humans at the apex of the food chain. At first, art was strictly an extension of the artist’s speculation, and slowly it branched out to imagination. It slowly evolved into a tool to form friendships and solidarities, establish authority, form groups, bands, tribes, civilisations, and societies. Societies as big as Russia were formed through art. And, unlike the other extension of human cognitive faculty, i.e. science, art has evolved on its own through vessels called artists. It has endured through time and adapted itself to epochal changes and cultural diversifications like a living, breathing organism. If there’s one thing on the planet that could come close to humans, it would be art.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Great Indian Intercourse</title>
      <link href="/The-Great-Indian-Intercourse" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Great Indian Intercourse" />
      <published>2019-06-28T21:29:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-28T21:29:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Great-Indian-Intercourse</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Great-Indian-Intercourse">&lt;p&gt;Of the many things that India, as a subcontinent, has achieved or done, such as
overpopulation, growing disparity between economic classes and the caste system,
probably one of the greatest would be the writing of the &lt;em&gt;Kama Sutra&lt;/em&gt;; and even
though we have, as a nation, owned up to most of the country’s achievements,
even the more bizarre ones such as child marriage, in case of sex we tend to
walk right by it without even a cursory glance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might argue that such prudish behaviour is a result of uneven distribution
of cultural capital, but I believe that’s an oxymoron in itself. I’m not here to
talk about how such prudence came into being in Indian culture – that is a topic
for another day. What I would like to draw attention to is the product of such
prudence taking shape in the form of coyness surrounding the topic of sex in
Indian society. Now, if you belong to an extremely liberal Indian family or
reside in the West, you’re probably not aware of the coyness I speak of. But we
plebs have felt it right from our childhood, when our mothers would, almost in a
frenzy, change the channel if we accidentally tuned into some English movie
channel with a couple kissing on the screen. This particular act of maternal
care and horror brought about two things; firstly, a curiosity about the most
basic and prevalent of human natures that would sooner or later manifest into
action, and secondly, through this suppression, we were being conditioned into
suppressing our very understanding of ourselves. If we do not properly accept
and understand the psychology underlying sex and sexuality we become blunt to
our very existence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of things that we, as a society, do are directly or indirectly inspired by
sex. We were taught, rather preached with sincerity that English films are a
matter of disgrace and can bring &lt;em&gt;Mata’s&lt;/em&gt; (the Hindu Mother Goddess’) curse upon
us. Problems started for my mother when Indian advertisements stared getting
liberal with sex as well. She was then left with little choice but to accept her
defeat, while commenting on how Indian culture was getting ‘corrupted’. As is
the norm in India, my parents never talked about sex in front of me, and as I
grew up they started keeping their bedroom door open most of the time, except at
night, so as to not arouse any suspicion in their growing child’s mind! And this
isn’t just the case with families that have children, rather with any family
where there are people besides the couple live. We are a sex hungry nation, lewd
staring in buses and public places are a testimony to that, and yet we continue
with this all-prevailing diktat of silence no matter where we go. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this diktat has a silver lining to it and we must not discount it. As sex
has grown to be the giant &lt;strong&gt;taboo&lt;/strong&gt; of Indian society, it has become all the
more &lt;strong&gt;pleasurable&lt;/strong&gt; to consume. Coyness has turned out to be more of a boon
than a bane for most couples around the nation and for one simple reason:
&lt;em&gt;forbidden fruit tastes better&lt;/em&gt;. Society, as a whole, sees sex as immoral. No
one quite imagines that the couple they randomly passed by on the street
actually has sex or to be more precise, one cannot picture them doing it. What
this does psychologically is that it makes one’s intimacy with their partner
ever so special. They choose to remain oblivious of sex happening in any place
besides their own chambers. Couples and other couples collectively, mutedly,
gorge through their disreputable escapades thinking that they are alone in doing
it. And the less they get to do it, the better; because that preserves the idea
of immorality. If talking about sex is normalised, the details, no matter how
small or vague, would start to come forward and one would realise what and how
they do it is the same as everyone else; which isn’t necessarily a bad thing but
it takes away that extra bit of pleasure which comes from the high of
&lt;em&gt;rebellion&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the millennials who probably don’t ‘get it’ and are scratching their heads
thinking, “sex is sex; it is great even without the coyness”, draw an analogy to
when you look for taboo porn or something offbeat on the internet when regular
stuff just doesn’t do it for you anymore. It’s the same with sex, the more it
remains sacred and clandestine, the better it feels when done. This theory
explains to some extent why people have extra-marital affairs, it is that
clandestine factor that makes it all the more coveted and hot. This also
explains why India ranks second in terms of population even with a culture of
muted sexual desires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This theory goes beyond sex, extending to almost everything that is forbidden by
society. The forbidden is a massive source of pleasure, no matter what, because
even when one is part of the chorus of society, rebellion against the same
society that one belongs to is enthralling, to say the least. Revolutions on any
scale are the greatest form of validation a human can enjoy. Although having sex
is not a revolution per se, but doing it, at the end of the day, after not even
hinting at the presence of one’s sexuality or sensuality throughout the day,
does have a massive sense of breaking free and disobeying our own sense of
immorality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, the diktat is dying out with the emergence of Generation Y. And although
this brings in a different set of pleasures to consume (in varied manners too),
it will be regretful, at least for me, not to taste the pleasure that came out
of the weird furtiveness our previous generations displayed.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Of the many things that India, as a subcontinent, has achieved or done, such as overpopulation, growing disparity between economic classes and the caste system, probably one of the greatest would be the writing of the Kama Sutra; and even though we have, as a nation, owned up to most of the country’s achievements, even the more bizarre ones such as child marriage, in case of sex we tend to walk right by it without even a cursory glance.  One might argue that such prudish behaviour is a result of uneven distribution of cultural capital, but I believe that’s an oxymoron in itself. I’m not here to talk about how such prudence came into being in Indian culture – that is a topic for another day. What I would like to draw attention to is the product of such prudence taking shape in the form of coyness surrounding the topic of sex in Indian society. Now, if you belong to an extremely liberal Indian family or reside in the West, you’re probably not aware of the coyness I speak of. But we plebs have felt it right from our childhood, when our mothers would, almost in a frenzy, change the channel if we accidentally tuned into some English movie channel with a couple kissing on the screen. This particular act of maternal care and horror brought about two things; firstly, a curiosity about the most basic and prevalent of human natures that would sooner or later manifest into action, and secondly, through this suppression, we were being conditioned into suppressing our very understanding of ourselves. If we do not properly accept and understand the psychology underlying sex and sexuality we become blunt to our very existence.  A lot of things that we, as a society, do are directly or indirectly inspired by sex. We were taught, rather preached with sincerity that English films are a matter of disgrace and can bring Mata’s (the Hindu Mother Goddess’) curse upon us. Problems started for my mother when Indian advertisements stared getting liberal with sex as well. She was then left with little choice but to accept her defeat, while commenting on how Indian culture was getting ‘corrupted’. As is the norm in India, my parents never talked about sex in front of me, and as I grew up they started keeping their bedroom door open most of the time, except at night, so as to not arouse any suspicion in their growing child’s mind! And this isn’t just the case with families that have children, rather with any family where there are people besides the couple live. We are a sex hungry nation, lewd staring in buses and public places are a testimony to that, and yet we continue with this all-prevailing diktat of silence no matter where we go.  But this diktat has a silver lining to it and we must not discount it. As sex has grown to be the giant taboo of Indian society, it has become all the more pleasurable to consume. Coyness has turned out to be more of a boon than a bane for most couples around the nation and for one simple reason: forbidden fruit tastes better. Society, as a whole, sees sex as immoral. No one quite imagines that the couple they randomly passed by on the street actually has sex or to be more precise, one cannot picture them doing it. What this does psychologically is that it makes one’s intimacy with their partner ever so special. They choose to remain oblivious of sex happening in any place besides their own chambers. Couples and other couples collectively, mutedly, gorge through their disreputable escapades thinking that they are alone in doing it. And the less they get to do it, the better; because that preserves the idea of immorality. If talking about sex is normalised, the details, no matter how small or vague, would start to come forward and one would realise what and how they do it is the same as everyone else; which isn’t necessarily a bad thing but it takes away that extra bit of pleasure which comes from the high of rebellion.  For the millennials who probably don’t ‘get it’ and are scratching their heads thinking, “sex is sex; it is great even without the coyness”, draw an analogy to when you look for taboo porn or something offbeat on the internet when regular stuff just doesn’t do it for you anymore. It’s the same with sex, the more it remains sacred and clandestine, the better it feels when done. This theory explains to some extent why people have extra-marital affairs, it is that clandestine factor that makes it all the more coveted and hot. This also explains why India ranks second in terms of population even with a culture of muted sexual desires. This theory goes beyond sex, extending to almost everything that is forbidden by society. The forbidden is a massive source of pleasure, no matter what, because even when one is part of the chorus of society, rebellion against the same society that one belongs to is enthralling, to say the least. Revolutions on any scale are the greatest form of validation a human can enjoy. Although having sex is not a revolution per se, but doing it, at the end of the day, after not even hinting at the presence of one’s sexuality or sensuality throughout the day, does have a massive sense of breaking free and disobeying our own sense of immorality. Sadly, the diktat is dying out with the emergence of Generation Y. And although this brings in a different set of pleasures to consume (in varied manners too), it will be regretful, at least for me, not to taste the pleasure that came out of the weird furtiveness our previous generations displayed.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The (Un)faithfuls</title>
      <link href="/The-Unfaithfuls" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The (Un)faithfuls" />
      <published>2019-04-10T11:30:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-10T11:30:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Unfaithfuls</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Unfaithfuls">&lt;p&gt;I recently had a breakdown of sorts, and the stifling confines of my room
tightened its shadows on me, as I desperately tried to get out of that place.
But where would I have gone? I certainly had no means to a Tesla or the unending
country roads to hit like BoJack Horseman, so I ended up quietly muffling my
screams in my pillow. And while I was grappling with desperation to end my life,
my eyes met God’s. Before I venture any further with the narrative, I must tell
you that I am the son of a devout Hindu, so it is quite natural for the walls of
my room to be installed not with posters of cool bands and stuff but with
posters of cool swagger Gods. My mother, who I dearly adore, has tried her fair
share and beyond to turn me into a devout as herself, but has not fared so well
yet. The least I could do was not frustrate her attempt at installing Durga’s (a
Hindu Warrior Goddess) poster in the most visible spot in my room. Initially,
her belief was that it would aid me to gradually turn into a god-fearing inmate
as herself, but now she has given up all hopes on me and doesn’t care as long as
I do no harm to her or society in general―especially by spreading or committing
blasphemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, when my eyes met God’s, I felt the excruciating urge to ask for her
help–putting myself in another struggle with my rational self–which clearly has
not yet accredited any credibility to the existence of any such deity and
considers it a sham. There, in the midst of this struggle, both my selves
settled on a critical question: why is faith important if it is a scam? To
answer this, I had to first address the victims of atheism: the millennial or
Generation Y. As evidenced by memes, a more than qualified instrument to gauge
the collective mindset of the globalised culture of the millennial, we are all
pseudo-nihilists and pseudo-existentialists with no particular belief system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This culture of disbelief is a stark characteristic of this generation and is so
as a consequence of science, which has with all its enigma deinstitutionalised
the notion of religion or anything that it entails. Now, what I have to ask here
is, if it has deinstitutionalised the institutions of faith, what does it
provide us in return? What does it offer us to cling on to when we are at our
worst? Does it offer itself us a replacement or does it offer the idea that we
are apex beings and nothing is higher than us? Now, although I am not in denial
of science’s contributions towards human society, what my problem is that
science is at the end of the day esoteric, exclusive. It is not everyone’s club
to join, and so the multitude with all its disillusionment is without a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science has taught us that we exist for no purpose and our existence is more of
a chance happening than something in the blueprint of a god. Science has since
its birth marshalled forward to perish existing belief systems, appropriating
the office of the apex belief system to itself. No wonder why such extreme
efforts are made for space expeditions, it is because science has run out of
things to unravel; science has run out of purpose as well but is simply
continuing with the faith in its purpose of serving mankind in ways greater than
itself. Ironically enough, while science has robbed us of the notion of faith
and belief and has left us naked to the vile truth of the universe, it has
itself nestled in the belief of something greater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we understand the importance of faith or communal belief systems. I am not
a student of theology so pardon my ill-service towards what I am going to say,
but, in my belief, communions or religions have existed since societies were
conceived for a very real reason. A society just like any organisation is
unmanageable without a fixed set of rules and morality that everyone who is a
part of such has to adhere to. This fixed set of rules and conduct of morality
has with time festered into unquestionable beliefs called religions. Now, where
religions came in handy back in the day was that they gave men a sense of
purpose. And, as is evident, man needs a purpose to go on in life. The piety
towards those set of rules existed because men believed that we exist for a
purpose and by following those rules we would have served that purpose and at
last be in the hands of Nirvana or whatever it is called around the world. I am
not at all bailing religion out of the many evils it has committed, but what
good it has reaped has to be stated. Religion’s greatest victory was that it
took the human psyche into consideration, unlike science, and pandered to our
greatest need, the need for validation. Now, this might seem like a coarse
conclusion, but this is what it is. Human species, in general, has the vehement
need to be validated, of our deeds in particular and existence in general. It is
this need for validation that gave birth to the question of “What is the purpose
of life?” And that is where many irrational beliefs of religion come into aid.
Reason gives us the validation we require in life and also places us in the
hands of faith which can get us through our most devastating times—giving us
meaning and purpose throughout all of it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, it may seem like I am antagonising science and making religion the
protagonist, but that is not the case. I am simply defending the case of
religion where it is due: it has given men a purpose and a belief in the fallacy
that there is something higher than us who is watching over us in our thinnest
of times. Some might argue here that it is better to be out of the shackles of
religion and feel liberated at being able to create our own purpose as Nietzsche
proposed, I argue otherwise.  What Nietzsche has proposed doesn’t apply to the
multitude; the multitude isn’t capable enough to create their own purpose in
life and requires a master to guide them. Imagine a herd of sheep bound by
fences - they stay in it, they work in it, and one day, a novel sheep kills the
master and breaks the fence and opens the sheep to an unending expanse. Although
at first, the change might enthral them, slowly they’d start feeling lost and
purposeless, because now they do not serve anything or anyone and are simply
roaming free. After a while, they scamper in insanity to find a purpose, but due
to their limited intelligence and faculties, they fall short. It goes fairly
Orwellian from there, the sheep, tired of such liberty again hands themselves
over to a new master, and that master in our case is science. Although science
has done great services to the society and we have enjoyed such for a long time,
we now have come to a standstill where nothing makes sense anymore and our
existence is boiled down to absurdity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, although religion has propagated many evils, it has time and again given men
purpose and a much needed coping mechanism to deal with their problems. And now
that we are disillusioned and hopeless, it might not do us much harm to commit
the psychological suicide that Albert Camus proposed, because unlike those
thinkers, we are a herd of simpletons with limited faculties. But that is not
possible at this stage, so I guess we are simply doomed with depression. All we
can simply do is stall our time by looking at memes.  &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I recently had a breakdown of sorts, and the stifling confines of my room tightened its shadows on me, as I desperately tried to get out of that place. But where would I have gone? I certainly had no means to a Tesla or the unending country roads to hit like BoJack Horseman, so I ended up quietly muffling my screams in my pillow. And while I was grappling with desperation to end my life, my eyes met God’s. Before I venture any further with the narrative, I must tell you that I am the son of a devout Hindu, so it is quite natural for the walls of my room to be installed not with posters of cool bands and stuff but with posters of cool swagger Gods. My mother, who I dearly adore, has tried her fair share and beyond to turn me into a devout as herself, but has not fared so well yet. The least I could do was not frustrate her attempt at installing Durga’s (a Hindu Warrior Goddess) poster in the most visible spot in my room. Initially, her belief was that it would aid me to gradually turn into a god-fearing inmate as herself, but now she has given up all hopes on me and doesn’t care as long as I do no harm to her or society in general―especially by spreading or committing blasphemies. Now, when my eyes met God’s, I felt the excruciating urge to ask for her help–putting myself in another struggle with my rational self–which clearly has not yet accredited any credibility to the existence of any such deity and considers it a sham. There, in the midst of this struggle, both my selves settled on a critical question: why is faith important if it is a scam? To answer this, I had to first address the victims of atheism: the millennial or Generation Y. As evidenced by memes, a more than qualified instrument to gauge the collective mindset of the globalised culture of the millennial, we are all pseudo-nihilists and pseudo-existentialists with no particular belief system. This culture of disbelief is a stark characteristic of this generation and is so as a consequence of science, which has with all its enigma deinstitutionalised the notion of religion or anything that it entails. Now, what I have to ask here is, if it has deinstitutionalised the institutions of faith, what does it provide us in return? What does it offer us to cling on to when we are at our worst? Does it offer itself us a replacement or does it offer the idea that we are apex beings and nothing is higher than us? Now, although I am not in denial of science’s contributions towards human society, what my problem is that science is at the end of the day esoteric, exclusive. It is not everyone’s club to join, and so the multitude with all its disillusionment is without a purpose. Science has taught us that we exist for no purpose and our existence is more of a chance happening than something in the blueprint of a god. Science has since its birth marshalled forward to perish existing belief systems, appropriating the office of the apex belief system to itself. No wonder why such extreme efforts are made for space expeditions, it is because science has run out of things to unravel; science has run out of purpose as well but is simply continuing with the faith in its purpose of serving mankind in ways greater than itself. Ironically enough, while science has robbed us of the notion of faith and belief and has left us naked to the vile truth of the universe, it has itself nestled in the belief of something greater. Here we understand the importance of faith or communal belief systems. I am not a student of theology so pardon my ill-service towards what I am going to say, but, in my belief, communions or religions have existed since societies were conceived for a very real reason. A society just like any organisation is unmanageable without a fixed set of rules and morality that everyone who is a part of such has to adhere to. This fixed set of rules and conduct of morality has with time festered into unquestionable beliefs called religions. Now, where religions came in handy back in the day was that they gave men a sense of purpose. And, as is evident, man needs a purpose to go on in life. The piety towards those set of rules existed because men believed that we exist for a purpose and by following those rules we would have served that purpose and at last be in the hands of Nirvana or whatever it is called around the world. I am not at all bailing religion out of the many evils it has committed, but what good it has reaped has to be stated. Religion’s greatest victory was that it took the human psyche into consideration, unlike science, and pandered to our greatest need, the need for validation. Now, this might seem like a coarse conclusion, but this is what it is. Human species, in general, has the vehement need to be validated, of our deeds in particular and existence in general. It is this need for validation that gave birth to the question of “What is the purpose of life?” And that is where many irrational beliefs of religion come into aid. Reason gives us the validation we require in life and also places us in the hands of faith which can get us through our most devastating times—giving us meaning and purpose throughout all of it.   Now, it may seem like I am antagonising science and making religion the protagonist, but that is not the case. I am simply defending the case of religion where it is due: it has given men a purpose and a belief in the fallacy that there is something higher than us who is watching over us in our thinnest of times. Some might argue here that it is better to be out of the shackles of religion and feel liberated at being able to create our own purpose as Nietzsche proposed, I argue otherwise.  What Nietzsche has proposed doesn’t apply to the multitude; the multitude isn’t capable enough to create their own purpose in life and requires a master to guide them. Imagine a herd of sheep bound by fences - they stay in it, they work in it, and one day, a novel sheep kills the master and breaks the fence and opens the sheep to an unending expanse. Although at first, the change might enthral them, slowly they’d start feeling lost and purposeless, because now they do not serve anything or anyone and are simply roaming free. After a while, they scamper in insanity to find a purpose, but due to their limited intelligence and faculties, they fall short. It goes fairly Orwellian from there, the sheep, tired of such liberty again hands themselves over to a new master, and that master in our case is science. Although science has done great services to the society and we have enjoyed such for a long time, we now have come to a standstill where nothing makes sense anymore and our existence is boiled down to absurdity. So, although religion has propagated many evils, it has time and again given men purpose and a much needed coping mechanism to deal with their problems. And now that we are disillusioned and hopeless, it might not do us much harm to commit the psychological suicide that Albert Camus proposed, because unlike those thinkers, we are a herd of simpletons with limited faculties. But that is not possible at this stage, so I guess we are simply doomed with depression. All we can simply do is stall our time by looking at memes.  </summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Hard Reality of Hardcopies</title>
      <link href="/The-Hard-Reality-on-Hardcopies" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Hard Reality of Hardcopies" />
      <published>2019-03-07T03:15:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-07T03:15:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Hard-Reality-on-Hardcopies</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Hard-Reality-on-Hardcopies">&lt;p&gt;Spring, which has almost become non-existential in Calcutta, is a much revered
and coveted time of the year for any of us living in the tropical zone,
especially when it precedes a season of pig-like sweating. The breezy streets
are a delight to the souls dampened by the winter, and a walk through those
streets with an old friend hits just the right note on the Spring Symphony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An old friend and I have shared a long, uneven but all the more enjoyable
friendship over the years, and our unending love for books has still, with old,
straining strings, held our friendship. Here, I must mention, with much
gratitude, that she was the person to introduce me to the vast, unending, and
marvellous land of books, lending me the first book I ever read by Sidney
Sheldon. When I raised my reservations about the unappealing demeanour of a
book, she just asked me to read for only thirty minutes every day before sleep,
and stated that if after a week I still found it ‘uninteresting’, I could drop
it and return it to her, with her promising to never again insist that I read a
book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprise! Surprise! I finished the book within a week, returned it to her, told
her I finished it and was prized with a look of priceless shock from her. I am
not such an active reader anymore, but what occurred to me then was how
immensely romantic holding the spine of a book is; and of the many sins that our
education system and technology has caused, one is causing a holocaust on the
romance of holding a book. Needless to say, books, since then, became an
inseparable part of my regime and my birthday gifts. But I must confess, after
my first read, I was still sceptical whether this enchantment I felt was
ephemeral or actually enduring. It persisted. Even though initially, I raised
doubts about the ‘unappealing’ demeanour of a book, it was that which drove me
most to the habit of reading books: the mellow chirps of the pages, the letters
marching on the beige field, the weaving and unravelling of tales, and the
hundreds of lives coming to life on those very seemingly lifeless pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, coming back to the spring evening of breezy streets: it was an occasion of
me returning my friend her long-given books, and as we were merrily discussing
things of grave concern to us, something graver ambushed us – what is the future
of hardcopies? I have always been troubled by the growing popularity of ebooks,
but it did not hit harder than when I heard her saying that she has to do her
college’s research work from an ebook. The general argument here would be that
an ebook offers almost everything that a book does, but god forbid the day when
writers romanticise reading an ebook by the window on a rainy day in their
novels or their Instagram posts per se. Leaving aside the romantic values, how
would an ebook ever satiate the bourgeois need of the book-hoarding class? Who
do you think would be impressed by your listless list of books on your device,
instead of the piles of webbed and tattered books with missing pages and
crumpled edges? How can looking up from your well-lit Kindle be the same as a
distracted stare into the distance as Tolstoy drones on in a thick copy of &lt;em&gt;War
and Peace&lt;/em&gt;? What would be more charming, lending book by just a few taps, or
rummaging through the hundreds of dust sprinkled books, whilst being cast under
the perverse magic of nostalgia?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a not so recent finding in 2017, it was published that the United States of
America recorded a greater sale of ebooks compared to hardcopies. I became
fairly unstable after reading this and looked with greater awe than ever at my
meagre collection of whatever hardcopies I possess. I, too, am guilty of
possessing ebooks. Of course, I am not all against ebooks (this article is being
published online, after all), it does provide many the opportunity to read
things that otherwise would be inaccessible to them and it certainly is a great
aid when travelling. Although the emergence of ebooks feels like a personal
defeat to me, I concede to the importance of ebooks in times of such great
distress to nature and society. And in fear that I might be misconstrued as a
privileged brat, let me tell you, I buy books using fees earned from part-time
teaching, which most assuredly isn’t much. Yet, still, for me, books and their
essence lies in their old-school charm that keeps us turning actual pages.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrei Tarkovsky once said that artists are there because the world is not
perfect, and such imperfection is reminded to us by those hardcopies that seem
frayed and old and decaying just like our world. The ebook is too perfect a
vessel for works that are born out of imperfection. It swerves us into a path
away from nature, away from reality into a dark realm of complete machine
dominance. In the end, maybe I am simply a hopeless romantic stuck in the past
when the world is aggressively progressing into the future, but I hope my voice
of unreason reaches a few romantic hearts so that we can keep the lineage of
hardcopies from dying a most ignominious and unromantic death.  &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Spring, which has almost become non-existential in Calcutta, is a much revered and coveted time of the year for any of us living in the tropical zone, especially when it precedes a season of pig-like sweating. The breezy streets are a delight to the souls dampened by the winter, and a walk through those streets with an old friend hits just the right note on the Spring Symphony. An old friend and I have shared a long, uneven but all the more enjoyable friendship over the years, and our unending love for books has still, with old, straining strings, held our friendship. Here, I must mention, with much gratitude, that she was the person to introduce me to the vast, unending, and marvellous land of books, lending me the first book I ever read by Sidney Sheldon. When I raised my reservations about the unappealing demeanour of a book, she just asked me to read for only thirty minutes every day before sleep, and stated that if after a week I still found it ‘uninteresting’, I could drop it and return it to her, with her promising to never again insist that I read a book. Surprise! Surprise! I finished the book within a week, returned it to her, told her I finished it and was prized with a look of priceless shock from her. I am not such an active reader anymore, but what occurred to me then was how immensely romantic holding the spine of a book is; and of the many sins that our education system and technology has caused, one is causing a holocaust on the romance of holding a book. Needless to say, books, since then, became an inseparable part of my regime and my birthday gifts. But I must confess, after my first read, I was still sceptical whether this enchantment I felt was ephemeral or actually enduring. It persisted. Even though initially, I raised doubts about the ‘unappealing’ demeanour of a book, it was that which drove me most to the habit of reading books: the mellow chirps of the pages, the letters marching on the beige field, the weaving and unravelling of tales, and the hundreds of lives coming to life on those very seemingly lifeless pages. Now, coming back to the spring evening of breezy streets: it was an occasion of me returning my friend her long-given books, and as we were merrily discussing things of grave concern to us, something graver ambushed us – what is the future of hardcopies? I have always been troubled by the growing popularity of ebooks, but it did not hit harder than when I heard her saying that she has to do her college’s research work from an ebook. The general argument here would be that an ebook offers almost everything that a book does, but god forbid the day when writers romanticise reading an ebook by the window on a rainy day in their novels or their Instagram posts per se. Leaving aside the romantic values, how would an ebook ever satiate the bourgeois need of the book-hoarding class? Who do you think would be impressed by your listless list of books on your device, instead of the piles of webbed and tattered books with missing pages and crumpled edges? How can looking up from your well-lit Kindle be the same as a distracted stare into the distance as Tolstoy drones on in a thick copy of War and Peace? What would be more charming, lending book by just a few taps, or rummaging through the hundreds of dust sprinkled books, whilst being cast under the perverse magic of nostalgia? In a not so recent finding in 2017, it was published that the United States of America recorded a greater sale of ebooks compared to hardcopies. I became fairly unstable after reading this and looked with greater awe than ever at my meagre collection of whatever hardcopies I possess. I, too, am guilty of possessing ebooks. Of course, I am not all against ebooks (this article is being published online, after all), it does provide many the opportunity to read things that otherwise would be inaccessible to them and it certainly is a great aid when travelling. Although the emergence of ebooks feels like a personal defeat to me, I concede to the importance of ebooks in times of such great distress to nature and society. And in fear that I might be misconstrued as a privileged brat, let me tell you, I buy books using fees earned from part-time teaching, which most assuredly isn’t much. Yet, still, for me, books and their essence lies in their old-school charm that keeps us turning actual pages.   Andrei Tarkovsky once said that artists are there because the world is not perfect, and such imperfection is reminded to us by those hardcopies that seem frayed and old and decaying just like our world. The ebook is too perfect a vessel for works that are born out of imperfection. It swerves us into a path away from nature, away from reality into a dark realm of complete machine dominance. In the end, maybe I am simply a hopeless romantic stuck in the past when the world is aggressively progressing into the future, but I hope my voice of unreason reaches a few romantic hearts so that we can keep the lineage of hardcopies from dying a most ignominious and unromantic death.  </summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">2001: A Metaphysical Odyssey</title>
      <link href="/2001-A-Metaphysical-Odyssey" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2001: A Metaphysical Odyssey" />
      <published>2019-02-07T02:33:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T02:33:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/2001-A-Metaphysical-Odyssey</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/2001-A-Metaphysical-Odyssey">&lt;p&gt;Stanley Kubrick has produced phenomenal works throughout his career. His relentless, unflinching approach to the subjects he chose certainly showed in his films and we cannot be thankful enough for his contribution to the art of filmmaking. That said, any further discourse on how great a filmmaker he was seems pointless to me as it has already been addressed umpteen times by several, far more accomplished personas at greater lengths. What I would prefer to bring under the microscope today is his magnum opus &lt;em&gt;2001: A Space Odyssey&lt;/em&gt; and what lay at its heart. The film, which has now been minced to mere GIFs and iconic ringtones, was presumably his life’s most important and ambitious work, although I have no grounds to claim so. He started to work on &lt;em&gt;2001&lt;/em&gt; in 1964 after his overture to Arthur C. Clarke, who co-wrote the script for the film and authored a book of the same name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2001&lt;/em&gt; opens with a black screen and eerie music, giving a sense of void with all its horror. From the very beginning, Kubrick made sure he doesn’t send the wrong signal about this odyssey being just any sci-fi. This void was then succeeded by a scene of the camera rising up to behold the sun from beyond the edges of the moon and the Earth to the tune of Richard Strauss’ &lt;em&gt;Thus Spake Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt;. Now, this is where things get real. The use of &lt;em&gt;Thus Spake Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt; was no mere coincidence, and it should not be with someone as seminal as Kubrick. The extraordinary work by Friedrich Nietzsche at the dusk of his life was indeed the prime theme of the entire project, which Kubrick concurred to later on. And as for the scene in question, it was clearly the beckoning of the new morning that Nietzsche suggested in the book when he said, &lt;i&gt;“The noon when man stands the middle of his way between beast and Superman… a way to a new morning.”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film primarily addresses three important themes: The Superman, Evolution and the Dionysian and Apollonian.
Now, if you’re familiar with these concepts you can avoid this paragraph and move on to the next, and if not I will walk you through them briefly. The Superman is a term coined not by DC comics but by Friedrich Nietzsche in his &lt;em&gt;Thus Spake Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt;. In it, he points out that it is not right for us to assume that evolution has ended. He argued that we are currently in the middle of our evolution, that we are the bridge between the hominids and the far superior Superman. Nietzsche declares in his book: &lt;i&gt;“What is ape to man? A laughing stock or a painful embarrassment. And man shall be that to the Superman: a laughing stock and painful embarrassment.”&lt;/i&gt; Nietzsche says his future Supermen would have their own values, being independently-minded, and forging their own path. These Supermen will accept the fact that they might need to hurt people for the sake of great things, that selfishness isn’t a vice but a necessity. They won’t despise the success of others and will accept suffering as a means to good things. They will also bear the cross of loneliness as a price for their hard nature. They will be gentle towards the weak because of their consciousness of their own strength and will exult at their capabilities. The other Nietzschean concepts, the Dionysian and Apollonian, are paradigms of human nature. The Dionysian engages in revelry, wine, and dance, in chaos and irrationality, he is instinctive and emotional; the Apollonian, on the other hand, is cultured, intellectual, engaging with logic and rationality, and wise and controlled. Finally there is evolution: while it is clear that our ancestors were Dionysian and we have evolved to be Apollonian, according to Nietzsche, we would further evolve to find the sublime balance between these two ideologies to forge our own paths.
Kubrick held Nietzsche in high regard and took dear to his views almost devoutly. He too believed that we are not at the end of evolution and must march forward to acquire greater psychological abilities. And even though many have foreseen machinery to be the biggest possible threat to humanity, Kubrick believed there’s nothing that our species cannot conquer given our superior psychological faculty, be it the leopards that once ambushed and attacked the apes or be it an artificially intelligent computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film starts at the dawn of mankind, when the ape-men amid their daily struggles to survive  and maintain their territory,  witnessed the first of four monoliths that supposedly changed the course of their lives. It bestowed them with the idea of using bones as weapons— this is Kubrick subtly asserting that violence underpins basic human nature. The second monolith is unearthed in the Moon, suggesting that humans are ready for their advent toward the next stage of evolution, to acquire the next level of intelligence. And thus the journey begins; the quiet and long journey which Kubrick infallibly filmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, the audience felt the tediousness of the journey. This is also the part where we come across the iconic Hal 9000 which till date is a big reference in pop culture. This artificially intelligent computer was given to monitor and supervise the journey but it all changed when it started making a few mistakes stoking doubts in the minds of the two other passengers – Dave and Frank - about its reliability. What follows is an epochal scene where Dave and Frank discuss in private in a pod bay about their plans to disconnect Hal which Hal oversees through the glass door of the pod bay. Dave first shows the signs of a Superman when he lets go of Frank to enter the spaceship himself without a moment’s trepidation. He sacrificed his colleague for the greater cause. When Dave struggled his way into the spaceship, he without delay hurried to disconnect Hal despite the constant pleadings from Hal, who tried to convince Dave into not disconnecting him.  Later, whilst he was disconnecting Hal, there was a moment when Dave took dear to Hal’s pleas and responded in kindness, knowing Hal’s final moments were soon approaching. Dave was gentle towards the weak Hal, even if he was ‘killing’ him, being aware of his own superiority. Dave personified independency of mind, being willing to act on his own accord even though he remained alone in the entire spaceship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, in the neoclassical room we see Dave, ageing and perishing in front of our eyes, approaching his final moments at the bridge, taking the next and final step towards evolution when he extends his hand toward the fourth monolith like Adam did in the painting, &lt;em&gt;Creation of Adam&lt;/em&gt; by Michelangelo. Nietzsche, through his character Zarathustra, says in his magnum opus, &lt;i&gt;“I love him who willeth the creation of something beyond himself and then perisheth.”&lt;/i&gt; Dave gives in to something greater than himself, he is the Star child on his deathbed. &lt;em&gt;Space Odyssey&lt;/em&gt; is about going beyond good and evil, it is Kubrick’s take on how we must evolve and embrace the Superman within in a future that may not be so far away.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Stanley Kubrick has produced phenomenal works throughout his career. His relentless, unflinching approach to the subjects he chose certainly showed in his films and we cannot be thankful enough for his contribution to the art of filmmaking. That said, any further discourse on how great a filmmaker he was seems pointless to me as it has already been addressed umpteen times by several, far more accomplished personas at greater lengths. What I would prefer to bring under the microscope today is his magnum opus 2001: A Space Odyssey and what lay at its heart. The film, which has now been minced to mere GIFs and iconic ringtones, was presumably his life’s most important and ambitious work, although I have no grounds to claim so. He started to work on 2001 in 1964 after his overture to Arthur C. Clarke, who co-wrote the script for the film and authored a book of the same name.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
