<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/trending/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-10-06T18:49:45+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/trending/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Be a Man: a Discourse on 21st Century Masculinity</title>
      <link href="/Be-a-Man" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Be a Man: a Discourse on 21st Century Masculinity" />
      <published>2019-03-14T01:45:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-14T01:45:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Be-a-Man</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Be-a-Man">&lt;p&gt;The Gillette Advert has, for reasons I do not fully understand, caused a
sensation. There are people who are praising it for sending out the right
message on toxic masculinity, and there are people condemning it vociferously
for portraying masculinity as inherently evil. The fact, however, is that an
advert really matters little—they are ultimately paid promotions of products,
not vehicles of social change, and the people who are quick to heap praise or
criticism on it (especially in this case) are either pretentious or simply
b*tthurt. Yet, even in what I consider to be an overreaction about a simple
advert on shaving products, there’s a deeper discussion that is going on. For
more than a couple of thousand years, men across the world have been told that
they are stronger, better and smarter; it has been their job to be responsible
for ‘their’ women and ‘their’ children; it has been their duty to die first in
battle and it has been their job to take charge without shedding a tear and
without ever doubting oneself. But now, in these feminist times, assumptions
about masculinity are not only being challenged but also being designated as
evil—and for a good reason. But with all of this change, masculinity is being
radically redefined. The question is &lt;em&gt;what should it be redefined into?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One has to appreciate the difficulty of this question to even begin to answer
it. There are so many issues, from the plain-fact biological to the unwittingly
socio-cultural, that one does not know what to address first. This means all
thoughts about what masculinity ought to be cannot be discussed in the abstract, for we
simply do not know what the source of masculinity as a social or perhaps natural
construct really is. All we can try to do is pragmatically accept its existence
and move on to see how we can mould it to suit our times—in both a moral and
philosophical sense. And that again reinforces the fact that instead of some
grand theory of what it &lt;em&gt;must mean to be a man&lt;/em&gt;, we must develop more specific
guidelines on what it &lt;em&gt;should mean to be a man&lt;/em&gt;.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fairly good place to begin would be in the surprisingly simple but
controversial question of who should pay for a date between heterosexual
couples. One can easily see why “old-world masculinity” would always make the
man pay: Men were supposed to have the financial resources which they would use
to ‘woo’ women. With women possessing little financial independence (or any
independence, really), and depending on men for nearly everything material, men
paying for dates made sense—even if it was due to unjust laws and the fantasies
of the patriarchy with regard to its own benevolence. But all of that has
changed now and women are (at least on paper) not denied basic rights like the
one to property, a voice and to work. So, the idea that men should have an
obligation to pay for food and alcohol as a projection of their ability to give
a damn when seeing someone seems morally bankrupt, not to mention unfair as
well. Yet, a change of the rules to equal sharing seems ham-handed. It does not
take into account that sometimes people are feeling rich or bound to old-school
values for no discernible reason. More importantly, it simply denies agency to
people, instead of letting them negotiate it with each other. A better kind of
masculinity that truly involves an end to male presumptions of power and
responsibility cannot simply say: &lt;em&gt;Thou shalt split the bill for thou art equal&lt;/em&gt;.
That is only a sign of compromising pride; it is a technical solution to a
psychological problem. The rules on dating must be an expression of true
cooperation, and they can only begin to be so when people recognise that
independent, equal individuals decide matters among themselves. To say that
people must split the bill all the time is to mould a masculinity that need not
actually listen or cooperate, for it feels that there is a simple rule in place.
But to say: there are no rules, you must exercise self-respect and empathy when
negotiating who pays, re-enforces a most important aspect of what modern
masculinity should be. It symbolises an attempt to outgrow the need for the
patriarchy itself as a balm to one’s self-esteem. A contextualised, no
overarching rules approach encourages real interaction, it forces both men and
women to actually ask the question of what is fair when two people, equal in
dignity, decide to strike a settlement for mutual benefit.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masculinity is undeniably linked to &lt;em&gt;how good men feel about themselves&lt;/em&gt;. I don’t
know if there is something biological to it or if it is purely cultural, but the
male to female ratio of suicides is proof to me that men not feeling good about
themselves has some serious consequences. Many people identify the root of this
problem to be toxic masculinity, but that only addresses the surface of the
issue. Of course, a man being forced to bottle all emotion save aggression is
bound to be attracted to suicide in the face of life’s sh*t. But conversely,
without a feeling of independence and strength in the face of one’s fears,
they’re not bound to feel very good about themselves either. The old patriarchal
notion of masculinity is not entirely wrong in wanting men to weather things
stoically. It is simply important for both men and women to try and take control
of their lives when in crisis, rather than near-constantly crying about it. The
only thing a new masculinity needs to do is stop emasculating an expression of
emotion, whilst certainly rewarding personal fortitude and the ability to
skilfully (and quietly) manage one’s misery. Without this positive change,
masculinity risks either being dependent on the fragile male ego of being ‘hard’
or being a source of emotional release that does not provide courage. This new
notion of male self-belief tells us that boys should cry, that they should not
be unwilling to admit to sadness and dejection. However, it cautions us that
crying should not replace men’s self-worth by perpetuating avoidance and
self-doubt. In other words, modern masculinity must give men a better way to
cry: it must tell them they must be “man enough” to be able to do so, and “man
enough” to be able to overcome the urge to only do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the crying bit set aside, the more difficult questions put forward by the
&lt;em&gt;#metoo&lt;/em&gt; movement need to be addressed. It is clear that old-world masculinity
has either failed to deal with an oppressive culture in the workplace or in
enforcing rules of consent. The problem is obvious: the patriarchy does make
women objects. But that misses the forest for the trees, for it does not ask the
difficult question of &lt;em&gt;why society decided to have the patriarchy in the first
place&lt;/em&gt;. I would contend the answer to that question is tantalisingly simple. As
Devdutt Pattanaik, a popular Indian mythologist contends, human beings have “the
patriarchy” verily because nature doesn’t consider males to be that important.
In nature, all that a whole pride of lionesses requires is one (perhaps two)
male lions to produce the next generation of cubs. Human society is entirely
different, even if it has polygamy or polyandry, it tries to value every virile
male as a prospective husband or partner for his ability to care for and produce
human offspring. Practically speaking, this translates into the notion of the
patriarchy, where a literal race for being an alpha male is replaced with the
notion that every male who can find a female(s) has rights and obligations in
relation to that female—which other males are restricted from having. This
creates some kind of social order, but it makes men, whether fathers, brothers,
husbands or lovers, believe that they can (and must) control what happens to the
females associated with them. And this leads to the inevitable manifestation of
the patriarchy that the #metoo movement has so clearly exposed. Men will (if
they choose) assert what they consider “sexual rights” over the women who are
associated with them because they believe their association with them, whether
at the workplace or inside a marriage, gives them that right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cultural paradigm so described is the source of all problems discussed in
the previous paragraphs, it is this fundamental insecurity of not being an alpha
male that leads to men wanting to own, protect and control the women they have
around them. They have to do so, there must be rules that enforce so, otherwise
all of us ‘inadequate’ men will be naturally selected out. We must ensure “our
property” understands who they belong to, whether it be through non-disclosure
agreements or entertaining our putrid pick-up lines at the workplace. One can
combat the patriarchy as a construct, but that hardly addresses the fragile male
ego that underpins this socio-cultural construct. To combat that, men need to be
told that their honour and their power doesn’t reside in their control of the
women around them. Men need to be reminded that it is okay if they feel
inadequate, that they must never seek subjugation of women (or anyone) as a
therapy for low self-esteem and an absurd “will to power”. How does one
crystallise that abstract notion in a practical context? Simple: to quote a
friend, we must remind men that &lt;em&gt;“life is an embarrassment, and we’re going to
die anyway”&lt;/em&gt;. So, if we find ourselves being unable to get the women we want, it
really matters little. The fundamental mortality and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Understanding-the-Absurdity-of-Life&quot;&gt;absurdity of life&lt;/a&gt; mean that
our need to define our self-worth through our power over women (or anything) is
futile—for we’re already inadequate, to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, that is the existential reality that stares at us men every time we
discuss what it means to be a man. We men already realise, deep down, that we
are pathetically inadequate. If we weren’t, we wouldn’t have to construct so
many fallacies to make ourselves feel better, whether they be rules that project
our wealth, rules on not crying, or rules that state: “boys will be boys”.
My conception of masculinity expresses a core desire to do away with all those
stupid rules that are completely unfit for a most egalitarian age. A new kind of
masculinity must rely on fostering an inner strength that lets men outgrow our
base fears. Self-esteem, in any moral or philosophical sense, cannot come from
the outside; it cannot come from protecting or subjugating others. Self-esteem
or the belief in oneself must be exuded, it must be a source of impregnable
strength from within. A modern definition of masculinity must reflect this deep
truth, it must seek to give men the ability to outgrow their weaknesses (and,
therefore, the patriarchy) and to embrace a more complete personality that is a
result of true internal self-belief.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      
        <category term="trending" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Gillette Advert has, for reasons I do not fully understand, caused a sensation. There are people who are praising it for sending out the right message on toxic masculinity, and there are people condemning it vociferously for portraying masculinity as inherently evil. The fact, however, is that an advert really matters little—they are ultimately paid promotions of products, not vehicles of social change, and the people who are quick to heap praise or criticism on it (especially in this case) are either pretentious or simply b*tthurt. Yet, even in what I consider to be an overreaction about a simple advert on shaving products, there’s a deeper discussion that is going on. For more than a couple of thousand years, men across the world have been told that they are stronger, better and smarter; it has been their job to be responsible for ‘their’ women and ‘their’ children; it has been their duty to die first in battle and it has been their job to take charge without shedding a tear and without ever doubting oneself. But now, in these feminist times, assumptions about masculinity are not only being challenged but also being designated as evil—and for a good reason. But with all of this change, masculinity is being radically redefined. The question is what should it be redefined into? One has to appreciate the difficulty of this question to even begin to answer it. There are so many issues, from the plain-fact biological to the unwittingly socio-cultural, that one does not know what to address first. This means all thoughts about what masculinity ought to be cannot be discussed in the abstract, for we simply do not know what the source of masculinity as a social or perhaps natural construct really is. All we can try to do is pragmatically accept its existence and move on to see how we can mould it to suit our times—in both a moral and philosophical sense. And that again reinforces the fact that instead of some grand theory of what it must mean to be a man, we must develop more specific guidelines on what it should mean to be a man.    A fairly good place to begin would be in the surprisingly simple but controversial question of who should pay for a date between heterosexual couples. One can easily see why “old-world masculinity” would always make the man pay: Men were supposed to have the financial resources which they would use to ‘woo’ women. With women possessing little financial independence (or any independence, really), and depending on men for nearly everything material, men paying for dates made sense—even if it was due to unjust laws and the fantasies of the patriarchy with regard to its own benevolence. But all of that has changed now and women are (at least on paper) not denied basic rights like the one to property, a voice and to work. So, the idea that men should have an obligation to pay for food and alcohol as a projection of their ability to give a damn when seeing someone seems morally bankrupt, not to mention unfair as well. Yet, a change of the rules to equal sharing seems ham-handed. It does not take into account that sometimes people are feeling rich or bound to old-school values for no discernible reason. More importantly, it simply denies agency to people, instead of letting them negotiate it with each other. A better kind of masculinity that truly involves an end to male presumptions of power and responsibility cannot simply say: Thou shalt split the bill for thou art equal. That is only a sign of compromising pride; it is a technical solution to a psychological problem. The rules on dating must be an expression of true cooperation, and they can only begin to be so when people recognise that independent, equal individuals decide matters among themselves. To say that people must split the bill all the time is to mould a masculinity that need not actually listen or cooperate, for it feels that there is a simple rule in place. But to say: there are no rules, you must exercise self-respect and empathy when negotiating who pays, re-enforces a most important aspect of what modern masculinity should be. It symbolises an attempt to outgrow the need for the patriarchy itself as a balm to one’s self-esteem. A contextualised, no overarching rules approach encourages real interaction, it forces both men and women to actually ask the question of what is fair when two people, equal in dignity, decide to strike a settlement for mutual benefit.      Masculinity is undeniably linked to how good men feel about themselves. I don’t know if there is something biological to it or if it is purely cultural, but the male to female ratio of suicides is proof to me that men not feeling good about themselves has some serious consequences. Many people identify the root of this problem to be toxic masculinity, but that only addresses the surface of the issue. Of course, a man being forced to bottle all emotion save aggression is bound to be attracted to suicide in the face of life’s sh*t. But conversely, without a feeling of independence and strength in the face of one’s fears, they’re not bound to feel very good about themselves either. The old patriarchal notion of masculinity is not entirely wrong in wanting men to weather things stoically. It is simply important for both men and women to try and take control of their lives when in crisis, rather than near-constantly crying about it. The only thing a new masculinity needs to do is stop emasculating an expression of emotion, whilst certainly rewarding personal fortitude and the ability to skilfully (and quietly) manage one’s misery. Without this positive change, masculinity risks either being dependent on the fragile male ego of being ‘hard’ or being a source of emotional release that does not provide courage. This new notion of male self-belief tells us that boys should cry, that they should not be unwilling to admit to sadness and dejection. However, it cautions us that crying should not replace men’s self-worth by perpetuating avoidance and self-doubt. In other words, modern masculinity must give men a better way to cry: it must tell them they must be “man enough” to be able to do so, and “man enough” to be able to overcome the urge to only do so. With the crying bit set aside, the more difficult questions put forward by the #metoo movement need to be addressed. It is clear that old-world masculinity has either failed to deal with an oppressive culture in the workplace or in enforcing rules of consent. The problem is obvious: the patriarchy does make women objects. But that misses the forest for the trees, for it does not ask the difficult question of why society decided to have the patriarchy in the first place. I would contend the answer to that question is tantalisingly simple. As Devdutt Pattanaik, a popular Indian mythologist contends, human beings have “the patriarchy” verily because nature doesn’t consider males to be that important. In nature, all that a whole pride of lionesses requires is one (perhaps two) male lions to produce the next generation of cubs. Human society is entirely different, even if it has polygamy or polyandry, it tries to value every virile male as a prospective husband or partner for his ability to care for and produce human offspring. Practically speaking, this translates into the notion of the patriarchy, where a literal race for being an alpha male is replaced with the notion that every male who can find a female(s) has rights and obligations in relation to that female—which other males are restricted from having. This creates some kind of social order, but it makes men, whether fathers, brothers, husbands or lovers, believe that they can (and must) control what happens to the females associated with them. And this leads to the inevitable manifestation of the patriarchy that the #metoo movement has so clearly exposed. Men will (if they choose) assert what they consider “sexual rights” over the women who are associated with them because they believe their association with them, whether at the workplace or inside a marriage, gives them that right. The cultural paradigm so described is the source of all problems discussed in the previous paragraphs, it is this fundamental insecurity of not being an alpha male that leads to men wanting to own, protect and control the women they have around them. They have to do so, there must be rules that enforce so, otherwise all of us ‘inadequate’ men will be naturally selected out. We must ensure “our property” understands who they belong to, whether it be through non-disclosure agreements or entertaining our putrid pick-up lines at the workplace. One can combat the patriarchy as a construct, but that hardly addresses the fragile male ego that underpins this socio-cultural construct. To combat that, men need to be told that their honour and their power doesn’t reside in their control of the women around them. Men need to be reminded that it is okay if they feel inadequate, that they must never seek subjugation of women (or anyone) as a therapy for low self-esteem and an absurd “will to power”. How does one crystallise that abstract notion in a practical context? Simple: to quote a friend, we must remind men that “life is an embarrassment, and we’re going to die anyway”. So, if we find ourselves being unable to get the women we want, it really matters little. The fundamental mortality and absurdity of life mean that our need to define our self-worth through our power over women (or anything) is futile—for we’re already inadequate, to begin with. In fact, that is the existential reality that stares at us men every time we discuss what it means to be a man. We men already realise, deep down, that we are pathetically inadequate. If we weren’t, we wouldn’t have to construct so many fallacies to make ourselves feel better, whether they be rules that project our wealth, rules on not crying, or rules that state: “boys will be boys”. My conception of masculinity expresses a core desire to do away with all those stupid rules that are completely unfit for a most egalitarian age. A new kind of masculinity must rely on fostering an inner strength that lets men outgrow our base fears. Self-esteem, in any moral or philosophical sense, cannot come from the outside; it cannot come from protecting or subjugating others. Self-esteem or the belief in oneself must be exuded, it must be a source of impregnable strength from within. A modern definition of masculinity must reflect this deep truth, it must seek to give men the ability to outgrow their weaknesses (and, therefore, the patriarchy) and to embrace a more complete personality that is a result of true internal self-belief.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Venezuela: A Country Being Played?</title>
      <link href="/Venezuela-A-Country-Being-Played" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Venezuela: A Country Being Played?" />
      <published>2019-02-07T05:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T05:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Venezuela-A-Country-Being-Played</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Venezuela-A-Country-Being-Played">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/atreyi.bhaumik/&quot;&gt;In my previous articles&lt;/a&gt;, I have spoken about Latin America, its foundations, shortcomings, and how the past shall shape its future. Today, I talk about Venezuela, its decade-old story, its battle for survival and the turn of events. Fate does play cruel games with us at times, and Venezuela is a prime example of a country that has been played. From being one of the stronger economies of Latin America, Venezuela has seen a chronic downfall which would have been unimaginable only two decades ago. In the span of ten short years, everything has miraculously changed. Venezuela is now one of the most volatile countries in the world and is facing absolute poverty like no other country at the moment. This is a strange phenomenon, for the country is well endowed with oil reserves and is also one of the OPEC members. A scarcity of resources for a ‘petronation’ seems to be astounding. But poverty isn’t the worst of all that Venezuela faces. The law and order of the country is in shambles and despite having skilled labour, it has gone down the same road as Syria or Iraq (though there is no terror organization functioning just yet). When other countries are reaching milestones in the context of economic freedom, and political liberty, Venezuela is coping up with poverty and extreme cases of starvation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign support to the country, especially in monetary terms, is relatively minuscule. China has poured almost $60 billion into the country as foreign investment, and through trade. But now, even China is reluctant, and new money given to the nation doesn’t add up to significant amounts. The only country showing faith amongst all others is Russia. However, foreign support or not, the disaster that has been wrecked throughout Venezuela by the present regime of Nicolas Maduro is too great to really be helped at all. There is not even an ounce of doubt regarding the fact that, under Nicolas Maduro, power has been abused. And from healthcare to education, the country is struggling to keep afloat. People in huge numbers are suffering from diseases like malaria, measles and tuberculosis, with no medical help or any other proper facilities. Underinvestment and corruption have left the healthcare system in shambles. Starvation, poverty, corruption, and violence in the nation has led to the commoners fleeing to get away from an oppressive rule. In fact, statistics show that approximately three million people have fled the country since 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venezuela is one of the most astounding cases of economic mismanagement and too much concentration of power in the hands of the state. Venezuela’s people see no hope for the future, while their country sees prices double every month. The GDP has halved and the country’s pension scheme helps no one. Oil production has gone down to a meagre one million barrels a day, cutting off a huge proportion of revenue from the oil export business. In addition, the country is so deep in debt that people have lost the ability to hold their heads high. The middle class is highly irked and aggressively vocal about their feelings towards the dictator. And this has led to protests in most of the regions, especially due to the fact that they believe the elections were rigged. According to a survey report, about 80% of the population (32 million) does not recognise Mr Maduro as their supreme leader. But Maduro seems to be untouchable with the army at his disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slowly, the world is finally responding to the crisis along with Venezuela’s political opposition. Juan Guaido, the leader of the National Assembly has proclaimed to be the true leader of the nation. To show support and appreciation for Guaido, around one million men and women took to the streets. Their march was a demand for a proper democracy and greater rights for the innocent people who are paying the price for an unruly regime. Guaido too is playing on the same emotions of the people. He has stated that he wants to “rebuild” the country and bring back proper democracy. The path to removing Maduro, however, is a dangerous one. Many might even call it fruitless. The dictatorship has in the past responded to such opposition leaders with violence. However, Venezuelans believe that Guaido’s case is different from the rest because of the timing. The army, which has fiercely protected Maduro till now, is said to have lost interest, given they are not paid enough. Due to hyperinflation, the 36 thousand bolivars that they earn per month is almost next to nothing. The army demands and supports the side with money. If Maduro cannot keep them satisfied, then the situation might reverse in favour of Guaido and the people. Towards the end of January, Guaido released a statement saying that he has indeed talked to the army in order to make it switch sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various western countries have stood up in support of Guaido as the interim President till the elections are announced.  The United States has taken the matter to the United Nations and has called for military intervention. So now, instead of it being a Venezuelan matter, it is becoming an issue of global politics. Everyone is pitching in according to whom they favour more. The US and its allies have come down on Maduro. The US government has withheld payments for oil and has stated that they would pay only when the legitimate leader, Guaido, comes into power. Economic sanctions imposed on the country have made Venezuela even poorer, and the lack of money has facilitated a sharper drop in the production of crude oil. The oil industry of Venezuela could collapse any day now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the main game, under such circumstances remains between the US, Russia, and China. It seems like this is a desperate move by the US to regain control in Latin America, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/China-in-Latin-America&quot;&gt;where Chinese presence has grown by leaps and bounds over half a decade&lt;/a&gt;. As for Russia, a military intervention in Venezuela would show (to put it bluntly) the finger to the US just like in Crimea. But the real question is, does military intervention (by the US or Russia) really help the masses in Venezuela? How can one be sure that it wouldn’t turn into another Libya or Syria, where the US military had intervened to “give power back to the people” but ended up causing chaos and violence. Will US military action unite Venezuela by removing Maduro from power or destroy yet another country with oil reserves? The truth of the situation right now is that if the US really comes down to military action, then no other country will stop it. Be it China or Russia. They will all watch the spectacle because going against the US in its own backyard is foolish and in every way a loss for them, economically or politically. The aggression will make them pay dearly, and they are not really interested in what happens to Venezuela. Also, the showdown will only make matters messier and no one wants another Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should get to know what happens next in a matter of time, given the amount of urgency that’s been shown on both the fronts. For the Venezuelans, it is a choice between the lesser and bigger evil, and one cannot know which is which. But the truth is that people are suffering and the world community, as usual, is playing the power game that it so dearly loves. What hasn’t changed is that human lives and their conditions are all being overlooked. In this day and age, power is dear to all. Thus, all try to hold on strongly to their power. All rationale aside, this situation begs the question of where power truly lies. Is the US way of military supremacy a better method than the Chinese methodical hegemony or not? Recognizing Juan Guaido as the interim President has already started a massive uprising, and we are yet to see if this intervention in Venezuela starts a civil war or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In my previous articles, I have spoken about Latin America, its foundations, shortcomings, and how the past shall shape its future. Today, I talk about Venezuela, its decade-old story, its battle for survival and the turn of events. Fate does play cruel games with us at times, and Venezuela is a prime example of a country that has been played. From being one of the stronger economies of Latin America, Venezuela has seen a chronic downfall which would have been unimaginable only two decades ago. In the span of ten short years, everything has miraculously changed. Venezuela is now one of the most volatile countries in the world and is facing absolute poverty like no other country at the moment. This is a strange phenomenon, for the country is well endowed with oil reserves and is also one of the OPEC members. A scarcity of resources for a ‘petronation’ seems to be astounding. But poverty isn’t the worst of all that Venezuela faces. The law and order of the country is in shambles and despite having skilled labour, it has gone down the same road as Syria or Iraq (though there is no terror organization functioning just yet). When other countries are reaching milestones in the context of economic freedom, and political liberty, Venezuela is coping up with poverty and extreme cases of starvation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Tobacco and Marketing: An Anomaly?</title>
      <link href="/Tobacco-and-Marketing-An-Anomaly" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tobacco and Marketing: An Anomaly?" />
      <published>2019-02-07T03:57:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T03:57:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Tobacco-and-Marketing-An-Anomaly</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Tobacco-and-Marketing-An-Anomaly">&lt;p&gt;In September 1995, Pierre Omidyar, a 28-year old computer programmer finished the code for what would soon become eBay. Searching around for a test item, he put up a broken laser pointer for sale with the base price as $1. The laser pointer sold for $14.83. Shocked, Omidyar contacted the winning bidder to make sure he understood the laser pointer was broken. “Oh yes”, the bidder replied, “I am a collector of broken laser pointers.” Trade creates value by moving goods from people who value them less to people who value them more. Tobacco happens to be a product valued greatly by a variety of stakeholders. It is for this reason that we continue to trade and rampantly consume it in spite of its tribulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like the laser pointer, tobacco products are also ‘broken’ goods – unfit for use. Regardless, however, one can always find people wanting to purchase them, even if they have to bid high to acquire them. But, has anyone cared to wonder why? The answer to this question is obscure and complicated, yet evident and simple: &lt;i&gt;“They are cool, available, and addictive.”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are they cool? Well, celebrities endorse them in movies; Mickey Mouse, Popeye and The Flintstones on television. Why are they available? Probably because we want them, just as governments want their tax revenues and companies their profits. But they are addictive! Are McDonald’s, PUBG, and One Direction not? Tobacco products are like any other commodity. They have a demand and hence a supply. Now, in order to help demand meet supply, companies need to reach out to consumers by marketing themselves. These companies too, are like all other companies. They have a profit maximisation target and hence a purpose for existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, despite having brought the tobacco industry at par with other industries, can we permit it to be part of the same marketing ambit? Or can we even permit it to market its products in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earliest known advertisement in the United States was for the snuff and tobacco products of &amp;lt;P. Lorillard and Company and was placed in the New York daily papers in 1789. Advertising was an emerging concept, and tobacco-related advertisements were not seen as any different from those for other products: their negative impact on health was unknown at the time. American Tobacco was engaged in competitive advertising of its Bull Durham chewable tobacco leaves as well. Around the Great Depression, it ran campaigns like the &lt;i&gt;“Roll Your Own”&lt;/i&gt; campaign and boosted outdoor advertising by way of elegant wall paintings and graffiti. These cleverly designed advertisements were made to persuade the lower and middle-class masses to imitate the upper-class gentry by purchasing elite yet economical tobacco products: a bag of tobacco for just a nickel at the time. Through their &lt;i&gt;“Hit the Bull”&lt;/i&gt; campaign, the Blackwell Company was able to rope in baseball players to endorse their brand. If we observe carefully, such marketing techniques are not only ludicrous but also morally unacceptable today. An advertisement depicting class distinction would bring doom upon the company, and no sports person would endorse these products, parents would rush to scrape off wall paintings before their children could have a glance. Why is there this sudden change in our attitude towards tobacco? It is generally a legal substance after all, unless specifically prohibited as done in a few countries…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer lies in our awareness: I believe we are more informed about the dangers of tobacco than ever before. The first noteworthy scientific report concerning the dangers of cigarettes was published in 1964, by the Surgeon General of the United States. Terry (1964) illustrates important deductions by the Advisory Committee – smoking was found to be: “A cause of lung cancer and laryngeal cancer in men, a probable cause of lung cancer in women, the most important cause of chronic bronchitis.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senators in the US, thereafter, passed several laws to regulate the advertising of tobacco products. The Federal Cigarette Labeling and Advertising Act of 1965 mandated all cigarette boxes to come with a warning label. In 1971, there was a ban on the advertisement of tobacco products on television and radio. Countries like Australia have defeated giants like Philip Morris by legislating “plain packaging” of cigarettes in order to intensify the fight against tobacco. Very similar to a depiction in the movie &lt;i&gt;Thank you for Smoking&lt;/i&gt;(2005), cigarette companies in India have attempted partnering with Bollywood to get celebrities to promote smoking. The government has hence made it mandatory to include cautionary messages in films and music videos that show people smoking. This comes in response to cigarette companies trying to attract and indulge youngsters in embracing their poison. &lt;i&gt;“They try to hook our kids using cartoons and symbols.”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The global population of smokers increased from 721 million in 1980 to 967 million in 2012, and the number of cigarettes smoked has risen from 4.96 trillion to 6.25 trillion between the same time periods. Of the 1.22 billion smokers today, 1 billion of them live in developing or transitional economies. Rates of smoking have levelled off or declined in the developed world. In the developing world, tobacco consumption is rising by 3.4% every year. In 2002, about 20% of teens aged 13 to 15 smoked tobacco worldwide. Approximately 80,000 to 100,000 children in this age bracket begin smoking every day. Half of those who begin smoking in adolescent years are projected to go on to smoke for 15 to 20 years. Today’s teenager is tomorrow’s potential regular customer. It has been rightly said that &lt;i&gt;“tobacco takes care of its own”&lt;/i&gt; and own only: an invisible Invisible Hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Against all odds, we are striving to change the &lt;i&gt;“smoking is cool”&lt;/i&gt; notion, we are motivated to invent new kinds of alternatives that are not ‘addictive’ and also come up with treatments for lung diseases, but, in the face of our numerous measures to counter the tobacco menace, nothing really seems to be working. Probably because of its extensive ‘availability’ that no one is willing to put an end to. Why would they? The global spending, right from manufacturing cigarettes to treating the diseases they leave behind, is unbelievably enormous. The tobacco industry generates an income for not only its own farmers and employees but also other industries, their stakeholders, and governments at large. In 2014, tobacco companies spent more than $9 billion on marketing cigarettes and smokeless tobacco in the United States. This amount translates to nearly $25 million each day, or about $1 million every hour (Federal Trade Commission, 2016). Smoking-related illness in the United States costs more than $300 billion each year (US Department of Health and Human Services, 2014). Notwithstanding the economic wonders (including tax revenues) it is doing, only truly passionate, non-profit, non-governmental organizations are capable of opposing the ‘availability’ of tobacco. But, how many of these godly organizations actually exist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having intricately analyzed the trade mechanics of tobacco and its marketing approach, I can obviously agree that tobacco products do not qualify as ethically marketable products. I will certainly not provide marketing services to Big Tobacco or be one of those lawyers that protect cigarette companies in lawsuits. However, this being said, I also do not believe it is morally correct for us to deprive tobacco companies of access to marketing. Should it be regulated? Absolutely. Can we allow it to cater to all age groups? Absolutely not. But should we not ban its marketing completely? If and only if we are also banning cigarettes and all other forms of tobacco. Half-convinced that would never happen, I believe there at least needs to be stringent legislation on a code of conduct for tobacco firms to follow for advertisement of their products locally. What is ethical for one country might be the gravest of crimes for another. We cannot have a universal code of conduct in this aspect, nor can we decide for legal consumers: that would be morally presumptuous. After all, they have a choice of their own.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shivang Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      
        <category term="trending" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In September 1995, Pierre Omidyar, a 28-year old computer programmer finished the code for what would soon become eBay. Searching around for a test item, he put up a broken laser pointer for sale with the base price as $1. The laser pointer sold for $14.83. Shocked, Omidyar contacted the winning bidder to make sure he understood the laser pointer was broken. “Oh yes”, the bidder replied, “I am a collector of broken laser pointers.” Trade creates value by moving goods from people who value them less to people who value them more. Tobacco happens to be a product valued greatly by a variety of stakeholders. It is for this reason that we continue to trade and rampantly consume it in spite of its tribulations.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why ‘Hindutva’ Should be a Good Word</title>
      <link href="/Why-Hindutva-Should-be-a-Good-Word" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why 'Hindutva’ Should be a Good Word" />
      <published>2019-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-Hindutva-Should-be-a-Good-Word</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-Hindutva-Should-be-a-Good-Word">&lt;p&gt;The term ‘Hindutva’ has a bad reputation and not without good reason. A most unholy concoction of unscientific claims by right-wing leaders, mob lynchings, casteism and communal hatred has come to define Hindutva. The term has become so contemptible, especially to the well-educated and well-to-do of Indian society, that anyone who has slightly Hindutvavadi inclinations is automatically branded a ‘Bigoted Bhakt’ or ‘Sanghi’. This is, however, a sad state-of-affairs, for a political ideology like ‘Hindutva’ can be so much more than ‘Mandir Wahin Banayenge’. This article is an attempt at defining (not revising) Hindutva. It is our attempt at showing the world that Hindutva can be a profoundly positive contributor to our lives and to the life of this diverse and great nation called India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindutva as a political ideology manifests the ‘Hinduness’ of the Indian people. On a primitive level, Hindutva means the ‘Inherent Hinduness’  of all Indian people. Savarkar, who coined the term Hindutva, was an atheist himself and defined Hindutva in a strictly geographical and cultural sense. The word ‘Hindu’ comes from ‘Indus’ (the river around which we started off as a civilization) and the common bond which all Indians inherently share is hence called ‘Hindutva’. Simply put, any person born within the boundaries of the subcontinent is a Hindu and his inherent ‘Bharatiyata’ is called Hindutva.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This definition of Hindutva is, historically, the only true answer for Indians to the question “Who are we?” All other answers divided Indians into different religions, castes, regions and even races. In fact, the Hindu Code Bill defined a Hindu as someone who is “NOT a Christian, Jew, Parsi or Muslim”! Clearly, we need this ‘Bharatiya’ definition of Hindutva to have a true, positive consciousness of our identity as an extremely diverse nation. Socially, the concept of Hindutva, or there being a certain kind of Hinduness which we inherit from the fact of us being born in this holy land looks beyond divisions of caste and religion to unify the Indian masses. It brilliantly distinguishes Indians from the rest of the world. An American does not start possessing Hindutva if he converts to Hinduism (Sorry David Frawley). But an Indian Muslim has an inherent Hindutva and is very distinct from an Arabic or South-east Asian Muslim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not fashioning an artificial answer here on the question of Indian identity based only in geography. Instead, we are verily identifying the common culture and syncretic tradition that exists only within that geography. The Hindutva we speak of is not simply due to the happenstance of people living in a piece of land, it’s due to the overarching unity among diversity they have developed, the story they have told themselves. This Hindutva is manifested in the numerous public holidays of Eid, Christmas and Diwali we Indians enjoy together― whether we are Hindu, Christian, or Muslim. It is found in the consistent requests for Biryani by Hindus to their Muslim friends. From the Rig Veda’s declaration (RV 1.164.46) that “Indra, Mitra, Varuna, Agni…The wise speak of what is One in many ways” to Kabir’s elegant verses on religious unity, Hindutva is about the rich cultural inheritance of all Indians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first key aspect of Hindutva is the fact that we have overcome so many foibles and problems, skirmishes and conflicts to emerge as one nation. Yes, there was once a time we officially designated people as ‘untouchable’ but still, our Constitution was written by a ‘Dalit’ man. Yes, Mahmud Ghazni plundered the Somnath Temple 17 times, but Ghalib’s verses would be non-existent without Muslims. It is through the schisms between us that we have developed this complex and unique identity. We have been through multiple disagreements on grounds of caste, faith, state and language. And in overcoming them we have discovered our underlying unity. Therefore, the first theme of Hindutva involves a sense of Indian pride, a feeling of common triumph of having risen above so many conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second aspect of Hindutva is religion, or rather the peculiar part it plays in making us so distinct. Religion is very strongly present in India’s public life, from the raucous dispute surrounding the Babri Masjid to the controversy on beef and mob lynchings. However, even if religion is a cause of conflict in India, it is undeniably the bedrock of its cultural identity too. Without Hinduism and its multiple gods, esoteric texts and ancient hymns, India is unimaginable. Without the Buddha its culture is barren; and without an Indian version of Islam, there would be no Sufism, no qawwalis. Faith is a wonderful thing in India that makes us separate from the barren West. In the West, as Nietzsche states (in The Gay Science), “God is dead, he remains dead, and [they] have killed him”. In India, the ‘Samudra Manthan’ of religions yields the nectar of meaning, whether it be in the form of Khwajaji’s sermons, Adi Shankara’s works, or Lalan Fakir’s songs, all we need to do is share it equally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third historical aspect of Hindutva explains how our unity exists through our diversity, and not despite it. We Indians may have had our problems, but just like a big Indian joint family, we are one. Hindutva ideologues like Golwalkar (in his Bunch of Thoughts) and Deendayal Upadhyaya (in his Integral Humanism) have time and again emphasised how Hindutva is broader than Hinduism because Indians following ‘Avaidik’ Dharmas like Sikhism, Jainism, Buddhism and even religions like Islam and Christianity have Hindutva in them. The reason for that is cultural intermingling. Arjuna’s marriage to Naga princess Ulupi and Manipuri princess Chitrangada in The Mahabharata is a classical and literary example of how we Indians cherish a mixing of traditions in our rich mythology. Even the Indian Supreme Court noted in 1995 that Hindutva is a way of life (and a ‘state of mind’). This way of life has been accepting of all people (both the oppressed and the oppressors), and even ‘foreign-origin’ rulers like the towering Mughal Emperor Akbar have patronised this way of life that epitomises a unity that stems from diversity. While the Parsis immigrated to both China and India, it was the latter where they finally found refuge in. The Jews have thanked us enough for being the only country without an instance of anti-Semitism. In fact, the Jewish quarters of Kochi stand right next to the Palace of the King of Kochi. The Hindu philosophical idea of every creature being a part of the Supreme Brahman (irrespective of his faith) has made us an all-welcoming people. And the word Hindutva embodies that openness of mind ever so poignantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line of this article is to tell the reader to embrace Hindutva. Why? Because Hindutva is India’s gift to the world. It was Hindutva which ‘Indianized’ parts of Iran, Afghanistan, Tibet, South-East Asia and even Japan. Thailand’s erstwhile capital is named Ayutthaya, after Lord Ram’s capital Ayodhya. What makes India stand out is not its history, its philosophy or its many religions, but an optimum combination  of all three. Once upon a time, European merchants wanted to trade with us, hence the mad pursuits by Columbus and Vasco Da Gama to ‘discover’ the magical land called India. But what do we find today? Growing westernization and inferiority complex amongst Indians! The same India which was a shining example of an ideal country to the world is now restyling itself based on western ‘isms’ like Capitalism and Socialism. This cannot happen. Hindutva is India’s ‘Soft Power’. All Indians have to be proud of Hindutva, for we can’t expect the world to respect us if we don’t respect ‘who we are’. Unless India becomes ‘Indianized’ again, ‘Superpower 2020’ (realistically speaking, ‘Superpower 2050’), will remain a distant dream.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>harsh.tiwari tushar.singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      
        <category term="trending" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The term ‘Hindutva’ has a bad reputation and not without good reason. A most unholy concoction of unscientific claims by right-wing leaders, mob lynchings, casteism and communal hatred has come to define Hindutva. The term has become so contemptible, especially to the well-educated and well-to-do of Indian society, that anyone who has slightly Hindutvavadi inclinations is automatically branded a ‘Bigoted Bhakt’ or ‘Sanghi’. This is, however, a sad state-of-affairs, for a political ideology like ‘Hindutva’ can be so much more than ‘Mandir Wahin Banayenge’. This article is an attempt at defining (not revising) Hindutva. It is our attempt at showing the world that Hindutva can be a profoundly positive contributor to our lives and to the life of this diverse and great nation called India.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Editorial: On The Importance of Sex</title>
      <link href="/Importance-of-sex" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Editorial: On The Importance of Sex" />
      <published>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Importance-of-sex</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Importance-of-sex">&lt;p&gt;It is most certainly not easy writing about sex. To begin with, you have to deal with the fact that once you start talking about orgasms, breasts, penises and foot fetishes (the human mind is an unholy place), it is very easy to sound like you are writing plain-old erotica—cheap, unsophisticated, and yet very arousing. At the same time though, if you try to distance yourself from the human depravity of sex, you could sound more like a plumber describing a u-bend when exploring whether the G-Spot really exists. I want to avoid making such serious stylistic errors, but I don’t want to forget that any conversation about sex has to be both erotic and exciting whilst being decidedly technical about a topic that is so serious. I remember watching an interview of Philip Roth (you kind of have to read and listen to him when thinking about sex and literature), where he declared quite hilariously that when he and his friends were sixteen they had only question about sex: &lt;em&gt;“WHEN? WHEN? WHEN?!!”&lt;/em&gt; That kind of desperation was not simply because of an animal drive within us, according to Roth. If his book &lt;i&gt;Portnoy’s Complaint&lt;/i&gt; (which is about a mother-obsessed, masturbation addict) is any indication, the want for sex in human beings can lead to all kinds of things both disgusting and sexy. The power that sex holds over our lives can lead to all sorts of problems, from the relatively benign but hideous (think Diogenes masturbating in the open streets) to the debauched (think Marquis De Sade’s &lt;i&gt;120 Days of Sodom&lt;/i&gt;) and to even wholesale exploitation (think prostitution). There is a reason why “sex sells” and there’s a reason why clerics don’t want even the ankles of women to be visible to men. Sex lies at the very human intersection of patriarchy, fulfilment, love, exploitation, power and everything else in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think a brilliant place to find a conversation about sex that is stimulating (in the right way) is the comments section of any porn video (it’s also a good way of ensuring the video is a good one!). The things people say (and don’t say) about sex in these comments is so profoundly revealing (never thought I’d use the word profound when writing about sex!). These comments tell us that people don’t just watch porn to simply &lt;em&gt;“bust a nut or yaw yaw the sisterhood”&lt;/em&gt;. Masturbation is a very sensuous thing in our lives: It relieves boredom, which is perennially the human mind’s most wicked enemy and it gives us the opportunity to enjoy the feelings (and hormones) that sex brings with the most important person in our erotic lives: ourselves. Therefore, it is no wonder that people have such strikingly specific criticisms of the acting in the video, or the stilettos of the female porn star, or the absolutely unrealistic time for which the male porn star lasts. People put up comments stating all sorts of things, from the things they found funny like the orgasm face of the actors or the scenes they felt where outright bizarre like one where they felt the porn star’s screaming was extremely unappealing as it sounded like a &lt;em&gt;“donkey braying”&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Porn is about the deep voyeurism that inhabits the human mind, it is about finding release (literally) and for that one needs a good experience. Put it this way: when we want to release our bowels we want a clean toilet that smells good, when we want to fulfil our hunger we want food that tastes good, and when we want to avoid the cold we want a jumper that looks good. If we want quality in all other things, should it surprise anyone that we want porn to be more than just people “doing it” with each other? Good pornography is important for the same reason that anything is important to human beings, we are not just Plato’s “featherless birds” and we don’t just have sex in caves (HA!). Unlike the plots and scripts of most porn movies, human beings are interesting in nature, and their erotic lives reflect that via their desires from pornography. There’s a reason why &lt;i&gt;Playboy&lt;/i&gt; Magazine, instead of just having any other nudes, had Marilyn Monroe’s nudes. And there is a reason why Pornhub has reported a phenomenal rise in the consumption of incest porn by…(drum-roll)…millennials!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sex as an activity is about satisfying the human imagination—otherwise, a few grunts and no foreplay would have kept everyone happy. On the issue of ‘grunts’, we all know that men can have very few problems when it ‘comes’ to (pardon the pun) reaching climax, whereas there is a whole body of feminist literature on how women don’t really climax at all most of the time. The common form that the female orgasm takes is due to clitoral stimulation, and the reason why women do not really come due to vaginal stimulation is because, well, men don’t usually last long enough. This creates an obviously skewered power dynamic in sex, where men are able to “unload” ever so easily and women are left feeling constantly under-appreciated. I don’t mean to say that this means men are near-constantly aroused pigs who pay no heed to the needs of their female partners, although there is truth in that contention. My point here is simply that without a good amount of foreplay and some good oral sex, our sexual activities with all their imaginative passion can simply end up being a dull series of painful thrusts for one whole half of the human population—and sex must be far more than that if in these feminist times we men are to redeem ourselves for having treated women as objects of sex for thousands of years. Ancient India, being a culture at a stupendous height of civilisation, was acutely aware of the consequences of denying women the beauty of an orgasm. As Wendy Doniger, a controversial yet revered Indologist, points out, even the legendary &lt;i&gt;Kama Sutra&lt;/i&gt; is clear on the fact that women must orgasm first, given how easy it is for men to do so. The message is clear and has been clear for more than a thousand years: boys, at least try to find the fabled G-spot once in a while instead of just seeking blowjobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power dynamics of sex bring up a very curious issue with specific regard to sex between homosexual men. It is difficult to accurately describe how significantly being either a ‘top’ or a ‘bottom’ has an effect on the masculinity of gay men (MEN!!). The power politics in that part of human sexuality has assumed new proportions with the world’s gay community bidding adieu to the stereotype of the “camp” gay man and welcoming a more traditionally masculine homosexual male as more desirable. As Kevin Troughton &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/nov/30/the-end-of-camp-straight-acting-gay&quot;&gt;writes&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;i&gt;The Guardian&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;em&gt;“very few find [camp] sexually attractive. That limp-wristed, bitchy queen might be hilarious, but you wouldn’t want him as a boyfriend, or even as a one-night stand.”&lt;/em&gt; The fact is “bottoming” gay men have always been stereotyped into the camp category, facing potentially even internalised homophobia due to their perceived passivity in the gay community. And now with the rise in the desirability of the straight-acting gay alpha male, it would appear that all men who wish to receive anal sex will potentially have greater issues relating to dominance and estimations of their own masculinity. Funny enough, all of this simply reinforces the words of Oscar Wilde: &lt;em&gt;“Everything in the world is about sex except sex. Sex is about power”&lt;/em&gt;. It is slightly hilarious but definitely unsurprising that men having sex with other men is where power dynamics take centre stage, after all, the ‘male ego’ manifests itself most strongly in front of other men!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between love and sex is complicated (well, of course). And if you have read a bit of Freud (he has to be mentioned in a discussion on sex, you know, #respect), sex and love are both about your mum. Obviously, his Oedipus Complex and theories on the development of libido are a bit bogus, but his underlying assertion that we learn how to have relationships primarily from our parents makes a lot of intuitive sense. Parents give their children a reality, they define what human interaction means for them and they do so simply because that’s how it is, for good or for bad. This means people’s relationships are (to a degree) shaped by the experiences given to them by their childhood and their parents. The problem is that people fall in love with the people they have sex with quite often and vice versa! And people falling in love leads to all sorts of problems like marriage, infidelity, drama and the responsibility to take care of children. The very point of sex leads to relationships that are determined on factors outside your control (your mum!), and lead to a sexual rut (your children) with added responsibilities of bringing up another human being—so that the cycle can continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is definitely weird talking about sex and extremely difficult to treat it with the sensitivity and respect it deserves. But it certainly is fun to think about and research on something that is so goddamn brilliant. I mean, my research showed me that orgasms could be had by brain dead people if the right nerves are stimulated! And it was facts and observations like this that made my task ever so out-of-control. Yes, sex is important, I could see that, but what is the common thread that makes it all ever so important? And why? I think I have chanced upon a simple answer to these questions: sex is humanity’s deepest desires manifested in the most physical of acts, and for that very reason it’s going to be more than just a simple act. Adieu!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      
        <category term="trending" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is most certainly not easy writing about sex. To begin with, you have to deal with the fact that once you start talking about orgasms, breasts, penises and foot fetishes (the human mind is an unholy place), it is very easy to sound like you are writing plain-old erotica—cheap, unsophisticated, and yet very arousing. At the same time though, if you try to distance yourself from the human depravity of sex, you could sound more like a plumber describing a u-bend when exploring whether the G-Spot really exists. I want to avoid making such serious stylistic errors, but I don’t want to forget that any conversation about sex has to be both erotic and exciting whilst being decidedly technical about a topic that is so serious. I remember watching an interview of Philip Roth (you kind of have to read and listen to him when thinking about sex and literature), where he declared quite hilariously that when he and his friends were sixteen they had only question about sex: “WHEN? WHEN? WHEN?!!” That kind of desperation was not simply because of an animal drive within us, according to Roth. If his book Portnoy’s Complaint (which is about a mother-obsessed, masturbation addict) is any indication, the want for sex in human beings can lead to all kinds of things both disgusting and sexy. The power that sex holds over our lives can lead to all sorts of problems, from the relatively benign but hideous (think Diogenes masturbating in the open streets) to the debauched (think Marquis De Sade’s 120 Days of Sodom) and to even wholesale exploitation (think prostitution). There is a reason why “sex sells” and there’s a reason why clerics don’t want even the ankles of women to be visible to men. Sex lies at the very human intersection of patriarchy, fulfilment, love, exploitation, power and everything else in between.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
