<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/trending/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-09-17T20:13:03+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/trending/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Silent Genocide in Zimbabwe</title>
      <link href="/The-Silent-Genocide" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Silent Genocide in Zimbabwe" />
      <published>2020-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Silent-Genocide</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Silent-Genocide">&lt;p&gt;On July 27, 2020, seven babies were stillborn in Harare Hospital on the same day. An anonymous doctor, in a letter to the nation, confirmed that the babies were of a healthy weight and could have been saved, but it was Zimbabwe’s crumbling health system that killed them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This incident is just one of the many unreported and completely avoidable deaths. Many patients are forced to be turned away from hospitals either due to lack of staff or lack of equipment. There have been reports of pregnant women giving birth in unconventional and unsafe places leading to increased mortality rates. Doctors and nurses have consistently been underpaid and overworked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this situation is common to many countries as a result of the COVID-19 pandemic, the situation in Zimbabwe has been dire for a long time. In September 2019, medical personnel across the country went on a 4-month long strike to protest their devastatingly low wages and poor working conditions. It was not that they did not want to work, it was that they could not afford to work. In the face of triple-digit inflation, doctors and nurses could barely meet their food and transport costs. In fact, the doctors did not call it a strike - rather an “incapacitation”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government’s response was disheartening, stating that it was not just medical personnel, but all workers who were suffering under inflation, including civil servants. However, looking at the standard of life of government officials, this did not seem plausible. Suspiciously enough, not long after the strike began, their union leader, Dr Peter Magombeyi, was abducted for five days under mysterious circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The staff only returned to work in January 2020 when the telecoms tycoon Strive Masiyiwa offered to supplement the government wages with a monthly subsistence allowance through his charitable foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in March 2020, COVID-19 reached Zimbabwe. President Emmerson Mnangagwa fell short in governance. Not just the healthcare system but the entire economy is facing an insurmountable challenge. The unemployment level is close to 90%, with most people falling deeper into poverty and being unable to afford a proper meal a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April, the High Court ordered the government to ensure all healthcare workers were supplied with Personal Protective Equipment (PPE). However, according to doctors, there is still hardly any PPE available. N-95 masks are occasionally provided but mostly a surgical mask and plastic aprons are given to last an entire day. An increasing number of medical personnel are being affected and there is no insurance for them. Adding to this risk of practicing, the pay has been dismally low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The situation is even more terrible for nurses. Many of them receive just $30 per month and cannot even afford proper food and housing. On these grounds, nurses in Zimbabwe went on a strike in June 2020. Instead of providing PPE kits and improving pay and working conditions, the government brought in student nurses and those who had been out of work for a long time. Thus, many wards were staffed with nurses who were either inexperienced or who had not received recent training. Shortly after, doctors followed them, demanding PPE, better conditions and equipment in hospitals, decent pay, and for salaries to be paid in US dollars rather than the RTGS dollar (or “Zimdollar”) which is subject to hyperinflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reinaldo Ortuno, head of mission at Médecins Sans Frontières Zimbabwe said, &lt;em&gt;“Hospitals and clinics are now manned by student nurses, junior doctors, and other staff who have no choice as they are still under training. This has compromised quality of care and has inadvertently contributed to high morbidity and mortality rates”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government seems to have little incentive to bring a change. The people in power do not exert pressure for a better healthcare system as they do not get treated in government hospitals. When they fall sick, they go abroad. Ex-President Robert Mugabe received treatment in Singapore before he passed away in 2019, at the age of 95. Vice-President Constantino Chiwenga, the former military man who played a major role in overthrowing Mugabe, has received four months of medical treatment in China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government even saw the pandemic as a money-making opportunity. This clearly revealed the multi-million-dollar equipment procurement scandal that led to the recent arrest of the Health Minister as well as the vindictive detention of Hopewell Chin’ono, the journalist who uncovered it. The government then appointed Constantine Chiwenga as the new Health Minister, even though he had made insulting and abusive comments against doctors in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pandemic has led to strikes by medical personnel all across the world. This presents a dilemma of whose needs should be put above the others. Should doctors and nurses suffer through their long hours and low wages as a part of their duty to society? The reality is that in Zimbabwe, they have been making this sacrifice for a long time. However, now the nature of COVID-19 means that this sacrifice could cost them their lives. Norman Matara, head of Zimbabwe Hospital Doctors Association said that about 15% of the nationally recorded virus infections had been detected among health workers. The lack of attention from the government has broken their spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many have called this crisis in Zimbabwe a “silent genocide”. The government must increase public spending in the healthcare sector on an emergency basis, and should also look towards securing foreign assistance for equipment and personnel, like Cuba has been providing, to support them through the pandemic. Refusing the demands of the workers and degrading their protest by accusing them of not fulfilling their duty is not beneficial to any side. President Emmerson Mnangagwa needs to act in order to rebuild the trust of doctors and nurses in the government. They are at the frontline of the fight against the pandemic, and their wellbeing, both physical and mental, is quite literally a matter of life and death.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On July 27, 2020, seven babies were stillborn in Harare Hospital on the same day. An anonymous doctor, in a letter to the nation, confirmed that the babies were of a healthy weight and could have been saved, but it was Zimbabwe’s crumbling health system that killed them.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">To Ally or not to Ally: Saudi-Pak Relations</title>
      <link href="/Saudi-Pak-Relations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To Ally or not to Ally: Saudi-Pak Relations" />
      <published>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Saudi-Pak-Relations</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Saudi-Pak-Relations">&lt;p&gt;The nation of Saudi Arabia is a strong believer in the concept of quid-pro-quo and it seems Saudi’s long time ally Pakistan is going to be reminded of this fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past two years, Saudi Arabia has been financing and investing in the Pakistan economy as a testament to their confidence in Pakistan’s loyalty. In 2018, Saudi rescued Pakistan from a financial crisis triggered by decreasing foreign reserves and increasing trade deficit by announcing a loan package of $6 billion, which was followed by an overall investment of $20 billion in Pakistan’s economy in 2019. In return, Saudi demanded unerring loyalty within and outside the Organisation of Islamic Countries (OIC). However, Pakistan has failed to uphold their side of the trade and is currently in deep waters with the Saudi regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a series of unfortunate events, Pakistan has managed to transgress on their agreements. The catalyst to these events was Pakistan’s bid to gain support in their quest to fight India on their decision to revoke Article 370 of the Indian Constitution which gave special status and provisions to Kashmir in India. Since 2019, Pakistan had been trying to arrange a special meeting with the OIC to discuss the matter of Kashmir and to convince the participating nations to hold India accountable for the abrogation of Article 370. However, Saudi refused to join the bandwagon and being a key player in the OIC, Saudi’s support was imperative for Pakistan to gain the support of other Islamic nations. Their refusal made it impossible for Pakistan to fulfil its objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owing to their precarious position post-Saudi’s refusal, Pakistan tried to gain the support of nations that were outside the OIC, namely Malaysia, Turkey and Qatar. Saudi has been engaged in regional disputes with Turkey, and China wants Turkey to replace the position Saudi holds in the Middle East due to Saudi’s relations with the United States. Amidst all this, Saudi and Qatar battle over the Gulf Cooperation Council (GCC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the aforementioned circumstances, Pakistan’s attempt to take advantage of Saudi’s disputes further soured their relations. Comments made by Pakistan’s Foreign Minister Shah Mahmood Qureshi on a talk show interview about asking Pakistani Prime Minister Imran Khan to call a meeting outside of OIC to gain support on the issue of Kashmir was the tipping point for the Saudi regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia could not let this public opposition to their and OIC’s decision go unpunished. Riyadh demanded immediate repayment of their loan of $3 billion. While Pakistan managed to pay back $1 billion with China’s help, Saudi refused to entertain pleas for deferred payment. Punishment in the form of monetary compensation is more than what Pakistan can bear considering its dwindling economy. Consequently, Pakistan Army Chief General Bajwa was sent to Riyadh to meet Crown Prince Mohammad Bin Salman with the hopes of making amends and smoothening the turbulent relations. However, the Crown Prince refused to meet the General, and instead, the Vice Minister of Defence and Chief of General Staff of Saudi were sent to entertain General Bajwa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blatant snub underscores the most pressing problem that Pakistan is currently facing. The Crown Prince’s refusal to meet the General is an indication that matters are much more grave, and that the Saudi regime would not be satisfied with appeasing words and meetings. This is only exacerbated by the impending conditions of loan repayment and the grave possibility of losing the $20 billion worth of investments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia’s refusal to stand with Pakistan on the issue of Kashmir is also an indicator of growing India-Saudi relations. According to a recent article in &lt;em&gt;The Indian Express&lt;/em&gt;, India imports around 19% of its oil requirements from Saudi. The trade between the two countries is estimated at approximately $28 billion. Hence, Saudi cannot oppose India’s decision regarding Kashmir. Saudi’s preference for India over Pakistan is a confirmation of Pakistan’s dwindling position in the OIC and as Saudi’s ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fearing the loss and wrath of a powerful ally, Shah Mahmood Qureshi made a trip to China as soon as the dignitaries sent to Saudi returned. While Pakistan does have China’s support, the strength and extent of the support remain to be seen. China has invested huge amounts of money in Pakistan’s economy under the former’s Belt and Road Initiative (BRI) and has kept the Pakistan economy from crumbling. Thereby, China holds sway over Pakistan, but whether the reverse is true or not cannot be ascertained. Qureshi’s trip to China may help Pakistan pay back the loans, however, the impact of their position with the OIC will certainly have a long-term impact on Pakistan’s trade and international relations. It also remains to be seen how long China would be willing to bail Pakistan out every time they manage to offend their allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a bid to gain the upper hand with India, Pakistan has managed to land itself in significant trouble with powerful nations. India’s expanding trade relations with Middle Eastern nations has made it extremely difficult for Pakistan to gather support against them. The issue of Kashmir has long been a festering wound for Pakistan, but is it important enough for the country to endanger their diplomatic tussle and lose out investments to keep their country afloat? In its current situation, Pakistan can either assuage the disgruntled Saudi regime or hold them at bay long enough to gather the funds necessary for loan repayment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, even if they manage to pay the loans, Pakistan’s economy faces the imminent threat of economic collapse. Pakistan will not be able to use China as a crutch, and this relationship is likely to end the same way as Pakistan-US agreements. Pakistan’s tendency to provide refuge to terrorists has further aggravated many of its allies, and India has recently made public statements about holding Pakistan liable for the same. Amidst tempestuous international relations, fragile trade relations and changing tides of globalisation, Pakistan needs to come up with a better strategy to reduce its dependence upon other countries or the consequences in the future would be far worse than angry Princes and loan repayments.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The nation of Saudi Arabia is a strong believer in the concept of quid-pro-quo and it seems Saudi’s long time ally Pakistan is going to be reminded of this fact.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Against a Liberal Anti-racism</title>
      <link href="/Against-a-Liberal-Anti-racism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Against a Liberal Anti-racism" />
      <published>2020-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Against-a-Liberal-Anti-racism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Against-a-Liberal-Anti-racism">&lt;p&gt;The months following the killing of George Floyd saw sales of books about race increase by up to 6,800%. The top seller was Robin DiAngelo’s &lt;em&gt;White Fragility&lt;/em&gt;, which increased sales by over 400,000 copies from May to June this year, a startling increase of over 2,000%. DiAngelo, a ‘diversity consultant’, has since been invited to deliver keynote speeches, charging up to $35,000 for a two-hour workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DiAngelo’s central premise, that white Americans must reckon with their own implicit biases and engage in rigorous introspection to remedy them, appears less of a repudiation of centuries-old institutional racism than it does an instructional manual for white liberals working in corporate jobs to avoid getting into trouble with HR. It characterises racism merely as an antipathy felt by individuals towards other individuals, leaving untouched the edifice of America’s racist socio-economic structure. It fails to acknowledge that white supremacy is not simply the supremacy of white over black, but also the supremacy of rich whites over poorer whites who can be trusted to vote themselves into economic ruin in return for the illusion of superiority. And even more egregiously, it focuses attention on the self-aggrandising antics of the white liberal, repackaging the fight against racism as a culture war between educated white liberals and less educated whites, many of whom do not view themselves as the beneficiaries of ‘privilege’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the first Africans arrived in Virginia in 1619, there were no ‘white’ people there. It would be another 60 years before colonial records would describe the settlers as ‘white’, as the idea of the ‘white’ race was deliberately constructed by the ruling class as a form of social control, dividing poor European indentured servants and African chattel-bond labourers, assimilating the Europeans into the ‘middle class’, and preventing the likelihood of the reemergence of an event such as Bacon’s Rebellion (1676). Europeans and Africans had jointly demanded the imposition of a land tax and Virginia’s transition from a large plantation economy to a diversified economy of small freeholders, chasing the planter bourgeoisie to the shore and burning Jamestown to the ground. Ira Berlin stated that in the aftermath of Bacon’s Rebellion &lt;em&gt;“they enact laws which say that people of African descent are hereditary slaves. And they increasingly give some power to the independent white farmers and land holders”&lt;/em&gt;. Therefore, rather than being simply a form of prejudice on the basis of skin colour, racism can be understood as a complex form of social control. Theodore W Allen’s book &lt;em&gt;The Invention of the White Race&lt;/em&gt; made a similar argument that racism is a “sociogenic” rather than a “phylogenic” phenomenon, analysing how the (phenotypically similar) British used racial oppression against Irish Catholics, later allowing the Irish Catholic bourgeoisie to assimilate into the oppressive structure, accepting the disenfranchisement of the forty-shilling freeholders in return for meagre ‘emancipation’ in 1829.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, liberal anti-racism of the DiAngelo variety, largely devoid of this analysis, becomes an exercise in narcissistic self-indulgence on the part of white liberals, who reframe discussions about race in terms of how they can be better people, and how it is incumbent on all whites to unlearn their white privilege. As this approach to anti-racism fails to acknowledge how racism functions as a tool of socioeconomic disenfranchisement by the ruling class, it assumes that all whites benefit equally from white privilege, ignoring and minimising the plight of working-class whites. A 2019 sociological study by E Cooley, etc. found that learning about white privilege did nothing to increase empathy for people of colour among white liberals, but simply made them less likely to empathise with poorer whites, placing greater personal blame on them on the basis that their privilege outweighed other social factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, reactionary and racist ideology abounds among the white working class, and this article is not intended to downplay such attitudes or pretend that they do not exist. It is to argue that if there is a hope that cross-racial solidarity can be achieved, and these reactionary tendencies extinguished, it will not be accomplished by lecturing working-class whites who are beset by low wages, deindustrialisation, and the opioid epidemic about their ‘privilege’, but by encouraging them to recognise that they have more in common with other races than with elites of the same race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term ‘class reductionist’ is consistently deployed against socialists who recognise that racism and capitalism are intimately connected as if this recognition downplays the significance of racism. But some of the most pernicious forms of American institutional racism, such as redlining and the prison-industrial complex, have explicitly capitalistic imperatives. For example, exclusion from ‘prime’ credit has forced black communities to secure housing through subprime loans and substandard rental accommodation. During the subprime lending boom, predatory loans were five times more likely to be made in black neighbourhoods than in white neighbourhoods, while black Americans were four times as likely as white Americans to be denied loans from the Bank of America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations such as the Blackstone Group have conspired to engage in predatory lending practices, buying up houses at cheap prices and selling them on for higher prices or charging exorbitant rents. Invitation Homes, a subsidiary of the Blackstone Group and a prominent lender to black communities, may have broken laws to give tenants loans that maximised profits as they could easily outbid first time buyers. It is issues such as these, the pervasive, material disparities which have concentrated generational wealth in the hands of white communities and generational disadvantage in the hands of black communities that should be the focus of anti-racists, not trivial ideas such as ‘white fragility’. These are not injustices that can be solved simply by more representation of black people within the highest echelons of power, but only through the de-privatisation and de-commodification of housing at a minimum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another consequence of viewing racism through a reductive, individualistic lens is the over-medicalisation of the problem, which treats racism as a pathology on the part of its perpetrators. As Kenan Malik writes, &lt;em&gt;“It was not unconscious bias that made a police officer place his knee on George Floyd’s neck”&lt;/em&gt;. A meta-analysis of nearly 500 studies found that unconscious bias training only had a “weak” effect on the behaviour of individuals. Reframing racism as a product of original sin, an aberration that could never be held by ‘normal’ people simply absolves those who are responsible for perpetuating it, as racial bigotry can, and often is, the product of a sound mind. The Nazi war criminals at Nuremberg, for instance, all tested as medically sane, had high IQs, and included a disproportionate number of PhDs. Far from being the irrational judgement of an insane mind, racism is the mendacious, calculated judgement of the elites who perpetuate it, to provide a constant stream of alienated unfree labour from those they impoverish, to divide and conquer and to subjugate. Only an approach that acknowledges the systemic and institutional manifestations of racism can grasp this central point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The systemic racism on which the United States was founded, that still exists today, cannot be expunged with ‘unconscious bias training’ or the recognition of white fragility. The injustices will remain, but white corporate consultants such as Robin DiAngelo will become very rich. What is required is not white guilt but white solidarity on a mass scale, such as has been seen in the recent protests, and a recognition that, as Karl Marx stated, &lt;em&gt;“Labour in the white skin cannot emancipate itself where in the black it is branded.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The months following the killing of George Floyd saw sales of books about race increase by up to 6,800%. The top seller was Robin DiAngelo’s White Fragility, which increased sales by over 400,000 copies from May to June this year, a startling increase of over 2,000%. DiAngelo, a ‘diversity consultant’, has since been invited to deliver keynote speeches, charging up to $35,000 for a two-hour workshop.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">God’s Homophobia will Die and We will Kill It</title>
      <link href="/God-s-Homophobia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="God's Homophobia will Die and We will Kill It" />
      <published>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/God-s-Homophobia</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/God-s-Homophobia">&lt;p&gt;It is no secret that most religions of the world are opposed to homosexuality. The Bible clearly states: &lt;em&gt;“If a man lies with a male as with a woman, both of them have committed an abomination; they shall surely be put to death; their blood is upon them.”&lt;/em&gt; (Leviticus 18:22). While the Quran does not have such an explicit declaration, traditional Islamic jurisprudence fully proscribes homosexual acts. Hindu jurisprudence has no equivalent bans on homosexual acts, and its law books do contain a recognition of a ‘third gender’, but most Hindus oppose it vigorously in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, none of these religions are monolithic and all contain various elements that are sympathetic towards homosexuality, whether among general followers or in their institutions. Despite all that, only a fool would say that the religions of the world fully accept homosexuals or their rights. This is epitomised in the most patronising argument religious people put forth, i.e. that while they accept LGBTQ persons like any other human being and believe homosexuality to be natural, their dogma commands that they continue to consider homosexual acts as immoral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is: what can one do in such a situation? Can an LGBTQ person agree to disagree with the religious person and still continue to co-exist? Or is peace simply not an option? The religious person obviously insists that they are only proceeding from a vantage point of empathy, that they demand restraint from the gay person not out of prejudice but because all persons have to control their desires under a religious framework, not just homosexuals. So, there is no ground to allege homophobia on their part at all. But all of this is utter hogwash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the fact that this new kind of argument is a clear attempt at dehumanising the homosexual, because it proscribes the very fruition of the gay person’s inner desires, it has more sinister implications: It leads to religious people favouring the maintenance of legal bans on homosexual acts because that is not seen as an impeachment of LGBTQ rights by itself. It also leads to a moral justification for continuing with the torturous practice of gay conversion therapy because that is verily seen as an expression of love which only seeks to prevent sin. And it is the brutality of these points as well as the very sinews of religious beliefs on homosexuality that makes such beliefs worthy of eradication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religions, after all, view the very fact of homosexuality as wrong. To them, it is fundamentally unnatural and a deviation from the human normal which God(s) has thought fit to prohibit. The outward empathy they seek to exhibit for LGBTQ rights is informed not by an understanding of the fact that homosexuality is no deviation from the normal, but by their desire to be kind in a way no different to the kindness/forgiveness they may have for the rapist or the murderer. When one takes that into account, one can clearly see that religious people want the LGBTQ community to become dogs on a leash - restraining themselves from a fruition of their sexual desires and a more visible existence in public life - in exchange for little treats of kindness and little beatings of gay conversion therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the question of making peace with the religious person who denies the normalcy of homosexual relations or deems them sinful is moot. The religious person may seek to caustically self-victimise here by saying that their human rights as religious people cannot be restricted by the homosexual agenda. But the fact of the matter is that their argument would likely not find traction in any human rights court save the ones found in America with elected Republican judges. It is well-known in human rights jurisprudence that the right to practice one’s faith may be qualified. The requirement is that such a qualification be for a legitimate aim, that it be the necessary means to achieve such an aim and that it be the least-intrusive means available for achieving that aim. We clearly know that a criminalisation of the espousal of anti-homosexual beliefs is for a very legitimate aim: the securing of fuller rights to LGBTQ person. We also know that such a measure is necessary to achieve that aim. If there is no threat of criminal sanction on the espousal of anti-LGBTQ beliefs, then a threat to the right of LGBTQ persons to lead a dignified existence forever remains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only hurdle would be the question of intrusiveness. But given the nature of the mischief sought to be controlled here, criminalisation is not in the least excessive. The threat of criminal sanction that secures the rights of homosexuals is hardly intrusive upon religious rights: such a measure does not require the religious person to go out of his way to do anything, it merely requires them to forbear from preaching certain values. That may be intrusive due to the fact that proselytisation is an article of some faiths, but again, there’s no ban on proselytisation here - just a ban on bigotry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religions will make every attempt to try and hold on to their homophobia, going so far as to to suggest that their moral values are given by a creator and are immutable, regardless of the fact that science and nature condone homosexuality. They will say that their laws are not bendable and that science does not provide an objectively ethical guide to what is permissible among humans. So, a restriction on their right to believe is not objective or valid. But that’s not the point, society is not here to play religion’s game of “my group’s values are objective and right, your group’s values are subjective and wrong”. What society, at this present moment, is required to do is secure complete rights to human beings who have sexual and romantic relations with persons of the same gender. This is the reality of the here and now, and it is non-negotiable, morally or otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is about time that religion killed God’s homophobia, lest He face the proverbial sulphur of a modern society.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>anon.anon</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is no secret that most religions of the world are opposed to homosexuality. The Bible clearly states: “If a man lies with a male as with a woman, both of them have committed an abomination; they shall surely be put to death; their blood is upon them.” (Leviticus 18:22). While the Quran does not have such an explicit declaration, traditional Islamic jurisprudence fully proscribes homosexual acts. Hindu jurisprudence has no equivalent bans on homosexual acts, and its law books do contain a recognition of a ‘third gender’, but most Hindus oppose it vigorously in practice.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Online Delivery: Adjusting to The New Normal</title>
      <link href="/Online-Delivery" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Online Delivery: Adjusting to The New Normal" />
      <published>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Online-Delivery</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Online-Delivery">&lt;p&gt;Imagine the times when in-store aisles were optimised for foot traffic and retail therapy, featuring better product discovery, impulse purchases and time spent in-store. The coronavirus pandemic has changed that almost overnight. Six months ago, on-demand home delivery was far from mainstream - a luxury for those willing to pay extra for delivery services and convenience, skewing towards young professionals in big cities. Now everyone is willing to order everything from household staples to ice cream on-demand. Stores, which were struggling for customer growth and retention are scrambling for more fulfilment capacity. Demand boom, which the experts believe is likely to persist even after the pandemic ends, makes it worthwhile to analyse the future of online marketplaces, and what opportunities this brings for the suppliers, the consumers, and the platform itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This market inversion has led to a growth of online delivery marketplaces, with even bigger market players in other segments pivoting their business strategies around home delivery. Delivery service marketplaces have inverted from demand-constrained to supply-constrained almost overnight, but new entrants in the delivery space have reportedly struggled with profits, reporting a boost in sales but thin margins. They claim that it is not terribly profitable, and it probably gets unprofitable with more orders. While many restaurants and supermarkets prefer the lower costs and hassle of having customers collect orders at stores, others see it as a threat to their existing customer relationships that could have been better taken care of, had the customers walked into the store. Online delivery was never a core part of these supplier’s revenue and made up only a small chunk of the total orders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issues and challenges that marketplaces face today are logistical and reputational, arising from increased demand and customer awareness rather than challenges arising from low consumer penetration and slim demand for services. Consumers are holding brands and companies to a higher standard than previously, favouring those perceived as doing more for society. Pre-crisis, a common complaint on the platforms was that drivers weren’t receiving enough orders. Now, those same drivers are overwhelmed with demand, and platforms have to figure out how to build product solutions to help stores balance their delivery loads. There have been inventory stockouts, closed stores, and supply chain disruptions due to COVID-19 — all while the customer service team has been inundated with order volume. That’s consistent with the experience of all mid-sized delivery platforms, and even that of Amazon. These platforms have had to switch their focus overnight and develop expertise around the new supply-side constraints. The bigger problem here is that many suppliers didn’t have the infrastructure set up to make delivery work at scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among all vociferous trumpets about ‘the demise of commuting’, ‘the death of retail’, and ‘the collapse of globalisation’, many executives have come to assume that everything will change accordingly when the recipe for survival is supposed to be a thorough transformation. The economic crisis does not necessarily spell the end of entire industries or companies but it does weed out business models that fail to pivot towards the new reality characterised by shorter value chains, remote work, social distancing, consumer introspection, and enhanced usage of technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, now is the time for marketplaces to help their suppliers invest in infrastructure and technology, and indulge in business practices that will enable them to compete in a world in which having a delivery sales presence is essential. Now is the time for them to shift their focus from customer acquisition and retention to investment in metrics for supporting retailer operations. Platforms can be a part of the supplier side transition which, in fact, is happening organically. With in-person retail restricted or outright eliminated, suppliers have been reimagining their store layouts and operations around online fulfilment and omnichannel retail, simultaneously leveraging marketplace platforms, a self-managed online presence, and traditional in-person sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can identify and share best practices around staffing and delivery processes, and provide technology solutions to help small businesses optimise their operations around delivery, with, for example, cloud-based inventory logs and modern point-of-sale systems. Marketplace platforms have vision into the whole market, which enables them to predict demand — an advantage they should use to the benefit of their suppliers. This could be helpful in forecasting when to schedule extra drivers on an hour-by-hour basis, and staffing driver teams in direct proportion to order volume. This can also increase capital efficiency by helping stores match inventory levels to predict future demand. Platforms can lower their tax rates to increase supplier participation — especially among chains and other established supplier networks. Food delivery marketplaces’ supplier-weighted cost structure may have worked when restaurants saw having a small stream of delivery orders as a promotional subsidy for in-person traffic — but it isn’t working in the current, in-person demand constrained marketplace environment. Likewise, some fees should be shifted over to the consumers, since they’re now the ‘long’ side of the market. In particular, it might make sense to institute per-order delivery fees, to encourage consumers to place large delivery orders instead of more frequent small ones, as well as to make it more valuable for a retailer to take an additional order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before COVID-19, a delivery service’s performance was mostly determined by convenience, speed and price. Now, by contrast, safety, availability and breadth of selection are the new priorities. Customers are placing bigger orders and are comfortable with longer lead times with ‘acceptable’ estimated time of arrival windows widening. Platforms also have the leeway to shift customer service efforts to prioritise responsiveness to retailers and allocate developer resources towards solving suppliers’ operational problems. All these solutions will help keep in place, exactly the right products on the supplier’s shelves. These improvements will benefit both parties but would require information sharing and communication on the part of the platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When suppliers make the best or most effective use of marketplace transactions, the consumer experience on the platform improves too — often due to increased availability, selection and price options. Overall, this results in much higher conversion rates: a customer with three stores and 1,000 items to choose from spends 67% more per session than a customer facing just one store with 300 items. Orders are processed more smoothly, and with fewer errors that will help translate fleeting customer relations into stronger consumer engagement post-crisis. Better and more optimised choices lead to more bargaining power in the hands of the customers, thereby increasing satisfaction and chances of application reuse. Bars and restaurants will eventually reopen and consumers will become comfortable shopping for goods in-person again but the supplier networks that marketplace platforms build will remain. When platforms invest in suppliers as partners, those suppliers will come out of the crisis stronger, improving the customer experience in the long run. It’s a three-way win — for suppliers, platforms and consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As worried consumers move to shop more online, choosing online platforms is an easy decision — with a click of the button, they can buy almost anything. But for sellers, doing business with them is a less straightforward proposition. Although partnering opens up access to more customers and offers operational efficiencies, brands risk leveraging power in favour of the platforms. Thus, they face an unavoidable dilemma — form the partnership and risk ceding profits, or eschew the partnership and forgo the operational cost savings and access to new customers. A big threat to these established brands is consumers’ increased willingness to experiment with different offerings during the crisis. Research suggests that consumers react badly even when the bad news extends beyond the company to its supply chain. They are more likely to believe that a company’s product is inferior in quality when there is a supply chain mishap, even when the product quality has nothing to do with the supply chain problem. They assume a product has decreased in quality whether the supply chain problems are related to an economic issue (like consistently low profits), a social issue (like racial discrimination in the hiring process), or an environmental issue (like polluting). Brands must, therefore, realise that pivots must be a lateral extension of the firm’s existing capabilities, cementing — not undermining — its strategic intent.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Mehul Goyal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Imagine the times when in-store aisles were optimised for foot traffic and retail therapy, featuring better product discovery, impulse purchases and time spent in-store. The coronavirus pandemic has changed that almost overnight. Six months ago, on-demand home delivery was far from mainstream - a luxury for those willing to pay extra for delivery services and convenience, skewing towards young professionals in big cities. Now everyone is willing to order everything from household staples to ice cream on-demand. Stores, which were struggling for customer growth and retention are scrambling for more fulfilment capacity. Demand boom, which the experts believe is likely to persist even after the pandemic ends, makes it worthwhile to analyse the future of online marketplaces, and what opportunities this brings for the suppliers, the consumers, and the platform itself.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lost Vision: The Many Failures of Masayoshi Son</title>
      <link href="/Lost-Vision" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lost Vision: The Many Failures of Masayoshi Son" />
      <published>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Lost-Vision</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lost-Vision">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;45 minutes, $45 billion, $1 billion per minute&lt;/em&gt;”, this is how SoftBank’s Chief Executive Officer Masayoshi Son, described his meeting with Saudi Arabia’s Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman. After this meeting, the Public Investment Fund of Saudi Arabia (PIF) became the largest investor in SoftBank’s outrageous $93 billion technology investment fund, the Vision Fund. This fund was unlike any other fund that anyone had ever seen before - &lt;em&gt;bigger, bolder, and better&lt;/em&gt;. The CEO’s exuberance was even highlighted in the size of the fund which was introduced. With this particular fund, Son wanted to make a presence in tech companies working in artificial intelligence, robotics and the Internet of Things. The fund did fulfil its purpose by giving the company a major share in some of the world’s ‘up and coming’ startups like OYO, Paytm, WeWork, Didi, Uber, Ola, Flipkart, along with 83 others. However, at what cost?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masayoshi Son has always been famous for his gut-led investment style, and it seems that he invests in people rather than in companies. One such person in whom Son invested was Alibaba founder, Jack Ma. Son himself said that Ma had no business plan, but he had “strong eyes”. However unconventional that might sound, it did turn out to be the most profitable investment of SoftBank till date. The investment in Alibaba, $20 million in 2000, turned into $60 billion when the company went public in September 2014. Masa expects every person in whom he invests to become the next Jack Ma. This strategy seemed to be working for the company as it reported a 62% return in the mid of 2019, after making 71 investments for a total of $64.2 billion, and the ride was supposed to be smooth from this point. On the flip side, the company has started facing hurdles and the return on the fund is negative 6%, compared with 62% just a year ago. The fund has lost more for the company than it has earned for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Son’s weakness for charismatic and flashy founders led him to invest in WeWork’s Adam Neumann. Through a combination of glamour and millennial charm, Adam was able to sell WeWrok to Son. It wasn’t even a tech company. Although Son was impressed, the company failed to impress financial analysts. People couldn’t understand the business model of WeWork and were reluctant to invest in it. Even after these speculations, the company decided to go public and as a result of this, their valuation came down to $3 billion from $47 billion in just a year. WeWork’s struggling finances, huge losses, hard-partying culture, and the CEO’s antics sank the ship. Eventually, SoftBank had to step in and buy the company. It came up with a $9.5 billion ‘rescue package’ and took over 80% of the shares. This takeover added dead weight to the company’s balance sheet as the onus to make the real estate firm profitable lay on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another such investment that might come to haunt SoftBank in the near future would be OYO. Son invested $1.5 billion in the company and asked the 26-year old founder, Ritesh Agarwal, to make it the world’s largest hotel operator by room count. The business model that worked so well in India wasn’t an obvious fit for the US and European markets, which already had well established, quality hotel chains. In a hasty attempt to expand outside India, OYO faced many logistical and technological challenges. These included double booking of rooms, failing to keep track of the keys, and reducing the rent of the landlords to mere pennies and taking days to fix these glitches. All these failures left the consumers as well as the vendors highly unsatisfied. OYO’s figures haven’t been impressive either, the company had revenue of $951 million for the fiscal year ending in March 2019, while losses surged six-fold to $335 million year-on-year. Furthermore, the young founder has further borrowed $2 billion, to buy out some investors. The loan has been personally guaranteed by Son, in a bizarre deal. The cash-pumping strategy has hampered the company’s natural course and put it on a path to become what many experts believe ‘the next WeWork’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the ongoing pandemic, tech companies have faced the most brutal brunt of the lockdowns across the globe. These unicorns have had to let go of people, lose consumers and face burgeoning costs. Uber, another major investment of SoftBank, has been one of the hardest hit. It had merely recovered from the saga of its poor-performing IPO that it had to face the impact of the virus. This has further added to the tensions of the Son-led company. The current scenario has dimmed the hopes of the CEO who was hoping for a $108 billion Vision Fund part-two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to tackle the mounting problems, the company has had to sell shares in Alibaba, its most valuable holding, to raise $11.5 billion. SoftBank is also likely to sell stock in its Japanese telecom unit SoftBank Corp and T-Mobile US Inc. Furthermore, the Japanese company also plans to spend up to ¥500 billion to buy back shares through March 2021, on top of an existing repurchase plan of the same size. That has helped to stabilise SoftBank shares giving them a boost of more than 75% from their low in March. The massive buyback remains the only good news for the shares. The company did not announce any dividend for the first time in its history this year and it has no plans to announce one next year as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separately, SoftBank said Jack Ma will step down as a director. Additionally, three new directors have been nominated. Son’s increasingly risky bets over the past few years coincided with departures from its board of some of its most outspoken members. With no famous outside directors left on SoftBank’s board, it’s not clear who is going to hold Son responsible anymore. It remains to be seen how that bodes for the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Undoubtedly, the Vision Fund has made massive losses for the company, it can still be argued that Masayoshi Son has faced worse after he made $70 billion in losses after the dot-com bubble burst and bounced back even stronger. However, to ensure that there is a comeback this time as well, the company needs to make some strategic changes. Instead of investing huge sums of money in these startups in their early stages and making them cash-burning machineries, they should let them grow according to their organic speed. The kind of ‘growth at all costs’ that comes with an asterisk with such large investments is what ruins a good company with a good business plan. Moreover, focussing on profitability rather than on growth solely would help in making the situation better for the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesson to learn here is that money can’t always buy success. The cheques that Son was blindly cutting for the companies were harming them more than they were helping. He was actually creating bigger and bigger bubbles, which came back to burst right in his face. Although, the enthusiastic CEO has reiterated several times during the past few months that he has learnt his lesson. It remains to be seen as to what he actually does to turn the situation around. Maybe, his self-confidence and stubbornness will help the company after all.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Amrit Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“45 minutes, $45 billion, $1 billion per minute”, this is how SoftBank’s Chief Executive Officer Masayoshi Son, described his meeting with Saudi Arabia’s Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman. After this meeting, the Public Investment Fund of Saudi Arabia (PIF) became the largest investor in SoftBank’s outrageous $93 billion technology investment fund, the Vision Fund. This fund was unlike any other fund that anyone had ever seen before - bigger, bolder, and better. The CEO’s exuberance was even highlighted in the size of the fund which was introduced. With this particular fund, Son wanted to make a presence in tech companies working in artificial intelligence, robotics and the Internet of Things. The fund did fulfil its purpose by giving the company a major share in some of the world’s ‘up and coming’ startups like OYO, Paytm, WeWork, Didi, Uber, Ola, Flipkart, along with 83 others. However, at what cost?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why are Gold Prices Soaring in the Midst of a Pandemic?</title>
      <link href="/Why-are-Gold-Prices-Soaring-in-the-Midst-of-a-Pandemic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why are Gold Prices Soaring in the Midst of a Pandemic?" />
      <published>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-are-Gold-Prices-Soaring-in-the-Midst-of-a-Pandemic</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-are-Gold-Prices-Soaring-in-the-Midst-of-a-Pandemic">&lt;p&gt;Want to invest your money and you are neither an equity person nor a mutual fund person and interest on fixed deposits is too low for you, what should you do? Of course, you should go and buy gold! Most people buy gold for making jewellery. It is also a place of investment for many. The precious metal has long been used by investors to hedge themselves against inflation. Considered a safe haven by those who don’t want to risk their savings in the stock market, it has always given positive returns to investors. Losing in the glittery metal market is far less likely but in the midst of a pandemic, every sort of investment seems to be too ‘dangerous’, so why are people still buying gold?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever there has been any economic crisis, people tend to stay away from the stock market because market crashes are highly unpredictable. We all know about the 2007-08 financial crisis, and how in every country there was reluctance in investing in the stock market. However, people who still had savings went right to the commodity exchange and bought gold. This was clearly visible from the fact that the rally in gold continued from 2007 to 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what we are witnessing in this current scenario with the coronavirus spreading all over the world and lockdown of economies leading to bankruptcy for many companies, people are pulling out their money from stocks and other financial instruments and buying bullion to park their money in safe investments. Exchange-Traded Funds (ETFs) have been piling up on gold reserves as well, which has more than made up for the domestic lack of demand. Demand for gold comes from another significant set of investors who tend to invest in real estate. The sector itself being in limbo due to the pandemic has forced such investors to invest in the yellow metal. Additionally, the metal is benefitting from the ultra-loose monetary policies being pursued by bankers and expectation that such a stance will tend to continue in the long run. Rising fiscal deficits and increasing debts are also contributing to the rising shift to gold. The fiscal policies adopted and the printing of more currency have led to inflation and have been the contributing factors in the current rally in gold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, central banks around the globe are regularly keeping a check on the economy and are providing liquidity. During the past few months, central banks too, have been buying gold and increasing their gold reserves in order to face any unforeseen circumstances. Central banks of China, Russia and India were the biggest buyers of gold in 2019, and many countries are still adding more to their coffers. This rally is expected to continue until we see any stability in the stock market and people feel safe to buy stocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gold prices have gone through the ceiling in the past few weeks and every banker has his/her own perception regarding the future price movement. All in all, it remains to be seen whether gold prices will continue to rise, or will gold lose its steam. However, the metal has yet again proven its mettle in trying times, when every other investment fails to provide returns, it keeps its investors happy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rachit Kumar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Want to invest your money and you are neither an equity person nor a mutual fund person and interest on fixed deposits is too low for you, what should you do? Of course, you should go and buy gold! Most people buy gold for making jewellery. It is also a place of investment for many. The precious metal has long been used by investors to hedge themselves against inflation. Considered a safe haven by those who don’t want to risk their savings in the stock market, it has always given positive returns to investors. Losing in the glittery metal market is far less likely but in the midst of a pandemic, every sort of investment seems to be too ‘dangerous’, so why are people still buying gold?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Policing the Police</title>
      <link href="/Policing-the-Police" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Policing the Police" />
      <published>2020-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Policing-the-Police</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Policing-the-Police">&lt;p&gt;Breonna Taylor, unarmed and asleep, was shot eight times after the police barged into her home at night suspecting a drug case that proved to be untrue. The policemen who were responsible for this were reassigned but remain free from charges of murder and still hold their positions in the police department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alton Sterling was shot six times after being tasered when he was selling his DVDs. The policeman responsible was fired, while his partner was suspended for a mere three days. They both have not faced any charges for his murder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen Clark was shot more than twenty times in his grandmother’s backyard because the police thought he was holding a gun. He was actually holding a phone. The police officer did not face charges, and Clark’s family was paid compensation money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just three of the innumerable stories of the victims of police brutality. I request you go through the &lt;em&gt;Know their names&lt;/em&gt; series by Alia Chughtai in Al Jazeera to know more about such stories. Their names deserve to be said aloud and remembered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such story is that of George Floyd. He was choked to death by officer Derek Chauvin who knelt on his neck for 8 minutes and 46 seconds, on suspicion of use of counterfeit $20 notes. George Floyd’s death proved to be a catalyst for pushing lawmakers into considering the vulnerability of the African-American community and the threat that excess power in the hands of police poses to the minority communities in the United States. The Police Reform Bill is a consequence of widespread public outrage and protests following the video of George Floyd’s murder. The video, while not being the only evidence of the brutal conduct by the police towards the African-American citizens, was the breaking point. The unprecedented yet extremely valid and long-awaited display of anger from the black community and their allies demanded consideration and attention of the lawmakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the police in the United States enjoys qualified immunity, allowing them to get away after committing crimes that led to the death of Breonna Taylor and Alton Sterling. The police do not get proper sensitivity and awareness training. Moreover, there are almost no checks and mechanisms to hold them accountable. In previous cases of police brutality, almost none of the officers faced criminal charges and received a mere slap on the wrist for their grievous offences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Police Reform Bill 2020 is aimed towards changing the aforementioned situations. The Bill bans maneuvers like chokeholds and ‘no-knock’ entry, which are the most common causes of death. It sets limits in the use of tear gas, mandates police officers to wear body cameras, and ensures dashboard cameras on police vehicles. This will act as a deterrent towards the use of excessive and violent methods of restraining people. It will limit the transfer of military-grade equipment to state and local police, and allow victims of police brutality to file a case against the police for using excessive force or for violating their constitutional rights. Sensitivity and racial awareness training programmes for police are also a part of the Bill amongst other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Bill is far from being adequate in ensuring police accountability. The new Bill limits qualified immunity but does not remove it from existence. The police will still continue to enjoy immunity in cases of police brutality until the situation is extreme. The lawmakers in many states argue that eliminating qualified immunity would result in frivolous cases and waste of funds. This only highlights the apathy of many lawmakers towards the civil rights and safety of their citizens. Additionally, the Bill does not de-fund or even reduce the funds allocated to the police. This emphasises the importance lawmakers place on the police regardless of their conduct and offences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Police Reform Bill having been passed in the house of representatives currently awaits being passed in the Senate, and still has a long way to go before it can become a law. The Bill remains stuck amidst the bipartisan politics, with the Republicans and Democrats fighting to gain the upper-hand in the Senate. States are voting towards passing the Bill with modifications while the Democrats and the Republicans continue to argue on the finer points of the Bill. The Connecticut Police Reform Bill was debated upon the entire night before it was passed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The significance of this Bill is not just limited to holding the police accountable and safeguarding the civil rights and liberty of the African-American and other minority communities, it is also an acknowledgement of the atrocities faced by the African-American community. The bill is a step towards recognising the names of the forgotten victims and a promise to do better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public’s reaction to this Bill is majorly positive. While they continue to advocate for defunding the police and completely removing qualified immunity, they are willing to listen, ready to fight for a better future, and acknowledge this Bill as a step towards the same. Sadly, yet expectedly, there also exists a faction of the public, thankfully small, that is not pleased with the idea of holding the police accountable. So far, their silly cries of “Blue Lives Matter” have been relatively ignored, and have faced criticism and backlash from their fellow citizens. Yet this faction, no matter how small, still indicates that America has a long way to go. The fight towards racism begins from this Bill, yet it would not do to ignore the root cause of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The responsibility for George Floyd’s death does not lie solely with the police. It also lies with the system that provided the perpetrators support, and with the system that was willing to ignore their actions. It lies in the lack of checks and balances on the police and most importantly, it lies with the people who spread the ideas of bigotry and hatred. They may not have been the one pressing the knee to an innocent man’s neck, but they were the ones who stood by, watched, and did nothing.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Breonna Taylor, unarmed and asleep, was shot eight times after the police barged into her home at night suspecting a drug case that proved to be untrue. The policemen who were responsible for this were reassigned but remain free from charges of murder and still hold their positions in the police department.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Football for Global Influence</title>
      <link href="/Football-for-Global-Influence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Football for Global Influence" />
      <published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Football-for-Global-Influence</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Football-for-Global-Influence">&lt;p&gt;I have a big question for all the football fans reading this article. What do Schalke 04, Red Star Belgrade, and Zenit have in common? I believe it’s difficult to answer this question so let me give you a hint: it’s something printed on their jerseys. Still didn’t get it? It’s the ‘Gazprom’ logo on their jerseys. From being on the jerseys of major football teams from various countries in Europe, it also features on the sidelines and advertisements during games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logo belongs to Gazprom, a Russian natural gas company. Logo sponsorships are normal in football. Teams make money offering jersey spaces to sponsors selling things like credit cards, cars and cell phones but Gazprom isn’t like most sponsors, i.e. private companies with products that football fans can buy. Instead, it’s a company owned by the Russian government that makes money selling natural gas to foreign countries. Yet, it’s everywhere in European football. So, if football fans can’t buy what they are selling, why is Gazprom spending millions to sponsor football games? The answer is part of a larger story that’s changing the sport of football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d7/Major_russian_gas_pipelines_to_europe.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/russiangaspipes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia has the world’s largest natural gas reserves and most of them are located in the Arctic gas fields controlled by Gazprom. The company is led by Alexey Miller, a close ally of Russian President Vladimir Putin. Since 2005, the Russian government has owned a majority stake in Gazprom. This means that the company profits are under Putin’s control, and gas sellers, along with oil, account for around 50% of Russia’s annual budget. Eastern European countries like Finland, Estonia, Lithuania, Poland, Slovakia depend on Russian oil for 75-100% of their natural gas needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we move further towards the West, the countries’ dependence begins to fall. At the end of the 20th century, Germany represented the biggest opportunity for Gazprom. German Chancellor Gerhard Schroeder had announced plans to phase out coal and nuclear power which meant Germany needed more natural gas to maintain their energy supply. Gazprom wanted to give it to them but there was a problem. To get to Germany, Russia’s gas needed to pass through pipelines crossing other countries that charged Gazprom transport fees. And most of them went through Ukraine, a country that has complicated political relations with Russia. Today, Ukraine still charges upwards of $3 billion each year to pump gas to Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, starting back in 2005, Russia began working on a strategy to bypass Ukraine and ship their gas directly to Western Europe through the Nord Stream pipeline, a route through the Baltic sea straight to Northern Germany. In late 2005, Gazprom was in the final stages of financing the project and Germany’s Chancellor was preparing for an election. During his time in the office, Gerhard Schroeder had become friendly with Putin, and critics in Germany were increasingly concerned about the Russian leader’s growing influence. Just a few weeks before the election, Schroeder met with Putin signing an agreement officially approving the pipeline. Two months later, he lost his re-election. However, by March, he found a new job overseeing Gazprom’s pipeline to Germany. It also came out that, before leaving office Schroeder had approved a secret Gazprom loan that provided over a billion euros to finance the project. This led to Gazprom’s big project being called a “story of scandal, corruption, and the creeping influence of Russia in Germany”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However in 2006 the story changed, Gazprom signed a deal to sponsor the German soccer team FC Schalke 04. At the time Schalke’s finances were worrying the team officials and Gazprom’s sponsorship provided money that the team desperately needed. At a press conference announcing the deal, a Gazprom chairman stated that Schalke’s connections with the German energy sector were the reason behind their decision to become its sponsors. Schalke played in Gelsenkirchen, a town in Germany’s Ruhr Valley, where much of the country’s energy industry is based. It’s also near the town of Rehden, a hub for pipelines to the rest of Europe and home to western Europe’s largest natural gas storage facilities. Schalke wasn’t Gazprom’s first football deal. The year before, they had bought a controlling stake in a team on the other end of the Nord Stream route: the Russian team Zenit St Petersburg. Gazprom’s investment made Zenit a major force in football. Two years after taking control, Zenit won their first-ever league championship. They’ve been able to sign expensive foreign stars like Axel Wetzel and Hulk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, as Gazprom logos were revealed around Schalke’s stadium, German headlines were hailing the Russian gas giant for pumping millions into the German team and hence, creating a positive image in German minds for the company. And over the next few years, the Gazprom logo would become a team symbol displayed at Schalke’s games and printed on official merchandise. Schalke also won a championship in 2011. By then, Nord Stream had been completed and it had started pumping gas to Germany. There was also another struggling team whose jerseys started featuring Gazprom’s logo, the Serbian team: Red Star Belgrade. Red Star was about $25 million in debt when Gazprom signed to become their jersey sponsor and again, there was also another pipeline: the south stream would have bypassed Ukraine by going directly through Serbia to Southern Europe. That project closed in 2014, but Gazprom further increased its access to Europe by building Nord Stream 2, a second pipeline doubling the amount of gas flowing from Russia to Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years in addition to its pipeline empire, Gazprom has also expanded its influence over global football to include energy partnership with Chelsea football club, UEFA Champions League, and the sport’s most famous tournament: the FIFA World Cup. These sponsorships have made Gazprom’s logo familiar to not only the fans in Europe but across the world. It also did something which boosted the Russian economy. Russia became the world’s largest exporter of natural gas and provided for almost half of all the natural gas supply to Europe becoming a major player in the energy field in Europe. This created a reliance of other countries on Russia for the supply of natural gas, power and energy generation. The strategy adopted by Russia turned out to be a ‘game-changer’ and as of 2019, Russia supplied 199 billion cubic meters of natural gas to Europe. The oil-and-gas sector accounted for 16% of GDP, 52% of federal budget revenues, and over 70% of total exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, Russia is the skipper when it comes to energy supply and generation in Europe and other countries are learning from their example. As the example of Gazprom shows, having prominent soccer sponsorship offers a way around bad publicity by winning approval on the field. Many companies such as Qatar Airways, Etihad Airways and Emirates Airlines have started sponsoring major teams in Europe such as AS Roma, Manchester City and AC Milan respectively. As an avid football supporter, I feel like it’s a big opportunity: their money helps teams win major championships and tournaments, but it is changing the sport itself. Now that it has become common to see a German team sponsored by Russia’s gas company facing off against an Italian team sponsored by Dubai’s state-owned airline, it is starting to seem like the field is hosting two competitions at once: a match between the two teams and larger play for a foreign influence that continues long after the final whistle.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I have a big question for all the football fans reading this article. What do Schalke 04, Red Star Belgrade, and Zenit have in common? I believe it’s difficult to answer this question so let me give you a hint: it’s something printed on their jerseys. Still didn’t get it? It’s the ‘Gazprom’ logo on their jerseys. From being on the jerseys of major football teams from various countries in Europe, it also features on the sidelines and advertisements during games.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">China’s Five Finger Plan: In Full Steam Ahead</title>
      <link href="/China-Five-Finger-Plan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="China’s Five Finger Plan: In Full Steam Ahead" />
      <published>2020-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/China-Five-Finger-Plan</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/China-Five-Finger-Plan">&lt;p&gt;Making a new addition to the long list of multifarious border disputes, China has now declared the Eastern region of Bhutan to be yet another victim of its ‘expansionist’ policy. The Sino-Bhutanese border dispute ranges back to 1984, since then the two countries have held 24 rounds of talks to resolve their border issues. Until now, the disputed region only consisted of the Central and Western sections of the boundary. The talks between the two were delimited to three areas of dispute, Jakarlung and Pasamlung Areas in Northern Bhutan and one region in the West. Thus, China’s new claim on the Sakteng region of East Bhutan was a bolt out of the blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Five Finger Plan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the annexation of Tibet by the People’s Republic of China, the Chinese leaders elucidated upon its Five Finger plan. In accordance with this, the Chinese believe Tibet to be the ‘palm’ with Ladakh, Nepal, Bhutan, Arunachal Pradesh, and Sikkim being the five ‘fingers’. China’s aggression in the Himalayas and its attempt at changing the status quo has been nothing but a clear adumbration of how China is all set to bring this plan into action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where does Bhutan come into the Picture?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With historically tense diplomatic ties, Bhutan’s border with Tibet has never been officially recognised. In 1959, in &lt;em&gt;A Brief History of China&lt;/em&gt;, China released a map that portrayed numerous territories of Bhutan as a part of China under the five finger plan. Later in the year, the annexation of Tibet by the People’s Republic of China began. During this process, The People’s Liberation Army (PLA) also captured several territories under the Bhutan region. These included regions of Gartok, Darchen, and several other monasteries that had been under the Bhutanese administration for more than 300 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tensions began to escalate in 1961 with the invasion of Chinese soldiers and herdsmen. A tensed Bhutanese nation imposed extensive border controls and a cross-border trade embargo in retaliation to the increasing incursions. In order to build a safety net in response to the rising tensions between the two nations, Bhutan began building strong diplomatic and extensive military ties with India. Thus, the strong Indo-Bhutanese ties were attributed to the deteriorating Sino-Bhutanese diplomatic ties. Though this soon turned into neutrality from Bhutan’s end with India’s defeat in the Sino-Indian war of 1962, as the loss put forth a question on India’s ability to defend Bhutan from the Chinese wrath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward to 1988, when the tensions between the two nations further escalated, Bhutan and China signed a bilateral peace agreement based on the Panchsheel Treaty (a treaty-based on diplomatic principles of India and China to ensure non-interference in others’ internal affairs and respect for each other’s territorial unity integrity and sovereignty). This treaty was later violated by the Chinese authorities on account of building roads in regions under the territory of Bhutan. This was later settled in 2002 with an interim agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Doklam Standoff&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plateau and a trijunction between China, India and Bhutan became the cause of a major uproar in 2017. Doklam was never a source of contention or interest. Even during the prior independence talks of border settlement between the British and the Chinese, neither of them placed any significance on the plateau. But, since 1962, Beijing has made numerous claims over the territory. What sprouted this sudden and ardent interest in the plateau was not the plateau region itself, but the area surrounding it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Siliguri corridor often referred to as the ‘chicken’s neck’ is the Achilles heel of India. The corridor is of vital importance to India as it connects the Indian mainland to its north-eastern counterparts. Doklam’s proximity to the corridor is what makes the trijunction strategically immensely significant. Along with this, the plateau is surrounded by the Chumbi Valley, where the Chinese are militarily disadvantaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, China has been undertaking innumerable measures by building a network of roads to provide a smooth flow to increase its military presence in the region. Doklam, hence, would provide commanding access to both the Siliguri corridor and the Chumbi Valley. To ensure proper security to the region, when the Chinese officials came with a target to extend its road networks southwards in Doklam, in regions under the authorisation of Bhutan, India rose to action to stop the construction. The construction of the road directly violated the terms of the 1988 peace agreement. This led to a two-month-long standoff in the region. In August 2017, a mutual disengagement on the plateau was undertaken to bring an end to the face-off in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the border tensions and issues have long continued, Chinese claim over the Sakteng valley is a new amendment to the long list. But out of all the disputed territory between the Sino-Bhutan authorities, the Sakteng valley constitutes to be the single largest of them all, comprising 11% of the region under the Bhutanese administration. Some believe that this claim is a threat to India, pertaining to the current Sino-Indian tensions in the Ladakh region. The Sakteng valley borders the Indian state of Arunachal Pradesh, which is claimed in its entirety by the Chinese Government. Others also believe that this claim is targeted as a threat to Bhutan to tip the scale on other disputed land areas including Doklam in favour of China in the 25th round of border talks long after the 2017 standoff. It remains to be seen what happens in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does it mean for India?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the world’s attention is diverted towards dealing with the COVID-19 pandemic, China is using this strategic time and is spreading its arm like an octopus: both in the Himalayan region and the South China sea. With neighbouring Nepal already an ally to China now and out of India’s orbit, India cannot afford to let loose its ties with Bhutan. With the growing attention of China towards the mountain kingdom, India is at a turmoil to be caught up in a bigger strategic ploy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tanisha Sukhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Making a new addition to the long list of multifarious border disputes, China has now declared the Eastern region of Bhutan to be yet another victim of its ‘expansionist’ policy. The Sino-Bhutanese border dispute ranges back to 1984, since then the two countries have held 24 rounds of talks to resolve their border issues. Until now, the disputed region only consisted of the Central and Western sections of the boundary. The talks between the two were delimited to three areas of dispute, Jakarlung and Pasamlung Areas in Northern Bhutan and one region in the West. Thus, China’s new claim on the Sakteng region of East Bhutan was a bolt out of the blue.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
