<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/trending/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2022-01-30T22:37:47+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/trending/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Healthcare Mantra for This Decade: Actionable, Accessible, Affordable!</title>
      <link href="/The-Healthcare-Mantra-for-This-Decade-Actionable-Accessible-Affordable" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Healthcare Mantra for This Decade: Actionable, Accessible, Affordable! " />
      <published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Healthcare-Mantra-for-This-Decade-Actionable-Accessible-Affordable-</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Healthcare-Mantra-for-This-Decade-Actionable-Accessible-Affordable">&lt;p&gt;While I was lazing around on a Sunday evening after spending the day watching some pointless TV show on Netflix, which would never further my intellect at any particular matter, my father pointedly remarked to me, ‘Health is Wealth! Go exercise your muscles for once.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That statement truly struck my brain muscles. I decided to exercise those for a change since I was too much of a sloth to get out and workout. It dawned upon me that the statement was absolutely bogus. Wonder why? In my limited experience of 23 years on this planet, it has often become vividly clear to me that indeed the reverse is true, ‘Wealth is Health.’ To die a death of peace, without gasping for oxygen, while sitting on a wheelchair, waiting outside a hospital for a bed and a cylinder, you would have needed (on an average) a few hundred thousand rupees back in May 2021 in New Delhi.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want to know the median household income in India? Well, it’s a handsome round off of about fifty thousand rupees per annum. Which begs the ultimate question, why is basic healthcare so expensive?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With socio-health inequalities being a raging issue of debate for most forums amidst the Covid era, the discussion has always started and ended with the incompetency of the government and the neglect of the public health infrastructure, respectively. Do I agree with that? Not in its entirety. But to delve deeper into how this mechanism works, it would be prudent for one to revisit the consequential economic steppingstones to such inequities around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Health Inequity, not Inequality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to address that health inequality should not be diluted into the mix of health inequity. That’s simply because health inequality is generally a by-product of disorders which kick in with older age, and often are hereditary, or genetic problems. For example, my mother’s forlorn battle with &lt;em&gt;Rheumatoid arthritis&lt;/em&gt; is one such inequality that couldn’t be helped.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the health inequity that the modern world faces so rampantly today, is different from my mother’s story. Health inequity often stems from a valley surrounded by the challenging mountains of income, physical environment, social support inequalities. Those are few of the major inequalities which isolate the socio-economically disadvantaged population into facing the burnt of a forged inequity arising from the disbalanced opportunities across our demographies. You literally must climb up the socio-economic mountain to attain the accessibility of such refined services and thus, better your chances at living a healthier and longer life. For example, research shows that asthma hospitalisations are over 1.5 times more in the lower-income neighbourhoods compared to the higher-income ones. Now this combined with our improved understanding of climate change, the ill-effects of bad air quality, and the ever-so-frequent cyclones, and floods, it is no joke when we finally realise that the physical and economic confinements of an individual lead them to bearing significant disadvantages in a health battle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Health is a Right, not a Commodity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, as an Economics major (which I am not sure if I should pride myself in), I cannot help but look at the notions of demand, supply, and utility in all aspects of life. They start with me succumbing to the urges of buying more affordable clothing from regular labour law abusers to deliberating if it's the healthcare policies which are truly at fault or not.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the situation from a strict Demand-Supply angle, I concede to the concept that government intervention is useless and give into the argument “let the forces of market play out to acquire efficiency”. Ah yes, ‘efficiency,’ the ‘It’ word of Economics. It is supposed to solve all our problems, right? Well, again not entirely true, just like every other ‘rational’ answer in economics which is based on an unstable jenga of numerous assumptions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allow me to explain the jargon of ‘efficiency’ to you. &lt;em&gt;Economic efficiency&lt;/em&gt; is defined as a state where all goods and factors of production are distributed or productively allocated amongst the consumers to eliminate any chances of waste. However, what the jargon often leaves behind is the inability of efficiency to incorporate all players in the market. For example, if someone has more money at his or her disposal, then that person is perfectly capable and encouraged to acquire the scarce resource at a higher price while defeating another without those means. You know the saddest truth of healthcare? It is a Scarce Resource.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the statement “let the market play out” along with the assumption that the intervention of government only leads to market failures (through monopolistic behaviour) is ridiculous and a sure shot at worsening the pickle that we already find ourselves in. Therefore, it is time to set the record straight, “Affordable healthcare is my Right, no matter if I am poor or rich, today or tomorrow.”&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big Pharma: Saints or Satan?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter the number of conventions, agreements and vigilance of health authorities, the pharmaceutical companies can not stop making billions off the pain of the global citizens. Again, going back to the demand and supply argument. The demand and supply should meet at equilibrium to fix the market prices. But it is a little different for drugs, especially life-saving ones. People simply don't have the option to refuse the exorbitant prices of drugs such as Hepatitis C or HIV, which gives the companies a massive leverage to fix prices as per their whims and profit margin targets.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, let’s talk about Turing Pharmaceuticals and the CEO Martin Shkreli who hiked the price of an essential drug, &lt;em&gt;Daraprim&lt;/em&gt;, by 5,000% (from $13.50 to $750). This begs the question: Can buying licences to public funded research and innovations, and then hiking prices to make the public pay for it, even legal? According to the laws, mostly it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview when asked about what he would have liked to do differently, Shkreli went on to answer that “Healthcare prices are inelastic, I could have raised it higher and made more profits for my shareholders.” This one statement sums up the motive with which big pharma operates; they are not responsible for their patients, they are answerable to their shareholders and investors.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unrivalled power in the lobbying halls of the American Congress and parliaments around the world has made big pharma the ultimate power player when it comes to deciding if we even have a shot at surviving. Even though they operate within the realms of humanity, they possess the strings to make us all dance on their commands. Recurring malaria symptoms due to a sudden lack of affordability to &lt;em&gt;Daraprim&lt;/em&gt; is not fateful, it is planned.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Public-Private Partnerships: A farce or a force?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strategic intervention of public policy in the healthcare sector is the need of the hour. In recent years, governments, international organisations and even private players have conceded to the argument that equality of opportunity should be the moral foundation to build our policies. The World Bank, for instance, has started using a Human Opportunity Index as one of the relevant indicators to assess social, human and economic development aspects.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many government initiatives, for example the Midday Meal Scheme in India, is geared towards ensuring social and educational protection routed through the maintenance of nutritional standards for children hailing from lower income communities. As deeply deliberated by economists Amartya Sen and Jean Dreze, nutritional inadequacies can often lead to future health problems, thus, making the poor vulnerable in a competitive labour market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, socio-health protection can stimulate economic growth for developing nations and be a key factor to combat a macroeconomic crisis. But the main problem, when seen through the lenses of developing countries, is often the laid-back attitude of the public sector projects which when coupled with a bar of fiscal deficit, can be difficult obstacles in planning a long-term inclusive plan. To bring in the private players into this mold would mean that it would contribute to capital accumulation and investment, risk management and offer diverse potential advantages to indirect stakeholders through multiplier effects. Therefore, bringing in private funding with the main hold of government in steering things to the correct conclusion, pricing, can be the way forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having suggested the inclusion of private players into the mold of healthcare, I must address the problem of private players slowly taking the charge to invest and maximise profits through expensive medication (inelastic demand). Therefore, the onus must lie upon the government to take action, diversify research, be responsible and accountable to the public at large, and be strict with the pricing models.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Am I Satisfied or Worried?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I would say, I am ‘impressed’. Don’t get me wrong, the statistics of COVID-19 cases unfolding while I cough my heart out to write these soulful words, has me chilled to my bones. But the honest truth is that the pandemic is here to stay. Yes, we already have a delta plus omicron variant and booster jabs available but it is not that which has impressed me (I am not a supporter of dystopia, in fact I am already dreading the advent of “oxicron”). I am impressed by the fact that our newsrooms, classrooms, zoom meetings and daily chats are now (more than ever before) focused on ‘health.’ It is probably for the first time in history that we have realised how much our lives are worth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one of my favourite dialogues from the movie &lt;em&gt;Troy&lt;/em&gt; (2004), the character Odysseus goes on to tell Achilles that “War is young men dying, and old men talking.” In my opinion, this battle against Covid has proven yet again that neglect in the healthcare systems will cost us lives at all fronts, no matter how boldly the wise, grey haired intellectuals deliberate on fixing the situation without adequate expenditures. The advent of COVID-19 with the surges in internet usage around the globe has made interaction possible between people living in different continents. The debate of healthcare affordability is now no longer limited to the fancy parliament halls and the elite think tanks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, the global citizens, have proudly taken a step forward to progress the discussions on affordable healthcare, equitable healthcare, climate change and so much more. The GDP figures are not impressive any more. In fact they are on a dedicated downhill safari. What will it take to impress us? An increase in human development and opportunity indices, for starters, would be good. The discussions on our physical and mental health would be even better.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier (pre-Covid) the politics in my country India would generally revolve around two parties trying to degrade one another with quirkier rhetoric. Now, I am not denying that those rhetorics weren’t fun. They are an absolute amaze, both for meme and conversation purposes. Who in the world would not enjoy a wholesome trash talk between the ‘defenders of faith’. It is terribly fun to watch. But it is not the essence of our existence as politics made us believe in. Our population will only truly prosper when everyone has equal opportunities and access. The world has finally started demanding what is truly theirs, and now we are debating these topics in our homes. Home, where the general scope of discussion was limited to taking trash out and gossiping about neighbours. That is steep progress according to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I am hopeful when I say that I am looking forward to this decade’s unfolding. This will no doubt be one of the most ‘efficient,’ remarkable and decisive decades of human history. This time the war will not be fought on the enemy lines, rather it will be fought within our homes as we sanitise our hands and take those jabs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 has brought more than 19 months of caged life. So much so that going out without a mask feels alien to me at this point. But what it also helped us realise is that being healthy (and ‘negative’) is golden. Therefore, socio-health protection, extensive public health research funding and awareness is required if we are to be the ‘defenders of human existence’ and strike down these ultra effective viruses and other anomalies. By being ultra productive in building infrastructure for it and investing in pertinent research, maybe we will have a shot at it. But above all what is to be appreciated amid all of this chaos, is the resilience of humankind in not giving up. So, three cheers to humanity at large!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      
        <category term="humanity" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">While I was lazing around on a Sunday evening after spending the day watching some pointless TV show on Netflix, which would never further my intellect at any particular matter, my father pointedly remarked to me, ‘Health is Wealth! Go exercise your muscles for once.’ That statement truly struck my brain muscles. I decided to exercise those for a change since I was too much of a sloth to get out and workout. It dawned upon me that the statement was absolutely bogus. Wonder why? In my limited experience of 23 years on this planet, it has often become vividly clear to me that indeed the reverse is true, ‘Wealth is Health.’ To die a death of peace, without gasping for oxygen, while sitting on a wheelchair, waiting outside a hospital for a bed and a cylinder, you would have needed (on an average) a few hundred thousand rupees back in May 2021 in New Delhi.&amp;nbsp; Want to know the median household income in India? Well, it’s a handsome round off of about fifty thousand rupees per annum. Which begs the ultimate question, why is basic healthcare so expensive? With socio-health inequalities being a raging issue of debate for most forums amidst the Covid era, the discussion has always started and ended with the incompetency of the government and the neglect of the public health infrastructure, respectively. Do I agree with that? Not in its entirety. But to delve deeper into how this mechanism works, it would be prudent for one to revisit the consequential economic steppingstones to such inequities around the world. Health Inequity, not Inequality It is important to address that health inequality should not be diluted into the mix of health inequity. That’s simply because health inequality is generally a by-product of disorders which kick in with older age, and often are hereditary, or genetic problems. For example, my mother’s forlorn battle with Rheumatoid arthritis is one such inequality that couldn’t be helped.&amp;nbsp; However, the health inequity that the modern world faces so rampantly today, is different from my mother’s story. Health inequity often stems from a valley surrounded by the challenging mountains of income, physical environment, social support inequalities. Those are few of the major inequalities which isolate the socio-economically disadvantaged population into facing the burnt of a forged inequity arising from the disbalanced opportunities across our demographies. You literally must climb up the socio-economic mountain to attain the accessibility of such refined services and thus, better your chances at living a healthier and longer life. For example, research shows that asthma hospitalisations are over 1.5 times more in the lower-income neighbourhoods compared to the higher-income ones. Now this combined with our improved understanding of climate change, the ill-effects of bad air quality, and the ever-so-frequent cyclones, and floods, it is no joke when we finally realise that the physical and economic confinements of an individual lead them to bearing significant disadvantages in a health battle. Health is a Right, not a Commodity Now, as an Economics major (which I am not sure if I should pride myself in), I cannot help but look at the notions of demand, supply, and utility in all aspects of life. They start with me succumbing to the urges of buying more affordable clothing from regular labour law abusers to deliberating if it's the healthcare policies which are truly at fault or not.&amp;nbsp; Looking at the situation from a strict Demand-Supply angle, I concede to the concept that government intervention is useless and give into the argument “let the forces of market play out to acquire efficiency”. Ah yes, ‘efficiency,’ the ‘It’ word of Economics. It is supposed to solve all our problems, right? Well, again not entirely true, just like every other ‘rational’ answer in economics which is based on an unstable jenga of numerous assumptions.&amp;nbsp; Allow me to explain the jargon of ‘efficiency’ to you. Economic efficiency is defined as a state where all goods and factors of production are distributed or productively allocated amongst the consumers to eliminate any chances of waste. However, what the jargon often leaves behind is the inability of efficiency to incorporate all players in the market. For example, if someone has more money at his or her disposal, then that person is perfectly capable and encouraged to acquire the scarce resource at a higher price while defeating another without those means. You know the saddest truth of healthcare? It is a Scarce Resource.&amp;nbsp; Therefore, the statement “let the market play out” along with the assumption that the intervention of government only leads to market failures (through monopolistic behaviour) is ridiculous and a sure shot at worsening the pickle that we already find ourselves in. Therefore, it is time to set the record straight, “Affordable healthcare is my Right, no matter if I am poor or rich, today or tomorrow.”&amp;nbsp; Big Pharma: Saints or Satan? No matter the number of conventions, agreements and vigilance of health authorities, the pharmaceutical companies can not stop making billions off the pain of the global citizens. Again, going back to the demand and supply argument. The demand and supply should meet at equilibrium to fix the market prices. But it is a little different for drugs, especially life-saving ones. People simply don't have the option to refuse the exorbitant prices of drugs such as Hepatitis C or HIV, which gives the companies a massive leverage to fix prices as per their whims and profit margin targets.&amp;nbsp; For instance, let’s talk about Turing Pharmaceuticals and the CEO Martin Shkreli who hiked the price of an essential drug, Daraprim, by 5,000% (from $13.50 to $750). This begs the question: Can buying licences to public funded research and innovations, and then hiking prices to make the public pay for it, even legal? According to the laws, mostly it is. In an interview when asked about what he would have liked to do differently, Shkreli went on to answer that “Healthcare prices are inelastic, I could have raised it higher and made more profits for my shareholders.” This one statement sums up the motive with which big pharma operates; they are not responsible for their patients, they are answerable to their shareholders and investors.&amp;nbsp; The unrivalled power in the lobbying halls of the American Congress and parliaments around the world has made big pharma the ultimate power player when it comes to deciding if we even have a shot at surviving. Even though they operate within the realms of humanity, they possess the strings to make us all dance on their commands. Recurring malaria symptoms due to a sudden lack of affordability to Daraprim is not fateful, it is planned.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Public-Private Partnerships: A farce or a force? Strategic intervention of public policy in the healthcare sector is the need of the hour. In recent years, governments, international organisations and even private players have conceded to the argument that equality of opportunity should be the moral foundation to build our policies. The World Bank, for instance, has started using a Human Opportunity Index as one of the relevant indicators to assess social, human and economic development aspects.&amp;nbsp; Many government initiatives, for example the Midday Meal Scheme in India, is geared towards ensuring social and educational protection routed through the maintenance of nutritional standards for children hailing from lower income communities. As deeply deliberated by economists Amartya Sen and Jean Dreze, nutritional inadequacies can often lead to future health problems, thus, making the poor vulnerable in a competitive labour market. Therefore, socio-health protection can stimulate economic growth for developing nations and be a key factor to combat a macroeconomic crisis. But the main problem, when seen through the lenses of developing countries, is often the laid-back attitude of the public sector projects which when coupled with a bar of fiscal deficit, can be difficult obstacles in planning a long-term inclusive plan. To bring in the private players into this mold would mean that it would contribute to capital accumulation and investment, risk management and offer diverse potential advantages to indirect stakeholders through multiplier effects. Therefore, bringing in private funding with the main hold of government in steering things to the correct conclusion, pricing, can be the way forward. Having suggested the inclusion of private players into the mold of healthcare, I must address the problem of private players slowly taking the charge to invest and maximise profits through expensive medication (inelastic demand). Therefore, the onus must lie upon the government to take action, diversify research, be responsible and accountable to the public at large, and be strict with the pricing models.&amp;nbsp; Am I Satisfied or Worried? Well, I would say, I am ‘impressed’. Don’t get me wrong, the statistics of COVID-19 cases unfolding while I cough my heart out to write these soulful words, has me chilled to my bones. But the honest truth is that the pandemic is here to stay. Yes, we already have a delta plus omicron variant and booster jabs available but it is not that which has impressed me (I am not a supporter of dystopia, in fact I am already dreading the advent of “oxicron”). I am impressed by the fact that our newsrooms, classrooms, zoom meetings and daily chats are now (more than ever before) focused on ‘health.’ It is probably for the first time in history that we have realised how much our lives are worth.&amp;nbsp; In one of my favourite dialogues from the movie Troy (2004), the character Odysseus goes on to tell Achilles that “War is young men dying, and old men talking.” In my opinion, this battle against Covid has proven yet again that neglect in the healthcare systems will cost us lives at all fronts, no matter how boldly the wise, grey haired intellectuals deliberate on fixing the situation without adequate expenditures. The advent of COVID-19 with the surges in internet usage around the globe has made interaction possible between people living in different continents. The debate of healthcare affordability is now no longer limited to the fancy parliament halls and the elite think tanks.&amp;nbsp; We, the global citizens, have proudly taken a step forward to progress the discussions on affordable healthcare, equitable healthcare, climate change and so much more. The GDP figures are not impressive any more. In fact they are on a dedicated downhill safari. What will it take to impress us? An increase in human development and opportunity indices, for starters, would be good. The discussions on our physical and mental health would be even better.&amp;nbsp; Earlier (pre-Covid) the politics in my country India would generally revolve around two parties trying to degrade one another with quirkier rhetoric. Now, I am not denying that those rhetorics weren’t fun. They are an absolute amaze, both for meme and conversation purposes. Who in the world would not enjoy a wholesome trash talk between the ‘defenders of faith’. It is terribly fun to watch. But it is not the essence of our existence as politics made us believe in. Our population will only truly prosper when everyone has equal opportunities and access. The world has finally started demanding what is truly theirs, and now we are debating these topics in our homes. Home, where the general scope of discussion was limited to taking trash out and gossiping about neighbours. That is steep progress according to me. Therefore, I am hopeful when I say that I am looking forward to this decade’s unfolding. This will no doubt be one of the most ‘efficient,’ remarkable and decisive decades of human history. This time the war will not be fought on the enemy lines, rather it will be fought within our homes as we sanitise our hands and take those jabs.&amp;nbsp; COVID-19 has brought more than 19 months of caged life. So much so that going out without a mask feels alien to me at this point. But what it also helped us realise is that being healthy (and ‘negative’) is golden. Therefore, socio-health protection, extensive public health research funding and awareness is required if we are to be the ‘defenders of human existence’ and strike down these ultra effective viruses and other anomalies. By being ultra productive in building infrastructure for it and investing in pertinent research, maybe we will have a shot at it. But above all what is to be appreciated amid all of this chaos, is the resilience of humankind in not giving up. So, three cheers to humanity at large!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Getting Our Sh*t Together: Wetlands and the Future of Sanitation</title>
      <link href="/Getting-Our-Sh-T-Together-Wetlands-and-the-Future-of-Sanitation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting Our Sh*t Together: Wetlands and the Future of Sanitation" />
      <published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Getting-Our-Sh-T-Together-Wetlands-and-the-Future-of-Sanitation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Getting-Our-Sh-T-Together-Wetlands-and-the-Future-of-Sanitation">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Human civilisation is rightly considered to be a departure from the natural order. No other species on this planet manipulates its external environment to the extent that we do for our needs. Yet, it stands to reason that we thrive most when we work &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; the environment instead of &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; it. Nowhere is this more true than in the realm of sewage disposal. It may seem odd to suggest that our economic and environmental salvation lies in eco-friendly potty disposal. But as it happens, getting our sh*t together is more than a mere metaphor when it comes to avoiding both ecological collapse and facilitating basic sanitation for all.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The biggest living proof of how nature is our friend in matters of sewage treatment is found in the East Calcutta Wetlands. The East Calcutta Wetlands are a vast network of marshland that cover an area of 125 sq km lying to the East of the city of Calcutta, India. These wetlands were named and discovered by a man named Dhrubajyoti Ghosh, a humble sanitation engineer, who then went on to win an award from the UN due to his assiduous efforts to conserve the wetlands.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The wetlands are, by all means, a marvel, as explained by Ray Chaudhuri Et al, in an article in the &lt;em&gt;OnLine Journal of Biological Sciences&lt;/em&gt;. The waterways and channels of the wetlands receive heaps of sewage and other solid waste (about one-third of the sewage produced by a city of over ten million) which are then deposited in setting ponds. In the shallow settling ponds, the waste is broken down by the sun's UV rays and the algae and plankton that are abound in the marshland. Water hyacinth processes some of the heavy metals in the purification process. The byproduct of this naturally-processed sewage is the nutrient-rich water and soil, which is used for extensive fish farming and vegetable farming. Precisely, the wetlands provide around 150 tons of vegetables daily and around 10,500 tons of fish every year. This is a great boon for Calcutta, its Bengali population is famously pescitarian and around much of the vegetable produce from the wetlands is supplied to the city. These activities also provide direct employment to more than 50 thousand people.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It is important to note that the wetlands are the result of years of assiduous human efforts, they aren't just nature's gift presented on a platter. Originally, the region consisted of large salt water lakes between the Bidyadhari river in the East and the Hooghly river in the West. The Bidyadhari river does not exist any longer due to the fact that the region became a dumping ground for the waste coming from the Second City of the Empire during the days of the British Raj and also post Indian Independence. Great strides were taken by a certain Bholanath Sen, who leased tracts of land in the marshes in 1879 and began growing vegetables using a unique landform which had alternate rows of garbage and water bodies. Thereafter, in the 1930's a gentleman named Bibhuti Bhushan Ghosh, innovated a perennial system of wastewater fisheries and in 1985 a comprehensive map of the marshes was published. Legal protections were put in place in 1992, when the High Court at Calcutta issued an order prohibiting the reclamation of the wetlands, which was followed by a law passed in 2006 that set up a conservation authority.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Thus, unlike the many stories of humanity being an enemy of the planet, the wetlands represent a concerted human attempt at preserving ecological balance. Not only that, the East Calcutta Wetlands are a beacon for humanity, guiding us to a future that might not involve climate collapse.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Man-made wetlands have now been recognised as a cheap and extremely effective means for dealing with effluents and waste generated by urbanisation. The first most striking feature of this organic sewage treatment mechanism is how little it costs. A book titled ‘&lt;em&gt;Treatment Wetlands’ &lt;/em&gt;published as far back as 1996 estimated that to treat 3,786 cubic meters of sewage per day, a conventional sewage treatment plant would cost $4.12 million for construction and then require $156,000 as yearly maintenance costs. However, for treating the same amount, a constructed wetland would require only $3.6 million as construction costs and a mere $45,000 as yearly maintenance costs. Recently, a sewage treatment plant in Arizona was replaced by a constructed wetland which cost a minuscule $3.5 million, compared to the estimated $625 million that would have been spent on upgrading the said plant.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Of course, all of this comes with a catch, we need a lot more land to construct a wetland than a conventional sewage treatment plant. For treating 3,786 cubic metres a day in a wetland, as mentioned above, one would need 90 acres of land, whereas a treatment plant would occupy a mere five acres of land. This problem would be multiplied by the fact that much expenditure would have to be incurred by authorities to acquire such lands and compensate the owners. But there is an opportunity presented by this challenge.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The use of constructed wetlands for aquaculture and vegetable farming can bring about serious economic rewards to any region. Non-arable land of low value can be transformed into fertile areas that bring prosperity to local communities as in the case of the East Calcutta Wetlands, thus increasing the asset profile and revenue-generation capacity of the authorities acquiring such land. In turn, this can help such authorities raise finances far more easily for funding projects that are proper investments rather than mere sewage treatment facilities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;That apart, there is the conservation of biodiversity that follows as a direct consequence of constructing wetlands. It is estimated that the East Calcutta Wetlands harbour around 104 plant species, 40 bird species, 20 important types of mammals, many rare endangered reptiles, and more than 52 varieties of fish, of which 34 species are endangered. It is well-known that habitat destruction due to human activity poses perhaps the greatest threat to Earth's flora and fauna. A constructed wetland bucks this trend. It's usage and making involves human activity that brings about habitat conservation and enrichment, thereby contributing significantly to environmental conservation in general. By making constructed wetlands an essential feature of urbanisation, we can turn our cities into supporters of the environment instead of being a drain on the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Indeed, constructed wetlands can be sensitive to climatic conditions, unlike traditional sewage treatment plants. Floods, droughts, changes in soil salinity, cyclones, etc., can really affect the viability of a man-made wetland. However, even that drawback is a blessing in disguise. The wetland can act as the first line of defence against such weather events, absorbing the worst of the impact, leaving cities unharmed in many ways and circumstances.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Finally, wetlands can be a great source of commercial utility. They can be beautified to create marvelous recreational spaces. In fact, the Environmental Protection Agency gives excruciating details on the kind of plant species that can be added to beautify man-made swamps in a document that lays out a plan for constructing wetlands. The flora and fauna can generate tourism-related revenue. The lakes can be used for boating and other light water sports. In other words, our shit can literally be used to make life more fun.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Keeping all of that in mind, it seems almost bizarre that such an easy and brilliant solution for one of humanity's fundamental problems is not utilised more often. Sewage swamps and wetlands are meant for many more cities and towns than my home city of Calcutta. If constructed scientifically and strategically, they can truly assist in sustainable development whilst also alleviating poverty and saving communities that may have been damaged due to the denigration of soil quality and loss of livelihoods. It is hoped that this article will stir the public imagination and induce readers to bat for an ingenious solution to a perennial problem.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      
        <category term="humanity" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Human civilisation is rightly considered to be a departure from the natural order. No other species on this planet manipulates its external environment to the extent that we do for our needs. Yet, it stands to reason that we thrive most when we work with the environment instead of against it. Nowhere is this more true than in the realm of sewage disposal. It may seem odd to suggest that our economic and environmental salvation lies in eco-friendly potty disposal. But as it happens, getting our sh*t together is more than a mere metaphor when it comes to avoiding both ecological collapse and facilitating basic sanitation for all.&amp;nbsp; The biggest living proof of how nature is our friend in matters of sewage treatment is found in the East Calcutta Wetlands. The East Calcutta Wetlands are a vast network of marshland that cover an area of 125 sq km lying to the East of the city of Calcutta, India. These wetlands were named and discovered by a man named Dhrubajyoti Ghosh, a humble sanitation engineer, who then went on to win an award from the UN due to his assiduous efforts to conserve the wetlands.&amp;nbsp; The wetlands are, by all means, a marvel, as explained by Ray Chaudhuri Et al, in an article in the OnLine Journal of Biological Sciences. The waterways and channels of the wetlands receive heaps of sewage and other solid waste (about one-third of the sewage produced by a city of over ten million) which are then deposited in setting ponds. In the shallow settling ponds, the waste is broken down by the sun's UV rays and the algae and plankton that are abound in the marshland. Water hyacinth processes some of the heavy metals in the purification process. The byproduct of this naturally-processed sewage is the nutrient-rich water and soil, which is used for extensive fish farming and vegetable farming. Precisely, the wetlands provide around 150 tons of vegetables daily and around 10,500 tons of fish every year. This is a great boon for Calcutta, its Bengali population is famously pescitarian and around much of the vegetable produce from the wetlands is supplied to the city. These activities also provide direct employment to more than 50 thousand people.&amp;nbsp; It is important to note that the wetlands are the result of years of assiduous human efforts, they aren't just nature's gift presented on a platter. Originally, the region consisted of large salt water lakes between the Bidyadhari river in the East and the Hooghly river in the West. The Bidyadhari river does not exist any longer due to the fact that the region became a dumping ground for the waste coming from the Second City of the Empire during the days of the British Raj and also post Indian Independence. Great strides were taken by a certain Bholanath Sen, who leased tracts of land in the marshes in 1879 and began growing vegetables using a unique landform which had alternate rows of garbage and water bodies. Thereafter, in the 1930's a gentleman named Bibhuti Bhushan Ghosh, innovated a perennial system of wastewater fisheries and in 1985 a comprehensive map of the marshes was published. Legal protections were put in place in 1992, when the High Court at Calcutta issued an order prohibiting the reclamation of the wetlands, which was followed by a law passed in 2006 that set up a conservation authority.&amp;nbsp; Thus, unlike the many stories of humanity being an enemy of the planet, the wetlands represent a concerted human attempt at preserving ecological balance. Not only that, the East Calcutta Wetlands are a beacon for humanity, guiding us to a future that might not involve climate collapse.&amp;nbsp; Man-made wetlands have now been recognised as a cheap and extremely effective means for dealing with effluents and waste generated by urbanisation. The first most striking feature of this organic sewage treatment mechanism is how little it costs. A book titled ‘Treatment Wetlands’ published as far back as 1996 estimated that to treat 3,786 cubic meters of sewage per day, a conventional sewage treatment plant would cost $4.12 million for construction and then require $156,000 as yearly maintenance costs. However, for treating the same amount, a constructed wetland would require only $3.6 million as construction costs and a mere $45,000 as yearly maintenance costs. Recently, a sewage treatment plant in Arizona was replaced by a constructed wetland which cost a minuscule $3.5 million, compared to the estimated $625 million that would have been spent on upgrading the said plant.&amp;nbsp; Of course, all of this comes with a catch, we need a lot more land to construct a wetland than a conventional sewage treatment plant. For treating 3,786 cubic metres a day in a wetland, as mentioned above, one would need 90 acres of land, whereas a treatment plant would occupy a mere five acres of land. This problem would be multiplied by the fact that much expenditure would have to be incurred by authorities to acquire such lands and compensate the owners. But there is an opportunity presented by this challenge.&amp;nbsp; The use of constructed wetlands for aquaculture and vegetable farming can bring about serious economic rewards to any region. Non-arable land of low value can be transformed into fertile areas that bring prosperity to local communities as in the case of the East Calcutta Wetlands, thus increasing the asset profile and revenue-generation capacity of the authorities acquiring such land. In turn, this can help such authorities raise finances far more easily for funding projects that are proper investments rather than mere sewage treatment facilities.&amp;nbsp; That apart, there is the conservation of biodiversity that follows as a direct consequence of constructing wetlands. It is estimated that the East Calcutta Wetlands harbour around 104 plant species, 40 bird species, 20 important types of mammals, many rare endangered reptiles, and more than 52 varieties of fish, of which 34 species are endangered. It is well-known that habitat destruction due to human activity poses perhaps the greatest threat to Earth's flora and fauna. A constructed wetland bucks this trend. It's usage and making involves human activity that brings about habitat conservation and enrichment, thereby contributing significantly to environmental conservation in general. By making constructed wetlands an essential feature of urbanisation, we can turn our cities into supporters of the environment instead of being a drain on the same.&amp;nbsp; Indeed, constructed wetlands can be sensitive to climatic conditions, unlike traditional sewage treatment plants. Floods, droughts, changes in soil salinity, cyclones, etc., can really affect the viability of a man-made wetland. However, even that drawback is a blessing in disguise. The wetland can act as the first line of defence against such weather events, absorbing the worst of the impact, leaving cities unharmed in many ways and circumstances.&amp;nbsp; Finally, wetlands can be a great source of commercial utility. They can be beautified to create marvelous recreational spaces. In fact, the Environmental Protection Agency gives excruciating details on the kind of plant species that can be added to beautify man-made swamps in a document that lays out a plan for constructing wetlands. The flora and fauna can generate tourism-related revenue. The lakes can be used for boating and other light water sports. In other words, our shit can literally be used to make life more fun.&amp;nbsp; Keeping all of that in mind, it seems almost bizarre that such an easy and brilliant solution for one of humanity's fundamental problems is not utilised more often. Sewage swamps and wetlands are meant for many more cities and towns than my home city of Calcutta. If constructed scientifically and strategically, they can truly assist in sustainable development whilst also alleviating poverty and saving communities that may have been damaged due to the denigration of soil quality and loss of livelihoods. It is hoped that this article will stir the public imagination and induce readers to bat for an ingenious solution to a perennial problem.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Rise of the Far Right in Europe</title>
      <link href="/The-Rise-of-the-Far-Right-in-Europe" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rise of the Far Right in Europe" />
      <published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Rise-of-the-Far-Right-in-Europe</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Rise-of-the-Far-Right-in-Europe">&lt;p&gt;For decades in our world, the far-right and Nazism have been almost synonymous. Horrific visuals of trains carrying naked Jews (or for the pop-culture loving generation of ours: the red jacket from &lt;em&gt;Schindler’s List&lt;/em&gt;) are nothing but absolute reminders of the terrible turns things can take if propaganda and falsehoods are left unchecked. Such ideologies are malignant tumours and deserve nothing but condemnation. While this has been the norm of moral and ethical conduct (even legal in the case of Eastern Europe), the world also has seen words like Neo-Nazism come into existence. The worst part is that it is not just Germany but the entire world, and particularly Europe, that is witnessing a rise in far-right activities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with the basics, what exactly is the political representation of the ‘far-right’? Far-right ideologies are political philosophies that call for unification, ultra-nationalism and nativist cultures and seek the exodus of migrants, they are against inter-racial unions and believe in the supremacy of their people against others. When the Allied powers annihilated the Axis powers and their unjust crimes came to light, everyone believed that the re-occurrence of such a strong belief in the far-right would be unlikely. However, smaller far-right units have existed ever since the end of the Second World War. Recently, such parties have seen a huge rise in their popularity and have gained a foothold in legislatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Central to this issue is the spilling out of migrants from the Middle East. “Europe is becoming another Islamic Caliphate”, claimed the then Interior Minister of Italy, Matteo Salvini, in a rally with thousands of people back in 2019. Soon, we saw the Prime Minister of Hungary Viktor Orban claiming in public that “Islamic invaders have reached Europe”.&amp;nbsp; More prominent problems can be seen in the patterns of how such groups have reached decision-making bodies. One such example is the Golden Dawn, a political outfit based out of Greece. In the 2019 elections, it was the seventh largest political party and once had around 7.0% acceptance around Greece, setting a very dangerous precedent. Fortunately enough, the outfit was banned, and its leadership was imprisoned in 2020.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a trend in Europe as political parties such as PEGIDA and AfD (Germany), the British National Party, Jobbik (Hungary), National Rally (France) have seen massive crowds being drawn to their events, their candidates have become lead runners to key positions in governments and policy formulation platforms, and access to social media has further intensified their anti-migration, anti-Islamic and, in general, fascist overtones and increased their reach multiple times. Apart from outfits openly cheering fascist literature, one can also observe a shift in preference for far-right politics in the general mindset of people, possibly due to higher unemployment (due to COVID-19) and rapidly rising anti-establishment thoughts. The COVID-19 pandemic has also provoked the general population to align themselves with far-right ideologies due to anti-lockdown sentiment, protests, and mandatory COVID-19 vaccinations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numerous studies and surveys have positively concluded that most people who associate with this violent form of right-wing politics are unemployed, anti-vaxxers and generally have shown idealisation of the Nazi Party. It is very concerning to note that many people have openly praised Adolf Hitler during anti-lockdown protests.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Governments have not been mute spectators in this either. The German government recently cracked down on Alternative for Germany (AfD), a political outfit known for its Euro-scepticism, anti-Islamic positions and anti-migrant stances. Interestingly, AfD has 82 seats in the Federal Parliament of Germany, so one can imagine the political opposition and accusations that the German government faced as it placed a prominent political opposition under strict surveillance for being an extremist outfit. Shortly after major media outlets reported the surveillance, courts blocked the move. Likewise, governments across Europe are taking significant actions to destroy these movements and preserve their cultural balance.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can see how the rhetoric of ultra-nationalism is on the rise and how elections are becoming an affair of migrant scepticism and a centre-stage show where migrants are the bait. Policies of selectively leaving Muslims out, changing the way they live by forcing them to integrate into western society and trying to change their religious texts institutionally are more spillovers of the entire crises that probably started with an inflammatory speech. Policymaking and such discourses in public light are intimately connected.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Union needs to accept the multiple changes that have led to the rise in far-right movements of Europe and decisively work with constituent governments to take corrective action. The threat of the far-right resurgence is evolving as many outfits are gaining a stronghold in rural and ill-kept areas of Europe. This transitional shift is very similar to how Hitler brainwashed millions: by giving them hope for a better and more equal future. The COVID-19 pandemic is easily comparable to World War I in this situation, where it feeds the people of the republic anti-establishment thoughts which they seek through far-right extremist outfits who champion themselves as their saviours and have a common enemy to pin the blame on (Jews back then, Muslims and migrants now). The political landscape is very volatile right now and a back-slide of Europe into its darkest age will only lead to spillovers to other countries in both political and economic ways.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shreyansh Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For decades in our world, the far-right and Nazism have been almost synonymous. Horrific visuals of trains carrying naked Jews (or for the pop-culture loving generation of ours: the red jacket from Schindler’s List) are nothing but absolute reminders of the terrible turns things can take if propaganda and falsehoods are left unchecked. Such ideologies are malignant tumours and deserve nothing but condemnation. While this has been the norm of moral and ethical conduct (even legal in the case of Eastern Europe), the world also has seen words like Neo-Nazism come into existence. The worst part is that it is not just Germany but the entire world, and particularly Europe, that is witnessing a rise in far-right activities.&amp;nbsp; Starting with the basics, what exactly is the political representation of the ‘far-right’? Far-right ideologies are political philosophies that call for unification, ultra-nationalism and nativist cultures and seek the exodus of migrants, they are against inter-racial unions and believe in the supremacy of their people against others. When the Allied powers annihilated the Axis powers and their unjust crimes came to light, everyone believed that the re-occurrence of such a strong belief in the far-right would be unlikely. However, smaller far-right units have existed ever since the end of the Second World War. Recently, such parties have seen a huge rise in their popularity and have gained a foothold in legislatures. Central to this issue is the spilling out of migrants from the Middle East. “Europe is becoming another Islamic Caliphate”, claimed the then Interior Minister of Italy, Matteo Salvini, in a rally with thousands of people back in 2019. Soon, we saw the Prime Minister of Hungary Viktor Orban claiming in public that “Islamic invaders have reached Europe”.&amp;nbsp; More prominent problems can be seen in the patterns of how such groups have reached decision-making bodies. One such example is the Golden Dawn, a political outfit based out of Greece. In the 2019 elections, it was the seventh largest political party and once had around 7.0% acceptance around Greece, setting a very dangerous precedent. Fortunately enough, the outfit was banned, and its leadership was imprisoned in 2020.&amp;nbsp; This has been a trend in Europe as political parties such as PEGIDA and AfD (Germany), the British National Party, Jobbik (Hungary), National Rally (France) have seen massive crowds being drawn to their events, their candidates have become lead runners to key positions in governments and policy formulation platforms, and access to social media has further intensified their anti-migration, anti-Islamic and, in general, fascist overtones and increased their reach multiple times. Apart from outfits openly cheering fascist literature, one can also observe a shift in preference for far-right politics in the general mindset of people, possibly due to higher unemployment (due to COVID-19) and rapidly rising anti-establishment thoughts. The COVID-19 pandemic has also provoked the general population to align themselves with far-right ideologies due to anti-lockdown sentiment, protests, and mandatory COVID-19 vaccinations.&amp;nbsp; Numerous studies and surveys have positively concluded that most people who associate with this violent form of right-wing politics are unemployed, anti-vaxxers and generally have shown idealisation of the Nazi Party. It is very concerning to note that many people have openly praised Adolf Hitler during anti-lockdown protests.&amp;nbsp; Governments have not been mute spectators in this either. The German government recently cracked down on Alternative for Germany (AfD), a political outfit known for its Euro-scepticism, anti-Islamic positions and anti-migrant stances. Interestingly, AfD has 82 seats in the Federal Parliament of Germany, so one can imagine the political opposition and accusations that the German government faced as it placed a prominent political opposition under strict surveillance for being an extremist outfit. Shortly after major media outlets reported the surveillance, courts blocked the move. Likewise, governments across Europe are taking significant actions to destroy these movements and preserve their cultural balance.&amp;nbsp; One can see how the rhetoric of ultra-nationalism is on the rise and how elections are becoming an affair of migrant scepticism and a centre-stage show where migrants are the bait. Policies of selectively leaving Muslims out, changing the way they live by forcing them to integrate into western society and trying to change their religious texts institutionally are more spillovers of the entire crises that probably started with an inflammatory speech. Policymaking and such discourses in public light are intimately connected.&amp;nbsp; The European Union needs to accept the multiple changes that have led to the rise in far-right movements of Europe and decisively work with constituent governments to take corrective action. The threat of the far-right resurgence is evolving as many outfits are gaining a stronghold in rural and ill-kept areas of Europe. This transitional shift is very similar to how Hitler brainwashed millions: by giving them hope for a better and more equal future. The COVID-19 pandemic is easily comparable to World War I in this situation, where it feeds the people of the republic anti-establishment thoughts which they seek through far-right extremist outfits who champion themselves as their saviours and have a common enemy to pin the blame on (Jews back then, Muslims and migrants now). The political landscape is very volatile right now and a back-slide of Europe into its darkest age will only lead to spillovers to other countries in both political and economic ways.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lights, Camera, Generalise!</title>
      <link href="/Lights-Camera-Generalise" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lights, Camera, Generalise!" />
      <published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Lights-Camera-Generalise</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lights-Camera-Generalise">&lt;p&gt;While going through my Google feed one day, I came across this&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indianexpress.com/article/entertainment/bollywood/meenakshi-sundareshwar-inauthentic-stereotypical-take-on-tamil-culture-sanya-malhotra-abhimanyu-dassani-7616835/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;in &lt;em&gt;The Indian Express &lt;/em&gt;about the review of the recent film,&lt;em&gt; Meenakshi Sundareshwar&lt;/em&gt;. Because I hail from Rajasthan, I could relate to what the author was trying to say. Whenever I introduce myself as a Rajasthani, certain visuals pop up in the mind of the listener; vast stretches of sand, men wearing colourful turbans, and women in sarees with ‘&lt;em&gt;matkas&lt;/em&gt;’ on their heads living in&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;kutcha&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;houses, and even though a large part of Rajasthan is similar to that, these visuals are not representative of the entire state. I too have played the role of ‘the listener’ in a lot of cases and had my fair share of stereotypes about places, people and cultures, merely based on their depiction in movies or series. If suppose, I mention Tamils; “loud exaggerated accents, dark-skinned villains, gajras, jhumkis, curd, aiyoo, and religiously inclined vegetarian folks without a sense of humour” (as pointed out by the article) is what comes to my mind. Indeed because this is how I have seen Tamils; whether it was Deepika Padukone portraying&amp;nbsp;Meenama&amp;nbsp;in&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Chennai Express&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;or Shiv Subramaniam acting as Alia’s father in&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Two States&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, what is the big deal about Bollywood stereotyping practically everything? The current value of the film industry is approximately ₹183 billion which explains the number of people who are influenced by the content of Bollywood films. Thus, Hindi cinema shapes the perception of a vast majority of Indians and for a lot of us, what we see in movies ends up being how we think things are. Moreover, the problem is not just limited to forming perceptions about different places; in fact, this is not even the tip of the iceberg. The real problem comes into picture when these perceptions start fuelling stereotypes that already exist in society. For example, women in Bollywood have always been portrayed as ‘damsels in distress’ whose apparent role is to have a love-hate relationship with the protagonist, and all her life problems get solved post their union. The little to no screen time given to female actresses in Hindi cinema except for brief appearances in a song, here and there, is a metaphor of the way women are positioned in the real society. The film&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Ranjhanaa&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;went overboard with the idea of Sonam Kapoor’s character in the film agreeing to meet the protagonist, her stalker, because he was ‘consistent’ in his ways and there was no love involved. The cliché storyline wherein the protagonist does everything to get the attention of the girl while the girl constantly ignores him but eventually gives in (because he is the protagonist) drives home the idea that girls actually want to say 'yes' but due to her &lt;em&gt;sanskari &lt;/em&gt;(traditional) values, she refrains from it. This portrayal absolutely undermines the concept of consent wherein the 'no' is lost in translation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the generalisations don’t stop here. Not just promoting sexist stereotypes, there are multiple instances (even in recent times) where Bollywood has promoted body shaming. The female actresses, with their perfect figure, end up setting unrealistic expectations about looks and body amongst the general population. Further, Bollywood seems to fuel these misconceptions of beauty when they appoint people who look a little different than the idealistic standards of beauty as the ‘side characters’ in films. These characters are seldom portrayed to have any loving relationships. This ends up communicating the idea that if you do not have a perfect body or glowing skin, you would have a hard time finding partners. Even Bollywood songs are heavily inclined towards appreciating the beauty of a ‘gora’ or ‘gori,’ which literally translates to white in English. “&lt;em&gt;Goriya Chura Na Mera Jiya” &lt;/em&gt;(O White Woman&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;don't steal my heart), &lt;em&gt;“Chura Ke Dil Mera Goriya Chali” &lt;/em&gt;(The White Woman has stolen my heart) are just a few cases of such lyrics&lt;em&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;Such stereotypes transcend onto races and religions as well. Whether it was 2000’s&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Phir Bhi Dil Hai Hindustani&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;or 2008’s&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Chandni Chowk To China,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;the weird obsession to make an mainland Indian actor have the ‘East Asian look’ by taping their eyes to slant them is the ugly truth of an industry consumed by over a billion people. Even people belonging to the LGBTQ+ community, especially homosexual men, are portrayed as having feminine features. Most movies stereotypically mock the way they walk and dress which was pretty evident in movies like&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Student Of The Year&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;and&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Dostana.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it might not be a big deal for many, it does hurt a community at large, and makes their attempts at fighting stigmas in society prove futile. There is no denying that Bollywood is evolving. The increasing number of heavyweight female characters who come in all sizes, shapes and color, sparks hope for a fairer, aware and more appropriate Bollywood culture in the future. However, Bollywood still has an immense population of stereotypes buried in its backyard, more so because it is the easiest route to singling out a community (generally minorities) or driving home the ideas that the majority in a country identifies with.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before parting ways, here is another&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indianexpress.com/article/trending/trending-in-india/tweeple-are-calling-out-stereotypes-in-movies-and-its-a-must-read-5528242/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; which I found while researching for my piece. It is hilarious but sadly true; and yes, I am still a Rajasthani, but I do not carry&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;‘matkas&lt;/em&gt;!’&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shiksha Mody</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">While going through my Google feed one day, I came across this&amp;nbsp;article&amp;nbsp;in The Indian Express about the review of the recent film, Meenakshi Sundareshwar. Because I hail from Rajasthan, I could relate to what the author was trying to say. Whenever I introduce myself as a Rajasthani, certain visuals pop up in the mind of the listener; vast stretches of sand, men wearing colourful turbans, and women in sarees with ‘matkas’ on their heads living in&amp;nbsp;kutcha&amp;nbsp;houses, and even though a large part of Rajasthan is similar to that, these visuals are not representative of the entire state. I too have played the role of ‘the listener’ in a lot of cases and had my fair share of stereotypes about places, people and cultures, merely based on their depiction in movies or series. If suppose, I mention Tamils; “loud exaggerated accents, dark-skinned villains, gajras, jhumkis, curd, aiyoo, and religiously inclined vegetarian folks without a sense of humour” (as pointed out by the article) is what comes to my mind. Indeed because this is how I have seen Tamils; whether it was Deepika Padukone portraying&amp;nbsp;Meenama&amp;nbsp;in&amp;nbsp;Chennai Express&amp;nbsp;or Shiv Subramaniam acting as Alia’s father in&amp;nbsp;Two States. However, what is the big deal about Bollywood stereotyping practically everything? The current value of the film industry is approximately ₹183 billion which explains the number of people who are influenced by the content of Bollywood films. Thus, Hindi cinema shapes the perception of a vast majority of Indians and for a lot of us, what we see in movies ends up being how we think things are. Moreover, the problem is not just limited to forming perceptions about different places; in fact, this is not even the tip of the iceberg. The real problem comes into picture when these perceptions start fuelling stereotypes that already exist in society. For example, women in Bollywood have always been portrayed as ‘damsels in distress’ whose apparent role is to have a love-hate relationship with the protagonist, and all her life problems get solved post their union. The little to no screen time given to female actresses in Hindi cinema except for brief appearances in a song, here and there, is a metaphor of the way women are positioned in the real society. The film&amp;nbsp;Ranjhanaa&amp;nbsp;went overboard with the idea of Sonam Kapoor’s character in the film agreeing to meet the protagonist, her stalker, because he was ‘consistent’ in his ways and there was no love involved. The cliché storyline wherein the protagonist does everything to get the attention of the girl while the girl constantly ignores him but eventually gives in (because he is the protagonist) drives home the idea that girls actually want to say 'yes' but due to her sanskari (traditional) values, she refrains from it. This portrayal absolutely undermines the concept of consent wherein the 'no' is lost in translation. Unfortunately, the generalisations don’t stop here. Not just promoting sexist stereotypes, there are multiple instances (even in recent times) where Bollywood has promoted body shaming. The female actresses, with their perfect figure, end up setting unrealistic expectations about looks and body amongst the general population. Further, Bollywood seems to fuel these misconceptions of beauty when they appoint people who look a little different than the idealistic standards of beauty as the ‘side characters’ in films. These characters are seldom portrayed to have any loving relationships. This ends up communicating the idea that if you do not have a perfect body or glowing skin, you would have a hard time finding partners. Even Bollywood songs are heavily inclined towards appreciating the beauty of a ‘gora’ or ‘gori,’ which literally translates to white in English. “Goriya Chura Na Mera Jiya” (O White Woman don't steal my heart), “Chura Ke Dil Mera Goriya Chali” (The White Woman has stolen my heart) are just a few cases of such lyrics. Such stereotypes transcend onto races and religions as well. Whether it was 2000’s&amp;nbsp;Phir Bhi Dil Hai Hindustani&amp;nbsp;or 2008’s&amp;nbsp;Chandni Chowk To China,&amp;nbsp;the weird obsession to make an mainland Indian actor have the ‘East Asian look’ by taping their eyes to slant them is the ugly truth of an industry consumed by over a billion people. Even people belonging to the LGBTQ+ community, especially homosexual men, are portrayed as having feminine features. Most movies stereotypically mock the way they walk and dress which was pretty evident in movies like&amp;nbsp;Student Of The Year&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;Dostana.&amp;nbsp; While it might not be a big deal for many, it does hurt a community at large, and makes their attempts at fighting stigmas in society prove futile. There is no denying that Bollywood is evolving. The increasing number of heavyweight female characters who come in all sizes, shapes and color, sparks hope for a fairer, aware and more appropriate Bollywood culture in the future. However, Bollywood still has an immense population of stereotypes buried in its backyard, more so because it is the easiest route to singling out a community (generally minorities) or driving home the ideas that the majority in a country identifies with.&amp;nbsp; Before parting ways, here is another&amp;nbsp;article which I found while researching for my piece. It is hilarious but sadly true; and yes, I am still a Rajasthani, but I do not carry&amp;nbsp;‘matkas!’</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Metaverse and the Need for Virtual Realities - Startling or Convivial?</title>
      <link href="/The-Metaverse-and-the-Need-for-Virtual-Realities-Startling-or-Convivial" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Metaverse and the Need for Virtual Realities - Startling or Convivial?" />
      <published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Metaverse-and-the-Need-for-Virtual-Realities-Startling-or-Convivial</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Metaverse-and-the-Need-for-Virtual-Realities-Startling-or-Convivial">&lt;p&gt;As the world still battles a pandemic, it remains imperative to understand that no matter in which condition man finds himself in, technology moves as it does: in leaps and bounds. It is often said that&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;it is not that we use technology, we live technology. &lt;/em&gt;Recently, Facebook unveiled new technology that may change the course of social media and connectivity to an all-new level. News forums call it&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;the internet of the future;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;it claims to transport people into a whole new world of human interactions. Mark Zuckerberg’s 81-minute video essay on the long run of human interactions that culminated with the rebranding of Facebook as Meta, this term has been effervescent this year. Leaders in technology, recreation and fashion have hurried to stake their claim on it, although few appear to agree on what it precisely is. The vital factor is that the technology is coming sooner than one thought it would.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversations regarding the metaverse cut back the sensation of FOMO (Fear of Missing Out). Neal Stephenson in his 1992 novel, “Snow Crash” coined the term metaverse, and it has recently been hurled into wide and varied use. For most enthusiasts, Zuckerberg’s idea may take several years to formulate completely. However, some believe that simpler versions of the metaverse could already exist. Recently, at the Web Summit, the CEO of Magic Leap, Peggy Johnson said, “We're&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;in the early stages of the metaverse, in some ways&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;”&amp;nbsp;Furthermore, Chris Cox, Meta's Chief Product Officer, who spoke to the BBC on the day of the rebranding, claimed that metaverse will change the way we use the internet as a whole and not simply imply a big change for the company alone. His words, &quot;Technology often starts in lower resolution versions of what it becomes.&quot;&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtual reality-based experiences have already been in play since the emergence of games like Pokemon Go. Such technologies have already been used by the medical personnel when undertaking complex surgeries involving conjoined twins. Companies like Roblox have welcomed the notion of metaverse as they have been using a platform similar to this. However, what remains a significant concern is how effectively Facebook will be able to make this platform safe, user friendly, and keep the public discourse moving. The company has claimed to have been working on a set of protocols that will ensure the aforementioned features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most gaming companies, who have used virtual realities in some form or the other, seem to look forward to Meta coming up with a form of virtual reality that would also define their work and procedure. Many others stand against the idea because they believe that what Meta plans to bring forth is dangerous and manipulative. They believe that it fails to ensure that the platform will not be misused, like how other, simpler social media platforms were in the past decades.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of Facebook's earliest investors, Roger McNamee has branded Facebook’s plans for a metaverse&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;as&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;dystopian&lt;/em&gt;. He said, &quot;It is a bad idea, and the fact we are all sitting and looking at this like it is normal, should be alarming to everyone. Facebook should not be allowed to create a dystopian metaverse,” and went on to say “there's no way that a regulator or policymaker should be allowing Facebook to operate there [in the metaverse] or get into cryptocurrencies.&quot;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr McNamee became an opponent of Meta as he began to see more misinformation on the platform. He said he is not convinced that the metaverse would be safe with Mark Zuckerberg. He again said that “Facebook should have lost the right to make its own choices. A regulator should be there giving pre-approval for everything they do. The amount of harm they've done is incalculable.&lt;em&gt;”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What must be noted is that the metaverse, with its wide usage, will bring people to participate in its virtual interactive spaces, undeniably allowing cultural contact globally. However, this would lead to the arising need for blockchain technologies which would involve a global system of recording information in a way that makes it difficult or impossible to change, hack, or cheat the system run by the company. Meta hence would have allocated the next decade to not only developing the metaverse but also to giving shape to a placeless, stateless system that manages all on its own, internationally. This is, indeed, a tough task to accomplish even for a company as massive as Meta.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the Web Summit, Peggy Johnson supported the notion that the metaverse, despite its criticisms, will eventually come into existence. She said that there is no clear, substantive evidence that proves that the metaverse will do more harm than good. These are merely suppositions without proper factual backing. When technology is about to take a huge leap, there is seldom a need to stop the change from coming because to make technology evolve would imply evolving lifestyles, which is simultaneously a welcoming and terrifying thought. Johnson, in the same summit, said that the change is inevitable and that it is foolish to resist it. She said that&lt;em&gt; &quot;&lt;/em&gt;Right now we're all looking down at our mobile phones,”&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;but with the use of AR glasses or AR headsets, consumers will be able to transform everything they see, from the name of the person to the review of cafes while walking past them. It will all be visible with such headsets.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked how she imagined the metaverse would seem like in another decade, she answered,&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;/em&gt;I think you’ll go back home to pick up your glasses because you left them at home, the same way you do with your mobile phones today.&lt;em&gt;”&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Herman, in his article published in The New York Times, said that there are several possibilities as to how the metaverse will progress and affect our lives. According to Herman, metaverse will take up space and become our usual environments, where virtual offices will emerge and we will eventually call it work space. However, what one has to wait and watch is if there would be spaces left for those who opt not to allocate their time and resources to such technologies and virtual realities. The discussions about this mainly move on to the fact that if metaverse does become a virtual reality and soon takes up the room for being essential to the future generation’s technological survival then would the freedom to choose not to use such technologies be a viable option? Or would not using such realities be a major form of shortcoming for those unable to afford it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A question, as mentioned before, is both terrifying and crucial.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aniba Junaid</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As the world still battles a pandemic, it remains imperative to understand that no matter in which condition man finds himself in, technology moves as it does: in leaps and bounds. It is often said that&amp;nbsp;it is not that we use technology, we live technology. Recently, Facebook unveiled new technology that may change the course of social media and connectivity to an all-new level. News forums call it&amp;nbsp;the internet of the future;&amp;nbsp;it claims to transport people into a whole new world of human interactions. Mark Zuckerberg’s 81-minute video essay on the long run of human interactions that culminated with the rebranding of Facebook as Meta, this term has been effervescent this year. Leaders in technology, recreation and fashion have hurried to stake their claim on it, although few appear to agree on what it precisely is. The vital factor is that the technology is coming sooner than one thought it would.&amp;nbsp; Conversations regarding the metaverse cut back the sensation of FOMO (Fear of Missing Out). Neal Stephenson in his 1992 novel, “Snow Crash” coined the term metaverse, and it has recently been hurled into wide and varied use. For most enthusiasts, Zuckerberg’s idea may take several years to formulate completely. However, some believe that simpler versions of the metaverse could already exist. Recently, at the Web Summit, the CEO of Magic Leap, Peggy Johnson said, “We're in the early stages of the metaverse, in some ways.”&amp;nbsp;Furthermore, Chris Cox, Meta's Chief Product Officer, who spoke to the BBC on the day of the rebranding, claimed that metaverse will change the way we use the internet as a whole and not simply imply a big change for the company alone. His words, &quot;Technology often starts in lower resolution versions of what it becomes.&quot;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Virtual reality-based experiences have already been in play since the emergence of games like Pokemon Go. Such technologies have already been used by the medical personnel when undertaking complex surgeries involving conjoined twins. Companies like Roblox have welcomed the notion of metaverse as they have been using a platform similar to this. However, what remains a significant concern is how effectively Facebook will be able to make this platform safe, user friendly, and keep the public discourse moving. The company has claimed to have been working on a set of protocols that will ensure the aforementioned features. Most gaming companies, who have used virtual realities in some form or the other, seem to look forward to Meta coming up with a form of virtual reality that would also define their work and procedure. Many others stand against the idea because they believe that what Meta plans to bring forth is dangerous and manipulative. They believe that it fails to ensure that the platform will not be misused, like how other, simpler social media platforms were in the past decades.&amp;nbsp; One of Facebook's earliest investors, Roger McNamee has branded Facebook’s plans for a metaverse&amp;nbsp;as&amp;nbsp;dystopian. He said, &quot;It is a bad idea, and the fact we are all sitting and looking at this like it is normal, should be alarming to everyone. Facebook should not be allowed to create a dystopian metaverse,” and went on to say “there's no way that a regulator or policymaker should be allowing Facebook to operate there [in the metaverse] or get into cryptocurrencies.&quot;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Mr McNamee became an opponent of Meta as he began to see more misinformation on the platform. He said he is not convinced that the metaverse would be safe with Mark Zuckerberg. He again said that “Facebook should have lost the right to make its own choices. A regulator should be there giving pre-approval for everything they do. The amount of harm they've done is incalculable.” What must be noted is that the metaverse, with its wide usage, will bring people to participate in its virtual interactive spaces, undeniably allowing cultural contact globally. However, this would lead to the arising need for blockchain technologies which would involve a global system of recording information in a way that makes it difficult or impossible to change, hack, or cheat the system run by the company. Meta hence would have allocated the next decade to not only developing the metaverse but also to giving shape to a placeless, stateless system that manages all on its own, internationally. This is, indeed, a tough task to accomplish even for a company as massive as Meta.&amp;nbsp; At the Web Summit, Peggy Johnson supported the notion that the metaverse, despite its criticisms, will eventually come into existence. She said that there is no clear, substantive evidence that proves that the metaverse will do more harm than good. These are merely suppositions without proper factual backing. When technology is about to take a huge leap, there is seldom a need to stop the change from coming because to make technology evolve would imply evolving lifestyles, which is simultaneously a welcoming and terrifying thought. Johnson, in the same summit, said that the change is inevitable and that it is foolish to resist it. She said that &quot;Right now we're all looking down at our mobile phones,”&amp;nbsp;but with the use of AR glasses or AR headsets, consumers will be able to transform everything they see, from the name of the person to the review of cafes while walking past them. It will all be visible with such headsets.&amp;nbsp; When asked how she imagined the metaverse would seem like in another decade, she answered,&amp;nbsp;“I think you’ll go back home to pick up your glasses because you left them at home, the same way you do with your mobile phones today.”&amp;nbsp; John Herman, in his article published in The New York Times, said that there are several possibilities as to how the metaverse will progress and affect our lives. According to Herman, metaverse will take up space and become our usual environments, where virtual offices will emerge and we will eventually call it work space. However, what one has to wait and watch is if there would be spaces left for those who opt not to allocate their time and resources to such technologies and virtual realities. The discussions about this mainly move on to the fact that if metaverse does become a virtual reality and soon takes up the room for being essential to the future generation’s technological survival then would the freedom to choose not to use such technologies be a viable option? Or would not using such realities be a major form of shortcoming for those unable to afford it? A question, as mentioned before, is both terrifying and crucial.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">COVID-19 and Economic Policy: From Saving Banks to Saving Businesses</title>
      <link href="/COVID-19-and-Economic-Policy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19 and Economic Policy: From Saving Banks to Saving Businesses" />
      <published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/COVID-19-and-Economic-Policy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/COVID-19-and-Economic-Policy">&lt;p&gt;Though any professional strategist, worth his/her salt, understands that no plan can be executed in its entirety, under any preconceived framework, however, the COVID -19 pandemic rattled the status-quo with such force that everything came to a grinding halt - literally. It neutered any semblance between the factors of the past and the present that influence policy-making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However unpalatable it may seem, the category that serves as one of the biggest pillars of any economy, sometimes simply by the virtue of its existence, is big business. That’s one of the reasons why the primary response that any government undertakes in such a case inevitably includes rushing through legislation that safeguards the existence of strategically selected corporations who can keep the economic juices flowing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking about such corporations - the only masters they serve are the shareholders. A lot of big-money companies try to leverage up as soon as they see an opening so that the maximum benefits go to a select class of shareholders. Though the phenomenon was global, a great pinpointed example would be the second quarter of the Trump presidency in the USA. The economy was booming and a Republican-led legislature had just passed a tax reform bill that slashed corporate tax rates on domestic and international incomes. Owing to all these factors, corporations like AT&amp;amp;T bought back stock and outsourced labour to Asian countries, effectively increasing their financial and operating leverage ratios.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming back to the point stated earlier, COVID struck like an angry bull, which put every leveraged-up corporation in harm's way. Supply chain lock jams and the absence of a physical workforce pushed companies towards defaults, leading to avoidable bankruptcies and undervalued dumping of assets.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help businesses of every scale sail through this hardship, governments of almost every country have reached across-the-aisle agreements on how they can alter the existing rules regarding a company's ability to negotiate its debts. As the Primary Impact of COVID was observed in Asia, Europe and North America, we can analyse the policy changes in India, UK and USA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The United Kingdom&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever corporations renegotiate debt, the creditors can be viewed as the aggrieved party because it, in essence, undermines their interests to ensure that the company is safe. Moreover, minor alterations in any of the affirmative or negative covenants running with the debt can shift the entire power dynamic. Therefore, creditors of all categories are engaged in the process of minimising the possibilities of future disagreements.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new restructuring guidelines ensure that the restructuring negotiations can proceed without the approval of classes of creditors or members who do not have an economic interest in the company. This prevents them from blocking common-sense reform because of motivations not rooted in the wellbeing of the corporation. Also, the requirement that a majority of creditors, of any particular class, must approve a scheme has not been included. The sole requirement is that holders representing 75% of the value of those voting approve the changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the amendments also prevent any supplier to a company from relying on any contractual provision to terminate the supply of goods or services because the company has entered into an insolvency process. A supplier will not be able to block the supply of goods and services on the pretext prior debts have not been satisfied&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;India&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Reserve Bank of India had announced, as a part of its COVID relief measures, guidelines for restructuring of loans up to ₹250 million. The approach was different from the UK's because it lays greater emphasis on institutional debt, effectively adding rung on the ladder.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The policy goal in the UK's case was to relax regulations on the extent and ease with which corporations can restructure debt, while Indian policy aimed at inducing the lending institutions to offer relief within a thin-lined framework and a high degree of discretion in terms of institution-specific suitability. The general framework entailed modification of repayment plans and an increased moratorium period to help alleviate the potential stress. Another important point to mention here is that once restructured, every loan would be considered standard and negotiations could not be reopened. The reconstruction framework was revamped for a second round with minor changes. The policy in India was focused on small scale businesses, which are the backbone of its economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The United States&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a part of various local and federal COVID-19 relief and stimulus bills, the Federal government and the states have implemented several amendments in their restructuring policies. The stark difference, when compared to policies of the UK and India, is the presence of an extensive evaluative framework to classify debt into different categories and sub-categories. By extension, the restructuring framework also differs for individual sub-categories or a basket of sub-categories along with discretion for deciding the rights of parties involved. As a midway point between India and UK, US policies have no fixed target segment and the power dynamic in terms of party rights has to be evaluated on a case-by-case basis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important element is the amortisation of fees/costs, which are also highly variable across loan sub-categories. For example - If a restructured loan is considered a 'new loan', any unamortised net fees or costs, as well as any prepayment penalties from the original loan, would be recognised in interest income when the said the new loan is granted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;America has gone to the greatest length to preserve the integrity of pre-entered contracts between corporations, individuals and government entities at all levels.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The policy toolkit that different countries have adopted to deal with the breakdowns caused by the pandemic has been deeply influenced by their circumstances. But the main takeaway is that the financial services sector has been asked to take a backseat. While in earlier crises, bailing out the big banks was priority number one, now, the systemic priority has been to ensure that employers stay afloat even if the banks have to take the hit for it. Will this bring about a fundamental shift in how we conduct economic policy? That is something only time can tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aryaman Dhiman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Though any professional strategist, worth his/her salt, understands that no plan can be executed in its entirety, under any preconceived framework, however, the COVID -19 pandemic rattled the status-quo with such force that everything came to a grinding halt - literally. It neutered any semblance between the factors of the past and the present that influence policy-making. However unpalatable it may seem, the category that serves as one of the biggest pillars of any economy, sometimes simply by the virtue of its existence, is big business. That’s one of the reasons why the primary response that any government undertakes in such a case inevitably includes rushing through legislation that safeguards the existence of strategically selected corporations who can keep the economic juices flowing.&amp;nbsp; Talking about such corporations - the only masters they serve are the shareholders. A lot of big-money companies try to leverage up as soon as they see an opening so that the maximum benefits go to a select class of shareholders. Though the phenomenon was global, a great pinpointed example would be the second quarter of the Trump presidency in the USA. The economy was booming and a Republican-led legislature had just passed a tax reform bill that slashed corporate tax rates on domestic and international incomes. Owing to all these factors, corporations like AT&amp;amp;T bought back stock and outsourced labour to Asian countries, effectively increasing their financial and operating leverage ratios.&amp;nbsp; Coming back to the point stated earlier, COVID struck like an angry bull, which put every leveraged-up corporation in harm's way. Supply chain lock jams and the absence of a physical workforce pushed companies towards defaults, leading to avoidable bankruptcies and undervalued dumping of assets.&amp;nbsp; To help businesses of every scale sail through this hardship, governments of almost every country have reached across-the-aisle agreements on how they can alter the existing rules regarding a company's ability to negotiate its debts. As the Primary Impact of COVID was observed in Asia, Europe and North America, we can analyse the policy changes in India, UK and USA. The United Kingdom Whenever corporations renegotiate debt, the creditors can be viewed as the aggrieved party because it, in essence, undermines their interests to ensure that the company is safe. Moreover, minor alterations in any of the affirmative or negative covenants running with the debt can shift the entire power dynamic. Therefore, creditors of all categories are engaged in the process of minimising the possibilities of future disagreements.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The new restructuring guidelines ensure that the restructuring negotiations can proceed without the approval of classes of creditors or members who do not have an economic interest in the company. This prevents them from blocking common-sense reform because of motivations not rooted in the wellbeing of the corporation. Also, the requirement that a majority of creditors, of any particular class, must approve a scheme has not been included. The sole requirement is that holders representing 75% of the value of those voting approve the changes. Finally, the amendments also prevent any supplier to a company from relying on any contractual provision to terminate the supply of goods or services because the company has entered into an insolvency process. A supplier will not be able to block the supply of goods and services on the pretext prior debts have not been satisfied India The Reserve Bank of India had announced, as a part of its COVID relief measures, guidelines for restructuring of loans up to ₹250 million. The approach was different from the UK's because it lays greater emphasis on institutional debt, effectively adding rung on the ladder.&amp;nbsp; The policy goal in the UK's case was to relax regulations on the extent and ease with which corporations can restructure debt, while Indian policy aimed at inducing the lending institutions to offer relief within a thin-lined framework and a high degree of discretion in terms of institution-specific suitability. The general framework entailed modification of repayment plans and an increased moratorium period to help alleviate the potential stress. Another important point to mention here is that once restructured, every loan would be considered standard and negotiations could not be reopened. The reconstruction framework was revamped for a second round with minor changes. The policy in India was focused on small scale businesses, which are the backbone of its economy.&amp;nbsp; The United States As a part of various local and federal COVID-19 relief and stimulus bills, the Federal government and the states have implemented several amendments in their restructuring policies. The stark difference, when compared to policies of the UK and India, is the presence of an extensive evaluative framework to classify debt into different categories and sub-categories. By extension, the restructuring framework also differs for individual sub-categories or a basket of sub-categories along with discretion for deciding the rights of parties involved. As a midway point between India and UK, US policies have no fixed target segment and the power dynamic in terms of party rights has to be evaluated on a case-by-case basis.&amp;nbsp; Another important element is the amortisation of fees/costs, which are also highly variable across loan sub-categories. For example - If a restructured loan is considered a 'new loan', any unamortised net fees or costs, as well as any prepayment penalties from the original loan, would be recognised in interest income when the said the new loan is granted. America has gone to the greatest length to preserve the integrity of pre-entered contracts between corporations, individuals and government entities at all levels.&amp;nbsp; The policy toolkit that different countries have adopted to deal with the breakdowns caused by the pandemic has been deeply influenced by their circumstances. But the main takeaway is that the financial services sector has been asked to take a backseat. While in earlier crises, bailing out the big banks was priority number one, now, the systemic priority has been to ensure that employers stay afloat even if the banks have to take the hit for it. Will this bring about a fundamental shift in how we conduct economic policy? That is something only time can tell.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Wall Street’s New Leviathan</title>
      <link href="/Wall-Street-s-New-Leviathan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wall Street’s New Leviathan" />
      <published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Wall-Street-s-New-Leviathan</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Wall-Street-s-New-Leviathan">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Thou art Peter, and upon this rock I will build my church.”&lt;/em&gt; (Matthew 16:18)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chances are high you’ll find a person who knows about this Peter, the bedrock of Christianity – it is the religion with the greatest number of adherents, after all. About two millennia later, the modern-day Peter has emerged, albeit less popular.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Americans pride themselves on being intelligent people, the folks who are good at everything – from fast food to babysitting world peace. Even if we were to believe these claims, one thing they’re &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; good at is answering a simple question – ‘&lt;em&gt;How much is too much?&lt;/em&gt;’&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This unanswered question has hurt the States time and again, and yet, answering it is &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; an ex-post job and not ex-ante. A decade after Wall Street fell victim to its own greed, regulations and investment trends of people who grew up through this collapse have shifted all headwinds to the buy-side, making them the new apex predators of what the country chooses to call capitalism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the buy-side firms are becoming as large as pre-crash investment banks, one particular name stands apart from the rest – literally and figuratively. It controls $9.5 trillion worth of assets and chances are, you have not heard of this firm - BlackRock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The firm and its asset growth are the true embodiment of the word exponential. Compared to the century-old financial behemoths such as Deutsche Bank, Goldman Sachs and Morgan Stanley, BlackRock was founded in 1988, a meagre three-decade-old company.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Founder Larry Fink was the man behind the infamous Mortgage-Backed Securities (MBS) market, which led to the 2008 crisis and subsequently his fall at Wall Street’s bulge bracket. Investment company First Boston used this as an opportunity and made him start an asset management firm: BlackRock, with an emphasis on risk management as their ace in the hole.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with a humble $5 million credit line from Blackstone, Fink and BlackRock quadrupled their assets within the year, a pace that continues till date - the firm adds a trillion to its asset base every year or so, which is the equivalent of saying it adds the &lt;em&gt;total&lt;/em&gt; asset base of leading asset management firms till date, to its balance sheet every year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BlackRock is like a Swiss-Army knife. As you’d expect, it is difficult to find a sector where the firm is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in. Currently, it is an institutional investor, money manager, consultant and private equity firm. It effectively is involved on all sides of the table in most industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A funny example is that of the environment. In 2017, announcements were made to support ESG practices within owned firms and improve the investment landscape in sustainable practices with new products. Two years later, BlackRock was a major shareholder in every big oil company and in seven of the leading producers of the other black rock – coal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this became public knowledge, protests were staged outside of BlackRock‘s France division, leading Fink to announce an exit from coal and fossil fuel assets. Alongside, revelations were made of letters to the boards of companies to improve sustainability and gender diversity practices or risk losing business with BlackRock.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other times, it simply has stakes in leading competitors – Apple and Microsoft, Deutsche Bank, JP Morgan Chase and Wells Fargo, just to name a few. It simply cannot lose money unless the entire sector goes bust.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can figure out other conflicts as well – a company goes to raise debt and BlackRock, a major shareholder, is already out to be a buyer of this debt. BlackRock is an advisor to most firms it’s an investor in. The ownership structure should ring a few alarms as well – Vanguard, another asset manager and a direct competitor of BlackRock, is its biggest shareholder. Many institutions that BlackRock invests in, are shareholders of BlackRock themselves.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is another part of BlackRock’s business that took flight in 1999 and is dubbed as “&lt;em&gt;a tech start-up&lt;/em&gt;” by CEO Fink – Aladdin, the risk management system. One would be damned if their start-up was managing risk for $21.6 trillion worth of assets including those of the Federal Reserve Board and the European Central Bank. BlackRock’s internal ‘Tech 2025’ plan aims to make Aladdin the standard, and perhaps the only used risk management platform in the industry. But that’s a monopoly for another time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, BlackRock is begging to be labelled as the present-day Illuminati, but that isn’t the case. However, it is a marionettist in its own right, and here is where things get murky. Back in the mid-to-late 00’s, Goldman Sachs was well known for hiring prominent policymakers who would go on to be part of America’s cabinet and ensure nothing went too awry for Wall Street.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 2008, one would expect that things would change and the blurred lines between White House and Wall Street would be redrawn but that’s the exact opposite of what happened. Who do you call when a set of financial products is threatening to, or rather, causing the biggest financial crisis in almost a century? Of course, it’s the creator!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the MBS markets were rearranging the food chain by the minute, one was eyeing the newly vacated spot of the apex predator – BlackRock. The Federal Reserve called in Fink and his team to manage the mess and has been a loyal customer ever since – be it Aladdin’s risk management, or an appropriate response to the coronavirus pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the pandemic hit, the Fed announced that it will purchase assets other than Treasury bonds as well – Corporate Bonds and Exchange Traded Funds (ETFs). Who else do we know as a major firm dealing in Corporate Bonds and ETFs? Do the math. The funds the Fed poured money in were a hit among retail investors and no prizes for guessing the issuer of the funds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are conversant with US law, you must have thought at least once about how BlackRock is not under the purview of ‘too big to fail’ or why the Dodd-Frank reform, which has riddled the powerhouses of the sell-side with multiple regulations on risk-taking, is not handicapping their earning potential?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is the same as that with Goldman – it has multiple former executives in Washington and multiple former Washington policymakers reside at the 52nd Street in Manhattan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This cosy revolving door is not just limited from Manhattan to Washington rather extends to Ottawa and Mexico City. For example, PEMEX, Mexico’s state-owned oil company was opened to private investment, and BlackRock quickly jumped in. Then it acquired a loss-making, scandalous private equity firm in the country, I Cuadrada, and a month down the line, Sierra Oil, a year-old portfolio company of the former, which had not had a project in its short life was awarded two major exploration contracts as the sole bidder.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BlackRock also holds the distinction of being the first global asset manager which has set up an onshore shop in China. There are multiple examples, from private to public sectors where the private firm has played on both sides of the court to benefit itself, earning the title of a white-collar mafia. Europe has dealt a stricter hand with criticism of the European Commission for awarding BlackRock a contract with a significant conflict of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the common person was never directly under attack from this leviathan but as it extends its power, it now faces a direct confrontation with the people – housing. The American Dream has always consisted of owning a place you can call home, however, that soon might not be the case as BlackRock and multiple other funds are outbidding individuals or paying the entire amount upfront with no inspection. These bids are too sweet for developers to pass.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you thought this was excessive, mega-funds are buying out entire neighbourhoods for a few factors above the listed prices and immediately putting them out on exorbitant rents. A new monopoly is unfolding before us and one can only hope America finds an answer to its age-old dilemma sooner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“For what does it profit a man to gain the whole world and forfeit his soul?”&lt;/em&gt; (Mark 8:36)&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aaradhya Daga</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Thou art Peter, and upon this rock I will build my church.” (Matthew 16:18) Chances are high you’ll find a person who knows about this Peter, the bedrock of Christianity – it is the religion with the greatest number of adherents, after all. About two millennia later, the modern-day Peter has emerged, albeit less popular.&amp;nbsp; Americans pride themselves on being intelligent people, the folks who are good at everything – from fast food to babysitting world peace. Even if we were to believe these claims, one thing they’re not good at is answering a simple question – ‘How much is too much?’&amp;nbsp; This unanswered question has hurt the States time and again, and yet, answering it is still an ex-post job and not ex-ante. A decade after Wall Street fell victim to its own greed, regulations and investment trends of people who grew up through this collapse have shifted all headwinds to the buy-side, making them the new apex predators of what the country chooses to call capitalism.&amp;nbsp; While the buy-side firms are becoming as large as pre-crash investment banks, one particular name stands apart from the rest – literally and figuratively. It controls $9.5 trillion worth of assets and chances are, you have not heard of this firm - BlackRock. The firm and its asset growth are the true embodiment of the word exponential. Compared to the century-old financial behemoths such as Deutsche Bank, Goldman Sachs and Morgan Stanley, BlackRock was founded in 1988, a meagre three-decade-old company.&amp;nbsp; Founder Larry Fink was the man behind the infamous Mortgage-Backed Securities (MBS) market, which led to the 2008 crisis and subsequently his fall at Wall Street’s bulge bracket. Investment company First Boston used this as an opportunity and made him start an asset management firm: BlackRock, with an emphasis on risk management as their ace in the hole.&amp;nbsp; Starting with a humble $5 million credit line from Blackstone, Fink and BlackRock quadrupled their assets within the year, a pace that continues till date - the firm adds a trillion to its asset base every year or so, which is the equivalent of saying it adds the total asset base of leading asset management firms till date, to its balance sheet every year.&amp;nbsp; BlackRock is like a Swiss-Army knife. As you’d expect, it is difficult to find a sector where the firm is not in. Currently, it is an institutional investor, money manager, consultant and private equity firm. It effectively is involved on all sides of the table in most industries. A funny example is that of the environment. In 2017, announcements were made to support ESG practices within owned firms and improve the investment landscape in sustainable practices with new products. Two years later, BlackRock was a major shareholder in every big oil company and in seven of the leading producers of the other black rock – coal.&amp;nbsp; When this became public knowledge, protests were staged outside of BlackRock‘s France division, leading Fink to announce an exit from coal and fossil fuel assets. Alongside, revelations were made of letters to the boards of companies to improve sustainability and gender diversity practices or risk losing business with BlackRock.&amp;nbsp; Other times, it simply has stakes in leading competitors – Apple and Microsoft, Deutsche Bank, JP Morgan Chase and Wells Fargo, just to name a few. It simply cannot lose money unless the entire sector goes bust.&amp;nbsp; You can figure out other conflicts as well – a company goes to raise debt and BlackRock, a major shareholder, is already out to be a buyer of this debt. BlackRock is an advisor to most firms it’s an investor in. The ownership structure should ring a few alarms as well – Vanguard, another asset manager and a direct competitor of BlackRock, is its biggest shareholder. Many institutions that BlackRock invests in, are shareholders of BlackRock themselves.&amp;nbsp; There is another part of BlackRock’s business that took flight in 1999 and is dubbed as “a tech start-up” by CEO Fink – Aladdin, the risk management system. One would be damned if their start-up was managing risk for $21.6 trillion worth of assets including those of the Federal Reserve Board and the European Central Bank. BlackRock’s internal ‘Tech 2025’ plan aims to make Aladdin the standard, and perhaps the only used risk management platform in the industry. But that’s a monopoly for another time. At this point, BlackRock is begging to be labelled as the present-day Illuminati, but that isn’t the case. However, it is a marionettist in its own right, and here is where things get murky. Back in the mid-to-late 00’s, Goldman Sachs was well known for hiring prominent policymakers who would go on to be part of America’s cabinet and ensure nothing went too awry for Wall Street. After 2008, one would expect that things would change and the blurred lines between White House and Wall Street would be redrawn but that’s the exact opposite of what happened. Who do you call when a set of financial products is threatening to, or rather, causing the biggest financial crisis in almost a century? Of course, it’s the creator! When the MBS markets were rearranging the food chain by the minute, one was eyeing the newly vacated spot of the apex predator – BlackRock. The Federal Reserve called in Fink and his team to manage the mess and has been a loyal customer ever since – be it Aladdin’s risk management, or an appropriate response to the coronavirus pandemic.&amp;nbsp; As the pandemic hit, the Fed announced that it will purchase assets other than Treasury bonds as well – Corporate Bonds and Exchange Traded Funds (ETFs). Who else do we know as a major firm dealing in Corporate Bonds and ETFs? Do the math. The funds the Fed poured money in were a hit among retail investors and no prizes for guessing the issuer of the funds. If you are conversant with US law, you must have thought at least once about how BlackRock is not under the purview of ‘too big to fail’ or why the Dodd-Frank reform, which has riddled the powerhouses of the sell-side with multiple regulations on risk-taking, is not handicapping their earning potential? The answer is the same as that with Goldman – it has multiple former executives in Washington and multiple former Washington policymakers reside at the 52nd Street in Manhattan.&amp;nbsp; This cosy revolving door is not just limited from Manhattan to Washington rather extends to Ottawa and Mexico City. For example, PEMEX, Mexico’s state-owned oil company was opened to private investment, and BlackRock quickly jumped in. Then it acquired a loss-making, scandalous private equity firm in the country, I Cuadrada, and a month down the line, Sierra Oil, a year-old portfolio company of the former, which had not had a project in its short life was awarded two major exploration contracts as the sole bidder.&amp;nbsp; BlackRock also holds the distinction of being the first global asset manager which has set up an onshore shop in China. There are multiple examples, from private to public sectors where the private firm has played on both sides of the court to benefit itself, earning the title of a white-collar mafia. Europe has dealt a stricter hand with criticism of the European Commission for awarding BlackRock a contract with a significant conflict of interest. While the common person was never directly under attack from this leviathan but as it extends its power, it now faces a direct confrontation with the people – housing. The American Dream has always consisted of owning a place you can call home, however, that soon might not be the case as BlackRock and multiple other funds are outbidding individuals or paying the entire amount upfront with no inspection. These bids are too sweet for developers to pass.&amp;nbsp; If you thought this was excessive, mega-funds are buying out entire neighbourhoods for a few factors above the listed prices and immediately putting them out on exorbitant rents. A new monopoly is unfolding before us and one can only hope America finds an answer to its age-old dilemma sooner. “For what does it profit a man to gain the whole world and forfeit his soul?” (Mark 8:36)</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Bright Side of Sharing Our Data</title>
      <link href="/The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-Our-Data" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Bright Side of Sharing Our Data" />
      <published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-Our-Data</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-Our-Data">&lt;p&gt;In recent times, there has been a wave of anger towards companies which use individual data without his or her knowledge. Campaigns like #OwnYourData, #MEGA and most recently, the movie documentary The Great Hack have brought the issue to the limelight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t argue that there is no malicious use of personal data, I would like to show that though there are some cases where data is used for ‘nefarious’ - I quote nefarious because it is subjective to each individual - purposes on a whole, the tool known as data analytics has brought far more benefits than harm to society…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen to the full session here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;audio id=&quot;pubcast-2&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; controlsList=&quot;nodownload&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/2021-11-04-The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-Our-Data.mp3&quot;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Or watch it on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f_0aWrVURq4&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative; width: 100%; height: 0; padding-top: 56.2500%;
 padding-bottom: 48px; box-shadow: 0 2px 8px 0 rgba(63,69,81,0.16); margin-top: 1.6em; margin-bottom: 0.9em; overflow: hidden;
 border-radius: 8px; will-change: transform;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; style=&quot;position: absolute; width: 100%; height: 100%; top: 0; left: 0; border: none; padding: 0;margin: 0;&quot; src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;www.canva.com&amp;#x2F;design&amp;#x2F;DAEm-hZBeLc&amp;#x2F;view?embed&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;*This session was recorded at Qworky Academy on 14th August 2021 and moderated by &lt;a href=&quot;/author/kheeran.naidu/&quot;&gt;Kheeran Naidu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Avinash Naidu</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      
        <category term="the-faraday-corner" />
      
        <category term="podcast" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In recent times, there has been a wave of anger towards companies which use individual data without his or her knowledge. Campaigns like #OwnYourData, #MEGA and most recently, the movie documentary The Great Hack have brought the issue to the limelight.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part II</title>
      <link href="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part II" />
      <published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-II</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-II">&lt;p&gt;In part I, we discussed what colourism is, what kind of activities perpetuate it today and some of the common consequences of the same. However, to actually tackle the problems of colourism, it is important to analyse what its possible root causes are.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A reasoning that is generally provided to explain the prevalence of colourism is colonialism. While it does not account for all the reasons behind the problem, it certainly is an important one. When various European powers occupied regions across the world, they took along with them their beauty standards which were based on what white people look like: thin nose, pale skin, straight hair and so on. Under colonial rule, the natives of the colonies were indoctrinated in Eurocentric views and soon, they learnt to view everything about the colonial power as superior to their own, including how they looked.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The colonial power also instituted various discriminatory practices and granted marginally more privilege to those who were brown or light skinned over those who were black or dark skinned. This later manifested among the non white populace in the form of practices like Blanqueamiento or whitening which is prevalent in post colonial countries in Oceania and America. It is aimed at mejorar la raza (“bettering the race”) to achieve the ideal of white. Basically, people try to marry a light skinned partner to produce fair skinned children. In fact, in the beginning of the 20th century, Latin American countries put in place policies that promoted Blanqueamiento (for instance, promoting immigration of Europeans in an attempt to whiten the population). Even today, in countries across the world, whiteness is seen as superior and beautiful and more often than not, in pageants and other forms of entertainment, people praise those who embody Eurocentric ideals of beauty.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many experts maintain that colourism predates colonialism. Let us take India for an example: Hindu religious texts refer to dark skinned people as people of the low caste. This stereotyping is probably born out of the fact that lower caste people were often relegated to manual labour in the sun, which resulted in them getting tanned. Dalits, who belong to the lowest caste, were treated as “untouchables” for a long time. Conversely, those with a fairer complexion were thought to belong to higher castes. The advent of colonialism and the colonial teachings that aimed to subjugate the Indians using a divide and conquer technique only polarised the castes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Indians started believing in a sort of supremacy of mixed race people, called the Anglo-Indians, over those who were full blooded Indians. The closer you were to your English ancestor, the higher up in the social strata you were.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, a vast majority of Hindu gods are portrayed as being very fair which too results in an unconscious bias in favour of those who possess a fair complexion.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hindi sound films became a thing only in 1931. Prior to that, Parsi theatre dominated the scene. Parsis were much fairer than other Indian ethnic groups because of their Iranian ancestry. This too played a role in promulgating the idea that fair is equivalent to beautiful.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, rarely any of the hundreds of Indian movies produced every year have someone from the lower castes or someone who is dark skinned in the leading roles. This lack of representation continues to harm the perception of Indians towards those who possess a darker complexion or belong to a lower caste.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the Indian Constitution does provide for protections against caste based discrimination, it is still widespread today. Dalits are looked down upon in positions of authority and responsibility, and also, often discriminated against in educational institutions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a consequence of this rampant colourism, fairness creams continue to find a place in the shops across India. One of the most famous brands in the country, “Fair and Lovely”, came under attack for their colourist commercials promoting their skin lightening products in 2020. In response to the criticism, instead of dealing with the actual problem, they rebranded as “Glow and Lovely” and continued to sell the same products. During this time, the company officials claimed that the product was never meant to be a skin bleaching product, rather it was meant to &amp;nbsp;'improve skin barrier function, improve skin firmness and smoothen skin texture'.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In countries like South Korea, colourism was born out of its feudal history. During the feudal ages of Korea those who belonged to the upper classes were lighter skinned owing to the fact that they could afford to stay indoors while those who belonged to the lower classes had to spend longer hours in the sun, often doing labour, and thus, were tanned. Fair skin was therefore a symbol of status and affluence, and consequently, coveted in Korea.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In more recent times, as Korea got more exposure to the west, western countries, dominated by white folk, were seen as more modern and thus, the higher status of fair skin failed to fade away into obscurity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, in Korea, fair skin continues to remain an important beauty ideal. As discussed in part 1, Kpop and Kdrama stars are expected to conform to the strict beauty standards which includes fair skin. It is deemed so important that many who do not fit into the ideal are expected and forced to get surgery to achieve the same. Moreover, the members of each group who are closest to the ideal are regarded as the “visual” of the group. For instance, Jin is the visual for BTS and Jisoo is the same for Blackpink.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In America, colourism was primarily born out of colonial practices and slavery. During the times of slavery, white people would rape their black slaves and the mixed race children who were born were treated marginally better than their darker skinned counterparts. They were allowed to work indoors while the dark complexioned slaves toiled out in the sun. In some cases, while it was still not allowed by the law, the white parent would informally recognise the child, though they could not inherit anything. This prevalence of the colourist divisions during the pre civil war times of America can be easily seen in James Stirling’s (a British writer who visited America in 1857) notes on the same:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In judging of the welfare of the slaves, it is necessary to distinguish the different conditions of slavery. The most important distinction, both as regards to numbers and its influence on the well being of the slave, is that between house­servants and farm or field hands. The house servant is comparatively well off. He is frequently born and bred in the family he belongs to; and even when this is not the case, the constant association of the slave and his master, and master's family, naturally leads to such an attachment as it ensures good treatment...The position of the field­hands is very different; of those, especially, who labour on large plantations. Here there are none of those humanizing influences at work which temper the rigour of the system, nor is there the same check of public opinion to control abuse. The 'force' is worked &lt;em&gt;en masse, &lt;/em&gt;as a great human mechanism; or, if you will, as a drove of human cattle.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li class=&quot;ql-align-right&quot;&gt;Letters from the Slave States, James Stirling&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This discrimination between Black people who are fair skinned and those who are dark complexioned due to the association of the same with a sort of marginal privilege, or lack thereof, led to light skin being coveted by African Americans. After the abolition of slavery, societies were set up which were open solely to the light skinned among the African American population. To determine whether one was suitable for being in such a company various tests were devised. The Brown Paper Bag Test required one to have a skin tone that was the same as or lighter than a brown paper bag to be admitted to such societies. Another similar test was the vein test: if one’s veins showed on their skin, then they were eligible for being a member.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another concept that was codified into the law in some of the US' states in the early 20th century was the “One Drop Rule”. This stated that if you had even a drop of African American blood, then you would be classified as black and thus, relegated to second class citizenship. This further polarised the demographic in matters of race and colour. Moreover, white passing black people took advantage of this to be registered as white and live as first class citizens, free from discrimination.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, people are becoming increasingly aware of the problems of colourism. Various companies have been making an effort to prevent the phenomenon of “beauty bias” (preference of individuals during the hiring process or during promotion decisions based on their attractiveness) through unconscious bias training. Several studies and researches have been conducted to gain more insight into the issues of implicit bias. A 2006 study concluded that fair skinned individuals were looked at favourably in employment decisions. Another research conducted in 2009 exposed that skin tone played a major role in the hiring of black employees and was often “more salient and regarded more highly than one’s educational background and prior work experience”. In 2010, a study carried out showed that children of all races chose light skinned characters in response to positive descriptors like “smart” or “pretty”, and ascribed negative attributes to darker characters, that is, a persistence of a implicit bias against dark skin. In 2016, Chika Okoro delivered a TedX talk titled&amp;nbsp; “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=8&amp;amp;v=fvoWoMIwr-g&amp;amp;feature=emb_logo&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Confessions of a D Girl: Colorism and Global Standards of Beauty'' in&lt;/a&gt; which she expatiates on the prevalence of colourism in the entertainment industry. In 2018, a study demonstrated that light complexioned individuals “attain a higher educational level, receive higher wages and enjoy better-quality jobs than their darker-skinned co-ethnics”, proving that there are both inter racial and intra racial wage gaps.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, an understanding and concern surrounding the pervasiveness of colourism is on the rise, and this is slowly manifesting in the form of increased and more diverse representation of various ethnic groups in the entertainment industry across the world alongside other marginal changes in policies and practices. However, the lack of awareness of the problem, its root causes, and its exclusion from popular discourse is making the process of change very slow. For now, we can educate ourselves better and reject discriminatory practices in order to aid in expediting the process of abolition of colourism.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In part I, we discussed what colourism is, what kind of activities perpetuate it today and some of the common consequences of the same. However, to actually tackle the problems of colourism, it is important to analyse what its possible root causes are.&amp;nbsp; A reasoning that is generally provided to explain the prevalence of colourism is colonialism. While it does not account for all the reasons behind the problem, it certainly is an important one. When various European powers occupied regions across the world, they took along with them their beauty standards which were based on what white people look like: thin nose, pale skin, straight hair and so on. Under colonial rule, the natives of the colonies were indoctrinated in Eurocentric views and soon, they learnt to view everything about the colonial power as superior to their own, including how they looked.&amp;nbsp; The colonial power also instituted various discriminatory practices and granted marginally more privilege to those who were brown or light skinned over those who were black or dark skinned. This later manifested among the non white populace in the form of practices like Blanqueamiento or whitening which is prevalent in post colonial countries in Oceania and America. It is aimed at mejorar la raza (“bettering the race”) to achieve the ideal of white. Basically, people try to marry a light skinned partner to produce fair skinned children. In fact, in the beginning of the 20th century, Latin American countries put in place policies that promoted Blanqueamiento (for instance, promoting immigration of Europeans in an attempt to whiten the population). Even today, in countries across the world, whiteness is seen as superior and beautiful and more often than not, in pageants and other forms of entertainment, people praise those who embody Eurocentric ideals of beauty.&amp;nbsp; Many experts maintain that colourism predates colonialism. Let us take India for an example: Hindu religious texts refer to dark skinned people as people of the low caste. This stereotyping is probably born out of the fact that lower caste people were often relegated to manual labour in the sun, which resulted in them getting tanned. Dalits, who belong to the lowest caste, were treated as “untouchables” for a long time. Conversely, those with a fairer complexion were thought to belong to higher castes. The advent of colonialism and the colonial teachings that aimed to subjugate the Indians using a divide and conquer technique only polarised the castes.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, Indians started believing in a sort of supremacy of mixed race people, called the Anglo-Indians, over those who were full blooded Indians. The closer you were to your English ancestor, the higher up in the social strata you were.&amp;nbsp; Additionally, a vast majority of Hindu gods are portrayed as being very fair which too results in an unconscious bias in favour of those who possess a fair complexion.&amp;nbsp; Hindi sound films became a thing only in 1931. Prior to that, Parsi theatre dominated the scene. Parsis were much fairer than other Indian ethnic groups because of their Iranian ancestry. This too played a role in promulgating the idea that fair is equivalent to beautiful.&amp;nbsp; Today, rarely any of the hundreds of Indian movies produced every year have someone from the lower castes or someone who is dark skinned in the leading roles. This lack of representation continues to harm the perception of Indians towards those who possess a darker complexion or belong to a lower caste.&amp;nbsp; While the Indian Constitution does provide for protections against caste based discrimination, it is still widespread today. Dalits are looked down upon in positions of authority and responsibility, and also, often discriminated against in educational institutions.&amp;nbsp; As a consequence of this rampant colourism, fairness creams continue to find a place in the shops across India. One of the most famous brands in the country, “Fair and Lovely”, came under attack for their colourist commercials promoting their skin lightening products in 2020. In response to the criticism, instead of dealing with the actual problem, they rebranded as “Glow and Lovely” and continued to sell the same products. During this time, the company officials claimed that the product was never meant to be a skin bleaching product, rather it was meant to &amp;nbsp;'improve skin barrier function, improve skin firmness and smoothen skin texture'.&amp;nbsp; In countries like South Korea, colourism was born out of its feudal history. During the feudal ages of Korea those who belonged to the upper classes were lighter skinned owing to the fact that they could afford to stay indoors while those who belonged to the lower classes had to spend longer hours in the sun, often doing labour, and thus, were tanned. Fair skin was therefore a symbol of status and affluence, and consequently, coveted in Korea.&amp;nbsp; In more recent times, as Korea got more exposure to the west, western countries, dominated by white folk, were seen as more modern and thus, the higher status of fair skin failed to fade away into obscurity.&amp;nbsp; Today, in Korea, fair skin continues to remain an important beauty ideal. As discussed in part 1, Kpop and Kdrama stars are expected to conform to the strict beauty standards which includes fair skin. It is deemed so important that many who do not fit into the ideal are expected and forced to get surgery to achieve the same. Moreover, the members of each group who are closest to the ideal are regarded as the “visual” of the group. For instance, Jin is the visual for BTS and Jisoo is the same for Blackpink.&amp;nbsp; In America, colourism was primarily born out of colonial practices and slavery. During the times of slavery, white people would rape their black slaves and the mixed race children who were born were treated marginally better than their darker skinned counterparts. They were allowed to work indoors while the dark complexioned slaves toiled out in the sun. In some cases, while it was still not allowed by the law, the white parent would informally recognise the child, though they could not inherit anything. This prevalence of the colourist divisions during the pre civil war times of America can be easily seen in James Stirling’s (a British writer who visited America in 1857) notes on the same:&amp;nbsp; “In judging of the welfare of the slaves, it is necessary to distinguish the different conditions of slavery. The most important distinction, both as regards to numbers and its influence on the well being of the slave, is that between house­servants and farm or field hands. The house servant is comparatively well off. He is frequently born and bred in the family he belongs to; and even when this is not the case, the constant association of the slave and his master, and master's family, naturally leads to such an attachment as it ensures good treatment...The position of the field­hands is very different; of those, especially, who labour on large plantations. Here there are none of those humanizing influences at work which temper the rigour of the system, nor is there the same check of public opinion to control abuse. The 'force' is worked en masse, as a great human mechanism; or, if you will, as a drove of human cattle.” Letters from the Slave States, James Stirling This discrimination between Black people who are fair skinned and those who are dark complexioned due to the association of the same with a sort of marginal privilege, or lack thereof, led to light skin being coveted by African Americans. After the abolition of slavery, societies were set up which were open solely to the light skinned among the African American population. To determine whether one was suitable for being in such a company various tests were devised. The Brown Paper Bag Test required one to have a skin tone that was the same as or lighter than a brown paper bag to be admitted to such societies. Another similar test was the vein test: if one’s veins showed on their skin, then they were eligible for being a member.&amp;nbsp; Another concept that was codified into the law in some of the US' states in the early 20th century was the “One Drop Rule”. This stated that if you had even a drop of African American blood, then you would be classified as black and thus, relegated to second class citizenship. This further polarised the demographic in matters of race and colour. Moreover, white passing black people took advantage of this to be registered as white and live as first class citizens, free from discrimination.&amp;nbsp; Today, people are becoming increasingly aware of the problems of colourism. Various companies have been making an effort to prevent the phenomenon of “beauty bias” (preference of individuals during the hiring process or during promotion decisions based on their attractiveness) through unconscious bias training. Several studies and researches have been conducted to gain more insight into the issues of implicit bias. A 2006 study concluded that fair skinned individuals were looked at favourably in employment decisions. Another research conducted in 2009 exposed that skin tone played a major role in the hiring of black employees and was often “more salient and regarded more highly than one’s educational background and prior work experience”. In 2010, a study carried out showed that children of all races chose light skinned characters in response to positive descriptors like “smart” or “pretty”, and ascribed negative attributes to darker characters, that is, a persistence of a implicit bias against dark skin. In 2016, Chika Okoro delivered a TedX talk titled&amp;nbsp; “Confessions of a D Girl: Colorism and Global Standards of Beauty'' in which she expatiates on the prevalence of colourism in the entertainment industry. In 2018, a study demonstrated that light complexioned individuals “attain a higher educational level, receive higher wages and enjoy better-quality jobs than their darker-skinned co-ethnics”, proving that there are both inter racial and intra racial wage gaps.&amp;nbsp; Clearly, an understanding and concern surrounding the pervasiveness of colourism is on the rise, and this is slowly manifesting in the form of increased and more diverse representation of various ethnic groups in the entertainment industry across the world alongside other marginal changes in policies and practices. However, the lack of awareness of the problem, its root causes, and its exclusion from popular discourse is making the process of change very slow. For now, we can educate ourselves better and reject discriminatory practices in order to aid in expediting the process of abolition of colourism.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part I</title>
      <link href="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-I" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=" Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part I" />
      <published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-I</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-I">&lt;p&gt;“Mirror, mirror on the wall, who is the fairest of them all?” (&lt;em&gt;Snow White&lt;/em&gt;) - is as iconic as quotes generally get. Anyone who has watched, read or listened to the story of &lt;em&gt;Snow White&lt;/em&gt; is aware of the Evil Queen’s aspirations: she wished to be the “fairest of them all”. 'Fair', as in not 'just' but 'pale' and ergo, beautiful. This declaration of the equivalence of a paler skin tone and beauty has been at the center of various cultures across the world, and has stood the test of time. Those with fairer skin tones are deemed more 'marriage worthy', less intimidating, more innocent, less violent and of course, more beautiful. This is colourism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it more formally, colourism is the discrimination against individuals based on skin tone, often within a particular ethnic or racial group. This differs from racism in the sense that racism is discrimination based on race, while colourism may be prevalent within and among the members of a particular race. Colourism is ubiquitous and intractable - almost every ethnic group suffers from its pernicious effects and it has been this way for a very long time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about the majority of Latin telenovelas, K dramas and Bollywood movies. A whole chunk of the demographic is missing from the portrayals: the darker skinned Latinas, Koreans and Indians. Those born with a darker skin are looked down upon, considered ugly and therefore, not deserving of a place in the entertainment industry. On the contrary, the fairer complexioned individuals are hailed as beautiful and looked at favourably in almost all avenues of human life.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In India, this obsession with fair skin has been aptly given the appellation 'The Snow White Syndrome'. In fact, the problem is so pervasive that Bollywood movies have been practicing something known as 'brownface' for quite a while now without any compunction. They darken the skin of fair skinned actors to have them portray characters from a background of disadvantage instead of actually hiring dark skinned actors, thereby perpetuating the age-old problem of colourism in India. A 2019 film named &lt;em&gt;Bala&lt;/em&gt; was supposed to be a critical opprobrium of colourism prevalent in India. Ironically, the female protagonist, who faces discrimination on the basis of her dark complexion, was played by a fair skinned actress, Bhumi Pednekar, in a brownface. The poster for the movie showed her dawning a brownface, surrounded by skin lightening products. There are countless other examples of recent Bollywood movies doing the same: &lt;em&gt;Gully Boy&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Super 30&lt;/em&gt; and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another very patent expression of colourism prevalent in India that exists in Bollywood movies are the background dancers in the so-called 'item songs'. These dance routines are aimed to cater to the male gaze and feature beautiful women dancing to catchy Hindi tunes. The background dancers are often white and have blonde hair because that is what is considered 'beautiful'. The love interests in movies are also, generally, fair complexioned. In 2020, a film called &lt;em&gt;Khali Peeli&lt;/em&gt; came under attack for having a song titled &lt;em&gt;Beyonce Sharma Jayegi&lt;/em&gt; (which roughly translates to 'Beyonce will become embarrassed'). The song praises the female protagonist of the film for her fair skin, which apparently even puts the gorgeous Beyonce to shame (“&lt;em&gt;tujhe dekh ke goriya, Beyonce sharma jayegi&lt;/em&gt;”). Many famous Indian actors, including but not limited to Shah Rukh Khan, Priyanka Chopra and Yami Gautam, have also, only recently though, come under attack for starring in commercials for skin whitening products, in some cases, throughout their illustrious careers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skin whitening or bleaching is a practice that is widespread in almost all the continents. Various products, legal and illegal alike, are available to achieve the desirable fair skin: injections, creams, surgeries and so on and so forth. Many of these are potentially dangerous as they contain more than the legal and safe amount of mercury, which is very toxic. However, it continues to be rampant and the market is expected to reach an estimated $8.9 billion by 2024. Moreover, images of Kpop stars and Kdrama actors are often edited by agencies and fansites to make them look fair and desirable. This is after agencies meticulously chose their trainees based on various factors, including how they look. Many of the trainees who do not conform to the very strict beauty standards in Korea are expected to undergo surgeries to achieve the desirable look.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, plastic surgeries are so common in South Korea, especially among the youth today, that it is deemed as the plastic surgery capital, and has the highest ratio of plastic surgery clinics in the world. There are a few tanned Kpop stars like Hwasa (Mamamoo), Kai (EXO) and Jessi (soloist). However, they are exceptions to the norm and treated as such by the industry and the audience: some with awe, some with admiration and some with rejection (they sometimes face a lot of backlash from the fans of Kpop because of their dark skin). In most cases, these idols are portrayed as the “sexy” members of their respective groups by their agencies: pale skin is marketed as pure and so, darker skin is marketed as fierce.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another common practice that is born out of colourism is the casting of white passing characters in movies and TV series. &lt;em&gt;Fate: The Winx Saga&lt;/em&gt;, which is a TV series based on the famous early 2000's cartoon &lt;em&gt;Winx Club&lt;/em&gt;, casted a white passing actress named Elisha Applebaum for the role of Musa, an East Asian coded fairy. While there are claims that she is some part Asian, the problem is that since the character is supposed to be full East Asian and look that way, it would have been better to cast someone who looked the part. This is not an isolated instance. Some other examples are Taylor Lautner in the &lt;em&gt;Twilight&lt;/em&gt; series (he portrayed Jacob Black, a Native American character), Scarlett Johansson in &lt;em&gt;Ghost In The Shell&lt;/em&gt; (she was cast as Motoko Kusanagi, a Japanese cyber-human), Tilda Swinton in the &lt;em&gt;MCU&lt;/em&gt; (as the Ancient One, an Asian man) and Emma Stone in &lt;em&gt;Aloha&lt;/em&gt; (she played Allison Ng, a Chinese-Hawaiian-Swedish character). Clearly, in some of these cases, they simply casted a white person, irrespective of whether they resemble the character they are meant to portray at all or not. Actors of various ethnic backgrounds, who have distinctive features (which are considered 'ugly' by Western beauty standards) are often not considered for roles that portray a person from the same background. This exclusion of non-white and non-white passing actors results in a lack of jobs for hopefuls from such backgrounds and often deters them from choosing a career in entertainment altogether.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In movies with Black cast members, it is often seen that the love interest or the 'attractive' character is light skinned, often casting mixed race actors for the role (fetishisation of mixed race people is another insidious issue). Some examples are the casting of Rege Jean-Page as the Duke in &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; and Zendaya in almost everything. Of course these are great actors, and I am in no position to question their acting skills. The problem is with everyone typecasting Zendaya into every 'black girl' role just because she fits the description of being black while simultaneously conforming to Western beauty standards.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research conducted by the Geena Davis Institute on Gender in Media in collaboration with USC Viterbi School of Engineering concluded that about 80% of black female characters are played by light or medium skinned actors. We also often see that the protagonist is light skinned and the side characters are dark skinned (for instance, in &lt;em&gt;Dear White People&lt;/em&gt;). Moreover, darker skinned actors are often cast for roles portraying unlikeable people like the Duke’s father in &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; or for rude, loud, boorish and/or violent (which are personality trait stereotypes that are born out of racism against the Black community) characters like Will Mondrich from &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the above propagate a beauty standard that is highly detrimental to the self-image of thousands born to colourist cultures and societies. They face discrimination in all walks of life, have body image issues, face shaming and bullying, even by family members and are often pushed to extreme measures to modify their body to look beautiful and reap the benefits of the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Statistical data suggests that darker skinned people are more likely to be incarcerated or have longer sentences. In India, having dark skin is equated with being 'dirty' and people are encouraged to wear makeup that is several shades lighter to appear paler and thus, more desirable. Dark skinned people are tormented with taunts about how they will never get married because they are not desirable. In South Asia, marriages are sometimes arranged based on advertisements published in newspapers and 'fair' is a very common requirement in partners. A lot of the times when asked why a particular individual prefers a light skinned partner, the response comes, one way or another, in the form of a preference argument. But why is it that everyone 'prefers' lighter skin? It is directly or indirectly based on the idea that pale is beautiful and because of practices like Blanqueamiento (this will be discussed in detail in part II of this article).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem of colourism is all-pervasive and yet often neglected from the discourse. In fact, it is so prevalent and mundane that it is almost impossible to find foundations beyond a specific shade range, one that most agrees with the fair skinned. Rihanna’s Fenty Beauty was widely extolled for having a very large range of shades, extending the limits in both directions of the colour spectrum. Unfortunately, not all companies cater to the non-white audience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, in sets of crayons for children, the name 'skin/flesh colour' is given to a light peach shade, which thereby perpetuates light skin as the standard or 'normal' or acceptable skin colour.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Hindu mythology there are a myriad of dark complexioned characters like the deity Kali and the avatar Krishna. However, in TV adaptations of the same, fair skinned individuals are painted in black or blue to achieve the look of the character instead of hiring a dark complexioned individual for the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only recently have people been questioning the age-old practices and antiquated beliefs that lie at the core of colourism. More and more non-white and non-white passing individuals have been winning beauty pageants and appearing in movies and TV series. However, we are yet to see appreciable changes in statistics involving dark and light skinned individuals of a particular ethnic group and the rates of rejection from jobs because of this. It is important to keep up this streak of questioning colourist practices to reach the point where the society is ready to change and does eventually change.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Mirror, mirror on the wall, who is the fairest of them all?” (Snow White) - is as iconic as quotes generally get. Anyone who has watched, read or listened to the story of Snow White is aware of the Evil Queen’s aspirations: she wished to be the “fairest of them all”. 'Fair', as in not 'just' but 'pale' and ergo, beautiful. This declaration of the equivalence of a paler skin tone and beauty has been at the center of various cultures across the world, and has stood the test of time. Those with fairer skin tones are deemed more 'marriage worthy', less intimidating, more innocent, less violent and of course, more beautiful. This is colourism. To put it more formally, colourism is the discrimination against individuals based on skin tone, often within a particular ethnic or racial group. This differs from racism in the sense that racism is discrimination based on race, while colourism may be prevalent within and among the members of a particular race. Colourism is ubiquitous and intractable - almost every ethnic group suffers from its pernicious effects and it has been this way for a very long time.&amp;nbsp; Think about the majority of Latin telenovelas, K dramas and Bollywood movies. A whole chunk of the demographic is missing from the portrayals: the darker skinned Latinas, Koreans and Indians. Those born with a darker skin are looked down upon, considered ugly and therefore, not deserving of a place in the entertainment industry. On the contrary, the fairer complexioned individuals are hailed as beautiful and looked at favourably in almost all avenues of human life.&amp;nbsp; In India, this obsession with fair skin has been aptly given the appellation 'The Snow White Syndrome'. In fact, the problem is so pervasive that Bollywood movies have been practicing something known as 'brownface' for quite a while now without any compunction. They darken the skin of fair skinned actors to have them portray characters from a background of disadvantage instead of actually hiring dark skinned actors, thereby perpetuating the age-old problem of colourism in India. A 2019 film named Bala was supposed to be a critical opprobrium of colourism prevalent in India. Ironically, the female protagonist, who faces discrimination on the basis of her dark complexion, was played by a fair skinned actress, Bhumi Pednekar, in a brownface. The poster for the movie showed her dawning a brownface, surrounded by skin lightening products. There are countless other examples of recent Bollywood movies doing the same: Gully Boy, Super 30 and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp; Another very patent expression of colourism prevalent in India that exists in Bollywood movies are the background dancers in the so-called 'item songs'. These dance routines are aimed to cater to the male gaze and feature beautiful women dancing to catchy Hindi tunes. The background dancers are often white and have blonde hair because that is what is considered 'beautiful'. The love interests in movies are also, generally, fair complexioned. In 2020, a film called Khali Peeli came under attack for having a song titled Beyonce Sharma Jayegi (which roughly translates to 'Beyonce will become embarrassed'). The song praises the female protagonist of the film for her fair skin, which apparently even puts the gorgeous Beyonce to shame (“tujhe dekh ke goriya, Beyonce sharma jayegi”). Many famous Indian actors, including but not limited to Shah Rukh Khan, Priyanka Chopra and Yami Gautam, have also, only recently though, come under attack for starring in commercials for skin whitening products, in some cases, throughout their illustrious careers.&amp;nbsp; Skin whitening or bleaching is a practice that is widespread in almost all the continents. Various products, legal and illegal alike, are available to achieve the desirable fair skin: injections, creams, surgeries and so on and so forth. Many of these are potentially dangerous as they contain more than the legal and safe amount of mercury, which is very toxic. However, it continues to be rampant and the market is expected to reach an estimated $8.9 billion by 2024. Moreover, images of Kpop stars and Kdrama actors are often edited by agencies and fansites to make them look fair and desirable. This is after agencies meticulously chose their trainees based on various factors, including how they look. Many of the trainees who do not conform to the very strict beauty standards in Korea are expected to undergo surgeries to achieve the desirable look.&amp;nbsp; In fact, plastic surgeries are so common in South Korea, especially among the youth today, that it is deemed as the plastic surgery capital, and has the highest ratio of plastic surgery clinics in the world. There are a few tanned Kpop stars like Hwasa (Mamamoo), Kai (EXO) and Jessi (soloist). However, they are exceptions to the norm and treated as such by the industry and the audience: some with awe, some with admiration and some with rejection (they sometimes face a lot of backlash from the fans of Kpop because of their dark skin). In most cases, these idols are portrayed as the “sexy” members of their respective groups by their agencies: pale skin is marketed as pure and so, darker skin is marketed as fierce.&amp;nbsp; Another common practice that is born out of colourism is the casting of white passing characters in movies and TV series. Fate: The Winx Saga, which is a TV series based on the famous early 2000's cartoon Winx Club, casted a white passing actress named Elisha Applebaum for the role of Musa, an East Asian coded fairy. While there are claims that she is some part Asian, the problem is that since the character is supposed to be full East Asian and look that way, it would have been better to cast someone who looked the part. This is not an isolated instance. Some other examples are Taylor Lautner in the Twilight series (he portrayed Jacob Black, a Native American character), Scarlett Johansson in Ghost In The Shell (she was cast as Motoko Kusanagi, a Japanese cyber-human), Tilda Swinton in the MCU (as the Ancient One, an Asian man) and Emma Stone in Aloha (she played Allison Ng, a Chinese-Hawaiian-Swedish character). Clearly, in some of these cases, they simply casted a white person, irrespective of whether they resemble the character they are meant to portray at all or not. Actors of various ethnic backgrounds, who have distinctive features (which are considered 'ugly' by Western beauty standards) are often not considered for roles that portray a person from the same background. This exclusion of non-white and non-white passing actors results in a lack of jobs for hopefuls from such backgrounds and often deters them from choosing a career in entertainment altogether.&amp;nbsp; In movies with Black cast members, it is often seen that the love interest or the 'attractive' character is light skinned, often casting mixed race actors for the role (fetishisation of mixed race people is another insidious issue). Some examples are the casting of Rege Jean-Page as the Duke in Bridgerton and Zendaya in almost everything. Of course these are great actors, and I am in no position to question their acting skills. The problem is with everyone typecasting Zendaya into every 'black girl' role just because she fits the description of being black while simultaneously conforming to Western beauty standards.&amp;nbsp; Research conducted by the Geena Davis Institute on Gender in Media in collaboration with USC Viterbi School of Engineering concluded that about 80% of black female characters are played by light or medium skinned actors. We also often see that the protagonist is light skinned and the side characters are dark skinned (for instance, in Dear White People). Moreover, darker skinned actors are often cast for roles portraying unlikeable people like the Duke’s father in Bridgerton or for rude, loud, boorish and/or violent (which are personality trait stereotypes that are born out of racism against the Black community) characters like Will Mondrich from Bridgerton.&amp;nbsp; All of the above propagate a beauty standard that is highly detrimental to the self-image of thousands born to colourist cultures and societies. They face discrimination in all walks of life, have body image issues, face shaming and bullying, even by family members and are often pushed to extreme measures to modify their body to look beautiful and reap the benefits of the same.&amp;nbsp; Statistical data suggests that darker skinned people are more likely to be incarcerated or have longer sentences. In India, having dark skin is equated with being 'dirty' and people are encouraged to wear makeup that is several shades lighter to appear paler and thus, more desirable. Dark skinned people are tormented with taunts about how they will never get married because they are not desirable. In South Asia, marriages are sometimes arranged based on advertisements published in newspapers and 'fair' is a very common requirement in partners. A lot of the times when asked why a particular individual prefers a light skinned partner, the response comes, one way or another, in the form of a preference argument. But why is it that everyone 'prefers' lighter skin? It is directly or indirectly based on the idea that pale is beautiful and because of practices like Blanqueamiento (this will be discussed in detail in part II of this article).&amp;nbsp; The problem of colourism is all-pervasive and yet often neglected from the discourse. In fact, it is so prevalent and mundane that it is almost impossible to find foundations beyond a specific shade range, one that most agrees with the fair skinned. Rihanna’s Fenty Beauty was widely extolled for having a very large range of shades, extending the limits in both directions of the colour spectrum. Unfortunately, not all companies cater to the non-white audience.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, in sets of crayons for children, the name 'skin/flesh colour' is given to a light peach shade, which thereby perpetuates light skin as the standard or 'normal' or acceptable skin colour.&amp;nbsp; In Hindu mythology there are a myriad of dark complexioned characters like the deity Kali and the avatar Krishna. However, in TV adaptations of the same, fair skinned individuals are painted in black or blue to achieve the look of the character instead of hiring a dark complexioned individual for the job. Only recently have people been questioning the age-old practices and antiquated beliefs that lie at the core of colourism. More and more non-white and non-white passing individuals have been winning beauty pageants and appearing in movies and TV series. However, we are yet to see appreciable changes in statistics involving dark and light skinned individuals of a particular ethnic group and the rates of rejection from jobs because of this. It is important to keep up this streak of questioning colourist practices to reach the point where the society is ready to change and does eventually change.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
