<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/trending/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-03-13T02:24:11+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/trending/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Micro Economies: Big Challenges and Small Opportunities</title>
      <link href="/Micro-Economies" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Micro Economies: Big Challenges and Small Opportunities" />
      <published>2019-03-08T23:30:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-08T23:30:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Micro-Economies</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Micro-Economies">&lt;p&gt;Niue (a small island nation in the Pacific Ocean) has a population even less
than the number of students studying in the Shri Ram College of Commerce,
University of Delhi. According to the World Bank, all economies with a
population of less than 0.5 million are considered to be “micro.” At present,
there are 29 such countries which constitute around 15% of the total number of
countries in the world. They are usually found together in groups and are
prevalent in three regions: the Caribbean, the Pacific, and Africa. Despite
their spread across the world, they have negligible say in the functioning of
the world economy. And this article is an attempt to understand the economic
systems of the ‘subaltern’ countries of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These economies (also called micro-economies) are either landlocked countries or
island nations, mostly present in the middle of nowhere. In either case, they
are isolated from the ‘markets’. This increases the cost of transportation as
the goods either have to travel long distances over oceans or through several
countries. This increases the overall cost of production which makes the goods
produced in these countries unattractive in international markets, and imports
costly. As a result, exports in the commodity sector is low in these economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Micro-economies have limited labour supply in the market. A labourer is expected
to perform several duties which leads to the overburdening of work. This reduces
labour productivity and labourers are unable to specialise in one kind of work.
Thus, the economy cannot receive the benefits of specialisation and division of
labour. Contrary to enjoying economies of scale, micro-economies face
‘&lt;em&gt;diseconomies of size’&lt;/em&gt; due to low demand and high production costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very evidently, micro-economies are unattractive for new market entrants. Hence,
these markets are generally a monopoly or an oligopoly, which provide a limited
range of products and services at high costs. High costs, in turn, lead to
poverty and large income inequalities. This can be substantiated from the fact
that countries like Lesotho, Guinea-Bissau, Gambia, Gabon, Suriname have more
than 40% of their total population living below the internationally accepted
poverty line of $1.90 per day. Limited production also leads to extremely low
GNP per capita: Comoros, Gambia, Guinea-Bissau and Sao Tome and Principe have a
GNP per capita of less than $500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Production is not the only area where economies of scale benefit a country. It
is seen that economies of scale greatly benefits an economy when it comes to
providing social security and creating social and economic infrastructure, as
well. A country with a huge population and a higher number of taxpayers has huge
amounts of money to spend on infrastructure. The cost of social security, as
well as social and economic infrastructure, is spread over a larger population.
This reduces the cost incurred per person for providing these facilities. In the
case of small economies, the population, as well as the number of taxpayers, is
low. Hence, the governments of these countries have almost no money to spend on
building and developing economic infrastructures such as highways and roadways,
and social infrastructures like schools and hospitals. All this ensures foreign
investment never comes into these countries, creating a &lt;em&gt;chakravyuh&lt;/em&gt; (vicious cycle) of poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With limited production capacities and little diversification, micro-economies
are generally capable of specialising in the production of one good or service,
in which they have an advantage over other economies. Due to the low population,
the demand for their commodities is low and limited. This means that they are
ready to export the commodity in which they have a competitive advantage over
the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of these economies are also highly dependent on tourism. This is evident
from the fact that tourism constitutes more than 50% in Fiji and more than 40%
in Vanuatu and the Caribbean States as part of their total exports. In fact,
imports and exports combined constitute more than 100% of the GDP of these
countries. But this high degree of openness also makes it highly vulnerable to
international events and shocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their vulnerability can be seen as how these economies developed at staggering
paces of more than 8% per annum before 2008. But, as soon as the 2008 financial
crisis hit, the income from tourism sector plummeted rapidly. This had such an
impact on the economies that these countries grew at -1% to 0% for the next two
years. Vulnerability also makes income more volatile. It is seen that the
standard deviation of the real per capita GDP growth is more than 9. This means
that there can be an average of 9% change per annum in their per capita GDP, as
compared to the world average of 3.2%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These economies also function as parasites. Just like parasites feed upon the
parent trees, these economies feed and depend upon a large economy which is
beside them. The Caribbean States depend upon Mexico and the US, the African
island nations in the Indian Ocean depend upon India, and those in the Pacific
depend upon Australia and New Zealand. Most of their trade (over 90%) is carried
out with these large economies and in most cases, they take up their currency as
well. Therefore, how these large economies fare in the global market decides the
fate of these micro-economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these ‘parent economies’ seldom take interest in investing in their
children. Hence, micro-economies turn towards the International Monetary Fund,
the International Development Association and various other regional and
international development banks for grants and unilateral advances for
developmental funding. These grants go a long way in helping micro-economies
provide their citizens with basic necessities. Research suggests that these
grants have helped reduce poverty levels by around 2-5% in different
micro-economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the recent challenges that these countries face is global warming and
increased danger of disasters. As most of these countries are islands or chains
of islands, they are just metres above sea level. The rising sea level and
the increased frequency of natural disasters has increased the risk of complete
disappearance of these island nations. Adequate disaster management is
necessary, which requires funds. Owing to lack of funds, these countries have to
look towards the international community and the United Nations for their
sustenance and to equip them with various techniques of disaster risk
management. &lt;em&gt;Debt bells ringing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of having so many problems, micro-economies have some advantages as
well. As most of these small economies are a group of islands, they have access
to huge amounts of the ocean as their territory. Thus, these economies have
Exclusive Economic Zones (EEZ’s) in the oceans. These economies usually grant
foreign multinational corporations permission for fishing and extract resources
from the EEZs against a charge. This has become one of the main sources of
income, apart from allowing military bases of other countries to be set up on
their territory (China and India are watching closely).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these economies also serve as tax havens for the rich billionaires and
multinational corporations. They have very lax to no tax laws. The most
prominent example would be of Cayman Islands (population - 23,000), which by the
mid-1990’s, became the world’s fifth largest banking centre measured by
deposits. There are more than 560 banks registered in this micro-nation,
including major accounting, audit and law firms. The Caymans are the ideal tax
haven as they provide “tax efficient asset protection”. There are no taxes, no
exchange controls and no threat to the ‘confidentiality’ of deposits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Alberto Alesina said in his book &lt;em&gt;Size of Nations&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Whether country size matters for economic prosperity depends on a country’s
degree of economic integration with the rest of the world.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, these economies too, have to integrate with the world economy if they
wish to develop and prosper. They cannot depend on a single economy or a single
commodity for their development. Maldives and Fiji are two micro-economies which
have seen tremendous growth in these recent years after opening up their
economies to the world. They are not totally dependent on their regional powers
or a single commodity for trade. However, they are still part of the exception
than the norm. Other micro-economies too can look up to them, and try, develop,
progress and finally contribute to the global economy. Recognising the existence
of microeconomics, and understanding their nuanced problems, will go a long way
in bringing a change.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhishek Sancheti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      
        <category term="trending" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Niue (a small island nation in the Pacific Ocean) has a population even less than the number of students studying in the Shri Ram College of Commerce, University of Delhi. According to the World Bank, all economies with a population of less than 0.5 million are considered to be “micro.” At present, there are 29 such countries which constitute around 15% of the total number of countries in the world. They are usually found together in groups and are prevalent in three regions: the Caribbean, the Pacific, and Africa. Despite their spread across the world, they have negligible say in the functioning of the world economy. And this article is an attempt to understand the economic systems of the ‘subaltern’ countries of the world. These economies (also called micro-economies) are either landlocked countries or island nations, mostly present in the middle of nowhere. In either case, they are isolated from the ‘markets’. This increases the cost of transportation as the goods either have to travel long distances over oceans or through several countries. This increases the overall cost of production which makes the goods produced in these countries unattractive in international markets, and imports costly. As a result, exports in the commodity sector is low in these economies. Micro-economies have limited labour supply in the market. A labourer is expected to perform several duties which leads to the overburdening of work. This reduces labour productivity and labourers are unable to specialise in one kind of work. Thus, the economy cannot receive the benefits of specialisation and division of labour. Contrary to enjoying economies of scale, micro-economies face ‘diseconomies of size’ due to low demand and high production costs. Very evidently, micro-economies are unattractive for new market entrants. Hence, these markets are generally a monopoly or an oligopoly, which provide a limited range of products and services at high costs. High costs, in turn, lead to poverty and large income inequalities. This can be substantiated from the fact that countries like Lesotho, Guinea-Bissau, Gambia, Gabon, Suriname have more than 40% of their total population living below the internationally accepted poverty line of $1.90 per day. Limited production also leads to extremely low GNP per capita: Comoros, Gambia, Guinea-Bissau and Sao Tome and Principe have a GNP per capita of less than $500. Production is not the only area where economies of scale benefit a country. It is seen that economies of scale greatly benefits an economy when it comes to providing social security and creating social and economic infrastructure, as well. A country with a huge population and a higher number of taxpayers has huge amounts of money to spend on infrastructure. The cost of social security, as well as social and economic infrastructure, is spread over a larger population. This reduces the cost incurred per person for providing these facilities. In the case of small economies, the population, as well as the number of taxpayers, is low. Hence, the governments of these countries have almost no money to spend on building and developing economic infrastructures such as highways and roadways, and social infrastructures like schools and hospitals. All this ensures foreign investment never comes into these countries, creating a chakravyuh (vicious cycle) of poverty. With limited production capacities and little diversification, micro-economies are generally capable of specialising in the production of one good or service, in which they have an advantage over other economies. Due to the low population, the demand for their commodities is low and limited. This means that they are ready to export the commodity in which they have a competitive advantage over the rest of the world. Many of these economies are also highly dependent on tourism. This is evident from the fact that tourism constitutes more than 50% in Fiji and more than 40% in Vanuatu and the Caribbean States as part of their total exports. In fact, imports and exports combined constitute more than 100% of the GDP of these countries. But this high degree of openness also makes it highly vulnerable to international events and shocks. Their vulnerability can be seen as how these economies developed at staggering paces of more than 8% per annum before 2008. But, as soon as the 2008 financial crisis hit, the income from tourism sector plummeted rapidly. This had such an impact on the economies that these countries grew at -1% to 0% for the next two years. Vulnerability also makes income more volatile. It is seen that the standard deviation of the real per capita GDP growth is more than 9. This means that there can be an average of 9% change per annum in their per capita GDP, as compared to the world average of 3.2%. These economies also function as parasites. Just like parasites feed upon the parent trees, these economies feed and depend upon a large economy which is beside them. The Caribbean States depend upon Mexico and the US, the African island nations in the Indian Ocean depend upon India, and those in the Pacific depend upon Australia and New Zealand. Most of their trade (over 90%) is carried out with these large economies and in most cases, they take up their currency as well. Therefore, how these large economies fare in the global market decides the fate of these micro-economies. However, these ‘parent economies’ seldom take interest in investing in their children. Hence, micro-economies turn towards the International Monetary Fund, the International Development Association and various other regional and international development banks for grants and unilateral advances for developmental funding. These grants go a long way in helping micro-economies provide their citizens with basic necessities. Research suggests that these grants have helped reduce poverty levels by around 2-5% in different micro-economies. One of the recent challenges that these countries face is global warming and increased danger of disasters. As most of these countries are islands or chains of islands, they are just metres above sea level. The rising sea level and the increased frequency of natural disasters has increased the risk of complete disappearance of these island nations. Adequate disaster management is necessary, which requires funds. Owing to lack of funds, these countries have to look towards the international community and the United Nations for their sustenance and to equip them with various techniques of disaster risk management. Debt bells ringing. In spite of having so many problems, micro-economies have some advantages as well. As most of these small economies are a group of islands, they have access to huge amounts of the ocean as their territory. Thus, these economies have Exclusive Economic Zones (EEZ’s) in the oceans. These economies usually grant foreign multinational corporations permission for fishing and extract resources from the EEZs against a charge. This has become one of the main sources of income, apart from allowing military bases of other countries to be set up on their territory (China and India are watching closely). Some of these economies also serve as tax havens for the rich billionaires and multinational corporations. They have very lax to no tax laws. The most prominent example would be of Cayman Islands (population - 23,000), which by the mid-1990’s, became the world’s fifth largest banking centre measured by deposits. There are more than 560 banks registered in this micro-nation, including major accounting, audit and law firms. The Caymans are the ideal tax haven as they provide “tax efficient asset protection”. There are no taxes, no exchange controls and no threat to the ‘confidentiality’ of deposits. As Alberto Alesina said in his book Size of Nations: “Whether country size matters for economic prosperity depends on a country’s degree of economic integration with the rest of the world.” Similarly, these economies too, have to integrate with the world economy if they wish to develop and prosper. They cannot depend on a single economy or a single commodity for their development. Maldives and Fiji are two micro-economies which have seen tremendous growth in these recent years after opening up their economies to the world. They are not totally dependent on their regional powers or a single commodity for trade. However, they are still part of the exception than the norm. Other micro-economies too can look up to them, and try, develop, progress and finally contribute to the global economy. Recognising the existence of microeconomics, and understanding their nuanced problems, will go a long way in bringing a change.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Venezuela: A Country Being Played?</title>
      <link href="/Venezuela-A-Country-Being-Played" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Venezuela: A Country Being Played?" />
      <published>2019-02-07T05:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T05:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Venezuela-A-Country-Being-Played</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Venezuela-A-Country-Being-Played">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/atreyi.bhaumik/&quot;&gt;In my previous articles&lt;/a&gt;, I have spoken about Latin America, its foundations, shortcomings, and how the past shall shape its future. Today, I talk about Venezuela, its decade-old story, its battle for survival and the turn of events. Fate does play cruel games with us at times, and Venezuela is a prime example of a country that has been played. From being one of the stronger economies of Latin America, Venezuela has seen a chronic downfall which would have been unimaginable only two decades ago. In the span of ten short years, everything has miraculously changed. Venezuela is now one of the most volatile countries in the world and is facing absolute poverty like no other country at the moment. This is a strange phenomenon, for the country is well endowed with oil reserves and is also one of the OPEC members. A scarcity of resources for a ‘petronation’ seems to be astounding. But poverty isn’t the worst of all that Venezuela faces. The law and order of the country is in shambles and despite having skilled labour, it has gone down the same road as Syria or Iraq (though there is no terror organization functioning just yet). When other countries are reaching milestones in the context of economic freedom, and political liberty, Venezuela is coping up with poverty and extreme cases of starvation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign support to the country, especially in monetary terms, is relatively minuscule. China has poured almost $60 billion into the country as foreign investment, and through trade. But now, even China is reluctant, and new money given to the nation doesn’t add up to significant amounts. The only country showing faith amongst all others is Russia. However, foreign support or not, the disaster that has been wrecked throughout Venezuela by the present regime of Nicolas Maduro is too great to really be helped at all. There is not even an ounce of doubt regarding the fact that, under Nicolas Maduro, power has been abused. And from healthcare to education, the country is struggling to keep afloat. People in huge numbers are suffering from diseases like malaria, measles and tuberculosis, with no medical help or any other proper facilities. Underinvestment and corruption have left the healthcare system in shambles. Starvation, poverty, corruption, and violence in the nation has led to the commoners fleeing to get away from an oppressive rule. In fact, statistics show that approximately three million people have fled the country since 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venezuela is one of the most astounding cases of economic mismanagement and too much concentration of power in the hands of the state. Venezuela’s people see no hope for the future, while their country sees prices double every month. The GDP has halved and the country’s pension scheme helps no one. Oil production has gone down to a meagre one million barrels a day, cutting off a huge proportion of revenue from the oil export business. In addition, the country is so deep in debt that people have lost the ability to hold their heads high. The middle class is highly irked and aggressively vocal about their feelings towards the dictator. And this has led to protests in most of the regions, especially due to the fact that they believe the elections were rigged. According to a survey report, about 80% of the population (32 million) does not recognise Mr Maduro as their supreme leader. But Maduro seems to be untouchable with the army at his disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slowly, the world is finally responding to the crisis along with Venezuela’s political opposition. Juan Guaido, the leader of the National Assembly has proclaimed to be the true leader of the nation. To show support and appreciation for Guaido, around one million men and women took to the streets. Their march was a demand for a proper democracy and greater rights for the innocent people who are paying the price for an unruly regime. Guaido too is playing on the same emotions of the people. He has stated that he wants to “rebuild” the country and bring back proper democracy. The path to removing Maduro, however, is a dangerous one. Many might even call it fruitless. The dictatorship has in the past responded to such opposition leaders with violence. However, Venezuelans believe that Guaido’s case is different from the rest because of the timing. The army, which has fiercely protected Maduro till now, is said to have lost interest, given they are not paid enough. Due to hyperinflation, the 36 thousand bolivars that they earn per month is almost next to nothing. The army demands and supports the side with money. If Maduro cannot keep them satisfied, then the situation might reverse in favour of Guaido and the people. Towards the end of January, Guaido released a statement saying that he has indeed talked to the army in order to make it switch sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various western countries have stood up in support of Guaido as the interim President till the elections are announced.  The United States has taken the matter to the United Nations and has called for military intervention. So now, instead of it being a Venezuelan matter, it is becoming an issue of global politics. Everyone is pitching in according to whom they favour more. The US and its allies have come down on Maduro. The US government has withheld payments for oil and has stated that they would pay only when the legitimate leader, Guaido, comes into power. Economic sanctions imposed on the country have made Venezuela even poorer, and the lack of money has facilitated a sharper drop in the production of crude oil. The oil industry of Venezuela could collapse any day now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the main game, under such circumstances remains between the US, Russia, and China. It seems like this is a desperate move by the US to regain control in Latin America, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/China-in-Latin-America&quot;&gt;where Chinese presence has grown by leaps and bounds over half a decade&lt;/a&gt;. As for Russia, a military intervention in Venezuela would show (to put it bluntly) the finger to the US just like in Crimea. But the real question is, does military intervention (by the US or Russia) really help the masses in Venezuela? How can one be sure that it wouldn’t turn into another Libya or Syria, where the US military had intervened to “give power back to the people” but ended up causing chaos and violence. Will US military action unite Venezuela by removing Maduro from power or destroy yet another country with oil reserves? The truth of the situation right now is that if the US really comes down to military action, then no other country will stop it. Be it China or Russia. They will all watch the spectacle because going against the US in its own backyard is foolish and in every way a loss for them, economically or politically. The aggression will make them pay dearly, and they are not really interested in what happens to Venezuela. Also, the showdown will only make matters messier and no one wants another Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should get to know what happens next in a matter of time, given the amount of urgency that’s been shown on both the fronts. For the Venezuelans, it is a choice between the lesser and bigger evil, and one cannot know which is which. But the truth is that people are suffering and the world community, as usual, is playing the power game that it so dearly loves. What hasn’t changed is that human lives and their conditions are all being overlooked. In this day and age, power is dear to all. Thus, all try to hold on strongly to their power. All rationale aside, this situation begs the question of where power truly lies. Is the US way of military supremacy a better method than the Chinese methodical hegemony or not? Recognizing Juan Guaido as the interim President has already started a massive uprising, and we are yet to see if this intervention in Venezuela starts a civil war or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      
        <category term="trending" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In my previous articles, I have spoken about Latin America, its foundations, shortcomings, and how the past shall shape its future. Today, I talk about Venezuela, its decade-old story, its battle for survival and the turn of events. Fate does play cruel games with us at times, and Venezuela is a prime example of a country that has been played. From being one of the stronger economies of Latin America, Venezuela has seen a chronic downfall which would have been unimaginable only two decades ago. In the span of ten short years, everything has miraculously changed. Venezuela is now one of the most volatile countries in the world and is facing absolute poverty like no other country at the moment. This is a strange phenomenon, for the country is well endowed with oil reserves and is also one of the OPEC members. A scarcity of resources for a ‘petronation’ seems to be astounding. But poverty isn’t the worst of all that Venezuela faces. The law and order of the country is in shambles and despite having skilled labour, it has gone down the same road as Syria or Iraq (though there is no terror organization functioning just yet). When other countries are reaching milestones in the context of economic freedom, and political liberty, Venezuela is coping up with poverty and extreme cases of starvation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Tobacco and Marketing: An Anomaly?</title>
      <link href="/Tobacco-and-Marketing-An-Anomaly" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tobacco and Marketing: An Anomaly?" />
      <published>2019-02-07T03:57:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T03:57:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Tobacco-and-Marketing-An-Anomaly</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Tobacco-and-Marketing-An-Anomaly">&lt;p&gt;In September 1995, Pierre Omidyar, a 28-year old computer programmer finished the code for what would soon become eBay. Searching around for a test item, he put up a broken laser pointer for sale with the base price as $1. The laser pointer sold for $14.83. Shocked, Omidyar contacted the winning bidder to make sure he understood the laser pointer was broken. “Oh yes”, the bidder replied, “I am a collector of broken laser pointers.” Trade creates value by moving goods from people who value them less to people who value them more. Tobacco happens to be a product valued greatly by a variety of stakeholders. It is for this reason that we continue to trade and rampantly consume it in spite of its tribulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like the laser pointer, tobacco products are also ‘broken’ goods – unfit for use. Regardless, however, one can always find people wanting to purchase them, even if they have to bid high to acquire them. But, has anyone cared to wonder why? The answer to this question is obscure and complicated, yet evident and simple: &lt;i&gt;“They are cool, available, and addictive.”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are they cool? Well, celebrities endorse them in movies; Mickey Mouse, Popeye and The Flintstones on television. Why are they available? Probably because we want them, just as governments want their tax revenues and companies their profits. But they are addictive! Are McDonald’s, PUBG, and One Direction not? Tobacco products are like any other commodity. They have a demand and hence a supply. Now, in order to help demand meet supply, companies need to reach out to consumers by marketing themselves. These companies too, are like all other companies. They have a profit maximisation target and hence a purpose for existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, despite having brought the tobacco industry at par with other industries, can we permit it to be part of the same marketing ambit? Or can we even permit it to market its products in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earliest known advertisement in the United States was for the snuff and tobacco products of &amp;lt;P. Lorillard and Company and was placed in the New York daily papers in 1789. Advertising was an emerging concept, and tobacco-related advertisements were not seen as any different from those for other products: their negative impact on health was unknown at the time. American Tobacco was engaged in competitive advertising of its Bull Durham chewable tobacco leaves as well. Around the Great Depression, it ran campaigns like the &lt;i&gt;“Roll Your Own”&lt;/i&gt; campaign and boosted outdoor advertising by way of elegant wall paintings and graffiti. These cleverly designed advertisements were made to persuade the lower and middle-class masses to imitate the upper-class gentry by purchasing elite yet economical tobacco products: a bag of tobacco for just a nickel at the time. Through their &lt;i&gt;“Hit the Bull”&lt;/i&gt; campaign, the Blackwell Company was able to rope in baseball players to endorse their brand. If we observe carefully, such marketing techniques are not only ludicrous but also morally unacceptable today. An advertisement depicting class distinction would bring doom upon the company, and no sports person would endorse these products, parents would rush to scrape off wall paintings before their children could have a glance. Why is there this sudden change in our attitude towards tobacco? It is generally a legal substance after all, unless specifically prohibited as done in a few countries…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer lies in our awareness: I believe we are more informed about the dangers of tobacco than ever before. The first noteworthy scientific report concerning the dangers of cigarettes was published in 1964, by the Surgeon General of the United States. Terry (1964) illustrates important deductions by the Advisory Committee – smoking was found to be: “A cause of lung cancer and laryngeal cancer in men, a probable cause of lung cancer in women, the most important cause of chronic bronchitis.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senators in the US, thereafter, passed several laws to regulate the advertising of tobacco products. The Federal Cigarette Labeling and Advertising Act of 1965 mandated all cigarette boxes to come with a warning label. In 1971, there was a ban on the advertisement of tobacco products on television and radio. Countries like Australia have defeated giants like Philip Morris by legislating “plain packaging” of cigarettes in order to intensify the fight against tobacco. Very similar to a depiction in the movie &lt;i&gt;Thank you for Smoking&lt;/i&gt;(2005), cigarette companies in India have attempted partnering with Bollywood to get celebrities to promote smoking. The government has hence made it mandatory to include cautionary messages in films and music videos that show people smoking. This comes in response to cigarette companies trying to attract and indulge youngsters in embracing their poison. &lt;i&gt;“They try to hook our kids using cartoons and symbols.”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The global population of smokers increased from 721 million in 1980 to 967 million in 2012, and the number of cigarettes smoked has risen from 4.96 trillion to 6.25 trillion between the same time periods. Of the 1.22 billion smokers today, 1 billion of them live in developing or transitional economies. Rates of smoking have levelled off or declined in the developed world. In the developing world, tobacco consumption is rising by 3.4% every year. In 2002, about 20% of teens aged 13 to 15 smoked tobacco worldwide. Approximately 80,000 to 100,000 children in this age bracket begin smoking every day. Half of those who begin smoking in adolescent years are projected to go on to smoke for 15 to 20 years. Today’s teenager is tomorrow’s potential regular customer. It has been rightly said that &lt;i&gt;“tobacco takes care of its own”&lt;/i&gt; and own only: an invisible Invisible Hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Against all odds, we are striving to change the &lt;i&gt;“smoking is cool”&lt;/i&gt; notion, we are motivated to invent new kinds of alternatives that are not ‘addictive’ and also come up with treatments for lung diseases, but, in the face of our numerous measures to counter the tobacco menace, nothing really seems to be working. Probably because of its extensive ‘availability’ that no one is willing to put an end to. Why would they? The global spending, right from manufacturing cigarettes to treating the diseases they leave behind, is unbelievably enormous. The tobacco industry generates an income for not only its own farmers and employees but also other industries, their stakeholders, and governments at large. In 2014, tobacco companies spent more than $9 billion on marketing cigarettes and smokeless tobacco in the United States. This amount translates to nearly $25 million each day, or about $1 million every hour (Federal Trade Commission, 2016). Smoking-related illness in the United States costs more than $300 billion each year (US Department of Health and Human Services, 2014). Notwithstanding the economic wonders (including tax revenues) it is doing, only truly passionate, non-profit, non-governmental organizations are capable of opposing the ‘availability’ of tobacco. But, how many of these godly organizations actually exist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having intricately analyzed the trade mechanics of tobacco and its marketing approach, I can obviously agree that tobacco products do not qualify as ethically marketable products. I will certainly not provide marketing services to Big Tobacco or be one of those lawyers that protect cigarette companies in lawsuits. However, this being said, I also do not believe it is morally correct for us to deprive tobacco companies of access to marketing. Should it be regulated? Absolutely. Can we allow it to cater to all age groups? Absolutely not. But should we not ban its marketing completely? If and only if we are also banning cigarettes and all other forms of tobacco. Half-convinced that would never happen, I believe there at least needs to be stringent legislation on a code of conduct for tobacco firms to follow for advertisement of their products locally. What is ethical for one country might be the gravest of crimes for another. We cannot have a universal code of conduct in this aspect, nor can we decide for legal consumers: that would be morally presumptuous. After all, they have a choice of their own.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shivang Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      
        <category term="trending" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In September 1995, Pierre Omidyar, a 28-year old computer programmer finished the code for what would soon become eBay. Searching around for a test item, he put up a broken laser pointer for sale with the base price as $1. The laser pointer sold for $14.83. Shocked, Omidyar contacted the winning bidder to make sure he understood the laser pointer was broken. “Oh yes”, the bidder replied, “I am a collector of broken laser pointers.” Trade creates value by moving goods from people who value them less to people who value them more. Tobacco happens to be a product valued greatly by a variety of stakeholders. It is for this reason that we continue to trade and rampantly consume it in spite of its tribulations.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Editorial: On The Importance of Sex</title>
      <link href="/Importance-of-sex" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Editorial: On The Importance of Sex" />
      <published>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Importance-of-sex</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Importance-of-sex">&lt;p&gt;It is most certainly not easy writing about sex. To begin with, you have to deal with the fact that once you start talking about orgasms, breasts, penises and foot fetishes (the human mind is an unholy place), it is very easy to sound like you are writing plain-old erotica—cheap, unsophisticated, and yet very arousing. At the same time though, if you try to distance yourself from the human depravity of sex, you could sound more like a plumber describing a u-bend when exploring whether the G-Spot really exists. I want to avoid making such serious stylistic errors, but I don’t want to forget that any conversation about sex has to be both erotic and exciting whilst being decidedly technical about a topic that is so serious. I remember watching an interview of Philip Roth (you kind of have to read and listen to him when thinking about sex and literature), where he declared quite hilariously that when he and his friends were sixteen they had only question about sex: &lt;em&gt;“WHEN? WHEN? WHEN?!!”&lt;/em&gt; That kind of desperation was not simply because of an animal drive within us, according to Roth. If his book &lt;i&gt;Portnoy’s Complaint&lt;/i&gt; (which is about a mother-obsessed, masturbation addict) is any indication, the want for sex in human beings can lead to all kinds of things both disgusting and sexy. The power that sex holds over our lives can lead to all sorts of problems, from the relatively benign but hideous (think Diogenes masturbating in the open streets) to the debauched (think Marquis De Sade’s &lt;i&gt;120 Days of Sodom&lt;/i&gt;) and to even wholesale exploitation (think prostitution). There is a reason why “sex sells” and there’s a reason why clerics don’t want even the ankles of women to be visible to men. Sex lies at the very human intersection of patriarchy, fulfilment, love, exploitation, power and everything else in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think a brilliant place to find a conversation about sex that is stimulating (in the right way) is the comments section of any porn video (it’s also a good way of ensuring the video is a good one!). The things people say (and don’t say) about sex in these comments is so profoundly revealing (never thought I’d use the word profound when writing about sex!). These comments tell us that people don’t just watch porn to simply &lt;em&gt;“bust a nut or yaw yaw the sisterhood”&lt;/em&gt;. Masturbation is a very sensuous thing in our lives: It relieves boredom, which is perennially the human mind’s most wicked enemy and it gives us the opportunity to enjoy the feelings (and hormones) that sex brings with the most important person in our erotic lives: ourselves. Therefore, it is no wonder that people have such strikingly specific criticisms of the acting in the video, or the stilettos of the female porn star, or the absolutely unrealistic time for which the male porn star lasts. People put up comments stating all sorts of things, from the things they found funny like the orgasm face of the actors or the scenes they felt where outright bizarre like one where they felt the porn star’s screaming was extremely unappealing as it sounded like a &lt;em&gt;“donkey braying”&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Porn is about the deep voyeurism that inhabits the human mind, it is about finding release (literally) and for that one needs a good experience. Put it this way: when we want to release our bowels we want a clean toilet that smells good, when we want to fulfil our hunger we want food that tastes good, and when we want to avoid the cold we want a jumper that looks good. If we want quality in all other things, should it surprise anyone that we want porn to be more than just people “doing it” with each other? Good pornography is important for the same reason that anything is important to human beings, we are not just Plato’s “featherless birds” and we don’t just have sex in caves (HA!). Unlike the plots and scripts of most porn movies, human beings are interesting in nature, and their erotic lives reflect that via their desires from pornography. There’s a reason why &lt;i&gt;Playboy&lt;/i&gt; Magazine, instead of just having any other nudes, had Marilyn Monroe’s nudes. And there is a reason why Pornhub has reported a phenomenal rise in the consumption of incest porn by…(drum-roll)…millennials!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sex as an activity is about satisfying the human imagination—otherwise, a few grunts and no foreplay would have kept everyone happy. On the issue of ‘grunts’, we all know that men can have very few problems when it ‘comes’ to (pardon the pun) reaching climax, whereas there is a whole body of feminist literature on how women don’t really climax at all most of the time. The common form that the female orgasm takes is due to clitoral stimulation, and the reason why women do not really come due to vaginal stimulation is because, well, men don’t usually last long enough. This creates an obviously skewered power dynamic in sex, where men are able to “unload” ever so easily and women are left feeling constantly under-appreciated. I don’t mean to say that this means men are near-constantly aroused pigs who pay no heed to the needs of their female partners, although there is truth in that contention. My point here is simply that without a good amount of foreplay and some good oral sex, our sexual activities with all their imaginative passion can simply end up being a dull series of painful thrusts for one whole half of the human population—and sex must be far more than that if in these feminist times we men are to redeem ourselves for having treated women as objects of sex for thousands of years. Ancient India, being a culture at a stupendous height of civilisation, was acutely aware of the consequences of denying women the beauty of an orgasm. As Wendy Doniger, a controversial yet revered Indologist, points out, even the legendary &lt;i&gt;Kama Sutra&lt;/i&gt; is clear on the fact that women must orgasm first, given how easy it is for men to do so. The message is clear and has been clear for more than a thousand years: boys, at least try to find the fabled G-spot once in a while instead of just seeking blowjobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power dynamics of sex bring up a very curious issue with specific regard to sex between homosexual men. It is difficult to accurately describe how significantly being either a ‘top’ or a ‘bottom’ has an effect on the masculinity of gay men (MEN!!). The power politics in that part of human sexuality has assumed new proportions with the world’s gay community bidding adieu to the stereotype of the “camp” gay man and welcoming a more traditionally masculine homosexual male as more desirable. As Kevin Troughton &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/nov/30/the-end-of-camp-straight-acting-gay&quot;&gt;writes&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;i&gt;The Guardian&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;em&gt;“very few find [camp] sexually attractive. That limp-wristed, bitchy queen might be hilarious, but you wouldn’t want him as a boyfriend, or even as a one-night stand.”&lt;/em&gt; The fact is “bottoming” gay men have always been stereotyped into the camp category, facing potentially even internalised homophobia due to their perceived passivity in the gay community. And now with the rise in the desirability of the straight-acting gay alpha male, it would appear that all men who wish to receive anal sex will potentially have greater issues relating to dominance and estimations of their own masculinity. Funny enough, all of this simply reinforces the words of Oscar Wilde: &lt;em&gt;“Everything in the world is about sex except sex. Sex is about power”&lt;/em&gt;. It is slightly hilarious but definitely unsurprising that men having sex with other men is where power dynamics take centre stage, after all, the ‘male ego’ manifests itself most strongly in front of other men!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between love and sex is complicated (well, of course). And if you have read a bit of Freud (he has to be mentioned in a discussion on sex, you know, #respect), sex and love are both about your mum. Obviously, his Oedipus Complex and theories on the development of libido are a bit bogus, but his underlying assertion that we learn how to have relationships primarily from our parents makes a lot of intuitive sense. Parents give their children a reality, they define what human interaction means for them and they do so simply because that’s how it is, for good or for bad. This means people’s relationships are (to a degree) shaped by the experiences given to them by their childhood and their parents. The problem is that people fall in love with the people they have sex with quite often and vice versa! And people falling in love leads to all sorts of problems like marriage, infidelity, drama and the responsibility to take care of children. The very point of sex leads to relationships that are determined on factors outside your control (your mum!), and lead to a sexual rut (your children) with added responsibilities of bringing up another human being—so that the cycle can continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is definitely weird talking about sex and extremely difficult to treat it with the sensitivity and respect it deserves. But it certainly is fun to think about and research on something that is so goddamn brilliant. I mean, my research showed me that orgasms could be had by brain dead people if the right nerves are stimulated! And it was facts and observations like this that made my task ever so out-of-control. Yes, sex is important, I could see that, but what is the common thread that makes it all ever so important? And why? I think I have chanced upon a simple answer to these questions: sex is humanity’s deepest desires manifested in the most physical of acts, and for that very reason it’s going to be more than just a simple act. Adieu!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      
        <category term="trending" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is most certainly not easy writing about sex. To begin with, you have to deal with the fact that once you start talking about orgasms, breasts, penises and foot fetishes (the human mind is an unholy place), it is very easy to sound like you are writing plain-old erotica—cheap, unsophisticated, and yet very arousing. At the same time though, if you try to distance yourself from the human depravity of sex, you could sound more like a plumber describing a u-bend when exploring whether the G-Spot really exists. I want to avoid making such serious stylistic errors, but I don’t want to forget that any conversation about sex has to be both erotic and exciting whilst being decidedly technical about a topic that is so serious. I remember watching an interview of Philip Roth (you kind of have to read and listen to him when thinking about sex and literature), where he declared quite hilariously that when he and his friends were sixteen they had only question about sex: “WHEN? WHEN? WHEN?!!” That kind of desperation was not simply because of an animal drive within us, according to Roth. If his book Portnoy’s Complaint (which is about a mother-obsessed, masturbation addict) is any indication, the want for sex in human beings can lead to all kinds of things both disgusting and sexy. The power that sex holds over our lives can lead to all sorts of problems, from the relatively benign but hideous (think Diogenes masturbating in the open streets) to the debauched (think Marquis De Sade’s 120 Days of Sodom) and to even wholesale exploitation (think prostitution). There is a reason why “sex sells” and there’s a reason why clerics don’t want even the ankles of women to be visible to men. Sex lies at the very human intersection of patriarchy, fulfilment, love, exploitation, power and everything else in between.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Diary of a Confused Indian Economics Student</title>
      <link href="/Confused-Indian-Econs-Student" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diary of a Confused Indian Economics Student" />
      <published>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Confused-Indian-Econs-Student</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Confused-Indian-Econs-Student">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dear Diary,&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I return to you, yet again. You have been a constant support in times like these. I wonder if this happens with everyone- for days, you are the king of your small world, a world which you understand; then, all of a sudden, everything crumbles down, every fact which you thought was true becomes fiction, every emotion you had turns out to be shallow, every moment you lived seems worthless. I feel shelterless, the roof of meaning taken away from above my head. Hence, here I am, meaningless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must be used to my spiraling down of emotions by now. However, this time, it’s different (trust me). Unlike all my previous breakdowns, there is no particular person to blame, and this leaves me even more clueless. How puny us humans are, always looking for a guilty party, to make ourselves feel lighter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On to the issue now. The reason behind my sudden disillusionment with the world is the new Indian GDP back series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is it? Oh, of course, I have to explain it, you are just a silly diary!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, the GDP growth rate of our country over the past decade or so has been revised and updated. As per the updated GDP data, India grew at 6.7% between 2004 and 2014. This is in contrast to previous figures of 8.1% from 2004-09 and 7.46% from 2009-14.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s the issue with that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I AM NOT SURE. That’s the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not sure if we are a high growth economy or not. The world thinks so (or thought so). Even I thought so, till yesterday. However, the new data doesn’t. We never crossed the 9% growth rate, EVER.  Some numbers here and there, and I am questioning my own country’s growth story, something which I was proud of (till yesterday, of course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this mean we never grew at the pace we thought we had? But, I have seen luxuries become necessities for the consumer every five years, middle class getting richer, sons earning in their first year more than what their fathers earned throughout their lives. Doesn’t this count as exceptional growth? Or worse, what we experienced in the past decade was nothing exceptional, and the Indian economy, even after 70 years, has nothing to show for achievements. No, no, this cannot be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, if we didn’t achieve high growth (more than 9%), what explains the high inflation we faced towards the end of 2013? How can there be high inflation without high growth? Was the inflation JUST because of external factors like Oil? So much purchasing power wiped away by double digit inflation rates because a few countries (Read: OPEC) wanted to have fun with the world? The worst of my thoughts are yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world knows that we have a highly indebted banking sector. Rising NPAs (non-performing assets, basically loans given by banks which don’t get repaid completely) have been the single largest threat to the Indian economy for the past 5 years, at least. It is widely acknowledged that banks lent rapidly (and sometimes indiscriminately) between 2008 and 2014, which has led to this problem today. However, in the short-term, this excessive lending helped us achieve exceptional growth rates, even touching 10.3% in 2010-11. All this, obviously, as per the old data. Now, the ‘excessive lending’ (should we still call it that?), which has created an unprecedented crisis in our economy, didn’t even help us achieve ‘high growth’ phase. Much ado about nothing. Why doesn’t the government also downgrade the NPAs in the economy? I am sure there is a way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh Diary, spare a thought for all the poor foreign investors who were fooled into investing into this apparently ‘high growth’ economy which wasn’t! A decade of optimism, all for nothing. It was a lie. A scam. In case I haven’t made it clear enough, an economy is in a ‘high growth’ phase when it crosses 9% growth, which India didn’t (I know I have made it pretty clear. I just needed another reason to repeat it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s interesting is that the new GDP data has been released by NITI Aayog, a government think-tank, and not by the Central Statistics Office, as is the norm. I feel sad for poor Adarsh, my close friend. He is working so hard to join the Indian Statistical Institute in Kolkata, only to find his dream job is being taken over by a bureaucrat run organization!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two beneficiaries from the new data, though, and this (somewhat) gives me a reason to smile: Unemployed youth and distressed farmers. These poor fellows had been wondering how did a high-growth phase not create enough jobs/ increase the standard of living for them. They now have an answer: there was no high growth economy to produce jobs/ increase standard of living in the first place!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I am just overreacting. Yes, yes. I am overreacting. Arvind Virmani, our former Chief Economic Advisor, has said that usually GDP data updates like this one lead to a downgrade of a country’s growth. He must know better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just, one thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before this data was released, another revised GDP data was ‘leaked’. As per this particular leaked data, India actually grew at a faster pace than even previously estimated. Yes! We touched double digit growth more often than we had thought. However, the government (this happened a few months ago) had then said that the revision of GDP numbers is still under process and these are not the final numbers. What I understand is that there are several ways to revise GDP numbers, and the leaked and the newly released official version are only two of the many alternatives. SURELY, the government won’t intentionally recognize a methodology to discredit the growth rates under it’s political rival. Surely, it won’t. Not before an election year. Definitely not. After all, this government is known for respecting institutions (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ndtv.com/india-news/rbi-vs-government-10-things-to-know-1941159&quot;&gt;Read: RBI&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am really sorry, I know I am going over-board. I just have a few silly questions to end with (Don’t laugh). If our percentage growth has been downgraded, our absolute GDP must have come down too, wouldn’t it? I was hearing that Indian GDP (nominal basis) will overtake United Kingdom’s in 2019. I suppose this won’t happen. OR will it? Why hasn’t our absolute GDP number been downgraded, yet? Data also shows that India did not recover from the global financial crisis as quickly as initially thought. Are we a resilient economy as we thought we were, or not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several international institutions have been coming up with research (using old data) showing the huge number of people India lifted out of poverty, something which I take pride in. A low GDP growth means more people must still be under poverty than previously estimated. &lt;em&gt;‘A stroke of a pen and millions are poor again’&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t end on such a melancholic note. Hear this story:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
 Last week, I asked my philosophy teacher this, “What GDP number, what military capability, what standard of living, what cultural clout do we need to achieve in order to become a Superpower?”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My teacher’s answer left me thinking, and it seems relevant today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

“0”

&lt;br /&gt;

“0?”, I asked confused.

&lt;br /&gt;

He said, “What use is any of what you said to a nation whose soul is great enough to capture hearts of billions? Develop the soul of your nation.”

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diary, you know what’s the best part about developing the soul of my nation? No methodology can downgrade it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidyarthi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      
        <category term="trending" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Dear Diary,</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
