<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/trending/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-01-16T13:19:22+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/trending/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Chomsky-esque Analysis of Farmer Protests</title>
      <link href="/A-Chomsky-esque-Analysis-of-Farmer-Protests" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Chomsky-esque Analysis of Farmer Protests" />
      <published>2021-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Chomsky-esque-Analysis-of-Farmer-Protests</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Chomsky-esque-Analysis-of-Farmer-Protests">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Arguably the most important intellectual alive&lt;/em&gt;” according to &lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt;, Noam Chomsky is a veteran linguist and public intellectual who has immensely contributed to the field of media studies. My exploration of Chomsky’s writings happened during my graduation course in journalism. What intrigued me most about his works was the application of his studies to a plethora of current affairs. Talking specifically about his ‘Propaganda Model’ which he first presented with Edward. S Herman in their book &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manufacturing_Consent&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manufacturing Consent: The Political Economy of the Mass Media&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (1988), the theory examines media control in the social, cultural and political sectors of society. In their book, Chomsky and Herman explain the effect of wealth and power on mass media interests and choices. They say, “[The model]&lt;em&gt; traces the routes by which money and power are able to filter out the news fit to print, marginalise dissent, and allow the government and dominant private interests to get their messages across to the public.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parallels of four of the five filters presented in the Propaganda Model seem to be striking in the current times as India records one of the biggest protests in world history, led by Indian farmers protesting against the three farm laws passed by the BJP Government (the Central Government). The first filter is about ‘media ownership’ which proposes that since media organisations (mostly) run with a profit motive, they tend to serve the consumers with biased news items. Selective promotion of interests and opinions fit well in the explanation of this filter. A clear depiction of this is how clearly the protesting farmers have defined the biased media by simply turning their backs at them and not agreeing to be reported by the channels that contribute to lapdog media, also popularly known as the ‘&lt;em&gt;Godi&lt;/em&gt; Media’ in India. The protestors seem to be aware of the business interests of media outlets as well as the hidden agendas of political figures who are principal investors in such outlets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advertising revenue is the second filter according to which stories that have a ‘buying mood’ in the economy find more space in the publications. What matters here is that these stories majorly rely upon the interests of the advertisers who see news more like a money-generating process than an information-driven service in journalism. This begins the marginalisation of news items as we evidently see in the current times. Top stories are altered so that there are more eyeballs on the news rather than understanding them from an objective point of view. While I agree that this very objectivity is over-celebrated in the world today, India sees a lack of representation of opinions because of conflict of interests and motives of the investors.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;News18&lt;/em&gt; channel broadcasted a piece of news titled “&lt;em&gt;Dilli Chalo War Cry: Who is misleading the farmers?&lt;/em&gt;” on November 26, 2020 that not only legitimised the injustice caused to the farmers but also assumed that they were being ‘misled’, further justifying or rather supporting the government’s decision and laws. This title brings me to the third filter that Chomsky termed as ‘sourcing’. It is important to note that the news that is broadcasted via television or print is provided through a source that can be either an agency or an individual. When the source itself decides a particular side, it only passes on information that it considers to be on the right side of the issue. This comprises the ethical and objective concerns of journalism. Asian News International (ANI), an Indian news agency has lately been criticised for such biased sourcing. While history records the largest protest in the world, reflecting the coexistence of hope and anger in the farmer’s agitation in India, ANI reported how a ‘delegation’ of farmers met the Union Agriculture Minister Narendra Singh Tomar and extended their support to the new farm laws. ANI is one of the biggest news agencies of India and its claims are widely consumed and believed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the mainstream media organisations have submitted themselves to propaganda by avoiding negative responses from the ruling party based on their published content. Here, ‘flak’, as the fourth filter, is used by such media to ensure that nothing against the will of the ‘right’ side is broadcasted as it might put the news outlet into trouble and bring down their relations and reputation amongst their viewers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we are moving towards the exponential development of the digital era, it becomes even more important to subject media to close scrutiny. News is travelling in no time and the repercussions of propaganda-based journalism can polarise the communities of the country instead of saving the sinking boat of democracy. Noam Chomsky’s Propaganda Model not only tells us about the limitations of objectivity in mass media but at the same time aligns with the manufactured consent as prevalent in the Indian context today during the Farmers’ Protest 2020.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Himanshi Saini</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Arguably the most important intellectual alive” according to The New York Times, Noam Chomsky is a veteran linguist and public intellectual who has immensely contributed to the field of media studies. My exploration of Chomsky’s writings happened during my graduation course in journalism. What intrigued me most about his works was the application of his studies to a plethora of current affairs. Talking specifically about his ‘Propaganda Model’ which he first presented with Edward. S Herman in their book Manufacturing Consent: The Political Economy of the Mass Media (1988), the theory examines media control in the social, cultural and political sectors of society. In their book, Chomsky and Herman explain the effect of wealth and power on mass media interests and choices. They say, “[The model] traces the routes by which money and power are able to filter out the news fit to print, marginalise dissent, and allow the government and dominant private interests to get their messages across to the public.” The parallels of four of the five filters presented in the Propaganda Model seem to be striking in the current times as India records one of the biggest protests in world history, led by Indian farmers protesting against the three farm laws passed by the BJP Government (the Central Government). The first filter is about ‘media ownership’ which proposes that since media organisations (mostly) run with a profit motive, they tend to serve the consumers with biased news items. Selective promotion of interests and opinions fit well in the explanation of this filter. A clear depiction of this is how clearly the protesting farmers have defined the biased media by simply turning their backs at them and not agreeing to be reported by the channels that contribute to lapdog media, also popularly known as the ‘Godi Media’ in India. The protestors seem to be aware of the business interests of media outlets as well as the hidden agendas of political figures who are principal investors in such outlets. Advertising revenue is the second filter according to which stories that have a ‘buying mood’ in the economy find more space in the publications. What matters here is that these stories majorly rely upon the interests of the advertisers who see news more like a money-generating process than an information-driven service in journalism. This begins the marginalisation of news items as we evidently see in the current times. Top stories are altered so that there are more eyeballs on the news rather than understanding them from an objective point of view. While I agree that this very objectivity is over-celebrated in the world today, India sees a lack of representation of opinions because of conflict of interests and motives of the investors.&amp;nbsp; News18 channel broadcasted a piece of news titled “Dilli Chalo War Cry: Who is misleading the farmers?” on November 26, 2020 that not only legitimised the injustice caused to the farmers but also assumed that they were being ‘misled’, further justifying or rather supporting the government’s decision and laws. This title brings me to the third filter that Chomsky termed as ‘sourcing’. It is important to note that the news that is broadcasted via television or print is provided through a source that can be either an agency or an individual. When the source itself decides a particular side, it only passes on information that it considers to be on the right side of the issue. This comprises the ethical and objective concerns of journalism. Asian News International (ANI), an Indian news agency has lately been criticised for such biased sourcing. While history records the largest protest in the world, reflecting the coexistence of hope and anger in the farmer’s agitation in India, ANI reported how a ‘delegation’ of farmers met the Union Agriculture Minister Narendra Singh Tomar and extended their support to the new farm laws. ANI is one of the biggest news agencies of India and its claims are widely consumed and believed. Most of the mainstream media organisations have submitted themselves to propaganda by avoiding negative responses from the ruling party based on their published content. Here, ‘flak’, as the fourth filter, is used by such media to ensure that nothing against the will of the ‘right’ side is broadcasted as it might put the news outlet into trouble and bring down their relations and reputation amongst their viewers. As we are moving towards the exponential development of the digital era, it becomes even more important to subject media to close scrutiny. News is travelling in no time and the repercussions of propaganda-based journalism can polarise the communities of the country instead of saving the sinking boat of democracy. Noam Chomsky’s Propaganda Model not only tells us about the limitations of objectivity in mass media but at the same time aligns with the manufactured consent as prevalent in the Indian context today during the Farmers’ Protest 2020.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Doxxing: Everything You Should Know About Not Falling Victim</title>
      <link href="/Doxxing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Doxxing: Everything You Should Know About Not Falling Victim" />
      <published>2021-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Doxxing</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Doxxing">&lt;p&gt;Doxxing has been around for a long time. You might have been a victim of doxxing – on a smaller or larger scale – and you didn't even know it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this piece, we discuss what doxxing is and what you can do to prevent it from happening in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is Doxxing?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also known as doxxing, it refers to a specific form of cyber-attack where an internet user's details are revealed and made publicly available.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doxing often occurs as a personal attack launched on a specific internet user to make them uncomfortable in their own homes. It is also a way to let the internet user know that they are not safe from their attacker's reach, no matter where they might go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to prevent doxxing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth about doxxing is that nothing you didn't put out there will be found. Thus, it can be prevented in its entirety if you know what you are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the ways to keep off the radar of this damaging attack include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Watching Social Media Activity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media is an information mine that you are not considering as much as you should be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From constant updates, picture uploads, random tweets, and more, you might be letting on bits and pieces of personal information which could be pieced together to uncover your identity online. Here, details such as your email address, home address, personal cell number, and more can be revealed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do well to limit the kind of information that you share online. If possible, make your social media accounts private such that only friends and family can follow your updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Masking your IP Address&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The internet works on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wpbeginner.com/glossary/ip-address/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;a system of IP addresses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which are uniquely assigned to each computer. Just like a physical address, the IP address is used to approximate or pinpoint the location where your computer is accessing the internet from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, anyone with access to your IP address information can extract where you are reaching the web from. Hence, they have your location also.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good measure against this is to use the Tor browser or get &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.expressvpn.com&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;a VPN app to protect your identity online&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Both services are excellent for assigning a new IP address to you whenever you access the web. Thus, anyone tracking you will always be sent on a wild goose chase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preventing Packet Sniffing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, make sure your internet network is as secure as it can be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, the hacker can break the Wi-Fi protocols and access the computers on that network. From there, there is no limit to the amount of personal information that they can get on you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An excellent place to start here is to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inc.com/comcast/risks-of-using-public-wifi.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;avoid public and free Wi-Fi networks altogether&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. When on a personal router network also, ensure the best practices at all times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a sponsored article from &lt;a href=&quot;https://techwarn.com/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TechWarn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>tech.warn</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="sponsored" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Doxxing has been around for a long time. You might have been a victim of doxxing – on a smaller or larger scale – and you didn't even know it. In this piece, we discuss what doxxing is and what you can do to prevent it from happening in the first place. What is Doxxing? Also known as doxxing, it refers to a specific form of cyber-attack where an internet user's details are revealed and made publicly available.&amp;nbsp; Doxing often occurs as a personal attack launched on a specific internet user to make them uncomfortable in their own homes. It is also a way to let the internet user know that they are not safe from their attacker's reach, no matter where they might go. How to prevent doxxing The truth about doxxing is that nothing you didn't put out there will be found. Thus, it can be prevented in its entirety if you know what you are doing. Some of the ways to keep off the radar of this damaging attack include: Watching Social Media Activity Social media is an information mine that you are not considering as much as you should be. From constant updates, picture uploads, random tweets, and more, you might be letting on bits and pieces of personal information which could be pieced together to uncover your identity online. Here, details such as your email address, home address, personal cell number, and more can be revealed. Do well to limit the kind of information that you share online. If possible, make your social media accounts private such that only friends and family can follow your updates. Masking your IP Address The internet works on a system of IP addresses which are uniquely assigned to each computer. Just like a physical address, the IP address is used to approximate or pinpoint the location where your computer is accessing the internet from. In other words, anyone with access to your IP address information can extract where you are reaching the web from. Hence, they have your location also. A good measure against this is to use the Tor browser or get a VPN app to protect your identity online. Both services are excellent for assigning a new IP address to you whenever you access the web. Thus, anyone tracking you will always be sent on a wild goose chase. Preventing Packet Sniffing In other words, make sure your internet network is as secure as it can be. Otherwise, the hacker can break the Wi-Fi protocols and access the computers on that network. From there, there is no limit to the amount of personal information that they can get on you. An excellent place to start here is to avoid public and free Wi-Fi networks altogether. When on a personal router network also, ensure the best practices at all times. This is a sponsored article from TechWarn.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The ‘America First’ Policy isn’t Going Anywhere</title>
      <link href="/The-America-First-Policy-isn-t-Going-Anywhere" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The ‘America First’ Policy isn’t Going Anywhere" />
      <published>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-America-First-Policy-isn-t-Going-Anywhere</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-America-First-Policy-isn-t-Going-Anywhere">&lt;p&gt;Europe never warmed to Donald Trump. His approval rating last year was 32% in Britain and 13% in Germany. In the corridors of the European Union (EU), I don’t imagine his approval rating edges out COVID-19’s.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Liberals in Europe are over-the-moon to see Trump go. Channel 4 was almost as excited about the election result as it was about the news of the Pfizer vaccine. They see Joe Biden as somebody to roll back Trump’s transactional foreign policy, summed up by the President’s promise of putting ‘America First’- he succeeded admirably in doing that for COVID deaths. For Europeans, however, Joe Biden will be a false dawn. ‘America First’ is here to stay.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From listening to Biden’s campaign speeches, you might share Europe’s optimism that America is about to inaugurate a President committed to rebuilding the Western alliance after four years of uncertainty. Like so much of the President-elect’s agenda, Biden’s policy towards Europe emphasises a return to normalcy. Trump never made much of an effort to impress his transatlantic partners; he imposed billions of dollars worth of tariffs on the European Union (EU) in 2019 and moaned (correctly, of course) that many North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) members weren’t committing enough money towards their own defence. Biden and his transition team have trashed Trump’s attitude towards Europe for being isolationist, and for damaging the sacred bond between Europe and the US. He stresses he wants to re-engage with old allies across the pond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a President’s tenure in the White House rarely comes to resemble the campaign they fight to get there. Why? There’s no simple answer to that. But probably the most straightforward reason is that on January 20, 2021, the Presidency will change hands, but the bureaucracy underneath it will stay almost exactly the same. Continuity is the order of the day in Washington.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In no area is this truer than America’s foreign policy. And the reality is that the unstated yet unequivocal aim of the US policy abroad has always been to put itself before others. The conventional view of the US foreign policy as being liberal and internationalist is a delusion. No President demonstrates this better than Woodrow Wilson, the man who is regarded as the flag-bearer for liberal internationalism and US engagement with the world. In spite of being remembered as an interventionist who came to the Allies’ aid during the First World War, Wilson initially resisted calls to engage in the War, preferring to condemn Europe to a ‘peace without victory’ for American gain. And what phrase did he use to justify this? You guessed it: “&lt;em&gt;America First!&lt;/em&gt;”. Franklin D Roosevelt’s (FDR) instincts were the same as Wilson’s as Europe went to war again in 1939. The US looks after its own interests first, and Europeans would do well not to fall for the Democratic party’s claims to the contrary.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this sense, Trump’s most important legacy as President will be to have capped the bullshit emanating from the State Department. His followers always loved him for ‘saying it as it is’, and he certainly did that when it came to foreign policy. He merely said out loud what the US had thought about its allies for decades. And on Europe, this rhetoric had the effect of speeding up a policy shift that was underway long before Trump got to Washington. From the US perspective, Europe is quickly becoming a backwater on the international chessboard. Asia is in the ascendancy, and nobody knows this better than Biden’s team. Don’t forget that it was Obama’s administration that pivoted towards Asia in 2013, not Trump’s.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the elephant in the room here is China. Trump’s stance on Europe and his belligerence towards the Chinese were two sides of the same coin. The Bush and Obama administrations gradually became uncomfortable with China’s rise to world power status, but on the surface, things remained rosy between the world’s two largest economies. Trump changed that, and it’s difficult to imagine Biden will put back on the gloves which the 45th President so obviously threw off. Congressional Democrats now sound just as critical of China as the Republicans do. ‘Soft on China’ has a nasty ring to it, just as ‘Soft on Communism’ did during the Cold War.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this mean for Europe? Probably that it’s time to wake up to the fact that the US isn’t as reliable an ally as it was once thought to be. The UK government’s pledge to increase defence spending is a welcome move, and I imagine that other European leaders will soon follow suit. As for the US, Biden will carry on putting his country first-in-line, but he may need to start being a little less coy about saying so. Americans love isolationism. After all, if America isn’t first in the President-elect’s eyes, where does he see it?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Europe never warmed to Donald Trump. His approval rating last year was 32% in Britain and 13% in Germany. In the corridors of the European Union (EU), I don’t imagine his approval rating edges out COVID-19’s.&amp;nbsp; Liberals in Europe are over-the-moon to see Trump go. Channel 4 was almost as excited about the election result as it was about the news of the Pfizer vaccine. They see Joe Biden as somebody to roll back Trump’s transactional foreign policy, summed up by the President’s promise of putting ‘America First’- he succeeded admirably in doing that for COVID deaths. For Europeans, however, Joe Biden will be a false dawn. ‘America First’ is here to stay.&amp;nbsp; From listening to Biden’s campaign speeches, you might share Europe’s optimism that America is about to inaugurate a President committed to rebuilding the Western alliance after four years of uncertainty. Like so much of the President-elect’s agenda, Biden’s policy towards Europe emphasises a return to normalcy. Trump never made much of an effort to impress his transatlantic partners; he imposed billions of dollars worth of tariffs on the European Union (EU) in 2019 and moaned (correctly, of course) that many North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) members weren’t committing enough money towards their own defence. Biden and his transition team have trashed Trump’s attitude towards Europe for being isolationist, and for damaging the sacred bond between Europe and the US. He stresses he wants to re-engage with old allies across the pond. But a President’s tenure in the White House rarely comes to resemble the campaign they fight to get there. Why? There’s no simple answer to that. But probably the most straightforward reason is that on January 20, 2021, the Presidency will change hands, but the bureaucracy underneath it will stay almost exactly the same. Continuity is the order of the day in Washington.&amp;nbsp; In no area is this truer than America’s foreign policy. And the reality is that the unstated yet unequivocal aim of the US policy abroad has always been to put itself before others. The conventional view of the US foreign policy as being liberal and internationalist is a delusion. No President demonstrates this better than Woodrow Wilson, the man who is regarded as the flag-bearer for liberal internationalism and US engagement with the world. In spite of being remembered as an interventionist who came to the Allies’ aid during the First World War, Wilson initially resisted calls to engage in the War, preferring to condemn Europe to a ‘peace without victory’ for American gain. And what phrase did he use to justify this? You guessed it: “America First!”. Franklin D Roosevelt’s (FDR) instincts were the same as Wilson’s as Europe went to war again in 1939. The US looks after its own interests first, and Europeans would do well not to fall for the Democratic party’s claims to the contrary.&amp;nbsp; In this sense, Trump’s most important legacy as President will be to have capped the bullshit emanating from the State Department. His followers always loved him for ‘saying it as it is’, and he certainly did that when it came to foreign policy. He merely said out loud what the US had thought about its allies for decades. And on Europe, this rhetoric had the effect of speeding up a policy shift that was underway long before Trump got to Washington. From the US perspective, Europe is quickly becoming a backwater on the international chessboard. Asia is in the ascendancy, and nobody knows this better than Biden’s team. Don’t forget that it was Obama’s administration that pivoted towards Asia in 2013, not Trump’s.&amp;nbsp; Of course, the elephant in the room here is China. Trump’s stance on Europe and his belligerence towards the Chinese were two sides of the same coin. The Bush and Obama administrations gradually became uncomfortable with China’s rise to world power status, but on the surface, things remained rosy between the world’s two largest economies. Trump changed that, and it’s difficult to imagine Biden will put back on the gloves which the 45th President so obviously threw off. Congressional Democrats now sound just as critical of China as the Republicans do. ‘Soft on China’ has a nasty ring to it, just as ‘Soft on Communism’ did during the Cold War. What does this mean for Europe? Probably that it’s time to wake up to the fact that the US isn’t as reliable an ally as it was once thought to be. The UK government’s pledge to increase defence spending is a welcome move, and I imagine that other European leaders will soon follow suit. As for the US, Biden will carry on putting his country first-in-line, but he may need to start being a little less coy about saying so. Americans love isolationism. After all, if America isn’t first in the President-elect’s eyes, where does he see it?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Meraki and More</title>
      <link href="/Meraki-and-More" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meraki and More" />
      <published>2020-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Meraki-and-More</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Meraki-and-More">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;I’ve recently had the opportunity to travel to the city where my freedom lies and be back in all of 30 minus 1 hour, and let me tell you- the thrill of running away from an ill-fashioned mask wearer, who is munching on chips as he coughs, and to look at Starbucks with nostalgia, and think of times when you didn’t have to worry about how many people might have touched that straw? Mind-blowing. The question of my sanity lies in if the risk, the multiple masks, the shield, the gloves, the chaos, all of it was worth a total of 40 minutes spent in ecstasy garnered from a bubble tea and nachos, a well-lit room and comfy hotel bed, oh, and well, a well-timed fight with your may-be/may-not-be boyfriend. Well, so was it? I wouldn’t know, might have to come back to that.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the world that we live now, not much seems to be as it was, most of all, the things that are. Every stressor is either exaggerated or it exasperates you to think of your stressor in the face of others’ much bigger ones. No problem is big enough to hold in the face of a pandemic, and that is known - but every problem is definitely magnified in the face of a pandemic and if that’s not the truth, I don’t know what is. The other day, I got my results back from an entrance that I barely prepared for and upon announcing my failure to my friend, you know what I received? “&lt;em&gt;It is the pandemic, no one expects better.&lt;/em&gt;” Pure empathy, pure justification, pure ‘hello, new issue causing other issues’. I’ve rationalised most things in the last 7 months to be external, and that maybe the fundamental attribution at play but I’m not to be blamed. Am I trying to shroud the pain the world has been due to this hazard? Absolutely not. I couldn’t if I wanted to, know that.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Last time I sat down to write, Kanye was in his first phase of the breakdown and today, Biden has bagged the highest votes in Pennsylvania. No amount of stimulus has been able to stimulate me enough to go back to my Googling days, oh! The blessed days of me finding a new word and reaching out to it every chance I could get, complete Icarus to the sun. Which reminds me, (in my most moving voice) they say when you do something with all your creativity, love and passion - you do it with Meraki. A word I’m extremely fond and am slightly terrified of. Like every other beautiful, soul-filling word (well, in this case, soul shedding, (you’ll see)), it belongs to the Greeks and implies that &lt;em&gt;“every time one works on something one really loves, they put a part of themselves into it&lt;/em&gt;”. While the concept is beautiful and has no English counterpart, there lies enough truth in it to make it completely sound. In my little to no knowledge of the ‘worldly’ affairs, I could only bring myself to compare it to Cathexis - the psychic energy one puts into people, objects, things, a gift given to us by my all-time favourite, Mr Freud. A close second could be ardour, or well, ardour. Ah, here I am again, stuck in words, when what I need to do is be stressed by my stressors, and subsequently, others’ stressors, too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Is this the time to get back to the drama that folds in from my may-be/may-be-not boyfriend? How about my (n)ever engaged and lengthy enough to go around the sun once (maybe, twice) to-do list? Ah, the joys. All I hope for is that if and when you read this, if and when you are in a position where it seems that you’re not working with Meraki anymore, this could work as a reinforcement, perhaps an aversive one. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I’ve recently had the opportunity to travel to the city where my freedom lies and be back in all of 30 minus 1 hour, and let me tell you- the thrill of running away from an ill-fashioned mask wearer, who is munching on chips as he coughs, and to look at Starbucks with nostalgia, and think of times when you didn’t have to worry about how many people might have touched that straw? Mind-blowing. The question of my sanity lies in if the risk, the multiple masks, the shield, the gloves, the chaos, all of it was worth a total of 40 minutes spent in ecstasy garnered from a bubble tea and nachos, a well-lit room and comfy hotel bed, oh, and well, a well-timed fight with your may-be/may-not-be boyfriend. Well, so was it? I wouldn’t know, might have to come back to that.&amp;nbsp; In the world that we live now, not much seems to be as it was, most of all, the things that are. Every stressor is either exaggerated or it exasperates you to think of your stressor in the face of others’ much bigger ones. No problem is big enough to hold in the face of a pandemic, and that is known - but every problem is definitely magnified in the face of a pandemic and if that’s not the truth, I don’t know what is. The other day, I got my results back from an entrance that I barely prepared for and upon announcing my failure to my friend, you know what I received? “It is the pandemic, no one expects better.” Pure empathy, pure justification, pure ‘hello, new issue causing other issues’. I’ve rationalised most things in the last 7 months to be external, and that maybe the fundamental attribution at play but I’m not to be blamed. Am I trying to shroud the pain the world has been due to this hazard? Absolutely not. I couldn’t if I wanted to, know that.&amp;nbsp; Last time I sat down to write, Kanye was in his first phase of the breakdown and today, Biden has bagged the highest votes in Pennsylvania. No amount of stimulus has been able to stimulate me enough to go back to my Googling days, oh! The blessed days of me finding a new word and reaching out to it every chance I could get, complete Icarus to the sun. Which reminds me, (in my most moving voice) they say when you do something with all your creativity, love and passion - you do it with Meraki. A word I’m extremely fond and am slightly terrified of. Like every other beautiful, soul-filling word (well, in this case, soul shedding, (you’ll see)), it belongs to the Greeks and implies that “every time one works on something one really loves, they put a part of themselves into it”. While the concept is beautiful and has no English counterpart, there lies enough truth in it to make it completely sound. In my little to no knowledge of the ‘worldly’ affairs, I could only bring myself to compare it to Cathexis - the psychic energy one puts into people, objects, things, a gift given to us by my all-time favourite, Mr Freud. A close second could be ardour, or well, ardour. Ah, here I am again, stuck in words, when what I need to do is be stressed by my stressors, and subsequently, others’ stressors, too.&amp;nbsp; Is this the time to get back to the drama that folds in from my may-be/may-be-not boyfriend? How about my (n)ever engaged and lengthy enough to go around the sun once (maybe, twice) to-do list? Ah, the joys. All I hope for is that if and when you read this, if and when you are in a position where it seems that you’re not working with Meraki anymore, this could work as a reinforcement, perhaps an aversive one.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Drama in Action: ‘Rent a Womb but at what Cost?’</title>
      <link href="/A-Drama-in-Action" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Drama in Action: ‘Rent a Womb but at what Cost?’" />
      <published>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Drama-in-Action</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Drama-in-Action">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene One: The Backdrop&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Change is the only constant. Evolution took humans from a hunch-backed species to one that stands upright, from broader jaws to narrower ones and, if we were to believe scientific findings, from a smaller brain size to a larger one. The species evolved and evolved from one huge scientific name to another. But three things that make humans what they inherently are remained unchanged – the body, the soul and expectations. If we are to believe religious and spiritual texts, the body and the soul are accompanied by the mind, but the mind begets expectations arising from desires, and hence for the sake of simplicity, just like an economist would do, we assume the mind to be our expectations. Therefore, even though humans evolved and changed in their physical form, one thing did in fact remain unchanged and constant, that is their expectations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene Two: The Groundwork&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drifting a little away from evolution and bringing ourselves to the present, societies are laden with a myriad of desires and expectations, more so than just their needs, and sometimes overstepping their wants. The sort of mindset embedded in a society’s head is that of the likelihood of certain outcomes, rather than a proven possibility of them to actually occur. Put in simpler words, the likelihood of someone getting severely hurt someday leads to families saving some money, the likelihood of earning profits leads to investments, and so on. This mirage of an outcome in the future leads to tremendous amounts of pressure in the society to do exactly what the society dictates and deems as 'fit' to exist. And society dictates – every married couple must have a child.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene Three: The Curtain Raiser.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equating happiness with expecting a child, millions of couples resort to the method of surrogacy to have a child of their own. In simple words, surrogacy is a process wherein a woman carries and cares for the child in her womb, that is not her own, but she is willingly carrying for the intended parents who can’t carry a child of their own. Whenever the intended parents compensate the surrogate mother monetarily, it is known as ‘commercial surrogacy’, and otherwise, an ‘altruistic surrogacy’, usually done by a relative/friend. The legality of such agreements between intended parents and the surrogate mother are subjective to various countries and their jurisdictions on the issue. While some countries have banned commercial surrogacy altogether, some developing countries are hubs of surrogacy with an incremental flow of intended parents to these hubs to fulfil their desires. This form of a transnational surrogacy has opened way too many doors for intended parents to exploit and prey on the poor and vulnerable surrogate mothers who are in dire need of the money they could have potentially earned by putting their bodies up for use.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene Four: The Highlight.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There hasn’t been a lack of debates around surrogacy and while most countries have spoken and passed laws in favour of altruistic surrogacy, there are still questions of whether it is ethical to commodify women’s bodies and the kinds of economic impacts attached with the legality of surrogacy. First issues first, the commodification of the bodies of these surrogate mothers is more than just an ethical question. Women who willingly opt to become surrogate mothers usually belong to the weaker sections of the society, which brings to light the kind of structural flaws existing in these developing economies that the women find it to be the last resort to put up their bodies to use in order to live from hand to mouth. Their livelihoods rely on this sort of money, and even when governments choose to ban commercial surrogacy to be able to curb the commodification of bodies, they don’t provide these women with a safety net, and hence their upliftment goes out of the question. In fact, for some, this is the only means of livelihood. For that, they have to go through so much emotional and physical labour and also have to change their entire lives’ priorities. Moreover, the fact that in a market, a commodity is taken from its producer and sold off to a consumer stands rather highly unethically true in this case, but it’s not the child being sold off here since the intended parents already have a right on it, but the gestational services of the surrogate being sold off as a mere commodity and as any other labour activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the economic implications of the legality of surrogacy come with a deep understanding of how economics in general works. The kind of expectations talked about at the beginning of the article is as much part of economics as any other economic jargon. That is because expectations lead to desires and wants, which is when we as rational humans choose to make decisions that provide us with maximum satisfaction and utility.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any legal agreement, the two sides of parties always choose the kind of terms that provide the maximum utility to each of them. Naturally, everybody responds to incentives and here, the intended parents wish for a child while the surrogate mother wishes to obtain that sum of money that she needs for herself or her family. The enforceability of these contracts is rather highly pedestaled by these parties because both of them want their end of the contract to be fulfilled. This is when the aspect of exploitation comes into play when these vulnerable women fail to understand the nitty-gritty of such contracts, of which the intended parents, who are in fact financially stable, take undue advantage and get away with paying less to no amount of money to these surrogate mothers. For several small towns in developing economies, the money coming in from surrogacy is extremely essential for the survival of families, and with the rise in exploitation, they are not just left economically worse-off, but also emotionally. The kind of emotional labour that goes into bearing a child is also something that the surrogate mothers already go through, but with the money coming in, it is marginally easier for them to let go of this attachment and to place the welfare of their families above everything. But when they are stripped off of this money, it becomes all the more difficult letting go of the emotional burden of having done so much for a child and seeing it go for no good of their own. Altruistic surrogacy does them no good either because now the ambit to earn the smallest amount of money through this is also taken away from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene Five: Culmination&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, surrogacy as an activity ends up reducing women to their wombs, and ends up monetising not just their services but also the life decisions they made in order to be able to carry a child, not just once but as many times as their body permits and their conditions demand. For many women, the cost of surrogacy can be enormous and simply not worthwhile. For other women, this cost can be minimal in comparison with choices they prefer to have and which they value more. The kind of opportunity costs these women have to incur are way beyond any measurable financial costs.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Scene One: The Backdrop.&amp;nbsp; Change is the only constant. Evolution took humans from a hunch-backed species to one that stands upright, from broader jaws to narrower ones and, if we were to believe scientific findings, from a smaller brain size to a larger one. The species evolved and evolved from one huge scientific name to another. But three things that make humans what they inherently are remained unchanged – the body, the soul and expectations. If we are to believe religious and spiritual texts, the body and the soul are accompanied by the mind, but the mind begets expectations arising from desires, and hence for the sake of simplicity, just like an economist would do, we assume the mind to be our expectations. Therefore, even though humans evolved and changed in their physical form, one thing did in fact remain unchanged and constant, that is their expectations.&amp;nbsp; Scene Two: The Groundwork.&amp;nbsp; Drifting a little away from evolution and bringing ourselves to the present, societies are laden with a myriad of desires and expectations, more so than just their needs, and sometimes overstepping their wants. The sort of mindset embedded in a society’s head is that of the likelihood of certain outcomes, rather than a proven possibility of them to actually occur. Put in simpler words, the likelihood of someone getting severely hurt someday leads to families saving some money, the likelihood of earning profits leads to investments, and so on. This mirage of an outcome in the future leads to tremendous amounts of pressure in the society to do exactly what the society dictates and deems as 'fit' to exist. And society dictates – every married couple must have a child.&amp;nbsp; Scene Three: The Curtain Raiser.&amp;nbsp; Equating happiness with expecting a child, millions of couples resort to the method of surrogacy to have a child of their own. In simple words, surrogacy is a process wherein a woman carries and cares for the child in her womb, that is not her own, but she is willingly carrying for the intended parents who can’t carry a child of their own. Whenever the intended parents compensate the surrogate mother monetarily, it is known as ‘commercial surrogacy’, and otherwise, an ‘altruistic surrogacy’, usually done by a relative/friend. The legality of such agreements between intended parents and the surrogate mother are subjective to various countries and their jurisdictions on the issue. While some countries have banned commercial surrogacy altogether, some developing countries are hubs of surrogacy with an incremental flow of intended parents to these hubs to fulfil their desires. This form of a transnational surrogacy has opened way too many doors for intended parents to exploit and prey on the poor and vulnerable surrogate mothers who are in dire need of the money they could have potentially earned by putting their bodies up for use.&amp;nbsp; Scene Four: The Highlight. There hasn’t been a lack of debates around surrogacy and while most countries have spoken and passed laws in favour of altruistic surrogacy, there are still questions of whether it is ethical to commodify women’s bodies and the kinds of economic impacts attached with the legality of surrogacy. First issues first, the commodification of the bodies of these surrogate mothers is more than just an ethical question. Women who willingly opt to become surrogate mothers usually belong to the weaker sections of the society, which brings to light the kind of structural flaws existing in these developing economies that the women find it to be the last resort to put up their bodies to use in order to live from hand to mouth. Their livelihoods rely on this sort of money, and even when governments choose to ban commercial surrogacy to be able to curb the commodification of bodies, they don’t provide these women with a safety net, and hence their upliftment goes out of the question. In fact, for some, this is the only means of livelihood. For that, they have to go through so much emotional and physical labour and also have to change their entire lives’ priorities. Moreover, the fact that in a market, a commodity is taken from its producer and sold off to a consumer stands rather highly unethically true in this case, but it’s not the child being sold off here since the intended parents already have a right on it, but the gestational services of the surrogate being sold off as a mere commodity and as any other labour activity. Secondly, the economic implications of the legality of surrogacy come with a deep understanding of how economics in general works. The kind of expectations talked about at the beginning of the article is as much part of economics as any other economic jargon. That is because expectations lead to desires and wants, which is when we as rational humans choose to make decisions that provide us with maximum satisfaction and utility.&amp;nbsp; In any legal agreement, the two sides of parties always choose the kind of terms that provide the maximum utility to each of them. Naturally, everybody responds to incentives and here, the intended parents wish for a child while the surrogate mother wishes to obtain that sum of money that she needs for herself or her family. The enforceability of these contracts is rather highly pedestaled by these parties because both of them want their end of the contract to be fulfilled. This is when the aspect of exploitation comes into play when these vulnerable women fail to understand the nitty-gritty of such contracts, of which the intended parents, who are in fact financially stable, take undue advantage and get away with paying less to no amount of money to these surrogate mothers. For several small towns in developing economies, the money coming in from surrogacy is extremely essential for the survival of families, and with the rise in exploitation, they are not just left economically worse-off, but also emotionally. The kind of emotional labour that goes into bearing a child is also something that the surrogate mothers already go through, but with the money coming in, it is marginally easier for them to let go of this attachment and to place the welfare of their families above everything. But when they are stripped off of this money, it becomes all the more difficult letting go of the emotional burden of having done so much for a child and seeing it go for no good of their own. Altruistic surrogacy does them no good either because now the ambit to earn the smallest amount of money through this is also taken away from them. Scene Five: Culmination.&amp;nbsp; All in all, surrogacy as an activity ends up reducing women to their wombs, and ends up monetising not just their services but also the life decisions they made in order to be able to carry a child, not just once but as many times as their body permits and their conditions demand. For many women, the cost of surrogacy can be enormous and simply not worthwhile. For other women, this cost can be minimal in comparison with choices they prefer to have and which they value more. The kind of opportunity costs these women have to incur are way beyond any measurable financial costs.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">An Investor’s Déjà Vu</title>
      <link href="/An-Investor-s-D-j-Vu" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Investor’s Déjà Vu" />
      <published>2020-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/An-Investor-s-D-j-Vu</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/An-Investor-s-D-j-Vu">&lt;p&gt;Picture this, you’re having a conversation with your parents while opening the refrigerator door. You extend your hand towards the half-eaten chocolate and in a moment of suddenness, it seems you’ve already done this before. But you can’t seem to remember when. That, my friend, is &lt;em&gt;déjà vu&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picture another scenario. Say you’re reading the newspaper this time and the S&amp;amp;P index has dipped more than the usual. You think you’ve been here before, except this time, you exactly remember when: 2008. Your memory is bitter about the experience because the last time it happened, it didn’t bode well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 2008 Debacle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone with a rough idea of the 2008 housing bubble would know that it wasn’t pretty. To quote &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/a-guide-to-the-financial-crisis--10-years-later/2018/09/10/114b76ba-af10-11e8-a20b-5f4f84429666_story.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Moody’s&lt;/a&gt;, “&lt;em&gt;The stock market plummeted, wiping out nearly $8 trillion in value between late 2007 and 2009. Unemployment climbed, peaking at 10 percent in October 2009. Americans lost $9.8 trillion in wealth&lt;/em&gt;”.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, just like the human mood, changes in the stock market come in waves. Where there is a low, there is a high. Thus, it’s no wonder that the stock market made a comeback: the home prices rebounded and the employment rate ticked upward. But unfortunately, the story doesn’t end here. Here’s the catch: the market may forget, but the human cannot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stocks have more than doubled since the financial crisis, and yet, a lot of investors have remarkably tweaked down their equity exposure. (For some context, equity is that part of your investment portfolio which leans towards risk. The same is compensated by the possibility of higher returns). Sounds weird, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The vast majority of people have some equity holdings in their 401(k) plans&lt;/em&gt;”, said &lt;a href=&quot;https://in.reuters.com/article/us-usa-stocks-retailinvestors/insight-mom-and-pop-investors-miss-out-on-stock-market-gains-idUSBRE88T0AE20120930&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Brian Reid&lt;/a&gt;, Chief Economist at the Investment Company Institute (ICI), but fewer are willing to take above-average or substantial risk than they were in 2008 before the market plummeted.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent Cogent Research report found that risk aversion among all age groups has been on the rise since 2006, including Generation X and Y, who have lived through a number of market collapses. To simplify, investors have become more risk-averse since the 2008 financial crisis. But why?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Déjà Vu&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, the ramifications of a financial crisis are more profound than we think: they perpetuate biases. The underlying bias observed here is called ‘Experiential Bias’. This occurs when investors' memory of recent events makes them biased or leads them to believe that an event is far more likely to occur again. This culminates in a lot of investors permanently quitting the market or overestimating the impending hardships in a market.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Facing the Music&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warren Buffet once said, “&lt;em&gt;Our favourite holding period is forever&lt;/em&gt;”. According to him, the secret recipe to minting clever money is holding on to stocks, even when their price collapses, for the simple reason that they will bounce back up, over time. But what happens to the investors who left the market at the end of 2008 or early 2009? It wouldn’t take big brains to figure out that they paid a high price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a personal level, quitting the market midway deprives investors of the opportunity of recovering their losses during the recoil. Moreover, reluctance to invest in risky avenues strips you of the prospects of earning fancy rewards. On a larger level, this may also contribute to negative consumer sentiment. Let us see how.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If every second investor hurt by the 2008 crisis exits the stock market, and consciously or subconsciously propels fellow investors to quit too, won’t economic transactions and activity tumble? Sounds unlikely, right? Why would I succumb to and base my decisions on borrowed apprehensions, instead of my own independent analysis? Enter ‘Herd Bias’, yet another fragment of behavioural finance. We’re hard-wired to herd and imitate what other investors are doing. Contrary to traditional beliefs, investors are not invariably rational, they have limits to their self-control and are prone to falling ill to their own biases and fallacies.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say that the aggrieved investor doesn’t quit the market but instead reads every non-average (but normal) dip in S&amp;amp;P or Dow Jones as the onset of something critical. Consequently and gradually, the investor might begin to disinvest (the move is motivated by a fallacy, but is disinvestment nevertheless). If there are sufficient people believing this idea, it is enough to drive the market down. Note that financial markets are driven by popular beliefs, not logical beliefs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too far-fetched, right? It is. But replicate this on a large scale, and voila, you have investor sentiment tipping a slowdown. Those who are still firmly gripped by the ravages of the crisis, have lost all appetite for risk and thus, shirk any and every opportunity that knocks on their doors. They focus on the preservation of capital, not its growth. Sadly though, escapism isn’t the key. Turns out, a no-risk portfolio leaves you financially unprepared.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breaking the Bias&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there might be some empiricism and truth driving such behaviour, one must actively try not to fall prey to his/her own biases. Here is some advice to help you steer through the horrors of the past (and life, generally) and take decisions objectively:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be Reflective: There are two approaches to arriving at investment decisions: Reflexive and Reflective. While the former is the default, automatic gut response to situations, the latter is the logical and methodical one. Even though the reflective approach demands efforts and research, it assists in making informed choices. So step back, dwell over the situation from a bird’s eye view, and then decide.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let Bygones be Bygones: Don’t anchor everything in the present to the traumatic events in your past. If it has happened once, don’t be so sure it will happen again. Learn from your mistakes and let the rest go.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most News is Noise: Don’t believe everything you read and don’t shoehorn every market dip into your past trauma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t Indulge in Peer Pressure: To quote Warren Buffet once again, “&lt;em&gt;The most important quality for an investor is temperament, not intellect. You need a temperament that neither derives great pleasure from being with the crowd or against the crowd&lt;/em&gt;”. You do you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To sum up, ‘Experiential Bias’ is natural. It’s like holding the umbrella when the rains have ceased. You don’t want to let go of it just yet, because it takes more than just time to shake the trauma out. But you know you’ll have to because it’s going to block the sunlight that comes your way.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Eeshita Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Picture this, you’re having a conversation with your parents while opening the refrigerator door. You extend your hand towards the half-eaten chocolate and in a moment of suddenness, it seems you’ve already done this before. But you can’t seem to remember when. That, my friend, is déjà vu.&amp;nbsp; Picture another scenario. Say you’re reading the newspaper this time and the S&amp;amp;P index has dipped more than the usual. You think you’ve been here before, except this time, you exactly remember when: 2008. Your memory is bitter about the experience because the last time it happened, it didn’t bode well.&amp;nbsp; The 2008 Debacle Anyone with a rough idea of the 2008 housing bubble would know that it wasn’t pretty. To quote Moody’s, “The stock market plummeted, wiping out nearly $8 trillion in value between late 2007 and 2009. Unemployment climbed, peaking at 10 percent in October 2009. Americans lost $9.8 trillion in wealth”.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; However, just like the human mood, changes in the stock market come in waves. Where there is a low, there is a high. Thus, it’s no wonder that the stock market made a comeback: the home prices rebounded and the employment rate ticked upward. But unfortunately, the story doesn’t end here. Here’s the catch: the market may forget, but the human cannot. Stocks have more than doubled since the financial crisis, and yet, a lot of investors have remarkably tweaked down their equity exposure. (For some context, equity is that part of your investment portfolio which leans towards risk. The same is compensated by the possibility of higher returns). Sounds weird, right? “The vast majority of people have some equity holdings in their 401(k) plans”, said Brian Reid, Chief Economist at the Investment Company Institute (ICI), but fewer are willing to take above-average or substantial risk than they were in 2008 before the market plummeted.&amp;nbsp; A recent Cogent Research report found that risk aversion among all age groups has been on the rise since 2006, including Generation X and Y, who have lived through a number of market collapses. To simplify, investors have become more risk-averse since the 2008 financial crisis. But why?&amp;nbsp; The Déjà Vu&amp;nbsp; Apparently, the ramifications of a financial crisis are more profound than we think: they perpetuate biases. The underlying bias observed here is called ‘Experiential Bias’. This occurs when investors' memory of recent events makes them biased or leads them to believe that an event is far more likely to occur again. This culminates in a lot of investors permanently quitting the market or overestimating the impending hardships in a market.&amp;nbsp; Facing the Music Warren Buffet once said, “Our favourite holding period is forever”. According to him, the secret recipe to minting clever money is holding on to stocks, even when their price collapses, for the simple reason that they will bounce back up, over time. But what happens to the investors who left the market at the end of 2008 or early 2009? It wouldn’t take big brains to figure out that they paid a high price. On a personal level, quitting the market midway deprives investors of the opportunity of recovering their losses during the recoil. Moreover, reluctance to invest in risky avenues strips you of the prospects of earning fancy rewards. On a larger level, this may also contribute to negative consumer sentiment. Let us see how.&amp;nbsp; If every second investor hurt by the 2008 crisis exits the stock market, and consciously or subconsciously propels fellow investors to quit too, won’t economic transactions and activity tumble? Sounds unlikely, right? Why would I succumb to and base my decisions on borrowed apprehensions, instead of my own independent analysis? Enter ‘Herd Bias’, yet another fragment of behavioural finance. We’re hard-wired to herd and imitate what other investors are doing. Contrary to traditional beliefs, investors are not invariably rational, they have limits to their self-control and are prone to falling ill to their own biases and fallacies.&amp;nbsp; Let’s say that the aggrieved investor doesn’t quit the market but instead reads every non-average (but normal) dip in S&amp;amp;P or Dow Jones as the onset of something critical. Consequently and gradually, the investor might begin to disinvest (the move is motivated by a fallacy, but is disinvestment nevertheless). If there are sufficient people believing this idea, it is enough to drive the market down. Note that financial markets are driven by popular beliefs, not logical beliefs.&amp;nbsp; Too far-fetched, right? It is. But replicate this on a large scale, and voila, you have investor sentiment tipping a slowdown. Those who are still firmly gripped by the ravages of the crisis, have lost all appetite for risk and thus, shirk any and every opportunity that knocks on their doors. They focus on the preservation of capital, not its growth. Sadly though, escapism isn’t the key. Turns out, a no-risk portfolio leaves you financially unprepared.&amp;nbsp; Breaking the Bias While there might be some empiricism and truth driving such behaviour, one must actively try not to fall prey to his/her own biases. Here is some advice to help you steer through the horrors of the past (and life, generally) and take decisions objectively: Be Reflective: There are two approaches to arriving at investment decisions: Reflexive and Reflective. While the former is the default, automatic gut response to situations, the latter is the logical and methodical one. Even though the reflective approach demands efforts and research, it assists in making informed choices. So step back, dwell over the situation from a bird’s eye view, and then decide.&amp;nbsp; Let Bygones be Bygones: Don’t anchor everything in the present to the traumatic events in your past. If it has happened once, don’t be so sure it will happen again. Learn from your mistakes and let the rest go.&amp;nbsp; Most News is Noise: Don’t believe everything you read and don’t shoehorn every market dip into your past trauma. Don’t Indulge in Peer Pressure: To quote Warren Buffet once again, “The most important quality for an investor is temperament, not intellect. You need a temperament that neither derives great pleasure from being with the crowd or against the crowd”. You do you! To sum up, ‘Experiential Bias’ is natural. It’s like holding the umbrella when the rains have ceased. You don’t want to let go of it just yet, because it takes more than just time to shake the trauma out. But you know you’ll have to because it’s going to block the sunlight that comes your way.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Intervention by Sanction</title>
      <link href="/Intervention-by-Sanction" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intervention by Sanction" />
      <published>2020-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Intervention-by-Sanction</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Intervention-by-Sanction">&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump may have railed against certain elements of Republican Party orthodoxy during his run for President in 2016, but his attitude towards Iran came straight from the Republican playbook. He was a staunch critic of the Nuclear Deal signed in 2015, which Iran negotiated with NATO, China and Russia. In a risky move, Trump ordered a drone strike on Iranian General Qasem Soleimani in Baghdad earlier this year. And, in a recent interview with Rush Limbaugh, Trump told the country not to “&lt;em&gt;f*ck around with us&lt;/em&gt;”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The backbone of the Trump administration’s bullish attitude towards the Islamic Republic has been the imposition of trade sanctions. Last week, the President imposed new sanctions on Iran, targeting the country’s financial sector. It wasn’t the first time ‘The Donald’ had tried to cripple the Iranian economy; since he became Commander in Chief in 2017, Trump has strangled foreign trade with the Ayatollah’s family and inner circle, the Iranian Space Agency, and the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sanctions are usually used by the American government against regimes it finds distasteful, but against whom it would be strategically difficult to deploy traditional hard power. Iran fits this description, given that its Twelver Shi’ite government is supported by Russia, and increasingly, China. The idea behind sanctions is to strangle the country’s economy until the governments are forced into negotiation with the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of Iran, the use of sanctions has been a mixed success thus far. Iran’s economy is now one of the least globalised in the world and suffers from stifling rates of inflation. However, the regime in Tehran has not yet returned to negotiations regarding its nuclear programme; it has said it will do so only if the US returns to Obama’s 2015 deal first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Trump’s policy sounds like an acceptable way of dealing with another country, it shouldn’t. The worrying side-note regarding this 'intervention by sanction' approach is that it is likely to do much more than force Iran’s hand over its nuclear programme. When sanctions on the country immiserate its people, a process which is already well underway, the Islamic regime’s days will be numbered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And make no mistake; the collapse of the Iranian government would cause a conflict which would make Syria look like the London Riots. Russia, Saudi Arabia, Turkey and Israel would undoubtedly involve themselves directly, with NATO watching over proceedings from the skies, drones at the ready. Hundreds of thousands of people would die, and many more would overwhelm Europe’s borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is at this point that Trump’s claim to have avoided direct intervention in the Middle East during his first term begins to sound less remarkable. If US sanctions on Iran cause the Twelver regime in Tehran to collapse anyway, resulting in a once-in-a-generation civil and proxy war, then the knowledge that American troops didn’t intervene directly in such a conflict wouldn’t provide much solace for the rest of us. Europe would likely live with the fallout of such a war for decades, whilst the Trumpies in Washington would score a political victory by claiming to have kept their boys out of the firing line. Trump’s policy is analogous to a mafia boss organising a drive-by-shooting, and then comforting himself by pointing out that he wasn’t the one who pulled the trigger. But the result is still the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there is little to like about the Iranian leadership, and the idea of them having nuclear weapons is unappetising, to say the least. But this has never been a likely prospect. The scenario I have just described of Iran falling to pieces, on the other hand, grows more plausible with every passing day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran isn’t the only victim of predatory American sanctions, either; for Venezuela and Russia, the combination of falling oil prices and Western trade embargoes have also proven to be a near-fatal combination. And this morally bankrupt way of undermining the international state system doesn’t just make us our world less secure; it also deprives the Western countries of allies. As I have written before, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Russia-and-Turkey&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Russia and Turkey&lt;/a&gt; could have been useful to the US and NATO in hemming in the Iranian regime. Now, from Russia’s perspective, the possibility of Iran building a nuclear weapon could be seen as insurance against American aggression. It would be one hell of a bargaining chip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joe Biden, for all his many faults as a candidate, would choose a more pragmatic approach to dealing with Iran. He has said that he will return to the 2015 Nuclear Deal he helped to negotiate as Vice President. But this doesn’t mean his administration shouldn’t be watched closely when it comes to sanctions. Let’s not forget that his administration sanctioned Russia to the eyeballs after the Ukraine crisis in 2014; an unwise move, as I have already pointed out. I’m not optimistic that the US will stop using sanctions anytime soon. But I do wish for them to show a little more promise in learning from their past mistakes. The next one could cost all of us big time. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Donald Trump may have railed against certain elements of Republican Party orthodoxy during his run for President in 2016, but his attitude towards Iran came straight from the Republican playbook. He was a staunch critic of the Nuclear Deal signed in 2015, which Iran negotiated with NATO, China and Russia. In a risky move, Trump ordered a drone strike on Iranian General Qasem Soleimani in Baghdad earlier this year. And, in a recent interview with Rush Limbaugh, Trump told the country not to “f*ck around with us”.&amp;nbsp; The backbone of the Trump administration’s bullish attitude towards the Islamic Republic has been the imposition of trade sanctions. Last week, the President imposed new sanctions on Iran, targeting the country’s financial sector. It wasn’t the first time ‘The Donald’ had tried to cripple the Iranian economy; since he became Commander in Chief in 2017, Trump has strangled foreign trade with the Ayatollah’s family and inner circle, the Iranian Space Agency, and the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps. Sanctions are usually used by the American government against regimes it finds distasteful, but against whom it would be strategically difficult to deploy traditional hard power. Iran fits this description, given that its Twelver Shi’ite government is supported by Russia, and increasingly, China. The idea behind sanctions is to strangle the country’s economy until the governments are forced into negotiation with the US. In the case of Iran, the use of sanctions has been a mixed success thus far. Iran’s economy is now one of the least globalised in the world and suffers from stifling rates of inflation. However, the regime in Tehran has not yet returned to negotiations regarding its nuclear programme; it has said it will do so only if the US returns to Obama’s 2015 deal first. If Trump’s policy sounds like an acceptable way of dealing with another country, it shouldn’t. The worrying side-note regarding this 'intervention by sanction' approach is that it is likely to do much more than force Iran’s hand over its nuclear programme. When sanctions on the country immiserate its people, a process which is already well underway, the Islamic regime’s days will be numbered. And make no mistake; the collapse of the Iranian government would cause a conflict which would make Syria look like the London Riots. Russia, Saudi Arabia, Turkey and Israel would undoubtedly involve themselves directly, with NATO watching over proceedings from the skies, drones at the ready. Hundreds of thousands of people would die, and many more would overwhelm Europe’s borders. It is at this point that Trump’s claim to have avoided direct intervention in the Middle East during his first term begins to sound less remarkable. If US sanctions on Iran cause the Twelver regime in Tehran to collapse anyway, resulting in a once-in-a-generation civil and proxy war, then the knowledge that American troops didn’t intervene directly in such a conflict wouldn’t provide much solace for the rest of us. Europe would likely live with the fallout of such a war for decades, whilst the Trumpies in Washington would score a political victory by claiming to have kept their boys out of the firing line. Trump’s policy is analogous to a mafia boss organising a drive-by-shooting, and then comforting himself by pointing out that he wasn’t the one who pulled the trigger. But the result is still the same.&amp;nbsp; Of course, there is little to like about the Iranian leadership, and the idea of them having nuclear weapons is unappetising, to say the least. But this has never been a likely prospect. The scenario I have just described of Iran falling to pieces, on the other hand, grows more plausible with every passing day. Iran isn’t the only victim of predatory American sanctions, either; for Venezuela and Russia, the combination of falling oil prices and Western trade embargoes have also proven to be a near-fatal combination. And this morally bankrupt way of undermining the international state system doesn’t just make us our world less secure; it also deprives the Western countries of allies. As I have written before, Russia and Turkey could have been useful to the US and NATO in hemming in the Iranian regime. Now, from Russia’s perspective, the possibility of Iran building a nuclear weapon could be seen as insurance against American aggression. It would be one hell of a bargaining chip. Joe Biden, for all his many faults as a candidate, would choose a more pragmatic approach to dealing with Iran. He has said that he will return to the 2015 Nuclear Deal he helped to negotiate as Vice President. But this doesn’t mean his administration shouldn’t be watched closely when it comes to sanctions. Let’s not forget that his administration sanctioned Russia to the eyeballs after the Ukraine crisis in 2014; an unwise move, as I have already pointed out. I’m not optimistic that the US will stop using sanctions anytime soon. But I do wish for them to show a little more promise in learning from their past mistakes. The next one could cost all of us big time.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Germany’s Future: A Question Mark?</title>
      <link href="/Germany-s-Future" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Germany’s Future: A Question Mark?" />
      <published>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Germany-s-Future</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Germany-s-Future">&lt;p&gt;Germany, the most powerful country in the European Union and home to over 80 million people, is the only economy in Europe to have retained a large manufacturing and export base. It has consistently benefited from the Euro, the continent’s single currency and has the largest economy in the Eurozone. Despite all of this, its leadership of Europe is reserved, even a little embarrassed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the height of the Greek debt crisis, photographs of protesters in Athens brandishing placards of Angela Merkel, the Chancellor of Germany, dressed as Hitler made the headlines across the world. In Britain, the sight was met with mixed emotions, ranging from bewilderment to hilarity, but not so in Germany. For Merkel’s government and its people, the placards were far more than an unfunny joke. Such a blatant reference to Germany’s ugly history was a suggestion that even after several decades of apologising for the atrocities of the Nazi regime, people across the continent still mistook German assertiveness and leadership for fascistic belligerence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merkel is renowned world over for her understated leadership style. Commentators abroad often applaud the Chancellor’s love for detail, her skill in consensus-building and her conviction. Economically, this may well be true; her government spared little mercy for Greece, even after the Greeks played the Nazi card. However in the social sphere, underpinning Merkel’s major decisions has always been a fear of causing a stir and there is a desire to prevent any association with what has passed before, no matter how far fetched these comparisons might be. In Germany, you really &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; mention the War. These earnest attempts to please all sides haven’t been good for Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious example of Merkel’s reluctance to take difficult decisions was during the migrant crisis of 2015 when millions of migrants from across the Levant, Sub-Saharan Africa and Central Asia cascaded into Europe over a matter of a few months. Merkel’s decision not to turn away any of these people who were trying to enter Germany, in essence dissolving the inner borders of the continent, was largely born out of a desire to definitively break with German history. She wanted to present Germany in a different light from what it had been shown as earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, whilst it was presented as the ultimate show of tolerance, the great irony of Merkel’s migrant policy is that it has made Germany a more racist place. Before 2015, nobody would have made a Nazi salute on the streets of a German city. Now, it is commonplace at far-right protests. The protests in Chemnitz two years ago showed that. The failure to integrate Muslim migrants into German society was the driving cause of the success of the Alternative fur Deutschland (AfD) party in 2017, the first far-right party to win seats in the German Bundestag since the Second World War. The migrant crisis was the best thing that ever happened to Europe’s populist parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that the German government’s constant attempts to apologise for the horrors of the Nazi era don’t help the Europe of today. What Germany did to Europe was unthinkable and no amount of money would ever repay the Jewish community for the atrocities committed after 1942. But we all know Angela Merkel isn’t Adolf Hitler. Her party is not the National Socialists. The world should distinguish between perfectly reasonable projections of German soft power on the one hand and Nazi dog-whistles on the other. Germany, though, must also learn to live with its own past. There will always be new crises around the corner for Europe, but only they have the clout to coordinate a European response to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December, the most important European election in recent years is taking place. Merkel’s party will most likely choose her successor as the German Chancellor. She leaves behind a party in power, but a party that is unsure of its future. Many in Merkel’s Christian Democratic Union (CDU) wish for Germany to take a tougher stance on issues such as immigration and German identity. For the most part, they are uniting around Friedrich Merz. Merz is a strong NATO backer and supports the formation of an EU army. He also raised controversy two decades ago when he became the first centre-right politician to open a debate around &lt;em&gt;leitkultur&lt;/em&gt; (translated as leading culture). In practical terms, this translates to formulating a more concrete idea of ‘German-ness’, based on a forthright endorsement of Judeo-Christian values and a rejection of multiculturalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of the rise of the AfD, such talk makes the centrist wing of Merkel’s party nervous of sounding overly chauvinistic. The centrists are leaning towards Armin Laschet for the party leadership, who has been a strong defender of Merkel’s migrant policy. Laschet seems less interested than Merz in winning back voters who peeled off to the AfD at the 2017 election and would likely follow Merkel’s quiet leadership style on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make no mistake; Merz is no Trump. He’s a mainstream politician who briefly held the CDU leadership before Merkel in the early 2000’s. But his election as a CDU leader would signal to the world that Germany intends to become more self-assured and unabashed in its international decision-making. This would be a welcome change, though, as established, it would not come without controversy. It is difficult to say whether Germans would see this new assertiveness as a throwback to something dark in their history. In this sense, the split within the CDU is about much more than party bureaucracy. It represents the airing of an uncomfortable question at the heart of the German psyche: how do we project ourselves? How Germany answers that question will impact us all.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Germany, the most powerful country in the European Union and home to over 80 million people, is the only economy in Europe to have retained a large manufacturing and export base. It has consistently benefited from the Euro, the continent’s single currency and has the largest economy in the Eurozone. Despite all of this, its leadership of Europe is reserved, even a little embarrassed.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Weaponised Words: A Tale of Hate Speech</title>
      <link href="/Weaponised-Words-A-Tale-of-Hate-Speech" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Weaponised Words: A Tale of Hate Speech" />
      <published>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Weaponised-Words-A-Tale-of-Hate-Speech</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Weaponised-Words-A-Tale-of-Hate-Speech">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&quot;There is a fine line between free speech and hate speech. Free speech encourages debate whereas hate speech incites violence&quot; -&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Newton Lee,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/work/quotes/24289059&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Counterterrorism and Cybersecurity: Total Information Awareness&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quotation is a constant reminder of how easily hate speech overlaps with the idea of freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp;Over the past few months, the challenge of separating hate speech from the Indian citizen’s right to ‘Freedom of Expression’ has increased tremendously. Recently, several citizens including journalists, political party leaders and activists have been charged with hate speech, inflammatory speech and sedition. On one hand, offended plaintiffs file complaints due to hurt caused to their sentiments by the comments of the accused people. On the other hand, the defendants perceive it as a violation of their right to Freedom of Speech.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the light of recent incidents in India, a crucial question arises.&amp;nbsp;Should hate speech be incorporated as a part of Freedom of Speech, or should hate speech be legally regulated?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to scrutinise the idea of ‘free, hate speech’, it is important to distinguish between the two ideas of hate speech and free speech.&amp;nbsp;'Freedom of Expression or Speech' is a principle supporting the idea of an individual or a community articulating their opinions and ideas freely. It ensures such freedom “without the fear of retaliation, censorship, or legal sanction.” On the other hand, hate speech is clearly defined by the &lt;em&gt;Cambridge Dictionary&lt;/em&gt; as a &quot;public speech that expresses hate or encourages violence towards a person or a group based on something such as race, religion, sex, or sexual orientation”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get a sense of how hate speech is treated by legislation, we must take a look at a few examples. While hate speech is not a legal term in some countries, victims of hate speech may seek redressal under civil law, criminal law, or both in other nations. For instance, in the United States, hate speech is constitutionally protected. On the contrary, de jure, freedom of expression is promised in North Korea but there is no de facto right to free speech as asserted by Amnesty International, a human rights group.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In India, hate speech is regulated. While ‘Freedom of Speech and Expression’ is a fundamental right of the Indian Constitution, under Article 19(2) &quot;reasonable restrictions&quot; can be imposed on this right. This is in order to protect &quot;the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of the State, friendly relations with foreign States, public order, decency or morality, or in relation to contempt of court, defamation or incitement to an offence&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hurdle of Hate&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hate speech is a threat to humankind because words have the power to influence people to take action. It causes instability and agitation across the society. It can lead to reduced motivation, lower tolerance, emotional trauma or in extreme cases, depression.&amp;nbsp;Raising this concern, Joyce Arthur, a Canadian activist, in an article titled 'Should Hate Speech be a Crime?' underlines the importance of hate speech legislation. She elucidates that hate speech needs to be regulated as it has a huge impact on people’s dignity and human rights. Hate speech is often derogatory to the sentiments of a particular caste, creed, sex or religion as it is often rooted in stereotypes, prejudices and personal experiences which may be an inaccurate perception of the group or community as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A product of hate speech is hate crime&lt;/strong&gt;. Hate crimes are dangerous as they jeopardise amity in society, instigate precarity among communities, and foster a sense of animosity in the democracy.&amp;nbsp;In the technological era, hate speech over social media causes a tremendous amount of intolerance and violence leading to hate crimes. For instance, the perpetrator of the 2019 New Zealand mosque shootings killed 49 Muslims at prayer and sought to broadcast the attack on YouTube. In Germany, a correlation was observed between anti-refugee Facebook posts by the Alternative for Germany party and increasing attacks on refugees. In India, the recent case of Delhi violence due to hate speech and rumors on social media is also another instance.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hate Speech in India&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While 2020 has been a relatively inactive year for India in terms of business and functioning of institutions, the story is very different when it comes to hate speech laws. Starting from January 2020, there have been 10+ cases involving charges for sedition and hate speech.&amp;nbsp;Among journalists, Arnab Goswami, Amish Devgan and Vinod Dua are a few who&amp;nbsp; have faced FIRs or First Information Reports against them. On one hand, Amish Devgan was accused of injuring religious sentiments on his show. On the other hand, Goswami and Dua faced charges for criticising the State in different forms. FIRs against Goswami have been filed in relation to his questioning opposition leader Sonia Gandhi regarding mob lynching in the Palghar district of Western India. And Dua has been charged with sedition for a Youtube broadcast wherein he said that the State failed to implement the lockdown.&amp;nbsp;Sharjeel Imam, an Indian activist, has been charged with sedition, hate speech and promoting religious antagonism for his speeches against the Citizenship Amendment Act.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These diverse cases point out that it is also challenging and important to define specifically what can be categorized as hate speech.&amp;nbsp;A striking point has been stated in one of the articles in &lt;em&gt;Indian Express&lt;/em&gt;. It says that out of the ten hate speech cases that were scrutinised, including the ones mentioned above, the cases where the State and the petitioner contended on the same side, relief was provided. However, in six cases, where the State was accused, no relief was granted to the petitioner. A ‘telling pattern’ of this sort indicates a fresh challenge of violation of the right to equality before the law.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of this is the regulation of hate speech over social media. While trolling is only the tip of the iceberg, Facebook has recently faced challenges concerning hate speech rules. The &lt;em&gt;Wall Street Journal&lt;/em&gt; has accused Facebook of having failed to apply hate speech regulations on content posted by a BJP leader from the state of Telangana. Three other party leaders’ posts have also been overlooked.&amp;nbsp;A great initiative to combat such challenges is Facebook’s Oversight Board. The Oversight Board is an entity vested with the power to moderate and make independent decisions regarding content over social media sites like Facebook and Instagram. Its purpose is the protection of Facebook users. Hate speech and cases related to ‘political bias’ are within the purview of the board.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Watershed Verdicts&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1962 Indian Supreme Court judgement in &lt;em&gt;Kedar Nath Singh vs State of Bihar&lt;/em&gt; is a landmark judgement concerning the right to Freedom of Expression. The defendant faced charges of sedition and inciting public mischief due to a criticism of the then ruling party, the Indian National Congress in his speech. The defendant argued that the provisions on sedition in the Indian Penal Code (IPC) violated the right to Freedom of Expression under Article 19(1)(a) of the Indian Constitution.&amp;nbsp;The Court asserted that these were not under the purview of “reasonable restrictions” under Article 19(2). It explained that the phrase “Government established by law” under section 124A is different from the criticism of a political party or political leaders.&amp;nbsp;Yet sedition continues to be criminalised under the IPC. However, its provision has been narrowed down to only criminalise expression that intends to jeopardize public order and peace through violence, thereby protecting the right to freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another remarkable judgement in the field of online free speech is &lt;em&gt;Shreya Singhal vs Union of India (UOI).&lt;/em&gt; Two women were arrested under Section 66A of the Information Technology Act, 2000 for ‘posting allegedly offensive comments on Facebook’. As per the section, any person who sends “grossly offensive information” or information “to cause insult, injury or ill will” can be punished. These women filed a petition arguing that Section 66A was constitutionally invalid on the grounds of violation of the right to freedom of speech.&amp;nbsp;In 2015, the Supreme Court declared Section 66A to be unconstitutional and it was struck down. This was because Section 66A was not recognized as a “reasonable restriction” under Article 19(2). Thus, this was a turning point for online free speech.&amp;nbsp;These landmark judgements are useful to cite in cases relating to hate speech and freedom of expression for stronger established arguments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above-mentioned arguments and instances indicate that hate speech needs to be tackled through a balanced approach. While the right to freedom of expression needs to be upheld, hate speech intending to cause violence, disturb public order and promote unrest can prove to be detrimental for humankind.&amp;nbsp;A study by the Pew Research Center reveals that 67% and 27% of people in the United States and Asia-Pacific, respectively, agree with free hate speech. Nonetheless, as the saying goes, “Hate begets more hate”, hate speech causes a vicious cycle of hatred that has no end.&amp;nbsp;Thus, to balance respectful and considerate free speech without hampering the true essence of the Freedom of Expression, regulation of hate speech and uniform implementation of such rules is the need of the hour.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Nirikta Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">&quot;There is a fine line between free speech and hate speech. Free speech encourages debate whereas hate speech incites violence&quot; - Newton Lee, Counterterrorism and Cybersecurity: Total Information Awareness This quotation is a constant reminder of how easily hate speech overlaps with the idea of freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp;Over the past few months, the challenge of separating hate speech from the Indian citizen’s right to ‘Freedom of Expression’ has increased tremendously. Recently, several citizens including journalists, political party leaders and activists have been charged with hate speech, inflammatory speech and sedition. On one hand, offended plaintiffs file complaints due to hurt caused to their sentiments by the comments of the accused people. On the other hand, the defendants perceive it as a violation of their right to Freedom of Speech.&amp;nbsp; In the light of recent incidents in India, a crucial question arises.&amp;nbsp;Should hate speech be incorporated as a part of Freedom of Speech, or should hate speech be legally regulated?&amp;nbsp; In order to scrutinise the idea of ‘free, hate speech’, it is important to distinguish between the two ideas of hate speech and free speech.&amp;nbsp;'Freedom of Expression or Speech' is a principle supporting the idea of an individual or a community articulating their opinions and ideas freely. It ensures such freedom “without the fear of retaliation, censorship, or legal sanction.” On the other hand, hate speech is clearly defined by the Cambridge Dictionary as a &quot;public speech that expresses hate or encourages violence towards a person or a group based on something such as race, religion, sex, or sexual orientation”. To get a sense of how hate speech is treated by legislation, we must take a look at a few examples. While hate speech is not a legal term in some countries, victims of hate speech may seek redressal under civil law, criminal law, or both in other nations. For instance, in the United States, hate speech is constitutionally protected. On the contrary, de jure, freedom of expression is promised in North Korea but there is no de facto right to free speech as asserted by Amnesty International, a human rights group.&amp;nbsp; In India, hate speech is regulated. While ‘Freedom of Speech and Expression’ is a fundamental right of the Indian Constitution, under Article 19(2) &quot;reasonable restrictions&quot; can be imposed on this right. This is in order to protect &quot;the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of the State, friendly relations with foreign States, public order, decency or morality, or in relation to contempt of court, defamation or incitement to an offence&quot;. Hurdle of Hate&amp;nbsp; Hate speech is a threat to humankind because words have the power to influence people to take action. It causes instability and agitation across the society. It can lead to reduced motivation, lower tolerance, emotional trauma or in extreme cases, depression.&amp;nbsp;Raising this concern, Joyce Arthur, a Canadian activist, in an article titled 'Should Hate Speech be a Crime?' underlines the importance of hate speech legislation. She elucidates that hate speech needs to be regulated as it has a huge impact on people’s dignity and human rights. Hate speech is often derogatory to the sentiments of a particular caste, creed, sex or religion as it is often rooted in stereotypes, prejudices and personal experiences which may be an inaccurate perception of the group or community as a whole. A product of hate speech is hate crime. Hate crimes are dangerous as they jeopardise amity in society, instigate precarity among communities, and foster a sense of animosity in the democracy.&amp;nbsp;In the technological era, hate speech over social media causes a tremendous amount of intolerance and violence leading to hate crimes. For instance, the perpetrator of the 2019 New Zealand mosque shootings killed 49 Muslims at prayer and sought to broadcast the attack on YouTube. In Germany, a correlation was observed between anti-refugee Facebook posts by the Alternative for Germany party and increasing attacks on refugees. In India, the recent case of Delhi violence due to hate speech and rumors on social media is also another instance.&amp;nbsp; Hate Speech in India&amp;nbsp; While 2020 has been a relatively inactive year for India in terms of business and functioning of institutions, the story is very different when it comes to hate speech laws. Starting from January 2020, there have been 10+ cases involving charges for sedition and hate speech.&amp;nbsp;Among journalists, Arnab Goswami, Amish Devgan and Vinod Dua are a few who&amp;nbsp; have faced FIRs or First Information Reports against them. On one hand, Amish Devgan was accused of injuring religious sentiments on his show. On the other hand, Goswami and Dua faced charges for criticising the State in different forms. FIRs against Goswami have been filed in relation to his questioning opposition leader Sonia Gandhi regarding mob lynching in the Palghar district of Western India. And Dua has been charged with sedition for a Youtube broadcast wherein he said that the State failed to implement the lockdown.&amp;nbsp;Sharjeel Imam, an Indian activist, has been charged with sedition, hate speech and promoting religious antagonism for his speeches against the Citizenship Amendment Act.&amp;nbsp; These diverse cases point out that it is also challenging and important to define specifically what can be categorized as hate speech.&amp;nbsp;A striking point has been stated in one of the articles in Indian Express. It says that out of the ten hate speech cases that were scrutinised, including the ones mentioned above, the cases where the State and the petitioner contended on the same side, relief was provided. However, in six cases, where the State was accused, no relief was granted to the petitioner. A ‘telling pattern’ of this sort indicates a fresh challenge of violation of the right to equality before the law.&amp;nbsp; Another aspect of this is the regulation of hate speech over social media. While trolling is only the tip of the iceberg, Facebook has recently faced challenges concerning hate speech rules. The Wall Street Journal has accused Facebook of having failed to apply hate speech regulations on content posted by a BJP leader from the state of Telangana. Three other party leaders’ posts have also been overlooked.&amp;nbsp;A great initiative to combat such challenges is Facebook’s Oversight Board. The Oversight Board is an entity vested with the power to moderate and make independent decisions regarding content over social media sites like Facebook and Instagram. Its purpose is the protection of Facebook users. Hate speech and cases related to ‘political bias’ are within the purview of the board.&amp;nbsp; Watershed Verdicts&amp;nbsp; The 1962 Indian Supreme Court judgement in Kedar Nath Singh vs State of Bihar is a landmark judgement concerning the right to Freedom of Expression. The defendant faced charges of sedition and inciting public mischief due to a criticism of the then ruling party, the Indian National Congress in his speech. The defendant argued that the provisions on sedition in the Indian Penal Code (IPC) violated the right to Freedom of Expression under Article 19(1)(a) of the Indian Constitution.&amp;nbsp;The Court asserted that these were not under the purview of “reasonable restrictions” under Article 19(2). It explained that the phrase “Government established by law” under section 124A is different from the criticism of a political party or political leaders.&amp;nbsp;Yet sedition continues to be criminalised under the IPC. However, its provision has been narrowed down to only criminalise expression that intends to jeopardize public order and peace through violence, thereby protecting the right to freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp; Another remarkable judgement in the field of online free speech is Shreya Singhal vs Union of India (UOI). Two women were arrested under Section 66A of the Information Technology Act, 2000 for ‘posting allegedly offensive comments on Facebook’. As per the section, any person who sends “grossly offensive information” or information “to cause insult, injury or ill will” can be punished. These women filed a petition arguing that Section 66A was constitutionally invalid on the grounds of violation of the right to freedom of speech.&amp;nbsp;In 2015, the Supreme Court declared Section 66A to be unconstitutional and it was struck down. This was because Section 66A was not recognized as a “reasonable restriction” under Article 19(2). Thus, this was a turning point for online free speech.&amp;nbsp;These landmark judgements are useful to cite in cases relating to hate speech and freedom of expression for stronger established arguments.&amp;nbsp; The above-mentioned arguments and instances indicate that hate speech needs to be tackled through a balanced approach. While the right to freedom of expression needs to be upheld, hate speech intending to cause violence, disturb public order and promote unrest can prove to be detrimental for humankind.&amp;nbsp;A study by the Pew Research Center reveals that 67% and 27% of people in the United States and Asia-Pacific, respectively, agree with free hate speech. Nonetheless, as the saying goes, “Hate begets more hate”, hate speech causes a vicious cycle of hatred that has no end.&amp;nbsp;Thus, to balance respectful and considerate free speech without hampering the true essence of the Freedom of Expression, regulation of hate speech and uniform implementation of such rules is the need of the hour.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Scottish Independence: Johnson Approved?</title>
      <link href="/Scottish-Independence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scottish Independence: Johnson Approved?" />
      <published>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Scottish-Independence</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Scottish-Independence">&lt;p&gt;One of the most destructive elements of Brexit has been its uncanny knack of underscoring the ill-feeling between the governments in London and Edinburgh. In keeping with its constituents’ wishes, Nicola Sturgeon’s Scottish government now looks set to frustrate the UK’s departure from the European Union (EU) at every turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigel Farage has often suggested that it would be illogical for Scotland to vote to become an independent country under Sturgeon’s leadership because a Scottish National Party (SNP) government would simply choose to pool Scottish sovereignty with Brussels instead of Westminster by re-joining the EU. Regardless of whether Farage’s point holds water, it might be more pertinent to turn his insight on its head: it was illogical, downright delusional in fact, to say Westminster would be totally sovereign over British laws after Brexit, because Parliament still governs the country alongside the regional assemblies in Edinburgh, Cardiff and Belfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-governance with the regional assemblies has been shown to be discordant ample times since ‘Brexit Day’ in January. The differing rules on the coronavirus lockdowns in the four nations of the UK have been immensely confusing, frequently smacking of plain political one-upmanship rather than proper scientific enquiry. On Brexit, it looks as if Sturgeon might disregard the government’s Internal Markets Bill and pass her own trade legislation, calling Johnson’s bill “a full-frontal assault on devolution”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not a constitutional expert, so I can’t say with certainty whether Sturgeon is right about that. But if the bill does in fact not represent overreach from Westminster, then part of the reason that Sturgeon can assert something which isn’t true is the fact that many of the terms of the relationship between Westminster and the devolved assemblies are poorly defined, arbitrary and hopelessly vulnerable to the transient whims of public opinion. Whilst most members of the commentariat have been focusing on making our relationship with the Europeans as stable and fruitful as possible, major instabilities within the British constitution have been overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three devolved Parliaments are not like American state governments, the rights and jurisdictions of which are clearly laid out in the Constitution. If a state believes the Federal Government has overstepped the mark, the Supreme Court refers to the Constitution to assess whether overreach has occurred. All states have the same powers, and state governments are just as inherent a part of the US governance as the Federal government in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Parliaments in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland, by contrast, were all created at different times, and all have slightly different powers. The devolved Parliaments can have their powers altered by the British government as long as the sitting Prime Minister desires it, and has a parliamentary majority to help him. After the Scottish independence referendum, David Cameron promised the Scots “devo-max”, as a way of responding to the close nature of the result. As a gesture of goodwill, he simultaneously enhanced the powers of the Welsh Assembly, but not to the same degree as the Scottish Parliament. However, he offered no explanation for why the Assembly in Cardiff would remain less powerful, or why he had interpreted nationalist fervour in Scotland as a clear sign that the Welsh were on the brink of drifting somewhere into the Irish Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between the three Parliaments and its mothership in London resembles a rickety old building, the roof of which boasts a series of asymmetric and poorly built extensions. If a constitutional revolution did happen in Britain after 1945, it was devolution, not joining the EU. Random and arbitrary devolution has inhibited Westminster from governing the entire country far more than the European Commission ever did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, dysfunctionality doesn’t make the Scottish Parliament unconstitutional; the British Constitution is malleable and unwritten, which makes it much easier to change than the US Constitution. Ted Heath’s Tory government pooled our sovereignty with the Europeans in 1972 with a simple act of Parliament, thereby changing the British Constitution overnight. But just because something is constitutional doesn’t mean it works well. It doesn’t make it a good idea. The Internal Market Bill won’t be the last time that there are impasses in the years ahead, because the mandates of the Parliaments’ clash and their powers are far too easy to change. I’ve focused on Scotland here, but the potential for disaster in Northern Ireland is just as obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where does the Prime Minister enter into the picture in all of this? He’s certainly having a torrid time dealing with Scotland at present. One year into his premiership, it’s obvious that he has few guiding principles. In truth, you didn’t need a year to see this. Whether Johnson’s love for the expedient would extend to advocating independence for Scotland is unlikely. But, privately at least, he must have clocked that not having to listen to those loudmouths over Hadrian’s Wall would definitely make his life easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t like the job he’s doing (I count myself among you, by the way), then you might conclude you don’t mind that a by-product of our constitutional disorder is Johnson’s failure to deliver on his manifesto. What is worrying though, is that far from enhancing democracy in our country, devolution is compounding an incipient feeling that Britain is now ungovernable. I don’t blame Sturgeon for this; there is nothing wrong with scrutinising the government and its legislation, but there is an ocean of difference between careful scrutiny and institutional collapse. The former, essential to any democracy, was traditionally the responsibility of the opposition parties, the House of Lords, and an independent judiciary. The country was governed reasonably well with just one government. Creating three regional Parliaments on a whim and handing them new powers arbitrarily has simply led to a pile-up of different mandates, rather than improving accountability. If many different governments squabble over the right to govern, none of them &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; govern. In handing back power to our domestic governments, Brexit seems poised to unleash a crisis of democratic legitimacy far greater in severity than even itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the most destructive elements of Brexit has been its uncanny knack of underscoring the ill-feeling between the governments in London and Edinburgh. In keeping with its constituents’ wishes, Nicola Sturgeon’s Scottish government now looks set to frustrate the UK’s departure from the European Union (EU) at every turn.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
