<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/trending/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-09-29T21:59:34+01:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/trending/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Female Labour Force Participation in India: Why Is It So Stunted?</title>
      <link href="/Female-Labour-Force-Participation-in-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Female Labour Force Participation in India: Why Is It So Stunted?" />
      <published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Female-Labour-Force-Participation-in-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Female-Labour-Force-Participation-in-India">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Recently, India has found itself in the monetary and segment conditions that would prompt an increased female workforce participation rate. Financial development has been high, averaging at 6-7% during the 1990's and 2000's. On the other hand, fertility has significantly fallen alongside the drastic rise in training of females.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, according to the International Labour Organisation's (ILO) estimates, the female labour force participation rate (FLPR) in India has declined from 30.27% in 1990 to 20.33% in 2020. The average value of the said figure for India during the period between 1990-2020 was 27.38%, with a minimum of 20.33% (in 2020) and maximum of 31.79% (in 2005).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The average for 2020, based on 182 countries, was 51.86%. Rwanda scored the highest rate of 83.95% and Yemen the lowest at 5.69%. The FLPR for China, the country with the largest population, was 64% while for the US, it was 56.3%. Women remained underrepresented in the Indian workforce, a circumstance that has not changed in the last 30 years.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Among its neighbouring countries, India’s FLPR is shockingly the lowest, falling even behind Afghanistan and Pakistan, which had scored half of India’s rates back in 1990. Nepal has a FLPR of 83% which is an all-time high amongst all the South Asian economies, and Pakistan (India’ biggest rival) has secured a higher position by 4 points, sitting at a FLPR of 24.6%. Globally only Yemen, Iraq, Jordan, Syria, Algeria, Iran, the West Bank and Gaza have lower rates than India.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Analysis of National Sampling Survey Office (NSSO) data (1970-2018) shows that women have largely been undertaking home-based and labour intensive informal work concentrated in low-productivity sectors. During the period of 1977-2017, the proportion of women working in agriculture fell from 88.1% to 73.2% in the rural areas, while their share in the service sector rose from 35.7% to 60.7% in the urban areas. Females in the tertiary sector concentrated in professions such as teaching and nursing, which provided restricted scope for progression in their careers. However, unlike their male counterparts, females could not increase their presence in the secondary sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What explains low participation in India?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the last decade, fertility has declined rapidly while wages have expanded considerably, and the contribution for this goes to the high speed of development in the country. Furthermore, avenues for job seekers are not rare, except for the educated workforce where there is a distinct relative shortage. So why are more females not entering the workforce?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to a paper published in 2008, much of the discussion on the falling trends in female labour force participation has focused on four key elements:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;1) rising enrolment in secondary schooling;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;2) wage and sex discrimination in the workplace;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;3) increase in household incomes; and&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;4) females engaged in either unpaid family jobs or marginal jobs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There has been an increase in the percentage of women who have completed a minimum of secondary level education or more, particularly in rural India. The NSSO data also confirms younger women have greater aspirations to participate in the labour market than the previous generations, however, due to norms around chastity and early marriage (still heavily prevalent in the country), they are prevented from doing so. The average age of marriage for girls in rural India is around 21.7 years. Additionally, there has been a fall in participation rate of approximately 30% owing to greater demand on their time to pursue education. Post their education, absence of appropriate job availability leads to their lower participation in the workforce.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There exists a U-shaped relation between education and paid work participation, yet the rate of return for each year of education is lower for women than men in India. This relation also asserts the fact that illiterate women are forced to rely on the unorganised sector for meeting their basic needs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Wage and sex dicrimination within the workplace is an addition amongst the above mentioned factors where females are rewarded with a lower pay and greater discrimination than their male counterparts. This is serious as it not only affects the economic growth of the nation but also speaks volume on the prevalent working conditions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Males are awarded with a pay of more than 19% than their female colleagues. This income disparity has only narrowed by 1% in 2018 from the 20% of the preceding year. The pay inequality can be corresponded to the following factors - discriminaton and occupational decisions by females into lower paying jobs, such as clerical work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another interesting reason for lower female workforce participation can be attributed to the fact that many educated females drop out of the workforce due the family income effect, i.e., with an increase in family earnings, the dependency on females to work fall, thereby shifting their attention towards domestic chores and child care. As a result women hailing from higher economic status are less likely to work than women belonging from lower income strata.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This gap widens when we look at the 2019 report by the Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation, wherein it becomes evident that the burden of unpaid labour falls on women significantly in the country. The report states that an average Indian woman spends nearly 84% of her working hours on unpaid work while the men spend 80% of their working hours on paid work.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the government doing?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Government has taken several steps to increase the female workforce participation rate in India.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Ministry of Skill Development and Entrepreneurship (MSDE) has been set up for improving the involvement rate across sectors and areas. Likewise the government has also initiated the National Career Service (NCS) project which entails a digital portal to link jobseekers and businesses for work and incorporate a repository of enlarged career content.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Other steps include incorporation of the &lt;em&gt;Maternity Benefit (Amendment) Act, 2017 &lt;/em&gt;by institutions which focuses on improvement in paid maternity leaves from 12 weeks to 26 weeks, and arrangement for compulsory crèche services in establishments having at least 50 employees; issue of an advisory to the States under the &lt;em&gt;Factories Act, 1948&lt;/em&gt; for allowing women workers of night shifts with sufficient safety measures.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Furthermore, to improve the employability of female labourers, numerous institutes have been set up to provide them with training ranging from vocational to industrial. Various work laws have been amended to foster a more safe and amicable work environment for women.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Laws for a fairer work environment passed by the government include:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Minimum Wage Act 1948&lt;/em&gt;, the wages set by the corresponding government are equally applicable to male and female workers, and therefore, the law doesn't segregate on the premise of sex.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Equal Remuneration Act 1976 &lt;/em&gt;provides for equal wages to be paid to employees for similar jobs, with no discrimination based on sex, class, caste or religion followed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Protection of Women against Sexual Harassment at Workplace Act 2013&lt;/em&gt; characterizes lewd behavior or sexual harassment at the workplace, and helps in the redressal of such objections. It provides shields against fake or noxious charges.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, many government policies are targeted towards the organised workforce while the&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;unorganised sector that homes the largest number of females has very little to no penetration of such&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;schemes, thereby making government policies ineffective to some extent. Additionally, in several areas, these policies are only restricted to documentation, thus, never making it to actual implementation. For instance, severe expenditure cuts associated with the centrally sponsored National Crèche Scheme had led to the closure of multiple crèches across the country, thus, de-incentivising female workers who could work earlier only because of the availability of such facilities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Moreover the government policies regularly fail to focus on the real audience. In order to avail most of the above listed benefits, there's an enormous process and cumbersome documentation requirement which excludes the illiterate or marginalised women of the country. While issues like corruption conjointly attack the system, and the welfare policies fail to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comprehensive approaches are needed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In India, the gender gap in labour force participation is high and is worsening continually when looked at from a global point of view. The decline in female employment&amp;nbsp; is primarily attributed to the sharp fall in female agricultural employment, which till date employs more than 65% of the total women in the workforce; half of them working as unpaid family workers. This decline in agriculture share is not accompanied by a commensurate increase in non-agricultural activities, except for construction. Employment opportunities are very limited for women, and are solely concentrated in only a few sub-sectors, mainly in low value-added activities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Agriculture, which is as yet the biggest employer of female labour, can be used as a wellspring of economic growth and job creation for women, if they are guaranteed possession rights and power over grounds while at the same time, movement of women is required towards the production of high value-added crops. These of course should be supplemented by other strategy measurements.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Moreover, promotion of female entrepreneurship can give way to economic elevation of women, and thus, distribution of its benefits more equitably. But lack of credit facilities in the absence of collateral, and complications of the established formalities present a major roadblock to such entrepreneurial ambitions. Self Help Groups (SHGs) can be utilised to improve access to finance, and links with formal financial institutions would enable women (especially from lower economic status) to access the market better.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Women in India face many barriers to enter the workforce, such as pre dominant socio-cultural practices, access to choice of work, poor working conditions, wage disparity, exploitation, balancing domestic and work responsibilities, and more. It is essential that policy makers adopt strategies to improve the labour market for women through gender neutral norms, education, proper infrastructure, and the creation of more opportunities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;At last, the objective isn't simply to increase the female labour force participation rate but to build opportunities for decent work and economic progression which can add to the financial strengthening of women and the economy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Cheshta Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Recently, India has found itself in the monetary and segment conditions that would prompt an increased female workforce participation rate. Financial development has been high, averaging at 6-7% during the 1990's and 2000's. On the other hand, fertility has significantly fallen alongside the drastic rise in training of females.&amp;nbsp; However, according to the International Labour Organisation's (ILO) estimates, the female labour force participation rate (FLPR) in India has declined from 30.27% in 1990 to 20.33% in 2020. The average value of the said figure for India during the period between 1990-2020 was 27.38%, with a minimum of 20.33% (in 2020) and maximum of 31.79% (in 2005).&amp;nbsp; The average for 2020, based on 182 countries, was 51.86%. Rwanda scored the highest rate of 83.95% and Yemen the lowest at 5.69%. The FLPR for China, the country with the largest population, was 64% while for the US, it was 56.3%. Women remained underrepresented in the Indian workforce, a circumstance that has not changed in the last 30 years.&amp;nbsp; Among its neighbouring countries, India’s FLPR is shockingly the lowest, falling even behind Afghanistan and Pakistan, which had scored half of India’s rates back in 1990. Nepal has a FLPR of 83% which is an all-time high amongst all the South Asian economies, and Pakistan (India’ biggest rival) has secured a higher position by 4 points, sitting at a FLPR of 24.6%. Globally only Yemen, Iraq, Jordan, Syria, Algeria, Iran, the West Bank and Gaza have lower rates than India.&amp;nbsp; Analysis of National Sampling Survey Office (NSSO) data (1970-2018) shows that women have largely been undertaking home-based and labour intensive informal work concentrated in low-productivity sectors. During the period of 1977-2017, the proportion of women working in agriculture fell from 88.1% to 73.2% in the rural areas, while their share in the service sector rose from 35.7% to 60.7% in the urban areas. Females in the tertiary sector concentrated in professions such as teaching and nursing, which provided restricted scope for progression in their careers. However, unlike their male counterparts, females could not increase their presence in the secondary sector.&amp;nbsp; What explains low participation in India? In the last decade, fertility has declined rapidly while wages have expanded considerably, and the contribution for this goes to the high speed of development in the country. Furthermore, avenues for job seekers are not rare, except for the educated workforce where there is a distinct relative shortage. So why are more females not entering the workforce? According to a paper published in 2008, much of the discussion on the falling trends in female labour force participation has focused on four key elements:&amp;nbsp; 1) rising enrolment in secondary schooling;&amp;nbsp; 2) wage and sex discrimination in the workplace;&amp;nbsp; 3) increase in household incomes; and&amp;nbsp; 4) females engaged in either unpaid family jobs or marginal jobs.&amp;nbsp; There has been an increase in the percentage of women who have completed a minimum of secondary level education or more, particularly in rural India. The NSSO data also confirms younger women have greater aspirations to participate in the labour market than the previous generations, however, due to norms around chastity and early marriage (still heavily prevalent in the country), they are prevented from doing so. The average age of marriage for girls in rural India is around 21.7 years. Additionally, there has been a fall in participation rate of approximately 30% owing to greater demand on their time to pursue education. Post their education, absence of appropriate job availability leads to their lower participation in the workforce.&amp;nbsp; There exists a U-shaped relation between education and paid work participation, yet the rate of return for each year of education is lower for women than men in India. This relation also asserts the fact that illiterate women are forced to rely on the unorganised sector for meeting their basic needs.&amp;nbsp; Wage and sex dicrimination within the workplace is an addition amongst the above mentioned factors where females are rewarded with a lower pay and greater discrimination than their male counterparts. This is serious as it not only affects the economic growth of the nation but also speaks volume on the prevalent working conditions.&amp;nbsp; Males are awarded with a pay of more than 19% than their female colleagues. This income disparity has only narrowed by 1% in 2018 from the 20% of the preceding year. The pay inequality can be corresponded to the following factors - discriminaton and occupational decisions by females into lower paying jobs, such as clerical work. Another interesting reason for lower female workforce participation can be attributed to the fact that many educated females drop out of the workforce due the family income effect, i.e., with an increase in family earnings, the dependency on females to work fall, thereby shifting their attention towards domestic chores and child care. As a result women hailing from higher economic status are less likely to work than women belonging from lower income strata.&amp;nbsp; This gap widens when we look at the 2019 report by the Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation, wherein it becomes evident that the burden of unpaid labour falls on women significantly in the country. The report states that an average Indian woman spends nearly 84% of her working hours on unpaid work while the men spend 80% of their working hours on paid work.&amp;nbsp; What is the government doing? The Government has taken several steps to increase the female workforce participation rate in India.&amp;nbsp; The Ministry of Skill Development and Entrepreneurship (MSDE) has been set up for improving the involvement rate across sectors and areas. Likewise the government has also initiated the National Career Service (NCS) project which entails a digital portal to link jobseekers and businesses for work and incorporate a repository of enlarged career content.&amp;nbsp; Other steps include incorporation of the Maternity Benefit (Amendment) Act, 2017 by institutions which focuses on improvement in paid maternity leaves from 12 weeks to 26 weeks, and arrangement for compulsory crèche services in establishments having at least 50 employees; issue of an advisory to the States under the Factories Act, 1948 for allowing women workers of night shifts with sufficient safety measures.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, to improve the employability of female labourers, numerous institutes have been set up to provide them with training ranging from vocational to industrial. Various work laws have been amended to foster a more safe and amicable work environment for women.&amp;nbsp; Laws for a fairer work environment passed by the government include:&amp;nbsp; Minimum Wage Act 1948, the wages set by the corresponding government are equally applicable to male and female workers, and therefore, the law doesn't segregate on the premise of sex.&amp;nbsp;The Equal Remuneration Act 1976 provides for equal wages to be paid to employees for similar jobs, with no discrimination based on sex, class, caste or religion followed.&amp;nbsp;The Protection of Women against Sexual Harassment at Workplace Act 2013 characterizes lewd behavior or sexual harassment at the workplace, and helps in the redressal of such objections. It provides shields against fake or noxious charges. However, many government policies are targeted towards the organised workforce while the&amp;nbsp; unorganised sector that homes the largest number of females has very little to no penetration of such schemes, thereby making government policies ineffective to some extent. Additionally, in several areas, these policies are only restricted to documentation, thus, never making it to actual implementation. For instance, severe expenditure cuts associated with the centrally sponsored National Crèche Scheme had led to the closure of multiple crèches across the country, thus, de-incentivising female workers who could work earlier only because of the availability of such facilities.&amp;nbsp; Moreover the government policies regularly fail to focus on the real audience. In order to avail most of the above listed benefits, there's an enormous process and cumbersome documentation requirement which excludes the illiterate or marginalised women of the country. While issues like corruption conjointly attack the system, and the welfare policies fail to deliver. Comprehensive approaches are needed In India, the gender gap in labour force participation is high and is worsening continually when looked at from a global point of view. The decline in female employment&amp;nbsp; is primarily attributed to the sharp fall in female agricultural employment, which till date employs more than 65% of the total women in the workforce; half of them working as unpaid family workers. This decline in agriculture share is not accompanied by a commensurate increase in non-agricultural activities, except for construction. Employment opportunities are very limited for women, and are solely concentrated in only a few sub-sectors, mainly in low value-added activities.&amp;nbsp; Agriculture, which is as yet the biggest employer of female labour, can be used as a wellspring of economic growth and job creation for women, if they are guaranteed possession rights and power over grounds while at the same time, movement of women is required towards the production of high value-added crops. These of course should be supplemented by other strategy measurements.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, promotion of female entrepreneurship can give way to economic elevation of women, and thus, distribution of its benefits more equitably. But lack of credit facilities in the absence of collateral, and complications of the established formalities present a major roadblock to such entrepreneurial ambitions. Self Help Groups (SHGs) can be utilised to improve access to finance, and links with formal financial institutions would enable women (especially from lower economic status) to access the market better.&amp;nbsp; Women in India face many barriers to enter the workforce, such as pre dominant socio-cultural practices, access to choice of work, poor working conditions, wage disparity, exploitation, balancing domestic and work responsibilities, and more. It is essential that policy makers adopt strategies to improve the labour market for women through gender neutral norms, education, proper infrastructure, and the creation of more opportunities.&amp;nbsp; At last, the objective isn't simply to increase the female labour force participation rate but to build opportunities for decent work and economic progression which can add to the financial strengthening of women and the economy.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Power Play: China’s Command &amp;amp; Control</title>
      <link href="/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Power Play: China's Command &amp; Control" />
      <published>2021-09-21T02:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-21T02:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control">&lt;p&gt;In November 2020, I authored an article on China’s move of&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Derailing-of-the-World-s-Biggest-IPO&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt; scuttling Ant Group Co.’s blockbuster $37 billion listing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Little did we know that it was just the beginning of an excessive clampdown on the country's technological sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To continue with the story of e-commerce giant Alibaba, the country’s authorities imposed a record fine - $2.8 billion in 2021, after an investigation that found it had abused its dominant market position for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China’s unprecedented crackdown on its tech industry has cost several companies and their investors hundreds of billions of dollars. Tencent alone has &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/markets/stocks/news/market-darling-tencent-turns-into-worlds-worst-stock-bet-with-170-billion-wipeout/articleshow/84853892.cms&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;had $170 billion shaved off its value&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; For context, that’s more than ten Byju’s, India’s biggest startup, which is valued at $16.5 billion.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The July Roundup by Goldman Sachs Group Inc shows that since November, the country’s regulators have taken more than 50 actual or reported actions on areas spanning antitrust, finance, data security and social equality, i.e. more than one move a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, China has assiduously built up its tech sector, and has borrowed an industrial and internet model from the West. Arguably it was a resounding success, then why is it now trying to strangle the golden goose it had once cradled?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.natlawreview.com/article/china-issues-data-security-law&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;adopted a new cybersecurity law in June&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which builds on the foundation of the 2017 Cyber Security Law, that started tightening the control of data flow. However, since the measure was vaguely worded, it remained unclear how it would be implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around the same time, the Chinese economy was rebounding from its bout with COVID-19, lifting the nation's&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/06/10/didi-chuxing-files-for-ipo-booked-6point4-billion-revenue-in-q1.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/06/10/didi-chuxing-files-for-ipo-booked-6point4-billion-revenue-in-q1.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;ride, hailing giant Didi Global&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s revenue with it as the US stock market continued to be in a bull run. Didi's long venture investors, including Softbank’s Vision Fund, urged seizing the moment to take the company public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company made its debut at $14 on the New York Stock Exchange on the last day of June 2021, raising $4.4 billion - the biggest stock sale by a Chinese company since the 2014 listing of Alibaba Group Holding Ltd.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its shares briefly topped $18 in the first days of trading, before China’s cyber security watchdog - Cyberspace Administration of China (CAC) stunned investors on July 2 by launching a data-security probe into Didi and blocking its China business from adding new users.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crackdown worsened on July 9, when 25 more Didi apps - including ones used by drivers - were ordered to be removed from app stores, potentially crippling the company’s operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this was not enough, the administration further extended its clampdown on other sectors in&amp;nbsp; July. On July 22, the government &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/tech/startups/china-strengthens-protection-for-food-delivery-workers-in-setback-for-meituan-alibaba/articleshow/84755202.cms&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;announced new worker protection rules&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, under which online food platforms must cover minimum wage and insurance benefits. This gutted the share price of delivery giants such as Meituan and its rival, Alibaba's Ele.me; which had drawn severe criticism on social media for their treatment of riders and guaranteed time-bound delivery which has compelled riders to undertake dangerous routes, risking their lives.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the following day, Beijing effectively torpedoed a multibillion-dollar industry - after-school tutoring - with a single administrative order. The new rules banned companies that teach the K-12 school curriculum from going public and registering themselves as non-profits. The shares of the three largest US-listed Chinese edtech firms - TAL Education, New Oriental and Gaotu Techedu, fell by 65-70% on the announcement, and the founders of the latter two companies went from billionaires to millionaires almost instantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The corporate intervention that has hammered internet stocks is now driving investors to sectors still in Beijing’s good graces, such as high-tech manufacturing and renewable energy. Indexes for new energy stocks, semiconductor makers and electric vehicle companies, outperformed the market from 4% to 18% since the beginning of July.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Broadly, Beijing is concerned about four pillars of stability: banking, antitrust regulation, data security and social equality. For example, social equality being at the heart of the ban of for-profit after-school tutors or rights concerning gig economy workers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some market participants believe China is trying to direct capital and human resources from internet companies into sectors that will help the country become more self-reliant. A portfolio manager at M&amp;amp;G Investments, Singapore, tracking the Chinese economy said, “&lt;em&gt;They are trying to reach a new equilibrium because it seems capital flows were not in line with long-term, top- down priorities.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts believe the government’s latest initiatives are motivated by a bigger ambition to realign the relationship between private business and the state, with a goal of ensuring companies do more to serve the Communist Party’s economic, social and national security concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it is worth noticing that Huawei, which should fall under the purview of the state on every possible reason in law, is entirely untouched.&amp;nbsp; As per some observers, the reason for the telecom giant being solidly backed by Beijing is due to the mutual benefit of both parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China’s vision for a domestic adversary as opposed to a Silicon Valley has benefited the private companies for years from lax regulatory oversight. However, leaders now worry that the tech giants have become too big and could be using personal and corporate digital records as leverage to build &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/china-blocked-jack-mas-ant-ipo-after-an-investigation-revealed-who-stood-to-gain-11613491292?mod=searchresults_pos10&amp;amp;page=1&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;alternative power centers&lt;/a&gt; in the one-party state.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, the government has often demanded data from private firms, and could sometimes enforce its wishes, especially for hunting down criminal suspects and silencing dissent but the tech companies have pushed back on requests to share and centralise their statistics.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, Beijing now wishes to undo these through their complex cyber security laws and regulations which would make it harder for companies to resist data sharing requests.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chinese regulators have formally made the data localisation requirement a prerequisite for foreign institutions trying to get a foothold in China, enabling the government to have more authority over the records. Western companies have long complained such “data localisation” requirements could stifle innovation in their global operations or enable Chinese authorities to steal their proprietary information.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US electric car maker &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/market-data/quotes/TSLA&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Tesla&lt;/a&gt; Inc has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/tesla-to-store-china-data-locally-in-new-data-center-11622015001?mod=article_inline&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pledged&lt;/a&gt; to build more data centers in China and to keep information generated by the vehicles it sells there, within Chinese borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Less invasive private-sector data collection anywhere is a good thing,” says analyst Ryan Fedasiuk at Georgetown University’s Center for Security and Emerging Technology. “But China’s push for data privacy strikes me as yet another move to strengthen the role of the government and the party vis-à-vis tech companies.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the EU rules, the Chinese version lacks restrictions on government entities when it comes to gathering information on people’s call logs, contact lists, location and other data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, these laws should also be seen against the backdrop of high tensions between US-China relations, which has sharpened President Xi’s focus on security and self-sufficiency. Beijing prohibits foreign ownership of larger sections of the Chinese economy, especially the profitable parts involving digital technology and data, and hence the companies follow a concept of&amp;nbsp; Variable-Interest-Entity or VIE, where the companies selling shares in foreign markets (including Hong Kong) can do so only quasi-legally at best. The workaround for VIE was the transparency that would come with foreign ownership and control which could reveal more about the state of the economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under a 2020 law signed by then-President, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/topics/person/donald-trump&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Donald Trump&lt;/a&gt;, Chinese companies would have to share their audit working papers with the US regulators. Failure to do so would lead to delisting of companies from US exchanges.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For China, that could risk allowing key data, such as detailed information about Chinese consumers and government agencies that may be included in the papers, to end up in the hands of a foreign government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both the second largest economy in the world and West see tech as a possible disrupter, however, it’s the Chinese who seem to be turbocharging a move towards the real tech, where they are ready to destroy the ‘pre-tender’ that exists today.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In November 2020, I authored an article on China’s move of scuttling Ant Group Co.’s blockbuster $37 billion listing. Little did we know that it was just the beginning of an excessive clampdown on the country's technological sector.&amp;nbsp; To continue with the story of e-commerce giant Alibaba, the country’s authorities imposed a record fine - $2.8 billion in 2021, after an investigation that found it had abused its dominant market position for years. China’s unprecedented crackdown on its tech industry has cost several companies and their investors hundreds of billions of dollars. Tencent alone has had $170 billion shaved off its value. For context, that’s more than ten Byju’s, India’s biggest startup, which is valued at $16.5 billion.&amp;nbsp; The July Roundup by Goldman Sachs Group Inc shows that since November, the country’s regulators have taken more than 50 actual or reported actions on areas spanning antitrust, finance, data security and social equality, i.e. more than one move a week. For decades, China has assiduously built up its tech sector, and has borrowed an industrial and internet model from the West. Arguably it was a resounding success, then why is it now trying to strangle the golden goose it had once cradled?&amp;nbsp; China adopted a new cybersecurity law in June, which builds on the foundation of the 2017 Cyber Security Law, that started tightening the control of data flow. However, since the measure was vaguely worded, it remained unclear how it would be implemented. Around the same time, the Chinese economy was rebounding from its bout with COVID-19, lifting the nation's ride, hailing giant Didi Global’s revenue with it as the US stock market continued to be in a bull run. Didi's long venture investors, including Softbank’s Vision Fund, urged seizing the moment to take the company public. The company made its debut at $14 on the New York Stock Exchange on the last day of June 2021, raising $4.4 billion - the biggest stock sale by a Chinese company since the 2014 listing of Alibaba Group Holding Ltd.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Its shares briefly topped $18 in the first days of trading, before China’s cyber security watchdog - Cyberspace Administration of China (CAC) stunned investors on July 2 by launching a data-security probe into Didi and blocking its China business from adding new users.&amp;nbsp; The crackdown worsened on July 9, when 25 more Didi apps - including ones used by drivers - were ordered to be removed from app stores, potentially crippling the company’s operations. If this was not enough, the administration further extended its clampdown on other sectors in&amp;nbsp; July. On July 22, the government announced new worker protection rules, under which online food platforms must cover minimum wage and insurance benefits. This gutted the share price of delivery giants such as Meituan and its rival, Alibaba's Ele.me; which had drawn severe criticism on social media for their treatment of riders and guaranteed time-bound delivery which has compelled riders to undertake dangerous routes, risking their lives.&amp;nbsp; On the following day, Beijing effectively torpedoed a multibillion-dollar industry - after-school tutoring - with a single administrative order. The new rules banned companies that teach the K-12 school curriculum from going public and registering themselves as non-profits. The shares of the three largest US-listed Chinese edtech firms - TAL Education, New Oriental and Gaotu Techedu, fell by 65-70% on the announcement, and the founders of the latter two companies went from billionaires to millionaires almost instantly. The corporate intervention that has hammered internet stocks is now driving investors to sectors still in Beijing’s good graces, such as high-tech manufacturing and renewable energy. Indexes for new energy stocks, semiconductor makers and electric vehicle companies, outperformed the market from 4% to 18% since the beginning of July.&amp;nbsp; Broadly, Beijing is concerned about four pillars of stability: banking, antitrust regulation, data security and social equality. For example, social equality being at the heart of the ban of for-profit after-school tutors or rights concerning gig economy workers.&amp;nbsp; Some market participants believe China is trying to direct capital and human resources from internet companies into sectors that will help the country become more self-reliant. A portfolio manager at M&amp;amp;G Investments, Singapore, tracking the Chinese economy said, “They are trying to reach a new equilibrium because it seems capital flows were not in line with long-term, top- down priorities.” Analysts believe the government’s latest initiatives are motivated by a bigger ambition to realign the relationship between private business and the state, with a goal of ensuring companies do more to serve the Communist Party’s economic, social and national security concerns. However, it is worth noticing that Huawei, which should fall under the purview of the state on every possible reason in law, is entirely untouched.&amp;nbsp; As per some observers, the reason for the telecom giant being solidly backed by Beijing is due to the mutual benefit of both parties. China’s vision for a domestic adversary as opposed to a Silicon Valley has benefited the private companies for years from lax regulatory oversight. However, leaders now worry that the tech giants have become too big and could be using personal and corporate digital records as leverage to build alternative power centers in the one-party state.&amp;nbsp; In the past, the government has often demanded data from private firms, and could sometimes enforce its wishes, especially for hunting down criminal suspects and silencing dissent but the tech companies have pushed back on requests to share and centralise their statistics.&amp;nbsp; Nonetheless, Beijing now wishes to undo these through their complex cyber security laws and regulations which would make it harder for companies to resist data sharing requests.&amp;nbsp; Chinese regulators have formally made the data localisation requirement a prerequisite for foreign institutions trying to get a foothold in China, enabling the government to have more authority over the records. Western companies have long complained such “data localisation” requirements could stifle innovation in their global operations or enable Chinese authorities to steal their proprietary information.&amp;nbsp; US electric car maker Tesla Inc has pledged to build more data centers in China and to keep information generated by the vehicles it sells there, within Chinese borders. “Less invasive private-sector data collection anywhere is a good thing,” says analyst Ryan Fedasiuk at Georgetown University’s Center for Security and Emerging Technology. “But China’s push for data privacy strikes me as yet another move to strengthen the role of the government and the party vis-à-vis tech companies.” Unlike the EU rules, the Chinese version lacks restrictions on government entities when it comes to gathering information on people’s call logs, contact lists, location and other data. Meanwhile, these laws should also be seen against the backdrop of high tensions between US-China relations, which has sharpened President Xi’s focus on security and self-sufficiency. Beijing prohibits foreign ownership of larger sections of the Chinese economy, especially the profitable parts involving digital technology and data, and hence the companies follow a concept of&amp;nbsp; Variable-Interest-Entity or VIE, where the companies selling shares in foreign markets (including Hong Kong) can do so only quasi-legally at best. The workaround for VIE was the transparency that would come with foreign ownership and control which could reveal more about the state of the economy.&amp;nbsp; Under a 2020 law signed by then-President, Donald Trump, Chinese companies would have to share their audit working papers with the US regulators. Failure to do so would lead to delisting of companies from US exchanges.&amp;nbsp; For China, that could risk allowing key data, such as detailed information about Chinese consumers and government agencies that may be included in the papers, to end up in the hands of a foreign government. Both the second largest economy in the world and West see tech as a possible disrupter, however, it’s the Chinese who seem to be turbocharging a move towards the real tech, where they are ready to destroy the ‘pre-tender’ that exists today.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Afghanistan Is Not Vietnam: The American Empire Is Dying</title>
      <link href="/Afghanistan-Is-Not-Vietnam" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Afghanistan Is Not Vietnam: The American Empire Is Dying" />
      <published>2021-09-19T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Afghanistan-Is-Not-Vietnam</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Afghanistan-Is-Not-Vietnam">&lt;p&gt;The professional pundits of foreign policy are busy discussing the parallels between Afghanistan and Vietnam. But the fact is that the US was a whole different country at the end of the Vietnam war: it was deadlocked with the USSR in a struggle for world domination, its internal politics were beset with the winds of change, welfare statism and economic growth were on the rise, and the new directions that the polity of the ‘Empire’ would take were being thrashed out.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At present, the social upheavals due to racial tensions, the extreme shifts in the politics of both the Republicans and Democrats, and the challenge presented by the Dragon in the East, do make it appear as though we are back in the 60's and the 70's. But we can sense that we are dealing with a very different America. Like President Joe Biden, the US is growing old, its grip on power is waning, its ability and commitment to expanding and maintaining its vast Empire is declining.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, let us look at America's finances. The US government's deficits and borrowing have been consistently high since the Great Recession. It is expected that the US' debt-to-GDP ratio will reach 277% by 2029, surpassing Japan's 272%, making it the country with the highest debt-to-GDP ratio in the world. Corporate debt, i.e. the debt of the real gods of America, has been steadily increasing as well. It has reached a high of nearly $11 trillion this year, causing grave concern for the Federal Reserve.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is that the huge expenses that are needed to maintain America's military might become exceedingly irrational. A quick look at the numbers from the last ten years would indicate that despite the Iraq War having been brought to an end by the Obama administration in 2011, the military budget of the United States has grown by nearly $80 billion. A third of the budget of the Department of Defense is spent on personnel and maintenance, which will probably rise by 100% by 2024 due to retirement and medical care costs. Moreover, the Department of Defense estimates that it is operating with 21% excess capacity in all its bases, since Congressmen cannot afford to allow their constituents to lose the jobs that these bases provide.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It becomes simply impossible to make sense of this kind of wasting of money when the US national debt is touching $22 trillion. It also goes to show that America's massive military might is built on a Jenga of dollar bills that simply cannot withstand that kind of weight. So, when America under the Trump administration brokered the deal with the Taliban and moved to exit swiftly from Afghanistan under the Biden administration, it did so just like that rich bully whose daddy had just been declared bankrupt.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the corporate side of things, the burgeoning debt signals its own kind of decline, i.e., the dependence on a chain of debt to sustain the investment and expenditure activities instead of consumer spending. When this is seen along with a real average wage that has the same purchasing power as in 1979, one can see that American corporations are not delivering on the free-market capitalist promise of a market economy that works for everyone. The consequence is that the power and ability of corporations to control American affairs and to benefit from the exploitation of the resources that form part of its Empire is dwindling. The very fact that workers are refusing to take up jobs despite there being a demand in the labour market is symptomatic of the extent to which American corporations are losing their god-like status.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of these present day crises can compare with the situation prevailing at the time of the Vietnam War. The total cost of the said war when compared with the $2 trillion cost of the Afghanistan War was a paltry $738 billion, when adjusted for inflation. The debt-to-GDP ratio actually decreased during the years of the Vietnam War. It stood at 43% in 1965, when America entered the war, and reduced to 32% in 1975, when America exited Vietnam.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only does America stand materially diminished in its ability to engage in the enterprise of Empire, its influence over its allies is waning as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allies are the grease which keep the war machines of an empire well-oiled, they are the support system that holds up its edifice. The British Empire in India was built on the Indian aristocracy and financial class switching loyalties from the Mughals to John Bull. It was Oxbridge-educated Indian civil servants, politicians, lawyers, etc., who ran the Empire in India and beyond. The British Empire began to falter the moment the elite class of Indians decided to no longer support the British Raj. From Gandhi to Nehru to Jinnah to Ambedkar, an overwhelming number of India and Pakistan's founding fathers were from elite Indian families, with a quintessentially British upper class education. In fact, it was this upper class education that exposed these leaders to ideas such as liberty, equality, and democracy, which they then used to dismantle the ideological core of the Empire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;America is losing the allies that make its Empire possible in a manner that is no different from the way in which the British lost their allies in India. In an attempt to bombard its allies with its own ideology, America has made its politics, food, music, and culture a global spectacle and phenomenon. From fast food joints to Marvel movies, America's allies, i.e. 'the West', are bombarded with assertions of the Empire's superiority. While at the time of the Vietnam War this cultural messaging united the West in service of the supposedly rules-based, international world order championed by America, it is now coming back to bite&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;America in the behind.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As American media and American culture infect the world, the conflicts and the issues that plague that culture seize the imagination of its allies. As America struggles so heavily with its nationalistic propaganda on one hand and the consequent backlash against the same on the other, the same point of conflict is assuming the centre-stage in very many Western countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Britain this phenomenon has led to Brexit and a renewed call for Scottish independence. In France, we see the rise of Marine Lé Pen. In Germany, we see the rise of the &lt;em&gt;Alternative für Deutschland&lt;/em&gt;. These nationalistic movements question the American hegemony, they call out the skewed nature of the relationship the West has with the US. Serious strains have developed in the 'special relationship' between the UK and the US. In fact, China has even proposed an Africa Quad with France and Germany. The fact of the matter is that American nationalism and populism has made its allies swerve towards their own kind of nationalism and populism as they begin to ask themselves whether accepting American hegemony should really be such an important priority.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, it's not like America is trying to keep its allies in mind when formulating its foreign policy objectives. This became starkly apparent during the Trump-era. Trump went straight ahead and questioned the usefulness of the NATO (North Atlantic Treaty Alliance) in a NATO summit itself. He berated Europe for its supposed inability to protect itself and even torpedoed the Iran nuclear deal – coming very close to starting a war with the country, much to the chagrin of key allies like France. In fact, President Macron of France had to step in to try and neutralise the situation after Trump exited the nuclear deal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Trump's America First policy is not being imitated in its rhetoric by the Biden administration, it is quite apparent that the Biden administration does not intend to change course. Biden's sudden withdrawal from Afghanistan and his statement that intervention would be written out of America's defence and foreign policy toolkit is symptomatic of how Biden is as uninterested in the Empire as Trump. The end of the Vietnam War never brought into question the Empire itself. That project was abandoned because it stopped making business sense after a point of time. Afghanistan, on the other hand, is being abandoned because the very task of maintaining world dominance seems too taxing for America to handle any longer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is the issue of social upheaval. Both the Vietnam War and the Afghanistan War were accompanied by a period of intense social unrest in America. With the benefit of hindsight, one can observe that the two are hardly comparable. The Vietnam War came at a time when the Civil Rights Movement was in full swing. It was accompanied by the Sexual Revolution, the Hippie movement, the growth of subaltern literature, and, of course, the Johnson Presidency's welfare reforms. All of these movements ultimately served to reinvigorate American exceptionalism. These movements did critique the American Empire, but they were ultimately the birth pangs of a new age of American domination, not a challenge to the core of the Empire. The abolition of the Jim Crow laws and the implementation of Medicaid made America fairer and more equal, they did not question America itself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the social unrest that has plagued America since the Great Recession is of a far more sinister kind. When the riots began after the killing of George Floyd, they did not merely call out racial injustice, they questioned the very existence of America as an entity which was built by slave-owners and continues to be exploitative of racial minorities. The protesters did not have a &quot;dream&quot; when they took down Robert E. Lee's statues, they had a pent up rage that had found its outlet through violent protest. The same sentiments were echoed in the Occupy Wall Street movements, the very basis of America, i.e., capitalism was brought into question by those movements. Large portions of the American populace are hitting the streets to express a desire to &quot;eat the rich&quot; at this point of time. A man calling himself a socialist would never have any popularity during the Vietnam War years, but in 2019, Senator Bernie Sanders nearly bagged the Democratic nomination for the Presidency.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seen in this light, the end of the Afghanistan War comes at a time when the American populace is questioning America itself. The American withdrawal from Afghanistan is an expression of exhaustion from a bloody conflict that the US just cannot afford. It is part of a series of events, both inside and outside America, which indicate that the torch of American hegemony is about to go out very soon, and far more horrifically than we may imagine. May God truly bless America.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The professional pundits of foreign policy are busy discussing the parallels between Afghanistan and Vietnam. But the fact is that the US was a whole different country at the end of the Vietnam war: it was deadlocked with the USSR in a struggle for world domination, its internal politics were beset with the winds of change, welfare statism and economic growth were on the rise, and the new directions that the polity of the ‘Empire’ would take were being thrashed out.&amp;nbsp; At present, the social upheavals due to racial tensions, the extreme shifts in the politics of both the Republicans and Democrats, and the challenge presented by the Dragon in the East, do make it appear as though we are back in the 60's and the 70's. But we can sense that we are dealing with a very different America. Like President Joe Biden, the US is growing old, its grip on power is waning, its ability and commitment to expanding and maintaining its vast Empire is declining.&amp;nbsp; First of all, let us look at America's finances. The US government's deficits and borrowing have been consistently high since the Great Recession. It is expected that the US' debt-to-GDP ratio will reach 277% by 2029, surpassing Japan's 272%, making it the country with the highest debt-to-GDP ratio in the world. Corporate debt, i.e. the debt of the real gods of America, has been steadily increasing as well. It has reached a high of nearly $11 trillion this year, causing grave concern for the Federal Reserve.&amp;nbsp; The result is that the huge expenses that are needed to maintain America's military might become exceedingly irrational. A quick look at the numbers from the last ten years would indicate that despite the Iraq War having been brought to an end by the Obama administration in 2011, the military budget of the United States has grown by nearly $80 billion. A third of the budget of the Department of Defense is spent on personnel and maintenance, which will probably rise by 100% by 2024 due to retirement and medical care costs. Moreover, the Department of Defense estimates that it is operating with 21% excess capacity in all its bases, since Congressmen cannot afford to allow their constituents to lose the jobs that these bases provide.&amp;nbsp; It becomes simply impossible to make sense of this kind of wasting of money when the US national debt is touching $22 trillion. It also goes to show that America's massive military might is built on a Jenga of dollar bills that simply cannot withstand that kind of weight. So, when America under the Trump administration brokered the deal with the Taliban and moved to exit swiftly from Afghanistan under the Biden administration, it did so just like that rich bully whose daddy had just been declared bankrupt.&amp;nbsp; On the corporate side of things, the burgeoning debt signals its own kind of decline, i.e., the dependence on a chain of debt to sustain the investment and expenditure activities instead of consumer spending. When this is seen along with a real average wage that has the same purchasing power as in 1979, one can see that American corporations are not delivering on the free-market capitalist promise of a market economy that works for everyone. The consequence is that the power and ability of corporations to control American affairs and to benefit from the exploitation of the resources that form part of its Empire is dwindling. The very fact that workers are refusing to take up jobs despite there being a demand in the labour market is symptomatic of the extent to which American corporations are losing their god-like status.&amp;nbsp; None of these present day crises can compare with the situation prevailing at the time of the Vietnam War. The total cost of the said war when compared with the $2 trillion cost of the Afghanistan War was a paltry $738 billion, when adjusted for inflation. The debt-to-GDP ratio actually decreased during the years of the Vietnam War. It stood at 43% in 1965, when America entered the war, and reduced to 32% in 1975, when America exited Vietnam.&amp;nbsp; Not only does America stand materially diminished in its ability to engage in the enterprise of Empire, its influence over its allies is waning as well.&amp;nbsp; Allies are the grease which keep the war machines of an empire well-oiled, they are the support system that holds up its edifice. The British Empire in India was built on the Indian aristocracy and financial class switching loyalties from the Mughals to John Bull. It was Oxbridge-educated Indian civil servants, politicians, lawyers, etc., who ran the Empire in India and beyond. The British Empire began to falter the moment the elite class of Indians decided to no longer support the British Raj. From Gandhi to Nehru to Jinnah to Ambedkar, an overwhelming number of India and Pakistan's founding fathers were from elite Indian families, with a quintessentially British upper class education. In fact, it was this upper class education that exposed these leaders to ideas such as liberty, equality, and democracy, which they then used to dismantle the ideological core of the Empire. America is losing the allies that make its Empire possible in a manner that is no different from the way in which the British lost their allies in India. In an attempt to bombard its allies with its own ideology, America has made its politics, food, music, and culture a global spectacle and phenomenon. From fast food joints to Marvel movies, America's allies, i.e. 'the West', are bombarded with assertions of the Empire's superiority. While at the time of the Vietnam War this cultural messaging united the West in service of the supposedly rules-based, international world order championed by America, it is now coming back to bite America in the behind.&amp;nbsp; As American media and American culture infect the world, the conflicts and the issues that plague that culture seize the imagination of its allies. As America struggles so heavily with its nationalistic propaganda on one hand and the consequent backlash against the same on the other, the same point of conflict is assuming the centre-stage in very many Western countries.&amp;nbsp; In Britain this phenomenon has led to Brexit and a renewed call for Scottish independence. In France, we see the rise of Marine Lé Pen. In Germany, we see the rise of the Alternative für Deutschland. These nationalistic movements question the American hegemony, they call out the skewed nature of the relationship the West has with the US. Serious strains have developed in the 'special relationship' between the UK and the US. In fact, China has even proposed an Africa Quad with France and Germany. The fact of the matter is that American nationalism and populism has made its allies swerve towards their own kind of nationalism and populism as they begin to ask themselves whether accepting American hegemony should really be such an important priority.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, it's not like America is trying to keep its allies in mind when formulating its foreign policy objectives. This became starkly apparent during the Trump-era. Trump went straight ahead and questioned the usefulness of the NATO (North Atlantic Treaty Alliance) in a NATO summit itself. He berated Europe for its supposed inability to protect itself and even torpedoed the Iran nuclear deal – coming very close to starting a war with the country, much to the chagrin of key allies like France. In fact, President Macron of France had to step in to try and neutralise the situation after Trump exited the nuclear deal.&amp;nbsp; While Trump's America First policy is not being imitated in its rhetoric by the Biden administration, it is quite apparent that the Biden administration does not intend to change course. Biden's sudden withdrawal from Afghanistan and his statement that intervention would be written out of America's defence and foreign policy toolkit is symptomatic of how Biden is as uninterested in the Empire as Trump. The end of the Vietnam War never brought into question the Empire itself. That project was abandoned because it stopped making business sense after a point of time. Afghanistan, on the other hand, is being abandoned because the very task of maintaining world dominance seems too taxing for America to handle any longer.&amp;nbsp; Finally, there is the issue of social upheaval. Both the Vietnam War and the Afghanistan War were accompanied by a period of intense social unrest in America. With the benefit of hindsight, one can observe that the two are hardly comparable. The Vietnam War came at a time when the Civil Rights Movement was in full swing. It was accompanied by the Sexual Revolution, the Hippie movement, the growth of subaltern literature, and, of course, the Johnson Presidency's welfare reforms. All of these movements ultimately served to reinvigorate American exceptionalism. These movements did critique the American Empire, but they were ultimately the birth pangs of a new age of American domination, not a challenge to the core of the Empire. The abolition of the Jim Crow laws and the implementation of Medicaid made America fairer and more equal, they did not question America itself.&amp;nbsp; In contrast, the social unrest that has plagued America since the Great Recession is of a far more sinister kind. When the riots began after the killing of George Floyd, they did not merely call out racial injustice, they questioned the very existence of America as an entity which was built by slave-owners and continues to be exploitative of racial minorities. The protesters did not have a &quot;dream&quot; when they took down Robert E. Lee's statues, they had a pent up rage that had found its outlet through violent protest. The same sentiments were echoed in the Occupy Wall Street movements, the very basis of America, i.e., capitalism was brought into question by those movements. Large portions of the American populace are hitting the streets to express a desire to &quot;eat the rich&quot; at this point of time. A man calling himself a socialist would never have any popularity during the Vietnam War years, but in 2019, Senator Bernie Sanders nearly bagged the Democratic nomination for the Presidency.&amp;nbsp; Seen in this light, the end of the Afghanistan War comes at a time when the American populace is questioning America itself. The American withdrawal from Afghanistan is an expression of exhaustion from a bloody conflict that the US just cannot afford. It is part of a series of events, both inside and outside America, which indicate that the torch of American hegemony is about to go out very soon, and far more horrifically than we may imagine. May God truly bless America.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Gender Roles: the Fallacy, the Irony and the Hypocrisy</title>
      <link href="/Gender-Roles-the-Fallacy-the-Irony-and-the-Hypocrisy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gender Roles: the Fallacy, the Irony and the Hypocrisy" />
      <published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Gender-Roles-the-Fallacy-the-Irony-and-the-Hypocrisy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Gender-Roles-the-Fallacy-the-Irony-and-the-Hypocrisy">&lt;p&gt;Gender roles and norms refer to a set of ideals that people of a particular sex (assigned at birth) are expected to conform to. They have, for years, set unrealistic standards for all people and formed the basis of an endless number of discriminatory and amoral practices. People lend support to them using the reasoning that they are based on scientific facts about biological sex. Recently, more and more people have started to openly show disdain for and disagreement with these norms, citing the numerous long standing and potentially dangerous effects of the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For long, anthropologists have put forward various pieces of evidence to prove that gender norms are but a social construct. They have repeatedly talked about how 'femininity' and 'masculinity' are relative terms. Margaret Mead was one such anthropologist, often deemed as a sort of a maverick in the field. She revolutionised the field of study, which was previously prominently arm-chair based knowledge, by taking up a more proactive approach. She travelled to remote parts of the world to understand how men and women related to each other, in comparison to the Western ideals of 'femininity', 'masculinity' and 'gender roles'. Over the course of her life, she penned down several preeminent books on the matter.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1933, Mead wrote &lt;em&gt;Sex and Temperament in Three Primitive Societies&lt;/em&gt;. She compared three indigenous groups from the South Pacific which she designated as Arapesh, Tchambuli and Mundugumor. The cultures wildly differed in their expectations and standards for men and women. She noted that in comparison to the established Western standards, all of Arapesh was feminine while the opposite was true for Mundugumor, that is, it was masculine. Tchambuli, on the other hand, reversed Western ideals completely - the dominant positions belonged to women while the dependent ones to men. Mead’s conclusion from the analysis was clear: human nature is malleable and it responds to cultural conditions. Nurture and not nature is responsible for the concept of gender. In other words, gender roles are social constructs, and do not have a basis in the more biological aspects of sex.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the fact that gender roles are social constructs can be lucidly seen in a particular culture too as the ideals change drastically over time, sometimes even undergoing a full 180 degree reversal. The perception of the colors pink and blue is one such example. Pink was not labelled as feminine color until the 1940's. Prior to this, color was generally assigned based on the complexion and so any baby could be dressed in blue or pink. Further back, during the 18th century, pink, which was seen as a close relative of the martial red color, was considered to be a masculine shade. Even as recently as in 1918, an article titled 'Pink or Blue' in &lt;em&gt;The Infants’ Department&lt;/em&gt; stated that pink was meant for boys and blue was for girls. The trend is the exact opposite of this today.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, perceptions about makeup have vacillated between being deemed as feminine and being expected of everyone, through the ages. Makeup was in common use by all people in ancient Egypt, Rome and other civilisations, dating back to as far as 4000 BC in humankind’s history. However, the scenario is obviously very different in the modern world where putting on makeup is predominantly deemed as a feminine activity. In Elizabethan England, makeup was very popular among men. In the mid-1800's however, Queen Victoria and the Church agreed that makeup was an “abomination”. The dissemination of this belief resulted in a long standing association of makeup with femininity and the “Devil’s Work”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These oscillations in ideals and standards associated with gender, within a particular community over time and between different communities at any specific point in time prove that gender norms and expectations are, in fact, not dictated by the biology of sex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gender norms have encouraged various discriminatory and immoral practices through the years of human history and they are still thriving today. More often than not, they're what is responsible for the microaggressions against people of all genders and sexes. For example, men are told not to cry or show emotions, and are expected to partake in activities deemed as worthy of men, often involving heavy manual labor. Those who indulge in the more 'feminine' activities like putting on makeup, cooking and playing sports seen as girly like cheerleading, are looked down upon and slandered.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other end of the spectrum, women are faced with disparaging comments that declare that they simply cannot be funny and belong in the kitchen. Similarly, limited mathematical aptitude and tendency of being loving, caring or sensitive is attributed to their gender. Women are repeatedly talked over and mansplained in professional spaces, in addition to being doubted, especially in leadership roles. Effeminate men are criticised for being too 'feminine', androgenous people are told they are too ambiguous and tomboys are told they are too 'masculine', all of these come paired with a negative undertone. The inferiority of women in the eyes of society is especially clear in such sexist jibes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fallacy, hypocrisy and irony in the gender roles and standards are especially evident through the everyday misogynistic and sexist microaggressions faced by people. Women are told that they are meant to be mothers and yet, young mothers are shamed and criticised almost as much as those who abort their fetus to escape the shame (apart from other reasons). Working women with families are denigrated just as much as those who choose to stay at home.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The former are slandered with claims of being an unfit mother - too calculating, too progressive, too career-oriented. The latter are faced with epithets like 'gold digger' and 'bad role model' as their work is often overlooked. They are also regularly accused of being indolent and lazy. When a woman refuses to give in to the sexual demands of entitled men, they are tagged as 'too prudish' and yet, giving in or choosing to be more sexually active earns them the label 'slut' or 'easy'. Liking dresses and heels is deemed to be too 'frivolous' and 'girly' (with a negative connotation attached) and conversely, women are flagged as gay (often used as a slur in this context) or too 'boyish' (and thus, unattractive) for choosing to have a more masculine aesthetic. Societal standards rooted in gender perception are a double-edged sword, especially for women and other minority genders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of history, an endless number of people have undermined the oppressive gender norms. Some of them achieve fame like Boudica and others attain notoriety like Mary, Queen of the Scots. But, more often than not, the contributions of women and other minority genders are overlooked. An important instance of erasure is the lack of acknowledgement of the contribution of medieval European women to the arts of the times.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Medieval women, especially widows, are generally portrayed as vulnerable, miserable and poor in history books and in literature. The truth, however, was far from this. Financially knowledgeable widows, who were well connected, often accumulated a lot of wealth through jointures and other mechanisms after the death of their husbands.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'Jointures' were pieces of land owned by both the wife and the husband. The ownership remained solely with the surviving spouse on the death of the other. This was very common in the 14th and 15th centuries and became a source of immense wealth for widows who outlived their husbands.They used this money to provide patronage to the arts. Some of the most well-known cathedrals and other monuments of the time were paid for by these widows. Many of them took this new liberty a step further; they commissioned the construction of memorials and mausoleums for themselves which transcended the boundaries of social and patriarchal expectations from women - extravagant architecture, statues of themselves as duchesses or more important than the men in their lives and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the patriarchal norms, a woman lost her individual identity with each marriage, taking up the name of their husbands in the medieval times. This makes it difficult to track the lives of these women (although not impossible) and their contributions to art are thus, largely unacknowledged. Modern public monuments also fail to represent women as history demands it. Of the more than 800 sculptures around the UK, only an abysmal 42 are those of named non-royal women.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, when simply ignoring history is difficult, people have opted to amend it to conform to society’s standards and expectations from a particular gender. Cleopatra VII has been portrayed several times in various books and movies, both Hollywood and otherwise. She is always shown as an unusually attractive seductress. 'Scandals' like her romance with Julius Caesar and Mark Anthony greatly overshadow her achievements, which are often completely ignored. Her stories are full of lies and rumours too. In reality, contrary to her popular portrayals, she was a great statesperson and could command armies. She was fluent in at least nine languages, including an Egyptian tongue, unlike her predecessors of the Ptolemaic dynasty. Additionally, Cleopatra was highly educated in the fields of astronomy, chemistry and literature, among other disciplines and can also be linked to numerous advancements in the field of alchemy of the time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides these, she has several administrative achievements under her belt including her proactive actions to curb corruption among the priests. Cleopatra was the reason for more than two decades of prosperity and stability in Egypt. Instead of acknowledging her numerous achievements, people are obsessed with her affairs with Caesar and Mark Anthony, going as far as blaming her for them and the fate and downfall they suffered later. This overlooks the fact that both Caesar and Mark Anthony were involved in countless other affairs. The queen was certainly not the beautiful seductress that we have been taught to believe. In fact, she might not even have been 'beautiful' as she was, much like most of the other Egyptian royal family members, a product of incest.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cleopatra’s character was questioned and her leadership was doubted by Greek and Roman writers, but this objection was primarily because she was a woman and therefore, according to them, unfit to rule. It is important to remember who the author of any particular story is when talking about its validity. In this case, it was the enemy and so, her stories are rife with rumours (like the story about her suicide by a snake bite). These canards are today frequently presented as history lessons and yet, they are far from the truth. Cleopatra VII is only one of numerous examples of women in history that we have wronged. We owe it to them to rectify the adulterations and remember them just as they were.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, we can say that gender norms have only encouraged damaging practices that have for years deprived us of an opportunity to celebrate the accurate history of humankind. It has paved the way for discriminatory practices against cis women, cis men, transgenders, non-binaries and so on and so forth. While many explain away the established gender roles with claims that they are rooted in biological tendencies and scientific facts about sex, anthropologists have long disagreed and put forward various pieces of evidence to substantiate the theory that gender is entirely a social construct. There is thus, absolutely no moral justification for upholding these standards any longer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Gender roles and norms refer to a set of ideals that people of a particular sex (assigned at birth) are expected to conform to. They have, for years, set unrealistic standards for all people and formed the basis of an endless number of discriminatory and amoral practices. People lend support to them using the reasoning that they are based on scientific facts about biological sex. Recently, more and more people have started to openly show disdain for and disagreement with these norms, citing the numerous long standing and potentially dangerous effects of the same.&amp;nbsp; For long, anthropologists have put forward various pieces of evidence to prove that gender norms are but a social construct. They have repeatedly talked about how 'femininity' and 'masculinity' are relative terms. Margaret Mead was one such anthropologist, often deemed as a sort of a maverick in the field. She revolutionised the field of study, which was previously prominently arm-chair based knowledge, by taking up a more proactive approach. She travelled to remote parts of the world to understand how men and women related to each other, in comparison to the Western ideals of 'femininity', 'masculinity' and 'gender roles'. Over the course of her life, she penned down several preeminent books on the matter.&amp;nbsp; In 1933, Mead wrote Sex and Temperament in Three Primitive Societies. She compared three indigenous groups from the South Pacific which she designated as Arapesh, Tchambuli and Mundugumor. The cultures wildly differed in their expectations and standards for men and women. She noted that in comparison to the established Western standards, all of Arapesh was feminine while the opposite was true for Mundugumor, that is, it was masculine. Tchambuli, on the other hand, reversed Western ideals completely - the dominant positions belonged to women while the dependent ones to men. Mead’s conclusion from the analysis was clear: human nature is malleable and it responds to cultural conditions. Nurture and not nature is responsible for the concept of gender. In other words, gender roles are social constructs, and do not have a basis in the more biological aspects of sex.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, the fact that gender roles are social constructs can be lucidly seen in a particular culture too as the ideals change drastically over time, sometimes even undergoing a full 180 degree reversal. The perception of the colors pink and blue is one such example. Pink was not labelled as feminine color until the 1940's. Prior to this, color was generally assigned based on the complexion and so any baby could be dressed in blue or pink. Further back, during the 18th century, pink, which was seen as a close relative of the martial red color, was considered to be a masculine shade. Even as recently as in 1918, an article titled 'Pink or Blue' in The Infants’ Department stated that pink was meant for boys and blue was for girls. The trend is the exact opposite of this today.&amp;nbsp; Likewise, perceptions about makeup have vacillated between being deemed as feminine and being expected of everyone, through the ages. Makeup was in common use by all people in ancient Egypt, Rome and other civilisations, dating back to as far as 4000 BC in humankind’s history. However, the scenario is obviously very different in the modern world where putting on makeup is predominantly deemed as a feminine activity. In Elizabethan England, makeup was very popular among men. In the mid-1800's however, Queen Victoria and the Church agreed that makeup was an “abomination”. The dissemination of this belief resulted in a long standing association of makeup with femininity and the “Devil’s Work”.&amp;nbsp; These oscillations in ideals and standards associated with gender, within a particular community over time and between different communities at any specific point in time prove that gender norms and expectations are, in fact, not dictated by the biology of sex. Gender norms have encouraged various discriminatory and immoral practices through the years of human history and they are still thriving today. More often than not, they're what is responsible for the microaggressions against people of all genders and sexes. For example, men are told not to cry or show emotions, and are expected to partake in activities deemed as worthy of men, often involving heavy manual labor. Those who indulge in the more 'feminine' activities like putting on makeup, cooking and playing sports seen as girly like cheerleading, are looked down upon and slandered.&amp;nbsp; On the other end of the spectrum, women are faced with disparaging comments that declare that they simply cannot be funny and belong in the kitchen. Similarly, limited mathematical aptitude and tendency of being loving, caring or sensitive is attributed to their gender. Women are repeatedly talked over and mansplained in professional spaces, in addition to being doubted, especially in leadership roles. Effeminate men are criticised for being too 'feminine', androgenous people are told they are too ambiguous and tomboys are told they are too 'masculine', all of these come paired with a negative undertone. The inferiority of women in the eyes of society is especially clear in such sexist jibes.&amp;nbsp; The fallacy, hypocrisy and irony in the gender roles and standards are especially evident through the everyday misogynistic and sexist microaggressions faced by people. Women are told that they are meant to be mothers and yet, young mothers are shamed and criticised almost as much as those who abort their fetus to escape the shame (apart from other reasons). Working women with families are denigrated just as much as those who choose to stay at home.&amp;nbsp; The former are slandered with claims of being an unfit mother - too calculating, too progressive, too career-oriented. The latter are faced with epithets like 'gold digger' and 'bad role model' as their work is often overlooked. They are also regularly accused of being indolent and lazy. When a woman refuses to give in to the sexual demands of entitled men, they are tagged as 'too prudish' and yet, giving in or choosing to be more sexually active earns them the label 'slut' or 'easy'. Liking dresses and heels is deemed to be too 'frivolous' and 'girly' (with a negative connotation attached) and conversely, women are flagged as gay (often used as a slur in this context) or too 'boyish' (and thus, unattractive) for choosing to have a more masculine aesthetic. Societal standards rooted in gender perception are a double-edged sword, especially for women and other minority genders.&amp;nbsp; Over the course of history, an endless number of people have undermined the oppressive gender norms. Some of them achieve fame like Boudica and others attain notoriety like Mary, Queen of the Scots. But, more often than not, the contributions of women and other minority genders are overlooked. An important instance of erasure is the lack of acknowledgement of the contribution of medieval European women to the arts of the times.&amp;nbsp; Medieval women, especially widows, are generally portrayed as vulnerable, miserable and poor in history books and in literature. The truth, however, was far from this. Financially knowledgeable widows, who were well connected, often accumulated a lot of wealth through jointures and other mechanisms after the death of their husbands.&amp;nbsp; 'Jointures' were pieces of land owned by both the wife and the husband. The ownership remained solely with the surviving spouse on the death of the other. This was very common in the 14th and 15th centuries and became a source of immense wealth for widows who outlived their husbands.They used this money to provide patronage to the arts. Some of the most well-known cathedrals and other monuments of the time were paid for by these widows. Many of them took this new liberty a step further; they commissioned the construction of memorials and mausoleums for themselves which transcended the boundaries of social and patriarchal expectations from women - extravagant architecture, statues of themselves as duchesses or more important than the men in their lives and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp; Due to the patriarchal norms, a woman lost her individual identity with each marriage, taking up the name of their husbands in the medieval times. This makes it difficult to track the lives of these women (although not impossible) and their contributions to art are thus, largely unacknowledged. Modern public monuments also fail to represent women as history demands it. Of the more than 800 sculptures around the UK, only an abysmal 42 are those of named non-royal women.&amp;nbsp; Sometimes, when simply ignoring history is difficult, people have opted to amend it to conform to society’s standards and expectations from a particular gender. Cleopatra VII has been portrayed several times in various books and movies, both Hollywood and otherwise. She is always shown as an unusually attractive seductress. 'Scandals' like her romance with Julius Caesar and Mark Anthony greatly overshadow her achievements, which are often completely ignored. Her stories are full of lies and rumours too. In reality, contrary to her popular portrayals, she was a great statesperson and could command armies. She was fluent in at least nine languages, including an Egyptian tongue, unlike her predecessors of the Ptolemaic dynasty. Additionally, Cleopatra was highly educated in the fields of astronomy, chemistry and literature, among other disciplines and can also be linked to numerous advancements in the field of alchemy of the time.&amp;nbsp; Besides these, she has several administrative achievements under her belt including her proactive actions to curb corruption among the priests. Cleopatra was the reason for more than two decades of prosperity and stability in Egypt. Instead of acknowledging her numerous achievements, people are obsessed with her affairs with Caesar and Mark Anthony, going as far as blaming her for them and the fate and downfall they suffered later. This overlooks the fact that both Caesar and Mark Anthony were involved in countless other affairs. The queen was certainly not the beautiful seductress that we have been taught to believe. In fact, she might not even have been 'beautiful' as she was, much like most of the other Egyptian royal family members, a product of incest.&amp;nbsp; Cleopatra’s character was questioned and her leadership was doubted by Greek and Roman writers, but this objection was primarily because she was a woman and therefore, according to them, unfit to rule. It is important to remember who the author of any particular story is when talking about its validity. In this case, it was the enemy and so, her stories are rife with rumours (like the story about her suicide by a snake bite). These canards are today frequently presented as history lessons and yet, they are far from the truth. Cleopatra VII is only one of numerous examples of women in history that we have wronged. We owe it to them to rectify the adulterations and remember them just as they were.&amp;nbsp; All in all, we can say that gender norms have only encouraged damaging practices that have for years deprived us of an opportunity to celebrate the accurate history of humankind. It has paved the way for discriminatory practices against cis women, cis men, transgenders, non-binaries and so on and so forth. While many explain away the established gender roles with claims that they are rooted in biological tendencies and scientific facts about sex, anthropologists have long disagreed and put forward various pieces of evidence to substantiate the theory that gender is entirely a social construct. There is thus, absolutely no moral justification for upholding these standards any longer.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What is Your Ideal Brand Doing for Your ‘Pride’?</title>
      <link href="/What-is-Your-Ideal-Brand-Doing-for-Your-Pride" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Your Ideal Brand Doing for Your ‘Pride’?" />
      <published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/What-is-Your-Ideal-Brand-Doing-for-Your-Pride</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-is-Your-Ideal-Brand-Doing-for-Your-Pride">&lt;p&gt;Each year, in the summertime, Pride collections emerge like a swarm of vividly coloured locusts. They envelop every storefront and Instagram feed in June, promising solidarity for LGBTQ+ communities. In 2021, we are yet again observing the second virtual celebration of pride month. Numerous brands have leveraged pride marketing to increase visibility and lend support to others within the LGBTQ+ community who are still exploring their identities. However, brands tend to forget the existence of the community as soon as July rolls on. It makes us question, is this just another marketing gimmick?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is customary for Pride-themed merchandise to spike during June, a practice known as rainbow capitalism, is often criticised and compared to pinkwashing. Nevertheless, there is still tremendous value that can come from rocking rainbows during this time of the year. Like ‘empowerment campaigns’, several brands climb the trend wagon in Pride month, with no concern for the cause. Pride marketing is empathetic, where aiming ‘just for sales’ will misfire and attract more backlash from the audience and hurt the entity's image in the long term. Therefore, brands should not use Pride month to ramp up the sales but instead use their platform to show support and disperse awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, Burger King's Pride month initiative was very thoughtful and won many hearts. Their tagline stated, &quot;&lt;em&gt;The pride is on you. The parade is on us&lt;/em&gt;&quot;, along with their delivery vehicles transformed. The campaign persisted till July 5. This year, diverse brands showcased their support to the community beyond rainbow washing and making the most out of pride marketing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Popular brands like Fossil, Apple, Reebok and others often dedicate enormous resources during Pride month to LGBTQ+ non-profit organisations (among them,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thetrevorproject.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Trevor Project&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.glsen.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GLSEN&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;and different groups), which means you could be helping others gain access to valuable resources, too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To honour Pride month, Fossil launched its all-new limited-edition Pride collection to celebrate the spirit of love, equality and the very essence of individuality. The proceeds from this collection will benefit The Trevor Project — the world’s most significant suicide prevention and crisis intervention organisation for LGBTQ+ young adults.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of Apple, it has released two new Apple Watch Pride bands this year and a new Pride watch face for users. The brand also supports many LGBTQ+ advocacy organisations, including&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://encircletogether.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Encircle&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;(which offers safe spaces for LGBTQ+ youth, young adults and families), the&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://transequality.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Center for Transgender Equality&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;(committed to social justice advocacy for transgender humans), and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To add on, Reebok’s newest collection celebrating the LGBTQ+ community features a vibrant assortment of Pride-inspired footwear and apparel. The items were designed by Colorful Soles, the brand’s LGBTQ+ employee community, which also partnered with the legendary House of Ninja (spotlighted in the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reviewed.com/streaming/features/black-history-documentaries-stream-now&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;iconic documentary&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Paris is Burning&lt;/em&gt;). Moreover, Reebok is donating $75,000 to the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://srlp.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sylvia Rivera Law Project&lt;/a&gt;, which advocates for affirming access to social, health and legal services for persons of all gender identities and expressions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Into the bargain, loads of fashion and beauty brands create Pride-inspired products that not only help you look great but also feel good as they support organisations that empower and uplift LGBTQ+ communities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give some instances, the Gap Collective Pride collection includes T-shirts, hoodies, socks and more for all ages. The brand is donating $50,000 this season to the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.glaad.org/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD)&lt;/a&gt;, an LGBTQ media advocacy organization.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Levi's is flaunting the Pride collection &quot;All Pronouns. All Love&quot; by emphasising respect for people's pronouns. They have the inscribed phrase &quot;they/them, she/her, he/him, we&quot; on their collections, which is gender-neutral. It will be donating 100% of the profits to OutRight Action International.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NYX's limited-edition collection comprises a wide makeup range that will bring a colourful ultra-metallic sheen. It will also donate $100,000 to Pride efforts globally and contribute towards the LA LGBT Center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other brands are also making their Pride-themed offerings and donations a year-round initiative, including Happy Socks, donating 10% of the sales from its rainbow-coloured socks to InterPride throughout the year, and Pink, which has expanded its offerings with its gender-inclusive Pink for All collection that debuted earlier this year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next door, LEGO has launched a limited-edition&amp;nbsp;LGBTQ themed set. This is the first LGBTQ set with 11 monochromatic figures, each with an assigned colour and 346 pieces creating a rainbow cascade.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, TGI Fridays have introduced a decadent, delicious dessert. This dessert is six layers of rainbow-coloured vanilla cake piled high with vanilla icing and sprinkles and is available for home delivery and in-store locations. Part of the profits generated from the sales will be donated to support GLSEN&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many music platforms in India, like music streaming service Jio Saavan and Spotify, and music channel VH1 are also celebrating Pride Month.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike other brands, Skittles took a bold move of launching limited-edition&amp;nbsp;Skittles Pride Packs&amp;nbsp;that come in grey packaging rather than rainbow washing. Even the candies inside are grey with delicious strawberries, orange, grape, apple, and lemon. For every pack sold, $1 will be donated to GLAAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shira Kogan, Director of Corporate Development at The Trevor Project, said &lt;em&gt;&quot;We are thrilled to see so many companies and brands stepping up to support Pride this year.&quot;&lt;/em&gt; Well, it is true that brands have the power and platform to influence others. These brands can tell stories to empower the LGBTQ+ community through marketing campaigns or a separate product line. Together they can create a world where the LGBTQ+ community is championed, celebrated and protected.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is that consumers of Pride gear are becoming more aware and are making an effort to shop where proceeds will make the most significant impact, including shopping at small, queer-owned businesses. For example, consumers are taking note when companies only feature underrepresented groups during their respective history or heritage months, says Ali Fazal, Vice President of Marketing at influencer marketing platform&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://grin.co/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GRIN&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;&quot;(If) the only time they see LGBT people represented is during Pride Month, it's clear that what you're doing is not a long-term evolution for your company and your marketing.&quot;&lt;/em&gt; says Fazal.&lt;em&gt;&quot;You're just trying to capitalize upon the seasonality of that month.&quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let's be honest: Most major brands have not maintained a consistent enough relationship with LGBTQ+ communities to survive Pride month without some level of scrutiny. More often than not, ‘rainbow washing’ — that is, the act of deploying Pride-themed versions of their products and marketing it without substantially engaging queer communities — tends to be the minimal-effort route that multiple brands take and majority of consumers recognise these attempts as inauthentic almost immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it's never too late to start developing real bonds with LGBTQ+ consumers. One of the most effective ways to show support is through charitable efforts, and Pride offers brands ample opportunities to turn their specialised products into the support that resonates beyond June.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a recent analysis, queer consumers who tend to maintain higher median household incomes, are more likely than other marginalised groups to actively seek and patronise the companies that engage with their collective community in a sustained fashion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, some brands understand the lasting power of giving back. It is important to remember the message one leaves out there can help lay the foundation of change. We need to understand that equality is not a once-a-month fight, but year-round support is necessary — not just for Pride month, but all the social causes we rise for. Together we can create a world, which is fairer for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samakshi Garg</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Each year, in the summertime, Pride collections emerge like a swarm of vividly coloured locusts. They envelop every storefront and Instagram feed in June, promising solidarity for LGBTQ+ communities. In 2021, we are yet again observing the second virtual celebration of pride month. Numerous brands have leveraged pride marketing to increase visibility and lend support to others within the LGBTQ+ community who are still exploring their identities. However, brands tend to forget the existence of the community as soon as July rolls on. It makes us question, is this just another marketing gimmick? While it is customary for Pride-themed merchandise to spike during June, a practice known as rainbow capitalism, is often criticised and compared to pinkwashing. Nevertheless, there is still tremendous value that can come from rocking rainbows during this time of the year. Like ‘empowerment campaigns’, several brands climb the trend wagon in Pride month, with no concern for the cause. Pride marketing is empathetic, where aiming ‘just for sales’ will misfire and attract more backlash from the audience and hurt the entity's image in the long term. Therefore, brands should not use Pride month to ramp up the sales but instead use their platform to show support and disperse awareness. In 2020, Burger King's Pride month initiative was very thoughtful and won many hearts. Their tagline stated, &quot;The pride is on you. The parade is on us&quot;, along with their delivery vehicles transformed. The campaign persisted till July 5. This year, diverse brands showcased their support to the community beyond rainbow washing and making the most out of pride marketing.&amp;nbsp; Popular brands like Fossil, Apple, Reebok and others often dedicate enormous resources during Pride month to LGBTQ+ non-profit organisations (among them,&amp;nbsp;The Trevor Project,&amp;nbsp;GLSEN&amp;nbsp;and different groups), which means you could be helping others gain access to valuable resources, too.&amp;nbsp; To honour Pride month, Fossil launched its all-new limited-edition Pride collection to celebrate the spirit of love, equality and the very essence of individuality. The proceeds from this collection will benefit The Trevor Project — the world’s most significant suicide prevention and crisis intervention organisation for LGBTQ+ young adults.&amp;nbsp; In the case of Apple, it has released two new Apple Watch Pride bands this year and a new Pride watch face for users. The brand also supports many LGBTQ+ advocacy organisations, including&amp;nbsp;Encircle&amp;nbsp;(which offers safe spaces for LGBTQ+ youth, young adults and families), the&amp;nbsp;National Center for Transgender Equality&amp;nbsp;(committed to social justice advocacy for transgender humans), and others. To add on, Reebok’s newest collection celebrating the LGBTQ+ community features a vibrant assortment of Pride-inspired footwear and apparel. The items were designed by Colorful Soles, the brand’s LGBTQ+ employee community, which also partnered with the legendary House of Ninja (spotlighted in the&amp;nbsp;iconic documentary,&amp;nbsp;Paris is Burning). Moreover, Reebok is donating $75,000 to the&amp;nbsp;Sylvia Rivera Law Project, which advocates for affirming access to social, health and legal services for persons of all gender identities and expressions.&amp;nbsp; Into the bargain, loads of fashion and beauty brands create Pride-inspired products that not only help you look great but also feel good as they support organisations that empower and uplift LGBTQ+ communities.&amp;nbsp; To give some instances, the Gap Collective Pride collection includes T-shirts, hoodies, socks and more for all ages. The brand is donating $50,000 this season to the&amp;nbsp;Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD), an LGBTQ media advocacy organization.&amp;nbsp; Levi's is flaunting the Pride collection &quot;All Pronouns. All Love&quot; by emphasising respect for people's pronouns. They have the inscribed phrase &quot;they/them, she/her, he/him, we&quot; on their collections, which is gender-neutral. It will be donating 100% of the profits to OutRight Action International.&amp;nbsp; NYX's limited-edition collection comprises a wide makeup range that will bring a colourful ultra-metallic sheen. It will also donate $100,000 to Pride efforts globally and contribute towards the LA LGBT Center. Other brands are also making their Pride-themed offerings and donations a year-round initiative, including Happy Socks, donating 10% of the sales from its rainbow-coloured socks to InterPride throughout the year, and Pink, which has expanded its offerings with its gender-inclusive Pink for All collection that debuted earlier this year.&amp;nbsp; Next door, LEGO has launched a limited-edition&amp;nbsp;LGBTQ themed set. This is the first LGBTQ set with 11 monochromatic figures, each with an assigned colour and 346 pieces creating a rainbow cascade.&amp;nbsp; Meanwhile, TGI Fridays have introduced a decadent, delicious dessert. This dessert is six layers of rainbow-coloured vanilla cake piled high with vanilla icing and sprinkles and is available for home delivery and in-store locations. Part of the profits generated from the sales will be donated to support GLSEN.&amp;nbsp; Many music platforms in India, like music streaming service Jio Saavan and Spotify, and music channel VH1 are also celebrating Pride Month.&amp;nbsp; Unlike other brands, Skittles took a bold move of launching limited-edition&amp;nbsp;Skittles Pride Packs&amp;nbsp;that come in grey packaging rather than rainbow washing. Even the candies inside are grey with delicious strawberries, orange, grape, apple, and lemon. For every pack sold, $1 will be donated to GLAAD. Shira Kogan, Director of Corporate Development at The Trevor Project, said &quot;We are thrilled to see so many companies and brands stepping up to support Pride this year.&quot; Well, it is true that brands have the power and platform to influence others. These brands can tell stories to empower the LGBTQ+ community through marketing campaigns or a separate product line. Together they can create a world where the LGBTQ+ community is championed, celebrated and protected.&amp;nbsp; The result is that consumers of Pride gear are becoming more aware and are making an effort to shop where proceeds will make the most significant impact, including shopping at small, queer-owned businesses. For example, consumers are taking note when companies only feature underrepresented groups during their respective history or heritage months, says Ali Fazal, Vice President of Marketing at influencer marketing platform&amp;nbsp;GRIN. &quot;(If) the only time they see LGBT people represented is during Pride Month, it's clear that what you're doing is not a long-term evolution for your company and your marketing.&quot; says Fazal.&quot;You're just trying to capitalize upon the seasonality of that month.&quot; Now let's be honest: Most major brands have not maintained a consistent enough relationship with LGBTQ+ communities to survive Pride month without some level of scrutiny. More often than not, ‘rainbow washing’ — that is, the act of deploying Pride-themed versions of their products and marketing it without substantially engaging queer communities — tends to be the minimal-effort route that multiple brands take and majority of consumers recognise these attempts as inauthentic almost immediately. But it's never too late to start developing real bonds with LGBTQ+ consumers. One of the most effective ways to show support is through charitable efforts, and Pride offers brands ample opportunities to turn their specialised products into the support that resonates beyond June.&amp;nbsp; According to a recent analysis, queer consumers who tend to maintain higher median household incomes, are more likely than other marginalised groups to actively seek and patronise the companies that engage with their collective community in a sustained fashion. Fortunately, some brands understand the lasting power of giving back. It is important to remember the message one leaves out there can help lay the foundation of change. We need to understand that equality is not a once-a-month fight, but year-round support is necessary — not just for Pride month, but all the social causes we rise for. Together we can create a world, which is fairer for everyone.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Post-COVID World Economy</title>
      <link href="/The-Post-COVID-World-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Post-COVID World Economy" />
      <published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Post-COVID-World-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Post-COVID-World-Economy">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The history of the world economy demonstrates a trend of economic shocks emerging in every generation. The World Health Organisation (WHO) declared COVID-19 as a global pandemic on March 11, 2020; and since then, almost every human endeavour has been disrupted.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The impact on the global economy is particularly worrying. We witnessed global supply chains being severely disrupted and strained, financial markets unsettled, resulting in a cross-border economic disaster. Border closures and lockdowns shattered the core sustaining pillars of modern world economies, with the economic shock due to these measures still being weighed across the globe. The ramifications of these disruptions are more far-reaching than anticipated, and the legacies of COVID-19 will shape global growth for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Even though economies are recovering at different paces throughout the world, the world economy is well on the way to recovery from a slump the likes of which none of its 7.7 billion inhabitants has seen in their lifetimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The new paradigms enforced in the COVID-19 era have led to an unprecedented acceleration in automation and digitisation of operations whilst highlighting the importance of upskilling the workforce. Turbulent labour markets provide additional challenges to professionals as the pace of technology adoption remains unabated while automation, in tandem with the COVID-19 recession, is creating a 'double-disruption' scenario for the labour force. There is more inequality between and within countries, and governments are playing a larger role in the lives of citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Looking at historical precedents, the World Economic Forum postulates that the pandemic is about three times as bad as the global financial crisis of 2008 in terms of GDP decline on an annual basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-center&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2020/09/an-economist-explains-what-covid-19-has-done-to-the-global-economy/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/IHS-Markit-gdp-growth.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Economists surmise that adopting a circular economy would be the best way for the world's economy to recover, whilst enabling the transition to an essentially low-carbon economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The pandemic also catalysed the rise of the digital economy, with the influx of digital behaviour such as remote working and learning, telemedicine, and delivery services. Due to this rapid digitisation, other structural changes can also be anticipated, including regionalisation of supply chains and a further explosion of cross-border data flows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The future of work has arrived faster, along with its myriad challenges such as worker vulnerability, income polarisation, more gig work, and the need for workers to adapt to occupational transitions multiplied in potential. This acceleration is the result not only of technological advances and recession, but also of new considerations for health and safety, and economies and labour markets will take time to recover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The quantum of the amplification of these trends and the realities of this crisis have also triggered a reconsideration of several beliefs, with implicit and long-lasting effects on the economy and society and attitudes about efficiency versus resilience, the future of capitalism, densification of economic activity and peoples’ lifestyles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The pandemic has also accelerated some of the key geopolitical trends that will shape our next world order - de-globalisation and nationalism, for instance, along with debilitating China’s hegemony in the supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While the quantitative disruptions in the economy, structured finance and credit facilities are quite explicit, the more permanent changes are perhaps the ones considered from humanitarian perspectives. The most prominent qualities that were on display during this time of distress were the adaptability and versatility of people, which caused the cataclysmic shift of buying patterns to the online medium and helped to keep it afloat while intensifying the focus on the triple bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Over the past two decades, in advancing economies, the onus of security has generally shifted from institutions to individuals. Healthcare systems are being tested and often found wanting, while benefits from paid sick leave to universal basic income are getting reviewed. There is potential for a long-term shift in how institutions offer support, through safety nets, and a more inclusive social contract.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;History bears witness that choices made during crises can shape the world for decades to come. What remains critical is the need for collective action to build economies that deliver inclusive economic growth, prosperity, and safety for all.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Maanya Oberoi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The history of the world economy demonstrates a trend of economic shocks emerging in every generation. The World Health Organisation (WHO) declared COVID-19 as a global pandemic on March 11, 2020; and since then, almost every human endeavour has been disrupted.&amp;nbsp; The impact on the global economy is particularly worrying. We witnessed global supply chains being severely disrupted and strained, financial markets unsettled, resulting in a cross-border economic disaster. Border closures and lockdowns shattered the core sustaining pillars of modern world economies, with the economic shock due to these measures still being weighed across the globe. The ramifications of these disruptions are more far-reaching than anticipated, and the legacies of COVID-19 will shape global growth for years to come. Even though economies are recovering at different paces throughout the world, the world economy is well on the way to recovery from a slump the likes of which none of its 7.7 billion inhabitants has seen in their lifetimes. The new paradigms enforced in the COVID-19 era have led to an unprecedented acceleration in automation and digitisation of operations whilst highlighting the importance of upskilling the workforce. Turbulent labour markets provide additional challenges to professionals as the pace of technology adoption remains unabated while automation, in tandem with the COVID-19 recession, is creating a 'double-disruption' scenario for the labour force. There is more inequality between and within countries, and governments are playing a larger role in the lives of citizens. Looking at historical precedents, the World Economic Forum postulates that the pandemic is about three times as bad as the global financial crisis of 2008 in terms of GDP decline on an annual basis. Economists surmise that adopting a circular economy would be the best way for the world's economy to recover, whilst enabling the transition to an essentially low-carbon economy. The pandemic also catalysed the rise of the digital economy, with the influx of digital behaviour such as remote working and learning, telemedicine, and delivery services. Due to this rapid digitisation, other structural changes can also be anticipated, including regionalisation of supply chains and a further explosion of cross-border data flows. The future of work has arrived faster, along with its myriad challenges such as worker vulnerability, income polarisation, more gig work, and the need for workers to adapt to occupational transitions multiplied in potential. This acceleration is the result not only of technological advances and recession, but also of new considerations for health and safety, and economies and labour markets will take time to recover. The quantum of the amplification of these trends and the realities of this crisis have also triggered a reconsideration of several beliefs, with implicit and long-lasting effects on the economy and society and attitudes about efficiency versus resilience, the future of capitalism, densification of economic activity and peoples’ lifestyles. The pandemic has also accelerated some of the key geopolitical trends that will shape our next world order - de-globalisation and nationalism, for instance, along with debilitating China’s hegemony in the supply chain. While the quantitative disruptions in the economy, structured finance and credit facilities are quite explicit, the more permanent changes are perhaps the ones considered from humanitarian perspectives. The most prominent qualities that were on display during this time of distress were the adaptability and versatility of people, which caused the cataclysmic shift of buying patterns to the online medium and helped to keep it afloat while intensifying the focus on the triple bottom line. Over the past two decades, in advancing economies, the onus of security has generally shifted from institutions to individuals. Healthcare systems are being tested and often found wanting, while benefits from paid sick leave to universal basic income are getting reviewed. There is potential for a long-term shift in how institutions offer support, through safety nets, and a more inclusive social contract. History bears witness that choices made during crises can shape the world for decades to come. What remains critical is the need for collective action to build economies that deliver inclusive economic growth, prosperity, and safety for all.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The World is Watching, But Will it Do Anything?</title>
      <link href="/The-World-is-Watching-But-Will-it-Do-Anything" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The World is Watching, But Will it Do Anything?" />
      <published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-World-is-Watching-But-Will-it-Do-Anything</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-World-is-Watching-But-Will-it-Do-Anything">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In 2019, when Notre-Dame de Paris caught fire, the world grieved at the harm caused to the marvellous monument. The potential damage to a beautiful monument, and all that it stood for meant support poured in from across the globe, monetary or otherwise. It was heartening to see the world collectively grieve over the monument. Naively, I had believed the world cared, so I was astonished to notice not a peep about the ugly aftermath of the attack on the Al-Aqsa mosque in Jerusalem by the Israeli forces, &lt;em&gt;during the holy month of Ramadan, in the middle of a prayer&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Al-Aqsa mosque is the third holiest site for Muslims. It is designated a world heritage site by the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation (UNESCO). The mosque is 986 years old, compared to Le Louvre’s age of 228. Perhaps it is unfair to compare the two sites. The damage to one was unintentional and garnered the world’s support, while the other was deliberately breached and attacked while it sheltered thousands of people, praying and celebrating their holy festival. When the police stormed the mosque, they fired ammunition and rubber bullets. They killed four, wounded over two hundred and shattered the beautiful centuries-old stained glass windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The tragedy of the Al-Aqsa violence is devastating. Sadly, it is nothing new nor out of the ordinary for the Palestinians. When I started writing this article, it began as an informational piece detailing the violence and the history of loss that frames the Israel-Palestine conflict. However, while reading about the details of the attack and the world’s response, I came across questions that I believe have reshaped the discourse. A most prominent one was if it’s anti-Semitic to criticise Israeli forces and government for their actions. The attention given to this question amazes me. The vast majority of people crying discrimination to justify and protect Israeli actions are confounding.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;When we condemn illegal and hostile Israeli occupation of Palestinian territory and the senseless violence unleashed by one of the strongest and well-funded militaries against a group of people armed with &lt;em&gt;rocks, &lt;/em&gt;we do not criticise them on the grounds of their religion. We criticise and protest because their actions are similar to that of a coloniser following a system eerily similar to the apartheid against the Palestinians. Perhaps, I oversimplify the issue; the formation of Israel is a huge part of Jewish history. But I believe that in this scenario, we transcend religion and identity. I do not believe that the horrific and vile treatment of Palestinian people can be attributed to anything other than the Israeli government’s greed and plan to colonise a land that does not belong to them.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another compelling argument that I came across during my research was if it is the Israeli government alone to blame for the situation of Palestine. The answer is no. The world and a majority of global superpowers are equally responsible for the persecution of Palestinian lives. It is not surprising to know that the USA is Israel’s biggest ally; it provides foreign aid, supplies and advanced military weapons even when Israel does not exactly need them and has built diplomatic relations with a majority of Islamic countries. The rest of the world bolsters Israel’s spirit by maintaining neutrality. France has been the only country so far to actively mention the term ‘Apartheid’ in the context of Israel. The other global superpowers, including Russia and India, have called for a ceasefire while actively discounting the argument that a ceasefire between Hamas and Israeli forces does not protect the Palestinian people from horrific treatment and displacement.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The displacements of Palestinian residents in Sheikh Jarrah (Jerusalem) form the centre of the conflict this time. The displacements highlight the systemic discrimination of Palestinians. Forced evictions, unlawful arrests and police brutality are the tip of the iceberg in this instance. While the displacements were halted because of the violence in Al-Aqsa and the clash between the Hamas and Israeli forces, the recent ceasefire between the two has reignited the fear of eviction for Palestinian residents.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The United Nations Human Rights Council has decided to probe the human rights violations in Gaza and the West Bank after 24 member nations voted in favour. Perhaps it is pessimistic of me to believe in the futility of such a probe. Violence and human rights violations have marred the Israel-Palestine conflict for decades. We are yet to see tangible efforts made to keep Israeli forces in check. And yes, the probe may yield results and proofs to hold Israel accountable, but it would not be enough.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Israel’s attack on Palestinians is a double-edged sword. Palestinians will be hurt irrespective of the probe’s result. If it will not be the bullets, it will be the forced evictions. If it will not be the missiles, it will be poverty and unemployment. If it will not be the police, it will be hunger and homelessness. The situation is, and it seems, will remain tantamount to death by a thousand cuts, and it will be innocent Palestinians that will continue to bleed. I have always thought the phrase “the world is watching” to be a sufficient reminder of the international community’s power to hold governments accountable; I never felt the need until now to amend it to say: &lt;em&gt;“The world is watching, but will it do anything?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In 2019, when Notre-Dame de Paris caught fire, the world grieved at the harm caused to the marvellous monument. The potential damage to a beautiful monument, and all that it stood for meant support poured in from across the globe, monetary or otherwise. It was heartening to see the world collectively grieve over the monument. Naively, I had believed the world cared, so I was astonished to notice not a peep about the ugly aftermath of the attack on the Al-Aqsa mosque in Jerusalem by the Israeli forces, during the holy month of Ramadan, in the middle of a prayer. The Al-Aqsa mosque is the third holiest site for Muslims. It is designated a world heritage site by the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation (UNESCO). The mosque is 986 years old, compared to Le Louvre’s age of 228. Perhaps it is unfair to compare the two sites. The damage to one was unintentional and garnered the world’s support, while the other was deliberately breached and attacked while it sheltered thousands of people, praying and celebrating their holy festival. When the police stormed the mosque, they fired ammunition and rubber bullets. They killed four, wounded over two hundred and shattered the beautiful centuries-old stained glass windows. The tragedy of the Al-Aqsa violence is devastating. Sadly, it is nothing new nor out of the ordinary for the Palestinians. When I started writing this article, it began as an informational piece detailing the violence and the history of loss that frames the Israel-Palestine conflict. However, while reading about the details of the attack and the world’s response, I came across questions that I believe have reshaped the discourse. A most prominent one was if it’s anti-Semitic to criticise Israeli forces and government for their actions. The attention given to this question amazes me. The vast majority of people crying discrimination to justify and protect Israeli actions are confounding.&amp;nbsp; When we condemn illegal and hostile Israeli occupation of Palestinian territory and the senseless violence unleashed by one of the strongest and well-funded militaries against a group of people armed with rocks, we do not criticise them on the grounds of their religion. We criticise and protest because their actions are similar to that of a coloniser following a system eerily similar to the apartheid against the Palestinians. Perhaps, I oversimplify the issue; the formation of Israel is a huge part of Jewish history. But I believe that in this scenario, we transcend religion and identity. I do not believe that the horrific and vile treatment of Palestinian people can be attributed to anything other than the Israeli government’s greed and plan to colonise a land that does not belong to them.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Another compelling argument that I came across during my research was if it is the Israeli government alone to blame for the situation of Palestine. The answer is no. The world and a majority of global superpowers are equally responsible for the persecution of Palestinian lives. It is not surprising to know that the USA is Israel’s biggest ally; it provides foreign aid, supplies and advanced military weapons even when Israel does not exactly need them and has built diplomatic relations with a majority of Islamic countries. The rest of the world bolsters Israel’s spirit by maintaining neutrality. France has been the only country so far to actively mention the term ‘Apartheid’ in the context of Israel. The other global superpowers, including Russia and India, have called for a ceasefire while actively discounting the argument that a ceasefire between Hamas and Israeli forces does not protect the Palestinian people from horrific treatment and displacement.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The displacements of Palestinian residents in Sheikh Jarrah (Jerusalem) form the centre of the conflict this time. The displacements highlight the systemic discrimination of Palestinians. Forced evictions, unlawful arrests and police brutality are the tip of the iceberg in this instance. While the displacements were halted because of the violence in Al-Aqsa and the clash between the Hamas and Israeli forces, the recent ceasefire between the two has reignited the fear of eviction for Palestinian residents.&amp;nbsp; The United Nations Human Rights Council has decided to probe the human rights violations in Gaza and the West Bank after 24 member nations voted in favour. Perhaps it is pessimistic of me to believe in the futility of such a probe. Violence and human rights violations have marred the Israel-Palestine conflict for decades. We are yet to see tangible efforts made to keep Israeli forces in check. And yes, the probe may yield results and proofs to hold Israel accountable, but it would not be enough.&amp;nbsp; Israel’s attack on Palestinians is a double-edged sword. Palestinians will be hurt irrespective of the probe’s result. If it will not be the bullets, it will be the forced evictions. If it will not be the missiles, it will be poverty and unemployment. If it will not be the police, it will be hunger and homelessness. The situation is, and it seems, will remain tantamount to death by a thousand cuts, and it will be innocent Palestinians that will continue to bleed. I have always thought the phrase “the world is watching” to be a sufficient reminder of the international community’s power to hold governments accountable; I never felt the need until now to amend it to say: “The world is watching, but will it do anything?”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Louis Vuitton - A Luxury Mecca</title>
      <link href="/Louis-Vuitton-A-Luxury-Mecca" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Louis Vuitton - A Luxury Mecca" />
      <published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Louis-Vuitton-A-Luxury-Mecca</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Louis-Vuitton-A-Luxury-Mecca">&lt;p&gt;When one thinks of Louis Vuitton, the first thing that comes to mind is an expensive luxury brand of supreme quality. LV is a true definition of aristocracy and elegance and kindles a utopian dream, a tantalising illusion. It is the best seller in the top range of luxury brands which produces high-quality, fashionable products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Established in France in 1854, Louis Vuitton started as a retailer for travelling bags. It opened the first store in Oxford Street, London. Louis Vuitton Moët Hennessy, usually abbreviated as LVMH, was the conglomerate founded in 1987 owing to a merger between Moët Hennessy and Louis Vuitton. Its headquarter is in Paris, France. Bernard Arnault, the President, owns 48% of LVMH. Today, the brand has a strong presence in categories like leather goods, handbags, ready-to-wear garments, jewellery and other accessories.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the very beginning, Louis Vuitton has attracted the support of customers who primarily belong to the upper echelons of society. The brand's mission is to represent the most refined qualities of the occidental art of living around the world. It firmly believes that fashion must follow the customer or die. Thus, it has stepped up its value proposition over time to provide a bespoke experience to its clientele, which adds to its dynamism. Louis Vuitton is one of the few fashion brands that started avant-garde fashion without compromising on traditional values. It won't be an exaggeration to say that LV is the holy grail of those seeking luxury.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current rise of Louis Vuitton is not a coincidence but instead can be attributed to an effective business model. It has always tried to counter mass production with limited edition series. This means that not everyone will have the same bags, and customers, therefore, get to enjoy fantastic exclusivity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Limited editions help to create an instant buzz. Because of the scarcity, waiting lists become longer and longer, and the products become even more desirable. The brand has worked in collaboration with various artists who have created their limited edition lines. This series helps the brand in connecting with new and younger audiences. Louis Vuitton uses the principle of special order, which allows the consumer to order merchandise tailored exactly for him and his preferences.&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;LV maintains and controls its distribution and sales.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it were to allow a large chain store, it undoubtedly would garner more sales in the short run. However, it would damage the brand image and its rarity due to it being easily available. Production efficiency is another crucial factor of LV's thriving business model. The production is completed through teamwork, and the employees are trained to be autonomous and multi-skilled so that the problems related to the product can be solved timely with their knowledge and experience. The whole production process is done in-house, including the manufacturing of raw material, which guarantees superior quality. This is not only rare in the industry, but it also requires a huge financial outlay. LV perpetuates the image of handmade quality. The brand is a true example of superior craftsmanship in an age of cheap mass production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The success of Louis Vuitton's business model can also be accredited to its first-mover advantage in Japan. Louis Vuitton entered Japan in 1977 and saw the Japanese economic boom. The company realised that Japanese consumers demonstrated a fascination with and passion for luxury.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Japanese culture of expressing social status through luxury goods together with the beauty conscious women demanding quality products helped ignite the rage of luxury shopping in Japan. LV began to collaborate with Japanese designers and combined fashionable elements with its heritage to offer fine quality products. This helped nurture an addiction of the Japanese to luxury and enhanced brand loyalty to help sustain profitability. With the company strategies becoming immensely successful, LV became the industry mogul in the Japanese luxury market and acquired a 28% share in the nation's market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louis Vuitton has successfully distinguished itself from other competitors by following a unique marketing strategy that is not utilised by most of its peer luxury brands. It has established a unique brand character that has created a high-standard barrier for others to compete. The LV monogram is high on recognition, and thus, people prefer to carry the monogrammed merchandise since it is associated with fame and reputation. This highlights the great importance that the brand attaches to a consumer's psychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LV does not have a second line to sell products that have a lower cost than the mainline. It only sells high-priced products and ignores those consumers who cannot purchase the high-priced items in the mainline. Although this could be called a haughty attitude, there is a logical reason according to the theory 'Product-out or Lord's business', which means the company would produce the item in limited quantity to satiate the desire of the buyers for prestige.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The high price that the brand commands is not only justified by its superior quality but also by a high degree of exclusivity. While looking at LV history, one can see that not once in 166 years its prices were reduced. “Why LV is never on sales” is a frequently asked question. This is because the brand knows the adverse effects of price reduction. For instance, the customers would wait until the brand goes on sale, which would reduce its exclusivity. Thus, it fixes the price to stimulate customers' demand at once and prevents them from postponing their purchasing habits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louis Vuitton pursues excellence that goes far beyond the supreme quality of its products. It encompasses the layout and location of its stores. It opens these stores only in the most prime locations since it would make the customers feel proud while buying the products. Louis Vuitton shops are distinctive and unique, which offer an experience in itself. It has always rejected mass advertising. It accentuates publicity in newspapers and magazines that last longer than 15-30 seconds of normal television advertisements. It produces catalogues, which, unlike other free ones, carry a charge. These catalogues contain immense information and sell out completely, which is only possible due to Louis Vuitton's unique stature. LV provides its customers with the opportunity to have their damaged products repaired. This helps to develop trust and brand loyalty and sustains the strength of the brand. This strategy has rarely been found adopted by any other brand in the industry.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the fashion industry is still experiencing the colossal ramifications of COVID-19, Louis Vuitton surprisingly has raised prices by a few percentage points over the last year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The affordable mask, which is the new life-saving accessory, just got its extravagant counterpart, that is, the LV mask. Clearly, it is not for the masses but a luxury layer of pandemic protection added by the aristocrats. The fashion house announced Wuhan, a culturally rich Chinese city, as the first stop for its new global travelling exhibition. This shows the rise of China as the new luxury hub post COVID.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been an intriguing change in consumer behaviour in the Chinese markets post lockdown. Many wealthy Chinese consumers are switching their spending from international travel to luxury purchases. During the lockdown, their pent-up spending desires are now being unleashed, a concept that is popularly known as revenge shopping. LV has been able to weather the lockdown thanks to the ever-growing consumer appetite for dresses and monogrammed bags. It is interesting to note that not all brands can afford to raise prices in such times. The ability to charge a higher price during such a crisis is a manifestation of brand power.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louis Vuitton was one of the first brands to reset and streamline its business model to face the challenges posed by the pandemic-led lockdown. Realising the troubles caused by the brick-and-mortar closures and tourism plunge, the brand turned its focus to the digital realm and reinvigorated its online presence. The brand undertook a 360-degree marketing and advertising campaign to remind the customers of the traditional and intrinsic value of its products. For its Spring 2021 collection, Louis Vuitton launched an animated film, followed by live touring runway shows. The brand took over 100 million impressions on its social media posts for the event. LV has begun a partnership with a video game company producing a collection of outfits inspired by one of the company's online games to instil a desire of developing unique virtual personas in the minds of the young audience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest threat that Louis Vuitton faces today is counterfeiting. This new epidemic for the brand has diluted the brand essence and its market share. LV can overcome this menace by making its supply chain transparent and monitoring the movement of its products right from manufacturing to the promotion and beyond. Educating the consumers to recognise the difference between legitimate products and fakes by providing a visual guide will also help curb counterfeiting.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brand now needs to channelise its energies in new directions by expanding into kids clothing or household paraphernalia, where it can take advantage of its pre-established image of superior craftsmanship and command higher margins. It can increase its market size by either investing in emerging wealthy markets like South America and the Indian subcontinent.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LV needs to make itself more attractive to the millennials and generation z by incubating innovative marketing and branding strategies. The brand needs to recalibrate its operations by going green, which would serve as a hedge against rising costs and contribute to sustainability. It needs to show a sense of responsibility and empathy in this hour of crisis for the consumers to embrace it. Revamping the brand image and retaining an insatiable desire for innovation is required to ultimately remind the public that brands like H&amp;amp;M and Zara do not have the elegance and class which Louis Vuitton commands and how it feels a class apart to own a genuine LV product.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Abhinav Gupta&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abhinav Gupta is a first year Bachelor of Commerce (Honours) student in Shaheed Bhagat Singh College, Delhi University. Inquisitive by nature, he loves to explore and learn new things.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhinav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">When one thinks of Louis Vuitton, the first thing that comes to mind is an expensive luxury brand of supreme quality. LV is a true definition of aristocracy and elegance and kindles a utopian dream, a tantalising illusion. It is the best seller in the top range of luxury brands which produces high-quality, fashionable products. Established in France in 1854, Louis Vuitton started as a retailer for travelling bags. It opened the first store in Oxford Street, London. Louis Vuitton Moët Hennessy, usually abbreviated as LVMH, was the conglomerate founded in 1987 owing to a merger between Moët Hennessy and Louis Vuitton. Its headquarter is in Paris, France. Bernard Arnault, the President, owns 48% of LVMH. Today, the brand has a strong presence in categories like leather goods, handbags, ready-to-wear garments, jewellery and other accessories.&amp;nbsp; Since the very beginning, Louis Vuitton has attracted the support of customers who primarily belong to the upper echelons of society. The brand's mission is to represent the most refined qualities of the occidental art of living around the world. It firmly believes that fashion must follow the customer or die. Thus, it has stepped up its value proposition over time to provide a bespoke experience to its clientele, which adds to its dynamism. Louis Vuitton is one of the few fashion brands that started avant-garde fashion without compromising on traditional values. It won't be an exaggeration to say that LV is the holy grail of those seeking luxury.&amp;nbsp; The current rise of Louis Vuitton is not a coincidence but instead can be attributed to an effective business model. It has always tried to counter mass production with limited edition series. This means that not everyone will have the same bags, and customers, therefore, get to enjoy fantastic exclusivity.&amp;nbsp; Limited editions help to create an instant buzz. Because of the scarcity, waiting lists become longer and longer, and the products become even more desirable. The brand has worked in collaboration with various artists who have created their limited edition lines. This series helps the brand in connecting with new and younger audiences. Louis Vuitton uses the principle of special order, which allows the consumer to order merchandise tailored exactly for him and his preferences.&amp;nbsp;LV maintains and controls its distribution and sales.&amp;nbsp; If it were to allow a large chain store, it undoubtedly would garner more sales in the short run. However, it would damage the brand image and its rarity due to it being easily available. Production efficiency is another crucial factor of LV's thriving business model. The production is completed through teamwork, and the employees are trained to be autonomous and multi-skilled so that the problems related to the product can be solved timely with their knowledge and experience. The whole production process is done in-house, including the manufacturing of raw material, which guarantees superior quality. This is not only rare in the industry, but it also requires a huge financial outlay. LV perpetuates the image of handmade quality. The brand is a true example of superior craftsmanship in an age of cheap mass production. The success of Louis Vuitton's business model can also be accredited to its first-mover advantage in Japan. Louis Vuitton entered Japan in 1977 and saw the Japanese economic boom. The company realised that Japanese consumers demonstrated a fascination with and passion for luxury.&amp;nbsp; The Japanese culture of expressing social status through luxury goods together with the beauty conscious women demanding quality products helped ignite the rage of luxury shopping in Japan. LV began to collaborate with Japanese designers and combined fashionable elements with its heritage to offer fine quality products. This helped nurture an addiction of the Japanese to luxury and enhanced brand loyalty to help sustain profitability. With the company strategies becoming immensely successful, LV became the industry mogul in the Japanese luxury market and acquired a 28% share in the nation's market. Louis Vuitton has successfully distinguished itself from other competitors by following a unique marketing strategy that is not utilised by most of its peer luxury brands. It has established a unique brand character that has created a high-standard barrier for others to compete. The LV monogram is high on recognition, and thus, people prefer to carry the monogrammed merchandise since it is associated with fame and reputation. This highlights the great importance that the brand attaches to a consumer's psychology. LV does not have a second line to sell products that have a lower cost than the mainline. It only sells high-priced products and ignores those consumers who cannot purchase the high-priced items in the mainline. Although this could be called a haughty attitude, there is a logical reason according to the theory 'Product-out or Lord's business', which means the company would produce the item in limited quantity to satiate the desire of the buyers for prestige.&amp;nbsp; The high price that the brand commands is not only justified by its superior quality but also by a high degree of exclusivity. While looking at LV history, one can see that not once in 166 years its prices were reduced. “Why LV is never on sales” is a frequently asked question. This is because the brand knows the adverse effects of price reduction. For instance, the customers would wait until the brand goes on sale, which would reduce its exclusivity. Thus, it fixes the price to stimulate customers' demand at once and prevents them from postponing their purchasing habits.&amp;nbsp; Louis Vuitton pursues excellence that goes far beyond the supreme quality of its products. It encompasses the layout and location of its stores. It opens these stores only in the most prime locations since it would make the customers feel proud while buying the products. Louis Vuitton shops are distinctive and unique, which offer an experience in itself. It has always rejected mass advertising. It accentuates publicity in newspapers and magazines that last longer than 15-30 seconds of normal television advertisements. It produces catalogues, which, unlike other free ones, carry a charge. These catalogues contain immense information and sell out completely, which is only possible due to Louis Vuitton's unique stature. LV provides its customers with the opportunity to have their damaged products repaired. This helps to develop trust and brand loyalty and sustains the strength of the brand. This strategy has rarely been found adopted by any other brand in the industry.&amp;nbsp; While the fashion industry is still experiencing the colossal ramifications of COVID-19, Louis Vuitton surprisingly has raised prices by a few percentage points over the last year.&amp;nbsp; The affordable mask, which is the new life-saving accessory, just got its extravagant counterpart, that is, the LV mask. Clearly, it is not for the masses but a luxury layer of pandemic protection added by the aristocrats. The fashion house announced Wuhan, a culturally rich Chinese city, as the first stop for its new global travelling exhibition. This shows the rise of China as the new luxury hub post COVID.&amp;nbsp; There has been an intriguing change in consumer behaviour in the Chinese markets post lockdown. Many wealthy Chinese consumers are switching their spending from international travel to luxury purchases. During the lockdown, their pent-up spending desires are now being unleashed, a concept that is popularly known as revenge shopping. LV has been able to weather the lockdown thanks to the ever-growing consumer appetite for dresses and monogrammed bags. It is interesting to note that not all brands can afford to raise prices in such times. The ability to charge a higher price during such a crisis is a manifestation of brand power.&amp;nbsp; Louis Vuitton was one of the first brands to reset and streamline its business model to face the challenges posed by the pandemic-led lockdown. Realising the troubles caused by the brick-and-mortar closures and tourism plunge, the brand turned its focus to the digital realm and reinvigorated its online presence. The brand undertook a 360-degree marketing and advertising campaign to remind the customers of the traditional and intrinsic value of its products. For its Spring 2021 collection, Louis Vuitton launched an animated film, followed by live touring runway shows. The brand took over 100 million impressions on its social media posts for the event. LV has begun a partnership with a video game company producing a collection of outfits inspired by one of the company's online games to instil a desire of developing unique virtual personas in the minds of the young audience.&amp;nbsp; The biggest threat that Louis Vuitton faces today is counterfeiting. This new epidemic for the brand has diluted the brand essence and its market share. LV can overcome this menace by making its supply chain transparent and monitoring the movement of its products right from manufacturing to the promotion and beyond. Educating the consumers to recognise the difference between legitimate products and fakes by providing a visual guide will also help curb counterfeiting.&amp;nbsp; The brand now needs to channelise its energies in new directions by expanding into kids clothing or household paraphernalia, where it can take advantage of its pre-established image of superior craftsmanship and command higher margins. It can increase its market size by either investing in emerging wealthy markets like South America and the Indian subcontinent.&amp;nbsp; LV needs to make itself more attractive to the millennials and generation z by incubating innovative marketing and branding strategies. The brand needs to recalibrate its operations by going green, which would serve as a hedge against rising costs and contribute to sustainability. It needs to show a sense of responsibility and empathy in this hour of crisis for the consumers to embrace it. Revamping the brand image and retaining an insatiable desire for innovation is required to ultimately remind the public that brands like H&amp;amp;M and Zara do not have the elegance and class which Louis Vuitton commands and how it feels a class apart to own a genuine LV product.&amp;nbsp; -Abhinav Gupta Abhinav Gupta is a first year Bachelor of Commerce (Honours) student in Shaheed Bhagat Singh College, Delhi University. Inquisitive by nature, he loves to explore and learn new things.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Sinews of an Industrialised Economy</title>
      <link href="/The-Sinews-of-an-Industrialised-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Sinews of an Industrialised Economy" />
      <published>2021-04-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-04-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Sinews-of-an-Industrialised-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Sinews-of-an-Industrialised-Economy">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The industrial sector, manufacturing, in particular, plays an important role in transforming a country from a low-income one, with agriculture dominating the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) composition, to a high-income, services-oriented country. The industrialisation of a country is a crucial phase in this transformation. Industrialisation is not only about a country becoming a manufacturing hub. There is a huge societal transformation that accompanies such industrialisation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Though the process of industrialisation is disruptive, it results in an increase in the income of the people. People become more refined in their behaviour, and education becomes a top priority in industrial society. Thus giving top priority to human investment. The state gains a monopoly over violence, the institutions of the state become more competent, and many other changes are observed. But the initiation of the process of industrialisation begins with the sectoral composition of the GDP moving from agriculture to industry, along with a similar shift in employment patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The transition from agriculture to an industrial economy is an important transformation that places a country on a high growth path. There is a tranche of changes that occur in different domains that facilitate a country in kick-starting its progression into a developed country.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;First, emerging as an industrial society increases the income of the people. There will be a guaranteed income flow for the average person in the society, unlike an agrarian economy where there is too much uncertainty in income generation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Second, with large scale migrations from rural to urban areas, whole new sectors emerge on the stage (e.g. daycare centres, dog walkers etc.) and the demand in the economy as a whole goes up.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Third, as people become more urban there is a deep social change that occurs, a change for good; this includes an increase in women's participation in the labour force, women becoming more independent and having a say in many things. Industrialisation can also be a factor that eases out the population pressure on society. Industrialisation also paves the way for education to become a major aspect in society. People hitherto employing their children on fields will send their kids to school because their income will suffice to support the family without the children having to work in the fields. But in all this, it is important to remember that industrialisation is a very disruptive activity. It, therefore, demands a strong state with strong enforcement mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The initial stages of industrialisation are, however, characterised by a population that has had only the experiences of a pre-industrial society. Literacy levels are generally low, most people are uneducated. This is where manufacturing comes into the picture. Manufacturing has the potential to absorb a large pool of labour. This is because of its fundamental characteristic of being dependent on labour for various reasons, despite the onset of technology.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;An increase in manufacturing also leads to a division of labour which increases mamifold the productivity of all sectors. To encourage manufacturing, however, there are a set of factors that need to be set in place. To discuss the factors that have to be put in place we may take the example of India, a textbook example of a country in the midst of the transformation from an agrarian society to an industrial one.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;First, India has reformed its archaic labour laws, which are a nightmare to anyone starting an industry. While regulation is desirable anytime, Indian labour laws are a case of over-regulation and need reform.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Second, India has to bring about land reforms. The Land Acquisition Bill, which was introduced in the Indian Parliament in 2014, was withdrawn due to a lack of political will. It is high time now that India passes that bill and makes land acquisitions easier.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, a consistent effort must be made to transition from an agricultural economy to an industrial economy. For this, a two-fold approach may be recommended. The Indian government should take all necessary steps to encourage industry, especially manufacturing; at the same time, it must improve the urban facilities of the country so as to accommodate the migration that occurs in the process of urbanisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the context of transforming India into an industrial economy, looking at China may offer some lessons. China began its reform process with agriculture by moving from the commune-based system to the household responsibility system, and by revising agricultural prices upwards by more than 20%, the results were for everyone to see. The agricultural growth rate jumped to 7.1% per annum during 1978-84, up from 2.5% during the pre-reform period of 1966-1977. This was followed by a dramatic reduction of poverty from 33% to 15% in the reform period between 1978 and 1984. Farm income in China grew by almost 14% per annum. It is high growth in farm incomes that boosted demand for manufacturing goods produced by town and village enterprises, kick-starting the manufacturing revolution in China.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In this context, Indian farm reforms are a welcome first step; though, a lot more could be done. India also has the necessary requirements in place. For instance, the Make in India scheme encourages the setting up of industries in India. It is imperative to back it up with other necessary steps. Initiatives like Skill India can be used for this purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Today, the Indian industry is complaining that rural demand is collapsing. One reason for that is the consistent reduction in rural population in India since the 1991 economic reforms. Another reason for this outcome is that India never had any major reforms with respect to its labour laws, land laws and agriculture laws; and farmers’ incomes have remained very low. However, it is also important to note that industry is not a substitute for agriculture, rather they are complementary to one another. Both these sectors are so intertwined that it is not possible to increase the growth of one sector without the improvement of the other sector. Industrialisation is also important to increase farm incomes in the country. This is because industrialisation moves people from farms to industries, thus consolidating the land holdings and thereby increasing productivity in the agriculture sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the long term, it is also imperative that India plan to address the issues of education and employment. There is a two-way correlation between industrialisation and education. In education, India seriously lacks skills-based education as the primary focus is always scoring marks rather than problem-solving and skills enhancement. To address this issue the government can partner with the industry to tailor the curriculum to suit the needs of the industry. The focus should shift to develop problem-solving skills. The government can also ask companies to spend their CSR amount on skills development programs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The elasticity of employment generation has been constantly falling and has come down to near zero in the last decade. This shows the grave danger that is in store in regards to job creation. In India, more often than not, entrepreneurs focus on price controls to cut down costs rather than on efficiency. In many cases, producers compete on the basis of price rather than efficiency. This should also change and for that, the government should incentivise firms to focus on efficiency rather than prices. India should act fast to take advantage of the changing scenario on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The economic reforms of 1991 have transformed the lives of the Indian people in many ways. The reforms led to new aspirations among the people, as the expectation was that the Indian economy would grow and India was going to be the next big thing on the world stage. Since the 1991 economic reforms were not adequately followed up, India has witnessed jobless growth for most of the period of its golden economic period of 2003-2008. Despite this, the Indian economy remained among the fastest-growing large economies of the world. Yet, it might appear paradoxical that with respect to achievements in human development, India is ranked at 129 out of 189 countries, according to the human development report 2019.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manufacturing has been the engine of modern economic growth, be it in Britain and the USA of the 19th century or Russia of the 20th century or China of the 21st century. India’s first plans to industrialise go as far back in time as the 1950's. The second Five-Year Plan spoke at lengths about the need for industrialisation and outlined the steps for the same. Unfortunately, India failed to industrialise. The Nehruvian model that the Indian state adopted subsequently proved disastrous for the country. Today, the time frame for India to take off and reap benefits of its demographic dividend is too small. India should act fast. Else, the future might be bleaker than we imagine today.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The industrial sector, manufacturing, in particular, plays an important role in transforming a country from a low-income one, with agriculture dominating the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) composition, to a high-income, services-oriented country. The industrialisation of a country is a crucial phase in this transformation. Industrialisation is not only about a country becoming a manufacturing hub. There is a huge societal transformation that accompanies such industrialisation.&amp;nbsp; Though the process of industrialisation is disruptive, it results in an increase in the income of the people. People become more refined in their behaviour, and education becomes a top priority in industrial society. Thus giving top priority to human investment. The state gains a monopoly over violence, the institutions of the state become more competent, and many other changes are observed. But the initiation of the process of industrialisation begins with the sectoral composition of the GDP moving from agriculture to industry, along with a similar shift in employment patterns. The transition from agriculture to an industrial economy is an important transformation that places a country on a high growth path. There is a tranche of changes that occur in different domains that facilitate a country in kick-starting its progression into a developed country.&amp;nbsp; First, emerging as an industrial society increases the income of the people. There will be a guaranteed income flow for the average person in the society, unlike an agrarian economy where there is too much uncertainty in income generation.&amp;nbsp; Second, with large scale migrations from rural to urban areas, whole new sectors emerge on the stage (e.g. daycare centres, dog walkers etc.) and the demand in the economy as a whole goes up.&amp;nbsp; Third, as people become more urban there is a deep social change that occurs, a change for good; this includes an increase in women's participation in the labour force, women becoming more independent and having a say in many things. Industrialisation can also be a factor that eases out the population pressure on society. Industrialisation also paves the way for education to become a major aspect in society. People hitherto employing their children on fields will send their kids to school because their income will suffice to support the family without the children having to work in the fields. But in all this, it is important to remember that industrialisation is a very disruptive activity. It, therefore, demands a strong state with strong enforcement mechanisms. The initial stages of industrialisation are, however, characterised by a population that has had only the experiences of a pre-industrial society. Literacy levels are generally low, most people are uneducated. This is where manufacturing comes into the picture. Manufacturing has the potential to absorb a large pool of labour. This is because of its fundamental characteristic of being dependent on labour for various reasons, despite the onset of technology.&amp;nbsp; An increase in manufacturing also leads to a division of labour which increases mamifold the productivity of all sectors. To encourage manufacturing, however, there are a set of factors that need to be set in place. To discuss the factors that have to be put in place we may take the example of India, a textbook example of a country in the midst of the transformation from an agrarian society to an industrial one.&amp;nbsp; First, India has reformed its archaic labour laws, which are a nightmare to anyone starting an industry. While regulation is desirable anytime, Indian labour laws are a case of over-regulation and need reform.&amp;nbsp; Second, India has to bring about land reforms. The Land Acquisition Bill, which was introduced in the Indian Parliament in 2014, was withdrawn due to a lack of political will. It is high time now that India passes that bill and makes land acquisitions easier.&amp;nbsp; However, a consistent effort must be made to transition from an agricultural economy to an industrial economy. For this, a two-fold approach may be recommended. The Indian government should take all necessary steps to encourage industry, especially manufacturing; at the same time, it must improve the urban facilities of the country so as to accommodate the migration that occurs in the process of urbanisation. In the context of transforming India into an industrial economy, looking at China may offer some lessons. China began its reform process with agriculture by moving from the commune-based system to the household responsibility system, and by revising agricultural prices upwards by more than 20%, the results were for everyone to see. The agricultural growth rate jumped to 7.1% per annum during 1978-84, up from 2.5% during the pre-reform period of 1966-1977. This was followed by a dramatic reduction of poverty from 33% to 15% in the reform period between 1978 and 1984. Farm income in China grew by almost 14% per annum. It is high growth in farm incomes that boosted demand for manufacturing goods produced by town and village enterprises, kick-starting the manufacturing revolution in China.&amp;nbsp; In this context, Indian farm reforms are a welcome first step; though, a lot more could be done. India also has the necessary requirements in place. For instance, the Make in India scheme encourages the setting up of industries in India. It is imperative to back it up with other necessary steps. Initiatives like Skill India can be used for this purpose. Today, the Indian industry is complaining that rural demand is collapsing. One reason for that is the consistent reduction in rural population in India since the 1991 economic reforms. Another reason for this outcome is that India never had any major reforms with respect to its labour laws, land laws and agriculture laws; and farmers’ incomes have remained very low. However, it is also important to note that industry is not a substitute for agriculture, rather they are complementary to one another. Both these sectors are so intertwined that it is not possible to increase the growth of one sector without the improvement of the other sector. Industrialisation is also important to increase farm incomes in the country. This is because industrialisation moves people from farms to industries, thus consolidating the land holdings and thereby increasing productivity in the agriculture sector. In the long term, it is also imperative that India plan to address the issues of education and employment. There is a two-way correlation between industrialisation and education. In education, India seriously lacks skills-based education as the primary focus is always scoring marks rather than problem-solving and skills enhancement. To address this issue the government can partner with the industry to tailor the curriculum to suit the needs of the industry. The focus should shift to develop problem-solving skills. The government can also ask companies to spend their CSR amount on skills development programs.&amp;nbsp; The elasticity of employment generation has been constantly falling and has come down to near zero in the last decade. This shows the grave danger that is in store in regards to job creation. In India, more often than not, entrepreneurs focus on price controls to cut down costs rather than on efficiency. In many cases, producers compete on the basis of price rather than efficiency. This should also change and for that, the government should incentivise firms to focus on efficiency rather than prices. India should act fast to take advantage of the changing scenario on the world stage. The economic reforms of 1991 have transformed the lives of the Indian people in many ways. The reforms led to new aspirations among the people, as the expectation was that the Indian economy would grow and India was going to be the next big thing on the world stage. Since the 1991 economic reforms were not adequately followed up, India has witnessed jobless growth for most of the period of its golden economic period of 2003-2008. Despite this, the Indian economy remained among the fastest-growing large economies of the world. Yet, it might appear paradoxical that with respect to achievements in human development, India is ranked at 129 out of 189 countries, according to the human development report 2019.&amp;nbsp; Manufacturing has been the engine of modern economic growth, be it in Britain and the USA of the 19th century or Russia of the 20th century or China of the 21st century. India’s first plans to industrialise go as far back in time as the 1950's. The second Five-Year Plan spoke at lengths about the need for industrialisation and outlined the steps for the same. Unfortunately, India failed to industrialise. The Nehruvian model that the Indian state adopted subsequently proved disastrous for the country. Today, the time frame for India to take off and reap benefits of its demographic dividend is too small. India should act fast. Else, the future might be bleaker than we imagine today.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Spirit of Brahminism and the Capitalist Reckoning</title>
      <link href="/The-Spirit-of-Brahminism-and-the-Capitalist-Reckoning" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Spirit of Brahminism and the Capitalist Reckoning" />
      <published>2021-04-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-04-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Spirit-of-Brahminism-and-the-Capitalist-Reckoning</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Spirit-of-Brahminism-and-the-Capitalist-Reckoning">&lt;p&gt;The Indian caste system was (or is) a most dehumanising, totalitarian and rigid system of social hierarchy and control. The oldest Hindu religious text, the Rig Veda, in its canto 10, hymn 90 defines how mankind came to be from the different parts of the supreme primordial being. It declares that &lt;em&gt;&quot;The Brahmin was His [i.e. the primordial being's] mouth; the Kshatriya His arms became. His thighs were the Vaisya; of His feet the Sudra was born.&quot;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These four castes: the Brahmins (the priestly and intellectual class), the Kshatriyas (the landowners and warriors), the Vaisya (the business class) and the Sudra (the labourer) represent the idealised division of social groups in the feudal social order of ancient India. The castes do not intermarry, they do not undertake work outside the profession assigned to their caste and the lowest castes and the outcastes are considered 'untouchable'.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One would think that capitalism, as the fundamental counterfoil to a feudal social order, has nothing to do with the caste system or anything like it. After all, capitalism is supposed to be a system in which the invisible hand of the market determines productive activity, rather than a system where a rigid hierarchy dictates social outcome. It is supposed to be based on open competition, where the best product wins, a rational social order, as Max Weber argued, instead of an irrational social order based on blood purity and ancient hymns on a primordial being.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But funny enough, the adaptability of the capitalist mode of production to varied challenges means that capitalism is evolving itself into a social hierarchy that looks very much like the caste system. More specifically, it is evolving to give us a group of people who are verily like the Brahmins of the Hindu social order, the mouths of the primordial being that is Capital.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group I speak of here is quite easily recognisable and thoroughly glamourised (and demonised) in world culture. Their activities are difficult to understand. They deal in items of pure abstraction, building nothing themselves but exercising control over all that is built. They are an exclusive club of people with an iron grip over power and money, whilst not being owners of any of those things themselves. They are the investment bankers, the equity analysts, the financiers and the asset managers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the Brahmin of yore who technically lived on alms but amassed vast wealth, the asset manager and the investment banker only shift wealth around but is rich &quot;via commission motherf*cker&quot; (to quote Matthew McConaughey's character from &lt;em&gt;Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;). Like the Brahmin who would zealously guard his secret knowledge of the sacred mantras and rituals which could make a mere warlord into a king, so does the Wall Street professional speak in the complex technical jargon of 'bonds', 'short-selling', 'derivatives' and 'collateralised debt obligations' which turn a mere productive activity into a sophisticated web of transactions. Like the killing of a Brahmin was the highest crime under ancient Hindu law, so is not bailing out the big banks and financial firms an impossibility.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These parallels are not some mere curiosity, they showcase how capitalism is so eminently adaptable to changing social conditions and how it verily controls the change in material conditions through its social architecture. In fact, this parallel upsets the fundamental assumptions that both pro-capitalist and many anti-capitalist thinkers make. It is not just the chains of economic power which define social relations, it is also the makeup of social relations that determines where economic power resides. The lords of high finance do not derive their power by owning and controlling the means of production. Instead, they define the interrelationships between economic power and those subject to its dominion.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can really appreciate this with a comparative example of the exercise of Brahminical power and the exercise of the power of the financiers. In the ancient Hindu fire rituals called the&lt;em&gt; yagna&lt;/em&gt;, the Brahmin priest would declare the officiator of the ritual as the '&lt;em&gt;yajaman'&lt;/em&gt;, he would make oblations to the various gods in the name of the &lt;em&gt;yajaman&lt;/em&gt;. The fruits of the &lt;em&gt;yagna&lt;/em&gt; would technically be available to the &lt;em&gt;yajaman&lt;/em&gt; alone, for it is his financial resources that make the &lt;em&gt;yagna&lt;/em&gt; possible. The Brahmin is a mere functionary in the entire process. But it is the Brahmin who knows the liturgy, it is the Brahmin who understands the secrets of the various rituals which confer wealth and power. In other words, it is the Brahmin who creates the&lt;em&gt; yajaman&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;yagna.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a similar way, the financier of today creates the capital and the capitalist. It is he who decides if a company can go public, it is he who sells its shares with an asking price and aims to raise capital with it. While the Brahmin made oblations to the gods, as a mere agent of the capitalist, the financier makes his oblations to the market. Technically, the financier is a mere agent. But it is he who knows the viability of the assets of the company, it is he who knows how to appease the market in favour of the capitalist.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as already alluded to, there is a stark difference between the Brahmin and the financiers: while one functions in a mystical social order, the other works in a rationalist one. So the interesting question is: why does this similarity emerge at all? Why is capitalism starting to look like feudalism?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is at once simple and complicated. It resides in that confusing term - 'human nature’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is known that we hunger, not just for food or shelter but also for meaning and security. We are, on some level, aware of our mortality and of how the universe is an uncaring void. At a time when there was no guarantee that the next harvest would give yield when natural disaster and disease could so easily destroy so many lives, the &lt;em&gt;yagna &lt;/em&gt;or the fire rituals gave humanity a sense of security. They made humanity feel a sense of control over its destiny in a fundamentally uncertain time. That is why the Brahmin was given a place of pride and of supreme importance in such an order, for on him rested society's basic sense of peace and order.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the present time, while our fears are not related to the next harvest, our fundamental existential dread remains the same. We do not know what exactly the market will demand next year, we do not know whether the invisible hand will drive prices up or down, whether wages will increase or decrease. Even if our order is rational, our fears of hunger and pain are not, we cannot live with the uncertainty of knowing that a mechanism of market forces will determine our bank balance, especially when the world is buffeted by the COVID-19 pandemic. The financier, by exercising influence and control over the market, gives us certainty. That is why he (or she) has so much power.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To go even deeper, the emergence of late capitalism represents the ultimate reckoning of the Age of Reason with its own assumptions. And the financier in late capitalism, advisedly or inadvertently, represents the reckoner. He confronts humanity with the limitations of his own rationalist systems. Nowhere is this more obvious than in the 2008 crisis. That crisis was, in many ways, completely and utterly the consequence of human beings trying to be too smart for their own good. Bankers so cleverly thought that if debts on homes were combined and converted into their own kind of mega debt, with that mega debt being sold in a market as a good, then money would just flow forever.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mega debts or ‘mortgage-backed securities’ as they were called, were a pure abstraction. They had no existence outside a system of pure formal logic, where obligations to pay back a home loan, which has no palpable existence, could be treated as a commodity and combined and sold as another obligation to pay back a loan, which also had no palpable existence. The real thing, the palpable thing: the home and the homeowner who undertook to pay back the loan was an eminently forgettable assumption in the hyper-rational mind of the financier. Needless to say, the results of this near-mystical, Brahminical rationalism are for all to see and they represent how there is such great folly in assuming that man is a creature of reason.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the ultimate question is: where do we go now? Will this inherent contradiction within capitalism unravel the same? (As Marx suggested) I think not. If the strength of the Brahmanical social order is any guide, a social order, no matter how flawed, no matter how decidedly routed by reality can maintain its spell, for that very weakness called human nature which in its yearning for security would rather believe the immediate lie than imagine a greater truth. So, the only thing that late capitalism and its Brahmin, the financier, tells us that it is here to stay no matter how many crises come and go. Unless, of course, humanity plucks up the courage to say: &quot;creatures of the heart and the flesh unite, we have nothing to lose but our rational brains''.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Indian caste system was (or is) a most dehumanising, totalitarian and rigid system of social hierarchy and control. The oldest Hindu religious text, the Rig Veda, in its canto 10, hymn 90 defines how mankind came to be from the different parts of the supreme primordial being. It declares that &quot;The Brahmin was His [i.e. the primordial being's] mouth; the Kshatriya His arms became. His thighs were the Vaisya; of His feet the Sudra was born.&quot;&amp;nbsp; These four castes: the Brahmins (the priestly and intellectual class), the Kshatriyas (the landowners and warriors), the Vaisya (the business class) and the Sudra (the labourer) represent the idealised division of social groups in the feudal social order of ancient India. The castes do not intermarry, they do not undertake work outside the profession assigned to their caste and the lowest castes and the outcastes are considered 'untouchable'.&amp;nbsp; One would think that capitalism, as the fundamental counterfoil to a feudal social order, has nothing to do with the caste system or anything like it. After all, capitalism is supposed to be a system in which the invisible hand of the market determines productive activity, rather than a system where a rigid hierarchy dictates social outcome. It is supposed to be based on open competition, where the best product wins, a rational social order, as Max Weber argued, instead of an irrational social order based on blood purity and ancient hymns on a primordial being.&amp;nbsp; But funny enough, the adaptability of the capitalist mode of production to varied challenges means that capitalism is evolving itself into a social hierarchy that looks very much like the caste system. More specifically, it is evolving to give us a group of people who are verily like the Brahmins of the Hindu social order, the mouths of the primordial being that is Capital.&amp;nbsp; The group I speak of here is quite easily recognisable and thoroughly glamourised (and demonised) in world culture. Their activities are difficult to understand. They deal in items of pure abstraction, building nothing themselves but exercising control over all that is built. They are an exclusive club of people with an iron grip over power and money, whilst not being owners of any of those things themselves. They are the investment bankers, the equity analysts, the financiers and the asset managers.&amp;nbsp; Like the Brahmin of yore who technically lived on alms but amassed vast wealth, the asset manager and the investment banker only shift wealth around but is rich &quot;via commission motherf*cker&quot; (to quote Matthew McConaughey's character from Wolf of Wall Street). Like the Brahmin who would zealously guard his secret knowledge of the sacred mantras and rituals which could make a mere warlord into a king, so does the Wall Street professional speak in the complex technical jargon of 'bonds', 'short-selling', 'derivatives' and 'collateralised debt obligations' which turn a mere productive activity into a sophisticated web of transactions. Like the killing of a Brahmin was the highest crime under ancient Hindu law, so is not bailing out the big banks and financial firms an impossibility.&amp;nbsp; These parallels are not some mere curiosity, they showcase how capitalism is so eminently adaptable to changing social conditions and how it verily controls the change in material conditions through its social architecture. In fact, this parallel upsets the fundamental assumptions that both pro-capitalist and many anti-capitalist thinkers make. It is not just the chains of economic power which define social relations, it is also the makeup of social relations that determines where economic power resides. The lords of high finance do not derive their power by owning and controlling the means of production. Instead, they define the interrelationships between economic power and those subject to its dominion.&amp;nbsp; We can really appreciate this with a comparative example of the exercise of Brahminical power and the exercise of the power of the financiers. In the ancient Hindu fire rituals called the yagna, the Brahmin priest would declare the officiator of the ritual as the 'yajaman', he would make oblations to the various gods in the name of the yajaman. The fruits of the yagna would technically be available to the yajaman alone, for it is his financial resources that make the yagna possible. The Brahmin is a mere functionary in the entire process. But it is the Brahmin who knows the liturgy, it is the Brahmin who understands the secrets of the various rituals which confer wealth and power. In other words, it is the Brahmin who creates the yajaman and the yagna.&amp;nbsp; In a similar way, the financier of today creates the capital and the capitalist. It is he who decides if a company can go public, it is he who sells its shares with an asking price and aims to raise capital with it. While the Brahmin made oblations to the gods, as a mere agent of the capitalist, the financier makes his oblations to the market. Technically, the financier is a mere agent. But it is he who knows the viability of the assets of the company, it is he who knows how to appease the market in favour of the capitalist.&amp;nbsp; However, as already alluded to, there is a stark difference between the Brahmin and the financiers: while one functions in a mystical social order, the other works in a rationalist one. So the interesting question is: why does this similarity emerge at all? Why is capitalism starting to look like feudalism? The answer is at once simple and complicated. It resides in that confusing term - 'human nature’.&amp;nbsp; It is known that we hunger, not just for food or shelter but also for meaning and security. We are, on some level, aware of our mortality and of how the universe is an uncaring void. At a time when there was no guarantee that the next harvest would give yield when natural disaster and disease could so easily destroy so many lives, the yagna or the fire rituals gave humanity a sense of security. They made humanity feel a sense of control over its destiny in a fundamentally uncertain time. That is why the Brahmin was given a place of pride and of supreme importance in such an order, for on him rested society's basic sense of peace and order.&amp;nbsp; In the present time, while our fears are not related to the next harvest, our fundamental existential dread remains the same. We do not know what exactly the market will demand next year, we do not know whether the invisible hand will drive prices up or down, whether wages will increase or decrease. Even if our order is rational, our fears of hunger and pain are not, we cannot live with the uncertainty of knowing that a mechanism of market forces will determine our bank balance, especially when the world is buffeted by the COVID-19 pandemic. The financier, by exercising influence and control over the market, gives us certainty. That is why he (or she) has so much power.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; To go even deeper, the emergence of late capitalism represents the ultimate reckoning of the Age of Reason with its own assumptions. And the financier in late capitalism, advisedly or inadvertently, represents the reckoner. He confronts humanity with the limitations of his own rationalist systems. Nowhere is this more obvious than in the 2008 crisis. That crisis was, in many ways, completely and utterly the consequence of human beings trying to be too smart for their own good. Bankers so cleverly thought that if debts on homes were combined and converted into their own kind of mega debt, with that mega debt being sold in a market as a good, then money would just flow forever.&amp;nbsp; The mega debts or ‘mortgage-backed securities’ as they were called, were a pure abstraction. They had no existence outside a system of pure formal logic, where obligations to pay back a home loan, which has no palpable existence, could be treated as a commodity and combined and sold as another obligation to pay back a loan, which also had no palpable existence. The real thing, the palpable thing: the home and the homeowner who undertook to pay back the loan was an eminently forgettable assumption in the hyper-rational mind of the financier. Needless to say, the results of this near-mystical, Brahminical rationalism are for all to see and they represent how there is such great folly in assuming that man is a creature of reason.&amp;nbsp; So, the ultimate question is: where do we go now? Will this inherent contradiction within capitalism unravel the same? (As Marx suggested) I think not. If the strength of the Brahmanical social order is any guide, a social order, no matter how flawed, no matter how decidedly routed by reality can maintain its spell, for that very weakness called human nature which in its yearning for security would rather believe the immediate lie than imagine a greater truth. So, the only thing that late capitalism and its Brahmin, the financier, tells us that it is here to stay no matter how many crises come and go. Unless, of course, humanity plucks up the courage to say: &quot;creatures of the heart and the flesh unite, we have nothing to lose but our rational brains''.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
