<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/trending/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-04-16T19:41:01+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/trending/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Neighborhood Friendly Taliban</title>
      <link href="/A-Neighborhood-Friendly-Taliban" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Neighborhood Friendly Taliban" />
      <published>2020-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Neighborhood-Friendly-Taliban</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Neighborhood-Friendly-Taliban">&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the US-Taliban peace deal, India’s situation can be very well described as the child whose older sibling just graduated high school. While the US may as well be India’s proverbial big brother, Taliban is the horrific high school experience that India will have to wade through all alone. And this experience is only worsened by the degenerating political and social environment of Afghanistan. The country is currently oscillating between Ashraf Ghani, the alleged winner of the Presidential election and Abdullah Abdullah, the self-declared winner of the same, while the US refuses to overtly acknowledge either as the President. For a country that has always depended upon America to ‘help’ them out, President Trump not congratulating his long term friend Mr. Ghani on his reelection is certainly grave. Additionally, a wobbly and conflicted team responsible for Intra-Afghan peace talks, amidst the Taliban assiduously violating its promise of maintaining peace, is the icing on the disastrous US-baked peace deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The catalyst for the aforementioned sad tale, the US-Taliban peace accord, signed February 29, 2020 holds the US time-bound to remove its troops within the decided 14-month time period, but not the Taliban to keep its promises. The removal of UN sanctions under the peace deal further weakens any leverage that the US might hold in Afghanistan. With the removal of the US-Troops, and a burgeoning Taliban influence, the people of Afghanistan have a bleak future to look forward to, and India, perhaps not as worse off, is definitely in the line of fire.s&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No individual who has ever witnessed an India-Pakistan cricket match can be ignorant of the 70-year old festering wound between the two countries. The unceasing tussle for power between the two countries and Pakistan’s inclination towards providing refuge to terrorist organisations as a way to one-up India is not a secret. And, consequently, Pakistan’s close friendship with and ideological alikeness to the Taliban is the primary impetus to the threat to India’s security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pakistan has been responsible for harbouring prominent terrorist organisations such as JeM and LeT on its territory and providing them protection after attacks on India. While Taliban promises not to allow Al-Qaeda in Afghanistan, the aforementioned organisations have been left out of the deal, allowing these terrorist organisations the opportunity to garner support and refuge in Afghanistan as well. Pakistan was a staunch supporter of having the Taliban as an active participant in the 2001 Bonn Agreement which was intended to establish an Afghani government after the Taliban’s removal. Furthermore, Pakistan’s support of a Taliban-led government in Afghanistan only makes Pakistan dearer to them. Juxtaposed with India’s past dealings (or lack thereof) with Taliban, India is likely to find itself in an ‘enemy of my friend’ situation. India has historically vehemently refused to acknowledge the Taliban as anything other than a terrorist organisation and has always supported the Afghanistan government. On a quest to counter Pakistani influence in Afghanistan, India has spent considerable time, money and effort to build a trusting relationship with the Afghan government through its multiple development and infrastructure projects, posing them as a direct adversary to the Taliban. And now that the Afghan government is itself in a precarious position, India’s assurance of relative peace on the India-Afghanistan border is dwindling and its efforts conclude to be naught.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another facet of this predicament is the apparent and sudden benevolence shown by the US to Pakistan. Pakistan has been a key player in bringing the Taliban to the table long enough for a peace accord to be established. And considering that President Trump’s re-election campaign is contingent on him bringing the American troops back, he currently considers Pakistan to be in his good books. Hence, Pakistan finds itself in a far more favourable position to cause considerable damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the US is by association to the Taliban making deals with the Haqqani network as well. The Haqqani network is a recognised terrorist organisation, which was also responsible for the attack on the Indian embassy in Kabul in 2008. Hence, America is giving legitimacy and validation to a terrorist group which has posed a threat to India in the past. This legitimisation and validation by a country that India considers to be an ally is only an affirmation of the USA’s indifference to any more peace violations by the Taliban in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding to this, the instability currently in India over the abrogation of Article 370 in Kashmir and the mass unrest and chaos due to the CAA/NRC protests, India finds itself in a pernicious position. The Al-Qaeda and the Haqqani network have made attempts and calls to fight India on the issue of Kashmir and on behalf of Pakistan. With the newly-minted support in Afghanistan and far more freedom once US-troops leave, India will have its hands full dealing with them. Much like Afghanistan, India’s dependence upon the US troops to fight a war not their own proves to be its Achilles heel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If one was to consider the possibility of India stepping up to protect its borders, it doesn’t seem improbable, however, it is the approach that remains to be seen. India could increase border security, employ more force and troops, it can hope for the peace accord to hold and pray that the Taliban does not establish a government and Pakistan does not use this to its advantage to attempt an ambush. Or perhaps, less likely and more smartly, India can continue to build and facilitate growth and development projects in Afghanistan, making India a friend to anyone in authority, very much like it did with the previous Ghani-led government. One cannot tell for sure what the currently-ruling BJP government will do, and keeping in mind their almost negligible previous response to the peace accord, we can only hope for some undertaking. The consequences of the deal may not be apparent right now especially when currently, the COVID-19 pandemic takes precedence, as it should, yet it will not always be so and India must be ready with a water-proof plan for when the time comes.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">When it comes to the US-Taliban peace deal, India’s situation can be very well described as the child whose older sibling just graduated high school. While the US may as well be India’s proverbial big brother, Taliban is the horrific high school experience that India will have to wade through all alone. And this experience is only worsened by the degenerating political and social environment of Afghanistan. The country is currently oscillating between Ashraf Ghani, the alleged winner of the Presidential election and Abdullah Abdullah, the self-declared winner of the same, while the US refuses to overtly acknowledge either as the President. For a country that has always depended upon America to ‘help’ them out, President Trump not congratulating his long term friend Mr. Ghani on his reelection is certainly grave. Additionally, a wobbly and conflicted team responsible for Intra-Afghan peace talks, amidst the Taliban assiduously violating its promise of maintaining peace, is the icing on the disastrous US-baked peace deal.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Calvin Coolidge: Libertarian Hero or Economic Assassin?</title>
      <link href="/Calvin-Coolidge" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Calvin Coolidge: Libertarian Hero or Economic Assassin?" />
      <published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Calvin-Coolidge</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Calvin-Coolidge">&lt;p&gt;In the American right, there has been longing for a fiscal conservative. For years, the most touted example was Ronald Reagan, and although he presided over one of the nation’s largest tax cuts, he ran up major deficits. With the election of President Trump and the implementation of his multiple socially conservative policies, many conservatives have cast away Ronald Regan as their poster-child for a conservative icon. But as far as issues go, neither can hold a candle to the smallest-government libertarian in American history: Calvin Coolidge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coolidge was born in Vermont in 1872 (ironically, the same state as the current democratic-socialist Presidential candidate Bernie Sanders). His father was a farmer, small business-owner and politician. Tragically, his mother died when he was only twelve years old. For college, Coolidge moved to Amherst in Massachusetts, then went on to open up a law firm in 1898. Seven years later, he married Grace Goodhue, a talkative social butterfly. She was an incredible contrast to Coolidge’s notoriously quiet and serious demeanour. Eventually, he started running for public office while branding himself as a progressive Republican. He quickly moved up through local government, the Massachusetts state legislature, and eventually was elected Governor. By today’s standard, one would think a progressive Republican from Massachusetts would be radically leftist, after all, Massachusetts is one of the most far-left states. However, over a hundred years ago, a progressive was not someone who advocated for transgender rights or the Green New Deal, but someone who fought for woman’s suffrage and the civil rights of people of colour. Nevertheless, they also saw a bigger and more powerful government as a means of producing this society. So how did Coolidge become both a libertarian hero and a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coolidgefoundation.org/blog/calvin-coolidges-surprise-contribution-to-progressivism/&quot;&gt;progressive Republican&lt;/a&gt;”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As stated earlier, he was notoriously restrained: both in personality and in government action. He believed it was progressive to restrain the government from restricting the liberty of others’ access to civil rights. This stood in stark contrast to a stream of previous progressive Presidents who sought to expand the reach and size of government as much as possible, such as Woodrow Wilson and Theodore Roosevelt. In spite of his silent personality, Coolidge was chosen to be the Vice President of the Republican Nominee, Warren Harding, for the 1920 Presidential race. In a twist of fate, his opponent — James Cox — had chosen the polar opposite to be his Vice President: the one and only Franklin Delano Roosevelt. In that election, Harding and Coolidge won. Although Harding did have a very conservative administration, his corrupt practices got ahead of him in what is known as “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.history.com/topics/roaring-twenties/teapot-dome-scandal&quot;&gt;The Teapot Dome Scandal&lt;/a&gt;.” In the midst of members right and left of Harding being found riddled with corruption, Harding died. Yes, just like that. He died.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily for the country’s sake, Coolidge was not found to be corrupt and &lt;a href=&quot;http://press-pubs.uchicago.edu/founders/tocs/a2_1_6.html&quot;&gt;was supposed to succeed the President anyway&lt;/a&gt;. After Harding’s death in August, 1923, Coolidge finished Harding’s term and ran for a full term in 1924 and didn’t bother seeking re-election. But what was the Coolidge administration like? Again, it cannot be restated enough, Coolidge believed in as little government action as possible, in virtually all areas of life. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coolidgefoundation.org/blog/budget-and-tax-lessons-from-president-calvin-coolidge/#_edn5&quot;&gt;In a speech&lt;/a&gt;, he once said, “Government extravagance is not only contrary to the whole teaching of our Constitution but violates the fundamental conceptions and the very genius of American institutions.” But how much did he enact this belief?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for policy, Coolidge still held too many old-time progressive ideals. On civil rights, he accomplished much for his time. During the height of the Jim Crow era, where government-sanctioned racial discrimination laws were prevalent, Coolidge didn’t appoint any member of the Ku Klux Klan to government or the judiciary, even though some Senators and Judges held strong ties to it. He also helped pass several anti-lynching laws. It should be no wonder that during the election of 1924, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coolidgefoundation.org/blog/1924-election-conflicting-minority-endorsements/&quot;&gt;historian John Berry estimated&lt;/a&gt; that “well over 90% of northern blacks voted Republican.” In addition, he supported child labour laws and women’s rights, making the first female appointment to the federal judiciary whilst giving Native Americans &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politico.com/story/2017/06/02/coolidge-signs-indian-citizenship-act-june-2-1924-238983&quot;&gt;citizenship&lt;/a&gt;. He also fought in the most contested battle of freedom during the era: prohibition. Coolidge wasn’t known to be a major drinker, but as far as public policy goes, he was a bit of a mixed bag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On foreign policy, he refused to recognise the new Soviet Union. Also, much to the delight of modern-day libertarians, he refused to join the League of Nations. Overall, he attempted to have America do as little as possible in foreign affairs. His economic policies really did reflect the libertarian &lt;em&gt;Laissez-Faire&lt;/em&gt; philosophy. Even to this day, he has been the only Republican in the past 100 years to have a surplus budget in any year, and the only President to have had one every year he served. Compared to now, almost no federal regulations were in place. Coolidge cut taxes, and unashamedly fought against farm subsidies (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coolidgefoundation.org/blog/well-farmers-never-have-made-much-money-coolidges-case-against-subsidies/&quot;&gt;a major issue at the time&lt;/a&gt;). In fact, perhaps Coolidge’s only fall from the libertarian’s grace is that he did favour tariffs to protect American manufacturing. But this was one of the major sources of revenue for the United States government &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/briandomitrovic/2018/03/09/when-tariffs-worked/#5a4dfd3770f9&quot;&gt;and had been the biggest&lt;/a&gt; until the income tax was instituted in 1913.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like his policy, Coolidge was a man of restraint. His nickname, ‘Silent Cal’, was given for a good reason. At a party, a woman once proclaimed that she had accepted a bet that she could get him to say three words. He curtly replied: “you lose.” During some periods of his Presidency, he would sleep for eleven hours and work only four hours a day. Some of that time was spent staring out of his window &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ozy.com/flashback/historys-laziest-leaders/6494/&quot;&gt;counting the cars&lt;/a&gt; that drove by. He would also hide in his office, then hit the emergency buzzer and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.historytoday.com/archive/silent-cal&quot;&gt;see how long it took&lt;/a&gt; for the guards to find him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As light-hearted the President might have seemed, he did not have a joyous presidency. While his son, Calvin Jr., was playing tennis without socks, he got a blister that became infected and &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@Anthony_Bergen/blister-the-day-calvin-coolidge-lost-his-favorite-son-and-his-passion-for-the-presidency-fe7b6b638f&quot;&gt;shortly resulted in his death&lt;/a&gt;. He was 16 years old. As this happened during the election year, Coolidge barely bothered to campaign. He still won overwhelmingly, but carrying out the duties of his Presidency was clearly painful. In his own autobiography, he wrote that once his son had died, “the power and the glory of the Presidency went with him.” Coolidge died of a broken man barely more than three years after leaving the Presidency at the age of sixty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Ronald Reagan hung a portrait of Coolidge in the Oval Office and claimed he was his favourite President. Perhaps Coolidge did inspire Reagan on many issues, but other than that, there are few traces of Coolidge’s administration today. Because he was so restrained on enacting legislation, we have few reminders of his presence, unlike Presidents who used the government to take action and left strong impressions generations after they left office. Lincoln’s victory over the South, Wilson creating the Federal Reserve, FDR’s New Deal, and LBJ’s Great Society all serve as living reminders of their legacies well after their deaths. But in Coolidge’s case, the conspicuous absence of grand schemes is what serves as a reminder of his brilliant legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till this day, there is still a great debate on what caused the Great Depression, and how much Coolidge was responsible for it. Those who oppose capitalism see him as the obvious culprit. However, &lt;a href=&quot;https://fee.org/articles/chaos-in-the-marketplace-don-t-believe-it/&quot;&gt;some economists&lt;/a&gt; credit tariffs to be the principal reason for the Great Depression, and since Coolidge did not remove them, he could be held partly responsible. Although most of the blame ought to fall on his Secretary of Commerce and successor: Herbert Hoover. Hoover was very much an interventionist in the economy and even expanded the tariffs by signing the Smoot-Hawley Tariff Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does this mean for us today? For one, it proves that there is no such thing as perfection or purity. As much as the American libertarian right would like to dream of a world without tariffs or silly government bans like prohibition, Coolidge was the best example of a libertarian President. But he also lived at a time when there was little government to restrain anyway. The United States was not entangled in virtually every region of the world, so there was little need to remove itself. There was no massive social safety net, nor sprawling government bureaucracy. Seven departments existed in the Executive Branch during Coolidge’s time and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_federal_executive_departments&quot;&gt;eight have been added since&lt;/a&gt;, not to mention so many government agencies within those departments: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/waynecrews/2017/07/05/how-many-federal-agencies-exist-we-cant-drain-the-swamp-until-we-know/#1205b8591aa2&quot;&gt;government itself isn’t sure how many are there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Coolidge was not perfect, he probably knew he couldn’t be. Perhaps that’s what made Coolidge so restraining. He knew he couldn’t do everything or be everyone. He simply did the best he could and allowed history to decide his fate. As all of us should.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Madajian</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In the American right, there has been longing for a fiscal conservative. For years, the most touted example was Ronald Reagan, and although he presided over one of the nation’s largest tax cuts, he ran up major deficits. With the election of President Trump and the implementation of his multiple socially conservative policies, many conservatives have cast away Ronald Regan as their poster-child for a conservative icon. But as far as issues go, neither can hold a candle to the smallest-government libertarian in American history: Calvin Coolidge.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Echoes of the Estates-General: A Comparison between Ancient Regime France and 21st Century America (Part I)</title>
      <link href="/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Echoes of the Estates-General: A Comparison between Ancient Regime France and 21st Century America (Part I)" />
      <published>2020-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General">&lt;p&gt;The background to the French Revolution chronicles the decline of the once-powerful State, beset by a multitude of economic and social problems. Chief among these issues were: a bourgeoning national debt brought on by the cost of war, the increasing antagonisms between an unproductive class of nepotistic oligarchs and an impoverished mass of peasants and small artisans, and the increasing irrelevance of the country in comparison to other, more economically dynamic states. The United States in the 21st Century bears striking similarities to the pre-revolutionary France, as discontent with stagnating wages and widening inequality reaches a fever pitch as the 2020 election draws nearer. This is the first of two articles examining the economic and political similarities between them, at a volatile time in the history of both nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;State Debt and Poor Finances&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between 1720 and 1780, France’s overseas trade had quadrupled, yet commercial prosperity was not enough to offset the abysmal condition of state finances. The combined cost of fighting the Seven Years’ War and the American War of Independence was 3.1 billion livres, over 4 times the Crown’s annual revenue. This was exacerbated by the fact that spending on war, the navy and diplomacy constituted 25% of Crown expenditure, in addition to the 50% that serviced the existing debt. Coupled with high interest rates that deterred moneylenders and an inefficient tax system that failed to raise revenue and allowed the nobility to remove officials who attempted to raise either direct or indirect taxes on them, there was a serious economic crisis by 1789.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 9/11, the United States has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2016/09/cost-wars-iraq-afghanistan/499007/&quot;&gt;poured $3.2 trillion into wars, reaching a total of $4.8 trillion once obligations to veterans have been paid.&lt;/a&gt;  Engagements in Iraq, Afghanistan, Libya, Syria and other places have caused excessive deficit spending, and like in France in the 1780’s, an inefficient system of taxation that has involved lower taxes on the wealthy has only shifted the burden of debt onto the poor and future generations. George W Bush’s tax cuts in 2001 and 2003, and the tax breaks given to the billionaires by Trump are analogous to the exemptions that the French nobles received at the time of mass social breakdown at the end of the 1780’s. Against the backdrop of ballooning debt and the 2008 Financial Crisis, the concerns of the younger generations of Americans who have flocked to Bernie Sanders can be understood as a revolt against a system that allocates inordinate amounts of money towards wars and bank bailouts, but claims that education and healthcare are too costly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inequality and Social Unrest&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The schisms and fissures that have opened up in American society as a result of widening inequality and resentment at excessive accumulation and monopolisation by unaccountable billionaires is reminiscent of the tax immunities and feudal privileges that exempted the French nobility from accountability along with the predominance of feudal privileges such as internal customs barriers and tolls that prevented the establishment of a home market for manufacturers, which Turgot’s reforms had failed to redress in 1774. The stultifying stagnation imposed on the French economy by the system of noble privileges made the conditions of the peasantry significantly worse, indicating that it was not only the burden of debt but mass social unrest that resulted from the Ancien Regime. Eric Hobsbawm, in his book the &lt;em&gt;Age of Revolution&lt;/em&gt; stated that the nobility encroached considerably on the autonomy of the peasantry as feudal dues, tithes and taxes occupied an increasing share of peasants’ income. Ground between the millstones of noble exactions and price inflation, social breakdown and revolts among the peasantry were made practically inevitable by the late 1780’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Kropotkin, writing in &lt;em&gt;The Great French Revolution&lt;/em&gt;, argued that the inequalities between the nobility and the peasantry, combined with the obstinacy of those in power, illustrated the sclerotic and outdated nature of what would later become the first and second estates of the Estates-General. He stated that “if despair and misery impelled the people to riot, it was the hope of obtaining some relief that incited them to revolt”. In 1777, 1,100,000 peasants were declared to be beggars. Between 1730 and 1789, wages rose by 22% but were unable to keep pace with prices, which rose by 60%, causing further immiseration for the French peasantry and precipitating risings of both the rural and the urban poor in 1788/1789. Inflation of the price of agrarian produce prevented the urban workers from gaining access to bread, and wage stagnation crippled a key market for manufactured goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three wealthiest billionaires in the United States: Jeff Bezos, Bill Gates and Warren Buffett, own as much wealth as the bottom half of the American population combined, indicating that capitalist accumulation has acted as an enormous fetter on the development of the productive forces, and that the majority of sectors of the economy have been sacrificed on the altar of short-term profit. Capital simply ‘goes on strike’ until it can find an adequate return on investment, as Big Pharma, for instance, has not produced a single new antibiotic in the nearly 4 decades since it was deregulated. Apple and Samsung, in lieu of investing in new technologies, have spent 7 years engaged in a costly ‘patent war’ over copying iPhones, have outsourced production to the Global South, or simply gambled on the stock exchange. The billionaire class in America has become a parasitic oligarchy that mirrors the nobility in Ancien Regime France, suffused with government subsidies and content with shoring up their positions on the market, as the nobility once clung to their feudal dues and court pensions. The unproductive nobility, who were not earners by birth, and who were barred from entering professions, influenced politics to increase their privileges, much as America’s unproductive billionaires buy off politicians today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether anything resembling the 1788/1789 agrarian riots will happen in America remains to be seen, although the levels of poverty in America have continued to climb recently. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2016/05/my-secret-shame/476415/&quot;&gt;49% of Americans now live paycheck to paycheck&lt;/a&gt;, and recent studies have linked &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-healthcare-deaths/study-links-45000-u-s-deaths-to-lack-of-insurance-idUSTRE58G6W520090917&quot;&gt;45,000 deaths per year to lack of health insurance.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loss of Global Hegemony&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The loss of power and influence on the world stage to other countries with expanding economies and greater political and technological capabilities is another major point of comparison between latter-day Ancien Regime France and 21st Century America. By the late 1780’s, Great Britain was already beginning to industrialise, buoyed by the prospect of free trade with the newly independent United States, the growing importance of slave-picked cotton from the American South, and the opening up of new markets in Latin America such as Brazil and Cuba whose economies of scale made them more profitable than mercantilist West Indian markets. The 1770’s and 1780’s saw the development of puddling furnaces, rolling mills and James Watt’s steam engine, alongside agricultural techniques that increased enclosures and developed profitable cash crops. France, by contrast, was still hampered by the inefficiency of feudal dues and tithes during Louis XVI’s administration, remaining &lt;em&gt;“a nation of agriculture and handicrafts”&lt;/em&gt; according to Georges Lefebvre. Its commercial and colonial supremacy began to decline, and its traditional economic methods, internal trade restrictions and inadequate transport links acted as a bottleneck on economic progress, as Great Britain surged ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collapse of American hegemony and the rise of China is one of the defining changes in modern geopolitics that radically &lt;em&gt;reorients&lt;/em&gt; the global balance of power. Once again, the domestic unrest and discontent fermenting amongst a people can be contextualised within the decline of the country at large. There are countless examples in history of leaders using patriotism and perceived national importance to distract from economic failures by galvanising the spirit of the population. This becomes increasingly difficult at a time of national decline, as shown by Trump’s recent attempts to escalate tensions with Iran. Public opinion polls found that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.people-press.org/2019/07/30/climate-change-and-russia-are-partisan-flashpoints-in-publics-views-of-global-threats/&quot;&gt;just 43% of the American public approved of the killing of General Soleimani&lt;/a&gt;, showing that the cynical use of patriotism to offset economic decline is becoming less tenable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the United States’ persistent refusal to allow the state to play a directing role in the allocation of resources has culminated in the United States ceding ground to the bureaucratic and ruthlessly efficient Chinese State, whose monopolistic tech companies exert a growing influence over countries ranging from Central Asia to Latin America. The United States remains a service economy, sustained by low wages, cheap credit and cheap imports which have led to a ballooning trade deficit of $616.8 billion (by late 2019). The Chinese, on the other hand, have understood the importance of digital infrastructure to the modern, interconnected global economy through the expansion of the Belt and Road Initiative and the Digital Silk Road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The background to the French Revolution shows that national decline, combined with economic stagnation and an unaccountable and bureaucratic class of elites who produce and contribute little of value can mobilise a mass of the labouring poor who recognise the injustice of the system they are living under. The concept of the ‘American Dream’ is becoming increasingly untenable as neoliberal capitalism proves itself incapable of innovation and only of injecting money into assets and speculation, while concentrating power and wealth in the hands of a few billionaires. From the demise of Bernie Sanders’ campaign to the desperate attempts of the ruling class to consolidate power in the wake of the Coronavirus by printing $1.5 trillion to stabilise markets while millions are still without health insurance, there is a significant chance that the current crisis of American neoliberalism may result in either social upheaval, or a revolutionary transformation of the economic system.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The background to the French Revolution chronicles the decline of the once-powerful State, beset by a multitude of economic and social problems. Chief among these issues were: a bourgeoning national debt brought on by the cost of war, the increasing antagonisms between an unproductive class of nepotistic oligarchs and an impoverished mass of peasants and small artisans, and the increasing irrelevance of the country in comparison to other, more economically dynamic states. The United States in the 21st Century bears striking similarities to the pre-revolutionary France, as discontent with stagnating wages and widening inequality reaches a fever pitch as the 2020 election draws nearer. This is the first of two articles examining the economic and political similarities between them, at a volatile time in the history of both nations.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Beer, anyone? Levity in a Time of Crisis</title>
      <link href="/Beer-anyone-Levity-in-a-Time-of-Crisis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beer, anyone? Levity in a Time of Crisis" />
      <published>2020-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Beer-anyone-Levity-in-a-Time-of-Crisis</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Beer-anyone-Levity-in-a-Time-of-Crisis">&lt;p&gt;If one were to tell me that I’d be receiving an impromptu holiday which may last anywhere between 10 days to the end of time (my personal time, friends) - I’d be elated, ecstatic, even. However, the very backing of the same would be resulting in deaths around the world and would be the reason for self-quarantining? Not as idealistic. While COVID-19 is no secret, and there is plenty known as well as unknown about this global pandemic, what has increasingly caught on like wildfire is the machinery related to the meme-making and the subsequent jokes that have flown in. While everyone is apprehensive about the unknown, the at-homeness has led to coping with the situation in any fashion we can. But, why humour? And what version of it is deemed appropriate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it that something that was born along one side of the world and has followed around the entirety of it has led to a strong sense of levity, at this dire time? What room do we have in our heads that makes us condone a business supposedly so corroded? And if not supposedly as corroded as it is supposed to be- what conception of this humour makes the cut?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From making fun of Trump and his infallible speeches (and more importantly, wigs) to now, suggesting how Bollywood star Ranveer Singh dresses like Coronavirus - believe you me, the latter tickled me about as much as it shocked me. The memes have hit like the plague, itself (no pun, intended) - quite unavoidable and with no cure. Just this morning, Snapchat informed me that a proficient actress was being ‘cancelled’ for making less of this pandemic. If she is at fault, aren’t we all? If Tom Hanks can tweet out that he’s lost 216 bouts of rummy with his wife due to the posited isolation of his positive-to-the-virus-self, we laugh, don’t we? It is ‘absolutely amazing’ how well he’s handling the issue at hand. However, if another individual so much as suggest that this pandemic is God’s gift to students- Ma’am, you have a #cancelled on your hands. I, a mere human, only ask for the boundary - where to build the wall, you know? (Please forgive me.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do what I can do best, right about now. I ask. People, Google, one and all. My friend tells me memes are the medicine to this pandemic, at least until you test positive, while a research published in ​Harvard Business Review explains that “laughter relieves stress and boredom, boosts engagement and well-being, and spurs not only creativity and collaboration but also analytic precision and productivity.” It’s the manna from heaven, my friends. All that has troubled us: stress, boredom- cured. One article went ahead and suggested that humour can be and is, very well a form of self-care when experiencing burnout and compassion fatigue. Finding a humorous angle together can serve as a doorway to a deeper connection with other individuals, acting as a buffer. Could it be that a sense of belonging is what we seek, it is this that makes these jokes and memes as popular as they are - our need for affiliation! ​Malchiodi, one of the greatest researchers of ‘the funnies’ has vastly discussed the positive mental and physical results of laughter and/or humour. “Since the late 1980s, a number of studies support the idea that laughter stimulates the immune system and counteracts the effects of stress ​hormones, although results are mixed about exactly how,” she said. “In brief, there’s agreement that it’s another way to arrive at the relaxation response.” ​We’ve got it, people - an explanation as to why there has been a surge in the circulation of COVID-19 memes, parodies and videos aiming to get a laugh out of people. It could be that for certain people, making light of things is more of a coping mechanism than it is a chance at fame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and what fame to give up, too. Please afford me another moment of pondering and I shall be done. In the extensive research that this phenomenon took - what became extremely apparent to me was the cultural difference. While Singapore is busy with how other countries are copying their way of work, or may I suggest, homework; the USA was busy with toilet paper memes (or, better yet, buttcoin, the new currency crowned after the infamous bitcoin.) India, out here, is confused about which issue to put higher up on the hierarchy - the failure of it as a democracy, the communal riots, the pandemic that is barely being considered as one or just the sheer amount of Whatsapp forwards that suggest you drink ‘gau mutra’ (cow urine) and get vaccinated towards Corona. Hitherto, the reigning queen, (and this I say with much bias) has to be the Corona Beer memes and the expected aversion to the same by the sages of the world. The economy is down the drain for most countries, the population - more so. But, I really do think Corona with/without lime deserves better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly enough, and this may be of interest to one and all, the place where Rapunzel isolated herself? Corona. In more ways than one, the world is coming full circle- and while it may be really difficult to go through, it is nonetheless entertaining to watch the unfolding. Just this morning, another friend and I had a long conversation about the conspiracy theories involved with the awakening of COVID-19. Oh, and if you weren’t aware CoronaVirus Disorder- 2019 getting abbreviated has very much to do with the memes, you can ask WHO, they’d attest. While I’m no meme connoisseur, conspiracy theories really get me going but that’s for another day, another time, another beer. Done with my rambling, I warrant my answer to my aforementioned question - why humour? Why this very coping mechanism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I think? It is non-violent resistance to any form of oppression. A successful one at that. It facilitates a culture of resistance, tries to bring levity, sure - but with it, interest and awareness. It’s the pink colour to cough syrups - the pretty packaging to venomous bottles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as ​at a personal level, self-irony and joking about one’s own shortcomings are considered to have the greatest impact on self-liberation through humour, dare I suggest that may be true at the social level, irrespective of cultural and individual differences? Now, what does mere me know? While I ride back home in an airplane where no individual is without a mask or sanitizer - while I go home because my mother would rather I be sick with her than without - while there’s panic and apprehension on almost possible levels of conscious awareness, I wonder if you’d like that Corona with lime or without.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">If one were to tell me that I’d be receiving an impromptu holiday which may last anywhere between 10 days to the end of time (my personal time, friends) - I’d be elated, ecstatic, even. However, the very backing of the same would be resulting in deaths around the world and would be the reason for self-quarantining? Not as idealistic. While COVID-19 is no secret, and there is plenty known as well as unknown about this global pandemic, what has increasingly caught on like wildfire is the machinery related to the meme-making and the subsequent jokes that have flown in. While everyone is apprehensive about the unknown, the at-homeness has led to coping with the situation in any fashion we can. But, why humour? And what version of it is deemed appropriate?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part III)</title>
      <link href="/Misunderstandings-Of-The-West" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part III)" />
      <published>2020-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Misunderstandings-Of-The-West</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Misunderstandings-Of-The-West">&lt;p&gt;I have written previously about the Arab-Israeli conflict twice now, but I’ve left out one aspect that none of us wants to talk about. It’s easy to criticise the failures of the West or endlessly discuss the history of the conflict, but there is one topic that truly plays a central role: religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blood, dirt, and money — or a combination of the three — are responsible for virtually all conflicts. Of course, the Arab-Israeli conflict is no exception, but on a fundamental level, the radicals on both sides see this as a religious struggle. In the current generation, we tend to secularise everything so that we can pretend to scientifically map out a solution. But with conflict as complicated as the Arab-Israeli conflict, it’s easy to wrap ourselves with the blanket of self-pity and proclaim “Oh! It’s just so complicated. So many different perspectives and feelings. I’ll just never understand it!” It is true that we will never solve the conflict with the systematic precisions given to us by science because not every societal problem can be solved in such a manner. If we want to progress, we have to move beyond the fact no one will completely understand everything about the conflict. However, we must still strive to understand it. Even if religion seems strange or difficult to understand for some, it is essential for one to recognise the control it has over people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before going any further, I must highlight my shortcomings. One popular saying I encountered while travelling to Israel was “two Jews have five opinions.” By this, the saying means that there are a lot of internal disagreements within the Jewish community. So when I write “The Jews believe this…” or “Muslims have faith that…”, I implore you to take it with a grain of salt. Every religion is filled with people who dissent on virtually every aspect. There are very few dogmas or beliefs completely agreed upon by an entire religion. Even among radicals, the interpretations of those dogmas are bitterly disputed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask any religious person, even those who have spent decades training and study, if they understand their own religion. I anxiously await to hear back from you. Until you find that person, the world will keep on rotating while the Israeli and Palestinian children die. We will &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; understand even just one perspective of this conflict, however, we can (and must) strive to at least understand where both sides are coming from. The Arab-Israel conflict is very much religious conflict. Not just between Jews and Muslims, but also between the different factions within those faiths, in addition to many other religions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Israel and Palestine have religious sites sacred to Christians and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldheritagesite.org/list/Bah%C3%A1%E2%80%99i+Holy+Places&quot;&gt;Baha’i&lt;/a&gt; (and probably more religions), the local population is mostly made up of Jews in Israel and Muslims in Palestine. Although the minorities play a role in the history and international relations, the chief actors — Israel and Palestine — have undeniable ties to the religion of their majorities. Therefore, if one does not understand religion, they will never understand this conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my dear secular readers, religion may superficially seem like a way of life or a set of traditions, but if that is the extent of your view of religion, then allow me to correct your course. This may be true for a casual religious observer, but we are not solely dealing with casual observers, we are dealing with hardliners and fundamentalists. Now I consider myself to be a Christian fundamentalist, so allow me to explain what ‘fundamentalism’ means. Essentially when one is seeking to get to the fundamentals of one’s religion, they are a fundamentalist. For some, it means pursuing a message of peace and love, for others, their perception of the fundamentals of their religion is to rid themselves (and others) of impurity by any means necessary. Again, even within fundamentalists, you can see a wide range of thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, a person may arrange their day-to-day schedule or diet around their religion. Perhaps take special holidays and be extra motivated to spend time with their family. But any serious or dedicated religious person will tell you, it is also a philosophy. It’s a framework for understanding how the world works and how you must act every day. Both Jews and Muslims may agree to pray often, not eat pork, celebrate certain holidays, or go to a special building for worship, but if you think that makes them essentially the same, you’re a fool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, they are both Abrahamic religions, they both admire similar people (such as Noah, Abraham, Moses, and Elijah to name a few), and they both love a good falafel. But these are all superficial things. Muslims believe the Jewish sacred law books (the Torah) have been corrupted, and their holy book (the Quran), which was completed over a thousand years later, is the true word of God. The fundamentalist Jewish zionists believe God has given them all of the land held by the Palestinians. These are two &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different religions. To expect them to put aside years of bloodshed is one thing, but to expect them to live without resentment for the other’s disrespect for their texts is not an expectation to be taken lightly. Nevertheless, if there is to be peace between Jews and Muslims, what should be the extent of our hopes? And how do we get there? Do we ask them both to just put aside their history? Their faith? Or we ask both of them to search for the fundamentals of their religion. What is the most fundamental aspect of religion? To look after the widows and orphans. Be you a Jew, Muslim, Chrisitan, Buddist, or Scientologist, if this act is not being done, how can you be so sure your religion — or your interpretation of your religion — is being fundamentally carried out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are voices of wisdom and charity on both sides. But because this conflict is so frustrating, people are giving ear to the voices of violence and hatred. In order to preserve peace, we must seek to give a stronger platform to the radicals. Not the radicals for their own religion, but the radicals for peace, justice and love. The radicals for those fundamental virtues all humans strive to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Madajian</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I have written previously about the Arab-Israeli conflict twice now, but I’ve left out one aspect that none of us wants to talk about. It’s easy to criticise the failures of the West or endlessly discuss the history of the conflict, but there is one topic that truly plays a central role: religion.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Are You Bored Enough?</title>
      <link href="/Are-You-Bored-Enough" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are You Bored Enough?" />
      <published>2020-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Are-You-Bored-Enough</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Are-You-Bored-Enough">&lt;p&gt;A happy new year, yeah, um, happy? From what I’ve been told, we’re unsubscribing from Jan’20, so, I hope for a good, uneven eleven-month’d year ahead. There has been a huge lapse on my end: I’ve been unable to pen down anything for the longest time. Not because I’m lacking the resources, definitely not the time―what it is, may only be described as dissatisfaction. Dissatisfaction in everything that, I, as an individual of a certain age- living in the country that I live in, belonging to the state I belong to, have had to see. The ghastly past few days and the subsequent coming days, all of it seems too much to bear and I’ve decided I am not to write on it. The awareness that this entire fascist regime (or, situation) in India deserves is beyond anything I can measure, and I can’t remotely do it justice, in no specific way. My bias holds too high and is nowhere near close to being over, not anytime soon. Hence, I’ll use this as a ‘breath of fresh air,’ with how polluted the air I breathe is. In more ways than one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I type this, I’ve Billie crooning in my ears about how she’s so bored, and well, let’s run with it, shall we? Billie deserves her answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bored? Boredom? Equivalent to disinterest? Or, is it a conditioned, negative feeling that shrouds us upon being unproductive? I’ve often felt awful after a day spent watching Netflix. But does that mean I was bored? I wouldn’t say so. But has the binge been productive? I wouldn’t say that, either. So, I go surfing, web surfing and find out what this damned concept entails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several authors from Pascal to Schopenhauer, from Kierkegaard to our very favourite Nietzsche, and Baudelaire, and Dostoevsky―everyone seems to have dropped a cent on this everyday phenomenon. Well, is it an everyday phenomenon all? It almost seems like the closer we get to the present day, the more destructive boredom becomes, compelling creative types—from writers and artists to rock musicians (Slash!!)—to reflect on this theme. Nevertheless, it remains a difficult psychological state to define, more so today, than ever. Kierkegaard equates boredom with the devil and defines it thus: “The demonic is that which is without content, boring.” According to Dostoevsky, boredom is “a bestial and indefinable affliction.” One of the present-day researchers, Elizabeth Goodstein, labels it “experience without qualities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure I agree. I mean, she’s clearly influenced by Robert Musil’s &lt;em&gt;The Man Without Qualities&lt;/em&gt;. The book is simply a diagnosis of everyday life and thrives on the concept of boredom. If one were to read Lars Svendsen’s (pretty much the father of boredom, and one who serves quite a heavy read) &lt;em&gt;A Philosophy of Boredom&lt;/em&gt;, one’ll find out that boredom is a social construction of the era that began in the middle of the 18th century. ‘Interesting’ as a concept came to light simultaneously with that of boredom. It was not up to then accepted practice to classify things as being either “boring” or “interesting.” Understandably, such a classification contrasted ‘boring’ with ‘interesting’. That which was interesting was attractive. To be interesting meant not being boring (I’d suggest you read that over a couple of times, I definitely did.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can definitely claim that boredom is a state of discomfort. The most common terms I can substitute it with may be uninteresting, a growth flowered by disinterest and detachment. It is often understood as a catch-all term. It may be understood in its simplicity, termed ‘simple boredom’, a product of temporarily unavoidable and predictable circumstances (being stuck in a bad date? A sad lecture? An awful movie?) as well as ‘existential boredom’ wherein underlies an unrelieved sense of isolation, emptiness, alienation and even helplessness. The main relationship between these two conditions is probably the loose use of the term ‘boredom’. Another close related concept, ‘chronic boredom’, is, one could guess, more like simple boredom, albeit not temporary. If simple boredom is the result of the circumstances we find ourselves in, chronic boredom is a symptom of a lower than normal level in the system of the neurotransmitter dopamine. The notion of chronic boredom is something that is especially the preserve of psychologists. It is measured in a famous test called the Boredom Proneness Scale (BPS) that was devised in 1986 by the now-retired psychologist Norman D Sundberg. Now that you know types of boredom and how fellow psychology enthusiasts are measuring the same, do you still have an unclear picture? Because I sure do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What of a nuanced concept such as this is so difficult to understand? In his book &lt;em&gt;The Will to Meaning&lt;/em&gt;, Viktor Frankl recorded that contemporary man suffered from a deep sense of loss of meaning; a state that he diagnosed as “existential vacuum.” This sense of loss of meaning characterises post-traditional man who cannot make up his mind as to what he wants and what he must do, since tradition no longer dictates what is necessary. If this way is the right way, boredom appears to be the polar opposite of what Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi has famously termed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brainpickings.org/2012/02/27/purpose-work-love/#flow&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;flow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;—a state of intense focus one enters whilst absorbed in an enthralling task, when one loses track of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen, if someone were to ask me to spend any more than 10 minutes by myself, with nothing else to think of, I’d go insane, and that brings me to the question: are we as a generation more or less bored than the ones who came before us? Now, every day brings a new article about how to stop the demon of lassitude, or a new invention designed to keep us from ever being at loose ends again. Come to think of it, phones got smart, and so did we, with easy access to more information and entertainment than ever before. Now, every moment one spends being bored—while riding an elevator, or waiting at the doctor’s office, or biding time until your date returns from the restroom—is a moment one doesn’t spend reading a book, skimming the news, or catching up on social media. What I may be suggesting is that, being bored in 2020, might just be a slap in the face of technology. Never again will we have nothing to do. This should be a good thing… Right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What in the world goes on in our brains when we get bored? Not just physically, but psychologically? And pray tell, what would go on in our brains if we were to never get bored?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers such as Mashuq Ally have led to a whirlwind romance between authors and the idea of boredom. It has been suggested that something super repetitive that doesn’t need one’s brain to be engaged, that’s when one ignites a network in their brain, one called the ‘default mode’. Neuroscientists have claimed that the default mode is when one does their most original thinking: problem-solving, imagination, empathy, all reside in the house of original thinking. The mind is told to be working as somewhat of a time traveling machine. One goes back and thinks of things that have already conspired and makes sense of them and then extracts lessons from them. They call it autobiographical planning. The unthinking mind-wandering that happens when one is bored takes all the information that has ever entered the brain and makes use of it in innovative ways. In other words: being bored is the difference between being good at &lt;em&gt;Jeopardy!&lt;/em&gt; and being someone who actually &lt;em&gt;uses&lt;/em&gt; the knowledge that one has learned to come up with solutions to fix problems (both of the personal and societal kind).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, boredom is good!? However, boredom too, like other fruits of modernity, has its geography. Despite the fact that no one is safe against boredom, the luxury of being bored is not equally accessible to all societies and strata. And that’s just that. The amount of information we feed ourselves, in this tech driven world, is absurd. No number of hard drives could ever retain all the information I gather from Instagram, or heck, a Buzzfeed video binge. So, why wouldn’t the idea of feeding ourselves more and more information and then never actually doing anything with it seem just perfect? Isn’t that what we’ve been taught ever since we were a kid? I have an art degree and I only have my mum’s concern towards my boredom to thank for it. I mean, I could leave social media, give away my joys in boredom, all so I could self-regulate my thoughts, use the knowledge I’ve previously gained and make the most of it, but wouldn’t that make me Joe from &lt;em&gt;You&lt;/em&gt; and I don’t reckon he was liked by many. Sketchy Joe is no good, friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a culture obsessed with productivity, boredom seems like a sin, not to mention impossible when so much of the everyday stimuli we take for granted—email, ads, Instagram, Netflix, YouTube (God, I can go on, and on and on)―is bent on robbing us of our attention. But sitting back and doing nothing is, ironically, exactly what you need to do in order to get more done. We were so scared of being bored at all that we failed to appreciate the frightening repercussions of not being bored enough. And I only have Billie to thank for this insight. So, next up (on my playlist and search engine): &lt;em&gt;Where do we go when we fall asleep?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A happy new year, yeah, um, happy? From what I’ve been told, we’re unsubscribing from Jan’20, so, I hope for a good, uneven eleven-month’d year ahead. There has been a huge lapse on my end: I’ve been unable to pen down anything for the longest time. Not because I’m lacking the resources, definitely not the time―what it is, may only be described as dissatisfaction. Dissatisfaction in everything that, I, as an individual of a certain age- living in the country that I live in, belonging to the state I belong to, have had to see. The ghastly past few days and the subsequent coming days, all of it seems too much to bear and I’ve decided I am not to write on it. The awareness that this entire fascist regime (or, situation) in India deserves is beyond anything I can measure, and I can’t remotely do it justice, in no specific way. My bias holds too high and is nowhere near close to being over, not anytime soon. Hence, I’ll use this as a ‘breath of fresh air,’ with how polluted the air I breathe is. In more ways than one.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Kuala Lumpur Summit: A Move for Unity in the Islamic World?</title>
      <link href="/Kuala-Lumpur-Summit" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kuala Lumpur Summit: A Move for Unity in the Islamic World?" />
      <published>2020-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Kuala-Lumpur-Summit</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Kuala-Lumpur-Summit">&lt;p&gt;The Kuala Lumpur Summit, held in the Malaysian capital for the first time in 2019, described itself as “an international platform for Muslim leaders, intellectuals and scholars from around the world to discuss and exchange ideas about the issues revolving in the Muslim world.” The summit, hosted by Malaysian Prime Minister Mahathir Mohamad from December 19-21 was viewed as an attempt to create a new bloc in the Muslim world that could become an alternative to the Organisation of Islamic Cooperation (OIC) led by Saudi Arabia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On December 19, 2019, leaders and senior representatives from some of the world’s most populous Muslim-majority countries gathered in the Malaysian capital to discuss issues agitating Muslims globally. The Summit was expected to answer some of the burning questions faced by the global Muslim community today including disputes in Kashmir and the Middle East, the conflicts in Syria and Yemen, the plight of Myanmar’s Rohingya Muslim minority, mounting outrage over China’s camps for Uighur Muslims in Xinjiang, and how to counter the spread of Islamophobia in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably, high-tier representatives from Saudi Arabia were not invited, which also resulted in a Saudi cleric publicly dismissing and snubbing the conference. Saudi Arabia said the Summit was the wrong forum for matters of importance to the world’s 1.75 billion Muslims. There are several geopolitical factors currently at work, which led to Saudi Arabia not receiving an invitation to the summit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it is clear that a growing number of Muslim-majority countries have become uncomfortable with Riyadh’s leadership in Islamic affairs since the ascendancy of Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman (MbS). From the Yemen war to a growing tacit alliance with Israel to the killing of Jamal Khashoggi, MbS has made a number of decisions that have unsettled many in Muslim-majority countries. Islamic leadership across the world is now afraid of the shock ripples that will erupt when MbS becomes the next Custodian of the Two Holy Mosques. These countries have perspectives on many issues facing Muslim countries that strongly differ from MbS’ own views and priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, Iranian President Hassan Rouhani and Qatari Emir Sheikh Tamim bin Hamid Al-Thani, were known to be coming for the Summit. These countries have severely hostile ties with Saudi Arabia and therefore, some analysts suspected the kingdom was being diplomatically isolated by regional rivals: Iran, Qatar and Turkey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally and most importantly, the summit is a clear attempt to break through the hegemonic power that the OIC has enjoyed, as far as redressal of global Islamic problems by the Muslim community is concerned. Qatari journalist Jaber al-Harami had stated that the Summit will be about laying the foundations for an Islamic alliance that could pursue joint projects, including, eventually, the introduction of a common currency. “The initiative is ambitious, and comes in accordance with the aspirations of these countries, especially as some of them talked about the creation of an Islamic bloc focused on defense industries, development, and good governance, and Qatar had a [lead] in this aspect.” And obviously, Saudi Arabia, has many problems with this clear challenge set out by the Islamic world, led by Malaysia’s 94-year PM and its own regional rivals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another turncoat for the Kuala Lumpur conference was Pakistan. Initially, Prime Minister Imran Khan not only offered his support for the initiative, but also announced that he would attend the event. Many in Pakistan’s policy-making circle are of the opinion that the OIC has done virtually nothing to call out India or offer support to Pakistan globally in this regard and, thus, the KL Summit offered an opportunity when it comes to discussing the Kashmir issue. However, Pakistan backed out of the conference, allegedly under extreme political pressure from its ally, Saudi Arabia. Riyadh’s anger over the initiative is such that Pakistan was forced to cancel even its ministerial-level representation. Pakistan’s decision shows that Riyadh still retains significant leverage over Pakistan’s foreign policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kuala Lumpur Summit has brought to light significant issues that still plague foreign policies in the Islamic world. It shows the resentment that several Islamic countries have garnered towards Saudi Arabia and the status it enjoys, both globally and within the Islamic community. It also depicts that the resistance towards Saudi’s powers is spreading beyond Turkey, Iran and Qatar and is now seeping into other corners of the world. This is not only a threat to Saudis but also to the USA, which is its central Western ally. The changing status of Saudi Arabia in the world also holds immense importance for the outcomes of the many proxy wars that it is invested in, including Yemen and Syria. The KL summit has brought to scrutiny the fractures and rifts that continue to exist in the modern Islamic world, despite being an initiative to bring the global Muslim community closer together.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Kuala Lumpur Summit, held in the Malaysian capital for the first time in 2019, described itself as “an international platform for Muslim leaders, intellectuals and scholars from around the world to discuss and exchange ideas about the issues revolving in the Muslim world.” The summit, hosted by Malaysian Prime Minister Mahathir Mohamad from December 19-21 was viewed as an attempt to create a new bloc in the Muslim world that could become an alternative to the Organisation of Islamic Cooperation (OIC) led by Saudi Arabia.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Colourism: An Introduction</title>
      <link href="/Colourism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Colourism: An Introduction" />
      <published>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Colourism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Colourism">&lt;p&gt;Colourism is a term increasingly mentioned in recent, modern racial discourse and is enjoying some much-needed attention during the current political climate. Colourism, by definition, is the “prejudice or discrimination against individuals with a dark skin tone, typically among people of the same ethnic or racial group” (&lt;em&gt;Oxford English Dictionary&lt;/em&gt;); but does this mean that this problem is something that is in fact conceived, and perpetuated, by black communities?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, no. Colourism is an overhang from slavery. It’s some form of diaspora from within your own diasporic community; where darker-skinned women, in particular, suffer poor treatment, fewer job opportunities and less representation in the film, television and music industries. Lighter skinned-artists such as Beyoncé Knowles, Robin ‘Rihanna’ Fenty, Jorja Smith and racially ambiguous artists like Cardi B, enjoy mainstream success, largely straddling both sides of the Black Atlantic (a concept developed by Paul Gilroy). On the other hand, artists like Nina Simone, Grace Jones and Azealia Banks have enjoyed lower levels of success or heightened criticism for their artistic choices. (Banks is admittedly a contentious choice to some, but still valid in demonstrating the wider point.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowles’ father, Matthew, conceded in an interview, when quizzed about whether the success of his daughters was in part down to their skin colour, that it was no ‘accident’ that the two were this way, elaborating further and revealing a greater attraction to lighter-skinned women. Mr Knowles admitted that his now ex-wife – Tina – seemed white to him when they first met. This was something that clearly was attractive to him and that he had been told by his mother to not bring home a “nappy headed black girl”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The negative portrait painted of women with darker skin seems to be a perpetuated tale of self-loathing from darker-skinned men and women reaching back over generations, since slavery – where white masters did show preferential treatment to and force themselves upon the lighter-skinned female slaves. Mr Knowles’ testimony, simultaneously explains that these ideas were ‘conditioned’ into him by his mother, yet this does no favours to the stereotypes of black women being angry and abusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyoncé Knowles’ &lt;em&gt;Lemonade&lt;/em&gt; visual album in 2016 was her third album away from the management of her father, who orchestrated her entire early career and her first three solo albums. On &lt;em&gt;Lemonade&lt;/em&gt;, Beyoncé sampled speeches from Malcolm X, notably in the music video for &lt;em&gt;Don’t’ Hurt Yourself&lt;/em&gt;: “The most disrespected person in America is the Black woman. The most unprotected person in America, is the Black woman. The most neglected woman in America is the Black Woman”. In addition, the promotional appearance at the 2016 Superbowl Half-time Show referenced the Black Panther movement in costume and staging, much to the shock and dismay of ‘White America’. US comedy show &lt;em&gt;Saturday Night Live&lt;/em&gt; even parodied the national reaction, joking that Beyoncé had become such a successful household name, that ‘they’ (‘White America’) had forgotten that she was in fact a black woman expressing – amongst other more personal things – her diasporic place in America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some would argue that the only way that this music was ever heard on a mainstream stage was due to her complexion and preferential treatment as a lighter-skinned woman, and as an established popular artist, with considerable influence and artistic independence thanks to signing with her husband’s label. Since then, Beyoncé also wrote a song for the &lt;em&gt;Lion King&lt;/em&gt; soundtrack &lt;em&gt;Brown Skinned Girl&lt;/em&gt; to empower and uplift women of darker shades—thereby using her privilege to uplift others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that this particular colouristic scrutiny doesn’t affect men in the same way, not to say it does not affect them at all. Black men in entertainment are seen in all shades, from Childish Gambino to the darker Kendrick Lamar, to the problematic Chris Brown who, despite several instances of abuse, continues to make music. Clearly the issue is not about representation, it’s about male privilege and a lack of self-worth or self-esteem that is passed down generations, which further marginalises women who do not enjoy the same privileges as their male counterparts in any ethnic group of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also about being held to a different standard to both men and people of lighter complexions. My earlier acknowledgement of Azealia Banks’ notorious spats serves a wider point. Many artists express un-savoury opinions about others, or are insensitive around hot-button issues: like Gina Rodriguez’s continued maligning of black women and throwaway use of the ‘N-word’; Cardi B’s abhorrent attitudes towards trans people, whilst appropriating LGBT+ turns of phrase; or Kanye West’s musings on slavery and support of Donald Trump under the guise of ‘free thought’. These are all people who swathes of people online have called out and ‘cancelled’ but who also mysteriously continue to enjoy success whilst remaining largely unscathed. It appears separating the artist from the art has qualifying factors and one of them is clearly skin tone – or at least when it comes to women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colourism itself highlights the complexities of ethnic minorities’ relationships with one another. It is perpetuated – at its root – by a form of white supremacy, that has filtered into various communities and left dark-skinned women feeling marginalised and unappreciated. Here, the term black is far from simple, as it does not encompass the inner prejudices within a diverse community of billions. Colourism is being discussed exponentially more in recent months and years; and hopefully, continues to get the attention it deserves for whom Malcom X described as the most ‘disrespected’, the most ‘unprotected’ and the most ‘neglected’ group in American society – and indeed the wider world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nat Richards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nat Richards is a freelance musician with a post-graduate degree from the University of Bristol.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Nat</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Colourism is a term increasingly mentioned in recent, modern racial discourse and is enjoying some much-needed attention during the current political climate. Colourism, by definition, is the “prejudice or discrimination against individuals with a dark skin tone, typically among people of the same ethnic or racial group” (Oxford English Dictionary); but does this mean that this problem is something that is in fact conceived, and perpetuated, by black communities?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lisbon: the New Start-up Hub of Europe</title>
      <link href="/New-Start-up-Hub-of-Europe" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lisbon: the New Start-up Hub of Europe" />
      <published>2020-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/New-Start-up-Hub-of-Europe</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/New-Start-up-Hub-of-Europe">&lt;p&gt;Aside from its amazing culture, stunning beaches and delicious cuisine, there is another reason why Lisbon is competing as one of the most vibrant and exciting cities in Europe. Lisbon’s start-up scene is thriving and with investment from the government and strong support from the private sector, this hidden gem of a city is really starting to garner attention not just from tourists, but also from young entrepreneurs around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vision of Lisbon as a premier start-up city began nearly a decade ago. The Mayor of Lisbon at the time, António Costa, who is now the Prime Minister of Portugal, introduced Startup Lisboa. This &lt;em&gt;incubator&lt;/em&gt; project is located right in the centre of the city, occupying what were historic buildings that had fallen into disuse. Its aims are to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Support the creation of companies and entrepreneurs in their first years of activity, to promote job creation, and aid the urban, social, and economic vitality of Lisbon.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last seven years, its success has been extremely impressive. It has supported around 400 start-ups, created 3,500 jobs and worked with entrepreneurs from more than 40 different countries. Well-known examples of companies that were assisted by Startup Lisboa include Uniplaces, a market leader in student accommodation which I myself used during my time spent in Lisbon. Startup Lisboa is just one of several incubator programmes that are supporting the growth of the various companies trying to establish themselves in Lisbon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important factor has been the Startup Visa, which is a residence visa scheme for entrepreneurs, aiming to attract investment, talent and innovation capacity. This was the first of its kind within Europe, demonstrating the forward-thinking attitude of the Portuguese government. Other visa settlement plans such as the Golden Visa have helped to bring foreign capital into the country, attracting nearly €5 billion of investment into Portugal since the scheme’s creation in 2012. Although a disproportionate amount of this investment has gone into property, it has still helped Lisbon to attract both smaller start-ups and bigger tech players. For example, last year, Google built a new support centre in Oeiras, on the outskirts of Lisbon, creating 500 jobs and establishing Lisbon as a hub for their operations in Europe, the Middle East and Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lisbon, and indeed Portugal, have also harnessed recent political developments to their advantage. Portugal IN is a temporary task force created by the government to capitalise on Brexit uncertainty. Historic links between the countries, regular flights, widespread knowledge of English, a similar time zone, and the British tourist’s partiality to a Portuguese package holidays are all strong motivators for British companies to expand to Portugal in these times of European uncertainty. Furthermore, rent prices and the cost of living is significantly lower in Lisbon than in London. Unlike some other European business hubs, Lisbon’s culture is one of its main draws and despite its smaller size compared to London, it more than makes up with its sunshine, vibrant society, relaxed atmosphere and spirit of work. In a world where work is becoming more agile and mobile, factors such as quality of life are becoming increasingly important in deciding where a business or employee should be based. In this way, Lisbon has and continues to develop an edge over its European counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another significant move for the Portuguese capital, Web Summit, the largest tech conference in Europe—to which &lt;em&gt;The Pangean&lt;/em&gt; was a media partner this year—has decided to move from Dublin to Lisbon for the last few years, thereby helping to establish the legitimacy of Lisbon as a key player in the technology sphere. Developments in the Portuguese education system have helped to support the political and social changes mentioned earlier. Focus on technology skills and engineering, coupled with the relatively low costs of living have created an abundance of local skilled labour for these domestic and international start-ups. Indeed, Portugal ranks very highly in government expenditure on education, female representation in the labour force and availability of skilled labour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This rise in the start-up scene has been made all the more important due to the current state of the economy in Portugal. Indeed, there are some critical issues on a national level. GDP per capita lags considerably behind other European countries; in 2018, it was nearly $10,000 less the EU average. Wages too have remained far below Western averages. Though it can be said that this cheap labour is part of the reason why international companies have been willing to invest in Portugal. Rising rents due to tourism and economic expansion in cities such as Lisbon and Porto are pushing locals out of the city. There has also been a lack of public investment, and anyone who has lived in Portugal will be able to cite the problems with outdated, inefficient infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all that said, there is cause for optimism. In recent years, the economy has shown consistent growth and unemployment has fallen from the high of 17.4% at the beginning of 2013 to a decent 6.6% as of September 2019. Household disposable income is rising at a rate of 2.9%, a figure which is higher than the UK, US, Denmark and Sweden. Moreover, the emergence of this exciting start-up culture can only serve to improve the Portuguese economic outlook and help modernise this Iberian economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As is stands, it seems that comparisons between Lisbon and Silicon Valley are only set to increase, with the Portuguese capital heavily promoting the image of a city attractive for its natural beauty and business opportunities. With Lisbon based start-ups raising hundreds of millions of Euros in investment, the favourable economic and political environment promoted by the local and national government has and continues to be successful, with the start-up boom in Lisbon here to stay.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Daniel Harris</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Aside from its amazing culture, stunning beaches and delicious cuisine, there is another reason why Lisbon is competing as one of the most vibrant and exciting cities in Europe. Lisbon’s start-up scene is thriving and with investment from the government and strong support from the private sector, this hidden gem of a city is really starting to garner attention not just from tourists, but also from young entrepreneurs around the world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The End of an Era</title>
      <link href="/End-of-an-Era" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The End of an Era" />
      <published>2020-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/End-of-an-Era</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/End-of-an-Era">&lt;p&gt;A globalized world means a lot of things, most of which is relegated to the back of our minds in the bustle of day-to-day life. The Brexit enigma too often fails to become imminent to those outside Europe, resting in our peripheral vision. This is partly owed to the large amount of time that has passed since Britain ‘left’ the European Union, without actually having left the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even until the December 12 general elections, with the possibility (not probability) of Labour leader Jeremy Corbyn’s victory, there were speculations regarding the future of the UK vis-a-vis leaving the EU. However, with the re-election of Conservative Party leader Boris Johnson as Prime Minister with an overwhelming majority, UK’s path to Brexit seems strikingly clear. In this environment, there is a need to clearly understand what has led to and what will potentially follow Brexit, hailed as possibly the most important moment in European history since the fall of the Berlin Wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of leaving the European Union has been on Britain’s mind from the moment it joined. Post Second World War tensions were high, and Britain’s economic growth was frightfully low. At the same time, in an attempt to ensure lasting peace, a few European states established the European Economic Community (EEC) hoping that economic interdependence would help avoid conflict. The EEC was a predecessor to the EU and surprisingly their old war ally Britain was not invited to the party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, in 1963, when the United Kingdom first applied for membership in the EEC, France’s President Charles de Gaulle &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/amp/s/www.bbc.co.uk/news/amp/world-europe-42165383&quot;&gt;vetoed its application&lt;/a&gt;. He claimed that the UK would always be on America’s side, even as a part of the EEC. UK became a member only in 1973 and just two years later a national referendum was held on whether to leave the Common Market. 67% voted to stay. In 1993, under the Maastricht Treaty, the European Union was formed to integrate states economically and politically, and to establish a common citizenship, currency and unified foreign policy. The EU was not bereft of skirmishes. Some of these would quite literally be the epitome of ‘first-world problems’ such as petty trade barriers on commodities ranging from beef to chocolate. Others were more prominent, such as those regarding immigration and sharing the burden of the crisis surrounding the Euro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three overarching reasons that fuelled the ‘eurosceptic’ view and simultaneously drove the ‘Leave campaign’ in Britain were sovereignty, immigration and the Euro. British conservatives loathed the idea that the mighty United Kingdom must take orders from someone else. The growing power of the European Parliament, the ridiculous amount of red tape and the growing lack of autonomy were major causes of resentment against the EU. The economic crisis of 2008 and the subsequent failure to deal with the flaws of the Euro made people not only in the UK but across the continent skeptical about the economic benefits of EU membership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, what arguably had the most effect on the voters during the referendum was the free flow of people within the EU. Employment of locals posed one problem and a perceived relationship between immigration and crime posed another. The Migration Advisory Committee, however, in its review of the evidence of the labour market impact of EU migration, found that migrants have had little or no impact on the employment and unemployment outcomes of the UK-born workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What should be noted is that EU states have a &lt;em&gt;choice&lt;/em&gt; to restrict free movement. It was a decision made by Tony Blair’s government in 2003 that allowed full free movement, which is what led to an increase in immigration. Nevertheless, in the EU referendum campaign, the Leave campaigners pinned the surge of workers on the EU and not the British government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, Prime Minister David Cameron promised a national referendum on European Union membership, convinced that ‘Remain’ camp would win handily. That turned out to be a serious miscalculation. The referendum passed by a slim 51.9% in favour of leaving. However, there were stark differences across the UK. Northern Ireland and London voted to remain in the EU, as did Scotland, leading to renewed calls for another referendum on Scottish independence. The rest of England and Wales, however, voted in favour of Brexit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After three of Theresa May’s Brexit deals were rejected by the UK, she resigned, leaving Brexit to her successor Boris Johnson. As of December 20, 2019, Johnson succeeded in getting his Withdrawal Agreement Bill (WAB) passed in the House of Commons, signaling the end of many years of political infighting regarding the issue. After the WAB becomes law, the withdrawal agreement also needs to be ratified by the European Parliament next month. Then the stage will be set for Brexit on January 31, when the post-Brexit transition period will begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 11 months, the UK will still follow all the EU’s rules and regulations, it will remain in the single market and the Customs Union, and the free movement of people will continue. The government and the EU will work out a Free Trade Agreement (FTA) for a smooth transition. Johnson has made it clear in the WAB that there will be no extension beyond 2020, and if no deal is worked out, then trade will carry on without agreement, meaning that tariffs would be levied on UK goods entering the EU and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WAB implies the following things. Firstly, the UK will have to settle its financial obligations to the EU. Secondly, UK citizens in the EU, and EU citizens in the UK, will retain their residency and social security rights after Brexit. Those residing in an EU country for five years or more can apply for residency in said country. Thirdly, the UK will leave the EU Customs Union, which exempts members from tariffs and levies uniform tariffs on other countries. Leaving the Customs Union means the UK will be able to strike trade deals with other countries in the future—although the exact extent of that freedom will only be revealed in the course of the trade talks with the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, there is the matter of how Johnson has dealt with the new ‘Irish question’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Northern Ireland and its land border with the Republic of Ireland has posed a problem for Brexit for many years. Largely due to the ‘backstop’. The backstop was designed to ensure there would be no border posts or barriers between Northern Ireland and the Republic of Ireland after Brexit. Such posts would rekindle tensions and also serve as targets for potential insurgents groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new deal solves this problem by shifting these posts to the UK-Northern Ireland border instead. The actual checks will be on what is effectively a customs border between Great Britain and the island of Ireland, with goods being checked at ‘points of entry’ into Northern Ireland. Taxes will only have to be paid on goods being moved from Great Britain to Northern Ireland if those products are considered ‘at risk’ of then being transported into the Republic of Ireland. The deal gives the Northern Ireland Assembly a vote on these new arrangements, but only four years after the end of the transition period, in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Unionist Party of Northern Ireland opposes the WAB for leaving Northern Ireland behind and creating a situation where it must comply with EU customs laws even though it will be a part of the UK’s foreign trade deals. They advocate upholding the “economic and constitutional integrity of Northern Ireland within the United Kingdom”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The integrity of the Kingdom is further rattled by Scotland, which had expressed a 62% desire to remain with the EU in 2016. Although it does not seem economically viable for Scotland to unilaterally remain with the EU, Brexit gave impetus to the Scottish Nationalist Party, for whom all roads lead to Scottish independence. Even though they had voted ‘yes’ to maintaining union with the UK in 2014, the Scottish public opinion is still sharply divided (50:50). The Scottish government has proposed holding a second referendum on Scottish independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brexit is no longer a lulling stream but a whirlpool that is approaching quickly and with near-complete certainty. Although the UK may achieve external sovereignty, the integrity of its union may be deeply affected. On the other hand, a year does not seem nearly enough to undo 46 years of Common Market. Although Johnson is staunch on wrapping up Brexit in 2020, things are bound to overflow. The ‘remain’ votes in 2016 were dominated by the youth. Which leads us to think that by the time deals are made and debts are paid, those who inherit a ‘free’ and ‘independent’ UK, may not want it at all. However, where there is political will there is a way, as can be seen in Boris Johnson’s dogged eagerness. We really are then, at the end of an era.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A globalized world means a lot of things, most of which is relegated to the back of our minds in the bustle of day-to-day life. The Brexit enigma too often fails to become imminent to those outside Europe, resting in our peripheral vision. This is partly owed to the large amount of time that has passed since Britain ‘left’ the European Union, without actually having left the European Union.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
