<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/trending/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-06-06T14:06:08+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/trending/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Crime of Menstruation</title>
      <link href="/The-Crime-of-Menstruation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Crime of Menstruation" />
      <published>2020-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Crime-of-Menstruation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Crime-of-Menstruation">&lt;p&gt;The amount one knows about the phenomenon known as menstruation depends on a number of things; sex, age, ethnicity and other characteristics. This is in spite of the fact that having periods is perhaps just as common as any other human bodily process, and is experienced on a monthly basis by roughly half of the world’s population. While there is a general awareness that periods are a necessity for fertility in women, not many people across the world are appreciative of what is involved in the process. Menstruating women are widely seen as ‘dirty’ and steps are taken to avoid them at all costs by people of certain communities. However, this stigma associated with menstruation is not just an issue of the ‘backward’ or ‘illiterate’ communities; it affects the most modern of societies too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several religious superstitions associated with periods and pink products like tampons and pads. In cultures like Hinduism, women who are on their periods are often exempted from the rites and rituals that characterise the religion. They are not permitted inside the kitchen, to adorn themselves with flowers or to even touch anyone or anything, as far as possible. In fact, there are several temples that do not permit the entry of menstruating women or women of menstruating age. One such instance that drew wide condemnation is the Sabarimala Temple located in the state of Kerala in India. For centuries, this temple has restricted the entry of women of menstruating age (roughly between 10 and 50 years). This is claimed to be out of respect for the celibate nature of the patron deity. In a historic verdict on September 28, 2018, the Supreme Court of India lifted the ban on the entry of women, stating that discrimination against them, even on the grounds of religion, is unconstitutional. While feminists hailed this as a great victory, many others, including women, were not very appreciative of the step, and the Court has decided to review its decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such restrictions are not unique to Hinduism. In Islam, women are not permitted to partake in the fasting that characterises the month of Ramadan and are essentially seen as ‘impure’. Men are instructed to stay away from women on their periods and to refrain from having sexual intercourse during this time. Similarly, Judaism refers to such women as &lt;em&gt;‘niddah’&lt;/em&gt; and the Torah bans intercourse between a man and a menstruating woman. Besides, early Western Christian cultures considered a menstruating woman dangerous and placed restrictions on her to ensure safety for all. Even today, some church fathers continue to support the exclusion of women from the ministry on the basis of ‘uncleanliness’. The idea of women being impure or unclean during their periods is a very common notion among most of the world’s most popular religions and cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are however, some religions that do not view menstruation in a bad light. This category includes the Sikhs and Buddhists. Now, there are some denominations of these religions that share the idea of menstruating women being unclean, but in general, their beliefs are less overbearing compared to the others. A similar and rather astonishing example is Shaktism, a major denomination of Hinduism. The followers of this sect celebrate the annual menstrual cycle, called Ambubachi, of Goddess Kamakhya at the Kamakhya Temple of Assam, India. This takes place every year in the month of June. It is celebrated in the form of the Ambubachi Mela, a four-day festival, wherein the doors of the temple remain closed for three days and open on the fourth to welcome thousands of pilgrims from around the world. This view of the natural process of menstruation is in stark contrast with the more popularly held Hindu views. It is important to note here that the most popular religions and their denominations across the world belong to the former category and do not view periods positively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discussion up until now provides a view that only the most religious people tend to see menstruation adversely. This is, however, not very accurate. A casual stigma associated with having periods pervades among all of us. Common experiences of women bear testimony to that. In India, packets of sanitary napkins are wrapped in newspaper and then handed over to the customer in a black polyethene packet. At this point, I am pretty sure the entire demographic is aware of what is inside and we might as well opt for a new measure to hide the fact that women menstruate. Girls often feel embarrassed while shopping for period products when the experience should be the same as buying band-aids. Many refrain from using tampons due to the fear of breaking their hymen before marriage, something that is often culturally looked down upon. Girls also usually feel ashamed after discovering a stain on their clothes, which again, under normal circumstances, should not have been viewed any differently than a blood soaked bandage. The point is this, we are consciously trying to hide the fact that having periods is a normal occurrence, affecting about half the human population every month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The misconceptions surrounding menstruation have always given it a bad name and resulted in women being oppressed. In Nepal, a very common practice is to move women on their periods to often very unhygienic menstrual huts. This practice, referred to as ‘Chhaupadi’, is actually illegal in Nepal, and yet it continues to exist as a commonplace practice. Several women die every year due to suffocation, snake bites, excessively cold weather and assault during their exile in these huts. The exact number of deaths due to this practice, however, is unknown as most of these cases go unreported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discrimination is not just limited to these instances. On a wider scale, menstruating women face the phenomenon of the ‘pink tax’. It is a common knowledge that a gender based wage gap exists even today in most fields of work. An additional value added tax to feminine products in such a scenario effectively reduces the purchasing power of women in general. Moreover, our economic structure fails to recognise period products as a necessity and chooses to see them as items of luxury. Thus, even they are not exempted from the pink tax. As I have mentioned in one of my previous articles, this comes across as if menstruation is a crime and women are being fined for the crime of menstruation. There have, however, been some positive changes in this avenue over the last few months. Due to the continuous efforts of Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez and other Democrats, a few states in the US have taken the decision to repeal the Tampon Tax. The biggest win in this avenue was achieved by Scotland when the country became the first in the world to make all period products available to all women free of cost on February 27, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, most other countries continue to charge heavily for menstrual hygiene products. The introduction of GST (Goods and Services Tax) in India on July 1, 2017 resulted in a 12% taxation on sanitary napkins. This sparked protests across the country and consequently, the tax on pads had to be repealed a year later. However, period products continue to be beyond the affordability of a large number of women in India. In rural areas of developing countries like India and other places where women’s accessibility to pads and tampons is very limited, menstruating women resort to the use of leaves for cleaning purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Period poverty is a major issue in the modern world. Many organisations across the world have taken it upon themselves to strive to ensure these basic requirements for all women. Sanjay Wijesekera, former UNICEF Chief of Water, Sanitation and Hygiene was once quoted as saying, “Meeting the hygiene needs of all adolescent girls is a fundamental issue of human rights, dignity and public health.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another rather surprising aspect of period products and menstruation is the lack of understanding of the subject among males. Now, since they do not have to face the monthly pain, they don’t really have to know how tampons are used. But a basic understanding of why it happens and the physical and mental complications associated with it is a necessity to at least make an attempt to tackle the misunderstandings and stigma around menstruation. Shockingly, even women tend to harbour a lot of misconceptions about the process like the belief that women living in close proximity sync up their menstrual cycles or that one cannot get pregnant while on their period. However, most educational set-ups across the world fail to clear these misconceptions due to the stigma associated with speaking about periods. It is almost an unspoken rule to not mention a naturally uncontrollable bodily phenomenon like menstruation. Even popular television shows like &lt;em&gt;Survivor&lt;/em&gt; and others, which have a basic premise of surviving in nature, fail to talk about how women deal with menstruation during their stay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of the fact that women have been experiencing this phenomenon forever, the advancement in period products is rather disappointing. Tampons and pads, which are among the most popular period products to be used, are actually very bad for the environment. Besides, wearing one of these for a prolonged period of time may lead to the overgrowth of &lt;em&gt;staphylococcus aureus&lt;/em&gt; bacteria in the vagina and result in a condition called toxic shock syndrome. The symptoms include dizziness, diarrhoea and even fever. Very few environmentally-friendly options that are completely safe to use exist and these are well beyond the affordability of most women across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another of the major side effects of the menstrual stigma are the taunts. Back in 2015, when Donald Trump was caught in a tirade of questions from Fox News host Megyn Kelly, he claimed that she had “blood coming out of her wherever”, probably in an attempt to shut her up. He, however, denied it, later saying that he was actually referring to Kelly’s apparently bleeding nose. Comments like this have always been around and various aspects of menstruation have been used to provide variety to the taunts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Premenstrual syndrome (PMS) is often used as a weapon to devalidate a woman’s concerns and feelings. In fact, my apprehensions involving PMS are not limited to just that. The phenomenon of premenstrual syndrome is characterised by a wide variety of symptoms including fatigue, cramps, diarrhoea, insomnia and depression. While each of these symptoms individually garners sympathy from most and can be a primary cause for being excused from work, the amalgamation of all, which is arguably worse, fails to do the same. This is primarily because of the association with the forbidden word: menstruation. The causes of these symptoms are not very well understood among the medical community but are primarily attributed to hormonal changes during the menstrual cycle. The lack of sympathy and understanding often results in adverse conditions for menstruating women, especially in the workplace. About 50 years ago, when Western women were entering the workforce in large numbers for the first time, conservative activists like Phyllis Schlafly claimed that women were hormonally ill-suited for positions of responsibility. This ideology continues to hinder women’s capacity to get an upgrade to a position of authority even today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that we are not talking enough about menstruation and unknowingly, continue to keep the stigma associated with it alive. As much as all of us want to believe that women are not oppressed anymore, it is still a dream that we might need a while to realise. Active measures to educate the masses on the body function, making period products and clean water available to all and actively fighting against cultural practices of discriminatory nature is the need of the hour. And this begins with people talking about periods, rather than pretending as if they are Voldemort and must not be named.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The amount one knows about the phenomenon known as menstruation depends on a number of things; sex, age, ethnicity and other characteristics. This is in spite of the fact that having periods is perhaps just as common as any other human bodily process, and is experienced on a monthly basis by roughly half of the world’s population. While there is a general awareness that periods are a necessity for fertility in women, not many people across the world are appreciative of what is involved in the process. Menstruating women are widely seen as ‘dirty’ and steps are taken to avoid them at all costs by people of certain communities. However, this stigma associated with menstruation is not just an issue of the ‘backward’ or ‘illiterate’ communities; it affects the most modern of societies too.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Rioting Doesn’t Matter, Nothing Does</title>
      <link href="/Rioting-Doesnt-Matter" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rioting Doesn't Matter, Nothing Does" />
      <published>2020-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Rioting-Doesnt-Matter</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Rioting-Doesnt-Matter">&lt;p&gt;To anyone with any concern for humanity, what has happened in America should be deeply saddening and infuriating. The brutal killing of George Floyd by a police officer in Minneapolis has opened the floodgates of fury in America’s general populace. The National Guard has had to be deployed in many places. Courthouses, shops, town halls, homes and so many places have been burned to the ground by rioters. While thousands have been arrested, some rioters, police officers and protestors have been killed. President Trump has declared Antifa a terrorist organisation and has threatened to use the military.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, the situation is dire. Those on America’s Right have broadly issued boilerplate condemnations of the incident of police brutality, of course, but with no acknowledgement of the systemic oppression of Black people in America. And in classic American conservative fashion, they have condemned the retributive violence with evident dog whistles like those calling for “law and order” to be restored. The liberals, well, have been liberals, making boilerplate condemnations of systemic oppression without any real commitment towards an actual solution. As usual, they have been busy ‘turning people’s heads’ to bring attention to the problem by changing their profile pictures. In complete contrast, the leftists have been rejoicing; to them this is the beginning of a revolution that is going to end the hegemony of the ruling class in America and fulfill Marx’s prophecy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the zeal of the American leftist in these riots is more masturbatory than it is idealistic, representing a mere Lacanian fantasy to find a new master instead of a true desire to usher in a just society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, one can see where the need for violence arises from. It would be foolish and immoral to argue that ‘violence is never the answer’. Violence becomes necessary to achieve tangible goals when the conscience of the powers that be simply remains unmoved by the scale of their own exploitation. Violence becomes unavoidable when the hand of the ‘system’ only seeks to whip and coerce people into submission. And in America, it should be incontrovertible to say that these conditions stand fulfilled, for police brutality against George Floyd is only the tip of the iceberg; crime, death, poverty, unfair treatment and so much more clearly evidences that American Black people are second-class citizens in a country that is partially built on enslaving them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, violence needs to be clearly channelised. It needs to be used to truly storm the Bastille or storm the Tsar’s Winter Palace. What it is definitely not supposed to be used for is burning a 7-11 or destroying the livelihoods of a lot of small businesses or pelting stones at everyday citizens. One can make theoretical arguments of how all businesses and everyday citizens who have been mute throughout, are complicit and need to face the fury as well. But one has to honestly ask oneself if that argument really holds water: The factum of being born in a society means one is subjected to its all-pervading influence that indoctrinates all into marginalising certain peoples, does that mean everyone in the world should be subjected to violence? Of course not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the social lives of conscious beings like humans, violence is as much physical as it is psychological. When we burn down a building or kill someone as part of a movement, we inevitably seek to psychologically challenge what that building or person represents. This is why there is a world of difference between burning a police station and vandalising a convenience store. The former is a clear challenge to the system of authority that killed George Floyd. The latter is saying that a person is not allowed to carry on his business because of their theoretical complicity, that the people who depended on that business for their wages do not deserve them. It should take no intellectual exegesis to point out that the latter kind of violence is directed at those who are merely the blind serfs of the overlord that is systemic oppression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is here that we find that the so-called revolution going on in America today is more ‘ideological’ in the postmodernist sense than anything. The violence in American streets hasn’t affected the American oligarchs at all. What it has done is far more miniscule yet far more sinister: the riots have ensured that the anger of the marginalised is directed at those who are only theoretically guilty to ensure that those who actually are guilty can continue to maintain their power. The ‘owners’ of the oasis in the desert of post-ideology have ensured that the thirsty fight against those who are allowed to fetch a pail of water instead of those who consume the whole pond. This is eminently proved by the outpouring of support that so many warlocks of the system, the TV show hosts, actors and musicians have shown for the riots. In fact, some of them have even offered to bail the rioters out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The riots in America are a clear example of how far late capitalism has gone to ensure it cannot be challenged. Even in this outpouring of violence, we are able to locate not a true challenge to the Machine. We can only see rage, rage that only affirms the master’s discourse. Perhaps that is all we can now have against capitalism, the trappings of ideology are far too great, the sinews of the invisible exploitative hand are too strong. Maybe, just maybe, we are doomed.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>anon.anon</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">To anyone with any concern for humanity, what has happened in America should be deeply saddening and infuriating. The brutal killing of George Floyd by a police officer in Minneapolis has opened the floodgates of fury in America’s general populace. The National Guard has had to be deployed in many places. Courthouses, shops, town halls, homes and so many places have been burned to the ground by rioters. While thousands have been arrested, some rioters, police officers and protestors have been killed. President Trump has declared Antifa a terrorist organisation and has threatened to use the military.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">European Central Bank: The Saviour of Europe?</title>
      <link href="/European-Central-Bank" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="European Central Bank: The Saviour of Europe?" />
      <published>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/European-Central-Bank</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/European-Central-Bank">&lt;p&gt;Time and again, Ms Lagarde, the first President of the European Central Bank (ECB) warned the European Union (EU) governments against the COVID-19 pandemic turning into a calamity. The pressures have been mounting as the largest economies of the Eurozone like France and Italy crumble. The EU, one of the world’s largest economies, has decided to take certain measures via its monetary policy, however, the question is how much can the ECB afford?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms Lagarde, however, is of the view that monetary policy is not the first line of defence and feels that fiscal response must be given much more importance. The persistent heterogeneity in the Euro area has also been a long-standing concern for the single monetary policy. It severely complicates the conduct of this policy. The current crisis exposed these vulnerabilities, once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since 2008, the EU has been in a non-stop crisis mode. Even the interest rate it charges to the commercial banks is almost nil leaving very little margin for further rate cuts to stimulate the economy out of this rut. The ECB has acknowledged how they are facing an unprecedented crisis with historic consequences which might just push the European economy to worse than what it was in 2008. If the crisis is not controlled by the stimuli, it risks pushing the already wobbly European economy to the state of recession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 16, the ECB went ahead and announced the measures it will be taking on the monetary policy front while it gives time to the respective governments to formulate fiscal policy measures. The ECB took certain measures to prevent the crisis from becoming a full-blown financial crisis with two broad objectives: first, to restore the orderly functioning of presently volatile European financial markets, and second, to ensure that the accommodative monetary policy measures support firms and households in incurring the social and economic costs of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ECB response consists of three major mutually reinforcing grounds. The first one relating to broad-based asset purchases to address illiquidity and volatility in core segments of the European economy. The temporary Pandemic Emergency Purchase Programme (PEPP) constitutes the core of this component. The economies in the entire Eurozone have been struggling with tightening fiscal and economic conditions, the PEPP expects to release the pressure on these economies. It foresees purchases at a volume of €750 billion of eligible private and public securities throughout this year, and longer if needed.  The ECB also aims to mitigate the impact of the crisis on the funding conditions of businesses and banks. For the same, it has decided to divert a considerable fraction of the additional €120 billion purchase envelope under the Asset Purchase Programmes (APP), as well as of the PEPP, for eligible private sector bonds. However, one cannot turn a blind eye to the fact that the bank has already been conducting purchases of government bonds, and now, it does not have much to re-purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, measures to ensure that the banks remain effective carriers of the monetary policy of the ECB have been introduced. The enhanced Targeted Longer-Term Refinancing Operations (TLTROs), as well as a comprehensive set of collateral easing measures, form part of this component.  The interest rate on all targeted TLTROs was reduced by 25 basis points to -0.5% from June 2020 to June 2021. Measures to ensure the solvency of banks by holding up the role of lender of the last resort to the banks which will help the ECB drive the way for economic growth. This becomes all the more necessary considering that the European economy is majorly a bank-based economy than a financial market one, so just supporting the financial markets would not help alleviate the effects of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measures for small and medium-sized firms are equally necessary, which include bank lending and loan guarantee schemes to protect the already overdrawn credit lines by cash strapped firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Italy, for example, bank lending conditions for firms remained remarkably resilient in recent years despite significant swings in market-based funding conditions of the banks and firms. Again, the measures can provide a valuable bridge to the future and help keep aggregate external funding costs of firms stable until the economy recovers and uncertainty diminishes further. This also includes accepting a wider range of assets as collaterals from small and medium-sized firms along with consistently working on the liquidity conditions of the banks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the ECB fails to improve liquidity indirectly through these measures, it always has the option to exercise its right to issue ‘helicopter money’. This alternative would put the money straight into the ‘hands’ of the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through these measures, the ECB hopes to improve liquidity and market behaviour in the sovereign yield bonds market, which in turn form the basis of pricing of assets in the economy. The ECB uses the GDP-weighted Euro area government bond yield curve as a measure for the effectiveness of the economy, but currently, this curve has been badly disrupted. So the ECB will focus on stabilising this curve and reversing the steepness of the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, while the Eurozone faces an increasingly threatening risk of a slowdown in the economy, which can take years to recover from and get back to the normal levels, the ECB and various governments are taking steps to tackle this challenge. The cluster of countries has recovered from far worse situations in the past, like the global economic crisis of 2008, and emerged stronger than ever. It remains to be seen what other steps the European Union takes as a much worse crisis than COVID-19 awaits the global economy and how the relief package unravels for the Union.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kashish Jindal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Time and again, Ms Lagarde, the first President of the European Central Bank (ECB) warned the European Union (EU) governments against the COVID-19 pandemic turning into a calamity. The pressures have been mounting as the largest economies of the Eurozone like France and Italy crumble. The EU, one of the world’s largest economies, has decided to take certain measures via its monetary policy, however, the question is how much can the ECB afford?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">China’s Banking Assets: A Recipe for Financial Crisis</title>
      <link href="/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="China’s Banking Assets: A Recipe for Financial Crisis" />
      <published>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Recipe-for-Financial-Crisis">&lt;p&gt;The global economy finds itself in a synchronised slowdown, with growth downgraded to as low as 3% in 2019, the lowest since the Global Financial Crisis. Adding to the economic tensions is COVID-19, which has brought the world economies to a near shutdown phase as they adopt preventive measures inclusive of complete lockdowns. What is more concerning is the fact that the two major engines of global growth, the United States of America and China, are the worst hit among many others. What makes the economic crisis worse in China? It is the worsening predicament of the banking sector which becomes a matter of immediate concern as China’s banking sector is three times larger than the size of its entire economy. The gigantic Chinese banking sector is capable of dwarfing out banking sectors in other parts of the world, including that of the United States of America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2019 China Financial Stability Report published by the People’s Bank of China officially deems 586 out of 4,379 Chinese lenders to be ‘high-risk’. The figures came into light only after the failure of a third bank within three months as national economic growth manifested a 30-year low. The Hengfeng Bank has become the third bank, after Baoshang Bank and Bank of Jinzhou, to suffer an economic collapse after a $40 trillion debt. But the Chinese government isn’t exceedingly famous for its honesty and transparency, thus the reported figure is likely masking the true extent of the banking quandary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chinese government has bailed out many of the high risk lenders. Precarious private shareholders have been effectively replaced by the ones backed by the state, often weaker in terms of their finances. The fact that bailouts are offered only for companies whose bankruptcy has a grave adverse impact on the economy as a whole and not just on a specified sector, cannot be ignored. Moreover, any amount of bailout allocated to this sector will have a domino effect on the Chinese economy which will be several times greater. For instance, the banking system calls for a 5-6% bailout which is equal to 20-24% of the Chinese GDP. A bailout of 20% of the GDP is a non-viable deal for any economy, even if it is China. The numeric is a statement of the fact that any pebble aimed at the banking sector shall bring ripples to the entire economy that in turn will shake China’s status of being a global economic power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The People’s Bank of China conducted a stress test in the first half of 2019 on 1,171 commercial banks, 7.7% were stated to be at ‘extreme risk’ and deemed incapable of absorbing even a light shock, 13.6% will probably not be able to endure the financial crisis that shall follow. In November, Yingkou Coastal Bank and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scmp.com/economy/china-economy/article/3035596/wechat-rumour-sparks-run-rural-chinese-bank-fresh-sign&quot;&gt;Yichuan Rural Commercial Bank&lt;/a&gt; – despite boasting healthy capital adequacy ratios – suffered bank runs as customers rushed to withdraw cash, fearing that the banks would close down, displaying a lack of confidence in banking institutions. The current situation is very similar to the one that cropped up in the late 1990’s. Towards the end of 1997, 20% of the main banks were non-performing, which was equivalent to a value of ¥1.19 trillion on the books of state-owned banks, which was deemed to be equal to 15.6% of the GDP. In order to resolve these crises and recapitalise the banks, ¥270 billion of special government bonds were issued and injected by August 1998. Walking on the same rope, the Chinese government is peddling its way through the crisis by adopting a somewhat similar technique. Today, the interbank market has been injected with around ¥2 trillion by the People’s Bank of China after the Baoshang Bank collapse. Along with this, a helping hand of the sovereign fund, China Investment Corporation, the Central Huijin Investment Company is injecting ¥60 billion into Hengfeng Bank. One of the 12 nationwide joint-stock banks in China, Hengfeng Bank is stacked up with non-performing loans and the situation became grimmer as the bank’s former president was handed out a death sentence for purloining funds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the similarities, overlooking the different macroeconomic situation shall prove fatal to the Chinese economy in the present scenario. The key antidote for the crisis back then was the spurt of hyper economic growth in the early 2000’s. If China wants to avoid tormenting its economy with the inevitability of bad loans and its weakening banking structure, it will have to aim for a masterful economic growth. However, this stands as a challenge with the outbreak of COVID-19 and its likely aftermath on the global economy. Secondly, continuous evolution over the years has resulted in an entwined and fragile banking structure. The financial system in modern times has given rise to an integrated market that ensures banking transactions are speeded up and are facile in nature. Since the speed of transactions and their impact on the economy is brisk, it also means that any kind of shock in the structure is transmitted faster than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The corporate and interbank customers suffer heavy losses, the volume of negotiable certificates of deposit—which are securities traded between financial institutions for short-term liquidity—has plunged by 90%. The situation threatens to cause the entire banking system to seize up as small and medium-sized banks are heavily dependent on liquidity in the interbank market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crisis should be an eye-opener for the administration as it calls for reforms in the entire financial system which has been overreliant on its banking sector for channeling funds. The fact that the financial structure has changed barely in the last fourteen years is an explanation for the crisis at hand. The world continues to keep a close watch on China, as this crisis is far too big to ignore because any large scale disruption in the driving engine of the global economy will lead the other economies into recession.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The global economy finds itself in a synchronised slowdown, with growth downgraded to as low as 3% in 2019, the lowest since the Global Financial Crisis. Adding to the economic tensions is COVID-19, which has brought the world economies to a near shutdown phase as they adopt preventive measures inclusive of complete lockdowns. What is more concerning is the fact that the two major engines of global growth, the United States of America and China, are the worst hit among many others. What makes the economic crisis worse in China? It is the worsening predicament of the banking sector which becomes a matter of immediate concern as China’s banking sector is three times larger than the size of its entire economy. The gigantic Chinese banking sector is capable of dwarfing out banking sectors in other parts of the world, including that of the United States of America.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Domestic Violence Pandemic</title>
      <link href="/The-Domestic-Violence-Pandemic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Domestic Violence Pandemic" />
      <published>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Domestic-Violence-Pandemic</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Domestic-Violence-Pandemic">&lt;p&gt;Domestic violence is among the most common forms of crime. Very often, it is not even seen as a serious issue in various countries. Diverse cultures around the world have normalised intimate partner violence and some even encourage it in certain scenarios. The lack of proper action against perpetrators has left millions of victims around the globe hopeless, and the number of cases keeps rising every year. In the absence of effective preventive measures and relief facilities, the matter can only be expected to get worse as the years pass by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason behind my decision to write this piece is the astonishing rise in the domestic violence cases ever since the pandemic lockdown began. The UK’s largest domestic abuse charity, Refuge recorded an over 700% increase in calls to its helpline in a single day after the lockdown was initiated. In addition, a separate helpline for the perpetrators of domestic violence looking for ways to change saw a 25% increase. Now, once you sit down and think about it, this is a crisis that could have been foreseen. Everyone has been asked to remain within the confines of their homes, as much as possible, meaning that the victims have nowhere to go. This is exactly the kind of a scenario that abusers thrive in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, such surges in the number of cases were noticed in previous instances of crises too. This includes the global financial crisis in 2008 and natural disasters like the Christchurch earthquake of 2011. A few countries, however, have seen a drop in the number of intimate partner violence complaints during the quarantine period. The Office of Domestic Violence for the Supreme Court of Argentina has seen a drop in such complaints from 50 a day to 5. A lawyer stated later that the drop was probably due to the fact that abusers can now actively control their victims, who have no way to escape. A reported 25% increase in the calls to the emergency hotline confirms his suspicions. A steep fall in calls to the domestic violence helplines in countries like France and Italy can also be attributed to the same reason; the victims are being controlled, have no way to escape and are finding it difficult to look for help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authorities have found it difficult to pin-point and to reach out to these victims. They have been actively trying to encourage victims to call them and let their conditions be known. Victoria Derbyshire, a BBC newsreader was seen hosting a BBC News programme with the domestic violence helpline number written on the back of her hand. She made it clear later that her aim was to get the number out to those who need it during the times of self-isolation. However, with the abuser always at home and the victim having nowhere else to go, something as simple as making a call for help can be an impossible task. It is estimated that on a regular basis, only 34% of those who are subjected to violence in the hands of an intimate partner receive medical help for their injuries. The numbers can only be expected to be worse in the present scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another recent incident in Canada solidified concerns about the situation. The country witnessed its worst mass shooting on April 18, 2020. A 12-hour rampage perpetrated by a gunman disguised as a police officer left 22 people dead. This started with an argument between the gunman and his girlfriend which eventually resulted in an assault. She, however, managed to escape and hid in the woods overnight in an attempt to save herself. This is believed to have been the trigger for the shooting. While in this case, the victim was able to escape death, not everyone is that lucky. According to the US-based National Coalition Against Domestic Violence (NCADV), the presence of a gun in a domestic violence situation increases the risk of a homicide by 500%. In addition, 19% of all reported cases of domestic violence involve a weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst all these issues, the heavily sensationalised Amber Heard-Johnny Depp situation has brought a small detail to light. Domestic violence is, more often than not, seen as an exclusively non-male issue. While it is true that the numbers are higher on that end, an ignorance of the issues faced by men makes the situation only worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, Amber Heard accused her ex-husband Johnny Depp of domestic violence. These claims were supported by pictures of Heard with bruises from the alleged assault and a video of angry Depp throwing a wine bottle and glass. People all across the globe extended support towards Heard, who, unlike many could gather the courage to file a case against her abuser. The public outrage against the actor resulted in him losing some of his most coveted movie roles including his leading role as Jack Sparrow in the very successful &lt;em&gt;Pirates of the Caribbean&lt;/em&gt; franchise. Amber Heard, on the other hand, landed the role of Mera in &lt;em&gt;Aquaman&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since she made her abuse story public, she has been given the opportunity to speak for women’s and children’s rights on numerous occasions. However, the real nature of Heard’s interactions with Johnny Depp while she was still married to him was brought to light earlier this year. The leaked recordings of conversations between the two showed a completely different story from the one that the actress had spent the last few years painting. Amber Heard was the abuser. Since then, several other sources helping prove Depp’s innocence in the matter have come to light and the actor has filed a defamation suit against his ex-wife. With the overwhelming amount of evidence against Heard, it is clear that the actress might face some jail time. However, in spite of massive support for her being removed from the DC cast, no such action has been taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike Depp, on the career front, she has not been affected at all. This has increased concerns about an unequal treatment of genders when it comes to domestic abuse. According to statistics provided by the NCADV, while 1 in 4 women experience intimate partner physical violence, contact sexual violence and/or partner stalking with impacts such as injury, fearfulness, PTSD, contraction of STDs and so on and so forth, 1 in 9 men experience the same. Very few instances in which males experience domestic violence in the hands of others are usually reported. Now, the reason behind this is twofold. Firstly, patriarchy teaches men to be ‘masculine’, a word that has attributes like not crying or asking for help and beliefs like non-males are physically weaker and are incapable of inflicting pain upon males, associated with it, resulting in most cases going unreported. The second reason is a bitter after-effect of the first: men’s cries for help are often rejected, their words are not believed and they are often ridiculed in such a scenario. They, therefore, fear opening up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many claim that feminism is at fault in the Heard-Depp case. However, the reality is slightly different. Feminism is an ideology which aims to tackle patriarchy and inequality. Therefore, at its core, it does involve standing up for male victims of domestic violence and against the unequal treatment meted out to them. In addition, it also involves standing up against those who use feminism to cover up their crimes and ensure a thriving gender based inequality in society. Besides, Johnny Depp’s victimisation is a failure of the patriarchal society which refuses to believe in the idea that a woman can beat up a man and treats the issue accordingly. We need to remember that domestic abuse is not always physical abuse. It can be sadistic control and/or economic, sexual, emotional and psychological abuse. Heard is simply a bad human being and a terrible example of a feminist. Her actions should not discredit feminism in general and the millions of others who have actually faced domestic violence and are unable to move out of the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are millions of people who live in poverty-stricken areas with no access to help in times of need. Many are unable to find a way out of their deplorable domestic situation and see their abusers face punishment for their actions. Besides, the fear of their partners is sometimes so intense that the victims even end up justifying the violence by claiming it as their own fault. There are also people of celebrity status who have faced such a situation. Case in point: Rihanna, who was assaulted by her ex-boyfriend Chris Brown in 2009. Anyone, anywhere can face abuse at any point of time. It is necessary to fight for these people and to ensure that the domestic violence pandemic sees an end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest issue concerning intimate partner violence is the societal perception surrounding it. The views on domestic violence are largely moulded by religious teachings. Before I go further into this, it is important that I mention here that most religions do not have an absolute consensus on any matter pertaining to their religious teachings across all denominations or sects. However, we can always talk about what the majority believes in. In Islam, many claim that Sharia law encourages domestic violence against women whose husbands suspect ‘nushuz’ (disobedience or disloyalty). Sharia Law forms the basis for the legal system in multiple Islamic nations in the world. Some abusers also cite Bible verses (often Ephesians 5:22) to justify violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in recent times, people have come out in large numbers to speak against this justification of violence on religious grounds. They claim that encouraging domestic violence is nothing more than a misinterpretation or an outdated understanding of the holy books. Contrary to the aforementioned religions, Hinduism primarily preaches non-violence on all fronts. Nevertheless, domestic violence is a common issue in modern Hindu families. The most recurrent reason is the inability of the wife’s family to pay the required dowry. The Dowry Prohibition Act, 1961 was aimed at abolishing the dowry system in India. In spite of these efforts, the giving and taking of dowry continues to be a commonplace practice in marriages in the country and is a major contributor to the violence observed against Indian women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue of domestic violence has been a concern of feminists for a while now and a variety of legislations in recent times have only made their job more difficult. In 2017, Russia came under fire for decriminalising intimate partner violence. The new law, signed by Putin and popularly referred to as the ‘slapping law’, reduced the punishment for counts of domestic violence. The reason behind such a decision was claimed to be a desire to reduce governmental interference in people’s private lives. Soon protests broke out across the country against this law. Some of the activists even noted that a crisis that is, more often than not, shoved under rugs has been thrust into limelight because of the actions of the legislature and an increasing number of people are understanding the gravity of the situation. However, as a consequence of the law, a surge in the number of cases of domestic battery was noticed. Besides Russia, there are many other countries which do not provide any legal protection to the victims of domestic abuse. In fact, several cultures fail to even view intimate partner violence as a crime and as an issue that needs to be discussed at length.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In India, the internalised acceptance of domestic violence is at a dangerous high. In addition to this, the act of slapping a woman has been romanticised to such an extent in the country that people view it as symbolic of love and care. In 2019, a Bollywood movie, titled &lt;em&gt;Kabir Singh&lt;/em&gt; was heavily criticised for its glorification of toxic relationships and abusive partners. In spite of this, the film went on to earn a whopping ₹3.8 billion. This is a clear indication of the fact that the majority of the public did not find an issue with the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On February 28, 2020, another movie titled &lt;em&gt;Thappad&lt;/em&gt; was released in India. The story follows a woman who is seeking divorce from her husband. Her reason, however, is not the conventional disloyalty. It is violence. Her husband slaps her at a party in front of a crowd and is unapologetic about it later. This act drives the woman to her decision. In her journey, she is faced with comments like “thoda bardasht karna sikhna chahiye auraton ko” (“women should learn to tolerate”) and “itni si baat?” (“such a tiny reason?”) over and over again. This movie was widely appreciated by feminists across the country. The IMDb rating of &lt;em&gt;Thappad&lt;/em&gt;, however, shows a marked difference between how men have rated it compared to women. The low ratings from men is an indication of the fact that many of the men in society disagree with the concept; for them domestic violence is justifiable. On the other hand, a higher rating from most women is an encouraging indication that the realisation of domestic violence being an unjustifiable act has finally started sinking in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is abundantly clear that the crisis of domestic violence is not limited to the times of pandemics, financial crises or natural disasters. It is a never-ending issue. Many people across the globe continue to refuse to acknowledge it as a heinous crime in the first place. This severely hampers the capacity to tackle the situation. For now, we can only hope that the increasing awareness among the people can one day result in an escalation in the number of protests and understanding among people, with the outcome of a safer world.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Domestic violence is among the most common forms of crime. Very often, it is not even seen as a serious issue in various countries. Diverse cultures around the world have normalised intimate partner violence and some even encourage it in certain scenarios. The lack of proper action against perpetrators has left millions of victims around the globe hopeless, and the number of cases keeps rising every year. In the absence of effective preventive measures and relief facilities, the matter can only be expected to get worse as the years pass by.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Dear Pandemic Diary</title>
      <link href="/Dear-Pandemic-Diary" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Dear Pandemic Diary" />
      <published>2020-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Dear-Pandemic-Diary</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Dear-Pandemic-Diary">&lt;p&gt;Last time I was here, I was asking if you would like that Corona (the beer, folks) with lime or without, today, I might take a dozen bottles with or without you. I apologise in advance; this may seem like an untoward journal entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the pandemic is upon us, and God, is it upon us - I wonder to myself, is this regression to teen years going to bring me down, or the virus? While I don’t have to wake up at 5 am, listen to VH1 till 6:30 and move to school by 6:40 anymore, I have to deal with chaos that nobody ever told me about. No school lessons taught me how to be home and keep sane; hiding under the table definitely doesn’t work. Crisis intervention only tells me so much that I might truly have to be infected in order to utilise my knowledge. I wish I could run back to my 3rd grade moral lessons and really be the person that they proposed we be - the sane, calm, adjusted one that obviously had nothing but respect and compassion for everyone. It would make life easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we speak of the pandemic, many don’t realise that while the certainty of having the virus is difficult to deal with (and that may as well be an understatement), the uncertainty it brings with itself is the silent killer that may lead us to a Noah’s Ark situation. The aforementioned teen regression that I speak of? Well, people my age and around my age have had to come back home from being away for college or their respective jobs plainly because, “better be sick with family than without.” And people who were home already, have lost their autonomy and are back to being home with the ‘others’ deciding what is to be done. My teenage hormones, albeit crazy, perhaps, were the only thing that led me to the slightly retained sanity I used to encompass, till, well, a few days ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having reread that paragraph, I understand if I might sound ungrateful, believe me, I’m not. I assure you, I’m aware of my privilege of being safe and healthy, of having resources to maintain that, of being able to share my thoughts and being able to help myself and others while I’m at it. I suppose all I’m trying to suggest here is how while ‘inside and isolated’ may drive us crazy, figuratively speaking - doing both while you’re in a toxic household or with someone who may be riddled with their own issues - may, literally speaking, make you crazy. Personally, having had to deal with a symptomatic-to-hypochondriac mother has been driving me up the walls, the paranoia that surfaces is so strong, that any denial will be harshly rejected, and that’s my reality to live with now. Upon asking my near and dear ones, I’m now able to recount several cases of unhealthy relationships, malfunctioning behaviour and what one may call unsettling dependency. My sample is too small, and perhaps not as generalisable - I mean it is, after all, purposive and convenient (Okay, I’m going to stop now). But, what may be concluded is that there’s a danger lurking, and we’re not aware of it or, well, not wanting to be aware of it. May as well dump it in that subconscious, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The curse on mental health that social isolation is, is not unknown; there are plenty of people with flared anxieties or triggered depression - and then, there are people who may not even be aware of what they’re going through and end up more hurt than ever. As a future mental health professional, I can sit here and count out hundreds of flaws in self-isolation and social distancing, but the science behind it is not unknown and it definitely is better of the two evils. I can’t give an informed solution, as someone once told me: mental health is like fingerprints, different for everybody (and definitely, incriminating!). I only ask everyone to be more receptive to the idea of keeping your thoughts open and look for more sources of help (and try to be one, too).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were to intimate yourself with my thoughts - I don’t suppose the fear of COVID-19 is as high as having to figure out how to placate my mother, submit two assignments and attend 3 classes and write 2 research papers, while simultaneously completing my to-dos of ‘productive work during quarantine.’ Every time I watch the news, I worry that maybe the numbers that rise up everyday are just becoming statistics to me and my brain, and my empathy and fear will be drained out by my need to do chores and completing tasks and just proving that I’m ‘productive’. Or perhaps, it’s the other way round, maybe that is good, denial till faced with the issue - a (good?) coping mechanism. I wouldn’t know; if you do please, page me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only think of today as possibly weighed by my worries and the silliness that pertains to “whoa, today was busy”. Maybe, you can do one better and ask your near and dear ones how their day was. And yourself, it’s important that you ask yourself about your day. My day was mopping, Humanism and the utter joy followed after finding recent, high Impact Factor research papers. Well, it’s yet to be over, but you know I’ll keep you posted.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Last time I was here, I was asking if you would like that Corona (the beer, folks) with lime or without, today, I might take a dozen bottles with or without you. I apologise in advance; this may seem like an untoward journal entry.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Japan: Testing the Limits of Pandemic Economics</title>
      <link href="/Testing-the-Limits-of-Pandemic-Economics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Japan: Testing the Limits of Pandemic Economics" />
      <published>2020-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Testing-the-Limits-of-Pandemic-Economics</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Testing-the-Limits-of-Pandemic-Economics">&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus has brought the entire world economy down to its knees, gasping for a breath of fresh air, production cycles all around the world have come to a halt, supply chains disrupted, and many businesses are on the brink of a shutdown. Social distancing is the measure being adopted throughout the world to reduce the spread of this disease leading to the imposition of total lockdowns in various countries, be it a developed or an underdeveloped nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One developed nation facing the brunt of the virus is Japan, which is actually trying to cushion the impact the virus is having by declaring a state of emergency. However, it seems like the end of the tunnel is near for Japan and that the government has already planned to launch a multipronged economic stimulus package to restart the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The package has been announced in two phases with a value of ¥117 trillion (translating to about $1.1 trillion), which is about 20% of Japan’s GDP, to expand cash payouts to its citizens as the virus threatens to push the world’s third-largest economy into depression. Japan will sell additional bonds worth more than ¥18 trillion to fund the package, adding to its huge debt which is almost 257% of its GDP. However, since the debt is owed to itself, there is little chance of a debt crisis. According to the Japanese Economic Minister, Yasutoshi Nishimura, the economic package is set to boost the real Japanese GDP by 4.4%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first phase of the package aims to curb job losses and bankruptcies, while the second round of aid, after the virus is contained, will try to support a V-shaped economic recovery; wherein even after suffering a sharp recession, the economic stimulus will be able to support the economy on the steep curve to recovery. The package is designed to give more than ¥6 trillion in cash payouts to households and small businesses and ¥26 trillion to allow deferred social security and tax payments. Apart from this, the government announced an increase in direct fiscal spending amounting to a whopping ¥39 trillion to help the economy get back on its feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Japan is planning to distribute ¥300,000 to lower-income households that have lost their livelihoods due to the virus along with households with children. Moreover, the government has encouraged businesses to keep workers on their payroll and has also proposed subsidies for the same. Additionally, it has offered to defer income and regional tax payments for a year for virus-hit companies, which has led to multiple small businesses reducing their property taxes to near zero. Furthermore, the government has offered emergency loans for those facing wage cuts or job losses due to a virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China, the home ground of the virus, has been facing global backlash due to the inefficient measures to contain the virus’ spread. As is known, most MNCs have set up production facilities in China owing to the low-cost of production in the country. This is also the case with Japanese companies, however, as a part of its economic package, the Japanese government has announced $2.2 billion to help its companies to shift their manufacturing units out of China, accommodating both the shift to Japan and other countries in the world. The Japanese government intends to shift all high value production to Japan and to diversify production across South East Asia. The world has indeed realised the consequences of depending on one country too much. This is a change we can expect to see in the post lockdown world when instead of concentrating production in one country, the global economy will move on to having diverse models to prevent complete disruption of production cycles (like this one) in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impact on the Japanese economy has been severe with the pandemic slowing down the economy of China, followed by that of the US, two of Japan’s largest trading partners. Anyhow, the Japanese government’s stimulus package might not be successful. The small businesses are disappointed at the size of the package to mitigate the economic fallout due to the virus, they say that not only is it insufficient, it might also be a little too late. The Reuters Corporate Survey found 46% of firms felt the government’s stimulus was somewhat not enough and 29% deemed it quite insufficient, keeping Abe’s government under pressure to top-up last week’s spending package. While 5% said it was too much, just 21% said it was sufficient and appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The poll indicates how not only the amounts are insufficient but the measures are too, people ask for bolder steps like sales tax cuts for small businesses apart from the very insufficient cash payouts. The companies demand higher public spending and more support for financing. While the package might superficially seem enough, when one delves deeper into the public opinion, we find how the package is actually insufficient and unsatisfying. However, the question is if the world’s most indebted country can afford to increase its spending in a bid to stimulate the economy?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kashish Jindal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Coronavirus has brought the entire world economy down to its knees, gasping for a breath of fresh air, production cycles all around the world have come to a halt, supply chains disrupted, and many businesses are on the brink of a shutdown. Social distancing is the measure being adopted throughout the world to reduce the spread of this disease leading to the imposition of total lockdowns in various countries, be it a developed or an underdeveloped nation. One developed nation facing the brunt of the virus is Japan, which is actually trying to cushion the impact the virus is having by declaring a state of emergency. However, it seems like the end of the tunnel is near for Japan and that the government has already planned to launch a multipronged economic stimulus package to restart the economy. The package has been announced in two phases with a value of ¥117 trillion (translating to about $1.1 trillion), which is about 20% of Japan’s GDP, to expand cash payouts to its citizens as the virus threatens to push the world’s third-largest economy into depression. Japan will sell additional bonds worth more than ¥18 trillion to fund the package, adding to its huge debt which is almost 257% of its GDP. However, since the debt is owed to itself, there is little chance of a debt crisis. According to the Japanese Economic Minister, Yasutoshi Nishimura, the economic package is set to boost the real Japanese GDP by 4.4%.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">An Insight into the World’s Favourite Hermit State</title>
      <link href="/Hermit-State" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Insight into the World’s Favourite Hermit State" />
      <published>2020-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Hermit-State</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Hermit-State">&lt;p&gt;A K-Drama that I was watching recently revolved around a North Korean soldier. The drama was great, but what stayed with me post bingeing it was the intrigue for North Korea: a country that calls itself the greatest nation in the world while its people suffer from the worst human rights violations; a country that calls itself a democracy with a 100% voter turnout in any election but has the world’s most authoritarian regime; a country built on the ideology of ‘self-reliance’ but heavily dependent on aid from the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On typing ‘North Korea’ in the search bar on Google, you note that the search results are dominated by nuclear weapons and North Korea’s relationship with the US and South Korea. Most of the articles paint them as enemies. However, this is where the problem lies - we equate the North Korean people with its government. While the leader and the high-ranking officials propagate an ideology and a culture that benefits them, the common man bears it. This is a country where there is no scope for upward mobility. Defecting is the only way that allows them the taste of a better life. However, in doing so, they are exposed to the racist world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian Myers notes that an international network on Google Earth is working on identifying structures visible in aerial photographs in North Korea. Yet, the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea (DPRK) remains a mystery to many. He attributes this to people’s view of DPRK via the lens of economics and nuclear weapons, and not via its propaganda and people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korea is effectively a totalitarian state run by a dynastic line of dictators. Its cultural and political ideology is based on devotion to leader Kim Il-Sung, whose eternal Presidential authority is written into the Constitution. Three branches constitute the government– executive, legislative and judiciary. The Premier and the Supreme Leader (Kim Jong-un) control the executive branch. The legislative branch is a congress, called the Supreme People’s Assembly, occupied by unopposed candidates from the Workers’ Party of Korea. They, however, rarely meet and have historically passed nearly all proposed laws without debate. The judicial branch is known for secretive trials headed by judges appointed by the SPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a gulag posing as a nation. Everything there is about the great leader: books, newspaper articles, songs and TV programs. The flowers are named after him, and mountains are carved with his slogans. In line with this, only ‘state-approved’ content is produced, as books, newspaper articles, songs and TV programs are all censored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korea calls itself a communist country, which it is not, it is also not the last bastion of Confucian patriarchy, as they often characterise it. Rather, it’s guided by a paranoid ideology of race-based nationalism, holding that Koreans are purer than all others. In his book, &lt;em&gt;The Cleanest Race: How North Koreans See Themselves and Why It Matters&lt;/em&gt;, Brian Myers notes that the nation’s race-based ideology has its roots in Japanese fascism. He states the government’s criteria for national identity paints its citizens as innocent and morally virtuous but militarily weak. Thus, they require Kim Il-Sung’s guidance and protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The country harbours a population of 25 million, with a low rate of population growth. The population of this ‘mighty’ and ‘prosperous’ is starving. The Soviet Union originally supported North Korea. However, the collapse of the USSR led to DPRK not receiving aid, making food production plummet in the early 1990’s. This, coupled with natural disasters, led to the infamous 1990 famine. In the years since, aid from the US and other countries has helped improve the situation. However, most North Koreans still don’t have access to food with necessary nutrients, subsiding on crops like rice, cabbages, and radish. In poorer regions, boiled grass and ground tree bark serve as food alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korean society is based on a social caste system called–‘songbun’, used to allocate government assistance like housing and rations. The loyalty to the North Korean government is the key factor in determining the ranks of the people, and any real or perceived slight against the government can lead to the demotion of an entire family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With no source of outside information, the North Koreans have been ignorant. And in this ignorance lies their safety. It’s a common myth that everyone in North Korea is brainwashed. A considerable number of people are brainwashed, as many committed suicides after the death of Kim Il-Sung as they didn’t know what to do without their leader. But the majority knows the nation is not as prosperous as it shows itself to be and thus, have defected. The fear of punishment has motivated the supposed admiration of the Supreme Leader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Juche’ ideology has shaped the lifestyle of these people. Every household in North Korea is supposed to display the portraits of the eternal leaders, Kim Il-Sung and Kim Jong-Il. There are strict rules and fines associated with dusting the pictures regularly, and their placement for maximum respect. As a symbol of the North Korean identity, all citizens wear a red lapel pin with portraits of the eternal leaders on themselves 24/7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korea observes an 11-year school for the children. In the formative years, the children are taught the legends of their eternal leader. Subjects like Science and Mathematics are paid less attention compared to North Korean history. Many defectors note that growing up they were taught to believe their great leader was a god working tirelessly for their benefit. The idea of their leader being a god was so deeply entrenched that they used to think he could even hear their thoughts, making them afraid of even thinking negatively about the eternal leader. The students have been simply told what to think, and they obey. In their world, critical thinking isn’t allowed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 10 and a 3-year military enlistment is compulsory for all men and women, respectively, after they’ve completed their high school. The government assigns jobs to its people, based on industry needs and location, which they’re supposed to do without fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government claims to provide free healthcare to all its citizens. However, reports say it spends less per citizen than almost any other country in the world. The country has a low standard of care, with nearly all regions suffering shortages of medical equipment and medication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public executions are also a common practice in the world’s favourite hermit state. In fact, too common. A defector revealed that her mother was publicly executed for watching a Hollywood movie. It is mandatory for every North Korean, 12 and above, to witness the public execution. Only the Great Leader has absolute human rights; all others are his vassals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way of escaping this regime, other than taking the government’s permission, is by defecting and illegally crossing the border. The most common strategy is to cross the border in northeast China before fleeing to a third country. This third country generally becomes South Korea, the country that is supposed to be their enemy, welcomes them with open arms. If, however, the defectors are caught in China; they are deported back where they often face harsh interrogations and years of punishment or even death in political prison camps. Post the 1990 famine, the number of defectors increased owing to the poor conditions. The number of defectors since then has only been increasing, the reason now being–freedom. To deal with this increase, the DPRK government now punishes 3 generations of the family, if even one member defects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the larger question remains—how does such a country still exist in the 21st century? We can attribute two major reasons for this. First, every conversation in North Korea is overheard, and the propagation of any ideology against the nation leads to immediate persecution. There is also a travel ban in North Korea with permission required from the government for even inter-state transport, hindering collectivisation. The fear of torture and starvation for their entire family has become a deterrent that has forced people to simply follow the government without dissent. Second, if North Korea falls, it will create a massive humanitarian and refugee crisis, a civil war, an insurgency that could have nuclear weapons and a state divided between the ideological difference of South Korea and China. Because of the looming threat of these scenarios, no country has ever done anything more than sanctioning North Korea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future in North Korea seems bleak. In an isolated world, these people are simply getting by each day trying to survive. However, amidst the tyranny, the people have created a world for themselves where they support one another. Many defectors note that while the country was poor, and the people were starving, but, they were warm to one another and cared for each other. Unlike its southern counterpart, where capitalism has induced stress and chasing materialistic needs, the Northern peninsula maintains a lifestyle where they are content even if they’re getting a small surplus. The more well off a person is, the more stressed out they are for instead of thinking about survival, they have time to overthink.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A K-Drama that I was watching recently revolved around a North Korean soldier. The drama was great, but what stayed with me post bingeing it was the intrigue for North Korea: a country that calls itself the greatest nation in the world while its people suffer from the worst human rights violations; a country that calls itself a democracy with a 100% voter turnout in any election but has the world’s most authoritarian regime; a country built on the ideology of ‘self-reliance’ but heavily dependent on aid from the international community.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Story of Easter</title>
      <link href="/The-Story-of-Easter" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Story of Easter" />
      <published>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Story-of%20Easter</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Story-of-Easter">&lt;p&gt;Everyone has a worldview. This might seem like a controversial assumption, given that many would deny having any concrete belief system of sorts, but I think the claim is warranted. No one truly acts neutrally – however implicitly, they have beliefs and assumptions that drive their day-to-day actions. These assumptions might be unnoticed even by the ones who hold to them, but they are there, working subtly behind the shadows. There might be someone, for example, who says he is disinterested in philosophy and religion, but if he lives in a secular godless manner, then you know that he is living as if God does not exist – and if he is living as if God does not exist, then clearly he has a belief, deep down in his subconscious, that the idea of God is not worth taking seriously, or, at the very least, that there is no good reason to live as if God does exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, everyone has a worldview, a lens through which he/she views the world, however implicit this worldview might be. And every worldview is, ultimately, a story. I don’t mean this in a condescending manner – stories can be true! My mother used to tell me stories about my childhood, and I have no doubt concerning the sincerity of her testimony. In fact, it is stories that drive our world. Everyone has their own story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I write this on the twelfth of April, 2020. It is a Sunday, it is Easter. And what better to write on this occasion than to simply tell the story of Easter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our world is a strange, dark and forsaken world. Even in the midst of apparent joy, there is deep and real suffering. Even the ancient Indian prince Siddhartha could not help but realise that the world was filled with pain and anguish. And this realisation was so shocking and heart-wrenching for him that, as the legend goes, he forsook all royalty in search for the enlightenment that he believed would reveal to him the secret of joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things haven’t changed much. In fact, today’s world is filled with Siddharthas, desperate to discover the secret of happiness. Every advertisement you have ever seen, every product you have been keen to buy, every place you have wanted to visit, every prize you have been ambitious to win – in other words, everything you have ever done, you have done it in the hope that what you are about to do will finally bring you the joy and peace that your heart desires – or at the very least, will increase the joy that you already have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet, here you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I too was a lot like Siddhartha. In fact, my mother wanted to name me Siddhartha, but ultimately decided against it for fear that I would ultimately become a monk. But against all hope, as it turned out, I did have a very ‘monastic’ spirit, even early on. From very early on in my life, I have been searching for answers – answers to the big questions of life. Why am I here? What is my purpose? Why does this world exist? Where am I going?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: what does it all mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thirst to discover these answers eventually became like a madness, like an obsession that had wormed itself deep into my psyche. I’m certain I was the only person in seventh grade who did not know how to play cricket, but who had, in fact, read the entire Bhagavad Gita cover to cover. I was the only kid in high school who was not a Muslim but who wanted to carry the Qur’an with him to read during the tiffin break. I was, in other words, probably exactly the kind of person my mother had initially dreaded I would become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most people, I sought for something that would give purpose to my life: religion, politics, worldly success as a writer or an actor were high on the list. And yet, the questions remained. At one point in my life, I even contemplated raw, naked materialist atheism. I started reading atheist literature and was initially greatly impressed by the force of the rhetoric. Richard Dawkins, in particular, was a crucial influence. There he stood, marshalling all the powers of reason and science in an intellectual assault upon all forms of religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, for a while, it seemed the candle had been blown out. There was no god. There was no purpose. There was no meaning to anything. There was no good, there was no evil – there was simply matter, endlessly morphing. As Christopher Hitchens wrote, “To the dumb question, ‘Why me?’ the cosmos barely bothers to return the reply: why not?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The atheist ‘enlightenment’ informed me that, at best, I was an accident. I didn’t have to be here, but I was. And I would one day flicker out of existence. I came into being for no reason, and eventually, I would perish for no reason. And all my precious joys, passions, loves, desires, ambitions, fears and sorrows would perish with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the worldview which the atheists presented to me, death was more real than life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was then that I encountered a person who completely changed my life. His name was Dr William Lane Craig. An academic philosopher of religion and a deeply Christian soul, he was a man who had debated leading atheists at universities around the world. He had faced off against big names like Lawrence Krauss, Dan Barker, Sam Harris, Peter Atkins and a whole host of other atheist heavyweights. And with him, for the first time, I saw someone who was able to give a clear and intellectually compelling case in favour of theism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, as I studied more, I came to realise that most militant atheism was more motivated by anger against religion than any careful consideration of the question of whether or not God exists. Many of the arguments atheists had been putting forward, I realised, were extremely poor and shabby, often based upon misunderstandings and caricatures of Christian arguments and theology. And some of the leading atheists like Lawrence Krauss seemed unwilling to even consider the possibility of there being a God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than overthrowing dogmas, at times it seemed that the atheists were championing new dogmas – dogmas based less upon careful intellectual thought and more upon prejudice and hatred for a particular social order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I identify not as an atheist, but as a convinced believer in Jesus Christ. I believe in Jesus – and, even more unthinkably, in the Catholic Church - because I believe Christianity – and Catholicism – are true. And I believe the story of Christianity, which is really the story of Easter, can truly change people’s lives for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bible opens with a very grand and simple line: In the beginning, God created the heavens and earth. In the Biblical worldview, God is the reason why this universe exists. God created us, and we exist because of Him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Bible also tells us that human beings sinned. Though we were originally created holy and good, we turned against God and rebelled against Him. All the evil that exists in the world is merely the outworking of man’s original sin. And the bad news is that none of us is innocent, because we have all participated in this unholy work of sin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the good news that Christianity brings is the proclamation that God did not abandon us. On the contrary, He descended from heaven and became one of us. He shared in our misery, our suffering, our loneliness, our pain and our anguish. But He did not share in our sins. He was crucified by men who hated His claims, but as He was dying on the Cross, He offered His life as a sacrifice – to atone for the sins of man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the powers of evil gathered together and climaxed on the Cross of Jesus 2,000 years ago… because there was no sin more grotesque than the murder of God’s only Son.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in the Christian worldview, death did not have the last word. On the contrary, Jesus Christ rose from the dead, physically, bodily, on the third day, triumphing over the powers of sin and death. Though men murdered Him, death could not hold Him, because He had committed no sin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who hold to materialist dogma will scoff at this idea. For countless souls, miracles and resurrections are the stuff of legend. They cannot happen and do not happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you doubt the Resurrection, then I highly recommend you to take the time to study it, historically. The Oxford atheist philosopher (and later convert to theism, though not to Christianity) Antony Flew admitted in his debate with the historian Gary Habermas that the Resurrection of Jesus had better evidence than claimed miracles in any other religion. I think he is right in this. The Gospels, after all, are not myths written centuries after the time of Jesus, but rather are biographical accounts that can, more or less, all be traced back to the first century. Though written by various authors, they all testify that Jesus rose bodily from the dead. It is the same with the letters of Paul of Tarsus, an anti-Christian Jew who was later converted after seeing a vision of the resurrected Jesus. His letter to the Galatians contains a moving testimony of his conversion, and his story is corroborated by the Book of Acts, written by a man named Luke. These documents I speak of are not fabrications, but rather the writings of real people, who lived at specific times in history, and whose biographical and at times autobiographical claims largely corroborate each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my mind, the Resurrection of Jesus is the single most extraordinary event of human history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I invite you – whoever you may be – to consider the claims of Christianity for yourself. You have nothing at all to lose. If Christianity is true, then you have everything to gain from discovering its truthfulness. But if it’s false, then a careful study will only reveal its falsity, because the truth cannot ultimately be hidden. Either way, you will increase your knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What convinced me was the intellectual arguments in favour of God’s existence, the extraordinary testimony of the resurrection of Jesus, the fulfilled prophecies of the Old Testament, the beauty and power of the very words of the Saviour, and, of course, my personal experience of grace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you might have questions, and you might want to learn more. If this is so, I rejoice in this, and I encourage you wholeheartedly to follow the truth wherever it leads. A good place to start is the YouTube channel Capturing Christianity, which regularly hosts discussions between Christian and atheist intellectuals and scholars. Bishop Robert Barron’s book &lt;em&gt;Catholicism: A Journey to the Heart of the Faith&lt;/em&gt; is also a great place to start. I also highly recommend the work of Edward Feser, an atheist philosopher whose studies in the philosophy of religion and mind eventually led him to convert to Christianity – I especially commend his book &lt;em&gt;Five Proofs of the Existence of God&lt;/em&gt;, which, in my mind, is the best intellectual and reasoned defence of classical theism that has been made in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all, I urge you to take the time out and read the New Testament, which is a collection of these ancient historical writings that testify to the life and works of Jesus of Nazareth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that there are people who will read this article of mine and laugh. Why then do I write? Why then do I spend so much time telling people about a man who lived 2,000 years ago, a man I have never met in person?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I believe this man is no mere man, but rather the incarnate Son of God. I write because this Man has changed my life, and He can change yours as well, if only you allow Him. And if you do, you will come to possess a joy that the world cannot give.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Telling people about the amazing person that is Jesus is worth any sacrifice and any cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the faith that has inspired millions, that has shaken empires, that has changed the course of human history. This is the faith of the martyrs, the confessors and the saints of the Cross. And this is the audacity with which I can stare death in the eye and proclaim that Christ is risen and that He lives forever more.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Everyone has a worldview. This might seem like a controversial assumption, given that many would deny having any concrete belief system of sorts, but I think the claim is warranted. No one truly acts neutrally – however implicitly, they have beliefs and assumptions that drive their day-to-day actions. These assumptions might be unnoticed even by the ones who hold to them, but they are there, working subtly behind the shadows. There might be someone, for example, who says he is disinterested in philosophy and religion, but if he lives in a secular godless manner, then you know that he is living as if God does not exist – and if he is living as if God does not exist, then clearly he has a belief, deep down in his subconscious, that the idea of God is not worth taking seriously, or, at the very least, that there is no good reason to live as if God does exist.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Neighborhood Friendly Taliban</title>
      <link href="/A-Neighborhood-Friendly-Taliban" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Neighborhood Friendly Taliban" />
      <published>2020-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Neighborhood-Friendly-Taliban</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Neighborhood-Friendly-Taliban">&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the US-Taliban peace deal, India’s situation can be very well described as the child whose older sibling just graduated high school. While the US may as well be India’s proverbial big brother, Taliban is the horrific high school experience that India will have to wade through all alone. And this experience is only worsened by the degenerating political and social environment of Afghanistan. The country is currently oscillating between Ashraf Ghani, the alleged winner of the Presidential election and Abdullah Abdullah, the self-declared winner of the same, while the US refuses to overtly acknowledge either as the President. For a country that has always depended upon America to ‘help’ them out, President Trump not congratulating his long term friend Mr. Ghani on his reelection is certainly grave. Additionally, a wobbly and conflicted team responsible for Intra-Afghan peace talks, amidst the Taliban assiduously violating its promise of maintaining peace, is the icing on the disastrous US-baked peace deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The catalyst for the aforementioned sad tale, the US-Taliban peace accord, signed February 29, 2020 holds the US time-bound to remove its troops within the decided 14-month time period, but not the Taliban to keep its promises. The removal of UN sanctions under the peace deal further weakens any leverage that the US might hold in Afghanistan. With the removal of the US-Troops, and a burgeoning Taliban influence, the people of Afghanistan have a bleak future to look forward to, and India, perhaps not as worse off, is definitely in the line of fire.s&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No individual who has ever witnessed an India-Pakistan cricket match can be ignorant of the 70-year old festering wound between the two countries. The unceasing tussle for power between the two countries and Pakistan’s inclination towards providing refuge to terrorist organisations as a way to one-up India is not a secret. And, consequently, Pakistan’s close friendship with and ideological alikeness to the Taliban is the primary impetus to the threat to India’s security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pakistan has been responsible for harbouring prominent terrorist organisations such as JeM and LeT on its territory and providing them protection after attacks on India. While Taliban promises not to allow Al-Qaeda in Afghanistan, the aforementioned organisations have been left out of the deal, allowing these terrorist organisations the opportunity to garner support and refuge in Afghanistan as well. Pakistan was a staunch supporter of having the Taliban as an active participant in the 2001 Bonn Agreement which was intended to establish an Afghani government after the Taliban’s removal. Furthermore, Pakistan’s support of a Taliban-led government in Afghanistan only makes Pakistan dearer to them. Juxtaposed with India’s past dealings (or lack thereof) with Taliban, India is likely to find itself in an ‘enemy of my friend’ situation. India has historically vehemently refused to acknowledge the Taliban as anything other than a terrorist organisation and has always supported the Afghanistan government. On a quest to counter Pakistani influence in Afghanistan, India has spent considerable time, money and effort to build a trusting relationship with the Afghan government through its multiple development and infrastructure projects, posing them as a direct adversary to the Taliban. And now that the Afghan government is itself in a precarious position, India’s assurance of relative peace on the India-Afghanistan border is dwindling and its efforts conclude to be naught.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another facet of this predicament is the apparent and sudden benevolence shown by the US to Pakistan. Pakistan has been a key player in bringing the Taliban to the table long enough for a peace accord to be established. And considering that President Trump’s re-election campaign is contingent on him bringing the American troops back, he currently considers Pakistan to be in his good books. Hence, Pakistan finds itself in a far more favourable position to cause considerable damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the US is by association to the Taliban making deals with the Haqqani network as well. The Haqqani network is a recognised terrorist organisation, which was also responsible for the attack on the Indian embassy in Kabul in 2008. Hence, America is giving legitimacy and validation to a terrorist group which has posed a threat to India in the past. This legitimisation and validation by a country that India considers to be an ally is only an affirmation of the USA’s indifference to any more peace violations by the Taliban in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding to this, the instability currently in India over the abrogation of Article 370 in Kashmir and the mass unrest and chaos due to the CAA/NRC protests, India finds itself in a pernicious position. The Al-Qaeda and the Haqqani network have made attempts and calls to fight India on the issue of Kashmir and on behalf of Pakistan. With the newly-minted support in Afghanistan and far more freedom once US-troops leave, India will have its hands full dealing with them. Much like Afghanistan, India’s dependence upon the US troops to fight a war not their own proves to be its Achilles heel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If one was to consider the possibility of India stepping up to protect its borders, it doesn’t seem improbable, however, it is the approach that remains to be seen. India could increase border security, employ more force and troops, it can hope for the peace accord to hold and pray that the Taliban does not establish a government and Pakistan does not use this to its advantage to attempt an ambush. Or perhaps, less likely and more smartly, India can continue to build and facilitate growth and development projects in Afghanistan, making India a friend to anyone in authority, very much like it did with the previous Ghani-led government. One cannot tell for sure what the currently-ruling BJP government will do, and keeping in mind their almost negligible previous response to the peace accord, we can only hope for some undertaking. The consequences of the deal may not be apparent right now especially when currently, the COVID-19 pandemic takes precedence, as it should, yet it will not always be so and India must be ready with a water-proof plan for when the time comes.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">When it comes to the US-Taliban peace deal, India’s situation can be very well described as the child whose older sibling just graduated high school. While the US may as well be India’s proverbial big brother, Taliban is the horrific high school experience that India will have to wade through all alone. And this experience is only worsened by the degenerating political and social environment of Afghanistan. The country is currently oscillating between Ashraf Ghani, the alleged winner of the Presidential election and Abdullah Abdullah, the self-declared winner of the same, while the US refuses to overtly acknowledge either as the President. For a country that has always depended upon America to ‘help’ them out, President Trump not congratulating his long term friend Mr. Ghani on his reelection is certainly grave. Additionally, a wobbly and conflicted team responsible for Intra-Afghan peace talks, amidst the Taliban assiduously violating its promise of maintaining peace, is the icing on the disastrous US-baked peace deal.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
