<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/trending/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-11-16T19:20:53+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/trending/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">An Investor’s Déjà Vu</title>
      <link href="/An-Investor-s-D-j-Vu" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Investor’s Déjà Vu" />
      <published>2020-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/An-Investor-s-D-j-Vu</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/An-Investor-s-D-j-Vu">&lt;p&gt;Picture this, you’re having a conversation with your parents while opening the refrigerator door. You extend your hand towards the half-eaten chocolate and in a moment of suddenness, it seems you’ve already done this before. But you can’t seem to remember when. That, my friend, is &lt;em&gt;déjà vu&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picture another scenario. Say you’re reading the newspaper this time and the S&amp;amp;P index has dipped more than the usual. You think you’ve been here before, except this time, you exactly remember when: 2008. Your memory is bitter about the experience because the last time it happened, it didn’t bode well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 2008 Debacle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone with a rough idea of the 2008 housing bubble would know that it wasn’t pretty. To quote &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/a-guide-to-the-financial-crisis--10-years-later/2018/09/10/114b76ba-af10-11e8-a20b-5f4f84429666_story.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Moody’s&lt;/a&gt;, “&lt;em&gt;The stock market plummeted, wiping out nearly $8 trillion in value between late 2007 and 2009. Unemployment climbed, peaking at 10 percent in October 2009. Americans lost $9.8 trillion in wealth&lt;/em&gt;”.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, just like the human mood, changes in the stock market come in waves. Where there is a low, there is a high. Thus, it’s no wonder that the stock market made a comeback: the home prices rebounded and the employment rate ticked upward. But unfortunately, the story doesn’t end here. Here’s the catch: the market may forget, but the human cannot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stocks have more than doubled since the financial crisis, and yet, a lot of investors have remarkably tweaked down their equity exposure. (For some context, equity is that part of your investment portfolio which leans towards risk. The same is compensated by the possibility of higher returns). Sounds weird, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The vast majority of people have some equity holdings in their 401(k) plans&lt;/em&gt;”, said &lt;a href=&quot;https://in.reuters.com/article/us-usa-stocks-retailinvestors/insight-mom-and-pop-investors-miss-out-on-stock-market-gains-idUSBRE88T0AE20120930&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Brian Reid&lt;/a&gt;, Chief Economist at the Investment Company Institute (ICI), but fewer are willing to take above-average or substantial risk than they were in 2008 before the market plummeted.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent Cogent Research report found that risk aversion among all age groups has been on the rise since 2006, including Generation X and Y, who have lived through a number of market collapses. To simplify, investors have become more risk-averse since the 2008 financial crisis. But why?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Déjà Vu&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, the ramifications of a financial crisis are more profound than we think: they perpetuate biases. The underlying bias observed here is called ‘Experiential Bias’. This occurs when investors' memory of recent events makes them biased or leads them to believe that an event is far more likely to occur again. This culminates in a lot of investors permanently quitting the market or overestimating the impending hardships in a market.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Facing the Music&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warren Buffet once said, “&lt;em&gt;Our favourite holding period is forever&lt;/em&gt;”. According to him, the secret recipe to minting clever money is holding on to stocks, even when their price collapses, for the simple reason that they will bounce back up, over time. But what happens to the investors who left the market at the end of 2008 or early 2009? It wouldn’t take big brains to figure out that they paid a high price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a personal level, quitting the market midway deprives investors of the opportunity of recovering their losses during the recoil. Moreover, reluctance to invest in risky avenues strips you of the prospects of earning fancy rewards. On a larger level, this may also contribute to negative consumer sentiment. Let us see how.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If every second investor hurt by the 2008 crisis exits the stock market, and consciously or subconsciously propels fellow investors to quit too, won’t economic transactions and activity tumble? Sounds unlikely, right? Why would I succumb to and base my decisions on borrowed apprehensions, instead of my own independent analysis? Enter ‘Herd Bias’, yet another fragment of behavioural finance. We’re hard-wired to herd and imitate what other investors are doing. Contrary to traditional beliefs, investors are not invariably rational, they have limits to their self-control and are prone to falling ill to their own biases and fallacies.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say that the aggrieved investor doesn’t quit the market but instead reads every non-average (but normal) dip in S&amp;amp;P or Dow Jones as the onset of something critical. Consequently and gradually, the investor might begin to disinvest (the move is motivated by a fallacy, but is disinvestment nevertheless). If there are sufficient people believing this idea, it is enough to drive the market down. Note that financial markets are driven by popular beliefs, not logical beliefs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too far-fetched, right? It is. But replicate this on a large scale, and voila, you have investor sentiment tipping a slowdown. Those who are still firmly gripped by the ravages of the crisis, have lost all appetite for risk and thus, shirk any and every opportunity that knocks on their doors. They focus on the preservation of capital, not its growth. Sadly though, escapism isn’t the key. Turns out, a no-risk portfolio leaves you financially unprepared.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breaking the Bias&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there might be some empiricism and truth driving such behaviour, one must actively try not to fall prey to his/her own biases. Here is some advice to help you steer through the horrors of the past (and life, generally) and take decisions objectively:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be Reflective: There are two approaches to arriving at investment decisions: Reflexive and Reflective. While the former is the default, automatic gut response to situations, the latter is the logical and methodical one. Even though the reflective approach demands efforts and research, it assists in making informed choices. So step back, dwell over the situation from a bird’s eye view, and then decide.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let Bygones be Bygones: Don’t anchor everything in the present to the traumatic events in your past. If it has happened once, don’t be so sure it will happen again. Learn from your mistakes and let the rest go.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most News is Noise: Don’t believe everything you read and don’t shoehorn every market dip into your past trauma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t Indulge in Peer Pressure: To quote Warren Buffet once again, “&lt;em&gt;The most important quality for an investor is temperament, not intellect. You need a temperament that neither derives great pleasure from being with the crowd or against the crowd&lt;/em&gt;”. You do you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To sum up, ‘Experiential Bias’ is natural. It’s like holding the umbrella when the rains have ceased. You don’t want to let go of it just yet, because it takes more than just time to shake the trauma out. But you know you’ll have to because it’s going to block the sunlight that comes your way.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Eeshita Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Picture this, you’re having a conversation with your parents while opening the refrigerator door. You extend your hand towards the half-eaten chocolate and in a moment of suddenness, it seems you’ve already done this before. But you can’t seem to remember when. That, my friend, is déjà vu.&amp;nbsp; Picture another scenario. Say you’re reading the newspaper this time and the S&amp;amp;P index has dipped more than the usual. You think you’ve been here before, except this time, you exactly remember when: 2008. Your memory is bitter about the experience because the last time it happened, it didn’t bode well.&amp;nbsp; The 2008 Debacle Anyone with a rough idea of the 2008 housing bubble would know that it wasn’t pretty. To quote Moody’s, “The stock market plummeted, wiping out nearly $8 trillion in value between late 2007 and 2009. Unemployment climbed, peaking at 10 percent in October 2009. Americans lost $9.8 trillion in wealth”.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; However, just like the human mood, changes in the stock market come in waves. Where there is a low, there is a high. Thus, it’s no wonder that the stock market made a comeback: the home prices rebounded and the employment rate ticked upward. But unfortunately, the story doesn’t end here. Here’s the catch: the market may forget, but the human cannot. Stocks have more than doubled since the financial crisis, and yet, a lot of investors have remarkably tweaked down their equity exposure. (For some context, equity is that part of your investment portfolio which leans towards risk. The same is compensated by the possibility of higher returns). Sounds weird, right? “The vast majority of people have some equity holdings in their 401(k) plans”, said Brian Reid, Chief Economist at the Investment Company Institute (ICI), but fewer are willing to take above-average or substantial risk than they were in 2008 before the market plummeted.&amp;nbsp; A recent Cogent Research report found that risk aversion among all age groups has been on the rise since 2006, including Generation X and Y, who have lived through a number of market collapses. To simplify, investors have become more risk-averse since the 2008 financial crisis. But why?&amp;nbsp; The Déjà Vu&amp;nbsp; Apparently, the ramifications of a financial crisis are more profound than we think: they perpetuate biases. The underlying bias observed here is called ‘Experiential Bias’. This occurs when investors' memory of recent events makes them biased or leads them to believe that an event is far more likely to occur again. This culminates in a lot of investors permanently quitting the market or overestimating the impending hardships in a market.&amp;nbsp; Facing the Music Warren Buffet once said, “Our favourite holding period is forever”. According to him, the secret recipe to minting clever money is holding on to stocks, even when their price collapses, for the simple reason that they will bounce back up, over time. But what happens to the investors who left the market at the end of 2008 or early 2009? It wouldn’t take big brains to figure out that they paid a high price. On a personal level, quitting the market midway deprives investors of the opportunity of recovering their losses during the recoil. Moreover, reluctance to invest in risky avenues strips you of the prospects of earning fancy rewards. On a larger level, this may also contribute to negative consumer sentiment. Let us see how.&amp;nbsp; If every second investor hurt by the 2008 crisis exits the stock market, and consciously or subconsciously propels fellow investors to quit too, won’t economic transactions and activity tumble? Sounds unlikely, right? Why would I succumb to and base my decisions on borrowed apprehensions, instead of my own independent analysis? Enter ‘Herd Bias’, yet another fragment of behavioural finance. We’re hard-wired to herd and imitate what other investors are doing. Contrary to traditional beliefs, investors are not invariably rational, they have limits to their self-control and are prone to falling ill to their own biases and fallacies.&amp;nbsp; Let’s say that the aggrieved investor doesn’t quit the market but instead reads every non-average (but normal) dip in S&amp;amp;P or Dow Jones as the onset of something critical. Consequently and gradually, the investor might begin to disinvest (the move is motivated by a fallacy, but is disinvestment nevertheless). If there are sufficient people believing this idea, it is enough to drive the market down. Note that financial markets are driven by popular beliefs, not logical beliefs.&amp;nbsp; Too far-fetched, right? It is. But replicate this on a large scale, and voila, you have investor sentiment tipping a slowdown. Those who are still firmly gripped by the ravages of the crisis, have lost all appetite for risk and thus, shirk any and every opportunity that knocks on their doors. They focus on the preservation of capital, not its growth. Sadly though, escapism isn’t the key. Turns out, a no-risk portfolio leaves you financially unprepared.&amp;nbsp; Breaking the Bias While there might be some empiricism and truth driving such behaviour, one must actively try not to fall prey to his/her own biases. Here is some advice to help you steer through the horrors of the past (and life, generally) and take decisions objectively: Be Reflective: There are two approaches to arriving at investment decisions: Reflexive and Reflective. While the former is the default, automatic gut response to situations, the latter is the logical and methodical one. Even though the reflective approach demands efforts and research, it assists in making informed choices. So step back, dwell over the situation from a bird’s eye view, and then decide.&amp;nbsp; Let Bygones be Bygones: Don’t anchor everything in the present to the traumatic events in your past. If it has happened once, don’t be so sure it will happen again. Learn from your mistakes and let the rest go.&amp;nbsp; Most News is Noise: Don’t believe everything you read and don’t shoehorn every market dip into your past trauma. Don’t Indulge in Peer Pressure: To quote Warren Buffet once again, “The most important quality for an investor is temperament, not intellect. You need a temperament that neither derives great pleasure from being with the crowd or against the crowd”. You do you! To sum up, ‘Experiential Bias’ is natural. It’s like holding the umbrella when the rains have ceased. You don’t want to let go of it just yet, because it takes more than just time to shake the trauma out. But you know you’ll have to because it’s going to block the sunlight that comes your way.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Intervention by Sanction</title>
      <link href="/Intervention-by-Sanction" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intervention by Sanction" />
      <published>2020-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Intervention-by-Sanction</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Intervention-by-Sanction">&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump may have railed against certain elements of Republican Party orthodoxy during his run for President in 2016, but his attitude towards Iran came straight from the Republican playbook. He was a staunch critic of the Nuclear Deal signed in 2015, which Iran negotiated with NATO, China and Russia. In a risky move, Trump ordered a drone strike on Iranian General Qasem Soleimani in Baghdad earlier this year. And, in a recent interview with Rush Limbaugh, Trump told the country not to “&lt;em&gt;f*ck around with us&lt;/em&gt;”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The backbone of the Trump administration’s bullish attitude towards the Islamic Republic has been the imposition of trade sanctions. Last week, the President imposed new sanctions on Iran, targeting the country’s financial sector. It wasn’t the first time ‘The Donald’ had tried to cripple the Iranian economy; since he became Commander in Chief in 2017, Trump has strangled foreign trade with the Ayatollah’s family and inner circle, the Iranian Space Agency, and the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sanctions are usually used by the American government against regimes it finds distasteful, but against whom it would be strategically difficult to deploy traditional hard power. Iran fits this description, given that its Twelver Shi’ite government is supported by Russia, and increasingly, China. The idea behind sanctions is to strangle the country’s economy until the governments are forced into negotiation with the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of Iran, the use of sanctions has been a mixed success thus far. Iran’s economy is now one of the least globalised in the world and suffers from stifling rates of inflation. However, the regime in Tehran has not yet returned to negotiations regarding its nuclear programme; it has said it will do so only if the US returns to Obama’s 2015 deal first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Trump’s policy sounds like an acceptable way of dealing with another country, it shouldn’t. The worrying side-note regarding this 'intervention by sanction' approach is that it is likely to do much more than force Iran’s hand over its nuclear programme. When sanctions on the country immiserate its people, a process which is already well underway, the Islamic regime’s days will be numbered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And make no mistake; the collapse of the Iranian government would cause a conflict which would make Syria look like the London Riots. Russia, Saudi Arabia, Turkey and Israel would undoubtedly involve themselves directly, with NATO watching over proceedings from the skies, drones at the ready. Hundreds of thousands of people would die, and many more would overwhelm Europe’s borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is at this point that Trump’s claim to have avoided direct intervention in the Middle East during his first term begins to sound less remarkable. If US sanctions on Iran cause the Twelver regime in Tehran to collapse anyway, resulting in a once-in-a-generation civil and proxy war, then the knowledge that American troops didn’t intervene directly in such a conflict wouldn’t provide much solace for the rest of us. Europe would likely live with the fallout of such a war for decades, whilst the Trumpies in Washington would score a political victory by claiming to have kept their boys out of the firing line. Trump’s policy is analogous to a mafia boss organising a drive-by-shooting, and then comforting himself by pointing out that he wasn’t the one who pulled the trigger. But the result is still the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there is little to like about the Iranian leadership, and the idea of them having nuclear weapons is unappetising, to say the least. But this has never been a likely prospect. The scenario I have just described of Iran falling to pieces, on the other hand, grows more plausible with every passing day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran isn’t the only victim of predatory American sanctions, either; for Venezuela and Russia, the combination of falling oil prices and Western trade embargoes have also proven to be a near-fatal combination. And this morally bankrupt way of undermining the international state system doesn’t just make us our world less secure; it also deprives the Western countries of allies. As I have written before, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Russia-and-Turkey&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Russia and Turkey&lt;/a&gt; could have been useful to the US and NATO in hemming in the Iranian regime. Now, from Russia’s perspective, the possibility of Iran building a nuclear weapon could be seen as insurance against American aggression. It would be one hell of a bargaining chip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joe Biden, for all his many faults as a candidate, would choose a more pragmatic approach to dealing with Iran. He has said that he will return to the 2015 Nuclear Deal he helped to negotiate as Vice President. But this doesn’t mean his administration shouldn’t be watched closely when it comes to sanctions. Let’s not forget that his administration sanctioned Russia to the eyeballs after the Ukraine crisis in 2014; an unwise move, as I have already pointed out. I’m not optimistic that the US will stop using sanctions anytime soon. But I do wish for them to show a little more promise in learning from their past mistakes. The next one could cost all of us big time. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Donald Trump may have railed against certain elements of Republican Party orthodoxy during his run for President in 2016, but his attitude towards Iran came straight from the Republican playbook. He was a staunch critic of the Nuclear Deal signed in 2015, which Iran negotiated with NATO, China and Russia. In a risky move, Trump ordered a drone strike on Iranian General Qasem Soleimani in Baghdad earlier this year. And, in a recent interview with Rush Limbaugh, Trump told the country not to “f*ck around with us”.&amp;nbsp; The backbone of the Trump administration’s bullish attitude towards the Islamic Republic has been the imposition of trade sanctions. Last week, the President imposed new sanctions on Iran, targeting the country’s financial sector. It wasn’t the first time ‘The Donald’ had tried to cripple the Iranian economy; since he became Commander in Chief in 2017, Trump has strangled foreign trade with the Ayatollah’s family and inner circle, the Iranian Space Agency, and the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps. Sanctions are usually used by the American government against regimes it finds distasteful, but against whom it would be strategically difficult to deploy traditional hard power. Iran fits this description, given that its Twelver Shi’ite government is supported by Russia, and increasingly, China. The idea behind sanctions is to strangle the country’s economy until the governments are forced into negotiation with the US. In the case of Iran, the use of sanctions has been a mixed success thus far. Iran’s economy is now one of the least globalised in the world and suffers from stifling rates of inflation. However, the regime in Tehran has not yet returned to negotiations regarding its nuclear programme; it has said it will do so only if the US returns to Obama’s 2015 deal first. If Trump’s policy sounds like an acceptable way of dealing with another country, it shouldn’t. The worrying side-note regarding this 'intervention by sanction' approach is that it is likely to do much more than force Iran’s hand over its nuclear programme. When sanctions on the country immiserate its people, a process which is already well underway, the Islamic regime’s days will be numbered. And make no mistake; the collapse of the Iranian government would cause a conflict which would make Syria look like the London Riots. Russia, Saudi Arabia, Turkey and Israel would undoubtedly involve themselves directly, with NATO watching over proceedings from the skies, drones at the ready. Hundreds of thousands of people would die, and many more would overwhelm Europe’s borders. It is at this point that Trump’s claim to have avoided direct intervention in the Middle East during his first term begins to sound less remarkable. If US sanctions on Iran cause the Twelver regime in Tehran to collapse anyway, resulting in a once-in-a-generation civil and proxy war, then the knowledge that American troops didn’t intervene directly in such a conflict wouldn’t provide much solace for the rest of us. Europe would likely live with the fallout of such a war for decades, whilst the Trumpies in Washington would score a political victory by claiming to have kept their boys out of the firing line. Trump’s policy is analogous to a mafia boss organising a drive-by-shooting, and then comforting himself by pointing out that he wasn’t the one who pulled the trigger. But the result is still the same.&amp;nbsp; Of course, there is little to like about the Iranian leadership, and the idea of them having nuclear weapons is unappetising, to say the least. But this has never been a likely prospect. The scenario I have just described of Iran falling to pieces, on the other hand, grows more plausible with every passing day. Iran isn’t the only victim of predatory American sanctions, either; for Venezuela and Russia, the combination of falling oil prices and Western trade embargoes have also proven to be a near-fatal combination. And this morally bankrupt way of undermining the international state system doesn’t just make us our world less secure; it also deprives the Western countries of allies. As I have written before, Russia and Turkey could have been useful to the US and NATO in hemming in the Iranian regime. Now, from Russia’s perspective, the possibility of Iran building a nuclear weapon could be seen as insurance against American aggression. It would be one hell of a bargaining chip. Joe Biden, for all his many faults as a candidate, would choose a more pragmatic approach to dealing with Iran. He has said that he will return to the 2015 Nuclear Deal he helped to negotiate as Vice President. But this doesn’t mean his administration shouldn’t be watched closely when it comes to sanctions. Let’s not forget that his administration sanctioned Russia to the eyeballs after the Ukraine crisis in 2014; an unwise move, as I have already pointed out. I’m not optimistic that the US will stop using sanctions anytime soon. But I do wish for them to show a little more promise in learning from their past mistakes. The next one could cost all of us big time.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Germany’s Future: A Question Mark?</title>
      <link href="/Germany-s-Future" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Germany’s Future: A Question Mark?" />
      <published>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Germany-s-Future</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Germany-s-Future">&lt;p&gt;Germany, the most powerful country in the European Union and home to over 80 million people, is the only economy in Europe to have retained a large manufacturing and export base. It has consistently benefited from the Euro, the continent’s single currency and has the largest economy in the Eurozone. Despite all of this, its leadership of Europe is reserved, even a little embarrassed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the height of the Greek debt crisis, photographs of protesters in Athens brandishing placards of Angela Merkel, the Chancellor of Germany, dressed as Hitler made the headlines across the world. In Britain, the sight was met with mixed emotions, ranging from bewilderment to hilarity, but not so in Germany. For Merkel’s government and its people, the placards were far more than an unfunny joke. Such a blatant reference to Germany’s ugly history was a suggestion that even after several decades of apologising for the atrocities of the Nazi regime, people across the continent still mistook German assertiveness and leadership for fascistic belligerence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merkel is renowned world over for her understated leadership style. Commentators abroad often applaud the Chancellor’s love for detail, her skill in consensus-building and her conviction. Economically, this may well be true; her government spared little mercy for Greece, even after the Greeks played the Nazi card. However in the social sphere, underpinning Merkel’s major decisions has always been a fear of causing a stir and there is a desire to prevent any association with what has passed before, no matter how far fetched these comparisons might be. In Germany, you really &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; mention the War. These earnest attempts to please all sides haven’t been good for Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious example of Merkel’s reluctance to take difficult decisions was during the migrant crisis of 2015 when millions of migrants from across the Levant, Sub-Saharan Africa and Central Asia cascaded into Europe over a matter of a few months. Merkel’s decision not to turn away any of these people who were trying to enter Germany, in essence dissolving the inner borders of the continent, was largely born out of a desire to definitively break with German history. She wanted to present Germany in a different light from what it had been shown as earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, whilst it was presented as the ultimate show of tolerance, the great irony of Merkel’s migrant policy is that it has made Germany a more racist place. Before 2015, nobody would have made a Nazi salute on the streets of a German city. Now, it is commonplace at far-right protests. The protests in Chemnitz two years ago showed that. The failure to integrate Muslim migrants into German society was the driving cause of the success of the Alternative fur Deutschland (AfD) party in 2017, the first far-right party to win seats in the German Bundestag since the Second World War. The migrant crisis was the best thing that ever happened to Europe’s populist parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that the German government’s constant attempts to apologise for the horrors of the Nazi era don’t help the Europe of today. What Germany did to Europe was unthinkable and no amount of money would ever repay the Jewish community for the atrocities committed after 1942. But we all know Angela Merkel isn’t Adolf Hitler. Her party is not the National Socialists. The world should distinguish between perfectly reasonable projections of German soft power on the one hand and Nazi dog-whistles on the other. Germany, though, must also learn to live with its own past. There will always be new crises around the corner for Europe, but only they have the clout to coordinate a European response to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December, the most important European election in recent years is taking place. Merkel’s party will most likely choose her successor as the German Chancellor. She leaves behind a party in power, but a party that is unsure of its future. Many in Merkel’s Christian Democratic Union (CDU) wish for Germany to take a tougher stance on issues such as immigration and German identity. For the most part, they are uniting around Friedrich Merz. Merz is a strong NATO backer and supports the formation of an EU army. He also raised controversy two decades ago when he became the first centre-right politician to open a debate around &lt;em&gt;leitkultur&lt;/em&gt; (translated as leading culture). In practical terms, this translates to formulating a more concrete idea of ‘German-ness’, based on a forthright endorsement of Judeo-Christian values and a rejection of multiculturalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of the rise of the AfD, such talk makes the centrist wing of Merkel’s party nervous of sounding overly chauvinistic. The centrists are leaning towards Armin Laschet for the party leadership, who has been a strong defender of Merkel’s migrant policy. Laschet seems less interested than Merz in winning back voters who peeled off to the AfD at the 2017 election and would likely follow Merkel’s quiet leadership style on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make no mistake; Merz is no Trump. He’s a mainstream politician who briefly held the CDU leadership before Merkel in the early 2000’s. But his election as a CDU leader would signal to the world that Germany intends to become more self-assured and unabashed in its international decision-making. This would be a welcome change, though, as established, it would not come without controversy. It is difficult to say whether Germans would see this new assertiveness as a throwback to something dark in their history. In this sense, the split within the CDU is about much more than party bureaucracy. It represents the airing of an uncomfortable question at the heart of the German psyche: how do we project ourselves? How Germany answers that question will impact us all.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Germany, the most powerful country in the European Union and home to over 80 million people, is the only economy in Europe to have retained a large manufacturing and export base. It has consistently benefited from the Euro, the continent’s single currency and has the largest economy in the Eurozone. Despite all of this, its leadership of Europe is reserved, even a little embarrassed.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Weaponised Words: A Tale of Hate Speech</title>
      <link href="/Weaponised-Words-A-Tale-of-Hate-Speech" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Weaponised Words: A Tale of Hate Speech" />
      <published>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Weaponised-Words-A-Tale-of-Hate-Speech</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Weaponised-Words-A-Tale-of-Hate-Speech">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&quot;There is a fine line between free speech and hate speech. Free speech encourages debate whereas hate speech incites violence&quot; -&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Newton Lee,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/work/quotes/24289059&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Counterterrorism and Cybersecurity: Total Information Awareness&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quotation is a constant reminder of how easily hate speech overlaps with the idea of freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp;Over the past few months, the challenge of separating hate speech from the Indian citizen’s right to ‘Freedom of Expression’ has increased tremendously. Recently, several citizens including journalists, political party leaders and activists have been charged with hate speech, inflammatory speech and sedition. On one hand, offended plaintiffs file complaints due to hurt caused to their sentiments by the comments of the accused people. On the other hand, the defendants perceive it as a violation of their right to Freedom of Speech.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the light of recent incidents in India, a crucial question arises.&amp;nbsp;Should hate speech be incorporated as a part of Freedom of Speech, or should hate speech be legally regulated?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to scrutinise the idea of ‘free, hate speech’, it is important to distinguish between the two ideas of hate speech and free speech.&amp;nbsp;'Freedom of Expression or Speech' is a principle supporting the idea of an individual or a community articulating their opinions and ideas freely. It ensures such freedom “without the fear of retaliation, censorship, or legal sanction.” On the other hand, hate speech is clearly defined by the &lt;em&gt;Cambridge Dictionary&lt;/em&gt; as a &quot;public speech that expresses hate or encourages violence towards a person or a group based on something such as race, religion, sex, or sexual orientation”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get a sense of how hate speech is treated by legislation, we must take a look at a few examples. While hate speech is not a legal term in some countries, victims of hate speech may seek redressal under civil law, criminal law, or both in other nations. For instance, in the United States, hate speech is constitutionally protected. On the contrary, de jure, freedom of expression is promised in North Korea but there is no de facto right to free speech as asserted by Amnesty International, a human rights group.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In India, hate speech is regulated. While ‘Freedom of Speech and Expression’ is a fundamental right of the Indian Constitution, under Article 19(2) &quot;reasonable restrictions&quot; can be imposed on this right. This is in order to protect &quot;the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of the State, friendly relations with foreign States, public order, decency or morality, or in relation to contempt of court, defamation or incitement to an offence&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hurdle of Hate&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hate speech is a threat to humankind because words have the power to influence people to take action. It causes instability and agitation across the society. It can lead to reduced motivation, lower tolerance, emotional trauma or in extreme cases, depression.&amp;nbsp;Raising this concern, Joyce Arthur, a Canadian activist, in an article titled 'Should Hate Speech be a Crime?' underlines the importance of hate speech legislation. She elucidates that hate speech needs to be regulated as it has a huge impact on people’s dignity and human rights. Hate speech is often derogatory to the sentiments of a particular caste, creed, sex or religion as it is often rooted in stereotypes, prejudices and personal experiences which may be an inaccurate perception of the group or community as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A product of hate speech is hate crime&lt;/strong&gt;. Hate crimes are dangerous as they jeopardise amity in society, instigate precarity among communities, and foster a sense of animosity in the democracy.&amp;nbsp;In the technological era, hate speech over social media causes a tremendous amount of intolerance and violence leading to hate crimes. For instance, the perpetrator of the 2019 New Zealand mosque shootings killed 49 Muslims at prayer and sought to broadcast the attack on YouTube. In Germany, a correlation was observed between anti-refugee Facebook posts by the Alternative for Germany party and increasing attacks on refugees. In India, the recent case of Delhi violence due to hate speech and rumors on social media is also another instance.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hate Speech in India&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While 2020 has been a relatively inactive year for India in terms of business and functioning of institutions, the story is very different when it comes to hate speech laws. Starting from January 2020, there have been 10+ cases involving charges for sedition and hate speech.&amp;nbsp;Among journalists, Arnab Goswami, Amish Devgan and Vinod Dua are a few who&amp;nbsp; have faced FIRs or First Information Reports against them. On one hand, Amish Devgan was accused of injuring religious sentiments on his show. On the other hand, Goswami and Dua faced charges for criticising the State in different forms. FIRs against Goswami have been filed in relation to his questioning opposition leader Sonia Gandhi regarding mob lynching in the Palghar district of Western India. And Dua has been charged with sedition for a Youtube broadcast wherein he said that the State failed to implement the lockdown.&amp;nbsp;Sharjeel Imam, an Indian activist, has been charged with sedition, hate speech and promoting religious antagonism for his speeches against the Citizenship Amendment Act.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These diverse cases point out that it is also challenging and important to define specifically what can be categorized as hate speech.&amp;nbsp;A striking point has been stated in one of the articles in &lt;em&gt;Indian Express&lt;/em&gt;. It says that out of the ten hate speech cases that were scrutinised, including the ones mentioned above, the cases where the State and the petitioner contended on the same side, relief was provided. However, in six cases, where the State was accused, no relief was granted to the petitioner. A ‘telling pattern’ of this sort indicates a fresh challenge of violation of the right to equality before the law.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of this is the regulation of hate speech over social media. While trolling is only the tip of the iceberg, Facebook has recently faced challenges concerning hate speech rules. The &lt;em&gt;Wall Street Journal&lt;/em&gt; has accused Facebook of having failed to apply hate speech regulations on content posted by a BJP leader from the state of Telangana. Three other party leaders’ posts have also been overlooked.&amp;nbsp;A great initiative to combat such challenges is Facebook’s Oversight Board. The Oversight Board is an entity vested with the power to moderate and make independent decisions regarding content over social media sites like Facebook and Instagram. Its purpose is the protection of Facebook users. Hate speech and cases related to ‘political bias’ are within the purview of the board.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Watershed Verdicts&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1962 Indian Supreme Court judgement in &lt;em&gt;Kedar Nath Singh vs State of Bihar&lt;/em&gt; is a landmark judgement concerning the right to Freedom of Expression. The defendant faced charges of sedition and inciting public mischief due to a criticism of the then ruling party, the Indian National Congress in his speech. The defendant argued that the provisions on sedition in the Indian Penal Code (IPC) violated the right to Freedom of Expression under Article 19(1)(a) of the Indian Constitution.&amp;nbsp;The Court asserted that these were not under the purview of “reasonable restrictions” under Article 19(2). It explained that the phrase “Government established by law” under section 124A is different from the criticism of a political party or political leaders.&amp;nbsp;Yet sedition continues to be criminalised under the IPC. However, its provision has been narrowed down to only criminalise expression that intends to jeopardize public order and peace through violence, thereby protecting the right to freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another remarkable judgement in the field of online free speech is &lt;em&gt;Shreya Singhal vs Union of India (UOI).&lt;/em&gt; Two women were arrested under Section 66A of the Information Technology Act, 2000 for ‘posting allegedly offensive comments on Facebook’. As per the section, any person who sends “grossly offensive information” or information “to cause insult, injury or ill will” can be punished. These women filed a petition arguing that Section 66A was constitutionally invalid on the grounds of violation of the right to freedom of speech.&amp;nbsp;In 2015, the Supreme Court declared Section 66A to be unconstitutional and it was struck down. This was because Section 66A was not recognized as a “reasonable restriction” under Article 19(2). Thus, this was a turning point for online free speech.&amp;nbsp;These landmark judgements are useful to cite in cases relating to hate speech and freedom of expression for stronger established arguments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above-mentioned arguments and instances indicate that hate speech needs to be tackled through a balanced approach. While the right to freedom of expression needs to be upheld, hate speech intending to cause violence, disturb public order and promote unrest can prove to be detrimental for humankind.&amp;nbsp;A study by the Pew Research Center reveals that 67% and 27% of people in the United States and Asia-Pacific, respectively, agree with free hate speech. Nonetheless, as the saying goes, “Hate begets more hate”, hate speech causes a vicious cycle of hatred that has no end.&amp;nbsp;Thus, to balance respectful and considerate free speech without hampering the true essence of the Freedom of Expression, regulation of hate speech and uniform implementation of such rules is the need of the hour.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Nirikta Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">&quot;There is a fine line between free speech and hate speech. Free speech encourages debate whereas hate speech incites violence&quot; - Newton Lee, Counterterrorism and Cybersecurity: Total Information Awareness This quotation is a constant reminder of how easily hate speech overlaps with the idea of freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp;Over the past few months, the challenge of separating hate speech from the Indian citizen’s right to ‘Freedom of Expression’ has increased tremendously. Recently, several citizens including journalists, political party leaders and activists have been charged with hate speech, inflammatory speech and sedition. On one hand, offended plaintiffs file complaints due to hurt caused to their sentiments by the comments of the accused people. On the other hand, the defendants perceive it as a violation of their right to Freedom of Speech.&amp;nbsp; In the light of recent incidents in India, a crucial question arises.&amp;nbsp;Should hate speech be incorporated as a part of Freedom of Speech, or should hate speech be legally regulated?&amp;nbsp; In order to scrutinise the idea of ‘free, hate speech’, it is important to distinguish between the two ideas of hate speech and free speech.&amp;nbsp;'Freedom of Expression or Speech' is a principle supporting the idea of an individual or a community articulating their opinions and ideas freely. It ensures such freedom “without the fear of retaliation, censorship, or legal sanction.” On the other hand, hate speech is clearly defined by the Cambridge Dictionary as a &quot;public speech that expresses hate or encourages violence towards a person or a group based on something such as race, religion, sex, or sexual orientation”. To get a sense of how hate speech is treated by legislation, we must take a look at a few examples. While hate speech is not a legal term in some countries, victims of hate speech may seek redressal under civil law, criminal law, or both in other nations. For instance, in the United States, hate speech is constitutionally protected. On the contrary, de jure, freedom of expression is promised in North Korea but there is no de facto right to free speech as asserted by Amnesty International, a human rights group.&amp;nbsp; In India, hate speech is regulated. While ‘Freedom of Speech and Expression’ is a fundamental right of the Indian Constitution, under Article 19(2) &quot;reasonable restrictions&quot; can be imposed on this right. This is in order to protect &quot;the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of the State, friendly relations with foreign States, public order, decency or morality, or in relation to contempt of court, defamation or incitement to an offence&quot;. Hurdle of Hate&amp;nbsp; Hate speech is a threat to humankind because words have the power to influence people to take action. It causes instability and agitation across the society. It can lead to reduced motivation, lower tolerance, emotional trauma or in extreme cases, depression.&amp;nbsp;Raising this concern, Joyce Arthur, a Canadian activist, in an article titled 'Should Hate Speech be a Crime?' underlines the importance of hate speech legislation. She elucidates that hate speech needs to be regulated as it has a huge impact on people’s dignity and human rights. Hate speech is often derogatory to the sentiments of a particular caste, creed, sex or religion as it is often rooted in stereotypes, prejudices and personal experiences which may be an inaccurate perception of the group or community as a whole. A product of hate speech is hate crime. Hate crimes are dangerous as they jeopardise amity in society, instigate precarity among communities, and foster a sense of animosity in the democracy.&amp;nbsp;In the technological era, hate speech over social media causes a tremendous amount of intolerance and violence leading to hate crimes. For instance, the perpetrator of the 2019 New Zealand mosque shootings killed 49 Muslims at prayer and sought to broadcast the attack on YouTube. In Germany, a correlation was observed between anti-refugee Facebook posts by the Alternative for Germany party and increasing attacks on refugees. In India, the recent case of Delhi violence due to hate speech and rumors on social media is also another instance.&amp;nbsp; Hate Speech in India&amp;nbsp; While 2020 has been a relatively inactive year for India in terms of business and functioning of institutions, the story is very different when it comes to hate speech laws. Starting from January 2020, there have been 10+ cases involving charges for sedition and hate speech.&amp;nbsp;Among journalists, Arnab Goswami, Amish Devgan and Vinod Dua are a few who&amp;nbsp; have faced FIRs or First Information Reports against them. On one hand, Amish Devgan was accused of injuring religious sentiments on his show. On the other hand, Goswami and Dua faced charges for criticising the State in different forms. FIRs against Goswami have been filed in relation to his questioning opposition leader Sonia Gandhi regarding mob lynching in the Palghar district of Western India. And Dua has been charged with sedition for a Youtube broadcast wherein he said that the State failed to implement the lockdown.&amp;nbsp;Sharjeel Imam, an Indian activist, has been charged with sedition, hate speech and promoting religious antagonism for his speeches against the Citizenship Amendment Act.&amp;nbsp; These diverse cases point out that it is also challenging and important to define specifically what can be categorized as hate speech.&amp;nbsp;A striking point has been stated in one of the articles in Indian Express. It says that out of the ten hate speech cases that were scrutinised, including the ones mentioned above, the cases where the State and the petitioner contended on the same side, relief was provided. However, in six cases, where the State was accused, no relief was granted to the petitioner. A ‘telling pattern’ of this sort indicates a fresh challenge of violation of the right to equality before the law.&amp;nbsp; Another aspect of this is the regulation of hate speech over social media. While trolling is only the tip of the iceberg, Facebook has recently faced challenges concerning hate speech rules. The Wall Street Journal has accused Facebook of having failed to apply hate speech regulations on content posted by a BJP leader from the state of Telangana. Three other party leaders’ posts have also been overlooked.&amp;nbsp;A great initiative to combat such challenges is Facebook’s Oversight Board. The Oversight Board is an entity vested with the power to moderate and make independent decisions regarding content over social media sites like Facebook and Instagram. Its purpose is the protection of Facebook users. Hate speech and cases related to ‘political bias’ are within the purview of the board.&amp;nbsp; Watershed Verdicts&amp;nbsp; The 1962 Indian Supreme Court judgement in Kedar Nath Singh vs State of Bihar is a landmark judgement concerning the right to Freedom of Expression. The defendant faced charges of sedition and inciting public mischief due to a criticism of the then ruling party, the Indian National Congress in his speech. The defendant argued that the provisions on sedition in the Indian Penal Code (IPC) violated the right to Freedom of Expression under Article 19(1)(a) of the Indian Constitution.&amp;nbsp;The Court asserted that these were not under the purview of “reasonable restrictions” under Article 19(2). It explained that the phrase “Government established by law” under section 124A is different from the criticism of a political party or political leaders.&amp;nbsp;Yet sedition continues to be criminalised under the IPC. However, its provision has been narrowed down to only criminalise expression that intends to jeopardize public order and peace through violence, thereby protecting the right to freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp; Another remarkable judgement in the field of online free speech is Shreya Singhal vs Union of India (UOI). Two women were arrested under Section 66A of the Information Technology Act, 2000 for ‘posting allegedly offensive comments on Facebook’. As per the section, any person who sends “grossly offensive information” or information “to cause insult, injury or ill will” can be punished. These women filed a petition arguing that Section 66A was constitutionally invalid on the grounds of violation of the right to freedom of speech.&amp;nbsp;In 2015, the Supreme Court declared Section 66A to be unconstitutional and it was struck down. This was because Section 66A was not recognized as a “reasonable restriction” under Article 19(2). Thus, this was a turning point for online free speech.&amp;nbsp;These landmark judgements are useful to cite in cases relating to hate speech and freedom of expression for stronger established arguments.&amp;nbsp; The above-mentioned arguments and instances indicate that hate speech needs to be tackled through a balanced approach. While the right to freedom of expression needs to be upheld, hate speech intending to cause violence, disturb public order and promote unrest can prove to be detrimental for humankind.&amp;nbsp;A study by the Pew Research Center reveals that 67% and 27% of people in the United States and Asia-Pacific, respectively, agree with free hate speech. Nonetheless, as the saying goes, “Hate begets more hate”, hate speech causes a vicious cycle of hatred that has no end.&amp;nbsp;Thus, to balance respectful and considerate free speech without hampering the true essence of the Freedom of Expression, regulation of hate speech and uniform implementation of such rules is the need of the hour.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Scottish Independence: Johnson Approved?</title>
      <link href="/Scottish-Independence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scottish Independence: Johnson Approved?" />
      <published>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Scottish-Independence</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Scottish-Independence">&lt;p&gt;One of the most destructive elements of Brexit has been its uncanny knack of underscoring the ill-feeling between the governments in London and Edinburgh. In keeping with its constituents’ wishes, Nicola Sturgeon’s Scottish government now looks set to frustrate the UK’s departure from the European Union (EU) at every turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigel Farage has often suggested that it would be illogical for Scotland to vote to become an independent country under Sturgeon’s leadership because a Scottish National Party (SNP) government would simply choose to pool Scottish sovereignty with Brussels instead of Westminster by re-joining the EU. Regardless of whether Farage’s point holds water, it might be more pertinent to turn his insight on its head: it was illogical, downright delusional in fact, to say Westminster would be totally sovereign over British laws after Brexit, because Parliament still governs the country alongside the regional assemblies in Edinburgh, Cardiff and Belfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-governance with the regional assemblies has been shown to be discordant ample times since ‘Brexit Day’ in January. The differing rules on the coronavirus lockdowns in the four nations of the UK have been immensely confusing, frequently smacking of plain political one-upmanship rather than proper scientific enquiry. On Brexit, it looks as if Sturgeon might disregard the government’s Internal Markets Bill and pass her own trade legislation, calling Johnson’s bill “a full-frontal assault on devolution”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not a constitutional expert, so I can’t say with certainty whether Sturgeon is right about that. But if the bill does in fact not represent overreach from Westminster, then part of the reason that Sturgeon can assert something which isn’t true is the fact that many of the terms of the relationship between Westminster and the devolved assemblies are poorly defined, arbitrary and hopelessly vulnerable to the transient whims of public opinion. Whilst most members of the commentariat have been focusing on making our relationship with the Europeans as stable and fruitful as possible, major instabilities within the British constitution have been overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three devolved Parliaments are not like American state governments, the rights and jurisdictions of which are clearly laid out in the Constitution. If a state believes the Federal Government has overstepped the mark, the Supreme Court refers to the Constitution to assess whether overreach has occurred. All states have the same powers, and state governments are just as inherent a part of the US governance as the Federal government in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Parliaments in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland, by contrast, were all created at different times, and all have slightly different powers. The devolved Parliaments can have their powers altered by the British government as long as the sitting Prime Minister desires it, and has a parliamentary majority to help him. After the Scottish independence referendum, David Cameron promised the Scots “devo-max”, as a way of responding to the close nature of the result. As a gesture of goodwill, he simultaneously enhanced the powers of the Welsh Assembly, but not to the same degree as the Scottish Parliament. However, he offered no explanation for why the Assembly in Cardiff would remain less powerful, or why he had interpreted nationalist fervour in Scotland as a clear sign that the Welsh were on the brink of drifting somewhere into the Irish Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between the three Parliaments and its mothership in London resembles a rickety old building, the roof of which boasts a series of asymmetric and poorly built extensions. If a constitutional revolution did happen in Britain after 1945, it was devolution, not joining the EU. Random and arbitrary devolution has inhibited Westminster from governing the entire country far more than the European Commission ever did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, dysfunctionality doesn’t make the Scottish Parliament unconstitutional; the British Constitution is malleable and unwritten, which makes it much easier to change than the US Constitution. Ted Heath’s Tory government pooled our sovereignty with the Europeans in 1972 with a simple act of Parliament, thereby changing the British Constitution overnight. But just because something is constitutional doesn’t mean it works well. It doesn’t make it a good idea. The Internal Market Bill won’t be the last time that there are impasses in the years ahead, because the mandates of the Parliaments’ clash and their powers are far too easy to change. I’ve focused on Scotland here, but the potential for disaster in Northern Ireland is just as obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where does the Prime Minister enter into the picture in all of this? He’s certainly having a torrid time dealing with Scotland at present. One year into his premiership, it’s obvious that he has few guiding principles. In truth, you didn’t need a year to see this. Whether Johnson’s love for the expedient would extend to advocating independence for Scotland is unlikely. But, privately at least, he must have clocked that not having to listen to those loudmouths over Hadrian’s Wall would definitely make his life easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t like the job he’s doing (I count myself among you, by the way), then you might conclude you don’t mind that a by-product of our constitutional disorder is Johnson’s failure to deliver on his manifesto. What is worrying though, is that far from enhancing democracy in our country, devolution is compounding an incipient feeling that Britain is now ungovernable. I don’t blame Sturgeon for this; there is nothing wrong with scrutinising the government and its legislation, but there is an ocean of difference between careful scrutiny and institutional collapse. The former, essential to any democracy, was traditionally the responsibility of the opposition parties, the House of Lords, and an independent judiciary. The country was governed reasonably well with just one government. Creating three regional Parliaments on a whim and handing them new powers arbitrarily has simply led to a pile-up of different mandates, rather than improving accountability. If many different governments squabble over the right to govern, none of them &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; govern. In handing back power to our domestic governments, Brexit seems poised to unleash a crisis of democratic legitimacy far greater in severity than even itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the most destructive elements of Brexit has been its uncanny knack of underscoring the ill-feeling between the governments in London and Edinburgh. In keeping with its constituents’ wishes, Nicola Sturgeon’s Scottish government now looks set to frustrate the UK’s departure from the European Union (EU) at every turn.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The World’s Odd Couple: Russia and Turkey</title>
      <link href="/Russia-and-Turkey" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The World’s Odd Couple: Russia and Turkey" />
      <published>2020-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Russia-and-Turkey</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Russia-and-Turkey">&lt;figure style=&quot;margin-bottom: 2em&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Listen to this article:&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;audio id=&quot;audio-1&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; controlsList=&quot;nodownload&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/2020-09-17-Russia-and-Turkey.mp3&quot;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of relations between Turkey and Russia has mostly been one of conflict rather than of peace. This could, of course, be said of Russia’s relations with most countries. But  this relationship merits a new examination since the pair is going through something of a détente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thawing of relations has been relatively quick. Four years ago, things were frosty. In Syria, Russia had just intervened on the side of the Assad government, whereas Turkey backed various rebel groups in the conflict. In 2015, the downing of a Russian fighter jet by the Turkish Air Force saw Russian President Vladimir Putin impose trade sanctions. The assassination of the Russian Ambassador to Turkey in Istanbul a year later, probably caused by Turkish Muslim objections to Putin’s intervention in Syria, exposed the deep rift between the nations with respect to the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, though, the countries have shown greater willingness to cooperate. Putin and Turkey’s President Erdogan met regularly (a veritable &lt;em&gt;Guess Who&lt;/em&gt; of world tyrants), Russia ended its sanctions and visa restrictions against the Turks in May 2017, and Turkey purchased the S-400 missile system from the Russian government later that year. In spite of their differences over Syria, the two countries negotiated a ceasefire in Idlib province in March. Such a rapprochement, if it is to continue, will have important implications for Europe and the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Russia and Turkey are clearly a hybrid of the two continents they straddle, the relationship between them has always impacted Europe more than it has impacted Asia. The Crimean War was caused in large part because the Britain and France feared Russian encroachment on the crumbling Ottoman Empire. In the modern-day, the West looks upon the Russian-Turkish rapprochement with bewilderment because Turkey is a North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) member fraternising with the alliance’s traditional adversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pertinent question to ask, then, is why the two countries are getting closer. Certainly, with regards to Syria, the countries have little reason to be cuddling with each other. My argument would be that the thawing of relations tells you little about what Russia and Turkey think of each other, but that it does show what both of them think about America, NATO and the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putin and Erdogan, like all great chauvinists, don’t just claim to rule nation-states, but entire cultures and civilisations. They are the Tsar and the Sultan reanointed. Among other things, this has meant that both have touted the idea of acting unilaterally on the world stage, and a central plank of this foreign policy has been bashing the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The uncomfortable truth is that NATO and the US have at times given the two leaders ample opportunities to paint the West as a bad-faith actor, especially in the case of Russia. NATO has been expanding eastwards into Russia’s sphere of influence since the end of the Cold War, not just into the Baltics but even into Georgia. US sanctions against Russia and Turkey, imposed in 2014 and 2019 respectively, hurt the economies of the countries and turned ordinary Russians and Turks even more firmly against the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you may say that you don’t care much for either Putin or Erdogan, and that you don’t care if the two countries are turning towards each other. It turns out, however, that isolating these countries means that they look elsewhere in the world for allies. Not phased by Turkey? How about by China? Or Iran? Russia now enjoys a relatively friendly relationship with the Chinese, underpinned by trade. It has also moved closer to Tehran, shown earlier this year when the killing of Qasem Soleimani by the US prompted a deeply negative response from Vladimir Putin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If diplomacy is about anything, it is about choosing allies to support you against your enemies. The US evidently sees China and Iran as threats to the world’s international system. In the fight to contain these countries, Russia and Turkey could have been key allies, especially considering that the history of Russia and China isn’t friendly. In pushing Putin and Erdogan away, the US and NATO have bolstered their adversaries in the world. If the US wishes to intervene in Iran in the future, it will surely face opposition from Russia and Turkey. NATO is now powerless to influence events in Syria, having ostracised Turkey, the one member of the alliance capable of intervening quickly in the Levant. The US and Russia could have collaborated on containing China, in a manner reminiscent of how Nixon and Kissinger courted Mao to contain the Soviets. Sadly, China and Russia now seem to be beating the Americans at their own game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of all this is that the US and NATO cannot stand alone in the world. They need allies. Russia and Turkey seem to understand what the US has forgotten: sometimes, you need to make deals with imperfect actors in order to heap pressure on genuinely malevolent ones. From the West’s perspective, I would put Putin and Erdogan in the former category, and the Chinese Communist Party and the Ayatollahs in the latter. In spurning Russia and Turkey, the US has made its objectives in the world much more difficult to achieve and has made these potential allies look much more adversarial and dangerous than they actually are.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Listen to this article: Your browser does not support the audio element.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Silent Genocide in Zimbabwe</title>
      <link href="/The-Silent-Genocide" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Silent Genocide in Zimbabwe" />
      <published>2020-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Silent-Genocide</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Silent-Genocide">&lt;p&gt;On July 27, 2020, seven babies were stillborn in Harare Hospital on the same day. An anonymous doctor, in a letter to the nation, confirmed that the babies were of a healthy weight and could have been saved, but it was Zimbabwe’s crumbling health system that killed them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This incident is just one of the many unreported and completely avoidable deaths. Many patients are forced to be turned away from hospitals either due to lack of staff or lack of equipment. There have been reports of pregnant women giving birth in unconventional and unsafe places leading to increased mortality rates. Doctors and nurses have consistently been underpaid and overworked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this situation is common to many countries as a result of the COVID-19 pandemic, the situation in Zimbabwe has been dire for a long time. In September 2019, medical personnel across the country went on a 4-month long strike to protest their devastatingly low wages and poor working conditions. It was not that they did not want to work, it was that they could not afford to work. In the face of triple-digit inflation, doctors and nurses could barely meet their food and transport costs. In fact, the doctors did not call it a strike - rather an “incapacitation”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government’s response was disheartening, stating that it was not just medical personnel, but all workers who were suffering under inflation, including civil servants. However, looking at the standard of life of government officials, this did not seem plausible. Suspiciously enough, not long after the strike began, their union leader, Dr Peter Magombeyi, was abducted for five days under mysterious circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The staff only returned to work in January 2020 when the telecoms tycoon Strive Masiyiwa offered to supplement the government wages with a monthly subsistence allowance through his charitable foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in March 2020, COVID-19 reached Zimbabwe. President Emmerson Mnangagwa fell short in governance. Not just the healthcare system but the entire economy is facing an insurmountable challenge. The unemployment level is close to 90%, with most people falling deeper into poverty and being unable to afford a proper meal a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April, the High Court ordered the government to ensure all healthcare workers were supplied with Personal Protective Equipment (PPE). However, according to doctors, there is still hardly any PPE available. N-95 masks are occasionally provided but mostly a surgical mask and plastic aprons are given to last an entire day. An increasing number of medical personnel are being affected and there is no insurance for them. Adding to this risk of practicing, the pay has been dismally low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The situation is even more terrible for nurses. Many of them receive just $30 per month and cannot even afford proper food and housing. On these grounds, nurses in Zimbabwe went on a strike in June 2020. Instead of providing PPE kits and improving pay and working conditions, the government brought in student nurses and those who had been out of work for a long time. Thus, many wards were staffed with nurses who were either inexperienced or who had not received recent training. Shortly after, doctors followed them, demanding PPE, better conditions and equipment in hospitals, decent pay, and for salaries to be paid in US dollars rather than the RTGS dollar (or “Zimdollar”) which is subject to hyperinflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reinaldo Ortuno, head of mission at Médecins Sans Frontières Zimbabwe said, &lt;em&gt;“Hospitals and clinics are now manned by student nurses, junior doctors, and other staff who have no choice as they are still under training. This has compromised quality of care and has inadvertently contributed to high morbidity and mortality rates”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government seems to have little incentive to bring a change. The people in power do not exert pressure for a better healthcare system as they do not get treated in government hospitals. When they fall sick, they go abroad. Ex-President Robert Mugabe received treatment in Singapore before he passed away in 2019, at the age of 95. Vice-President Constantino Chiwenga, the former military man who played a major role in overthrowing Mugabe, has received four months of medical treatment in China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government even saw the pandemic as a money-making opportunity. This clearly revealed the multi-million-dollar equipment procurement scandal that led to the recent arrest of the Health Minister as well as the vindictive detention of Hopewell Chin’ono, the journalist who uncovered it. The government then appointed Constantine Chiwenga as the new Health Minister, even though he had made insulting and abusive comments against doctors in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pandemic has led to strikes by medical personnel all across the world. This presents a dilemma of whose needs should be put above the others. Should doctors and nurses suffer through their long hours and low wages as a part of their duty to society? The reality is that in Zimbabwe, they have been making this sacrifice for a long time. However, now the nature of COVID-19 means that this sacrifice could cost them their lives. Norman Matara, head of Zimbabwe Hospital Doctors Association said that about 15% of the nationally recorded virus infections had been detected among health workers. The lack of attention from the government has broken their spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many have called this crisis in Zimbabwe a “silent genocide”. The government must increase public spending in the healthcare sector on an emergency basis, and should also look towards securing foreign assistance for equipment and personnel, like Cuba has been providing, to support them through the pandemic. Refusing the demands of the workers and degrading their protest by accusing them of not fulfilling their duty is not beneficial to any side. President Emmerson Mnangagwa needs to act in order to rebuild the trust of doctors and nurses in the government. They are at the frontline of the fight against the pandemic, and their wellbeing, both physical and mental, is quite literally a matter of life and death.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On July 27, 2020, seven babies were stillborn in Harare Hospital on the same day. An anonymous doctor, in a letter to the nation, confirmed that the babies were of a healthy weight and could have been saved, but it was Zimbabwe’s crumbling health system that killed them.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">To Ally or not to Ally: Saudi-Pak Relations</title>
      <link href="/Saudi-Pak-Relations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To Ally or not to Ally: Saudi-Pak Relations" />
      <published>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Saudi-Pak-Relations</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Saudi-Pak-Relations">&lt;p&gt;The nation of Saudi Arabia is a strong believer in the concept of quid-pro-quo and it seems Saudi’s long time ally Pakistan is going to be reminded of this fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past two years, Saudi Arabia has been financing and investing in the Pakistan economy as a testament to their confidence in Pakistan’s loyalty. In 2018, Saudi rescued Pakistan from a financial crisis triggered by decreasing foreign reserves and increasing trade deficit by announcing a loan package of $6 billion, which was followed by an overall investment of $20 billion in Pakistan’s economy in 2019. In return, Saudi demanded unerring loyalty within and outside the Organisation of Islamic Countries (OIC). However, Pakistan has failed to uphold their side of the trade and is currently in deep waters with the Saudi regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a series of unfortunate events, Pakistan has managed to transgress on their agreements. The catalyst to these events was Pakistan’s bid to gain support in their quest to fight India on their decision to revoke Article 370 of the Indian Constitution which gave special status and provisions to Kashmir in India. Since 2019, Pakistan had been trying to arrange a special meeting with the OIC to discuss the matter of Kashmir and to convince the participating nations to hold India accountable for the abrogation of Article 370. However, Saudi refused to join the bandwagon and being a key player in the OIC, Saudi’s support was imperative for Pakistan to gain the support of other Islamic nations. Their refusal made it impossible for Pakistan to fulfil its objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owing to their precarious position post-Saudi’s refusal, Pakistan tried to gain the support of nations that were outside the OIC, namely Malaysia, Turkey and Qatar. Saudi has been engaged in regional disputes with Turkey, and China wants Turkey to replace the position Saudi holds in the Middle East due to Saudi’s relations with the United States. Amidst all this, Saudi and Qatar battle over the Gulf Cooperation Council (GCC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the aforementioned circumstances, Pakistan’s attempt to take advantage of Saudi’s disputes further soured their relations. Comments made by Pakistan’s Foreign Minister Shah Mahmood Qureshi on a talk show interview about asking Pakistani Prime Minister Imran Khan to call a meeting outside of OIC to gain support on the issue of Kashmir was the tipping point for the Saudi regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia could not let this public opposition to their and OIC’s decision go unpunished. Riyadh demanded immediate repayment of their loan of $3 billion. While Pakistan managed to pay back $1 billion with China’s help, Saudi refused to entertain pleas for deferred payment. Punishment in the form of monetary compensation is more than what Pakistan can bear considering its dwindling economy. Consequently, Pakistan Army Chief General Bajwa was sent to Riyadh to meet Crown Prince Mohammad Bin Salman with the hopes of making amends and smoothening the turbulent relations. However, the Crown Prince refused to meet the General, and instead, the Vice Minister of Defence and Chief of General Staff of Saudi were sent to entertain General Bajwa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blatant snub underscores the most pressing problem that Pakistan is currently facing. The Crown Prince’s refusal to meet the General is an indication that matters are much more grave, and that the Saudi regime would not be satisfied with appeasing words and meetings. This is only exacerbated by the impending conditions of loan repayment and the grave possibility of losing the $20 billion worth of investments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia’s refusal to stand with Pakistan on the issue of Kashmir is also an indicator of growing India-Saudi relations. According to a recent article in &lt;em&gt;The Indian Express&lt;/em&gt;, India imports around 19% of its oil requirements from Saudi. The trade between the two countries is estimated at approximately $28 billion. Hence, Saudi cannot oppose India’s decision regarding Kashmir. Saudi’s preference for India over Pakistan is a confirmation of Pakistan’s dwindling position in the OIC and as Saudi’s ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fearing the loss and wrath of a powerful ally, Shah Mahmood Qureshi made a trip to China as soon as the dignitaries sent to Saudi returned. While Pakistan does have China’s support, the strength and extent of the support remain to be seen. China has invested huge amounts of money in Pakistan’s economy under the former’s Belt and Road Initiative (BRI) and has kept the Pakistan economy from crumbling. Thereby, China holds sway over Pakistan, but whether the reverse is true or not cannot be ascertained. Qureshi’s trip to China may help Pakistan pay back the loans, however, the impact of their position with the OIC will certainly have a long-term impact on Pakistan’s trade and international relations. It also remains to be seen how long China would be willing to bail Pakistan out every time they manage to offend their allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a bid to gain the upper hand with India, Pakistan has managed to land itself in significant trouble with powerful nations. India’s expanding trade relations with Middle Eastern nations has made it extremely difficult for Pakistan to gather support against them. The issue of Kashmir has long been a festering wound for Pakistan, but is it important enough for the country to endanger their diplomatic tussle and lose out investments to keep their country afloat? In its current situation, Pakistan can either assuage the disgruntled Saudi regime or hold them at bay long enough to gather the funds necessary for loan repayment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, even if they manage to pay the loans, Pakistan’s economy faces the imminent threat of economic collapse. Pakistan will not be able to use China as a crutch, and this relationship is likely to end the same way as Pakistan-US agreements. Pakistan’s tendency to provide refuge to terrorists has further aggravated many of its allies, and India has recently made public statements about holding Pakistan liable for the same. Amidst tempestuous international relations, fragile trade relations and changing tides of globalisation, Pakistan needs to come up with a better strategy to reduce its dependence upon other countries or the consequences in the future would be far worse than angry Princes and loan repayments.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The nation of Saudi Arabia is a strong believer in the concept of quid-pro-quo and it seems Saudi’s long time ally Pakistan is going to be reminded of this fact.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Against a Liberal Anti-racism</title>
      <link href="/Against-a-Liberal-Anti-racism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Against a Liberal Anti-racism" />
      <published>2020-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Against-a-Liberal-Anti-racism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Against-a-Liberal-Anti-racism">&lt;p&gt;The months following the killing of George Floyd saw sales of books about race increase by up to 6,800%. The top seller was Robin DiAngelo’s &lt;em&gt;White Fragility&lt;/em&gt;, which increased sales by over 400,000 copies from May to June this year, a startling increase of over 2,000%. DiAngelo, a ‘diversity consultant’, has since been invited to deliver keynote speeches, charging up to $35,000 for a two-hour workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DiAngelo’s central premise, that white Americans must reckon with their own implicit biases and engage in rigorous introspection to remedy them, appears less of a repudiation of centuries-old institutional racism than it does an instructional manual for white liberals working in corporate jobs to avoid getting into trouble with HR. It characterises racism merely as an antipathy felt by individuals towards other individuals, leaving untouched the edifice of America’s racist socio-economic structure. It fails to acknowledge that white supremacy is not simply the supremacy of white over black, but also the supremacy of rich whites over poorer whites who can be trusted to vote themselves into economic ruin in return for the illusion of superiority. And even more egregiously, it focuses attention on the self-aggrandising antics of the white liberal, repackaging the fight against racism as a culture war between educated white liberals and less educated whites, many of whom do not view themselves as the beneficiaries of ‘privilege’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the first Africans arrived in Virginia in 1619, there were no ‘white’ people there. It would be another 60 years before colonial records would describe the settlers as ‘white’, as the idea of the ‘white’ race was deliberately constructed by the ruling class as a form of social control, dividing poor European indentured servants and African chattel-bond labourers, assimilating the Europeans into the ‘middle class’, and preventing the likelihood of the reemergence of an event such as Bacon’s Rebellion (1676). Europeans and Africans had jointly demanded the imposition of a land tax and Virginia’s transition from a large plantation economy to a diversified economy of small freeholders, chasing the planter bourgeoisie to the shore and burning Jamestown to the ground. Ira Berlin stated that in the aftermath of Bacon’s Rebellion &lt;em&gt;“they enact laws which say that people of African descent are hereditary slaves. And they increasingly give some power to the independent white farmers and land holders”&lt;/em&gt;. Therefore, rather than being simply a form of prejudice on the basis of skin colour, racism can be understood as a complex form of social control. Theodore W Allen’s book &lt;em&gt;The Invention of the White Race&lt;/em&gt; made a similar argument that racism is a “sociogenic” rather than a “phylogenic” phenomenon, analysing how the (phenotypically similar) British used racial oppression against Irish Catholics, later allowing the Irish Catholic bourgeoisie to assimilate into the oppressive structure, accepting the disenfranchisement of the forty-shilling freeholders in return for meagre ‘emancipation’ in 1829.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, liberal anti-racism of the DiAngelo variety, largely devoid of this analysis, becomes an exercise in narcissistic self-indulgence on the part of white liberals, who reframe discussions about race in terms of how they can be better people, and how it is incumbent on all whites to unlearn their white privilege. As this approach to anti-racism fails to acknowledge how racism functions as a tool of socioeconomic disenfranchisement by the ruling class, it assumes that all whites benefit equally from white privilege, ignoring and minimising the plight of working-class whites. A 2019 sociological study by E Cooley, etc. found that learning about white privilege did nothing to increase empathy for people of colour among white liberals, but simply made them less likely to empathise with poorer whites, placing greater personal blame on them on the basis that their privilege outweighed other social factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, reactionary and racist ideology abounds among the white working class, and this article is not intended to downplay such attitudes or pretend that they do not exist. It is to argue that if there is a hope that cross-racial solidarity can be achieved, and these reactionary tendencies extinguished, it will not be accomplished by lecturing working-class whites who are beset by low wages, deindustrialisation, and the opioid epidemic about their ‘privilege’, but by encouraging them to recognise that they have more in common with other races than with elites of the same race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term ‘class reductionist’ is consistently deployed against socialists who recognise that racism and capitalism are intimately connected as if this recognition downplays the significance of racism. But some of the most pernicious forms of American institutional racism, such as redlining and the prison-industrial complex, have explicitly capitalistic imperatives. For example, exclusion from ‘prime’ credit has forced black communities to secure housing through subprime loans and substandard rental accommodation. During the subprime lending boom, predatory loans were five times more likely to be made in black neighbourhoods than in white neighbourhoods, while black Americans were four times as likely as white Americans to be denied loans from the Bank of America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations such as the Blackstone Group have conspired to engage in predatory lending practices, buying up houses at cheap prices and selling them on for higher prices or charging exorbitant rents. Invitation Homes, a subsidiary of the Blackstone Group and a prominent lender to black communities, may have broken laws to give tenants loans that maximised profits as they could easily outbid first time buyers. It is issues such as these, the pervasive, material disparities which have concentrated generational wealth in the hands of white communities and generational disadvantage in the hands of black communities that should be the focus of anti-racists, not trivial ideas such as ‘white fragility’. These are not injustices that can be solved simply by more representation of black people within the highest echelons of power, but only through the de-privatisation and de-commodification of housing at a minimum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another consequence of viewing racism through a reductive, individualistic lens is the over-medicalisation of the problem, which treats racism as a pathology on the part of its perpetrators. As Kenan Malik writes, &lt;em&gt;“It was not unconscious bias that made a police officer place his knee on George Floyd’s neck”&lt;/em&gt;. A meta-analysis of nearly 500 studies found that unconscious bias training only had a “weak” effect on the behaviour of individuals. Reframing racism as a product of original sin, an aberration that could never be held by ‘normal’ people simply absolves those who are responsible for perpetuating it, as racial bigotry can, and often is, the product of a sound mind. The Nazi war criminals at Nuremberg, for instance, all tested as medically sane, had high IQs, and included a disproportionate number of PhDs. Far from being the irrational judgement of an insane mind, racism is the mendacious, calculated judgement of the elites who perpetuate it, to provide a constant stream of alienated unfree labour from those they impoverish, to divide and conquer and to subjugate. Only an approach that acknowledges the systemic and institutional manifestations of racism can grasp this central point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The systemic racism on which the United States was founded, that still exists today, cannot be expunged with ‘unconscious bias training’ or the recognition of white fragility. The injustices will remain, but white corporate consultants such as Robin DiAngelo will become very rich. What is required is not white guilt but white solidarity on a mass scale, such as has been seen in the recent protests, and a recognition that, as Karl Marx stated, &lt;em&gt;“Labour in the white skin cannot emancipate itself where in the black it is branded.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The months following the killing of George Floyd saw sales of books about race increase by up to 6,800%. The top seller was Robin DiAngelo’s White Fragility, which increased sales by over 400,000 copies from May to June this year, a startling increase of over 2,000%. DiAngelo, a ‘diversity consultant’, has since been invited to deliver keynote speeches, charging up to $35,000 for a two-hour workshop.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">God’s Homophobia will Die and We will Kill It</title>
      <link href="/God-s-Homophobia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="God's Homophobia will Die and We will Kill It" />
      <published>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/God-s-Homophobia</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/God-s-Homophobia">&lt;p&gt;It is no secret that most religions of the world are opposed to homosexuality. The Bible clearly states: &lt;em&gt;“If a man lies with a male as with a woman, both of them have committed an abomination; they shall surely be put to death; their blood is upon them.”&lt;/em&gt; (Leviticus 18:22). While the Quran does not have such an explicit declaration, traditional Islamic jurisprudence fully proscribes homosexual acts. Hindu jurisprudence has no equivalent bans on homosexual acts, and its law books do contain a recognition of a ‘third gender’, but most Hindus oppose it vigorously in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, none of these religions are monolithic and all contain various elements that are sympathetic towards homosexuality, whether among general followers or in their institutions. Despite all that, only a fool would say that the religions of the world fully accept homosexuals or their rights. This is epitomised in the most patronising argument religious people put forth, i.e. that while they accept LGBTQ persons like any other human being and believe homosexuality to be natural, their dogma commands that they continue to consider homosexual acts as immoral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is: what can one do in such a situation? Can an LGBTQ person agree to disagree with the religious person and still continue to co-exist? Or is peace simply not an option? The religious person obviously insists that they are only proceeding from a vantage point of empathy, that they demand restraint from the gay person not out of prejudice but because all persons have to control their desires under a religious framework, not just homosexuals. So, there is no ground to allege homophobia on their part at all. But all of this is utter hogwash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the fact that this new kind of argument is a clear attempt at dehumanising the homosexual, because it proscribes the very fruition of the gay person’s inner desires, it has more sinister implications: It leads to religious people favouring the maintenance of legal bans on homosexual acts because that is not seen as an impeachment of LGBTQ rights by itself. It also leads to a moral justification for continuing with the torturous practice of gay conversion therapy because that is verily seen as an expression of love which only seeks to prevent sin. And it is the brutality of these points as well as the very sinews of religious beliefs on homosexuality that makes such beliefs worthy of eradication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religions, after all, view the very fact of homosexuality as wrong. To them, it is fundamentally unnatural and a deviation from the human normal which God(s) has thought fit to prohibit. The outward empathy they seek to exhibit for LGBTQ rights is informed not by an understanding of the fact that homosexuality is no deviation from the normal, but by their desire to be kind in a way no different to the kindness/forgiveness they may have for the rapist or the murderer. When one takes that into account, one can clearly see that religious people want the LGBTQ community to become dogs on a leash - restraining themselves from a fruition of their sexual desires and a more visible existence in public life - in exchange for little treats of kindness and little beatings of gay conversion therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the question of making peace with the religious person who denies the normalcy of homosexual relations or deems them sinful is moot. The religious person may seek to caustically self-victimise here by saying that their human rights as religious people cannot be restricted by the homosexual agenda. But the fact of the matter is that their argument would likely not find traction in any human rights court save the ones found in America with elected Republican judges. It is well-known in human rights jurisprudence that the right to practice one’s faith may be qualified. The requirement is that such a qualification be for a legitimate aim, that it be the necessary means to achieve such an aim and that it be the least-intrusive means available for achieving that aim. We clearly know that a criminalisation of the espousal of anti-homosexual beliefs is for a very legitimate aim: the securing of fuller rights to LGBTQ person. We also know that such a measure is necessary to achieve that aim. If there is no threat of criminal sanction on the espousal of anti-LGBTQ beliefs, then a threat to the right of LGBTQ persons to lead a dignified existence forever remains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only hurdle would be the question of intrusiveness. But given the nature of the mischief sought to be controlled here, criminalisation is not in the least excessive. The threat of criminal sanction that secures the rights of homosexuals is hardly intrusive upon religious rights: such a measure does not require the religious person to go out of his way to do anything, it merely requires them to forbear from preaching certain values. That may be intrusive due to the fact that proselytisation is an article of some faiths, but again, there’s no ban on proselytisation here - just a ban on bigotry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religions will make every attempt to try and hold on to their homophobia, going so far as to to suggest that their moral values are given by a creator and are immutable, regardless of the fact that science and nature condone homosexuality. They will say that their laws are not bendable and that science does not provide an objectively ethical guide to what is permissible among humans. So, a restriction on their right to believe is not objective or valid. But that’s not the point, society is not here to play religion’s game of “my group’s values are objective and right, your group’s values are subjective and wrong”. What society, at this present moment, is required to do is secure complete rights to human beings who have sexual and romantic relations with persons of the same gender. This is the reality of the here and now, and it is non-negotiable, morally or otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is about time that religion killed God’s homophobia, lest He face the proverbial sulphur of a modern society.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>anon.anon</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is no secret that most religions of the world are opposed to homosexuality. The Bible clearly states: “If a man lies with a male as with a woman, both of them have committed an abomination; they shall surely be put to death; their blood is upon them.” (Leviticus 18:22). While the Quran does not have such an explicit declaration, traditional Islamic jurisprudence fully proscribes homosexual acts. Hindu jurisprudence has no equivalent bans on homosexual acts, and its law books do contain a recognition of a ‘third gender’, but most Hindus oppose it vigorously in practice.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
