<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/aryaman.dhiman/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-10-12T17:38:48+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/aryaman.dhiman/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What COVID-19 Means for the US Education System?</title>
      <link href="/COVID-19-US-Education-System" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What COVID-19 Means for the US Education System?" />
      <published>2020-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/COVID-19-US-Education-System</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/COVID-19-US-Education-System">&lt;p&gt;Every generation of humanity has experienced their share of transitional periods, be it as consequential as the Second World War, or as small as being temporarily bedridden due to injury. The same concept can be used to study history in a different light - as a compilation of events that initiated the strongest ripples of transition in the various aspects of human life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As any mature and experienced enough man would tell you, change is a constant in the universe. It’s this change that led to human evolution and towards the development of society and the invention of all the things that make life worth living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as everything has exceptions, one of the few constants in life is the importance of education. It is something that has been so deeply ingrained in our culture that we cannot let go of it irrespective of the substitutes available to us. Today we see a scenario which is a clash between this constant and the period of fundamental transition fostered by COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States is a global education hub, with some of the most coveted educational institutes across the field of STEM, business, law and the arts. Students from all over the world dedicate a significant portion of their lives to the cause of securing admission into an elite US university. The country also greatly benefits from the international student community, as their annual contribution to the US GDP is at a massive $41 billion. Additionally, the cultural influence and innovation that the international community brings has, over the years, furthered the stronghold of many American companies in their respective markets. Nevertheless, the Trump administration has been rooting against international students who migrate to the USA in search of education and livelihood. That paired with a disease outbreak that has no fool-proof methods of containment has damaged educational prospects for a lot of international students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The American Council of Education predicts that a fall of as much as 25% in foreign student applications is anticipated for the upcoming academic year. This, though backed by the administration in charge, sets off a loud alarm as the impact would be drastic on the American corporate sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, America may be the pioneer in education, but it’s not the only player in the game. A lot of other countries like the UK, Canada and Australia offer equally enticing educational opportunities and have better migration and settlement policies. This may turn out to be the deciding factor for international students for whom an investment in a country other than the USA brings more to the table, especially in a highly uncertain situation like that of the present. The growing culture of administrative hostility towards immigrants would eventually lead to stagnation in diversity and curb the advantages that it offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, America is severely undermining the importance of international talent in keeping its corporate sector afloat. The influx of international funds in the form of fees, taxes, healthcare, bank deposits, etc contributes significantly to the economy. Due to the strictness of pre-existing work visa and green card policies, the proportion of foreign students that enrol in US programmes to those who actually find employment in the US to those who receive special work visas like H1B or obtain green cards moves in a decreasing order. Moreover, 1 out of 4 US startups, which are worth millions of dollars, are founded by international students. Therefore, calculation of the net impact of international students on the economy, irrespective of the time period, would yield a positive quotient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the lack of foreign influence would push the US into a state of cyclical perpetuity. The presence of international student communities supports more than just the economy, as it has been pivotal in reforming American society, and overcoming racial and cultural prejudice. This has helped American companies expand and explore international opportunities, and develop a workforce that is comfortable working outside their countries. It has popularised US education across the globe, which, over the years, has attracted countless employers and investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, many American institutions have moulded personalities who would go on to become leaders and forerunners in their respective fields. It has helped the American education system develop a global imprint, as a lot of individuals, that are its product, represent it in any sphere they venture into. Reduction in international students, after a certain point, would reduce this influence that the US enjoys in shaping leaders of various sectors, disciplines, and even nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summing it all up, the US, like any other nation, needs to evolve in various respects as and when required to maintain its reputation as a global leader. The driving force behind such evolution is the product of interactions between the international and local communities. A long term trend of decline in international students would cause the nation to involuntarily impose a glass ceiling on its growth potential. Therefore, it is indispensable for American colleges and universities to acknowledge the “new normal” and devise methods to attract international student applications. The first step that can be taken in this regard would be dismissing the suspension of student and special work visas, and ensuring that the impact of the pandemic-induced economic slowdown is minimal on college fees, educational loans and international student aid.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aryaman Dhiman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Every generation of humanity has experienced their share of transitional periods, be it as consequential as the Second World War, or as small as being temporarily bedridden due to injury. The same concept can be used to study history in a different light - as a compilation of events that initiated the strongest ripples of transition in the various aspects of human life.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Icarus Paradox: Why Successful Ventures Fail?</title>
      <link href="/Icarus-Paradox" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Icarus Paradox: Why Successful Ventures Fail?" />
      <published>2020-08-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Icarus-Paradox</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Icarus-Paradox">&lt;p&gt;Though most people deem pride as transgression, some appraise it as a trait that can be capitalised upon. Research teams at the University of Montreal and UC Santa Barbara’s Center for Evolutionary Psychology (CEP) suggest that pride is an evolutionary by-product of the trait of self-preservation. Because of the frequent lethal reversals that our ancestors faced, they needed their fellow band members to value them enough during hardships to pull them through. Therefore, in making choices, humans had to weigh their self-interest over the approval of others, so that when they needed help, others would value them enough to give it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though we have come a long way, &lt;em&gt;hubris&lt;/em&gt; is still not hard to come across. Irrespective of the peculiarity of its radix, pride is not limited to individuals - organisations also emanate it. The anomaly, however, is that organisational hubris is just a compendium of the egos of individuals who comprise it, but people in an organisation struggle to keep their individual pride in parity with the organisational one. Therefore, in theory, there is no comprehensible line distinguishing individual pride from organisational pride, as one is a concoction of the other. The practical aspect, however, differentiates between the magnitude and gravity of the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vanity is believed to be the root of all sin by cultures across the globe. While the widely followed Abrahamic religions talk about the spiritual descent of Lucifer into Satan as a result of his pride, the Greeks present the tale of Icarus. Icarus was the son of Daedalus - a famous Greek inventor. While in captivity, Daedalus crafted two pairs of wings which would enable him and his son to escape certain execution. Before taking off, Daedalus specifically instructed his son not to fly too high. Ignoring the words of his father, Icarus soared too near to the clouds, which ultimately led to his wings failing him. The boy plummeted to his death in the sea because his pride clouded his judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Danny Miller coined the term ‘Icarus Paradox’ in 1990. The term, alluding to the Greek tale, refers to the phenomenon of businesses suddenly failing after a period of success, where this failure is brought about by the very elements that led to their initial uprise. Miller noted that it’s the victories of the past that conceit a successful organisation, lulling them into complacency. The very values that usher companies upwards in the pecking order - such as tried-and-true business strategies, dauntless and self-assured management, and the overall combination of all these elements - may be rendered blunt and platitudinous, ultimately leading to business catastrophes. Managers tend to make injudicious decisions, as they cling onto the past success of their manoeuvres and fail to factor in the revamp in the external business environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most successful firms owe their fortune to a unique competitive algorithm which guides the formulation and execution of their policies. It helps it gain momentum and reach a higher pedestal, but cloaks its dynamism and its ability to acclimatise because the management’s confidence in this winning formula is bolstered. Eventually, the firm ends up focusing only on refining and extending these strategies, products and values. Activities/policies that do not conform to the paradigm are neglected or even discouraged. This may be profitable in the short run as companies continue to specialise and improve in a certain product or strategy, leading to higher efficiency, sales and growth as they develop a competitive advantage in a particular area. However, its viability is leached away in the long run, as the stereotypical aspect ingrained in their corporate culture barres them from keeping up with the threats of new competitors, changing consumer demands, newly developed business models and changes in the external environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Standard economic theory explains the high rate of failures as an inevitable result of companies taking rational risks in the face of peaky situations. The rewards of a few successes outweigh losses incurred from many failures in the long run. Executives know this and accept the risk. Anyhow, this theory absolves them from blame as they simply obey rationality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lovallo and Kahneman from the &lt;em&gt;Harvard Business Review&lt;/em&gt;, however, argue that most failures are actually the results of flawed decision making. While predicting the outcomes of potentially risky projects, executives easily fall victim to what psychologists call the ‘planning fallacy’. They make decisions based on delusional optimism instead of rational computation of gains, losses, and probabilities, dwelling in situations of hypothetical success while overlooking potential problems. Consequently, they are overly optimistic and pursue opportunities that are unlikely to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A prime example of the paradox at work would be Tesco’s experimental venture into the US market – Fresh &amp;amp; Easy. Tesco opened the chain in 2007- right before the economic recession which took a severe toll on consumer spending. Tesco also did not anticipate the upshot in the popularity of online grocery shopping. Additionally, Tesco’s research segment misconstrued the spending habits of their consumer base. While their Metro stores in the UK were popular, there was not enough demand in the US as the population was not accustomed to grab-and-go meals. Most of the Americans would usually order take out or cook their own meals - as purchasing such meals would be comparatively costlier than grocery shopping. Lastly, an elementary point of distinction was the statistics indicating that most people in the US buy their groceries once a week, with bulk and diversity of purchase being the key takeaways. Conversely, Europeans tend to make more frequent, but smaller trips to the grocery stores. After they took a hit of approximately £1.2bn ($1.8bn), Tesco’s net profit slithered down by 96%, compelling them to abandon the US market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, Tesco’s confidence in bringing its successful concept of ready meals to the US market contributed heavily to its failure. The intensive marketing required to change people’s daily consumption proclivities takes time and money, neither of which Tesco invested enough of. Tesco was also confident enough to continue to hang on for over 5 years despite indications of possible failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above example highlights &lt;em&gt;hubris&lt;/em&gt; in its raw essence, which can be used as a base for conceptual bifurcation, creating multiple subdivisions rooted in the same basic concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Humans have a natural tendency to amplify their own talents, which leads a lot of executives to believe that they transcend the rest in ability and output. This is further reinforced by the tendency to misperceive causes of certain events and attribute success to their abilities when it might have been out of pure luck.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People also display keenness to take credit for positive outcomes and ascribe undesirable ones to external factors. A study of letters to shareholders in annual reports, for example, found that managers tend to attribute favourable outcomes to variables under their control, like corporate strategy or R&amp;amp;D (research and development) programs, while inimical ones were more likely to be attributed to uncontrollable external factors like the weather or inflation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A company’s values unify its people. Strong, meaningful credos can help inculcate employee loyalty, strengthen the bonds between a company and its customers, attract like-minded partners, and hold together a company’s far-flung operations. However, as companies mature, these values may morph into commandments- which contribute more towards suppressing novelty and flexibility, rather than inspiring moral conduct.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A peculiar observation made in business process analysis is that, as more investment is made in information technology, worker productivity may go down instead of going up. This observation has been firmly supported by empirical evidence from the 1970’s to the early 1990’s. Prior to the upward jolt in IT investment, the expected return on investment in terms of productivity was 3-4%. The aberration, however, was that with IT, the normal return on investment was only 1% from the 1970’s to the early 1990’s. Thus, the investment in IT - done for performance enhancement - led to contradictory outcomes that threatened to pick the organisation apart. This is known as the ‘paradox of information technology’- a concept encapsulated by the Icarus paradox.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it may seem easy to deal with, the paradox is a trap that is too hard to escape, with companies like Lehman Brothers, Xerox, Atari, Digital Equipment, Tupperware and Revlon on the victim list. Also, a lot of unforeseen complications arise upon the initial implementation of solutions. The key is an optimum blend of flexibility, innovation, and diversification, which needs to be instilled in the bedrock of the organisational structure of business entities.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aryaman Dhiman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Though most people deem pride as transgression, some appraise it as a trait that can be capitalised upon. Research teams at the University of Montreal and UC Santa Barbara’s Center for Evolutionary Psychology (CEP) suggest that pride is an evolutionary by-product of the trait of self-preservation. Because of the frequent lethal reversals that our ancestors faced, they needed their fellow band members to value them enough during hardships to pull them through. Therefore, in making choices, humans had to weigh their self-interest over the approval of others, so that when they needed help, others would value them enough to give it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Economic Indicator 007</title>
      <link href="/Economic-Indicator-007" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Economic Indicator 007" />
      <published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Economic-Indicator-007</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Economic-Indicator-007">&lt;p&gt;Economic trends are inordinately erratic and display a tendency to react to the smallest stimulus. Unfortunately, the patterns manifested by these trends is all we have to predict the trajectory of the economic system. Going by the book, we have a predominant set of indices that are used to portray an economy’s state of affairs, overriding among them being the GDP, GNP, unemployment rate, inflation rate, rate of interest, consumer price index, etc. However, that’s not even the half of it, as there are a prodigious number of accurate indicators that are undermined by economic planners and analysts. Who thought James Bond would be one of them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know who James Bond is. His reputation as an international man of mystery, a guru of gadgets and espionage thrills, and as the one licensed to kill, precedes him. Since its creation in 1953 by Ian Fleming, the character has etched itself into pop culture and earned itself a spot on the Mount Rushmore of Hollywood. But that’s not the end of its legacy- turns out that it has established one of the most unusual precedents in the economic history of the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &lt;em&gt;Casino Royale&lt;/em&gt; was first published in 1953, the US economy was greatly compromised. The US war spending had helped add $236 billion to the debt. It was a 1048% increase, the largest percentage increase to debt for any President. A recession also sprouted, owing to the demobilisation following the Korean war, and the unemployment levels reached their loftiest at 6.1% in 1954. The same could not be said for Bond, as the book became one of the hottest on the shelves. People started loving the persona of Bond: a dashing agent with seemingly limitless resources and abilities, and he unknowingly became a ridiculously accurate economic barometer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first on-screen adaptation of Bond came with the release of &lt;em&gt;Dr No&lt;/em&gt; in 1962. The times were good, as the economy was exalted as a result of the post the Second World War expansion. President Kennedy had introduced various reforms to revive the economy from the 1960-61 recession. These comprised an increase in the minimum wage for a larger pool of workers, an increase in unemployment compensation plus increased aid to children of unemployed workers, increased social security benefits, emergency relief for feed grain farmers, area redevelopment, vocational training for displaced workers, federal funding for home building and slum eradication and tax cuts. Overseas investment also rose. The film was conferred with critical acclaim, but came up short in commercial success, and is ranked as one of the least earning Bond movies. Still, the film had a significance of its own, as it formed the bedrock for the dazzling success of future installments. What no one seemed to notice was that the success of Bond films and the state of economic well-being were displaying a nebulously accurate disagreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trail of years that followed were not kind to America. President John F Kennedy, the man pivotal in uplifting the economy and perpetuating its growth, had been assassinated. The country’s economy was facing the corroding effects of the Vietnam War, the most famous highlight of which was ‘The Great Botch’ of 1966. The botch involved miscalculation of the war cost by the Defense Department under President Johnson’s administration. The budget was underestimated by a staggering 100%, which squandered the steady income and employment growth rate achieved post the Second World War. The budget deficit also escalated at an alarming rate, hitting the $23 billion mark in 1968.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film franchise, on the other hand, unveiled to the world its most popular antagonist - a fat, decadent psychopath who covers everything in gold and is literally trying to steal all of America’s money - Auric Goldfinger. &lt;em&gt;Thunderball&lt;/em&gt; (1965), &lt;em&gt;Goldfinger&lt;/em&gt; (1964), and &lt;em&gt;You Only Live Twice&lt;/em&gt; (1967) were massive commercial blockbusters, grossing a whopping total of $1.5 billion. Actor Sean Connery got the biggest piece of the pie, as he received a great push towards a legendary career, accompanied by a big fat pay-cheque. The decade ended with a shift in the scales of power, as Richard Nixon took the reigns in 1969.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 70’s witnessed an oscillatory trend for Bond cinema, displaying perfectly negative parallelism to what the economy was enduring. When &lt;em&gt;Diamonds Are Forever&lt;/em&gt; hit the screens in 1971, the US was witnessing a decline in its economic power, and the economy was pegging away to recover from the 1970 recession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Nixon fought the recession by turning the American dollar into a fiat currency, as a result of which the dollar was devalued and millions of foreigners holding dollars, including Arab oil barons with tens of millions of petro-dollars, saw the value of dollars slashed. He also imposed wage and price controls. As you can guess now, the movie was average. It made decent money and was fairly appreciated, but it was no &lt;em&gt;Goldfinger&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the arrival of 1973, the economy stumbled deeper into the trenches. The USA was facing the severest recession since the Second World War, with the rate of inflation at a deplorable 8.8% in the fourth quarter. The Organisation of Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) was blamed for quadrupling oil prices, but that was just the tip of the iceberg. President Nixon’s price controls kept prices too high, reducing demand, while wage controls made salaries too high and forced businesses to lay off workers. Additionally, Nixon took the United States off the gold standard in response to a run on the gold held at Fort Knox, which led to inflation. The price of gold skyrocketed to $120 an ounce while the dollar’s value plummeted. Negative GDP growth of 2.1% was also observed in the third quarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roger Moore’s &lt;em&gt;Live and Let Die&lt;/em&gt; came during the same year, and by now it shouldn’t be a surprise that it was the highest-grossing Bond movie of the 70’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next came time for another turn of tables, with the release of &lt;em&gt;The Man with the Golden Gun&lt;/em&gt; in December 1974. Owing to its late release, its primary collection period was the year 1975, the same year American economy began emerging from recession. An upturn in GDP and industrial output was evident, alongside the dwindling rate of inflation (from 10.4% in 1974 to 6.5 % in 1975). The volume of shares traded on the New York stock exchange also rose from 3.5 to 4.7 billion shares. &lt;em&gt;The Man with the Golden Gun&lt;/em&gt; is still considered to be the most flawed and pointless addition to the Bond universe, loathed by critics and the audience alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The climax for the 70’s economy came with another capricious change in economic trends, displayed by cascading economic growth. Inflation and unemployment were up again, and the economic system was slithering into another recession. The timing could not have been better for &lt;em&gt;The Spy Who Loved Me&lt;/em&gt; (1977) and &lt;em&gt;Moonraker&lt;/em&gt; (1979), as both of them grossed a stupendous $1.3 billion combined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the year 1981 rolled in, the recession boomeranged back to plague the economy. The Regan government caused this recession by raising interest rates to curb inflation, which undesirably reduced business spending. The Iranian oil embargo added fuel to the fire, as it reduced US oil supplies, which drove up the prices. GDP growth was negative for the whole year, the worst being the second quarter at a negative 8.0%. Unemployment rose to 10.8% in November and December 1982, the highest level in any modern recession. President Reagan lowered the tax rate and boosted the defense budget, helping to end the recession. Summing it up, the economy was toiling to fend off the unemployment and inflationary outbreaks. The commercial struggle of &lt;em&gt;For Your Eyes Only&lt;/em&gt; (1983) epitomised a more complicated one going on in the economy. However, the film is the best Bond portrayal of the 1980’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining decade was all Reagan-show, as he painted a masterpiece on the economic canvas. The first step was signing the Economic Recovery Tax Act of 1981, which brought reductions in individual income tax rates, the expensing of depreciable property, incentives for small businesses and incentives for savings. So began the Reagan Recovery. A few years later, the Tax Reform Act of 1986 brought the lowest individual and corporate income tax rates of any major industrialised country in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The numbers tell the story. Over the eight years of the Reagan Administration:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• 20 million new jobs were created. Employment of African-Americans rose by more than 25% between 1982 and 1988, and more than half of the new jobs created went to women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Inflation dropped from 13.5% in 1980 to 4.1% by 1988.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Unemployment fell from 7.6% to 5.5%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Net worth of families earning between $20,000 and $50,000 annually grew by 27%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Real gross national product rose by 26%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• The prime interest rate was slashed by more than half, from an unprecedented 21.5% in January 1981 to 10% in August 1988.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Growth in government spending plummeted from 10% in 1982 to just over 1% in 1987. With inflation factored in, federal spending actually went down in 1987– the first time that had happened in well over a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the economy boomed, Bond got tanked again, facing consecutive low earning entries in the series. The decade leached away Bond’s persona as the charismatic spy who could always get the job done and turned him into a goofy, lethargic and confused man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to 1995, the economy was recovering from the recession of 1990-91 and was turning increasingly healthy in performance as the 1990’s progressed. The fall of the Soviet Union and Eastern European communism in the late 1980’s opened up trade opportunities across the world. Technological developments brought a wide range of new, more efficient electronic products, and innovations in telecommunications and computer networking spawned a vast computer hardware and software industry. This, in turn, revolutionised the way many other industries operated. The growth rate and corporate earnings rose rapidly. A combination of desirable inflation, unemployment, and corporate profits sent the stock market surging. Moreover, the Dow Jones Industrial Average, which had stood at just 1,000 in the late 1970’s, hit the 11,000 mark in 1999, adding substantially to the wealth of many - though not all - Americans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An idiosyncrasy of the final decade of the century was the increasing speculation in online websites, also known as the ‘dot-com bubble’. People were rapidly dumping cash in online domains. Capital from venture capitalists was also easy to raise, as investment banks profited from the Initial Public Offers (IPOs). A combination of rapidly increasing stock prices in the quaternary sector of the economy and confidence that the companies would turn future profits created an environment in which many investors were willing to overlook traditional metrics, such as the price-earnings ratio, and base confidence on technological advancements, which ultimately led to a stock market bubble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar was the case with Bond movies. Almost all of the previous Bond films had an average budget of about $30 million. So 1989’s &lt;em&gt;License to Kill&lt;/em&gt;, which is still the worst-performing entry of the entire franchise, wound up earning almost four times its budget. Though 1999’s &lt;em&gt;Tomorrow Never Dies&lt;/em&gt; grossed way more, producers had dumped over $110 million into it and funneled even more cash into the next two installments. Such a large investment in movies led to the formation of an investment bubble of its own. However, filmmakers’ bulletproof investment bubble burst, just like all the dot-coms of the 90’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decade changed, but the story didn’t. Bond made millions whenever inflation and unemployment got the better of the economy. Be it &lt;em&gt;Quantum of Solace&lt;/em&gt; (2008) and the financial crisis 2007-08 or &lt;em&gt;Skyfall&lt;/em&gt; (2012) and the global economic crisis 2012, it’s always the same. Higher the severity of the crisis, the more dollars Bond films rake in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the phenomenon first got noticed, it was spurned as a mere case of coincidences. Till today, no one has been able to decipher the reason behind this absurd correlation. In my opinion, one aspect of it can be identified as what is known as the ‘butter popcorn effect’, which is an unconventional economic indicator. The rationale behind it is that during the initial stages of a recession, people show a greater inclination towards entertainment, as they want to escape the hardships of the real world. As this pushes more people into cinema halls, the sale of butter popcorn also increases. For instance, the box office posted one of its biggest years during the 2009 recession, before plateauing as markets eased. Still, there is no solid explanation about why Bond films fail during economic expansion.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aryaman Dhiman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Economic trends are inordinately erratic and display a tendency to react to the smallest stimulus. Unfortunately, the patterns manifested by these trends is all we have to predict the trajectory of the economic system. Going by the book, we have a predominant set of indices that are used to portray an economy’s state of affairs, overriding among them being the GDP, GNP, unemployment rate, inflation rate, rate of interest, consumer price index, etc. However, that’s not even the half of it, as there are a prodigious number of accurate indicators that are undermined by economic planners and analysts. Who thought James Bond would be one of them?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Green Paradox</title>
      <link href="/Green-Paradox" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Green Paradox" />
      <published>2020-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Green-Paradox</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Green-Paradox">&lt;p&gt;The colour ‘green’ has a multitude of connotations running with it and is associated with the meanings of growth, freshness, fertility, and the environment. It is also commonly used to represent nature. In the discipline of economics, the term ‘nature’ indicates the gargantuan cluster of resources that it provides, and not the spiritual or primordial aspects associated with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tenability of an economy can be deciphered by ascertaining the number of natural resources it wields. Thus, safeguarding the environment and its resources has been one of the most imperative concerns of economists and planners across the globe. The standard way by which an economy tries to accomplish it is through government intervention. The authorities try to strike a balance between effective utilisation and adequate cushioning of its scarce resources. Almost every government in an economy with abounding resources introduces legislative provisions with the intent of achieving this balance. Thus, policies or acts of legislation, passed with such or similar intent, are known as &lt;em&gt;green policies&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a side note, it is impossible to conceive the idea of an economy devoid of human wants, as it is one of its salient features and is the catalyst that drives it. An interesting attribute of human wants is that they are unbiased of any moral/legal presumption associated with them. This is what shapes a consumer to be rational. However, with the popularity of the concept of social cost on the uprise, one cannot help but notice the toll that rationality takes on the resources. The interlinkage of every entity in an economy with the other, the behaviour they display in certain situations as predicted by the economic principles, and the deviations/alterations in such predictions by the dynamic external forces and circumstances sometimes cause these principles to fail. This gives rise to a paradoxical situation, characterised by the display of discrepancy in behaviour by these principals/constants. On connecting the dots, it can be observed that the unpredictability of the human psyche, tinted with negotiable morality, exposes certain chinks and loopholes in the policies introduced by the authorities. This sometimes leads to a display of contrary results, and subsequent failure of such policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best examples of this would be green policies, as they display paradoxical tendency in the long run. The main rationale responsible is the resistance of human wants to such restrictive measures. The level of pollution/environmental degradation is measured by the bulk of pollutant particles accumulated in a specific environmental sample. One of the primary contributors to such pollutants is fossil fuels. The social cost incurred on account of the consumption of fossil fuel is the corrosion of the environment. Every molecule of the fuel extracted, upon combustion, would contribute to the addition of carbon to the atmosphere. Even on employing the most efficient methods, the emission cannot be curbed significantly, as a quarter of the emitted carbon would dwell in the atmosphere practically forever, thereby contributing to global warming. As a result, the authorities are backed into a corner, and forced to choose the restrictive use policy as a last resort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the government cannot make restrictions unannounced. The general rule is that it is obligated to make a reasonably prior notification to the resource owners. The resource owners anticipate the prices to fall in the future, as the clogging of permitted extraction and use of these resources causes the long-run demand to decrease. Thus, the utility of these resources as assets falls for their owners, as they would not enjoy any future appreciation from them. This induces them to intensify the extraction in the current period when the restrictions are not yet active and the demand is still fair. Then, they divest by selling off the stock of the extracted resources and reinvest the proceeds into something with better prospects of future appreciation. This renders the policy useless, as the share of resources that are to be used judicially in the future is squandered in the current period. The human instinct of self-preservation causes the entire policy framework to collapse. Such a situation is called the ‘green paradox’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term was first coined by the German economist, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hans-Werner_Sinn&quot;&gt;Hans-Werner Sinn&lt;/a&gt;, and has since become one of the most controversial topics under environmental economics. The green paradox is rooted in the fundamental argument of Hotelling’s rule- which states that for the owners of non-renewable resources, time acts as the deciding factor for the extraction of the resources they possess. Because of their scarce nature, non-renewable resources will always command a price that is higher than the cost of their extraction. The owner ends up at a crossroads between keeping the resource intact in the hope of a better price in the future, or extracting and selling it to invest the proceeds in higher-yielding security. Hence, for the paradox to operate, obedience to the Hotelling’s rule is a prerequisite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst all the scepticism, there have been several accounts of empirical evidence in full or partial support of the rule and paradox. When the carbon cap bill was introduced in the US senate in 2010, the expectation of a possible demand shortage had started to induce excessive extractions in the current period. Till the time the bill collapsed, a 12 million ton increase in the normal CO2 emission rate was observed. Also, the price of oil and coal for the future contracts that expired before the imposition of the cap showed a significant rise. However, the evidence from the US Acid Rain Project states that though the prices were driven down as a result of the paradox, there was no material increase in the persisting rate of coal extraction. This goes to show that due to a large number of factors, the predicted outcomes seldom fully confirm the theoretically suggested outcomes. Moreover, the reliance of the outcome on the sentiment of the suppliers also creates a lot of room for deviations. Though only a portion of the entire phenomenon can be observed in a given sample, it is still safe to say that the fundamental premises of the argument hold when subjected to the practical aspect of the markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greatest challenge for economists and policymakers is to develop a climate policy in which the paradox and the variation in its significance at the national and global level is accounted for, and which also reduces the overall extraction of these resources rather than restricting their usage. A good point to start would be to develop an effective formula/algorithm to update and revamp the allocation of the global carbon budget to different countries, using an effective evaluation system to calculate the weightage of the dynamic political and economic factors.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aryaman Dhiman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The colour ‘green’ has a multitude of connotations running with it and is associated with the meanings of growth, freshness, fertility, and the environment. It is also commonly used to represent nature. In the discipline of economics, the term ‘nature’ indicates the gargantuan cluster of resources that it provides, and not the spiritual or primordial aspects associated with it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
