<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/from-the-horses-mouth/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-06-10T00:37:26+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/from-the-horses-mouth/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Dear Pandemic Diary</title>
      <link href="/Dear-Pandemic-Diary" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Dear Pandemic Diary" />
      <published>2020-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Dear-Pandemic-Diary</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Dear-Pandemic-Diary">&lt;p&gt;Last time I was here, I was asking if you would like that Corona (the beer, folks) with lime or without, today, I might take a dozen bottles with or without you. I apologise in advance; this may seem like an untoward journal entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the pandemic is upon us, and God, is it upon us - I wonder to myself, is this regression to teen years going to bring me down, or the virus? While I don’t have to wake up at 5 am, listen to VH1 till 6:30 and move to school by 6:40 anymore, I have to deal with chaos that nobody ever told me about. No school lessons taught me how to be home and keep sane; hiding under the table definitely doesn’t work. Crisis intervention only tells me so much that I might truly have to be infected in order to utilise my knowledge. I wish I could run back to my 3rd grade moral lessons and really be the person that they proposed we be - the sane, calm, adjusted one that obviously had nothing but respect and compassion for everyone. It would make life easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we speak of the pandemic, many don’t realise that while the certainty of having the virus is difficult to deal with (and that may as well be an understatement), the uncertainty it brings with itself is the silent killer that may lead us to a Noah’s Ark situation. The aforementioned teen regression that I speak of? Well, people my age and around my age have had to come back home from being away for college or their respective jobs plainly because, “better be sick with family than without.” And people who were home already, have lost their autonomy and are back to being home with the ‘others’ deciding what is to be done. My teenage hormones, albeit crazy, perhaps, were the only thing that led me to the slightly retained sanity I used to encompass, till, well, a few days ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having reread that paragraph, I understand if I might sound ungrateful, believe me, I’m not. I assure you, I’m aware of my privilege of being safe and healthy, of having resources to maintain that, of being able to share my thoughts and being able to help myself and others while I’m at it. I suppose all I’m trying to suggest here is how while ‘inside and isolated’ may drive us crazy, figuratively speaking - doing both while you’re in a toxic household or with someone who may be riddled with their own issues - may, literally speaking, make you crazy. Personally, having had to deal with a symptomatic-to-hypochondriac mother has been driving me up the walls, the paranoia that surfaces is so strong, that any denial will be harshly rejected, and that’s my reality to live with now. Upon asking my near and dear ones, I’m now able to recount several cases of unhealthy relationships, malfunctioning behaviour and what one may call unsettling dependency. My sample is too small, and perhaps not as generalisable - I mean it is, after all, purposive and convenient (Okay, I’m going to stop now). But, what may be concluded is that there’s a danger lurking, and we’re not aware of it or, well, not wanting to be aware of it. May as well dump it in that subconscious, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The curse on mental health that social isolation is, is not unknown; there are plenty of people with flared anxieties or triggered depression - and then, there are people who may not even be aware of what they’re going through and end up more hurt than ever. As a future mental health professional, I can sit here and count out hundreds of flaws in self-isolation and social distancing, but the science behind it is not unknown and it definitely is better of the two evils. I can’t give an informed solution, as someone once told me: mental health is like fingerprints, different for everybody (and definitely, incriminating!). I only ask everyone to be more receptive to the idea of keeping your thoughts open and look for more sources of help (and try to be one, too).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were to intimate yourself with my thoughts - I don’t suppose the fear of COVID-19 is as high as having to figure out how to placate my mother, submit two assignments and attend 3 classes and write 2 research papers, while simultaneously completing my to-dos of ‘productive work during quarantine.’ Every time I watch the news, I worry that maybe the numbers that rise up everyday are just becoming statistics to me and my brain, and my empathy and fear will be drained out by my need to do chores and completing tasks and just proving that I’m ‘productive’. Or perhaps, it’s the other way round, maybe that is good, denial till faced with the issue - a (good?) coping mechanism. I wouldn’t know; if you do please, page me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only think of today as possibly weighed by my worries and the silliness that pertains to “whoa, today was busy”. Maybe, you can do one better and ask your near and dear ones how their day was. And yourself, it’s important that you ask yourself about your day. My day was mopping, Humanism and the utter joy followed after finding recent, high Impact Factor research papers. Well, it’s yet to be over, but you know I’ll keep you posted.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Last time I was here, I was asking if you would like that Corona (the beer, folks) with lime or without, today, I might take a dozen bottles with or without you. I apologise in advance; this may seem like an untoward journal entry.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Beer, anyone? Levity in a Time of Crisis</title>
      <link href="/Beer-anyone-Levity-in-a-Time-of-Crisis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beer, anyone? Levity in a Time of Crisis" />
      <published>2020-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Beer-anyone-Levity-in-a-Time-of-Crisis</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Beer-anyone-Levity-in-a-Time-of-Crisis">&lt;p&gt;If one were to tell me that I’d be receiving an impromptu holiday which may last anywhere between 10 days to the end of time (my personal time, friends) - I’d be elated, ecstatic, even. However, the very backing of the same would be resulting in deaths around the world and would be the reason for self-quarantining? Not as idealistic. While COVID-19 is no secret, and there is plenty known as well as unknown about this global pandemic, what has increasingly caught on like wildfire is the machinery related to the meme-making and the subsequent jokes that have flown in. While everyone is apprehensive about the unknown, the at-homeness has led to coping with the situation in any fashion we can. But, why humour? And what version of it is deemed appropriate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it that something that was born along one side of the world and has followed around the entirety of it has led to a strong sense of levity, at this dire time? What room do we have in our heads that makes us condone a business supposedly so corroded? And if not supposedly as corroded as it is supposed to be- what conception of this humour makes the cut?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From making fun of Trump and his infallible speeches (and more importantly, wigs) to now, suggesting how Bollywood star Ranveer Singh dresses like Coronavirus - believe you me, the latter tickled me about as much as it shocked me. The memes have hit like the plague, itself (no pun, intended) - quite unavoidable and with no cure. Just this morning, Snapchat informed me that a proficient actress was being ‘cancelled’ for making less of this pandemic. If she is at fault, aren’t we all? If Tom Hanks can tweet out that he’s lost 216 bouts of rummy with his wife due to the posited isolation of his positive-to-the-virus-self, we laugh, don’t we? It is ‘absolutely amazing’ how well he’s handling the issue at hand. However, if another individual so much as suggest that this pandemic is God’s gift to students- Ma’am, you have a #cancelled on your hands. I, a mere human, only ask for the boundary - where to build the wall, you know? (Please forgive me.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do what I can do best, right about now. I ask. People, Google, one and all. My friend tells me memes are the medicine to this pandemic, at least until you test positive, while a research published in ​Harvard Business Review explains that “laughter relieves stress and boredom, boosts engagement and well-being, and spurs not only creativity and collaboration but also analytic precision and productivity.” It’s the manna from heaven, my friends. All that has troubled us: stress, boredom- cured. One article went ahead and suggested that humour can be and is, very well a form of self-care when experiencing burnout and compassion fatigue. Finding a humorous angle together can serve as a doorway to a deeper connection with other individuals, acting as a buffer. Could it be that a sense of belonging is what we seek, it is this that makes these jokes and memes as popular as they are - our need for affiliation! ​Malchiodi, one of the greatest researchers of ‘the funnies’ has vastly discussed the positive mental and physical results of laughter and/or humour. “Since the late 1980s, a number of studies support the idea that laughter stimulates the immune system and counteracts the effects of stress ​hormones, although results are mixed about exactly how,” she said. “In brief, there’s agreement that it’s another way to arrive at the relaxation response.” ​We’ve got it, people - an explanation as to why there has been a surge in the circulation of COVID-19 memes, parodies and videos aiming to get a laugh out of people. It could be that for certain people, making light of things is more of a coping mechanism than it is a chance at fame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and what fame to give up, too. Please afford me another moment of pondering and I shall be done. In the extensive research that this phenomenon took - what became extremely apparent to me was the cultural difference. While Singapore is busy with how other countries are copying their way of work, or may I suggest, homework; the USA was busy with toilet paper memes (or, better yet, buttcoin, the new currency crowned after the infamous bitcoin.) India, out here, is confused about which issue to put higher up on the hierarchy - the failure of it as a democracy, the communal riots, the pandemic that is barely being considered as one or just the sheer amount of Whatsapp forwards that suggest you drink ‘gau mutra’ (cow urine) and get vaccinated towards Corona. Hitherto, the reigning queen, (and this I say with much bias) has to be the Corona Beer memes and the expected aversion to the same by the sages of the world. The economy is down the drain for most countries, the population - more so. But, I really do think Corona with/without lime deserves better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly enough, and this may be of interest to one and all, the place where Rapunzel isolated herself? Corona. In more ways than one, the world is coming full circle- and while it may be really difficult to go through, it is nonetheless entertaining to watch the unfolding. Just this morning, another friend and I had a long conversation about the conspiracy theories involved with the awakening of COVID-19. Oh, and if you weren’t aware CoronaVirus Disorder- 2019 getting abbreviated has very much to do with the memes, you can ask WHO, they’d attest. While I’m no meme connoisseur, conspiracy theories really get me going but that’s for another day, another time, another beer. Done with my rambling, I warrant my answer to my aforementioned question - why humour? Why this very coping mechanism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I think? It is non-violent resistance to any form of oppression. A successful one at that. It facilitates a culture of resistance, tries to bring levity, sure - but with it, interest and awareness. It’s the pink colour to cough syrups - the pretty packaging to venomous bottles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as ​at a personal level, self-irony and joking about one’s own shortcomings are considered to have the greatest impact on self-liberation through humour, dare I suggest that may be true at the social level, irrespective of cultural and individual differences? Now, what does mere me know? While I ride back home in an airplane where no individual is without a mask or sanitizer - while I go home because my mother would rather I be sick with her than without - while there’s panic and apprehension on almost possible levels of conscious awareness, I wonder if you’d like that Corona with lime or without.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">If one were to tell me that I’d be receiving an impromptu holiday which may last anywhere between 10 days to the end of time (my personal time, friends) - I’d be elated, ecstatic, even. However, the very backing of the same would be resulting in deaths around the world and would be the reason for self-quarantining? Not as idealistic. While COVID-19 is no secret, and there is plenty known as well as unknown about this global pandemic, what has increasingly caught on like wildfire is the machinery related to the meme-making and the subsequent jokes that have flown in. While everyone is apprehensive about the unknown, the at-homeness has led to coping with the situation in any fashion we can. But, why humour? And what version of it is deemed appropriate?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Are You Bored Enough?</title>
      <link href="/Are-You-Bored-Enough" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are You Bored Enough?" />
      <published>2020-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Are-You-Bored-Enough</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Are-You-Bored-Enough">&lt;p&gt;A happy new year, yeah, um, happy? From what I’ve been told, we’re unsubscribing from Jan’20, so, I hope for a good, uneven eleven-month’d year ahead. There has been a huge lapse on my end: I’ve been unable to pen down anything for the longest time. Not because I’m lacking the resources, definitely not the time―what it is, may only be described as dissatisfaction. Dissatisfaction in everything that, I, as an individual of a certain age- living in the country that I live in, belonging to the state I belong to, have had to see. The ghastly past few days and the subsequent coming days, all of it seems too much to bear and I’ve decided I am not to write on it. The awareness that this entire fascist regime (or, situation) in India deserves is beyond anything I can measure, and I can’t remotely do it justice, in no specific way. My bias holds too high and is nowhere near close to being over, not anytime soon. Hence, I’ll use this as a ‘breath of fresh air,’ with how polluted the air I breathe is. In more ways than one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I type this, I’ve Billie crooning in my ears about how she’s so bored, and well, let’s run with it, shall we? Billie deserves her answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bored? Boredom? Equivalent to disinterest? Or, is it a conditioned, negative feeling that shrouds us upon being unproductive? I’ve often felt awful after a day spent watching Netflix. But does that mean I was bored? I wouldn’t say so. But has the binge been productive? I wouldn’t say that, either. So, I go surfing, web surfing and find out what this damned concept entails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several authors from Pascal to Schopenhauer, from Kierkegaard to our very favourite Nietzsche, and Baudelaire, and Dostoevsky―everyone seems to have dropped a cent on this everyday phenomenon. Well, is it an everyday phenomenon all? It almost seems like the closer we get to the present day, the more destructive boredom becomes, compelling creative types—from writers and artists to rock musicians (Slash!!)—to reflect on this theme. Nevertheless, it remains a difficult psychological state to define, more so today, than ever. Kierkegaard equates boredom with the devil and defines it thus: “The demonic is that which is without content, boring.” According to Dostoevsky, boredom is “a bestial and indefinable affliction.” One of the present-day researchers, Elizabeth Goodstein, labels it “experience without qualities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure I agree. I mean, she’s clearly influenced by Robert Musil’s &lt;em&gt;The Man Without Qualities&lt;/em&gt;. The book is simply a diagnosis of everyday life and thrives on the concept of boredom. If one were to read Lars Svendsen’s (pretty much the father of boredom, and one who serves quite a heavy read) &lt;em&gt;A Philosophy of Boredom&lt;/em&gt;, one’ll find out that boredom is a social construction of the era that began in the middle of the 18th century. ‘Interesting’ as a concept came to light simultaneously with that of boredom. It was not up to then accepted practice to classify things as being either “boring” or “interesting.” Understandably, such a classification contrasted ‘boring’ with ‘interesting’. That which was interesting was attractive. To be interesting meant not being boring (I’d suggest you read that over a couple of times, I definitely did.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can definitely claim that boredom is a state of discomfort. The most common terms I can substitute it with may be uninteresting, a growth flowered by disinterest and detachment. It is often understood as a catch-all term. It may be understood in its simplicity, termed ‘simple boredom’, a product of temporarily unavoidable and predictable circumstances (being stuck in a bad date? A sad lecture? An awful movie?) as well as ‘existential boredom’ wherein underlies an unrelieved sense of isolation, emptiness, alienation and even helplessness. The main relationship between these two conditions is probably the loose use of the term ‘boredom’. Another close related concept, ‘chronic boredom’, is, one could guess, more like simple boredom, albeit not temporary. If simple boredom is the result of the circumstances we find ourselves in, chronic boredom is a symptom of a lower than normal level in the system of the neurotransmitter dopamine. The notion of chronic boredom is something that is especially the preserve of psychologists. It is measured in a famous test called the Boredom Proneness Scale (BPS) that was devised in 1986 by the now-retired psychologist Norman D Sundberg. Now that you know types of boredom and how fellow psychology enthusiasts are measuring the same, do you still have an unclear picture? Because I sure do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What of a nuanced concept such as this is so difficult to understand? In his book &lt;em&gt;The Will to Meaning&lt;/em&gt;, Viktor Frankl recorded that contemporary man suffered from a deep sense of loss of meaning; a state that he diagnosed as “existential vacuum.” This sense of loss of meaning characterises post-traditional man who cannot make up his mind as to what he wants and what he must do, since tradition no longer dictates what is necessary. If this way is the right way, boredom appears to be the polar opposite of what Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi has famously termed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brainpickings.org/2012/02/27/purpose-work-love/#flow&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;flow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;—a state of intense focus one enters whilst absorbed in an enthralling task, when one loses track of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen, if someone were to ask me to spend any more than 10 minutes by myself, with nothing else to think of, I’d go insane, and that brings me to the question: are we as a generation more or less bored than the ones who came before us? Now, every day brings a new article about how to stop the demon of lassitude, or a new invention designed to keep us from ever being at loose ends again. Come to think of it, phones got smart, and so did we, with easy access to more information and entertainment than ever before. Now, every moment one spends being bored—while riding an elevator, or waiting at the doctor’s office, or biding time until your date returns from the restroom—is a moment one doesn’t spend reading a book, skimming the news, or catching up on social media. What I may be suggesting is that, being bored in 2020, might just be a slap in the face of technology. Never again will we have nothing to do. This should be a good thing… Right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What in the world goes on in our brains when we get bored? Not just physically, but psychologically? And pray tell, what would go on in our brains if we were to never get bored?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers such as Mashuq Ally have led to a whirlwind romance between authors and the idea of boredom. It has been suggested that something super repetitive that doesn’t need one’s brain to be engaged, that’s when one ignites a network in their brain, one called the ‘default mode’. Neuroscientists have claimed that the default mode is when one does their most original thinking: problem-solving, imagination, empathy, all reside in the house of original thinking. The mind is told to be working as somewhat of a time traveling machine. One goes back and thinks of things that have already conspired and makes sense of them and then extracts lessons from them. They call it autobiographical planning. The unthinking mind-wandering that happens when one is bored takes all the information that has ever entered the brain and makes use of it in innovative ways. In other words: being bored is the difference between being good at &lt;em&gt;Jeopardy!&lt;/em&gt; and being someone who actually &lt;em&gt;uses&lt;/em&gt; the knowledge that one has learned to come up with solutions to fix problems (both of the personal and societal kind).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, boredom is good!? However, boredom too, like other fruits of modernity, has its geography. Despite the fact that no one is safe against boredom, the luxury of being bored is not equally accessible to all societies and strata. And that’s just that. The amount of information we feed ourselves, in this tech driven world, is absurd. No number of hard drives could ever retain all the information I gather from Instagram, or heck, a Buzzfeed video binge. So, why wouldn’t the idea of feeding ourselves more and more information and then never actually doing anything with it seem just perfect? Isn’t that what we’ve been taught ever since we were a kid? I have an art degree and I only have my mum’s concern towards my boredom to thank for it. I mean, I could leave social media, give away my joys in boredom, all so I could self-regulate my thoughts, use the knowledge I’ve previously gained and make the most of it, but wouldn’t that make me Joe from &lt;em&gt;You&lt;/em&gt; and I don’t reckon he was liked by many. Sketchy Joe is no good, friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a culture obsessed with productivity, boredom seems like a sin, not to mention impossible when so much of the everyday stimuli we take for granted—email, ads, Instagram, Netflix, YouTube (God, I can go on, and on and on)―is bent on robbing us of our attention. But sitting back and doing nothing is, ironically, exactly what you need to do in order to get more done. We were so scared of being bored at all that we failed to appreciate the frightening repercussions of not being bored enough. And I only have Billie to thank for this insight. So, next up (on my playlist and search engine): &lt;em&gt;Where do we go when we fall asleep?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A happy new year, yeah, um, happy? From what I’ve been told, we’re unsubscribing from Jan’20, so, I hope for a good, uneven eleven-month’d year ahead. There has been a huge lapse on my end: I’ve been unable to pen down anything for the longest time. Not because I’m lacking the resources, definitely not the time―what it is, may only be described as dissatisfaction. Dissatisfaction in everything that, I, as an individual of a certain age- living in the country that I live in, belonging to the state I belong to, have had to see. The ghastly past few days and the subsequent coming days, all of it seems too much to bear and I’ve decided I am not to write on it. The awareness that this entire fascist regime (or, situation) in India deserves is beyond anything I can measure, and I can’t remotely do it justice, in no specific way. My bias holds too high and is nowhere near close to being over, not anytime soon. Hence, I’ll use this as a ‘breath of fresh air,’ with how polluted the air I breathe is. In more ways than one.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Here’s to Feeling Good All The Time!</title>
      <link href="/Here-s-to-Feeling-Good-All-the-Time" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Here’s to Feeling Good All The Time!" />
      <published>2019-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Here-s-to-Feeling-Good-All-the-Time</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Here-s-to-Feeling-Good-All-the-Time">&lt;p&gt;If you were to walk through my door today, I’d only welcome you with a question: Are you happy? I’m no Dr. Phil, it’s not so much as to check on your well-being (well, not completely), it is mostly to comprehend how happiness became the most important thing ever. Personally, I’ve come to a conclusion. Happiness is overrated and way too popular. Happiness is that jock in high school that everybody crushes on, but no one knows how to talk to. I can put a million researches here explaining how it all works: the biology, physiology, and all of the rest. But, why are we so attracted to the concept? What is this constant desire to be happy? And, pressure!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several aspects of our lives revolve around trying to be happy, wanting to be happy. God! take a shot every time you read happy. Or maybe do that every time you see a sunny post on Instagram giving you lessons on how to be more joyous. Believe you me, you’re about to be very intoxicated. We’re now living in a world where even several social media platforms have changed their algorithm so as to promote a more positive content. We’ve all, in a way, turned into Sisyphus, continuously pushing for joy and happiness, but in return only to find it rolling back on nearing the top. This push seems like it’s going to last us a lifetime, and the irony is not lost on any of us. Out of all the ‘feels’ one could feel- why stick to one and work for it so hard that we forget to feel the rest of the lot?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever heard of ‘struggle porn’? It has been trending in the business world for a long time- it alludes to how romanticised entrepreneurs make struggle out to be. Well, I think, what we have in our hands is- ‘happiness porn’. I’m not here to tell you that feeling good is bad—friend, feeling good is always great, but by putting this impractical expectation on oneself we are actually hurting our manifesting powers more than we are helping them. This constant need to feel a certain way restricts our way to ascertain what we’re feeling all together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re almost, in most ways, taught to judge our feelings as wrong. There are negative feelings and positive ones, but right or wrong? I don’t think so. It’s like being in a battle with yourself, which is causing resistance, which is really the only obstacle that stands between you and the realisation of your feelings. Therefore, feeling bad is not the problem, feeling bad about feeling bad definitely is. Quite an inception. One distinction I have to make is that the opposite of happiness is not sadness, it couldn’t be. Its apathy. It is the opposite of every feeling- not feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feeling good is good, this is a belief that is so intuitive to be almost axiomatic, and there is now substantial data to support it. Yet, most of us do know that perpetual joy is not a practical goal. Recent research is actually starting to suggest that it may actually be a harmful one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Galen_Bodenhausen&quot;&gt;Bodenhausen&lt;/a&gt; and&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/scientific-contributions/79839499_Geoffrey_P_Kramer&quot;&gt; Kramer&lt;/a&gt; (pretty credible names, wouldn’t you say?) stated that “happiness is a kind of a safety signal, indicating that there is no current need for problem solving…..Unhappy people will think more deeply about their social environment (in an effort to solve their problems), whereas happy people can contentedly coast on cruise control, not bothering to think very deeply about surrounding events unless they impinge directly on their well-being”—basically suggesting you’re better off solving things when you’re not obliterated with absolute joy. Serious focus may not be pleasant, but it may be the optimal mood for certain tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that might be troubling? People who are in a good mood are more likely to jump to conclusions about others and less likely to consciously correct any stereotypical notions they harbour. There you go people, want to be in 2020 still harbouring stereotypes? In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/222401249_On_being_happy_and_gullible_Mood_effects_on_skepticism_and_the_detection_of_deception&quot;&gt;2008 study&lt;/a&gt;, nearly 120 students were induced to feel amused, neutral, or sad (by watching a comedy video, a nature documentary, or a film clip about cancer). Then, they watched interrogation videos where other students lied or told the truth about stealing a movie ticket (yeah, they were very thorough). It was seen that the negative-mood group was better at detecting deception than the neutral or positive groups, correctly identifying the liars more often. So, you better keep your Kanye West on when trying to check if people are trying to pull one over you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon talking to a friend this morning about this ‘high school jock’, she expressed that feeling sad is when she feels the most creative. Feeling FOMO may actually foster a more proactive approach. What I’m trying to imply is that all of the rest feelings we’re constantly combating? They ain’t so bad! Instead, let’s look into how, when we express high levels of happiness, research suggests, we are &lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.obhdp.2016.05.006&quot;&gt;perceived as more naive&lt;/a&gt; and are more likely to be targets of exploitation than when we express moderate happiness. This obviously explains why we wait for people to be in a good mood before we ask them for money, hoping that they won’t be as critical and careful in considering our request. Listen, the evolutionary psychologists have made a living off of telling us just what I’m trying to say- that other, less-blissful feelings serve a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are people who have an irrational aversion to being happy, they’re said to suffer from something called ‘cherophobia’, another term could be ‘hedonophobia’, which is defined as the fear of pleasure. This is not what yours truly is drawing upon, not at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you remember the very, very famous movie (that may be credited for the increased tourism in India) -* Eat, Pray, Love*? There was an entire monologue by Elizabeth, herself- “Happiness is the consequence of personal effort. You fight for it, strive for it, insist upon it, and sometimes even travel around the world looking for it, you have to participate relentlessly in the manifestations of your own blessings. And once you have achieved a state of happiness, you must make a mighty effort to keep swimming upward into that happiness forever, to stay afloat on top of it. If you don’t, you will leak away your innate contentment.” This chips at a person’s ability to ever feel okay about loneliness or personal failure. It reads to you that nothing except complete and absolute happiness is all one warrants. Downright absurd, right? People might set very high standards for their own happiness as a function of this view- they may think they should be happy all the time, or extremely happy, and that can set people up to feel disappointed with themselves, that they fall short- and that could have these self-defeating effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our world focuses on happiness and treats unhappiness as an unnecessary or useless feeling. In a 2017 article titled, “The Secret of Happiness, Feeling Good or Feeling Right,” published in the &lt;em&gt;Journal of Experimental Psychology General&lt;/em&gt;, 2,324 university students in eight countries were studied. The researchers found that people may be happier when they feel the emotions they desire, regardless of whether those desired emotions were pleasant or unpleasant. In other words, feeling our feelings is important, more so than whether they are positive or negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure I can use the word happy anymore, especially if you’ve been taking those shots this entire time. All I have to say is that if you were to play &lt;em&gt;Seinfeld&lt;/em&gt;’s S05E04 at 11:46:47, you will hear Kramer say, “here’s to feeling good all the time!” And let’s just remember, that’s not all there is to life.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">If you were to walk through my door today, I’d only welcome you with a question: Are you happy? I’m no Dr. Phil, it’s not so much as to check on your well-being (well, not completely), it is mostly to comprehend how happiness became the most important thing ever. Personally, I’ve come to a conclusion. Happiness is overrated and way too popular. Happiness is that jock in high school that everybody crushes on, but no one knows how to talk to. I can put a million researches here explaining how it all works: the biology, physiology, and all of the rest. But, why are we so attracted to the concept? What is this constant desire to be happy? And, pressure!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Highs and Lows</title>
      <link href="/Highs-and-Lows" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Highs and Lows" />
      <published>2019-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Highs-and-Lows</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Highs-and-Lows">&lt;p&gt;What questions do I bring forth today? What mundane instances caught my eye and left me high and dry? What search brought on a flurry of more searches? Well, today’s going to be a little different. In the past few weeks, I’ve found a multitude of things that I want to talk, write and think about, and I shall, soon enough, but today, I’m switching my tandem just a tad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, life’s been more Rocky Road and less Blueberry Swirl. Submerged under a mountainous pile of assignments - some pending and most, already doomed - a couple of really strenuous friendships and a moderately significant heartbreak, the painting seemed all too grey. And while that’s my favourite colour, I don’t prefer it in shades of life. And hence, I did what most suggest you do in times of need: sit, reflect, meditate, or better yet, run away to the hills or the beaches. So, I chose the latter and ran away - to older hills, for a couple of days, met a couple of new people, stayed in a hostel - even strayed away from social media. Phew, right? But, why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, it was just procrastination with a beautiful view and some good food and wine. But that isn’t the case for most, is it? An &lt;em&gt;Eat, Pray, Love&lt;/em&gt; escape is not warranted for all. I overheard a fellow dorm-mate say he had earned enough money to buy a big house, but he didn’t want to share it with anyone, so he packed his bags and lo and behold- has been travelling for the last 2 years. His joy and reflection almost made me feel guilty. I didn’t have a good enough reason, nothing as inspirational, nothing with foreshadow per se. Mostly just running away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people travel to challenge themselves - to run amok places one shouldn’t be able to, to jump off of cliffs, to rage in the adrenaline. Some travel with a specific goal. The goal being to learn something: a new dialect, a new cuisine, a different culture or to develop a deeper appreciation for faith or spirituality. Some do it with others to build stronger relationships, to strengthen their bonds. &lt;em&gt;Virtuoso&lt;/em&gt;, a popular travel magazine, named ‘Multigenerational Travel’ as the top trend of 2018. One may even move around to find new people to create new friendships, new bonds. Traveling seems like a gift that keeps giving. It expands your perspective, as seen in several eudaimonic travel experience researches. It helps us appreciate our lives, a little more than usual. It also is the reason you can come home and excuse a picture of your room, on your Instagram, with a gif - home sweet home. On note of that, it also makes you InstaPopular (but that’d be very shallow of me to add, so excuse me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you may think why is this girl jabbering on and on about one trip and how travel is the boon of our existence? Truthfully? I am not so sure. All I had in my head when I started this off was why is it that people suggest traveling when one is sad, or not having the best time. I understand a change of view may bring a change of heart, or how looking at others’ challenges may bring in a better perspective for your own, or how just taking a break must feel amazing. Hell, there’s so much to see, why must there be a reason to feast your eyes? I’m only looking for this socialised understanding’s bare roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year millions of people leave all that they have, in order to see the world; some in joy, some out of worry, some because there’s no other option. If you’ve watched &lt;em&gt;Parts Unknown&lt;/em&gt;, I’m sure Bourdain made you feel all kinds of joy. I distinctly remember him saying in an episode shot in Tangier, Morocco: “I’ve always wanted to get as far away as possible from the place that I was born. Far both geographically and spiritually. To leave it behind.” While this might seem contrary to the inherent human desire to fit into a tribe, to have a close community, it does reflect a state of being less understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a thousand and one songs - all talking about how one wants to fly away, zoom into sunsets, never to be back - leave it all behind. And while, I’d say most people would love to open their hair, wear 90’s glasses, drive a Camaro along the LA coast, I’m not sure the romanticisation of going away is healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, no part of me can say that I didn’t have a good time. I understand and recognise my privilege at being able to plan a trip to a place and visit it all in about 24 hours. I feel lucky to have seen all that I did and experience all that I experienced. What expunges my certainty of how good all this is - how to let go of the nuisances in your life just by going to a scenic place? I can’t say that when I sat there, listening to a fellow person play the ukulele, sipping my blessed coffee, staring at snow-capped mountains - that I didn’t forget all there was to forget. Sure, I did. But, for how long? And honestly, if I were to forget it all anyway, wouldn’t that be worse? Pathway to repression? Not Disney perfect, albeit Disney recommended. Suppression, the conscious forcing of unwanted thoughts, memories, or feelings out of conscious awareness, more apropos than repression in this scenario, leads to bottling up of feelings and emotions and inability to deal with misgivings in the long run. If used in the right fashion, it may be beneficial, but everytime one is given the chance to run away instead of dealing with something, they miss out on learning. Not to mention, suppression requires that we focus our mind on a negative emotion. By suppressing a feeling of anger, we start worrying about feeling angry, which attaches us to the emotion and heats up our mind and costs us extra energy. A cycle that maybe never ending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I’m not saying don’t go around the world and explore, I implore that you don’t run away from something to look at these otherworldly scenes. I suggest that you deal with all the uglies at hand and then go around looking for beauty. To be what you really want to be, you need to accustom yourself to the steps underneath. Well, that’s all I got today. Thanks for coming to my TED Talk.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">What questions do I bring forth today? What mundane instances caught my eye and left me high and dry? What search brought on a flurry of more searches? Well, today’s going to be a little different. In the past few weeks, I’ve found a multitude of things that I want to talk, write and think about, and I shall, soon enough, but today, I’m switching my tandem just a tad.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What Even is Happening?</title>
      <link href="/What-Even-is-Happening" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Even is Happening?" />
      <published>2019-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-Even-is-Happening</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-Even-is-Happening">&lt;p&gt;Hello, I’m Harshita and I’m addicted to this phenomenon called ‘web surfing’,
which sounds like the closest adventure sport I could ever be into and oh well.
Today, I bring to you a new question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, perhaps not as new as I’d like it to be. About an hour or two ago, on a
podcast I heard a 15-year-old say and I quote, “… in previous eras, they had
wars with guns and gas, and in ours, we war with our own self.” To give you more
context, she reinstated what we all can see but perhaps are unable to
acknowledge- we’re all in an epidemic, one which is not as visible as we think
it to be- mental health issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With more than 10 million posts on Instagram with the hashtag ‘mental_health’
and about ten times more of blogs on Tumblr, it’d be wrong of me to say we don’t
talk about it enough. I know that we do, hell, we more than just talk about it.
And yet, it’s an epidemic with no foreseeable solution. I can sit here and go on
and on about how maybe we are more aware of these mental issues now because
people are more knowledgeable of the same, maybe because the stigma is being
fought against, perhaps, we just are more courageous than the ones who came
before us. What I can’t give up on are the words by my 15-year-old muse, is she
right in believing that just as every era is to go through one huge
debilitation, we’ve been destined to fall into the chasm of mental health chaos?
Would it be wrong of me to assume that there are more factors than just
awareness that are making us all a little more troubled than ever?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t give you a solid number for the amount of times I’ve said ‘Same!’
when someone around me said, ‘I can’t live this life no more’ or, ‘Ugh! I’m so
depressed’ or something akin to it. I know I’ve uttered the words ‘I want to
die’ on multiple accounts, once because I couldn’t bear the heat. Albeit the
fact that I know it’s asinine to have claimed the same, it is difficult not to
do the same. I could tell you it’s because it’s ingrained, because I’ve been
conditioned and been rewarded quite positively or, perhaps, because everyone
around me does it and if Bandura had anything to say for it, he’d agree. All
around us- in the spaces we most frequent, there’s a strong prevalence of (and I
say this off of my personal disposition) romanticisation of mental illness.
Somehow our move to ‘delete the stigma’ has drastically changed towards a trend
to ‘romanticise the stigma’. While it’s not something that one should be ashamed
of, it also isn’t something one should aspire for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it that on Tumblr, #Thinspo is always trending, why is it that not
sleeping and being perpetually tired has become a way of popular culture? How
did self-inflicted scars come to be called art? When did the ‘Sad Girls Club’
become the new ideal, often propagated by the VSCO girls or the new e-girls?
What about #proana? I remember reading &lt;em&gt;Looking for Alaska&lt;/em&gt; and being astounded
by how easily the teenage girl said, and oh, ‘with delight of a kid on a
Christmas morning’- “Y’all smoke to enjoy it. I smoke to die.” If you’ve ever
gone down the Instagram explore page, you’ve definitely been acquainted with Sir
R.M. Drake and his well-fonted, honey-coloured quotes such as that of, ‘We
desire to keep the pain close, close enough to destroy us.’  Upon learning more,
I found out about how a popular jewellery brand conceived a new line of
necklaces with the words- ‘depression’, ‘anxiety’ and ‘bipolar’ inscribed on
them. Twitter has multiple accounts such as that of &lt;em&gt;So Sad Today&lt;/em&gt;. I guess what
I’m trying to allude to is- The Sad Online Culture. You can’t tell me you’ve
never seen a post where someone is staring into the distance, the picture tuned
to darker shades, and a caption with something negative/sad. There is a new
culture of equalling beauty to tragedy. Pain, melancholy are seen as artsy. It’s
not to say I don’t like my fair share of Lana Del Rey or I don’t appreciate all
the API trimmed sappy content Instagram throws at me. In fact, if you’ve got
time- you really ought to check out this feminist philosophy called &lt;a href=&quot;https://believermag.com/in-conversation-with-mira-gonzalez/&quot;&gt;Sad Girl
Theory&lt;/a&gt;, penned by
artist Audrey Wollen, who, by the way, goes by ’&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/audreywollen/?hl=en&quot;&gt;Tragic
Queen&lt;/a&gt;‘ on Instagram. There’s the
complicated concept of creativity and mental illness, but that requires a long,
let’s get cookies and milk/wine (whatever’s your poison), sit down. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Withstanding all that I’ve mentioned above, I’m still well aware of how social
media has allowed mental health issues to become more widely known and accepted,
how they have allowed us all to share personal stories and accounts of many a
psychological disorder. They’re often seen as support systems to encourage and
inform others of one’s own personal experiences and yet, it also comprises an
entire added bonus of trivialising these disorders. Sites that allow anonymous
posting end up becoming group therapy sessions with no therapist to take charge
of the situation. This is where one may find people suffering the same way that
they are but it is highly likely that instead of improving their situation, it
ends up becoming a constant, painful cycle of reinforcement. All of this leads
to people expressing their emotions and hardships which end up looking like an
effort to romanticise the ordeals. It is noteworthy, however, to know that one
might just be unaware that one is romanticising something. People feel that they
are merely sharing their thoughts and feelings. For the vulnerable mind, these
online spaces become communities that seemingly provide the ideal solution:
support, understanding, acceptance. To be accepted by this community, it is
almost as if one has to advertise one’s suffering. Thus, subconsciously a choice
is made- to suffer, to fit in and get acceptance. “Adaptability is what makes us
both wonderful and terrible. We can easily forget what’s healthy- can adapt to
really unhealthy environments quickly. And it so often feels somehow right even
when it’s not,” said Whitlock. This is not a ‘you’ or ‘me’ situation, this is a
complete trajectory of a ‘we’ situation. More often than not, we invest in this
world, consciously or not- and help it prosper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might have made a lot of foes for saying all that I have, but once in a while,
one’s bound to have a curious case of ‘What even is happening?’ I don’t come
here with ways to live one’s life, I only come here with questions.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="from-the-horses-mouth" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Hello, I’m Harshita and I’m addicted to this phenomenon called ‘web surfing’, which sounds like the closest adventure sport I could ever be into and oh well. Today, I bring to you a new question. Okay, perhaps not as new as I’d like it to be. About an hour or two ago, on a podcast I heard a 15-year-old say and I quote, “… in previous eras, they had wars with guns and gas, and in ours, we war with our own self.” To give you more context, she reinstated what we all can see but perhaps are unable to acknowledge- we’re all in an epidemic, one which is not as visible as we think it to be- mental health issues. With more than 10 million posts on Instagram with the hashtag ‘mental_health’ and about ten times more of blogs on Tumblr, it’d be wrong of me to say we don’t talk about it enough. I know that we do, hell, we more than just talk about it. And yet, it’s an epidemic with no foreseeable solution. I can sit here and go on and on about how maybe we are more aware of these mental issues now because people are more knowledgeable of the same, maybe because the stigma is being fought against, perhaps, we just are more courageous than the ones who came before us. What I can’t give up on are the words by my 15-year-old muse, is she right in believing that just as every era is to go through one huge debilitation, we’ve been destined to fall into the chasm of mental health chaos? Would it be wrong of me to assume that there are more factors than just awareness that are making us all a little more troubled than ever? I couldn’t give you a solid number for the amount of times I’ve said ‘Same!’ when someone around me said, ‘I can’t live this life no more’ or, ‘Ugh! I’m so depressed’ or something akin to it. I know I’ve uttered the words ‘I want to die’ on multiple accounts, once because I couldn’t bear the heat. Albeit the fact that I know it’s asinine to have claimed the same, it is difficult not to do the same. I could tell you it’s because it’s ingrained, because I’ve been conditioned and been rewarded quite positively or, perhaps, because everyone around me does it and if Bandura had anything to say for it, he’d agree. All around us- in the spaces we most frequent, there’s a strong prevalence of (and I say this off of my personal disposition) romanticisation of mental illness. Somehow our move to ‘delete the stigma’ has drastically changed towards a trend to ‘romanticise the stigma’. While it’s not something that one should be ashamed of, it also isn’t something one should aspire for. Why is it that on Tumblr, #Thinspo is always trending, why is it that not sleeping and being perpetually tired has become a way of popular culture? How did self-inflicted scars come to be called art? When did the ‘Sad Girls Club’ become the new ideal, often propagated by the VSCO girls or the new e-girls? What about #proana? I remember reading Looking for Alaska and being astounded by how easily the teenage girl said, and oh, ‘with delight of a kid on a Christmas morning’- “Y’all smoke to enjoy it. I smoke to die.” If you’ve ever gone down the Instagram explore page, you’ve definitely been acquainted with Sir R.M. Drake and his well-fonted, honey-coloured quotes such as that of, ‘We desire to keep the pain close, close enough to destroy us.’  Upon learning more, I found out about how a popular jewellery brand conceived a new line of necklaces with the words- ‘depression’, ‘anxiety’ and ‘bipolar’ inscribed on them. Twitter has multiple accounts such as that of So Sad Today. I guess what I’m trying to allude to is- The Sad Online Culture. You can’t tell me you’ve never seen a post where someone is staring into the distance, the picture tuned to darker shades, and a caption with something negative/sad. There is a new culture of equalling beauty to tragedy. Pain, melancholy are seen as artsy. It’s not to say I don’t like my fair share of Lana Del Rey or I don’t appreciate all the API trimmed sappy content Instagram throws at me. In fact, if you’ve got time- you really ought to check out this feminist philosophy called Sad Girl Theory, penned by artist Audrey Wollen, who, by the way, goes by ’Tragic Queen‘ on Instagram. There’s the complicated concept of creativity and mental illness, but that requires a long, let’s get cookies and milk/wine (whatever’s your poison), sit down.  Withstanding all that I’ve mentioned above, I’m still well aware of how social media has allowed mental health issues to become more widely known and accepted, how they have allowed us all to share personal stories and accounts of many a psychological disorder. They’re often seen as support systems to encourage and inform others of one’s own personal experiences and yet, it also comprises an entire added bonus of trivialising these disorders. Sites that allow anonymous posting end up becoming group therapy sessions with no therapist to take charge of the situation. This is where one may find people suffering the same way that they are but it is highly likely that instead of improving their situation, it ends up becoming a constant, painful cycle of reinforcement. All of this leads to people expressing their emotions and hardships which end up looking like an effort to romanticise the ordeals. It is noteworthy, however, to know that one might just be unaware that one is romanticising something. People feel that they are merely sharing their thoughts and feelings. For the vulnerable mind, these online spaces become communities that seemingly provide the ideal solution: support, understanding, acceptance. To be accepted by this community, it is almost as if one has to advertise one’s suffering. Thus, subconsciously a choice is made- to suffer, to fit in and get acceptance. “Adaptability is what makes us both wonderful and terrible. We can easily forget what’s healthy- can adapt to really unhealthy environments quickly. And it so often feels somehow right even when it’s not,” said Whitlock. This is not a ‘you’ or ‘me’ situation, this is a complete trajectory of a ‘we’ situation. More often than not, we invest in this world, consciously or not- and help it prosper. I might have made a lot of foes for saying all that I have, but once in a while, one’s bound to have a curious case of ‘What even is happening?’ I don’t come here with ways to live one’s life, I only come here with questions.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
