<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/manya.manushi/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-02-25T08:37:04+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/manya.manushi/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">South Africa’s New Land Policy - Inclusion with Exclusion</title>
      <link href="/South-Africa-Land-Policy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="South Africa's New Land Policy - Inclusion with Exclusion" />
      <published>2019-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/South%20Africa-Land-Policy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/South-Africa-Land-Policy">&lt;p&gt;Purple hiring (providing employment opportunities to the differently-abled) or positive discrimination in jobs and financial literacy are seemingly unrelated concepts. However, the underlying idea is common - inclusion. Some people talk about ‘inclusion’ as though it is topical, for politicians it is new rhetoric, for activists it is an instrument of social justice and, for businesses, it is an opportunity. In South Africa, inclusion is being seen by many as a way to correct apartheid era injustice through land expropriation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue has its genesis in the Natives Land Act, 1913, that reserved about 93% of the land for the white minority. The Native Trust and Land Act, 1936, subsequently reduced it to 87%. Further, these Acts legally sanctioned historical dispossession of the African people’s land. The year 1994 saw the end of apartheid in South Africa. It brought along with it hope of land redistribution to the Rainbow Nation’s communities. Section 25 of the Constitution provided for land expropriation with just and equitable compensation. The government relied on a “willing-seller, willing-buyer” land redistribution policy to correct the historical wrong. Under this approach, the government bought land against compensation and redistributed it to the dispossessed people. The policy did not yield desired results due to the unwillingness of property owners to sell and their demand of exorbitantly high prices in many cases. Even today, 72% of agricultural land is in the hands of white South Africans, i.e. 8% of the population, whereas only 4% of land is owned by black South Africans (over 80% of the population). President Jacob Zuma’s government tried to address this issue in 2016 by introducing a bill in the parliament to end the “willing-buyer, willing-seller” policy and providing for payment for land acquired by expropriation in the public interest at adjudicator value. In view of growing discontent coupled with a high rate of unemployment, Zuma’s successor, Cyril Ramaphosa pushed the idea of redistribution of (only unused) land without compensation in 2017. The year 2018 saw the adoption of a report by the South African Parliament, recommending the amendment of section 25 of the Constitution to expropriate land without compensation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This idea of addressing the present skewed land ownership issue has initiated a debate and has made land a hot-button issue. The breakaway group of the ruling African National Congress, the Economic Freedom Fighters (EFF), is in principle against Ramaphosa’s policy. But only because it favours a more radical nationalisation of banks and land as the only means to undo historical injustice. However, opponents of expropriation without compensation argue that South Africa may go Zimbabwe’s way, where a fast track land reform process led to large-scale violence. Many white farmers fled the country at the turn of the century to neighbouring countries like Zambia, Mozambique, the Congo and Nigeria. This exodus converted Zimbabwe from a food exporting country to one facing frequent food shortages. According to an estimate by a Zimbabwean economist and legislator, Eddie Cross, the total cost that the economy has borne due to the adoption of this policy is around $20 billion. Banks have also expressed their reservation on the proposed amendment. They have about $114 billion of mortgages outstanding against land. Their concerns are not being addressed. Further, the possibility of civil war engulfing the most industrialised country in Africa cannot be ruled out. Many far-right groups have claimed that white farmers are being killed and forced expropriations are already happening. In August 2018, Donald Trump’s tweet in their support added fuel to the fire. If violence spreads, it is likely to affect tourism, which contributes about 10% to the GDP. It would dampen the investor sentiment as well. The country, at present, is an attractive emerging market despite economic woes for investors because of two reasons. Firstly, it has an expanding middle class and secondly, its location at the tip of the African continent makes it a perfect gateway to the huge African market consisting of about one billion people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many defects in Ramaphosa’s policy design. It is unclear on what basis land will be redistributed, and how the beneficiaries will be identified. If land has changed hands against adequate compensation, will it have any impact on new owner’s rights? The parameters to identify ‘unused land’ have not been clearly defined. The policy seems to be the government’s ploy to counter the growing popularity of the EFF in the country, particularly against the background of upcoming elections in May 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One really wonders why politicians around the world try to achieve inclusion of one group by excluding another. Such inclusion-exclusion is certainly not a zero-sum game because players over the years change. After all, why must the present generation pay for the ‘wrongs’ done by their forefathers? The Indian policy of caste-based quotas for achieving social justice through inclusion is continuing even after seventy years of independence. More and more groups are demanding quotas, causing social unrest at times. In South Africa, even after 25 years in power, the ANC has failed to conclude a fair land reform process successfully. But will South Africa’s new (and potentially dangerous) experiment with inclusion lead to the desired result (whatever that is)? Only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Purple hiring (providing employment opportunities to the differently-abled) or positive discrimination in jobs and financial literacy are seemingly unrelated concepts. However, the underlying idea is common - inclusion. Some people talk about ‘inclusion’ as though it is topical, for politicians it is new rhetoric, for activists it is an instrument of social justice and, for businesses, it is an opportunity. In South Africa, inclusion is being seen by many as a way to correct apartheid era injustice through land expropriation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Green Finance: A Financial Policy Innovation</title>
      <link href="/Green-Finance" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Green Finance: A Financial Policy Innovation" />
      <published>2019-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Green-Finance</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Green-Finance">&lt;p&gt;“Go Green” is no longer mere rhetoric, it is imperative in our times. Decision-makers, whether at the level of the country or corporate, need to internalize environmental externalities while framing almost all strategic policies. Financial policy is certainly no exception. The concept that integrates concern for the environment and adequate return on investments is ‘Green Finance’. It is defined by scholars as “financial investments flowing into sustainable development projects and initiatives, environmental products, and policies that encourage the development of a more sustainable economy.” Besides climate finance, it includes financial inflows made in projects with objectives such as controlling industrial pollution, better waste management, encouraging sustainable agriculture, and the protection of aquatic and terrestrial ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The role of carbon emissions in causing global warming is a matter of common knowledge and an issue of concern for humanity. According to a World Bank estimate, infrastructure development, construction, power plants, and transport system operations are responsible for 70% of global greenhouse emissions. There is an urgent need to develop technologies that are not based on greenhouse gases and the combustion of fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shift requires huge investment for green transformation. New investment is also needed for other green endeavours like those that seek to protect biodiversity, or to control all types of pollution. To mobilise this money, innovative financial instruments like green bonds are being issued by corporates, green banks are being set up, and many commercial banks, central banks, governments and institutional investors across the world have adopted policies to ensure green financial governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raising Green Finance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Greening’ the financial system requires long term funds that are being made available through green bonds, green grants and the establishment of financial institutions like green banks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green bonds are financial instruments whose proceeds are used to encourage investment in sustainability/climate or environment-related projects. The most important institutional investor in this space is the World Bank and as on March 2018, the World Bank has raised over $10 billion through green bonds. It finances green projects all over the world. India’s Rampur Hydropower Project, which aims to provide low-carbon hydroelectric power to northern India’s electricity grid is a case in point. Both developed and developing countries are raising money through green bonds. The first Asian green bond was issued in 2013 by the Export-Import Bank of Korea, raising $500 million. China, the global leader in green finance, accounts for about 40% of green bonds issued globally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The banking sector contributes to the greening of the financial system by providing green loans and by establishing green banks. Triodos Bank NV, based in the Netherlands is the first bank in the world that started financing green projects in 1991. Banks all over the world followed suit. Green banks are established specifically with the objective of making finance available for environment-friendly projects or for cleaner technologies. The Connecticut Green Bank in the United States, established in 2011, is the first green bank in the world. Similar banks have started operations in the United Kingdom, Malaysia, Australia, and Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Governments provide grants, particularly, to small and medium businesses to invest in green technologies. Non-profit foundations with an environmental mission offer grants or invest in green banks and projects. The Toyota Foundation, the Hewlett Foundation, and the Rockefeller Foundation are among those that give grants to support clean energy. Even companies such as Boeing, Ford, PVR Ltd, and others offer green grants to NGOs and individuals. Oil majors such as ONGC (India), Total (France), BP (United Kingdom), Repsol (Spain) and many others are adopting a futuristic approach and are making substantial investments for development of renewable energy. On December 28, 2018, Anglo-Dutch oil company Shell announced its intention to double the amount it spends on green energy to $4bn a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Barriers to Greening of Finance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projects that need funding through green finance have long gestation periods. Thus, the risk associated with green investment is typically long term in nature while lending is, generally, available for the short term. Mark Carney, the Governor of the Bank of England, has aptly termed this mismatch in lending and investment as a “tragedy of the horizon”. Parameters for risk assessment of green projects are also still evolving. Due to this, it is difficult for banks to assess credit risk and hence there is a reluctance to lend to such projects. Moreover, there is an acute shortage of staff that can screen green projects. Finally, businesses that tap green finance have to bear additional costs as finance for green projects is raised at a higher cost as compared to conventional projects due to the higher risk involved. In this competitive world, such businesses cannot pass it to consumers and hence, their bottom line gets adversely affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Way Forward&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the issues outlined, the amount to be mobilised through green finance is huge. For Southeast Asia alone, the amount to be mobilised for high carbon emission sectors like power and transport, and sectors vital for humanity such as water and sanitation through 2025 is estimated to be $110 billion a year (ASEAN Investment Report, 2015). This huge investment cannot come through unless there is a revamp of policy measures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;a. Institutional Support&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No country in the world can remain unaffected from consequences of disturbance in its ecological balance. Though the World Bank and International Finance Corporation are doing good work to promote green finance, a multilateral financial institution is needed to give it the desired push. It is surprising that at the Climate Summits, this issue has never been brought up. Mitigation cost is always the core issue of discussion, but never is the issue of green finance required for new projects. The International Investors Group on Climate Change (IIGCC), a network of nearly 150 members, including nine of the 10 largest pension funds in Europe has been formed to encourage the inflow of green finance, but the scope of its activities is limited only to projects involving clean energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;b. Adequate Disclosures&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many companies in G-20 nations are giving environment-related information in their financial filings. The top 500 listed companies in India have to make such disclosures in a Business Responsibility Report as a part of their annual reports. But these disclosure norms have not been standardised, leading to difficulty in greening finance. Regulatory authorities should ensure that banks disclose their green loan data at regular intervals. Chinese banks do it and their model may be replicated by other banks across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;c. Factoring of Environmental Cost in Lending Portfolios&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financial intermediaries, which include multilateral development banks, commercial banks, and private equity firms should develop mechanisms to factor environmental costs to determine the cost of capital for their projects. This will ensure the total cost of projects which are likely to damage the environment is higher than green projects. In this domain, the UNEP Finance Initiative is working with banks, insurers, and investors to remove the issues emanating from difficulty in assessing environmental risk. Natural Capital Finance Alliance (NCFA), a finance sector-led initiative, has recently launched ENCORE (Exploring Natural Capital Opportunities, Risks and Exposure), which is a web-based tool to assess the environmental cost of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To promote green finance, priority areas should be identified by policymakers in consultation with all the stakeholders. Only then an enabling framework can be developed. The regulators and world leaders need to embrace a vision for development that integrates economic growth with sustainability issues. And to do that, they must ensure that money, whether private or public, is pumped into the right kind of activities and projects. After all, without proper financing, no projects or initiatives can achieve tangible results. The same goes for green projects and the dream of a sustainable future.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Go Green” is no longer mere rhetoric, it is imperative in our times. Decision-makers, whether at the level of the country or corporate, need to internalize environmental externalities while framing almost all strategic policies. Financial policy is certainly no exception. The concept that integrates concern for the environment and adequate return on investments is ‘Green Finance’. It is defined by scholars as “financial investments flowing into sustainable development projects and initiatives, environmental products, and policies that encourage the development of a more sustainable economy.” Besides climate finance, it includes financial inflows made in projects with objectives such as controlling industrial pollution, better waste management, encouraging sustainable agriculture, and the protection of aquatic and terrestrial ecosystems.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Climate Pacts: Can They Alone Deliver Climate Justice?</title>
      <link href="/Climate-Pacts" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climate Pacts: Can They Alone Deliver Climate Justice?" />
      <published>2019-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Climate-Pacts</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Climate-Pacts">&lt;p&gt;The concern for rising global temperatures due to climate change is seemingly pervasive across the world. While combating climate change is important, ensuring climate justice in the process of doing so is equally important. Climate justice involves upholding the rights of those affected by climate change and factoring in the concerns of developing countries in the fight against climate change. Some major policy initiatives taken at the global level to combat climate change and deliver climate justice include the Kyoto Protocol (1992) and the Paris Agreement (2015). The latest development in this sphere has been the 24th edition of the UN Climate Change Conference (called COP24) held in the coal town of Katowice, Poland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this round of climate talks, the participating members agreed upon the adoption of rules framed for the implementation of the Paris Agreement. While the Agreement has specified that nations will work towards reducing global temperatures by 2°C, the rulebook provides the action plan that needs to be undertaken to ensure that reduction. Two weeks of negotiations among nations culminated in the drafting of this rulebook. It is certainly dynamic in nature: new guidelines can be added and existing ones can be amended. The basic aim of these guidelines, which will come into force in the year 2020, is to provide countries with a standard framework. It will help them to record and report the emission of greenhouse gases in their own country, to monitor financial flows for climate mitigation and adaptation, and to transfer technologies amongst countries. These initiatives are necessary to aid populations of developing countries to cope with natural disasters that have a strong link to climate change. They are also needed to allow for the development of climate-resilient varieties of crops, improved weather forecasts, reduction in pollution and for dealing with public health issues arising due to climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rulebook has devised an accounting framework to measure and verify the financial inflows―loans, grants or concessions. It is likely to bring in transparency in the sphere of climate finance. Many global leaders have termed this as a victory for multilateralism, particularly at a time when the 13th summit of the Group of Twenty (G20) members (held in Argentina) gave a clear signal that this concept is under threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, however, there are a plethora of issues which have been left unaddressed in this rulebook. Firstly, the rulebook does not adequately address the issue of carbon trading systems envisaged by the Kyoto Protocol. A country or an industry, in a carbon market, can earn carbon credits if it mitigates emissions beyond the limit set under Art. 6 of the Paris Agreement, and later it can trade them too. When this topic was taken up in Katowice, the issue of double-counting of emission reductions was brought to the fore. In the context of carbon trading, double-counting is a situation when a country, let us say X, transfers its carbon credits to another country, Y, to enable Y to meet its emission targets whilst X also counts its own carbon credits towards meeting its own targets. Another issue of contention related to carbon credits was the adjustment of unused accumulated carbon credits by countries like China and Brazil. The current talks have failed to settle these issues; rather the discussion has been postponed to the next year. One fails to understand how postponement of a contentious issue would help the cause of climate justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the rulebook fails to recognise that developed and developing countries must have different responsibilities towards climate change mitigation and adaptation. The argument for a climate clean-up has been built, until now, upon a fundamental tenet of equity. Art. 14 of the Paris Agreement captures it emphatically and states &lt;em&gt;“…equity demands that the vulnerabilities, problems, and challenges of the poor and marginalised be prioritised to ensure climate justice..”&lt;/em&gt;. The Agreement envisaged climate mitigation funds as an important means to ensure equity. However, in the rulebook, there is no clarity on how funds would be mobilised for the fight against climate change. This lacuna is all the more conspicuous because even after promising $100 billion every year as mitigation funds in 2009, rich countries have actually paid out only 12% of this figure. If climate justice is to be delivered, arranging climate finance with regard to the economic status of different countries should be the top-most priority of global leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the lack of ambition of global leaders, as captured during climate negotiations, is a major impediment in the way of delivering climate justice. The rising parochialism of citizens across the world is also a matter of great concern. The elevation of some leaders to the position of Head of State clearly reflects this. Scott Morrison, who openly exhibited his support for the world’s dirtiest fossil fuel-coal-by bringing a lump of it to the Australian Parliament, became Prime Minister of Australia in August 2018, replacing Malcolm Turnbull, who was working towards a transition to cleaner forms of energy. Donald Trump, who wants to “Make America Great Again”, has announced his country’s withdrawal from the Paris Agreement. And in November 2018, the Brazilians elected Jair Bolsonaro as President who proposes to promote agribusiness in the Amazon forest and construct roads there. This can have a seriously negative impact on the climate as the Amazon Basin is the world’s largest carbon sink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line seems to be that climate justice cannot be ensured through climate pacts alone. The first thing we need to ensure is that these climate pacts are actually implemented and that developing countries stand up for their poor and vulnerable citizens. India and China put together have about 36% of the world’s population living in them. They are important consumer markets for various multinational companies from the developed world, which is historically responsible for carbon emissions. These two countries should use this advantage and pitch for climate justice by ensuring proper implementation frameworks and equitable distribution of funds at the global level. In addition, citizens of the world should stand against the indifference of leaders to climate change concerns, and speak out on the issue to ensure a sustainable future for themselves. The aim of preventing climate change and ensuring climate justice requires the combined effort of both the world’s peoples and its governments. And a reliance on climate pacts alone will only provide solutions on &lt;i&gt;paper &lt;/i&gt; to a potentially grave problem.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The concern for rising global temperatures due to climate change is seemingly pervasive across the world. While combating climate change is important, ensuring climate justice in the process of doing so is equally important. Climate justice involves upholding the rights of those affected by climate change and factoring in the concerns of developing countries in the fight against climate change. Some major policy initiatives taken at the global level to combat climate change and deliver climate justice include the Kyoto Protocol (1992) and the Paris Agreement (2015). The latest development in this sphere has been the 24th edition of the UN Climate Change Conference (called COP24) held in the coal town of Katowice, Poland.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Universal Healthcare and The India Story</title>
      <link href="/Universal-Healthcare-and-The-India-Story" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Universal Healthcare and The India Story" />
      <published>2019-01-03T20:40:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T20:40:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Universal-Healthcare-and-The-India-Story</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Universal-Healthcare-and-The-India-Story">&lt;p&gt;A joint study by the World Bank and the World Health Organisation (WHO): Tracking Universal Health Coverage: 2017 Global Monitoring Report, points out the abysmal state of health services across the globe. According to it, at least half of the world’s population does not have access to essential health services and for about 100 million people out-of-pocket health expenses are high enough to push them into extreme poverty each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Nations has envisaged Universal Health Coverage (UHC) as a possible solution to address this humongous problem. According to the WHO, Universal health coverage (UHC) means, “all people and communities can use the promotive, preventive, curative, rehabilitative and palliative health services they need, of sufficient quality to be effective, while also ensuring that the use of these services does not expose the user to financial hardship”. The underlying idea behind UHC is health for all at an affordable cost. The concept of Universal Health Coverage (UHC) emerged with the World Health Report of 2010 and considering its importance, the United Nation (UN) in 2015 included it as one of the Sustainable Development Goals. It has earmarked December 12 of every year as International Universal Health Coverage (UHC) Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the UHC movement has gained unprecedented momentum globally during the last five-six years, Japan, Singapore, and Thailand in Asia have been doing commendable work in this arena for many of the past decades. More than seventy countries across the world, with the notable exception of USA, have framed policies around the UHC. The common thread running across all such programmes is governmental involvement and action. India, the largest democracy of the world, too, has taken a vital step towards Universal Health Coverage (UHC). The Indian government rolled out a scheme- Ayushman Bharat: the National Health Protection Mission on September 25, 2018. This scheme has been framed after taking into consideration the dismal status of the health-care system in India, and also as a response to the order given by the Supreme Court of India to the Central Government to “do something” when the exorbitant prices of medical care were brought to its attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ayushman Bharat is aimed at providing guaranteed access to free treatment to about 40% of India’s population. The population will be selected based on socio-economic factors. About 150,000 wellness clinics will be set up. They will provide comprehensive health care facilities such as free essential drugs, maternal and child health services, treatment for non-communicable diseases and much more. Setting up clinics is a tried and tested component of UHC that many countries like China and Sri Lanka have adopted to improve access to health services to the poor. And, theoretically, it should work in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1977, South Korea gave a strong push to compulsory health insurance and Japan designed national health insurance coverage as early as in 1961. To replicate their success, a second element  of Ayushman Bharat is providing insurance cover to a fixed percentage of the population of the country against expensive in-patient hospital care. They are assured a sum of over 7000 USD (half a million INR) per year per family. Both these elements are integrated to form the base of the policy. The scheme aims to cover 100 million poor and vulnerable families, making it the world’s largest public health-care scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implementation of any UHC scheme requires huge financial resources. The financing issue is a matter of greater concern in countries like India with low public health care financing. The Indian Government’s public health spending is less than 1.5% of its GDP while the global average is six percent and even the World Health Organisation (WHO) recommends at least 5%. To bridge this huge gap in financing, some countries have devised innovative public finance schemes. The government spending on health care in the Philippines increased from 1.8% to 4.8% within a span of six years after the implementation of the Sin Tax Reform Law of 2012. Sin taxes collected on tobacco and alcohol were used to finance this increased spending. President Jokowi of Indonesia is financing expenditure on providing health care facilities to the poor through savings from cutting fuel subsidies besides increasing taxes on tobacco. In order to raise finance for the country’s public health system, the NITI Aayog, India’s government think-tank, in its Vision Document has proposed raising taxes on tobacco, alcohol and unhealthy foods such as sweetened beverages. The Indian Government has also committed to raising its public health spending to 2.5 percent of GDP by 2025. But that is hardly enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another factor that is important for the success of UHC is cooperation among nations. To take an example, India and Japan have signed an agreement in October to hone the surgery skills of Indian doctors in the treatment of trauma. Countries can enter into arrangements similar to the International Health Partnership (IHP) entered into by the European Union countries to promote Health Systems Strengthening (HSS) and effective development of cooperation in the field of health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without a serious look at and resolution of all the related policy issues, UHC could also pass off as mere rhetoric. India has made some progress with Ayushman Bharat, but there are still issues with the policy and major challenges ahead. India’s PM Modi faces elections this year and his underperformance vis-a-vis UHC in India will cost him both policy-wise and politics-wise.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A joint study by the World Bank and the World Health Organisation (WHO): Tracking Universal Health Coverage: 2017 Global Monitoring Report, points out the abysmal state of health services across the globe. According to it, at least half of the world’s population does not have access to essential health services and for about 100 million people out-of-pocket health expenses are high enough to push them into extreme poverty each year.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
