<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/manya.manushi/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2022-02-07T21:45:37+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/manya.manushi/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘Two Cats and a Monkey: Retold in the Context of the Iraq – Iran &amp;amp; US Conflict</title>
      <link href="/Two-Cats-and-a-Monkey" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="'Two Cats and a Monkey: Retold in the Context of the Iraq – Iran &amp; US Conflict" />
      <published>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Two-Cats-and-a-Monkey</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Two-Cats-and-a-Monkey">&lt;p&gt;As a child, I heard the story of “Two Cats and a Monkey”. The story goes like this: two cats, who were neighbours, fought over a piece of cake; they divided it into two halves to resolve the issue but the fight shifted over to the size of the halves; then, a monkey came to mediate, and took away the cake! Moral of the story: when two neighbours fight, both end up losing, and a third party tries to gain. Is this true in modern day geo-politics too? Of course, the neighbours here are Iran and Iraq, and the third party is the only superpower of the world: the United States of America. The question to which I am seeking the answer is what exactly has the US gained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran and Iraq, two formidable countries of the Middle East, derive their power from rich oil reserves. Besides a long border, they share a deep cultural heritage. Their relationship has seen many ups and downs. But the Islamic Revolution in Iran in 1979 and the subsequent invasion by Iraq led by military dictator Saddam Hussein to control oil rich territories of Iran resulted in a long-drawn battle between the two nations. It lasted for eight years. Besides costing about one trillion dollars and the loss of half a million lives, it set the stage for military intervention by the US later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iraq - US Ties&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The emerging oil industry in Iraq attracted the attention of US companies in the 1920’s. The relationship grew from strength-to-strength till in 1958, after the fall of the Hashemite monarchy, the political leaders found support in the Soviet Union. Later, the disposable income in the Gulf increased due to the oil boom of the 1970’s and US multinationals did not want to miss the bus. Iraq provided a market for all kinds of goods, including military equipment, even chemical weapons. During the decade long Iran-Iraq war, the US extended military and diplomatic support to the military dictator of Iraq, Saddam Hussein. But Iraq invaded Kuwait in 1990 to gain control of its oil fields. The US realised the importance of containing the former before it turned into a Frankenstein Monster of sorts, and America led an international coalition to oust Iraq out of Kuwait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Gulf and Iraq Wars, a new phase of their relationship began in June 2014. The Iraqi government invited America to lead a military intervention to counter the offensives conducted by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islamic_State_of_Iraq_and_the_Levant&quot;&gt;Islamic State. Since then,&lt;/a&gt; the American-led coalition has provided support not only in military operations but also through training personnel and providing intelligence input. The American Embassy in Baghdad is the largest US embassy in any country of the world. However, the hardliners in Iraq continuously opposed and still are against the presence of foreign soldiers on their soil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iran – US Relationship&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, Iran and the US were close allies but the Iranian Revolution changed this. The Iran hostage crisis, increased oil revenues and human rights excesses, and America’s ambition for regional hegemony may be seen as the root causes for dramatic reversal of their relationship. The US- Iran conflict has been termed by the historian David Crist as a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Twilight-War-Americas-Thirty-Year-Conflict/dp/014312367X&quot;&gt;twilight war&lt;/a&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, the United States and Iran reached a deal to limit Iran’s nuclear capabilities that, ironically, was built in the late 1950’s and 1960’s under American tutelage. The Iran Deal or the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joint_Comprehensive_Plan_of_Action&quot;&gt;Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action&lt;/a&gt; was agreed upon between Iran and six countries: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Permanent_members_of_the_United_Nations_Security_Council&quot;&gt;permanent members of the United Nations Security Council&lt;/a&gt;—the United States, the United Kingdom, Russia, France, China, Germany and the European Union. Under the accord, Iran agreed to limit its nuclear activities in return for the lifting of sanctions that were hurting its economy. However, in May 2018, the Trump administration unilaterally pulled out of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joint_Comprehensive_Plan_of_Action&quot;&gt;Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action&lt;/a&gt; of 2015 and announced fresh sanctions against Iran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recent Developments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Iraqi government led by Shi’ite Muslims that came to power in Iraq after Saddam’s government was toppled. The relationship between the neighbours improved after this. Crushed by sanctions, Iran sees Iraq as a saviour in times of economic recession. It provides the former a useful land link with the Syrian regime and the Lebanese Hezbollah. Iran remains the most influential external actor in Iraq, besides the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2019, the US imposed fresh sanctions on Iran and targeted its oil exports also. Shooting down of military drones and air strikes on each other followed. But the biggest of all acts was the killing of Qasem Soleimani, the Iranian Quds Force chief in Iraq. He had met Abu Mahdi al-Muhandis, the deputy commander of the Iraqi Shia organisation - Popular Mobilisation Forces on Iraqi soil. A US Reaper drone fired a missile that killed the two along with other members of the cavalcade. To retaliate, Iran attacked US air bases in Iraq with ballistic missiles. Iran, admittedly, shot down a Boeing 737 belonging to Ukraine International Airlines by mistake killing all 176 passengers on board. The US and Iran have quickly realised that any more retaliatory strikes would be suicidal for both and have announced to stop these. The Iraqi Parliament passed a resolution seeking to expel American troops immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soleimani’s killing has changed the flavour of the face off between the US and Iran. A three-cornered crisis involving the US, Iran and Iraq is likely to emerge. Many Iraqis are seeing it as an attack on their sovereignty. The Supreme Leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei has minced no words in criticising the US, and his intention to seek revenge is clear. Though Donald Trump has threatened Iraq with sanctions if US troops are expelled from Iraq, it seems likely to happen any time during this year. International leaders including the Pope have advised him to exercise restraint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the possibility of a US invasion looks remote. At the domestic front, a President facing impeachment and also elections in the next few months will have to bow before public opinion. Even after losing the lives of 5,000 soldiers and spending about $1 trillion of taxpayers money in the last seventeen years, the grip of the US over Iraq is hardly strong. American Iraq policy seems to have only one objective: the containment of Iran. Evidently, Iran seems to still be the dominant power in the region. A deep feeling of patriotism has replaced unrest due to economic hardships among the Iranian population. Millions thronged the streets to attend the last rites of the General. Various political factions in Iran stand united today. This unity along with the strong possibility of withdrawal of US troops has been termed so aptly as “a posthumous victory” of Qassaem Suleimani by Tom  Warrick, a former US official and current fellow at the Atlantic Council. The relationship between the two neighbours and their bond with Syria and Lebanon is likely to grow stronger. If this happens, the geopolitics of this region will change forever, and the US will wonder what has it gained after interfering in the Iran-Iraq situation for decades. In other words, the monkey should act with wisdom in fight between the cats and should do nothing to make the cats understand that they share a common ground. Otherwise, he stands to lose money and more importantly, the support of his clan.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As a child, I heard the story of “Two Cats and a Monkey”. The story goes like this: two cats, who were neighbours, fought over a piece of cake; they divided it into two halves to resolve the issue but the fight shifted over to the size of the halves; then, a monkey came to mediate, and took away the cake! Moral of the story: when two neighbours fight, both end up losing, and a third party tries to gain. Is this true in modern day geo-politics too? Of course, the neighbours here are Iran and Iraq, and the third party is the only superpower of the world: the United States of America. The question to which I am seeking the answer is what exactly has the US gained.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Educating the Millennials: Whose Responsibility?</title>
      <link href="/Educating-the-Millennials" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Educating the Millennials: Whose Responsibility?" />
      <published>2019-07-12T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Educating-the-Millennials</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Educating-the-Millennials">&lt;p&gt;“Education is the most powerful weapon which you can use to change the world.” These words of Nelson Mandela capture the importance of obtaining an education for every individual across any generation. Millennials, too, recognise the importance of getting educated. In fact, according to the Pew Research Center, they are the most educated generation yet. However, the major impediment that comes in their way of entering the formal schooling system and, later, higher education is limited availability of finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Education funding is the most important means to strengthen education systems in the world. This has evolved over the years. In mid-19th century, governments across the world did most of the funding using revenue from taxes levied at the local level. Around the 20th century, the growth of the education sector became a global phenomenon. Other sources of education financing such as external grants or loans provided by foreign government, private organisations such as NGOs, and local administrations were being increasingly tapped. The amount spent by developing countries on improving the condition was close enough to the average spent in developed countries. A historical decline in education inequalities was observed during this time. UNGC’s Millennium Development Goals were signed in 2000, in which the second goal was to achieve universal primary education. The first decade of the 21st century saw increased international financial flows for development assistance. Post-2010, there was a notable reduction in the amount of public funds being used to finance education. Secondary and tertiary levels of education receive more funding than the primary level. Notable examples in this regard would be Europe and Sub-Saharan Africa where less development assistance is provided for primary education. The UNICEF report, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unicef.org/publications/files/Investment_Case_for_Education_and_Equity_FINAL.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Investment Case for Education and Equity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;2015&lt;/em&gt;, shows that in low-income countries, on average 46% of public resources for education are allocated to the 10% of students who are most educated – while this figure goes down to 26% and 13% in lower-middle and upper-middle income countries respectively. Larger allocation to higher education is important to ensure better national competitiveness through innovation, and to enhance the skills of millennials. Moreover, there is cross-country heterogeneity with respect to the importance of the education sector vis-à-vis other sectors. For example, American Samoa and Kiribati spend more than 12% of their national income on education while countries such as Bangladesh and Bermuda spend only about 1% for this purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is interesting to note is even when more public funds are allocated and private funding is also playing its part towards higher education financing, they are not enough. The demand for higher education among millennials is constantly growing and this is inevitably transforming this sector from an elite to a mass system across different parts of the world. The traditional revenue-driven model was based on public funding, student tuition fees and other charges collected from them, along with endowments. A major component of the revenue so collected goes into paying salaries to the faculty. It is necessary because of the increased opportunity cost of employment avenues. Besides dwindling public funding, the rate of increase in the cost of higher education exceeds the inflation rate in most countries. As a result, the cost of higher education is escalating at an alarming rate. Even in a country like India, where higher education has traditionally been highly subsidised, the government is pulling its purse strings. Across the world, public funding is moving from committal funds to assessment-based funding. Now even the youngest millennial is an adult and is ready for higher education. It is the responsibility of all stakeholders to ensure that education is within the means of each interested millennial. Christensen and Eyring in 2011 introduced the concept of ‘disruptive innovation’ in their book &lt;em&gt;The Innovative University&lt;/em&gt;. This idea was used to implement information and communication technology in education, which was done by the introduction of online courses. Virtual education not only reduced the cost of education for millennials but also helped improve the quality of teaching. Many universities have ‘Work-Study Programs’ and offer an opportunity to study and work part-time simultaneously under such initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Countries are designing different models for sustainable funding of education. In some countries, like Germany, need-based student aid is provided for students, while in the UK, financial institutions are generally tapped to raise capital. New Zealand follows a Performance-Linked Funding Policy wherein students over the 50th percentile receive 100% government funding, while the remaining students receive 95%. To keep a check on the exorbitant tuition fees, a Tuition Grant Scheme (TGS) is in place in Singapore where students enjoy a substantially subsidised tuition. A new system of philanthro-capitalism has been introduced in India where capitalistic style objectives direct the entry of philanthropic enterprises in the education sector. Compared to the slow growth rate in higher education enrolment in North America and Europe, India enjoys the advantage of a large youth population so higher education sees enrolment in huge numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennials are doing their bit to reduce strain on resources. Some students enter the workforce while being enrolled in higher education to either financially support themselves or to gain practical experience. Many start-up stories unfold in universities. Many millennials believe in the ‘earn while you learn’ concept. Education loans are becoming increasingly popular as a means to finance education in developed as well as developing countries. According to an estimate by CNBC, student debt stands at nearly $1.5 trillion and, roughly, one in four American adults is paying off student loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financing of higher education institutions assumes great significance in today’s extremely competitive world. Higher education makes an immense contribution towards building the social capital of a nation. The government should have a futuristic outlook and increase spending on education with a focus on the quality. This is important because millennials see education as a means not only to acquire a degree but an avenue to enhance their knowledge and employability. While need-based grants and scholarships are available to some students, there are many who are denied these. Industry can provide lucrative internship opportunities to students, which help them finance their education. Policymakers should assess the impact of student loans as a source of financing education. Loan servicing results in reduced disposable income, which may impact the economic growth of a country adversely. For example, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.federalreserve.gov/econresdata/feds/2016/files/2016010pap.pdf&quot;&gt;Federal Reserve Board of Washington,&lt;/a&gt; DC concluded in a study that increasing student debt in the US has resulted in reduced homeownership. The growth of the housing sector is important for the economic revival of any country because of backward and forward linkages. High student debt will have implications for workforce composition as well. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nerdwallet.com/blog/investing/millennial-grad-retirement-age-is-75/&quot;&gt;A study&lt;/a&gt; from NerdWallet predicts that students who graduated from US colleges in 2015 will have to delay retirement until the age of 75, in part because of the increasing burden of student debt. It is, thus, imperative for policymakers across the world to brainstorm and find ways to finance education in a manner that it becomes a win-win situation for millennials and their successors – Generation Z.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Education is the most powerful weapon which you can use to change the world.” These words of Nelson Mandela capture the importance of obtaining an education for every individual across any generation. Millennials, too, recognise the importance of getting educated. In fact, according to the Pew Research Center, they are the most educated generation yet. However, the major impediment that comes in their way of entering the formal schooling system and, later, higher education is limited availability of finance.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Has the Dragon Woken Up? A Look at China’s Arctic Policy</title>
      <link href="/China-Arctic-Policy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Has the Dragon Woken Up? A Look at China’s Arctic Policy" />
      <published>2019-05-10T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/China-Arctic-Policy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/China-Arctic-Policy">&lt;p&gt;The urge to control resources is as old as human civilisation. European travellers’ constant endeavour to find new trade routes with the Far East from the sixteenth to the eighteenth century, and the establishment of European settlements and colonies in Asian and African countries are the best manifestations of this urge. Most of the twentieth century was marked by efforts of countries like America and the erstwhile USSR at increasing their military and economic sphere of influence. This lust continues even in the present century but, interestingly, new players have appeared on the horizon. The most notable of these is China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Arctic-Pie Everyone Wants a Slice Of&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Control on land has reached, probably, its exhaustion limit. Space and water are new frontiers human beings are exploring. As a testimonial, one can take the example of the Arctic region. Besides littoral states — Canada, Denmark, Norway, Russia and the United States, China, lacking even an Arctic coast, is asserting its right over the waters of the Arctic. Interest in the Arctic, which is a twenty-first century happening, has its roots in climate change. The region at present is characterised by thick white sheets of snow. It is pitch dark for half of the year and has bizarre ‘white nights’ for the remaining half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the deal: global warming is likely to lead to the melting of these snow sheets and, in turn, to the discovery of huge energy deposits. In 2008, the US Geological Survey released an assessment, and, according to it, the Arctic possesses 30% of the world’s undiscovered natural gas and 13% of its undiscovered oil reserves. In addition to this, the ocean would become navigable and shorter trade routes would ensure faster movement of ships when the snow caps melt. Analysts believe that, because of the melting snow, the ‘north-east passage’ will open-up towards Europe and the ‘north-west passage’ will ensure better connectivity between the USA and Canada. China’s Arctic ambition can be seen in the background of this hunt for resources and new trade routes, fuelled by its desire to be an important geopolitical player and an energy giant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2010, Chinese Rear Admiral Yin Zhuo, putting forth his country’s claim and questioning the territorial rights of littoral states said, “The Arctic belongs to all the people around the world, as no nation has sovereignty over it. . . . China must plan an indispensable role in Arctic exploration as we have one-fifth of the world’s population.” His remarks upended the international relations policy of China, which is embodied in the Five Principles of Peaceful Coexistence rooted in respect for the sovereignty of nations. To support its argument, Beijing says that as per the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea, the Arctic is a shipping commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;China and the Arctic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, China secured a permanent observer status in the Arctic Council, which many saw as a sign of growing Chinese influence in the region. The Arctic Council is an intergovernmental forum formed in 1996. Its members - Canada, Denmark, Finland, Iceland, Norway, Russia, Sweden and the United States address issues of sustainable development and those faced by the indigenous people of the Arctic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In January 2018, Beijing came up with a White Paper on Chinese Arctic Policy, the first official document on Arctic strategy. It explains the economic possibilities the region offers to the country and declares China to be a major stakeholder by labelling itself as a “near-Arctic State” even though Beijing is almost 3,000 km (1,800 miles) from the Arctic Circle. The document seeks Beijing’s close involvement in areas like scientific research, resource exploration, shipping and security. As per the White Paper, China wants to integrate the ‘Polar Silk Road’ or ‘blue economic passage’ with the greater Belt and Road Initiative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The former is a predominantly China-Russian partnership to link China and Europe through the Arctic Ocean. The Belt and Road Initiative is the brainchild of President Xi Jinping and aims to connect 152 countries in Asia, Europe, the Middle East, Latin America and Africa through vast logistics and transport networks. Many countries including India are sceptical about BRI as they see it as a veneer under which China wants to boost its own economic and political influence. China’s plans for a Polar Silk Road include developing Arctic shipping routes. It has bought or commissioned several ice-breakers - including nuclear-powered ones - to carve out new routes for its goods through the Arctic ice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to allay the fear of countries which are sceptical about its intentions, China is courting countries of the region near the Arctic through diplomatic and economic initiatives. It is making investments in Greenland and wants access to its mines. The Chinese company Shenghe Resources purchased a 12.5% share in Greenland Minerals and Energy. Xiao Yang, director of the Arctic Research Center at Beijing International Studies University recently wrote in a paper, “Greenland will be the key node for the successful implementation of the Polar Silk Road.” Greenland is self-governing, though still nominally controlled by Denmark. And this Chinese move is worrying the Danes and the Americans too, as the latter has the vast Thule Air Base located in the far north of Greenland. In fact, in 2013, Iceland became the first European country to enter into a Free Trade Agreement with China. Chinese banks have made huge investments in Iceland after the 2008 crisis. The China-Iceland Arctic Science Observatory in northern Iceland will conduct research on glaciology, oceanography and other similar fields. In addition, the state-owned China Development Bank has made a huge investment in the Russian energy company Novatek. It will provide China access to Arctic’s liquefied natural gas from the Yamal liquefied natural gas project in the northern port of Sabetta. The first cross-border railway bridge to link China and Russia was completed on April 2, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides diplomatic initiatives, China is spending more than $60 million annually on polar research. The China-Nordic Arctic Research Center has been set up in Shanghai. Until now, nine Arctic expeditions have been undertaken by China. The last one will make long-term atmospheric and oceanographic monitoring possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An insight into the Arctic policy of China makes one believe that diplomatic endeavours of Xi Jinping are moving in the right direction. The Second Belt and Road Forum in Beijing concluded on April 27 this year. China claims 150 countries participated in this forum, indicating Chinese prowess. Of course, India was a notable exception. As Napoleon famously aphorised about 170 years ago, “Let China sleep; when she wakes she will shake the world.” It seems the dragon is finally awake. It is difficult to underestimate the growing economic influence of China in the world and, in particular, the Arctic region―where its power grows in leaps and bounds. Only time will tell how successful it will be in camouflaging its ‘predatory economics’ with environmental monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The urge to control resources is as old as human civilisation. European travellers’ constant endeavour to find new trade routes with the Far East from the sixteenth to the eighteenth century, and the establishment of European settlements and colonies in Asian and African countries are the best manifestations of this urge. Most of the twentieth century was marked by efforts of countries like America and the erstwhile USSR at increasing their military and economic sphere of influence. This lust continues even in the present century but, interestingly, new players have appeared on the horizon. The most notable of these is China.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Industrial Corridors in India: A New Vehicle for Industrialisation</title>
      <link href="/Industrial-Corridors-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Industrial Corridors in India: A New Vehicle for Industrialisation" />
      <published>2019-04-19T23:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-19T23:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Industrial-Corridors-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Industrial-Corridors-India">&lt;p&gt;According to a Briefing Paper prepared for the UK’s House of Commons, China’s
share as a percentage of world manufacturing is 20% and as a percentage of its
GDP, it is 27%. In contrast, for India, the corresponding figures stand dismally
at 4% and 16% respectively. The Report has taken manufacturing output in 2015 as
the basis, using 2005 exchange rates. The burgeoning services sector
contribution to India’s GDP during the last decade has gone past 60%, whereas
the contribution of manufacturing activity to GDP has remained virtually
stagnant. This clearly indicates that India has been quick to adopt
technological advances in the services sector, but has failed to encourage
manufacturing entrepreneurship. Over the years, a clear need has been felt to
boost manufacturing activity in India. Mass consumerization of Indian society
due to rising disposable income and increased rural electrification have led to
a rise in demand for electronic consumer goods. It is expected to reach ₹3.15
trillion in the year 2022. If quality domestic products are not available,
people will buy imported goods. All this has further added to the necessity of
manufacturing led industrialisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to boost domestic manufacturing, the Indian Government tried to emulate
the Chinese experience as China had immensely benefited from its SEZ (Special
Economic Zones) policy. On similar lines, India enacted the SEZ Act in 2005.
However, Indian SEZs lacked the all-important connectivity to ports and thus,
failed to augment manufacturing activity in the country. It is this realisation
that has resulted in the introduction of the concept of industrial corridors
that is modelled on similar corridors in Japan and China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is an Industrial Corridor?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An industrial corridor or economic corridor is a pathway comprising
manufacturing clusters, ancillary units and smart cities connected with rail,
road, air or sea links. The Indian government has envisaged five integrated
industrial corridors across the country in partnership with the respective State
governments. The National Industrial Corridor Development &amp;amp; Implementation Trust
(NICDIT) has been established as the apex body to oversee development of all
industrial corridors across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dmicdc.com/about-DMICDC&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Industrial_Corridors.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Source:&lt;/b&gt; http://www.dmicdc.com/about-DMICDC
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Industrial Corridor as Wheels of Progress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industrial corridors recognise the interdependence of various sectors of the
economy and offer effective integration between industry and infrastructure
leading to overall socio-economic development. Industrial corridors lead to the
creation of state-of-art infrastructure such as high-speed transportation
(rail/road) networks, ports with advanced cargo handling equipment, modern
airports, special economic regions/ industrial areas, logistic parks, etc. that
are focused on fulfilling the requirements of the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The late C.K. Prahalad, a renowned management expert, had said that over the
next three decades if India does not create new cities to accommodate a whopping
500 million people desirous of urban life, every existing city would become a
slum. The establishment of manufacturing zones along the industrial corridors
will prevent distress migration and provide people with job opportunities close
to their dwelling place. The new smart cities created will mark the beginning of
a new wave of urbanisation in India and reduce pressure on existing cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The buzz word connecting the various programmes PM of Modi’s Government - Make
in India, Digital India, and Skill India - is employment generation. Smart
cities and industrial corridors are no exceptions. The educational institutions,
roads, railways, airports, hospitals that will come up in these corridors is
expected to generate employment and raise the overall standard of living. The
government is targeting 100 million new jobs through industrial corridors.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Way Forward&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘The wheels of progress’ are encountering a plethora of issues on their road to
success, however. Of all the issues, acquisition of land at a snail’s pace is
the single biggest concern owing to the Right to Fair Compensation and
Transparency in Land Acquisition, Rehabilitation and Resettlement Act, 2013. To
take an example, the $100-billion Delhi-Mumbai Industrial Corridor (DMIC) was
expected to be completed in three phases spread over nine years starting from
January 2008. However, owing to mostly land acquisition issues, the first phase
is likely to be completed by December 2019 and revised deadlines for the second
phase and third phase have already been shifted to 2027 and 2037. The
governments at both India’s Central and State levels need to work out a
comprehensive land acquisition policy and not approach this issue in a piecemeal
manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, as India lacks technological expertise, it is prudent to bring in
foreign direct investment through established foreign entities that have the
required skill. At the same time, it is also important to encourage Indian
investment in setting up ancillary units in the same sector. This will provide
for smooth backward integration by ensuring regular supply of raw materials and
forward integration by providing ready markets. For example, the Chennai to
Bengaluru defence production corridor in India’s southern States will pass
through towns such as Trichy, Coimbatore, Salem and Hosur and will connect
ordnance factories and defence public sector units to ancillary units (which are
small and medium scale industries in the said corridor). The supplies from these
units to factories and Public Sector Undertakings is an example of forward
integration and purchases by the latter is backward integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, in order to encourage FDI, the government needs to rationalise the tax
structure. India’s corporate tax rate is high in comparison to many ASEAN
countries and stands at 30%. It is 20% in Cambodia, Thailand and Vietnam.
Moreover, India also has very high import tariffs that make manufacturing of
products with imported components economically unviable or expensive as compared
to countries like Taiwan. To achieve success, the government should rationalise
the tariff structure, realising that it is export promotion not import
prevention that actually benefits an economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategy of industrial corridors is poised to develop a sound industrial
base, characterised by excellent infrastructure and uninhibited growth of
manufacturing. However, all this would remain only rhetoric if stumbling blocks
are not removed and issues plaguing industrial corridor projects are not
resolved. This requires a holistic approach and involvement of all the
government departments, stakeholders such as farmers from whom land is to be
acquired, manufacturers who would be setting units for production, transport
operators, etc. With the onset of election season in India, it would be naive to
assume anyone has the time to truly calibrate policy, but with a new Government
and new ambitions post elections, one can only hope that the Industrial
Corridors project will take on new heights.  &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">According to a Briefing Paper prepared for the UK’s House of Commons, China’s share as a percentage of world manufacturing is 20% and as a percentage of its GDP, it is 27%. In contrast, for India, the corresponding figures stand dismally at 4% and 16% respectively. The Report has taken manufacturing output in 2015 as the basis, using 2005 exchange rates. The burgeoning services sector contribution to India’s GDP during the last decade has gone past 60%, whereas the contribution of manufacturing activity to GDP has remained virtually stagnant. This clearly indicates that India has been quick to adopt technological advances in the services sector, but has failed to encourage manufacturing entrepreneurship. Over the years, a clear need has been felt to boost manufacturing activity in India. Mass consumerization of Indian society due to rising disposable income and increased rural electrification have led to a rise in demand for electronic consumer goods. It is expected to reach ₹3.15 trillion in the year 2022. If quality domestic products are not available, people will buy imported goods. All this has further added to the necessity of manufacturing led industrialisation. In order to boost domestic manufacturing, the Indian Government tried to emulate the Chinese experience as China had immensely benefited from its SEZ (Special Economic Zones) policy. On similar lines, India enacted the SEZ Act in 2005. However, Indian SEZs lacked the all-important connectivity to ports and thus, failed to augment manufacturing activity in the country. It is this realisation that has resulted in the introduction of the concept of industrial corridors that is modelled on similar corridors in Japan and China. What is an Industrial Corridor? An industrial corridor or economic corridor is a pathway comprising manufacturing clusters, ancillary units and smart cities connected with rail, road, air or sea links. The Indian government has envisaged five integrated industrial corridors across the country in partnership with the respective State governments. The National Industrial Corridor Development &amp;amp; Implementation Trust (NICDIT) has been established as the apex body to oversee development of all industrial corridors across the country. Source: http://www.dmicdc.com/about-DMICDC Industrial Corridor as Wheels of Progress Industrial corridors recognise the interdependence of various sectors of the economy and offer effective integration between industry and infrastructure leading to overall socio-economic development. Industrial corridors lead to the creation of state-of-art infrastructure such as high-speed transportation (rail/road) networks, ports with advanced cargo handling equipment, modern airports, special economic regions/ industrial areas, logistic parks, etc. that are focused on fulfilling the requirements of the industry. The late C.K. Prahalad, a renowned management expert, had said that over the next three decades if India does not create new cities to accommodate a whopping 500 million people desirous of urban life, every existing city would become a slum. The establishment of manufacturing zones along the industrial corridors will prevent distress migration and provide people with job opportunities close to their dwelling place. The new smart cities created will mark the beginning of a new wave of urbanisation in India and reduce pressure on existing cities. The buzz word connecting the various programmes PM of Modi’s Government - Make in India, Digital India, and Skill India - is employment generation. Smart cities and industrial corridors are no exceptions. The educational institutions, roads, railways, airports, hospitals that will come up in these corridors is expected to generate employment and raise the overall standard of living. The government is targeting 100 million new jobs through industrial corridors.   The Way Forward ‘The wheels of progress’ are encountering a plethora of issues on their road to success, however. Of all the issues, acquisition of land at a snail’s pace is the single biggest concern owing to the Right to Fair Compensation and Transparency in Land Acquisition, Rehabilitation and Resettlement Act, 2013. To take an example, the $100-billion Delhi-Mumbai Industrial Corridor (DMIC) was expected to be completed in three phases spread over nine years starting from January 2008. However, owing to mostly land acquisition issues, the first phase is likely to be completed by December 2019 and revised deadlines for the second phase and third phase have already been shifted to 2027 and 2037. The governments at both India’s Central and State levels need to work out a comprehensive land acquisition policy and not approach this issue in a piecemeal manner. Secondly, as India lacks technological expertise, it is prudent to bring in foreign direct investment through established foreign entities that have the required skill. At the same time, it is also important to encourage Indian investment in setting up ancillary units in the same sector. This will provide for smooth backward integration by ensuring regular supply of raw materials and forward integration by providing ready markets. For example, the Chennai to Bengaluru defence production corridor in India’s southern States will pass through towns such as Trichy, Coimbatore, Salem and Hosur and will connect ordnance factories and defence public sector units to ancillary units (which are small and medium scale industries in the said corridor). The supplies from these units to factories and Public Sector Undertakings is an example of forward integration and purchases by the latter is backward integration. Thirdly, in order to encourage FDI, the government needs to rationalise the tax structure. India’s corporate tax rate is high in comparison to many ASEAN countries and stands at 30%. It is 20% in Cambodia, Thailand and Vietnam. Moreover, India also has very high import tariffs that make manufacturing of products with imported components economically unviable or expensive as compared to countries like Taiwan. To achieve success, the government should rationalise the tariff structure, realising that it is export promotion not import prevention that actually benefits an economy. The strategy of industrial corridors is poised to develop a sound industrial base, characterised by excellent infrastructure and uninhibited growth of manufacturing. However, all this would remain only rhetoric if stumbling blocks are not removed and issues plaguing industrial corridor projects are not resolved. This requires a holistic approach and involvement of all the government departments, stakeholders such as farmers from whom land is to be acquired, manufacturers who would be setting units for production, transport operators, etc. With the onset of election season in India, it would be naive to assume anyone has the time to truly calibrate policy, but with a new Government and new ambitions post elections, one can only hope that the Industrial Corridors project will take on new heights.  </summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">It Happens Only In India!</title>
      <link href="/Only-In-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="It Happens Only In India!" />
      <published>2019-04-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Only-In-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Only-In-India">&lt;p&gt;First-time Indian voters like me, along with other eligible ones, are keenly looking forward to flaunting the blue mark on their index finger. Seven-phased, four weeks long, this is the ‘Festival of the country’ (&lt;em&gt;Desh ka tyohaar&lt;/em&gt;, in Hindi) to choose the seventeenth Indian Lok Sabha. It is aptly called so because it witnesses unparalleled participation and everything in relation to it. About 900 million eligible voters will vote at a million polling stations in 543 constituencies across India. There are likely to be fifteen candidates, on an average, in each constituency. About 450 political parties are in the fray. This event has more people participating in it as compared to the combined population of Europe and Australia. Almost 3.96 million robust and tamper-proof Electronic Voting Machines (EVMs) accompanied by VVPAT (voter-verified paper audit trail) have been deployed. Estimated expenditure on these elections stands at $7 billion, which is 3.2 times the cost involved in conducting the US Presidential elections of 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elections 2019 is likely to be a close one and is a keen contest between two alliances - the ruling National Democratic Alliance (NDA) and the present opposition, United Progressive Alliance (UPA). The respective important constituents of these alliances are - the Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) and the Indian National Congress (INC). This election reminds me of the famous  Abba  song – &lt;em&gt;Take a chance on me&lt;/em&gt;. Narendra Modi, the incumbent Prime Minister, and Rahul Gandhi, the most important leader of the Congress, have widely travelled across the length and breadth of the country in the past two months to woo voters. Both have liberally referred to armed forces in their speeches to derive some kind of political advantage. The five-year vision document of both the parties – the election manifesto - talks about the pro-farmer approach. While the Congress has promised to approach the issue of rural distress through a separate budget for farmers, the BJP has vowed to provide pensions for small and marginal farmers after the age of 60 and to double the income of farmers by 2022. Both parties have announced their cash transfer and income support schemes for people living in extreme poverty. Employment, security, and infrastructure feature prominently in the manifestos of both parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many contentious issues have no reference in Congress’ vision document while BJP is emphatic about these. Firstly, it has promised to build the Ram temple in Ayodhya (an important Hindu God believed to have been born there), whose construction Muslims have been opposing because of the existence of the Babri mosque at the same location. Its hardline approach on the abrogation of Articles 370 and 35A of the Indian Constitution is also evident in the document. These two articles give special status and privileges to the state and to the people of Jammu and Kashmir. The proposal to have a National Registry of Citizens (NRC) to check foreign nationals or illegal immigrants in India’s North-East, particularly in the State of Assam is also included.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is closure possible?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elections to the Indian legislature highlights some important electoral policy issues that require, if not closure, then a serious attempt to address them. The first being the issue of simultaneous election to the Indian Parliament and the State Legislatures, second, the funding of elections, and third, the role of the media, including social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first four elections in India from 1952 through 1967 were conducted simultaneously. This concept ended when the fourth Lok Sabha was dissolved before the end of its term. The Law Commission wanted to reinstate this system as they felt that there is no proper governance across the country and the nation is continuously in the election mode, which leads to ministerial work suffering. Simultaneous elections will ensure that the ruling parties at the State and the Centre level will get sufficient time to execute the policies that they had talked about in their respective manifestos. This also will help in reducing the cost of elections. Though BJP has proposed it again, it seems to be too difficult a plan to be implemented, especially in light of the severe resistance it faces from the opposition parties. The stiff resistance is because it will involve cutting down or increasing the tenure of some present State Legislatures and a Constitutional Amendment as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In India, despite the Election Commission’s commitment to the idea of State funding of elections and recommendations for the same by various committees, not much progress has been made in this direction. In 2017, probably one of its kind in the world, Electoral Bonds were envisaged as an interest-free instrument to raise funding in a transparent manner. A corporate or an individual can purchase these promissory notes from an authorised bank and the identity of the donor will be known only to the bank. The anonymity clause attracted criticism and it was contended that it would lead to shell companies making donations. The very purpose of transparent funding would be defeated. Taking cognisance of this, on a petition, the Indian Supreme Court has asked all political parties to furnish receipts of electoral bonds along with the identity and bank account details of the donors and the amounts received to the Election Commission by May 30. The Electoral Bonds, in their present form, are otherwise playing a limited role. Experts estimate that all the political parties put together have raised only around $300 million through these bonds, which, is of course, far less than what they seem to be spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the electoral history of India, the media, especially electronic, has never spelled out its political affiliation as clearly as in this election. Instead of taking an independent stand, the views expressed by television channels are a reflection of their owner’s political ideology. Social media is being used by different parties for propaganda as well as to spread misinformation. Prominent social media companies, including Facebook along with its app services - Instagram and WhatsApp, have adopted a voluntary code of ethics for the general elections with the Election Commission of India (ECI). According to Facebook sources, it is removing around one million abusive accounts every day using Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Machine Learning (ML).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Voting the Indian way&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the syncretic nature of Indian society, the massive scale of elections and many related issues remaining unresolved, the process and its resilience is quite impressive. It is quite interesting to note that a Pew Research poll on democracy, conducted last year, showed that 79% of the Indians are satisfied with democracy as a whole. Americans, whose country takes pride in being the cradle of democracy, have a satisfaction rate of only 46%. India’s free and fair elections for the last seventy years or so is no mean achievement for a country whose democratic institutions were far from being developed at the time of its independence. And, of course, there is no doubt in the matter that every Indian regards his/her freedom dearly. Probably, two hundred years of oppression have been proof enough that the freedom and democratic institution is of utmost importance. A nation, with vast diversity and chronic inequality, this is the time of the year when rich and poor come together to make a choice for their collective future. This is the time to voice out their desires and problems. Every Indian certainly takes pride in it. It is for young Indians to ensure that politicians do not disturb the democratic fibre of the country. It is for them to carry forward the greatness behind the legacy that was slowly built over the years, and that they too take pride in flaunting the blue mark on their finger. The blue mark is more than just a sign of vote, it is a symbol of the reminder that now they are free to choose their leader, and that the people run the country and elect the government. Their dissent towards the leaders comes as a vote against their party. So, they better serve in people’s favour.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">First-time Indian voters like me, along with other eligible ones, are keenly looking forward to flaunting the blue mark on their index finger. Seven-phased, four weeks long, this is the ‘Festival of the country’ (Desh ka tyohaar, in Hindi) to choose the seventeenth Indian Lok Sabha. It is aptly called so because it witnesses unparalleled participation and everything in relation to it. About 900 million eligible voters will vote at a million polling stations in 543 constituencies across India. There are likely to be fifteen candidates, on an average, in each constituency. About 450 political parties are in the fray. This event has more people participating in it as compared to the combined population of Europe and Australia. Almost 3.96 million robust and tamper-proof Electronic Voting Machines (EVMs) accompanied by VVPAT (voter-verified paper audit trail) have been deployed. Estimated expenditure on these elections stands at $7 billion, which is 3.2 times the cost involved in conducting the US Presidential elections of 2016.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Earth to the Robots: Fourth Industrial Revolution</title>
      <link href="/Earth-to-the-robots" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Earth to the Robots: Fourth Industrial Revolution" />
      <published>2019-03-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Earth-to-the-robots</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Earth-to-the-robots">&lt;p&gt;Imagine you book something from your favourite food outlet online. A robot cooks the food and it is then delivered by a driverless van or a drone. A world where humans are being replaced by robots no longer seems to be a scene from a Sci-Fi film. Recently, a British online supermarket, ‘Ocado,’ successfully developed a completely automatic system of picking up grocery items for its customers. This is representative of the fact that we are moving towards a &lt;em&gt;Digital Revolution&lt;/em&gt;, which is generally termed as the ‘Fourth Industrial Revolution’ (IR 4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to policy makers, the world economy has been on a continuous decline for the last three-four years and a revolution seems to be imperative. In the past, a phase of substantial growth has always been preceded by a revolution. The first such instance dates back to the 1760’s, when Industrial Revolution 1.0 began and was called a &lt;em&gt;Mechanical Revolution&lt;/em&gt;. It revolved around the production of machines that were powered and driven by water and steam. The &lt;em&gt;Technological Revolution&lt;/em&gt;, which was the Second Industrial Revolution, entailed the usage of electrical energy in the manufacturing process, helping in voluminous production. The launch of the internet was the third revolution, which was termed the &lt;em&gt;Virtual Revolution&lt;/em&gt;. The information technology sector had a boom, which promoted the use of electronics to automate the production line and achieve economies of scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Industry Revolution 4.0 and its impact&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What sets IR 4.0 apart from the earlier revolutions is the speed at which the revolution is approaching the world, and how its effects will be intangible. Industrial Revolution 4.0 is where the lines between the physical, digital and biological spheres get merged. Production, management and governance systems are likely to be revamped. And policies aligning Artificial intelligence (AI), drones and blockchain technology are already being implemented. Taking up AI technology helps in reducing the operational costs that are involved in the production process, increasing not only efficiency but also revenue. Improvement in the customer experience is also a benefit AI brings with itself. Only 15% of the enterprises in the world are using AI as of today, but 31% are expected to start making use of it in the coming 12 months, according to Adobe. The Fourth Industrial Revolution will allow hyper-connection. This will help connect not only one person to another person, but also machines to people. Amazon’s Alexa works using this technology and is representative of the hyper-connectivity between devices and humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will have an impact on a lot of sectors. The recruitment industry will be impacted in multiple ways. Firstly, less people will be required to be employed as robots will be prevalent. Secondly, the time taken to screen all CVs will get drastically reduced due to the invention of AI softwares, like Ideal, which will help recruiters. Increased automation is already phasing out the role of humans in the manufacturing industry and agriculture sector. It might even affect the pharmaceutical industry by replacing doctors with applications, and chemist with robots. Thirdly, the transportation sector will flourish with applications which help people to track their cab and ensure safety. The retail sector will also receive a lot of traffic as AI technology advances, where these online stores will already know what you want before you even place the order. With cashlessness taking over the globe, the banking sector will face a setback as everything will be online. With a substantial impact on each of these sectors, it surely will lead to digitising the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenges posed to policy makers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data forms the base of the revolution, and for a digital economy, exchange of data holds utmost significance. Facebook’s data breach took everybody by surprise. Security of the IT sector, privacy of data, maintenance of the integrity of the production process and excessive investment are few of the challenges associated with the transformation. Another challenge is the availability of AI talent. These people are in high demand, and the demand-supply ratio is quite skewed. The skill set required by the companies isn’t readily available in the job seekers currently. The maximum supply gap is at the middle-level. If these professionals get lured by high salaries being offered by companies in the developed world, it would not help to bridge the technological gap between developing and developed nations. Further, cities across the world are already grappling with parking space issues. The situation is likely to get worsened as by the end of the next decade, large fleets of drones will be very common and would need parking space. Policy makers have to equip themselves to solve these issues, both big and small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are we moving towards a “jobless future”?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dystopian future where robots are ubiquitous and humans are merely power sources may be the norm in the coming decades. It is important for humans to change the complexion of the job market. A recent research by McKinsey says that 45% of the current jobs can be automated. Few beginnings have already been made in this direction. Japan has already taken the first step towards this advancement and there are companies that are in the business of “saying sorry.” They hire people to apologise on behalf of others. Not far behind, in China, one can hire boyfriends who can help ladies with shopping and take perfect selfies. Robots that have been created to help humans, may become job creators for humans in future. They will require an entire ecosystem of support staff to optimise their performance and to avail services such as robot maintenance and robot monitoring. Robot ethicists may also be in great demand. But what we need to understand is that AI as whole could be a big benefit to entire humanity if used in the proper direction. What a lot of experts believe is that to make a productive future, it is pertinent for humans to work alongside robots to make the process faster. Therefore, it wouldn’t be a surprise to see robots doing the work which requires mindless skills whilst humans work on managing the system and adding a creative touch to the process. Their jobs would transform, and re-skilling themselves and expanding their skill set is the need of the hour. This goes on to prove that jobs are changing, but not going away, humans simply need to change and keep evolving to fit in society better.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Imagine you book something from your favourite food outlet online. A robot cooks the food and it is then delivered by a driverless van or a drone. A world where humans are being replaced by robots no longer seems to be a scene from a Sci-Fi film. Recently, a British online supermarket, ‘Ocado,’ successfully developed a completely automatic system of picking up grocery items for its customers. This is representative of the fact that we are moving towards a Digital Revolution, which is generally termed as the ‘Fourth Industrial Revolution’ (IR 4).</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">South Africa’s New Land Policy - Inclusion with Exclusion</title>
      <link href="/South-Africa-Land-Policy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="South Africa's New Land Policy - Inclusion with Exclusion" />
      <published>2019-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/South%20Africa-Land-Policy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/South-Africa-Land-Policy">&lt;p&gt;Purple hiring (providing employment opportunities to the differently-abled) or positive discrimination in jobs and financial literacy are seemingly unrelated concepts. However, the underlying idea is common - inclusion. Some people talk about ‘inclusion’ as though it is topical, for politicians it is new rhetoric, for activists it is an instrument of social justice and, for businesses, it is an opportunity. In South Africa, inclusion is being seen by many as a way to correct apartheid era injustice through land expropriation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue has its genesis in the Natives Land Act, 1913, that reserved about 93% of the land for the white minority. The Native Trust and Land Act, 1936, subsequently reduced it to 87%. Further, these Acts legally sanctioned historical dispossession of the African people’s land. The year 1994 saw the end of apartheid in South Africa. It brought along with it hope of land redistribution to the Rainbow Nation’s communities. Section 25 of the Constitution provided for land expropriation with just and equitable compensation. The government relied on a “willing-seller, willing-buyer” land redistribution policy to correct the historical wrong. Under this approach, the government bought land against compensation and redistributed it to the dispossessed people. The policy did not yield desired results due to the unwillingness of property owners to sell and their demand of exorbitantly high prices in many cases. Even today, 72% of agricultural land is in the hands of white South Africans, i.e. 8% of the population, whereas only 4% of land is owned by black South Africans (over 80% of the population). President Jacob Zuma’s government tried to address this issue in 2016 by introducing a bill in the parliament to end the “willing-buyer, willing-seller” policy and providing for payment for land acquired by expropriation in the public interest at adjudicator value. In view of growing discontent coupled with a high rate of unemployment, Zuma’s successor, Cyril Ramaphosa pushed the idea of redistribution of (only unused) land without compensation in 2017. The year 2018 saw the adoption of a report by the South African Parliament, recommending the amendment of section 25 of the Constitution to expropriate land without compensation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This idea of addressing the present skewed land ownership issue has initiated a debate and has made land a hot-button issue. The breakaway group of the ruling African National Congress, the Economic Freedom Fighters (EFF), is in principle against Ramaphosa’s policy. But only because it favours a more radical nationalisation of banks and land as the only means to undo historical injustice. However, opponents of expropriation without compensation argue that South Africa may go Zimbabwe’s way, where a fast track land reform process led to large-scale violence. Many white farmers fled the country at the turn of the century to neighbouring countries like Zambia, Mozambique, the Congo and Nigeria. This exodus converted Zimbabwe from a food exporting country to one facing frequent food shortages. According to an estimate by a Zimbabwean economist and legislator, Eddie Cross, the total cost that the economy has borne due to the adoption of this policy is around $20 billion. Banks have also expressed their reservation on the proposed amendment. They have about $114 billion of mortgages outstanding against land. Their concerns are not being addressed. Further, the possibility of civil war engulfing the most industrialised country in Africa cannot be ruled out. Many far-right groups have claimed that white farmers are being killed and forced expropriations are already happening. In August 2018, Donald Trump’s tweet in their support added fuel to the fire. If violence spreads, it is likely to affect tourism, which contributes about 10% to the GDP. It would dampen the investor sentiment as well. The country, at present, is an attractive emerging market despite economic woes for investors because of two reasons. Firstly, it has an expanding middle class and secondly, its location at the tip of the African continent makes it a perfect gateway to the huge African market consisting of about one billion people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many defects in Ramaphosa’s policy design. It is unclear on what basis land will be redistributed, and how the beneficiaries will be identified. If land has changed hands against adequate compensation, will it have any impact on new owner’s rights? The parameters to identify ‘unused land’ have not been clearly defined. The policy seems to be the government’s ploy to counter the growing popularity of the EFF in the country, particularly against the background of upcoming elections in May 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One really wonders why politicians around the world try to achieve inclusion of one group by excluding another. Such inclusion-exclusion is certainly not a zero-sum game because players over the years change. After all, why must the present generation pay for the ‘wrongs’ done by their forefathers? The Indian policy of caste-based quotas for achieving social justice through inclusion is continuing even after seventy years of independence. More and more groups are demanding quotas, causing social unrest at times. In South Africa, even after 25 years in power, the ANC has failed to conclude a fair land reform process successfully. But will South Africa’s new (and potentially dangerous) experiment with inclusion lead to the desired result (whatever that is)? Only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Purple hiring (providing employment opportunities to the differently-abled) or positive discrimination in jobs and financial literacy are seemingly unrelated concepts. However, the underlying idea is common - inclusion. Some people talk about ‘inclusion’ as though it is topical, for politicians it is new rhetoric, for activists it is an instrument of social justice and, for businesses, it is an opportunity. In South Africa, inclusion is being seen by many as a way to correct apartheid era injustice through land expropriation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Green Finance: A Financial Policy Innovation</title>
      <link href="/Green-Finance" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Green Finance: A Financial Policy Innovation" />
      <published>2019-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Green-Finance</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Green-Finance">&lt;p&gt;“Go Green” is no longer mere rhetoric, it is imperative in our times. Decision-makers, whether at the level of the country or corporate, need to internalize environmental externalities while framing almost all strategic policies. Financial policy is certainly no exception. The concept that integrates concern for the environment and adequate return on investments is ‘Green Finance’. It is defined by scholars as “financial investments flowing into sustainable development projects and initiatives, environmental products, and policies that encourage the development of a more sustainable economy.” Besides climate finance, it includes financial inflows made in projects with objectives such as controlling industrial pollution, better waste management, encouraging sustainable agriculture, and the protection of aquatic and terrestrial ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The role of carbon emissions in causing global warming is a matter of common knowledge and an issue of concern for humanity. According to a World Bank estimate, infrastructure development, construction, power plants, and transport system operations are responsible for 70% of global greenhouse emissions. There is an urgent need to develop technologies that are not based on greenhouse gases and the combustion of fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shift requires huge investment for green transformation. New investment is also needed for other green endeavours like those that seek to protect biodiversity, or to control all types of pollution. To mobilise this money, innovative financial instruments like green bonds are being issued by corporates, green banks are being set up, and many commercial banks, central banks, governments and institutional investors across the world have adopted policies to ensure green financial governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raising Green Finance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Greening’ the financial system requires long term funds that are being made available through green bonds, green grants and the establishment of financial institutions like green banks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green bonds are financial instruments whose proceeds are used to encourage investment in sustainability/climate or environment-related projects. The most important institutional investor in this space is the World Bank and as on March 2018, the World Bank has raised over $10 billion through green bonds. It finances green projects all over the world. India’s Rampur Hydropower Project, which aims to provide low-carbon hydroelectric power to northern India’s electricity grid is a case in point. Both developed and developing countries are raising money through green bonds. The first Asian green bond was issued in 2013 by the Export-Import Bank of Korea, raising $500 million. China, the global leader in green finance, accounts for about 40% of green bonds issued globally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The banking sector contributes to the greening of the financial system by providing green loans and by establishing green banks. Triodos Bank NV, based in the Netherlands is the first bank in the world that started financing green projects in 1991. Banks all over the world followed suit. Green banks are established specifically with the objective of making finance available for environment-friendly projects or for cleaner technologies. The Connecticut Green Bank in the United States, established in 2011, is the first green bank in the world. Similar banks have started operations in the United Kingdom, Malaysia, Australia, and Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Governments provide grants, particularly, to small and medium businesses to invest in green technologies. Non-profit foundations with an environmental mission offer grants or invest in green banks and projects. The Toyota Foundation, the Hewlett Foundation, and the Rockefeller Foundation are among those that give grants to support clean energy. Even companies such as Boeing, Ford, PVR Ltd, and others offer green grants to NGOs and individuals. Oil majors such as ONGC (India), Total (France), BP (United Kingdom), Repsol (Spain) and many others are adopting a futuristic approach and are making substantial investments for development of renewable energy. On December 28, 2018, Anglo-Dutch oil company Shell announced its intention to double the amount it spends on green energy to $4bn a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Barriers to Greening of Finance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projects that need funding through green finance have long gestation periods. Thus, the risk associated with green investment is typically long term in nature while lending is, generally, available for the short term. Mark Carney, the Governor of the Bank of England, has aptly termed this mismatch in lending and investment as a “tragedy of the horizon”. Parameters for risk assessment of green projects are also still evolving. Due to this, it is difficult for banks to assess credit risk and hence there is a reluctance to lend to such projects. Moreover, there is an acute shortage of staff that can screen green projects. Finally, businesses that tap green finance have to bear additional costs as finance for green projects is raised at a higher cost as compared to conventional projects due to the higher risk involved. In this competitive world, such businesses cannot pass it to consumers and hence, their bottom line gets adversely affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Way Forward&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the issues outlined, the amount to be mobilised through green finance is huge. For Southeast Asia alone, the amount to be mobilised for high carbon emission sectors like power and transport, and sectors vital for humanity such as water and sanitation through 2025 is estimated to be $110 billion a year (ASEAN Investment Report, 2015). This huge investment cannot come through unless there is a revamp of policy measures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;a. Institutional Support&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No country in the world can remain unaffected from consequences of disturbance in its ecological balance. Though the World Bank and International Finance Corporation are doing good work to promote green finance, a multilateral financial institution is needed to give it the desired push. It is surprising that at the Climate Summits, this issue has never been brought up. Mitigation cost is always the core issue of discussion, but never is the issue of green finance required for new projects. The International Investors Group on Climate Change (IIGCC), a network of nearly 150 members, including nine of the 10 largest pension funds in Europe has been formed to encourage the inflow of green finance, but the scope of its activities is limited only to projects involving clean energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;b. Adequate Disclosures&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many companies in G-20 nations are giving environment-related information in their financial filings. The top 500 listed companies in India have to make such disclosures in a Business Responsibility Report as a part of their annual reports. But these disclosure norms have not been standardised, leading to difficulty in greening finance. Regulatory authorities should ensure that banks disclose their green loan data at regular intervals. Chinese banks do it and their model may be replicated by other banks across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;c. Factoring of Environmental Cost in Lending Portfolios&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financial intermediaries, which include multilateral development banks, commercial banks, and private equity firms should develop mechanisms to factor environmental costs to determine the cost of capital for their projects. This will ensure the total cost of projects which are likely to damage the environment is higher than green projects. In this domain, the UNEP Finance Initiative is working with banks, insurers, and investors to remove the issues emanating from difficulty in assessing environmental risk. Natural Capital Finance Alliance (NCFA), a finance sector-led initiative, has recently launched ENCORE (Exploring Natural Capital Opportunities, Risks and Exposure), which is a web-based tool to assess the environmental cost of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To promote green finance, priority areas should be identified by policymakers in consultation with all the stakeholders. Only then an enabling framework can be developed. The regulators and world leaders need to embrace a vision for development that integrates economic growth with sustainability issues. And to do that, they must ensure that money, whether private or public, is pumped into the right kind of activities and projects. After all, without proper financing, no projects or initiatives can achieve tangible results. The same goes for green projects and the dream of a sustainable future.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Go Green” is no longer mere rhetoric, it is imperative in our times. Decision-makers, whether at the level of the country or corporate, need to internalize environmental externalities while framing almost all strategic policies. Financial policy is certainly no exception. The concept that integrates concern for the environment and adequate return on investments is ‘Green Finance’. It is defined by scholars as “financial investments flowing into sustainable development projects and initiatives, environmental products, and policies that encourage the development of a more sustainable economy.” Besides climate finance, it includes financial inflows made in projects with objectives such as controlling industrial pollution, better waste management, encouraging sustainable agriculture, and the protection of aquatic and terrestrial ecosystems.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Climate Pacts: Can They Alone Deliver Climate Justice?</title>
      <link href="/Climate-Pacts" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climate Pacts: Can They Alone Deliver Climate Justice?" />
      <published>2019-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Climate-Pacts</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Climate-Pacts">&lt;p&gt;The concern for rising global temperatures due to climate change is seemingly pervasive across the world. While combating climate change is important, ensuring climate justice in the process of doing so is equally important. Climate justice involves upholding the rights of those affected by climate change and factoring in the concerns of developing countries in the fight against climate change. Some major policy initiatives taken at the global level to combat climate change and deliver climate justice include the Kyoto Protocol (1992) and the Paris Agreement (2015). The latest development in this sphere has been the 24th edition of the UN Climate Change Conference (called COP24) held in the coal town of Katowice, Poland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this round of climate talks, the participating members agreed upon the adoption of rules framed for the implementation of the Paris Agreement. While the Agreement has specified that nations will work towards reducing global temperatures by 2°C, the rulebook provides the action plan that needs to be undertaken to ensure that reduction. Two weeks of negotiations among nations culminated in the drafting of this rulebook. It is certainly dynamic in nature: new guidelines can be added and existing ones can be amended. The basic aim of these guidelines, which will come into force in the year 2020, is to provide countries with a standard framework. It will help them to record and report the emission of greenhouse gases in their own country, to monitor financial flows for climate mitigation and adaptation, and to transfer technologies amongst countries. These initiatives are necessary to aid populations of developing countries to cope with natural disasters that have a strong link to climate change. They are also needed to allow for the development of climate-resilient varieties of crops, improved weather forecasts, reduction in pollution and for dealing with public health issues arising due to climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rulebook has devised an accounting framework to measure and verify the financial inflows―loans, grants or concessions. It is likely to bring in transparency in the sphere of climate finance. Many global leaders have termed this as a victory for multilateralism, particularly at a time when the 13th summit of the Group of Twenty (G20) members (held in Argentina) gave a clear signal that this concept is under threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, however, there are a plethora of issues which have been left unaddressed in this rulebook. Firstly, the rulebook does not adequately address the issue of carbon trading systems envisaged by the Kyoto Protocol. A country or an industry, in a carbon market, can earn carbon credits if it mitigates emissions beyond the limit set under Art. 6 of the Paris Agreement, and later it can trade them too. When this topic was taken up in Katowice, the issue of double-counting of emission reductions was brought to the fore. In the context of carbon trading, double-counting is a situation when a country, let us say X, transfers its carbon credits to another country, Y, to enable Y to meet its emission targets whilst X also counts its own carbon credits towards meeting its own targets. Another issue of contention related to carbon credits was the adjustment of unused accumulated carbon credits by countries like China and Brazil. The current talks have failed to settle these issues; rather the discussion has been postponed to the next year. One fails to understand how postponement of a contentious issue would help the cause of climate justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the rulebook fails to recognise that developed and developing countries must have different responsibilities towards climate change mitigation and adaptation. The argument for a climate clean-up has been built, until now, upon a fundamental tenet of equity. Art. 14 of the Paris Agreement captures it emphatically and states &lt;em&gt;“…equity demands that the vulnerabilities, problems, and challenges of the poor and marginalised be prioritised to ensure climate justice..”&lt;/em&gt;. The Agreement envisaged climate mitigation funds as an important means to ensure equity. However, in the rulebook, there is no clarity on how funds would be mobilised for the fight against climate change. This lacuna is all the more conspicuous because even after promising $100 billion every year as mitigation funds in 2009, rich countries have actually paid out only 12% of this figure. If climate justice is to be delivered, arranging climate finance with regard to the economic status of different countries should be the top-most priority of global leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the lack of ambition of global leaders, as captured during climate negotiations, is a major impediment in the way of delivering climate justice. The rising parochialism of citizens across the world is also a matter of great concern. The elevation of some leaders to the position of Head of State clearly reflects this. Scott Morrison, who openly exhibited his support for the world’s dirtiest fossil fuel-coal-by bringing a lump of it to the Australian Parliament, became Prime Minister of Australia in August 2018, replacing Malcolm Turnbull, who was working towards a transition to cleaner forms of energy. Donald Trump, who wants to “Make America Great Again”, has announced his country’s withdrawal from the Paris Agreement. And in November 2018, the Brazilians elected Jair Bolsonaro as President who proposes to promote agribusiness in the Amazon forest and construct roads there. This can have a seriously negative impact on the climate as the Amazon Basin is the world’s largest carbon sink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line seems to be that climate justice cannot be ensured through climate pacts alone. The first thing we need to ensure is that these climate pacts are actually implemented and that developing countries stand up for their poor and vulnerable citizens. India and China put together have about 36% of the world’s population living in them. They are important consumer markets for various multinational companies from the developed world, which is historically responsible for carbon emissions. These two countries should use this advantage and pitch for climate justice by ensuring proper implementation frameworks and equitable distribution of funds at the global level. In addition, citizens of the world should stand against the indifference of leaders to climate change concerns, and speak out on the issue to ensure a sustainable future for themselves. The aim of preventing climate change and ensuring climate justice requires the combined effort of both the world’s peoples and its governments. And a reliance on climate pacts alone will only provide solutions on &lt;i&gt;paper &lt;/i&gt; to a potentially grave problem.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The concern for rising global temperatures due to climate change is seemingly pervasive across the world. While combating climate change is important, ensuring climate justice in the process of doing so is equally important. Climate justice involves upholding the rights of those affected by climate change and factoring in the concerns of developing countries in the fight against climate change. Some major policy initiatives taken at the global level to combat climate change and deliver climate justice include the Kyoto Protocol (1992) and the Paris Agreement (2015). The latest development in this sphere has been the 24th edition of the UN Climate Change Conference (called COP24) held in the coal town of Katowice, Poland.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Universal Healthcare and The India Story</title>
      <link href="/Universal-Healthcare-and-The-India-Story" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Universal Healthcare and The India Story" />
      <published>2019-01-03T20:40:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T20:40:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Universal-Healthcare-and-The-India-Story</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Universal-Healthcare-and-The-India-Story">&lt;p&gt;A joint study by the World Bank and the World Health Organisation (WHO): Tracking Universal Health Coverage: 2017 Global Monitoring Report, points out the abysmal state of health services across the globe. According to it, at least half of the world’s population does not have access to essential health services and for about 100 million people out-of-pocket health expenses are high enough to push them into extreme poverty each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Nations has envisaged Universal Health Coverage (UHC) as a possible solution to address this humongous problem. According to the WHO, Universal health coverage (UHC) means, “all people and communities can use the promotive, preventive, curative, rehabilitative and palliative health services they need, of sufficient quality to be effective, while also ensuring that the use of these services does not expose the user to financial hardship”. The underlying idea behind UHC is health for all at an affordable cost. The concept of Universal Health Coverage (UHC) emerged with the World Health Report of 2010 and considering its importance, the United Nation (UN) in 2015 included it as one of the Sustainable Development Goals. It has earmarked December 12 of every year as International Universal Health Coverage (UHC) Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the UHC movement has gained unprecedented momentum globally during the last five-six years, Japan, Singapore, and Thailand in Asia have been doing commendable work in this arena for many of the past decades. More than seventy countries across the world, with the notable exception of USA, have framed policies around the UHC. The common thread running across all such programmes is governmental involvement and action. India, the largest democracy of the world, too, has taken a vital step towards Universal Health Coverage (UHC). The Indian government rolled out a scheme- Ayushman Bharat: the National Health Protection Mission on September 25, 2018. This scheme has been framed after taking into consideration the dismal status of the health-care system in India, and also as a response to the order given by the Supreme Court of India to the Central Government to “do something” when the exorbitant prices of medical care were brought to its attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ayushman Bharat is aimed at providing guaranteed access to free treatment to about 40% of India’s population. The population will be selected based on socio-economic factors. About 150,000 wellness clinics will be set up. They will provide comprehensive health care facilities such as free essential drugs, maternal and child health services, treatment for non-communicable diseases and much more. Setting up clinics is a tried and tested component of UHC that many countries like China and Sri Lanka have adopted to improve access to health services to the poor. And, theoretically, it should work in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1977, South Korea gave a strong push to compulsory health insurance and Japan designed national health insurance coverage as early as in 1961. To replicate their success, a second element  of Ayushman Bharat is providing insurance cover to a fixed percentage of the population of the country against expensive in-patient hospital care. They are assured a sum of over 7000 USD (half a million INR) per year per family. Both these elements are integrated to form the base of the policy. The scheme aims to cover 100 million poor and vulnerable families, making it the world’s largest public health-care scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implementation of any UHC scheme requires huge financial resources. The financing issue is a matter of greater concern in countries like India with low public health care financing. The Indian Government’s public health spending is less than 1.5% of its GDP while the global average is six percent and even the World Health Organisation (WHO) recommends at least 5%. To bridge this huge gap in financing, some countries have devised innovative public finance schemes. The government spending on health care in the Philippines increased from 1.8% to 4.8% within a span of six years after the implementation of the Sin Tax Reform Law of 2012. Sin taxes collected on tobacco and alcohol were used to finance this increased spending. President Jokowi of Indonesia is financing expenditure on providing health care facilities to the poor through savings from cutting fuel subsidies besides increasing taxes on tobacco. In order to raise finance for the country’s public health system, the NITI Aayog, India’s government think-tank, in its Vision Document has proposed raising taxes on tobacco, alcohol and unhealthy foods such as sweetened beverages. The Indian Government has also committed to raising its public health spending to 2.5 percent of GDP by 2025. But that is hardly enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another factor that is important for the success of UHC is cooperation among nations. To take an example, India and Japan have signed an agreement in October to hone the surgery skills of Indian doctors in the treatment of trauma. Countries can enter into arrangements similar to the International Health Partnership (IHP) entered into by the European Union countries to promote Health Systems Strengthening (HSS) and effective development of cooperation in the field of health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without a serious look at and resolution of all the related policy issues, UHC could also pass off as mere rhetoric. India has made some progress with Ayushman Bharat, but there are still issues with the policy and major challenges ahead. India’s PM Modi faces elections this year and his underperformance vis-a-vis UHC in India will cost him both policy-wise and politics-wise.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A joint study by the World Bank and the World Health Organisation (WHO): Tracking Universal Health Coverage: 2017 Global Monitoring Report, points out the abysmal state of health services across the globe. According to it, at least half of the world’s population does not have access to essential health services and for about 100 million people out-of-pocket health expenses are high enough to push them into extreme poverty each year.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
