<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/society/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2022-02-21T19:21:22+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/society/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Sanitation: A Stinking Legacy of Social Stigma and Suffocation</title>
      <link href="/Sanitation-A-Stinking-Legacy-of-Social-Stigma-and-Suffocation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sanitation: A Stinking Legacy of Social Stigma and Suffocation" />
      <published>2022-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Sanitation-A-Stinking-Legacy-of-Social-Stigma-and-Suffocation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Sanitation-A-Stinking-Legacy-of-Social-Stigma-and-Suffocation">&lt;p&gt;Imagine you are in your car with your windows down while it crosses a garbage dump or an open sewage drain. What would you do immediately? You will shut the car windows, perhaps make an annoyed face and cover your nose. But have you ever wondered about those who have to bear this smell - that too a hundred times more magnificent - those who are involved in manually cleaning it, daily?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one question that needs to be seriously pondered upon!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every one of us has heard of the term - SANITATION. While most of us care about the sanitation and hygiene of ourselves and our homes, there are many who are deprived of sanitation in our society. It is so sad that on one hand, India has made significant progress in human and technological development wherein we are planning bullet trains, but on the other hand, it stands amongst the top in the list of countries with poor sanitation. The top 10% of the country enjoy clean and hygienic surroundings while there exists a community that makes its living by carrying human excreta and has no proper access to sanitation. Around 300 million Indians still practise open defecation. On top of it, every other day, one gets to hear of the death of sanitation workers working in extremely unhygienic conditions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sanitation and cleaning are often linked to social stigma. It is considered as the work of the poor, more specifically to those belonging to lower castes in India. The caste system has impacted society to an extent that even basic sanitation and hygiene is considered to be a privilege. Our society not only differentiates spaces as pure and impure but also its people. Scooping out the filth and bearing the stench of sewage is considered as the legacy of the poor and lower castes; this social status has been pre-determined for ages and has remained that way. The most esteemed 'google' has&amp;nbsp; defined this work of manual scavenging as an inhuman practice and I won't even question the web! The sad fact is that in our country, not every person belonging to a lower caste is a manual scavenger but almost every sanitation worker does belong to a lower caste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From drains and sewers to septic tanks and railway tracks, millions of people are engaged in cleaning, carrying and disposing of human excreta in return for pittances of this humiliating job. People still believe - &lt;em&gt;&quot;Hamari jaati ke logo ka yahi kaam hota hai&quot;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&quot;hamare bache bhi yahi karenge.&quot;&lt;/em&gt; (&quot;People of our caste have only this work to do&quot; and &quot;Our children will also do this&quot;). It is astonishing to see how this age-old legacy created by our society has made them believe it to be their fate and destiny.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why does this problem still exist? And are there not enough strict rules to deal with it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;'No manual scavenging deaths, 941 died while cleaning sewers'&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above statement was recently released by the government. It clearly points out a major problem. Even though there have been laws made to protect the dignity and rights of sanitation workers, either there is some flawed enactment within them or they are badly implemented. Although it has been claimed that there have been no deaths due to manual scavenging, does that mean it is justified to have deaths while cleaning sewers, when in reality there's hardly any difference between the two.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schemes and policies are being implemented in our country giving people the access to toilets but they haven't yet provided an appropriate and hygienic method for disposal. The manual work of carrying out human excreta is not only caste dependent, but also gender influenced. The majority of women from lower communities get paid as low as ₹10 to ₹50 per month for carrying human excreta. This reflects upon the huge irony which exists within the country. There have been schemes and policies aiming to protect the dignity of women by providing them with private sanitation spaces, while on the other hand, in reality their oppression has been further perpetuated through the humiliation of women dealing with human excreta.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actions and promises of the concerned authorities only come up at the time of elections with several inherent flaws. The multilevel-structural domination has left the sanitation workers with no option but to continue working. Moreover, government surveys are only confined to statutory towns, highlighting the fact that the concern is seen as an urban problem. This survey also misses out over a million estimated uncounted deaths of sanitation workers in the last 50 years who belonged to the private sector thereby not getting included. The pandemic also witnessed a surge in deaths of sanitation workers who handled the dead bodies in semi-urban and rural areas, and on the banks of the river Ganga.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem has prevailed for a long time and still continues to exist across regions. Despite the laws being in place, implementation and execution has been slow and redundant leading to numerous deaths over the years. The problem doesn’t limit itself to the present day workers but also to their families and generations that will follow. Attributing the job to certain vulnerable sections denies the people of their basic rights as individuals. This also sets up a ripple effect on the speed of development of a nation. Most of the workers suffer from severe illnesses and live shorter lives, thereby producing and earning less, and are unable to afford education and stable futures for their children.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need of the hour is to remove this blot on the idioms of justice. The social and gender issues related to sanitation have to be eradicated at the grassroots level. Assuring sustainable freedom not only requires awareness but also accessibility. Accessibility to alternate livelihood options with a right to a dignified life needs to be ensured. The problem of poor sanitation and such related issues won't be eradicated with the construction of toilets unless new and innovative ways to empty the pits without human intervention are explored. Moreover, a lot more difference can be made once individuals start thinking about the questions raised at the beginning of this article. The answer to 'how' will come up once it is truly understood by everyone!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shruti Indoria</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      
        <category term="humanity" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Imagine you are in your car with your windows down while it crosses a garbage dump or an open sewage drain. What would you do immediately? You will shut the car windows, perhaps make an annoyed face and cover your nose. But have you ever wondered about those who have to bear this smell - that too a hundred times more magnificent - those who are involved in manually cleaning it, daily? This is one question that needs to be seriously pondered upon! Every one of us has heard of the term - SANITATION. While most of us care about the sanitation and hygiene of ourselves and our homes, there are many who are deprived of sanitation in our society. It is so sad that on one hand, India has made significant progress in human and technological development wherein we are planning bullet trains, but on the other hand, it stands amongst the top in the list of countries with poor sanitation. The top 10% of the country enjoy clean and hygienic surroundings while there exists a community that makes its living by carrying human excreta and has no proper access to sanitation. Around 300 million Indians still practise open defecation. On top of it, every other day, one gets to hear of the death of sanitation workers working in extremely unhygienic conditions.&amp;nbsp; Sanitation and cleaning are often linked to social stigma. It is considered as the work of the poor, more specifically to those belonging to lower castes in India. The caste system has impacted society to an extent that even basic sanitation and hygiene is considered to be a privilege. Our society not only differentiates spaces as pure and impure but also its people. Scooping out the filth and bearing the stench of sewage is considered as the legacy of the poor and lower castes; this social status has been pre-determined for ages and has remained that way. The most esteemed 'google' has&amp;nbsp; defined this work of manual scavenging as an inhuman practice and I won't even question the web! The sad fact is that in our country, not every person belonging to a lower caste is a manual scavenger but almost every sanitation worker does belong to a lower caste. From drains and sewers to septic tanks and railway tracks, millions of people are engaged in cleaning, carrying and disposing of human excreta in return for pittances of this humiliating job. People still believe - &quot;Hamari jaati ke logo ka yahi kaam hota hai&quot; and &quot;hamare bache bhi yahi karenge.&quot; (&quot;People of our caste have only this work to do&quot; and &quot;Our children will also do this&quot;). It is astonishing to see how this age-old legacy created by our society has made them believe it to be their fate and destiny.&amp;nbsp; Why does this problem still exist? And are there not enough strict rules to deal with it? 'No manual scavenging deaths, 941 died while cleaning sewers' The above statement was recently released by the government. It clearly points out a major problem. Even though there have been laws made to protect the dignity and rights of sanitation workers, either there is some flawed enactment within them or they are badly implemented. Although it has been claimed that there have been no deaths due to manual scavenging, does that mean it is justified to have deaths while cleaning sewers, when in reality there's hardly any difference between the two.&amp;nbsp; Schemes and policies are being implemented in our country giving people the access to toilets but they haven't yet provided an appropriate and hygienic method for disposal. The manual work of carrying out human excreta is not only caste dependent, but also gender influenced. The majority of women from lower communities get paid as low as ₹10 to ₹50 per month for carrying human excreta. This reflects upon the huge irony which exists within the country. There have been schemes and policies aiming to protect the dignity of women by providing them with private sanitation spaces, while on the other hand, in reality their oppression has been further perpetuated through the humiliation of women dealing with human excreta.&amp;nbsp; The actions and promises of the concerned authorities only come up at the time of elections with several inherent flaws. The multilevel-structural domination has left the sanitation workers with no option but to continue working. Moreover, government surveys are only confined to statutory towns, highlighting the fact that the concern is seen as an urban problem. This survey also misses out over a million estimated uncounted deaths of sanitation workers in the last 50 years who belonged to the private sector thereby not getting included. The pandemic also witnessed a surge in deaths of sanitation workers who handled the dead bodies in semi-urban and rural areas, and on the banks of the river Ganga.&amp;nbsp; The problem has prevailed for a long time and still continues to exist across regions. Despite the laws being in place, implementation and execution has been slow and redundant leading to numerous deaths over the years. The problem doesn’t limit itself to the present day workers but also to their families and generations that will follow. Attributing the job to certain vulnerable sections denies the people of their basic rights as individuals. This also sets up a ripple effect on the speed of development of a nation. Most of the workers suffer from severe illnesses and live shorter lives, thereby producing and earning less, and are unable to afford education and stable futures for their children.&amp;nbsp; The need of the hour is to remove this blot on the idioms of justice. The social and gender issues related to sanitation have to be eradicated at the grassroots level. Assuring sustainable freedom not only requires awareness but also accessibility. Accessibility to alternate livelihood options with a right to a dignified life needs to be ensured. The problem of poor sanitation and such related issues won't be eradicated with the construction of toilets unless new and innovative ways to empty the pits without human intervention are explored. Moreover, a lot more difference can be made once individuals start thinking about the questions raised at the beginning of this article. The answer to 'how' will come up once it is truly understood by everyone!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The 21st Century Pandemics: What Does the Future Hold?</title>
      <link href="/The-21st-Century-Pandemics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 21st Century Pandemics: What Does the Future Hold?" />
      <published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-21st-Century-Pandemics</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-21st-Century-Pandemics">&lt;p&gt;Pandemics have made appearances throughout history and many a time, are credited with exceptional events and periods like the Renaissance (which took place after the Black Death) and the Roaring 20’s (which followed the Spanish Flu pandemic of the early 20th century). But what is often overlooked in history lessons but we, as a community, have learnt over the past two years is how scary and devastating these pandemics are. No amount of hope for a more golden period in the future can give anyone the strength to endure such a difficult time. Not without breaking down once in a while at the very least. It is important to acknowledge the urgency of the medical threats that the human world is currently facing or is expected to face shortly and take action accordingly. Some problems can be prevented while some can be made tractable. This article discusses three such threats and what the future holds for us.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The COVID-19 Pandemic&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quite honestly, there is not much I could add to the knowledge that almost each one of us already possess about the ongoing pandemic due to the fear surrounding the same. At the time of writing this article, the Omicron variant, which is 25% more infectious than the Delta variant, is causing panic and claiming lives across several countries. Therefore, yes, it is present and will most likely continue to be a cause for concern for a while.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How long this pandemic is going to continue is up for debate. It is dependent on multiple factors: how fast can the booster doses of the vaccines, that are effective against the Omicron variant, be rolled out; whether oral therapeutics can be scaled and made available to the public to restrict an infection to a mild one; and whether the society is capable of taking notes from the mistakes committed over the last two years and make urgent changes. For now, it is safe to say that we might have to hang on to the masks and take necessary COVID-19 safety precautions for a while.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Permafrost Pandemic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The possible permafrost pandemic is something that the scientific community and everyone else outside has been studying and debating for the last couple of years. Siberia and other parts of the Arctic have been facing record-breaking heat waves recently. Land surface temperatures as high as 45°C have been recorded, and studies have confirmed that the Arctic is heating up almost twice as fast as the rest of the planet. And this is all thanks to the much questioned and quoted phenomenon of 'global warming'. Global warming is very simply the warming up of the planet. This is primarily caused by the Greenhouse Effect.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An increase in the number of greenhouse gases (GHGs) like carbon dioxide, sulphur dioxide, oxides of nitrogen and methane in our atmosphere results in the formation of a sort of a blanket that traps the sun’s heat, resulting in climate change. GHGs are released by the burning of fossil fuels, among various other sources. Deforestation too has a huge contribution in this matter. Trees are capable of absorbing CO2 and giving out oxygen. In the absence of trees, this process does not occur, resulting in the accumulation of CO2.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we get into the details of the possible permafrost pandemic, it is important to understand what the term 'permafrost' really means. It refers to any kind of earth material like soil or gravel which has been at or under 0°C for two or more consecutive years. This definition, contrary to popular belief, does not include the glacial or sea ice. The thawing of the permafrost is what has been bothering scientists for a while. Apart from being the main cause of the ever-rising sea levels and the runaway climate change due to the release of the greenhouse gases trapped within, it might have several disease-causing microbes frozen at the moment which may be released eventually. The thawing of the permafrost is a phenomenon that has been around for no longer than the last two decades. It is only in its fetal stages and the process is likely to be expedited by the way the world is run today.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The active layer of the permafrost is in the form of water over the summer. It has been growing for a while now and is capable of forming a habitat for the newly thawed microbes. Essential biological processes can be activated here. The talik layer of the permafrost is rarely frozen. The microbes can even move to this layer and this would ensure that they are not frozen again. While the scientific community is in agreement that bacteria can survive for quite a long time, how long they can survive is still a matter of inquiry. Researchers have been attempting to revive ancient viruses from permafrost samples to determine the possibility of a pandemic caused by newly thawed microbes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, DNA viruses are the most feared in this matter. Being more chemically stable than RNA viruses, they are more likely to survive the process of freezing and thawing. The two known possible viruses that could emerge from the permafrost are pox and anthrax. However, several other microbes are yet unknown and could be even more deadly than those known to mankind presently. Exactly how dangerous this possible permafrost pandemic could be is one of the many questions that the scientific community is unable to answer or agree on.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is exacerbated by the refusal of a portion of the human population to acknowledge the existence and effects of global warming. Barely anything at all is being done to tackle climate change. However, it is very clear that preparing the health systems for a permafrost pandemic eventuality and working to reverse climate change are the main, and perhaps, the only ways to survive it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Silent Pandemic&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antimicrobial Resistance (AMR), meaning resistance to antimicrobial drugs possessed by certain microbes, is a popular term in the scientific and medical communities. This is more so because of the ever-increasing fear of a pandemic due to diseases caused by microbes resistant to all existing drugs, also known as 'superbugs'. Superbugs kill about 700,000 (estimated) people each year and the statistics are predicted to cross ten million by the year 2050.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antibiotics have been around since the discovery of penicillin by Sir Alexander Fleming in 1928. They have revolutionised our lives by adding 23 years to the average life span and by becoming an integral part of modern medical practices. When a person suffers from a bacterial disease, they are offered antibiotics and this kills some of the bacteria. The remaining microbes, which are resistant to the drug, survive and proliferate. This leads to the existence of panic-inducing superbugs that are resistant to all known drugs. It makes it difficult and, in some cases, impossible to cure previously tractable diseases. Densely populated regions of the world with poor sanitary conditions and water quality are feared to be more susceptible to the possibility of becoming epicentres of outbreaks of superbugs. The change in microbes that make them resistant to drugs is unstoppable. When antibiotics are overused (much like it is today), microbes are exponentially more likely to become resistant. If the situation is not handled exigently, minor infections may turn fatal. This is known as the silent pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the story does not end there. The COVID-19 pandemic has had a hand in making the situation much worse. Studies have demonstrated that over 70% of COVID-19 patients have been administered antibiotic treatment despite only 10% of the cases having bacterial infections. This was especially because in the embryonic stages of the pandemic it was difficult to distinguish between a bacterial infection and COVID-19 infection. Later, the fear of bacterial co-infections caused the overuse of antibiotic drugs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must spread awareness about AMR and the overuse of antibiotics. Otherwise, they will soon be rendered ineffective and alternative treatment may be required to tackle diseases. This might have even more severe side effects or may not be effective at all. Prudent use of antibiotics can decelerate the AMR, ensuring their availability to treat microbial infections effectively in the future.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this article is not to create fear but to point out that neglecting concerns like those that preceded the outbreak of COVID-19 could result in other, perhaps even more catastrophic, pandemics. It is important to learn from our past mistakes when it comes to handling diseases. It is also important to know that it is practicable to reduce the possible effects or even prevent certain disastrous eventualities. All it takes is to have an open mind, make changes in our lifestyles and carry out proper scientific research to address the problems.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      
        <category term="humanity" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Pandemics have made appearances throughout history and many a time, are credited with exceptional events and periods like the Renaissance (which took place after the Black Death) and the Roaring 20’s (which followed the Spanish Flu pandemic of the early 20th century). But what is often overlooked in history lessons but we, as a community, have learnt over the past two years is how scary and devastating these pandemics are. No amount of hope for a more golden period in the future can give anyone the strength to endure such a difficult time. Not without breaking down once in a while at the very least. It is important to acknowledge the urgency of the medical threats that the human world is currently facing or is expected to face shortly and take action accordingly. Some problems can be prevented while some can be made tractable. This article discusses three such threats and what the future holds for us.&amp;nbsp; The COVID-19 Pandemic&amp;nbsp; Quite honestly, there is not much I could add to the knowledge that almost each one of us already possess about the ongoing pandemic due to the fear surrounding the same. At the time of writing this article, the Omicron variant, which is 25% more infectious than the Delta variant, is causing panic and claiming lives across several countries. Therefore, yes, it is present and will most likely continue to be a cause for concern for a while.&amp;nbsp; How long this pandemic is going to continue is up for debate. It is dependent on multiple factors: how fast can the booster doses of the vaccines, that are effective against the Omicron variant, be rolled out; whether oral therapeutics can be scaled and made available to the public to restrict an infection to a mild one; and whether the society is capable of taking notes from the mistakes committed over the last two years and make urgent changes. For now, it is safe to say that we might have to hang on to the masks and take necessary COVID-19 safety precautions for a while.&amp;nbsp; The Permafrost Pandemic The possible permafrost pandemic is something that the scientific community and everyone else outside has been studying and debating for the last couple of years. Siberia and other parts of the Arctic have been facing record-breaking heat waves recently. Land surface temperatures as high as 45°C have been recorded, and studies have confirmed that the Arctic is heating up almost twice as fast as the rest of the planet. And this is all thanks to the much questioned and quoted phenomenon of 'global warming'. Global warming is very simply the warming up of the planet. This is primarily caused by the Greenhouse Effect.&amp;nbsp; An increase in the number of greenhouse gases (GHGs) like carbon dioxide, sulphur dioxide, oxides of nitrogen and methane in our atmosphere results in the formation of a sort of a blanket that traps the sun’s heat, resulting in climate change. GHGs are released by the burning of fossil fuels, among various other sources. Deforestation too has a huge contribution in this matter. Trees are capable of absorbing CO2 and giving out oxygen. In the absence of trees, this process does not occur, resulting in the accumulation of CO2.&amp;nbsp; Before we get into the details of the possible permafrost pandemic, it is important to understand what the term 'permafrost' really means. It refers to any kind of earth material like soil or gravel which has been at or under 0°C for two or more consecutive years. This definition, contrary to popular belief, does not include the glacial or sea ice. The thawing of the permafrost is what has been bothering scientists for a while. Apart from being the main cause of the ever-rising sea levels and the runaway climate change due to the release of the greenhouse gases trapped within, it might have several disease-causing microbes frozen at the moment which may be released eventually. The thawing of the permafrost is a phenomenon that has been around for no longer than the last two decades. It is only in its fetal stages and the process is likely to be expedited by the way the world is run today.&amp;nbsp; The active layer of the permafrost is in the form of water over the summer. It has been growing for a while now and is capable of forming a habitat for the newly thawed microbes. Essential biological processes can be activated here. The talik layer of the permafrost is rarely frozen. The microbes can even move to this layer and this would ensure that they are not frozen again. While the scientific community is in agreement that bacteria can survive for quite a long time, how long they can survive is still a matter of inquiry. Researchers have been attempting to revive ancient viruses from permafrost samples to determine the possibility of a pandemic caused by newly thawed microbes.&amp;nbsp; Generally, DNA viruses are the most feared in this matter. Being more chemically stable than RNA viruses, they are more likely to survive the process of freezing and thawing. The two known possible viruses that could emerge from the permafrost are pox and anthrax. However, several other microbes are yet unknown and could be even more deadly than those known to mankind presently. Exactly how dangerous this possible permafrost pandemic could be is one of the many questions that the scientific community is unable to answer or agree on.&amp;nbsp; The problem is exacerbated by the refusal of a portion of the human population to acknowledge the existence and effects of global warming. Barely anything at all is being done to tackle climate change. However, it is very clear that preparing the health systems for a permafrost pandemic eventuality and working to reverse climate change are the main, and perhaps, the only ways to survive it.&amp;nbsp; The Silent Pandemic&amp;nbsp; Antimicrobial Resistance (AMR), meaning resistance to antimicrobial drugs possessed by certain microbes, is a popular term in the scientific and medical communities. This is more so because of the ever-increasing fear of a pandemic due to diseases caused by microbes resistant to all existing drugs, also known as 'superbugs'. Superbugs kill about 700,000 (estimated) people each year and the statistics are predicted to cross ten million by the year 2050.&amp;nbsp; Antibiotics have been around since the discovery of penicillin by Sir Alexander Fleming in 1928. They have revolutionised our lives by adding 23 years to the average life span and by becoming an integral part of modern medical practices. When a person suffers from a bacterial disease, they are offered antibiotics and this kills some of the bacteria. The remaining microbes, which are resistant to the drug, survive and proliferate. This leads to the existence of panic-inducing superbugs that are resistant to all known drugs. It makes it difficult and, in some cases, impossible to cure previously tractable diseases. Densely populated regions of the world with poor sanitary conditions and water quality are feared to be more susceptible to the possibility of becoming epicentres of outbreaks of superbugs. The change in microbes that make them resistant to drugs is unstoppable. When antibiotics are overused (much like it is today), microbes are exponentially more likely to become resistant. If the situation is not handled exigently, minor infections may turn fatal. This is known as the silent pandemic.&amp;nbsp; Unfortunately, the story does not end there. The COVID-19 pandemic has had a hand in making the situation much worse. Studies have demonstrated that over 70% of COVID-19 patients have been administered antibiotic treatment despite only 10% of the cases having bacterial infections. This was especially because in the embryonic stages of the pandemic it was difficult to distinguish between a bacterial infection and COVID-19 infection. Later, the fear of bacterial co-infections caused the overuse of antibiotic drugs.&amp;nbsp; We must spread awareness about AMR and the overuse of antibiotics. Otherwise, they will soon be rendered ineffective and alternative treatment may be required to tackle diseases. This might have even more severe side effects or may not be effective at all. Prudent use of antibiotics can decelerate the AMR, ensuring their availability to treat microbial infections effectively in the future.&amp;nbsp; The aim of this article is not to create fear but to point out that neglecting concerns like those that preceded the outbreak of COVID-19 could result in other, perhaps even more catastrophic, pandemics. It is important to learn from our past mistakes when it comes to handling diseases. It is also important to know that it is practicable to reduce the possible effects or even prevent certain disastrous eventualities. All it takes is to have an open mind, make changes in our lifestyles and carry out proper scientific research to address the problems.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lights, Camera, Generalise!</title>
      <link href="/Lights-Camera-Generalise" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lights, Camera, Generalise!" />
      <published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Lights-Camera-Generalise</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lights-Camera-Generalise">&lt;p&gt;While going through my Google feed one day, I came across this&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indianexpress.com/article/entertainment/bollywood/meenakshi-sundareshwar-inauthentic-stereotypical-take-on-tamil-culture-sanya-malhotra-abhimanyu-dassani-7616835/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;in &lt;em&gt;The Indian Express &lt;/em&gt;about the review of the recent film,&lt;em&gt; Meenakshi Sundareshwar&lt;/em&gt;. Because I hail from Rajasthan, I could relate to what the author was trying to say. Whenever I introduce myself as a Rajasthani, certain visuals pop up in the mind of the listener; vast stretches of sand, men wearing colourful turbans, and women in sarees with ‘&lt;em&gt;matkas&lt;/em&gt;’ on their heads living in&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;kutcha&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;houses, and even though a large part of Rajasthan is similar to that, these visuals are not representative of the entire state. I too have played the role of ‘the listener’ in a lot of cases and had my fair share of stereotypes about places, people and cultures, merely based on their depiction in movies or series. If suppose, I mention Tamils; “loud exaggerated accents, dark-skinned villains, gajras, jhumkis, curd, aiyoo, and religiously inclined vegetarian folks without a sense of humour” (as pointed out by the article) is what comes to my mind. Indeed because this is how I have seen Tamils; whether it was Deepika Padukone portraying&amp;nbsp;Meenama&amp;nbsp;in&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Chennai Express&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;or Shiv Subramaniam acting as Alia’s father in&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Two States&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, what is the big deal about Bollywood stereotyping practically everything? The current value of the film industry is approximately ₹183 billion which explains the number of people who are influenced by the content of Bollywood films. Thus, Hindi cinema shapes the perception of a vast majority of Indians and for a lot of us, what we see in movies ends up being how we think things are. Moreover, the problem is not just limited to forming perceptions about different places; in fact, this is not even the tip of the iceberg. The real problem comes into picture when these perceptions start fuelling stereotypes that already exist in society. For example, women in Bollywood have always been portrayed as ‘damsels in distress’ whose apparent role is to have a love-hate relationship with the protagonist, and all her life problems get solved post their union. The little to no screen time given to female actresses in Hindi cinema except for brief appearances in a song, here and there, is a metaphor of the way women are positioned in the real society. The film&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Ranjhanaa&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;went overboard with the idea of Sonam Kapoor’s character in the film agreeing to meet the protagonist, her stalker, because he was ‘consistent’ in his ways and there was no love involved. The cliché storyline wherein the protagonist does everything to get the attention of the girl while the girl constantly ignores him but eventually gives in (because he is the protagonist) drives home the idea that girls actually want to say 'yes' but due to her &lt;em&gt;sanskari &lt;/em&gt;(traditional) values, she refrains from it. This portrayal absolutely undermines the concept of consent wherein the 'no' is lost in translation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the generalisations don’t stop here. Not just promoting sexist stereotypes, there are multiple instances (even in recent times) where Bollywood has promoted body shaming. The female actresses, with their perfect figure, end up setting unrealistic expectations about looks and body amongst the general population. Further, Bollywood seems to fuel these misconceptions of beauty when they appoint people who look a little different than the idealistic standards of beauty as the ‘side characters’ in films. These characters are seldom portrayed to have any loving relationships. This ends up communicating the idea that if you do not have a perfect body or glowing skin, you would have a hard time finding partners. Even Bollywood songs are heavily inclined towards appreciating the beauty of a ‘gora’ or ‘gori,’ which literally translates to white in English. “&lt;em&gt;Goriya Chura Na Mera Jiya” &lt;/em&gt;(O White Woman&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;don't steal my heart), &lt;em&gt;“Chura Ke Dil Mera Goriya Chali” &lt;/em&gt;(The White Woman has stolen my heart) are just a few cases of such lyrics&lt;em&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;Such stereotypes transcend onto races and religions as well. Whether it was 2000’s&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Phir Bhi Dil Hai Hindustani&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;or 2008’s&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Chandni Chowk To China,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;the weird obsession to make an mainland Indian actor have the ‘East Asian look’ by taping their eyes to slant them is the ugly truth of an industry consumed by over a billion people. Even people belonging to the LGBTQ+ community, especially homosexual men, are portrayed as having feminine features. Most movies stereotypically mock the way they walk and dress which was pretty evident in movies like&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Student Of The Year&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;and&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Dostana.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it might not be a big deal for many, it does hurt a community at large, and makes their attempts at fighting stigmas in society prove futile. There is no denying that Bollywood is evolving. The increasing number of heavyweight female characters who come in all sizes, shapes and color, sparks hope for a fairer, aware and more appropriate Bollywood culture in the future. However, Bollywood still has an immense population of stereotypes buried in its backyard, more so because it is the easiest route to singling out a community (generally minorities) or driving home the ideas that the majority in a country identifies with.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before parting ways, here is another&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indianexpress.com/article/trending/trending-in-india/tweeple-are-calling-out-stereotypes-in-movies-and-its-a-must-read-5528242/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; which I found while researching for my piece. It is hilarious but sadly true; and yes, I am still a Rajasthani, but I do not carry&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;‘matkas&lt;/em&gt;!’&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shiksha Mody</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">While going through my Google feed one day, I came across this&amp;nbsp;article&amp;nbsp;in The Indian Express about the review of the recent film, Meenakshi Sundareshwar. Because I hail from Rajasthan, I could relate to what the author was trying to say. Whenever I introduce myself as a Rajasthani, certain visuals pop up in the mind of the listener; vast stretches of sand, men wearing colourful turbans, and women in sarees with ‘matkas’ on their heads living in&amp;nbsp;kutcha&amp;nbsp;houses, and even though a large part of Rajasthan is similar to that, these visuals are not representative of the entire state. I too have played the role of ‘the listener’ in a lot of cases and had my fair share of stereotypes about places, people and cultures, merely based on their depiction in movies or series. If suppose, I mention Tamils; “loud exaggerated accents, dark-skinned villains, gajras, jhumkis, curd, aiyoo, and religiously inclined vegetarian folks without a sense of humour” (as pointed out by the article) is what comes to my mind. Indeed because this is how I have seen Tamils; whether it was Deepika Padukone portraying&amp;nbsp;Meenama&amp;nbsp;in&amp;nbsp;Chennai Express&amp;nbsp;or Shiv Subramaniam acting as Alia’s father in&amp;nbsp;Two States. However, what is the big deal about Bollywood stereotyping practically everything? The current value of the film industry is approximately ₹183 billion which explains the number of people who are influenced by the content of Bollywood films. Thus, Hindi cinema shapes the perception of a vast majority of Indians and for a lot of us, what we see in movies ends up being how we think things are. Moreover, the problem is not just limited to forming perceptions about different places; in fact, this is not even the tip of the iceberg. The real problem comes into picture when these perceptions start fuelling stereotypes that already exist in society. For example, women in Bollywood have always been portrayed as ‘damsels in distress’ whose apparent role is to have a love-hate relationship with the protagonist, and all her life problems get solved post their union. The little to no screen time given to female actresses in Hindi cinema except for brief appearances in a song, here and there, is a metaphor of the way women are positioned in the real society. The film&amp;nbsp;Ranjhanaa&amp;nbsp;went overboard with the idea of Sonam Kapoor’s character in the film agreeing to meet the protagonist, her stalker, because he was ‘consistent’ in his ways and there was no love involved. The cliché storyline wherein the protagonist does everything to get the attention of the girl while the girl constantly ignores him but eventually gives in (because he is the protagonist) drives home the idea that girls actually want to say 'yes' but due to her sanskari (traditional) values, she refrains from it. This portrayal absolutely undermines the concept of consent wherein the 'no' is lost in translation. Unfortunately, the generalisations don’t stop here. Not just promoting sexist stereotypes, there are multiple instances (even in recent times) where Bollywood has promoted body shaming. The female actresses, with their perfect figure, end up setting unrealistic expectations about looks and body amongst the general population. Further, Bollywood seems to fuel these misconceptions of beauty when they appoint people who look a little different than the idealistic standards of beauty as the ‘side characters’ in films. These characters are seldom portrayed to have any loving relationships. This ends up communicating the idea that if you do not have a perfect body or glowing skin, you would have a hard time finding partners. Even Bollywood songs are heavily inclined towards appreciating the beauty of a ‘gora’ or ‘gori,’ which literally translates to white in English. “Goriya Chura Na Mera Jiya” (O White Woman don't steal my heart), “Chura Ke Dil Mera Goriya Chali” (The White Woman has stolen my heart) are just a few cases of such lyrics. Such stereotypes transcend onto races and religions as well. Whether it was 2000’s&amp;nbsp;Phir Bhi Dil Hai Hindustani&amp;nbsp;or 2008’s&amp;nbsp;Chandni Chowk To China,&amp;nbsp;the weird obsession to make an mainland Indian actor have the ‘East Asian look’ by taping their eyes to slant them is the ugly truth of an industry consumed by over a billion people. Even people belonging to the LGBTQ+ community, especially homosexual men, are portrayed as having feminine features. Most movies stereotypically mock the way they walk and dress which was pretty evident in movies like&amp;nbsp;Student Of The Year&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;Dostana.&amp;nbsp; While it might not be a big deal for many, it does hurt a community at large, and makes their attempts at fighting stigmas in society prove futile. There is no denying that Bollywood is evolving. The increasing number of heavyweight female characters who come in all sizes, shapes and color, sparks hope for a fairer, aware and more appropriate Bollywood culture in the future. However, Bollywood still has an immense population of stereotypes buried in its backyard, more so because it is the easiest route to singling out a community (generally minorities) or driving home the ideas that the majority in a country identifies with.&amp;nbsp; Before parting ways, here is another&amp;nbsp;article which I found while researching for my piece. It is hilarious but sadly true; and yes, I am still a Rajasthani, but I do not carry&amp;nbsp;‘matkas!’</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part II</title>
      <link href="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part II" />
      <published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-II</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-II">&lt;p&gt;In part I, we discussed what colourism is, what kind of activities perpetuate it today and some of the common consequences of the same. However, to actually tackle the problems of colourism, it is important to analyse what its possible root causes are.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A reasoning that is generally provided to explain the prevalence of colourism is colonialism. While it does not account for all the reasons behind the problem, it certainly is an important one. When various European powers occupied regions across the world, they took along with them their beauty standards which were based on what white people look like: thin nose, pale skin, straight hair and so on. Under colonial rule, the natives of the colonies were indoctrinated in Eurocentric views and soon, they learnt to view everything about the colonial power as superior to their own, including how they looked.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The colonial power also instituted various discriminatory practices and granted marginally more privilege to those who were brown or light skinned over those who were black or dark skinned. This later manifested among the non white populace in the form of practices like Blanqueamiento or whitening which is prevalent in post colonial countries in Oceania and America. It is aimed at mejorar la raza (“bettering the race”) to achieve the ideal of white. Basically, people try to marry a light skinned partner to produce fair skinned children. In fact, in the beginning of the 20th century, Latin American countries put in place policies that promoted Blanqueamiento (for instance, promoting immigration of Europeans in an attempt to whiten the population). Even today, in countries across the world, whiteness is seen as superior and beautiful and more often than not, in pageants and other forms of entertainment, people praise those who embody Eurocentric ideals of beauty.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many experts maintain that colourism predates colonialism. Let us take India for an example: Hindu religious texts refer to dark skinned people as people of the low caste. This stereotyping is probably born out of the fact that lower caste people were often relegated to manual labour in the sun, which resulted in them getting tanned. Dalits, who belong to the lowest caste, were treated as “untouchables” for a long time. Conversely, those with a fairer complexion were thought to belong to higher castes. The advent of colonialism and the colonial teachings that aimed to subjugate the Indians using a divide and conquer technique only polarised the castes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Indians started believing in a sort of supremacy of mixed race people, called the Anglo-Indians, over those who were full blooded Indians. The closer you were to your English ancestor, the higher up in the social strata you were.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, a vast majority of Hindu gods are portrayed as being very fair which too results in an unconscious bias in favour of those who possess a fair complexion.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hindi sound films became a thing only in 1931. Prior to that, Parsi theatre dominated the scene. Parsis were much fairer than other Indian ethnic groups because of their Iranian ancestry. This too played a role in promulgating the idea that fair is equivalent to beautiful.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, rarely any of the hundreds of Indian movies produced every year have someone from the lower castes or someone who is dark skinned in the leading roles. This lack of representation continues to harm the perception of Indians towards those who possess a darker complexion or belong to a lower caste.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the Indian Constitution does provide for protections against caste based discrimination, it is still widespread today. Dalits are looked down upon in positions of authority and responsibility, and also, often discriminated against in educational institutions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a consequence of this rampant colourism, fairness creams continue to find a place in the shops across India. One of the most famous brands in the country, “Fair and Lovely”, came under attack for their colourist commercials promoting their skin lightening products in 2020. In response to the criticism, instead of dealing with the actual problem, they rebranded as “Glow and Lovely” and continued to sell the same products. During this time, the company officials claimed that the product was never meant to be a skin bleaching product, rather it was meant to &amp;nbsp;'improve skin barrier function, improve skin firmness and smoothen skin texture'.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In countries like South Korea, colourism was born out of its feudal history. During the feudal ages of Korea those who belonged to the upper classes were lighter skinned owing to the fact that they could afford to stay indoors while those who belonged to the lower classes had to spend longer hours in the sun, often doing labour, and thus, were tanned. Fair skin was therefore a symbol of status and affluence, and consequently, coveted in Korea.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In more recent times, as Korea got more exposure to the west, western countries, dominated by white folk, were seen as more modern and thus, the higher status of fair skin failed to fade away into obscurity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, in Korea, fair skin continues to remain an important beauty ideal. As discussed in part 1, Kpop and Kdrama stars are expected to conform to the strict beauty standards which includes fair skin. It is deemed so important that many who do not fit into the ideal are expected and forced to get surgery to achieve the same. Moreover, the members of each group who are closest to the ideal are regarded as the “visual” of the group. For instance, Jin is the visual for BTS and Jisoo is the same for Blackpink.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In America, colourism was primarily born out of colonial practices and slavery. During the times of slavery, white people would rape their black slaves and the mixed race children who were born were treated marginally better than their darker skinned counterparts. They were allowed to work indoors while the dark complexioned slaves toiled out in the sun. In some cases, while it was still not allowed by the law, the white parent would informally recognise the child, though they could not inherit anything. This prevalence of the colourist divisions during the pre civil war times of America can be easily seen in James Stirling’s (a British writer who visited America in 1857) notes on the same:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In judging of the welfare of the slaves, it is necessary to distinguish the different conditions of slavery. The most important distinction, both as regards to numbers and its influence on the well being of the slave, is that between house­servants and farm or field hands. The house servant is comparatively well off. He is frequently born and bred in the family he belongs to; and even when this is not the case, the constant association of the slave and his master, and master's family, naturally leads to such an attachment as it ensures good treatment...The position of the field­hands is very different; of those, especially, who labour on large plantations. Here there are none of those humanizing influences at work which temper the rigour of the system, nor is there the same check of public opinion to control abuse. The 'force' is worked &lt;em&gt;en masse, &lt;/em&gt;as a great human mechanism; or, if you will, as a drove of human cattle.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li class=&quot;ql-align-right&quot;&gt;Letters from the Slave States, James Stirling&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This discrimination between Black people who are fair skinned and those who are dark complexioned due to the association of the same with a sort of marginal privilege, or lack thereof, led to light skin being coveted by African Americans. After the abolition of slavery, societies were set up which were open solely to the light skinned among the African American population. To determine whether one was suitable for being in such a company various tests were devised. The Brown Paper Bag Test required one to have a skin tone that was the same as or lighter than a brown paper bag to be admitted to such societies. Another similar test was the vein test: if one’s veins showed on their skin, then they were eligible for being a member.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another concept that was codified into the law in some of the US' states in the early 20th century was the “One Drop Rule”. This stated that if you had even a drop of African American blood, then you would be classified as black and thus, relegated to second class citizenship. This further polarised the demographic in matters of race and colour. Moreover, white passing black people took advantage of this to be registered as white and live as first class citizens, free from discrimination.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, people are becoming increasingly aware of the problems of colourism. Various companies have been making an effort to prevent the phenomenon of “beauty bias” (preference of individuals during the hiring process or during promotion decisions based on their attractiveness) through unconscious bias training. Several studies and researches have been conducted to gain more insight into the issues of implicit bias. A 2006 study concluded that fair skinned individuals were looked at favourably in employment decisions. Another research conducted in 2009 exposed that skin tone played a major role in the hiring of black employees and was often “more salient and regarded more highly than one’s educational background and prior work experience”. In 2010, a study carried out showed that children of all races chose light skinned characters in response to positive descriptors like “smart” or “pretty”, and ascribed negative attributes to darker characters, that is, a persistence of a implicit bias against dark skin. In 2016, Chika Okoro delivered a TedX talk titled&amp;nbsp; “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=8&amp;amp;v=fvoWoMIwr-g&amp;amp;feature=emb_logo&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Confessions of a D Girl: Colorism and Global Standards of Beauty'' in&lt;/a&gt; which she expatiates on the prevalence of colourism in the entertainment industry. In 2018, a study demonstrated that light complexioned individuals “attain a higher educational level, receive higher wages and enjoy better-quality jobs than their darker-skinned co-ethnics”, proving that there are both inter racial and intra racial wage gaps.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, an understanding and concern surrounding the pervasiveness of colourism is on the rise, and this is slowly manifesting in the form of increased and more diverse representation of various ethnic groups in the entertainment industry across the world alongside other marginal changes in policies and practices. However, the lack of awareness of the problem, its root causes, and its exclusion from popular discourse is making the process of change very slow. For now, we can educate ourselves better and reject discriminatory practices in order to aid in expediting the process of abolition of colourism.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In part I, we discussed what colourism is, what kind of activities perpetuate it today and some of the common consequences of the same. However, to actually tackle the problems of colourism, it is important to analyse what its possible root causes are.&amp;nbsp; A reasoning that is generally provided to explain the prevalence of colourism is colonialism. While it does not account for all the reasons behind the problem, it certainly is an important one. When various European powers occupied regions across the world, they took along with them their beauty standards which were based on what white people look like: thin nose, pale skin, straight hair and so on. Under colonial rule, the natives of the colonies were indoctrinated in Eurocentric views and soon, they learnt to view everything about the colonial power as superior to their own, including how they looked.&amp;nbsp; The colonial power also instituted various discriminatory practices and granted marginally more privilege to those who were brown or light skinned over those who were black or dark skinned. This later manifested among the non white populace in the form of practices like Blanqueamiento or whitening which is prevalent in post colonial countries in Oceania and America. It is aimed at mejorar la raza (“bettering the race”) to achieve the ideal of white. Basically, people try to marry a light skinned partner to produce fair skinned children. In fact, in the beginning of the 20th century, Latin American countries put in place policies that promoted Blanqueamiento (for instance, promoting immigration of Europeans in an attempt to whiten the population). Even today, in countries across the world, whiteness is seen as superior and beautiful and more often than not, in pageants and other forms of entertainment, people praise those who embody Eurocentric ideals of beauty.&amp;nbsp; Many experts maintain that colourism predates colonialism. Let us take India for an example: Hindu religious texts refer to dark skinned people as people of the low caste. This stereotyping is probably born out of the fact that lower caste people were often relegated to manual labour in the sun, which resulted in them getting tanned. Dalits, who belong to the lowest caste, were treated as “untouchables” for a long time. Conversely, those with a fairer complexion were thought to belong to higher castes. The advent of colonialism and the colonial teachings that aimed to subjugate the Indians using a divide and conquer technique only polarised the castes.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, Indians started believing in a sort of supremacy of mixed race people, called the Anglo-Indians, over those who were full blooded Indians. The closer you were to your English ancestor, the higher up in the social strata you were.&amp;nbsp; Additionally, a vast majority of Hindu gods are portrayed as being very fair which too results in an unconscious bias in favour of those who possess a fair complexion.&amp;nbsp; Hindi sound films became a thing only in 1931. Prior to that, Parsi theatre dominated the scene. Parsis were much fairer than other Indian ethnic groups because of their Iranian ancestry. This too played a role in promulgating the idea that fair is equivalent to beautiful.&amp;nbsp; Today, rarely any of the hundreds of Indian movies produced every year have someone from the lower castes or someone who is dark skinned in the leading roles. This lack of representation continues to harm the perception of Indians towards those who possess a darker complexion or belong to a lower caste.&amp;nbsp; While the Indian Constitution does provide for protections against caste based discrimination, it is still widespread today. Dalits are looked down upon in positions of authority and responsibility, and also, often discriminated against in educational institutions.&amp;nbsp; As a consequence of this rampant colourism, fairness creams continue to find a place in the shops across India. One of the most famous brands in the country, “Fair and Lovely”, came under attack for their colourist commercials promoting their skin lightening products in 2020. In response to the criticism, instead of dealing with the actual problem, they rebranded as “Glow and Lovely” and continued to sell the same products. During this time, the company officials claimed that the product was never meant to be a skin bleaching product, rather it was meant to &amp;nbsp;'improve skin barrier function, improve skin firmness and smoothen skin texture'.&amp;nbsp; In countries like South Korea, colourism was born out of its feudal history. During the feudal ages of Korea those who belonged to the upper classes were lighter skinned owing to the fact that they could afford to stay indoors while those who belonged to the lower classes had to spend longer hours in the sun, often doing labour, and thus, were tanned. Fair skin was therefore a symbol of status and affluence, and consequently, coveted in Korea.&amp;nbsp; In more recent times, as Korea got more exposure to the west, western countries, dominated by white folk, were seen as more modern and thus, the higher status of fair skin failed to fade away into obscurity.&amp;nbsp; Today, in Korea, fair skin continues to remain an important beauty ideal. As discussed in part 1, Kpop and Kdrama stars are expected to conform to the strict beauty standards which includes fair skin. It is deemed so important that many who do not fit into the ideal are expected and forced to get surgery to achieve the same. Moreover, the members of each group who are closest to the ideal are regarded as the “visual” of the group. For instance, Jin is the visual for BTS and Jisoo is the same for Blackpink.&amp;nbsp; In America, colourism was primarily born out of colonial practices and slavery. During the times of slavery, white people would rape their black slaves and the mixed race children who were born were treated marginally better than their darker skinned counterparts. They were allowed to work indoors while the dark complexioned slaves toiled out in the sun. In some cases, while it was still not allowed by the law, the white parent would informally recognise the child, though they could not inherit anything. This prevalence of the colourist divisions during the pre civil war times of America can be easily seen in James Stirling’s (a British writer who visited America in 1857) notes on the same:&amp;nbsp; “In judging of the welfare of the slaves, it is necessary to distinguish the different conditions of slavery. The most important distinction, both as regards to numbers and its influence on the well being of the slave, is that between house­servants and farm or field hands. The house servant is comparatively well off. He is frequently born and bred in the family he belongs to; and even when this is not the case, the constant association of the slave and his master, and master's family, naturally leads to such an attachment as it ensures good treatment...The position of the field­hands is very different; of those, especially, who labour on large plantations. Here there are none of those humanizing influences at work which temper the rigour of the system, nor is there the same check of public opinion to control abuse. The 'force' is worked en masse, as a great human mechanism; or, if you will, as a drove of human cattle.” Letters from the Slave States, James Stirling This discrimination between Black people who are fair skinned and those who are dark complexioned due to the association of the same with a sort of marginal privilege, or lack thereof, led to light skin being coveted by African Americans. After the abolition of slavery, societies were set up which were open solely to the light skinned among the African American population. To determine whether one was suitable for being in such a company various tests were devised. The Brown Paper Bag Test required one to have a skin tone that was the same as or lighter than a brown paper bag to be admitted to such societies. Another similar test was the vein test: if one’s veins showed on their skin, then they were eligible for being a member.&amp;nbsp; Another concept that was codified into the law in some of the US' states in the early 20th century was the “One Drop Rule”. This stated that if you had even a drop of African American blood, then you would be classified as black and thus, relegated to second class citizenship. This further polarised the demographic in matters of race and colour. Moreover, white passing black people took advantage of this to be registered as white and live as first class citizens, free from discrimination.&amp;nbsp; Today, people are becoming increasingly aware of the problems of colourism. Various companies have been making an effort to prevent the phenomenon of “beauty bias” (preference of individuals during the hiring process or during promotion decisions based on their attractiveness) through unconscious bias training. Several studies and researches have been conducted to gain more insight into the issues of implicit bias. A 2006 study concluded that fair skinned individuals were looked at favourably in employment decisions. Another research conducted in 2009 exposed that skin tone played a major role in the hiring of black employees and was often “more salient and regarded more highly than one’s educational background and prior work experience”. In 2010, a study carried out showed that children of all races chose light skinned characters in response to positive descriptors like “smart” or “pretty”, and ascribed negative attributes to darker characters, that is, a persistence of a implicit bias against dark skin. In 2016, Chika Okoro delivered a TedX talk titled&amp;nbsp; “Confessions of a D Girl: Colorism and Global Standards of Beauty'' in which she expatiates on the prevalence of colourism in the entertainment industry. In 2018, a study demonstrated that light complexioned individuals “attain a higher educational level, receive higher wages and enjoy better-quality jobs than their darker-skinned co-ethnics”, proving that there are both inter racial and intra racial wage gaps.&amp;nbsp; Clearly, an understanding and concern surrounding the pervasiveness of colourism is on the rise, and this is slowly manifesting in the form of increased and more diverse representation of various ethnic groups in the entertainment industry across the world alongside other marginal changes in policies and practices. However, the lack of awareness of the problem, its root causes, and its exclusion from popular discourse is making the process of change very slow. For now, we can educate ourselves better and reject discriminatory practices in order to aid in expediting the process of abolition of colourism.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part I</title>
      <link href="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-I" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=" Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part I" />
      <published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-I</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-I">&lt;p&gt;“Mirror, mirror on the wall, who is the fairest of them all?” (&lt;em&gt;Snow White&lt;/em&gt;) - is as iconic as quotes generally get. Anyone who has watched, read or listened to the story of &lt;em&gt;Snow White&lt;/em&gt; is aware of the Evil Queen’s aspirations: she wished to be the “fairest of them all”. 'Fair', as in not 'just' but 'pale' and ergo, beautiful. This declaration of the equivalence of a paler skin tone and beauty has been at the center of various cultures across the world, and has stood the test of time. Those with fairer skin tones are deemed more 'marriage worthy', less intimidating, more innocent, less violent and of course, more beautiful. This is colourism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it more formally, colourism is the discrimination against individuals based on skin tone, often within a particular ethnic or racial group. This differs from racism in the sense that racism is discrimination based on race, while colourism may be prevalent within and among the members of a particular race. Colourism is ubiquitous and intractable - almost every ethnic group suffers from its pernicious effects and it has been this way for a very long time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about the majority of Latin telenovelas, K dramas and Bollywood movies. A whole chunk of the demographic is missing from the portrayals: the darker skinned Latinas, Koreans and Indians. Those born with a darker skin are looked down upon, considered ugly and therefore, not deserving of a place in the entertainment industry. On the contrary, the fairer complexioned individuals are hailed as beautiful and looked at favourably in almost all avenues of human life.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In India, this obsession with fair skin has been aptly given the appellation 'The Snow White Syndrome'. In fact, the problem is so pervasive that Bollywood movies have been practicing something known as 'brownface' for quite a while now without any compunction. They darken the skin of fair skinned actors to have them portray characters from a background of disadvantage instead of actually hiring dark skinned actors, thereby perpetuating the age-old problem of colourism in India. A 2019 film named &lt;em&gt;Bala&lt;/em&gt; was supposed to be a critical opprobrium of colourism prevalent in India. Ironically, the female protagonist, who faces discrimination on the basis of her dark complexion, was played by a fair skinned actress, Bhumi Pednekar, in a brownface. The poster for the movie showed her dawning a brownface, surrounded by skin lightening products. There are countless other examples of recent Bollywood movies doing the same: &lt;em&gt;Gully Boy&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Super 30&lt;/em&gt; and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another very patent expression of colourism prevalent in India that exists in Bollywood movies are the background dancers in the so-called 'item songs'. These dance routines are aimed to cater to the male gaze and feature beautiful women dancing to catchy Hindi tunes. The background dancers are often white and have blonde hair because that is what is considered 'beautiful'. The love interests in movies are also, generally, fair complexioned. In 2020, a film called &lt;em&gt;Khali Peeli&lt;/em&gt; came under attack for having a song titled &lt;em&gt;Beyonce Sharma Jayegi&lt;/em&gt; (which roughly translates to 'Beyonce will become embarrassed'). The song praises the female protagonist of the film for her fair skin, which apparently even puts the gorgeous Beyonce to shame (“&lt;em&gt;tujhe dekh ke goriya, Beyonce sharma jayegi&lt;/em&gt;”). Many famous Indian actors, including but not limited to Shah Rukh Khan, Priyanka Chopra and Yami Gautam, have also, only recently though, come under attack for starring in commercials for skin whitening products, in some cases, throughout their illustrious careers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skin whitening or bleaching is a practice that is widespread in almost all the continents. Various products, legal and illegal alike, are available to achieve the desirable fair skin: injections, creams, surgeries and so on and so forth. Many of these are potentially dangerous as they contain more than the legal and safe amount of mercury, which is very toxic. However, it continues to be rampant and the market is expected to reach an estimated $8.9 billion by 2024. Moreover, images of Kpop stars and Kdrama actors are often edited by agencies and fansites to make them look fair and desirable. This is after agencies meticulously chose their trainees based on various factors, including how they look. Many of the trainees who do not conform to the very strict beauty standards in Korea are expected to undergo surgeries to achieve the desirable look.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, plastic surgeries are so common in South Korea, especially among the youth today, that it is deemed as the plastic surgery capital, and has the highest ratio of plastic surgery clinics in the world. There are a few tanned Kpop stars like Hwasa (Mamamoo), Kai (EXO) and Jessi (soloist). However, they are exceptions to the norm and treated as such by the industry and the audience: some with awe, some with admiration and some with rejection (they sometimes face a lot of backlash from the fans of Kpop because of their dark skin). In most cases, these idols are portrayed as the “sexy” members of their respective groups by their agencies: pale skin is marketed as pure and so, darker skin is marketed as fierce.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another common practice that is born out of colourism is the casting of white passing characters in movies and TV series. &lt;em&gt;Fate: The Winx Saga&lt;/em&gt;, which is a TV series based on the famous early 2000's cartoon &lt;em&gt;Winx Club&lt;/em&gt;, casted a white passing actress named Elisha Applebaum for the role of Musa, an East Asian coded fairy. While there are claims that she is some part Asian, the problem is that since the character is supposed to be full East Asian and look that way, it would have been better to cast someone who looked the part. This is not an isolated instance. Some other examples are Taylor Lautner in the &lt;em&gt;Twilight&lt;/em&gt; series (he portrayed Jacob Black, a Native American character), Scarlett Johansson in &lt;em&gt;Ghost In The Shell&lt;/em&gt; (she was cast as Motoko Kusanagi, a Japanese cyber-human), Tilda Swinton in the &lt;em&gt;MCU&lt;/em&gt; (as the Ancient One, an Asian man) and Emma Stone in &lt;em&gt;Aloha&lt;/em&gt; (she played Allison Ng, a Chinese-Hawaiian-Swedish character). Clearly, in some of these cases, they simply casted a white person, irrespective of whether they resemble the character they are meant to portray at all or not. Actors of various ethnic backgrounds, who have distinctive features (which are considered 'ugly' by Western beauty standards) are often not considered for roles that portray a person from the same background. This exclusion of non-white and non-white passing actors results in a lack of jobs for hopefuls from such backgrounds and often deters them from choosing a career in entertainment altogether.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In movies with Black cast members, it is often seen that the love interest or the 'attractive' character is light skinned, often casting mixed race actors for the role (fetishisation of mixed race people is another insidious issue). Some examples are the casting of Rege Jean-Page as the Duke in &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; and Zendaya in almost everything. Of course these are great actors, and I am in no position to question their acting skills. The problem is with everyone typecasting Zendaya into every 'black girl' role just because she fits the description of being black while simultaneously conforming to Western beauty standards.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research conducted by the Geena Davis Institute on Gender in Media in collaboration with USC Viterbi School of Engineering concluded that about 80% of black female characters are played by light or medium skinned actors. We also often see that the protagonist is light skinned and the side characters are dark skinned (for instance, in &lt;em&gt;Dear White People&lt;/em&gt;). Moreover, darker skinned actors are often cast for roles portraying unlikeable people like the Duke’s father in &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; or for rude, loud, boorish and/or violent (which are personality trait stereotypes that are born out of racism against the Black community) characters like Will Mondrich from &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the above propagate a beauty standard that is highly detrimental to the self-image of thousands born to colourist cultures and societies. They face discrimination in all walks of life, have body image issues, face shaming and bullying, even by family members and are often pushed to extreme measures to modify their body to look beautiful and reap the benefits of the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Statistical data suggests that darker skinned people are more likely to be incarcerated or have longer sentences. In India, having dark skin is equated with being 'dirty' and people are encouraged to wear makeup that is several shades lighter to appear paler and thus, more desirable. Dark skinned people are tormented with taunts about how they will never get married because they are not desirable. In South Asia, marriages are sometimes arranged based on advertisements published in newspapers and 'fair' is a very common requirement in partners. A lot of the times when asked why a particular individual prefers a light skinned partner, the response comes, one way or another, in the form of a preference argument. But why is it that everyone 'prefers' lighter skin? It is directly or indirectly based on the idea that pale is beautiful and because of practices like Blanqueamiento (this will be discussed in detail in part II of this article).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem of colourism is all-pervasive and yet often neglected from the discourse. In fact, it is so prevalent and mundane that it is almost impossible to find foundations beyond a specific shade range, one that most agrees with the fair skinned. Rihanna’s Fenty Beauty was widely extolled for having a very large range of shades, extending the limits in both directions of the colour spectrum. Unfortunately, not all companies cater to the non-white audience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, in sets of crayons for children, the name 'skin/flesh colour' is given to a light peach shade, which thereby perpetuates light skin as the standard or 'normal' or acceptable skin colour.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Hindu mythology there are a myriad of dark complexioned characters like the deity Kali and the avatar Krishna. However, in TV adaptations of the same, fair skinned individuals are painted in black or blue to achieve the look of the character instead of hiring a dark complexioned individual for the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only recently have people been questioning the age-old practices and antiquated beliefs that lie at the core of colourism. More and more non-white and non-white passing individuals have been winning beauty pageants and appearing in movies and TV series. However, we are yet to see appreciable changes in statistics involving dark and light skinned individuals of a particular ethnic group and the rates of rejection from jobs because of this. It is important to keep up this streak of questioning colourist practices to reach the point where the society is ready to change and does eventually change.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Mirror, mirror on the wall, who is the fairest of them all?” (Snow White) - is as iconic as quotes generally get. Anyone who has watched, read or listened to the story of Snow White is aware of the Evil Queen’s aspirations: she wished to be the “fairest of them all”. 'Fair', as in not 'just' but 'pale' and ergo, beautiful. This declaration of the equivalence of a paler skin tone and beauty has been at the center of various cultures across the world, and has stood the test of time. Those with fairer skin tones are deemed more 'marriage worthy', less intimidating, more innocent, less violent and of course, more beautiful. This is colourism. To put it more formally, colourism is the discrimination against individuals based on skin tone, often within a particular ethnic or racial group. This differs from racism in the sense that racism is discrimination based on race, while colourism may be prevalent within and among the members of a particular race. Colourism is ubiquitous and intractable - almost every ethnic group suffers from its pernicious effects and it has been this way for a very long time.&amp;nbsp; Think about the majority of Latin telenovelas, K dramas and Bollywood movies. A whole chunk of the demographic is missing from the portrayals: the darker skinned Latinas, Koreans and Indians. Those born with a darker skin are looked down upon, considered ugly and therefore, not deserving of a place in the entertainment industry. On the contrary, the fairer complexioned individuals are hailed as beautiful and looked at favourably in almost all avenues of human life.&amp;nbsp; In India, this obsession with fair skin has been aptly given the appellation 'The Snow White Syndrome'. In fact, the problem is so pervasive that Bollywood movies have been practicing something known as 'brownface' for quite a while now without any compunction. They darken the skin of fair skinned actors to have them portray characters from a background of disadvantage instead of actually hiring dark skinned actors, thereby perpetuating the age-old problem of colourism in India. A 2019 film named Bala was supposed to be a critical opprobrium of colourism prevalent in India. Ironically, the female protagonist, who faces discrimination on the basis of her dark complexion, was played by a fair skinned actress, Bhumi Pednekar, in a brownface. The poster for the movie showed her dawning a brownface, surrounded by skin lightening products. There are countless other examples of recent Bollywood movies doing the same: Gully Boy, Super 30 and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp; Another very patent expression of colourism prevalent in India that exists in Bollywood movies are the background dancers in the so-called 'item songs'. These dance routines are aimed to cater to the male gaze and feature beautiful women dancing to catchy Hindi tunes. The background dancers are often white and have blonde hair because that is what is considered 'beautiful'. The love interests in movies are also, generally, fair complexioned. In 2020, a film called Khali Peeli came under attack for having a song titled Beyonce Sharma Jayegi (which roughly translates to 'Beyonce will become embarrassed'). The song praises the female protagonist of the film for her fair skin, which apparently even puts the gorgeous Beyonce to shame (“tujhe dekh ke goriya, Beyonce sharma jayegi”). Many famous Indian actors, including but not limited to Shah Rukh Khan, Priyanka Chopra and Yami Gautam, have also, only recently though, come under attack for starring in commercials for skin whitening products, in some cases, throughout their illustrious careers.&amp;nbsp; Skin whitening or bleaching is a practice that is widespread in almost all the continents. Various products, legal and illegal alike, are available to achieve the desirable fair skin: injections, creams, surgeries and so on and so forth. Many of these are potentially dangerous as they contain more than the legal and safe amount of mercury, which is very toxic. However, it continues to be rampant and the market is expected to reach an estimated $8.9 billion by 2024. Moreover, images of Kpop stars and Kdrama actors are often edited by agencies and fansites to make them look fair and desirable. This is after agencies meticulously chose their trainees based on various factors, including how they look. Many of the trainees who do not conform to the very strict beauty standards in Korea are expected to undergo surgeries to achieve the desirable look.&amp;nbsp; In fact, plastic surgeries are so common in South Korea, especially among the youth today, that it is deemed as the plastic surgery capital, and has the highest ratio of plastic surgery clinics in the world. There are a few tanned Kpop stars like Hwasa (Mamamoo), Kai (EXO) and Jessi (soloist). However, they are exceptions to the norm and treated as such by the industry and the audience: some with awe, some with admiration and some with rejection (they sometimes face a lot of backlash from the fans of Kpop because of their dark skin). In most cases, these idols are portrayed as the “sexy” members of their respective groups by their agencies: pale skin is marketed as pure and so, darker skin is marketed as fierce.&amp;nbsp; Another common practice that is born out of colourism is the casting of white passing characters in movies and TV series. Fate: The Winx Saga, which is a TV series based on the famous early 2000's cartoon Winx Club, casted a white passing actress named Elisha Applebaum for the role of Musa, an East Asian coded fairy. While there are claims that she is some part Asian, the problem is that since the character is supposed to be full East Asian and look that way, it would have been better to cast someone who looked the part. This is not an isolated instance. Some other examples are Taylor Lautner in the Twilight series (he portrayed Jacob Black, a Native American character), Scarlett Johansson in Ghost In The Shell (she was cast as Motoko Kusanagi, a Japanese cyber-human), Tilda Swinton in the MCU (as the Ancient One, an Asian man) and Emma Stone in Aloha (she played Allison Ng, a Chinese-Hawaiian-Swedish character). Clearly, in some of these cases, they simply casted a white person, irrespective of whether they resemble the character they are meant to portray at all or not. Actors of various ethnic backgrounds, who have distinctive features (which are considered 'ugly' by Western beauty standards) are often not considered for roles that portray a person from the same background. This exclusion of non-white and non-white passing actors results in a lack of jobs for hopefuls from such backgrounds and often deters them from choosing a career in entertainment altogether.&amp;nbsp; In movies with Black cast members, it is often seen that the love interest or the 'attractive' character is light skinned, often casting mixed race actors for the role (fetishisation of mixed race people is another insidious issue). Some examples are the casting of Rege Jean-Page as the Duke in Bridgerton and Zendaya in almost everything. Of course these are great actors, and I am in no position to question their acting skills. The problem is with everyone typecasting Zendaya into every 'black girl' role just because she fits the description of being black while simultaneously conforming to Western beauty standards.&amp;nbsp; Research conducted by the Geena Davis Institute on Gender in Media in collaboration with USC Viterbi School of Engineering concluded that about 80% of black female characters are played by light or medium skinned actors. We also often see that the protagonist is light skinned and the side characters are dark skinned (for instance, in Dear White People). Moreover, darker skinned actors are often cast for roles portraying unlikeable people like the Duke’s father in Bridgerton or for rude, loud, boorish and/or violent (which are personality trait stereotypes that are born out of racism against the Black community) characters like Will Mondrich from Bridgerton.&amp;nbsp; All of the above propagate a beauty standard that is highly detrimental to the self-image of thousands born to colourist cultures and societies. They face discrimination in all walks of life, have body image issues, face shaming and bullying, even by family members and are often pushed to extreme measures to modify their body to look beautiful and reap the benefits of the same.&amp;nbsp; Statistical data suggests that darker skinned people are more likely to be incarcerated or have longer sentences. In India, having dark skin is equated with being 'dirty' and people are encouraged to wear makeup that is several shades lighter to appear paler and thus, more desirable. Dark skinned people are tormented with taunts about how they will never get married because they are not desirable. In South Asia, marriages are sometimes arranged based on advertisements published in newspapers and 'fair' is a very common requirement in partners. A lot of the times when asked why a particular individual prefers a light skinned partner, the response comes, one way or another, in the form of a preference argument. But why is it that everyone 'prefers' lighter skin? It is directly or indirectly based on the idea that pale is beautiful and because of practices like Blanqueamiento (this will be discussed in detail in part II of this article).&amp;nbsp; The problem of colourism is all-pervasive and yet often neglected from the discourse. In fact, it is so prevalent and mundane that it is almost impossible to find foundations beyond a specific shade range, one that most agrees with the fair skinned. Rihanna’s Fenty Beauty was widely extolled for having a very large range of shades, extending the limits in both directions of the colour spectrum. Unfortunately, not all companies cater to the non-white audience.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, in sets of crayons for children, the name 'skin/flesh colour' is given to a light peach shade, which thereby perpetuates light skin as the standard or 'normal' or acceptable skin colour.&amp;nbsp; In Hindu mythology there are a myriad of dark complexioned characters like the deity Kali and the avatar Krishna. However, in TV adaptations of the same, fair skinned individuals are painted in black or blue to achieve the look of the character instead of hiring a dark complexioned individual for the job. Only recently have people been questioning the age-old practices and antiquated beliefs that lie at the core of colourism. More and more non-white and non-white passing individuals have been winning beauty pageants and appearing in movies and TV series. However, we are yet to see appreciable changes in statistics involving dark and light skinned individuals of a particular ethnic group and the rates of rejection from jobs because of this. It is important to keep up this streak of questioning colourist practices to reach the point where the society is ready to change and does eventually change.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Most Oppressive Fashion Trends Throughout History</title>
      <link href="/The-Most-Oppressive-Fashion-Trends-Throughout-History" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Most Oppressive Fashion Trends Throughout History" />
      <published>2021-09-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-21T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Most-Oppressive-Fashion-Trends-Throughout-History</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Most-Oppressive-Fashion-Trends-Throughout-History">&lt;p&gt;For much of history, women have lived as second-class citizens. American women were only given the right to vote in the twentieth century. As recently as in the 1970's, a woman should be denied a credit card unless it had her husband’s signature. The freedom we enjoy today is a fairly recent thing; our grandmothers lived in an era with fewer rights, and the generations that came before them had it even worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from having fewer legal rights, women in the past also had fewer fashion choices.&amp;nbsp; As recently as in the 1940's, women were arrested for wearing pants in public, as they were considered to be menswear. In some cases, historical fashion trends should even be deadly. Here are some of the most oppressive fashion trends that have existed throughout history, which give us a gruesome reminder of how women's bodies have been policed since time immemorial to achieve certain extremely artificial ideals of beauty.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Waist-cinching corsets made it difficult to breathe&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corsets are still worn today, but most of them aren’t nearly as restrictive as the ones our ancestors wore. The rise of the corset as a device to slash the waistline dates back to the 16th century. Historical corsets were notoriously uncomfortable, and constructed from confining materials such as whalebone.&amp;nbsp; When laced into a tight, rigid corset, women should not raise their arms above their heads, move too quickly without running out of breath, or slouch. The corsets made women have impeccable posture by essentially locking them in a cage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the 19th century, doctors were warning women against lacing their corsets too tightly. As the 20th century progressed, bras began to displace the corset as the undergarment of choice, but the corset hasn’t really died out and still sees widespread use in the 21st century.&amp;nbsp; Fortunately, it is no longer a fashion staple or considered societally mandated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chinese women had their feet broken to make them smaller&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most horrifying examples of oppressive fashion comes from China during the Tang Dynasty, which lasted from 618 to 906 AD.&amp;nbsp; In the 10th century, small feet were highly prized, and the practice of foot binding in order to achieve 'Golden Lotus' feet began. Girls as young as five would have their four smaller toes bent under their foot and then tightly bound. This would impede the growth of the foot, and permanently deform it. The feet would be kept bound (although the bindings would be regularly changed) for the rest of a woman’s life.&amp;nbsp; Losing toes to infection was not uncommon, and even women who kept all of their toes had great difficulty walking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the practice of foot binding was most common in the upper classes, the lower classes would sometimes adopt the process in order to improve the marriage prospects of their daughters. Foot binding continued well into the 20th century, in spite of several attempts over the centuries to ban it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ridiculously wide skirts led to deadly accidents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the many fashions that inhibited a woman’s ability to walk with ease, wide skirts were some of the most dangerous.&amp;nbsp; Full skirts have cycled in and out of style for centuries. They were in vogue during the Renaissance era. By the end of the 18th century, skirts were straight, but began expanding again in the first half of the 19th century. By the middle of the century, women were wearing massive hoop crinolines underneath their dresses. In Europe, this fad came to be known as Crinolinemania. Skirts could be as large as six feet in diameter, making it difficult to navigate crowded areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, however, wasn’t the greatest drawback of the crinoline. The voluminous skirts could also get stuck in carriage wheels, and also posed a fire hazard. Since the skirts were so large and difficult to maneuver, thousands of women managed to set their dresses aflame when walking by a fire or a lit candle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hobble skirts prevented women from taking large sters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ease of movement was clearly a pretty low priority for women’s fashion designers throughout history. This was particularly apparent in the 1900's, when a new trend hit the fashion scene. The decline of the crinoline resulted in narrower skirts, but this time the fashion went too far in the opposite direction. By the turn of the 20th century, women were wearing skirts so narrow that they were dubbed “hobble skirts.&quot; These hobble skirts were fitted so tightly around the lower legs that women were forced to take tiny steps, hobbling along in their stylish garments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women wearing these dresses not only had trouble walking and dancing, but many also found themselves in dangerous predicaments. The constricting garments led to accidents and even death, making the trend one of the most dangerous of the century. Many people in the era were confused by the popularity of the wildly impractical trend, and hobble skirts were widely mocked in the newspapers of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Absurdly large gigot sleeves made it difficult for women to move their arms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too often, clothing is designed to be aesthetically appealing without being functional. Beginning in the 1820's, women had limited use of their arms thanks to gigot sleeves, also known as leg o’ mutton sleeves.&amp;nbsp; While ruffed sleeves can still be found in clothes today, the sleeves of the 19th century were so outrageously large that women could barely move. The sleeve would balloon at the shoulders, then tarer down along the arm before ending tightly at the wrist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These sleeves would prevent women from raising their arms above their heads. The large sleeve trend would continue throughout the Vistorian era. Combined with other trends of the time including wider skirts, tighter corsets, and layers of undergarments, women in this era were so encased in fabric that the summer months must have been agonizing for them.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These trends resulted in a generation of women who were barely able to move, let alone breathe. A physical manifestation of oppression if we ever heard of one and a practical manifestation of the dangers of 'aesthetic&amp;nbsp; perfection'.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, we’re stepping into an age where the media is beginning to celebrate diversity of race and body type — though there’s still a long way to go. Before New York Fashion Week 2017, the Council of Fashion Designers of America sent out a memo to remind designers to seek out healthy models and a wider range of types saying, “New York Fashion Week is also a celebration of our city's diversity, which we hope to see on the runways.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing to remember is that most of the historical standards of beauty were based on a drawing or a painting of a man’s fantasy!&amp;nbsp; Nowadays Photoshop has the same effect, making already-petite models look unattainably perfect. One can’t possibly live up to a fictional piece of art or a masterfully altered photograph. Since standards have changed so much over history (just try to wear big 80's hair and makeup to look hot today), it proves that these standards are really just temporary ideals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your body isn’t considered 'perfect' today?&amp;nbsp; Who cares! 'Perfect' is an illusion that no one can attain. So, be happy with the body you have and celebrate all the things that make up your gorgeous, imperfect self.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tejasvi Joshi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For much of history, women have lived as second-class citizens. American women were only given the right to vote in the twentieth century. As recently as in the 1970's, a woman should be denied a credit card unless it had her husband’s signature. The freedom we enjoy today is a fairly recent thing; our grandmothers lived in an era with fewer rights, and the generations that came before them had it even worse. Aside from having fewer legal rights, women in the past also had fewer fashion choices.&amp;nbsp; As recently as in the 1940's, women were arrested for wearing pants in public, as they were considered to be menswear. In some cases, historical fashion trends should even be deadly. Here are some of the most oppressive fashion trends that have existed throughout history, which give us a gruesome reminder of how women's bodies have been policed since time immemorial to achieve certain extremely artificial ideals of beauty.&amp;nbsp; Waist-cinching corsets made it difficult to breathe Corsets are still worn today, but most of them aren’t nearly as restrictive as the ones our ancestors wore. The rise of the corset as a device to slash the waistline dates back to the 16th century. Historical corsets were notoriously uncomfortable, and constructed from confining materials such as whalebone.&amp;nbsp; When laced into a tight, rigid corset, women should not raise their arms above their heads, move too quickly without running out of breath, or slouch. The corsets made women have impeccable posture by essentially locking them in a cage. By the 19th century, doctors were warning women against lacing their corsets too tightly. As the 20th century progressed, bras began to displace the corset as the undergarment of choice, but the corset hasn’t really died out and still sees widespread use in the 21st century.&amp;nbsp; Fortunately, it is no longer a fashion staple or considered societally mandated. Chinese women had their feet broken to make them smaller One of the most horrifying examples of oppressive fashion comes from China during the Tang Dynasty, which lasted from 618 to 906 AD.&amp;nbsp; In the 10th century, small feet were highly prized, and the practice of foot binding in order to achieve 'Golden Lotus' feet began. Girls as young as five would have their four smaller toes bent under their foot and then tightly bound. This would impede the growth of the foot, and permanently deform it. The feet would be kept bound (although the bindings would be regularly changed) for the rest of a woman’s life.&amp;nbsp; Losing toes to infection was not uncommon, and even women who kept all of their toes had great difficulty walking. While the practice of foot binding was most common in the upper classes, the lower classes would sometimes adopt the process in order to improve the marriage prospects of their daughters. Foot binding continued well into the 20th century, in spite of several attempts over the centuries to ban it. Ridiculously wide skirts led to deadly accidents Of the many fashions that inhibited a woman’s ability to walk with ease, wide skirts were some of the most dangerous.&amp;nbsp; Full skirts have cycled in and out of style for centuries. They were in vogue during the Renaissance era. By the end of the 18th century, skirts were straight, but began expanding again in the first half of the 19th century. By the middle of the century, women were wearing massive hoop crinolines underneath their dresses. In Europe, this fad came to be known as Crinolinemania. Skirts could be as large as six feet in diameter, making it difficult to navigate crowded areas. This, however, wasn’t the greatest drawback of the crinoline. The voluminous skirts could also get stuck in carriage wheels, and also posed a fire hazard. Since the skirts were so large and difficult to maneuver, thousands of women managed to set their dresses aflame when walking by a fire or a lit candle. Hobble skirts prevented women from taking large sters Ease of movement was clearly a pretty low priority for women’s fashion designers throughout history. This was particularly apparent in the 1900's, when a new trend hit the fashion scene. The decline of the crinoline resulted in narrower skirts, but this time the fashion went too far in the opposite direction. By the turn of the 20th century, women were wearing skirts so narrow that they were dubbed “hobble skirts.&quot; These hobble skirts were fitted so tightly around the lower legs that women were forced to take tiny steps, hobbling along in their stylish garments. Women wearing these dresses not only had trouble walking and dancing, but many also found themselves in dangerous predicaments. The constricting garments led to accidents and even death, making the trend one of the most dangerous of the century. Many people in the era were confused by the popularity of the wildly impractical trend, and hobble skirts were widely mocked in the newspapers of the time. Absurdly large gigot sleeves made it difficult for women to move their arms Too often, clothing is designed to be aesthetically appealing without being functional. Beginning in the 1820's, women had limited use of their arms thanks to gigot sleeves, also known as leg o’ mutton sleeves.&amp;nbsp; While ruffed sleeves can still be found in clothes today, the sleeves of the 19th century were so outrageously large that women could barely move. The sleeve would balloon at the shoulders, then tarer down along the arm before ending tightly at the wrist. These sleeves would prevent women from raising their arms above their heads. The large sleeve trend would continue throughout the Vistorian era. Combined with other trends of the time including wider skirts, tighter corsets, and layers of undergarments, women in this era were so encased in fabric that the summer months must have been agonizing for them.&amp;nbsp; These trends resulted in a generation of women who were barely able to move, let alone breathe. A physical manifestation of oppression if we ever heard of one and a practical manifestation of the dangers of 'aesthetic&amp;nbsp; perfection'.&amp;nbsp; Luckily, we’re stepping into an age where the media is beginning to celebrate diversity of race and body type — though there’s still a long way to go. Before New York Fashion Week 2017, the Council of Fashion Designers of America sent out a memo to remind designers to seek out healthy models and a wider range of types saying, “New York Fashion Week is also a celebration of our city's diversity, which we hope to see on the runways.&quot; The thing to remember is that most of the historical standards of beauty were based on a drawing or a painting of a man’s fantasy!&amp;nbsp; Nowadays Photoshop has the same effect, making already-petite models look unattainably perfect. One can’t possibly live up to a fictional piece of art or a masterfully altered photograph. Since standards have changed so much over history (just try to wear big 80's hair and makeup to look hot today), it proves that these standards are really just temporary ideals. If your body isn’t considered 'perfect' today?&amp;nbsp; Who cares! 'Perfect' is an illusion that no one can attain. So, be happy with the body you have and celebrate all the things that make up your gorgeous, imperfect self.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Art for Thought</title>
      <link href="/Art-for-Thought" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Art for Thought" />
      <published>2021-09-03T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Art-for-Thought</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Art-for-Thought">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It would be a no-brainer today to say that the world is lacking in beauty and happiness. COVID-19 has wreaked havoc on our lives. So many people have lost their jobs. So many people have succumbed to the plague. So much despair colours the air. In all of this turmoil, it is not only easy to believe that there is no light at the end of the tunnel but also stupid to think that happiness can be more than a dream. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Nevertheless, we know that we cannot give in to the demons that beset the path of our whole species. We already know that we must give ourselves hope. For without hope there can be no survival. But the question is how? How can we overcome our human limitations? How do we convince a mind so affected by malaise to believe in a better tomorrow? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The answer lies in art. Art is the yearning of the human soul for something greater than itself. Art screams out to every human being out there that no matter how small they may be, they’re capable of wonderful things. Art is salvation for our restless minds in these times, when our bodies stay caged within four walls.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;We need art not just in some magnificent Da Vinci painting, but in every-day items: small but necessary things which remind us that life is worth living and that all is not lost. It is here that Vantheshoe comes to our aid. This small start-up, run by a charming young lady, by definition, refuses to give up on the soul of humanity. With charming floral prints and vivacious colours on all kinds of items like handbags, phone covers, and so on, Vantheshoe reminds you that this pandemic cannot take away the beauty that is within you. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;No, this is not just some pithy advertorial trying to sell you a product by exploiting your deeper unhappiness. Rather, it is a heartfelt article telling you about the work of someone who is genuinely interested in giving you something that you can truly cherish. We are here not to sell Vantheshoes’s products, but to tell you why at all they are worth buying. In other words, we’re here in true solidarity with the depth of human feeling. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Thus, we implore you to explore &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vantheshoe.com/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Vantheshoe’s products&lt;/a&gt;, to appreciate the designs and the hours of work that have gone into making them. We will not ask you to buy the products, that would be presumptuous, but we will ask you to see for yourselves that in every mobile cover, in every handbag, every coaster, there is the soul of an artist trapped inside waiting to be adored by the right person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/vantheshoe1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/vantheshoe2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>.</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      
        <category term="sponsored" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It would be a no-brainer today to say that the world is lacking in beauty and happiness. COVID-19 has wreaked havoc on our lives. So many people have lost their jobs. So many people have succumbed to the plague. So much despair colours the air. In all of this turmoil, it is not only easy to believe that there is no light at the end of the tunnel but also stupid to think that happiness can be more than a dream. Nevertheless, we know that we cannot give in to the demons that beset the path of our whole species. We already know that we must give ourselves hope. For without hope there can be no survival. But the question is how? How can we overcome our human limitations? How do we convince a mind so affected by malaise to believe in a better tomorrow? The answer lies in art. Art is the yearning of the human soul for something greater than itself. Art screams out to every human being out there that no matter how small they may be, they’re capable of wonderful things. Art is salvation for our restless minds in these times, when our bodies stay caged within four walls.&amp;nbsp; We need art not just in some magnificent Da Vinci painting, but in every-day items: small but necessary things which remind us that life is worth living and that all is not lost. It is here that Vantheshoe comes to our aid. This small start-up, run by a charming young lady, by definition, refuses to give up on the soul of humanity. With charming floral prints and vivacious colours on all kinds of items like handbags, phone covers, and so on, Vantheshoe reminds you that this pandemic cannot take away the beauty that is within you. No, this is not just some pithy advertorial trying to sell you a product by exploiting your deeper unhappiness. Rather, it is a heartfelt article telling you about the work of someone who is genuinely interested in giving you something that you can truly cherish. We are here not to sell Vantheshoes’s products, but to tell you why at all they are worth buying. In other words, we’re here in true solidarity with the depth of human feeling. Thus, we implore you to explore Vantheshoe’s products, to appreciate the designs and the hours of work that have gone into making them. We will not ask you to buy the products, that would be presumptuous, but we will ask you to see for yourselves that in every mobile cover, in every handbag, every coaster, there is the soul of an artist trapped inside waiting to be adored by the right person.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Women in Corporations: Breaking the Glass Ceiling or Standing at the Glass Cliff?</title>
      <link href="/Women-in-Corporations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Women in Corporations: Breaking the Glass Ceiling or Standing at the Glass Cliff?" />
      <published>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Women-in-Corporations</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Women-in-Corporations">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While listening to Ava Max’s song &lt;em&gt;Kings and Queens&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;whenever the line ‘&lt;em&gt;If all of the kings had queens on their throne, we would pop champagne and raise a toast’ &lt;/em&gt;comes,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;a gush of enthusiasm runs through my veins and the thought of women leading everywhere leaves me in awe of the world that they would create. However, as I sit down to write this article today, contemplating upon the lyrics, I am left baffled by the thought of whether the problem of gender discrimination is really solved by passing of thrones or is there more to it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Historically, men have been perceived to be natural leaders while women and other minority groups have fought for their way upwards in any organisation. Around only 8.1% of the latest fortune 500 companies are being run by women CEOs. Though it is a milestone in itself that should be celebrated, yet the numbers are not so encouraging.&amp;nbsp; This underrepresentation of women in the higher positions of an organisation is called the ‘glass ceiling effect’. But there’s more to the story. Even if a small portion of determined and strong women break the glass ceiling and demonstrate their innate talent of being a leader, they are faced with yet another patriarchal barrier – the glass cliff effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Recently, Blizzard Company appointed Jen Oneal as its first female lead. Though it would have been an encouraging move under normal circumstances, currently it is a testimony to the prevalence of the glass cliff effect. Why? The promotion of Jen was preceded by a big lawsuit of sexual harassment that the company is tackling. More like a sister to the glass ceiling effect, the glass cliff effect refers to the phenomenon whereby women are promoted to higher positions during a precarious situation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This term was coined by two researchers at the University of Exeter, Michelle Ryan and Alexander Haslam in 2005. Haslam and Ryan looked at the 100 companies that were a part of the FTSE 100 Index listed on the London Stock Exchange to analyse what happened at those firms before and after men and women board members were brought on board. The findings suggested that during periods of stock market decline, firms that brought women on their board were more likely to have experienced constantly bad performance in the preceding five months than those who brought men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The glass cliff effect assumes greater importance as it fuels the traditionally-existing stereotypes about women leaders. When women leaders are unable to perform under precarious situations they are dismissed as being not competent enough to hold positions of power. The effect is closely knit with the saviour effect. When women are not able to deliver results under a glass cliff appointment they are immediately replaced by men.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, I believe there’s more to the glass cliff effect than just research backed by statistics. I believe the roots of the glass cliff effect go to the way girls are conditioned from the beginning. Apart from painting the picture of a damsel in distress waiting to be saved by a prince in shining armour, a lot of women are conditioned to believe that they are responsible for cleaning the 'mess' that has so far been created by dominant patriarchal characters in their life. The submissive and complacent attitude that is imbibed in girls during their childhood adds up to become a phenomenon like the glass cliff effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Why do women choose to accept an offer of being promoted to a higher stature if they know that the company is currently in a dangerous situation? Well, women as a group have to face a lot of struggles to climb up the corporate ladder. The offer of a C-suite position is just too lucrative for a lot of women to pass on. So, instead, they take up a chance and try to fight the situation; and if we look at the flip side, there have been a lot many instances where women have vigorously fought against the glass cliff effect, pulled companies out of crisis and proved their acumen. Mary Barra, CEO and Chairman of General Motors is one such example. When she was promoted after a controversial bail-out, the odds of her succeeding&amp;nbsp;were low. However, she defied all the odds and succeeded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Though the saddening part still remains. Imagine that you’ve been trying hard to break through the glass and finally succeed. You let out a sigh of relief. However, as soon as you look around, you find yourself standing at the edge of a cliff. You are disheartened. This is what a glass cliff effect looks like. The glass cliff effect is a lesser-known fact however it impacts the lives of almost millions of women working in the corporate sector. Will women ever break out of these shackles or are there more glass barriers waiting for them?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shiksha Mody</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">While listening to Ava Max’s song Kings and Queens, whenever the line ‘If all of the kings had queens on their throne, we would pop champagne and raise a toast’ comes, a gush of enthusiasm runs through my veins and the thought of women leading everywhere leaves me in awe of the world that they would create. However, as I sit down to write this article today, contemplating upon the lyrics, I am left baffled by the thought of whether the problem of gender discrimination is really solved by passing of thrones or is there more to it? Historically, men have been perceived to be natural leaders while women and other minority groups have fought for their way upwards in any organisation. Around only 8.1% of the latest fortune 500 companies are being run by women CEOs. Though it is a milestone in itself that should be celebrated, yet the numbers are not so encouraging.&amp;nbsp; This underrepresentation of women in the higher positions of an organisation is called the ‘glass ceiling effect’. But there’s more to the story. Even if a small portion of determined and strong women break the glass ceiling and demonstrate their innate talent of being a leader, they are faced with yet another patriarchal barrier – the glass cliff effect. Recently, Blizzard Company appointed Jen Oneal as its first female lead. Though it would have been an encouraging move under normal circumstances, currently it is a testimony to the prevalence of the glass cliff effect. Why? The promotion of Jen was preceded by a big lawsuit of sexual harassment that the company is tackling. More like a sister to the glass ceiling effect, the glass cliff effect refers to the phenomenon whereby women are promoted to higher positions during a precarious situation.&amp;nbsp; This term was coined by two researchers at the University of Exeter, Michelle Ryan and Alexander Haslam in 2005. Haslam and Ryan looked at the 100 companies that were a part of the FTSE 100 Index listed on the London Stock Exchange to analyse what happened at those firms before and after men and women board members were brought on board. The findings suggested that during periods of stock market decline, firms that brought women on their board were more likely to have experienced constantly bad performance in the preceding five months than those who brought men. The glass cliff effect assumes greater importance as it fuels the traditionally-existing stereotypes about women leaders. When women leaders are unable to perform under precarious situations they are dismissed as being not competent enough to hold positions of power. The effect is closely knit with the saviour effect. When women are not able to deliver results under a glass cliff appointment they are immediately replaced by men.&amp;nbsp; However, I believe there’s more to the glass cliff effect than just research backed by statistics. I believe the roots of the glass cliff effect go to the way girls are conditioned from the beginning. Apart from painting the picture of a damsel in distress waiting to be saved by a prince in shining armour, a lot of women are conditioned to believe that they are responsible for cleaning the 'mess' that has so far been created by dominant patriarchal characters in their life. The submissive and complacent attitude that is imbibed in girls during their childhood adds up to become a phenomenon like the glass cliff effect. Why do women choose to accept an offer of being promoted to a higher stature if they know that the company is currently in a dangerous situation? Well, women as a group have to face a lot of struggles to climb up the corporate ladder. The offer of a C-suite position is just too lucrative for a lot of women to pass on. So, instead, they take up a chance and try to fight the situation; and if we look at the flip side, there have been a lot many instances where women have vigorously fought against the glass cliff effect, pulled companies out of crisis and proved their acumen. Mary Barra, CEO and Chairman of General Motors is one such example. When she was promoted after a controversial bail-out, the odds of her succeeding&amp;nbsp;were low. However, she defied all the odds and succeeded. Though the saddening part still remains. Imagine that you’ve been trying hard to break through the glass and finally succeed. You let out a sigh of relief. However, as soon as you look around, you find yourself standing at the edge of a cliff. You are disheartened. This is what a glass cliff effect looks like. The glass cliff effect is a lesser-known fact however it impacts the lives of almost millions of women working in the corporate sector. Will women ever break out of these shackles or are there more glass barriers waiting for them?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Fixating on The Male Gaze</title>
      <link href="/Fixating-on-The-Male-Gaze" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fixating on The Male Gaze" />
      <published>2021-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Fixating-on-The-Male-Gaze</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Fixating-on-The-Male-Gaze">&lt;p&gt;If you’ve seen&lt;em&gt; Emily in Paris&lt;/em&gt;, you must have come across the perfume advertisement shooting scene. For those who haven’t, here’s what the scene looked like: a naked model strolls down a bridge while a bunch of men stare at her. Yes, nothing more, nothing less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, our sensible Emily was disturbed to see that. She points out how this would lead to the objectification of the model through the 'Male Gaze', which is followed by the male client explaining to her how the model is wearing nothing but the perfume, which is meant to empower her, by giving her that sex appeal. Emily then went on to pose a very pertinent question, “&lt;em&gt;Is it ‘sexy or sexist?&lt;/em&gt;’” While the question initiates a separate debate altogether, let us first focus on understanding what ‘The Male Gaze’ is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The media that we consume are presented to us through the Male Gaze, where the female character is projected as an ‘object’ of heterosexual male desire. Positioning the cameras in such a manner that they exclusively follow a woman’s figure in zoom is the perfect example to illustrate my point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The visual presentation of the Male Gaze has three perspectives: (i) that of the man behind the camera, (ii) that of the male characters within the film; and lastly (iii) that of the spectator gazing at the image. Here’s an interesting&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/feministinfo/photos/a.977236942375184/3816179241814259/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/feministinfo/photos/a.977236942375184/3816179241814259/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Facebook post&lt;/a&gt; I stumbled upon a few days ago, which prompted me to take up this article. It perfectly spells out how to identify the ‘Male Gaze’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us visit different forms of media which employ the Male Gaze rather conveniently (and make millions out of it):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiatoday.in/movies/bollywood/story/depicting-women-in-bollywood-222702-2014-10-11&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;India Today&lt;/em&gt; article&lt;/a&gt; decodes how Bollywood has forever tacitly engaged in building female lead archetypes and depicting them as subtle caricatures of the Male Gaze. Depiction of female artists as 'Abla Naari' or &lt;em&gt;'the weaker sex'&lt;/em&gt; (Sana Ranaut from &lt;em&gt;Rajjo&lt;/em&gt;), 'Sanskari Ladki' or &lt;em&gt;'the traditional woman' &lt;/em&gt;(Amrita Rao from &lt;em&gt;Vivah&lt;/em&gt;), the selfless-devoted mother (Nirupa Roy from &lt;em&gt;Deewar&lt;/em&gt;) and the bad girl (Deepika Padukone from &lt;em&gt;Cocktail&lt;/em&gt;) are some examples, to name a few.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, any typical American comedy is incomplete without a slow, zoomed-in, down-up shot of a bimbo, in the backdrop of cheesy music. Not to mention the portrayal of women as supporting sexual objects in films like &lt;em&gt;Transformers&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Spectre&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Grown Ups&lt;/em&gt;, and some of Marvel’s/DC’s films.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that’s not enough, here’s an article that sums up what I’ve tried to convey so far: &lt;a href=&quot;https://talkiewood.com/2014/07/megan-vs-rosie-vs-nicola-who-was-the-best-transformers-girl-2/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Megan vs Rosie vs Nicola: Who was the best Transformers girl?&lt;/a&gt; (Do notice the title and the clipping of the article, especially the angle from which the shots have been taken: there’s more focus on the female’s body than her face).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;Three paragraphs into the Talkiewood article, and here’s what we get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;To determine the ‘winner’ (if we want to call it that), we have decided to rank the three actresses based on five criteria: Memorability, hotness in Transformers, hotness outside Transformers, desirability, and their character function.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why so shallow? Let’s be real; these are Michael Bay films. These actresses didn’t exactly play deep characters&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per research in 2012, women are ingredients for higher profitability, hence some critics argue that as sex sells, sexualising female bodies through the male gaze isn’t as concerned with objectification as it is with aesthetics. Thus the use of the erotic is a significantly above-average technique used by creators in communicating with the market. As a consequence, the marketing strategy worked well for &lt;em&gt;Transformers&lt;/em&gt; as it is the thirteenth highest-grossing film series, with a total of $4.8 billion in sales.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not just limited to movies but references of the Male Gaze can also be observed in music, ranging from men preferring a colour (&lt;em&gt;Chittiyaan Kalaiyaan-'White Wrists &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Brown Rang' or 'Brown Woman'&lt;/em&gt;) to men being okay with any colour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&quot;&lt;em&gt;Ek garam chai ki pyaali ho – May there be a hot cup of tea&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Koi usko pilaane waali ho… – May there be someone who serves me that&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chaahe gori ho ya kaali ho – She may be fair or dark toned&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Seene se lagaane waali ho – She should just embrace me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Raat ko jab main waapas aaoon – when I come at night&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Woh darwaaza khole – She'll open the door&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sajke mere saamne aaye – She'll adorn herself and come in front of me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Saare din ki thakaan mitaaye…– She'll erase all my tiredness of the day&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Voh meri gharwaali ho. – She'll be my wife&quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A point worth considering is that the female character doesn't necessarily have to be hyper-sexualised to be the object of the Male Gaze. As long as she, as the passive party, is able to incite the male protagonist to take action towards his ultimate goal, or act as a prop in the service of the male, we’re catching on to a million bucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not like this is absent from music industry either, listen to &lt;em&gt;Trap Queen, Blurred Lines, Wiggle&lt;/em&gt;, or almost every second rap song. As per a&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ijstr.org/final-print/feb2020/and-I-Swear-Profanity-In-Pop-Music-Lyrics-On-The-American-Billboard-Charts-2009-2018-And-The-Effect-On-Youtube-Popularity.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ijstr.org/final-print/feb2020/and-I-Swear-Profanity-In-Pop-Music-Lyrics-On-The-American-Billboard-Charts-2009-2018-And-The-Effect-On-Youtube-Popularity.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;recent study&lt;/a&gt;, Hip-Hop/Rap is the most popular genre in the US and by far the most explicit genre, containing on average, around 77% profane material, thus making it the most active tool to perpetuate the Male Gaze imagery.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commercialisation of the Male Gaze has increased incessantly over the past few years. Most of the so-called Bollywood item songs are not part of the narratives, however, they are placed for the sole purpose of titillation since the business of cinema is all about visuals. The huge online viewership illustrates how this objectification is used as bait for heterosexual males. Some illustrations of this can be grossing viewerships of songs like &lt;em&gt;Chikni Chameli&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp; (lubricious Chameli), any Honey Singh song or even Drake’s &lt;em&gt;Hotline Bling&lt;/em&gt; or Jason Derulo’s &lt;em&gt;Swalla.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence it is important to question whether such a gaze acts as an ‘audience bait ’- a means to improve visual aesthetics, or as a systemic tool to breed patriarchy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming on to the industry that majorly thrives on the sexualisation of the human body (most commonly females) - PORN. The fact that there is such a massive difference between the type of porn made for male vs female audiences, speaks volumes on how dehumanising and degrading the Male Gaze is. But the truth of the matter remains, the viler and more abusive the content is, the more profits it grosses. Current revenue estimates of the porn industry in The United States range from $9 billion - $97 billion a year, thus making it bigger than not only Netflix but also Hollywood as a whole. In other words, online porn is huge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, their audience is getting younger, which inherently means their market is getting bigger (and more problematic). And the million-dollar profits of porn aren’t just limited to this industry but also to many companies (like&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/porn/business/mainstream.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/porn/business/mainstream.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Yahoo!, AT&amp;amp;T, DirecTV, Marriott and General Motors&lt;/a&gt;) that seemingly have no relation with the porn industry. Emerging technologies such as VR are also getting a boost from this industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The male gaze does not spare the younger generation either, cutting across different configurations. The following section talks about this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comic books often serve as graphic repositories for a heterosexual male’s erotic fantasies. Take, for example, victims waiting to be rescued like Diana (&lt;em&gt;The Phantom&lt;/em&gt;), Lois Lane (&lt;em&gt;Superman&lt;/em&gt;), or DC’s empowered female protagonists like Catwoman and She-Hulk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The power and control that characters such as Wonder Woman seemingly have are, in fact, fake, because it is taken away by male writers at will when they depict their images in extremely provocative poses; bending over, arching their heads back, tossing their hair, fighting in the rain, etc, for absolutely no reason at all. In 2018, the total revenue for the comic book publishing industry was estimated at $865 million and moreover, half of the top 10 grossing films released in the same year were based on comic books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In video games, female characters are portrayed in two broad ways: Either the 'Damsel in Distress' or the 'Ultimate Warrior' (both being the perfect victims pandering to the Male Gaze), of which, the latter is unnecessarily hyper-sexualised (having a scantily clothed body with unrealistic proportions). According to an analysis by &lt;em&gt;Downs and Smith&lt;/em&gt;, playable and plot-relevant characters in the 60 best-selling video games of 2003 were predominantly male. Females who were depicted were frequently sexualised, reaffirming the buttery business of the Male Gaze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lara Croft’s (&lt;em&gt;Tomb Raider&lt;/em&gt; series) original character designer, Toby Gard, also known as ‘The Father of Lara’, acknowledged that he initially set the protagonist as a woman so that the 3D physical models could attract more male players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disney princesses’ movies were supposed to be one pure, uncharted territory but well, look where we are. In case you haven't noticed, the female protagonists in Disney movies are almost always white, cis women in corsets with tiny waists and big bosoms, most of whose stories end when they find love (and hence all their answers) in a man. If you look at it, almost none of these princesses ended up alone, happily. But this drama of the Male Gaze is where the money lies. As of today, Disney’s net worth lies close to $122.18 billion, which they only plan to augment by retelling the same story over and over again.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fitting example would be the recent adaptation of Disney’s 1992 animated film &lt;em&gt;Aladdin&lt;/em&gt;, which grossed over $1 billion worldwide, becoming the ninth-highest-grossing film of 2019. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.studiobinder.com/blog/what-is-the-male-gaze-definition/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;studiobinder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;article explains how Jasmine is nothing but a precious artefact locked away for safekeeping - for her father, a valuable commodity - for the villain, and a prize to be won - for &lt;em&gt;Aladdin&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was recently watching a video on ‘The Male Gaze’ on YouTube, and here’s the first comment I came across:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Women grew up watching successful, ‘beautiful’ women always portrayed through the male gaze and now that we ourselves are playing the role of the camera (selfies/Instagram), we present ourselves through the male gaze!”&lt;/em&gt;, which got me thinking about how we're all victims of the Male Gaze in some way or the other. The Male Gaze has stealthily crept into our minds like a parasite and is benefitting by feeding off our insecurities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hitherto, it wouldn’t take big brains to figure out how deeply problematic the Male Gaze is. Firstly, it normalises perceiving women as deserving of one-way surveillance by heterosexual men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, it negatively alters the way women look at themselves. They start to objectify themselves and inherently feel that their primary purpose is to please heterosexual men, whether it’s by being a doting mother succumbing to gender roles, a girl next door fulfilling your sexual desires, or a submissive subject desperately waiting to feed a man’s ego by being ‘saved’ by him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Male Gaze quietly typecasts women as the ‘aesthetic’ half of humankind and gradually detracts from them other ambitions that men and women have alike. Scarily enough, it even normalises predatory gazes at women and perpetuates rape culture. And it haunts me to think that we all, so ordinarily consume the ‘Male Gaze’ served to us on the platter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin Waters, CEO of Victoria's Secret said after the big announcement of the replacement of its spokespeople, &quot;&lt;em&gt;We're moving from what men want to what women want, from sexy for a few to sexy for all&lt;/em&gt;&quot;. In June 2021, Victoria's Secret ditched its Angels post a successful decade-long partnership after it realised that they were no longer ‘culturally relevant’, a euphemism for ‘morally acceptable’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the first&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriassecret.com/us/thevscollective&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriassecret.com/us/thevscollective&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;seven women selected&lt;/a&gt; to join the ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriassecret.com/us/thevscollective&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;VS Collective&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;’&lt;/em&gt; are professional soccer star Megan Rapinoe, actress Priyanka Chopra Jonas and LGBTQ model and activist Valentina Sampaio. Because hey, that’s what women are, a little bit of everything!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if Victoria’s Secret can identify the problem with the Male Gaze, I assume it’s not a secret anymore, is it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, let's come back to the question Emily raised at the beginning of the article. Who draws the line between sexy and sexist, or say, the line between Cardi B’s sexualisation in her music video and a French model’s sexualisation in an advertisement? Who’s to say one is empowering and the other is not? If women want to make money off the Male Gaze, who are we to stop them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the line is indisputably hard to draw. But here’s the thing, when a video agency sexualises a model while directing a perfume advertisement, the model is regulated, since she is a mere medium to convey what the agency wants to. However, when Cardi B sexualises herself, she does that as an independent artist, to express her own personal message, which is indeed empowering. Moreover, in either case, we end up normalising the unrealistic standards for and expectations from the women community at large, which is yet another ethical debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, as long as sexualisation is the subject’s choice, we, coming from a place of privilege, don’t get to draw the line. But that doesn’t mean it’s okay for men to unwarrantedly keep reducing women to objects of sexual gratification on the pretext of making money. Clearly, we need more women creators to present women through a more realistic, humane perspective, but we're far from that, as of now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also known that money will find its way to the Male Gaze, giving it all the more incentive to creep into every line of business. However, in the meantime, as rational consumers of media, we can actively identify the wrong type of content and consciously choose to not feed its business. After all, they make money off &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The choice is yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until then.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Eeshita Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">If you’ve seen Emily in Paris, you must have come across the perfume advertisement shooting scene. For those who haven’t, here’s what the scene looked like: a naked model strolls down a bridge while a bunch of men stare at her. Yes, nothing more, nothing less. Naturally, our sensible Emily was disturbed to see that. She points out how this would lead to the objectification of the model through the 'Male Gaze', which is followed by the male client explaining to her how the model is wearing nothing but the perfume, which is meant to empower her, by giving her that sex appeal. Emily then went on to pose a very pertinent question, “Is it ‘sexy or sexist?’” While the question initiates a separate debate altogether, let us first focus on understanding what ‘The Male Gaze’ is. The media that we consume are presented to us through the Male Gaze, where the female character is projected as an ‘object’ of heterosexual male desire. Positioning the cameras in such a manner that they exclusively follow a woman’s figure in zoom is the perfect example to illustrate my point. The visual presentation of the Male Gaze has three perspectives: (i) that of the man behind the camera, (ii) that of the male characters within the film; and lastly (iii) that of the spectator gazing at the image. Here’s an interesting Facebook post I stumbled upon a few days ago, which prompted me to take up this article. It perfectly spells out how to identify the ‘Male Gaze’. Let us visit different forms of media which employ the Male Gaze rather conveniently (and make millions out of it): An India Today article decodes how Bollywood has forever tacitly engaged in building female lead archetypes and depicting them as subtle caricatures of the Male Gaze. Depiction of female artists as 'Abla Naari' or 'the weaker sex' (Sana Ranaut from Rajjo), 'Sanskari Ladki' or 'the traditional woman' (Amrita Rao from Vivah), the selfless-devoted mother (Nirupa Roy from Deewar) and the bad girl (Deepika Padukone from Cocktail) are some examples, to name a few.&amp;nbsp; Similarly, any typical American comedy is incomplete without a slow, zoomed-in, down-up shot of a bimbo, in the backdrop of cheesy music. Not to mention the portrayal of women as supporting sexual objects in films like Transformers, Wolf of Wall Street, Spectre, Grown Ups, and some of Marvel’s/DC’s films. If that’s not enough, here’s an article that sums up what I’ve tried to convey so far: Megan vs Rosie vs Nicola: Who was the best Transformers girl? (Do notice the title and the clipping of the article, especially the angle from which the shots have been taken: there’s more focus on the female’s body than her face). &amp;nbsp;Three paragraphs into the Talkiewood article, and here’s what we get: “To determine the ‘winner’ (if we want to call it that), we have decided to rank the three actresses based on five criteria: Memorability, hotness in Transformers, hotness outside Transformers, desirability, and their character function. Why so shallow? Let’s be real; these are Michael Bay films. These actresses didn’t exactly play deep characters.” As per research in 2012, women are ingredients for higher profitability, hence some critics argue that as sex sells, sexualising female bodies through the male gaze isn’t as concerned with objectification as it is with aesthetics. Thus the use of the erotic is a significantly above-average technique used by creators in communicating with the market. As a consequence, the marketing strategy worked well for Transformers as it is the thirteenth highest-grossing film series, with a total of $4.8 billion in sales.&amp;nbsp; This is not just limited to movies but references of the Male Gaze can also be observed in music, ranging from men preferring a colour (Chittiyaan Kalaiyaan-'White Wrists and Brown Rang' or 'Brown Woman') to men being okay with any colour. &amp;nbsp;&quot;Ek garam chai ki pyaali ho – May there be a hot cup of tea Koi usko pilaane waali ho… – May there be someone who serves me that Chaahe gori ho ya kaali ho – She may be fair or dark toned Seene se lagaane waali ho – She should just embrace me Raat ko jab main waapas aaoon – when I come at night Woh darwaaza khole – She'll open the door&amp;nbsp; Sajke mere saamne aaye – She'll adorn herself and come in front of me Saare din ki thakaan mitaaye…– She'll erase all my tiredness of the day Voh meri gharwaali ho. – She'll be my wife&quot; A point worth considering is that the female character doesn't necessarily have to be hyper-sexualised to be the object of the Male Gaze. As long as she, as the passive party, is able to incite the male protagonist to take action towards his ultimate goal, or act as a prop in the service of the male, we’re catching on to a million bucks. It's not like this is absent from music industry either, listen to Trap Queen, Blurred Lines, Wiggle, or almost every second rap song. As per a recent study, Hip-Hop/Rap is the most popular genre in the US and by far the most explicit genre, containing on average, around 77% profane material, thus making it the most active tool to perpetuate the Male Gaze imagery.&amp;nbsp; The commercialisation of the Male Gaze has increased incessantly over the past few years. Most of the so-called Bollywood item songs are not part of the narratives, however, they are placed for the sole purpose of titillation since the business of cinema is all about visuals. The huge online viewership illustrates how this objectification is used as bait for heterosexual males. Some illustrations of this can be grossing viewerships of songs like Chikni Chameli&amp;nbsp; (lubricious Chameli), any Honey Singh song or even Drake’s Hotline Bling or Jason Derulo’s Swalla. Hence it is important to question whether such a gaze acts as an ‘audience bait ’- a means to improve visual aesthetics, or as a systemic tool to breed patriarchy? Coming on to the industry that majorly thrives on the sexualisation of the human body (most commonly females) - PORN. The fact that there is such a massive difference between the type of porn made for male vs female audiences, speaks volumes on how dehumanising and degrading the Male Gaze is. But the truth of the matter remains, the viler and more abusive the content is, the more profits it grosses. Current revenue estimates of the porn industry in The United States range from $9 billion - $97 billion a year, thus making it bigger than not only Netflix but also Hollywood as a whole. In other words, online porn is huge. Furthermore, their audience is getting younger, which inherently means their market is getting bigger (and more problematic). And the million-dollar profits of porn aren’t just limited to this industry but also to many companies (like Yahoo!, AT&amp;amp;T, DirecTV, Marriott and General Motors) that seemingly have no relation with the porn industry. Emerging technologies such as VR are also getting a boost from this industry. The male gaze does not spare the younger generation either, cutting across different configurations. The following section talks about this point. Comic books often serve as graphic repositories for a heterosexual male’s erotic fantasies. Take, for example, victims waiting to be rescued like Diana (The Phantom), Lois Lane (Superman), or DC’s empowered female protagonists like Catwoman and She-Hulk. The power and control that characters such as Wonder Woman seemingly have are, in fact, fake, because it is taken away by male writers at will when they depict their images in extremely provocative poses; bending over, arching their heads back, tossing their hair, fighting in the rain, etc, for absolutely no reason at all. In 2018, the total revenue for the comic book publishing industry was estimated at $865 million and moreover, half of the top 10 grossing films released in the same year were based on comic books. In video games, female characters are portrayed in two broad ways: Either the 'Damsel in Distress' or the 'Ultimate Warrior' (both being the perfect victims pandering to the Male Gaze), of which, the latter is unnecessarily hyper-sexualised (having a scantily clothed body with unrealistic proportions). According to an analysis by Downs and Smith, playable and plot-relevant characters in the 60 best-selling video games of 2003 were predominantly male. Females who were depicted were frequently sexualised, reaffirming the buttery business of the Male Gaze. Lara Croft’s (Tomb Raider series) original character designer, Toby Gard, also known as ‘The Father of Lara’, acknowledged that he initially set the protagonist as a woman so that the 3D physical models could attract more male players. Disney princesses’ movies were supposed to be one pure, uncharted territory but well, look where we are. In case you haven't noticed, the female protagonists in Disney movies are almost always white, cis women in corsets with tiny waists and big bosoms, most of whose stories end when they find love (and hence all their answers) in a man. If you look at it, almost none of these princesses ended up alone, happily. But this drama of the Male Gaze is where the money lies. As of today, Disney’s net worth lies close to $122.18 billion, which they only plan to augment by retelling the same story over and over again.&amp;nbsp; A fitting example would be the recent adaptation of Disney’s 1992 animated film Aladdin, which grossed over $1 billion worldwide, becoming the ninth-highest-grossing film of 2019. A studiobinder article explains how Jasmine is nothing but a precious artefact locked away for safekeeping - for her father, a valuable commodity - for the villain, and a prize to be won - for Aladdin.&amp;nbsp; I was recently watching a video on ‘The Male Gaze’ on YouTube, and here’s the first comment I came across: “Women grew up watching successful, ‘beautiful’ women always portrayed through the male gaze and now that we ourselves are playing the role of the camera (selfies/Instagram), we present ourselves through the male gaze!”, which got me thinking about how we're all victims of the Male Gaze in some way or the other. The Male Gaze has stealthily crept into our minds like a parasite and is benefitting by feeding off our insecurities. Hitherto, it wouldn’t take big brains to figure out how deeply problematic the Male Gaze is. Firstly, it normalises perceiving women as deserving of one-way surveillance by heterosexual men. Secondly, it negatively alters the way women look at themselves. They start to objectify themselves and inherently feel that their primary purpose is to please heterosexual men, whether it’s by being a doting mother succumbing to gender roles, a girl next door fulfilling your sexual desires, or a submissive subject desperately waiting to feed a man’s ego by being ‘saved’ by him. The Male Gaze quietly typecasts women as the ‘aesthetic’ half of humankind and gradually detracts from them other ambitions that men and women have alike. Scarily enough, it even normalises predatory gazes at women and perpetuates rape culture. And it haunts me to think that we all, so ordinarily consume the ‘Male Gaze’ served to us on the platter. Martin Waters, CEO of Victoria's Secret said after the big announcement of the replacement of its spokespeople, &quot;We're moving from what men want to what women want, from sexy for a few to sexy for all&quot;. In June 2021, Victoria's Secret ditched its Angels post a successful decade-long partnership after it realised that they were no longer ‘culturally relevant’, a euphemism for ‘morally acceptable’. Among the first seven women selected to join the ‘VS Collective’ are professional soccer star Megan Rapinoe, actress Priyanka Chopra Jonas and LGBTQ model and activist Valentina Sampaio. Because hey, that’s what women are, a little bit of everything! Now if Victoria’s Secret can identify the problem with the Male Gaze, I assume it’s not a secret anymore, is it? Finally, let's come back to the question Emily raised at the beginning of the article. Who draws the line between sexy and sexist, or say, the line between Cardi B’s sexualisation in her music video and a French model’s sexualisation in an advertisement? Who’s to say one is empowering and the other is not? If women want to make money off the Male Gaze, who are we to stop them? Well, the line is indisputably hard to draw. But here’s the thing, when a video agency sexualises a model while directing a perfume advertisement, the model is regulated, since she is a mere medium to convey what the agency wants to. However, when Cardi B sexualises herself, she does that as an independent artist, to express her own personal message, which is indeed empowering. Moreover, in either case, we end up normalising the unrealistic standards for and expectations from the women community at large, which is yet another ethical debate. Still, as long as sexualisation is the subject’s choice, we, coming from a place of privilege, don’t get to draw the line. But that doesn’t mean it’s okay for men to unwarrantedly keep reducing women to objects of sexual gratification on the pretext of making money. Clearly, we need more women creators to present women through a more realistic, humane perspective, but we're far from that, as of now. It is also known that money will find its way to the Male Gaze, giving it all the more incentive to creep into every line of business. However, in the meantime, as rational consumers of media, we can actively identify the wrong type of content and consciously choose to not feed its business. After all, they make money off your attention. The choice is yours. Until then.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Gender Roles: the Fallacy, the Irony and the Hypocrisy</title>
      <link href="/Gender-Roles-the-Fallacy-the-Irony-and-the-Hypocrisy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gender Roles: the Fallacy, the Irony and the Hypocrisy" />
      <published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Gender-Roles-the-Fallacy-the-Irony-and-the-Hypocrisy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Gender-Roles-the-Fallacy-the-Irony-and-the-Hypocrisy">&lt;p&gt;Gender roles and norms refer to a set of ideals that people of a particular sex (assigned at birth) are expected to conform to. They have, for years, set unrealistic standards for all people and formed the basis of an endless number of discriminatory and amoral practices. People lend support to them using the reasoning that they are based on scientific facts about biological sex. Recently, more and more people have started to openly show disdain for and disagreement with these norms, citing the numerous long standing and potentially dangerous effects of the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For long, anthropologists have put forward various pieces of evidence to prove that gender norms are but a social construct. They have repeatedly talked about how 'femininity' and 'masculinity' are relative terms. Margaret Mead was one such anthropologist, often deemed as a sort of a maverick in the field. She revolutionised the field of study, which was previously prominently arm-chair based knowledge, by taking up a more proactive approach. She travelled to remote parts of the world to understand how men and women related to each other, in comparison to the Western ideals of 'femininity', 'masculinity' and 'gender roles'. Over the course of her life, she penned down several preeminent books on the matter.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1933, Mead wrote &lt;em&gt;Sex and Temperament in Three Primitive Societies&lt;/em&gt;. She compared three indigenous groups from the South Pacific which she designated as Arapesh, Tchambuli and Mundugumor. The cultures wildly differed in their expectations and standards for men and women. She noted that in comparison to the established Western standards, all of Arapesh was feminine while the opposite was true for Mundugumor, that is, it was masculine. Tchambuli, on the other hand, reversed Western ideals completely - the dominant positions belonged to women while the dependent ones to men. Mead’s conclusion from the analysis was clear: human nature is malleable and it responds to cultural conditions. Nurture and not nature is responsible for the concept of gender. In other words, gender roles are social constructs, and do not have a basis in the more biological aspects of sex.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the fact that gender roles are social constructs can be lucidly seen in a particular culture too as the ideals change drastically over time, sometimes even undergoing a full 180 degree reversal. The perception of the colors pink and blue is one such example. Pink was not labelled as feminine color until the 1940's. Prior to this, color was generally assigned based on the complexion and so any baby could be dressed in blue or pink. Further back, during the 18th century, pink, which was seen as a close relative of the martial red color, was considered to be a masculine shade. Even as recently as in 1918, an article titled 'Pink or Blue' in &lt;em&gt;The Infants’ Department&lt;/em&gt; stated that pink was meant for boys and blue was for girls. The trend is the exact opposite of this today.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, perceptions about makeup have vacillated between being deemed as feminine and being expected of everyone, through the ages. Makeup was in common use by all people in ancient Egypt, Rome and other civilisations, dating back to as far as 4000 BC in humankind’s history. However, the scenario is obviously very different in the modern world where putting on makeup is predominantly deemed as a feminine activity. In Elizabethan England, makeup was very popular among men. In the mid-1800's however, Queen Victoria and the Church agreed that makeup was an “abomination”. The dissemination of this belief resulted in a long standing association of makeup with femininity and the “Devil’s Work”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These oscillations in ideals and standards associated with gender, within a particular community over time and between different communities at any specific point in time prove that gender norms and expectations are, in fact, not dictated by the biology of sex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gender norms have encouraged various discriminatory and immoral practices through the years of human history and they are still thriving today. More often than not, they're what is responsible for the microaggressions against people of all genders and sexes. For example, men are told not to cry or show emotions, and are expected to partake in activities deemed as worthy of men, often involving heavy manual labor. Those who indulge in the more 'feminine' activities like putting on makeup, cooking and playing sports seen as girly like cheerleading, are looked down upon and slandered.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other end of the spectrum, women are faced with disparaging comments that declare that they simply cannot be funny and belong in the kitchen. Similarly, limited mathematical aptitude and tendency of being loving, caring or sensitive is attributed to their gender. Women are repeatedly talked over and mansplained in professional spaces, in addition to being doubted, especially in leadership roles. Effeminate men are criticised for being too 'feminine', androgenous people are told they are too ambiguous and tomboys are told they are too 'masculine', all of these come paired with a negative undertone. The inferiority of women in the eyes of society is especially clear in such sexist jibes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fallacy, hypocrisy and irony in the gender roles and standards are especially evident through the everyday misogynistic and sexist microaggressions faced by people. Women are told that they are meant to be mothers and yet, young mothers are shamed and criticised almost as much as those who abort their fetus to escape the shame (apart from other reasons). Working women with families are denigrated just as much as those who choose to stay at home.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The former are slandered with claims of being an unfit mother - too calculating, too progressive, too career-oriented. The latter are faced with epithets like 'gold digger' and 'bad role model' as their work is often overlooked. They are also regularly accused of being indolent and lazy. When a woman refuses to give in to the sexual demands of entitled men, they are tagged as 'too prudish' and yet, giving in or choosing to be more sexually active earns them the label 'slut' or 'easy'. Liking dresses and heels is deemed to be too 'frivolous' and 'girly' (with a negative connotation attached) and conversely, women are flagged as gay (often used as a slur in this context) or too 'boyish' (and thus, unattractive) for choosing to have a more masculine aesthetic. Societal standards rooted in gender perception are a double-edged sword, especially for women and other minority genders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of history, an endless number of people have undermined the oppressive gender norms. Some of them achieve fame like Boudica and others attain notoriety like Mary, Queen of the Scots. But, more often than not, the contributions of women and other minority genders are overlooked. An important instance of erasure is the lack of acknowledgement of the contribution of medieval European women to the arts of the times.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Medieval women, especially widows, are generally portrayed as vulnerable, miserable and poor in history books and in literature. The truth, however, was far from this. Financially knowledgeable widows, who were well connected, often accumulated a lot of wealth through jointures and other mechanisms after the death of their husbands.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'Jointures' were pieces of land owned by both the wife and the husband. The ownership remained solely with the surviving spouse on the death of the other. This was very common in the 14th and 15th centuries and became a source of immense wealth for widows who outlived their husbands.They used this money to provide patronage to the arts. Some of the most well-known cathedrals and other monuments of the time were paid for by these widows. Many of them took this new liberty a step further; they commissioned the construction of memorials and mausoleums for themselves which transcended the boundaries of social and patriarchal expectations from women - extravagant architecture, statues of themselves as duchesses or more important than the men in their lives and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the patriarchal norms, a woman lost her individual identity with each marriage, taking up the name of their husbands in the medieval times. This makes it difficult to track the lives of these women (although not impossible) and their contributions to art are thus, largely unacknowledged. Modern public monuments also fail to represent women as history demands it. Of the more than 800 sculptures around the UK, only an abysmal 42 are those of named non-royal women.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, when simply ignoring history is difficult, people have opted to amend it to conform to society’s standards and expectations from a particular gender. Cleopatra VII has been portrayed several times in various books and movies, both Hollywood and otherwise. She is always shown as an unusually attractive seductress. 'Scandals' like her romance with Julius Caesar and Mark Anthony greatly overshadow her achievements, which are often completely ignored. Her stories are full of lies and rumours too. In reality, contrary to her popular portrayals, she was a great statesperson and could command armies. She was fluent in at least nine languages, including an Egyptian tongue, unlike her predecessors of the Ptolemaic dynasty. Additionally, Cleopatra was highly educated in the fields of astronomy, chemistry and literature, among other disciplines and can also be linked to numerous advancements in the field of alchemy of the time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides these, she has several administrative achievements under her belt including her proactive actions to curb corruption among the priests. Cleopatra was the reason for more than two decades of prosperity and stability in Egypt. Instead of acknowledging her numerous achievements, people are obsessed with her affairs with Caesar and Mark Anthony, going as far as blaming her for them and the fate and downfall they suffered later. This overlooks the fact that both Caesar and Mark Anthony were involved in countless other affairs. The queen was certainly not the beautiful seductress that we have been taught to believe. In fact, she might not even have been 'beautiful' as she was, much like most of the other Egyptian royal family members, a product of incest.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cleopatra’s character was questioned and her leadership was doubted by Greek and Roman writers, but this objection was primarily because she was a woman and therefore, according to them, unfit to rule. It is important to remember who the author of any particular story is when talking about its validity. In this case, it was the enemy and so, her stories are rife with rumours (like the story about her suicide by a snake bite). These canards are today frequently presented as history lessons and yet, they are far from the truth. Cleopatra VII is only one of numerous examples of women in history that we have wronged. We owe it to them to rectify the adulterations and remember them just as they were.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, we can say that gender norms have only encouraged damaging practices that have for years deprived us of an opportunity to celebrate the accurate history of humankind. It has paved the way for discriminatory practices against cis women, cis men, transgenders, non-binaries and so on and so forth. While many explain away the established gender roles with claims that they are rooted in biological tendencies and scientific facts about sex, anthropologists have long disagreed and put forward various pieces of evidence to substantiate the theory that gender is entirely a social construct. There is thus, absolutely no moral justification for upholding these standards any longer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Gender roles and norms refer to a set of ideals that people of a particular sex (assigned at birth) are expected to conform to. They have, for years, set unrealistic standards for all people and formed the basis of an endless number of discriminatory and amoral practices. People lend support to them using the reasoning that they are based on scientific facts about biological sex. Recently, more and more people have started to openly show disdain for and disagreement with these norms, citing the numerous long standing and potentially dangerous effects of the same.&amp;nbsp; For long, anthropologists have put forward various pieces of evidence to prove that gender norms are but a social construct. They have repeatedly talked about how 'femininity' and 'masculinity' are relative terms. Margaret Mead was one such anthropologist, often deemed as a sort of a maverick in the field. She revolutionised the field of study, which was previously prominently arm-chair based knowledge, by taking up a more proactive approach. She travelled to remote parts of the world to understand how men and women related to each other, in comparison to the Western ideals of 'femininity', 'masculinity' and 'gender roles'. Over the course of her life, she penned down several preeminent books on the matter.&amp;nbsp; In 1933, Mead wrote Sex and Temperament in Three Primitive Societies. She compared three indigenous groups from the South Pacific which she designated as Arapesh, Tchambuli and Mundugumor. The cultures wildly differed in their expectations and standards for men and women. She noted that in comparison to the established Western standards, all of Arapesh was feminine while the opposite was true for Mundugumor, that is, it was masculine. Tchambuli, on the other hand, reversed Western ideals completely - the dominant positions belonged to women while the dependent ones to men. Mead’s conclusion from the analysis was clear: human nature is malleable and it responds to cultural conditions. Nurture and not nature is responsible for the concept of gender. In other words, gender roles are social constructs, and do not have a basis in the more biological aspects of sex.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, the fact that gender roles are social constructs can be lucidly seen in a particular culture too as the ideals change drastically over time, sometimes even undergoing a full 180 degree reversal. The perception of the colors pink and blue is one such example. Pink was not labelled as feminine color until the 1940's. Prior to this, color was generally assigned based on the complexion and so any baby could be dressed in blue or pink. Further back, during the 18th century, pink, which was seen as a close relative of the martial red color, was considered to be a masculine shade. Even as recently as in 1918, an article titled 'Pink or Blue' in The Infants’ Department stated that pink was meant for boys and blue was for girls. The trend is the exact opposite of this today.&amp;nbsp; Likewise, perceptions about makeup have vacillated between being deemed as feminine and being expected of everyone, through the ages. Makeup was in common use by all people in ancient Egypt, Rome and other civilisations, dating back to as far as 4000 BC in humankind’s history. However, the scenario is obviously very different in the modern world where putting on makeup is predominantly deemed as a feminine activity. In Elizabethan England, makeup was very popular among men. In the mid-1800's however, Queen Victoria and the Church agreed that makeup was an “abomination”. The dissemination of this belief resulted in a long standing association of makeup with femininity and the “Devil’s Work”.&amp;nbsp; These oscillations in ideals and standards associated with gender, within a particular community over time and between different communities at any specific point in time prove that gender norms and expectations are, in fact, not dictated by the biology of sex. Gender norms have encouraged various discriminatory and immoral practices through the years of human history and they are still thriving today. More often than not, they're what is responsible for the microaggressions against people of all genders and sexes. For example, men are told not to cry or show emotions, and are expected to partake in activities deemed as worthy of men, often involving heavy manual labor. Those who indulge in the more 'feminine' activities like putting on makeup, cooking and playing sports seen as girly like cheerleading, are looked down upon and slandered.&amp;nbsp; On the other end of the spectrum, women are faced with disparaging comments that declare that they simply cannot be funny and belong in the kitchen. Similarly, limited mathematical aptitude and tendency of being loving, caring or sensitive is attributed to their gender. Women are repeatedly talked over and mansplained in professional spaces, in addition to being doubted, especially in leadership roles. Effeminate men are criticised for being too 'feminine', androgenous people are told they are too ambiguous and tomboys are told they are too 'masculine', all of these come paired with a negative undertone. The inferiority of women in the eyes of society is especially clear in such sexist jibes.&amp;nbsp; The fallacy, hypocrisy and irony in the gender roles and standards are especially evident through the everyday misogynistic and sexist microaggressions faced by people. Women are told that they are meant to be mothers and yet, young mothers are shamed and criticised almost as much as those who abort their fetus to escape the shame (apart from other reasons). Working women with families are denigrated just as much as those who choose to stay at home.&amp;nbsp; The former are slandered with claims of being an unfit mother - too calculating, too progressive, too career-oriented. The latter are faced with epithets like 'gold digger' and 'bad role model' as their work is often overlooked. They are also regularly accused of being indolent and lazy. When a woman refuses to give in to the sexual demands of entitled men, they are tagged as 'too prudish' and yet, giving in or choosing to be more sexually active earns them the label 'slut' or 'easy'. Liking dresses and heels is deemed to be too 'frivolous' and 'girly' (with a negative connotation attached) and conversely, women are flagged as gay (often used as a slur in this context) or too 'boyish' (and thus, unattractive) for choosing to have a more masculine aesthetic. Societal standards rooted in gender perception are a double-edged sword, especially for women and other minority genders.&amp;nbsp; Over the course of history, an endless number of people have undermined the oppressive gender norms. Some of them achieve fame like Boudica and others attain notoriety like Mary, Queen of the Scots. But, more often than not, the contributions of women and other minority genders are overlooked. An important instance of erasure is the lack of acknowledgement of the contribution of medieval European women to the arts of the times.&amp;nbsp; Medieval women, especially widows, are generally portrayed as vulnerable, miserable and poor in history books and in literature. The truth, however, was far from this. Financially knowledgeable widows, who were well connected, often accumulated a lot of wealth through jointures and other mechanisms after the death of their husbands.&amp;nbsp; 'Jointures' were pieces of land owned by both the wife and the husband. The ownership remained solely with the surviving spouse on the death of the other. This was very common in the 14th and 15th centuries and became a source of immense wealth for widows who outlived their husbands.They used this money to provide patronage to the arts. Some of the most well-known cathedrals and other monuments of the time were paid for by these widows. Many of them took this new liberty a step further; they commissioned the construction of memorials and mausoleums for themselves which transcended the boundaries of social and patriarchal expectations from women - extravagant architecture, statues of themselves as duchesses or more important than the men in their lives and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp; Due to the patriarchal norms, a woman lost her individual identity with each marriage, taking up the name of their husbands in the medieval times. This makes it difficult to track the lives of these women (although not impossible) and their contributions to art are thus, largely unacknowledged. Modern public monuments also fail to represent women as history demands it. Of the more than 800 sculptures around the UK, only an abysmal 42 are those of named non-royal women.&amp;nbsp; Sometimes, when simply ignoring history is difficult, people have opted to amend it to conform to society’s standards and expectations from a particular gender. Cleopatra VII has been portrayed several times in various books and movies, both Hollywood and otherwise. She is always shown as an unusually attractive seductress. 'Scandals' like her romance with Julius Caesar and Mark Anthony greatly overshadow her achievements, which are often completely ignored. Her stories are full of lies and rumours too. In reality, contrary to her popular portrayals, she was a great statesperson and could command armies. She was fluent in at least nine languages, including an Egyptian tongue, unlike her predecessors of the Ptolemaic dynasty. Additionally, Cleopatra was highly educated in the fields of astronomy, chemistry and literature, among other disciplines and can also be linked to numerous advancements in the field of alchemy of the time.&amp;nbsp; Besides these, she has several administrative achievements under her belt including her proactive actions to curb corruption among the priests. Cleopatra was the reason for more than two decades of prosperity and stability in Egypt. Instead of acknowledging her numerous achievements, people are obsessed with her affairs with Caesar and Mark Anthony, going as far as blaming her for them and the fate and downfall they suffered later. This overlooks the fact that both Caesar and Mark Anthony were involved in countless other affairs. The queen was certainly not the beautiful seductress that we have been taught to believe. In fact, she might not even have been 'beautiful' as she was, much like most of the other Egyptian royal family members, a product of incest.&amp;nbsp; Cleopatra’s character was questioned and her leadership was doubted by Greek and Roman writers, but this objection was primarily because she was a woman and therefore, according to them, unfit to rule. It is important to remember who the author of any particular story is when talking about its validity. In this case, it was the enemy and so, her stories are rife with rumours (like the story about her suicide by a snake bite). These canards are today frequently presented as history lessons and yet, they are far from the truth. Cleopatra VII is only one of numerous examples of women in history that we have wronged. We owe it to them to rectify the adulterations and remember them just as they were.&amp;nbsp; All in all, we can say that gender norms have only encouraged damaging practices that have for years deprived us of an opportunity to celebrate the accurate history of humankind. It has paved the way for discriminatory practices against cis women, cis men, transgenders, non-binaries and so on and so forth. While many explain away the established gender roles with claims that they are rooted in biological tendencies and scientific facts about sex, anthropologists have long disagreed and put forward various pieces of evidence to substantiate the theory that gender is entirely a social construct. There is thus, absolutely no moral justification for upholding these standards any longer.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
