<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/society/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-01-10T16:36:45+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/society/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Virtual Classrooms and Open Book Examinations</title>
      <link href="/Virtual-Classrooms-and-Open-Book-Examinations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Virtual Classrooms and Open Book Examinations" />
      <published>2020-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Virtual-Classrooms-and-Open-Book-Examinations</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Virtual-Classrooms-and-Open-Book-Examinations">&lt;p&gt;Virtual classrooms is a phrase that has become an important part of the new normal, and along with it comes the infamous open-book examinations. Who would have thought that in 2020, the mainstream physical examinations would be replaced by open book examinations. But then again, who in their wildest dreams would have thought that the whole world will be stuck inside their homes, or away from it, for almost a year. The pandemic has clearly uprooted the lives of many, and the students, all across the globe, are no different.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students have been forced to stay within the four walls of their houses, and attend digital schooling. In a country like India or the UK, it was March or April when the lockdown started as a result of the pandemic, and honestly, at that time no one thought it would go on for this long. In fact, no one was prepared for this pandemic and surely wasn’t ready to adapt to it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was clear from the start that the educational institutions were going to make decisions that might not be suited for the heterogeneous society that we are. Too many debates, discussions and uncertainty led to all sorts of discussions on what to do for the students who had their exams approaching. Thus, emerged the idea of open-book examinations for final year college students. This was initially taken up by Delhi University. The exams got postponed so many times that by the time we took the test we had lost the count. But when these examinations did take place, they happened at a definite, not-so-unclear cost.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, as a person, who could afford to have a separate room and a laptop to take the exams in peace, I was still drowned in intense amounts of anxiety. For, as a student since the past 17 years, all I had to focus on was my paper. Anything from a wrong question, to doubts, to submission of sheets was to be taken care of by the invigilators. The usage of any sort of technology wasn't even a part of the discussion. So these 17 years taught me to dedicate my whole three hours to write the exam. But with this pandemic and open-book examinations, it meant that for once I was required to do all the tasks by myself, using technology, an approach that many of us were clueless about, the added stress being whether the sheets were being uploaded and were the scanned images even clear. All this made me wonder about those who did not have all these layers of privilege I had, and the added stress levels they had to deal with. Obviously, by no means can I even come close to understanding how dreadful all this would have been for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is in times like these where the only source of interaction and schooling is through technology, people are forced to be left out, just because they cannot afford such a luxury. Thus, in such situations, something like education that we consider a necessity, in fact, becomes a luxury for many people.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the past few months, all the classes are being taken online. Within the span of these months, the mode of examinations has expanded to become MCQ-based or assignment-based. Despite all of this, looking at the state of students, it all doesn't look so different from the idea of a zero academic year, which many people find absurd. The students are constantly stuck onto the screens to study and then to do their homework and assignments, no wonder they are so tired from it all. From teachers figuring out how to make it all understandable to a class with no video and microphone on, to the students attending the class but sleeping through most of it. There is little to no education taking place.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this seems like it was bound to happen because our teaching methods have been developed for face-to-face interactions and not for video-call sessions. Moreover, Indian education systems aren't even reformed enough to focus on teaching the concepts, rather than focusing on exams, which clearly doesn't sit well with the condition we are in currently. Hence, it really makes no sense to have open-book examinations or any form of virtual examinations for that matter, when our whole education system is based on seeing how well you remember what you have learnt, and not really how well you grasp the concept.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pandemic has already increased our anxiety levels, and an education like this just adds to it all. This is only the state of the ones who are privileged enough to actually have access to such resources and means of education. There are so many students out there who due to different reasons cannot take up online classes. And hence have no other option but to skip this year, in the hopes that they'll get to join next year. No one can imagine the stress of these children and the huge loss to their mental health as a result of not being able to take up classes this year. We did see one such incident come forth from Lady Shri Ram College, Delhi University, where a brilliant student was so burdened by the stress of her family's financial incapability that it made her take her own life. It was only then that the college decided to take action towards reducing fees and providing help to those in need. But is it really the lack of financial capability of the family, or the lack of concern of the people sitting on the other end, who refuse to look into how the pandemic could be affecting the students and their families?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking around we do see differences when it comes to how the private institutions and government institutions have dealt with digital schooling. And definitely, there is a clear difference between nations across the globe. However, despite these differences, with some institutions clearly having a better grasp of virtual classroom systems, none of the institutions were prepared to shift their entire curriculum fully online for a whole year, or maybe even more. And even though, for once I am willing to believe that all the educational institutions took the most suitable option in the current scenario, there are still aspects which they just chose to ignore. While they adapted to the new normal, they forgot to look into the students who too had to adapt to it. From lack of concern towards the cash crunch that people are facing, to the effects of the pandemic on the mental and physical well-being of students — all of this is far from being discussed. There are still students left who haven't taken examinations due to various reasons, and they are constantly under stress, with the uncertainty of when they'll actually take them only growing. Every day my Instagram stories are filled with students crying over the extensive amount of pressure from the deadlines of assignments and the upcoming exams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this makes us wonder what is the point of such an education that only focuses on finishing the curriculum and not even on making sure that each and every student is actually able to attend these classes. Even if it seems that digital schooling is the only possible option right now, is it really worth it if it is at the expense of the sanity of the students, especially with so many students being left out of it altogether?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Priyanshi Mehra</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Virtual classrooms is a phrase that has become an important part of the new normal, and along with it comes the infamous open-book examinations. Who would have thought that in 2020, the mainstream physical examinations would be replaced by open book examinations. But then again, who in their wildest dreams would have thought that the whole world will be stuck inside their homes, or away from it, for almost a year. The pandemic has clearly uprooted the lives of many, and the students, all across the globe, are no different.&amp;nbsp; Students have been forced to stay within the four walls of their houses, and attend digital schooling. In a country like India or the UK, it was March or April when the lockdown started as a result of the pandemic, and honestly, at that time no one thought it would go on for this long. In fact, no one was prepared for this pandemic and surely wasn’t ready to adapt to it.&amp;nbsp; It was clear from the start that the educational institutions were going to make decisions that might not be suited for the heterogeneous society that we are. Too many debates, discussions and uncertainty led to all sorts of discussions on what to do for the students who had their exams approaching. Thus, emerged the idea of open-book examinations for final year college students. This was initially taken up by Delhi University. The exams got postponed so many times that by the time we took the test we had lost the count. But when these examinations did take place, they happened at a definite, not-so-unclear cost.&amp;nbsp; You see, as a person, who could afford to have a separate room and a laptop to take the exams in peace, I was still drowned in intense amounts of anxiety. For, as a student since the past 17 years, all I had to focus on was my paper. Anything from a wrong question, to doubts, to submission of sheets was to be taken care of by the invigilators. The usage of any sort of technology wasn't even a part of the discussion. So these 17 years taught me to dedicate my whole three hours to write the exam. But with this pandemic and open-book examinations, it meant that for once I was required to do all the tasks by myself, using technology, an approach that many of us were clueless about, the added stress being whether the sheets were being uploaded and were the scanned images even clear. All this made me wonder about those who did not have all these layers of privilege I had, and the added stress levels they had to deal with. Obviously, by no means can I even come close to understanding how dreadful all this would have been for them. It is in times like these where the only source of interaction and schooling is through technology, people are forced to be left out, just because they cannot afford such a luxury. Thus, in such situations, something like education that we consider a necessity, in fact, becomes a luxury for many people.&amp;nbsp; Since the past few months, all the classes are being taken online. Within the span of these months, the mode of examinations has expanded to become MCQ-based or assignment-based. Despite all of this, looking at the state of students, it all doesn't look so different from the idea of a zero academic year, which many people find absurd. The students are constantly stuck onto the screens to study and then to do their homework and assignments, no wonder they are so tired from it all. From teachers figuring out how to make it all understandable to a class with no video and microphone on, to the students attending the class but sleeping through most of it. There is little to no education taking place.&amp;nbsp; All of this seems like it was bound to happen because our teaching methods have been developed for face-to-face interactions and not for video-call sessions. Moreover, Indian education systems aren't even reformed enough to focus on teaching the concepts, rather than focusing on exams, which clearly doesn't sit well with the condition we are in currently. Hence, it really makes no sense to have open-book examinations or any form of virtual examinations for that matter, when our whole education system is based on seeing how well you remember what you have learnt, and not really how well you grasp the concept.&amp;nbsp; The pandemic has already increased our anxiety levels, and an education like this just adds to it all. This is only the state of the ones who are privileged enough to actually have access to such resources and means of education. There are so many students out there who due to different reasons cannot take up online classes. And hence have no other option but to skip this year, in the hopes that they'll get to join next year. No one can imagine the stress of these children and the huge loss to their mental health as a result of not being able to take up classes this year. We did see one such incident come forth from Lady Shri Ram College, Delhi University, where a brilliant student was so burdened by the stress of her family's financial incapability that it made her take her own life. It was only then that the college decided to take action towards reducing fees and providing help to those in need. But is it really the lack of financial capability of the family, or the lack of concern of the people sitting on the other end, who refuse to look into how the pandemic could be affecting the students and their families?&amp;nbsp; Looking around we do see differences when it comes to how the private institutions and government institutions have dealt with digital schooling. And definitely, there is a clear difference between nations across the globe. However, despite these differences, with some institutions clearly having a better grasp of virtual classroom systems, none of the institutions were prepared to shift their entire curriculum fully online for a whole year, or maybe even more. And even though, for once I am willing to believe that all the educational institutions took the most suitable option in the current scenario, there are still aspects which they just chose to ignore. While they adapted to the new normal, they forgot to look into the students who too had to adapt to it. From lack of concern towards the cash crunch that people are facing, to the effects of the pandemic on the mental and physical well-being of students — all of this is far from being discussed. There are still students left who haven't taken examinations due to various reasons, and they are constantly under stress, with the uncertainty of when they'll actually take them only growing. Every day my Instagram stories are filled with students crying over the extensive amount of pressure from the deadlines of assignments and the upcoming exams. All of this makes us wonder what is the point of such an education that only focuses on finishing the curriculum and not even on making sure that each and every student is actually able to attend these classes. Even if it seems that digital schooling is the only possible option right now, is it really worth it if it is at the expense of the sanity of the students, especially with so many students being left out of it altogether?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Retail Binge for the Mental Twinge</title>
      <link href="/Retail-Binge-for-the-Mental-Twinge" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Retail Binge for the Mental Twinge" />
      <published>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Retail-Binge-for-the-Mental-Twinge</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Retail-Binge-for-the-Mental-Twinge">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;They say, “When the going gets tough, the tough go shopping.” This is more commonly known as &lt;em&gt;Retail Therapy&lt;/em&gt;. It is a phenomenon where people shop to improve one’s disposition and raise spirits. People in distress often resort to this as a source of solace. A study published in the journal &lt;em&gt;Psychology and Marketing&lt;/em&gt; states that retail therapy has a lasting positive effect on mood. While its findings pointed out that these are impulsive purchases, the survey suggested that feelings of guilt or regret were not associated among the respondents.&amp;nbsp;The name in itself is ironic. Shopping is a concept deeply rooted in materialism. As its positive impact is temporary, it does not qualify as a ‘therapy’ in the medical sense. However, it is a fairly popular phrase used around the world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In a 2001 survey conducted by the European Union, it was found that 33% of the shoppers surveyed had a “high level of addiction to rash buying”. The study also revealed that ‘binge purchasing’ was most common among the Scottish youth. Another study of 1,000 American adults, conducted in 2013, detected that more than half of the respondents indulged in retail therapy. It also threw light on the gender aspect of the practice, stating that it is more common among women than men. It was found that 64.9% of women and 38.9% of men binge purchased while women mostly bought clothing, men indulged in ‘comfort food’. This was further reinforced by the Youngstown State University with similar male-female percentages, showing that relief from stress was the most common reason behind the practice. A more adverse extension of retail therapy is Oniomania or Compulsive Buying Disorder, which is an obsession with shopping, resulting in serious financial and mental consequences.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Whys behind the Comfort Buys&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While stress, anxiety and sadness are a part of daily life, they can be tackled through other means such as reaching out to others, practicing yoga, mindfulness and meditation, journaling, exercising and consulting experts in more severe cases. Despite there being these solutions, which on an average are cheaper than shopping, why do people indulge in purchasing things to boost their mood? To understand the causes behind retail therapy, the behavioral aspect of individuals needs to be analysed in a twofold manner. Even though, at first glance, these reasons seem simple — associated with daily life, a deeper analysis suggests that the root cause can be traced back to psychological theory.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Firstly, we examine the relatively straightforward causes.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;When everything goes wrong and nothing falls into place as you imagined it to, how do you feel? Out of control, right? Thus, one of the reasons people indulge in retail therapy is that shopping is a coping mechanism that helps people feel more in control. From deciding where to shop, to choosing what to purchase, it allows people to exercise autonomy and make decisions. In my personal opinion, shopping can also make one feel a sense of achievement. Utilising good offers and deals, applying coupons to get discounts and sometimes even getting goods for free certainly makes one feel happier as they ‘save’ along with fulfilling a guilty pleasure.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Secondly, retail therapy can be a useful mechanism for smooth transitions of life as it enables people to envisage their lives post such changes. For instance, people often shop excessively before they are going to live alone for the first time, shifting to a new house, getting married or having a baby. Shopping may ease anxiety by making people feel more in control by helping them to prepare themselves for such huge transitions through the process of ‘visualisation’, which is a process that boosts performance, confidence and reduces anxiety.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another way in which retail therapy boosts mood is through a pleasant gush of creativity. Specifically, clothing of various kinds of colors and textures, accessories like jewelry, footwear, bags, sunglasses, etc, home decor items may induce a positive breeze of art and aesthetics. For example, the arrival of a new outfit may stir your creative juices in thinking about what shoes, jewelry and bag to pair it up with. This may certainly bring about a calmness in a way similar to art therapy, a well-known method of healing and reducing stress.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Some people treat shopping, both online and offline as a source of refreshment from the humdrum of daily life. Being a mindless activity, it enables people to relax and take some time off from their sources of stress. This form may vary from window shopping to scrolling on an online website or going to a shopping-mall for a break.&amp;nbsp;Yet another reason behind binge-purchasing may be the need to ‘feel connected’. For instance, one may shop for a sweater with a snowman or bells, candies and wreaths for decoration during Christmas, to feel more socially connected to the festival. Or someone may shop for a beret before visiting Paris to feel a part of the culture of the fashion capital. Thus, retail therapy may help individuals to feel closer to society and culture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;An extensive scrutiny of the idea suggests that the root cause lies in Sigmund Freud’s Pleasure Principle of psychology. The principle claims that individuals instinctively seek immediate pleasure to avoid experiencing feelings of stress, pain and sadness. In the context of impulsive purchasing, the principle fits well, as it is only a short term coping mechanism rooted in instant relief from stress. As compared to the Freudian Reality Principle, the Pleasure Principle is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Present-Bias-Focus-on-the-Now-but-maybe-Not-Always&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;inability of individuals to defer immediate gratification of certain desires and wants that rationality and reality may disallow.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Sadness Cycle&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Even though retail therapy eases the anxiety and pain in people’s lives, such a positive impact may be short-lived. While retail therapy can be supported by psychological reasoning, Economics does not go hand-in-hand with the concept due to its assumption of rationality among all individuals. From the point of view of rationality, the problems of running out of budget and debts arise due to limited financial resources. Impulsive overspending may lead people to become even more anxious and distressed due to the inability of paying bills and lacking a sound financial base, in the long run. A rough patch after having run out of budget may seem more dramatic and difficult to handle, due to a lack of finance to purchase something to feel better. In desperate times like these, individuals addicted to the method, may resort to desperate measures like taking loans from others or stealing. This might be complemented with feelings of guilt due to unrealistically high expenditure patterns.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Thus, retail therapy, to an obsessive degree can lead to reverse effects by introducing a cycle of stress and anxiety for an individual rather than helping one fight the tough times.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The ‘Viral’ Remedy&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;With the Coronavirus pandemic hitting the world, people across the globe felt paralysed due to being restricted homes all the time. While this altered the work culture among people, the norms of schooling among students and put a halt to dining out, it had an impact on the shoppers. Research suggests that elements appealing to an individual’s senses, like aroma, music, a creative arrangement of products in a store, temperature contribute to the experience of shoppers. Unfortunately, with the lockdown implemented across the world, this ‘sensory’ experience was no longer available. As a result of this, one would expect sales to fall. However, the online retail industry led to a different turn of events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to &lt;em&gt;Forbes&lt;/em&gt;, as of March 2020, several online retail categories experienced a 74% year over year increase in sales, as compared to March 2018. Some of the top categories that saw a surge in the sale are home goods like furniture and home decor items and athletic and loungewear. While it may be argued that these categories resonate more with individuals in the current scenario due to the need to stay home, it must be noted that none of these items are essentials. Thus, it can be suggested that individuals binge purchased during the pandemic to escape the fears and stress of the situation and its uncertainty, thereby serving as a recent instance of retail therapy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The impact of retail therapy on an individual’s life depends upon the degree of engagement. On one hand, retail therapy in the form of window shopping, purchasing with adherence to one’s budget or buying pre-planned things can help to reduce stress and sadness both in the short term and long run. On the other hand, if the simple habit intensifies to become an addiction, it results in adverse problems which in turn brings more distress, thereby defeating the purpose of the ‘therapy’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Nirikta Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">They say, “When the going gets tough, the tough go shopping.” This is more commonly known as Retail Therapy. It is a phenomenon where people shop to improve one’s disposition and raise spirits. People in distress often resort to this as a source of solace. A study published in the journal Psychology and Marketing states that retail therapy has a lasting positive effect on mood. While its findings pointed out that these are impulsive purchases, the survey suggested that feelings of guilt or regret were not associated among the respondents.&amp;nbsp;The name in itself is ironic. Shopping is a concept deeply rooted in materialism. As its positive impact is temporary, it does not qualify as a ‘therapy’ in the medical sense. However, it is a fairly popular phrase used around the world.&amp;nbsp; In a 2001 survey conducted by the European Union, it was found that 33% of the shoppers surveyed had a “high level of addiction to rash buying”. The study also revealed that ‘binge purchasing’ was most common among the Scottish youth. Another study of 1,000 American adults, conducted in 2013, detected that more than half of the respondents indulged in retail therapy. It also threw light on the gender aspect of the practice, stating that it is more common among women than men. It was found that 64.9% of women and 38.9% of men binge purchased while women mostly bought clothing, men indulged in ‘comfort food’. This was further reinforced by the Youngstown State University with similar male-female percentages, showing that relief from stress was the most common reason behind the practice. A more adverse extension of retail therapy is Oniomania or Compulsive Buying Disorder, which is an obsession with shopping, resulting in serious financial and mental consequences.&amp;nbsp; The Whys behind the Comfort Buys&amp;nbsp; While stress, anxiety and sadness are a part of daily life, they can be tackled through other means such as reaching out to others, practicing yoga, mindfulness and meditation, journaling, exercising and consulting experts in more severe cases. Despite there being these solutions, which on an average are cheaper than shopping, why do people indulge in purchasing things to boost their mood? To understand the causes behind retail therapy, the behavioral aspect of individuals needs to be analysed in a twofold manner. Even though, at first glance, these reasons seem simple — associated with daily life, a deeper analysis suggests that the root cause can be traced back to psychological theory.&amp;nbsp; Firstly, we examine the relatively straightforward causes.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;When everything goes wrong and nothing falls into place as you imagined it to, how do you feel? Out of control, right? Thus, one of the reasons people indulge in retail therapy is that shopping is a coping mechanism that helps people feel more in control. From deciding where to shop, to choosing what to purchase, it allows people to exercise autonomy and make decisions. In my personal opinion, shopping can also make one feel a sense of achievement. Utilising good offers and deals, applying coupons to get discounts and sometimes even getting goods for free certainly makes one feel happier as they ‘save’ along with fulfilling a guilty pleasure.&amp;nbsp; Secondly, retail therapy can be a useful mechanism for smooth transitions of life as it enables people to envisage their lives post such changes. For instance, people often shop excessively before they are going to live alone for the first time, shifting to a new house, getting married or having a baby. Shopping may ease anxiety by making people feel more in control by helping them to prepare themselves for such huge transitions through the process of ‘visualisation’, which is a process that boosts performance, confidence and reduces anxiety.&amp;nbsp; Another way in which retail therapy boosts mood is through a pleasant gush of creativity. Specifically, clothing of various kinds of colors and textures, accessories like jewelry, footwear, bags, sunglasses, etc, home decor items may induce a positive breeze of art and aesthetics. For example, the arrival of a new outfit may stir your creative juices in thinking about what shoes, jewelry and bag to pair it up with. This may certainly bring about a calmness in a way similar to art therapy, a well-known method of healing and reducing stress.&amp;nbsp; Some people treat shopping, both online and offline as a source of refreshment from the humdrum of daily life. Being a mindless activity, it enables people to relax and take some time off from their sources of stress. This form may vary from window shopping to scrolling on an online website or going to a shopping-mall for a break.&amp;nbsp;Yet another reason behind binge-purchasing may be the need to ‘feel connected’. For instance, one may shop for a sweater with a snowman or bells, candies and wreaths for decoration during Christmas, to feel more socially connected to the festival. Or someone may shop for a beret before visiting Paris to feel a part of the culture of the fashion capital. Thus, retail therapy may help individuals to feel closer to society and culture.&amp;nbsp; An extensive scrutiny of the idea suggests that the root cause lies in Sigmund Freud’s Pleasure Principle of psychology. The principle claims that individuals instinctively seek immediate pleasure to avoid experiencing feelings of stress, pain and sadness. In the context of impulsive purchasing, the principle fits well, as it is only a short term coping mechanism rooted in instant relief from stress. As compared to the Freudian Reality Principle, the Pleasure Principle is the inability of individuals to defer immediate gratification of certain desires and wants that rationality and reality may disallow.&amp;nbsp; The Sadness Cycle&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Even though retail therapy eases the anxiety and pain in people’s lives, such a positive impact may be short-lived. While retail therapy can be supported by psychological reasoning, Economics does not go hand-in-hand with the concept due to its assumption of rationality among all individuals. From the point of view of rationality, the problems of running out of budget and debts arise due to limited financial resources. Impulsive overspending may lead people to become even more anxious and distressed due to the inability of paying bills and lacking a sound financial base, in the long run. A rough patch after having run out of budget may seem more dramatic and difficult to handle, due to a lack of finance to purchase something to feel better. In desperate times like these, individuals addicted to the method, may resort to desperate measures like taking loans from others or stealing. This might be complemented with feelings of guilt due to unrealistically high expenditure patterns.&amp;nbsp; Thus, retail therapy, to an obsessive degree can lead to reverse effects by introducing a cycle of stress and anxiety for an individual rather than helping one fight the tough times.&amp;nbsp; The ‘Viral’ Remedy&amp;nbsp; With the Coronavirus pandemic hitting the world, people across the globe felt paralysed due to being restricted homes all the time. While this altered the work culture among people, the norms of schooling among students and put a halt to dining out, it had an impact on the shoppers. Research suggests that elements appealing to an individual’s senses, like aroma, music, a creative arrangement of products in a store, temperature contribute to the experience of shoppers. Unfortunately, with the lockdown implemented across the world, this ‘sensory’ experience was no longer available. As a result of this, one would expect sales to fall. However, the online retail industry led to a different turn of events. According to Forbes, as of March 2020, several online retail categories experienced a 74% year over year increase in sales, as compared to March 2018. Some of the top categories that saw a surge in the sale are home goods like furniture and home decor items and athletic and loungewear. While it may be argued that these categories resonate more with individuals in the current scenario due to the need to stay home, it must be noted that none of these items are essentials. Thus, it can be suggested that individuals binge purchased during the pandemic to escape the fears and stress of the situation and its uncertainty, thereby serving as a recent instance of retail therapy.&amp;nbsp; The impact of retail therapy on an individual’s life depends upon the degree of engagement. On one hand, retail therapy in the form of window shopping, purchasing with adherence to one’s budget or buying pre-planned things can help to reduce stress and sadness both in the short term and long run. On the other hand, if the simple habit intensifies to become an addiction, it results in adverse problems which in turn brings more distress, thereby defeating the purpose of the ‘therapy’.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Present Bias: Focus on the Now but maybe Not Always</title>
      <link href="/Present-Bias-Focus-on-the-Now-but-maybe-Not-Always" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Present Bias: Focus on the Now but maybe Not Always" />
      <published>2020-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Present-Bias-Focus-on-the-Now-but-maybe-Not-Always</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Present-Bias-Focus-on-the-Now-but-maybe-Not-Always">&lt;p&gt;Many times we wonder, what is it that makes us procrastinate? Why do we spend the whole day scrolling through Instagram instead of finishing the assignment that is due tomorrow? Apart from the fact that social media is designed to distract us, procrastinating isn't as simple as just being lazy. It isn't only about not wanting to do the task at hand, but more about how we humans are wired.&amp;nbsp; Procrastination is in fact related to a cognitive bias called the &lt;em&gt;present bias&lt;/em&gt;. As the name in itself suggests, it is the tendency of humans to be biased towards the present. This means that we tend to go for short-term rewards that provide us instant gratification rather than choosing long-term benefits. Thus, even though the benefit of finishing that assignment is clearly more than simply being on Instagram, the sense of gratification is achieved faster in the latter. Therefore, our brain might as well trick us into choosing the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to understand why humans are actually biased towards the present. The answer lies in how our ancestors lived their lives. The times they lived in, it only made sense that they focused on the present. With the uncertainty of the future and the environment they lived in, they had no other option but to be short-sighted in their decision making. This present bias allowed them to survive and deal with the immediate threats that existed around them. Over the centuries, this outlook of theirs seems to have been so well engraved in our brains that even today we have a similar mindset. Despite us having a far more stable lifestyle and a future to actually look forward to, our brain still makes us biased towards our present. It still makes us believe that the future is a scary avenue that one shouldn't be focusing much on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of the present bias has been studied by many researchers over the years, in order to understand to what extent such a bias can affect the lives of individuals. An interesting experiment in this field was conducted by Walter Mischel. This experiment that goes by the name of &lt;em&gt;Marshmallow Test &lt;/em&gt;is a famous experiment which involved finding out whether children delayed gratification. It involved children being asked to either choose a marshmallow now or wait for 15-20 minutes to get two of them. This experiment, however, did not end here only. After a few years, these very children, who were by then adolescents, were traced and it was seen that the children who delayed gratification at a younger age were able to be more successful in the later period of their lives. Thus, shedding light on the connection between small decisions turning into a lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting aspect of present bias is that it is not just limited to the field of psychology but also equally important for economics. Take for an example, if you were to choose between getting a job of ₹15,000/month now, or interning for free for a year and getting a job of ₹30,000/month. You are more likely to choose the former. But if you were asked to either complete your 3 years of Bachelor's and get a job starting at ₹15,000/month or to choose an integrated programme of 4 years that would allow you to get a package starting at ₹30,000/month, then you are most likely to choose the second option. Even though there isn’t a difference between these two cases other than the time periods, your choice would potentially differ. This is because our brain can only distinguish between the present and the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether the future is three or four years down the lane, our brain fails to distinguish between them, because both are considered as far-sighted. Since our mind takes the future as uncertain it wants to make decisions for now, even though they might not be as beneficial. In economics, present bias is used when we talk about time inconsistency and discounting. Time inconsistency refers to the fact that individuals are inconsistent over time. That is, for instance, you decide to hit the gym next month, but when next month arrives, you are more likely to postpone it to another month. Thus, meaning that people aren't as rational in making decisions, but there are various social and psychological factors that govern their decisions. People have the tendency to change their choices, over different time periods even though the benefits remain the same. Richard H Thaler (a Nobel Prize Winner for his work in the field of behavioural economics) has conducted researches that show that economics and psychology are far more closely related than one can imagine, thus expanding the scope and importance of behavioural economics. He along with H M Shefrin wrote a paper titled &lt;em&gt;An Economic Theory of Self-control&lt;/em&gt; that introduced an economic model of self-control. This model explains that people aren't only lacking self-control when it comes to not buying new clothes, or when it comes to stopping with just another episode. But the lack of self-control can also be seen towards how people handle their finances, especially saving for their retirements before it gets late. To us, saving money seems more like a loss now even though it’ll benefit us in future, and thus people tend to postpone saving money. In fact, this research has led to various social policies to emerge to help people with saving their money from early days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since it is wired into our system to focus on what could harm us immediately, rather than what could harm us in the long-term, present bias manifests itself in many of our actions. The concept of present bias explains why we humans tend to make self-harming choices that provide us instant gratification but clearly have harmful consequences in the future. It also explains why we tend to ignore the importance of climate change, since it doesn't seem like an instant harm to our minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living in the present is important, but it isn't all we should be focused on. In reality, our lives are a combination of the past, present and future and therefore it becomes equally important to realise that the present is only a small piece in the puzzle of life. Understanding what present bias is, and how strongly it can control our decision making, allows us to be more aware of our own selves. It makes us realise that our brains aren't always thinking what's best for us and can quite a few times make impulsive decisions that might not seem so right in the years to come. Clearly, our brains are guided by the fear of the future, because of all the uncertainty it brings. So it only makes sense that we continue to ignore the future, and be in a more comfortable zone, the present. And honestly, instant gratification, no matter for how little of a time, does feel good. But it also feels fulfilling to make decisions that'll help our future selves. This is the dilemma that present bias poses. Whether to choose the time that we know of or to choose the time that'll come. It isn't easy to break away from our habits, especially the ones that are so well engraved in our nerves. Self-control and will power aren't as easily attained as we are likely to believe. But what we can do is to be more aware of how our brains have a tendency of fooling our own selves, and maybe for once not trust whatever our brain has to say.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Priyanshi Mehra</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Many times we wonder, what is it that makes us procrastinate? Why do we spend the whole day scrolling through Instagram instead of finishing the assignment that is due tomorrow? Apart from the fact that social media is designed to distract us, procrastinating isn't as simple as just being lazy. It isn't only about not wanting to do the task at hand, but more about how we humans are wired.&amp;nbsp; Procrastination is in fact related to a cognitive bias called the present bias. As the name in itself suggests, it is the tendency of humans to be biased towards the present. This means that we tend to go for short-term rewards that provide us instant gratification rather than choosing long-term benefits. Thus, even though the benefit of finishing that assignment is clearly more than simply being on Instagram, the sense of gratification is achieved faster in the latter. Therefore, our brain might as well trick us into choosing the latter. It is important to understand why humans are actually biased towards the present. The answer lies in how our ancestors lived their lives. The times they lived in, it only made sense that they focused on the present. With the uncertainty of the future and the environment they lived in, they had no other option but to be short-sighted in their decision making. This present bias allowed them to survive and deal with the immediate threats that existed around them. Over the centuries, this outlook of theirs seems to have been so well engraved in our brains that even today we have a similar mindset. Despite us having a far more stable lifestyle and a future to actually look forward to, our brain still makes us biased towards our present. It still makes us believe that the future is a scary avenue that one shouldn't be focusing much on it. The idea of the present bias has been studied by many researchers over the years, in order to understand to what extent such a bias can affect the lives of individuals. An interesting experiment in this field was conducted by Walter Mischel. This experiment that goes by the name of Marshmallow Test is a famous experiment which involved finding out whether children delayed gratification. It involved children being asked to either choose a marshmallow now or wait for 15-20 minutes to get two of them. This experiment, however, did not end here only. After a few years, these very children, who were by then adolescents, were traced and it was seen that the children who delayed gratification at a younger age were able to be more successful in the later period of their lives. Thus, shedding light on the connection between small decisions turning into a lifestyle. An interesting aspect of present bias is that it is not just limited to the field of psychology but also equally important for economics. Take for an example, if you were to choose between getting a job of ₹15,000/month now, or interning for free for a year and getting a job of ₹30,000/month. You are more likely to choose the former. But if you were asked to either complete your 3 years of Bachelor's and get a job starting at ₹15,000/month or to choose an integrated programme of 4 years that would allow you to get a package starting at ₹30,000/month, then you are most likely to choose the second option. Even though there isn’t a difference between these two cases other than the time periods, your choice would potentially differ. This is because our brain can only distinguish between the present and the future. Whether the future is three or four years down the lane, our brain fails to distinguish between them, because both are considered as far-sighted. Since our mind takes the future as uncertain it wants to make decisions for now, even though they might not be as beneficial. In economics, present bias is used when we talk about time inconsistency and discounting. Time inconsistency refers to the fact that individuals are inconsistent over time. That is, for instance, you decide to hit the gym next month, but when next month arrives, you are more likely to postpone it to another month. Thus, meaning that people aren't as rational in making decisions, but there are various social and psychological factors that govern their decisions. People have the tendency to change their choices, over different time periods even though the benefits remain the same. Richard H Thaler (a Nobel Prize Winner for his work in the field of behavioural economics) has conducted researches that show that economics and psychology are far more closely related than one can imagine, thus expanding the scope and importance of behavioural economics. He along with H M Shefrin wrote a paper titled An Economic Theory of Self-control that introduced an economic model of self-control. This model explains that people aren't only lacking self-control when it comes to not buying new clothes, or when it comes to stopping with just another episode. But the lack of self-control can also be seen towards how people handle their finances, especially saving for their retirements before it gets late. To us, saving money seems more like a loss now even though it’ll benefit us in future, and thus people tend to postpone saving money. In fact, this research has led to various social policies to emerge to help people with saving their money from early days. Since it is wired into our system to focus on what could harm us immediately, rather than what could harm us in the long-term, present bias manifests itself in many of our actions. The concept of present bias explains why we humans tend to make self-harming choices that provide us instant gratification but clearly have harmful consequences in the future. It also explains why we tend to ignore the importance of climate change, since it doesn't seem like an instant harm to our minds. Living in the present is important, but it isn't all we should be focused on. In reality, our lives are a combination of the past, present and future and therefore it becomes equally important to realise that the present is only a small piece in the puzzle of life. Understanding what present bias is, and how strongly it can control our decision making, allows us to be more aware of our own selves. It makes us realise that our brains aren't always thinking what's best for us and can quite a few times make impulsive decisions that might not seem so right in the years to come. Clearly, our brains are guided by the fear of the future, because of all the uncertainty it brings. So it only makes sense that we continue to ignore the future, and be in a more comfortable zone, the present. And honestly, instant gratification, no matter for how little of a time, does feel good. But it also feels fulfilling to make decisions that'll help our future selves. This is the dilemma that present bias poses. Whether to choose the time that we know of or to choose the time that'll come. It isn't easy to break away from our habits, especially the ones that are so well engraved in our nerves. Self-control and will power aren't as easily attained as we are likely to believe. But what we can do is to be more aware of how our brains have a tendency of fooling our own selves, and maybe for once not trust whatever our brain has to say.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Height of Oppression</title>
      <link href="/The-Height-of-Oppression" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Height of Oppression" />
      <published>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Height-of-Oppression</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Height-of-Oppression">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Heels are most often associated with femininity, and as a result, generally imposed on women for the sake of keeping up with the imagery. Multiple versions of the heel have been invented, such as pumps, stilettos, kitten heels and many more, and it is expected of women to wear heels to most places outside of the casual settings – their workspaces, fashion runways and extending, but not limited, to parties of differing natures. Multiple ceremonies and awards functions have a requirement that women must wear heels, the Cannes Film Festival in France is one of the biggest examples of this; one of their rules regarding the dress code stipulates that all women attendees must wear high heels in order to attend the ever so prestigious film festival. Over the years, several women celebrities have been stopped from attending the film festival for not wearing high heels. Not only such events but many companies, office places and restaurants require female employees to wear heels. There have been several instances of discrimination against women for their refusal to wear heels. For example, one such case of discrimination occurred when Nicola Thorp was fired by her manager for refusing to wear heels on her first day of work at an office job in London back in 2016. She was dressed in a suit and a pair of formal shoes. Shortly after she was fired, Thorp gained worldwide support for challenging the manager by filing a petition. The government concurred and felt that she had been discriminated against for not wearing heels, which is unlawful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Wearing heels has become common in this day and age, it is expected of women to wear exhaustingly high heels everywhere. But there is a question that arises, how much of this expectation to wear heels for formal occasions is justified? It is evident that women must have the freedom of choice to wear whichever footwear or clothing they feel most comfortable in. If a woman feels most comfortable while wearing heels, then that is a fully valid choice. But even in these progressive times, it is men who enjoy the very same freedom, i.e. the freedom of controlling what a woman has to wear in most situations. Most women do not expressly enjoy wearing heels every single day, the same footwear which can become extremely painful for a person to wear for a mere few hours. Aside from giving women a sense of authority and power while wearing heels, there seem to be no other evident benefits or signs of comfort for a woman to wear the same. The question arises, why do women continue wearing heels despite all the negative aspects, and there being no apparent need to? The answer to this lies in the oppression of women, which ultimately stems from the system of patriarchy which is persistent in remaining pervasive in society. In order to truly understand the reasons though, we must look at the history of the ‘heel,’ and the shift in society’s perspective regarding it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The history of heels can be traced back to the 3,500 BCE; where it was mostly the nobility who wore heels, as opposed to the common people who roamed around barefoot. Heels were also used for practical purposes, such as by butchers to ensure their feet did not come in contact with the blood or the meat of the animal. Heels were later on adopted by the Greeks and Romans to display the differences between different social classes, it is suggested that men belonging to the Middle East – who wore heels during wars while riding horses in order to get a better grip while shooting arrows – brought the concept of heels to Europe. Thus, European aristocracy soon thereafter realised that heels served a practical purpose of keeping their feet out of the mud. After all, it was mostly the higher classes who cared about protecting their feet from mud or dirt as a means to distinguish themselves from the lower classes whilst also serving a useful purpose at the same time. Both men and women had begun wearing heels around this time. Soon after the ‘chopines’ emerged, they were the first instance of platform heels that were invented. They were famous for being severely uncomfortable and hard to walk in, and often required the assistance of several men to help in walking. The chopines were the first heels that were specifically designed for women, but many feminists argue that they were invented to limit the movement of women and to ensure they do not leave their households as much. In addition to this, it became common practice to force Chinese concubines and Turkish odalisques to wear chopines in order to ensure that they would not flee. The very first example of men using heels to control the movement or freedom of women can be seen here.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up and until the 17th century, heels were most commonly worn by men. In the 18th century, however, when the idea of imperialism had started to spread around the world, men started to abandon heels. By the 19th century, heels went on to be recognised as something inherently feminine. Post the Second World War, Christian Dior came up with ‘stilettos,’ in which he used steel rods, raising the height of the heels to three inches or more. Since then, a multitude of designers such as Manolo Blahnik, Jimmy Choo, Alexander Mcqueen, and Christian Louboutin have invented different versions of the heel – all men designers scrambled to create a more elevated and much more impractical version of the heel. Designers who are known for creating quality heels usually happen to be men; the irony of men creating such footwear meant especially for women cannot go unnoticed. High heels are known and are proven to be harmful for a woman’s posture and feet, yet there is a persistent buildup of undue pressure on women to continue wearing heels. Christian Louboutin, when asked to comment upon the fact that heels are uncomfortable to walk in and slow a woman down, said, “&lt;em&gt;What is the point of wanting to run?&lt;/em&gt;” he continued, “&lt;em&gt;I am all for the pace getting slower, and high heels are very good for that.&lt;/em&gt;” That's right, ‘no point of women moving at a fast pace in a man’s world’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to a study conducted by the &lt;em&gt;American Orthopaedic Foot and Ankle Society&lt;/em&gt;, 50% of women experience daily pain from wearing their heels. Heels often put pressure on not only the feet but also the back, spines, knees and toes. High and tightly worn heels also cause blisters for a lot. Aside from this, heels can cause a myriad of other long-term problems as well, such as nerve damage and sciatica. Still, a majority of women continue wearing heels – either by their own choice or otherwise. In most parties or companies, men only feel obligated to wear suits with formal shoes; whereas women feel obligated to wear a dress and high heels as it shows ‘professional etiquette’, and many times dressing professionally can be mistaken with dressing uncomfortably just to please others. Although, women choose to wear heels most of the time as it may hand them a sense of ‘power’ and ‘authority,’ (heels are treated with a sense of hyper feminisation) but in most cases, women feel the need to abide by the invisible aura of the social construct.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Nowadays, due to the influence of the fashion industry that has capitalised off of the social construct created by the existence of heels for women, there is a shift or a transition in the way heels have started to be perceived by women in general - earlier, heels used to be treated as modes that were used by a very limited number of people whose usage of heels usually did not allow for free movement or allow for any comfort. Now, due to high-end designers coming up with more innovative heel designs and popularising the usage of heels, women perceive heels to be footwear that, when worn, can be empowering, bold, sexy and fashionable instead of simply being uncomfortable and constrictive.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2013, Louboutin told Vogue, “&lt;em&gt;It's almost three people who are different in terms of character. I never forget that shoes also have to please men. As a man, I totally understand looking at a girl and saying, “Darling, we're having dinner together tonight, so do you mind to change?” I understand that type of mentality from a man who loves his wife, his woman. He's concerned about the way you look. It's not an ugly thing. I understand also that a woman could not care. I like my design to please women, but also to please men.&lt;/em&gt;”&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His own words make it sound like women are meant to wear heels for ‘the male gaze,’ which seems to be the only somewhat reasonable explanation behind a woman wearing heels. This can be interpreted as women not having to be overly concerned with the way they look while wearing heels, it only matters as long as a man likes what his wife or girlfriend might be wearing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has become extremely normal to see women wearing extremely high heels in their everyday lives – no matter how unbearable it may be to walk in them. There will most likely not be any shift in society regarding the same, women will continue wearing heels for a long time. What can be normalised though, is ensuring that women need not feel as though they need to adhere to a certain set of expectations from society. The shift from heels being used mostly by men to then being used solely by women is a drastic one; and before we all start feminising heels to such a large extent, we must remember where they originated from and which of the two sexes wore them in the beginning, and also helped in popularising them all around the world. Heels have had a sexist and controlling past, traces of which can be seen in today’s time as well. One can only hope that fashion does not aid in the widening of the gap between men and women. At the end of the day, we must remember that gendered clothing and footwear are not defined by which sex dons the piece the most, but it is defined by how people aside from that specific gender view it. Heels can be worn by any sex or gender, but it happens to be attached to femininity.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pooja Bommareddy</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Heels are most often associated with femininity, and as a result, generally imposed on women for the sake of keeping up with the imagery. Multiple versions of the heel have been invented, such as pumps, stilettos, kitten heels and many more, and it is expected of women to wear heels to most places outside of the casual settings – their workspaces, fashion runways and extending, but not limited, to parties of differing natures. Multiple ceremonies and awards functions have a requirement that women must wear heels, the Cannes Film Festival in France is one of the biggest examples of this; one of their rules regarding the dress code stipulates that all women attendees must wear high heels in order to attend the ever so prestigious film festival. Over the years, several women celebrities have been stopped from attending the film festival for not wearing high heels. Not only such events but many companies, office places and restaurants require female employees to wear heels. There have been several instances of discrimination against women for their refusal to wear heels. For example, one such case of discrimination occurred when Nicola Thorp was fired by her manager for refusing to wear heels on her first day of work at an office job in London back in 2016. She was dressed in a suit and a pair of formal shoes. Shortly after she was fired, Thorp gained worldwide support for challenging the manager by filing a petition. The government concurred and felt that she had been discriminated against for not wearing heels, which is unlawful. Wearing heels has become common in this day and age, it is expected of women to wear exhaustingly high heels everywhere. But there is a question that arises, how much of this expectation to wear heels for formal occasions is justified? It is evident that women must have the freedom of choice to wear whichever footwear or clothing they feel most comfortable in. If a woman feels most comfortable while wearing heels, then that is a fully valid choice. But even in these progressive times, it is men who enjoy the very same freedom, i.e. the freedom of controlling what a woman has to wear in most situations. Most women do not expressly enjoy wearing heels every single day, the same footwear which can become extremely painful for a person to wear for a mere few hours. Aside from giving women a sense of authority and power while wearing heels, there seem to be no other evident benefits or signs of comfort for a woman to wear the same. The question arises, why do women continue wearing heels despite all the negative aspects, and there being no apparent need to? The answer to this lies in the oppression of women, which ultimately stems from the system of patriarchy which is persistent in remaining pervasive in society. In order to truly understand the reasons though, we must look at the history of the ‘heel,’ and the shift in society’s perspective regarding it.&amp;nbsp; The history of heels can be traced back to the 3,500 BCE; where it was mostly the nobility who wore heels, as opposed to the common people who roamed around barefoot. Heels were also used for practical purposes, such as by butchers to ensure their feet did not come in contact with the blood or the meat of the animal. Heels were later on adopted by the Greeks and Romans to display the differences between different social classes, it is suggested that men belonging to the Middle East – who wore heels during wars while riding horses in order to get a better grip while shooting arrows – brought the concept of heels to Europe. Thus, European aristocracy soon thereafter realised that heels served a practical purpose of keeping their feet out of the mud. After all, it was mostly the higher classes who cared about protecting their feet from mud or dirt as a means to distinguish themselves from the lower classes whilst also serving a useful purpose at the same time. Both men and women had begun wearing heels around this time. Soon after the ‘chopines’ emerged, they were the first instance of platform heels that were invented. They were famous for being severely uncomfortable and hard to walk in, and often required the assistance of several men to help in walking. The chopines were the first heels that were specifically designed for women, but many feminists argue that they were invented to limit the movement of women and to ensure they do not leave their households as much. In addition to this, it became common practice to force Chinese concubines and Turkish odalisques to wear chopines in order to ensure that they would not flee. The very first example of men using heels to control the movement or freedom of women can be seen here.&amp;nbsp; Up and until the 17th century, heels were most commonly worn by men. In the 18th century, however, when the idea of imperialism had started to spread around the world, men started to abandon heels. By the 19th century, heels went on to be recognised as something inherently feminine. Post the Second World War, Christian Dior came up with ‘stilettos,’ in which he used steel rods, raising the height of the heels to three inches or more. Since then, a multitude of designers such as Manolo Blahnik, Jimmy Choo, Alexander Mcqueen, and Christian Louboutin have invented different versions of the heel – all men designers scrambled to create a more elevated and much more impractical version of the heel. Designers who are known for creating quality heels usually happen to be men; the irony of men creating such footwear meant especially for women cannot go unnoticed. High heels are known and are proven to be harmful for a woman’s posture and feet, yet there is a persistent buildup of undue pressure on women to continue wearing heels. Christian Louboutin, when asked to comment upon the fact that heels are uncomfortable to walk in and slow a woman down, said, “What is the point of wanting to run?” he continued, “I am all for the pace getting slower, and high heels are very good for that.” That's right, ‘no point of women moving at a fast pace in a man’s world’. According to a study conducted by the American Orthopaedic Foot and Ankle Society, 50% of women experience daily pain from wearing their heels. Heels often put pressure on not only the feet but also the back, spines, knees and toes. High and tightly worn heels also cause blisters for a lot. Aside from this, heels can cause a myriad of other long-term problems as well, such as nerve damage and sciatica. Still, a majority of women continue wearing heels – either by their own choice or otherwise. In most parties or companies, men only feel obligated to wear suits with formal shoes; whereas women feel obligated to wear a dress and high heels as it shows ‘professional etiquette’, and many times dressing professionally can be mistaken with dressing uncomfortably just to please others. Although, women choose to wear heels most of the time as it may hand them a sense of ‘power’ and ‘authority,’ (heels are treated with a sense of hyper feminisation) but in most cases, women feel the need to abide by the invisible aura of the social construct.&amp;nbsp; Nowadays, due to the influence of the fashion industry that has capitalised off of the social construct created by the existence of heels for women, there is a shift or a transition in the way heels have started to be perceived by women in general - earlier, heels used to be treated as modes that were used by a very limited number of people whose usage of heels usually did not allow for free movement or allow for any comfort. Now, due to high-end designers coming up with more innovative heel designs and popularising the usage of heels, women perceive heels to be footwear that, when worn, can be empowering, bold, sexy and fashionable instead of simply being uncomfortable and constrictive.&amp;nbsp; In 2013, Louboutin told Vogue, “It's almost three people who are different in terms of character. I never forget that shoes also have to please men. As a man, I totally understand looking at a girl and saying, “Darling, we're having dinner together tonight, so do you mind to change?” I understand that type of mentality from a man who loves his wife, his woman. He's concerned about the way you look. It's not an ugly thing. I understand also that a woman could not care. I like my design to please women, but also to please men.”&amp;nbsp; His own words make it sound like women are meant to wear heels for ‘the male gaze,’ which seems to be the only somewhat reasonable explanation behind a woman wearing heels. This can be interpreted as women not having to be overly concerned with the way they look while wearing heels, it only matters as long as a man likes what his wife or girlfriend might be wearing.&amp;nbsp; It has become extremely normal to see women wearing extremely high heels in their everyday lives – no matter how unbearable it may be to walk in them. There will most likely not be any shift in society regarding the same, women will continue wearing heels for a long time. What can be normalised though, is ensuring that women need not feel as though they need to adhere to a certain set of expectations from society. The shift from heels being used mostly by men to then being used solely by women is a drastic one; and before we all start feminising heels to such a large extent, we must remember where they originated from and which of the two sexes wore them in the beginning, and also helped in popularising them all around the world. Heels have had a sexist and controlling past, traces of which can be seen in today’s time as well. One can only hope that fashion does not aid in the widening of the gap between men and women. At the end of the day, we must remember that gendered clothing and footwear are not defined by which sex dons the piece the most, but it is defined by how people aside from that specific gender view it. Heels can be worn by any sex or gender, but it happens to be attached to femininity.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Retelling of Childhood</title>
      <link href="/A-Retelling-of-Childhood" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Retelling of Childhood" />
      <published>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Retelling-of-Childhood</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Retelling-of-Childhood">&lt;p&gt;All of us have grown up with stories and tales aplenty - that our parents, grandparents and older siblings used to read to us. I had a little corner in my chest of drawers where I kept my A-3 sized colourfully illustrated books about the &lt;em&gt;Little Mermaid, Beauty and the Beast, Thumbelina, Cinderella&lt;/em&gt; and many others. I would take out one copy of those thin, 15-paged books and ask someone to read them to me or even give it a go at reading myself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a kid, I was fascinated with that world and maybe still haven’t lost my touch with it - because who doesn’t enjoy a good Disney&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;movie and some hot chocolate to go with it? Disney&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;is one such institution that has cemented and eternalised the stories that were written hundreds of years ago for children, now told and retold through years, they have changed into a different form - liked by people of all age groups.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A while back, I came across the writer behind these beloved stories - Hans Christian Anderson. Even though he revolutionised the world of storytelling through his selected works like - &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;em&gt; The Snow Queen &lt;/em&gt;(now adapted into the Disney production of &lt;em&gt;Frozen&lt;/em&gt;) and&lt;em&gt; The Ugly Duckling &lt;/em&gt;- his work is criticised for being unfit for children. Now that his work, that dates back to 1835, has been adapted into so many plays, productions and movies, one would think that he used to write perfect fairy tales for a blissful childhood. However, the truth is a bit far from that. Anderson is known for his dark and bitter tales that were written for children but without any filters - just blatant truth and atrocities staring oneself in the face.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anderson was born and raised in Denmark in a poor family to a shoemaker father and an illiterate washerwoman mother. Still, he persisted with his education at the local school for the poor, and at night used to listen to the tales of the &lt;em&gt;Arabian Nights&lt;/em&gt; from his father. He had a rough go at childhood and had to move out and provide for himself at an early age - the pain of which is reflected in his early-written pieces. The first and original edition of his stories is unlike the retold versions of them in many ways. For starters, his stories were not as happy-go-lucky as we see them now to be. &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt;, a classic tale of love and redemption, was actually a disturbing and morbid tale about a mermaid who makes a diabolical bargain with a sea witch and suffers her tongue to be cut out and her tail to be lost, all for the love of a prince. Unfortunately, he completely fails to recognise the enormity of her sacrifice and love for him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Disney film adaption of this tale was morphed into a story about love which always unites, as Ariel and Eric get together in the end, and she leaves her world to be with him. Even though Anderson’s story was bitter, it was realistic because it told you that life doesn’t always give you what or whom you desire, and that it’s not okay to give up your life and the things that make you who you are for anyone - because that never ends well. It reflected that no sacrifice will get you eternal love but maybe patience, time and consent would. Even the tale of &lt;em&gt;Thumbelina&lt;/em&gt; was that of grave pain and a torturous existence, unlike the popular idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might not have understood that as a kid, but if something is repeatedly told, from a young age then it can have an impact on you in many ways. The debate around protecting kids from bad and traumatic things is acceptable and justified, but only as long as the truth is harmful to them. If not, even kids have a right to be exposed to the right and wrong of life, to disappointment and failure - so that they learn to take something from it instead of thinking of it as the end. A lot of Anderson’s stories were changed for this reason alone. Because his stories did not twist the truth into entangled sentences about a utopian world but told them things that everyone should know - the reality of this harsh world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only Anderson’s, but many of children’s tales and stories are moulded according to what adults deem right; in fact, some are banned or censored too. A children’s book by the name of &lt;em&gt;And Tango Makes Three&lt;/em&gt; written by Parnell and Richardson was published in 2005, after a real-life incident that occurred in the Central Park Zoo of New York, where two male, chinstrap penguins, Roy and Silo fell in love. The book tells the story of these two male penguins who&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;create a family together. With the help of the zookeeper, Mr Gramsay, Roy and Silo are given an egg which they help hatch. The female chick, that completes their family, is consequently named 'Tango' by the zookeepers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book wasn’t received well by many parents, because according to them, homosexuality in animals suggested homosexuality in humans as well. They argued that they weren’t able to explain to their kids as to why “&lt;em&gt;a male penguin has a baby with another male penguin instead of a mommy penguin&lt;/em&gt;”. After retaliation from parents across the world, the book was consequently banned in Singapore, Hong Kong and places across the United States, like Utah, Missouri and Massachusetts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ql-cursor&quot;&gt;﻿It is these ingrained notions and our discomfort with the truth that anything different from what we consider ‘normal’, we try to hide from kids instead of having a conversation with them which they might be completely open to.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;p&gt;The question that wavers in my mind is, ‘how much of reality is too much’ to be introduced to children? The reason those stories were changed is that it was considered unfit and inappropriate for a child’s brains. Which might be true from one vantage point, however, why must children be veiled from the realities of the world until a certain age only to be exposed to them suddenly at one go? What is really the right age to see the world in its face?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve always wondered how fair it is to concoct a picture of a world that only disappoints you when you grow up. One, it creates unreal expectations from the world and two, it teaches you things that should be shattered as a concept early on while growing up - be it a princess being saved by the valiant hero at the end, kissing someone without their consent (&lt;em&gt;The Sleeping Beauty&lt;/em&gt;) or having to be perfect for people to like you.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I go back and forth in my mind as to why we think of children as weak or want to shield them from the truth? According to many child psychologists, the impulse to protect kids from unpleasant facts is similar to the self-esteem fad practised by educators. The idea rests on the assumption, not backed by any evidence, that high self-esteem must lead to high academic achievement. Similarly, the instinct to protect children from anything unpleasant is simply out of one’s idea of what a child should and shouldn’t know.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But if one asks themselves, is this reality protecting your child from long-term pain or is just an area of discussion that you don’t want to deal with, or better answer, and so you choose what is convenient - that is, to digress, to lie and to manoeuvre. You leave your children to figure out the jarring and upsetting realities of life by themselves as they grow up. And more often than not, the sources through which your children consume all the things that were hidden from them during their nascent years are not the most reliable or truthful sources. Thus, as we grow up, we are ambushed with facts and to find answers to them we tend to rely on treacherous sources which skew our ideas all the more. Instead of nurturing our kids with righteousness and practicality from the beginning, we try to mask them from facts, for as long as possible - which might not help them as much as one would hope.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The thing about the ‘real’ world is that unlike fairytales, it’s flawed and filled with imperfections. Which is what drives life ahead, the little or large hiccups in the flow of life. From Anderson’s stories to the truth about sexuality, identity, religion and relationships - a lot is made inconspicuous for the kids so that the information dissemination is controlled according to the norms that we have constructed and reaches them in a palatable form. But the question remains: who gets to decide what is right or wrong for these kids? Are flowery stories with morals sieved through our model of heteronormativity, appropriate culture and paradigms of acceptable behaviour the way to go about raising our kids? Only to impel them later into a world where they stumble as they go through life deconstructing their thoughts and knowledge, indoctrinated throughout childhood and then rebuilding it in a frenzy of emotions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wonder if it would’ve been better, had my parents read me stories of women who didn’t enforce ideals of self-sacrifice to find the truest form of love or tales of women and people in general, who didn’t settle for anything less than what they deserved, did not change themselves only to be accepted by society, and stories that told that life’s utmost purpose was not to find a perfect partner but to find yourself. And in the process of that, you will meet people who will make life worthwhile. But not one of the stories told us, that it is very much okay, even if you don’t. Because in life, there is no blueprint or algorithm like in stories - all the milestones of life are supposed to make your journey easier and not all the more pressurizing. So the moral of this article is maybe that it is okay to chart your own path - because if you find yourself not fitting in with any of the existing stories, you can always write a new one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">All of us have grown up with stories and tales aplenty - that our parents, grandparents and older siblings used to read to us. I had a little corner in my chest of drawers where I kept my A-3 sized colourfully illustrated books about the Little Mermaid, Beauty and the Beast, Thumbelina, Cinderella and many others. I would take out one copy of those thin, 15-paged books and ask someone to read them to me or even give it a go at reading myself.&amp;nbsp; As a kid, I was fascinated with that world and maybe still haven’t lost my touch with it - because who doesn’t enjoy a good Disney movie and some hot chocolate to go with it? Disney is one such institution that has cemented and eternalised the stories that were written hundreds of years ago for children, now told and retold through years, they have changed into a different form - liked by people of all age groups.&amp;nbsp; A while back, I came across the writer behind these beloved stories - Hans Christian Anderson. Even though he revolutionised the world of storytelling through his selected works like - The Little Mermaid, The Snow Queen (now adapted into the Disney production of Frozen) and The Ugly Duckling - his work is criticised for being unfit for children. Now that his work, that dates back to 1835, has been adapted into so many plays, productions and movies, one would think that he used to write perfect fairy tales for a blissful childhood. However, the truth is a bit far from that. Anderson is known for his dark and bitter tales that were written for children but without any filters - just blatant truth and atrocities staring oneself in the face.&amp;nbsp; Anderson was born and raised in Denmark in a poor family to a shoemaker father and an illiterate washerwoman mother. Still, he persisted with his education at the local school for the poor, and at night used to listen to the tales of the Arabian Nights from his father. He had a rough go at childhood and had to move out and provide for himself at an early age - the pain of which is reflected in his early-written pieces. The first and original edition of his stories is unlike the retold versions of them in many ways. For starters, his stories were not as happy-go-lucky as we see them now to be. The Little Mermaid, a classic tale of love and redemption, was actually a disturbing and morbid tale about a mermaid who makes a diabolical bargain with a sea witch and suffers her tongue to be cut out and her tail to be lost, all for the love of a prince. Unfortunately, he completely fails to recognise the enormity of her sacrifice and love for him. The Disney film adaption of this tale was morphed into a story about love which always unites, as Ariel and Eric get together in the end, and she leaves her world to be with him. Even though Anderson’s story was bitter, it was realistic because it told you that life doesn’t always give you what or whom you desire, and that it’s not okay to give up your life and the things that make you who you are for anyone - because that never ends well. It reflected that no sacrifice will get you eternal love but maybe patience, time and consent would. Even the tale of Thumbelina was that of grave pain and a torturous existence, unlike the popular idea. I might not have understood that as a kid, but if something is repeatedly told, from a young age then it can have an impact on you in many ways. The debate around protecting kids from bad and traumatic things is acceptable and justified, but only as long as the truth is harmful to them. If not, even kids have a right to be exposed to the right and wrong of life, to disappointment and failure - so that they learn to take something from it instead of thinking of it as the end. A lot of Anderson’s stories were changed for this reason alone. Because his stories did not twist the truth into entangled sentences about a utopian world but told them things that everyone should know - the reality of this harsh world. Not only Anderson’s, but many of children’s tales and stories are moulded according to what adults deem right; in fact, some are banned or censored too. A children’s book by the name of And Tango Makes Three written by Parnell and Richardson was published in 2005, after a real-life incident that occurred in the Central Park Zoo of New York, where two male, chinstrap penguins, Roy and Silo fell in love. The book tells the story of these two male penguins who create a family together. With the help of the zookeeper, Mr Gramsay, Roy and Silo are given an egg which they help hatch. The female chick, that completes their family, is consequently named 'Tango' by the zookeepers.&amp;nbsp; This book wasn’t received well by many parents, because according to them, homosexuality in animals suggested homosexuality in humans as well. They argued that they weren’t able to explain to their kids as to why “a male penguin has a baby with another male penguin instead of a mommy penguin”. After retaliation from parents across the world, the book was consequently banned in Singapore, Hong Kong and places across the United States, like Utah, Missouri and Massachusetts. ﻿It is these ingrained notions and our discomfort with the truth that anything different from what we consider ‘normal’, we try to hide from kids instead of having a conversation with them which they might be completely open to.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;The question that wavers in my mind is, ‘how much of reality is too much’ to be introduced to children? The reason those stories were changed is that it was considered unfit and inappropriate for a child’s brains. Which might be true from one vantage point, however, why must children be veiled from the realities of the world until a certain age only to be exposed to them suddenly at one go? What is really the right age to see the world in its face?&amp;nbsp;I’ve always wondered how fair it is to concoct a picture of a world that only disappoints you when you grow up. One, it creates unreal expectations from the world and two, it teaches you things that should be shattered as a concept early on while growing up - be it a princess being saved by the valiant hero at the end, kissing someone without their consent (The Sleeping Beauty) or having to be perfect for people to like you.&amp;nbsp;I go back and forth in my mind as to why we think of children as weak or want to shield them from the truth? According to many child psychologists, the impulse to protect kids from unpleasant facts is similar to the self-esteem fad practised by educators. The idea rests on the assumption, not backed by any evidence, that high self-esteem must lead to high academic achievement. Similarly, the instinct to protect children from anything unpleasant is simply out of one’s idea of what a child should and shouldn’t know.&amp;nbsp;But if one asks themselves, is this reality protecting your child from long-term pain or is just an area of discussion that you don’t want to deal with, or better answer, and so you choose what is convenient - that is, to digress, to lie and to manoeuvre. You leave your children to figure out the jarring and upsetting realities of life by themselves as they grow up. And more often than not, the sources through which your children consume all the things that were hidden from them during their nascent years are not the most reliable or truthful sources. Thus, as we grow up, we are ambushed with facts and to find answers to them we tend to rely on treacherous sources which skew our ideas all the more. Instead of nurturing our kids with righteousness and practicality from the beginning, we try to mask them from facts, for as long as possible - which might not help them as much as one would hope.&amp;nbsp;The thing about the ‘real’ world is that unlike fairytales, it’s flawed and filled with imperfections. Which is what drives life ahead, the little or large hiccups in the flow of life. From Anderson’s stories to the truth about sexuality, identity, religion and relationships - a lot is made inconspicuous for the kids so that the information dissemination is controlled according to the norms that we have constructed and reaches them in a palatable form. But the question remains: who gets to decide what is right or wrong for these kids? Are flowery stories with morals sieved through our model of heteronormativity, appropriate culture and paradigms of acceptable behaviour the way to go about raising our kids? Only to impel them later into a world where they stumble as they go through life deconstructing their thoughts and knowledge, indoctrinated throughout childhood and then rebuilding it in a frenzy of emotions.I wonder if it would’ve been better, had my parents read me stories of women who didn’t enforce ideals of self-sacrifice to find the truest form of love or tales of women and people in general, who didn’t settle for anything less than what they deserved, did not change themselves only to be accepted by society, and stories that told that life’s utmost purpose was not to find a perfect partner but to find yourself. And in the process of that, you will meet people who will make life worthwhile. But not one of the stories told us, that it is very much okay, even if you don’t. Because in life, there is no blueprint or algorithm like in stories - all the milestones of life are supposed to make your journey easier and not all the more pressurizing. So the moral of this article is maybe that it is okay to chart your own path - because if you find yourself not fitting in with any of the existing stories, you can always write a new one.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Do People Still Listen to Radio in 2020?: A Decentralised Understanding of Radio Broadcasting in India</title>
      <link href="/Do-People-Still-Listen-to-Radio-in-2020" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do People Still Listen to Radio in 2020?: A Decentralised Understanding of Radio Broadcasting in India " />
      <published>2020-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Do-People-Still-Listen-to-Radio-in-2020</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Do-People-Still-Listen-to-Radio-in-2020">&lt;p&gt;Mass media is generally used to disseminate information through various modes of communication. It helps in the exchange of ideas and information to large segments of society. Broadcast is a field of mass communication that transmits information, imparts knowledge and helps in creating a dialogue between the news agency and the audience via mediums like radio and television. The term ‘broadcast’ refers to visual or audio content dispersion to the people through electronic communication in a one-to-many module.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Radio as a Mass Medium&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Known as the ‘theatre of mind’, radio is the most pervasive, accessible and affordable mass media available in the developing world. It networks developing programmes to diverse populations and connects them all on the national and international levels. It is a cheap alternative to the glamourous mediums that have evolved with technology. The radio still remains a potential driver of information and entertainment to highly targeted audiences such as the rural population. Especially in a developing country, like India, this plays a major role in spreading information because most of the rural population is generally left bereft of the newer mechanisms.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evolution of Radio&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objective of the first radio program in India which was transmitted by the Madras Presidency Radio Club (MPRC) and led by C V Krishnaswami Cheti, was to stimulate interest, inform and instruct the public, and to foster the study of radio communications in the presidency. With the approval being given for the privatisation of radio media organisations by the British colonial government, the Indian Broadcasting Company set up radio stations in Calcutta and Bombay. In 1936, this corporation was renamed All India Radio (AIR), and when India became independent in 1947, AIR became a separate department under the Ministry of Information and Broadcasting. Presently, radio broadcasting gets coverage in 24 languages and 146 dialects all across India. 111 million households own a radio set in the country. Regional radio has reached all states individually, catering to its colloquial audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://d2r2ijn7njrktv.cloudfront.net/IL/uploads/2017/02/community-radio.jpg&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/community-radio.jpg&quot; /&gt;Community Radio stations are popular among all age groups and used extensively to spread awareness.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local Broadcasting: Community Radio&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It refers to a type of radio service that caters to the interests of a particular person in an area. The primary focus is on the local population and issues concerning them. Use of broadcast here acts as a link between the community problems and the authorities who can do something about the resolution of the same. Community radio is a broadcast tool that is of the people, by the people and for the people. It is a decentralised use of the larger medium of communication, that is, the radio. It is important to talk about community radio in today’s times as it provides a platform to the local people to become citizen journalists and educate themselves and their fellow beings. While FM Radio caters to the urban population mostly, community radio’s target audience includes rural, urban, suburban, regional and sectional communities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Radio Udaan &lt;/strong&gt;is an example of community radio. Launched in 2014, it is an online radio station developed by and for specially-abled people. &amp;nbsp;It is the only type of radio station that is run by visually challenged people and is widely listened to in more than 115 countries. The vision of the radio station is broad and its agendas are diverse, which is- “&lt;em&gt;To entertain, empower and elevate the listeners. Radio Udaan aims to reach out to maximum possible people. It wants to become not only a supplier of entertainment and knowledge to the listeners but also a part of their daily routine, family and lifestyle. The station seeks to shoulder the burdens of its listeners by empowering them and listening to their stories and problems, and eventually catering them solutions&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apno Radio, 90.4 MHz, Rajasthan &lt;/strong&gt;was launched in 2005 and is Rajasthan’s first community radio station. The station’s objective is to promote self-reliance and women's empowerment. It focuses on several social issues ailing the rural communities of the state such as education, health, nutrition, environment, agriculture, depicting folk, art, culture, rural and community development.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is Radio Dying?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the millennials in urban life devote their maximum time to Apple Music and Spotify, this question often pops up with “yes” as an answer to it. However, that is not true. Radio is not dying but rather it is evolving. The term ‘Tradigital’ (traditional plus digital) is assigned to this evolution wherein traditional radio stations are using digital media platforms for two reasons - one, to expand their audience reach and two, to keep up with the technology and not let the broadcasting medium which has a reach of over 100 million people in India die because of the takeover by bigger and international online streaming platforms, television and satellite revolution. The newer versions of mass communications generally caters to a literate population with access to higher-end devices and it must be acknowledged that radio initially started to educate the uneducated and still plays a pivotal role in doing this duty as a medium of communication. Recognition of local broadcasting is crucial to its development and as we talk more about ‘Communication as a Development Source’ in the 21st century, community reach can boost the country’s process to achieve 2030 Sustainable Development Goals by imparting knowledge in a decentralised manner to the regional sections. Moreover, radio acts as a tool for both development and freedom which provides a platform for people to exercise their freedom of speech and expression, uphold the liberty of thought, especially with the growth of community radio.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand this better, I would like to connect this with a media theory called the Knowledge Gap Theory of 1970. It is the brainchild of Philip J Tichenor, George A Donohue and Clarice N Olien. They explained the Knowledge Gap theory as “&lt;em&gt;the infusion of mass media information into a social system where higher socioeconomic status segments tend to acquire this information faster than lower socioeconomic status population segments. Hence&amp;nbsp;the&amp;nbsp;gap between the two tends to increase rather than decrease.&lt;/em&gt;” In 2020, these faster modes of communication can be through the accessibility of various sources of information. The availability of these mediums come with a price tag and not everyone can afford it. Radio and especially the growing community radio has revolutionised news delivery in various parts of the country that do not get the proper mainstream coverage in the primetime and are highly underrepresented and neglected in the little coverage that they receive. The only way to connect to the grassroots is by reducing this knowledge gap with a tool of communication. This is where the power of radio lies, in the heart of the community people who use this broadcasting medium to connect and embrace positive change in their society. A boost to a media platform which caters to the lower rungs of the socio-economic ladder is necessary in these times when inequality and unemployment are raging and the youth is being fed with narratives filled with hatred and bigotry. This medium can be the harbinger of change in the society for the better, we just have to care enough about the people left behind to dedicate ourselves to such discourse. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Himanshi Saini</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Mass media is generally used to disseminate information through various modes of communication. It helps in the exchange of ideas and information to large segments of society. Broadcast is a field of mass communication that transmits information, imparts knowledge and helps in creating a dialogue between the news agency and the audience via mediums like radio and television. The term ‘broadcast’ refers to visual or audio content dispersion to the people through electronic communication in a one-to-many module.&amp;nbsp; Radio as a Mass Medium Known as the ‘theatre of mind’, radio is the most pervasive, accessible and affordable mass media available in the developing world. It networks developing programmes to diverse populations and connects them all on the national and international levels. It is a cheap alternative to the glamourous mediums that have evolved with technology. The radio still remains a potential driver of information and entertainment to highly targeted audiences such as the rural population. Especially in a developing country, like India, this plays a major role in spreading information because most of the rural population is generally left bereft of the newer mechanisms.&amp;nbsp; Evolution of Radio The objective of the first radio program in India which was transmitted by the Madras Presidency Radio Club (MPRC) and led by C V Krishnaswami Cheti, was to stimulate interest, inform and instruct the public, and to foster the study of radio communications in the presidency. With the approval being given for the privatisation of radio media organisations by the British colonial government, the Indian Broadcasting Company set up radio stations in Calcutta and Bombay. In 1936, this corporation was renamed All India Radio (AIR), and when India became independent in 1947, AIR became a separate department under the Ministry of Information and Broadcasting. Presently, radio broadcasting gets coverage in 24 languages and 146 dialects all across India. 111 million households own a radio set in the country. Regional radio has reached all states individually, catering to its colloquial audience. Community Radio stations are popular among all age groups and used extensively to spread awareness. Local Broadcasting: Community Radio&amp;nbsp; It refers to a type of radio service that caters to the interests of a particular person in an area. The primary focus is on the local population and issues concerning them. Use of broadcast here acts as a link between the community problems and the authorities who can do something about the resolution of the same. Community radio is a broadcast tool that is of the people, by the people and for the people. It is a decentralised use of the larger medium of communication, that is, the radio. It is important to talk about community radio in today’s times as it provides a platform to the local people to become citizen journalists and educate themselves and their fellow beings. While FM Radio caters to the urban population mostly, community radio’s target audience includes rural, urban, suburban, regional and sectional communities.&amp;nbsp; Radio Udaan is an example of community radio. Launched in 2014, it is an online radio station developed by and for specially-abled people. &amp;nbsp;It is the only type of radio station that is run by visually challenged people and is widely listened to in more than 115 countries. The vision of the radio station is broad and its agendas are diverse, which is- “To entertain, empower and elevate the listeners. Radio Udaan aims to reach out to maximum possible people. It wants to become not only a supplier of entertainment and knowledge to the listeners but also a part of their daily routine, family and lifestyle. The station seeks to shoulder the burdens of its listeners by empowering them and listening to their stories and problems, and eventually catering them solutions.” Apno Radio, 90.4 MHz, Rajasthan was launched in 2005 and is Rajasthan’s first community radio station. The station’s objective is to promote self-reliance and women's empowerment. It focuses on several social issues ailing the rural communities of the state such as education, health, nutrition, environment, agriculture, depicting folk, art, culture, rural and community development.&amp;nbsp; Is Radio Dying? While the millennials in urban life devote their maximum time to Apple Music and Spotify, this question often pops up with “yes” as an answer to it. However, that is not true. Radio is not dying but rather it is evolving. The term ‘Tradigital’ (traditional plus digital) is assigned to this evolution wherein traditional radio stations are using digital media platforms for two reasons - one, to expand their audience reach and two, to keep up with the technology and not let the broadcasting medium which has a reach of over 100 million people in India die because of the takeover by bigger and international online streaming platforms, television and satellite revolution. The newer versions of mass communications generally caters to a literate population with access to higher-end devices and it must be acknowledged that radio initially started to educate the uneducated and still plays a pivotal role in doing this duty as a medium of communication. Recognition of local broadcasting is crucial to its development and as we talk more about ‘Communication as a Development Source’ in the 21st century, community reach can boost the country’s process to achieve 2030 Sustainable Development Goals by imparting knowledge in a decentralised manner to the regional sections. Moreover, radio acts as a tool for both development and freedom which provides a platform for people to exercise their freedom of speech and expression, uphold the liberty of thought, especially with the growth of community radio.&amp;nbsp; To understand this better, I would like to connect this with a media theory called the Knowledge Gap Theory of 1970. It is the brainchild of Philip J Tichenor, George A Donohue and Clarice N Olien. They explained the Knowledge Gap theory as “the infusion of mass media information into a social system where higher socioeconomic status segments tend to acquire this information faster than lower socioeconomic status population segments. Hence&amp;nbsp;the&amp;nbsp;gap between the two tends to increase rather than decrease.” In 2020, these faster modes of communication can be through the accessibility of various sources of information. The availability of these mediums come with a price tag and not everyone can afford it. Radio and especially the growing community radio has revolutionised news delivery in various parts of the country that do not get the proper mainstream coverage in the primetime and are highly underrepresented and neglected in the little coverage that they receive. The only way to connect to the grassroots is by reducing this knowledge gap with a tool of communication. This is where the power of radio lies, in the heart of the community people who use this broadcasting medium to connect and embrace positive change in their society. A boost to a media platform which caters to the lower rungs of the socio-economic ladder is necessary in these times when inequality and unemployment are raging and the youth is being fed with narratives filled with hatred and bigotry. This medium can be the harbinger of change in the society for the better, we just have to care enough about the people left behind to dedicate ourselves to such discourse.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Jewish Persecution Through the Ages</title>
      <link href="/Jewish-Persecution-Through-the-Ages" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jewish Persecution Through the Ages" />
      <published>2020-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Jewish-Persecution-Through-the-Ages</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Jewish-Persecution-Through-the-Ages">&lt;p&gt;By our very nature, we humans have the tendency to adapt and mould everything to suit our purpose. We have razed mountains to rubble, developed sustainable civilisations, and harnessed various forces of nature to our service. We need to see the world in a way that makes sense to us because not knowing what’s out there is one of the worst fears of humankind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anomalously, this theory also explains both the cause of developments and the inevitable resistance a society poses to them. Some individuals through their efforts generate new and more plausible explanations of existing phenomena. However, society generally fixates on the traditional notions and feels somewhat threatened by the existence of a new answer - something they’re completely ignorant of.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, advancement in human society is also characterised by free-will and greater acceptance of one’s beliefs and perception. So, the only thing that needs to be decided upon is - do the benefits and costs of clinging onto traditionality and remaining in the comfort zone outweigh that of adapting to developments and being more receptive?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after considering the sentiment of people and the factor of coincidence in the associated events and stories, all the scientific evidence points to the fact that religion is a product of human psychology. People want to make sense of the immeasurable number of interdependent or independent events that take place in the world around them and when they believe they have hit a dead end, they instinctively correlate them with the supernatural or the divine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this theory in its own capacity poses a very interesting philosophical question - why are people willing to mortify, hurt, torture or even kill fellow human beings when there is a very high chance that the argument which they believe absolves them of these crimes may be rooted in ignorance?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ql-cursor&quot;&gt;﻿Jews, throughout history, have been one of the most abused communities around the world. The Greeks did it, the Roman did it, even fellow monothesitics like Christians and Muslims did it, but they were all eventually put to shame by Hitler.&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;p&gt;Monotheistic cultures are widely popular today. When it comes to suitability to the highly dynamic lifestyle of the modern world, they check almost all the boxes. Yet, the forerunners of the bunch - Christianity and Islam - made meagre efforts for upliftment of the Jewish community in their respective reigns over the Middle East and Europe. Also, an important point to mention is that Judaism, Christianity and Islam are highly analogous. Christianity revamped the Jewish ideologies and labeled them as their own, and Islam did the same to Christianity. The fundamental religious doctrine is the same in all three of them, and concepts like prophets, heaven, hell, etc. are fairly consistent. This further intensifies the nefariousness of the former's actions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moreover, it won’t be completely fair to blame this history of blatant inhumanity on poor governance as the laws of that time made no clear cut distinction between the state and the apex religious body. Therefore, it is the medieval thought process of these communities that is to be blamed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ancient Greek and Roman societies were governed by a class of strong believers in polytheism. They prayed to their gods in temples, made blood sacrifices, and tried their best to live their lives by the stories they heard about them. The arrival of monotheistic faith, whose beliefs and practices were not even remotely close to theirs, was not well received by them. Public executions, selective poll tax, and defilement of synagogues were a common method to overrule the other belief system. Jews were expelled from the city and some Roman emperors went to the length of declaring the possession of Jewish scriptures a capital crime. Such acts of hostility, though morally incoherent, can be justified rationally by the fundamental pattern of society's initial reaction to change in any case whatsoever. Moreover, Jews were not the only monotheists being harassed, the Romans reacted similarly to Christianity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moving up the timeline, Rome was Christianised in the late 300 AD and the capital of the Christian stronghold was established in Constantinople, Byzantine. In the late 600 AD, Islam came into being in the Arabian region of the Middle East and started growing rapidly owing to the expansionary crusades of Mohammad and the succeeding Muslim leaders. Jewish groups in Byzantine were treated as aliens for their disbelief in the absolution of Christianity. Their social standing and religious liberty varied with the ruler. Eventually, Islamic leaders reached the borders of Byzantine (Christianized Rome) and toppled the rule of Christians who retaliated with a series of crusades to reclaim the holy lands. All of the conflict lasted for about 200 years and the Jewish community was dishevelled as a byproduct. Muslim rulers aggressively imposed Islamic credo upon them and whenever Christians invaded as a result of the crusades, they wiped entire Jewish colonies off the map.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The situation was especially bad in Persia, as under the prejudice of being spiritually unclean, Jews were forced to live in ghettos outside of towns. They were not allowed to enter shops, and even if they managed to, they were not allowed to touch or inspect any item. If the latter was to happen, the laws clearly stated that the Jew was obligated to buy the product and the seller had an absolute right of charging as much as they wanted. Also, Jews were not allowed to roam the cities during rain, as it was believed that the&amp;nbsp; dirt of their spirituality would wash down with the raindrops and rub off on the locals who walked the same paths.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the middle ages rolled in, anti-semitic groups evolved their methods of suppression, as they started destroying the political standing of the Jews and catalysed it for their physical extermination. During the Black Death period, orthodox Crhritian and Muslim groups in the middle east accused Jews of poisoning the wells within cities and orchestrating the plague. These accusations were used to make initial arrests, upon which the prisoners were tortured and threatened into confessing to crimes that they never committed. Even for executions, slow death methods like public stoning &amp;amp; death by fire were used. As a final touch of cruelty, their respective properties and places of worship were seized without cause and converted into churches, mosques, and libraries.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to the 1940’s. Religious and racial fanaticism had poisoned Germany. Almost everyone is aware of the horrific ordeal that Hitler and his racial political agendas put Jews through - pogroms, mass shootings, concentration camps and the gas chambers. When the dust settled, two-thirds of the European Jewish population had been exterminated- “genocide” in the perfect sense of the word. The scapegoating does not end there, as Jews were also blamed for capitalism and excessively controlling the american financial market via their dominance of the premiere financial institutions of the time like Rothschilds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even today, the other communities prey on Jews for conversions. Their faith is still undermined and their rights as members of the society are still kept subservient to those of other cultures. It is imperative to understand that the concept of “sustainability”- a term which is amassing a lot of popularity lately- is not selective. Developing a world where everyone is willing to live their life of their own volition is the very foundation of the term. Therefore, security and free will for some and impositions on others is a betrayal to the very essence of sustainability as it makes the society more prone to implosion rather than consolidation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aryaman Dhiman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">By our very nature, we humans have the tendency to adapt and mould everything to suit our purpose. We have razed mountains to rubble, developed sustainable civilisations, and harnessed various forces of nature to our service. We need to see the world in a way that makes sense to us because not knowing what’s out there is one of the worst fears of humankind. Anomalously, this theory also explains both the cause of developments and the inevitable resistance a society poses to them. Some individuals through their efforts generate new and more plausible explanations of existing phenomena. However, society generally fixates on the traditional notions and feels somewhat threatened by the existence of a new answer - something they’re completely ignorant of.&amp;nbsp; In retrospect, advancement in human society is also characterised by free-will and greater acceptance of one’s beliefs and perception. So, the only thing that needs to be decided upon is - do the benefits and costs of clinging onto traditionality and remaining in the comfort zone outweigh that of adapting to developments and being more receptive? Even after considering the sentiment of people and the factor of coincidence in the associated events and stories, all the scientific evidence points to the fact that religion is a product of human psychology. People want to make sense of the immeasurable number of interdependent or independent events that take place in the world around them and when they believe they have hit a dead end, they instinctively correlate them with the supernatural or the divine. Now, this theory in its own capacity poses a very interesting philosophical question - why are people willing to mortify, hurt, torture or even kill fellow human beings when there is a very high chance that the argument which they believe absolves them of these crimes may be rooted in ignorance?&amp;nbsp; ﻿Jews, throughout history, have been one of the most abused communities around the world. The Greeks did it, the Roman did it, even fellow monothesitics like Christians and Muslims did it, but they were all eventually put to shame by Hitler.&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;Monotheistic cultures are widely popular today. When it comes to suitability to the highly dynamic lifestyle of the modern world, they check almost all the boxes. Yet, the forerunners of the bunch - Christianity and Islam - made meagre efforts for upliftment of the Jewish community in their respective reigns over the Middle East and Europe. Also, an important point to mention is that Judaism, Christianity and Islam are highly analogous. Christianity revamped the Jewish ideologies and labeled them as their own, and Islam did the same to Christianity. The fundamental religious doctrine is the same in all three of them, and concepts like prophets, heaven, hell, etc. are fairly consistent. This further intensifies the nefariousness of the former's actions.&amp;nbsp;Moreover, it won’t be completely fair to blame this history of blatant inhumanity on poor governance as the laws of that time made no clear cut distinction between the state and the apex religious body. Therefore, it is the medieval thought process of these communities that is to be blamed.&amp;nbsp;Ancient Greek and Roman societies were governed by a class of strong believers in polytheism. They prayed to their gods in temples, made blood sacrifices, and tried their best to live their lives by the stories they heard about them. The arrival of monotheistic faith, whose beliefs and practices were not even remotely close to theirs, was not well received by them. Public executions, selective poll tax, and defilement of synagogues were a common method to overrule the other belief system. Jews were expelled from the city and some Roman emperors went to the length of declaring the possession of Jewish scriptures a capital crime. Such acts of hostility, though morally incoherent, can be justified rationally by the fundamental pattern of society's initial reaction to change in any case whatsoever. Moreover, Jews were not the only monotheists being harassed, the Romans reacted similarly to Christianity.&amp;nbsp;Moving up the timeline, Rome was Christianised in the late 300 AD and the capital of the Christian stronghold was established in Constantinople, Byzantine. In the late 600 AD, Islam came into being in the Arabian region of the Middle East and started growing rapidly owing to the expansionary crusades of Mohammad and the succeeding Muslim leaders. Jewish groups in Byzantine were treated as aliens for their disbelief in the absolution of Christianity. Their social standing and religious liberty varied with the ruler. Eventually, Islamic leaders reached the borders of Byzantine (Christianized Rome) and toppled the rule of Christians who retaliated with a series of crusades to reclaim the holy lands. All of the conflict lasted for about 200 years and the Jewish community was dishevelled as a byproduct. Muslim rulers aggressively imposed Islamic credo upon them and whenever Christians invaded as a result of the crusades, they wiped entire Jewish colonies off the map.&amp;nbsp;The situation was especially bad in Persia, as under the prejudice of being spiritually unclean, Jews were forced to live in ghettos outside of towns. They were not allowed to enter shops, and even if they managed to, they were not allowed to touch or inspect any item. If the latter was to happen, the laws clearly stated that the Jew was obligated to buy the product and the seller had an absolute right of charging as much as they wanted. Also, Jews were not allowed to roam the cities during rain, as it was believed that the&amp;nbsp; dirt of their spirituality would wash down with the raindrops and rub off on the locals who walked the same paths.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;As the middle ages rolled in, anti-semitic groups evolved their methods of suppression, as they started destroying the political standing of the Jews and catalysed it for their physical extermination. During the Black Death period, orthodox Crhritian and Muslim groups in the middle east accused Jews of poisoning the wells within cities and orchestrating the plague. These accusations were used to make initial arrests, upon which the prisoners were tortured and threatened into confessing to crimes that they never committed. Even for executions, slow death methods like public stoning &amp;amp; death by fire were used. As a final touch of cruelty, their respective properties and places of worship were seized without cause and converted into churches, mosques, and libraries.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Fast forward to the 1940’s. Religious and racial fanaticism had poisoned Germany. Almost everyone is aware of the horrific ordeal that Hitler and his racial political agendas put Jews through - pogroms, mass shootings, concentration camps and the gas chambers. When the dust settled, two-thirds of the European Jewish population had been exterminated- “genocide” in the perfect sense of the word. The scapegoating does not end there, as Jews were also blamed for capitalism and excessively controlling the american financial market via their dominance of the premiere financial institutions of the time like Rothschilds.Even today, the other communities prey on Jews for conversions. Their faith is still undermined and their rights as members of the society are still kept subservient to those of other cultures. It is imperative to understand that the concept of “sustainability”- a term which is amassing a lot of popularity lately- is not selective. Developing a world where everyone is willing to live their life of their own volition is the very foundation of the term. Therefore, security and free will for some and impositions on others is a betrayal to the very essence of sustainability as it makes the society more prone to implosion rather than consolidation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Weaponised Words: A Tale of Hate Speech</title>
      <link href="/Weaponised-Words-A-Tale-of-Hate-Speech" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Weaponised Words: A Tale of Hate Speech" />
      <published>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Weaponised-Words-A-Tale-of-Hate-Speech</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Weaponised-Words-A-Tale-of-Hate-Speech">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&quot;There is a fine line between free speech and hate speech. Free speech encourages debate whereas hate speech incites violence&quot; -&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Newton Lee,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/work/quotes/24289059&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Counterterrorism and Cybersecurity: Total Information Awareness&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quotation is a constant reminder of how easily hate speech overlaps with the idea of freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp;Over the past few months, the challenge of separating hate speech from the Indian citizen’s right to ‘Freedom of Expression’ has increased tremendously. Recently, several citizens including journalists, political party leaders and activists have been charged with hate speech, inflammatory speech and sedition. On one hand, offended plaintiffs file complaints due to hurt caused to their sentiments by the comments of the accused people. On the other hand, the defendants perceive it as a violation of their right to Freedom of Speech.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the light of recent incidents in India, a crucial question arises.&amp;nbsp;Should hate speech be incorporated as a part of Freedom of Speech, or should hate speech be legally regulated?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to scrutinise the idea of ‘free, hate speech’, it is important to distinguish between the two ideas of hate speech and free speech.&amp;nbsp;'Freedom of Expression or Speech' is a principle supporting the idea of an individual or a community articulating their opinions and ideas freely. It ensures such freedom “without the fear of retaliation, censorship, or legal sanction.” On the other hand, hate speech is clearly defined by the &lt;em&gt;Cambridge Dictionary&lt;/em&gt; as a &quot;public speech that expresses hate or encourages violence towards a person or a group based on something such as race, religion, sex, or sexual orientation”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get a sense of how hate speech is treated by legislation, we must take a look at a few examples. While hate speech is not a legal term in some countries, victims of hate speech may seek redressal under civil law, criminal law, or both in other nations. For instance, in the United States, hate speech is constitutionally protected. On the contrary, de jure, freedom of expression is promised in North Korea but there is no de facto right to free speech as asserted by Amnesty International, a human rights group.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In India, hate speech is regulated. While ‘Freedom of Speech and Expression’ is a fundamental right of the Indian Constitution, under Article 19(2) &quot;reasonable restrictions&quot; can be imposed on this right. This is in order to protect &quot;the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of the State, friendly relations with foreign States, public order, decency or morality, or in relation to contempt of court, defamation or incitement to an offence&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hurdle of Hate&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hate speech is a threat to humankind because words have the power to influence people to take action. It causes instability and agitation across the society. It can lead to reduced motivation, lower tolerance, emotional trauma or in extreme cases, depression.&amp;nbsp;Raising this concern, Joyce Arthur, a Canadian activist, in an article titled 'Should Hate Speech be a Crime?' underlines the importance of hate speech legislation. She elucidates that hate speech needs to be regulated as it has a huge impact on people’s dignity and human rights. Hate speech is often derogatory to the sentiments of a particular caste, creed, sex or religion as it is often rooted in stereotypes, prejudices and personal experiences which may be an inaccurate perception of the group or community as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A product of hate speech is hate crime&lt;/strong&gt;. Hate crimes are dangerous as they jeopardise amity in society, instigate precarity among communities, and foster a sense of animosity in the democracy.&amp;nbsp;In the technological era, hate speech over social media causes a tremendous amount of intolerance and violence leading to hate crimes. For instance, the perpetrator of the 2019 New Zealand mosque shootings killed 49 Muslims at prayer and sought to broadcast the attack on YouTube. In Germany, a correlation was observed between anti-refugee Facebook posts by the Alternative for Germany party and increasing attacks on refugees. In India, the recent case of Delhi violence due to hate speech and rumors on social media is also another instance.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hate Speech in India&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While 2020 has been a relatively inactive year for India in terms of business and functioning of institutions, the story is very different when it comes to hate speech laws. Starting from January 2020, there have been 10+ cases involving charges for sedition and hate speech.&amp;nbsp;Among journalists, Arnab Goswami, Amish Devgan and Vinod Dua are a few who&amp;nbsp; have faced FIRs or First Information Reports against them. On one hand, Amish Devgan was accused of injuring religious sentiments on his show. On the other hand, Goswami and Dua faced charges for criticising the State in different forms. FIRs against Goswami have been filed in relation to his questioning opposition leader Sonia Gandhi regarding mob lynching in the Palghar district of Western India. And Dua has been charged with sedition for a Youtube broadcast wherein he said that the State failed to implement the lockdown.&amp;nbsp;Sharjeel Imam, an Indian activist, has been charged with sedition, hate speech and promoting religious antagonism for his speeches against the Citizenship Amendment Act.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These diverse cases point out that it is also challenging and important to define specifically what can be categorized as hate speech.&amp;nbsp;A striking point has been stated in one of the articles in &lt;em&gt;Indian Express&lt;/em&gt;. It says that out of the ten hate speech cases that were scrutinised, including the ones mentioned above, the cases where the State and the petitioner contended on the same side, relief was provided. However, in six cases, where the State was accused, no relief was granted to the petitioner. A ‘telling pattern’ of this sort indicates a fresh challenge of violation of the right to equality before the law.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of this is the regulation of hate speech over social media. While trolling is only the tip of the iceberg, Facebook has recently faced challenges concerning hate speech rules. The &lt;em&gt;Wall Street Journal&lt;/em&gt; has accused Facebook of having failed to apply hate speech regulations on content posted by a BJP leader from the state of Telangana. Three other party leaders’ posts have also been overlooked.&amp;nbsp;A great initiative to combat such challenges is Facebook’s Oversight Board. The Oversight Board is an entity vested with the power to moderate and make independent decisions regarding content over social media sites like Facebook and Instagram. Its purpose is the protection of Facebook users. Hate speech and cases related to ‘political bias’ are within the purview of the board.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Watershed Verdicts&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1962 Indian Supreme Court judgement in &lt;em&gt;Kedar Nath Singh vs State of Bihar&lt;/em&gt; is a landmark judgement concerning the right to Freedom of Expression. The defendant faced charges of sedition and inciting public mischief due to a criticism of the then ruling party, the Indian National Congress in his speech. The defendant argued that the provisions on sedition in the Indian Penal Code (IPC) violated the right to Freedom of Expression under Article 19(1)(a) of the Indian Constitution.&amp;nbsp;The Court asserted that these were not under the purview of “reasonable restrictions” under Article 19(2). It explained that the phrase “Government established by law” under section 124A is different from the criticism of a political party or political leaders.&amp;nbsp;Yet sedition continues to be criminalised under the IPC. However, its provision has been narrowed down to only criminalise expression that intends to jeopardize public order and peace through violence, thereby protecting the right to freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another remarkable judgement in the field of online free speech is &lt;em&gt;Shreya Singhal vs Union of India (UOI).&lt;/em&gt; Two women were arrested under Section 66A of the Information Technology Act, 2000 for ‘posting allegedly offensive comments on Facebook’. As per the section, any person who sends “grossly offensive information” or information “to cause insult, injury or ill will” can be punished. These women filed a petition arguing that Section 66A was constitutionally invalid on the grounds of violation of the right to freedom of speech.&amp;nbsp;In 2015, the Supreme Court declared Section 66A to be unconstitutional and it was struck down. This was because Section 66A was not recognized as a “reasonable restriction” under Article 19(2). Thus, this was a turning point for online free speech.&amp;nbsp;These landmark judgements are useful to cite in cases relating to hate speech and freedom of expression for stronger established arguments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above-mentioned arguments and instances indicate that hate speech needs to be tackled through a balanced approach. While the right to freedom of expression needs to be upheld, hate speech intending to cause violence, disturb public order and promote unrest can prove to be detrimental for humankind.&amp;nbsp;A study by the Pew Research Center reveals that 67% and 27% of people in the United States and Asia-Pacific, respectively, agree with free hate speech. Nonetheless, as the saying goes, “Hate begets more hate”, hate speech causes a vicious cycle of hatred that has no end.&amp;nbsp;Thus, to balance respectful and considerate free speech without hampering the true essence of the Freedom of Expression, regulation of hate speech and uniform implementation of such rules is the need of the hour.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Nirikta Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">&quot;There is a fine line between free speech and hate speech. Free speech encourages debate whereas hate speech incites violence&quot; - Newton Lee, Counterterrorism and Cybersecurity: Total Information Awareness This quotation is a constant reminder of how easily hate speech overlaps with the idea of freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp;Over the past few months, the challenge of separating hate speech from the Indian citizen’s right to ‘Freedom of Expression’ has increased tremendously. Recently, several citizens including journalists, political party leaders and activists have been charged with hate speech, inflammatory speech and sedition. On one hand, offended plaintiffs file complaints due to hurt caused to their sentiments by the comments of the accused people. On the other hand, the defendants perceive it as a violation of their right to Freedom of Speech.&amp;nbsp; In the light of recent incidents in India, a crucial question arises.&amp;nbsp;Should hate speech be incorporated as a part of Freedom of Speech, or should hate speech be legally regulated?&amp;nbsp; In order to scrutinise the idea of ‘free, hate speech’, it is important to distinguish between the two ideas of hate speech and free speech.&amp;nbsp;'Freedom of Expression or Speech' is a principle supporting the idea of an individual or a community articulating their opinions and ideas freely. It ensures such freedom “without the fear of retaliation, censorship, or legal sanction.” On the other hand, hate speech is clearly defined by the Cambridge Dictionary as a &quot;public speech that expresses hate or encourages violence towards a person or a group based on something such as race, religion, sex, or sexual orientation”. To get a sense of how hate speech is treated by legislation, we must take a look at a few examples. While hate speech is not a legal term in some countries, victims of hate speech may seek redressal under civil law, criminal law, or both in other nations. For instance, in the United States, hate speech is constitutionally protected. On the contrary, de jure, freedom of expression is promised in North Korea but there is no de facto right to free speech as asserted by Amnesty International, a human rights group.&amp;nbsp; In India, hate speech is regulated. While ‘Freedom of Speech and Expression’ is a fundamental right of the Indian Constitution, under Article 19(2) &quot;reasonable restrictions&quot; can be imposed on this right. This is in order to protect &quot;the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of the State, friendly relations with foreign States, public order, decency or morality, or in relation to contempt of court, defamation or incitement to an offence&quot;. Hurdle of Hate&amp;nbsp; Hate speech is a threat to humankind because words have the power to influence people to take action. It causes instability and agitation across the society. It can lead to reduced motivation, lower tolerance, emotional trauma or in extreme cases, depression.&amp;nbsp;Raising this concern, Joyce Arthur, a Canadian activist, in an article titled 'Should Hate Speech be a Crime?' underlines the importance of hate speech legislation. She elucidates that hate speech needs to be regulated as it has a huge impact on people’s dignity and human rights. Hate speech is often derogatory to the sentiments of a particular caste, creed, sex or religion as it is often rooted in stereotypes, prejudices and personal experiences which may be an inaccurate perception of the group or community as a whole. A product of hate speech is hate crime. Hate crimes are dangerous as they jeopardise amity in society, instigate precarity among communities, and foster a sense of animosity in the democracy.&amp;nbsp;In the technological era, hate speech over social media causes a tremendous amount of intolerance and violence leading to hate crimes. For instance, the perpetrator of the 2019 New Zealand mosque shootings killed 49 Muslims at prayer and sought to broadcast the attack on YouTube. In Germany, a correlation was observed between anti-refugee Facebook posts by the Alternative for Germany party and increasing attacks on refugees. In India, the recent case of Delhi violence due to hate speech and rumors on social media is also another instance.&amp;nbsp; Hate Speech in India&amp;nbsp; While 2020 has been a relatively inactive year for India in terms of business and functioning of institutions, the story is very different when it comes to hate speech laws. Starting from January 2020, there have been 10+ cases involving charges for sedition and hate speech.&amp;nbsp;Among journalists, Arnab Goswami, Amish Devgan and Vinod Dua are a few who&amp;nbsp; have faced FIRs or First Information Reports against them. On one hand, Amish Devgan was accused of injuring religious sentiments on his show. On the other hand, Goswami and Dua faced charges for criticising the State in different forms. FIRs against Goswami have been filed in relation to his questioning opposition leader Sonia Gandhi regarding mob lynching in the Palghar district of Western India. And Dua has been charged with sedition for a Youtube broadcast wherein he said that the State failed to implement the lockdown.&amp;nbsp;Sharjeel Imam, an Indian activist, has been charged with sedition, hate speech and promoting religious antagonism for his speeches against the Citizenship Amendment Act.&amp;nbsp; These diverse cases point out that it is also challenging and important to define specifically what can be categorized as hate speech.&amp;nbsp;A striking point has been stated in one of the articles in Indian Express. It says that out of the ten hate speech cases that were scrutinised, including the ones mentioned above, the cases where the State and the petitioner contended on the same side, relief was provided. However, in six cases, where the State was accused, no relief was granted to the petitioner. A ‘telling pattern’ of this sort indicates a fresh challenge of violation of the right to equality before the law.&amp;nbsp; Another aspect of this is the regulation of hate speech over social media. While trolling is only the tip of the iceberg, Facebook has recently faced challenges concerning hate speech rules. The Wall Street Journal has accused Facebook of having failed to apply hate speech regulations on content posted by a BJP leader from the state of Telangana. Three other party leaders’ posts have also been overlooked.&amp;nbsp;A great initiative to combat such challenges is Facebook’s Oversight Board. The Oversight Board is an entity vested with the power to moderate and make independent decisions regarding content over social media sites like Facebook and Instagram. Its purpose is the protection of Facebook users. Hate speech and cases related to ‘political bias’ are within the purview of the board.&amp;nbsp; Watershed Verdicts&amp;nbsp; The 1962 Indian Supreme Court judgement in Kedar Nath Singh vs State of Bihar is a landmark judgement concerning the right to Freedom of Expression. The defendant faced charges of sedition and inciting public mischief due to a criticism of the then ruling party, the Indian National Congress in his speech. The defendant argued that the provisions on sedition in the Indian Penal Code (IPC) violated the right to Freedom of Expression under Article 19(1)(a) of the Indian Constitution.&amp;nbsp;The Court asserted that these were not under the purview of “reasonable restrictions” under Article 19(2). It explained that the phrase “Government established by law” under section 124A is different from the criticism of a political party or political leaders.&amp;nbsp;Yet sedition continues to be criminalised under the IPC. However, its provision has been narrowed down to only criminalise expression that intends to jeopardize public order and peace through violence, thereby protecting the right to freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp; Another remarkable judgement in the field of online free speech is Shreya Singhal vs Union of India (UOI). Two women were arrested under Section 66A of the Information Technology Act, 2000 for ‘posting allegedly offensive comments on Facebook’. As per the section, any person who sends “grossly offensive information” or information “to cause insult, injury or ill will” can be punished. These women filed a petition arguing that Section 66A was constitutionally invalid on the grounds of violation of the right to freedom of speech.&amp;nbsp;In 2015, the Supreme Court declared Section 66A to be unconstitutional and it was struck down. This was because Section 66A was not recognized as a “reasonable restriction” under Article 19(2). Thus, this was a turning point for online free speech.&amp;nbsp;These landmark judgements are useful to cite in cases relating to hate speech and freedom of expression for stronger established arguments.&amp;nbsp; The above-mentioned arguments and instances indicate that hate speech needs to be tackled through a balanced approach. While the right to freedom of expression needs to be upheld, hate speech intending to cause violence, disturb public order and promote unrest can prove to be detrimental for humankind.&amp;nbsp;A study by the Pew Research Center reveals that 67% and 27% of people in the United States and Asia-Pacific, respectively, agree with free hate speech. Nonetheless, as the saying goes, “Hate begets more hate”, hate speech causes a vicious cycle of hatred that has no end.&amp;nbsp;Thus, to balance respectful and considerate free speech without hampering the true essence of the Freedom of Expression, regulation of hate speech and uniform implementation of such rules is the need of the hour.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Caustic Crass of Casteism</title>
      <link href="/Caustic-Crass-of-Casteism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Caustic Crass of Casteism" />
      <published>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Caustic-Crass-of-Casteism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Caustic-Crass-of-Casteism">&lt;p&gt;Facebook in India is incessantly flooded with memes — pictures or videos of casteist slurs against the marginalised communities, as those who belong to ‘upper caste’ per se, lament against caste-based reservations in public institutes and government jobs. Their rationale, more prominently since the implementation of the Mandal Commission in 1990, has been that it ‘kills’ the merit factor, i.e. meritorious students who belong to the namesake ‘General’ category are deprived of opportunities that marginalised communities get due to reservation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the mind of every student in this country is filled with this narrative even before they burn the midnight oil to crack the draconian entrance exams. Such a hate-spewing narrative naturally brings a certain anathema towards the ‘reserved’ categories of students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This hatred is evident from the repetitive use of &lt;em&gt;cham**r&lt;/em&gt;, a word used as a casteist expletive which generalises all the marginalised communities under a derogative umbrella term, by many students studying in various educational institutions, sub-consciously fuming their exasperation against reservation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author of this article, who has been through the rat-race of preparing for the draconian engineering entrance exams, also blindly believed in this narrative. In hindsight, he now sees how it actually culminated with him profiling classmates and batchmates in the coaching classes, based on whether they could reap the benefits of reservation or not. His time also coincided with the ascendancy of Hindu-supremacist BJP at the centre, which also made him look slyly at Dr Ambedkar and the entire anti-caste movement. Of course, he found little sense in those rallying against casteism — for he only saw from a prism which showed them ‘entitled’ to higher-education in prestigious institutes without ‘merit’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This anecdote supports the aforementioned argument of how upper-caste propaganda embarks students on a path of discrimination and hatred — the wrongdoings of which are extremely difficult, if not impossible, to undo. What is even more concerning is that this propaganda under the garb of ‘merit’ and ‘equality’ brings a certain wind of legitimacy, the whiff of which is often hard to resist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, ‘merit’ is the key working word in this debate. However, it has been painstakingly dissected and presented in “Does ‘Merit’ have a Caste?” on &lt;em&gt;The Wire&lt;/em&gt; and it would be a great disservice to the author if it is reiterated only for the sake of argumentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The duopoly of casteism and classism are the biggest yet the most obscure threat to India’s Xanadu, the liveable manifestation of the promulgations of the Indian Constitution. Caste and class inequalities, on the contrary, are being pushed further into obscurity by a rising intolerance towards monotheistic religions, Islam in particular. Hindu vigilantes are often in what could be a self-perceived duel against their Muslim counterparts and vice versa. The macabre riots in Delhi are a testament to this intolerance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any conflict between religious communities obviously takes precedence over atrocities committed in the name of caste. In fact, the growing divide between monotheistic Islam and polytheistic Hinduism has given the latter a very powerful rationale for a ‘war cry’ of sorts, exhorting Hindus to ‘unite’ to ‘protect’ their sacrosanct religion. In reality, such exhortations culminate only with upper-caste Hindus to make a more impregnable clout and thereby, pushing the marginalised communities further away into oblivion. The upper echelons of public life in India are still largely dominated by upper-caste Hindus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, the author also believes that caste-based politicking is another reason for this growing divide. Whilst the government has brought upon the reformist measures to alleviate centuries of oppression, it still isn’t a step towards abolishing caste altogether. Many upper-caste Hindus often accuse political parties of caste-based political skullduggery for the marginalised communities have always been of a ‘vote-bank’, a sizeable population whose vote is crucial to win elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the author himself was led to strongly believe in the upper-caste narrative which denounces the existence of caste-based oppression altogether and accuses the marginalised communities to raise the caste question only to ‘cling’ onto the reservations that they are entitled to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an opinion of caste comes from a selective reading of society. In order to subscribe to this narrative, one must have class privilege, where the society is so-called ‘westernised’ enough to not bother knowing one’s caste as long as everyone belongs to the same economic class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it would be unfair to assume that being on top of the class pyramid saves one from the caste question, such selective perception of caste also comes from denial and ignorance; to put it crudely, one cannot deny the existence of casteism if one has never been subjected to caste-based discrimination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The caste dynamics in India are so precariously balanced that leaders such as Mahatma Gandhi are also accused of ensuring that the caste hierarchy remains. Man Booker-prize winning author Arundhati Roy in her essay ‘The Doctor and the Saint’ has opined that Gandhi supported the caste hierarchy only to appease the high-caste Marwari businessmen who, financially or otherwise, supported his &lt;em&gt;satyagraha&lt;/em&gt; (policy of nonviolent resistance) movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If probably the greatest statesman of this country paid his obeisance to casteism, it would be foolish to assume that a Hindu-supremacist government like the BJP would uproot this anachronistic practice. On the contrary, many Dalit activists are wary of the party’s intentions, and accuse it of ethnic profiling and cleansing with their divisive Citizenship Amendment Act (CAA) and the draconian National Register of Citizens (NRC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legacy of Dr B R Ambedkar, who perhaps was the most profound Dalit thinker, is also thrown in the cesspool of profanities and slurs, hurled by the upper-caste, the propaganda of hate deeply entrenched in their minds. The Indian education system, among its many inherent flaws, also fails to elucidate students about Dr Ambedkar as much as it embellishes Gandhi, which again reeks of the politics behind how impressionable minds are moulded to perceive the history and ethos of the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Xanadu which was envisaged by those who broke the shackles of an oppressive colonial rule is questioned and dissected now. Despite Dr Ambedkar’s tribulations for a more egalitarian and just society, the existence of marginalised communities is reduced to a transactional relationship where ‘reservation’ is given in exchange for their suffrage. Whether the doors of an independent India were open for Dalits and tribals is a question that remains unanswered even after 73 years.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rishi Kant</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Facebook in India is incessantly flooded with memes — pictures or videos of casteist slurs against the marginalised communities, as those who belong to ‘upper caste’ per se, lament against caste-based reservations in public institutes and government jobs. Their rationale, more prominently since the implementation of the Mandal Commission in 1990, has been that it ‘kills’ the merit factor, i.e. meritorious students who belong to the namesake ‘General’ category are deprived of opportunities that marginalised communities get due to reservation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Clout of A New World Order</title>
      <link href="/Clout-of-A-New-World-Order" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Clout of A New World Order" />
      <published>2020-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Clout-of-A-New-World-Order</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Clout-of-A-New-World-Order">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Social psychologists believe that feelings of frailty and uncertainty associate an individual with a tendency to believe in conspiracies”&lt;/em&gt;, said Karen M Douglas, Professor of Social Psychology at the University of Kent in the United Kingdom. Conceivably, it is true, to have something to lean on is an instinct to regain a sense of control, even if the conspiracy is unrelated to what caused the lack of control in an individual’s life. But what if this is just another conspiracy theory to dwarf all the other conspiracy theories?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you remember watching &lt;em&gt;The Matrix&lt;/em&gt;, you would probably remember Mr Anderson (Keanu Reaves), an otherwise rational person making the leap from prudent paranoia to a not so illogical conspiracy, which led him to the dilemma of choosing between the red and the blue pill. There exists a gnawing feeling of not having control over your life - the dissatisfaction which hinders you from living your life to the fullest. And that is what happened with Adam Weishaupt, founder of The Illuminati.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Born in 1748 in Ingolstadt, Bavaria, Weishaupt was a descendant of Jewish converts to Christianity. Orphaned at a young age, his uncle took care of his education. After completing his studies, Weishaupt became a Professor of canon law at the University of Ingolstadt, got married and started a family. He seemed to have a conventional career until 1784 when the Bavarian state learned about his distinct and provocative ideas. Since childhood, being an avid reader, Weishaupt was convinced that religious ideas were no longer an adequate belief system and hence, he decided to find another form of illumination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May 1, 1776 saw the first Illuminati meet in a forest near Ingolstadt to find the order and there, they established the rules that were to govern the order. The order was a set of scientific ideas and practices that could be applied to radically change the way European states were run. By the end of 1784, Weishaupt’s secret order grew considerably to 3,000 members and by the mid 1780’s, theIlluminati caught the Bavarian government’s attention, which put an end to the secret society. Weishaupt fled and gave up the secret shenanigans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does the Illuminati want?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conspiracy theorists obsessively analyse public events for evidence of Illuminati infiltration in the modern-day world. There have been many events which are said to be proof of the fact that the Illuminati has infiltrated the ranks of prominent leaders, celebrities, clergymen, business tycoons and pharmaceutical companies around the globe, who are affiliated with it and are collectively working to secure their main objective. Back in 2013, when Beyonce performed at superbowl and flashed a pyramid (believed to be the Illuminati’s symbol) with her hands, the internet was lit up with conjectures that she was a member of the secret society. While this might be a baseless conspiracy theory on the grounds of impracticality, it is logical for many who believe they have seen things. Moreover, there exists a condition called Pareidolia, which causes humans to see objective patterns in random stimuli, often attaching humane characteristics to non-living objects, for instance, seeing the face of Jesus in a cream cracker or the date of Apocalypse in Trump’s social security number. Though rationality makes conditions like Pareidolia seem utter nonsense, one can argue that wild-imagination has always fuelled pragmatic creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conspiracy theorists have been warning about a New World Order for decades, going all the way back to the isolationist critics of Franklin Delano Roosevelt. The New World Order or NWO is claimed to be a totalitarian world government led by a secretive power elite conspiring to rule the planet. Though it holds little significance whether any secret society wants to instigate a new world order or a group of power-hungry humans who want to control the world, it nonetheless merits some investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the New World Order?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New World Order is a supposedly autocratic world government (or a Cosmocratic government), which signifies the idea of having ONE central government for every country, institution and state in the world. A Cosmocratic style of government can come to power either through violent world domination or voluntary supranational union. Cosmocracy is a polity made up with recombinant structures that are themselves products of constantly changing, yet permanently unfolding processes. It is a moving target that produces unexpected and highly unstable targets. Though that is one way to look at it, there are numerous ways to perceive this form of world order. Having a single government for everybody will result in absolute harmony among different nations implying that most likely there will be no trade and nuclear wars, rather homogeneity will breed bonhomie between countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single government at the world stage may also ensure that after people become unbound from nature, they will create more anthropocentric forms of organizations, and one among them is democracy. Cosmocracy brings this cycle to a close and leads us back to the essential unity of all things - nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is something like the NWO feasible?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The likeliness of a Cosmocratic government’s rise to power is undoubtedly negligible, given the severe political and socio-economic turmoil it may bring. Any leader who is at the top of the world’s power structure and wields enormous power has a good chance of indulging in malpractices and corruption. The world surely cannot afford to give such power to a small group of individuals, because at the end of the day, they are just humans and have a good chance of becoming corrupt because of the unlimited power the position entails. Also, in the status quo, we live in a world in which people are inherently very proud of their cultural practices, which naturally results in any of their actions (at a macro level) aimed towards making their ‘nation’ great. In such a scenario, if we elect people from a particular country or even if we ensure that the Cosmocratic government is such which consists of equal representation from all parts of the world, there is no way we can eradicate personal bias towards their nations. This is a factor which defeats the purpose of having one government at a global level because if the leaders do not work to cater to the interests of all people across the world, the implementation of this new order will be futile. Moreover, setting up such a government is not pragmatic at all. We have around 200 countries in the world, albeit we cannot have 200 leaders at the world centre, so there has to be some type of filtration system to see from where the leaders are to be elected, which will naturally give the leaders from the first world nations an upper-hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, such a type of government may surely be beneficial in a post-apocalyptic scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the course of history, the most powerful advocates of change have emerged out of destructive circumstances. Citing some examples from history - the nation-state to geopolitics emerged from the Peace of Westphalia, which marked the end of the Thirty Years’ War (1618-48) in Central Europe. The political concept of balance of power gained greater importance with the Congress of Vienna, which emerged in the aftermath of the French Revolution and Napoleonic Wars (1792-1815). Besides, The League of Nations, a noble, yet short-lived experiment in circumscribing power competition, emerged from the First World War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transformation of the world order into a new world order may result from extremely farsighted diplomacy, for which diplomats and policymakers around the world will have to do more than push for incremental improvements within an inadequate system. A possibility entails that if not from diplomacy, the NWO may arise from an apocalypse, though it is terrifying to consider what might have to occur for a new order to emerge in this way, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Anshdeep Singh Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Social psychologists believe that feelings of frailty and uncertainty associate an individual with a tendency to believe in conspiracies”, said Karen M Douglas, Professor of Social Psychology at the University of Kent in the United Kingdom. Conceivably, it is true, to have something to lean on is an instinct to regain a sense of control, even if the conspiracy is unrelated to what caused the lack of control in an individual’s life. But what if this is just another conspiracy theory to dwarf all the other conspiracy theories? If you remember watching The Matrix, you would probably remember Mr Anderson (Keanu Reaves), an otherwise rational person making the leap from prudent paranoia to a not so illogical conspiracy, which led him to the dilemma of choosing between the red and the blue pill. There exists a gnawing feeling of not having control over your life - the dissatisfaction which hinders you from living your life to the fullest. And that is what happened with Adam Weishaupt, founder of The Illuminati. Born in 1748 in Ingolstadt, Bavaria, Weishaupt was a descendant of Jewish converts to Christianity. Orphaned at a young age, his uncle took care of his education. After completing his studies, Weishaupt became a Professor of canon law at the University of Ingolstadt, got married and started a family. He seemed to have a conventional career until 1784 when the Bavarian state learned about his distinct and provocative ideas. Since childhood, being an avid reader, Weishaupt was convinced that religious ideas were no longer an adequate belief system and hence, he decided to find another form of illumination. May 1, 1776 saw the first Illuminati meet in a forest near Ingolstadt to find the order and there, they established the rules that were to govern the order. The order was a set of scientific ideas and practices that could be applied to radically change the way European states were run. By the end of 1784, Weishaupt’s secret order grew considerably to 3,000 members and by the mid 1780’s, theIlluminati caught the Bavarian government’s attention, which put an end to the secret society. Weishaupt fled and gave up the secret shenanigans. What does the Illuminati want?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
