<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/society/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-04-05T17:32:40+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/society/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Feminist? No, of course not.</title>
      <link href="/Feminist-No-of-course-not" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Feminist? No, of course not." />
      <published>2019-03-28T01:33:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-28T01:33:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Feminist-No-of-course-not</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Feminist-No-of-course-not">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I don’t want to get into it! No, not me.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very recently, after a long conversation about everything ranging from Paganism
to Masculinity with some very articulate people, I was offered to put my words
to use in talk of feminism. I didn’t know what to make of the instantaneous
rejection that came out of me, I recall thinking I don’t want to dip my feet
into that pool. One of the conversationalists (a very openly-proclaimed
feminist) took it upon herself to tell me that I was welcome to voice my
opinions, that ‘they’ are open to one and all. I never did talk about whether or
not I identified as a feminist, however, her welcome led me to think about why
someone would not want to be a part of this ‘them.’ The new F-word in the market
that people are so scared of had, I think, tied me up in knots too. Not
believing that you could be a part of this movement of feminism would be absurd,
right? How can I, a woman, remove myself from a movement of and about all women?
I am not here to tell you which way to tilt or which fashion to conform to. This
is just me talking about what I’ve dug up in relation to the aforementioned
conversation. My attempt here is only to explore one simple question: why do
some women not want to be ‘feminists’?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the #MeToo movement barrels forward, as record numbers of women seek office,
with the #everydaysexism trending, feminism is reaching a level of cultural
relevance it hasn’t enjoyed in years. It’s now a major object of cultural
discourse–which has led to some very confusing conversations because not
everyone is familiar with or agrees on the basic terminology of feminism. The
&lt;em&gt;Oxford Dictionary&lt;/em&gt; suggests that feminism is the advocacy of women’s rights on
the ground of the equality of the sexes. But when the term feminism entered the
English language, towards the mid-19th century, it meant “feminine qualities or
character”, a meaning no longer in use, obviously. However, the late 19th
century unfolded and feminism unambiguously took on its modern meanings.
Moreover, one of the most basic and most confusing terminologies has to do with
the waves of feminism. I don’t know of one person who is sure of what wave
belongs to which specific timeline. The wave metaphor, over time, has become a
way to describe and distinguish between different eras and generations of
feminism. However, the metaphor can be reductive, it can suggest that each wave
of feminism is a monolith with a single unified agenda, when in fact the history
of feminism is a history of different ideas in wild conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, the first wave (1848-1920) refers to the West’s first
sustained political movement dedicated to achieving political equality for
women: the Suffragettes of the late 19th and early 20th centuries. The second
wave’s (1963-1980) focus was on changing the way society thought about women.
The second wave cared deeply about the casual, systemic sexism ingrained in
society, fighting it by proving that women were no less than men. It cared about
racism too, but it could be clumsy in working with people of colour . The image
of feminists as angry, man-hating and lonely would become canonical as the
second wave began to lose its momentum, and it continues to haunt the way we
talk about feminism today. It would also become foundational to the way the
third wave would position itself as it emerged. It is almost impossible to talk
with any clarity about the third wave because few people agree on exactly what
the third wave is, when it started, or if it’s still going on. “The confusion
surrounding what constitutes third wave feminism,” writes feminist scholar
Elizabeth Evans, “is in some respects its defining feature.” Early third wave
activism tended to involve fighting against workplace sexual harassment and
working to increase the number of women in positions of power. While a lot of
people believe we’re still into the third wave, a new vision of feminism as an
online movement has caught on as the “fourth wave”. This wave is seen to have
begun to hold our culture’s most powerful men accountable for their behaviour.
It has begun a radical critique of the systems of power that allow predators to
target women with impunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, with all of these great accomplishments (despite the confusions), why then,
would a person, especially a woman, not want to be a part of this movement?
Remember those women I talked about: Several were keen on their identity as
feminists, explicitly so. But the ones who weren’t, their answers held my
interest. The top answer would usually be: “I prescribe to egalitarianism and
not feminism.” But saying you’re not a feminist and an egalitarian may come off
as moot from the outset because there’s not one without the other. Feminism is
verily the mechanism and egalitarianism, the goal.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A close second was the idea that a feminist corresponds to a man-hating,
lesbian, non-shaving, free-the-nipple woman. Of course, when put in this manner,
it sounds abhorrent, but a large part of the world believes that every feminist
has to hate men or that feminists need to shirk away from being feminine. This
viewpoint is hardly new. In the 1920’s, feminists were called spinsters, and
speculations on their sexuality were rife. The fact that this view still holds
sway is very telling. To put everything in categories is human nature, but to
understand a spectrum is just as important. The scapegoating of femininity might
as well be the albatross around the feminist movement’s neck. The idea of women
wanting to stay at home and caring for their children, wearing a pink dress,
while serving their husbands breakfast is said to portray a woman who cannot be
a feminist or a bad one at that. These categorical notions make people not
wanting to be hitched to the identity of a feminist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s another reason—that being God. Some suggest that God didn’t want women
and men to be equal. Which is why he made them different. I quote from one of my
acquaintances, “That’s why ideal women are dainty, while men are hunky.” On
this, all I could say was a living, 4-5 kg organism (sometimes, multiple) comes
out of a woman’s most vulnerable area, well, they sure are made to be dainty and
fragile! Again, this is not me trying to fight against someone’s beliefs–I’m
aware that, physiologically, we’re different, but the concept of what our
physicality has to do with our rights still confounds me. Other reasonings
included the idea of ‘Feminazis’. How can a term signifying the systematic
genocide of millions of innocent individuals get conflated with a term that in
all its spirit aims to demolish social hierarchies? You may ask. Well, just like
that the Bra-Burning-Woman imagery was born.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google made me aware of how Katy Perry, the year she received the Woman of the
Year award, showed an unwillingness to be called a feminist. Her reasoning, from
what I could gather was how it’d affect her fan base. Or perhaps, she was scared
of its radicality. Yahoo’s CEO also doesn’t abide by the concept. With the
reasons placed above, and a great multitude of others, one can see how it’d make
sense to be happy to live in a neutral place than to choose somewhat of a
position that may make you seem extremist. The way one may see feminism, now, in
this very moment, is so far from how it was supposed to be. But that’s a very
small percentage. Or, is it? If you’re a part of the magical world of Tumblr,
you’re already aware of the womenagainstfeminism tag. And all the other subtags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come to think about it, if a man proclaims himself as a feminist–he’s applauded,
even favoured. He carries the stereotypical image of being understanding of
women’s dilemmas and struggles, of him being by their side. But a feminist woman
is seen as someone who’ll lecture you at turns, go on rants about issues at the
drop of a hat whilst wearing androgynous clothes. The duality of what we’ve been
taught is traced in every stitch of our social fragmentation. I read something a
while back, “Men are afraid women will laugh at them, and women are afraid men
will kill them.” Hold me wrong if you may, but the issue may not be in how all
of us see feminism, but how we perceive it. The fear of being called a feminist
really rests in the assumed social consequences and implications of being called
one. It is difficult to undertake the personal accountability required to trace
out one’s own position in the multiple systems of domination and oppression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All, I, as a laywoman, can say is that we should see the aversion as a sign, not
of feminism’s failures, but of its continuing relevance. It would be better if
feminism were more widely accepted, sure, but failing that, the least a movement
for radical social change can do is to freak people out a little. Feminism still
provokes resistance; it still has enemies; it still makes many people in the
mainstream nervous. And that, in itself, seems like a victory. Just like the
feminist who welcomed my aversion, feminism too welcomes us all. After all, you
don’t have to understand everything, you just have to try to not be a d*ck!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“I don’t want to get into it! No, not me.” Very recently, after a long conversation about everything ranging from Paganism to Masculinity with some very articulate people, I was offered to put my words to use in talk of feminism. I didn’t know what to make of the instantaneous rejection that came out of me, I recall thinking I don’t want to dip my feet into that pool. One of the conversationalists (a very openly-proclaimed feminist) took it upon herself to tell me that I was welcome to voice my opinions, that ‘they’ are open to one and all. I never did talk about whether or not I identified as a feminist, however, her welcome led me to think about why someone would not want to be a part of this ‘them.’ The new F-word in the market that people are so scared of had, I think, tied me up in knots too. Not believing that you could be a part of this movement of feminism would be absurd, right? How can I, a woman, remove myself from a movement of and about all women? I am not here to tell you which way to tilt or which fashion to conform to. This is just me talking about what I’ve dug up in relation to the aforementioned conversation. My attempt here is only to explore one simple question: why do some women not want to be ‘feminists’? As the #MeToo movement barrels forward, as record numbers of women seek office, with the #everydaysexism trending, feminism is reaching a level of cultural relevance it hasn’t enjoyed in years. It’s now a major object of cultural discourse–which has led to some very confusing conversations because not everyone is familiar with or agrees on the basic terminology of feminism. The Oxford Dictionary suggests that feminism is the advocacy of women’s rights on the ground of the equality of the sexes. But when the term feminism entered the English language, towards the mid-19th century, it meant “feminine qualities or character”, a meaning no longer in use, obviously. However, the late 19th century unfolded and feminism unambiguously took on its modern meanings. Moreover, one of the most basic and most confusing terminologies has to do with the waves of feminism. I don’t know of one person who is sure of what wave belongs to which specific timeline. The wave metaphor, over time, has become a way to describe and distinguish between different eras and generations of feminism. However, the metaphor can be reductive, it can suggest that each wave of feminism is a monolith with a single unified agenda, when in fact the history of feminism is a history of different ideas in wild conflict. Generally speaking, the first wave (1848-1920) refers to the West’s first sustained political movement dedicated to achieving political equality for women: the Suffragettes of the late 19th and early 20th centuries. The second wave’s (1963-1980) focus was on changing the way society thought about women. The second wave cared deeply about the casual, systemic sexism ingrained in society, fighting it by proving that women were no less than men. It cared about racism too, but it could be clumsy in working with people of colour . The image of feminists as angry, man-hating and lonely would become canonical as the second wave began to lose its momentum, and it continues to haunt the way we talk about feminism today. It would also become foundational to the way the third wave would position itself as it emerged. It is almost impossible to talk with any clarity about the third wave because few people agree on exactly what the third wave is, when it started, or if it’s still going on. “The confusion surrounding what constitutes third wave feminism,” writes feminist scholar Elizabeth Evans, “is in some respects its defining feature.” Early third wave activism tended to involve fighting against workplace sexual harassment and working to increase the number of women in positions of power. While a lot of people believe we’re still into the third wave, a new vision of feminism as an online movement has caught on as the “fourth wave”. This wave is seen to have begun to hold our culture’s most powerful men accountable for their behaviour. It has begun a radical critique of the systems of power that allow predators to target women with impunity. Now, with all of these great accomplishments (despite the confusions), why then, would a person, especially a woman, not want to be a part of this movement? Remember those women I talked about: Several were keen on their identity as feminists, explicitly so. But the ones who weren’t, their answers held my interest. The top answer would usually be: “I prescribe to egalitarianism and not feminism.” But saying you’re not a feminist and an egalitarian may come off as moot from the outset because there’s not one without the other. Feminism is verily the mechanism and egalitarianism, the goal.   A close second was the idea that a feminist corresponds to a man-hating, lesbian, non-shaving, free-the-nipple woman. Of course, when put in this manner, it sounds abhorrent, but a large part of the world believes that every feminist has to hate men or that feminists need to shirk away from being feminine. This viewpoint is hardly new. In the 1920’s, feminists were called spinsters, and speculations on their sexuality were rife. The fact that this view still holds sway is very telling. To put everything in categories is human nature, but to understand a spectrum is just as important. The scapegoating of femininity might as well be the albatross around the feminist movement’s neck. The idea of women wanting to stay at home and caring for their children, wearing a pink dress, while serving their husbands breakfast is said to portray a woman who cannot be a feminist or a bad one at that. These categorical notions make people not wanting to be hitched to the identity of a feminist. There’s another reason—that being God. Some suggest that God didn’t want women and men to be equal. Which is why he made them different. I quote from one of my acquaintances, “That’s why ideal women are dainty, while men are hunky.” On this, all I could say was a living, 4-5 kg organism (sometimes, multiple) comes out of a woman’s most vulnerable area, well, they sure are made to be dainty and fragile! Again, this is not me trying to fight against someone’s beliefs–I’m aware that, physiologically, we’re different, but the concept of what our physicality has to do with our rights still confounds me. Other reasonings included the idea of ‘Feminazis’. How can a term signifying the systematic genocide of millions of innocent individuals get conflated with a term that in all its spirit aims to demolish social hierarchies? You may ask. Well, just like that the Bra-Burning-Woman imagery was born.     Google made me aware of how Katy Perry, the year she received the Woman of the Year award, showed an unwillingness to be called a feminist. Her reasoning, from what I could gather was how it’d affect her fan base. Or perhaps, she was scared of its radicality. Yahoo’s CEO also doesn’t abide by the concept. With the reasons placed above, and a great multitude of others, one can see how it’d make sense to be happy to live in a neutral place than to choose somewhat of a position that may make you seem extremist. The way one may see feminism, now, in this very moment, is so far from how it was supposed to be. But that’s a very small percentage. Or, is it? If you’re a part of the magical world of Tumblr, you’re already aware of the womenagainstfeminism tag. And all the other subtags. Come to think about it, if a man proclaims himself as a feminist–he’s applauded, even favoured. He carries the stereotypical image of being understanding of women’s dilemmas and struggles, of him being by their side. But a feminist woman is seen as someone who’ll lecture you at turns, go on rants about issues at the drop of a hat whilst wearing androgynous clothes. The duality of what we’ve been taught is traced in every stitch of our social fragmentation. I read something a while back, “Men are afraid women will laugh at them, and women are afraid men will kill them.” Hold me wrong if you may, but the issue may not be in how all of us see feminism, but how we perceive it. The fear of being called a feminist really rests in the assumed social consequences and implications of being called one. It is difficult to undertake the personal accountability required to trace out one’s own position in the multiple systems of domination and oppression. All, I, as a laywoman, can say is that we should see the aversion as a sign, not of feminism’s failures, but of its continuing relevance. It would be better if feminism were more widely accepted, sure, but failing that, the least a movement for radical social change can do is to freak people out a little. Feminism still provokes resistance; it still has enemies; it still makes many people in the mainstream nervous. And that, in itself, seems like a victory. Just like the feminist who welcomed my aversion, feminism too welcomes us all. After all, you don’t have to understand everything, you just have to try to not be a d*ck!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Cl*t Wants What it Wants</title>
      <link href="/The-Clit-Wants-What-it-Wants" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Cl*t Wants What it Wants" />
      <published>2019-03-21T10:52:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-21T10:52:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Clit-Wants-What-it-Wants</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Clit-Wants-What-it-Wants">&lt;p&gt;Manically cross-checking to ensure that your search history is finally cleared
of every &lt;em&gt;flogging&lt;/em&gt; and every &lt;em&gt;caning&lt;/em&gt; or suddenly having no faith in
technology’s ability to truly remain incognito: People will go to any length to
avoid the embarrassment of enjoying kink. Interestingly, it’s not the idea that
one consumes porn that one feels the need to hide but the kind or &lt;em&gt;category&lt;/em&gt; of
porn, especially the moment it starts deviating from the missionary position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anxiety of being caught watching BDSM is no different from the anxiety one
feels when telling friends about a new crush. “Oh, but he looks better in
person!”, “His meme game isn’t strong but I swear he’s hilarious when you talk
to him.” Crushes are people we aren’t even emotionally invested in (yet), so why
do we care about what our friends think of them? It’s because of what we &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt;,
we perceive as an extension of us. And this applies to kinky porn as well. We’re
scared of what it says about us, we are scared of the fact that &lt;em&gt;these&lt;/em&gt; are our
innermost cravings and desires, that this is who we are. We’re not only scared
of how others see us but also of how we see ourselves, we’re scared of being a
certain person. And this fear magnifies when how we feel is in conflict with how
we think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, the brain just can’t accept what the clitoris wants. One could detest
the word ‘slut’ otherwise, but love being called one during sex. What’s
offensive in daylight is often a turn-on at night. And while there is definitely
a context of consent to any healthy form of kink and acts like &lt;em&gt;choking&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;slapping&lt;/em&gt; cannot be seen in isolation, consent is not the whole answer to why
we want something, it’s not the answer to why we crave something. I think that’s
the hauntingly beautiful role sex plays in our lives because it is the place
where we confront the distinction between what we believe and what we feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the undeniability of the desire, (people will literally have sex even if
there’s a risk of getting stoned to death) that makes sex as scary as it is
wonderful. Sex scandalises the very proprieties and ideas of self we hold so
dear while also feeling good enough to incentivise us to navigate through those
same discomforting ideas and get to the G(ood) spot. Sex is frightening because
it betrays us. In an era of intellectual dissection and analysis of every topic,
we think we have a certain degree of control over who we are, we think our sense
of self arises from all that we know, we think that our thoughts can control
what we do or do not &lt;strong&gt;desire&lt;/strong&gt;. We think we can choose to want or not want
something. But that’s exactly how it does not work. Ultimately, it is the
dominance of the subconscious that manifests in yearning and in longing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is notable how fantasies often play around concepts of morality that are
borrowed from the traditional cultural fabric. For instance, what underlies the
‘good girl’ fantasy? It entails punishing a girl during sex for liking sex or
craving it, judged by indicators such as having an engorged clitoris or a wet
pussy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems rather counterintuitive to shame the girl for liking sex as a way to
further arouse her, but there’s a reason it works. The ‘good girl’ trope in
role-plays exploits the archaic idea of how a woman is not supposed to want sex,
and the notion of how in order to be a ‘good woman’, a woman must never want sex
for her own physical gratification but only for the purpose of pleasing a man.
The moment (in role-play) the man is able to make her feel like she isn’t the
one seeking sex she feels she is fulfilling her &lt;em&gt;role&lt;/em&gt; by serving only his
needs. When she is punished for enjoying something she isn’t supposed to, the
appeal lies in the justice of getting what she deserves (the punishment) for
betraying the rule (women not desiring sex).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spirit behind it is the idea: am I finally being what a woman is supposed to
be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of forms of kink revolve around power, specifically the distortions in its
proportions. There is a whole spectrum to kink and the spectrum is so wide that
most of us fall somewhere in it. It isn’t just about chains and straps in sex
dungeons, it could be something as simple as liking it when a guy takes your
hair by his fists. Cravings for power distortions are much more relatable for an
average individual than one might realise. And like in every other discussion, a
discussion about sexual kink too will reek of naivete if it doesn’t take into
account the politics of gender. The overwhelming overlap of women with
submission and men with dominance has more to it than just men being ‘on top’.
Seizing sovereignty in a sexual scenario is quite territorial in nature. To
claim and to be claimed both give the same kind of comfort, that we’re someone
else’s. For instance, tying your partner’s hands during sex and being able to
restrain them is attached to the thrill of owning them, even if only in fantasy
or even if only for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a romance to that, because it screams the message, “You and only you
can do that with me because I love you and I’m yours, just yours.” After all, we
are all just frazzled souls looking to belong to other humans. While we try to
understand and get to the heart of these fantasies, the important thing to
remember is: &lt;em&gt;desires don’t cease to exist just because you can’t make sense of
them.&lt;/em&gt; No logic or its absence thereof can ever invalidate something that has
been felt. In fact, I think it’s comforting that there’s at least one part of
life which is ruled by the subconscious and there is peace in the knowledge that
this has already been determined for us and it’s not something that needs to be
built and established. It is an exercise in futility to try and tamper with
these desires. Desires arise from within, what happens on the outside is merely
the manifestation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let sexuality be outside the realm of your control. Let your fantasies betray
you.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Stuti Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Manically cross-checking to ensure that your search history is finally cleared of every flogging and every caning or suddenly having no faith in technology’s ability to truly remain incognito: People will go to any length to avoid the embarrassment of enjoying kink. Interestingly, it’s not the idea that one consumes porn that one feels the need to hide but the kind or category of porn, especially the moment it starts deviating from the missionary position. The anxiety of being caught watching BDSM is no different from the anxiety one feels when telling friends about a new crush. “Oh, but he looks better in person!”, “His meme game isn’t strong but I swear he’s hilarious when you talk to him.” Crushes are people we aren’t even emotionally invested in (yet), so why do we care about what our friends think of them? It’s because of what we want, we perceive as an extension of us. And this applies to kinky porn as well. We’re scared of what it says about us, we are scared of the fact that these are our innermost cravings and desires, that this is who we are. We’re not only scared of how others see us but also of how we see ourselves, we’re scared of being a certain person. And this fear magnifies when how we feel is in conflict with how we think. Sometimes, the brain just can’t accept what the clitoris wants. One could detest the word ‘slut’ otherwise, but love being called one during sex. What’s offensive in daylight is often a turn-on at night. And while there is definitely a context of consent to any healthy form of kink and acts like choking and slapping cannot be seen in isolation, consent is not the whole answer to why we want something, it’s not the answer to why we crave something. I think that’s the hauntingly beautiful role sex plays in our lives because it is the place where we confront the distinction between what we believe and what we feel. It is the undeniability of the desire, (people will literally have sex even if there’s a risk of getting stoned to death) that makes sex as scary as it is wonderful. Sex scandalises the very proprieties and ideas of self we hold so dear while also feeling good enough to incentivise us to navigate through those same discomforting ideas and get to the G(ood) spot. Sex is frightening because it betrays us. In an era of intellectual dissection and analysis of every topic, we think we have a certain degree of control over who we are, we think our sense of self arises from all that we know, we think that our thoughts can control what we do or do not desire. We think we can choose to want or not want something. But that’s exactly how it does not work. Ultimately, it is the dominance of the subconscious that manifests in yearning and in longing. It is notable how fantasies often play around concepts of morality that are borrowed from the traditional cultural fabric. For instance, what underlies the ‘good girl’ fantasy? It entails punishing a girl during sex for liking sex or craving it, judged by indicators such as having an engorged clitoris or a wet pussy. It seems rather counterintuitive to shame the girl for liking sex as a way to further arouse her, but there’s a reason it works. The ‘good girl’ trope in role-plays exploits the archaic idea of how a woman is not supposed to want sex, and the notion of how in order to be a ‘good woman’, a woman must never want sex for her own physical gratification but only for the purpose of pleasing a man. The moment (in role-play) the man is able to make her feel like she isn’t the one seeking sex she feels she is fulfilling her role by serving only his needs. When she is punished for enjoying something she isn’t supposed to, the appeal lies in the justice of getting what she deserves (the punishment) for betraying the rule (women not desiring sex). The spirit behind it is the idea: am I finally being what a woman is supposed to be? A lot of forms of kink revolve around power, specifically the distortions in its proportions. There is a whole spectrum to kink and the spectrum is so wide that most of us fall somewhere in it. It isn’t just about chains and straps in sex dungeons, it could be something as simple as liking it when a guy takes your hair by his fists. Cravings for power distortions are much more relatable for an average individual than one might realise. And like in every other discussion, a discussion about sexual kink too will reek of naivete if it doesn’t take into account the politics of gender. The overwhelming overlap of women with submission and men with dominance has more to it than just men being ‘on top’. Seizing sovereignty in a sexual scenario is quite territorial in nature. To claim and to be claimed both give the same kind of comfort, that we’re someone else’s. For instance, tying your partner’s hands during sex and being able to restrain them is attached to the thrill of owning them, even if only in fantasy or even if only for a while. There is a romance to that, because it screams the message, “You and only you can do that with me because I love you and I’m yours, just yours.” After all, we are all just frazzled souls looking to belong to other humans. While we try to understand and get to the heart of these fantasies, the important thing to remember is: desires don’t cease to exist just because you can’t make sense of them. No logic or its absence thereof can ever invalidate something that has been felt. In fact, I think it’s comforting that there’s at least one part of life which is ruled by the subconscious and there is peace in the knowledge that this has already been determined for us and it’s not something that needs to be built and established. It is an exercise in futility to try and tamper with these desires. Desires arise from within, what happens on the outside is merely the manifestation. Let sexuality be outside the realm of your control. Let your fantasies betray you.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Be a Man: a Discourse on 21st Century Masculinity</title>
      <link href="/Be-a-Man" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Be a Man: a Discourse on 21st Century Masculinity" />
      <published>2019-03-14T01:45:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-14T01:45:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Be-a-Man</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Be-a-Man">&lt;p&gt;The Gillette Advert has, for reasons I do not fully understand, caused a
sensation. There are people who are praising it for sending out the right
message on toxic masculinity, and there are people condemning it vociferously
for portraying masculinity as inherently evil. The fact, however, is that an
advert really matters little—they are ultimately paid promotions of products,
not vehicles of social change, and the people who are quick to heap praise or
criticism on it (especially in this case) are either pretentious or simply
b*tthurt. Yet, even in what I consider to be an overreaction about a simple
advert on shaving products, there’s a deeper discussion that is going on. For
more than a couple of thousand years, men across the world have been told that
they are stronger, better and smarter; it has been their job to be responsible
for ‘their’ women and ‘their’ children; it has been their duty to die first in
battle and it has been their job to take charge without shedding a tear and
without ever doubting oneself. But now, in these feminist times, assumptions
about masculinity are not only being challenged but also being designated as
evil—and for a good reason. But with all of this change, masculinity is being
radically redefined. The question is &lt;em&gt;what should it be redefined into?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One has to appreciate the difficulty of this question to even begin to answer
it. There are so many issues, from the plain-fact biological to the unwittingly
socio-cultural, that one does not know what to address first. This means all
thoughts about what masculinity ought to be cannot be discussed in the abstract, for we
simply do not know what the source of masculinity as a social or perhaps natural
construct really is. All we can try to do is pragmatically accept its existence
and move on to see how we can mould it to suit our times—in both a moral and
philosophical sense. And that again reinforces the fact that instead of some
grand theory of what it &lt;em&gt;must mean to be a man&lt;/em&gt;, we must develop more specific
guidelines on what it &lt;em&gt;should mean to be a man&lt;/em&gt;.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fairly good place to begin would be in the surprisingly simple but
controversial question of who should pay for a date between heterosexual
couples. One can easily see why “old-world masculinity” would always make the
man pay: Men were supposed to have the financial resources which they would use
to ‘woo’ women. With women possessing little financial independence (or any
independence, really), and depending on men for nearly everything material, men
paying for dates made sense—even if it was due to unjust laws and the fantasies
of the patriarchy with regard to its own benevolence. But all of that has
changed now and women are (at least on paper) not denied basic rights like the
one to property, a voice and to work. So, the idea that men should have an
obligation to pay for food and alcohol as a projection of their ability to give
a damn when seeing someone seems morally bankrupt, not to mention unfair as
well. Yet, a change of the rules to equal sharing seems ham-handed. It does not
take into account that sometimes people are feeling rich or bound to old-school
values for no discernible reason. More importantly, it simply denies agency to
people, instead of letting them negotiate it with each other. A better kind of
masculinity that truly involves an end to male presumptions of power and
responsibility cannot simply say: &lt;em&gt;Thou shalt split the bill for thou art equal&lt;/em&gt;.
That is only a sign of compromising pride; it is a technical solution to a
psychological problem. The rules on dating must be an expression of true
cooperation, and they can only begin to be so when people recognise that
independent, equal individuals decide matters among themselves. To say that
people must split the bill all the time is to mould a masculinity that need not
actually listen or cooperate, for it feels that there is a simple rule in place.
But to say: there are no rules, you must exercise self-respect and empathy when
negotiating who pays, re-enforces a most important aspect of what modern
masculinity should be. It symbolises an attempt to outgrow the need for the
patriarchy itself as a balm to one’s self-esteem. A contextualised, no
overarching rules approach encourages real interaction, it forces both men and
women to actually ask the question of what is fair when two people, equal in
dignity, decide to strike a settlement for mutual benefit.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masculinity is undeniably linked to &lt;em&gt;how good men feel about themselves&lt;/em&gt;. I don’t
know if there is something biological to it or if it is purely cultural, but the
male to female ratio of suicides is proof to me that men not feeling good about
themselves has some serious consequences. Many people identify the root of this
problem to be toxic masculinity, but that only addresses the surface of the
issue. Of course, a man being forced to bottle all emotion save aggression is
bound to be attracted to suicide in the face of life’s sh*t. But conversely,
without a feeling of independence and strength in the face of one’s fears,
they’re not bound to feel very good about themselves either. The old patriarchal
notion of masculinity is not entirely wrong in wanting men to weather things
stoically. It is simply important for both men and women to try and take control
of their lives when in crisis, rather than near-constantly crying about it. The
only thing a new masculinity needs to do is stop emasculating an expression of
emotion, whilst certainly rewarding personal fortitude and the ability to
skilfully (and quietly) manage one’s misery. Without this positive change,
masculinity risks either being dependent on the fragile male ego of being ‘hard’
or being a source of emotional release that does not provide courage. This new
notion of male self-belief tells us that boys should cry, that they should not
be unwilling to admit to sadness and dejection. However, it cautions us that
crying should not replace men’s self-worth by perpetuating avoidance and
self-doubt. In other words, modern masculinity must give men a better way to
cry: it must tell them they must be “man enough” to be able to do so, and “man
enough” to be able to overcome the urge to only do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the crying bit set aside, the more difficult questions put forward by the
&lt;em&gt;#metoo&lt;/em&gt; movement need to be addressed. It is clear that old-world masculinity
has either failed to deal with an oppressive culture in the workplace or in
enforcing rules of consent. The problem is obvious: the patriarchy does make
women objects. But that misses the forest for the trees, for it does not ask the
difficult question of &lt;em&gt;why society decided to have the patriarchy in the first
place&lt;/em&gt;. I would contend the answer to that question is tantalisingly simple. As
Devdutt Pattanaik, a popular Indian mythologist contends, human beings have “the
patriarchy” verily because nature doesn’t consider males to be that important.
In nature, all that a whole pride of lionesses requires is one (perhaps two)
male lions to produce the next generation of cubs. Human society is entirely
different, even if it has polygamy or polyandry, it tries to value every virile
male as a prospective husband or partner for his ability to care for and produce
human offspring. Practically speaking, this translates into the notion of the
patriarchy, where a literal race for being an alpha male is replaced with the
notion that every male who can find a female(s) has rights and obligations in
relation to that female—which other males are restricted from having. This
creates some kind of social order, but it makes men, whether fathers, brothers,
husbands or lovers, believe that they can (and must) control what happens to the
females associated with them. And this leads to the inevitable manifestation of
the patriarchy that the #metoo movement has so clearly exposed. Men will (if
they choose) assert what they consider “sexual rights” over the women who are
associated with them because they believe their association with them, whether
at the workplace or inside a marriage, gives them that right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cultural paradigm so described is the source of all problems discussed in
the previous paragraphs, it is this fundamental insecurity of not being an alpha
male that leads to men wanting to own, protect and control the women they have
around them. They have to do so, there must be rules that enforce so, otherwise
all of us ‘inadequate’ men will be naturally selected out. We must ensure “our
property” understands who they belong to, whether it be through non-disclosure
agreements or entertaining our putrid pick-up lines at the workplace. One can
combat the patriarchy as a construct, but that hardly addresses the fragile male
ego that underpins this socio-cultural construct. To combat that, men need to be
told that their honour and their power doesn’t reside in their control of the
women around them. Men need to be reminded that it is okay if they feel
inadequate, that they must never seek subjugation of women (or anyone) as a
therapy for low self-esteem and an absurd “will to power”. How does one
crystallise that abstract notion in a practical context? Simple: to quote a
friend, we must remind men that &lt;em&gt;“life is an embarrassment, and we’re going to
die anyway”&lt;/em&gt;. So, if we find ourselves being unable to get the women we want, it
really matters little. The fundamental mortality and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Understanding-the-Absurdity-of-Life&quot;&gt;absurdity of life&lt;/a&gt; mean that
our need to define our self-worth through our power over women (or anything) is
futile—for we’re already inadequate, to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, that is the existential reality that stares at us men every time we
discuss what it means to be a man. We men already realise, deep down, that we
are pathetically inadequate. If we weren’t, we wouldn’t have to construct so
many fallacies to make ourselves feel better, whether they be rules that project
our wealth, rules on not crying, or rules that state: “boys will be boys”.
My conception of masculinity expresses a core desire to do away with all those
stupid rules that are completely unfit for a most egalitarian age. A new kind of
masculinity must rely on fostering an inner strength that lets men outgrow our
base fears. Self-esteem, in any moral or philosophical sense, cannot come from
the outside; it cannot come from protecting or subjugating others. Self-esteem
or the belief in oneself must be exuded, it must be a source of impregnable
strength from within. A modern definition of masculinity must reflect this deep
truth, it must seek to give men the ability to outgrow their weaknesses (and,
therefore, the patriarchy) and to embrace a more complete personality that is a
result of true internal self-belief.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Gillette Advert has, for reasons I do not fully understand, caused a sensation. There are people who are praising it for sending out the right message on toxic masculinity, and there are people condemning it vociferously for portraying masculinity as inherently evil. The fact, however, is that an advert really matters little—they are ultimately paid promotions of products, not vehicles of social change, and the people who are quick to heap praise or criticism on it (especially in this case) are either pretentious or simply b*tthurt. Yet, even in what I consider to be an overreaction about a simple advert on shaving products, there’s a deeper discussion that is going on. For more than a couple of thousand years, men across the world have been told that they are stronger, better and smarter; it has been their job to be responsible for ‘their’ women and ‘their’ children; it has been their duty to die first in battle and it has been their job to take charge without shedding a tear and without ever doubting oneself. But now, in these feminist times, assumptions about masculinity are not only being challenged but also being designated as evil—and for a good reason. But with all of this change, masculinity is being radically redefined. The question is what should it be redefined into? One has to appreciate the difficulty of this question to even begin to answer it. There are so many issues, from the plain-fact biological to the unwittingly socio-cultural, that one does not know what to address first. This means all thoughts about what masculinity ought to be cannot be discussed in the abstract, for we simply do not know what the source of masculinity as a social or perhaps natural construct really is. All we can try to do is pragmatically accept its existence and move on to see how we can mould it to suit our times—in both a moral and philosophical sense. And that again reinforces the fact that instead of some grand theory of what it must mean to be a man, we must develop more specific guidelines on what it should mean to be a man.    A fairly good place to begin would be in the surprisingly simple but controversial question of who should pay for a date between heterosexual couples. One can easily see why “old-world masculinity” would always make the man pay: Men were supposed to have the financial resources which they would use to ‘woo’ women. With women possessing little financial independence (or any independence, really), and depending on men for nearly everything material, men paying for dates made sense—even if it was due to unjust laws and the fantasies of the patriarchy with regard to its own benevolence. But all of that has changed now and women are (at least on paper) not denied basic rights like the one to property, a voice and to work. So, the idea that men should have an obligation to pay for food and alcohol as a projection of their ability to give a damn when seeing someone seems morally bankrupt, not to mention unfair as well. Yet, a change of the rules to equal sharing seems ham-handed. It does not take into account that sometimes people are feeling rich or bound to old-school values for no discernible reason. More importantly, it simply denies agency to people, instead of letting them negotiate it with each other. A better kind of masculinity that truly involves an end to male presumptions of power and responsibility cannot simply say: Thou shalt split the bill for thou art equal. That is only a sign of compromising pride; it is a technical solution to a psychological problem. The rules on dating must be an expression of true cooperation, and they can only begin to be so when people recognise that independent, equal individuals decide matters among themselves. To say that people must split the bill all the time is to mould a masculinity that need not actually listen or cooperate, for it feels that there is a simple rule in place. But to say: there are no rules, you must exercise self-respect and empathy when negotiating who pays, re-enforces a most important aspect of what modern masculinity should be. It symbolises an attempt to outgrow the need for the patriarchy itself as a balm to one’s self-esteem. A contextualised, no overarching rules approach encourages real interaction, it forces both men and women to actually ask the question of what is fair when two people, equal in dignity, decide to strike a settlement for mutual benefit.      Masculinity is undeniably linked to how good men feel about themselves. I don’t know if there is something biological to it or if it is purely cultural, but the male to female ratio of suicides is proof to me that men not feeling good about themselves has some serious consequences. Many people identify the root of this problem to be toxic masculinity, but that only addresses the surface of the issue. Of course, a man being forced to bottle all emotion save aggression is bound to be attracted to suicide in the face of life’s sh*t. But conversely, without a feeling of independence and strength in the face of one’s fears, they’re not bound to feel very good about themselves either. The old patriarchal notion of masculinity is not entirely wrong in wanting men to weather things stoically. It is simply important for both men and women to try and take control of their lives when in crisis, rather than near-constantly crying about it. The only thing a new masculinity needs to do is stop emasculating an expression of emotion, whilst certainly rewarding personal fortitude and the ability to skilfully (and quietly) manage one’s misery. Without this positive change, masculinity risks either being dependent on the fragile male ego of being ‘hard’ or being a source of emotional release that does not provide courage. This new notion of male self-belief tells us that boys should cry, that they should not be unwilling to admit to sadness and dejection. However, it cautions us that crying should not replace men’s self-worth by perpetuating avoidance and self-doubt. In other words, modern masculinity must give men a better way to cry: it must tell them they must be “man enough” to be able to do so, and “man enough” to be able to overcome the urge to only do so. With the crying bit set aside, the more difficult questions put forward by the #metoo movement need to be addressed. It is clear that old-world masculinity has either failed to deal with an oppressive culture in the workplace or in enforcing rules of consent. The problem is obvious: the patriarchy does make women objects. But that misses the forest for the trees, for it does not ask the difficult question of why society decided to have the patriarchy in the first place. I would contend the answer to that question is tantalisingly simple. As Devdutt Pattanaik, a popular Indian mythologist contends, human beings have “the patriarchy” verily because nature doesn’t consider males to be that important. In nature, all that a whole pride of lionesses requires is one (perhaps two) male lions to produce the next generation of cubs. Human society is entirely different, even if it has polygamy or polyandry, it tries to value every virile male as a prospective husband or partner for his ability to care for and produce human offspring. Practically speaking, this translates into the notion of the patriarchy, where a literal race for being an alpha male is replaced with the notion that every male who can find a female(s) has rights and obligations in relation to that female—which other males are restricted from having. This creates some kind of social order, but it makes men, whether fathers, brothers, husbands or lovers, believe that they can (and must) control what happens to the females associated with them. And this leads to the inevitable manifestation of the patriarchy that the #metoo movement has so clearly exposed. Men will (if they choose) assert what they consider “sexual rights” over the women who are associated with them because they believe their association with them, whether at the workplace or inside a marriage, gives them that right. The cultural paradigm so described is the source of all problems discussed in the previous paragraphs, it is this fundamental insecurity of not being an alpha male that leads to men wanting to own, protect and control the women they have around them. They have to do so, there must be rules that enforce so, otherwise all of us ‘inadequate’ men will be naturally selected out. We must ensure “our property” understands who they belong to, whether it be through non-disclosure agreements or entertaining our putrid pick-up lines at the workplace. One can combat the patriarchy as a construct, but that hardly addresses the fragile male ego that underpins this socio-cultural construct. To combat that, men need to be told that their honour and their power doesn’t reside in their control of the women around them. Men need to be reminded that it is okay if they feel inadequate, that they must never seek subjugation of women (or anyone) as a therapy for low self-esteem and an absurd “will to power”. How does one crystallise that abstract notion in a practical context? Simple: to quote a friend, we must remind men that “life is an embarrassment, and we’re going to die anyway”. So, if we find ourselves being unable to get the women we want, it really matters little. The fundamental mortality and absurdity of life mean that our need to define our self-worth through our power over women (or anything) is futile—for we’re already inadequate, to begin with. In fact, that is the existential reality that stares at us men every time we discuss what it means to be a man. We men already realise, deep down, that we are pathetically inadequate. If we weren’t, we wouldn’t have to construct so many fallacies to make ourselves feel better, whether they be rules that project our wealth, rules on not crying, or rules that state: “boys will be boys”. My conception of masculinity expresses a core desire to do away with all those stupid rules that are completely unfit for a most egalitarian age. A new kind of masculinity must rely on fostering an inner strength that lets men outgrow our base fears. Self-esteem, in any moral or philosophical sense, cannot come from the outside; it cannot come from protecting or subjugating others. Self-esteem or the belief in oneself must be exuded, it must be a source of impregnable strength from within. A modern definition of masculinity must reflect this deep truth, it must seek to give men the ability to outgrow their weaknesses (and, therefore, the patriarchy) and to embrace a more complete personality that is a result of true internal self-belief.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Most Hated Religion in the World</title>
      <link href="/The-Most-Hated-Religion-in-the-World" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Most Hated Religion in the World" />
      <published>2019-03-07T04:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-07T04:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Most-Hated-Religion-in-the-World</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Most-Hated-Religion-in-the-World">&lt;p&gt;If you were to ask the Joe on the street “Which is the most
hated/persecuted/marginalized religious group in the world?” you would probably
get a range of different answers, depending upon the interviewee’s political
orientation(s).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People leaning towards the left would most likely say, “Islam. Islamophobia is a
big problem in the West. Definitely.” Others leaning towards the right would
probably say “The Jews. They have suffered the most and even now, Israel is
under threat from Islamic fundamentalists. We must stand with Israel.” In India,
it would probably be, “The Hindus! Just look at the Kashmiri Pandits.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I don’t deny that each of these groups has suffered immensely in the past. I
sympathise strongly with anyone who has been persecuted or discriminated against
in the secular sphere on the basis of their race, religion, economic status or
sex. It goes without saying that I condemn all forms of religious bigotry. But
in my humble opinion, neither Islam nor Judaism can claim the title. In my mind,
the most hated religion in the world today is Catholic Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“What?!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know. It sounds strange. But spare me the incredulous look, because I am just
about to back up my claims with extraordinarily strong evidence. But before I do
that, let me tell you my story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I myself was raised in the Hindu community, but after a decade-long search for
the truth, I lost faith in the faith of my forefathers. I am now making my way
across to Christianity, and in all likelihood, I will end up either Roman
Catholic or in Eastern Orthodoxy. I have studied more religions and
denominations than I can remember – from the Ahl-e-Hadith (and the lesser known
Ahl-e-Qur’an) to the long-extinct Zurvanism – and I will soon begin an
undergraduate degree in Theology at the University of Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friends, I can testify with all my heart that there is no religious group
that is more maligned, slandered and attacked in popular culture than the
Catholic Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each and every worldview is built upon some major controlling narrative or the
other. Modern society is the offspring of three great ideological uprisings in
the past, all of which are overtly and vehemently anti-Catholic, either
prominently or tangentially. You might have guessed two of them, but the third
one may surprise you. I am speaking of the Enlightenment, the Protestant
Reformation and the rise of Marxism. Now let’s consider their controlling
narratives one by one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Enlightenment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world had great and immense potential since the evolution of the &lt;em&gt;homo
sapiens&lt;/em&gt;. A great example of this was Europe, which in the classical world was a
great hub of learning, philosophy, art, and science. Great thinkers and minds
arose who tirelessly “stretched forward their hands towards perfection” in
Greece and Rome. All of this was happening – until the rise of Christianity, the
most intolerant branch of which is the Catholic Church. Led by the theocratic
impositions of Constantine, the Catholic Church brought all of Europe under
their tyrannical captivity. Superstition reigned; science was stifled; the
freedom of the heart was curbed; man was put into chains. The growth and
progress of Europe were stunted… until the great Renaissance dawned upon
mankind, and Europe was reborn – a phoenix rising from the ashes. The captivity
of Rome was overthrown and the great continent emerged, to build its future on
its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Protestant Reformation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning, Christ and the Apostles built up the Church and commanded them
to preach the Gospel far and wide. All was going well… but over the centuries,
slowly but gradually, pagan influence began to creep into the Church.
Superstition and idolatry gradually came to cloud the Gospel, and eventually, it
was lost for good! The situation was especially bad in Western Europe, where the
Pope presided in the place of God, reigning down his ungodly tyranny upon the
masses, chaining the Christian and denying him his rightful freedom. The Spirit
of God departed for a while from the pagan Roman church… until at last, the
seeds laid by the great martyrs Wycliffe and Hus bore fruit, and the heroes of
the faith – Luther, Zwingli, and Calvin – emerged. These luminaries showed us
the path and helped us break the chains of Roman tyranny. The Reformation was a
glorious cleansing of the church, and countless souls were freed from the
captivity of the Roman harlot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marxism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History is marked primarily by class-struggle. From ages past, the privileged
(the haves) have oppressed the have-nots. A prime example of this is seen in the
decadent, superstitious Catholic Church. This is an organisation that has
promoted colonialism (the Crusades being a great example) and continues to have
an authoritarian patriarchal structure of clericalism and privilege that
oppresses the common man. To this day, the Pope and his henchmen participate in
the oppression of the masses, by opposing abortion, contraception and denying
women equality by not ordaining them to the priesthood. This organisation must
change, or perish. The common people must arise out of the chains of this
tyranny!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you have been studying the three movements I describe, you will quickly
see that absolutely nothing I have written is an exaggeration. For example, if
you are acquainted with Protestant polemical literature (as I am), you will
notice that many of the terms I have used – “Roman harlot”, “Roman [Babylonian]
captivity”, “freedom of the Christian”, “chains of bondage and superstition”,
“false gospel”, etc. – are not mine, but the exact terms used by Protestants to
this day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice also, another thing: though these movements all originated in Europe,
they have since then been widely disseminated. There are more than 900 million
Protestants around the world (almost an eighth of the world population). The
philosophy of the Enlightenment has spread around the globe as well, as
evidenced by the fact that most of the countries in the world are (or, at least,
claim to be) liberal secular democracies. And, of course, Marxism has claimed
the most populous country in the world as its own and continues to have a loud
presence around the world (particularly among the students and youth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it just me? Am I just seeing it this way because I myself strongly lean RC?
(Well, technically, I began leaning RC after I saw its theology being vastly
misrepresented and slandered in Protestant fundamentalist circles on the
internet). But it’s not just me by any stretch of the imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is what pro-life activist, journalist and Orthodox Jew Ben Shapiro had to
say at a conference in Dana Point, CA: “Unfortunately, the attacks [by radical
leftists] on Catholics have come first and foremost […] It’s really fascinating
to watch, not just from a Jewish perspective. Usually, we’re the first on the
hit list. Now it’s you guys.” Shapiro went on to note several instances of
anti-Catholic prejudice in the popular media. But one could also note the
attitude of contempt several Democrat politicians displayed towards conservative
Catholicism as we see, for example, US Senator Diane Feinstein’s bluntly stated
to the Catholic judicial nominee Amy Barrett, “The dogma lives loudly within
you”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about the historical data? Don’t they prove that the Catholic Church
is, indeed, so to speak, “guilty as charged”? Not so, says non-Catholic
sociologist, University of California Berkeley scholar and Pulitzer
Prize-winning author Rodney Stark, who has written many books on Christian
history, including several defending Catholicism from what he says as unfounded
attacks and slanderous misrepresentations. Among his many works are &lt;em&gt;God’s
Battalions: The Case for the Crusades&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Reformation Myths and Bearing False
Witness: Debunking Centuries of Anti-Catholic Lies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;America, of course, is historically extremely anti-Catholic. And with the
worldwide dominance of American culture as well as the proliferation of
American-style Evangelicalism, anti-Catholicism too has spread around the world.
But don’t take my word for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ryan Reeves is Cambridge scholar and a professor of Church history at
Gordon-Conwell Theological Seminary, one of the eminent Protestant institutions
in the USA. Several of his lectures are available on his YouTube channel (in my
opinion, an invaluable contribution to public education). I highly recommend his
lecture &lt;em&gt;Catholics in America&lt;/em&gt;. In it, Reeves discusses how, historically, large
sections of the Protestant population in America have always tried to,
especially in the face of Catholic immigration, “slander and to mock and to
lampoon Catholics, in an effort to demoralize and ideally to get them to convert
to Protestantism”. (Since Professor Reeves is teaching at a well-respected
Protestant institution, I will similarly assume that he is a Protestant and has
no dog in this fight.) He goes on to discuss historically famous instances of
anti-Catholic propaganda, including the ghost-written 18th century bestseller
autobiography of “Maria Monk”, which claimed to expose scandalous debauchery and
immorality within Catholic convents, and which – according to Dr. Reeves - we
now know to be a complete hoax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-evidently, hatred against Catholics must change due to the simple social
rule that one ought not to be persecuted for one’s beliefs. Here are three
things which I think need to happen in order to help the situation change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, people need to better appreciate and understand the Catholic Church’s
rich and vibrant intellectual history, especially the glories of the Middle Ages - figures like Aquinas, Anselm, Ockham, Peter Abelard, Duns Scotus and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the anti-fideism of Catholic theology needs to be properly recognised
as well (I’m looking at you, Christopher Hitchens). The doctrine of the
interplay and complementary nature of faith and reason, popularised by Aquinas
and officially adopted by the Catholic Church at the First Vatican Council, will
only lead the devout Catholic to a deeper admiration of and respect towards the
sciences, not a fear of them. Hence, we have great Catholic scientists like
Gregor Mendel, George Lemaitre, Roger Bacon, Albertus Magnus and – of course –
Nicolaus Copernicus (who, by the way, was respected and admired by several
Catholic clergymen of his time, including Pope Clement VII). For example, on
November 1, 1536, Cardinal Nikolaus von Schönberg, Archbishop of Capua, wrote to
Copernicus expressing profound admiration, and requesting him to tell him more
about his new cosmology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, people need to remember the mistakes made by Catholics in the past.
Yes, Catholics are not, and have never been, perfect people. They have made
mistakes, like any other group. We must not repeat the errors of antiquity, and
we must remember and learn from them. But, at the same time, we must also
recognise the fact that the Catholic hierarchy (I’m talking about folks like
Popes John Paul II and Francis I) has publicly apologised for many of the past
excesses and sought forgiveness for the same. An institution that is ready to
own up to its mistakes in such a public manner shines a ray of hope for the
world. And it is only such an attitude of humility, repentance, and desire to
change that will help contemporary Catholics overcome the ecclesiastical abuses
and errors of the modern world.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">If you were to ask the Joe on the street “Which is the most hated/persecuted/marginalized religious group in the world?” you would probably get a range of different answers, depending upon the interviewee’s political orientation(s). People leaning towards the left would most likely say, “Islam. Islamophobia is a big problem in the West. Definitely.” Others leaning towards the right would probably say “The Jews. They have suffered the most and even now, Israel is under threat from Islamic fundamentalists. We must stand with Israel.” In India, it would probably be, “The Hindus! Just look at the Kashmiri Pandits.” And I don’t deny that each of these groups has suffered immensely in the past. I sympathise strongly with anyone who has been persecuted or discriminated against in the secular sphere on the basis of their race, religion, economic status or sex. It goes without saying that I condemn all forms of religious bigotry. But in my humble opinion, neither Islam nor Judaism can claim the title. In my mind, the most hated religion in the world today is Catholic Christianity. “What?!” I know. It sounds strange. But spare me the incredulous look, because I am just about to back up my claims with extraordinarily strong evidence. But before I do that, let me tell you my story. I myself was raised in the Hindu community, but after a decade-long search for the truth, I lost faith in the faith of my forefathers. I am now making my way across to Christianity, and in all likelihood, I will end up either Roman Catholic or in Eastern Orthodoxy. I have studied more religions and denominations than I can remember – from the Ahl-e-Hadith (and the lesser known Ahl-e-Qur’an) to the long-extinct Zurvanism – and I will soon begin an undergraduate degree in Theology at the University of Oxford. My friends, I can testify with all my heart that there is no religious group that is more maligned, slandered and attacked in popular culture than the Catholic Church. Each and every worldview is built upon some major controlling narrative or the other. Modern society is the offspring of three great ideological uprisings in the past, all of which are overtly and vehemently anti-Catholic, either prominently or tangentially. You might have guessed two of them, but the third one may surprise you. I am speaking of the Enlightenment, the Protestant Reformation and the rise of Marxism. Now let’s consider their controlling narratives one by one. The Enlightenment The world had great and immense potential since the evolution of the homo sapiens. A great example of this was Europe, which in the classical world was a great hub of learning, philosophy, art, and science. Great thinkers and minds arose who tirelessly “stretched forward their hands towards perfection” in Greece and Rome. All of this was happening – until the rise of Christianity, the most intolerant branch of which is the Catholic Church. Led by the theocratic impositions of Constantine, the Catholic Church brought all of Europe under their tyrannical captivity. Superstition reigned; science was stifled; the freedom of the heart was curbed; man was put into chains. The growth and progress of Europe were stunted… until the great Renaissance dawned upon mankind, and Europe was reborn – a phoenix rising from the ashes. The captivity of Rome was overthrown and the great continent emerged, to build its future on its own. The Protestant Reformation In the beginning, Christ and the Apostles built up the Church and commanded them to preach the Gospel far and wide. All was going well… but over the centuries, slowly but gradually, pagan influence began to creep into the Church. Superstition and idolatry gradually came to cloud the Gospel, and eventually, it was lost for good! The situation was especially bad in Western Europe, where the Pope presided in the place of God, reigning down his ungodly tyranny upon the masses, chaining the Christian and denying him his rightful freedom. The Spirit of God departed for a while from the pagan Roman church… until at last, the seeds laid by the great martyrs Wycliffe and Hus bore fruit, and the heroes of the faith – Luther, Zwingli, and Calvin – emerged. These luminaries showed us the path and helped us break the chains of Roman tyranny. The Reformation was a glorious cleansing of the church, and countless souls were freed from the captivity of the Roman harlot. Marxism History is marked primarily by class-struggle. From ages past, the privileged (the haves) have oppressed the have-nots. A prime example of this is seen in the decadent, superstitious Catholic Church. This is an organisation that has promoted colonialism (the Crusades being a great example) and continues to have an authoritarian patriarchal structure of clericalism and privilege that oppresses the common man. To this day, the Pope and his henchmen participate in the oppression of the masses, by opposing abortion, contraception and denying women equality by not ordaining them to the priesthood. This organisation must change, or perish. The common people must arise out of the chains of this tyranny! Now, if you have been studying the three movements I describe, you will quickly see that absolutely nothing I have written is an exaggeration. For example, if you are acquainted with Protestant polemical literature (as I am), you will notice that many of the terms I have used – “Roman harlot”, “Roman [Babylonian] captivity”, “freedom of the Christian”, “chains of bondage and superstition”, “false gospel”, etc. – are not mine, but the exact terms used by Protestants to this day! Notice also, another thing: though these movements all originated in Europe, they have since then been widely disseminated. There are more than 900 million Protestants around the world (almost an eighth of the world population). The philosophy of the Enlightenment has spread around the globe as well, as evidenced by the fact that most of the countries in the world are (or, at least, claim to be) liberal secular democracies. And, of course, Marxism has claimed the most populous country in the world as its own and continues to have a loud presence around the world (particularly among the students and youth). Is it just me? Am I just seeing it this way because I myself strongly lean RC? (Well, technically, I began leaning RC after I saw its theology being vastly misrepresented and slandered in Protestant fundamentalist circles on the internet). But it’s not just me by any stretch of the imagination. Here is what pro-life activist, journalist and Orthodox Jew Ben Shapiro had to say at a conference in Dana Point, CA: “Unfortunately, the attacks [by radical leftists] on Catholics have come first and foremost […] It’s really fascinating to watch, not just from a Jewish perspective. Usually, we’re the first on the hit list. Now it’s you guys.” Shapiro went on to note several instances of anti-Catholic prejudice in the popular media. But one could also note the attitude of contempt several Democrat politicians displayed towards conservative Catholicism as we see, for example, US Senator Diane Feinstein’s bluntly stated to the Catholic judicial nominee Amy Barrett, “The dogma lives loudly within you”. But what about the historical data? Don’t they prove that the Catholic Church is, indeed, so to speak, “guilty as charged”? Not so, says non-Catholic sociologist, University of California Berkeley scholar and Pulitzer Prize-winning author Rodney Stark, who has written many books on Christian history, including several defending Catholicism from what he says as unfounded attacks and slanderous misrepresentations. Among his many works are God’s Battalions: The Case for the Crusades, Reformation Myths and Bearing False Witness: Debunking Centuries of Anti-Catholic Lies. America, of course, is historically extremely anti-Catholic. And with the worldwide dominance of American culture as well as the proliferation of American-style Evangelicalism, anti-Catholicism too has spread around the world. But don’t take my word for it. Ryan Reeves is Cambridge scholar and a professor of Church history at Gordon-Conwell Theological Seminary, one of the eminent Protestant institutions in the USA. Several of his lectures are available on his YouTube channel (in my opinion, an invaluable contribution to public education). I highly recommend his lecture Catholics in America. In it, Reeves discusses how, historically, large sections of the Protestant population in America have always tried to, especially in the face of Catholic immigration, “slander and to mock and to lampoon Catholics, in an effort to demoralize and ideally to get them to convert to Protestantism”. (Since Professor Reeves is teaching at a well-respected Protestant institution, I will similarly assume that he is a Protestant and has no dog in this fight.) He goes on to discuss historically famous instances of anti-Catholic propaganda, including the ghost-written 18th century bestseller autobiography of “Maria Monk”, which claimed to expose scandalous debauchery and immorality within Catholic convents, and which – according to Dr. Reeves - we now know to be a complete hoax. Self-evidently, hatred against Catholics must change due to the simple social rule that one ought not to be persecuted for one’s beliefs. Here are three things which I think need to happen in order to help the situation change. Firstly, people need to better appreciate and understand the Catholic Church’s rich and vibrant intellectual history, especially the glories of the Middle Ages - figures like Aquinas, Anselm, Ockham, Peter Abelard, Duns Scotus and so on. Secondly, the anti-fideism of Catholic theology needs to be properly recognised as well (I’m looking at you, Christopher Hitchens). The doctrine of the interplay and complementary nature of faith and reason, popularised by Aquinas and officially adopted by the Catholic Church at the First Vatican Council, will only lead the devout Catholic to a deeper admiration of and respect towards the sciences, not a fear of them. Hence, we have great Catholic scientists like Gregor Mendel, George Lemaitre, Roger Bacon, Albertus Magnus and – of course – Nicolaus Copernicus (who, by the way, was respected and admired by several Catholic clergymen of his time, including Pope Clement VII). For example, on November 1, 1536, Cardinal Nikolaus von Schönberg, Archbishop of Capua, wrote to Copernicus expressing profound admiration, and requesting him to tell him more about his new cosmology. Thirdly, people need to remember the mistakes made by Catholics in the past. Yes, Catholics are not, and have never been, perfect people. They have made mistakes, like any other group. We must not repeat the errors of antiquity, and we must remember and learn from them. But, at the same time, we must also recognise the fact that the Catholic hierarchy (I’m talking about folks like Popes John Paul II and Francis I) has publicly apologised for many of the past excesses and sought forgiveness for the same. An institution that is ready to own up to its mistakes in such a public manner shines a ray of hope for the world. And it is only such an attitude of humility, repentance, and desire to change that will help contemporary Catholics overcome the ecclesiastical abuses and errors of the modern world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">On Criminals and Psychopaths: Why is Ted Bundy, Ted Bundy?</title>
      <link href="/On-Criminals-and-Psychopaths" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Criminals and Psychopaths: Why is Ted Bundy, Ted Bundy?" />
      <published>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/On-Criminals-and-Psychopaths</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/On-Criminals-and-Psychopaths">&lt;p&gt;From the infamous Roman Poison Ring to Lu Shenatir to Locusta the Gaul in the early moments of human civilization. From Samuel Mason, the famous highway gang-leader in the USA, to the infamous Elizabeth Bathory, also called the Blood Countess, who is claimed to have killed at least  400 people. And, more recently, from the infamous Jack The Ripper to H H Holmes and his house of murders. Humans and these so-called Masters of Death have a long history between them. As a certain psychological study in California notes, humans are originally designed to kill each other off. The infamous Biblical tale of Cain and Abel, it seems, was not a one-off tale of warning but rather a foreshadowing of the true nature of mankind and its base predispositions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the criminal context, this leads to some bold and difficult questions that have left even the Behavioral Science Unit of the FBI scratching their heads. How could we, by asking the right set of questions, successfully identify what kind of person is likely to commit a crime? How can we understand his possible motive behind his crime? And, most importantly, can we preempt the criminal’s future course of action? In examining these questions, the term this Behavioral Science Unit coined for the perpetrators of repeated crimes, i.e. ‘serial killer’ is now cult famous. These were the people who would go on a certain form of a spree, committing possibly similar or even dissimilar acts in order to prevent any trace leading up to them. The Unit was exploring how to connect these actions and how to develop a fool-proof method of doing so. Moreover, the Unit wanted to distinguish someone who just kills people and someone who does that because he believes the devil commands him to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were too many questions which could have been asked and none of them could have had any proper answers. But John E Douglas, a member of the Behavioral Science Unit, notes that there was a lot of fruit borne out of their investigations and rightly so. Douglas and his colleagues spent years interviewing criminals across penitentiaries all over the country in a span of more than a decade. Their subjects included Ted Bundy, the killer of several innocent girls, John Wayne Gacy, the infamous “Killer Clown”, who is also thought of to be the inspiration for &lt;em&gt;IT&lt;/em&gt;’s antagonist—a killer clown called Pennywise. The Unit interviewed the “Son of Sam”, David Berkowitz, who claimed that he shot people in cold blood because his cat – a manifestation of Satan himself – asked him to do so. They also interviewed Ed Kemper, a ‘giant’ in all literal senses with an extraordinary IQ of 145, who was convicted of killing his own mother, grandparents and 3 others whilst engaging in necrophilia with their bodies. The insight the Behavioral Science Unit gained from these studies influenced criminal profiling and psychopathic documentation over the years, giving rise to new fields within psychology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distinctive features, John Douglas noted, that were possessed by most of these subjects was an incessant amount of ego. Douglas compared Ted Kaczynski, the Unabomber who was an extraordinarily intelligent criminal, and Dennis Rader, a comparatively less-educated one, and said that both their downfalls were due to their narcissism. Douglas contended that a heightened sense of ego, a lack of remorse and all such associated feelings, innate aggression, a traumatic childhood, and a poor, sexually malignant upbringing were all factors that could contribute to a person’s choices of insanity and crimes. He wrote his critically-acclaimed book, &lt;em&gt;The Mindhunter&lt;/em&gt;, on his studies which till date serves as a manual for some at the Quantico, which is the training ground for FBI agents in the US. This book explores all of his findings and delves deeper into the psyche of how a psychopath could possibly be thinking in accordance with Freudian psycho-sexual stimulation or violence-induced arousal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interesting fact, however, is that Douglas points out that it is wrong to believe that all psychopaths are just remorseless, guiltless, killing machines. He says that there is more complexity to them than that. Psychopaths have a lopsided view of emotions and morality, it’s not that they don’t ‘feel’, just that they feel very differently from the way most people do. Their ability to take cold, completely unemotional decisions is one that is cherished by most CEOs in today’s world. The only difference between psychopathic killers and corporate executives is the presence of external factors like a tough childhood, poverty, trauma etc., which makes the former a threat to society. As it is posed by another psychopath, albeit fictional in this case, Hannibal Lecter from the series of books by Thomas Harris, the human mind has an unfathomable level of variability and complexity. Who knows for sure what makes the Bundys and the Kempers the people they are? All we know is that they’re not born so, they are made to be so.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">From the infamous Roman Poison Ring to Lu Shenatir to Locusta the Gaul in the early moments of human civilization. From Samuel Mason, the famous highway gang-leader in the USA, to the infamous Elizabeth Bathory, also called the Blood Countess, who is claimed to have killed at least 400 people. And, more recently, from the infamous Jack The Ripper to H H Holmes and his house of murders. Humans and these so-called Masters of Death have a long history between them. As a certain psychological study in California notes, humans are originally designed to kill each other off. The infamous Biblical tale of Cain and Abel, it seems, was not a one-off tale of warning but rather a foreshadowing of the true nature of mankind and its base predispositions.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Cry Me A River? A Dialogue on Laughing at Other People’s Pain</title>
      <link href="/Cry-Me-A-River" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cry Me A River? A Dialogue on Laughing at Other People's Pain" />
      <published>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Cry-Me-A-River</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Cry-Me-A-River">&lt;p&gt;While I was scrolling through Instagram, as one is bound to do for the 51st time, I found myself falling down the vortex of what one may only call the “Fail Videos”; and oh! was I there for the next hour or more (definitely more). But upon much thought about why it tickles us all to see someone fall down the stairs or to see them get hit by animals, I couldn’t justify my behaviour, it was hard for me to come up with a reason other than “…they probably deserved it.” Well, as a Psychology student who is pretty much taught to be empathetic, it irked me why this so happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t have to look much further, one search on Google and I was met with my favourite word ever: Schadenfreude. Oxford Dictionary defines Schadenfreude as pleasure derived by someone from another person’s misfortune. The word is borrowed from German and is a compound of Schaden, “damage, harm”, and Freude, ‘joy’. “Harm-Joy”, that’s the only equivalent in English one can find for this word. In fact, in 1926, a journalist in &lt;em&gt;The Spectator&lt;/em&gt; asserted that “there is no English word for Schadenfreude because there is no such feeling here.” We shall see about that, UK, we shall. One can mistake Sadism for it, but sadism has an implication of infliction, while Schadenfreude is about merely observing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;English might be falling behind on finding a word for this feeling, others? Not so much. The Japanese have a saying: “The misfortunes of others taste like honey.” The French speak of ‘joiemaligne’, a diabolical delight in other people’s suffering. The Danish talk of ‘skadefryd’, and the Dutch of ‘leedvermaak’. In Hebrew, enjoying other people’s catastrophes is ‘simcha la‑ed’, in Mandarin, ‘xìng‑zāi‑lè‑huò’, in Serbo-Croat it is ‘zlùradōst’, and in Russian ‘zloradstvo’. More than 2,000 years ago, Romans spoke of ‘malevolentia’. Earlier still, the Greeks described ‘epichairekakia’ (literally epi, over, chairo, rejoice, kakia, disgrace). “To see others suffer does one good,” wrote the philosopher Friedrich Nietzsche, “To make others suffer even more so. This is a hard saying, but a mighty, human, all-too-human principle.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking about the emotion, how does it even manifest itself? Exactly like joy does: gleam in our eyes, a wide smile, or perhaps a small one, one may even consider it a smirk. In a laboratory in Würzburg in Germany in 2015, thirty-two football fans agreed to have electromyography pads attached to their faces, which would measure their smiles and frowns while watching TV clips of successful and unsuccessful football penalties by the German team, and by their arch-rivals, the Dutch. The psychologists found that when the Dutch missed a goal, the German fans’ smiles appeared more quickly and were broader than when the German team scored a goal themselves. The smiles of Schadenfreude and joy are indistinguishable except in one crucial respect: we smile more at the failures of our enemies than at our own success. We have used humiliation and the failures of other people to make ourselves happy for a long time. We often use said emotion to work in our favour, people use self-deprecating stories in novice situations to evoke ease amongst the rest and present themselves as non-threatening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word was first mentioned in German in the 1740’s, and in English writing in 1853. Richard Chenevix Trench mentioned it in his book on philology &lt;em&gt;On the Study of Words&lt;/em&gt;. For Trench, however, the mere existence of the word Schadenfreude was unholy and fearful, a “mournful record of the strange wickednesses which the genius of man, so fertile in evil, has invented.” Ever since, several have spoken it and have eagerly adopted the word, associating it with a range of pleasures, from hilarity to self-righteous vindication, and from triumph to relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are five common themes to be found in the idea of Schadenfreude. The first being that Schadenfreude is usually thought of as an opportunistic pleasure, felt when we stumble across another’s misfortune which we have not caused ourselves. The Hollywood villain gloating when Bond is caught by his dastardly plot is not experiencing Schadenfreude, but sadistic pleasure. By contrast, the sidekick who sniggers as a Hollywood villain is accidentally foiled by his own dastardly plot when he trips and presses the self-destruct button is enjoying Schadenfreude. The second is as a furtive emotion, outbursts of merriment at another’s catastrophes are generally a sign of great villain-ness. Shylock can barely contain himself on learning that his rival Antonio has lost a cargo ship at sea: “I thank God, I thank God. Is’t true, is’t true?” We might be worried not just about looking malicious, but that our Schadenfreude exposes our other flaws too—our pettiness, our envy, our feelings of inadequacy. However, the third feature is that we often feel entitled to it when the other person’s suffering can be construed as a comeuppance—a deserved punishment for being smug or hypocritical or for breaking the law. While it is unlikely that we’d enjoy our moral superiority to their face, gloating is generally permissible at a safe distance. Fourth, we may see it as a form of respite—the failures of others appease our own envy and inadequacy and give us a much-needed feeling of superiority. And just as satire is only funny when it punches up, we are most comfortable sniggering at the failures of those more wealthy, attractive and talented than us. Fifth, often thought of as glee at minor discomforts and gaffes rather than at dire tragedies and deaths, we are willing to see celebrities, or people from the remote past, endure horrors that would dismay us if they were happening now or to our friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent decades, Schadenfreude has been talked about more often than ever. Now I don’t know what it says about our generation, i.e. if we’re more aware than ever or if Schadenfreude is a ‘problem’. A great multitude of researches exist to explain to us how it works, what ages experience it more, is it okay to experience it in the first place, and if not, how not to feel it? As somewhat of a researcher, I can conclude that the latter questions are yet to receive a clear answer. While everybody experiences it every now and then, the literature shows that people with the traits of Machiavellianism, narcissism, or psychopathy, together known as the “dark triad”, feel Schadenfreude more often. Some researchers propose that feeling Schadenfreude requires us to dehumanise the person whose failure we are laughing at. They further suggest dehumanisation might be the fundamental aspect of this emotion, though further research is needed before that can be proven. They sure sound dark, especially because Schadenfreude is such a universal emotion (this had me sweating, I can’t lie). But they justify it by suggesting that dehumanisation occurs more often than most would like to think. The researchers explain that people with low self-esteem are more likely to feel Schadenfreude when they see other people fail. This is because the success of others can be a threat to their sense of self and seeing the mighty fall can be a comfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In today’s age, Schadenfreude is all around us, it’s in the way we do politics, how we treat celebrities, and in online fail videos. We felt it when NASA lost a $125 million Mars orbiter because half the team was using imperial measurements, and the other half, metric. We felt it when Trump walked the ramp to his private flight with toilet paper stuck to his right shoe. We feel it when the self-righteous satisfaction of hypocrites is thoroughly exposed, when a celebrity is caught cheating on his/her significant other. You hear it when Bob Dylan sings ‘Like a Rolling Stone’, or when Jessie J flaunts her success in ‘Who’s Laughing Now’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The philosopher Arthur Schopenhauer called Schadenfreude “an infallible sign of a thoroughly bad heart and profound moral worthlessness,” the very worst trait in human nature. There are often comparisons to how the emotion is on the flip side of empathy. Debates muster up enough evidence for the same but not enough for the debate to be over. Twenty-first-century humanists who regard empathy as a “natural” response under threat in a frenetic, atomistic modern world find Schadenfreude awkward too. It has variously been called the “absence of empathy,” the “opposite of empathy” and “empathy’s shadow,” casting the two as fundamentally incompatible. Some suggest that only a few of us enjoy other people’s pain for its own sake, but more often because we have judged it deserved or useful in some way, evidence not strictly of malice but of our desire to preserve a moral balance. Schadenfreude has been told to be beneficial by some, a quick win which alleviates inferiority or envy; a way of bonding over the failure of a boss or smug senior colleague. And above all, it is a testament to our capacity for emotional flexibility, as opposed to moral rigidity, and our ability to hold apparently contradictory thoughts and feelings in the mind simultaneously. If asked, I’d say Schadenfreude and sympathy are not either/or responses as is sometimes suggested, but can be felt all at once, but, that is for all of us to seek for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schadenfreude has become a part of how we are engaging with everyone online – it creates camaraderie and political momentum. The big question for moral philosophers, now, is whether by enjoying Schadenfreude you are endangering empathy, trust, and a good society. Both ancient and early modern descriptions of comic enjoyment acknowledge proximity to cruelty, but they usually stop short of admitting kinship. The same goes for Schadenfreude, it may well be rested in the bed of cruelty but what connections may we retain? We may well be living in an Age of Schadenfreude, and fear that this emotion is leading us astray. But as with all emotions, condemning it only gets you so far. What we really need is to think afresh about the work this much-maligned emotion does for us, and what it tells us about our relationships with ourselves and each other. The brain will always choose pleasure over fear, always. Understanding why you feel what you feel creates an advantage and opportunity to respond with more thought than impulsivity. As a very smart lady once said, &lt;em&gt;“Don’t reach for the halo too soon. You have plenty of time to enjoy yourself, even a little maliciously sometimes, before you settle down to being a saint.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">While I was scrolling through Instagram, as one is bound to do for the 51st time, I found myself falling down the vortex of what one may only call the “Fail Videos”; and oh! was I there for the next hour or more (definitely more). But upon much thought about why it tickles us all to see someone fall down the stairs or to see them get hit by animals, I couldn’t justify my behaviour, it was hard for me to come up with a reason other than “…they probably deserved it.” Well, as a Psychology student who is pretty much taught to be empathetic, it irked me why this so happens.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Christendom Today: How Christianity is still Shaping the Modern World</title>
      <link href="/Christendom-Today" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Christendom Today: How Christianity is still Shaping the Modern World" />
      <published>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Christendom-Today</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Christendom-Today">&lt;p&gt;There are many religions in the world, but only Christianity can boast of having more than two billion followers across the world, comprising people from nearly every ethnicity, race, and social class. Even Islam – its closest contender and the “fastest growing religion in the world” is nearly a billion followers behind. But how is the religion that names itself after Jesus the Messiah influencing the 21st century? The answer may surprise you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christianity certainly is a house divided. The Protestant Reformation played a major role in this (and the proliferation of Protestant denominations continues to prove this) but it also made the Catholic Church wake up from centuries of semi-stagnation, resulting in a major resurgence of traditionalism, as we see in the great world missions of the Counter-Reformation. Indeed, the Jesuits – zealous evangelists and promoters of the Roman faith – probably wouldn’t have existed hadn’t it been for the polarising catalyst that was Martin Luther.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those divisions haven’t yet come to an end, rather Christianity is even more diverse than it was in the 17th century. Thankfully, the different bodies calling themselves Christian are reaching out to each other in a spirit of sincerity and dialogue and are repenting the terrible sectarian bloodshed that so often categorised post-Enlightenment Europe. But the various Christian ‘sects’ are still very different and continue to operate and influence the world in their own unique way. Let us begin with the largest group of all – the Roman Catholic Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“The Spirit of Vatican II”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mid-20th century, the Catholic Church held a worldwide pastoral council called the Second Council of the Vatican, or – to put it simply – “Vatican II” (hereafter referred to as V2). Unlike previous councils, V2 never chose to define dogma or clarify church teaching – rather it wanted to bring about ecclesiastical reforms to be able to better respond to the new world of the 20th century. But many Catholics agree that V2 was an absolute disaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V2 resulted in the sharp splintering of the Church. The liberals and the ‘modernists’ complain that it didn’t go far enough in eroding “medieval superstition”, while the conservatives argue that the ambiguous language in its documents creates a great danger for doctrinal error to be spread. In addition to these two groups, there are more than half-a-million traditionalist Catholics who reject it altogether, calling it a non-infallible “robber’s council” – the best example of this is the Priestly Society of St Pius X, with supporters around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, V2 has resulted in a change of attitude among many believers. Today, Catholics are much more focused on preaching about “social justice” than before. This is best seen in the lives of Mother Teresa and Oscar Romero, both saints of the Catholic Church, as well as in the current Pontiff, Pope Francis. The rise of the so-called “Liberation theology” has created a great impact in Latin America (particularly Brazil), with some calling it the “Marxist version of Catholicism”. The “left-wing Church” in this part of the world has played an instrumental role in protesting against totalitarian right-wing bigotry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberation theologians contend that the root cause of poverty and social injustice is sin (the implication being that social justice cannot return unless people begin to lead saintly lives) and that the poor, the oppressed and the marginalized are the “privileged channels of God’s grace”. The result is that a direct link has been made between theology and social activism. To be a good Christian, one must fight against and oppose oppressive structures of power, say the Liberation theologians. While Liberation theology is certainly not a branch of Communism in any formal sense of the word, the similarity with Marxist rhetoric has, at times, concerned many conservatives, not least among them being Pope Emeritus Benedict XVI. This is very ironic because the Catholic Church of the 20th century was one of the most powerful anti-Communist forces in the world, with many (including New York Times bestselling author and scholar Paul Kengor) crediting Pope St John Paul II as having played an instrumental role in the fall of the Soviet Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luther’s Revenge: The Worldwide Resurgence of Evangelicalism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evangelical Christianity is by far the most powerful and dynamic religious force in the world today. Evangelicalism is converting people by the hundreds of thousands. The best example of this is the late Baptist missionary Billy Grace, who preached to more than 3 billion people during his career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evangelicalism is characterised by both simplicity and zeal. There is no Pope or central authority structure to dictate dogma – the Bible is the only rule. There is no long and boring liturgy as we see in Catholic and Orthodox Churches – rather, church services tend to have contemporary music that is very appealing to the youth. They are not led by old and haggard clerics barely able to even speak a word – on the contrary, their leaders tend to be charismatic, scholarly and lively. The sacramental emphasis is replaced by a much freer and fluid form of spirituality, and it is not uncommon to hear the phrase “Christianity is a relationship, not a religion”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the Christian apologists defending the veracity of Christian truth in the academia are also Evangelicals. William Lane Craig, Ravi Zacharias, NT Wright, Richard Bauckham, Michael F Bird, Craig Keener, Craig Blomberg, James DG Dunn, Alvin Plantinga – the list is very impressive indeed. Not only are these devoted (Evangelical) Christians eager to convert souls, they also represent the top brass of scholarship in their respective fields. For instance, William Lane Craig and Alvin Plantinga are one of the most cited scholars in the philosophy of religion, while Wright and Bauckham have both had an association with universities like Oxford and Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny enough, Evangelical Christianity is very American, and very, very Republican. So, while Catholics seem to veer leftward, Evangelicals are solidly in support of capitalism and the notion of a culturally advanced Western Civilisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Holy Mother Russia: The Re-Baptism of Rus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the fall of the USSR, the resurgence of Eastern Orthodoxy was all but inevitable. Today, the Moscow Patriarchate can be called the unofficial state religion of the Russian Federation. Now operating with Vladimir Putin’s open consent and cooperation, they are rebuilding Churches long destroyed and reconstructing schools that had been annihilated by anti-religious sentiment. In fact, some Orthodox followers and clergy are actively advocating the restoration of a Christian state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orthodox Christians are very, well, ‘orthodox’. When the Pope visited Serbia, he was greeted by sloganeers protesting “the Papist heresy”. Even the Patriarch – while having met the Pope at the airport – refused to offer Mass with him. Similarly, Russia is cracking down on “fringe groups” – not least among them being the non-Trinitarian Jehovah’s Witnesses, who have had to face fierce persecution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What animates these people? It a vision of the legendary Byzantium, an empire so wonderful that it may be fittingly called the kingdom of God on earth. When the ambassadors of Prince Vladimir of Kiev first saw the Latin Mass, they were not too impressed, but when they witnessed the Byzantine Divine Liturgy, they wrote back exclaiming that this was the most heavenly thing they had ever seen. In the Orthodox narrative, the Church of Rome fell into heresy when it started claiming for itself ecclesiastical supremacy. It was then excommunicated and replaced by the Church of Constantinople, the New Rome. And when Constantinople fell under the sword of Islam, God raised up Moscow – the “Third Rome”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that if there will ever be a Christian state in the 21st century, it will exist mainly in Orthodox-dominated lands (and perhaps in Catholic Poland). For the rest of the Christian world, political Christendom is dead and gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atheists and critics of religion sometimes contend that Christianity is on the decline. But is this true? While it is without a doubt correct to say that Europe and the Western World is secularising at an exponential rate, this does not hold true with regard to the rest of the world. There is an explosion of Christian growth in the global south, particularly in Africa which has proven to be a fertile mission field for the Christian message. As far as academia is concerned, the resurgence of orthodox Christian scholarship in recent years is also a sign of life. However unpopular the faith may be among young white people, it certainly has a long and bright future ahead.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There are many religions in the world, but only Christianity can boast of having more than two billion followers across the world, comprising people from nearly every ethnicity, race, and social class. Even Islam – its closest contender and the “fastest growing religion in the world” is nearly a billion followers behind. But how is the religion that names itself after Jesus the Messiah influencing the 21st century? The answer may surprise you.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Questioning Humanity: The Stanford Prison Experiment</title>
      <link href="/Questioning-Humanity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Questioning Humanity: The Stanford Prison Experiment" />
      <published>2019-02-14T21:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-14T21:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Questioning-Humanity</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Questioning-Humanity">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Whoever fights monsters should see to it that in the process he does not become a monster. And if you gaze long enough into an abyss, the abyss will gaze back into you.”&lt;/em&gt; - Friedrich Nietzsche&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Humanity’ as a word essentially includes, but is not limited to, all the better things in the world: Peace, Happiness, Co-operational Existence for the betterment of the community, Altruism and so on. But what if this definition was farcical at the very least, or worse, misleading and based on chosen references rather the entire spectra of Truth? What if humans are the monsters they are themselves scared of? History does cite its own examples and notions on this issue. Tyrants, dictators and people in positions of power have always exploited those not in power since the beginning of time. But what if this was the true nature of Man? To seek answers to this question and more, Dr Philip Zimbardo along with his associates conducted the now infamous Stanford Prison Experiment in August 1971 in the basements of Stanford University’s Psychology Department. The aim of the experiment, as decided by Dr Zimbardo, was to conduct a social psychology experiment. Zimbardo’s primary motive for conducting the experiment was to focus on the power of roles, rules, symbols, group identity and situational validation of behaviour that generally would repulse ordinary individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Zimbardo, in his own words at the Toronto Symposium in 1996, “had been conducting research for some years on deindividuation, vandalism and dehumanization that illustrated the ease with which ordinary people could be led to engage in antisocial acts by putting them in situations where they felt anonymous, or they could perceive of others in ways that made them less than human, as enemies or objects”. In the Stanford Prison Experiment, he created a struggle of sorts between two groups and decided to evaluate the power dynamics behind it. He created a prison-like setup, where a certain set of individuals would be representing the ‘guards’ (the dominant strata) who would be controlling the ‘prisoners’ (the lower strata). The unsuspecting, and must we also add, willing volunteers in the experiment were divided into the groups only as a matter of chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Zimbardo set up the experiments to establish the breakdown of one’s own personality to take someone else’s. The guards were asked to react harshly in order to establish their power over the prisoners. Dave Eshelman, the most infamous guard during the experiment recalled that all actions were committed in order to fulfil the purpose behind the experiment, even though the experiment showed that some guards had very sadistic tendencies. The prisoners were taken from their own homes, and the Palo Alto Police cooperated with Zimbardo for a more genuine atmosphere. The prisoners were stripped and searched, their names were taken away from them and they were assigned numbers. The first day of the experiment went as it was expected to, without any issues. There were 9+3 guards and they were arranged to take charge in shifts. The conditions of the small container-like prison cells were largely in contrast with the living conditions of the guards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the second day, however, things started turning more macabre. The prisoners locked their doors and refused to come out. The guards used fire extinguishers to subdue the revolt without any permission from Zimbardo, who acted as the “superintendent of the prison”. The guards decided that there would be privilege rooms, which had way better food and beds, where the prisoners who did not support the rebellion would be kept. The interesting thing was even the people who had not supported the rebellion did not choose to be in these rooms. The guards continued to establish their dominance by removing the mattresses and forcing the prisoners to sleep on the ground, not even allowing them to clean their chamber pots. After 36 hours, a certain prisoner #8612 claimed to have lost his mind and was forced to be released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the atrocities of the guards continued. They stripped the prisoners and asked them to repeat the numbers assigned to them in order to enforce their new identity on them. While Zimbardo was concerned that the released prisoner would come back and was busy relocating the experiment, the guards continued their naked displays of power. A certain prisoner #416 locked himself in his room and refused to eat his sausages. He was forced into solitary confinement. There were several times when the prisoners asked for parole, only to be refused under the condition of no payment for their services. Zimbardo claimed that the prisoners stayed back even if no money was involved because they had internalised the roles of the oppressed prisoners in themselves. It was only after Zimbardo’s fiancé, Maslach, arrived on the sixth day of the experiment and questioned the morality of the situation that finally the experiment concluded. Zimbardo noted that out of the 50 people who participated in the experimented, nobody questioned its morality apart from Maslach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been several thought experiments and social and anthropogenic situations reenacted along the lines of the Stanford Prison Experiment. A notable one is the Milgram Experiment, where a person in one room was given the option of using an electronic switch which would send a current to another person in another room. The result of these experiments gives us a simple forlorn conclusion: Humans are, in most circumstances, sadistic creatures, and those with power will most likely prey on those without it. Even though the Stanford Experiment is challenged for having fraudulent methodology, the question remains that if humans are provided with an unrestricted and unbounded amount of power, will they behave like the guards did or will their ways be dependent on other factors such as the surrounding environment, i.e. the factors which were left unaccounted for in Zimbardo’s version? Or is there more to it than what meets the eye?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several questions which arise on the origins of morality and cognitive behaviour if we analyse the results of the Stanford Prison Experiment. Maybe we will find more about it when we recreate the circumstances. Or maybe we could all just accept the tyrant within us, the mass murderer within us and also embrace the empathy within ourselves and let them battle it out for the soul of mankind. In &lt;i&gt;Dark Knight&lt;/i&gt; , the movie, The Joker presents a similar experiment where he provides people with the option of destroying one of two boats, where one is filled with civilians and the other is filled with criminals and the remote for the detonation of the bomb in one boat is placed in the other boat. Even though the film chooses not to explore the darker aspects of the human mind and depicts humanity as still residing within us, it is after all the matter of a film. The question is: what if this happens with all of us right now? What would you choose? The ball is in your court.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Whoever fights monsters should see to it that in the process he does not become a monster. And if you gaze long enough into an abyss, the abyss will gaze back into you.” - Friedrich Nietzsche</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Should Family Come First?</title>
      <link href="/Should-Family-Come-First" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Should Family Come First?" />
      <published>2019-02-07T03:46:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T03:46:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Should-Family-Come-First</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Should-Family-Come-First">&lt;p&gt;The institution of family lies at the foundation of every society on Earth. But in India, it is so much more than just a foundation, family is the sustenance and the bane, the crutch and the agony of all festivals and all funerals, all of society and all of culture. But even when it’s a pain, it’s a pain we do not know how to live without. What seems overbearing and out of line in most cultures is the norm in Indian families. Indian families, with their little comprehension of space and boundaries, constantly barge, intrude and critique. From the ‘aunties’ glaring at exposed cleavages to the uncles who are making matches on marital websites, Indian families have never believed in hesitation. No advice is ever unsolicited. But there is something to say of the large joint families with people constantly milling around the house, the warm grandmothers with their secret recipes and the numberless siblings and cousins. There is something to say of the tightly knit structure of Indian households with an abundance of canopies of comfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ever-presence and the intrusions are symbols of a certain type of familiarity; a manifestation and reminder of a claim, of a sanction given long ago in the pages of history. Families lay a claim over us, over our mental and spiritual selves, over our sense of being. These claims perhaps go a long way in making us feel loved, because who else would intrude and scold and worry except those who want to keep us safe and invest in us. Even though it might feel like an encroachment upon autonomy, it certainly has a warmth to it, a charm not found in western homes, which let go. India’s collective inability to let go is rooted in our love, our ever-holding-on, unwilling-to-be-apart love; it is rooted in the way we have been brought up: our values of butting in, and pointing out, and determining for others, what’s best for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with the present generation and its streak of rebellion against family and tradition, familial bonds continue to be magnificent and powerful, encroaching and unjust, bustling with its magic and unwavering in its unfairness. These bonds become crucial because of increasing isolationism and the interference of ego in relationships, which make “enforcement and encroachment” necessary. Even when the connection is an enforced one, at least there is some degree of retention of connectedness. The presence of any support system, even if it is far from ideal, is better than having nothing but a dreary 1BHK to come back to. The price of complete autonomy is a high one, one that we Indians are yet to pay. Yet, is their romanticism in our narrative?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value that comes out of family and the revered Indian lens through which it is viewed should not blind us to the problems that manifest as a result of the “family structure” being placed on a pedestal. The narratives of queer individuals, of women and of children cannot be pushed to the sidelines. It is easy to look at the cheery side of families and ignore the harshness. This attempt at pretence is easy, almost second nature to us. Growing up, we Indians imbibe a lesson from the world around us; that the front we put up for the world to see is far, far more important than what really goes on. India lives in a world in which the publicity of injustice wounds one more than the injustice itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Indian may dismiss abuse and torture of women as isolated incidents, not as crimes committed by depraved people not fit to engage with civilised society. Abuse doesn’t pop out of a void or only lurk in alleys. It stems from the idea of patriarchal entitlement over the bodies and decisions of women. It is in a household that this &lt;em&gt;entitlement&lt;/em&gt; begins and heightens, and manifests in the worst forms. There is a misguided sense of ownership men feel they have over the women in their families, and society just accepts that, which is why violence against women by family members does not scandalise one’s idea of social propriety or elicit the same response that violence by an outsider would.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The false idea that familial ties lend some form of ownership over another human’s body is fed and drilled into one ever since childhood. India is a nation that is still far from even frowning upon children being hit by the elders of the family. Beyond the physical and emotional ramifications, hitting children also instills in them the idea that they have only partial autonomy over their bodies. It teaches children the lesson that bodily autonomy, while otherwise a valid concept, loses all ground when inside the house. This leads to toxic ideas of ownership which in turn leads to a path of denying oneself victimhood in the face of abuse, because if it’s family how wrong can it really be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problems lie with us as a society when we twist and bend our limits and thresholds for what is right and what is wrong in order to excuse and justify whatever family does. This stems from the family being glorified as sacred and notions of entitlement that equate familial love with ownership. One’s inability to open up about any kind of trauma, pain or even smaller complaints that have to do with family comes from the belief that family always comes first. “Family always comes first” sounds like a noble sentiment but it can be exploited to make individuals feel as though they have to dismiss the wrong done to them by their family members, family being first is extrapolated to make a person feel as if opening up about family problems in front of friends, teachers, or lovers is wrong, or a form of shameful betrayal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of this article is not to say that Indian society must abandon the family structure that glues together the fabric of its society, but to examine how we have been systematically taught to worship and &lt;i&gt;pedestalize&lt;/i&gt; this structure, the institution of family and the people who constitute it. All the problematic things with family life become even more problematic because when our assumption that families provide a safe space fails, there is no alternative safe space to fall back on. The friends, peers, and lovers that should act as a safe space do not, because it becomes very difficult for a victim to break that inner wall of shame and talk about family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sad part is that communities are meant to look after the well-being of its members, but we Indians have become obsessed with merely the “illusion of functionality”. We venerate the ‘structure’ so much that we want to protect it even at the cost of real humans and their very real lives. So long as the overhanging structures of marriage, parenthood, and households stay intact we don’t really care what happens to the cogs that make up the wheel. How is it still that we have not redefined our idea of brokenness, how is it that people get abused and children are driven to committing suicide but we still think it’s working?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love and abuse, on the surface, seem to be mutually exclusive. Two concepts, so contrary, so antithetical to each other that they can never be thought of as coexistent. How can one love their abuser? How obvious, right? But the relationship between the abuser and the abused is anything but obvious. The world and this great nation are littered with tales of how the two thrive together, grip and dig into each other. Maybe the nature of love is such that it is with great difficulty that one might stop loving their abuser, but third parties and well-wishers can go a long way in helping one. Talking about experiences surrounding family that are grim will lead to a much-needed counter-narrative that will finally paint abuse as abuse, whether physical or emotional, that will finally show family as human beings, capable of falling, capable of wrong, and not as oracles who can dictate morality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the love that comes for parents and siblings is not as organic in nature as one would like to believe. A lot of it also comes from the narrative that is flashed around us, of how much we are &lt;i&gt;supposed&lt;/i&gt; to and are &lt;i&gt;obligated&lt;/i&gt; to love. The love that is regarded with so much veneration, the devotion towards parents that is thought of as moral accomplishment itself is manufactured by society, it does not arise as authentically as one would like to believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After reading all of this one might ask, &lt;i&gt;so what&lt;/i&gt;? So what if the structure is a certain way that has both pros and cons? The answer lies in valuing family but not pedestalizing it. The answer lies in acknowledging how the family has cared for one whilst understanding that families are not incapable of wrongdoing and some families even inflict grave abuse and injustice. Asking a nation which is willed to throw-off all balance, to approach a middle path might seem counterproductive. A nation in which family is all or nothing, asking for a path that both loves and censures family is daunting in itself. But God knows we’ve needed it, we’ve needed the balance.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Stuti Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The institution of family lies at the foundation of every society on Earth. But in India, it is so much more than just a foundation, family is the sustenance and the bane, the crutch and the agony of all festivals and all funerals, all of society and all of culture. But even when it’s a pain, it’s a pain we do not know how to live without. What seems overbearing and out of line in most cultures is the norm in Indian families. Indian families, with their little comprehension of space and boundaries, constantly barge, intrude and critique. From the ‘aunties’ glaring at exposed cleavages to the uncles who are making matches on marital websites, Indian families have never believed in hesitation. No advice is ever unsolicited. But there is something to say of the large joint families with people constantly milling around the house, the warm grandmothers with their secret recipes and the numberless siblings and cousins. There is something to say of the tightly knit structure of Indian households with an abundance of canopies of comfort.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Transphobia, Political Correctness and the Jordan Peterson Phenomenon</title>
      <link href="/Jordan-Peterson-Phenomenon" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transphobia, Political Correctness and the Jordan Peterson Phenomenon" />
      <published>2019-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Jordan-Peterson-Phenomenon</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Jordan-Peterson-Phenomenon">&lt;p&gt;Hero. Mentor. Thinker. Professor. Ideologue. Right-Winger. Transphobic Hate-Monger. “Mean Mad White Man.” These are but some of the epithets which have been used to refer to Jordan B. Peterson, an eminent clinical psychologist who became famous overnight for opposing legislation that intended to make it illegal for people to not refer to transgender people by their preferred pronouns. Since then, he has been at the epicentre of a raging controversy about political correctness that has made an impact over most of the Western Anglophone world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peterson is a professor at the University of Toronto. He earned his doctorate from McGill University and has taught at eminent institutions, including Harvard University. He is the author of &lt;i&gt;Maps of Meaning: The Architecture of Belief &lt;/i&gt; and a more recent international bestseller &lt;i&gt;12 Rules for Life: An Antidote to Chaos&lt;/i&gt;. An erudite Jungian and Nietzschean scholar and a gifted speaker, he has inspired countless young men to “embrace their masculinity”. However, his opposition to government-backed impositions on free speech and his critique of the feminist concept of patriarchy has made him an almost hated figure in some circles. The foundation of all these positions, however, is his staunch opposition to political correctness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are approximately 3 million people in the European Union and the United States of America put together who identify as transgender. The exact estimate the world over is difficult to ascertain. Nonetheless, however minute they might be in proportion to the total world population, this is a sizable number of people. But can a trans woman be considered a “real woman”? That is the question Jo Coburn of the BBC’s &lt;i&gt;The Daily Politics&lt;/i&gt; asked Peterson. His reply was simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No. […] Because I think that women are capable, generally speaking, of having babies and they have female genitalia and they have an XX Chromosome and I think the biological markers are relevant.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are Peterson’s comments controversial? Certainly. Insulting? For many, yes. But transphobic? Discriminatory? Prejudiced? Is Peterson taking his alleged “freedom of speech” a bit too far? How would we react if someone today claimed that a black person was not a “real person” or a “real human” and would use that as a basis for denying that such a person is entitled to human rights? I am not making this up. That is precisely what many Southern Americans believed about non-white people. The idea was that humanoid beings pre-existed before Adam, and that blacks were among the “beasts of the field” described in the initial chapters of the Book of Genesis. White supremacists used this religious belief in order to justify slavery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone were to make this claim today, we would be appalled, and rightly so. But how different is Professor Peterson’s claim? At least, that’s the argument that might be made by some on the left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, numerous trans-people claim a number of distinctive rights. The right to be called by their preferred pronouns is one of them. Another is the right to use public bathrooms of their own choice, that correspond to their “gender identity”. But are they actually entitled to these rights?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not my intention to comment on whether transgenderism is legitimate or not. That is a topic for the experts and I am not sure I have any opinion on this. What I want to focus on though is the concept of free speech. Nowhere is free speech upheld in an absolute manner, and rightly so because that would lead to dangerous anarchy. There are a number of things which people are forbidden from saying, which would constitute “hate speech”. We cannot, for instance, encourage people to engage in acts of genocide. Well and good. The real dilemma lies, however, in the simple fact that the precise demarcation between authentic speech and hate speech can be very blurred at times. Doubtlessly, many transgenders have probably felt Peterson’s comments to be extremely offensive. But does this constitute “hate”? The man has not called for violence of any kind; quite the contrary, he advocates treating transgender people with the same respect and dignity that we would any other ordinary human being. It is the same with Ben Shapiro. The latter is not calling for persecution; from his perspective, he is merely exercising his freedom of speech to express his genuinely held opinion that transgenderism is mental illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question that arises then is this: What do we do when genuinely held opinions are so offensive for some on the other side that it almost &lt;i&gt;sounds&lt;/i&gt; hateful to their ears? What opinions are permissible, and what are not? Who decides?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some might say “Hate speech is when we call upon people to engage in violence”. But this presents its own problems. What if someone were to salute the grave of Hitler and publicly hang swastika flags over their homes? They may not be explicitly calling for hatred and violence, but can we deny that such actions are, at least to some extent, ‘hateful’? Others might argue, “We must restrict speech which goes against the common good of society”. This, of course, is even more vague – what exactly constitutes the “common good of society”? From such a perspective, it could be argued that “heretics” should be prevented from preaching, because by spreading heresies, they would be leading countless souls to hell – at least that was the argument of St. Thomas Aquinas. Or do we take a utilitarian view, and measure common good in terms of material happiness? Such measurements are, of course, very difficult to make. Because Stalin would probably argue that speaking out against Communism is against the common good of society because it creates unrest, raises discontent against the “ideal form of government” and misleads simple people, who are too illiterate and ignorant of the principles of economics to make a sound judgment in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is in these dilemmas that we see the absurdity of liberal democracy. If the goal of the state is to provide ‘liberty’ to all, then failure is unavoidable. What is liberal to one is inevitably oppressive to the other. What is freedom of speech to one is violation of rights to another. There are, of course, many states which call themselves ‘liberal’. But in each and every one of them, one will find people who are discontented, for whom the revolution has not even begun. So, while Dr. Peterson may be offensive and hateful to so many, he cannot be deemed to lie in the hate speech side of things. To deem his exercise of free speech as hateful would be to draw an arbitrary line between free speech and hate speech on the basis of offense, which, like any other arbitrary separation explained above cannot be sustained. As Peterson pointed out in the Cathy Newman Interview, he has to be able to risk offense to be able to honestly communicate.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Hero. Mentor. Thinker. Professor. Ideologue. Right-Winger. Transphobic Hate-Monger. “Mean Mad White Man.” These are but some of the epithets which have been used to refer to Jordan B. Peterson, an eminent clinical psychologist who became famous overnight for opposing legislation that intended to make it illegal for people to not refer to transgender people by their preferred pronouns. Since then, he has been at the epicentre of a raging controversy about political correctness that has made an impact over most of the Western Anglophone world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
