<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/society/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-08-18T19:28:14+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/society/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Only I Exist</title>
      <link href="/Only-I-Exist" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Only I Exist" />
      <published>2019-08-01T11:45:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-01T11:45:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Only-I-Exist</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Only-I-Exist">&lt;p&gt;Questions have been the very heart and soul of philosophy and, unlike any other
discipline, it has raised more questions than it has answered. The dire
intellectual need to discern the abstract, in the form of reality and truth,
consumes all thinkers alike. They all seek answers that spring from an objective
source to bring an end to the seemingly perpetual quest for knowledge. However,
it is not that simple. Philosophy, over the years, has gotten mired down in
countless irrefutable hypotheses, thriving on the body of possibilities and
reason. This is especially true of metaphysical discussions, which have resulted
in the blossoming of unconventional, at times, bizarre theories to explain
reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt;? One way to grasp reality amounts to the way you understand the
world external to you. But what if that understanding is faulty? Take, for
instance, the understanding of the earth as a flat disc. Today we can ‘claim to
know’ that the earth is spherical, yet in those times the supposed axiom of the
earth being flat was the foundational truth on which the early peoples developed
an understanding of other concepts and ideas. This is disconcerting, because
there’s a pretty high possibility of us assuming a false belief as an
irrefutable fact, because although there are proofs to make claims, science per
se isn’t perfect, just workable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us now go even further to understand the concept of matter that we &lt;em&gt;assume&lt;/em&gt;
to be real. As Bertrand Russell discussed in his &lt;em&gt;Problems of Philosophy&lt;/em&gt;,
whatever we perceive is the mere appearance of an object, as opposed to its
reality. The surface of an apple that is seen with the naked eye is very
different when viewed under the microscope, its colour varies with the changing
source of light too. In short, what your perception leads you into believing is
real is actually nothing but the appearance of the apple, in varying degrees of
magnification. If this is the case, then the existence of the apple becomes
questionable. Does an &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; apple exist at all? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some, it does not. A philosopher named Bishop Berkeley, for instance, argued
in favour of &lt;em&gt;immaterialism&lt;/em&gt; – that rather than being a form of matter, an apple
in actuality is the amalgamation of several qualities which cannot exist
independent of the mind. You can test this, try defining an apple devoid of its
qualities and properties. It is almost impossible to do so. So are the qualities
(of the objects) that we perceive in the universe, are they created by our
imagination or do they exist as a comprehensive whole contained in an underlying
substratum called matter? This is the starting point of the idea of ‘solipsism.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solipsism revolves around the idea that only I exist and weave the fabric of my
reality. The &lt;em&gt;certainty&lt;/em&gt; I can ascribe to my experience is limited to my &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt;
existence and thoughts, everything else in this world, including the existence
of this article, is doubtable. This may seem very absurd to hear, at first, but
it’s a possibility that is hard to deny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The empirical experiences one goes through forms an essential part of their own
subjective reality. One can, in no way validate the experience of anybody else
(egocentric predicament). One’s understanding of the apple is theirs alone and
cannot be grasped by anyone else. The comprehension of all that is external to
their consciousness is beyond their ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, your thoughts and ideas are the only undisputed and obvious entities that
exist. This is to say that all humans have their own psychological conceptions
whose understanding is forbidden to others. And so, we cannot be certain of the
independent existence of other bodies and minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory of solipsism has subtly remained embedded in other philosophical
ideas. One such idea was propounded by Rene Descartes’ principle of “&lt;em&gt;Cogito,
ergo sum&lt;/em&gt;” (I think, therefore I am). Descartes was convinced that he was being
deceived, by an evil genius, into believing some essentially flawed concepts as
true. Maintaining that every thought is dubitable, he cleansed his mind of all
distortions and came up with the most irrefutable, indubitable truth (as the
basic frame of reference to understand all the other truths)- “I think therefore
I am.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solipsism takes this idea of &lt;em&gt;Cogito&lt;/em&gt; way too seriously. Nothing but the mind is
true for the solipsist. While Descartes did believe in rationality and
mathematics as a means to search for truth, for the solipsist (metaphysically
and epistemologically) such conceptions are your own inventions, something you
make up in your head, bereft of any independent existence (here your
consciousness shall assume the place of Descartes’ demon). One can understand it
as a perpetual state of hallucination, characterised by vivid details. If you
are a solipsist, then whatever you experience, this article, your friends,
family, nature, all the coolest things in the world are actually an invention of
your own! An understanding of the world devoid of the ego is impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However fascinating it may sound, solipsism has some dire outcomes, when
accepted as a lifestyle choice. It possesses the potential to throw the world
into utter chaos. Since everything that one sees around them is a creation of
their imagination, they would have all the power of calling the shots and
asserting their dominance over the entire world around them. Morality and ethics
would lose their credibility and an individual’s will would determine the fate
of all that is around them. Or else, it could make a person abnegate everything,
despairing about the loneliness they experience every second of their existence,
since they have no proof of the existence of any other. Either way, solipsism
could inflict more harm than good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficult to refute, solipsism continues to haunt the imagination of humankind.
However, rejecting the theory altogether wouldn’t be right either, given the
crucial questions it raises on reality and the foundations of epistemological
speculations. The question of solipsism has stirred minds and propelled
philosophy from a state of certainty to that of unpredictability, thereby adding
profundity and beauty to the subject. And as long as such ingenious thoughts
continue to flow in the body of philosophy, the answer to this problem, along
with all problems, I believe, is not too far away.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Questions have been the very heart and soul of philosophy and, unlike any other discipline, it has raised more questions than it has answered. The dire intellectual need to discern the abstract, in the form of reality and truth, consumes all thinkers alike. They all seek answers that spring from an objective source to bring an end to the seemingly perpetual quest for knowledge. However, it is not that simple. Philosophy, over the years, has gotten mired down in countless irrefutable hypotheses, thriving on the body of possibilities and reason. This is especially true of metaphysical discussions, which have resulted in the blossoming of unconventional, at times, bizarre theories to explain reality. What is real? One way to grasp reality amounts to the way you understand the world external to you. But what if that understanding is faulty? Take, for instance, the understanding of the earth as a flat disc. Today we can ‘claim to know’ that the earth is spherical, yet in those times the supposed axiom of the earth being flat was the foundational truth on which the early peoples developed an understanding of other concepts and ideas. This is disconcerting, because there’s a pretty high possibility of us assuming a false belief as an irrefutable fact, because although there are proofs to make claims, science per se isn’t perfect, just workable.  Let us now go even further to understand the concept of matter that we assume to be real. As Bertrand Russell discussed in his Problems of Philosophy, whatever we perceive is the mere appearance of an object, as opposed to its reality. The surface of an apple that is seen with the naked eye is very different when viewed under the microscope, its colour varies with the changing source of light too. In short, what your perception leads you into believing is real is actually nothing but the appearance of the apple, in varying degrees of magnification. If this is the case, then the existence of the apple becomes questionable. Does an actual apple exist at all?  For some, it does not. A philosopher named Bishop Berkeley, for instance, argued in favour of immaterialism – that rather than being a form of matter, an apple in actuality is the amalgamation of several qualities which cannot exist independent of the mind. You can test this, try defining an apple devoid of its qualities and properties. It is almost impossible to do so. So are the qualities (of the objects) that we perceive in the universe, are they created by our imagination or do they exist as a comprehensive whole contained in an underlying substratum called matter? This is the starting point of the idea of ‘solipsism.’ Solipsism revolves around the idea that only I exist and weave the fabric of my reality. The certainty I can ascribe to my experience is limited to my own existence and thoughts, everything else in this world, including the existence of this article, is doubtable. This may seem very absurd to hear, at first, but it’s a possibility that is hard to deny. The empirical experiences one goes through forms an essential part of their own subjective reality. One can, in no way validate the experience of anybody else (egocentric predicament). One’s understanding of the apple is theirs alone and cannot be grasped by anyone else. The comprehension of all that is external to their consciousness is beyond their ability. Thus, your thoughts and ideas are the only undisputed and obvious entities that exist. This is to say that all humans have their own psychological conceptions whose understanding is forbidden to others. And so, we cannot be certain of the independent existence of other bodies and minds. The theory of solipsism has subtly remained embedded in other philosophical ideas. One such idea was propounded by Rene Descartes’ principle of “Cogito, ergo sum” (I think, therefore I am). Descartes was convinced that he was being deceived, by an evil genius, into believing some essentially flawed concepts as true. Maintaining that every thought is dubitable, he cleansed his mind of all distortions and came up with the most irrefutable, indubitable truth (as the basic frame of reference to understand all the other truths)- “I think therefore I am.”  Solipsism takes this idea of Cogito way too seriously. Nothing but the mind is true for the solipsist. While Descartes did believe in rationality and mathematics as a means to search for truth, for the solipsist (metaphysically and epistemologically) such conceptions are your own inventions, something you make up in your head, bereft of any independent existence (here your consciousness shall assume the place of Descartes’ demon). One can understand it as a perpetual state of hallucination, characterised by vivid details. If you are a solipsist, then whatever you experience, this article, your friends, family, nature, all the coolest things in the world are actually an invention of your own! An understanding of the world devoid of the ego is impossible. However fascinating it may sound, solipsism has some dire outcomes, when accepted as a lifestyle choice. It possesses the potential to throw the world into utter chaos. Since everything that one sees around them is a creation of their imagination, they would have all the power of calling the shots and asserting their dominance over the entire world around them. Morality and ethics would lose their credibility and an individual’s will would determine the fate of all that is around them. Or else, it could make a person abnegate everything, despairing about the loneliness they experience every second of their existence, since they have no proof of the existence of any other. Either way, solipsism could inflict more harm than good. Difficult to refute, solipsism continues to haunt the imagination of humankind. However, rejecting the theory altogether wouldn’t be right either, given the crucial questions it raises on reality and the foundations of epistemological speculations. The question of solipsism has stirred minds and propelled philosophy from a state of certainty to that of unpredictability, thereby adding profundity and beauty to the subject. And as long as such ingenious thoughts continue to flow in the body of philosophy, the answer to this problem, along with all problems, I believe, is not too far away.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Secrets of Sorcery</title>
      <link href="/Secrets-of-Sorcery" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Secrets of Sorcery" />
      <published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Secrets-of-Sorcery</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Secrets-of-Sorcery">&lt;p&gt;The mention of witchcraft is bound to conjure up some image in your mind. Now,
that image could be of Hermione Granger, with her bushy brown hair and dragon
heartstring wand, or that of an old lady with terrible green skin and a long
crooked nose or even Bonnie Bennett from &lt;em&gt;The Vampire Diaries&lt;/em&gt;. But have you
ever wondered if witches are real and if witchcraft is an actual practice?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer that question, yes, witchcraft is not alien to our world. It is,
however, slightly different from the conventional perceptions that surround it.
Historically, witches have always been seen as all-female Satanists whose agenda
behind practising magic is to inflict pain or damage upon others. This
historical perception has resulted in witch-hunts across cultures. Shockingly
enough, mass hysteria being caused by witches is not just a thing of the past.
In 2016, over 400 women in Tanzania were convicted of practising witchcraft and
subsequently killed for performing black magic. Many villages have been
abandoned by its residents out of the fear of being harmed by witches. Every
Tanzanian community, even today, has a witch doctor, whose job is to spot
witches. These ‘witches’ are then killed and their bodies burned. With so many
women dead, the question that arises is this: who is fuelling this witch
hysteria? Tanzania continues to have laws that ban the use of magic, indirectly
lending legitimacy to witch doctors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in India, witch hunts are common. Since 2001, an estimated 2,500 people
have been killed for the practice of witchcraft around the country. In fact,
witch hunters are often highly esteemed by the villagers, who genuinely see them
as rescuers, protecting the village from the hands of evil witches. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Romania, the home of Count Dracula, witchcraft is recognised by the current
government. There are many thriving organisations of witches, all government
recognised. Being a witch is considered to be a job. They are employed, not just
by Romanians, but people from all over the globe to cure them of heartbreak,
depression, demonic possession or even to kill or harm enemies. Our Romanian
witches carry out most of their operations online these days and are confident
that their influence is not dying out. Instead, thanks to modern technology, it
is only on the rise. This isn’t how it always was in Romania. In fact, under
Communist rule, witchcraft was banned and punishable by law. And yet, the secret
societies of witches and their practices survived, in hiding from the eyes of
the ruler. Today, witchcraft is commonly accepted by Romanian society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witch doctors are very common across the continent of Africa. In South Africa,
commonly among the Zulu, they are of two main types: &lt;em&gt;Inyanga&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Sangoma&lt;/em&gt;.
While &lt;em&gt;Inyanga&lt;/em&gt; practice natural medicine, &lt;em&gt;Sangoma&lt;/em&gt; practice magic, predict the
future and use various rituals to communicate with ancestors. Many seek out
their expertise and help, without any fear. There are some, however, who
consider these practices unnatural and thus, are afraid of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various countries have come up with innovative ways to deal with the mass
hysteria surrounding witches. In Ghana, nearly a century ago, witch camps were
established to help people who were accused of practising witchcraft by the
locals. Many countries have separate laws altogether to deal with the practice
of magic and those who falsely accuse innocent women of being witches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the West, pagan witchcraft or Wicca is on the surge. It is the
fastest-growing religion in the USA and the only truly British religion. The
followers of this exponentially growing religion, born not before 1940, are
self-proclaimed witches who believe in magic. Even though for many, a belief in
magic outside the realm of Harry Potter is a taboo, the growing Wiccan community
is reaching beyond the British Isles with a strength in the millions. However,
contrary to popular belief, they do not just comprise women. Men can be witches
too. Wiccans are not a Satanic cult either. In fact, Wicca takes pride in
worshipping nature and abides by the saying: “An it harm none, do what ye will.”
Their rituals do not involve any kind of sacrifices or dead animals or their
poop, as one might expect. They, however, do draw energy from natural phenomena
like the solstices and equinoxes; a common feature among many such communities.
Most of their spells and incantations are compiled in a book named &lt;em&gt;The Book of
Shadows&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most famous witches that have ever roamed our earth were probably the
witches of Salem, Massachusetts in 1692 (although it is unlikely that they ever
actually practised witchcraft). During the infamous Salem witch trials, some of
the women, like Tituba, confessed to having used black magic to inflict pain and
disease upon young girls in the community. It is possible that the confessions
were a result of community pressure. The witch trials saw the death of several
females and a few males. The accusations, unlike most other witch hunts, weren’t
made by adult males and instead by young girls, who were ill with various
conditions. Between 1482 and 1782, around 100,000 people across Europe were
convicted of witchcraft. Not all of them were burned at the stake, though. Some
were hanged to death. They were generally not persecuted by the Church, contrary
to popular opinion. Although most of the accused were women, in some places,
male witches outnumbered the females. The ratio between male and female witches
stood at 7:3 to in Moscow and 3:1 in Normandy. &lt;em&gt;Malleus Maleficarum&lt;/em&gt; was
published in 1486 and it quickly became a best-seller, being second only to the
Bible. This book was considered to be the highest authority on how to spot,
interrogate and kill witches and, thus, guided witch hunts for centuries to
come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think sorcery and belief in magic are only a few centuries old, then you
are wrong! It is actually a few millennia old. Ancient Egyptians had many
secrets to hide. Besides building humongous structures like the pyramids, they
also practised magic. Sorcery was an integral part of their lives. The position
of a sorcerer was hereditary and the spells were passed down through
generations. &lt;em&gt;The Book of the Dead&lt;/em&gt; famously contains various spells to aid one
in the transitional journey to the afterlife. The sorcerers of ancient Egypt
often tried to tackle deadly diseases using magical potions. Though there is no
written record of what actually happened following the administration of such a
cure, it would be stupid, in our science-driven millennial minds to believe that
potions of rats’ tails benefitted anyone. And yet, the sorcerers weren’t ever
condemned or banned from practice. Routine trials of their potions on humans
continued as long as the great civilisation thrived. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all the advancement of science comes the rejection of the existence of
magic. Many, however, believe that Egyptian curses might have been real. Let’s
go back to 1922 when Pharaoh Tutankhamen’s tomb was discovered in the Valley of
Kings by Howard Carter. 4 months and 7 days after the opening of the tomb,
George Herbert, 5th Earl of Carnarvon, who had financially backed the excavation
team died after a mosquito bite became infected. There have been around 11
deaths following the opening of the tomb. These deaths have been popularly
attributed to the famous Pharaoh’s curse. This curse was placed on tombs and is
believed to affect anyone who disturbs the final resting place of the tomb’s
occupant, especially if it’s a Pharaoh. The curse did not distinguish between
robbers and Egyptologists. However, it is important to note here that Howard
Carter himself died only in 1939, almost two decades later. Hollywood movies
have done a great job of instilling a fear of ancient Egyptian curses among the
masses. The truth, however, is that no one has seen these curses in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witches are surprisingly ubiquitous. But the problem is this: they evolved in
different cultures, separately and yet almost identically. Most cultures have
only female witches. And burning them at the stake almost universally seems to
solve the problem. Although some communities, mostly modern ones, seem to hold
beliefs that witches are helpful, historically, they have often been associated
with famines, death, and other ill-occurrences. Humans have always strived to
decipher mysteries and whenever there are gaps in our understanding, we have
assumed that something supernatural is at play. As our understanding widened, we
rejected pagan explanations of lightning and rainbows and moved on to more
complex schools of thought. Presently, atheism is on the rise. Interestingly
enough, paganism is on the rise too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some have dismissed it as a historical practice, in others witchcraft
still thrives as a part of their culture to this day. While some have reduced
witchcraft to a fictional plot device, for many those spells and incantations
hold supernatural powers. It isn’t so much about witchcraft, after all, as it is
about the world’s relationship with it. Dismissing it seems rational. But what’s
intriguing is the existence of the human &lt;strong&gt;urge&lt;/strong&gt; to look for magic in a world
that tells you against it, an urge that transcends beyond the modern world
desperation to cling to rationale.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The mention of witchcraft is bound to conjure up some image in your mind. Now, that image could be of Hermione Granger, with her bushy brown hair and dragon heartstring wand, or that of an old lady with terrible green skin and a long crooked nose or even Bonnie Bennett from The Vampire Diaries. But have you ever wondered if witches are real and if witchcraft is an actual practice? To answer that question, yes, witchcraft is not alien to our world. It is, however, slightly different from the conventional perceptions that surround it. Historically, witches have always been seen as all-female Satanists whose agenda behind practising magic is to inflict pain or damage upon others. This historical perception has resulted in witch-hunts across cultures. Shockingly enough, mass hysteria being caused by witches is not just a thing of the past. In 2016, over 400 women in Tanzania were convicted of practising witchcraft and subsequently killed for performing black magic. Many villages have been abandoned by its residents out of the fear of being harmed by witches. Every Tanzanian community, even today, has a witch doctor, whose job is to spot witches. These ‘witches’ are then killed and their bodies burned. With so many women dead, the question that arises is this: who is fuelling this witch hysteria? Tanzania continues to have laws that ban the use of magic, indirectly lending legitimacy to witch doctors. Even in India, witch hunts are common. Since 2001, an estimated 2,500 people have been killed for the practice of witchcraft around the country. In fact, witch hunters are often highly esteemed by the villagers, who genuinely see them as rescuers, protecting the village from the hands of evil witches.  In Romania, the home of Count Dracula, witchcraft is recognised by the current government. There are many thriving organisations of witches, all government recognised. Being a witch is considered to be a job. They are employed, not just by Romanians, but people from all over the globe to cure them of heartbreak, depression, demonic possession or even to kill or harm enemies. Our Romanian witches carry out most of their operations online these days and are confident that their influence is not dying out. Instead, thanks to modern technology, it is only on the rise. This isn’t how it always was in Romania. In fact, under Communist rule, witchcraft was banned and punishable by law. And yet, the secret societies of witches and their practices survived, in hiding from the eyes of the ruler. Today, witchcraft is commonly accepted by Romanian society. Witch doctors are very common across the continent of Africa. In South Africa, commonly among the Zulu, they are of two main types: Inyanga and Sangoma. While Inyanga practice natural medicine, Sangoma practice magic, predict the future and use various rituals to communicate with ancestors. Many seek out their expertise and help, without any fear. There are some, however, who consider these practices unnatural and thus, are afraid of them. Various countries have come up with innovative ways to deal with the mass hysteria surrounding witches. In Ghana, nearly a century ago, witch camps were established to help people who were accused of practising witchcraft by the locals. Many countries have separate laws altogether to deal with the practice of magic and those who falsely accuse innocent women of being witches. In the West, pagan witchcraft or Wicca is on the surge. It is the fastest-growing religion in the USA and the only truly British religion. The followers of this exponentially growing religion, born not before 1940, are self-proclaimed witches who believe in magic. Even though for many, a belief in magic outside the realm of Harry Potter is a taboo, the growing Wiccan community is reaching beyond the British Isles with a strength in the millions. However, contrary to popular belief, they do not just comprise women. Men can be witches too. Wiccans are not a Satanic cult either. In fact, Wicca takes pride in worshipping nature and abides by the saying: “An it harm none, do what ye will.” Their rituals do not involve any kind of sacrifices or dead animals or their poop, as one might expect. They, however, do draw energy from natural phenomena like the solstices and equinoxes; a common feature among many such communities. Most of their spells and incantations are compiled in a book named The Book of Shadows. The most famous witches that have ever roamed our earth were probably the witches of Salem, Massachusetts in 1692 (although it is unlikely that they ever actually practised witchcraft). During the infamous Salem witch trials, some of the women, like Tituba, confessed to having used black magic to inflict pain and disease upon young girls in the community. It is possible that the confessions were a result of community pressure. The witch trials saw the death of several females and a few males. The accusations, unlike most other witch hunts, weren’t made by adult males and instead by young girls, who were ill with various conditions. Between 1482 and 1782, around 100,000 people across Europe were convicted of witchcraft. Not all of them were burned at the stake, though. Some were hanged to death. They were generally not persecuted by the Church, contrary to popular opinion. Although most of the accused were women, in some places, male witches outnumbered the females. The ratio between male and female witches stood at 7:3 to in Moscow and 3:1 in Normandy. Malleus Maleficarum was published in 1486 and it quickly became a best-seller, being second only to the Bible. This book was considered to be the highest authority on how to spot, interrogate and kill witches and, thus, guided witch hunts for centuries to come. If you think sorcery and belief in magic are only a few centuries old, then you are wrong! It is actually a few millennia old. Ancient Egyptians had many secrets to hide. Besides building humongous structures like the pyramids, they also practised magic. Sorcery was an integral part of their lives. The position of a sorcerer was hereditary and the spells were passed down through generations. The Book of the Dead famously contains various spells to aid one in the transitional journey to the afterlife. The sorcerers of ancient Egypt often tried to tackle deadly diseases using magical potions. Though there is no written record of what actually happened following the administration of such a cure, it would be stupid, in our science-driven millennial minds to believe that potions of rats’ tails benefitted anyone. And yet, the sorcerers weren’t ever condemned or banned from practice. Routine trials of their potions on humans continued as long as the great civilisation thrived.  With all the advancement of science comes the rejection of the existence of magic. Many, however, believe that Egyptian curses might have been real. Let’s go back to 1922 when Pharaoh Tutankhamen’s tomb was discovered in the Valley of Kings by Howard Carter. 4 months and 7 days after the opening of the tomb, George Herbert, 5th Earl of Carnarvon, who had financially backed the excavation team died after a mosquito bite became infected. There have been around 11 deaths following the opening of the tomb. These deaths have been popularly attributed to the famous Pharaoh’s curse. This curse was placed on tombs and is believed to affect anyone who disturbs the final resting place of the tomb’s occupant, especially if it’s a Pharaoh. The curse did not distinguish between robbers and Egyptologists. However, it is important to note here that Howard Carter himself died only in 1939, almost two decades later. Hollywood movies have done a great job of instilling a fear of ancient Egyptian curses among the masses. The truth, however, is that no one has seen these curses in action. Witches are surprisingly ubiquitous. But the problem is this: they evolved in different cultures, separately and yet almost identically. Most cultures have only female witches. And burning them at the stake almost universally seems to solve the problem. Although some communities, mostly modern ones, seem to hold beliefs that witches are helpful, historically, they have often been associated with famines, death, and other ill-occurrences. Humans have always strived to decipher mysteries and whenever there are gaps in our understanding, we have assumed that something supernatural is at play. As our understanding widened, we rejected pagan explanations of lightning and rainbows and moved on to more complex schools of thought. Presently, atheism is on the rise. Interestingly enough, paganism is on the rise too. While some have dismissed it as a historical practice, in others witchcraft still thrives as a part of their culture to this day. While some have reduced witchcraft to a fictional plot device, for many those spells and incantations hold supernatural powers. It isn’t so much about witchcraft, after all, as it is about the world’s relationship with it. Dismissing it seems rational. But what’s intriguing is the existence of the human urge to look for magic in a world that tells you against it, an urge that transcends beyond the modern world desperation to cling to rationale.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Great (Millennial) Depression</title>
      <link href="/The-Great-Millennial-Depression" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Great (Millennial) Depression" />
      <published>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Great-Millennial-Depression</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Great-Millennial-Depression">&lt;p&gt;If you are depressed or some, possibly most, of your friends about the same age are depressed too, then it is highly likely that you are a Millennial. Yes, you belong to the infamous “ME ME ME” generation that is too obsessed to look beyond the self (at least that is what the magazines tell us). Millennials are supposedly narcissistic and egoistic. And yes, of course, they are sad, deeply sad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the WHO, about 300 million people around the world are affected by depression. Nearly 800,000 people commit suicide every year. Suicide is second on the list of leading causes of deaths in 15 to 29 year-olds today. In spite of this, only 1 in every 5 depressed people receives treatment consistent with modern practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Numerous TV series and films have been made, aimed at tackling this. Their failure, however, has been appalling. Season 1 of the TV series &lt;em&gt;13 Reasons Wh&lt;/em&gt;y features a series of tapes left behind by a girl who commits suicide while in high school. In these tapes, she explains the 13 reasons behind her drastic step. No wonder this series became very popular; it was not just relatable to the very core but the drama of listening to a dead girl’s tapes, explaining why she committed suicide, was scintillating. Besides the wave of awareness, the series left behind one adverse impact. The number of suicides increased by almost a third, instead of going down, ever since the series aired. Within three weeks of being aired, searches about suicides increased by a staggering 20%. Many blame it on the very graphic depiction of how Hannah Baker, the protagonist, took her life by slitting her wrists at the very end of the series. This is not something that audiences have witnessed before on television, certainly not in programmes aimed at teenagers. The popularity of the series earned it two more seasons in the years that followed. However, amidst all the concerns, Netflix altered the 3-minute sequence, although convinced that the series had nothing to do with the increase in suicide rates in the USA, over 2 years after its initial release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has, however, been a decline in the stigma surrounding mental health. People do seek to talk about and actively treat depression and other mental health problems. Various online portals and helplines are active to give help to those seeking it. Earlier, they failed to recognise depression as a disease that needed treatment. Instead, they saw it as inadequacy or incompetence. Certain old asylums are often considered to be haunted because of the unspoken torture within its walls in the past. Hundreds have died in various such locations around the world, after being shunned by society for being mentally ill. Shock therapy, invented in the Italy of the 1930s, was commonly practiced to treat ‘madness’. Many, even today, believe in the effectiveness of electroconvulsive therapy, although it has been repeatedly tagged as medical abuse by different organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennials are convinced that they are but &lt;strong&gt;doomed&lt;/strong&gt;. And this conviction comes from a place of hyperawareness. There is near-constant exposure to news of thousands being beheaded in the name of religion or people committing suicide by bringing down an entire airbus full of people along with themselves. Or, maybe, that people are capable of democratically electing a person who doesn’t believe that Global Warming, which, by the way, can facilitate the extinction of humanity, is real, as the Leader of the Free World. We are always talking and making memes about Trump’s tweets, the melting ice caps or India’s water crisis. We see the expendability of human life in the deaths of our beloved Cameron Boyce, Stan Lee, Avicii, Stephen Hawking, Dolores O’Riordan, David Cassidy, Chester Bennington, Bill Paxton, Carrie Fisher, Harper Lee, and Alan Rickman. In fact, most Millennials do not even conform to the term ‘Millennial’, tagging it as &lt;em&gt;overly optimistic&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media and its ultra-fast nature have made it clear to the Millennials that humans are irrevocable. Millennials are &lt;strong&gt;aware&lt;/strong&gt; that the Zodiac Killer was never caught, MH-370 was never found and that France experienced its highest ever temperature in recorded history, earlier this year. They are aware of students shooting down hundreds in schools, abortion being banned and trees being cut. We know how this is affecting us all as a species and yet, there seems to be nothing that we can do about it. The news of bad incidents looms over us every day along with the knowledge that it can happen to any of us too. The incredibly talented and very dead singer Kurt Cobain did tell us, “Just because you are paranoid, does not mean they are not after you.” Millennials are the first generation to grow up in an era of both overwhelming awareness and paralysing feeling of our incapability to be able to solve them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know what is expected of us, the perfect job and the perfect partner, and we are aware of how it is just a pipe dream. They tell us it is social media reinforcements of everyone else living the perfect life that is making our generation depressed. That we are trying to reach for standards we will never attain. But I think there is more to the Great Millennial Depression than just that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s assume that you are Einstein-smart, devilishly beautiful and incredibly funny. Are you among the top 10 something? If you are not, well then, you do not matter. Let us assume that you are among the world’s top 10 most hilarious people. Will you hold the position forever? What happens next year? What if you face a decade-long writer’s block and go bankrupt? Perhaps you &lt;em&gt;succeed&lt;/em&gt; and go on a cruise with your soulmate and drown in your bathtub? We all will die one day and there will be nothing left of us in a few decades. No one will remember our sacrifices, pain, hard work or the embarrassing moments that we have shared with our crushes. The question is, are we important? Are our actions significant? Why is it that humans have had the privilege to even exist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have asked these for long and today, Millennials are convinced that nothing has an explanation. There is nowhere a certain someone is meant to be or something they are meant to do. They just exist. The stars were not specially created to dazzle us. Neither are we at the centre of the solar system, the universe or Creation in general. Things just exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think I am right, well then, congratulations, you are a nihilist. It is highly likely that you are a Millennial too. Turns out, the term nihilism has a very simple meaning. It is the rejection of all religious and moral principles. Nihilists believe that life has absolutely no meaning and yet humans keep seeking a way to give it some meaning, some purpose, but eventually die and are forgotten. In Tyler Durden’s &lt;em&gt;immortal&lt;/em&gt; words: “We are the middle children of history, man. No purpose or place. We have no Great War, No Great Depression. Our Great War’s a spiritual war… Our Great Depression is our Lives.” Nihilism is hot today. The great success of &lt;em&gt;BoJack Horseman, Rick and Morty, Hazel’s response to Augustus’ confession of the fear of oblivion&lt;/em&gt; and so on bear testimony to this very fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that depression and the popularity of nihilistic ideas have increased exponentially about the same time makes me wonder if they share some sort of a symbiotic relationship. If someone is depressed, the consolation that nothing really matters must help, surely? In fact, Optimistic Nihilism emphasises the notion that no one will ever remember one’s ill actions or embarrassing moments. Not all people who are depressed believe in nihilism though. But all nihilists may to some extent be sad. Everything productive that people do today is because they believe that it has meaning and life has a purpose. Nihilists dismiss this idea as nonsense. To them nothing has meaning and thus, there is no use doing anything. And the depressed do feel this way. Besides, I am sure you might have noticed the surge of suicidal and nihilistic memes’ pages on Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nihilists do not care about anything because nothing makes sense or has any significance. And thus, nothing can make them sad. Embarrassing moments do not matter and so there is no need to overthink them. Mistakes and bad deeds do not matter and so, they can move on and do something better. Of course, life has no meaning. But we can try to give it one or at least try and be happy for the little time that we have on our hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nihilism, however, contrary to popular opinion, is not the lack of hope. Life has no meaning. But, that does not mean that you cannot give it some purpose. Moreover, your failures do not count in anyone’s book and so, one should not be held back by them. Whether or not nihilism has been helping the depressed generation is up for debate. But, then again, there is no point in arguing. Alan Moore in &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; did very accurately say- “Why do we argue? Life is so fragile, a successful virus clinging to a speck of mud, suspended in endless nothing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a generation trapped in the growing realisation that they must face and solve the environmental, social and political crises of the day while lodged in the belief that nothing really matters. The same thing that causes our depression is also the source of our respite; how &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; it all matters.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">If you are depressed or some, possibly most, of your friends about the same age are depressed too, then it is highly likely that you are a Millennial. Yes, you belong to the infamous “ME ME ME” generation that is too obsessed to look beyond the self (at least that is what the magazines tell us). Millennials are supposedly narcissistic and egoistic. And yes, of course, they are sad, deeply sad.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Do Millennials Fetishise Productivity?</title>
      <link href="/Do-Millennials-Fetishise-Productivity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do Millennials Fetishise Productivity?" />
      <published>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Do-Millennials-Fetishise-Productivity</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Do-Millennials-Fetishise-Productivity">&lt;p&gt;There’s always that one favorite cousin in the family, who wakes up at 5 AM to meditate and revise the previous day’s lessons, pays attention during all lectures, is up to date with social media and is going to intern at Microsoft for the coming summer. And then, there’s every other Millennial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennials; who manage to sleep through eight alarms in a span of ten minutes, we are not eating healthy and we are definitely not performing well in college. But we are still quite there. Last I remember, we were thriving on self-deprivation, grinding through work and pulling off all-nighters just to submit that one assignment on time. We are most definitely not the ‘ungrateful, lazy, unambitious generation’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This obsession with maximising the resources at hand (case in point: time) goes beyond just textbooks on neoclassical economists’ theories of optimisation. It runs in our blood. Internalised capitalism or a fetish for productivity, call it what you want. We feel we must work hard all the time and rest should bring on a bout of guilt. We are relentless in the act of pursuing something, to the point that the fixation with pursuance takes precedence over asking ourselves what we truly want. We take ourselves too seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our days are intricately scheduled because how else will we be content? The Starbucks way of life has inspired us to grind through the week to be able to enjoy the weekend. But that happy weekend never arrives. We work hard every weekend to better the next one. The drive to the movies is reserved for making calls, emails are catered to while waiting on a dinner date, backlog and future plans are left for vacations. All this with the hope of this professional development turning into essentially, what we call, a good life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anti-capitalism, social justice flag-waving, trying to embody ‘wokeness’ generation finds itself in a state of inner turmoil. Corporate lifestyles leave no time for leisure, ‘the basis of culture’ (courtesy: Josef Pieper, German philosopher). The normalisation of dissatisfaction with the existing work environment and of constant struggle is dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pervading uncertainty in our lives contributes to our anxiety. The rapid development of technology has added to the fear of being automated out, more so now than ever before, and adapting to the highly dynamic work environments in different sectors is not easy either. Moreover, with the dwindling employment rates, it is safe to say the economy has not particularly been a friend. The apprehensions cultivating from the need to pay off student debt means we cannot switch jobs in this exceedingly competitive job market. The Millennials have, therefore, resigned to working excruciatingly hard in college and grad school to avail, at least, a job with decent pay. As long as we need the money and real estate, we will learn to live with the misery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not just a mundane 9 AM to 5 PM job. There is also passion. Passion, because what is life without it? A reason to be fiercely alive, a way to be ferociously happy. Millennials spend a huge amount of their lives looking for a passion to offset the effect of stress. We love being unique, to do something different from the rest. So, we go the extra mile to stand out and outdo our peers. It is not called a hobby anymore, it is a skill. It is something we can have on our resume while being equally fascinating to qualify as something to post about on our social media. We attend galas, watch theatre, immerse ourselves in poetry, visit exhibitions and try extremely hard to keep up with pop culture. Even art is not for the sake of art anymore, it is something to be done; a territory waiting to be embarked upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The invasion of technology has wiped away the distinction between our personal and work lives in a way it had not happened for previous generations. With the convenience of always being able to send and receive emails, documenting at all times, we have brought the office back home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are part of a society which has taught us that stagnancy is acceptable, but quitting is not. The romanticisation of stability has made us layout an entire plan for our life. Being the generation that has inherited soaring housing, education, and living costs, settling down becomes the ultimate goal. It is not something that has come to us as a matter of personal choice. Our childhoods were meticulously supervised. Regular homework, summer classes to learn a new hobby, timely school assessments, yada yada. Things that do not eventually lead to a bigger goal do not belong in our lives, which is why we are always expected to know what we want. What to study, where to get a job, which job after the current one. Moreover, there is a sense of finality in every decision; the first decision needs to be the right one, otherwise, everything goes downhill. Quitting jobs we do not like is a sign of ‘impulsiveness’ and ‘weakness’. We all wish to achieve stability, what we end up getting is monotonicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do life in bits and pieces. When we seek thrill, we resort to extreme sports (ah, passion). Finding a little bit of happiness to thrive on, in between life. In the fear of being left behind, we have reached so far ahead that we are blinded to all the life that’s happening outside of our work-home space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we hustle because we are uncomfortable. The discomfort arriving from the feeling of losing out on time; the same time we spend watching inspirational videos on YouTube and scrolling through Instagram feeds, constantly reiterating feelings of inadequacy and of not being ‘good enough’. And for the rest, we know the drill. The drill of the hustle. Panic, dissatisfaction, failure. Rather, the fear of failure. As a generation, we were built to not be akin to failure. We tell ourselves these marks matter the most, this social gathering I cannot miss, if I do not get this job…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The break down of the journey has vanished, there is an origin and destiny. A far fetched destiny that is so flawless, we tend to make the path longer and more and more dreadful.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Hrishita Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There’s always that one favorite cousin in the family, who wakes up at 5 AM to meditate and revise the previous day’s lessons, pays attention during all lectures, is up to date with social media and is going to intern at Microsoft for the coming summer. And then, there’s every other Millennial.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Millennials, The Gentle Souls</title>
      <link href="/Millennials-the-Gentle-Souls" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Millennials, The Gentle Souls" />
      <published>2019-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Millennials-the-Gentle-Souls</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Millennials-the-Gentle-Souls">&lt;p&gt;It is perhaps for the first time ever that postmodernism has found such a lovely
home: social media. The diffusion of the political, philosophical and
sociological microphones has done more than just prove that multiple conflicting
truths coexist; it has given a voice to all of those narratives, to all of our
realities. Contradictions are not grounds to invalidate your story. Social media
has shaped how today’s youth discusses the world they inhabit. We are exposed to
a vivid pluralism of beliefs and ideas, almost on a real-time basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point on the axis of time, Facebook and Instagram became places to
discuss our collective anguish over misogyny, casteism, racism, homophobia, our
parents and pineapple pizza. Candidly, the discourse that exists as of today, is
not ideal, in fact far from it. It’s a chaos of constantly clashing opinions.
And not the most sophisticated of chaoses even. It’s not the most nuanced or
informed discussion, our arguments don’t necessarily feature brilliance or dare
I say, intelligence. However, I am not looking for a great emancipatory utility
to this discourse. I am merely looking at the hint of nobility that underlies
this chaos. What’s noble is that we care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A concern that is evident in the endearing frustration of our angry tweets about
how bras are a tool of the patriarchy or the activist pages on Instagram which
tell you that it’s okay to not be able to orgasm. It’s visible in the
fifteen-year-old slam poets who dream of changing the world, often not for
themselves but for others, and in all of us, a type of audience, clicking our
fingers in praise. We realise the passivity of the nature of our activism. We
face the brunt of accusations that tell us all we can do is yell at each other
in our insular echo chambers. We realise the frustration that this social media
activism will get us nowhere. But are we not already somewhere? Especially, the
moment we begin to realise the inadequacies and fallibility of our own
endeavours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of my insistence upon this chaotic discussion being romantically beautiful
is reduced to hokum with the words ‘woke culture.’ The ‘woke millennial’ gives
up plastic straws and embraces veganism only because it is suddenly cool to care
about the environment, not out of actual concern for the Earth. Atrocious
millennials!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Woke culture’ is criticised, as it should be. But the very fact that caring
about social issues is now a metric for social acceptance and approval, is
nothing short of a paradigm shift. We are trying to create the socially ratified
moral compass we never inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennial culture extends beyond the political or social, it enters the deeply
intimate, personal spaces of our lives. Here’s where bullying comes into the
picture, and what, I believe, shapes us into being the gentler generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bullying arises, mostly, from differences in historically sanctioned prowess;
like beauty in women and toughness in men or things like wealth and having a
favourable orientation. What most generations have absently done is aspire to be
like their bullies. The ‘prowess’ that our intimidators possessed was fed as
aspirational. And the moment you begin to believe that your inadequacies are to
blame for your pain, you stop empathising with yourself and with others. But
here we have our millennials who have gone a step beyond the condemnation of
bullies. They are questioning the arbitrary distributions of power and prowess.
We are disarming power itself. We are gentler, not only with others but, more
courageously, also with ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world has been hungover on patriarchal ideas that seek glory in strength,
for far too long. We are saying, it is okay to feel. What I am saying is our
generation fights the urge to want to be like Regina George and instead embraces
the freaky Janis Ian who lurks within. Millennials exhibit the ferociousness of
daring to live authentically. The history of our world has strung together
stories of the suppression of any kind of human authenticity. From Victorian
women who could not renounce corsets and religious laws that tell us men cannot
f*ck other men to mothers who tell their daughters not to laugh too loud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you contextualise the past, you begin to see what a rebellious idea it is
to dream to live unencumbered. Social reinforcements are what make it painful to
be yourself; the eye rolls and the condescending laughs when something about you
hints at you being different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we are well on our way towards breaking those stringent, stringent shackles.
We are breaking notions of propriety, right down to the way we converse with
each other. We let each other be the dramatic, flamboyant and weird creatures
humans were meant to be. We are not just secretly engaging with our indecorous
selves, but finally talking about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The millennial ability to let people be the way they want to be, in short,
acceptance, arises from somewhere. We admit our imperfections and the colossal
mountains of our insecurities. It is this admittance that lends us the empathy
to be able to see the fallibility of other humans without feeling the need to
shame it. We have stopped holding ourselves up to a pedestal of perfection and
have accepted how utterly human it is to be flawed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our personal and political capacities, we are striving towards one thing; the
complete utter and humanisation of humans. Our empathy manifests both in the
acrimonious outrage over the romanticisation of sexual violence in our cinema
and in the tenderness with which we listen to our friends’ cathartic rants.
Millennial sensitivity is seen in how they will call out a certain brand of
motivational videos for being the inspiration porn that they are. Millennials
will tell you that the first step to respecting pain is to not voyeur over it.
Let humans be human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They say millennials are lonely, and maybe we are, but we are also surviving
through the solidarities we have constructed for ourselves. Sometimes that
solidarity is sisterhood, sometimes it is merely commenting ‘Me, as hell’ on a
meme rooted in self-deprecation.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Stuti Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is perhaps for the first time ever that postmodernism has found such a lovely home: social media. The diffusion of the political, philosophical and sociological microphones has done more than just prove that multiple conflicting truths coexist; it has given a voice to all of those narratives, to all of our realities. Contradictions are not grounds to invalidate your story. Social media has shaped how today’s youth discusses the world they inhabit. We are exposed to a vivid pluralism of beliefs and ideas, almost on a real-time basis. At some point on the axis of time, Facebook and Instagram became places to discuss our collective anguish over misogyny, casteism, racism, homophobia, our parents and pineapple pizza. Candidly, the discourse that exists as of today, is not ideal, in fact far from it. It’s a chaos of constantly clashing opinions. And not the most sophisticated of chaoses even. It’s not the most nuanced or informed discussion, our arguments don’t necessarily feature brilliance or dare I say, intelligence. However, I am not looking for a great emancipatory utility to this discourse. I am merely looking at the hint of nobility that underlies this chaos. What’s noble is that we care. A concern that is evident in the endearing frustration of our angry tweets about how bras are a tool of the patriarchy or the activist pages on Instagram which tell you that it’s okay to not be able to orgasm. It’s visible in the fifteen-year-old slam poets who dream of changing the world, often not for themselves but for others, and in all of us, a type of audience, clicking our fingers in praise. We realise the passivity of the nature of our activism. We face the brunt of accusations that tell us all we can do is yell at each other in our insular echo chambers. We realise the frustration that this social media activism will get us nowhere. But are we not already somewhere? Especially, the moment we begin to realise the inadequacies and fallibility of our own endeavours. All of my insistence upon this chaotic discussion being romantically beautiful is reduced to hokum with the words ‘woke culture.’ The ‘woke millennial’ gives up plastic straws and embraces veganism only because it is suddenly cool to care about the environment, not out of actual concern for the Earth. Atrocious millennials! ‘Woke culture’ is criticised, as it should be. But the very fact that caring about social issues is now a metric for social acceptance and approval, is nothing short of a paradigm shift. We are trying to create the socially ratified moral compass we never inherited. Millennial culture extends beyond the political or social, it enters the deeply intimate, personal spaces of our lives. Here’s where bullying comes into the picture, and what, I believe, shapes us into being the gentler generation. Bullying arises, mostly, from differences in historically sanctioned prowess; like beauty in women and toughness in men or things like wealth and having a favourable orientation. What most generations have absently done is aspire to be like their bullies. The ‘prowess’ that our intimidators possessed was fed as aspirational. And the moment you begin to believe that your inadequacies are to blame for your pain, you stop empathising with yourself and with others. But here we have our millennials who have gone a step beyond the condemnation of bullies. They are questioning the arbitrary distributions of power and prowess. We are disarming power itself. We are gentler, not only with others but, more courageously, also with ourselves. The world has been hungover on patriarchal ideas that seek glory in strength, for far too long. We are saying, it is okay to feel. What I am saying is our generation fights the urge to want to be like Regina George and instead embraces the freaky Janis Ian who lurks within. Millennials exhibit the ferociousness of daring to live authentically. The history of our world has strung together stories of the suppression of any kind of human authenticity. From Victorian women who could not renounce corsets and religious laws that tell us men cannot f*ck other men to mothers who tell their daughters not to laugh too loud. Once you contextualise the past, you begin to see what a rebellious idea it is to dream to live unencumbered. Social reinforcements are what make it painful to be yourself; the eye rolls and the condescending laughs when something about you hints at you being different. But we are well on our way towards breaking those stringent, stringent shackles. We are breaking notions of propriety, right down to the way we converse with each other. We let each other be the dramatic, flamboyant and weird creatures humans were meant to be. We are not just secretly engaging with our indecorous selves, but finally talking about them. The millennial ability to let people be the way they want to be, in short, acceptance, arises from somewhere. We admit our imperfections and the colossal mountains of our insecurities. It is this admittance that lends us the empathy to be able to see the fallibility of other humans without feeling the need to shame it. We have stopped holding ourselves up to a pedestal of perfection and have accepted how utterly human it is to be flawed. In our personal and political capacities, we are striving towards one thing; the complete utter and humanisation of humans. Our empathy manifests both in the acrimonious outrage over the romanticisation of sexual violence in our cinema and in the tenderness with which we listen to our friends’ cathartic rants. Millennial sensitivity is seen in how they will call out a certain brand of motivational videos for being the inspiration porn that they are. Millennials will tell you that the first step to respecting pain is to not voyeur over it. Let humans be human. They say millennials are lonely, and maybe we are, but we are also surviving through the solidarities we have constructed for ourselves. Sometimes that solidarity is sisterhood, sometimes it is merely commenting ‘Me, as hell’ on a meme rooted in self-deprecation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Wandering Wonder</title>
      <link href="/The-Wandering-Wondar" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Wandering Wonder" />
      <published>2019-07-12T17:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-12T17:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Wandering-Wondar</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Wandering-Wondar">&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wandered off while sitting down―all in your head, all out of
wonder? Ever imagined multiple lives for yourself? Ever wondered how there are a
gazillion lives that are all affected by the interconnectedness of everything?
Has there been a time when you have wanted to exchange places, or be at multiple
places, living multiple lives at the same time? If you have, my friend, we are
aboard the same boat and I hope your frustration wards off just as soon as I
wish for mine to leave. Or maybe, just maybe, better yet, this wonder is what
keeps us afloat, keeps us from dreading the worst. We know there’s a lot that
exists, we know we may never know about it all, and maybe it’s this wonder that
keeps us excited to be alive. I may be rationalising here and I promise to get
rid of this defence mechanism as soon as I find a better one. But language is
funny in more ways than not. We feel liberated using it, and at the same time,
there is also a strange kind of entrapment. We cannot communicate without words,
and yet are words sufficient to voice everything we feel?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I did not know that the frustration of being limited to one
experience was a common dilemma, I had no idea there was even a name for it,
albeit none that one can use in their English essay. Onism, and we shall all
thank John Koenig for the same, is a word that tries to explain the frustration
of being stuck in just one body, that inhabits only one place at a time. It is
understood to be like standing in front of the departures screen at an airport,
flickering over with strange place names like other people’s passwords, each
representing one more thing you will never get to see before you die―and all
because, as the arrow on the map helpfully points out, you are here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can imagine how much more rich and satisfying it would be to have multiple
bodies, not just one―so one could escape themselves for a while and live on the
other side of the planet. Or take a step back and see themselves from someone
else’s point of view, in full context with the rest of the world, with their
face the right way around, their eyes un-flattened, just as vivid as one appears
to other people. It would be like knowing yourself like others do, judging our
own quirks but with much less self-loathing, just seeing them as unique factions
of our being. However absurd the idea may seem; it would bring so much more
clarity and joy. Of course, this may be coming from a place of bias, with myself
being someone who has felt this for a long time and only just recently found out
about the word that expresses it so well on an unanticipated night. A friend
introduced me to &lt;em&gt;The Dictionary of Obscure Sorrows&lt;/em&gt; and that’s when I met with
the genius work of John Koenig. This man is on a mission to fill the gaps
incurred in the English language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His dictionary includes words that describe emotions that one may feel but can’t
put into motion through speech or writing, it includes questioning the
limitations that language puts on us. One has to acknowledge that our bodies and
minds are bombarded with so many complex sensations throughout the day that it
would be impossible to assign a name to each. Feelings are a product of any
stimulation one can procure―the lack of it―a phenomenon in itself. Even though
&lt;em&gt;Merriam&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Oxford&lt;/em&gt; haven’t made it yet, Koenig with his popular Tumblr Blog
and subsequent YouTube Channel and website is paving the way. &lt;em&gt;TDOBS&lt;/em&gt; is
intriguing because it presents a word that is obscure or completely invented and
then connects it to a stylised video to further enhance the definition of that
word. As Koenig indicates on his website, “Each original definition aims to fill
a hole in the language—to give a name to emotions we all might experience but
don’t yet have a word for.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Koenig has said multiple times that the blog began with his desire to write
poems. He made up words to help frame the poems better. He insists that the
inception began at a dark time in his life. In his Ted Talk, Koenig recollects
the time when his own melancholy triggered him to compose the dictionary, and
how people later came up to him to thank him for his work. The graphic
designer/editor/voice performer speaks of how his sombreness gave him a penchant
for words. One should be aware of the fact that he makes sure that all his words
have etymological significance. That they all have sense and reason behind them.
&lt;em&gt;TDOBS&lt;/em&gt; gained popularity with the wilfulness of Twitter, someone tweeted out 23
of the words and then, boom! The crowd came rushing, in shared understanding of
the un-worded emotions. Words such as ‘sonder’ have made it to the bigwigs, with
companies using them to name products. A very prominent bar in New York has
named its drinks after the 23 popularised words; artists too have now started
naming their paintings with the help of these words, so as to express themselves
better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might wonder why out of every interesting word this man has invented, I
longed to make this word the winter sun―Onism. Onism is a portmanteau of monism&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;onanism. In philosophy, monism is the view that a variety of things can be
explained in terms of a single reality or substance, or a distinct source. Onism
can be seen as a kind of monism, because one’s life is indeed limited to a
single reality, by virtue of being restricted to a single body, but something is
clearly missing. Meanwhile, onanism is another word for masturbation or
self-pleasure, transfixed inside our own menagerie of fantasies like going on a
sightseeing tour of our own apartment—frustrating in its closed-off familiarity.
Again, something is missing. What makes it even more special is that Onism was
born while Koenig was travelling in an airplane, across 6 countries, in the
process of moving places and struggling with the idea of a new life. To me, this
brings in the idea more so than anything else. It makes me think of Remedial
Chaos Theory: there are lots of me in other timelines who - collectively - have
done everything I have not. It is the awareness of everything you are giving up,
to be where you are right now. It is questioning the excuses we have invented to
explain why so much of our life belongs in the background. Koenig very well
expresses this in how he words his video transcripts- “We sketch monsters on the
map because we find their presence comforting. They guard the edges of the
abyss, and force us to look away; so, we can live comfortably in the Known
World, at least for a little while.” An analogy I came across may help you
visualise it better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time we enter primary school, we have heard all about the planets in our
Solar System. As we grow older, we learn that the Solar System is just a speck
in the Milky Way Galaxy, and that there are thousands of galaxies out there,
peppering our universe with their glow and might. The celestial mysteries that
beckon to us are countless, but we resign ourselves to the fact that they are
limited to computer screens and observatories. We accept the fact that the stars
are too far away to take seriously, that Jupiter has a turbulent red spot over
twice the size of our planet, that the moon will always be a distant relative.
So instead, we look around at how far the horizon is and how hauntingly it
encircles us. That scircle is just a fleck of life, dotted on the surface of the
earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may think about the number of adventures we could be having, the divergent
memories we could be creating, the new people we could be meeting—within the
ring that encircles us. We have only one body, although our minds would surely
wish we had ten. The world becomes even more intriguing once we extricate
ourselves from that ring- there are mountains and slopes waiting to be climbed,
fields of snow waiting to be shaped into spheres and thrown, peaks that are
craving to be mounted, oceans with shadowy depths, beautiful creatures, and fish
that we still do not know exist. There are villages waiting to be visited, whose
culture is unlike anything we have ever witnessed. There are waterfalls,
rainforests, and glaciers still unknown to the human mind, foreign sunshine that
is waiting to infuse itself into our bloodstreams, caves that scream adrenaline
and excitement. There are airplanes, trains, cars, bicycles, and our own two
feet. But something stops us, limitations confine us. The lack of time, money,
and flexibility in our schedules. The fact that the seconds keep ticking by,
that so much of our time goes in useless endeavours we will never remember. And
the reality that we cannot be in two places at once. The fact that our two feet
are rooted in the same place, that there are millions of places we could be in
right now—but we are always forced to choose one. That when we are at the
airport, we have only one destination to go to—while the other cities flicker
like candlelight on a windy afternoon. When we drive a car, there are thousands
of alternate routes we could take. And yet, we do not—because we believe that we
are not meant to deviate from our predetermined route. In other words, we are
unknowingly ensnared. Onism is the frustration of knowing how little of the
universe we will be able to appreciate; the impatience of seeing the stars
twinkling at night, as if mocking our inability to escape the ground. But
somehow, it only makes us dream more. Our inability to traverse the Solar System
makes us imagine; it makes us envisage a universe that is probably more
beautiful and romantic than what it really is. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may construe Onism as something that resembles sadness or sorrow, or one may
call it the Chi Force and what keeps us alive, but whatever it may be thought of
as- we are all affected by it, however it may come. I’d really encourage people
to go about looking for &lt;em&gt;The Dictionary of Obscure Sorrows&lt;/em&gt; and open their minds
to new words that express age-old emotions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the chance, I’d definitely like to end with a line from Koenig’s script- &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But if someone were to ask you on your Deathbed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it was like to live here on Earth&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the only honest answer would be,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know, I passed through it once, but I’ve never really been there.”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Have you ever wandered off while sitting down―all in your head, all out of wonder? Ever imagined multiple lives for yourself? Ever wondered how there are a gazillion lives that are all affected by the interconnectedness of everything? Has there been a time when you have wanted to exchange places, or be at multiple places, living multiple lives at the same time? If you have, my friend, we are aboard the same boat and I hope your frustration wards off just as soon as I wish for mine to leave. Or maybe, just maybe, better yet, this wonder is what keeps us afloat, keeps us from dreading the worst. We know there’s a lot that exists, we know we may never know about it all, and maybe it’s this wonder that keeps us excited to be alive. I may be rationalising here and I promise to get rid of this defence mechanism as soon as I find a better one. But language is funny in more ways than not. We feel liberated using it, and at the same time, there is also a strange kind of entrapment. We cannot communicate without words, and yet are words sufficient to voice everything we feel? Personally, I did not know that the frustration of being limited to one experience was a common dilemma, I had no idea there was even a name for it, albeit none that one can use in their English essay. Onism, and we shall all thank John Koenig for the same, is a word that tries to explain the frustration of being stuck in just one body, that inhabits only one place at a time. It is understood to be like standing in front of the departures screen at an airport, flickering over with strange place names like other people’s passwords, each representing one more thing you will never get to see before you die―and all because, as the arrow on the map helpfully points out, you are here. One can imagine how much more rich and satisfying it would be to have multiple bodies, not just one―so one could escape themselves for a while and live on the other side of the planet. Or take a step back and see themselves from someone else’s point of view, in full context with the rest of the world, with their face the right way around, their eyes un-flattened, just as vivid as one appears to other people. It would be like knowing yourself like others do, judging our own quirks but with much less self-loathing, just seeing them as unique factions of our being. However absurd the idea may seem; it would bring so much more clarity and joy. Of course, this may be coming from a place of bias, with myself being someone who has felt this for a long time and only just recently found out about the word that expresses it so well on an unanticipated night. A friend introduced me to The Dictionary of Obscure Sorrows and that’s when I met with the genius work of John Koenig. This man is on a mission to fill the gaps incurred in the English language. His dictionary includes words that describe emotions that one may feel but can’t put into motion through speech or writing, it includes questioning the limitations that language puts on us. One has to acknowledge that our bodies and minds are bombarded with so many complex sensations throughout the day that it would be impossible to assign a name to each. Feelings are a product of any stimulation one can procure―the lack of it―a phenomenon in itself. Even though Merriam and Oxford haven’t made it yet, Koenig with his popular Tumblr Blog and subsequent YouTube Channel and website is paving the way. TDOBS is intriguing because it presents a word that is obscure or completely invented and then connects it to a stylised video to further enhance the definition of that word. As Koenig indicates on his website, “Each original definition aims to fill a hole in the language—to give a name to emotions we all might experience but don’t yet have a word for.” Koenig has said multiple times that the blog began with his desire to write poems. He made up words to help frame the poems better. He insists that the inception began at a dark time in his life. In his Ted Talk, Koenig recollects the time when his own melancholy triggered him to compose the dictionary, and how people later came up to him to thank him for his work. The graphic designer/editor/voice performer speaks of how his sombreness gave him a penchant for words. One should be aware of the fact that he makes sure that all his words have etymological significance. That they all have sense and reason behind them. TDOBS gained popularity with the wilfulness of Twitter, someone tweeted out 23 of the words and then, boom! The crowd came rushing, in shared understanding of the un-worded emotions. Words such as ‘sonder’ have made it to the bigwigs, with companies using them to name products. A very prominent bar in New York has named its drinks after the 23 popularised words; artists too have now started naming their paintings with the help of these words, so as to express themselves better. One might wonder why out of every interesting word this man has invented, I longed to make this word the winter sun―Onism. Onism is a portmanteau of monism onanism. In philosophy, monism is the view that a variety of things can be explained in terms of a single reality or substance, or a distinct source. Onism can be seen as a kind of monism, because one’s life is indeed limited to a single reality, by virtue of being restricted to a single body, but something is clearly missing. Meanwhile, onanism is another word for masturbation or self-pleasure, transfixed inside our own menagerie of fantasies like going on a sightseeing tour of our own apartment—frustrating in its closed-off familiarity. Again, something is missing. What makes it even more special is that Onism was born while Koenig was travelling in an airplane, across 6 countries, in the process of moving places and struggling with the idea of a new life. To me, this brings in the idea more so than anything else. It makes me think of Remedial Chaos Theory: there are lots of me in other timelines who - collectively - have done everything I have not. It is the awareness of everything you are giving up, to be where you are right now. It is questioning the excuses we have invented to explain why so much of our life belongs in the background. Koenig very well expresses this in how he words his video transcripts- “We sketch monsters on the map because we find their presence comforting. They guard the edges of the abyss, and force us to look away; so, we can live comfortably in the Known World, at least for a little while.” An analogy I came across may help you visualise it better. By the time we enter primary school, we have heard all about the planets in our Solar System. As we grow older, we learn that the Solar System is just a speck in the Milky Way Galaxy, and that there are thousands of galaxies out there, peppering our universe with their glow and might. The celestial mysteries that beckon to us are countless, but we resign ourselves to the fact that they are limited to computer screens and observatories. We accept the fact that the stars are too far away to take seriously, that Jupiter has a turbulent red spot over twice the size of our planet, that the moon will always be a distant relative. So instead, we look around at how far the horizon is and how hauntingly it encircles us. That scircle is just a fleck of life, dotted on the surface of the earth. We may think about the number of adventures we could be having, the divergent memories we could be creating, the new people we could be meeting—within the ring that encircles us. We have only one body, although our minds would surely wish we had ten. The world becomes even more intriguing once we extricate ourselves from that ring- there are mountains and slopes waiting to be climbed, fields of snow waiting to be shaped into spheres and thrown, peaks that are craving to be mounted, oceans with shadowy depths, beautiful creatures, and fish that we still do not know exist. There are villages waiting to be visited, whose culture is unlike anything we have ever witnessed. There are waterfalls, rainforests, and glaciers still unknown to the human mind, foreign sunshine that is waiting to infuse itself into our bloodstreams, caves that scream adrenaline and excitement. There are airplanes, trains, cars, bicycles, and our own two feet. But something stops us, limitations confine us. The lack of time, money, and flexibility in our schedules. The fact that the seconds keep ticking by, that so much of our time goes in useless endeavours we will never remember. And the reality that we cannot be in two places at once. The fact that our two feet are rooted in the same place, that there are millions of places we could be in right now—but we are always forced to choose one. That when we are at the airport, we have only one destination to go to—while the other cities flicker like candlelight on a windy afternoon. When we drive a car, there are thousands of alternate routes we could take. And yet, we do not—because we believe that we are not meant to deviate from our predetermined route. In other words, we are unknowingly ensnared. Onism is the frustration of knowing how little of the universe we will be able to appreciate; the impatience of seeing the stars twinkling at night, as if mocking our inability to escape the ground. But somehow, it only makes us dream more. Our inability to traverse the Solar System makes us imagine; it makes us envisage a universe that is probably more beautiful and romantic than what it really is.  One may construe Onism as something that resembles sadness or sorrow, or one may call it the Chi Force and what keeps us alive, but whatever it may be thought of as- we are all affected by it, however it may come. I’d really encourage people to go about looking for The Dictionary of Obscure Sorrows and open their minds to new words that express age-old emotions.  Given the chance, I’d definitely like to end with a line from Koenig’s script-  “But if someone were to ask you on your Deathbed What it was like to live here on Earth Perhaps the only honest answer would be, I don’t know, I passed through it once, but I’ve never really been there.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Fall of Religion in the Millennial West</title>
      <link href="/The-Fall-of-Religion" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fall of Religion in the Millennial West" />
      <published>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Fall-of-Religion</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Fall-of-Religion">&lt;p&gt;One of the most important demographic changes, in recent times, is the rise of the ‘nones’ in Western society. These are a group of people who refuse to identify themselves with any mainstream religious group or denomination. A 2012 article, by the Pew Research Center, noted that “[o]ne-fifth of the U.S. public – and a third of adults under 30 – are religiously unaffiliated today” and “[i]n the last five years alone, the unaffiliated have increased from just over 15% to just under 20% of all U.S. adults. Their ranks now include more than 13 million self-described atheists and agnostics (nearly 6% of the U.S. public), as well as nearly 33 million people who say they have no particular religious affiliation (14%)”. If we look at certain Western European countries and even in some parts of Eastern Europe, the numbers will undoubtedly be higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this happening? Why are young people increasingly disassociating themselves from organised religion, especially in what can only be fittingly described as a post-Christian society?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are four main reasons which I put forward, all of which can be summed up in a single sentence: &lt;strong&gt;Christianity – and, especially, Catholicism - has lost its credibility in the minds of our youth.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1: The Dominant Historical Narrative&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each one of us has heard it sometime or the other. The popular narrative runs thus: human society began well and reached summits of excellence and achievement, especially in the classical age. But when Christianity came, all that progress and achievement, as well as the scientific impulse, came to an end and was effectively destroyed. For centuries, the West was embroiled in a quagmire of oppressive feudalism and religious intolerance, in which free-thinkers were labelled heretics and persecuted fiercely. This was called the &lt;em&gt;Dark Ages&lt;/em&gt;, and rightly so, because human civilisation was truly held in captivity in the darkness of religious bigotry and superstition. All of this was the case, until the time of the Renaissance and the Enlightenment when, finally, we were able to break free of the chains of theocracy and emerge into the bright new world, to build our future for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least, that is how countless millennials understand the Medieval period. It is certainly the way history is taught in our schools, and thus the way many millennials understand this era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Added to this is the stigma of the Crusades and the Inquisitions, both of which are believed to be butcheries of human life and liberty based on religious (and especially Catholic) dogmatism and fanaticism. Fresh in the mind of many of our fellow millennials is the Galileo Affair, in which – it is believed – the geocentric Catholics tried to murder the heliocentric Galileo for the crime of trying to think rationally and not superstitiously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of this narrative, however, is myopic, and fails to take into account the various other factors which were at play. But, unfortunately for people like me, many of my fellow millennials believe this to be the Gospel truth. And naturally, it has distanced them from a religion which, they are convinced, is responsible for stifling human civilisation and progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2: The Widening Gap Between the Jesus of History and the Christ of Faith&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan Brown is one of the most popular fiction authors in the world today. I have had the chance of reading parts of his books, and have found his style to be most engaging. However, Brown is more than your average thriller writer. Thanks to books like &lt;em&gt;The Da Vinci Code&lt;/em&gt;, Brown has managed to bring the ‘Lost Gospels’ to the forefront of public discourse. And boy, has it fired the imagination of the masses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What people like Brown have managed to do is convince the populace – and especially the youth – that there is big difference between the Jesus of Catholicism and the actual Jesus whom we read about in works like the Gospel of Peter and Phillip, for example. He has also managed to alert people regarding the issue of the Biblical canon; why are these four Gospels part of the Bible and not others? Why has the Church chosen to only highlight these particular narratives and declare others heretical?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way information is put out in books such as these has convinced countless many that in the very early history of Christianity, there emerged a power-hungry faction which sought to glorify their own theology at the expense of others. We are told that there was not one but several ‘Christianities’ in the beginning. But one faction – which today exists as the Catholic Church – gained ascendancy and, with quite a bit of patronage from Romam Emperor Constantine, persecuted the other factions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This adds to the impression that today’s youth already has regarding the Christian faith and leaves them with a deep distrust towards anything related to Catholicism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3: The Rise of Philosophical Naturalism and Postmodern Nihilism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone looks at the world through a set of lenses. We all operate with basic metaphysical and epistemological presuppositions. However, in recent times, especially in universities, a particular philosophical perspective has been put forward vociferously, and other points of view have largely been isolated and marginalized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, for a while, was an undergraduate philosophy student at a well-respected university in India. And what I encountered from my professors was not a careful treatment of the various opposing perspectives but rather open and brazen bias, especially when it came to the philosophy of religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What young undergraduates are consistently taught is that the arguments for the existence of God – as put forward by people like Augustine, Aquinas, Leibniz and others – are all extremely poor and fallacious bits of reasoning which can be so easily debunked that one wonders how such eminent men came to such bizarre conclusions. We are also told that these people were motivated by their own personal religious beliefs, and sought to back them up the best they could. What remained was a set of arguments that would only convince people who already had faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least, that is the dominant narrative in philosophical academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And young philosophers usually accept this without question, without delving deeper into the works of Augustine and Aquinas to see if this is indeed true. Most of them don’t bother to later study the philosophy of religion, but rather end up specialising in other fields. And so what they uncritically accept as true in their early years, they end up carrying throughout life. And it is in this way that a consistent naturalist philosophical narrative has been built up over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this has led our young people to be extremely skeptical of any supernatural claims and has, therefore, led them to the conclusion that this world is all there is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting development happening simultaneously is the rise of postmodernism. This is entirely different from the dogmatic atheism I have just described. Rather, this is a dogmatic rejection of all dogmatism, an objective denial of all objectivity. It is a position some might characterise as absurd, but this appellation is readily embraced by some of its vociferous proponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Postmodernism is basically summed up in three maxims: “Truth is what you make of it. Morality is what you shape of it. God is Who you think He/She/It is.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways, this attitude is the product of the younger generation’s exposure to other cultures, viewpoints and ways of thinking. Young people see heated debates in which scholars on both sides put forward their cases and state their opinions, each backing themselves up with copious argumentation. They see different religions and ways of life, entirely different from the ones they had been exposed to. And having no strong rational grounds to support the religion of their upbringing, they naturally come to the conclusion that ‘man is the measure of all things’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This understanding of life is indeed very attractive since it promises a kind of godhood. One is free to shape one’s reality and one’s destiny as one sees it. One is free to identify as whatever one pleases and be whoever one wishes to be. Above all, one is liberated from the shackles of dogmatism, free to believe whatever they wish to believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, anyone addicted to this euphoria of freedom will find organised religion, with all its creeds and ancient affirmations, very unattractive indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4: The Transformation of Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps the most important and significant of all, since it strikes not merely at our intellect but also at our emotions. The cultural elite of the West are working very hard to change and transform culture. They do this through books, films, magazines and mass media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example: Imagine that you have grown up in a very conservative society, your parents told you that the right thing to do was to dress modestly, especially in front of the opposite sex. What happens when you are constantly exposed to pictures of men and women in states of partial or complete undress, when you can hardly go to the movies or even switch on a television without coming across some scene or advertisement that is either sexually explicit or has strong sexual themes, that too being performed by men and women who are great artists whom you admire?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, your perception is going to shift. You would in all likelihood rather imitate your heroes and role models rather than your parents, in this case. And in all probability, your friends have similar attitudes in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these factors come together and compound in such a way that it is possible to change views about something as fundamental as human sexuality across the course of a generation! Changing one’s views on sexual ethics is nothing more and nothing less than a paradigm shift. Instead of being something that is sacred and to be enjoyed within the context of marriage in a reproductively responsible manner, young people are offered the alluring option of ‘sex with no strings attached’. Rather than being the self-giving expression of commitment and love between two spouses (as Christians have traditionally believed), it has become a ‘casual’ affair. It is, therefore, no wonder that our young people are losing their faith in traditional Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popular music has played an inestimable role in detaching young people from the Christian faith. Young people see singers who are clearly extraordinarily talented, beloved by all their friends and peer groups, and who sing songs that contain themes that are clearly contrary to Christian faith and morals, in more ways than one. Naturally, over time, one comes to favour one’s friend groups rather than one’s parents and one begins to side with the more secularising culture rather than traditional ways of living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I am a millennial myself. But I am not your average millennial. In fact, I am a convert to the Catholic Church, having come from a liberal Hindu background myself. I am the black sheep, so to speak, of this modern and enlightened generation. What causes me to remain traditional and Catholic? Why don’t I simply join the great secular bus and enjoy all the many benefits its offers? Why do I remain in the shadows and willingly disassociate myself from much of the modern world and even isolate myself, at times, enjoying but a few friends?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons are endless, but I will summarise it in a few brief points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, it is my firmest conviction that the conventional narrative about the &lt;em&gt;Dark Ages&lt;/em&gt; is thoroughly erroneous, and in fact holds little water in academic circles, thank God. This view of the Medieval Church as an oppressive, science-persecuting religion has been increasingly discredited in modern times, not least by the excellent work of the Pulitzer-Prize winning Rodney Stark who, although himself a non-Catholic, has taken it upon himself to work towards exonerating the Catholic Church from baseless myths and lies, as can be seen in his work &lt;em&gt;Bearing False Witness&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, this idea that the Church persecuted scientists fails to take into account the immense contributions the Church made to science, in the Middle Ages and after as well. It is true that Galileo was persecuted – on charges of heresy. But what is left unmentioned is that Copernicus’s heliocentrism fascinated the Pope of his time, who spoke highly of him on numerous occasions. What is also conveniently left out is the devoutly Christian spirit of the countless intellectuals across the course of history who laid the foundations of modern science, believing that their study and analysis of the natural world was a kind of worship of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are we then left with? Is there no future for religion in the West?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religion will survive. The Church will always be there in the West, even if it is weakened and marginalised. Popular culture and the mass media already brand the Christian faith as regressive. It is perhaps only a matter of time before popular opinion turns into political legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Church will survive. It always has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only that, it has found a new homeland. As the West continues to go down this slippery slope and continues to schism itself from its Christian roots, the great African continent has already opened its arms wide open, in welcome of the Gospel and the Church.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the most important demographic changes, in recent times, is the rise of the ‘nones’ in Western society. These are a group of people who refuse to identify themselves with any mainstream religious group or denomination. A 2012 article, by the Pew Research Center, noted that “[o]ne-fifth of the U.S. public – and a third of adults under 30 – are religiously unaffiliated today” and “[i]n the last five years alone, the unaffiliated have increased from just over 15% to just under 20% of all U.S. adults. Their ranks now include more than 13 million self-described atheists and agnostics (nearly 6% of the U.S. public), as well as nearly 33 million people who say they have no particular religious affiliation (14%)”. If we look at certain Western European countries and even in some parts of Eastern Europe, the numbers will undoubtedly be higher.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Are We ‘Doing It’ Enough?</title>
      <link href="/Are-We-Doing-It-Enough" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are We ‘Doing It’ Enough?" />
      <published>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Are-We-Doing-It-Enough</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Are-We-Doing-It-Enough">&lt;p&gt;The generation that fails all? After a myriad of people belting out how we, the Millennials, have failed the world, there’s a new complaint in the game, and if I may, a superfluous one. If you haven’t heard about it yet, let me enlighten you, we, are falling, yet again; falling behind on our duty as sexual beings. We’re not having enough intercourse, the coitus is lacking, we’re not hiding the salami right, we are to fornicate/copulate more often, I can go ahead and call it a thousand more names, but what it comes down to is that we are not having enough sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sexual economy of the world seems to be in danger. Of course, this conclusion is met with evidence from surveys done on American grounds and on Americans but there seems to lie an innate truth to it. &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt;’s December cover story threw light on this. I’m sure Kate Julian’s extensive research on the topic and terming of the phenomenon ‘Sexual Recession’ brought her just as much hate as it did fame, but from what I could procure, she left no page unturned, except the veil of obvious bias, but we’ll come to that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a full tell-all, supported by a General Social Survey (GSS) in 2016, conducted at the University of Chicago, she lists out reasons behind the recession―the assumed ones, why it occurred in the first place and why this recession is specific to the Millennials. Her article is a long read―heavy with insight and stories from across her social sphere―and, given a choice, I’d award her. Her article shone light upon something that we were all aware of in parts, and albeit she only showed off the parts that worked in her favour, she did make sure that all was listed, with enough to make us not counter her points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Foucault would say, we love talking about sex, we enjoy discussing it not just as a primal need rather as a form of entertainment. Sexuality, he said, was a construct of human discourse. “We convince ourselves that we have never said enough on the subject,” he wrote in his (four-volume) &lt;em&gt;The History of Sexuality&lt;/em&gt;. “It is possible that where sex is concerned, the most long-winded, the most impatient of societies is our own.” Personally, I’d say, few fields of human behaviour—and none more important—are this hard to explain. As something that has been talked about ever so often, from religious scriptures telling us how and when to do it, oh, and of course, when not to, to trilogies earning billions with 1001 pages of ‘teeth-clenchingly good’ sex. We all know of it, but why and how it became the talk of the town, albeit uttered only in hushed tones, is vague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned GSS determined that people who are in their early 20s right now are two and a half times as likely to be abstinent as Gen Xers were at the same age. Specifically, between the years 1990 to 2014, the average adult went from having sex 62 times a year to 54 times a year, therefore, the hoola-hoo about the downfall in the Sexual Economy. If I were to meet the ‘spokesperson’ of this Sexual Economy that we all have now been made aware of, I’d only have one word to say: ‘Damn.’ Just so one is kept in the know, it’s not just an American problem. Most countries don’t track their citizens’ sex lives closely. But those that try, mostly the ones who are extremely wealthy, are reporting their own sex delays and declines. One of the most respected sex studies in the world, Britain’s National Survey of Sexual Attitudes and Lifestyles, reported in 2001 that people between the ages of 16 to 44 were having sex more than six times a month, on average. By 2012, the rate had dropped to fewer than five times. Over approximately the same period, Australians in relationships went from having sex around 1.8 times a week to 1.4 times. Finland’s ‘Finsex’ study found declines in frequency of coitus, coupled with increasing rates of masturbation. In the Netherlands, the median age at which people first have intercourse rose from 17.1 in 2012 to 18.6 in 2017, and other types of physical contact also got pushed back, even kissing. In fertility-challenged Japan, which is already in the midst of a demographic crisis and has become something of a case study in the dangers of sexlessness, a third of single people aged 18 to 34 were virgins as of the year 2005; but by 2015, 43% of people reported the same. Japan has been infiltrated by several cultural complexes: Hikikomori (the phenomenon of complete isolation from society) being one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, whatever’s going on here does not seem like a ‘millennial trend’. It really probably pertains to people in their 20s, so younger millennials or Gen-Z. We tend to talk about millennials as if they are some group that just landed here intact, whereas it’s more useful to talk about what it’s like to be a young person, at this point. Not to mention, the fear of a “sex recession” is misdirected. A drop in sexual encounters from 62 to 54 times a year means that the average adult is still having sex more than once a week. Millennials are having to deal with things previous generations haven’t dealt with, and it’s useful to clarify that. As and when I read more about this, I found that people think online connectivity and smartphones have had a dramatic effect on how people’s lives are shaped and their behaviours. That’s probably true for most generational groups, and for the groups that use technology more, that’d be truer. Tinder has only made things easier, so why the lack? My only problem was why 2 and 2 didn’t add up to 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I went digging, and found a &lt;em&gt;Cosmopolitan&lt;/em&gt; article (yes, I went there) and believe me, if &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt; makes you believe you’re not having enough sex, &lt;em&gt;Cosmopolitan&lt;/em&gt; will assure you enough for a lifetime, or well, at least a couple of months. The survey research showed a decline in sex mainly among white, middle-aged, married couples, which, of course, is a very, very small bracket to be construed as an entire generation’s problem. Julian’s tone in &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt;––listing a myriad of theories to explain the drop, from smartphones to economic instability to Tinder––was cautionary, I’ll give her that. But, news of the so-called “sex recession” provoked reactions across the internet, from &lt;em&gt;Vox&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Vice&lt;/em&gt;—not to mention the plethora of comments which turned it into madness with no method. Companies have picked up on this, more researches are being based on the same and while all that is great, there’s a problem that doesn’t exist and is yet being worked upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are different now; sex is different now. Dictionaries may still consider sex to be vaginal penetration, but to us—it may be anything from second base to the seventh one. Sexuality is explored more. People are more aware of what it is that they want, there’s more to it than just genitals having a meet and greet, pleasure plays a huge role in how sex is seen. I would highly recommend that people read Julian’s article and all the reasons she gives for us to not be having enough sex: from stress to bad, painful encounters, but with a grain of salt. We may be failing to do a gazillion more things, but for once, I can attest sex is something we’re doing a bang-up job of (all puns intended.) Tinder, Bumble and Grindr have only made it more relevant. Nothing one does to explore it can be wrong, not until someone is harmed. There is no ‘normal’ amount of sex. Worrying about how much sex one’s having—which can increase anxiety, decrease body confidence, and hinder healthy communication—is not good for one’s sex life, either. Ironic, isn’t it? In terms of desired sexual activity, every individual, and every couple is different, including people who identify as asexual. Just the idea of #MeToo challenges the notion that we can measure our sex lives by anything other than our own generational values and self-reported satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a fundamental level, I share Julian’s concern when she writes that she “was taken aback by what seemed like heartbreaking changes in the way many people were relating—or not relating—to one another.” This is what we should focus our attention on. It turns out, though, that a small drop in aggregate annual sexual frequency has no demonstrable effect on how couples form and sustain, fulfilling relationships. If people aren’t having sex but they’re doing other things they find fulfilling, that’s great. But if people are not having sex, and wish they were, that’s more of a concern, wouldn’t you say?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I have to say is that every generation has its faults counted, every generation has to face things the previous ones didn’t have to endure. While one is yet to see how much more can be done, can be changed or morphed, I am sure that our shapeshifter of a generation won’t be a disappointment. Sex or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The generation that fails all? After a myriad of people belting out how we, the Millennials, have failed the world, there’s a new complaint in the game, and if I may, a superfluous one. If you haven’t heard about it yet, let me enlighten you, we, are falling, yet again; falling behind on our duty as sexual beings. We’re not having enough intercourse, the coitus is lacking, we’re not hiding the salami right, we are to fornicate/copulate more often, I can go ahead and call it a thousand more names, but what it comes down to is that we are not having enough sex.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Were Ancient (Egyptian) Times More Modern Than We Think?</title>
      <link href="/Were-Ancient-Times-More-Modern-Than-We-Think" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Were Ancient (Egyptian) Times More Modern Than We Think?" />
      <published>2019-07-02T12:29:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-02T12:29:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Were-Ancient-Times-More-Modern-Than-We-Think</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Were-Ancient-Times-More-Modern-Than-We-Think">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Egypt gave birth to what later would become known as ‘western civilization’;
long before the greatness of Greece and Rome.”&lt;/em&gt; -John Henrik Clark&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hollywood movies have played their part in creating the notion that the Nile’s
gift was a land riddled with mysterious forms of art, sorcery, murder and
extravagant eye makeup. We all grew up with stories of the beautiful seductress
Cleopatra and the great lands of Egypt ruled by the native Egyptians for
millennia before the Greeks finally arrived. The funny part is this: Cleopatra
probably wasn’t very beautiful (incest was a common practice among the royals
back then, and in the absence of genetic diversity, deformed features like
elongated faces were common among them) and the Egyptians had been ruled by
foreigners like the Ethiopians long before the Ptolemaic dynasty, the last
dynasty of Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Egypt was a rather modern and ahead-of-its-time kind of a society. This fact
finds reflection in their inscriptions, their rulers, their trade affairs and so
on. Let’s start with their family lives and societal norms. The ancient
Egyptians had their own religion and two of their most important Gods and
Goddesses were Osiris and Isis, a brother-sister duo married to each other
(again, incest was okay). Unlike most religions, wherein the man is portrayed as
dominant and the woman as submissive, Isis, the goddess of magic, was the
dominant one in their duo. In fact, every ruler needed a partner in order to
rule Egypt. Unlike most modern societies, the husband and the wife were at the
same pedestal. All of this is evidenced by inscriptions depicting the husband
and the wife (Pharaoh and Queen) together, even showing them commanding an army
of soldiers (best examples include the inscriptions dating back to the Amarna
period) and coins showing faces of both side by side (from the Ptolemaic
period).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In ancient Egyptian society, virginity was not a requisite for marriage but
loyalty after marriage was expected. If a couple were to fall out of love, they
could get a divorce; a common enough practice and therefore free of stigma. In
countries like India, even today, people who walk away from their marriages
fearing shaming and ostracisation at the hands of society. Nuclear families
dominated their communities and lineage was traced through both parents’ sides
alike. Both of these bear testimony to the fact that the Egyptian lifestyle was
very different from that of its contemporary civilisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Egyptian inscriptions, it seems unlikely that they ever practised slavery,
once again, contrary to popular belief. The labourers who worked on the pyramids
or the temples were well fed and housed. Their mummified bodies also indicate
that they were natives of the land. They lived close to where they worked and
were even buried there, literally in the shadows of the pyramids- the Pharaoh’s
last resting place (considered to be a great honour).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their houses were intriguing too. They had courtyards and separate studios.
Another very common feature was a flat roof, where they often cooked or slept
during hot nights. Ancient folk are not expected to share the ideals of
cleanliness that modern society holds. But lo and behold, the Egyptians had
toilets in their homes and their own systems of drainage and cleaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of ancient Egypt’s greatest contributions include the &lt;strong&gt;papyrus&lt;/strong&gt;. At one
point, the Egyptians mass produced (handwritten, of course) &lt;em&gt;‘The Book of the
Dead’&lt;/em&gt; to be buried with the mummified bodies of their loved ones. Besides,
Kings and Queens used this ‘paper’ to sign away their declarations and orders
too, a practice, surprisingly similar to the present-day passing of bills.
Drinking beer was a common practice, even among the commoners. Ancient Egypt can
also be credited with the development of several methods of contraception and
various pregnancy tests. The Egyptians valued knowledge a lot and this is
evident from the remains of the great library at Alexandria. We might as well
call Egypt &lt;em&gt;the Land of Inventions&lt;/em&gt; because of the numerous inventions that came
out of this particular ancient culture, some of which revolutionised human life
long before the Renaissance or the Industrial Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike most contemporary civilisations, the Egyptians did not have a calendar
based on the moon’s cycle. Instead, their calendar was based on the Earth’s
revolution around the sun (Turns out Copernicus might have had some help in the
form of ancient inspiration!). These ancient humans had 365 days in a year and
an extra day every four years (Julius Caesar later took this idea to Greece
during Cleopatra’s reign). Sounds very familiar, doesn’t it? Surprisingly
enough, their religion lent support to the science that pervaded their society!
In fact, most of their mythological stories revolve around facts that have been
proven to be scientifically correct. The Egyptians were also pioneers in the
field of astronomy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their architectural brilliance proves the fact that they were great engineers
and mathematicians too. The angle of inclination of the pyramids, the lengths of
their sides and so on, were accurate down to minutes and a couple of inches
respectively. Granite blocks used in the Great Pyramid of Giza’s burial chamber
are cut to perfection and fit into each other such that not even a credit card
can slip in between. The pyramids are spectacles that cannot be explained even
today. Each stone block used in its construction weighs at least a couple of
tonnes and the entire structure rises up to a staggering height of 139 metres.
Did I mention that the Egyptians did not even have the wheel? How the pyramids
were constructed is up for debate. What is undeniable is the fact that they were
masters of the art of building and made structures meant to stand the test of
time unlike any other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all have either heard or read about the Gods and Goddesses of Egypt. As I
learnt more about their culture and society, I came across something that left
me astonished: monotheism- a very modern ideology and isn’t uncommon today. But,
I guess, Pharaoh Akhenaten and his wife Queen Nefertiti were way ahead of their
times. They devoted all their lives to the worship of a single God- Aten (the
Sun). This religion, however, did not address one major question that had always
plagued the Egyptians: ‘What happens after death?’. This obviously did not sit
very well with the priests and the practice was discarded right after
Akhenaten’s reign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most famous of ancient Egyptian practices is probably the process of
mummification. The method that they developed was nothing short of genius. They
wanted immortality and in some ways, they did achieve it. We know what they did,
ate and entertained themselves with, just like any other civilisation. But,
here, we also have their bodies; their stories &lt;em&gt;literally&lt;/em&gt; have faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very recently, Egyptian inscriptions were located in Australia. It is undeniable
that their trade flourished. With the advent of the Ptolemaic dynasty (after
Alexander the Great’s invasion), coins were introduced in trade. The second
Pharaoh of this dynasty, Queen Arsinoe introduced coins with her face on them -
she wanted everyone to know who held the reigns. Most rulers were well versed in
several languages and were very diplomatic. Cleopatra is claimed to have been
fluent in around 9 languages. That, however, is not the only shocking thing in
her resume. She was intelligent and trained in alchemy, geography, philosophy
and so on and so forth. She knew chemistry too, in fact, she owned a perfume
factory. To me, it all sounds like capitalism might have had some really ancient
roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a pity that the only thing that we usually care about is whether the
Egyptians were black, how beautiful the pyramids are and how was Cleopatra able
to seduce both Mark Anthony and Julius Caesar, and speculations about how
beautiful she was. The Egyptians accomplished tasks their contemporaries could
only ever dream to accomplish–feats involving mind-boggling architecture,
freakishly modern societal norms, mastery in mathematics, astronomy and art, and
unique practices that would later go on to shape the world. They lived up to
every word they ever wrote or spoke:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“What I hate is ignorance, smallness of imagination, the eye that sees no
farther than its own lashes. All things are possible… Who you are is limited
only by who you think you are.”&lt;/em&gt; – Egyptian Book of the Dead&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Egypt gave birth to what later would become known as ‘western civilization’; long before the greatness of Greece and Rome.” -John Henrik Clark Hollywood movies have played their part in creating the notion that the Nile’s gift was a land riddled with mysterious forms of art, sorcery, murder and extravagant eye makeup. We all grew up with stories of the beautiful seductress Cleopatra and the great lands of Egypt ruled by the native Egyptians for millennia before the Greeks finally arrived. The funny part is this: Cleopatra probably wasn’t very beautiful (incest was a common practice among the royals back then, and in the absence of genetic diversity, deformed features like elongated faces were common among them) and the Egyptians had been ruled by foreigners like the Ethiopians long before the Ptolemaic dynasty, the last dynasty of Egypt. Egypt was a rather modern and ahead-of-its-time kind of a society. This fact finds reflection in their inscriptions, their rulers, their trade affairs and so on. Let’s start with their family lives and societal norms. The ancient Egyptians had their own religion and two of their most important Gods and Goddesses were Osiris and Isis, a brother-sister duo married to each other (again, incest was okay). Unlike most religions, wherein the man is portrayed as dominant and the woman as submissive, Isis, the goddess of magic, was the dominant one in their duo. In fact, every ruler needed a partner in order to rule Egypt. Unlike most modern societies, the husband and the wife were at the same pedestal. All of this is evidenced by inscriptions depicting the husband and the wife (Pharaoh and Queen) together, even showing them commanding an army of soldiers (best examples include the inscriptions dating back to the Amarna period) and coins showing faces of both side by side (from the Ptolemaic period). In ancient Egyptian society, virginity was not a requisite for marriage but loyalty after marriage was expected. If a couple were to fall out of love, they could get a divorce; a common enough practice and therefore free of stigma. In countries like India, even today, people who walk away from their marriages fearing shaming and ostracisation at the hands of society. Nuclear families dominated their communities and lineage was traced through both parents’ sides alike. Both of these bear testimony to the fact that the Egyptian lifestyle was very different from that of its contemporary civilisations. From Egyptian inscriptions, it seems unlikely that they ever practised slavery, once again, contrary to popular belief. The labourers who worked on the pyramids or the temples were well fed and housed. Their mummified bodies also indicate that they were natives of the land. They lived close to where they worked and were even buried there, literally in the shadows of the pyramids- the Pharaoh’s last resting place (considered to be a great honour). Their houses were intriguing too. They had courtyards and separate studios. Another very common feature was a flat roof, where they often cooked or slept during hot nights. Ancient folk are not expected to share the ideals of cleanliness that modern society holds. But lo and behold, the Egyptians had toilets in their homes and their own systems of drainage and cleaning. Some of ancient Egypt’s greatest contributions include the papyrus. At one point, the Egyptians mass produced (handwritten, of course) ‘The Book of the Dead’ to be buried with the mummified bodies of their loved ones. Besides, Kings and Queens used this ‘paper’ to sign away their declarations and orders too, a practice, surprisingly similar to the present-day passing of bills. Drinking beer was a common practice, even among the commoners. Ancient Egypt can also be credited with the development of several methods of contraception and various pregnancy tests. The Egyptians valued knowledge a lot and this is evident from the remains of the great library at Alexandria. We might as well call Egypt the Land of Inventions because of the numerous inventions that came out of this particular ancient culture, some of which revolutionised human life long before the Renaissance or the Industrial Revolution. Unlike most contemporary civilisations, the Egyptians did not have a calendar based on the moon’s cycle. Instead, their calendar was based on the Earth’s revolution around the sun (Turns out Copernicus might have had some help in the form of ancient inspiration!). These ancient humans had 365 days in a year and an extra day every four years (Julius Caesar later took this idea to Greece during Cleopatra’s reign). Sounds very familiar, doesn’t it? Surprisingly enough, their religion lent support to the science that pervaded their society! In fact, most of their mythological stories revolve around facts that have been proven to be scientifically correct. The Egyptians were also pioneers in the field of astronomy! Their architectural brilliance proves the fact that they were great engineers and mathematicians too. The angle of inclination of the pyramids, the lengths of their sides and so on, were accurate down to minutes and a couple of inches respectively. Granite blocks used in the Great Pyramid of Giza’s burial chamber are cut to perfection and fit into each other such that not even a credit card can slip in between. The pyramids are spectacles that cannot be explained even today. Each stone block used in its construction weighs at least a couple of tonnes and the entire structure rises up to a staggering height of 139 metres. Did I mention that the Egyptians did not even have the wheel? How the pyramids were constructed is up for debate. What is undeniable is the fact that they were masters of the art of building and made structures meant to stand the test of time unlike any other. We all have either heard or read about the Gods and Goddesses of Egypt. As I learnt more about their culture and society, I came across something that left me astonished: monotheism- a very modern ideology and isn’t uncommon today. But, I guess, Pharaoh Akhenaten and his wife Queen Nefertiti were way ahead of their times. They devoted all their lives to the worship of a single God- Aten (the Sun). This religion, however, did not address one major question that had always plagued the Egyptians: ‘What happens after death?’. This obviously did not sit very well with the priests and the practice was discarded right after Akhenaten’s reign. The most famous of ancient Egyptian practices is probably the process of mummification. The method that they developed was nothing short of genius. They wanted immortality and in some ways, they did achieve it. We know what they did, ate and entertained themselves with, just like any other civilisation. But, here, we also have their bodies; their stories literally have faces. Very recently, Egyptian inscriptions were located in Australia. It is undeniable that their trade flourished. With the advent of the Ptolemaic dynasty (after Alexander the Great’s invasion), coins were introduced in trade. The second Pharaoh of this dynasty, Queen Arsinoe introduced coins with her face on them - she wanted everyone to know who held the reigns. Most rulers were well versed in several languages and were very diplomatic. Cleopatra is claimed to have been fluent in around 9 languages. That, however, is not the only shocking thing in her resume. She was intelligent and trained in alchemy, geography, philosophy and so on and so forth. She knew chemistry too, in fact, she owned a perfume factory. To me, it all sounds like capitalism might have had some really ancient roots. It’s a pity that the only thing that we usually care about is whether the Egyptians were black, how beautiful the pyramids are and how was Cleopatra able to seduce both Mark Anthony and Julius Caesar, and speculations about how beautiful she was. The Egyptians accomplished tasks their contemporaries could only ever dream to accomplish–feats involving mind-boggling architecture, freakishly modern societal norms, mastery in mathematics, astronomy and art, and unique practices that would later go on to shape the world. They lived up to every word they ever wrote or spoke: “What I hate is ignorance, smallness of imagination, the eye that sees no farther than its own lashes. All things are possible… Who you are is limited only by who you think you are.” – Egyptian Book of the Dead</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Great Indian Intercourse</title>
      <link href="/The-Great-Indian-Intercourse" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Great Indian Intercourse" />
      <published>2019-06-28T21:29:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-28T21:29:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Great-Indian-Intercourse</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Great-Indian-Intercourse">&lt;p&gt;Of the many things that India, as a subcontinent, has achieved or done, such as
overpopulation, growing disparity between economic classes and the caste system,
probably one of the greatest would be the writing of the &lt;em&gt;Kama Sutra&lt;/em&gt;; and even
though we have, as a nation, owned up to most of the country’s achievements,
even the more bizarre ones such as child marriage, in case of sex we tend to
walk right by it without even a cursory glance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might argue that such prudish behaviour is a result of uneven distribution
of cultural capital, but I believe that’s an oxymoron in itself. I’m not here to
talk about how such prudence came into being in Indian culture – that is a topic
for another day. What I would like to draw attention to is the product of such
prudence taking shape in the form of coyness surrounding the topic of sex in
Indian society. Now, if you belong to an extremely liberal Indian family or
reside in the West, you’re probably not aware of the coyness I speak of. But we
plebs have felt it right from our childhood, when our mothers would, almost in a
frenzy, change the channel if we accidentally tuned into some English movie
channel with a couple kissing on the screen. This particular act of maternal
care and horror brought about two things; firstly, a curiosity about the most
basic and prevalent of human natures that would sooner or later manifest into
action, and secondly, through this suppression, we were being conditioned into
suppressing our very understanding of ourselves. If we do not properly accept
and understand the psychology underlying sex and sexuality we become blunt to
our very existence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of things that we, as a society, do are directly or indirectly inspired by
sex. We were taught, rather preached with sincerity that English films are a
matter of disgrace and can bring &lt;em&gt;Mata’s&lt;/em&gt; (the Hindu Mother Goddess’) curse upon
us. Problems started for my mother when Indian advertisements stared getting
liberal with sex as well. She was then left with little choice but to accept her
defeat, while commenting on how Indian culture was getting ‘corrupted’. As is
the norm in India, my parents never talked about sex in front of me, and as I
grew up they started keeping their bedroom door open most of the time, except at
night, so as to not arouse any suspicion in their growing child’s mind! And this
isn’t just the case with families that have children, rather with any family
where there are people besides the couple live. We are a sex hungry nation, lewd
staring in buses and public places are a testimony to that, and yet we continue
with this all-prevailing diktat of silence no matter where we go. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this diktat has a silver lining to it and we must not discount it. As sex
has grown to be the giant &lt;strong&gt;taboo&lt;/strong&gt; of Indian society, it has become all the
more &lt;strong&gt;pleasurable&lt;/strong&gt; to consume. Coyness has turned out to be more of a boon
than a bane for most couples around the nation and for one simple reason:
&lt;em&gt;forbidden fruit tastes better&lt;/em&gt;. Society, as a whole, sees sex as immoral. No
one quite imagines that the couple they randomly passed by on the street
actually has sex or to be more precise, one cannot picture them doing it. What
this does psychologically is that it makes one’s intimacy with their partner
ever so special. They choose to remain oblivious of sex happening in any place
besides their own chambers. Couples and other couples collectively, mutedly,
gorge through their disreputable escapades thinking that they are alone in doing
it. And the less they get to do it, the better; because that preserves the idea
of immorality. If talking about sex is normalised, the details, no matter how
small or vague, would start to come forward and one would realise what and how
they do it is the same as everyone else; which isn’t necessarily a bad thing but
it takes away that extra bit of pleasure which comes from the high of
&lt;em&gt;rebellion&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the millennials who probably don’t ‘get it’ and are scratching their heads
thinking, “sex is sex; it is great even without the coyness”, draw an analogy to
when you look for taboo porn or something offbeat on the internet when regular
stuff just doesn’t do it for you anymore. It’s the same with sex, the more it
remains sacred and clandestine, the better it feels when done. This theory
explains to some extent why people have extra-marital affairs, it is that
clandestine factor that makes it all the more coveted and hot. This also
explains why India ranks second in terms of population even with a culture of
muted sexual desires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This theory goes beyond sex, extending to almost everything that is forbidden by
society. The forbidden is a massive source of pleasure, no matter what, because
even when one is part of the chorus of society, rebellion against the same
society that one belongs to is enthralling, to say the least. Revolutions on any
scale are the greatest form of validation a human can enjoy. Although having sex
is not a revolution per se, but doing it, at the end of the day, after not even
hinting at the presence of one’s sexuality or sensuality throughout the day,
does have a massive sense of breaking free and disobeying our own sense of
immorality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, the diktat is dying out with the emergence of Generation Y. And although
this brings in a different set of pleasures to consume (in varied manners too),
it will be regretful, at least for me, not to taste the pleasure that came out
of the weird furtiveness our previous generations displayed.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Of the many things that India, as a subcontinent, has achieved or done, such as overpopulation, growing disparity between economic classes and the caste system, probably one of the greatest would be the writing of the Kama Sutra; and even though we have, as a nation, owned up to most of the country’s achievements, even the more bizarre ones such as child marriage, in case of sex we tend to walk right by it without even a cursory glance.  One might argue that such prudish behaviour is a result of uneven distribution of cultural capital, but I believe that’s an oxymoron in itself. I’m not here to talk about how such prudence came into being in Indian culture – that is a topic for another day. What I would like to draw attention to is the product of such prudence taking shape in the form of coyness surrounding the topic of sex in Indian society. Now, if you belong to an extremely liberal Indian family or reside in the West, you’re probably not aware of the coyness I speak of. But we plebs have felt it right from our childhood, when our mothers would, almost in a frenzy, change the channel if we accidentally tuned into some English movie channel with a couple kissing on the screen. This particular act of maternal care and horror brought about two things; firstly, a curiosity about the most basic and prevalent of human natures that would sooner or later manifest into action, and secondly, through this suppression, we were being conditioned into suppressing our very understanding of ourselves. If we do not properly accept and understand the psychology underlying sex and sexuality we become blunt to our very existence.  A lot of things that we, as a society, do are directly or indirectly inspired by sex. We were taught, rather preached with sincerity that English films are a matter of disgrace and can bring Mata’s (the Hindu Mother Goddess’) curse upon us. Problems started for my mother when Indian advertisements stared getting liberal with sex as well. She was then left with little choice but to accept her defeat, while commenting on how Indian culture was getting ‘corrupted’. As is the norm in India, my parents never talked about sex in front of me, and as I grew up they started keeping their bedroom door open most of the time, except at night, so as to not arouse any suspicion in their growing child’s mind! And this isn’t just the case with families that have children, rather with any family where there are people besides the couple live. We are a sex hungry nation, lewd staring in buses and public places are a testimony to that, and yet we continue with this all-prevailing diktat of silence no matter where we go.  But this diktat has a silver lining to it and we must not discount it. As sex has grown to be the giant taboo of Indian society, it has become all the more pleasurable to consume. Coyness has turned out to be more of a boon than a bane for most couples around the nation and for one simple reason: forbidden fruit tastes better. Society, as a whole, sees sex as immoral. No one quite imagines that the couple they randomly passed by on the street actually has sex or to be more precise, one cannot picture them doing it. What this does psychologically is that it makes one’s intimacy with their partner ever so special. They choose to remain oblivious of sex happening in any place besides their own chambers. Couples and other couples collectively, mutedly, gorge through their disreputable escapades thinking that they are alone in doing it. And the less they get to do it, the better; because that preserves the idea of immorality. If talking about sex is normalised, the details, no matter how small or vague, would start to come forward and one would realise what and how they do it is the same as everyone else; which isn’t necessarily a bad thing but it takes away that extra bit of pleasure which comes from the high of rebellion.  For the millennials who probably don’t ‘get it’ and are scratching their heads thinking, “sex is sex; it is great even without the coyness”, draw an analogy to when you look for taboo porn or something offbeat on the internet when regular stuff just doesn’t do it for you anymore. It’s the same with sex, the more it remains sacred and clandestine, the better it feels when done. This theory explains to some extent why people have extra-marital affairs, it is that clandestine factor that makes it all the more coveted and hot. This also explains why India ranks second in terms of population even with a culture of muted sexual desires. This theory goes beyond sex, extending to almost everything that is forbidden by society. The forbidden is a massive source of pleasure, no matter what, because even when one is part of the chorus of society, rebellion against the same society that one belongs to is enthralling, to say the least. Revolutions on any scale are the greatest form of validation a human can enjoy. Although having sex is not a revolution per se, but doing it, at the end of the day, after not even hinting at the presence of one’s sexuality or sensuality throughout the day, does have a massive sense of breaking free and disobeying our own sense of immorality. Sadly, the diktat is dying out with the emergence of Generation Y. And although this brings in a different set of pleasures to consume (in varied manners too), it will be regretful, at least for me, not to taste the pleasure that came out of the weird furtiveness our previous generations displayed.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
