<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/society/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-08-31T20:20:59+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/society/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Stranded by the Sea</title>
      <link href="/Stranded-by-the-Sea" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stranded by the Sea" />
      <published>2020-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Stranded-by-the-Sea</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Stranded-by-the-Sea">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;Refugee&lt;/em&gt; is a term we read and hear about often, on the internet or the news and dissect into it like any other topic that we came across on a particular day. Be it the Syrian refugee crisis, the Afghanistan refugee crisis, people displaced in the Middle East fleeing to Europe for desperate rehabilitation, the partition of India or the result of a civil war. These are all issues originating in different parts of the world, delineated by boundaries and separated based on geography or the cause or origin of conflict. However, even though conflicts might vary in terms of nature- political, economic or social - it’s corollary remains immutable across borders and religion, that is, displacement of people and wreckage of homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve fled your country (or have been chased out by the majority population/authoritarian government), it’s nearly impossible to come back. The unsafe and riotous situation in certain countries caused by wars or feud creates conditions that make it fatal to a come back to a place they once called home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rohingya are one such community, facing persecution and fleeing from one place to another since 58 years, circa 1962.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of the persecution of the Rohingyas can be traced back to the colonization of India by the British, which endured for over 200 years. Tracing back to the British colonial period in the 1800’s, many people from India and Bangladesh were brought to Myanmar to work in the British led administration, doubling the Muslim community in Myanmar. This decision was received with acrimony by the local Myanmar people. This stands as one of the root cause of the animosity against the Rohingyas. During the World Wars, this hostility further deepened its roots since the majority of the Muslim population supported the British whereas the Buddhist population was predisposed towards the Japanese. This incongruity, as a result of the disparity between The Allies and The Axis Powers, aggravated the situation for the Muslim population in Myanmar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The official status of “refugee” is something the Rohingya people have struggled with for years now. In 1962, military rule became the norm and law throughout Myanmar. As a result, the Muslim population in Rakhine State was overpowered by militants and the Buddhist majority, thus causing the refugees to flee to Bangladesh. Since then, from 1962 to 2017 a large number of Rohingya people have migrated to the neighbouring countries, especially Bangladesh, having faced oppression in their own country. In 1982, an official Myanmar announcement declared 135 nationally recognized ethnic groups and the Rohingya were not included in the list, leaving them stateless and without citizenship. Further, in 2012 riots were waged against the Rohingyas and 200 people were killed while leaving 15,000 homeless and displaced. The Myanmar government even prohibited them from participating in the national census and the voting procedure during the elections. These acts of negligence, violence and repression continued till 2017 causing more than 600,000 Rohingya people to flee the Rakhine State since their communities were destroyed. But that doesn’t mean that things are any safer for them now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, there are some 860,000 Rohingya people seeking refuge in Bangladesh and at least 1.3 million people — Rohingya refugees and Bangladeshi host communities — who rely on humanitarian assistance to meet their basic needs. More than half of them are children. These populations live in desperately overcrowded camps and communities, highly vulnerable to oncoming monsoon and cyclone seasons, violence, sexual harassment and unhygienic environment. These camps provide them with less than the meagre amenities, leaving them to live a life of ignorance, in a vicious cycle of poverty, violence and substandard living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) and Médecins Sans Frontières (MSF) (also known as Doctors without Borders) describes the Rohingya as one of the most persecuted people in the world. The world we live in prides itself on its safety and peacekeeping system at the international level. Since after the Second World War, many nations came together and pledged to save vulnerable people and nations in crises. Yet, their (Rohingyas) struggle and oppression has been one of the most under-reported humanitarian crises in the world. The international media and community have practically ignored the situation of these people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all of this because of one reason, deeply entrenched in our parochial minds: ethnic animosity and conflict on the grounds of religion and historical beliefs of territory and ownership. This practice has left the Rohingya people without a beacon of hope for a better future. It has normalized a humanitarian crisis of this gravity, leading us to believe that it’s okay to treat a community of people with mindless hostility and utter disregard for their lives. (Because they might’ve done something to deserve it)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having faced persecution even in the camps of Bangladesh’s Cox Bazaar (and Myanmar, of course) the Rohingya people have made attempts to reach Malaysia, Thailand, Indonesia and other countries for years now. Since they lack visas, travel documents and are subjected to strict restrictions, boats are often the only option left for them to undertake transnational crossing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to MSF, it is estimated that around 167 countries across the world have fully or partially closed their borders during COVID-19 pandemic and 57 states made no exception for people seeking asylum. Even though closing borders is an acceptable reaction to the pandemic, not providing a concession for people looking for a refugee status amidst these tough times, stranded by the sea and in between nations is unacceptable. Countries such as Italy and Malta closed their ports for refugees and are using the excuse of the pandemic to reject refugees from entering their land and water borders. Several hundred Rohingyas fleeing persecution at home and refugee camps in Bangladesh have been stranded for months after countries sealed their borders to block the spread of the coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have reported that their relatives are stranded by the sea and their traffickers, holding hundreds of Rohingya refugees, are demanding money to release them from boats that have been off Southeast Asia since February, trying to find a place to land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Material cupidity has yet again taken precedence over humanity in a situation of a deadly life-crisis. The refugees travelling on these boats could hardly gather the money and documents to take this journey across the sea, and now with the pandemic having engulfed the world, they’re stuck on these boats, suffering, starving and seething in pain, waiting to get across any border to find some refuge and shelter from these treacherous circumstances. On top of this, they are being exploited for money in a situation of utmost helplessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To think why these people landed in such a chronic crisis, which has persisted for over five decades now; to think why we as a community allow and tolerate a humanitarian crisis at such a cosmic level. It is because somewhere deep down, we all have our own set of ideas and beliefs tied by social norms of caste, creed and culture. Because we all have ingrained the idea of &lt;em&gt;Us vs Them&lt;/em&gt;, so concretely in our heads that it’s almost impossible to break down those walls around us. But if there’s something that this pandemic has taught us, it’s that we’re all in this together. No problem is a standalone issue - it’s always linked to a larger affliction and it’s not outside the ambit of possibility for it to find its way to you. If we don’t untangle this issue as a community and for the community, it’ll always remain unresolved and will surface time and again.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A Refugee is a term we read and hear about often, on the internet or the news and dissect into it like any other topic that we came across on a particular day. Be it the Syrian refugee crisis, the Afghanistan refugee crisis, people displaced in the Middle East fleeing to Europe for desperate rehabilitation, the partition of India or the result of a civil war. These are all issues originating in different parts of the world, delineated by boundaries and separated based on geography or the cause or origin of conflict. However, even though conflicts might vary in terms of nature- political, economic or social - it’s corollary remains immutable across borders and religion, that is, displacement of people and wreckage of homes.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Western Media Texts</title>
      <link href="/Western-Media-Texts" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Western Media Texts" />
      <published>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Western-Media-Texts</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Western-Media-Texts">&lt;p&gt;The digital revolution of old media into new media has taken shape very rapidly. Old media has seldom been given its due recognition. Traditional sources of information like newspapers and radio have sustained their quality in truth telling for ages. Its comparison is unparalleled when it comes to new media, which is why it still has a wide market and is almost irreplaceable. On the other hand, new media rose to power because of its instantaneous quality to connect and communicate. News became easy to deliver as new media defined its timeliness. It has definitely changed the dynamics of public consumption of news, heralding a phase in humanity where everything can be reported, by anyone, and at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this has caused a severe decline in the ethics and philosophies of news providers. The power of creating news and gathering information is privy to distortion. Popularising preconceived notions as news is an emerging norm. This leads to misrepresentation and unfortunate consequences. The multiplicity of perspectives, opinions, and beliefs, entailing even factual wrongdoings, mixed with propaganda, has corrupted what was once considered an industry full of good samaritans. It is now a blotch on the entire concept of truth, information and news. Even traditional media faced this deterioration. The downward spiral of media credibility first footed at the advent of selling sensational news. The entire concept of ‘tabloidisation’ in garnering an audience, for the sake of business growth by corporations, led to a complete dilution in the way the public’s sensibilities allowed them to evaluate news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the media’s very history has dictated cultural behaviour throughout the course of time, it has become a core part of our lives. From newspapers to television networks to the abundance of information disseminated on social media, different types of media have both evolved and learnt to coexist. Thus, understanding the people and corporations behind these media networks, and the faces that decide news value, will further provide transparency in this respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Television is a writer’s playground, and online platforms only widen this space. The artistic freedom and the creative liberty that comes with it, was hitherto unheard of. So what would earlier be written for network audience traction is now developing into its own qualitative entity. All shows based on varied walks of life, using diverse plots, and being highly representative, have a loyal audience. Film and television also influence us in the most impactful ways. Therefore, the story and the way of storytelling employed is imperative to the niche audience it targets. When we talk about journalism and media, it is easy to assume how its machine functions. However, we hardly know the works behind the scenes. That is news nobody can tell us. We are oblivious to what goes into reporting a two minute segment, or a five page article. It always varies depending on the story, the source, the journalist, the editor, and the thousand inbetweeners that it takes to put a story out there. There have been innumerable assumptions around what a media workplace should be or how a journalistic practice must work, usually tied around speculation and hearsay. There’s seldom any representation within media texts portraying the media itself. Let us analyse two stand out accomplishments that tried to do it right, and well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Newsroom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Aaron Sorkin original, HBO’s &lt;em&gt;The Newsroom&lt;/em&gt; revolves around the dramatisation of a fictional news broadcast media network - Atlantis Cable Network. The name itself suggests that it is a fictional, idealistic world of the media elite. It is essentially a newsroom drama, a tale only seen panned out in movies before. Therefore, the scope for incorporating real time journalistic stories is high. And Sorkin knows how to merge that plethora of opportunity through witty dialogue and righteous ethical commentary. The plot revolves around some passionate workaholic journalists who only live by their virtues of delivering the unfiltered truth, without being bothered about the network ratings or audience commands. It is representative of what every journalist wants to be - equally intellectual and ethical - despite being held back by outside forces. The show reiterates that the value of journalistic integrity is above all else. It is a stark contrast to broadcast networks in real life, which are constantly required to entertain rather than provide information. In this day and age, ratings and viewership is highly important for a network to sustain itself. Thus, this show posits itself as an ideal of how every journalist wants to work and does not delve into a practical solution for how broadcast may allow its journalists to change that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The show tends to remain positive even during the darkest stories that have plagued the United States of America, by the up and coming celebration of democracy that the nation prevails to be. Its coverage of real time political events and serious stories, is not only well written but amazingly performed by the ensemble cast. While the show does not accurately portray broadcast networks in the West (and is especially inaccurate in doing that), it sure lives up to the narrative it is trying to convey - that which every network must strive to achieve. The show also satires and ridicules networks that have different ideologies and functions. Its constant snarky digs at &lt;em&gt;Thirty Mile Zone (TMZ)&lt;/em&gt; for exploitation, and &lt;em&gt;Cable News Network (CNN)&lt;/em&gt; for false reporting, is well-handled and brave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorkin’s masterful writing aids him in articulating some narratives within the media industry that need to be heard. For networks not just in the US, but even worldwide. Even if it’s not an accurate representation, the technical representation and the chaotic nuance of a newsroom workplace is on point. With some admirable takeaways from beloved performances of some truly heroic characters, the show does its job and does it well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Morning Show&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Apple TV+ venture, &lt;em&gt;The Morning Show&lt;/em&gt; represents a morning broadcast media show and what the happy rosy environment actually masks. Its script originally dealt with a common plot threading various stories in between, but it ended up changing to accentuate the overarching common storyline due to its relevance. Entailing the #MeToo movement, the show focuses on the alleged sexual harassment cases that women at the media house workplace suffered at the hands of a powerful lead anchor. The anchor is fired and denies the claims. While fictionalised, this premise is taken from what happened to Matt Lauer at the &lt;em&gt;Today Show&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It shows the complicity of the workplace environment in perpetuating the harassment. This is representative of not just media organisations but of any working environment. Through its complex characters, and dramatic plot twists, the first season does justice in representing the consequences of such unfortunate workplace incidents. It humanises every character involved and doesn’t judge through its writing. It’s everything that is expected from a gripping drama. The story explores the nuanced details of the #MeToo movement, but leaves the audience in suspense about the actual truth until the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its course, the show is riddled with characters that are dayside journalists, so the media premise is naturally different. Everything from the type of stories covered, to the positivity that it propagates, it is accurately representative of that broadcast niche. The lead anchors are shown being vain and self absorbed. But the entrance of a righteous journalist who enters this feel-good world, shakes the flow of the show. She has doubts about the kind of journalism this media group stands for. She has constant outbursts of journalistic integrity (much like she’s plucked out of the Sorkin universe), is absolutely apprehended by the overly narcissistic environment, and continually calls out the hypocrisies of the organisation. She acts as a conscience trope for journalism as a virtue. The news producer, and the owner have their own tensions and roles at the backdrop of the story. They show is well-balanced in its media representation that way and does for the media industry, what was long overdue. Gearing up for its second season, the show can further elevate or deteriorate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were some of the representations of new broadcast media in the West, and of the West, that were worth analysing due to their brilliant execution. The developing countries of the East, like India, are still short of well-made media representations. Recent releases like &lt;em&gt;Paatal Lok&lt;/em&gt; have stirred this conversation in a much-needed direction, by accurately representing the dichotomies and hypocrisies of Indian journalism and media. Being a fourth pillar to democracy, we mustn’t infuriatingly bash our media sources. A way of portraying gratitude is through such media texts, and encouraging that is reinstating our belief in journalism and truth-telling.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The digital revolution of old media into new media has taken shape very rapidly. Old media has seldom been given its due recognition. Traditional sources of information like newspapers and radio have sustained their quality in truth telling for ages. Its comparison is unparalleled when it comes to new media, which is why it still has a wide market and is almost irreplaceable. On the other hand, new media rose to power because of its instantaneous quality to connect and communicate. News became easy to deliver as new media defined its timeliness. It has definitely changed the dynamics of public consumption of news, heralding a phase in humanity where everything can be reported, by anyone, and at any time.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Against a Liberal Anti-racism</title>
      <link href="/Against-a-Liberal-Anti-racism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Against a Liberal Anti-racism" />
      <published>2020-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Against-a-Liberal-Anti-racism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Against-a-Liberal-Anti-racism">&lt;p&gt;The months following the killing of George Floyd saw sales of books about race increase by up to 6,800%. The top seller was Robin DiAngelo’s &lt;em&gt;White Fragility&lt;/em&gt;, which increased sales by over 400,000 copies from May to June this year, a startling increase of over 2,000%. DiAngelo, a ‘diversity consultant’, has since been invited to deliver keynote speeches, charging up to $35,000 for a two-hour workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DiAngelo’s central premise, that white Americans must reckon with their own implicit biases and engage in rigorous introspection to remedy them, appears less of a repudiation of centuries-old institutional racism than it does an instructional manual for white liberals working in corporate jobs to avoid getting into trouble with HR. It characterises racism merely as an antipathy felt by individuals towards other individuals, leaving untouched the edifice of America’s racist socio-economic structure. It fails to acknowledge that white supremacy is not simply the supremacy of white over black, but also the supremacy of rich whites over poorer whites who can be trusted to vote themselves into economic ruin in return for the illusion of superiority. And even more egregiously, it focuses attention on the self-aggrandising antics of the white liberal, repackaging the fight against racism as a culture war between educated white liberals and less educated whites, many of whom do not view themselves as the beneficiaries of ‘privilege’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the first Africans arrived in Virginia in 1619, there were no ‘white’ people there. It would be another 60 years before colonial records would describe the settlers as ‘white’, as the idea of the ‘white’ race was deliberately constructed by the ruling class as a form of social control, dividing poor European indentured servants and African chattel-bond labourers, assimilating the Europeans into the ‘middle class’, and preventing the likelihood of the reemergence of an event such as Bacon’s Rebellion (1676). Europeans and Africans had jointly demanded the imposition of a land tax and Virginia’s transition from a large plantation economy to a diversified economy of small freeholders, chasing the planter bourgeoisie to the shore and burning Jamestown to the ground. Ira Berlin stated that in the aftermath of Bacon’s Rebellion &lt;em&gt;“they enact laws which say that people of African descent are hereditary slaves. And they increasingly give some power to the independent white farmers and land holders”&lt;/em&gt;. Therefore, rather than being simply a form of prejudice on the basis of skin colour, racism can be understood as a complex form of social control. Theodore W Allen’s book &lt;em&gt;The Invention of the White Race&lt;/em&gt; made a similar argument that racism is a “sociogenic” rather than a “phylogenic” phenomenon, analysing how the (phenotypically similar) British used racial oppression against Irish Catholics, later allowing the Irish Catholic bourgeoisie to assimilate into the oppressive structure, accepting the disenfranchisement of the forty-shilling freeholders in return for meagre ‘emancipation’ in 1829.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, liberal anti-racism of the DiAngelo variety, largely devoid of this analysis, becomes an exercise in narcissistic self-indulgence on the part of white liberals, who reframe discussions about race in terms of how they can be better people, and how it is incumbent on all whites to unlearn their white privilege. As this approach to anti-racism fails to acknowledge how racism functions as a tool of socioeconomic disenfranchisement by the ruling class, it assumes that all whites benefit equally from white privilege, ignoring and minimising the plight of working-class whites. A 2019 sociological study by E Cooley, etc. found that learning about white privilege did nothing to increase empathy for people of colour among white liberals, but simply made them less likely to empathise with poorer whites, placing greater personal blame on them on the basis that their privilege outweighed other social factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, reactionary and racist ideology abounds among the white working class, and this article is not intended to downplay such attitudes or pretend that they do not exist. It is to argue that if there is a hope that cross-racial solidarity can be achieved, and these reactionary tendencies extinguished, it will not be accomplished by lecturing working-class whites who are beset by low wages, deindustrialisation, and the opioid epidemic about their ‘privilege’, but by encouraging them to recognise that they have more in common with other races than with elites of the same race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term ‘class reductionist’ is consistently deployed against socialists who recognise that racism and capitalism are intimately connected as if this recognition downplays the significance of racism. But some of the most pernicious forms of American institutional racism, such as redlining and the prison-industrial complex, have explicitly capitalistic imperatives. For example, exclusion from ‘prime’ credit has forced black communities to secure housing through subprime loans and substandard rental accommodation. During the subprime lending boom, predatory loans were five times more likely to be made in black neighbourhoods than in white neighbourhoods, while black Americans were four times as likely as white Americans to be denied loans from the Bank of America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations such as the Blackstone Group have conspired to engage in predatory lending practices, buying up houses at cheap prices and selling them on for higher prices or charging exorbitant rents. Invitation Homes, a subsidiary of the Blackstone Group and a prominent lender to black communities, may have broken laws to give tenants loans that maximised profits as they could easily outbid first time buyers. It is issues such as these, the pervasive, material disparities which have concentrated generational wealth in the hands of white communities and generational disadvantage in the hands of black communities that should be the focus of anti-racists, not trivial ideas such as ‘white fragility’. These are not injustices that can be solved simply by more representation of black people within the highest echelons of power, but only through the de-privatisation and de-commodification of housing at a minimum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another consequence of viewing racism through a reductive, individualistic lens is the over-medicalisation of the problem, which treats racism as a pathology on the part of its perpetrators. As Kenan Malik writes, &lt;em&gt;“It was not unconscious bias that made a police officer place his knee on George Floyd’s neck”&lt;/em&gt;. A meta-analysis of nearly 500 studies found that unconscious bias training only had a “weak” effect on the behaviour of individuals. Reframing racism as a product of original sin, an aberration that could never be held by ‘normal’ people simply absolves those who are responsible for perpetuating it, as racial bigotry can, and often is, the product of a sound mind. The Nazi war criminals at Nuremberg, for instance, all tested as medically sane, had high IQs, and included a disproportionate number of PhDs. Far from being the irrational judgement of an insane mind, racism is the mendacious, calculated judgement of the elites who perpetuate it, to provide a constant stream of alienated unfree labour from those they impoverish, to divide and conquer and to subjugate. Only an approach that acknowledges the systemic and institutional manifestations of racism can grasp this central point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The systemic racism on which the United States was founded, that still exists today, cannot be expunged with ‘unconscious bias training’ or the recognition of white fragility. The injustices will remain, but white corporate consultants such as Robin DiAngelo will become very rich. What is required is not white guilt but white solidarity on a mass scale, such as has been seen in the recent protests, and a recognition that, as Karl Marx stated, &lt;em&gt;“Labour in the white skin cannot emancipate itself where in the black it is branded.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The months following the killing of George Floyd saw sales of books about race increase by up to 6,800%. The top seller was Robin DiAngelo’s White Fragility, which increased sales by over 400,000 copies from May to June this year, a startling increase of over 2,000%. DiAngelo, a ‘diversity consultant’, has since been invited to deliver keynote speeches, charging up to $35,000 for a two-hour workshop.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Importance of Human Connections, as Told by the Coronavirus</title>
      <link href="/The-Importance-of-Human-Connections" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Importance of Human Connections, as Told by the Coronavirus" />
      <published>2020-08-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Importance-of-Human-Connections</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Importance-of-Human-Connections">&lt;p&gt;Every day, we step out of our homes with ambition in our eyes,  aspirations in our heart  and a desire to change the world as we want to see it (until someone ate a bat somewhere?). At the heart of this colossal myriad of &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; lies something that defines our whole existence – the ability to connect with another human being. Human connection is the exchange of positive energy between people.  The potential of feeling understood and united through human connection is one of the most rewarding elements in life. It has the power to deepen the moment and the bond between people, inspire change and build trust. It has proven to lower anxiety &amp;amp; depression, help us regulate our emotions better and lead to higher self-esteem and empathy, which is actually said to change our immune systems for the better. A research study by Harvard, conducted over a period of 80 years, proves that human connections and healthy relationships are the number one &amp;amp; two drivers of longevity, respectively. Though, our inherent need for a human connection doesn’t mean that every introvert must become a social butterfly. Instead, having a human connection can look different for everyone. Irrespective of what it is for each person, it serves a purpose which nothing else can – make someone feel genuinely happy, and at peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Humans have this dire need to connect. Our brains have learned from brutal evolutionary lessons that social isolation is a death sentence”&lt;/em&gt; said James Coan, a Professor of Psychology at the University of Virginia. The power of touch releases oxytocin, the feel-good hormone. Albeit temporarily, the coronavirus has stripped us all of this supposed elixir for the mind. We are a social species and hence it is not easy to NOT touch each other, as so much of our communication is defined by these touches. While technology seems to be connecting us more than ever, the blue-light emitting screens disconnect us from nature, from ourselves, and from other human beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as people are struggling with an economic recession, they are struggling with an emotional recession too, due to loneliness. Loneliness is not just a feeling in one’s head; it is a biological instinct to seek out other human beings, just like hunger is a signal that sends a person to seek out food. In a situation where we have to stay at home, all by ourselves, such as the one caused by this pandemic, this feeling of loneliness might escalate for many, with limited ways of assuaging it. Even though in some parts of the world, nations have started to open up, the fear of catching the disease will remain in people’s minds, for a long time to come.  The isolation caused by this is proven by science to exact a physical toll on the brain’s circuitry. The confluence of multiple challenges during the pandemic – to health, education, jobs, access to resources has produced a bizarre assemblage of circumstances that increase the risk of depression and Post-traumatic Stress Disorder. In times of disaster, we seek respite in the fact that there is an ending to it which can be accurately predicted. But with this pandemic, we see no end in sight, which makes it more traumatic and compounds the negatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a situation where loneliness exacerbates the negative effects of the pandemic, how do we ensure that we connect in a way which is good for us and also reduces the risk of spreading the disease? In our current situation, the need to reduce physical distances, boost social or relational connections, and not see a rise in loneliness and related mental health problems poses a big problem for us. We need a connection culture, which is rich in relational connection while maintaining a physical distance between individuals. Technology has been a big boon for man since time immemorial, and it is this technology that comes to our rescue here. Be it a conventional video call with friends, a virtual cocktail party, gaming sites where people can compete virtually, watching movies and shows with your friends, or any other thing, we have seen a lot of new inventions throughout the course of this pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how does the coronavirus revolutionise human connection and communication? For the past few decades, humans have focused increasingly on earning money and material belongings, which coupled with rapid technological growth led to the neglect of human relationships, at large. But now that we’re stuck in our homes, the best means of surviving psychologically is to interact with people by whatever means possible. But most importantly, we have begun to understand the value of a human connection, a panacea for all mental health issues, that has no other substitute, in its true essence. &lt;em&gt;‘We realise the true value of anything, only after it is taken away from us’&lt;/em&gt; – asserts a very common saying. Each and every one of us, throughout the course of this pandemic, have felt the importance of a human connection, and it is this realisation in our hearts, which will make us value real connections over materialistic things. And it is this realisation, that finally helps us understand what’s more important: material wealth or mental health?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Anshdeep Singh Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Every day, we step out of our homes with ambition in our eyes, aspirations in our heart and a desire to change the world as we want to see it (until someone ate a bat somewhere?). At the heart of this colossal myriad of everything lies something that defines our whole existence – the ability to connect with another human being. Human connection is the exchange of positive energy between people. The potential of feeling understood and united through human connection is one of the most rewarding elements in life. It has the power to deepen the moment and the bond between people, inspire change and build trust. It has proven to lower anxiety &amp;amp; depression, help us regulate our emotions better and lead to higher self-esteem and empathy, which is actually said to change our immune systems for the better. A research study by Harvard, conducted over a period of 80 years, proves that human connections and healthy relationships are the number one &amp;amp; two drivers of longevity, respectively. Though, our inherent need for a human connection doesn’t mean that every introvert must become a social butterfly. Instead, having a human connection can look different for everyone. Irrespective of what it is for each person, it serves a purpose which nothing else can – make someone feel genuinely happy, and at peace.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">God’s Homophobia will Die and We will Kill It</title>
      <link href="/God-s-Homophobia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="God's Homophobia will Die and We will Kill It" />
      <published>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/God-s-Homophobia</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/God-s-Homophobia">&lt;p&gt;It is no secret that most religions of the world are opposed to homosexuality. The Bible clearly states: &lt;em&gt;“If a man lies with a male as with a woman, both of them have committed an abomination; they shall surely be put to death; their blood is upon them.”&lt;/em&gt; (Leviticus 18:22). While the Quran does not have such an explicit declaration, traditional Islamic jurisprudence fully proscribes homosexual acts. Hindu jurisprudence has no equivalent bans on homosexual acts, and its law books do contain a recognition of a ‘third gender’, but most Hindus oppose it vigorously in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, none of these religions are monolithic and all contain various elements that are sympathetic towards homosexuality, whether among general followers or in their institutions. Despite all that, only a fool would say that the religions of the world fully accept homosexuals or their rights. This is epitomised in the most patronising argument religious people put forth, i.e. that while they accept LGBTQ persons like any other human being and believe homosexuality to be natural, their dogma commands that they continue to consider homosexual acts as immoral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is: what can one do in such a situation? Can an LGBTQ person agree to disagree with the religious person and still continue to co-exist? Or is peace simply not an option? The religious person obviously insists that they are only proceeding from a vantage point of empathy, that they demand restraint from the gay person not out of prejudice but because all persons have to control their desires under a religious framework, not just homosexuals. So, there is no ground to allege homophobia on their part at all. But all of this is utter hogwash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the fact that this new kind of argument is a clear attempt at dehumanising the homosexual, because it proscribes the very fruition of the gay person’s inner desires, it has more sinister implications: It leads to religious people favouring the maintenance of legal bans on homosexual acts because that is not seen as an impeachment of LGBTQ rights by itself. It also leads to a moral justification for continuing with the torturous practice of gay conversion therapy because that is verily seen as an expression of love which only seeks to prevent sin. And it is the brutality of these points as well as the very sinews of religious beliefs on homosexuality that makes such beliefs worthy of eradication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religions, after all, view the very fact of homosexuality as wrong. To them, it is fundamentally unnatural and a deviation from the human normal which God(s) has thought fit to prohibit. The outward empathy they seek to exhibit for LGBTQ rights is informed not by an understanding of the fact that homosexuality is no deviation from the normal, but by their desire to be kind in a way no different to the kindness/forgiveness they may have for the rapist or the murderer. When one takes that into account, one can clearly see that religious people want the LGBTQ community to become dogs on a leash - restraining themselves from a fruition of their sexual desires and a more visible existence in public life - in exchange for little treats of kindness and little beatings of gay conversion therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the question of making peace with the religious person who denies the normalcy of homosexual relations or deems them sinful is moot. The religious person may seek to caustically self-victimise here by saying that their human rights as religious people cannot be restricted by the homosexual agenda. But the fact of the matter is that their argument would likely not find traction in any human rights court save the ones found in America with elected Republican judges. It is well-known in human rights jurisprudence that the right to practice one’s faith may be qualified. The requirement is that such a qualification be for a legitimate aim, that it be the necessary means to achieve such an aim and that it be the least-intrusive means available for achieving that aim. We clearly know that a criminalisation of the espousal of anti-homosexual beliefs is for a very legitimate aim: the securing of fuller rights to LGBTQ person. We also know that such a measure is necessary to achieve that aim. If there is no threat of criminal sanction on the espousal of anti-LGBTQ beliefs, then a threat to the right of LGBTQ persons to lead a dignified existence forever remains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only hurdle would be the question of intrusiveness. But given the nature of the mischief sought to be controlled here, criminalisation is not in the least excessive. The threat of criminal sanction that secures the rights of homosexuals is hardly intrusive upon religious rights: such a measure does not require the religious person to go out of his way to do anything, it merely requires them to forbear from preaching certain values. That may be intrusive due to the fact that proselytisation is an article of some faiths, but again, there’s no ban on proselytisation here - just a ban on bigotry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religions will make every attempt to try and hold on to their homophobia, going so far as to to suggest that their moral values are given by a creator and are immutable, regardless of the fact that science and nature condone homosexuality. They will say that their laws are not bendable and that science does not provide an objectively ethical guide to what is permissible among humans. So, a restriction on their right to believe is not objective or valid. But that’s not the point, society is not here to play religion’s game of “my group’s values are objective and right, your group’s values are subjective and wrong”. What society, at this present moment, is required to do is secure complete rights to human beings who have sexual and romantic relations with persons of the same gender. This is the reality of the here and now, and it is non-negotiable, morally or otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is about time that religion killed God’s homophobia, lest He face the proverbial sulphur of a modern society.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>anon.anon</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is no secret that most religions of the world are opposed to homosexuality. The Bible clearly states: “If a man lies with a male as with a woman, both of them have committed an abomination; they shall surely be put to death; their blood is upon them.” (Leviticus 18:22). While the Quran does not have such an explicit declaration, traditional Islamic jurisprudence fully proscribes homosexual acts. Hindu jurisprudence has no equivalent bans on homosexual acts, and its law books do contain a recognition of a ‘third gender’, but most Hindus oppose it vigorously in practice.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Tale of Two Words: Climate Change</title>
      <link href="/A-Tale-of-Two-Words-Climate-Change" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Tale of Two Words: Climate Change" />
      <published>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Tale-of-Two-Words-Climate-Change</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Tale-of-Two-Words-Climate-Change">&lt;p&gt;There are ample things in the world- a mix of ideas, notions and facts that we dust off as ostensible, a fabricated theory or in the words of the President of the ‘Great’ nation of America, a &lt;em&gt;hoax&lt;/em&gt;. And what tops this list is the acknowledgement (or lack thereof) of climate change across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you set out to find how deep the reality of climate change has (or has not) seeped into our being, you’d probably roam forever like &lt;em&gt;Diogenes of Sinope&lt;/em&gt;, holding up a lamp to people’s face, looking for a solution, a solace. Diogenes claimed that people were trapped in this make-believe world which they thought to be real and hitherto were living in a dream state. Although this is a myth which dates back to 445-365 BCE (number of years I can’t even count), it oddly makes sense even today. He stood for something that went above and beyond the bar of normality of our society; he challenged the society and thus was termed a ‘Socrates gone mad’. Mad or &lt;em&gt;radical-liberalist&lt;/em&gt; is a term I hear almost every time I try to explain to someone how exigent the issue of climate change is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our society has tainted climate change as a secondary issue, an elitist issue that the first world countries fight for because there are more pressing issues around the world that third-world nations are grappling with- like hunger, poverty, unemployment and lack of healthcare. And I agree that these issues are foundational and require a country’s full attention- but whilst you’re making developmental plans and ignoring climate change, the world is becoming more predisposed to calamities, disasters and diseases, global warming is increasing alarmingly and destroying this intricately knit web that is our earth, one grain at a time. And what good is this cupidity that we’re after when you don’t have a planet good enough to inhabit anymore?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The famous &lt;em&gt;’12 years left’&lt;/em&gt; statement isn’t a hoax, a notion or an arbitrary idea that someone woke up to. It’s based on empirical calculations by scientists around the world who claim that to avoid a scourge on humanity we have to be on a realistic path toward a carbon-free global economy by 2030. People take this to mean that we can live freely without any delimitation till 2030 and start alleviating our output of hazardous emissions after that. However, to keep the global temperature from rising more than 1.5 degrees, countries would have to cut their carbon dioxide emissions to almost net-zero by around 2050. And to reach that goal, CO2 emissions would have to start dropping &lt;em&gt;“well before 2030”&lt;/em&gt; so that it falls close to 45 per cent by around 2030. Even though such thorough studies have been conducted and there is no shortage of scientific evidence that we need to &lt;em&gt;stop&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;listen&lt;/em&gt; to these words of caution if we want a future of any kind, let alone a sustainable one, many nations continue to live in climate science denial. President Trump is one of those many, who went so far ahead to claim that climate change was invented by China to disable American industry. (According to the very diffident American President every move of China alludes to a clandestine act towards the United States)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People turn a blind eye toward climate change, thinking how much it could possibly affect them. But the fact is that no one has the resources or the faculty to shield themselves from the wrath of climate change. It is biased to no one and would wipe out whatever comes in its way. The recent California wildfires, hurricane Dorian in the US, the Australian bushfire, and unprecedented heat waves sweeping Verkhoyansk- a Siberian town in the arctic circle weren’t a startling enough wake-up call for the world, because we continue to resort to our exploitative methods. Two of the most catastrophic cyclones hit India in the last couple of months, Amphan in Kolkata and Nisarga in Mumbai which was the worst cyclone to have hit the city of Mumbai since 1891.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The financial costs of these calamities aside, loss of flora and fauna and a colossal number of deaths reflect how the world’s poorest and most vulnerable pay the heaviest price for the consequences of climate change, be it the underprivileged in developing countries or the oppressed in first-world nations. It’s not just these drastic tragedies, but the actual danger can be traced from the little changes happening across the world as well, ranging from scorching heat waves in the northern parts of India worsening every year to a hail storm as closely tantamount to snow as the subtropical and semi-arid city of Delhi would’ve ever seen. It was enjoyed by the residents of the city, indifferent to how unnatural it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Climate change is not a stand-alone issue; it’s chained and linked to other societal maladies like a domino effect, be it infrastructure, economy or politics. This cyclic motion continues until we exert force to stop it, or at least ease it down. We’re now witnessing how humanity is paying a price for its benightedness over the last 200 years, since after the Industrial Revolution- as we have been driven by capitalism and materialism instead of welfare and rehabilitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After traversing halfway through a deadly pandemic, increased calamity, crime, racism and right-wing oppression, it’s time to stop and accept the fallacy in our system and pay our dues for the prolonged procrastination on accepting and abating climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can agree that climate change is here to stay. After hundreds of years of exploitation of resources and massive technological advancements that have left us wanting a life of ease and luxuries at the cost of our environment, nature cannot disappear into thin air. But the first step towards having a sustainable future would be to understand the gravity of this issue and not let it hang entirely on the shoulders of the Gen-Z. In recent decades, we’ve had to fight our own battle for a healthy world that we will potentially live in, that our forebears have set on fire, left for us to extinguish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Greta Thunberg, a 17-year-old soul, who deserves to be studying and living her life to the fullest, can leave her hedonic lifestyle and take to revolting on the streets for the right to have a sustainable future, then why can’t we support her and thousands of others fighting for the earth? If she can chant these two simple words and make them her anthem then how hard is it for our aged leaders to comprehend that this world that they want to dominate is withering one day at a time, and if climate change is not tamed now then all there will be left to reign over will be a kingdom of embers?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There are ample things in the world- a mix of ideas, notions and facts that we dust off as ostensible, a fabricated theory or in the words of the President of the ‘Great’ nation of America, a hoax. And what tops this list is the acknowledgement (or lack thereof) of climate change across the globe.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Oppression Matters, The Rioting Matters</title>
      <link href="/The-Oppression-Matters" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Oppression Matters, The Rioting Matters" />
      <published>2020-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Oppression%20Matters</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Oppression-Matters">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Slavery was not born out of racism, but racism was born out of slavery.”&lt;/em&gt; – Eric Williams&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often use the word &lt;em&gt;racism&lt;/em&gt; with a feeling of ‘otherness’ and a sense of disconnect, as if participating in racism is something that we’re all immune to. Yet, the history of racism dates back to hundreds of years, and after tens and thousands of revolutions led by Black folks, racism in all of its forms - ideological and systematic, is just as prevalent now as it was back then. The United States of America has been revolting and fighting for justice for Black lives after George Floyd’s institutionalised murder in the recent weeks. Many citizens have expressed their extreme discontent by looting and targeting multi-billion-dollar organisations. My question is, who are we to police how oppressed communities should fight against the system? Isn’t this an integral part of the fight against racism itself? Aren’t capitalism and racism inherently linked?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of us are equipped with the knowledge about the Atlantic slave trade. In summary, thousands of African Americans were enslaved by European colonizers in the 1600’s, when they, on a ludicrous quest to loot and colonise nations to facilitate trade and make profits, stumbled upon mass profiteering potential in the Caribbean, Africa and America, where valuable crops were aplenty. They were sold as slaves and made to work for hours extending to days at plantations. Many people mistake the enslavement of Black people as a product of racism, ignoring the capitalist intentions with which these atrocities were committed. A capitalist society rests on the principle of exploitation of the working class - the European colonisers treated Black people as a means of making profits; racial prejudices didn’t necessarily drive this motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the rich and elite slave-owners wished to create a divide between the working class so as to retain their influence and ‘divide and rule’, they introduced a system within a system; a system built on the colour and culture of a community. As a result, racism gradually emerged as a tool for many economic elites worldwide to keep the working class from uniting against a system making profits off of their hard labour. Racism was used as a justification for slavery, citing all the negative stereotypes relating to Black people - they are “lazy, unintelligent and violent”. Many modern-day American billionaires and millionaires are guilty of perpetuating the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming to the modern-day scenario, capitalism and racism work together to establish a system fundamentally against Black and non-Black people of colour. Capitalism will never thrive at full employment - it works on the existence of a certain percentage of unemployment. You ask how? When people fear being replaced, they’d be willing to work at the lowest of wages. The rich feed off of this fear and make profits in billions. Unemployment and poverty won’t deter many from scraping for money and food for their family, leading them to indulge in illegal ways of earning money. More often than not, racism is deployed as a tool to put Black people at the extreme bottom of income distribution, leading to higher rates of unemployment among them. So, when the rich threaten White people with unemployment, the latter think “No, I am not like them (Black people). I must earn enough money and become rich”. This is how capitalism and racism work in partnership and keep the cycle of exploitation and discrimination spinning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Marxist theory has laid out the foundations of two social evils we witness in our society. However, opponents of this argument deem that proponents of this theory often indulge in class-reductionist behaviour and that to reduce racism down to only class instead of addressing the years of social conditioning and building negative stereotypes is a huge disservice to Black folks, and I agree. Citing that the real issue is only class and not race propagates the notion that rich and middle-class Black citizens don’t face racism, which is nowhere near the truth. Racism has definitely emerged out of economics; however, it has also turned into a social exclusionary tool, stripping so many Black people of their rights and dignity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, a debate has ensued on the extent to which looting billion-dollar corporations aids the fight against police brutality and racism. The answer lies in the question itself. The police serve the elite; they work for the protection of their interests and wishes in order to uphold the status quo. During the 1900’s, when more and more immigrant working citizens entered the economy, the ruling class employed hundreds of armed men to maintain ‘order’ within the working class. This has extended to the modern-day police who disproportionately target poor Black and Latino people. The use of the police force over Black people is significantly biased and racially-motivated. They are 3x times as likely to be victims of police brutality as their White counterparts. George Floyd was just one of many Black people to lose his life to a system so antagonistic toward people of his community. Under the farce of serving and protecting people of an area, the police are responsible for inflicting violence upon hundreds of unarmed citizens. Whose interest is the police upholding if not the ruling class? Why can’t citizens democratically vote for a police force rather than letting strangers exercise so much power over them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding the origins of things affecting us and thousands of lives everyday is of paramount importance. Racism didn’t appear out of nowhere; it was carefully woven into the very economic system of the US. In the same way, the police weren’t introduced to protect the common citizen, instead they are meant to control the ‘violence’ of the working class and resistors of the system, which in the American scenario, are mostly Black people. Racism and capitalism are the two sides of the same coin; each depends on the other to survive.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aarushi Mittal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Slavery was not born out of racism, but racism was born out of slavery.” – Eric Williams</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Crime of Menstruation</title>
      <link href="/The-Crime-of-Menstruation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Crime of Menstruation" />
      <published>2020-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Crime-of-Menstruation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Crime-of-Menstruation">&lt;p&gt;The amount one knows about the phenomenon known as menstruation depends on a number of things; sex, age, ethnicity and other characteristics. This is in spite of the fact that having periods is perhaps just as common as any other human bodily process, and is experienced on a monthly basis by roughly half of the world’s population. While there is a general awareness that periods are a necessity for fertility in women, not many people across the world are appreciative of what is involved in the process. Menstruating women are widely seen as ‘dirty’ and steps are taken to avoid them at all costs by people of certain communities. However, this stigma associated with menstruation is not just an issue of the ‘backward’ or ‘illiterate’ communities; it affects the most modern of societies too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several religious superstitions associated with periods and pink products like tampons and pads. In cultures like Hinduism, women who are on their periods are often exempted from the rites and rituals that characterise the religion. They are not permitted inside the kitchen, to adorn themselves with flowers or to even touch anyone or anything, as far as possible. In fact, there are several temples that do not permit the entry of menstruating women or women of menstruating age. One such instance that drew wide condemnation is the Sabarimala Temple located in the state of Kerala in India. For centuries, this temple has restricted the entry of women of menstruating age (roughly between 10 and 50 years). This is claimed to be out of respect for the celibate nature of the patron deity. In a historic verdict on September 28, 2018, the Supreme Court of India lifted the ban on the entry of women, stating that discrimination against them, even on the grounds of religion, is unconstitutional. While feminists hailed this as a great victory, many others, including women, were not very appreciative of the step, and the Court has decided to review its decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such restrictions are not unique to Hinduism. In Islam, women are not permitted to partake in the fasting that characterises the month of Ramadan and are essentially seen as ‘impure’. Men are instructed to stay away from women on their periods and to refrain from having sexual intercourse during this time. Similarly, Judaism refers to such women as &lt;em&gt;‘niddah’&lt;/em&gt; and the Torah bans intercourse between a man and a menstruating woman. Besides, early Western Christian cultures considered a menstruating woman dangerous and placed restrictions on her to ensure safety for all. Even today, some church fathers continue to support the exclusion of women from the ministry on the basis of ‘uncleanliness’. The idea of women being impure or unclean during their periods is a very common notion among most of the world’s most popular religions and cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are however, some religions that do not view menstruation in a bad light. This category includes the Sikhs and Buddhists. Now, there are some denominations of these religions that share the idea of menstruating women being unclean, but in general, their beliefs are less overbearing compared to the others. A similar and rather astonishing example is Shaktism, a major denomination of Hinduism. The followers of this sect celebrate the annual menstrual cycle, called Ambubachi, of Goddess Kamakhya at the Kamakhya Temple of Assam, India. This takes place every year in the month of June. It is celebrated in the form of the Ambubachi Mela, a four-day festival, wherein the doors of the temple remain closed for three days and open on the fourth to welcome thousands of pilgrims from around the world. This view of the natural process of menstruation is in stark contrast with the more popularly held Hindu views. It is important to note here that the most popular religions and their denominations across the world belong to the former category and do not view periods positively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discussion up until now provides a view that only the most religious people tend to see menstruation adversely. This is, however, not very accurate. A casual stigma associated with having periods pervades among all of us. Common experiences of women bear testimony to that. In India, packets of sanitary napkins are wrapped in newspaper and then handed over to the customer in a black polyethene packet. At this point, I am pretty sure the entire demographic is aware of what is inside and we might as well opt for a new measure to hide the fact that women menstruate. Girls often feel embarrassed while shopping for period products when the experience should be the same as buying band-aids. Many refrain from using tampons due to the fear of breaking their hymen before marriage, something that is often culturally looked down upon. Girls also usually feel ashamed after discovering a stain on their clothes, which again, under normal circumstances, should not have been viewed any differently than a blood soaked bandage. The point is this, we are consciously trying to hide the fact that having periods is a normal occurrence, affecting about half the human population every month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The misconceptions surrounding menstruation have always given it a bad name and resulted in women being oppressed. In Nepal, a very common practice is to move women on their periods to often very unhygienic menstrual huts. This practice, referred to as ‘Chhaupadi’, is actually illegal in Nepal, and yet it continues to exist as a commonplace practice. Several women die every year due to suffocation, snake bites, excessively cold weather and assault during their exile in these huts. The exact number of deaths due to this practice, however, is unknown as most of these cases go unreported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discrimination is not just limited to these instances. On a wider scale, menstruating women face the phenomenon of the ‘pink tax’. It is a common knowledge that a gender based wage gap exists even today in most fields of work. An additional value added tax to feminine products in such a scenario effectively reduces the purchasing power of women in general. Moreover, our economic structure fails to recognise period products as a necessity and chooses to see them as items of luxury. Thus, even they are not exempted from the pink tax. As I have mentioned in one of my previous articles, this comes across as if menstruation is a crime and women are being fined for the crime of menstruation. There have, however, been some positive changes in this avenue over the last few months. Due to the continuous efforts of Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez and other Democrats, a few states in the US have taken the decision to repeal the Tampon Tax. The biggest win in this avenue was achieved by Scotland when the country became the first in the world to make all period products available to all women free of cost on February 27, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, most other countries continue to charge heavily for menstrual hygiene products. The introduction of GST (Goods and Services Tax) in India on July 1, 2017 resulted in a 12% taxation on sanitary napkins. This sparked protests across the country and consequently, the tax on pads had to be repealed a year later. However, period products continue to be beyond the affordability of a large number of women in India. In rural areas of developing countries like India and other places where women’s accessibility to pads and tampons is very limited, menstruating women resort to the use of leaves for cleaning purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Period poverty is a major issue in the modern world. Many organisations across the world have taken it upon themselves to strive to ensure these basic requirements for all women. Sanjay Wijesekera, former UNICEF Chief of Water, Sanitation and Hygiene was once quoted as saying, “Meeting the hygiene needs of all adolescent girls is a fundamental issue of human rights, dignity and public health.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another rather surprising aspect of period products and menstruation is the lack of understanding of the subject among males. Now, since they do not have to face the monthly pain, they don’t really have to know how tampons are used. But a basic understanding of why it happens and the physical and mental complications associated with it is a necessity to at least make an attempt to tackle the misunderstandings and stigma around menstruation. Shockingly, even women tend to harbour a lot of misconceptions about the process like the belief that women living in close proximity sync up their menstrual cycles or that one cannot get pregnant while on their period. However, most educational set-ups across the world fail to clear these misconceptions due to the stigma associated with speaking about periods. It is almost an unspoken rule to not mention a naturally uncontrollable bodily phenomenon like menstruation. Even popular television shows like &lt;em&gt;Survivor&lt;/em&gt; and others, which have a basic premise of surviving in nature, fail to talk about how women deal with menstruation during their stay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of the fact that women have been experiencing this phenomenon forever, the advancement in period products is rather disappointing. Tampons and pads, which are among the most popular period products to be used, are actually very bad for the environment. Besides, wearing one of these for a prolonged period of time may lead to the overgrowth of &lt;em&gt;staphylococcus aureus&lt;/em&gt; bacteria in the vagina and result in a condition called toxic shock syndrome. The symptoms include dizziness, diarrhoea and even fever. Very few environmentally-friendly options that are completely safe to use exist and these are well beyond the affordability of most women across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another of the major side effects of the menstrual stigma are the taunts. Back in 2015, when Donald Trump was caught in a tirade of questions from Fox News host Megyn Kelly, he claimed that she had “blood coming out of her wherever”, probably in an attempt to shut her up. He, however, denied it, later saying that he was actually referring to Kelly’s apparently bleeding nose. Comments like this have always been around and various aspects of menstruation have been used to provide variety to the taunts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Premenstrual syndrome (PMS) is often used as a weapon to devalidate a woman’s concerns and feelings. In fact, my apprehensions involving PMS are not limited to just that. The phenomenon of premenstrual syndrome is characterised by a wide variety of symptoms including fatigue, cramps, diarrhoea, insomnia and depression. While each of these symptoms individually garners sympathy from most and can be a primary cause for being excused from work, the amalgamation of all, which is arguably worse, fails to do the same. This is primarily because of the association with the forbidden word: menstruation. The causes of these symptoms are not very well understood among the medical community but are primarily attributed to hormonal changes during the menstrual cycle. The lack of sympathy and understanding often results in adverse conditions for menstruating women, especially in the workplace. About 50 years ago, when Western women were entering the workforce in large numbers for the first time, conservative activists like Phyllis Schlafly claimed that women were hormonally ill-suited for positions of responsibility. This ideology continues to hinder women’s capacity to get an upgrade to a position of authority even today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that we are not talking enough about menstruation and unknowingly, continue to keep the stigma associated with it alive. As much as all of us want to believe that women are not oppressed anymore, it is still a dream that we might need a while to realise. Active measures to educate the masses on the body function, making period products and clean water available to all and actively fighting against cultural practices of discriminatory nature is the need of the hour. And this begins with people talking about periods, rather than pretending as if they are Voldemort and must not be named.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The amount one knows about the phenomenon known as menstruation depends on a number of things; sex, age, ethnicity and other characteristics. This is in spite of the fact that having periods is perhaps just as common as any other human bodily process, and is experienced on a monthly basis by roughly half of the world’s population. While there is a general awareness that periods are a necessity for fertility in women, not many people across the world are appreciative of what is involved in the process. Menstruating women are widely seen as ‘dirty’ and steps are taken to avoid them at all costs by people of certain communities. However, this stigma associated with menstruation is not just an issue of the ‘backward’ or ‘illiterate’ communities; it affects the most modern of societies too.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Rioting Doesn’t Matter, Nothing Does</title>
      <link href="/Rioting-Doesnt-Matter" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rioting Doesn't Matter, Nothing Does" />
      <published>2020-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Rioting-Doesnt-Matter</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Rioting-Doesnt-Matter">&lt;p&gt;To anyone with any concern for humanity, what has happened in America should be deeply saddening and infuriating. The brutal killing of George Floyd by a police officer in Minneapolis has opened the floodgates of fury in America’s general populace. The National Guard has had to be deployed in many places. Courthouses, shops, town halls, homes and so many places have been burned to the ground by rioters. While thousands have been arrested, some rioters, police officers and protestors have been killed. President Trump has declared Antifa a terrorist organisation and has threatened to use the military.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, the situation is dire. Those on America’s Right have broadly issued boilerplate condemnations of the incident of police brutality, of course, but with no acknowledgement of the systemic oppression of Black people in America. And in classic American conservative fashion, they have condemned the retributive violence with evident dog whistles like those calling for “law and order” to be restored. The liberals, well, have been liberals, making boilerplate condemnations of systemic oppression without any real commitment towards an actual solution. As usual, they have been busy ‘turning people’s heads’ to bring attention to the problem by changing their profile pictures. In complete contrast, the leftists have been rejoicing; to them this is the beginning of a revolution that is going to end the hegemony of the ruling class in America and fulfill Marx’s prophecy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the zeal of the American leftist in these riots is more masturbatory than it is idealistic, representing a mere Lacanian fantasy to find a new master instead of a true desire to usher in a just society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, one can see where the need for violence arises from. It would be foolish and immoral to argue that ‘violence is never the answer’. Violence becomes necessary to achieve tangible goals when the conscience of the powers that be simply remains unmoved by the scale of their own exploitation. Violence becomes unavoidable when the hand of the ‘system’ only seeks to whip and coerce people into submission. And in America, it should be incontrovertible to say that these conditions stand fulfilled, for police brutality against George Floyd is only the tip of the iceberg; crime, death, poverty, unfair treatment and so much more clearly evidences that American Black people are second-class citizens in a country that is partially built on enslaving them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, violence needs to be clearly channelised. It needs to be used to truly storm the Bastille or storm the Tsar’s Winter Palace. What it is definitely not supposed to be used for is burning a 7-11 or destroying the livelihoods of a lot of small businesses or pelting stones at everyday citizens. One can make theoretical arguments of how all businesses and everyday citizens who have been mute throughout, are complicit and need to face the fury as well. But one has to honestly ask oneself if that argument really holds water: The factum of being born in a society means one is subjected to its all-pervading influence that indoctrinates all into marginalising certain peoples, does that mean everyone in the world should be subjected to violence? Of course not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the social lives of conscious beings like humans, violence is as much physical as it is psychological. When we burn down a building or kill someone as part of a movement, we inevitably seek to psychologically challenge what that building or person represents. This is why there is a world of difference between burning a police station and vandalising a convenience store. The former is a clear challenge to the system of authority that killed George Floyd. The latter is saying that a person is not allowed to carry on his business because of their theoretical complicity, that the people who depended on that business for their wages do not deserve them. It should take no intellectual exegesis to point out that the latter kind of violence is directed at those who are merely the blind serfs of the overlord that is systemic oppression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is here that we find that the so-called revolution going on in America today is more ‘ideological’ in the postmodernist sense than anything. The violence in American streets hasn’t affected the American oligarchs at all. What it has done is far more miniscule yet far more sinister: the riots have ensured that the anger of the marginalised is directed at those who are only theoretically guilty to ensure that those who actually are guilty can continue to maintain their power. The ‘owners’ of the oasis in the desert of post-ideology have ensured that the thirsty fight against those who are allowed to fetch a pail of water instead of those who consume the whole pond. This is eminently proved by the outpouring of support that so many warlocks of the system, the TV show hosts, actors and musicians have shown for the riots. In fact, some of them have even offered to bail the rioters out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The riots in America are a clear example of how far late capitalism has gone to ensure it cannot be challenged. Even in this outpouring of violence, we are able to locate not a true challenge to the Machine. We can only see rage, rage that only affirms the master’s discourse. Perhaps that is all we can now have against capitalism, the trappings of ideology are far too great, the sinews of the invisible exploitative hand are too strong. Maybe, just maybe, we are doomed.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>anon.anon</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">To anyone with any concern for humanity, what has happened in America should be deeply saddening and infuriating. The brutal killing of George Floyd by a police officer in Minneapolis has opened the floodgates of fury in America’s general populace. The National Guard has had to be deployed in many places. Courthouses, shops, town halls, homes and so many places have been burned to the ground by rioters. While thousands have been arrested, some rioters, police officers and protestors have been killed. President Trump has declared Antifa a terrorist organisation and has threatened to use the military.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lockdown Diaries and the Smell of Strange Perfume</title>
      <link href="/Lockdown-Diaries" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lockdown Diaries and the Smell of Strange Perfume" />
      <published>2020-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Lockdown-Diaries</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lockdown-Diaries">&lt;p&gt;Dear Diary (are you still supposed to write that or is it totally outdated?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t know how to start; the last time I wrote to myself was in the eighth grade, when I wished desperately for the English exam to end, lest my hand fall off and I live without one with an awkward story to tell for as long as the world sustains. It’s not as weird as I thought it would be, honestly. I do talk to myself all the time, at 3 AM, wavering between what I should’ve said to some people two years back and all the possible ways that the world might end in (Armageddon is not left unconsidered, by the way).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pretty sure this time is hard for every living person on the surface of this planet, and I’m not in this alone. Sometimes, my problems seem like a tiny little whine when I open the news and read about the horrible things happening around; people trying to survive, to get food and just breathe every day, hoping the sun doesn’t set, because if it does, there is another day of suffering waiting for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whereas as soon as I wake up, I wait eagerly for the dusk, creating a mental picture of the day ahead in my head, trying to bring a sense of organisation and calm to this commotion that life has become. It is almost like an annoying traffic jam, cars glued to the ground, an utterly piercing horn in the background that isn’t ready to subside and your foot on the pedal trying to move your car one bit at a time, as much as you can, to get out of this rut so that you can finally glide onto the highway, roll down your windows and let the cool autumn breeze embrace you until it touches your feet and you feel like all is okay in the world again. I feel as if these days I’m just waiting for this jam to clear, so that I can take in that air again as I rush my car through the freeway, and go anywhere I want, no restrictions, just the journey and the destination ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I just romanticise a pandemic? I’m afraid so. Reading a little too much of Mitch Albom, watching a string of Jane Austen classic movies and smelling books and teas doesn’t make you a &lt;em&gt;cool&lt;/em&gt; millennial, I’m sure. Just your average old-school -person, who loves cardigans and sighs when they look at &lt;em&gt;tiktoks&lt;/em&gt;, referring to it as ‘these kids’ when you’re a 20-year-old yourself (or more like an 80-year-old woman stuck in a 20-year-old’s body).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even though I enjoy my old-person traits most days, it’s certainly hard to keep up with it when you live in the year 2020, jailed amidst the four walls of your room. The internet and social media isn’t a respite because you cannot for the life of you comprehend the conundrum that is #quarantineandchill or the Dalgona coffee trend? (I mean it’s just coffee upside down). I know that I have all the time in the world to read all those books and literary wonders that I keep crying about when I didn’t have enough time or listen to Sam Cooke all day and Paul McCartney the next. And it was all about those books, songs and heartwarming movies but only for a good four weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the fifth week started to unfold, I missed the smell of freshly roasted coffee that came wafting from the cafes that I walked past, pulling me towards themselves as the moon does to the tides - just simple laws of gravity. And that’s just not it. I miss my entire commute to university every day - waking up early yet late, at 7 am (yes that was sadly late) and crying about it, while I rush to get ready and catch a ride to the metro-station as my hair is soaking wet and I drench the marble floors of my house as I sprint around, trying to find my glasses and earphones. I would gulp my cold coffee whole, while my mother gave me a sniggering look for skipping breakfast and yet would sneak in a sandwich wrapped in aluminium foil in my bag when I wasn’t looking. I miss the morning breeze that air-dried my hair in the auto-rickshaw, while I fiddled with my earphones and rummaged through my playlist for a morning boost of Mumford and Sons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would give up all of the social media, yes, Instagram and Snapchat and whatever new application the kids are using these days for a train ride to college, filled with strangers, all so hurried, so hasty, to reach somewhere, pushing and fumbling through the metro - I would find an uncanny sense of calm in it. This uncertainty and muddled life has made me realize how much I also miss studying or skipping the first-morning class to hang out in the cafeteria instead with a cup of steaming coffee and half-forgotten anecdotes from old nights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it just me or does anyone else also miss the yellow and red flowers strewn about on the streets in March? It is not easy for a memory hoarder to get through these tough times without lapsing into nostalgia every other minute. Not easy for a person who loves stray discourses on politics, life, love, career and books over a cup of tea to text people and still have that fiery enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not undermining my privilege, for I know these aren’t the issues that matter in the least right now. But I think writing them down makes me feel a tad better - like I’m ranting to someone as I would in the &lt;em&gt;old days&lt;/em&gt;, if I may.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And like a true old-soul, these past three months have made me realize how much I enjoy my own company rather than texting away or relying on social media to get through the day. And I don’t think less of anyone who does that; whatever one finds their peace in. But it’s hard to blend in sometimes for monochromes in this vibrant world, when all you want is to cook yourself nice, steaming-hot banana bread and curl into your bed with a sad PDF. (I miss the smell of books).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think all I want is a redo sometimes. I know I couldn’t change anything; I couldn’t stop the pandemic because that is beyond my corporeal control. However, if I do get a redo, as I imagine- &lt;em&gt;I see myself standing at the jostling platform of Rajiv Chowk Metro Station in Delhi- people brushing past and into each other. I might be looking at them indifferently, as my earphones pulse to the tunes of The Beach Boys. It looks like a tiresome day and I don’t pay heed to the stranger next to me, who smells like Fijian Water Lotus mist. If only I knew it was the last time I’d smell an unfamiliar perfume, I would’ve stepped a little lighter, would’ve breathed a little longer. I would’ve lingered for a slow second before stepping out the metro doors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waiting,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poorvi.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Dear Diary (are you still supposed to write that or is it totally outdated?)</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
