<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/society/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-08-15T17:03:54+01:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/society/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Fixating on The Male Gaze</title>
      <link href="/Fixating-on-The-Male-Gaze" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fixating on The Male Gaze" />
      <published>2021-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Fixating-on-The-Male-Gaze</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Fixating-on-The-Male-Gaze">&lt;p&gt;If you’ve seen&lt;em&gt; Emily in Paris&lt;/em&gt;, you must have come across the perfume advertisement shooting scene. For those who haven’t, here’s what the scene looked like: a naked model strolls down a bridge while a bunch of men stare at her. Yes, nothing more, nothing less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, our sensible Emily was disturbed to see that. She points out how this would lead to the objectification of the model through the 'Male Gaze', which is followed by the male client explaining to her how the model is wearing nothing but the perfume, which is meant to empower her, by giving her that sex appeal. Emily then went on to pose a very pertinent question, “&lt;em&gt;Is it ‘sexy or sexist?&lt;/em&gt;’” While the question initiates a separate debate altogether, let us first focus on understanding what ‘The Male Gaze’ is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The media that we consume are presented to us through the Male Gaze, where the female character is projected as an ‘object’ of heterosexual male desire. Positioning the cameras in such a manner that they exclusively follow a woman’s figure in zoom is the perfect example to illustrate my point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The visual presentation of the Male Gaze has three perspectives: (i) that of the man behind the camera, (ii) that of the male characters within the film; and lastly (iii) that of the spectator gazing at the image. Here’s an interesting&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/feministinfo/photos/a.977236942375184/3816179241814259/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/feministinfo/photos/a.977236942375184/3816179241814259/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Facebook post&lt;/a&gt; I stumbled upon a few days ago, which prompted me to take up this article. It perfectly spells out how to identify the ‘Male Gaze’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us visit different forms of media which employ the Male Gaze rather conveniently (and make millions out of it):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiatoday.in/movies/bollywood/story/depicting-women-in-bollywood-222702-2014-10-11&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;India Today&lt;/em&gt; article&lt;/a&gt; decodes how Bollywood has forever tacitly engaged in building female lead archetypes and depicting them as subtle caricatures of the Male Gaze. Depiction of female artists as 'Abla Naari' or &lt;em&gt;'the weaker sex'&lt;/em&gt; (Sana Ranaut from &lt;em&gt;Rajjo&lt;/em&gt;), 'Sanskari Ladki' or &lt;em&gt;'the traditional woman' &lt;/em&gt;(Amrita Rao from &lt;em&gt;Vivah&lt;/em&gt;), the selfless-devoted mother (Nirupa Roy from &lt;em&gt;Deewar&lt;/em&gt;) and the bad girl (Deepika Padukone from &lt;em&gt;Cocktail&lt;/em&gt;) are some examples, to name a few.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, any typical American comedy is incomplete without a slow, zoomed-in, down-up shot of a bimbo, in the backdrop of cheesy music. Not to mention the portrayal of women as supporting sexual objects in films like &lt;em&gt;Transformers&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Spectre&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Grown Ups&lt;/em&gt;, and some of Marvel’s/DC’s films.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that’s not enough, here’s an article that sums up what I’ve tried to convey so far: &lt;a href=&quot;https://talkiewood.com/2014/07/megan-vs-rosie-vs-nicola-who-was-the-best-transformers-girl-2/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Megan vs Rosie vs Nicola: Who was the best Transformers girl?&lt;/a&gt; (Do notice the title and the clipping of the article, especially the angle from which the shots have been taken: there’s more focus on the female’s body than her face).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;Three paragraphs into the Talkiewood article, and here’s what we get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;To determine the ‘winner’ (if we want to call it that), we have decided to rank the three actresses based on five criteria: Memorability, hotness in Transformers, hotness outside Transformers, desirability, and their character function.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why so shallow? Let’s be real; these are Michael Bay films. These actresses didn’t exactly play deep characters&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per research in 2012, women are ingredients for higher profitability, hence some critics argue that as sex sells, sexualising female bodies through the male gaze isn’t as concerned with objectification as it is with aesthetics. Thus the use of the erotic is a significantly above-average technique used by creators in communicating with the market. As a consequence, the marketing strategy worked well for &lt;em&gt;Transformers&lt;/em&gt; as it is the thirteenth highest-grossing film series, with a total of $4.8 billion in sales.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not just limited to movies but references of the Male Gaze can also be observed in music, ranging from men preferring a colour (&lt;em&gt;Chittiyaan Kalaiyaan-'White Wrists &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Brown Rang' or 'Brown Woman'&lt;/em&gt;) to men being okay with any colour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&quot;&lt;em&gt;Ek garam chai ki pyaali ho – May there be a hot cup of tea&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Koi usko pilaane waali ho… – May there be someone who serves me that&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chaahe gori ho ya kaali ho – She may be fair or dark toned&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Seene se lagaane waali ho – She should just embrace me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Raat ko jab main waapas aaoon – when I come at night&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Woh darwaaza khole – She'll open the door&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sajke mere saamne aaye – She'll adorn herself and come in front of me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Saare din ki thakaan mitaaye…– She'll erase all my tiredness of the day&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Voh meri gharwaali ho. – She'll be my wife&quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A point worth considering is that the female character doesn't necessarily have to be hyper-sexualised to be the object of the Male Gaze. As long as she, as the passive party, is able to incite the male protagonist to take action towards his ultimate goal, or act as a prop in the service of the male, we’re catching on to a million bucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not like this is absent from music industry either, listen to &lt;em&gt;Trap Queen, Blurred Lines, Wiggle&lt;/em&gt;, or almost every second rap song. As per a&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ijstr.org/final-print/feb2020/and-I-Swear-Profanity-In-Pop-Music-Lyrics-On-The-American-Billboard-Charts-2009-2018-And-The-Effect-On-Youtube-Popularity.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ijstr.org/final-print/feb2020/and-I-Swear-Profanity-In-Pop-Music-Lyrics-On-The-American-Billboard-Charts-2009-2018-And-The-Effect-On-Youtube-Popularity.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;recent study&lt;/a&gt;, Hip-Hop/Rap is the most popular genre in the US and by far the most explicit genre, containing on average, around 77% profane material, thus making it the most active tool to perpetuate the Male Gaze imagery.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commercialisation of the Male Gaze has increased incessantly over the past few years. Most of the so-called Bollywood item songs are not part of the narratives, however, they are placed for the sole purpose of titillation since the business of cinema is all about visuals. The huge online viewership illustrates how this objectification is used as bait for heterosexual males. Some illustrations of this can be grossing viewerships of songs like &lt;em&gt;Chikni Chameli&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp; (lubricious Chameli), any Honey Singh song or even Drake’s &lt;em&gt;Hotline Bling&lt;/em&gt; or Jason Derulo’s &lt;em&gt;Swalla.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence it is important to question whether such a gaze acts as an ‘audience bait ’- a means to improve visual aesthetics, or as a systemic tool to breed patriarchy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming on to the industry that majorly thrives on the sexualisation of the human body (most commonly females) - PORN. The fact that there is such a massive difference between the type of porn made for male vs female audiences, speaks volumes on how dehumanising and degrading the Male Gaze is. But the truth of the matter remains, the viler and more abusive the content is, the more profits it grosses. Current revenue estimates of the porn industry in The United States range from $9 billion - $97 billion a year, thus making it bigger than not only Netflix but also Hollywood as a whole. In other words, online porn is huge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, their audience is getting younger, which inherently means their market is getting bigger (and more problematic). And the million-dollar profits of porn aren’t just limited to this industry but also to many companies (like&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/porn/business/mainstream.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/porn/business/mainstream.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Yahoo!, AT&amp;amp;T, DirecTV, Marriott and General Motors&lt;/a&gt;) that seemingly have no relation with the porn industry. Emerging technologies such as VR are also getting a boost from this industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The male gaze does not spare the younger generation either, cutting across different configurations. The following section talks about this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comic books often serve as graphic repositories for a heterosexual male’s erotic fantasies. Take, for example, victims waiting to be rescued like Diana (&lt;em&gt;The Phantom&lt;/em&gt;), Lois Lane (&lt;em&gt;Superman&lt;/em&gt;), or DC’s empowered female protagonists like Catwoman and She-Hulk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The power and control that characters such as Wonder Woman seemingly have are, in fact, fake, because it is taken away by male writers at will when they depict their images in extremely provocative poses; bending over, arching their heads back, tossing their hair, fighting in the rain, etc, for absolutely no reason at all. In 2018, the total revenue for the comic book publishing industry was estimated at $865 million and moreover, half of the top 10 grossing films released in the same year were based on comic books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In video games, female characters are portrayed in two broad ways: Either the 'Damsel in Distress' or the 'Ultimate Warrior' (both being the perfect victims pandering to the Male Gaze), of which, the latter is unnecessarily hyper-sexualised (having a scantily clothed body with unrealistic proportions). According to an analysis by &lt;em&gt;Downs and Smith&lt;/em&gt;, playable and plot-relevant characters in the 60 best-selling video games of 2003 were predominantly male. Females who were depicted were frequently sexualised, reaffirming the buttery business of the Male Gaze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lara Croft’s (&lt;em&gt;Tomb Raider&lt;/em&gt; series) original character designer, Toby Gard, also known as ‘The Father of Lara’, acknowledged that he initially set the protagonist as a woman so that the 3D physical models could attract more male players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disney princesses’ movies were supposed to be one pure, uncharted territory but well, look where we are. In case you haven't noticed, the female protagonists in Disney movies are almost always white, cis women in corsets with tiny waists and big bosoms, most of whose stories end when they find love (and hence all their answers) in a man. If you look at it, almost none of these princesses ended up alone, happily. But this drama of the Male Gaze is where the money lies. As of today, Disney’s net worth lies close to $122.18 billion, which they only plan to augment by retelling the same story over and over again.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fitting example would be the recent adaptation of Disney’s 1992 animated film &lt;em&gt;Aladdin&lt;/em&gt;, which grossed over $1 billion worldwide, becoming the ninth-highest-grossing film of 2019. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.studiobinder.com/blog/what-is-the-male-gaze-definition/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;studiobinder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;article explains how Jasmine is nothing but a precious artefact locked away for safekeeping - for her father, a valuable commodity - for the villain, and a prize to be won - for &lt;em&gt;Aladdin&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was recently watching a video on ‘The Male Gaze’ on YouTube, and here’s the first comment I came across:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Women grew up watching successful, ‘beautiful’ women always portrayed through the male gaze and now that we ourselves are playing the role of the camera (selfies/Instagram), we present ourselves through the male gaze!”&lt;/em&gt;, which got me thinking about how we're all victims of the Male Gaze in some way or the other. The Male Gaze has stealthily crept into our minds like a parasite and is benefitting by feeding off our insecurities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hitherto, it wouldn’t take big brains to figure out how deeply problematic the Male Gaze is. Firstly, it normalises perceiving women as deserving of one-way surveillance by heterosexual men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, it negatively alters the way women look at themselves. They start to objectify themselves and inherently feel that their primary purpose is to please heterosexual men, whether it’s by being a doting mother succumbing to gender roles, a girl next door fulfilling your sexual desires, or a submissive subject desperately waiting to feed a man’s ego by being ‘saved’ by him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Male Gaze quietly typecasts women as the ‘aesthetic’ half of humankind and gradually detracts from them other ambitions that men and women have alike. Scarily enough, it even normalises predatory gazes at women and perpetuates rape culture. And it haunts me to think that we all, so ordinarily consume the ‘Male Gaze’ served to us on the platter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin Waters, CEO of Victoria's Secret said after the big announcement of the replacement of its spokespeople, &quot;&lt;em&gt;We're moving from what men want to what women want, from sexy for a few to sexy for all&lt;/em&gt;&quot;. In June 2021, Victoria's Secret ditched its Angels post a successful decade-long partnership after it realised that they were no longer ‘culturally relevant’, a euphemism for ‘morally acceptable’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the first&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriassecret.com/us/thevscollective&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriassecret.com/us/thevscollective&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;seven women selected&lt;/a&gt; to join the ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriassecret.com/us/thevscollective&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;VS Collective&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;’&lt;/em&gt; are professional soccer star Megan Rapinoe, actress Priyanka Chopra Jonas and LGBTQ model and activist Valentina Sampaio. Because hey, that’s what women are, a little bit of everything!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if Victoria’s Secret can identify the problem with the Male Gaze, I assume it’s not a secret anymore, is it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, let's come back to the question Emily raised at the beginning of the article. Who draws the line between sexy and sexist, or say, the line between Cardi B’s sexualisation in her music video and a French model’s sexualisation in an advertisement? Who’s to say one is empowering and the other is not? If women want to make money off the Male Gaze, who are we to stop them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the line is indisputably hard to draw. But here’s the thing, when a video agency sexualises a model while directing a perfume advertisement, the model is regulated, since she is a mere medium to convey what the agency wants to. However, when Cardi B sexualises herself, she does that as an independent artist, to express her own personal message, which is indeed empowering. Moreover, in either case, we end up normalising the unrealistic standards for and expectations from the women community at large, which is yet another ethical debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, as long as sexualisation is the subject’s choice, we, coming from a place of privilege, don’t get to draw the line. But that doesn’t mean it’s okay for men to unwarrantedly keep reducing women to objects of sexual gratification on the pretext of making money. Clearly, we need more women creators to present women through a more realistic, humane perspective, but we're far from that, as of now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also known that money will find its way to the Male Gaze, giving it all the more incentive to creep into every line of business. However, in the meantime, as rational consumers of media, we can actively identify the wrong type of content and consciously choose to not feed its business. After all, they make money off &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The choice is yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until then.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Eeshita Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">If you’ve seen Emily in Paris, you must have come across the perfume advertisement shooting scene. For those who haven’t, here’s what the scene looked like: a naked model strolls down a bridge while a bunch of men stare at her. Yes, nothing more, nothing less. Naturally, our sensible Emily was disturbed to see that. She points out how this would lead to the objectification of the model through the 'Male Gaze', which is followed by the male client explaining to her how the model is wearing nothing but the perfume, which is meant to empower her, by giving her that sex appeal. Emily then went on to pose a very pertinent question, “Is it ‘sexy or sexist?’” While the question initiates a separate debate altogether, let us first focus on understanding what ‘The Male Gaze’ is. The media that we consume are presented to us through the Male Gaze, where the female character is projected as an ‘object’ of heterosexual male desire. Positioning the cameras in such a manner that they exclusively follow a woman’s figure in zoom is the perfect example to illustrate my point. The visual presentation of the Male Gaze has three perspectives: (i) that of the man behind the camera, (ii) that of the male characters within the film; and lastly (iii) that of the spectator gazing at the image. Here’s an interesting Facebook post I stumbled upon a few days ago, which prompted me to take up this article. It perfectly spells out how to identify the ‘Male Gaze’. Let us visit different forms of media which employ the Male Gaze rather conveniently (and make millions out of it): An India Today article decodes how Bollywood has forever tacitly engaged in building female lead archetypes and depicting them as subtle caricatures of the Male Gaze. Depiction of female artists as 'Abla Naari' or 'the weaker sex' (Sana Ranaut from Rajjo), 'Sanskari Ladki' or 'the traditional woman' (Amrita Rao from Vivah), the selfless-devoted mother (Nirupa Roy from Deewar) and the bad girl (Deepika Padukone from Cocktail) are some examples, to name a few.&amp;nbsp; Similarly, any typical American comedy is incomplete without a slow, zoomed-in, down-up shot of a bimbo, in the backdrop of cheesy music. Not to mention the portrayal of women as supporting sexual objects in films like Transformers, Wolf of Wall Street, Spectre, Grown Ups, and some of Marvel’s/DC’s films. If that’s not enough, here’s an article that sums up what I’ve tried to convey so far: Megan vs Rosie vs Nicola: Who was the best Transformers girl? (Do notice the title and the clipping of the article, especially the angle from which the shots have been taken: there’s more focus on the female’s body than her face). &amp;nbsp;Three paragraphs into the Talkiewood article, and here’s what we get: “To determine the ‘winner’ (if we want to call it that), we have decided to rank the three actresses based on five criteria: Memorability, hotness in Transformers, hotness outside Transformers, desirability, and their character function. Why so shallow? Let’s be real; these are Michael Bay films. These actresses didn’t exactly play deep characters.” As per research in 2012, women are ingredients for higher profitability, hence some critics argue that as sex sells, sexualising female bodies through the male gaze isn’t as concerned with objectification as it is with aesthetics. Thus the use of the erotic is a significantly above-average technique used by creators in communicating with the market. As a consequence, the marketing strategy worked well for Transformers as it is the thirteenth highest-grossing film series, with a total of $4.8 billion in sales.&amp;nbsp; This is not just limited to movies but references of the Male Gaze can also be observed in music, ranging from men preferring a colour (Chittiyaan Kalaiyaan-'White Wrists and Brown Rang' or 'Brown Woman') to men being okay with any colour. &amp;nbsp;&quot;Ek garam chai ki pyaali ho – May there be a hot cup of tea Koi usko pilaane waali ho… – May there be someone who serves me that Chaahe gori ho ya kaali ho – She may be fair or dark toned Seene se lagaane waali ho – She should just embrace me Raat ko jab main waapas aaoon – when I come at night Woh darwaaza khole – She'll open the door&amp;nbsp; Sajke mere saamne aaye – She'll adorn herself and come in front of me Saare din ki thakaan mitaaye…– She'll erase all my tiredness of the day Voh meri gharwaali ho. – She'll be my wife&quot; A point worth considering is that the female character doesn't necessarily have to be hyper-sexualised to be the object of the Male Gaze. As long as she, as the passive party, is able to incite the male protagonist to take action towards his ultimate goal, or act as a prop in the service of the male, we’re catching on to a million bucks. It's not like this is absent from music industry either, listen to Trap Queen, Blurred Lines, Wiggle, or almost every second rap song. As per a recent study, Hip-Hop/Rap is the most popular genre in the US and by far the most explicit genre, containing on average, around 77% profane material, thus making it the most active tool to perpetuate the Male Gaze imagery.&amp;nbsp; The commercialisation of the Male Gaze has increased incessantly over the past few years. Most of the so-called Bollywood item songs are not part of the narratives, however, they are placed for the sole purpose of titillation since the business of cinema is all about visuals. The huge online viewership illustrates how this objectification is used as bait for heterosexual males. Some illustrations of this can be grossing viewerships of songs like Chikni Chameli&amp;nbsp; (lubricious Chameli), any Honey Singh song or even Drake’s Hotline Bling or Jason Derulo’s Swalla. Hence it is important to question whether such a gaze acts as an ‘audience bait ’- a means to improve visual aesthetics, or as a systemic tool to breed patriarchy? Coming on to the industry that majorly thrives on the sexualisation of the human body (most commonly females) - PORN. The fact that there is such a massive difference between the type of porn made for male vs female audiences, speaks volumes on how dehumanising and degrading the Male Gaze is. But the truth of the matter remains, the viler and more abusive the content is, the more profits it grosses. Current revenue estimates of the porn industry in The United States range from $9 billion - $97 billion a year, thus making it bigger than not only Netflix but also Hollywood as a whole. In other words, online porn is huge. Furthermore, their audience is getting younger, which inherently means their market is getting bigger (and more problematic). And the million-dollar profits of porn aren’t just limited to this industry but also to many companies (like Yahoo!, AT&amp;amp;T, DirecTV, Marriott and General Motors) that seemingly have no relation with the porn industry. Emerging technologies such as VR are also getting a boost from this industry. The male gaze does not spare the younger generation either, cutting across different configurations. The following section talks about this point. Comic books often serve as graphic repositories for a heterosexual male’s erotic fantasies. Take, for example, victims waiting to be rescued like Diana (The Phantom), Lois Lane (Superman), or DC’s empowered female protagonists like Catwoman and She-Hulk. The power and control that characters such as Wonder Woman seemingly have are, in fact, fake, because it is taken away by male writers at will when they depict their images in extremely provocative poses; bending over, arching their heads back, tossing their hair, fighting in the rain, etc, for absolutely no reason at all. In 2018, the total revenue for the comic book publishing industry was estimated at $865 million and moreover, half of the top 10 grossing films released in the same year were based on comic books. In video games, female characters are portrayed in two broad ways: Either the 'Damsel in Distress' or the 'Ultimate Warrior' (both being the perfect victims pandering to the Male Gaze), of which, the latter is unnecessarily hyper-sexualised (having a scantily clothed body with unrealistic proportions). According to an analysis by Downs and Smith, playable and plot-relevant characters in the 60 best-selling video games of 2003 were predominantly male. Females who were depicted were frequently sexualised, reaffirming the buttery business of the Male Gaze. Lara Croft’s (Tomb Raider series) original character designer, Toby Gard, also known as ‘The Father of Lara’, acknowledged that he initially set the protagonist as a woman so that the 3D physical models could attract more male players. Disney princesses’ movies were supposed to be one pure, uncharted territory but well, look where we are. In case you haven't noticed, the female protagonists in Disney movies are almost always white, cis women in corsets with tiny waists and big bosoms, most of whose stories end when they find love (and hence all their answers) in a man. If you look at it, almost none of these princesses ended up alone, happily. But this drama of the Male Gaze is where the money lies. As of today, Disney’s net worth lies close to $122.18 billion, which they only plan to augment by retelling the same story over and over again.&amp;nbsp; A fitting example would be the recent adaptation of Disney’s 1992 animated film Aladdin, which grossed over $1 billion worldwide, becoming the ninth-highest-grossing film of 2019. A studiobinder article explains how Jasmine is nothing but a precious artefact locked away for safekeeping - for her father, a valuable commodity - for the villain, and a prize to be won - for Aladdin.&amp;nbsp; I was recently watching a video on ‘The Male Gaze’ on YouTube, and here’s the first comment I came across: “Women grew up watching successful, ‘beautiful’ women always portrayed through the male gaze and now that we ourselves are playing the role of the camera (selfies/Instagram), we present ourselves through the male gaze!”, which got me thinking about how we're all victims of the Male Gaze in some way or the other. The Male Gaze has stealthily crept into our minds like a parasite and is benefitting by feeding off our insecurities. Hitherto, it wouldn’t take big brains to figure out how deeply problematic the Male Gaze is. Firstly, it normalises perceiving women as deserving of one-way surveillance by heterosexual men. Secondly, it negatively alters the way women look at themselves. They start to objectify themselves and inherently feel that their primary purpose is to please heterosexual men, whether it’s by being a doting mother succumbing to gender roles, a girl next door fulfilling your sexual desires, or a submissive subject desperately waiting to feed a man’s ego by being ‘saved’ by him. The Male Gaze quietly typecasts women as the ‘aesthetic’ half of humankind and gradually detracts from them other ambitions that men and women have alike. Scarily enough, it even normalises predatory gazes at women and perpetuates rape culture. And it haunts me to think that we all, so ordinarily consume the ‘Male Gaze’ served to us on the platter. Martin Waters, CEO of Victoria's Secret said after the big announcement of the replacement of its spokespeople, &quot;We're moving from what men want to what women want, from sexy for a few to sexy for all&quot;. In June 2021, Victoria's Secret ditched its Angels post a successful decade-long partnership after it realised that they were no longer ‘culturally relevant’, a euphemism for ‘morally acceptable’. Among the first seven women selected to join the ‘VS Collective’ are professional soccer star Megan Rapinoe, actress Priyanka Chopra Jonas and LGBTQ model and activist Valentina Sampaio. Because hey, that’s what women are, a little bit of everything! Now if Victoria’s Secret can identify the problem with the Male Gaze, I assume it’s not a secret anymore, is it? Finally, let's come back to the question Emily raised at the beginning of the article. Who draws the line between sexy and sexist, or say, the line between Cardi B’s sexualisation in her music video and a French model’s sexualisation in an advertisement? Who’s to say one is empowering and the other is not? If women want to make money off the Male Gaze, who are we to stop them? Well, the line is indisputably hard to draw. But here’s the thing, when a video agency sexualises a model while directing a perfume advertisement, the model is regulated, since she is a mere medium to convey what the agency wants to. However, when Cardi B sexualises herself, she does that as an independent artist, to express her own personal message, which is indeed empowering. Moreover, in either case, we end up normalising the unrealistic standards for and expectations from the women community at large, which is yet another ethical debate. Still, as long as sexualisation is the subject’s choice, we, coming from a place of privilege, don’t get to draw the line. But that doesn’t mean it’s okay for men to unwarrantedly keep reducing women to objects of sexual gratification on the pretext of making money. Clearly, we need more women creators to present women through a more realistic, humane perspective, but we're far from that, as of now. It is also known that money will find its way to the Male Gaze, giving it all the more incentive to creep into every line of business. However, in the meantime, as rational consumers of media, we can actively identify the wrong type of content and consciously choose to not feed its business. After all, they make money off your attention. The choice is yours. Until then.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Gender Roles: the Fallacy, the Irony and the Hypocrisy</title>
      <link href="/Gender-Roles-the-Fallacy-the-Irony-and-the-Hypocrisy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gender Roles: the Fallacy, the Irony and the Hypocrisy" />
      <published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Gender-Roles-the-Fallacy-the-Irony-and-the-Hypocrisy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Gender-Roles-the-Fallacy-the-Irony-and-the-Hypocrisy">&lt;p&gt;Gender roles and norms refer to a set of ideals that people of a particular sex (assigned at birth) are expected to conform to. They have, for years, set unrealistic standards for all people and formed the basis of an endless number of discriminatory and amoral practices. People lend support to them using the reasoning that they are based on scientific facts about biological sex. Recently, more and more people have started to openly show disdain for and disagreement with these norms, citing the numerous long standing and potentially dangerous effects of the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For long, anthropologists have put forward various pieces of evidence to prove that gender norms are but a social construct. They have repeatedly talked about how 'femininity' and 'masculinity' are relative terms. Margaret Mead was one such anthropologist, often deemed as a sort of a maverick in the field. She revolutionised the field of study, which was previously prominently arm-chair based knowledge, by taking up a more proactive approach. She travelled to remote parts of the world to understand how men and women related to each other, in comparison to the Western ideals of 'femininity', 'masculinity' and 'gender roles'. Over the course of her life, she penned down several preeminent books on the matter.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1933, Mead wrote &lt;em&gt;Sex and Temperament in Three Primitive Societies&lt;/em&gt;. She compared three indigenous groups from the South Pacific which she designated as Arapesh, Tchambuli and Mundugumor. The cultures wildly differed in their expectations and standards for men and women. She noted that in comparison to the established Western standards, all of Arapesh was feminine while the opposite was true for Mundugumor, that is, it was masculine. Tchambuli, on the other hand, reversed Western ideals completely - the dominant positions belonged to women while the dependent ones to men. Mead’s conclusion from the analysis was clear: human nature is malleable and it responds to cultural conditions. Nurture and not nature is responsible for the concept of gender. In other words, gender roles are social constructs, and do not have a basis in the more biological aspects of sex.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the fact that gender roles are social constructs can be lucidly seen in a particular culture too as the ideals change drastically over time, sometimes even undergoing a full 180 degree reversal. The perception of the colors pink and blue is one such example. Pink was not labelled as feminine color until the 1940's. Prior to this, color was generally assigned based on the complexion and so any baby could be dressed in blue or pink. Further back, during the 18th century, pink, which was seen as a close relative of the martial red color, was considered to be a masculine shade. Even as recently as in 1918, an article titled 'Pink or Blue' in &lt;em&gt;The Infants’ Department&lt;/em&gt; stated that pink was meant for boys and blue was for girls. The trend is the exact opposite of this today.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, perceptions about makeup have vacillated between being deemed as feminine and being expected of everyone, through the ages. Makeup was in common use by all people in ancient Egypt, Rome and other civilisations, dating back to as far as 4000 BC in humankind’s history. However, the scenario is obviously very different in the modern world where putting on makeup is predominantly deemed as a feminine activity. In Elizabethan England, makeup was very popular among men. In the mid-1800's however, Queen Victoria and the Church agreed that makeup was an “abomination”. The dissemination of this belief resulted in a long standing association of makeup with femininity and the “Devil’s Work”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These oscillations in ideals and standards associated with gender, within a particular community over time and between different communities at any specific point in time prove that gender norms and expectations are, in fact, not dictated by the biology of sex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gender norms have encouraged various discriminatory and immoral practices through the years of human history and they are still thriving today. More often than not, they're what is responsible for the microaggressions against people of all genders and sexes. For example, men are told not to cry or show emotions, and are expected to partake in activities deemed as worthy of men, often involving heavy manual labor. Those who indulge in the more 'feminine' activities like putting on makeup, cooking and playing sports seen as girly like cheerleading, are looked down upon and slandered.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other end of the spectrum, women are faced with disparaging comments that declare that they simply cannot be funny and belong in the kitchen. Similarly, limited mathematical aptitude and tendency of being loving, caring or sensitive is attributed to their gender. Women are repeatedly talked over and mansplained in professional spaces, in addition to being doubted, especially in leadership roles. Effeminate men are criticised for being too 'feminine', androgenous people are told they are too ambiguous and tomboys are told they are too 'masculine', all of these come paired with a negative undertone. The inferiority of women in the eyes of society is especially clear in such sexist jibes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fallacy, hypocrisy and irony in the gender roles and standards are especially evident through the everyday misogynistic and sexist microaggressions faced by people. Women are told that they are meant to be mothers and yet, young mothers are shamed and criticised almost as much as those who abort their fetus to escape the shame (apart from other reasons). Working women with families are denigrated just as much as those who choose to stay at home.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The former are slandered with claims of being an unfit mother - too calculating, too progressive, too career-oriented. The latter are faced with epithets like 'gold digger' and 'bad role model' as their work is often overlooked. They are also regularly accused of being indolent and lazy. When a woman refuses to give in to the sexual demands of entitled men, they are tagged as 'too prudish' and yet, giving in or choosing to be more sexually active earns them the label 'slut' or 'easy'. Liking dresses and heels is deemed to be too 'frivolous' and 'girly' (with a negative connotation attached) and conversely, women are flagged as gay (often used as a slur in this context) or too 'boyish' (and thus, unattractive) for choosing to have a more masculine aesthetic. Societal standards rooted in gender perception are a double-edged sword, especially for women and other minority genders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of history, an endless number of people have undermined the oppressive gender norms. Some of them achieve fame like Boudica and others attain notoriety like Mary, Queen of the Scots. But, more often than not, the contributions of women and other minority genders are overlooked. An important instance of erasure is the lack of acknowledgement of the contribution of medieval European women to the arts of the times.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Medieval women, especially widows, are generally portrayed as vulnerable, miserable and poor in history books and in literature. The truth, however, was far from this. Financially knowledgeable widows, who were well connected, often accumulated a lot of wealth through jointures and other mechanisms after the death of their husbands.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'Jointures' were pieces of land owned by both the wife and the husband. The ownership remained solely with the surviving spouse on the death of the other. This was very common in the 14th and 15th centuries and became a source of immense wealth for widows who outlived their husbands.They used this money to provide patronage to the arts. Some of the most well-known cathedrals and other monuments of the time were paid for by these widows. Many of them took this new liberty a step further; they commissioned the construction of memorials and mausoleums for themselves which transcended the boundaries of social and patriarchal expectations from women - extravagant architecture, statues of themselves as duchesses or more important than the men in their lives and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the patriarchal norms, a woman lost her individual identity with each marriage, taking up the name of their husbands in the medieval times. This makes it difficult to track the lives of these women (although not impossible) and their contributions to art are thus, largely unacknowledged. Modern public monuments also fail to represent women as history demands it. Of the more than 800 sculptures around the UK, only an abysmal 42 are those of named non-royal women.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, when simply ignoring history is difficult, people have opted to amend it to conform to society’s standards and expectations from a particular gender. Cleopatra VII has been portrayed several times in various books and movies, both Hollywood and otherwise. She is always shown as an unusually attractive seductress. 'Scandals' like her romance with Julius Caesar and Mark Anthony greatly overshadow her achievements, which are often completely ignored. Her stories are full of lies and rumours too. In reality, contrary to her popular portrayals, she was a great statesperson and could command armies. She was fluent in at least nine languages, including an Egyptian tongue, unlike her predecessors of the Ptolemaic dynasty. Additionally, Cleopatra was highly educated in the fields of astronomy, chemistry and literature, among other disciplines and can also be linked to numerous advancements in the field of alchemy of the time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides these, she has several administrative achievements under her belt including her proactive actions to curb corruption among the priests. Cleopatra was the reason for more than two decades of prosperity and stability in Egypt. Instead of acknowledging her numerous achievements, people are obsessed with her affairs with Caesar and Mark Anthony, going as far as blaming her for them and the fate and downfall they suffered later. This overlooks the fact that both Caesar and Mark Anthony were involved in countless other affairs. The queen was certainly not the beautiful seductress that we have been taught to believe. In fact, she might not even have been 'beautiful' as she was, much like most of the other Egyptian royal family members, a product of incest.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cleopatra’s character was questioned and her leadership was doubted by Greek and Roman writers, but this objection was primarily because she was a woman and therefore, according to them, unfit to rule. It is important to remember who the author of any particular story is when talking about its validity. In this case, it was the enemy and so, her stories are rife with rumours (like the story about her suicide by a snake bite). These canards are today frequently presented as history lessons and yet, they are far from the truth. Cleopatra VII is only one of numerous examples of women in history that we have wronged. We owe it to them to rectify the adulterations and remember them just as they were.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, we can say that gender norms have only encouraged damaging practices that have for years deprived us of an opportunity to celebrate the accurate history of humankind. It has paved the way for discriminatory practices against cis women, cis men, transgenders, non-binaries and so on and so forth. While many explain away the established gender roles with claims that they are rooted in biological tendencies and scientific facts about sex, anthropologists have long disagreed and put forward various pieces of evidence to substantiate the theory that gender is entirely a social construct. There is thus, absolutely no moral justification for upholding these standards any longer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Gender roles and norms refer to a set of ideals that people of a particular sex (assigned at birth) are expected to conform to. They have, for years, set unrealistic standards for all people and formed the basis of an endless number of discriminatory and amoral practices. People lend support to them using the reasoning that they are based on scientific facts about biological sex. Recently, more and more people have started to openly show disdain for and disagreement with these norms, citing the numerous long standing and potentially dangerous effects of the same.&amp;nbsp; For long, anthropologists have put forward various pieces of evidence to prove that gender norms are but a social construct. They have repeatedly talked about how 'femininity' and 'masculinity' are relative terms. Margaret Mead was one such anthropologist, often deemed as a sort of a maverick in the field. She revolutionised the field of study, which was previously prominently arm-chair based knowledge, by taking up a more proactive approach. She travelled to remote parts of the world to understand how men and women related to each other, in comparison to the Western ideals of 'femininity', 'masculinity' and 'gender roles'. Over the course of her life, she penned down several preeminent books on the matter.&amp;nbsp; In 1933, Mead wrote Sex and Temperament in Three Primitive Societies. She compared three indigenous groups from the South Pacific which she designated as Arapesh, Tchambuli and Mundugumor. The cultures wildly differed in their expectations and standards for men and women. She noted that in comparison to the established Western standards, all of Arapesh was feminine while the opposite was true for Mundugumor, that is, it was masculine. Tchambuli, on the other hand, reversed Western ideals completely - the dominant positions belonged to women while the dependent ones to men. Mead’s conclusion from the analysis was clear: human nature is malleable and it responds to cultural conditions. Nurture and not nature is responsible for the concept of gender. In other words, gender roles are social constructs, and do not have a basis in the more biological aspects of sex.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, the fact that gender roles are social constructs can be lucidly seen in a particular culture too as the ideals change drastically over time, sometimes even undergoing a full 180 degree reversal. The perception of the colors pink and blue is one such example. Pink was not labelled as feminine color until the 1940's. Prior to this, color was generally assigned based on the complexion and so any baby could be dressed in blue or pink. Further back, during the 18th century, pink, which was seen as a close relative of the martial red color, was considered to be a masculine shade. Even as recently as in 1918, an article titled 'Pink or Blue' in The Infants’ Department stated that pink was meant for boys and blue was for girls. The trend is the exact opposite of this today.&amp;nbsp; Likewise, perceptions about makeup have vacillated between being deemed as feminine and being expected of everyone, through the ages. Makeup was in common use by all people in ancient Egypt, Rome and other civilisations, dating back to as far as 4000 BC in humankind’s history. However, the scenario is obviously very different in the modern world where putting on makeup is predominantly deemed as a feminine activity. In Elizabethan England, makeup was very popular among men. In the mid-1800's however, Queen Victoria and the Church agreed that makeup was an “abomination”. The dissemination of this belief resulted in a long standing association of makeup with femininity and the “Devil’s Work”.&amp;nbsp; These oscillations in ideals and standards associated with gender, within a particular community over time and between different communities at any specific point in time prove that gender norms and expectations are, in fact, not dictated by the biology of sex. Gender norms have encouraged various discriminatory and immoral practices through the years of human history and they are still thriving today. More often than not, they're what is responsible for the microaggressions against people of all genders and sexes. For example, men are told not to cry or show emotions, and are expected to partake in activities deemed as worthy of men, often involving heavy manual labor. Those who indulge in the more 'feminine' activities like putting on makeup, cooking and playing sports seen as girly like cheerleading, are looked down upon and slandered.&amp;nbsp; On the other end of the spectrum, women are faced with disparaging comments that declare that they simply cannot be funny and belong in the kitchen. Similarly, limited mathematical aptitude and tendency of being loving, caring or sensitive is attributed to their gender. Women are repeatedly talked over and mansplained in professional spaces, in addition to being doubted, especially in leadership roles. Effeminate men are criticised for being too 'feminine', androgenous people are told they are too ambiguous and tomboys are told they are too 'masculine', all of these come paired with a negative undertone. The inferiority of women in the eyes of society is especially clear in such sexist jibes.&amp;nbsp; The fallacy, hypocrisy and irony in the gender roles and standards are especially evident through the everyday misogynistic and sexist microaggressions faced by people. Women are told that they are meant to be mothers and yet, young mothers are shamed and criticised almost as much as those who abort their fetus to escape the shame (apart from other reasons). Working women with families are denigrated just as much as those who choose to stay at home.&amp;nbsp; The former are slandered with claims of being an unfit mother - too calculating, too progressive, too career-oriented. The latter are faced with epithets like 'gold digger' and 'bad role model' as their work is often overlooked. They are also regularly accused of being indolent and lazy. When a woman refuses to give in to the sexual demands of entitled men, they are tagged as 'too prudish' and yet, giving in or choosing to be more sexually active earns them the label 'slut' or 'easy'. Liking dresses and heels is deemed to be too 'frivolous' and 'girly' (with a negative connotation attached) and conversely, women are flagged as gay (often used as a slur in this context) or too 'boyish' (and thus, unattractive) for choosing to have a more masculine aesthetic. Societal standards rooted in gender perception are a double-edged sword, especially for women and other minority genders.&amp;nbsp; Over the course of history, an endless number of people have undermined the oppressive gender norms. Some of them achieve fame like Boudica and others attain notoriety like Mary, Queen of the Scots. But, more often than not, the contributions of women and other minority genders are overlooked. An important instance of erasure is the lack of acknowledgement of the contribution of medieval European women to the arts of the times.&amp;nbsp; Medieval women, especially widows, are generally portrayed as vulnerable, miserable and poor in history books and in literature. The truth, however, was far from this. Financially knowledgeable widows, who were well connected, often accumulated a lot of wealth through jointures and other mechanisms after the death of their husbands.&amp;nbsp; 'Jointures' were pieces of land owned by both the wife and the husband. The ownership remained solely with the surviving spouse on the death of the other. This was very common in the 14th and 15th centuries and became a source of immense wealth for widows who outlived their husbands.They used this money to provide patronage to the arts. Some of the most well-known cathedrals and other monuments of the time were paid for by these widows. Many of them took this new liberty a step further; they commissioned the construction of memorials and mausoleums for themselves which transcended the boundaries of social and patriarchal expectations from women - extravagant architecture, statues of themselves as duchesses or more important than the men in their lives and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp; Due to the patriarchal norms, a woman lost her individual identity with each marriage, taking up the name of their husbands in the medieval times. This makes it difficult to track the lives of these women (although not impossible) and their contributions to art are thus, largely unacknowledged. Modern public monuments also fail to represent women as history demands it. Of the more than 800 sculptures around the UK, only an abysmal 42 are those of named non-royal women.&amp;nbsp; Sometimes, when simply ignoring history is difficult, people have opted to amend it to conform to society’s standards and expectations from a particular gender. Cleopatra VII has been portrayed several times in various books and movies, both Hollywood and otherwise. She is always shown as an unusually attractive seductress. 'Scandals' like her romance with Julius Caesar and Mark Anthony greatly overshadow her achievements, which are often completely ignored. Her stories are full of lies and rumours too. In reality, contrary to her popular portrayals, she was a great statesperson and could command armies. She was fluent in at least nine languages, including an Egyptian tongue, unlike her predecessors of the Ptolemaic dynasty. Additionally, Cleopatra was highly educated in the fields of astronomy, chemistry and literature, among other disciplines and can also be linked to numerous advancements in the field of alchemy of the time.&amp;nbsp; Besides these, she has several administrative achievements under her belt including her proactive actions to curb corruption among the priests. Cleopatra was the reason for more than two decades of prosperity and stability in Egypt. Instead of acknowledging her numerous achievements, people are obsessed with her affairs with Caesar and Mark Anthony, going as far as blaming her for them and the fate and downfall they suffered later. This overlooks the fact that both Caesar and Mark Anthony were involved in countless other affairs. The queen was certainly not the beautiful seductress that we have been taught to believe. In fact, she might not even have been 'beautiful' as she was, much like most of the other Egyptian royal family members, a product of incest.&amp;nbsp; Cleopatra’s character was questioned and her leadership was doubted by Greek and Roman writers, but this objection was primarily because she was a woman and therefore, according to them, unfit to rule. It is important to remember who the author of any particular story is when talking about its validity. In this case, it was the enemy and so, her stories are rife with rumours (like the story about her suicide by a snake bite). These canards are today frequently presented as history lessons and yet, they are far from the truth. Cleopatra VII is only one of numerous examples of women in history that we have wronged. We owe it to them to rectify the adulterations and remember them just as they were.&amp;nbsp; All in all, we can say that gender norms have only encouraged damaging practices that have for years deprived us of an opportunity to celebrate the accurate history of humankind. It has paved the way for discriminatory practices against cis women, cis men, transgenders, non-binaries and so on and so forth. While many explain away the established gender roles with claims that they are rooted in biological tendencies and scientific facts about sex, anthropologists have long disagreed and put forward various pieces of evidence to substantiate the theory that gender is entirely a social construct. There is thus, absolutely no moral justification for upholding these standards any longer.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Clean Sheet and a Cleaner Mind</title>
      <link href="/A-Clean-Sheet-and-a-Cleaner-Mind" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Clean Sheet and a Cleaner Mind" />
      <published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-07-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Clean-Sheet-and-a-Cleaner-Mind</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Clean-Sheet-and-a-Cleaner-Mind">&lt;p&gt;The months of June and July provided a shade from the exhaustion of the lockdown in the guise of various sporting events, ironically, despite being the hottest months of the year. They brought with them a momentary respite and distraction from the overbearing pandemic and the disconcerting healthcare crisis around the world. The much anticipated Euro Cup 2020 was the highlight of this summer, with new records being made and new players and teams taking the centre stage after what seemed like a long wait.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those two hours at night, people across the world would leave their chores, rush through dinner or complete assignments in haste so that they could give their undivided attention to the game. For those few hours, they would forget about their surroundings and become one with the spirit of the game and diffuse with the energy in the room.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It almost works like alchemy, the allure of sports. As someone who started watching football not so long ago, I have come to two deductions. Firstly, the 20 long years of my life wherein I did not take out enough time for sports have been wasted on the endorphins I could have brimmed with. Secondly, sports, especially football is a festival of emotions for which you do not need expert knowledge or an undying allegiance to a team to enjoy but simply a fervour to follow it through till the end.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to appreciate this game for what it is - a collection of moments that are so fleeting that you have no time to waste on temporal matters but focus wholeheartedly on the game. You sit down in front of a big screen with a tub of popcorn and a cold beverage (pro tip: avoid hot drinks in and around a room where a feisty match is on the go) and for the next two hours you forget about the deadlines, or a fight with your partner, or your family’s daily dysfunctionality, and even maybe that you're amid a pandemic and that life has come to a standstill for the most part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those two hours, you do not take it one day at a time, you do not take deep breaths and think about how the pieces of your life will fall into place, but you dive deep as all the bets are off. You feel like you’re going through a ridge of crests and troughs, but you don't mind the troughs because those little moments, good or bad, is what sums up the experience of this sport into something wholesome. It is somehow okay even through the lows because you risked it all when you started to watch the game- accepting its outcome for the sheer journey of it all. It is sufficient to say that it is therapeutic to see those players make their lives’ commitment and devotion come alive in a matter of seconds.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey of a spectator is anything but linear for the period of a football match - it is chaotic and intense. To think of the journey of the players - out on the field, flowing, flying, heaving and yearning has to be an enigmatic experience - one that we can only speculate, assess and discuss but never actualise.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final of the Euros was a pivotal event for both Italy and England. Italy went from plummeting to their bottom in 2018 when they did not even qualify for the World Cup to successfully lifting the championship trophy of Euro Cup 2020. Historical giants of the footballing world not qualifying for the World Cup of 2018 was as close to sacrilege for their team and Italy's fans as it could've been.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Italy lost its zeal, some players retired and some just left due to the backlash that they faced from their fans and their counterparts. Italy went through their worst phase brought about by a lack of driven players, direction, ideology, and dismal management. Until they found their way back to their calling, led by their manager Roberto Mancini who turned their trajectory by 180 degrees, back toward their ascent. With his tactics and shrewd man-management, he ignited the dying fire and passion in those players, manifested in their unmatched grit and determination during the Euro 2020 season.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When no one expected anything from Italy, they changed the face of the game, their retired players came back to fight and they proved to be the dark horses of the season. It was a historic and beautiful victory for Italy, finally after all their hard work. It was a classic case of rising from the ashes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As important as this victory was for Italy, it was also a watershed game for England who made it to the finals for the first time in 60 years, since the Cup commenced their games in 1960. For a team who hadn't even made it to the finals before, this was a glorious moment for them to 'bring it home’ as the world chanted on. England had reached the semi-finals and quarter-finals in the previous years but never made it past that, losing quite a few games during the penalty shoot-outs in those instances. Thus, one can imagine how terribly fraught this moment must have been for the players badged with the three lions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happened during the penalty shoot out was unfortunate for England due to their history with penalties and the pressure of the moment, but what happened after the match was even more pitiful - the backlash and violence at the stadium by the English fans, who publicly booed the Italian national anthem first and then caused a ruckus with policemen and other supporters in a post-match rage. Racist slurs were hurled at the three players who missed the penalty shootout. Bukayo Saka, 19 (one of the youngest players on the England squad), Marcus Rashford and Jadon Sancho were the three players who were subjected to unfairly carrying on the burden of England’s defeat and faced the brunt of the English audience’s racist and insensitive reaction. It goes on to show the ignorance and bias still entrenched in people’s minds about race. Makes you wonder if all the acceptance is just a perfunctory act.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is by no means justified to have to face the kind of abuse that these players did, even if they missed the penalty. It is easy to rebuke sportspersons for missing a shot but what the spectators don't realise is the trepidation that is induced by these heavy moments of &lt;em&gt;do or die&lt;/em&gt;, where one shot of yours will decide the fate of not just your team but your entire country. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://believeperform.com/the-effect-of-anxiety-on-world-cup-penalty-shootouts/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt;, such moments in a penalty shootout may lead to footballers experiencing symptoms of anxiety. Some commonly occurring symptoms are increases in muscle tension affecting coordination and an increase in heart rate and sweating. Psychologically, anxiety can cause concentration changes such as loss of awareness due to mental tension or poor selective perception. The weakening physiological and attentional changes that occur are the factors that can lead to ‘choking’ in the moment. Imagine your stage fright or nervousness in a new social situation and multiply that by a hundred and maybe then you'll begin to fathom the mental state of a person in such a situation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rashford faced a deluge of slander on his Instagram and people went so far ahead as to even destroy his mural in his own home country, a country wherein he excelled not just in football but even outside the field. This is a man who has done so much good for society and even received The Most Excellent Order of the British Empire award for his efforts to tackle food poverty among vulnerable children, especially during the pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not that it matters that he did all of this, even if he hadn’t, there is no cop-out for the abuse. But this is to say how racial abuse still affects one’s life. Wherever you reach, however much you do, the so-called ‘privileged’ race, class, or gender will always find ways to bring you down. The xenophobic and rowdy behaviour of the English fans was abhorrent in ways ineffable. Even though these racist remarks were received with intolerance and chide from many people across the world, who stood with these players through staunch social media support and protests near Rashford’s mural, we are still far from the response these players and many others deserve from the world football community and association. This is just one case that came to light because of the enormity of the game's scale, but such petty racism is still prevalent in every corner of this world's football fields. To not let another Rashford, Saka or Sancho feel this disparaged and harassed, the world needs to put their foot down and refuse to tolerate such immature cowards in the guise of bullies. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The months of June and July provided a shade from the exhaustion of the lockdown in the guise of various sporting events, ironically, despite being the hottest months of the year. They brought with them a momentary respite and distraction from the overbearing pandemic and the disconcerting healthcare crisis around the world. The much anticipated Euro Cup 2020 was the highlight of this summer, with new records being made and new players and teams taking the centre stage after what seemed like a long wait.&amp;nbsp; For those two hours at night, people across the world would leave their chores, rush through dinner or complete assignments in haste so that they could give their undivided attention to the game. For those few hours, they would forget about their surroundings and become one with the spirit of the game and diffuse with the energy in the room.&amp;nbsp; It almost works like alchemy, the allure of sports. As someone who started watching football not so long ago, I have come to two deductions. Firstly, the 20 long years of my life wherein I did not take out enough time for sports have been wasted on the endorphins I could have brimmed with. Secondly, sports, especially football is a festival of emotions for which you do not need expert knowledge or an undying allegiance to a team to enjoy but simply a fervour to follow it through till the end.&amp;nbsp; You need to appreciate this game for what it is - a collection of moments that are so fleeting that you have no time to waste on temporal matters but focus wholeheartedly on the game. You sit down in front of a big screen with a tub of popcorn and a cold beverage (pro tip: avoid hot drinks in and around a room where a feisty match is on the go) and for the next two hours you forget about the deadlines, or a fight with your partner, or your family’s daily dysfunctionality, and even maybe that you're amid a pandemic and that life has come to a standstill for the most part. For those two hours, you do not take it one day at a time, you do not take deep breaths and think about how the pieces of your life will fall into place, but you dive deep as all the bets are off. You feel like you’re going through a ridge of crests and troughs, but you don't mind the troughs because those little moments, good or bad, is what sums up the experience of this sport into something wholesome. It is somehow okay even through the lows because you risked it all when you started to watch the game- accepting its outcome for the sheer journey of it all. It is sufficient to say that it is therapeutic to see those players make their lives’ commitment and devotion come alive in a matter of seconds.&amp;nbsp; The journey of a spectator is anything but linear for the period of a football match - it is chaotic and intense. To think of the journey of the players - out on the field, flowing, flying, heaving and yearning has to be an enigmatic experience - one that we can only speculate, assess and discuss but never actualise.&amp;nbsp; The final of the Euros was a pivotal event for both Italy and England. Italy went from plummeting to their bottom in 2018 when they did not even qualify for the World Cup to successfully lifting the championship trophy of Euro Cup 2020. Historical giants of the footballing world not qualifying for the World Cup of 2018 was as close to sacrilege for their team and Italy's fans as it could've been.&amp;nbsp; Italy lost its zeal, some players retired and some just left due to the backlash that they faced from their fans and their counterparts. Italy went through their worst phase brought about by a lack of driven players, direction, ideology, and dismal management. Until they found their way back to their calling, led by their manager Roberto Mancini who turned their trajectory by 180 degrees, back toward their ascent. With his tactics and shrewd man-management, he ignited the dying fire and passion in those players, manifested in their unmatched grit and determination during the Euro 2020 season.&amp;nbsp; When no one expected anything from Italy, they changed the face of the game, their retired players came back to fight and they proved to be the dark horses of the season. It was a historic and beautiful victory for Italy, finally after all their hard work. It was a classic case of rising from the ashes.&amp;nbsp; As important as this victory was for Italy, it was also a watershed game for England who made it to the finals for the first time in 60 years, since the Cup commenced their games in 1960. For a team who hadn't even made it to the finals before, this was a glorious moment for them to 'bring it home’ as the world chanted on. England had reached the semi-finals and quarter-finals in the previous years but never made it past that, losing quite a few games during the penalty shoot-outs in those instances. Thus, one can imagine how terribly fraught this moment must have been for the players badged with the three lions.&amp;nbsp; What happened during the penalty shoot out was unfortunate for England due to their history with penalties and the pressure of the moment, but what happened after the match was even more pitiful - the backlash and violence at the stadium by the English fans, who publicly booed the Italian national anthem first and then caused a ruckus with policemen and other supporters in a post-match rage. Racist slurs were hurled at the three players who missed the penalty shootout. Bukayo Saka, 19 (one of the youngest players on the England squad), Marcus Rashford and Jadon Sancho were the three players who were subjected to unfairly carrying on the burden of England’s defeat and faced the brunt of the English audience’s racist and insensitive reaction. It goes on to show the ignorance and bias still entrenched in people’s minds about race. Makes you wonder if all the acceptance is just a perfunctory act.&amp;nbsp; It is by no means justified to have to face the kind of abuse that these players did, even if they missed the penalty. It is easy to rebuke sportspersons for missing a shot but what the spectators don't realise is the trepidation that is induced by these heavy moments of do or die, where one shot of yours will decide the fate of not just your team but your entire country. According to research, such moments in a penalty shootout may lead to footballers experiencing symptoms of anxiety. Some commonly occurring symptoms are increases in muscle tension affecting coordination and an increase in heart rate and sweating. Psychologically, anxiety can cause concentration changes such as loss of awareness due to mental tension or poor selective perception. The weakening physiological and attentional changes that occur are the factors that can lead to ‘choking’ in the moment. Imagine your stage fright or nervousness in a new social situation and multiply that by a hundred and maybe then you'll begin to fathom the mental state of a person in such a situation.&amp;nbsp; Rashford faced a deluge of slander on his Instagram and people went so far ahead as to even destroy his mural in his own home country, a country wherein he excelled not just in football but even outside the field. This is a man who has done so much good for society and even received The Most Excellent Order of the British Empire award for his efforts to tackle food poverty among vulnerable children, especially during the pandemic.&amp;nbsp; Not that it matters that he did all of this, even if he hadn’t, there is no cop-out for the abuse. But this is to say how racial abuse still affects one’s life. Wherever you reach, however much you do, the so-called ‘privileged’ race, class, or gender will always find ways to bring you down. The xenophobic and rowdy behaviour of the English fans was abhorrent in ways ineffable. Even though these racist remarks were received with intolerance and chide from many people across the world, who stood with these players through staunch social media support and protests near Rashford’s mural, we are still far from the response these players and many others deserve from the world football community and association. This is just one case that came to light because of the enormity of the game's scale, but such petty racism is still prevalent in every corner of this world's football fields. To not let another Rashford, Saka or Sancho feel this disparaged and harassed, the world needs to put their foot down and refuse to tolerate such immature cowards in the guise of bullies.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What’s at the End of a Rainbow? A Gold Pot</title>
      <link href="/What-s-at-the-End-of-a-Rainbow" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What's at the End of a Rainbow? A Gold Pot" />
      <published>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/What-s-at-the-End-of-a-Rainbow</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-s-at-the-End-of-a-Rainbow">&lt;p&gt;The month of June is coloured with colours of solidarity, determination and struggles of the LGBTQ+ community. Pride month is and was, indeed, a month full of people taking &lt;em&gt;pride &lt;/em&gt;in who they are and pride parades are a sight to behold. However, this article is not a fairytale painting a happy picture of the month but rather explores its dark side, i.e. rainbow washing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would scroll through the LinkedIn profiles of a big, or as a matter-of-fact, any company during the month of June, it would not be hard to notice that most of them have rainbows slapped on their logos. Isn't it something to be happy about? After all, this is a sign of increasing acceptance of the LGBTQ+ community by society. If the previous two sentences outlined your thought process, then it reinforces the importance of awareness about rainbow washing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before starting with rainbow washing, it is important to understand another terminology associated with it that is 'pink money'. Pink money refers to the purchasing power of LGBTQ+ community. The 'pink' here is a reference to the pink triangle which was used as a badge in Nazi concentration camps to identify homosexuals. When the gay rights community became active it took it as a symbol to identify their movement and till date it serves as a strong symbol of their struggles. According to the sources, the LGBT population accounts for 5-10% of the total population. If it were a country, the community could claim to have the fourth-largest GDP in the world, estimated at $4.6 trillion. Now, a lot of corporations can and do go out of their way to monetise this 'pink money'. Here's where rainbow washing comes into the picture.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rainbow washing refers to the practice of supporting LGBTQ issues in public to gather an audience while having private policies that are detrimental for them. To put it in simple words, corporations put rainbows on their logos, products and icons to tap the LGBTQ+ markets. Though when it comes to issues such as recruiting and helping them concretely, the companies back out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A survey found that about 50% of people belonging to this group believed being out at work would end up hurting their careers. During pride month, this year, Lego launched its special series titled 'Everybody is awesome' adorned in rainbow colours and priced it at $30, with it being a limited edition. Most other big brands such as Apple came up with products specifically targeted towards this segment intending to donate the proceeds generated through these sales towards organisations working for the betterment of the community. However, the past records tell a different story. A large part of this revenue is never actually spent on the betterment of the community.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rainbow washing may seem like a pretty marketing tactic or a petty issue but it has a lot of detrimental effects on the existence of pride. The commodification and monetisation of an event like pride end up demeaning the struggles and identity of the community celebrating it. As opposed to being a month of acceptance and love, pride turns into a month of closing business deals and getting traction for your product. A majority of people from the community said that rainbow washing made them feel uncomfortable about their identity. The fact that their coming out or acceptance is being reduced to a marketing tactic makes them feel used.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If business conglomerates actually want to support the cause and fight for the community, they should indeed open up employment opportunities or destigmatize the talk around LGBTQ+ issues. Most of them are just trying to tap into the 'pink money' while the people are left behind. Their economic condition is not robust and at a lot of places, they are not even allowed to enter a shop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, looking at the flip side of rainbow washing, the symbolism has helped spread awareness about the issue in the marginalised or backward communities. The advertisements during pride month do provide a lot of opportunities to the people of the community. Although again, the phenomenon is not year-round. Hence, the opportunities end up being more like a company-influencer relationship rather than being a company-employee relationship. As soon as the pride month starts coming to an end, the support and charisma behind these rainbow coloured logos starts fading and so does the love and acceptance bestowed upon the community by the corporates. Life for them returns to normalcy with all its struggles and rocky roads, and the community for them seems long forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shiksha Mody</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The month of June is coloured with colours of solidarity, determination and struggles of the LGBTQ+ community. Pride month is and was, indeed, a month full of people taking pride in who they are and pride parades are a sight to behold. However, this article is not a fairytale painting a happy picture of the month but rather explores its dark side, i.e. rainbow washing. If you would scroll through the LinkedIn profiles of a big, or as a matter-of-fact, any company during the month of June, it would not be hard to notice that most of them have rainbows slapped on their logos. Isn't it something to be happy about? After all, this is a sign of increasing acceptance of the LGBTQ+ community by society. If the previous two sentences outlined your thought process, then it reinforces the importance of awareness about rainbow washing. Before starting with rainbow washing, it is important to understand another terminology associated with it that is 'pink money'. Pink money refers to the purchasing power of LGBTQ+ community. The 'pink' here is a reference to the pink triangle which was used as a badge in Nazi concentration camps to identify homosexuals. When the gay rights community became active it took it as a symbol to identify their movement and till date it serves as a strong symbol of their struggles. According to the sources, the LGBT population accounts for 5-10% of the total population. If it were a country, the community could claim to have the fourth-largest GDP in the world, estimated at $4.6 trillion. Now, a lot of corporations can and do go out of their way to monetise this 'pink money'. Here's where rainbow washing comes into the picture.&amp;nbsp; Rainbow washing refers to the practice of supporting LGBTQ issues in public to gather an audience while having private policies that are detrimental for them. To put it in simple words, corporations put rainbows on their logos, products and icons to tap the LGBTQ+ markets. Though when it comes to issues such as recruiting and helping them concretely, the companies back out. A survey found that about 50% of people belonging to this group believed being out at work would end up hurting their careers. During pride month, this year, Lego launched its special series titled 'Everybody is awesome' adorned in rainbow colours and priced it at $30, with it being a limited edition. Most other big brands such as Apple came up with products specifically targeted towards this segment intending to donate the proceeds generated through these sales towards organisations working for the betterment of the community. However, the past records tell a different story. A large part of this revenue is never actually spent on the betterment of the community.&amp;nbsp; Rainbow washing may seem like a pretty marketing tactic or a petty issue but it has a lot of detrimental effects on the existence of pride. The commodification and monetisation of an event like pride end up demeaning the struggles and identity of the community celebrating it. As opposed to being a month of acceptance and love, pride turns into a month of closing business deals and getting traction for your product. A majority of people from the community said that rainbow washing made them feel uncomfortable about their identity. The fact that their coming out or acceptance is being reduced to a marketing tactic makes them feel used.&amp;nbsp; If business conglomerates actually want to support the cause and fight for the community, they should indeed open up employment opportunities or destigmatize the talk around LGBTQ+ issues. Most of them are just trying to tap into the 'pink money' while the people are left behind. Their economic condition is not robust and at a lot of places, they are not even allowed to enter a shop. However, looking at the flip side of rainbow washing, the symbolism has helped spread awareness about the issue in the marginalised or backward communities. The advertisements during pride month do provide a lot of opportunities to the people of the community. Although again, the phenomenon is not year-round. Hence, the opportunities end up being more like a company-influencer relationship rather than being a company-employee relationship. As soon as the pride month starts coming to an end, the support and charisma behind these rainbow coloured logos starts fading and so does the love and acceptance bestowed upon the community by the corporates. Life for them returns to normalcy with all its struggles and rocky roads, and the community for them seems long forgotten.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Not Tying the Knot in Korea</title>
      <link href="/Not-Tying-the-Knot-in-Korea" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Not Tying the Knot in Korea" />
      <published>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Not-Tying-the-Knot-in-Korea</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Not-Tying-the-Knot-in-Korea">&lt;p&gt;Korea's value for marriage can be recognised from the popular saying: &quot;&lt;em&gt;A person becomes an adult only after marriage&lt;/em&gt;&quot;&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; which is broadly used in the country. This reveals that the culture often sees being married as the equivalent of being an adult. Moreover, there is the obvious influence of Confucianism in South Korea which considers marriage to be essential for maintaining bloodlines.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The&amp;nbsp;Sampo&amp;nbsp;Generation (&amp;nbsp;삼포세대 ) however, disagrees.&amp;nbsp;Sampo&amp;nbsp;Generation, which literally translates to 'giving up on three, generation' is the younger generation of the country who are giving up on dating, marriage and having children. If we look at the statistics over the last three decades (1981-2011), the average age of marriage for South Korean women has increased by six years (23.0 to 29.1), a year more than it has for men (26.4 to 31.9). Furthermore, there has also been a drastic increase in single households (9% in 1990 to 26% in 2013). What are the factors that have led to such an increase?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Korea, as a society,&amp;nbsp;stereotypically&amp;nbsp;preferred sons to daughters. While daughters were prepared for their future roles as mothers and wives, education for women was not thought to be as important as it was for men. However, there were also social groups like the&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Gisaeng&lt;/em&gt;s.&amp;nbsp;The &lt;em&gt;Gisaeng&lt;/em&gt;s first appeared in the&amp;nbsp;Goryeo&amp;nbsp;Dynasty (918-1392) and were often historically misrepresented to be only entertainers for the rich and upper class, but, in actuality, they were intelligent and extraordinarily skilled women, who can be compared to today's professionally-trained and educated women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women, after first democratic Korea was established, got increased opportunities to pursue education and engage in other economic activities. Now women are successful in every field: from business to law, and from science to architecture. But successful careers could also entail increased working hours. According to a report by OECD, on average, a South Korean person works about 38.9 hours a week, ranking the nation third among 37 countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increased working hours lead to disinterest in dating or the inability to maintain existing relationships. A successful position in any industry for a woman comes with the fear of having to abandon it after her marriage. Marriage would mean the addition of another family (her in-laws) and the pressure of having a baby. Even if a working female decides to have a baby after her marriage, she would have to be away from her job for a while, which in turn would be a threat to the position she holds at her workplace. The work culture is very competitive in Korea and you can easily find replacements for any position. For a man to replace a woman is even easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marriage is not a union between two individuals but two families. This is even more appropriate for East Asian cultures, where, from marriage to childbearing, everything is linked. For a society bearing such thinking, it is only natural for a girl's parents to find an ideal groom for their daughter. An ideal son-in-law would be someone who can provide their daughter emotional and financial support.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many women in Korea would not marry the man of their choice if their parents do not approve of him. Even if she decides to marry the guy her parents have chosen for her, she would still have to rely on her parents' financial help as marriages in Korea are very expensive. According to&amp;nbsp;Statista, in 2018 an average Korean wedding cost around 230 million Korean Won which includes&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Yedam&lt;/em&gt;, the gifts given to the groom's family. In a country where marriage comes with such a cost, it is only natural that a 21st-century South Korean woman finds having enough money in her bank account to own an apartment in&amp;nbsp;Gangnam&amp;nbsp;to be more attractive than getting married, even if it means that she has to work a few extra hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, with the growing popularity of Korean dramas which portray getting married to an older woman to be desirable, it is seen that the female population, when it does tie the knot, is also inclining towards getting married to men who are younger by five years and sometimes even ten years. This has led to increased growth in the number of remarriages, even though Korea's culture does not&amp;nbsp;favour&amp;nbsp;remarriage. In fact, given the increasing popularity of marriages with older women, changing trends can be seen with the subtle possibility of a matriarchy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But all of this comes with a cost. Fertility in Korea has become not only an issue that concerns the people of the country but is also often talked about by various international news outlets. South Korea is known to have one of the lowest fertility rates in the world. The World Bank reports that women in South Korea have 1.2 children per capita (global average being 2.5 children). The problem, however, multiplies with the rapidly ageing population. The declining popularity of marriage among women has led to lessening birth rates in the country which indicates that there aren't enough babies being born to replace the older generations. This entails a high possibility of population decline. In fact, the UN reports that, by 2100, South Korea's population would reach as low as 29 million which is the same as the country's population in 1966.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;South Korea has been one of the flag bearers when it comes to exemplifying ideal romantic relationships to the consumers of television dramas but the reality is a bit different.&amp;nbsp;The&amp;nbsp;government's effort to popularise dating and marriage to defend the country from a possible population decline includes introducing schemes and policies like providing one-off payment for each baby born to cover parental costs to turning off the Ministry of Health and Family Affairs' lights at 7 pm, once a month, with the hope that their employees would not be too tired to date and even have babies!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dristi Das is a student at the University of Delhi, who is pursuing her Bachelor's degree in Philosophy. Her field of interest is East Asian culture and she likes reading and researching on the same.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Guest</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Korea's value for marriage can be recognised from the popular saying: &quot;A person becomes an adult only after marriage&quot;, which is broadly used in the country. This reveals that the culture often sees being married as the equivalent of being an adult. Moreover, there is the obvious influence of Confucianism in South Korea which considers marriage to be essential for maintaining bloodlines.&amp;nbsp; The&amp;nbsp;Sampo&amp;nbsp;Generation (&amp;nbsp;삼포세대 ) however, disagrees.&amp;nbsp;Sampo&amp;nbsp;Generation, which literally translates to 'giving up on three, generation' is the younger generation of the country who are giving up on dating, marriage and having children. If we look at the statistics over the last three decades (1981-2011), the average age of marriage for South Korean women has increased by six years (23.0 to 29.1), a year more than it has for men (26.4 to 31.9). Furthermore, there has also been a drastic increase in single households (9% in 1990 to 26% in 2013). What are the factors that have led to such an increase? Korea, as a society,&amp;nbsp;stereotypically&amp;nbsp;preferred sons to daughters. While daughters were prepared for their future roles as mothers and wives, education for women was not thought to be as important as it was for men. However, there were also social groups like the&amp;nbsp;Gisaengs.&amp;nbsp;The Gisaengs first appeared in the&amp;nbsp;Goryeo&amp;nbsp;Dynasty (918-1392) and were often historically misrepresented to be only entertainers for the rich and upper class, but, in actuality, they were intelligent and extraordinarily skilled women, who can be compared to today's professionally-trained and educated women. Women, after first democratic Korea was established, got increased opportunities to pursue education and engage in other economic activities. Now women are successful in every field: from business to law, and from science to architecture. But successful careers could also entail increased working hours. According to a report by OECD, on average, a South Korean person works about 38.9 hours a week, ranking the nation third among 37 countries.&amp;nbsp; Increased working hours lead to disinterest in dating or the inability to maintain existing relationships. A successful position in any industry for a woman comes with the fear of having to abandon it after her marriage. Marriage would mean the addition of another family (her in-laws) and the pressure of having a baby. Even if a working female decides to have a baby after her marriage, she would have to be away from her job for a while, which in turn would be a threat to the position she holds at her workplace. The work culture is very competitive in Korea and you can easily find replacements for any position. For a man to replace a woman is even easier. Marriage is not a union between two individuals but two families. This is even more appropriate for East Asian cultures, where, from marriage to childbearing, everything is linked. For a society bearing such thinking, it is only natural for a girl's parents to find an ideal groom for their daughter. An ideal son-in-law would be someone who can provide their daughter emotional and financial support.&amp;nbsp; Many women in Korea would not marry the man of their choice if their parents do not approve of him. Even if she decides to marry the guy her parents have chosen for her, she would still have to rely on her parents' financial help as marriages in Korea are very expensive. According to&amp;nbsp;Statista, in 2018 an average Korean wedding cost around 230 million Korean Won which includes&amp;nbsp;Yedam, the gifts given to the groom's family. In a country where marriage comes with such a cost, it is only natural that a 21st-century South Korean woman finds having enough money in her bank account to own an apartment in&amp;nbsp;Gangnam&amp;nbsp;to be more attractive than getting married, even if it means that she has to work a few extra hours. Interestingly, with the growing popularity of Korean dramas which portray getting married to an older woman to be desirable, it is seen that the female population, when it does tie the knot, is also inclining towards getting married to men who are younger by five years and sometimes even ten years. This has led to increased growth in the number of remarriages, even though Korea's culture does not&amp;nbsp;favour&amp;nbsp;remarriage. In fact, given the increasing popularity of marriages with older women, changing trends can be seen with the subtle possibility of a matriarchy. But all of this comes with a cost. Fertility in Korea has become not only an issue that concerns the people of the country but is also often talked about by various international news outlets. South Korea is known to have one of the lowest fertility rates in the world. The World Bank reports that women in South Korea have 1.2 children per capita (global average being 2.5 children). The problem, however, multiplies with the rapidly ageing population. The declining popularity of marriage among women has led to lessening birth rates in the country which indicates that there aren't enough babies being born to replace the older generations. This entails a high possibility of population decline. In fact, the UN reports that, by 2100, South Korea's population would reach as low as 29 million which is the same as the country's population in 1966. South Korea has been one of the flag bearers when it comes to exemplifying ideal romantic relationships to the consumers of television dramas but the reality is a bit different.&amp;nbsp;The&amp;nbsp;government's effort to popularise dating and marriage to defend the country from a possible population decline includes introducing schemes and policies like providing one-off payment for each baby born to cover parental costs to turning off the Ministry of Health and Family Affairs' lights at 7 pm, once a month, with the hope that their employees would not be too tired to date and even have babies! Dristi Das is a student at the University of Delhi, who is pursuing her Bachelor's degree in Philosophy. Her field of interest is East Asian culture and she likes reading and researching on the same.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Millennial Bermuda Triangle</title>
      <link href="/The-Millennial-Bermuda-Triangle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Millennial Bermuda Triangle" />
      <published>2021-06-13T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Millennial-Bermuda-Triangle</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Millennial-Bermuda-Triangle">&lt;p&gt;The Bermuda Triangle is an unreal patch of sea in the Atlantic Ocean which is infamous for the disappearance of thousands of ships, cargo and airplanes in its vicinity. While there has been a lot of speculation about the reasons for such disappearances, there has been no consensus on one single theory to explain these mysterious occurrences. People have proposed theories from the triangle being an alleged home of aliens to mysterious creatures residing there and engulfing the ships that go that way.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I will not decipher the fundamental reasons behind these disappearances in this article, I will outline the aspects of another Bermuda Triangle that almost all of us have sailed through. While some of us could cross it successfully, some lost a part of themselves there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man is a social animal. As Darwin said, &lt;em&gt;&quot;Society is something that precedes an individual&quot;&lt;/em&gt;. Thus, the need to belong is intuitive. This fact that ‘belongingness is a need’ means that it is imperative for humans to maintain and establish some relationships. This theory has been explored by various psychologists including Freud and Maslow. Abraham Maslow placed belongingness in the needs hierarchy between physical needs and the need for self-esteem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media, the technology-enabled communication systems, have drastically altered the way we perceive ourselves as belonging in society. Social media is more about psychology and community rather than technology.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a student who has just joined university amidst the COVID scenario, there's one thing I could definitely say- social media has had a lot of effect on my perceptions of myself. With the onset of university, there is one more social media that is added to your list apart from the usual networking sites, i.e. LinkedIn. When you start networking here, all of you would come across profiles that are absolute gold. With this facade that social media and networking sites create, they inadvertently point towards a better and happy life that is being led by people behind these profiles. Competition and comparison is inevitable. However, these personas are also attached to a false sense of belonging. People who are passive consumers on these sites suffer from greater levels of social loneliness and feelings of ostracism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two studies conducted in this domain brought out the effect of social media consumption on the self esteem of the passive users. In the first one, some Facebook users were divided into two groups. One group was asked to post as usual over the study period, while the other group was instructed not to post during the same period. All participants could log in to Facebook and read posts, but only the first group was allowed to make public posts or respond to other people’s posts. After the lapse of the time of study it was found that the second group reported lower levels of “belonging” and “meaningful existence” than those in the first group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of the second study were even more astonishing and clearly depicted the role that social validation plays in our life. In the second study by the team, participants were asked to make a status update on a Facebook account set up by these researchers. However, the researchers had conditioned the experiment so that only half of them would receive a response on the update. Participants who received no feedback reported lower levels of belonging, self-esteem, meaningful activity than the ones who did receive feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Existentialism is a philosophical concept which deals with answering major life questions such as &quot;who am I?&quot; and underlining the major purpose behind one's existence. All of us face existential crises at some point of time in our life but social media just seems to have accelerated the process. Whenever something happens, we are more concerned about posting it and seeking others' opinions. We are not concerned about our perceptions but want others to hold a mirror for ourselves and ultimately their ideologies become our perceptions. The 'I' in the &quot;Who am I?&quot; is lost forever.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media presents a very skewed image of a person's life. Instead of portraying what your actual life is, you portray the kind of life you want others to see. This alone can create emptiness and push someone into an existential crisis. But there's more to it. Even your friends are doing the same thing. They’re posting selfies and bits of their life outlining the fabulous things they’re doing with their lives. And when you compare these things to your own relatively bleak existence, the cumulative effects lead to depression, anxiety and existential dread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The situation has been further aggravated with the advent of COVID-19. With everybody locked inside their homes, there is no other way to stay connected other than on these sites. The biased and tainted information that we receive through these social media handles have been responsible for worsening our mental health and psychological distress during this pandemic. With each passing day, the information makes you ruminate a little more till you have nothing but emptiness. In a study it was found that US college students are on their smartphones around nine hours a day. Further, coincidentally, anxiety in young people is alarmingly high.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As humans we cannot fight the need to fit in or the need for acceptance. Caught in the rising waves of this bermuda triangle and driven by the endless rat race, a lot of us forget what it's like to be ourselves. The mask of social media productivity and LinkedIn badges take away the little joys. Bruises on our bodies are visible but the bruises on someone's self image are never seen. However, there's one thing that makes you sail through these storms and that's faith. The curated world of social media is not even half of the truth. The struggles and downfalls behind those glittering profiles are silent. So, give yourself a daily reminder to take some time off this world. Prepare yourself to walk endlessly and no matter how cliché it may sound, we all should keep faith that it will all make sense one day.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>vanshika.singh shiksha.mody</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Bermuda Triangle is an unreal patch of sea in the Atlantic Ocean which is infamous for the disappearance of thousands of ships, cargo and airplanes in its vicinity. While there has been a lot of speculation about the reasons for such disappearances, there has been no consensus on one single theory to explain these mysterious occurrences. People have proposed theories from the triangle being an alleged home of aliens to mysterious creatures residing there and engulfing the ships that go that way.&amp;nbsp; Though I will not decipher the fundamental reasons behind these disappearances in this article, I will outline the aspects of another Bermuda Triangle that almost all of us have sailed through. While some of us could cross it successfully, some lost a part of themselves there. Man is a social animal. As Darwin said, &quot;Society is something that precedes an individual&quot;. Thus, the need to belong is intuitive. This fact that ‘belongingness is a need’ means that it is imperative for humans to maintain and establish some relationships. This theory has been explored by various psychologists including Freud and Maslow. Abraham Maslow placed belongingness in the needs hierarchy between physical needs and the need for self-esteem. Social media, the technology-enabled communication systems, have drastically altered the way we perceive ourselves as belonging in society. Social media is more about psychology and community rather than technology.&amp;nbsp; As a student who has just joined university amidst the COVID scenario, there's one thing I could definitely say- social media has had a lot of effect on my perceptions of myself. With the onset of university, there is one more social media that is added to your list apart from the usual networking sites, i.e. LinkedIn. When you start networking here, all of you would come across profiles that are absolute gold. With this facade that social media and networking sites create, they inadvertently point towards a better and happy life that is being led by people behind these profiles. Competition and comparison is inevitable. However, these personas are also attached to a false sense of belonging. People who are passive consumers on these sites suffer from greater levels of social loneliness and feelings of ostracism. Two studies conducted in this domain brought out the effect of social media consumption on the self esteem of the passive users. In the first one, some Facebook users were divided into two groups. One group was asked to post as usual over the study period, while the other group was instructed not to post during the same period. All participants could log in to Facebook and read posts, but only the first group was allowed to make public posts or respond to other people’s posts. After the lapse of the time of study it was found that the second group reported lower levels of “belonging” and “meaningful existence” than those in the first group. The results of the second study were even more astonishing and clearly depicted the role that social validation plays in our life. In the second study by the team, participants were asked to make a status update on a Facebook account set up by these researchers. However, the researchers had conditioned the experiment so that only half of them would receive a response on the update. Participants who received no feedback reported lower levels of belonging, self-esteem, meaningful activity than the ones who did receive feedback. Existentialism is a philosophical concept which deals with answering major life questions such as &quot;who am I?&quot; and underlining the major purpose behind one's existence. All of us face existential crises at some point of time in our life but social media just seems to have accelerated the process. Whenever something happens, we are more concerned about posting it and seeking others' opinions. We are not concerned about our perceptions but want others to hold a mirror for ourselves and ultimately their ideologies become our perceptions. The 'I' in the &quot;Who am I?&quot; is lost forever.&amp;nbsp; Social media presents a very skewed image of a person's life. Instead of portraying what your actual life is, you portray the kind of life you want others to see. This alone can create emptiness and push someone into an existential crisis. But there's more to it. Even your friends are doing the same thing. They’re posting selfies and bits of their life outlining the fabulous things they’re doing with their lives. And when you compare these things to your own relatively bleak existence, the cumulative effects lead to depression, anxiety and existential dread. The situation has been further aggravated with the advent of COVID-19. With everybody locked inside their homes, there is no other way to stay connected other than on these sites. The biased and tainted information that we receive through these social media handles have been responsible for worsening our mental health and psychological distress during this pandemic. With each passing day, the information makes you ruminate a little more till you have nothing but emptiness. In a study it was found that US college students are on their smartphones around nine hours a day. Further, coincidentally, anxiety in young people is alarmingly high.&amp;nbsp; As humans we cannot fight the need to fit in or the need for acceptance. Caught in the rising waves of this bermuda triangle and driven by the endless rat race, a lot of us forget what it's like to be ourselves. The mask of social media productivity and LinkedIn badges take away the little joys. Bruises on our bodies are visible but the bruises on someone's self image are never seen. However, there's one thing that makes you sail through these storms and that's faith. The curated world of social media is not even half of the truth. The struggles and downfalls behind those glittering profiles are silent. So, give yourself a daily reminder to take some time off this world. Prepare yourself to walk endlessly and no matter how cliché it may sound, we all should keep faith that it will all make sense one day.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Work Hard, Pay Hard</title>
      <link href="/Work-Hard-Pay-Hard" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Work Hard, Pay Hard" />
      <published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Work-Hard-Pay-Hard</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Work-Hard-Pay-Hard">&lt;p&gt;On my way to university, I heard two women chatting beside me on the train and I couldn't help but eavesdrop at the horrors exchanged in their dialogue. They were engrossed in discussing or rather denouncing the daughter-in-law of one of their acquaintances for her values and time devoted to her family. From what I heard, they believed that she doesn't contribute much to the household chores as she continues to work after marriage (a heinous crime apparently) and comes home late. One of them said that this is bound to happen when women study too much.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This made me spiral into thinking about what most women, both married or unmarried, but mostly married, living with huge families and kids go through. They work from 9-5 or more I assume, complete their chores, handle their kids and still are not compensated enough for the same, be it the remuneration at their jobs in terms of money or the healthcare and safety provisions, and, on top of that, they are conveniently expected to undertake relentless unpaid work at home.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after all the effort that women put in every sphere of life, they still earn less respect and salary than their male counterparts for the same job, irrespective of their qualification and experience, contingent merely on their gender. &lt;em&gt;Because women are child-bearers and menstruators who expect the bare minimum of maternity and period leaves as an employee. Because women can't lead teams as capably as their male counterparts, since they aren't dominant by birth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This led me to realise that the gender-pay-gap is one of the most exploitative and discriminative features of our economic systems staring us in the face. One would expect a better system of rewards based on one’s merit and calibre, but even in the 21st century only six countries in the world, namely, Belgium, Denmark, France, Latvia, Luxembourg and Sweden grant men and women equal legal work rights, which is a concept as old as only a decade, according to a report by &lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even so, bringing about legal changes does not translate into effective actions. In Sweden, women still earn about 5% less than their male counterparts and, globally, women earn 79 cents for every dollar paid to a man - which might not sound like a huge gap in theory but again, this is just a statistic which might not even reflect the actual situation flailing about in our system. It might not even consider the many women who are employed in the informal sectors of developing countries or are labouring away in the agricultural-sector without reaping any significant benefits out of it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wage gap exists for women of all educational backgrounds - from high school graduates to women with advanced degrees. According to a report by the Economic Policy Institute, this gap ranges from three dollars for women having an education level of less than high school to twelve dollars for women with advanced degrees. This is the opposite of what one would expect and a strong argument against how gender-wage-gap stems from the lower education levels of women. The gap only widens as the level of education increases, which is testament to the fact that the more literate and intelligent the woman, the more of a threat she is made out to be.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this bias is not limited to merely the pecuniary aspect of the work culture; it is deeply embedded in how women are treated in offices, always put on a rung lower than men, listened to but never heard or appreciated. From bearing the ‘motherhood penalty’ to being biologically ‘complicated’, women around the world are stifled at every step of their way to success. A recent American study deduced the average by which women’s future wages fall—at 4% per child, and 10% for the highest-earning, most skilled white women.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women are considered assets as long as they do not ask for anything that lies outside the zone of anyone's convenience - be it providing maternity leaves or transportation for late work hours. And are also looked at like a nuisance for any lawsuits and uncomfortable conversations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the famous #MeToo movement, many companies and men in position suggested that hiring a woman nowadays can prove to be a risky investment because everything these days leads to lawsuits. Blaming the MeToo movement, many men claim that they are afraid to be alone with women in the workspace or hesitant to be around in their close vicinity - which is a complete rationalisation of the actions that are not okay in any workspace. And these men flagrantly choose to ignore that the issue doesn’t lie in women’s capability to live by the rules created by men but in men’s inability to treat them like human beings with boundaries that are to be respected.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zomato, a food-delivery service was one of the first major-league companies in India to grant paid period leaves - an action heavily slated by men. Even so, only bringing a policy in place doesn't seem enough to provoke a change because most women might be hesitant to take those leaves due to the pronounced stigma around menstruation and being considered weak and fragile for going through with it. Menstruation is not given enough medical importance, contingent on how potent its symptoms can be- from nausea and backache to stomach cramps that can invalidate any healthy and strong person. The hope is that with policies like these there is wider acceptance towards the gravity of this issue without it being used as a pretext for inequality or inferiority in the workplace.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though women are more substantially employed now, occupying more positions in the workspace than before especially in developed countries, the proportion of women in managerial and top executive positions still remains abysmally low and according to the Enterprise Survey by the World Bank, only 18% of businesses had a female CEO. On the other hand in legislatures, the proportion of women is approximately 24%. Women, in their entirety, comprise less than one-fourth of the major domains of the working world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue is not just gender-based discrimination but also discrimination against occupations that are majorly dominated by women. Professions of nurses, teachers, secretaries, child-care workers are found to be respected less and paid less too. According to a report by &lt;em&gt;The Economist&lt;/em&gt;, Primary teachers in the OECD countries earn 81% of the average for graduate jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This issue leads to a polarity in the jobs pursued by men and women and thus demotivates and intimidates women to take up jobs in the field of law and litigation, engineering and the police force. It is found that only 3.5% of women are firefighters, which is one of the most heavily male-dominated industries next to male technicians and mechanics who dominate 99.19% of the industry. Even something as universal as religion is dominated by men, according to &lt;em&gt;the Insider&lt;/em&gt;, only 17.6% of the clergy is female. And I am pretty sure this is not pertinent only to America but most of the world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, an important solution to gender-wage-gap is the migration of genders from female-dominated sectors to the male-dominated sectors and vice-versa. As important as it is for women to pursue fields that are considered too ambitious for them, it is equally imperative for men to be accepted in industries that are primarily governed by women. It is also important for the parental-care axle to shift from mothers, who drop out of the workforce or shift to less-intensive jobs to take care of their children to fathers, with a higher emphasis on the implementation of paternity leaves.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While discussing gender-based discrimination, to not consider the prejudice faced by trans people and other non-binary genders in the workplace would be unjust to the cause of equal wages for all. Trans people have even lesser representation and provisions to fall back on than women in the workplace and face persistent abuse and hiring-discrimination throughout the world, but more so in third-world and developing countries. Let alone provisions in the workplace, third-world countries like Kenya, Uganda, Senegal and Haiti do not even have basic anti-discriminatory laws for trans people. The transgender social acceptance rate, according to a report by Kimberly Tower is -2 whereas, in countries like India, Nepal and Argentina, it is positive yet wretchedly low, that is, 3, 2 and 1.5 respectively. Thus, there is still a long way to go for other genders to have equal remuneration and dignity as our &lt;em&gt;patriarchal lords&lt;/em&gt; in the workplace.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These statistics and facts only substantiate the actuality of domination of men in most sectors of the world, which leads to the gender-wage-gap. This majority that men enjoy in legislation, business or the sciences, is what propagates ideas, policies and products fabricated by men, which more often than not are not gender-friendly. Representation is salient as it leads to better targeted economic and social policies which will help bridge this widening gap and actualise acceptance - thus ameliorating the social and economic status of minority genders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On my way to university, I heard two women chatting beside me on the train and I couldn't help but eavesdrop at the horrors exchanged in their dialogue. They were engrossed in discussing or rather denouncing the daughter-in-law of one of their acquaintances for her values and time devoted to her family. From what I heard, they believed that she doesn't contribute much to the household chores as she continues to work after marriage (a heinous crime apparently) and comes home late. One of them said that this is bound to happen when women study too much.&amp;nbsp; This made me spiral into thinking about what most women, both married or unmarried, but mostly married, living with huge families and kids go through. They work from 9-5 or more I assume, complete their chores, handle their kids and still are not compensated enough for the same, be it the remuneration at their jobs in terms of money or the healthcare and safety provisions, and, on top of that, they are conveniently expected to undertake relentless unpaid work at home.&amp;nbsp; Even after all the effort that women put in every sphere of life, they still earn less respect and salary than their male counterparts for the same job, irrespective of their qualification and experience, contingent merely on their gender. Because women are child-bearers and menstruators who expect the bare minimum of maternity and period leaves as an employee. Because women can't lead teams as capably as their male counterparts, since they aren't dominant by birth.&amp;nbsp; This led me to realise that the gender-pay-gap is one of the most exploitative and discriminative features of our economic systems staring us in the face. One would expect a better system of rewards based on one’s merit and calibre, but even in the 21st century only six countries in the world, namely, Belgium, Denmark, France, Latvia, Luxembourg and Sweden grant men and women equal legal work rights, which is a concept as old as only a decade, according to a report by The Guardian.&amp;nbsp; Even so, bringing about legal changes does not translate into effective actions. In Sweden, women still earn about 5% less than their male counterparts and, globally, women earn 79 cents for every dollar paid to a man - which might not sound like a huge gap in theory but again, this is just a statistic which might not even reflect the actual situation flailing about in our system. It might not even consider the many women who are employed in the informal sectors of developing countries or are labouring away in the agricultural-sector without reaping any significant benefits out of it.&amp;nbsp; The wage gap exists for women of all educational backgrounds - from high school graduates to women with advanced degrees. According to a report by the Economic Policy Institute, this gap ranges from three dollars for women having an education level of less than high school to twelve dollars for women with advanced degrees. This is the opposite of what one would expect and a strong argument against how gender-wage-gap stems from the lower education levels of women. The gap only widens as the level of education increases, which is testament to the fact that the more literate and intelligent the woman, the more of a threat she is made out to be.&amp;nbsp; However, this bias is not limited to merely the pecuniary aspect of the work culture; it is deeply embedded in how women are treated in offices, always put on a rung lower than men, listened to but never heard or appreciated. From bearing the ‘motherhood penalty’ to being biologically ‘complicated’, women around the world are stifled at every step of their way to success. A recent American study deduced the average by which women’s future wages fall—at 4% per child, and 10% for the highest-earning, most skilled white women.&amp;nbsp; Women are considered assets as long as they do not ask for anything that lies outside the zone of anyone's convenience - be it providing maternity leaves or transportation for late work hours. And are also looked at like a nuisance for any lawsuits and uncomfortable conversations.&amp;nbsp; After the famous #MeToo movement, many companies and men in position suggested that hiring a woman nowadays can prove to be a risky investment because everything these days leads to lawsuits. Blaming the MeToo movement, many men claim that they are afraid to be alone with women in the workspace or hesitant to be around in their close vicinity - which is a complete rationalisation of the actions that are not okay in any workspace. And these men flagrantly choose to ignore that the issue doesn’t lie in women’s capability to live by the rules created by men but in men’s inability to treat them like human beings with boundaries that are to be respected.&amp;nbsp; Zomato, a food-delivery service was one of the first major-league companies in India to grant paid period leaves - an action heavily slated by men. Even so, only bringing a policy in place doesn't seem enough to provoke a change because most women might be hesitant to take those leaves due to the pronounced stigma around menstruation and being considered weak and fragile for going through with it. Menstruation is not given enough medical importance, contingent on how potent its symptoms can be- from nausea and backache to stomach cramps that can invalidate any healthy and strong person. The hope is that with policies like these there is wider acceptance towards the gravity of this issue without it being used as a pretext for inequality or inferiority in the workplace.&amp;nbsp; Even though women are more substantially employed now, occupying more positions in the workspace than before especially in developed countries, the proportion of women in managerial and top executive positions still remains abysmally low and according to the Enterprise Survey by the World Bank, only 18% of businesses had a female CEO. On the other hand in legislatures, the proportion of women is approximately 24%. Women, in their entirety, comprise less than one-fourth of the major domains of the working world.&amp;nbsp; The issue is not just gender-based discrimination but also discrimination against occupations that are majorly dominated by women. Professions of nurses, teachers, secretaries, child-care workers are found to be respected less and paid less too. According to a report by The Economist, Primary teachers in the OECD countries earn 81% of the average for graduate jobs. This issue leads to a polarity in the jobs pursued by men and women and thus demotivates and intimidates women to take up jobs in the field of law and litigation, engineering and the police force. It is found that only 3.5% of women are firefighters, which is one of the most heavily male-dominated industries next to male technicians and mechanics who dominate 99.19% of the industry. Even something as universal as religion is dominated by men, according to the Insider, only 17.6% of the clergy is female. And I am pretty sure this is not pertinent only to America but most of the world.&amp;nbsp; Thus, an important solution to gender-wage-gap is the migration of genders from female-dominated sectors to the male-dominated sectors and vice-versa. As important as it is for women to pursue fields that are considered too ambitious for them, it is equally imperative for men to be accepted in industries that are primarily governed by women. It is also important for the parental-care axle to shift from mothers, who drop out of the workforce or shift to less-intensive jobs to take care of their children to fathers, with a higher emphasis on the implementation of paternity leaves.&amp;nbsp; While discussing gender-based discrimination, to not consider the prejudice faced by trans people and other non-binary genders in the workplace would be unjust to the cause of equal wages for all. Trans people have even lesser representation and provisions to fall back on than women in the workplace and face persistent abuse and hiring-discrimination throughout the world, but more so in third-world and developing countries. Let alone provisions in the workplace, third-world countries like Kenya, Uganda, Senegal and Haiti do not even have basic anti-discriminatory laws for trans people. The transgender social acceptance rate, according to a report by Kimberly Tower is -2 whereas, in countries like India, Nepal and Argentina, it is positive yet wretchedly low, that is, 3, 2 and 1.5 respectively. Thus, there is still a long way to go for other genders to have equal remuneration and dignity as our patriarchal lords in the workplace.&amp;nbsp; These statistics and facts only substantiate the actuality of domination of men in most sectors of the world, which leads to the gender-wage-gap. This majority that men enjoy in legislation, business or the sciences, is what propagates ideas, policies and products fabricated by men, which more often than not are not gender-friendly. Representation is salient as it leads to better targeted economic and social policies which will help bridge this widening gap and actualise acceptance - thus ameliorating the social and economic status of minority genders.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Spirit of Brahminism and the Capitalist Reckoning</title>
      <link href="/The-Spirit-of-Brahminism-and-the-Capitalist-Reckoning" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Spirit of Brahminism and the Capitalist Reckoning" />
      <published>2021-04-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-04-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Spirit-of-Brahminism-and-the-Capitalist-Reckoning</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Spirit-of-Brahminism-and-the-Capitalist-Reckoning">&lt;p&gt;The Indian caste system was (or is) a most dehumanising, totalitarian and rigid system of social hierarchy and control. The oldest Hindu religious text, the Rig Veda, in its canto 10, hymn 90 defines how mankind came to be from the different parts of the supreme primordial being. It declares that &lt;em&gt;&quot;The Brahmin was His [i.e. the primordial being's] mouth; the Kshatriya His arms became. His thighs were the Vaisya; of His feet the Sudra was born.&quot;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These four castes: the Brahmins (the priestly and intellectual class), the Kshatriyas (the landowners and warriors), the Vaisya (the business class) and the Sudra (the labourer) represent the idealised division of social groups in the feudal social order of ancient India. The castes do not intermarry, they do not undertake work outside the profession assigned to their caste and the lowest castes and the outcastes are considered 'untouchable'.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One would think that capitalism, as the fundamental counterfoil to a feudal social order, has nothing to do with the caste system or anything like it. After all, capitalism is supposed to be a system in which the invisible hand of the market determines productive activity, rather than a system where a rigid hierarchy dictates social outcome. It is supposed to be based on open competition, where the best product wins, a rational social order, as Max Weber argued, instead of an irrational social order based on blood purity and ancient hymns on a primordial being.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But funny enough, the adaptability of the capitalist mode of production to varied challenges means that capitalism is evolving itself into a social hierarchy that looks very much like the caste system. More specifically, it is evolving to give us a group of people who are verily like the Brahmins of the Hindu social order, the mouths of the primordial being that is Capital.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group I speak of here is quite easily recognisable and thoroughly glamourised (and demonised) in world culture. Their activities are difficult to understand. They deal in items of pure abstraction, building nothing themselves but exercising control over all that is built. They are an exclusive club of people with an iron grip over power and money, whilst not being owners of any of those things themselves. They are the investment bankers, the equity analysts, the financiers and the asset managers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the Brahmin of yore who technically lived on alms but amassed vast wealth, the asset manager and the investment banker only shift wealth around but is rich &quot;via commission motherf*cker&quot; (to quote Matthew McConaughey's character from &lt;em&gt;Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;). Like the Brahmin who would zealously guard his secret knowledge of the sacred mantras and rituals which could make a mere warlord into a king, so does the Wall Street professional speak in the complex technical jargon of 'bonds', 'short-selling', 'derivatives' and 'collateralised debt obligations' which turn a mere productive activity into a sophisticated web of transactions. Like the killing of a Brahmin was the highest crime under ancient Hindu law, so is not bailing out the big banks and financial firms an impossibility.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These parallels are not some mere curiosity, they showcase how capitalism is so eminently adaptable to changing social conditions and how it verily controls the change in material conditions through its social architecture. In fact, this parallel upsets the fundamental assumptions that both pro-capitalist and many anti-capitalist thinkers make. It is not just the chains of economic power which define social relations, it is also the makeup of social relations that determines where economic power resides. The lords of high finance do not derive their power by owning and controlling the means of production. Instead, they define the interrelationships between economic power and those subject to its dominion.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can really appreciate this with a comparative example of the exercise of Brahminical power and the exercise of the power of the financiers. In the ancient Hindu fire rituals called the&lt;em&gt; yagna&lt;/em&gt;, the Brahmin priest would declare the officiator of the ritual as the '&lt;em&gt;yajaman'&lt;/em&gt;, he would make oblations to the various gods in the name of the &lt;em&gt;yajaman&lt;/em&gt;. The fruits of the &lt;em&gt;yagna&lt;/em&gt; would technically be available to the &lt;em&gt;yajaman&lt;/em&gt; alone, for it is his financial resources that make the &lt;em&gt;yagna&lt;/em&gt; possible. The Brahmin is a mere functionary in the entire process. But it is the Brahmin who knows the liturgy, it is the Brahmin who understands the secrets of the various rituals which confer wealth and power. In other words, it is the Brahmin who creates the&lt;em&gt; yajaman&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;yagna.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a similar way, the financier of today creates the capital and the capitalist. It is he who decides if a company can go public, it is he who sells its shares with an asking price and aims to raise capital with it. While the Brahmin made oblations to the gods, as a mere agent of the capitalist, the financier makes his oblations to the market. Technically, the financier is a mere agent. But it is he who knows the viability of the assets of the company, it is he who knows how to appease the market in favour of the capitalist.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as already alluded to, there is a stark difference between the Brahmin and the financiers: while one functions in a mystical social order, the other works in a rationalist one. So the interesting question is: why does this similarity emerge at all? Why is capitalism starting to look like feudalism?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is at once simple and complicated. It resides in that confusing term - 'human nature’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is known that we hunger, not just for food or shelter but also for meaning and security. We are, on some level, aware of our mortality and of how the universe is an uncaring void. At a time when there was no guarantee that the next harvest would give yield when natural disaster and disease could so easily destroy so many lives, the &lt;em&gt;yagna &lt;/em&gt;or the fire rituals gave humanity a sense of security. They made humanity feel a sense of control over its destiny in a fundamentally uncertain time. That is why the Brahmin was given a place of pride and of supreme importance in such an order, for on him rested society's basic sense of peace and order.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the present time, while our fears are not related to the next harvest, our fundamental existential dread remains the same. We do not know what exactly the market will demand next year, we do not know whether the invisible hand will drive prices up or down, whether wages will increase or decrease. Even if our order is rational, our fears of hunger and pain are not, we cannot live with the uncertainty of knowing that a mechanism of market forces will determine our bank balance, especially when the world is buffeted by the COVID-19 pandemic. The financier, by exercising influence and control over the market, gives us certainty. That is why he (or she) has so much power.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To go even deeper, the emergence of late capitalism represents the ultimate reckoning of the Age of Reason with its own assumptions. And the financier in late capitalism, advisedly or inadvertently, represents the reckoner. He confronts humanity with the limitations of his own rationalist systems. Nowhere is this more obvious than in the 2008 crisis. That crisis was, in many ways, completely and utterly the consequence of human beings trying to be too smart for their own good. Bankers so cleverly thought that if debts on homes were combined and converted into their own kind of mega debt, with that mega debt being sold in a market as a good, then money would just flow forever.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mega debts or ‘mortgage-backed securities’ as they were called, were a pure abstraction. They had no existence outside a system of pure formal logic, where obligations to pay back a home loan, which has no palpable existence, could be treated as a commodity and combined and sold as another obligation to pay back a loan, which also had no palpable existence. The real thing, the palpable thing: the home and the homeowner who undertook to pay back the loan was an eminently forgettable assumption in the hyper-rational mind of the financier. Needless to say, the results of this near-mystical, Brahminical rationalism are for all to see and they represent how there is such great folly in assuming that man is a creature of reason.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the ultimate question is: where do we go now? Will this inherent contradiction within capitalism unravel the same? (As Marx suggested) I think not. If the strength of the Brahmanical social order is any guide, a social order, no matter how flawed, no matter how decidedly routed by reality can maintain its spell, for that very weakness called human nature which in its yearning for security would rather believe the immediate lie than imagine a greater truth. So, the only thing that late capitalism and its Brahmin, the financier, tells us that it is here to stay no matter how many crises come and go. Unless, of course, humanity plucks up the courage to say: &quot;creatures of the heart and the flesh unite, we have nothing to lose but our rational brains''.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Indian caste system was (or is) a most dehumanising, totalitarian and rigid system of social hierarchy and control. The oldest Hindu religious text, the Rig Veda, in its canto 10, hymn 90 defines how mankind came to be from the different parts of the supreme primordial being. It declares that &quot;The Brahmin was His [i.e. the primordial being's] mouth; the Kshatriya His arms became. His thighs were the Vaisya; of His feet the Sudra was born.&quot;&amp;nbsp; These four castes: the Brahmins (the priestly and intellectual class), the Kshatriyas (the landowners and warriors), the Vaisya (the business class) and the Sudra (the labourer) represent the idealised division of social groups in the feudal social order of ancient India. The castes do not intermarry, they do not undertake work outside the profession assigned to their caste and the lowest castes and the outcastes are considered 'untouchable'.&amp;nbsp; One would think that capitalism, as the fundamental counterfoil to a feudal social order, has nothing to do with the caste system or anything like it. After all, capitalism is supposed to be a system in which the invisible hand of the market determines productive activity, rather than a system where a rigid hierarchy dictates social outcome. It is supposed to be based on open competition, where the best product wins, a rational social order, as Max Weber argued, instead of an irrational social order based on blood purity and ancient hymns on a primordial being.&amp;nbsp; But funny enough, the adaptability of the capitalist mode of production to varied challenges means that capitalism is evolving itself into a social hierarchy that looks very much like the caste system. More specifically, it is evolving to give us a group of people who are verily like the Brahmins of the Hindu social order, the mouths of the primordial being that is Capital.&amp;nbsp; The group I speak of here is quite easily recognisable and thoroughly glamourised (and demonised) in world culture. Their activities are difficult to understand. They deal in items of pure abstraction, building nothing themselves but exercising control over all that is built. They are an exclusive club of people with an iron grip over power and money, whilst not being owners of any of those things themselves. They are the investment bankers, the equity analysts, the financiers and the asset managers.&amp;nbsp; Like the Brahmin of yore who technically lived on alms but amassed vast wealth, the asset manager and the investment banker only shift wealth around but is rich &quot;via commission motherf*cker&quot; (to quote Matthew McConaughey's character from Wolf of Wall Street). Like the Brahmin who would zealously guard his secret knowledge of the sacred mantras and rituals which could make a mere warlord into a king, so does the Wall Street professional speak in the complex technical jargon of 'bonds', 'short-selling', 'derivatives' and 'collateralised debt obligations' which turn a mere productive activity into a sophisticated web of transactions. Like the killing of a Brahmin was the highest crime under ancient Hindu law, so is not bailing out the big banks and financial firms an impossibility.&amp;nbsp; These parallels are not some mere curiosity, they showcase how capitalism is so eminently adaptable to changing social conditions and how it verily controls the change in material conditions through its social architecture. In fact, this parallel upsets the fundamental assumptions that both pro-capitalist and many anti-capitalist thinkers make. It is not just the chains of economic power which define social relations, it is also the makeup of social relations that determines where economic power resides. The lords of high finance do not derive their power by owning and controlling the means of production. Instead, they define the interrelationships between economic power and those subject to its dominion.&amp;nbsp; We can really appreciate this with a comparative example of the exercise of Brahminical power and the exercise of the power of the financiers. In the ancient Hindu fire rituals called the yagna, the Brahmin priest would declare the officiator of the ritual as the 'yajaman', he would make oblations to the various gods in the name of the yajaman. The fruits of the yagna would technically be available to the yajaman alone, for it is his financial resources that make the yagna possible. The Brahmin is a mere functionary in the entire process. But it is the Brahmin who knows the liturgy, it is the Brahmin who understands the secrets of the various rituals which confer wealth and power. In other words, it is the Brahmin who creates the yajaman and the yagna.&amp;nbsp; In a similar way, the financier of today creates the capital and the capitalist. It is he who decides if a company can go public, it is he who sells its shares with an asking price and aims to raise capital with it. While the Brahmin made oblations to the gods, as a mere agent of the capitalist, the financier makes his oblations to the market. Technically, the financier is a mere agent. But it is he who knows the viability of the assets of the company, it is he who knows how to appease the market in favour of the capitalist.&amp;nbsp; However, as already alluded to, there is a stark difference between the Brahmin and the financiers: while one functions in a mystical social order, the other works in a rationalist one. So the interesting question is: why does this similarity emerge at all? Why is capitalism starting to look like feudalism? The answer is at once simple and complicated. It resides in that confusing term - 'human nature’.&amp;nbsp; It is known that we hunger, not just for food or shelter but also for meaning and security. We are, on some level, aware of our mortality and of how the universe is an uncaring void. At a time when there was no guarantee that the next harvest would give yield when natural disaster and disease could so easily destroy so many lives, the yagna or the fire rituals gave humanity a sense of security. They made humanity feel a sense of control over its destiny in a fundamentally uncertain time. That is why the Brahmin was given a place of pride and of supreme importance in such an order, for on him rested society's basic sense of peace and order.&amp;nbsp; In the present time, while our fears are not related to the next harvest, our fundamental existential dread remains the same. We do not know what exactly the market will demand next year, we do not know whether the invisible hand will drive prices up or down, whether wages will increase or decrease. Even if our order is rational, our fears of hunger and pain are not, we cannot live with the uncertainty of knowing that a mechanism of market forces will determine our bank balance, especially when the world is buffeted by the COVID-19 pandemic. The financier, by exercising influence and control over the market, gives us certainty. That is why he (or she) has so much power.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; To go even deeper, the emergence of late capitalism represents the ultimate reckoning of the Age of Reason with its own assumptions. And the financier in late capitalism, advisedly or inadvertently, represents the reckoner. He confronts humanity with the limitations of his own rationalist systems. Nowhere is this more obvious than in the 2008 crisis. That crisis was, in many ways, completely and utterly the consequence of human beings trying to be too smart for their own good. Bankers so cleverly thought that if debts on homes were combined and converted into their own kind of mega debt, with that mega debt being sold in a market as a good, then money would just flow forever.&amp;nbsp; The mega debts or ‘mortgage-backed securities’ as they were called, were a pure abstraction. They had no existence outside a system of pure formal logic, where obligations to pay back a home loan, which has no palpable existence, could be treated as a commodity and combined and sold as another obligation to pay back a loan, which also had no palpable existence. The real thing, the palpable thing: the home and the homeowner who undertook to pay back the loan was an eminently forgettable assumption in the hyper-rational mind of the financier. Needless to say, the results of this near-mystical, Brahminical rationalism are for all to see and they represent how there is such great folly in assuming that man is a creature of reason.&amp;nbsp; So, the ultimate question is: where do we go now? Will this inherent contradiction within capitalism unravel the same? (As Marx suggested) I think not. If the strength of the Brahmanical social order is any guide, a social order, no matter how flawed, no matter how decidedly routed by reality can maintain its spell, for that very weakness called human nature which in its yearning for security would rather believe the immediate lie than imagine a greater truth. So, the only thing that late capitalism and its Brahmin, the financier, tells us that it is here to stay no matter how many crises come and go. Unless, of course, humanity plucks up the courage to say: &quot;creatures of the heart and the flesh unite, we have nothing to lose but our rational brains''.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Rise of the New Age Nazis</title>
      <link href="/Rise-of-the-New-Age-Nazis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rise of the New Age Nazis" />
      <published>2021-04-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-04-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Rise-of-the-New-Age-Nazis</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Rise-of-the-New-Age-Nazis">&lt;p&gt;On December 14, 2020, the UK Labour party leader Keir Starmer appeared on the radio show LBC with host Nick Ferrari when a caller, introducing herself as ‘Gemma from Cambridge,’ took the opportunity to propagate the Neo-Nazi ‘Great Replacement’ conspiracy theory on a national media platform. She stated: “in the wake of organisations such as BLM and other racial advocacy groups pushing what’s best for their people, I just want to ask, should white people also start playing identity politics now, before they become a minority themselves by 2066?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This bizarre event was made even more bewildering when a Twitter user &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/redflareinfo/status/1338453892661714945&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;revealed&lt;/a&gt; that ‘Gemma from Cambridge’ was in fact Jody Swingler, a yoga teacher and musician living in Ibiza, a far cry from the archetypal image of the hapless neo-nazi social outcast in their parents’ basement, pulling the wings off flies and ranting on obscure online messageboards about how The Jews had prevented them from securing a girlfriend. Swingler had also &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/redflareinfo/status/1338453897258668033&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;recorded&lt;/a&gt; two YouTube shows with Mark Collett and Laura Melia, leaders of the white nationalist political party Patriotic Alternative, which &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hopenothate.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/HnH_Patriotic-Alternative-report_2020-08-v3.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;opposes&lt;/a&gt; the “replacement and displacement” of white Britons by people who “have no right to these lands.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may seem striking that people who advocate new age, spiritual beliefs, previously associated with ‘flower power’ and the countercultural movement of the 1960's, could wind up on the same side as the far right. But in fact, the link between new age spirituality and extremist politics is not new. The Nazis drew support from the occultist Thule Society, and prominent Nazi figures such as Heinrich Himmler and Rudolf Hess endorsed homeopathy and alternative medicine, with Himmler supporting using plant extracts to cure cancer. In 1934, Hess set up an alternative medicine centre in Dresden. Their embrace of holism and spirituality, broadly, was underpinned by a rejection of the precepts of the Enlightenment, which posited that the world could be understood through logical processes, subordinating religious and monarchical obscurantism to the supremacy of the faculty of reason. Many Nazi figures saw a romanticised, agrarian age as a solution to the modern menaces of industrialisation and materialism. For example, Ernst Lehmann, a Nazi professor of botany, stated:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We recognize that separating humanity from nature, from the whole of life, leads to humankind’s own destruction and to the death of nations. Only through a reintegration of humanity into the whole of nature can our people be made stronger… This striving toward connectedness with the totality of life, with nature itself, a nature into which we are born, this is the deepest meaning and the true essence of National Socialist thought.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A desire to undo the crude, materialist logic that undergirded liberal democracy, and to restructure the relationship between the citizen and the State, therefore, spawned the Nazis’ fascination with holism and the reintegration of man with nature. 'Blood and soil' meant an organic connection with one’s homeland that could not be expressed through the civic or legal frameworks engendered by the minority protection clauses of the League of Nations, but only through the maintenance of racial purity. Mark Mazower wrote in his book &lt;em&gt;Dark Continent &lt;/em&gt;that:“The League (of Nations) , after all, was an organisation of States. But what was the State? According to Hitler’s biological view of politics, it was no less than a ‘living organism,’” adding: “Hitler’s own vision of geopolitics unlike that of many geopoliticians — rested upon race: the State itself was merely an expression of the racial ‘Volk.’” Railing against the ‘juridification of politics,’ many Nazi legal theorists saw the nation as a biological organism, corruptible by outside influences and requiring protection from alleged Jewish subversion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Marquette University history professor Peter Staudenmeier &lt;a href=&quot;https://newrepublic.com/article/154971/rise-ecofascism-history-white-nationalism-environmental-preservation-immigration&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;describes&lt;/a&gt; as the “link between a yearning for purity in the environmental sphere and a desire for racialized purity in the social sphere” also undergirds the ecofascist tendencies common to many modern neo-nazis such as Anders Brevik and the El Paso shooter, who characterised non-white populations as invaders seeking to despoil the environment through having more children and consuming more resources. This was also reflected in the writings of ecologist Garrett Hardin, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.splcenter.org/fighting-hate/extremist-files/individual/garrett-hardin&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;listed&lt;/a&gt; by the SPLC (Southern Poverty Law Centre) as a white nationalist, who wrote about the supposed threats that overpopulation posed to the Earth’s future. The myth of overpopulation has, however, been roundly debunked; a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2020/sep/21/worlds-richest-1-cause-double-co2-emissions-of-poorest-50-says-oxfam#:~:text=1%20month%20old-,World's%20richest%201%25%20cause%20double%20CO2,of%20poorest%2050%25%2C%20says%20Oxfam&amp;amp;text=The%20wealthiest%201%25%20of%20the,2015%2C%20according%20to%20new%20research.&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; from Oxfam showed that the world’s richest 1% are responsible for double the CO2 emissions of the poorest 50%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently, the contention that COVID-19 is a hoax has been a point of convergence between new age hippies and the far-right. Back in October, thousands of anti-vaxxers marched through Trafalgar Square in London at the COVID-sceptic ‘Unite for Freedom’ event, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nicktolhurst/status/1299729414767497219?lang=en&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;during which&lt;/a&gt; a BUF (British Union of Fascists) flag was spotted. The event was hosted by notorious conspiracy theorist David Icke, whose theories have been endorsed by both neo-nazis groups such as Combat 18, and the new age spiritual movement. It was also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/us-election-2020/jake-angeli-qanon-shaman-stormed-capitol-b1784091.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;revealed&lt;/a&gt; that Jake Angeli, a Trump supporter nicknamed the ‘QAnon shaman’ who stormed the Capitol, had stated that COVID-19 was a hoax. According to his mother, he had also refused to eat non-organic food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two groups are united in their rejection of the perceived infringement on their liberties; in the case of the far-right, the supposed stifling of their ability to criticise the unaccountable technocracy that is allegedly imposing open borders and multiculturalism, and in the case of the new age conspiracists, the personal, bodily autonomy connoted by 'natural' methods of healing, which are at odds with modern, scientific forms of inoculation such as vaccines. The excoriation of Bill Gates as a central figure in a supposed global plot to undermine civil liberties by using vaccines as a method of social control, including implanting microchips into unfortunate victims, has also been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dailymotion.com/video/x64vj4&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;propagated&lt;/a&gt; by conspiracy theorist Alex Jones, who has suggested that vaccines are part of a government-induced eugenics programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A theory known as the ‘Great Reset’ has also taken root in many far right circles, pushed by websites such as &lt;em&gt;Breitbart&lt;/em&gt;, which asserts that COVID-19 represents an attempt by a cabal of wealthy politicians, financiers and bureaucrats to establish a global government, eroding national sovereignty and dictating fiscal and monetary policy. During a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ugRnjpXEwTo&amp;amp;t=114s&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;conversation&lt;/a&gt; with former Alex Jones acolyte Paul Joseph Watson, &lt;em&gt;Breitbart&lt;/em&gt; columnist James Delingpole described the Great Reset as “another variation on the theme of the New World Order,” stating: “it’s a technocratic elite — an unelected technocratic elite — deciding how you and I should live our lives.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scepticism towards authority and heightened awareness of the erosion of civil liberties by governments using crises as a pretext to usher in technocratic dominance is not without merit. In an era characterised by the technocratic monopolisation of communications by companies whose business models are predicated on mining consumer data, in which a global pandemic has drastically increased the purview of the State’s influence over the lives of ordinary citizens, and in which finance, industry and production have all been centralised in the hands of a few multinational corporations, it is not unreasonable to be wary of authoritarian overreach.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the vague criticisms of systems of power enunciated by new age hippies, and the wild, conspiratorial denunciations of the ‘New World Order’ or the ‘Great Reset,’ common to extreme right wing political figures lack an empirical, material analysis. While it is certainly true that in Britain, at least, the pandemic has seen a worrying development in outsourcing the ‘Test and Trace’ system to companies such as G4S and Serco, which have been involved in nefarious operations from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-sussex-51573510&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;setting up&lt;/a&gt; immigration detention centres to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.justice.gov.uk/about/hmps/contracted-out&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;developing&lt;/a&gt; some of Britain’s first for-profit prisons, the potential for government overreach is no grounds for denying the existence, or the severity, of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As outlined above, both aforementioned groups reject a materialist, empirically rigorous analysis of the global economy and the role of the State in abrogating civil liberties, idealising a preindustrial, agrarian past and asserting that the world’s problems are caused by a shadowy cabal (the root of most antisemitic conspiracy theories). This pandemic has shown that these groups, though widely considered to have diametrically opposed political interests, are more similar than they appear, and have been willing to set aside their ideological differences for the pursuit of wider goals. Unless their scepticism of the technocratic impulses of governments seeking to curtail civil liberties, much of which is justified, can be countered with a thorough and precise refutation of conspiratorial political narratives, the implications of this unholy alliance could be significant.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On December 14, 2020, the UK Labour party leader Keir Starmer appeared on the radio show LBC with host Nick Ferrari when a caller, introducing herself as ‘Gemma from Cambridge,’ took the opportunity to propagate the Neo-Nazi ‘Great Replacement’ conspiracy theory on a national media platform. She stated: “in the wake of organisations such as BLM and other racial advocacy groups pushing what’s best for their people, I just want to ask, should white people also start playing identity politics now, before they become a minority themselves by 2066?” This bizarre event was made even more bewildering when a Twitter user revealed that ‘Gemma from Cambridge’ was in fact Jody Swingler, a yoga teacher and musician living in Ibiza, a far cry from the archetypal image of the hapless neo-nazi social outcast in their parents’ basement, pulling the wings off flies and ranting on obscure online messageboards about how The Jews had prevented them from securing a girlfriend. Swingler had also recorded two YouTube shows with Mark Collett and Laura Melia, leaders of the white nationalist political party Patriotic Alternative, which opposes the “replacement and displacement” of white Britons by people who “have no right to these lands.” It may seem striking that people who advocate new age, spiritual beliefs, previously associated with ‘flower power’ and the countercultural movement of the 1960's, could wind up on the same side as the far right. But in fact, the link between new age spirituality and extremist politics is not new. The Nazis drew support from the occultist Thule Society, and prominent Nazi figures such as Heinrich Himmler and Rudolf Hess endorsed homeopathy and alternative medicine, with Himmler supporting using plant extracts to cure cancer. In 1934, Hess set up an alternative medicine centre in Dresden. Their embrace of holism and spirituality, broadly, was underpinned by a rejection of the precepts of the Enlightenment, which posited that the world could be understood through logical processes, subordinating religious and monarchical obscurantism to the supremacy of the faculty of reason. Many Nazi figures saw a romanticised, agrarian age as a solution to the modern menaces of industrialisation and materialism. For example, Ernst Lehmann, a Nazi professor of botany, stated: “We recognize that separating humanity from nature, from the whole of life, leads to humankind’s own destruction and to the death of nations. Only through a reintegration of humanity into the whole of nature can our people be made stronger… This striving toward connectedness with the totality of life, with nature itself, a nature into which we are born, this is the deepest meaning and the true essence of National Socialist thought.” A desire to undo the crude, materialist logic that undergirded liberal democracy, and to restructure the relationship between the citizen and the State, therefore, spawned the Nazis’ fascination with holism and the reintegration of man with nature. 'Blood and soil' meant an organic connection with one’s homeland that could not be expressed through the civic or legal frameworks engendered by the minority protection clauses of the League of Nations, but only through the maintenance of racial purity. Mark Mazower wrote in his book Dark Continent that:“The League (of Nations) , after all, was an organisation of States. But what was the State? According to Hitler’s biological view of politics, it was no less than a ‘living organism,’” adding: “Hitler’s own vision of geopolitics unlike that of many geopoliticians — rested upon race: the State itself was merely an expression of the racial ‘Volk.’” Railing against the ‘juridification of politics,’ many Nazi legal theorists saw the nation as a biological organism, corruptible by outside influences and requiring protection from alleged Jewish subversion. What Marquette University history professor Peter Staudenmeier describes as the “link between a yearning for purity in the environmental sphere and a desire for racialized purity in the social sphere” also undergirds the ecofascist tendencies common to many modern neo-nazis such as Anders Brevik and the El Paso shooter, who characterised non-white populations as invaders seeking to despoil the environment through having more children and consuming more resources. This was also reflected in the writings of ecologist Garrett Hardin, listed by the SPLC (Southern Poverty Law Centre) as a white nationalist, who wrote about the supposed threats that overpopulation posed to the Earth’s future. The myth of overpopulation has, however, been roundly debunked; a study from Oxfam showed that the world’s richest 1% are responsible for double the CO2 emissions of the poorest 50%. More recently, the contention that COVID-19 is a hoax has been a point of convergence between new age hippies and the far-right. Back in October, thousands of anti-vaxxers marched through Trafalgar Square in London at the COVID-sceptic ‘Unite for Freedom’ event, during which a BUF (British Union of Fascists) flag was spotted. The event was hosted by notorious conspiracy theorist David Icke, whose theories have been endorsed by both neo-nazis groups such as Combat 18, and the new age spiritual movement. It was also revealed that Jake Angeli, a Trump supporter nicknamed the ‘QAnon shaman’ who stormed the Capitol, had stated that COVID-19 was a hoax. According to his mother, he had also refused to eat non-organic food. The two groups are united in their rejection of the perceived infringement on their liberties; in the case of the far-right, the supposed stifling of their ability to criticise the unaccountable technocracy that is allegedly imposing open borders and multiculturalism, and in the case of the new age conspiracists, the personal, bodily autonomy connoted by 'natural' methods of healing, which are at odds with modern, scientific forms of inoculation such as vaccines. The excoriation of Bill Gates as a central figure in a supposed global plot to undermine civil liberties by using vaccines as a method of social control, including implanting microchips into unfortunate victims, has also been propagated by conspiracy theorist Alex Jones, who has suggested that vaccines are part of a government-induced eugenics programme. A theory known as the ‘Great Reset’ has also taken root in many far right circles, pushed by websites such as Breitbart, which asserts that COVID-19 represents an attempt by a cabal of wealthy politicians, financiers and bureaucrats to establish a global government, eroding national sovereignty and dictating fiscal and monetary policy. During a conversation with former Alex Jones acolyte Paul Joseph Watson, Breitbart columnist James Delingpole described the Great Reset as “another variation on the theme of the New World Order,” stating: “it’s a technocratic elite — an unelected technocratic elite — deciding how you and I should live our lives.” Scepticism towards authority and heightened awareness of the erosion of civil liberties by governments using crises as a pretext to usher in technocratic dominance is not without merit. In an era characterised by the technocratic monopolisation of communications by companies whose business models are predicated on mining consumer data, in which a global pandemic has drastically increased the purview of the State’s influence over the lives of ordinary citizens, and in which finance, industry and production have all been centralised in the hands of a few multinational corporations, it is not unreasonable to be wary of authoritarian overreach.&amp;nbsp; However, the vague criticisms of systems of power enunciated by new age hippies, and the wild, conspiratorial denunciations of the ‘New World Order’ or the ‘Great Reset,’ common to extreme right wing political figures lack an empirical, material analysis. While it is certainly true that in Britain, at least, the pandemic has seen a worrying development in outsourcing the ‘Test and Trace’ system to companies such as G4S and Serco, which have been involved in nefarious operations from setting up immigration detention centres to developing some of Britain’s first for-profit prisons, the potential for government overreach is no grounds for denying the existence, or the severity, of COVID-19. As outlined above, both aforementioned groups reject a materialist, empirically rigorous analysis of the global economy and the role of the State in abrogating civil liberties, idealising a preindustrial, agrarian past and asserting that the world’s problems are caused by a shadowy cabal (the root of most antisemitic conspiracy theories). This pandemic has shown that these groups, though widely considered to have diametrically opposed political interests, are more similar than they appear, and have been willing to set aside their ideological differences for the pursuit of wider goals. Unless their scepticism of the technocratic impulses of governments seeking to curtail civil liberties, much of which is justified, can be countered with a thorough and precise refutation of conspiratorial political narratives, the implications of this unholy alliance could be significant.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why Poorer Countries are More Conservative - As Told by the Brain</title>
      <link href="/Why-Poorer-Countries-are-More-Conservative-As-Told-by-the-Brain" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Poorer Countries are More Conservative - As Told by the Brain" />
      <published>2021-03-31T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-03-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-Poorer-Countries-are-More-Conservative-As-Told-by-the-Brain</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-Poorer-Countries-are-More-Conservative-As-Told-by-the-Brain">&lt;p&gt;There is no denying that people from different cultures have different attitudes towards life and the world around them. Some of these differences seem to lie between people living in the developed world and those living in the less developed nations, where people appear more liberal in the former and more conservative in the latter. An example of this phenomenon is attitudes towards homosexuality, while 32 out of the 54 African nations criminalise homosexuality, no country in Europe has a law expressly prohibiting homosexual activities. Contrasts in people’s attitudes between the developed and developing world can also be seen in other areas such as religion, premarital sex and even the modesty of female clothing. Additionally, just a century ago most, if not all, of today’s developed nations experienced a high rate of poverty. Back then, people’s mindsets were also what we would today call conservative, a prominent example of which was the prudency of people living in Victorian England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This raises one question: what is the link between the intangible mindsets of people living within a given society and the tangible advancement, or lack thereof, in said society? In order to assess the way humans behave, the most logical place to turn to is the brain. Brain scans have shown that people who self-identify as conservatives have a larger right amygdala; this is the area of the brain responsible for processing fear. This makes sense, given that in poor nations people tend to live in more fear than in their developed counterparts. Even within a developed nation such as the United States, it has been shown that shortly after the events of September 11, there was an increase in conservative leanings with increased support for military spending. If this is the state of a wealthy nation, what would it mean for one where people live fearfully on a day-to-day basis?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a variety of ways in which the right amygdala, and by extension fear, would affect the way people behave in different countries. For instance, it goes without saying that citizens of conservative countries are traditional and resistant to change. A 2008 study, which catalogued the items in the dormitory rooms of university students, found that liberal-leaning students tended to own more books and travel-related items, which implied their desire for a sense of adventure in their lives. On the other hand, in conservative rooms, there were found to be more items including calendars and cleaning supplies, which were intended to maintain order in their lives. These findings suggest that liberals are more open to more novel experiences, whereas conservatives prefer more order and structure. This could explain the conservative inclination towards familiarity and hence resistance to change. Furthermore, their predisposition towards fear is potentially what makes them more risk-averse and resistant to what is not already an established norm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many developing countries are also known for their populations’ intolerance across lines of ethnicity, religion or otherwise. A study conducted in 2018 showed that people with more conservative viewpoints were quicker to look away when shown disgusting images - such as vomit, faeces or blood - compared to those with more liberal leanings. From an evolutionary standpoint, this knee-jerk reaction is good for human survival, as this helps to avert potentially harmful pathogens. This quick reaction could also be encouraged by their aforementioned predisposition to fear. However, separate research also suggests that this affects the way in which conservatives view others who are different from themselves, which may explain the affinity towards intolerance in many developing nations. To add to that, this may also explain the negative attitude in such countries towards mental health and people with disabilities, which people perceive as ‘deviating’ from the norm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as religion goes, this itself is a factor that seems to differ between economic levels of development. In fact, there is a clear negative correlation between the GDP per capita of a country and the religiosity of its citizens according to a 2009 Gallup survey. This may also be linked to the predisposition towards fear, as religion is seen by many as a means of maintaining feelings of safety and security in the dangerous world around them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From these findings, it can be inferred that the conservative mentality is centred around fear and viewing the world as a dangerous place. There appears to be a tendency for inhabitants of liberal nations to judge those of conservative nations for being overly repressive and restrictive, while the latter judge the former as being immoral and depraved. One could argue, however, that neither side is right or wrong, only people’s brains adapt to the context around them, particularly in the context of fear where the brain tailors itself to aid in its owner’s survival. That having been said, the developed countries of today have only relatively recently seen widespread prosperity amongst their citizens and along with it only recently adopted their liberal ideas in the mainstream. Thus, we may have to wait for many other countries to develop to gauge whether such a correlation truly exists between a society’s physical development and the mentality of its citizens. There may well be one but for now, only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Joseph Situmorang</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There is no denying that people from different cultures have different attitudes towards life and the world around them. Some of these differences seem to lie between people living in the developed world and those living in the less developed nations, where people appear more liberal in the former and more conservative in the latter. An example of this phenomenon is attitudes towards homosexuality, while 32 out of the 54 African nations criminalise homosexuality, no country in Europe has a law expressly prohibiting homosexual activities. Contrasts in people’s attitudes between the developed and developing world can also be seen in other areas such as religion, premarital sex and even the modesty of female clothing. Additionally, just a century ago most, if not all, of today’s developed nations experienced a high rate of poverty. Back then, people’s mindsets were also what we would today call conservative, a prominent example of which was the prudency of people living in Victorian England. This raises one question: what is the link between the intangible mindsets of people living within a given society and the tangible advancement, or lack thereof, in said society? In order to assess the way humans behave, the most logical place to turn to is the brain. Brain scans have shown that people who self-identify as conservatives have a larger right amygdala; this is the area of the brain responsible for processing fear. This makes sense, given that in poor nations people tend to live in more fear than in their developed counterparts. Even within a developed nation such as the United States, it has been shown that shortly after the events of September 11, there was an increase in conservative leanings with increased support for military spending. If this is the state of a wealthy nation, what would it mean for one where people live fearfully on a day-to-day basis? There are a variety of ways in which the right amygdala, and by extension fear, would affect the way people behave in different countries. For instance, it goes without saying that citizens of conservative countries are traditional and resistant to change. A 2008 study, which catalogued the items in the dormitory rooms of university students, found that liberal-leaning students tended to own more books and travel-related items, which implied their desire for a sense of adventure in their lives. On the other hand, in conservative rooms, there were found to be more items including calendars and cleaning supplies, which were intended to maintain order in their lives. These findings suggest that liberals are more open to more novel experiences, whereas conservatives prefer more order and structure. This could explain the conservative inclination towards familiarity and hence resistance to change. Furthermore, their predisposition towards fear is potentially what makes them more risk-averse and resistant to what is not already an established norm. Many developing countries are also known for their populations’ intolerance across lines of ethnicity, religion or otherwise. A study conducted in 2018 showed that people with more conservative viewpoints were quicker to look away when shown disgusting images - such as vomit, faeces or blood - compared to those with more liberal leanings. From an evolutionary standpoint, this knee-jerk reaction is good for human survival, as this helps to avert potentially harmful pathogens. This quick reaction could also be encouraged by their aforementioned predisposition to fear. However, separate research also suggests that this affects the way in which conservatives view others who are different from themselves, which may explain the affinity towards intolerance in many developing nations. To add to that, this may also explain the negative attitude in such countries towards mental health and people with disabilities, which people perceive as ‘deviating’ from the norm. As far as religion goes, this itself is a factor that seems to differ between economic levels of development. In fact, there is a clear negative correlation between the GDP per capita of a country and the religiosity of its citizens according to a 2009 Gallup survey. This may also be linked to the predisposition towards fear, as religion is seen by many as a means of maintaining feelings of safety and security in the dangerous world around them. From these findings, it can be inferred that the conservative mentality is centred around fear and viewing the world as a dangerous place. There appears to be a tendency for inhabitants of liberal nations to judge those of conservative nations for being overly repressive and restrictive, while the latter judge the former as being immoral and depraved. One could argue, however, that neither side is right or wrong, only people’s brains adapt to the context around them, particularly in the context of fear where the brain tailors itself to aid in its owner’s survival. That having been said, the developed countries of today have only relatively recently seen widespread prosperity amongst their citizens and along with it only recently adopted their liberal ideas in the mainstream. Thus, we may have to wait for many other countries to develop to gauge whether such a correlation truly exists between a society’s physical development and the mentality of its citizens. There may well be one but for now, only time will tell.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
