<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/society/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-11-17T10:54:01+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/society/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Uncomfortable Parallels: The Revenge of the Anglophone Elites</title>
      <link href="/Uncomfortable-Parallels" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Uncomfortable Parallels: The Revenge of the Anglophone Elites" />
      <published>2019-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Uncomfortable-Parallels</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Uncomfortable-Parallels">&lt;p&gt;The political elite of the United States, in the form of Democrats in the Congress, Democrats in the media, and jealous Republicans in the political establishment, are all upset that the people rejected them in favour of a populist man with zero political experience or connections, and have now united together for the first time since the bomb that was the Mueller testimony to try and overturn the election of 2016. They have announced they will support the impeachment of the American President, although House Speaker Pelosi’s ‘announcement’ of an ‘impeachment inquiry’ thus far has no actual effect because there hasn’t been a vote taken in the House on the issue. However, by September 26, 2019, there were 217 Democrats announcing they’d vote in favour of such an inquiry plus former Republican Justin Amash of Michigan, giving the majority of 218 needed if a vote were brought to the floor. So what did the bad orange man do that finally pushed a majority of the oldest democratic legislative body in the world to declare their official attempts to prematurely remove the chief executive, elected independently of themselves by the people? He talked to a foreign president about trying to end corruption in said President’s nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, a majority of members of the US House of Representatives want to now overturn an election of over 120,000,000 voters and 538 electors because the President that process produced talked to President Vladimir Zelensky of Ukraine to ask him what he was doing to fight corruption. Nothing about threats, nothing about money, and nothing about the election. In fact, while the media and the left all across the world have been screaming about the ‘fact’ that there is a ‘coverup’ or that there was ‘quid pro quo’ or even ‘election interference’ in the form of investigating Trump’s ‘opponent’, they have completely missed that the transcript of the call in question was released and says nothing of the sort. Joe Biden is not Trump’s opponent and there is corruption in the Ukraine that Trump wants to look at, which could possibly include Vice President Joe Biden actually withholding money from Ukraine until they fired a prosecutor looking into a company involving his son, Hunter. Finally, and probably most importantly, not a single mention of aid appears, nor are there any threats. In total, it is a nothingburger, but the leftists in all spheres, from media to Congress, have organised to move forward in the next attempt to throw out the president for the crime of winning the 2016 election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could very well spell trouble for the Democrats in 2020, with Speaker Pelosi going so far as to say “we have to impeach him, even if it means we lose the House in 2020.” The left knows very well the fire it is playing with and this will most likely backfire on them gloriously. However, for the time being, they are playing their hand and doing everything they can to ensure that Trump is taken out somehow. While this effort is doomed to fail like previous efforts, to see them so united in such a hostile manner, essentially unmasking themselves for the radicals they really are, it becomes clear how big the fight for the future of the United States and its culture will be in the coming years. They don’t just want to get rid of Trump, but they would also like to force everyone who supported him to witness his overthrow as an example of what happens when you upset their little club by getting uppity and thinking you should have a voice in government. That type of mentality leads to dark roads and must be rejected and defeated at every turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings me across the pond to Britain, going through its own democratic crisis due to its own 2016 middle finger to the elites, Brexit. Since that day, the elite Remainers in all parties had been fighting long and hard to overturn the results, however they just could not unite to do it. Not that Brexiteers in power have been the most united, however, their message has been consistent throughout: deliver Brexit with a good deal or leave the EU on World Trade Organisation rules two years after the invocation of Article 50. Theresa May, a Remainer at heart, extended the current deadline of October 31 due to her abysmal withdrawal treaty suffering three humiliating defeats in the House of Commons before the original deadline. So when she was finally deposed and more upbeat, can do, ‘we will leave, do or die’ Boris Johnson took her place, it seemed things would be going okay for the Brexiteers, and Remainers would finally be on the path to the dustbin of history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the Parliament first met under PM Johnson and votes started happening, after his announcement of the prorogation of Parliament to put a fresh Queen’s Speech down and finally end the longest Parliament since the Rump Parliament during the English Civil War. This reasonable request was met by Remainer elites in the media, Labour Party, Liberal Democrats, Scottish National Party, and bitter, anti democratic, Conservatives with screeches of “Stop the coup” and “this is a dictatorship.” They declared the reduction of the session by four days was designed to take away debate for the apocalypse they think would be a no-deal Brexit. The fact that they have been debating and fear-mongering on for over three years at this point has not seemed to occur to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next came the fact that PM Johnson started losing every vote put to the floor, including one which effectively called for the formation of a new government by the back door and was made a motion of confidence in the Conservative Party, and resulted in the loss of the majority to where it currently stands at -44. Because of the ungovernability of such a position, Johnson asked for an election to be had under the Fixed Terms Parliaments Act…twice. Both times, it was rejected by the opposition and the former Conservative members of Parliament. They then claimed it was undemocratic what Johnson was doing and they would not abide so long as no-deal was still an option. Their rejection of an election was hailed by their friends in the media as them standing up to the declared disdain for democracy Johnson supposedly has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prorogation finally went into effect, however, and the legal battles were to continue on whether the PM had to seek an extension. Then came the Supreme Court of the United Kingdom, squarely and officially inserting themselves into the political process by declaring the entire thing unlawful and ordering Parliament back. They did come back, just to further show their absolute ineffectiveness as they currently stand. They have essentially thrown out the government and inserted themselves as the government without asking the people or through a motion of no-confidence. They continue to reject an election to be held because they know the people can see right through their nonsense and would reject them at the ballot box for this. However, like in America, they currently have united and will work tirelessly to show to the people who dared vote against them in 2016 that they are to never rise up and do it again—a state-of-affairs that could be fatal to the deal negotiated by Johnson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Anglophone leftist/Remainer elites are now a united force once again, reinvigorated by a media class who have as much an interest in overturning the greatest political mandate in British history and the biggest electoral upset in modern American history. They have the reigns of government for the time being in both nations and are ramping up their efforts to put down these uprisings once and for all, presumably as one final big push as they know they will lose. In their desperate last grasps at power, they do not care if they destroy the greatest democratic organisations in the world. They will lie about those who dared choose Brexit or Trump. They will destroy the lives of anybody who helped in making those momentous occasions to happen. They will only be emboldened if they are able to complete their missions in destroying the idea of democratic governance. We must not let them do so. They need to be soundly rejected and defeated at the ballot box and need to be stopped from overturning previous election results they do not like. If we fail to do so, the uncomfortable parallels between the two great Anglophone nations will go from uncomfortable to disastrous.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sam Valk</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The political elite of the United States, in the form of Democrats in the Congress, Democrats in the media, and jealous Republicans in the political establishment, are all upset that the people rejected them in favour of a populist man with zero political experience or connections, and have now united together for the first time since the bomb that was the Mueller testimony to try and overturn the election of 2016. They have announced they will support the impeachment of the American President, although House Speaker Pelosi’s ‘announcement’ of an ‘impeachment inquiry’ thus far has no actual effect because there hasn’t been a vote taken in the House on the issue. However, by September 26, 2019, there were 217 Democrats announcing they’d vote in favour of such an inquiry plus former Republican Justin Amash of Michigan, giving the majority of 218 needed if a vote were brought to the floor. So what did the bad orange man do that finally pushed a majority of the oldest democratic legislative body in the world to declare their official attempts to prematurely remove the chief executive, elected independently of themselves by the people? He talked to a foreign president about trying to end corruption in said President’s nation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What Feminism Ought To Be?</title>
      <link href="/What-Feminism-Ought-To-Be" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Feminism Ought To Be?" />
      <published>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-Feminism-Ought-To-Be</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-Feminism-Ought-To-Be">&lt;p&gt;There is no reason why one shouldn’t be a feminist in this day and age. Any suggestion that is contrary to the notion that women’s rights ought to be protected and that patriarchy ought to be completely dismantled is, ipso facto, foolish and thoroughly immoral. But, post the #metoo movement and torrents of online rage from ‘feminists’, one is bound to ask: is this supposed collective expression of anger against societal discrimination, sexual harrasment and patriarchal structures, well-intentioned as it may be, leading to a material change in the status of women in society? To answer that question in the affirmative seems disingenuous at best and nefarious at worst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The #metoo movement has been both shocking yet brilliant in exposing the rot beneath the veneer of equality. But has this exposition led to meaningful change? Or, for that matter, do passionate supporters of the #metoo movement really seek to bring about changes in, say, sexual harassment legislation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent seminar organised by the Calcutta High Court and American embassy in Calcutta, I was woken up to the reality of how precious little had changed with regard to America’s Civil Rights Act of 1964 or India’s Sexual Harassment of Women at Workplace (Prevention, Prohibition and Redressal) Act, 2013 in the wake of the #metoo movement. There are umpteen criticisms that can be made of both these laws, but one with regard to each should suffice to illustrate why these laws are programmed to protect the Harvey Weinsteins of our age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian Act contemplates an Internal Complaints Committee to function as a redressal mechanism for aggrieved women in a workplace of more than ten employees. The Committee does require an external member who is familiar with issues relating to sexual assault or from an organisation committed to the cause of women, but the nagging sense that this is a mechanism where the “fox is guarding the hen’s house” disturbingly remains. In the case of the American Civil Rights Act, the same ends up happening even though complaints are supposed to be filed with the external US Equal Employment Opportunity Commission. This is because of two American Supreme Court decisions in &lt;em&gt;Faragher v. City of Boca Raton&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Burlington v. Ellerth&lt;/em&gt;. While both these decisions attempted to clarify the law, they inadvertently laid down a point of law that has, in the words of &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5319966/sexual-harassment-scotus-anniversary/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; magazine, “contributed to a key reason why workplace sexual harassment lawsuits are still hard to file today”. The Supreme Court ruled in these cases that an employer may not be liable under the Civil Rights Act for sexual harassment if, inter alia, the complainant fails to take advantage of any internal mechanisms for redressal of the complaint provided by the employer. In other words, we have a situation not dissimilar to the state of the Indian law, where a potential victim of sexual harassment must reckon with the fox before she can truly reach the hen’s house. This, quite obviously, means that numerous sexual harassment claims simply go unnoticed and are, quite simply, suppressed in America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That these and other legal issues have been significant contributors to the extent of harassment and abuse exposed by the #metoo movement ought to be apparent to anyone with a brain. However, a call for reforms to such laws is hardly the defining conversation of today’s feminist movements. Indeed, one can appreciate that perhaps the nitty-gritties of legal reform cannot form part of an exoteric conversation. But one cannot deny that if feminists engaged in advocating meaningful legislative reform with half the passion that they use to ‘destroy’ incels and dudebros online, we would be living in a better world. This is not an anti-feminist rant from a privileged little boy, it is a Greta Thunbergesque (&lt;em&gt;bless her&lt;/em&gt;) “how dare you?!” to all those who claim to stand for women’s rights but are so pathetic at delivering those rights to women. Of course, it is important that society evolves to develop zero tolerance for misogynistic bigots, but to pay more attention to a hurtful tweet instead of the silent suffering of so many working women is rather dystopian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of misplaced priorities, we must address the representation of women in the workplace, and, of course, the feminist’s refusal to do anything real about it. As was pointed out by Baroness Arden of Heswall, Deputy President of the UK Supreme Court, in a guest lecture at the University of Bristol (which I had the privilege to attend), the percentage of women who were partners in London law firms in 2019, 100 years after women got the right to practice law in England, was a mere 29%. What’s more, Lady Arden stated that when she, as a Judge of the English Court of Appeal, proposed that a daycare centre be set up for women barristers near the Royal Courts of Justice, the other male Judges simply dismissed her by stating that this would be a nuisance to male barristers. That Lady Arden was a Judge of the Court of Appeal from 2000-2018 should serve to indicate that such horrendous attitudes are definitely not from some distant age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern feminist’s response to these facts and realities is not very different from the dialogues delivered by Samuel L Jackson in &lt;em&gt;Pulp Fiction&lt;/em&gt;, they are expressions of “furious anger” that seek to lay their vengeance upon men. But these responses are, to quote The Merovingian from the second &lt;em&gt;Matrix&lt;/em&gt; movie, “so boring, so obvious, so bourgeoisie.” They very simply ignore the import of Lady Arden’s arguments: that the next step towards a greater representation of women in the workplace requires some important tangible changes. For instance, one needs to ensure mandatory maternity leave as well as paternity leave is a reality in all big organisations—something that is far from being a reality in a country as developed as America. Secondly, one needs to concentrate on making daycare cheaper and more accessible to women so that the beauty of becoming a mother doesn’t end up penalising a booming career. Thirdly, one needs to change office culture and, sorry right-wing crackpots, that includes ensuring that air conditioning is not set in accordance with the metabolism of middle-aged men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, battling against the patriarchy to implement such changes sounds awfully hard, it is far easier to just obsess over cats (okay, fair enough, they are amazing) and share disgustingly bad feminist slam poetry. Why challenge patriarchs to be better and to do better when one can simply raise one’s hands and declare that they’re trash. And not to mention, how could we possibly change attitudes surrounding women without changing the colour of people’s toys. All of this is not for some comedic effect, it is to expose the Goebbellian lie that is modern feminism, a movement (if it can be called one) that concentrates less on change and more on empty expressions of supposed solidarity with the numerous problems faced by women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most dangerous effects of this is borne out by the feminist’s treatment of rape culture. Speaking logically, one would presume that the only way to destroy an oppressive social construct like rape culture is to teach people to know better. But that definitely is not what today’s feminist does. Today’s feminist hardly seeks to bat for rigorous consent classes in universities and schools. They rarely seek to educate people on understanding the humanity of women and they are loathe to contemplate on how men can be used as allies in combating rape culture. This not only fails to go to the root of the problem by dealing with the cultural rot that a priori drives men’s most problematic behaviours, it has far more nefarious effects. This misandry-is-feminism attitude of so many feminists incentivises a lot of men to simply pretend to be feminists in a bid to get sex. And it should go without saying that this is a most poisonous kind of objectification that relies on its antithesis to survive and grow. This verily means that feminists end up giving traction to a very fundamental sabotage of their own movement by refusing to actually deal with a problem and by stooping to lowly instinct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of that being said, credit must be given where credit is due, modern feminism has been very sharp in changing broader culture to simply not be accommodative of abusers and bigots. It has created a rightfully hostile environment for those who would dare say that women are lesser than men and it has clarified that sexist attitudes are simply not going to fly anymore. However, that is simply not enough. One has to go beyond a great grand shriek about how sexist and patriarchal the world is to actually contemplate upon how it could look better. And one has to understand that without such a constructive contemplation, one is going to have a world with a smokescreen of verbose activism but with a ground reality of festering oppression.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There is no reason why one shouldn’t be a feminist in this day and age. Any suggestion that is contrary to the notion that women’s rights ought to be protected and that patriarchy ought to be completely dismantled is, ipso facto, foolish and thoroughly immoral. But, post the #metoo movement and torrents of online rage from ‘feminists’, one is bound to ask: is this supposed collective expression of anger against societal discrimination, sexual harrasment and patriarchal structures, well-intentioned as it may be, leading to a material change in the status of women in society? To answer that question in the affirmative seems disingenuous at best and nefarious at worst.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Groupthink: A World-Governing Herd Mentality</title>
      <link href="/A-World-Governing-Herd-Mentality" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Groupthink: A World-Governing Herd Mentality" />
      <published>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-World-Governing-Herd-Mentality</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-World-Governing-Herd-Mentality">&lt;p&gt;We’ve all followed the pack at some points of time in our lives. Be it decisions
about what kind of studies to pursue, which rat race to run, which Beyblade to
buy or which new friend to include in our otherwise exclusive gang. Why we like
to do so is because it’s easier than thinking for oneself. Once you figure out
how this same thought process affects government policies, major industries,
workplace regulations, national elections, and other such important-sounding
things, you realise that maybe even important people, unlike us, have an
inherent laziness seen in their readiness to accept the easiest narrative. This,
however, is just the tip of the iceberg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what Irving L Janis, a research psychologist from Yale University, set
out to establish when he pioneered the initial research on groupthink - a term
inspired by doublethink, the phenomenon of accepting two contradictory beliefs
because of political propaganda (the term was coined by George Orwell in his
novel &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt;). Janis believed that groups that suffered from groupthink had some
common characteristics among them. He identified 8 common symptoms in his
original paper: &lt;em&gt;invulnerability&lt;/em&gt; in the belief that they can never be defeated,
&lt;em&gt;rationalising&lt;/em&gt; all sorts of warnings that hint towards an adversity that the
group wouldn’t prefer, blind faith in the group’s &lt;em&gt;moral high ground&lt;/em&gt; without
actually considering the consequences, &lt;em&gt;stereotyping&lt;/em&gt; the enemy, &lt;em&gt;peer
pressure&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;self-censorship&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;unanimity&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;mindguards&lt;/em&gt; that prevent
unfavourable but true information from changing the group leader’s decision.
It’s also very interesting to think of group dynamics in this way. Ideally being
in a circle of friends must mean that you find solace in it and you can
gleefully say anything without feeling the need to censor yourself. If this
circle has some unspoken ideals that are conditions for you to remain in it, the
phenomenon of groupthink arises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink offers a sense of comfort. Think of the first time you left for
college, unshackled by the rules that bound you in school. You were probably
afraid of the amount of freedom you had, of how alone you were. You would rather
go back to a time when you were governed by rules, at home, because at the very
least there was someone who would take care of you, every step of the way. You
don’t want to be part of this ugly, competitive world and instead of sorting
life out for yourself, you’d rather have someone else do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting how many instances from history one can draw in order to fit
this model. Janis advances his argument about groupthink, primarily, by talking
about the Bay of Pigs invasion that inevitably led to the defeat of the CIA-led
American personnel. Janis provided proof of the mechanisms that the Kennedy
administration had in place, such that only the anti-communist narrative could
prevail in their decisions, with little space left for dissent. They believed
that, as a communist nation, Cuba had very little firepower against the
capitalist might of the US. Arthur Schlesinger, one of the members of Kennedy’s
circle, was an active dissenter but he was constantly suppressed. In a similar
vein but far worse off is the Vietnam War. The Nixon administration truly
believed they could ride the wave of American integrity being threatened abroad
and communists being inherently evil despite being told that it was unlikely
that they could defeat the Viet Cong. Not only did they end up losing horribly
but also lost the trust of the soldiers, who had been sent on government orders,
and the American public that saw very little wrong in having leftist leanings.
The government earned the wrath of a generation that decided to pour their pain
into anti-war music, psychedelics and alternative living. Lesson learnt: don’t
piss off people who can become the future Rolling Stones or Black Sabbath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US isn’t the only nation to have fallen prey to this. The Chernobyl tragedy
speaks for why unwavering belief in any ideology, especially one that
prioritises the nation over its citizens, is the surest route to disaster. The
Soviet Union’s adherence to not leaking any information about the nuclear power
plant, its belief that it was virtually impossible for any Soviet construction
to fail, let alone one that displayed its true might in a cold war, and
immediate dismissal of scientific backing behind what could happen was what
caused Mikhail Gorbachev to proclaim the Chernobyl disaster as the event that
led to the collapse of the USSR. Nazi Germany is an even better example; people
were wilfully ignorant of the dictatorship’s treatment of Jews in concentration
camps. They believed that the power of the fatherland could extend everywhere
without consequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink is not a thing of the past either. In the present, groupthink is how
groups of people become alienated from other ideas. Elite, educated liberals of
the day choose not to explain their stance to people who oppose them, assuming
the opposition to be &lt;em&gt;inherently stupid&lt;/em&gt;. The same ‘inherently stupid’ then
collectivise and assume majority power. Thereafter, even if someone from this
group is presented with an alternative rationale, they will choose to reject it
due to the distrust that has already been formed. This is best exemplified in
how, in an age where political correctness has become a ‘necessity’, anyone with
a contrary view of things is bashed instead of educated. This is not to say that
all political correctness is unwarranted. However, if liberals choose to deride
rather than increase awareness then they are simply contributing to the
aforementioned alienation. On the other hand, conservatives around the world
(who often overlap with the aforementioned ‘inherently stupid’) stick to
societal norms that have existed for ages, even if they’re regressive.
Groupthink is often the basis for dinner table conversations that revolve around
politics; opposition to the favourite narrative, if any, will be met with loud,
sharp words. These dynamics are used to the advantage of politicians like Donald
Trump, who know how to appeal to their voter base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink extends beyond politics. It led to the subprime crisis in 2008. The
financial industry ardently believed that no rational human being would ever
default on his/her home loan. However, they took this to mean that loans could
be given to anyone and everyone, and then they built complex securities based on
these loans that were dependent on each other. The dot-com bubble in the early
2000’s is a good example too. The internet was the hottest property that was
virtual, and people were naturally excited about its potential. This sentiment
led to massive overvaluation of companies that merely had a website which
combined with tech companies prioritising growth over profit and cash flow
stability, led to the downfall of a number of firms. It is happening even today,
with startups like Uber and WeWork launching their initial public offerings.
WeWork is currently burning cash, and it has been subject to lots of scrutiny by
the market. Adam Neumann, the founder, was recently ousted from the post of CEO.
Uber took a huge plunge on its first day of going public. This shows how
groupthink is responsible for hype value. Brands like Supreme, that rely simply
on their logo being printed on what would otherwise be a plain white T-shirt,
have the power of hype working in their favour. This hype has no concrete basis
like quality. It builds up through targeted marketing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does one escape groupthink? Most articles state one method right off the
bat: create awareness of critical thinking skills that lead to thoughtful
criticism. It might just be the case that what we do not wish to hear is what
truly makes sense to us at times. Silence isn’t proof of consent from members.
People who do not speak up must be encouraged to talk, since it’s entirely
possible that they don’t want to only out of the fear of being chastised.
Another way is to have the leader of the group take a poll before they announce
their opinion. In that way, especially if the poll is anonymous, those who were
not comfortable providing a perspective contrarian to the existing status quo
can freely say what they want to. Another way is to appoint a devil’s advocate
specifically for this purpose, or a red-team that makes a B-plan in contrast to
yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink offers a comfortable seat where you may not have to do a lot of
thinking, or take a lot of responsibility. If a decision goes horribly wrong,
then no &lt;em&gt;single&lt;/em&gt; individual can be held accountable. However, if everyone in a
group feels a heightened sense of pride towards the goal of a group, and can be
made to believe that their actions have a large impact, positive or negative,
then decisions will be taken with greater forethought and discussion. In times
that value nuanced discussions over various ideas, we must be heading towards
the ideal of free-flowing thought instead succumbing to peer pressure.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pranav Manie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">We’ve all followed the pack at some points of time in our lives. Be it decisions about what kind of studies to pursue, which rat race to run, which Beyblade to buy or which new friend to include in our otherwise exclusive gang. Why we like to do so is because it’s easier than thinking for oneself. Once you figure out how this same thought process affects government policies, major industries, workplace regulations, national elections, and other such important-sounding things, you realise that maybe even important people, unlike us, have an inherent laziness seen in their readiness to accept the easiest narrative. This, however, is just the tip of the iceberg. This is what Irving L Janis, a research psychologist from Yale University, set out to establish when he pioneered the initial research on groupthink - a term inspired by doublethink, the phenomenon of accepting two contradictory beliefs because of political propaganda (the term was coined by George Orwell in his novel 1984). Janis believed that groups that suffered from groupthink had some common characteristics among them. He identified 8 common symptoms in his original paper: invulnerability in the belief that they can never be defeated, rationalising all sorts of warnings that hint towards an adversity that the group wouldn’t prefer, blind faith in the group’s moral high ground without actually considering the consequences, stereotyping the enemy, peer pressure, self-censorship, unanimity and mindguards that prevent unfavourable but true information from changing the group leader’s decision. It’s also very interesting to think of group dynamics in this way. Ideally being in a circle of friends must mean that you find solace in it and you can gleefully say anything without feeling the need to censor yourself. If this circle has some unspoken ideals that are conditions for you to remain in it, the phenomenon of groupthink arises. Groupthink offers a sense of comfort. Think of the first time you left for college, unshackled by the rules that bound you in school. You were probably afraid of the amount of freedom you had, of how alone you were. You would rather go back to a time when you were governed by rules, at home, because at the very least there was someone who would take care of you, every step of the way. You don’t want to be part of this ugly, competitive world and instead of sorting life out for yourself, you’d rather have someone else do it. It’s interesting how many instances from history one can draw in order to fit this model. Janis advances his argument about groupthink, primarily, by talking about the Bay of Pigs invasion that inevitably led to the defeat of the CIA-led American personnel. Janis provided proof of the mechanisms that the Kennedy administration had in place, such that only the anti-communist narrative could prevail in their decisions, with little space left for dissent. They believed that, as a communist nation, Cuba had very little firepower against the capitalist might of the US. Arthur Schlesinger, one of the members of Kennedy’s circle, was an active dissenter but he was constantly suppressed. In a similar vein but far worse off is the Vietnam War. The Nixon administration truly believed they could ride the wave of American integrity being threatened abroad and communists being inherently evil despite being told that it was unlikely that they could defeat the Viet Cong. Not only did they end up losing horribly but also lost the trust of the soldiers, who had been sent on government orders, and the American public that saw very little wrong in having leftist leanings. The government earned the wrath of a generation that decided to pour their pain into anti-war music, psychedelics and alternative living. Lesson learnt: don’t piss off people who can become the future Rolling Stones or Black Sabbath. The US isn’t the only nation to have fallen prey to this. The Chernobyl tragedy speaks for why unwavering belief in any ideology, especially one that prioritises the nation over its citizens, is the surest route to disaster. The Soviet Union’s adherence to not leaking any information about the nuclear power plant, its belief that it was virtually impossible for any Soviet construction to fail, let alone one that displayed its true might in a cold war, and immediate dismissal of scientific backing behind what could happen was what caused Mikhail Gorbachev to proclaim the Chernobyl disaster as the event that led to the collapse of the USSR. Nazi Germany is an even better example; people were wilfully ignorant of the dictatorship’s treatment of Jews in concentration camps. They believed that the power of the fatherland could extend everywhere without consequence. Groupthink is not a thing of the past either. In the present, groupthink is how groups of people become alienated from other ideas. Elite, educated liberals of the day choose not to explain their stance to people who oppose them, assuming the opposition to be inherently stupid. The same ‘inherently stupid’ then collectivise and assume majority power. Thereafter, even if someone from this group is presented with an alternative rationale, they will choose to reject it due to the distrust that has already been formed. This is best exemplified in how, in an age where political correctness has become a ‘necessity’, anyone with a contrary view of things is bashed instead of educated. This is not to say that all political correctness is unwarranted. However, if liberals choose to deride rather than increase awareness then they are simply contributing to the aforementioned alienation. On the other hand, conservatives around the world (who often overlap with the aforementioned ‘inherently stupid’) stick to societal norms that have existed for ages, even if they’re regressive. Groupthink is often the basis for dinner table conversations that revolve around politics; opposition to the favourite narrative, if any, will be met with loud, sharp words. These dynamics are used to the advantage of politicians like Donald Trump, who know how to appeal to their voter base. Groupthink extends beyond politics. It led to the subprime crisis in 2008. The financial industry ardently believed that no rational human being would ever default on his/her home loan. However, they took this to mean that loans could be given to anyone and everyone, and then they built complex securities based on these loans that were dependent on each other. The dot-com bubble in the early 2000’s is a good example too. The internet was the hottest property that was virtual, and people were naturally excited about its potential. This sentiment led to massive overvaluation of companies that merely had a website which combined with tech companies prioritising growth over profit and cash flow stability, led to the downfall of a number of firms. It is happening even today, with startups like Uber and WeWork launching their initial public offerings. WeWork is currently burning cash, and it has been subject to lots of scrutiny by the market. Adam Neumann, the founder, was recently ousted from the post of CEO. Uber took a huge plunge on its first day of going public. This shows how groupthink is responsible for hype value. Brands like Supreme, that rely simply on their logo being printed on what would otherwise be a plain white T-shirt, have the power of hype working in their favour. This hype has no concrete basis like quality. It builds up through targeted marketing. How does one escape groupthink? Most articles state one method right off the bat: create awareness of critical thinking skills that lead to thoughtful criticism. It might just be the case that what we do not wish to hear is what truly makes sense to us at times. Silence isn’t proof of consent from members. People who do not speak up must be encouraged to talk, since it’s entirely possible that they don’t want to only out of the fear of being chastised. Another way is to have the leader of the group take a poll before they announce their opinion. In that way, especially if the poll is anonymous, those who were not comfortable providing a perspective contrarian to the existing status quo can freely say what they want to. Another way is to appoint a devil’s advocate specifically for this purpose, or a red-team that makes a B-plan in contrast to yours. Groupthink offers a comfortable seat where you may not have to do a lot of thinking, or take a lot of responsibility. If a decision goes horribly wrong, then no single individual can be held accountable. However, if everyone in a group feels a heightened sense of pride towards the goal of a group, and can be made to believe that their actions have a large impact, positive or negative, then decisions will be taken with greater forethought and discussion. In times that value nuanced discussions over various ideas, we must be heading towards the ideal of free-flowing thought instead succumbing to peer pressure.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What Makes Bengal Bangla?</title>
      <link href="/What-Makes-Bengal-Bangla" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Makes Bengal Bangla?" />
      <published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-Makes-Bengal-Bangla</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-Makes-Bengal-Bangla">&lt;p&gt;This year, on our (India’s) Independence Day, a group of my friends were talking
about the celebrations when one of them mentioned that he feels that Bengalis
are the most patriotic of all in India. I had never really given this a lot of
thought before but the comment got me thinking: do we Bengalis really put our
country before everything? Do we put India before Bengal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always lived in the state of West Bengal, India. Now that I am studying
in Goa with people of different backgrounds and from different states, I see a
lot of differences between our culture and that of the rest of the country.
While we do share similar sentiments of pride towards our culture as the other
Indian states, the way our love for our traditions and heritage finds
manifestation is wildly different from anywhere else, possibly in the whole
world. For the longest time, India has taken pride in its diversity. The country
seeks unity in acknowledging, respecting and preserving the diversity in
culture, lineage and heritage. When politicians come up with ideas involving
linguistic homogenization of the country, India and her people respond with
passionate protests. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Language, an integral part of an ethnic group’s culture and an essence of their
non-material heritage, is a powerful political tool. It has the power to unify
nations like it did for Italy and Germany and on the other hand, create
conflicts like Catalonia and Spain. Language has been a central factor in the
demarcation of states in India. The ethno-linguistic divisions are definitely
not perfect for there exists over a hundred languages and more of their dialects
in the country. As a result, the political map of India is forever changing with
Telangana being born in 2014 and the fight for the Nepali majority Darjeeling
district of West Bengal’s fight for a separate state, Gorkhaland, still being
on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way Bengalis feel about their language is slightly different though. They
have never been afraid of giving up their lives to preserve their
mother-language, Bangla (or Bangali as non-Bengalis would call it). Unlike
France and groups of Gandhian ideologues, Bengalis do not seek to elevate their
mother-tongue to a higher pedestal only to counter the supremacy of English
(colonial language for the Indians). It is our love for our language,
literature, art and so on and so forth that make us do so, all thanks to the
Bangali Renaissance of the 1700s-1900s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1947, when British India was partitioned into the Republic of India and the
Islamic Republic of Pakistan right before their independence from colonial rule,
East Bengal became East Pakistan, solely because of the fact that it was home to
a majority of the Muslim population. Besides, the 200 years of the British
colonial policy of ‘Divide and Rule’ had proven to be remarkably efficacious,
resulting in alienating and pitting the Hindus and Muslims against each other in
the erstwhile state of Bengal. This helped in the Partition of Bengal into East
and West Bengal by the then British viceroy, Lord Curzon in 1905. Various
movements sprung up against the partition. Famous freedom fighter and future
Nobel-laureate, Rabindranath Tagore encouraged the celebration of
Raksha-Bandhan, a Hindu festival to honour the bond between a brother and a
sister, between Hindus and Muslims instead. Songs celebrating the unity between
the two religions found popularity as battle-cries of the energetic protests
against the actions of the English. However, Indians failed to stop what in my
personal opinion has been one of the most strategic ways to destroy Bengal’s
unity and a future as a unified state. The Partition of Bengal was later
annulled in 1911 but the province was never to be the same again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India was similarly partitioned, yet again, right before the transfer of power
in 1947. East Bengal was handed over to Prime Minister Jinnah’s Pakistan in a
platter that year. 55% of Pakistan’s population resided in East Pakistan and
yet, the distant minority residing in West Pakistan was to rule over them. This
lead to a great deal of resentment and problems, and they were not just limited
to the communication issues resulting from the uncomfortable fact that the two
halves of the country were separated by the state of India. Urdu was to be given
the status of the national language, effectively making it a language superior
to East Pakistan’s beloved mother-tongue Bangla. The Bangladesh Liberation
Movement, which finally concluded with the birth of yet another country,
Bangladesh in 1971, found momentum because of the Bangali population’s love for
their &lt;em&gt;Bangaliayana&lt;/em&gt;- the Bangali culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dhaka University played a central role in this movement. No wonder it had to see
blood spilt multiple times. One of the most shocking incidents of this movement,
fuelled by the love for Bangla also happens to be one of those incidents that
Bangalis, across borders, hold very close to heart. It took place on February
21st, 1952, when 4 students of Dhaka University were killed by the Pakistani
forces for opposing the sole use of Urdu in educational institutions across the
Bangali majority region. Today, the UN commemorates this day (21st of February)
as the International Mother Language Day every year. Every Bangali looks back at
this massacre with pride and respect because it symbolises the fact that their
love for their language is stronger than anything else can ever be.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, Bangalis have always been a very politically active culture. They
have never shied away from a revolution. The fact that most revolutionaries of
the Independence Movement were Bangali bears testimony to this fact. Even today,
West Bengal finds itself amidst protests and revolutions against what it
considers wrong throughout the year. It has already witnessed the &lt;em&gt;Doctor’s
Revolution&lt;/em&gt; and the protest against ABVP and RSS’s Hindutva-centric actions in
Jadavpur University this year itself. People of West Bengal’s love for
revolutions, change and socialism lies in stark contrast to the political
compass of most of the other parts of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sentimental views of how Bangladesh and the Bangali majority regions of India
ought to be a single country has existed for quite some time now. In fact, Prime
Minister Clement Attlee of UK predicted that Bengal would want to be united
under a single banner- it would want to rise above the religious demarcations
that virtually defined the rest of the country and unify for the love of Bangla
in 1946. HS Suhrawardy, the then premier of Bengal explained his stance in
support of an ‘independent, undivided and sovereign Bengal’ and appealed to the
masses on April 27th of 1947:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Let us pause for a moment to consider what Bengal can be if it remains united.
It will be a great country, indeed the richest and the most prosperous in India
capable of giving to its people a high standard of living, where a great people
will be able to rise to the fullest height of their stature, a land that will
truly be plentiful. It will be rich in agriculture, rich in industry and
commerce and in the course of time it will be one of the most powerful and
progressive states of the world. If Bengal remains united this will be no dream,
no fantasy.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the appeal to the Bangali exceptionalism, left-wingers supported this
cause, blaming all of Bengal’s ills on the non-Bangali capitalists. GD Birla was
quoted saying: “I am in favour of separation, and I do not think it is
impracticable or against the interest of Hindus” as early as 1942, on behalf of
the Marwari business community in Kolkata. If only the plan for Bengal
unification had been all about catering to the sole interests of Hindus. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even MA Jinnah supported the cause instead of wanting Bengal for Pakistan
although he had a slightly different reasoning, stating: “what is the use of
Bengal without Calcutta?” The most influential supporter of the plan to make
Bengal a separate nation was Sarat Chandra Bose, a popular congressman and the
elder brother of the celebrated freedom fighter, Subhash Chandra Bose. The
proposal for United Bengal involved equal quotas for Hindus and Muslims in the
military and the police, which were to be indigenised and ‘manned by Bangalis’.
The plan that was eventually made public on May 24th of 1947, 10 days before the
final Partition plan was announced, provided for a Hindu-Muslim coalition
Government in Unified Bengal. The Prime Minister was to be a Muslim and the Home
Minister a Hindu. However, the Hindu-Muslim riots in Kolkata around the same
time and the open opposition to the unification of Bengal by Sardar Vallabhai
Patil, Jawaharlal Nehru and later even Gandhiji, eventually led to this plan
being discarded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why most non-Bangali Indian leaders failed to support the idea of the
formation of a third country is because they thought that it would lay down a
precedent for other states to follow and demand independence. On May 27th, 1947,
Nehru made a formal declaration that he would support the unification only if
Bengal was to remain as a part of the Indian Union. This sparked a response from
the last British Governor of Bengal, Sir Frederick Burrows: “Bengal will be
sacrificed at the altar of Nehru’s all-India outlook.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sentiments did not, however, die with the failure of the plan to unify
Bengal in 1947. The Brihot Bangla or Bishal Bangla Movement (Greater Bengal
Movement) is a nationalist political ideology which seeks to unite all bangali
speaking regions of today’s India, Bangladesh and Myanmar into a single nation.
If I am to draw an analogy (although it is very difficult to find one for it is
as unique as it can possibly get), I would say that it is like Kurdistan. The
Kurds are a nation without a state. The Bangalis too are unified by their
language but not by land. bangali literature has always referred to their
country as ‘Bangla’, the same word as they use to refer to their language.
However, Bangla does not refer to either India or Bangladesh, it refers to the
Unified Bengal. So yes, Bangalis are patriotic. But, they are patriotic towards
Bangla before any country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Nehru thought Bengal was just like other Indian states and that the
unification of Bengal and a consequent separate state would result in similar
sentiments in other states like Tamil Nadu, I disagree. The sentiments are
stronger among Bangalis because half of our own state (or country, for a
Bangladeshi) is a separate country. People from West Bengal have grown up with
stories of Bangla and how some of our ancestors had to cross borders during the
Partition and how they still long to go back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nostalgia, the resentment of the Hindu-Muslim divide and the love for
Bangla, both the language and the motherland keeps the emotions and nationalist
sentiments alive even today. For every Bangali, half of their identity lies in
West Bengal and the remaining half lies in Bangladesh. For every Bangali,
language is the identity- not religion, not dialects but Bangla. Whether or not
we are destined to ever be unified is a question yet to be answered. What
doesn’t change is the fact that even though we do not have a separate country of
Bangla, we are still unified as Bangalis.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This year, on our (India’s) Independence Day, a group of my friends were talking about the celebrations when one of them mentioned that he feels that Bengalis are the most patriotic of all in India. I had never really given this a lot of thought before but the comment got me thinking: do we Bengalis really put our country before everything? Do we put India before Bengal? I have always lived in the state of West Bengal, India. Now that I am studying in Goa with people of different backgrounds and from different states, I see a lot of differences between our culture and that of the rest of the country. While we do share similar sentiments of pride towards our culture as the other Indian states, the way our love for our traditions and heritage finds manifestation is wildly different from anywhere else, possibly in the whole world. For the longest time, India has taken pride in its diversity. The country seeks unity in acknowledging, respecting and preserving the diversity in culture, lineage and heritage. When politicians come up with ideas involving linguistic homogenization of the country, India and her people respond with passionate protests.  Language, an integral part of an ethnic group’s culture and an essence of their non-material heritage, is a powerful political tool. It has the power to unify nations like it did for Italy and Germany and on the other hand, create conflicts like Catalonia and Spain. Language has been a central factor in the demarcation of states in India. The ethno-linguistic divisions are definitely not perfect for there exists over a hundred languages and more of their dialects in the country. As a result, the political map of India is forever changing with Telangana being born in 2014 and the fight for the Nepali majority Darjeeling district of West Bengal’s fight for a separate state, Gorkhaland, still being on.  The way Bengalis feel about their language is slightly different though. They have never been afraid of giving up their lives to preserve their mother-language, Bangla (or Bangali as non-Bengalis would call it). Unlike France and groups of Gandhian ideologues, Bengalis do not seek to elevate their mother-tongue to a higher pedestal only to counter the supremacy of English (colonial language for the Indians). It is our love for our language, literature, art and so on and so forth that make us do so, all thanks to the Bangali Renaissance of the 1700s-1900s.  In 1947, when British India was partitioned into the Republic of India and the Islamic Republic of Pakistan right before their independence from colonial rule, East Bengal became East Pakistan, solely because of the fact that it was home to a majority of the Muslim population. Besides, the 200 years of the British colonial policy of ‘Divide and Rule’ had proven to be remarkably efficacious, resulting in alienating and pitting the Hindus and Muslims against each other in the erstwhile state of Bengal. This helped in the Partition of Bengal into East and West Bengal by the then British viceroy, Lord Curzon in 1905. Various movements sprung up against the partition. Famous freedom fighter and future Nobel-laureate, Rabindranath Tagore encouraged the celebration of Raksha-Bandhan, a Hindu festival to honour the bond between a brother and a sister, between Hindus and Muslims instead. Songs celebrating the unity between the two religions found popularity as battle-cries of the energetic protests against the actions of the English. However, Indians failed to stop what in my personal opinion has been one of the most strategic ways to destroy Bengal’s unity and a future as a unified state. The Partition of Bengal was later annulled in 1911 but the province was never to be the same again. India was similarly partitioned, yet again, right before the transfer of power in 1947. East Bengal was handed over to Prime Minister Jinnah’s Pakistan in a platter that year. 55% of Pakistan’s population resided in East Pakistan and yet, the distant minority residing in West Pakistan was to rule over them. This lead to a great deal of resentment and problems, and they were not just limited to the communication issues resulting from the uncomfortable fact that the two halves of the country were separated by the state of India. Urdu was to be given the status of the national language, effectively making it a language superior to East Pakistan’s beloved mother-tongue Bangla. The Bangladesh Liberation Movement, which finally concluded with the birth of yet another country, Bangladesh in 1971, found momentum because of the Bangali population’s love for their Bangaliayana- the Bangali culture. Dhaka University played a central role in this movement. No wonder it had to see blood spilt multiple times. One of the most shocking incidents of this movement, fuelled by the love for Bangla also happens to be one of those incidents that Bangalis, across borders, hold very close to heart. It took place on February 21st, 1952, when 4 students of Dhaka University were killed by the Pakistani forces for opposing the sole use of Urdu in educational institutions across the Bangali majority region. Today, the UN commemorates this day (21st of February) as the International Mother Language Day every year. Every Bangali looks back at this massacre with pride and respect because it symbolises the fact that their love for their language is stronger than anything else can ever be.    Historically, Bangalis have always been a very politically active culture. They have never shied away from a revolution. The fact that most revolutionaries of the Independence Movement were Bangali bears testimony to this fact. Even today, West Bengal finds itself amidst protests and revolutions against what it considers wrong throughout the year. It has already witnessed the Doctor’s Revolution and the protest against ABVP and RSS’s Hindutva-centric actions in Jadavpur University this year itself. People of West Bengal’s love for revolutions, change and socialism lies in stark contrast to the political compass of most of the other parts of India. Sentimental views of how Bangladesh and the Bangali majority regions of India ought to be a single country has existed for quite some time now. In fact, Prime Minister Clement Attlee of UK predicted that Bengal would want to be united under a single banner- it would want to rise above the religious demarcations that virtually defined the rest of the country and unify for the love of Bangla in 1946. HS Suhrawardy, the then premier of Bengal explained his stance in support of an ‘independent, undivided and sovereign Bengal’ and appealed to the masses on April 27th of 1947: “Let us pause for a moment to consider what Bengal can be if it remains united. It will be a great country, indeed the richest and the most prosperous in India capable of giving to its people a high standard of living, where a great people will be able to rise to the fullest height of their stature, a land that will truly be plentiful. It will be rich in agriculture, rich in industry and commerce and in the course of time it will be one of the most powerful and progressive states of the world. If Bengal remains united this will be no dream, no fantasy.” Besides the appeal to the Bangali exceptionalism, left-wingers supported this cause, blaming all of Bengal’s ills on the non-Bangali capitalists. GD Birla was quoted saying: “I am in favour of separation, and I do not think it is impracticable or against the interest of Hindus” as early as 1942, on behalf of the Marwari business community in Kolkata. If only the plan for Bengal unification had been all about catering to the sole interests of Hindus.  Even MA Jinnah supported the cause instead of wanting Bengal for Pakistan although he had a slightly different reasoning, stating: “what is the use of Bengal without Calcutta?” The most influential supporter of the plan to make Bengal a separate nation was Sarat Chandra Bose, a popular congressman and the elder brother of the celebrated freedom fighter, Subhash Chandra Bose. The proposal for United Bengal involved equal quotas for Hindus and Muslims in the military and the police, which were to be indigenised and ‘manned by Bangalis’. The plan that was eventually made public on May 24th of 1947, 10 days before the final Partition plan was announced, provided for a Hindu-Muslim coalition Government in Unified Bengal. The Prime Minister was to be a Muslim and the Home Minister a Hindu. However, the Hindu-Muslim riots in Kolkata around the same time and the open opposition to the unification of Bengal by Sardar Vallabhai Patil, Jawaharlal Nehru and later even Gandhiji, eventually led to this plan being discarded.  The reason why most non-Bangali Indian leaders failed to support the idea of the formation of a third country is because they thought that it would lay down a precedent for other states to follow and demand independence. On May 27th, 1947, Nehru made a formal declaration that he would support the unification only if Bengal was to remain as a part of the Indian Union. This sparked a response from the last British Governor of Bengal, Sir Frederick Burrows: “Bengal will be sacrificed at the altar of Nehru’s all-India outlook.”  The sentiments did not, however, die with the failure of the plan to unify Bengal in 1947. The Brihot Bangla or Bishal Bangla Movement (Greater Bengal Movement) is a nationalist political ideology which seeks to unite all bangali speaking regions of today’s India, Bangladesh and Myanmar into a single nation. If I am to draw an analogy (although it is very difficult to find one for it is as unique as it can possibly get), I would say that it is like Kurdistan. The Kurds are a nation without a state. The Bangalis too are unified by their language but not by land. bangali literature has always referred to their country as ‘Bangla’, the same word as they use to refer to their language. However, Bangla does not refer to either India or Bangladesh, it refers to the Unified Bengal. So yes, Bangalis are patriotic. But, they are patriotic towards Bangla before any country.   While Nehru thought Bengal was just like other Indian states and that the unification of Bengal and a consequent separate state would result in similar sentiments in other states like Tamil Nadu, I disagree. The sentiments are stronger among Bangalis because half of our own state (or country, for a Bangladeshi) is a separate country. People from West Bengal have grown up with stories of Bangla and how some of our ancestors had to cross borders during the Partition and how they still long to go back. The nostalgia, the resentment of the Hindu-Muslim divide and the love for Bangla, both the language and the motherland keeps the emotions and nationalist sentiments alive even today. For every Bangali, half of their identity lies in West Bengal and the remaining half lies in Bangladesh. For every Bangali, language is the identity- not religion, not dialects but Bangla. Whether or not we are destined to ever be unified is a question yet to be answered. What doesn’t change is the fact that even though we do not have a separate country of Bangla, we are still unified as Bangalis.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Modern Slavery: Inside the Transgender Communities of India and Pakistan</title>
      <link href="/Modern-Slavery" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modern Slavery: Inside the Transgender Communities of India and Pakistan" />
      <published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Modern-Slavery</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Modern-Slavery">&lt;p&gt;Our world is imbued with contradictions and opposing realities which inform our lives. Nowhere is this more evident than in our social setting. While some reap benefits of the rights and privileges bestowed upon them, others remain tangled in the subjugating mesh of society. The trapped transgenders either end up mangled under the massive burden of gender roles or end up conforming to the gender expectations ascribed to the sex in which they were &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; born, as a means of expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accident of birth has had serious ramifications on many, but none have been affected as gravely as the transgender. Betrayed by their bodies, and disowned by their families and communities, the transgender (including the eunuch and the intersex), popularly termed as &lt;em&gt;hijras&lt;/em&gt; in India and Pakistan, live as social outcasts, misfits for committing the grave crime of expressing their identities. Their existence itself poses a great threat to social conceptions of gender and sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living in such countries, especially Pakistan where a manic obsession with gender roles reigns over every soul, certainly isn’t easy. The slightest deviation from societal conventions may result in ostracisation and humiliation; primarily the reason why the community is forced into darkness, into total seclusion. The expression of individuality comes at the great price of losing honour and respect. Having been stripped of all rights and dignity, they are forced into begging, prostitution, dancing as a means to earn their living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of mankind has largely revolved around freedom, power and recognition. It is a human need to be recognised and respected by others. Our identities form the very basis of our personhood. This is primarily why we assert ourselves wherever we go. We want our presence to be felt. But what if somebody just takes it all away from us? It would cause a massive dent on our personhood. This is precisely what the transgender community undergoes. Society robs them of their personhood. Life for them is suffering; it begins with gender dysphoria and their struggle to recognise themselves and ends with society deeming them as weeds unfit to be with others; the &lt;em&gt;normal&lt;/em&gt; lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forced to remain hidden from the public eye, they form secret communities that observe their own mysterious codes and customs. One such custom is the rite of initiation, where every new transgender wishing to join the community must go through the painful procedure of emasculation and then be accepted by a &lt;em&gt;guru&lt;/em&gt;, who assumes a paternalistic role in the life of the newly initiated novice. The guru – novice relationship forms the bedrock of the transgender community. This is where things start turning really dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initiate or the novice, who is purchased in exchange of money, is literally at the mercy of the guru. She is penalised and punished severely if she fails to discharge the duties imposed on her. And if at all she decides to leave, she is shunned from the entire community. After being purchased, the novice is then forced by the guru into performing professions like begging, dancing, etc. to earn money; a major chunk of which goes to the guru. This practice almost seems like a modern form of slavery, but because of how inherent it is to the culture, it goes unquestioned and unopposed. Sadly, the tradition which was created to protect starts fettering them and taking away their freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the tremendous pressure imposed by the gurus, the novices at times may even have to indulge in sex work for money. Since they are denied all respectable jobs, several transgenders have to undergo this torment. They are coerced, tortured, raped- all under the knowledge of their gurus. Unable to complain to the authorities and fearing further harassment, they are forced to remain silent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the young transgender, there remains no respite. On one end, they have to deal with repression from society and on the other, the monopoly of the greedy gurus. Another threat looming over their reality is the possibility of acquiring sexually transmitted diseases. Living in denial, they refuse to get themselves medically examined and continue living in unsafe conditions. They, nevertheless, continue existing, because for them nothing can surpass the feeling of power that comes along with expressing oneself and getting acknowledged as the person one wishes to be. The exhibition of identity becomes the sole purpose of their existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back to the guru-novice relationship, it’s important to understand that no cultural practice is free of fault. As in the case of this relationship, every cultural practice harbours in itself certain forms of darkness, often hidden from the rest of the world. The only way out here, is for change to come from the outside, so that these cultural practices automatically dismantle and disintegrate, without being meddled with. Change is slowly coming about; transgenders in India and Pakistan are being recognised as a third gender. With a state-issued identity of their own, they can now avail opportunities previously known only to the two genders, and therefore, reduce their dependence on the guru-novice practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acceptance in society can only come with greater visibility. For an all-inclusive world, the transgender community, with all its eccentricity and richness, must be integrated into the mainstream of society. There exists a need to create space for identity to breathe, which must then be recognised and respected. Especially in Asian countries where these groups are attached to labels of abnormality, there is a necessity to uproot the social stigma surrounding their existence. This can only happen when we begin to recognise them as humans before ascribing a gender identity to them.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Our world is imbued with contradictions and opposing realities which inform our lives. Nowhere is this more evident than in our social setting. While some reap benefits of the rights and privileges bestowed upon them, others remain tangled in the subjugating mesh of society. The trapped transgenders either end up mangled under the massive burden of gender roles or end up conforming to the gender expectations ascribed to the sex in which they were not born, as a means of expression.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Watch Me Watch You Watch Me</title>
      <link href="/Watch-Me-Watch-You-Watch-Me" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Watch Me Watch You Watch Me" />
      <published>2019-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Watch-Me-Watch-You-Watch-Me</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Watch-Me-Watch-You-Watch-Me">&lt;p&gt;Most of us in some way, shape or form love social media. We spend hours
scrolling through content, liking and commenting as we go along. All of our
actions generate data which is then collected by these social media companies
and used, to encourage us to use their platforms more: the so-called addictive
factor. The more data a social media platform collects, the larger their profit
margins. Not only do we consume content, but we also partake in the creation of
content which further keeps users on these platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take Instagram for example. When you upload a photo of yourself on a beach
holiday in Mauritius, it is added to the collective of all posts by Instagram.
Now Instagram is going to do its best to get as many people to view, like and
comment on your post. This brings two benefits to them. One, it learns about the
consumer’s preferences and interests based on what they look at. Two, each
notification you receive about that post will trigger a dopamine response making
you more likely to click on it and get back on the app. Now you can see from
just one post, Instagram is able to keep your followers on the app as well as
yourself. And every additional action carried out on Instagram generates a data
point on us to be sold to the highest bidder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media sites are also designed to make it as easy as possible for us to
post something. By studying how we use the app, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/habits-five-ways-to-help-users-change-them&quot;&gt;UI/UX designers are further
improving apps to make creating content a force of
habit&lt;/a&gt;.
These habits slowly meld into our lives to the point we don’t even have to think
before carrying out all the actions required to open Facebook on our phones and
get onto a Livestream. Now that we have come full circle, we realise the
horrible truth, that we are the creators of our own downfall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;em&gt;“Social media, it’s just the market’s answer to a generation that demanded to
perform. So the market said, ‘Here, perform everything to each other, all the
time, for no reason.’ It’s prison. It’s horrific. It is performer and audience
melded together,”&lt;/em&gt; He then goes on to add, &lt;em&gt;“I know very little about anything,
but what I do know is that if you can live your life without an audience, you
should do it.”&lt;/em&gt; - Bo Burnham's comedy special &lt;em&gt;Make Happy&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does this mean for us? Once you understand how social media works, you
begin to realise that the platforms only have power because we give it to them.
And if we can give them the power, we can also take it back. Sometimes it feels
like one person can’t make a difference, but much like democracy, every single
person counts. The next time you find yourself appalled by Facebook’s unethical
data practices. Just stop and think for a little, how much of an accomplice are
you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media is a great tool to connect, discover and learn but failure to
understand the machinations behind how social media works can lead us down a
vicious cycle of consumption. Sometimes all we need to take control… is to
take a step back.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Avinash Naidu</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Most of us in some way, shape or form love social media. We spend hours scrolling through content, liking and commenting as we go along. All of our actions generate data which is then collected by these social media companies and used, to encourage us to use their platforms more: the so-called addictive factor. The more data a social media platform collects, the larger their profit margins. Not only do we consume content, but we also partake in the creation of content which further keeps users on these platforms. Let’s take Instagram for example. When you upload a photo of yourself on a beach holiday in Mauritius, it is added to the collective of all posts by Instagram. Now Instagram is going to do its best to get as many people to view, like and comment on your post. This brings two benefits to them. One, it learns about the consumer’s preferences and interests based on what they look at. Two, each notification you receive about that post will trigger a dopamine response making you more likely to click on it and get back on the app. Now you can see from just one post, Instagram is able to keep your followers on the app as well as yourself. And every additional action carried out on Instagram generates a data point on us to be sold to the highest bidder. Social media sites are also designed to make it as easy as possible for us to post something. By studying how we use the app, UI/UX designers are further improving apps to make creating content a force of habit. These habits slowly meld into our lives to the point we don’t even have to think before carrying out all the actions required to open Facebook on our phones and get onto a Livestream. Now that we have come full circle, we realise the horrible truth, that we are the creators of our own downfall. “Social media, it’s just the market’s answer to a generation that demanded to perform. So the market said, ‘Here, perform everything to each other, all the time, for no reason.’ It’s prison. It’s horrific. It is performer and audience melded together,” He then goes on to add, “I know very little about anything, but what I do know is that if you can live your life without an audience, you should do it.” - Bo Burnham's comedy special Make Happy. So what does this mean for us? Once you understand how social media works, you begin to realise that the platforms only have power because we give it to them. And if we can give them the power, we can also take it back. Sometimes it feels like one person can’t make a difference, but much like democracy, every single person counts. The next time you find yourself appalled by Facebook’s unethical data practices. Just stop and think for a little, how much of an accomplice are you? Social media is a great tool to connect, discover and learn but failure to understand the machinations behind how social media works can lead us down a vicious cycle of consumption. Sometimes all we need to take control… is to take a step back.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">On TikTok and The Breathlessness of Social Climbing</title>
      <link href="/The-Breathlessness-of-Social-Climbing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On TikTok and The Breathlessness of Social Climbing" />
      <published>2019-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Breathlessness-of-Social-Climbing</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Breathlessness-of-Social-Climbing">&lt;p&gt;As he fishhooks his worn-out khaki &lt;em&gt;jhola&lt;/em&gt; (bag) for keys and reaches out arm
deep to the floor of his bag, the peculiar lines on his forehead curl up into a
sweaty keyhole around his sandalwood &lt;em&gt;tilak&lt;/em&gt;, and it is with some pensive
exertion that he says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“You cannot ever erase your caste. But you sure can pretend to change it. &lt;br /&gt;
The rules of the game are pretty simple back in my village. &lt;br /&gt;
If you have a hearth and nothing else, you count on god. &lt;br /&gt;
If you have a hearth and a cow, you can negotiate with your god. &lt;br /&gt;
If you have a hearth and a cow and a land, you are your own god.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ronge Kumar is a 39-year-old sweeper and errand guy at the local temple near my
place of domicile in North Delhi, India. His favourite sport, second only to
knowing all the Hindu gods’ genealogy trivia like the back of his hand, is
stealing time for his almost ritualistic TikTok consumption in the slimy
contours between the work-home binary at the temple.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I conjecture up an introduction for him in foresight of a biographical
essay I might someday write about him, he overruns my train of thought to
continue his monologue: “One of the greatest pieces of unwitting disclosure is
your father’s name. Your father might not leave you an inheritance but he sure
will leave you a family name as a mortgage against your self respect. How do you
go on pretending to be a different person while carrying your family tree on
your shoulder? The city, with all its noise, is easy on you, because it does not
have time to care.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If all identity is indeed a performance, Kumar’s predicament really leaves me
questioning the semantics of visibility in a society that, at once, implicates
us as performers of our everyday identities and an audience to others’. This, I
intend not as much in a Shakespearean sense of the word as much in a social
constructionist sort of way. The fact that I ‘pass’ as a normal, functional unit
of the social context, is but a deliberate, concerted project of everyday
performance. However, when the context is all too familiar and the performer too
visible, it is hard to ‘pass’ without being held to public scrutiny for
everything you do. Thus, the respite Kumar attributes to the city is the
relative autonomy that his anonymity here can afford for him. This anonymity is
only augmented when he enters the internet, to a point of discord, if not
dissociation from his identities back home and in the city. This is not to say
that the internet exists in a social vacuum, free from the social categories
that define our identity on the ground, but that it offers every new entrant a
clean slate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kumar’s TikTok profile, then, is an embodiment of his existential anxieties of
upward social mobility. His TikTok username, ‘Pandit’ Ronge, above everything,
enables him to attach a Brahminical prefix to his name, something that is
inaccessible to him in the material world. What we see with Kumar then is a more
universal tendency to use the virtual world to live one’s aspirations
vicariously, as in when a 5-year-old chooses a conventionally attractive gaming
avatar to represent themself to the other players, but more so, a social desire
for upward movement. The caste system in India, like most hierarchies, can be
understood as a classic game of Jenga, wherein each participant takes a turn
removing one of the blocks not located on the top three levels and places it on
top of the tower without knocking it down. One’s participation in the game not
only presupposes but also actively ensures that the larger structure of
hierarchical arrangement of the blocks stays in place. An inevitable consequence
of the mobility of the blocks, however, is that the base of the tower
progressively becomes more unstable and struggles to support its heavy top until
it eventually collapses, with the loser being the participant who pulled the
block that caused the demolition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How caste operates in India is much like the rules of Jenga, in that it is as
self preservatory as it is self-destructive. This is to say that while the rules
of the game ensure that the larger structure stays in place, acting out those
very rules also creates possibilities of change within it. But nobody wants to
be singled out as the loser who upset the structure. Thus, mobility desires, if
not demands, anonymity. Most social systems, in that sense, are a long
negotiation of social position within the structure. In negotiating this place,
it puts forth its end of the bargain, creates new fiction to support its claim,
and gradually acquires cultural practices of those above it in the hierarchy.
Social mobility is a cumbersome summit. You spend most days social climbing and
other days catching your breath from all the climbing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in the true Foucauldian sense, what Pandit Ronge also does is that in order
of being represented, ends up subjectifying himself by the very presupposition
of representation. That is, while you start with a clean slate, the moment you
start representing yourself, you also start creating fiction about yourself and
the group people associate you with. This idea approximates the terrain this
essay attempts to explore. Most of what I am trying to say then lies in the
contours of being the butt of a joke and cracking a joke, which is to say, “Are
we laughing at a person or with a person?” or “Is the person less subject, more
object of humour?” This is not to say that performance of humorous content
cannot be funny but the fact that something that is being performed diligently
by one, comes across as funny to another, is an act of violence to the
performer’s diligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ways in which TikTok is consumed today, like most entertainment, is an idiom
for our social existence. For the uninitiated, TikTok is a video app for
creating and sharing short lip-sync, comedy, and talent videos. Previously known
as ‘Musical.ly’, it was acquired in 2018 by a Chinese tech firm and merged with
its Asian counterpart to become TikTok. Currently, with over 800 million active
users, the app has snowballed into an online entertainment giant with popular
creators on the app burgeoning into social media influencers. How then is TikTok
any different from its American short-form video counterpart ‘Vine’, except that
it is not shutting down anytime soon? Social context, mostly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TikTok in India has seeped into Indian houses through the creaks in our
ceilings, and the damp in our walls, strumming the iron bars on our windows like
an amateur guitarist mindlessly learning to toy around with a guitar. From the
iconisation of the Indian mother butting out her kid from the frame to invite
people for tea with her catchphrase, “Hello friends, chai peelo”, to
impassioned, young, brown men, bawling their eyes out in classic misogynistic
Bollywood bereavement fashion; from drought-hit farmers in Maharashtra
lip-syncing to colloquial protest songs and unionising on the internet to
teenagers turned lip-syncing social media influencers, landing modelling
contracts, TikTok has captured the popular imagination in India, with no
precedent. While humour is one of the top genres of content creation on the app,
a larger source of humour is that which is unintended. While the content of most
of these videos reinstates heteronormative, fat-phobic, often hyper nationalist
semantics of Indian households, the performers are also, more often than not,
rampantly fat-shamed and trolled in casteist, classist ways by the elite, the
ignorant, the woke and the conservative, alike. Meme pages on Facebook and
Instagram create targeted content laughing away what they call the ‘chapri’
TikToker. ‘Chapri’, as defined by the urban dictionary is a colloquial slur in
Bombay for ‘low-tier wannabe fuckboys, characterised by ripped jeans, neon
flip-flops, coloured hair, and speeding motorcycles. Mostly found within the
Bandra-Kurla-Andheri triad.’ Given how hyperlocal it is, the context of the
‘chapri’ performers is that the Kurla- Andheri region houses some of the
largest, most densely populated slums in the country. We cannot thus, begin to
understand the violence of humour without politicising identities. TikTok in
India is as much about entertainment and trolling, characteristic of the rest of
the internet, as it is about reclamation and ownership of entertainment. While
it lets some live a Bollywood dream or a social mobility dream, it is also
implicated in the meanings that construct it. This is to say that the liberation
it affords comes from a presupposed bargain of socio-cultural capital, where a
17-year-old with a ring light and an iPhone will pivot an influencer career, &lt;em&gt;in
spite&lt;/em&gt; of trolls, while a 19-year-old ‘gully boy’ becomes a one-hit wonder
&lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of trolls or is jettisoned in the hyperspace of the internet. But,
again, it is not as binary as my last sentence makes it sound and the
eclecticism is where the heart of internet democratisation lies. As I sit musing
the politics of humour in the temple backyard, the large clock in the temple
ticks six and Ronge calls me out from through the large iron gate of the temple
asking if I want to watch him record his prayers for TikTok. I relent and call
it a day.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Yashna Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As he fishhooks his worn-out khaki jhola (bag) for keys and reaches out arm deep to the floor of his bag, the peculiar lines on his forehead curl up into a sweaty keyhole around his sandalwood tilak, and it is with some pensive exertion that he says, “You cannot ever erase your caste. But you sure can pretend to change it.  The rules of the game are pretty simple back in my village.  If you have a hearth and nothing else, you count on god. If you have a hearth and a cow, you can negotiate with your god. If you have a hearth and a cow and a land, you are your own god.” Ronge Kumar is a 39-year-old sweeper and errand guy at the local temple near my place of domicile in North Delhi, India. His favourite sport, second only to knowing all the Hindu gods’ genealogy trivia like the back of his hand, is stealing time for his almost ritualistic TikTok consumption in the slimy contours between the work-home binary at the temple.   While I conjecture up an introduction for him in foresight of a biographical essay I might someday write about him, he overruns my train of thought to continue his monologue: “One of the greatest pieces of unwitting disclosure is your father’s name. Your father might not leave you an inheritance but he sure will leave you a family name as a mortgage against your self respect. How do you go on pretending to be a different person while carrying your family tree on your shoulder? The city, with all its noise, is easy on you, because it does not have time to care.” If all identity is indeed a performance, Kumar’s predicament really leaves me questioning the semantics of visibility in a society that, at once, implicates us as performers of our everyday identities and an audience to others’. This, I intend not as much in a Shakespearean sense of the word as much in a social constructionist sort of way. The fact that I ‘pass’ as a normal, functional unit of the social context, is but a deliberate, concerted project of everyday performance. However, when the context is all too familiar and the performer too visible, it is hard to ‘pass’ without being held to public scrutiny for everything you do. Thus, the respite Kumar attributes to the city is the relative autonomy that his anonymity here can afford for him. This anonymity is only augmented when he enters the internet, to a point of discord, if not dissociation from his identities back home and in the city. This is not to say that the internet exists in a social vacuum, free from the social categories that define our identity on the ground, but that it offers every new entrant a clean slate. Kumar’s TikTok profile, then, is an embodiment of his existential anxieties of upward social mobility. His TikTok username, ‘Pandit’ Ronge, above everything, enables him to attach a Brahminical prefix to his name, something that is inaccessible to him in the material world. What we see with Kumar then is a more universal tendency to use the virtual world to live one’s aspirations vicariously, as in when a 5-year-old chooses a conventionally attractive gaming avatar to represent themself to the other players, but more so, a social desire for upward movement. The caste system in India, like most hierarchies, can be understood as a classic game of Jenga, wherein each participant takes a turn removing one of the blocks not located on the top three levels and places it on top of the tower without knocking it down. One’s participation in the game not only presupposes but also actively ensures that the larger structure of hierarchical arrangement of the blocks stays in place. An inevitable consequence of the mobility of the blocks, however, is that the base of the tower progressively becomes more unstable and struggles to support its heavy top until it eventually collapses, with the loser being the participant who pulled the block that caused the demolition. How caste operates in India is much like the rules of Jenga, in that it is as self preservatory as it is self-destructive. This is to say that while the rules of the game ensure that the larger structure stays in place, acting out those very rules also creates possibilities of change within it. But nobody wants to be singled out as the loser who upset the structure. Thus, mobility desires, if not demands, anonymity. Most social systems, in that sense, are a long negotiation of social position within the structure. In negotiating this place, it puts forth its end of the bargain, creates new fiction to support its claim, and gradually acquires cultural practices of those above it in the hierarchy. Social mobility is a cumbersome summit. You spend most days social climbing and other days catching your breath from all the climbing.  But, in the true Foucauldian sense, what Pandit Ronge also does is that in order of being represented, ends up subjectifying himself by the very presupposition of representation. That is, while you start with a clean slate, the moment you start representing yourself, you also start creating fiction about yourself and the group people associate you with. This idea approximates the terrain this essay attempts to explore. Most of what I am trying to say then lies in the contours of being the butt of a joke and cracking a joke, which is to say, “Are we laughing at a person or with a person?” or “Is the person less subject, more object of humour?” This is not to say that performance of humorous content cannot be funny but the fact that something that is being performed diligently by one, comes across as funny to another, is an act of violence to the performer’s diligence. The ways in which TikTok is consumed today, like most entertainment, is an idiom for our social existence. For the uninitiated, TikTok is a video app for creating and sharing short lip-sync, comedy, and talent videos. Previously known as ‘Musical.ly’, it was acquired in 2018 by a Chinese tech firm and merged with its Asian counterpart to become TikTok. Currently, with over 800 million active users, the app has snowballed into an online entertainment giant with popular creators on the app burgeoning into social media influencers. How then is TikTok any different from its American short-form video counterpart ‘Vine’, except that it is not shutting down anytime soon? Social context, mostly.  TikTok in India has seeped into Indian houses through the creaks in our ceilings, and the damp in our walls, strumming the iron bars on our windows like an amateur guitarist mindlessly learning to toy around with a guitar. From the iconisation of the Indian mother butting out her kid from the frame to invite people for tea with her catchphrase, “Hello friends, chai peelo”, to impassioned, young, brown men, bawling their eyes out in classic misogynistic Bollywood bereavement fashion; from drought-hit farmers in Maharashtra lip-syncing to colloquial protest songs and unionising on the internet to teenagers turned lip-syncing social media influencers, landing modelling contracts, TikTok has captured the popular imagination in India, with no precedent. While humour is one of the top genres of content creation on the app, a larger source of humour is that which is unintended. While the content of most of these videos reinstates heteronormative, fat-phobic, often hyper nationalist semantics of Indian households, the performers are also, more often than not, rampantly fat-shamed and trolled in casteist, classist ways by the elite, the ignorant, the woke and the conservative, alike. Meme pages on Facebook and Instagram create targeted content laughing away what they call the ‘chapri’ TikToker. ‘Chapri’, as defined by the urban dictionary is a colloquial slur in Bombay for ‘low-tier wannabe fuckboys, characterised by ripped jeans, neon flip-flops, coloured hair, and speeding motorcycles. Mostly found within the Bandra-Kurla-Andheri triad.’ Given how hyperlocal it is, the context of the ‘chapri’ performers is that the Kurla- Andheri region houses some of the largest, most densely populated slums in the country. We cannot thus, begin to understand the violence of humour without politicising identities. TikTok in India is as much about entertainment and trolling, characteristic of the rest of the internet, as it is about reclamation and ownership of entertainment. While it lets some live a Bollywood dream or a social mobility dream, it is also implicated in the meanings that construct it. This is to say that the liberation it affords comes from a presupposed bargain of socio-cultural capital, where a 17-year-old with a ring light and an iPhone will pivot an influencer career, in spite of trolls, while a 19-year-old ‘gully boy’ becomes a one-hit wonder because of trolls or is jettisoned in the hyperspace of the internet. But, again, it is not as binary as my last sentence makes it sound and the eclecticism is where the heart of internet democratisation lies. As I sit musing the politics of humour in the temple backyard, the large clock in the temple ticks six and Ronge calls me out from through the large iron gate of the temple asking if I want to watch him record his prayers for TikTok. I relent and call it a day.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">I Hate You Like I Love You: Demythologising The Indian Mother</title>
      <link href="/The-Indian-Mother" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Hate You Like I Love You: Demythologising The Indian Mother" />
      <published>2019-09-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Indian-Mother</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Indian-Mother">&lt;p&gt;If you’ve cringed at the Mother’s Day wishes that flooded social media a few weeks ago, which were basically variations of ‘she is the world’s smartest, strongest punching bag’, (go Leslie Knope!) you’ll probably see a valid point in what I have to discuss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mothers are strange creatures. But do you know what’s stranger? The myth of motherhood, carefully curated by patriarchy and capitalism in India. What’s in it for them? Well, everything. This myth furthers their profiteering ventures through the sinister exploitation of a sentiment. They show mothers as goddesses, whose only joy lies in serving you, and her family well. She has no personal wishes, and her sexuality can very well be forgotten about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advertisements portray women with ten hands (and I do not mean this figuratively), happily cooking up idlis, dosas, and parathas to serve a perfect breakfast to each member of the family. The grandfather nonchalantly reads the newspaper, the three petulant children complain (among whom is her husband, complaining the loudest about the late breakfast, so go figure), when the mother magically appears with trays full of scrumptious food. The mother is supposed to flutter her eyelashes and cry tears of joy when her husband decides to make her breakfast once a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian mother is supposed to selflessly love and consistently deliver. The ‘progressive’ advertisements are no better. The mother has short hair, works outside the house but god forbid if she comes home and lies down on the sofa after a long day. The ‘woke’ ads are packaged to comfortably suit our definition of empowerment without radically questioning it or demanding any action. The mother must juggle office work and domestic duties dexterously because, well, human fatigue does not apply to mythological beings, and this is what motherhood has mostly been depicted as in popular culture. A myth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m choosing to bypass Bollywood because that would require a separate article of its own, but I am sure you can make the connections. I choose standard examples from advertising because they’re made specifically to appeal to consumers, to make them relate to its essence. The mother usually applies oil to the daughter’s scalp, or some lotion on her skin, or they’re exchanging recipes because what else can mothers and daughters talk to each other about except skin care and cooking?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our relationships with our mothers is not one only of careless laughter and light banter. It is the core love story of our lives till adulthood, and it is a burden and a duty. Thankfully, there exist refreshing counter narratives to the myth of motherhood that question the iconic status of motherhood in popular culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rituporno Ghosh’s &lt;em&gt;Titli&lt;/em&gt; is the story of Urmila (played by Aparna Sen) and Rohit Roy (played by Mithun Chakraborty) who were lovers in their youth. Urmila was married off at 20 to a tea estate manager, and Titli is their daughter. Blowing bubblegums and restlessly shaking her legs, the 17 year old Titli develops a massive crush on Rohit, who is now a Bollywood film star. In the beginning of the film, Titli is seen hovering around her mother, asking her to dress her up or put on a specific perfume. There is clear admiration and longing in her voice. This longing is something the myth dare not acknowledge; the physical envy between the mother and the daughter. While the daughter struggles through awkward breasts, menstruation and pimples, the mother is a graceful lady comfortable in her womanhood and her sexuality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Titli wistfully asks her mother, “Ma, why can’t I marry someone 20 years older? Grandpa was 20 years older than Grandma. Was grandma unhappy?” Urmila casually replies, “My mother wouldn’t dream of asking her mother this question”, the conversation shows the shift between the mother-daughter dynamic over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a chance meeting, where Titli and Urmila meet Rohit, Titli learns of her mother’s past and the adoration she had changes to jealousy and malice. Titli can not bear that fact that prior to her, her mother had a romantic past. To her, this feels like an intense betrayal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same is seen in Ghosh’s film &lt;em&gt;Unishe April&lt;/em&gt; (19th April), where the mother, Sarojini, a renowned classical dancer, is always elegantly dressed in sarees and jewelry. The daughter, Mithu, training to be a doctor, despises dressing up and covers herself in baggy t-shirts and long skirts. She holds the grief of her father’s death against her mother. Her grief makes her powerful, and in her eyes, a better person who &lt;em&gt;conforms&lt;/em&gt; to traditional norms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During her father’s funeral, the other female relatives of the house, while serving tea to guests also spill some gossip. “Sarojini is in Madras…or Mumbai. Who knows? If she wanted to become a famous dancer so badly, she should have just limited herself to that. Why would you marry and have a daughter as well?” There is a tinge of jealousy in this woman’s moralising; Sarojini is living the life she probably was too afraid to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, eighteen years later, on the father’s death anniversary, Sarojini receives a National award, which sets off a chain of reactions between her and Mithu. One can sense the constant ego tussle between the mother and the daughter, but the audience knows that this is due to miscommunication. When Mithu sits and cries in front of the telephone because her boyfriend has refused to marry her (because her mother is a dancer), Sarojini interprets this as her daughter’s jealousy towards her success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I loved the most about these films were their explorations into two important facets of the mother-daughter relationship: envy and miscommunication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Titli&lt;/em&gt;, Urmila comes into Titli’s room to shut the windows as there is a storm raging outside. In the wind, her shawl falls off and Titli watches her mother’s body, clad in a strappy nightgown, and there is a distinct recognition of her mother as a sexual being in her eyes. She tells her mother, “Whatever idea I had of you, has changed after tonight.” This might seem like an emotionally exaggerated response, but it is something to think about. Why would there be such reluctance to accept the mother as a sexual being? The simple answer is because it makes us uncomfortable. Of course, these conversations are uncomfortable, but that’s verily why they are all the more necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mother is acceptable as long as she lives her life vicariously through others - her husband’s promotion, her son’s academic performance, but never her own achievements or her personal desires. Women’s sexuality is acceptable as long as it comfortably services a man within acceptable social customs. The daughter isn’t supposed to have any knowledge of her mother’s seductive charm. Titli realises she has crossed a line, and Urmila opens up to her about her past relationship. For the first time, they converse as equals. The film &lt;em&gt;Titli&lt;/em&gt; ends with the daughter requesting her mother to recite a poem she knew Urmila recited for Rohit. The envy has faded away, the lines of miscommunication have been bridged. We remember what Urmila had told Rohit during their meeting. “When Titli watches you, I watch her. For as long as she watches you, I watch her. When you fight villains on stage, she chews her gum faster. When you dance with your heroine, envy and anger cloud her face.” The audience realises what the film was always about: the love story between a mother and her daughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Unishe April&lt;/em&gt; too, we have a similar reconciliation. Sarojini returns home to find Mithu has decided to commit suicide on the day of her father’s death, heartbroken by the rejection of her marriage proposal. The constant friction in their conversation fades away as Mithu breaks down and asks her mother “Why didn’t you ever ask me to join your dance class?” This is her deepest grievance, laid bare before us. All the intense tension between the two has been building up to this moment. Mithu never felt needed by her mother, and her way of coping was to immerse herself in books and be a doctor like her father. Sarojini, in between her sobbing, replies, “I did not understand you wanted to. I never asked, Mithu. I’m sorry.” The remarkable aspect of &lt;em&gt;Unishe April&lt;/em&gt; is how Sarojini is unapologetic about her decisions. She offers an explanation for her actions but stands by them. In the end, we find Mithu writing her a prescription to help with her knee pain while Sarojini requests her to accompany her to Madras, to meet her dance guru, making an active effort to include her in her life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mothers make mistakes. This is something mainstream culture refuses to accept. The standards motherhood is held to are unbelievably high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Gilmore Girls&lt;/em&gt;, Lorelai and Rory come across as sisters in the first scene. Rory is often the ‘mother’ in the relationship, asking Lorelai to think through practical decisions, consume a liquid that isn’t Luke’s coffee, and managing the intense drama between her grandmother Emily and her mother. Lorelai makes mistakes, but she makes a significant effort to acknowledge and make up for them. When Rory wanted to drop out of Yale and moved out to live with her grandparents, Lorelai and her get into a huge fight. However, when Rory reconsiders and rejoins Yale, and comes home to apologise, Lorelai says “I should have pulled you out of there.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Greta Gerwig’s &lt;em&gt;Lady Bird&lt;/em&gt;, the only moment of peace is perhaps the beginning where Christine “Lady Bird” McPherson and her mother sleep on the same bed. Two minutes later in the movie, Lady Bird jumps out of moving car as her mother tells her, “You know, with your work ethic, you should probably go to City College, then to jail, then back to City College.” From the moment the movie starts, to its very end, their relationship is one of constant pushes and pulls. Her mother reminds her of their financial status when Lady Bird wants to buy a magazine, “that’s what rich people do, we’re not rich people.” When they’re in a thrift store, Lady Bird drags her feet and her mother says “Are you tired? I couldn’t really say, because you were dragging your feet”, to which Lady Bird replies “You are SO INFURIATING!” In the very next second her mother pulls out a dress which both of them begin gushing over, completely forgetting the argument. Lady Bird is fiercely individualistic, dramatic, driven, confident, but she struggles because she wants her mother to &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; her, so bad. You have to love Greta Gerwig for getting it so well. Lady Bird’s mother writes and throws away a dozen letters because she felt she would judge her writing capability. Envy and miscommunication again. This gap is bridged, when after getting super drunk after moving away to college, Lady Bird calls her mother to say, “I love you. Thank you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The common thread that runs through &lt;em&gt;Titli&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Unishe April&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lady Bird&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Gilmore Girls&lt;/em&gt;, connecting the stories across timelines and countries is a simple one: daughters want to feel validated and acknowledged by their mothers. However, these emotions of envy, jealousy, doubt, resentment and anger that our characters feel &lt;strong&gt;need&lt;/strong&gt; to be celebrated. Why? Because the myth of motherhood says unconditional love and care should come naturally. It makes no space for other healthy human emotions. Since our mothers are inherently programmed to want the best for us and see the best in us, there should be no conflict. These counter narratives show that this path towards a stable, loving relationship is not a linear one. It requires careful negotiation between power dynamics, emotions (of which, not all are pleasant) and effort, just like any other relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is rather unfortunate, even unfair, that we need a demythologising of the mother figure in popular culture in the first place. To put it reductively, I’m glad that women are finally telling their imperfect and messy stories. What we need is more of it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ayantika Nath</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">If you’ve cringed at the Mother’s Day wishes that flooded social media a few weeks ago, which were basically variations of ‘she is the world’s smartest, strongest punching bag’, (go Leslie Knope!) you’ll probably see a valid point in what I have to discuss.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘What Do You Believe?’ How Ideology Will Shape the Culture Wars of the 21st Century</title>
      <link href="/What-Do-You-Believe" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘What Do You Believe?’ How Ideology Will Shape the Culture Wars of the 21st Century" />
      <published>2019-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-Do-You-Believe</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-Do-You-Believe">&lt;p&gt;In a way, all of human history is an endless cycle of war and peace. As the old proverb goes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hard times create strong men.&lt;br /&gt;
Strong men create good times.&lt;br /&gt;
Good times create weak men.&lt;br /&gt;
Weak men create hard times.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all at war – in some way or the other, with something or the other. We are all fighting, even for our daily bread. Whether it be bargaining with the local shopkeeper or actually taking up arms against an invader, conflict of some sort or the other pervades our very social existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In centuries past, certain nations decided that the best way to promote their own interest would be to colonise faraway lands located across the seas. This was the age of Conquest, the age of Empires. The result was that entire nations and civilisations came under the commercial and political dominance of unreachable overlords, living in another world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people of these subjugated races and tribes suddenly found themselves living as if on rent on the very land which their ancestors had tilled, ploughed and reaped for their own benefit. Hardship led to resentment. Resentment led to anger. Anger led to rage. Rage led to rebellion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tired of being mocked, of being made to feel ashamed for the colour of their skin or the rhythm of their tongue or the lyric of their songs, they rose in revolt against the imperialist yoke. Those who were wise, left. But those who underestimated the fury of an oppressed race came to rue it to their very last breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nation fought nation; tribe fought tribe. People of one language ostracised those who spoke a different tongue. Those of a particular hue of skin detested those who looked different. These were the ways of a time when one’s loyalty and one’s pride was still rooted to the soil upon which one lived and toiled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that age is no more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;War remains, perhaps ever more keenly than before. But it is a different kind of war. Out of the crucible of human conflict, a new world is being forged. There are several things which have led to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first was the shocking discovery that this Earth could indeed be tamed by the force of human ingenuity. We were told that only the sky is the limit – but even this has proven to be false. The Earth has shown itself to be a very small place indeed, and a new frontier has emerged – the great dark horizon of space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this contraction has only brought people closer together – geographically speaking. We are no longer bound to the soil on which our ancestors lived, moved and had their being. The coming together of continents, facilitated by the meteoric rise of modern transport, has led to the birth of multicultural and multi-ethnic societies around the world, where people of different beliefs and various walks of life have been forced to live their lives side-by-side. Seldom do we think of this, but the fact remains that what we see today – people of myriad ethnicities working together in the same office – would have been unthinkable even a century ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has led to the trivialisation of what originally divided mankind. The white man has come to see in the black man not an inferior creature, but a fellow human being. And the black man has come to see in his white neighbour not a fiendish oppressor from the pits of the underworld, but rather a mere man – with faults and flaws, just like everyone else. The close contact of daily interaction has ensured this. And this has led to a radical change in thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow’s battles will not be fought on the basis of race, language or ethnicity. Tomorrow’s wars will be wars of ideology, wars of belief, wars of religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideology, you see, is not like skin colour or tribal identity. It cannot be as easily brushed aside. Abortion is either right or wrong. It cannot be both right and wrong. Pornography is either moral or immoral. Giving condoms to high school students is either a magnificent step forward in promoting safe sex and sexual freedom, or it is a sign of growing decadence and degeneracy in a society which shamelessly normalises the divorce of sex from marriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when an unstoppable force meets an immovable mass? What happens when one belief system clashes with another? Two world views which are diametrically opposed to each other cannot coexist peacefully. One must prevail; the other must fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The political scientist Samuel P. Huntington famously argued that what the post-Cold War era was about to see was not conflict between countries, but rather between cultures. He called it &lt;em&gt;The Clash of Civilizations&lt;/em&gt;, and hypothesised that ideology – and especially religion – would play a crucially important role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you lived, say, three thousand years ago, you would probably have been born in a monolithic homogeneous society, where there would have been one main philosophy of life, which would have answered all the big questions for you. And in all likelihood, you could have lived your entire life without questioning it – quite natural, given that everyone you knew believed the same things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that is no longer true. The confluence of cultures has resulted in people being exposed to a myriad of different philosophies and beliefs, each quite distinct from their own. Man can no longer be satisfied with accepting answers by faith alone. He has to think and rethink the big questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is his place in the world? Where does he come from? What does it all mean? And what ought one to do while one lives in this changing, transient world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are big questions, and this sudden clash of civilisations has forced the different camps to stop and regroup. And since interaction between different communities is all but inevitable, the conflict of ideas has begun anew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result can easily be seen. Muslims are studying the New Testament and trying to understand what implications it might have on their own beliefs. Christians are studying Arabic and seeking to understand what the Quran actually says. Atheists are studying theology in universities and devout religious believers are devouring the works of Nietzsche and Russell with vigour. And this very happy situation is causing conversions on all sides, of the most lucrative and imaginative kinds. The clash certainly continues and democracy has played a crucial role in ensuring this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The struggle for power is natural to all human societies. In the Middle Ages, it was restricted mostly to the ruling class – aristocrats, nobles, princes, royal families and the like. But the advent of democracy has ensured that the vast citizenry have a vital and crucial say in who ultimately becomes King. And this means that people are much more informed and critical than ever before. Everyone has a vested interest. And everyone is trying to realize their own vision of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;em&gt;belief&lt;/em&gt; plays a crucial role in all this. What do people &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; would be the best for their country, and for the world? Should abortion be legalised or criminalised? Is patriarchy real or is it a myth? Should borders be opened or closed? Is climate change real or is it a hoax? Should churches be taxed or should they be exempted? Should we seek to establish a one world government or do we support the idea of independent, autonomous nation states?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideology shapes the world we live in. And this naturally means that every election – which inevitably guarantees a victory for one side and a defeat for all others – is a microcosm of the great culture war playing out around the world. Whichever side wins, the other naturally feels aggrieved, oppressed and persecuted, and blames the ‘decadent’ victor for ruining the world. This is the sad, but unavoidable result, of a small world in which beliefs and philosophies of life are this varied and polarised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fruits of this are often surprising and, at times, humorous. Today, conservative white Christian folk would rather have fellow Christians of different ethnicities, races and cultures as their neighbours and citizens rather than those of their own race who don’t hold similar values. It’s the same with the Muslim community. Generally speaking, racial differences are becoming less and less relevant, and ideological differences are becoming more pronounced and prominent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, ironically, means that religion and philosophy will come to enjoy an influence they perhaps have not had in the immediate past. The new world war will not be over race or national identity, but over one’s vision for life. The main question our young people will be asked is not “Where do you come from?” but rather “What do you believe?”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In a way, all of human history is an endless cycle of war and peace. As the old proverb goes:</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Marvel of Mediocrity</title>
      <link href="/The-Marvel-of-Mediocrity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Marvel of Mediocrity" />
      <published>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Marvel-of-Mediocrity</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Marvel-of-Mediocrity">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A prisoner’s affliction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might contest this by speaking of war-torn Syrians or the muddle of mental health, but Gen Y and Gen Z are sufferers of the worst kind of affliction; the affliction of &lt;em&gt;mediocrity&lt;/em&gt;. What makes this affliction so bad is its non-threatening nature. And I beg your pardon, we are not sufferers of this affliction, we are its prisoners. But what has made us prisoners? And why is this such a big issue?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tales from the West&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The West has always had an influence, directly or indirectly, over the entire world. We have adopted many of their cultural idiosyncrasies and even live them out everyday, without consciously realising it. One such Western quirk we’ve embraced is &lt;em&gt;individualism&lt;/em&gt;. I am not claiming that the West holds prerogative of it, but they are the ones to have so earnestly sermonised the concept of individualism. Western literature preaches the purpose and value of individual worth; how the world is every individual’s oyster. To permeate the consciousness with a sense of personal worth, they even went a step ahead and materialised it through architecture, giving almost every member of the family a room of their own. Think of the sense of autonomy and powerfulness you feel when you sit in your room, sip coffee or whatever, and ask for nudes. You feel the illusion of having control over your life and that of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Indian subcontinent too, we have had literature that spoke of princes being born with a divine purpose, be it the Tiger King or the Buddha. For a layman back then, however, to have acquired such works was a rarity, and even if he did find himself with one, the stories held little relevance in his life. These factors prevented popularisation and consequentially, realisation of individualism through architecture. As the communal form of existence in families continued through the generations, the concept of individualism never bloomed. We believed in a person’s societal worth rather than personal worth, in caste values rather than personal value, in purpose according to status in society rather than according to an individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A global distress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this changed when globalisation happened. After decades of being hungover on colonialism, once again we got a whiff of the West, and couldn’t get enough of it. Since then, we’ve consumed it like opium until the concept of individualism solidified through material means, i.e. architecture. Today, an average suburban household has separate rooms for almost everyone in the family. This is an embodiment of the privileges which, earlier, we only got to see in films and books of the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how does any of this make us prisoners of mediocrity? The feeling of not being good enough stems from the inability to actualise the personal worth or capability that popular discourse and architecture tell us we’re born with. To begin with, the very sense of personal value gives birth to an ill child called mediocrity. Since birth, we have been taught that we are unique, that we have a purpose to fulfil and that there’s a special place for us in the grand scheme of things. While growing up, we started to realise that perhaps we aren’t as special as we once believed. Right then, along comes someone like Aamir Khan, convincing an entire generation to reinstate their belief in uniqueness. Our existence could exude confidence and hope, once again! Don’t get me wrong, I am not against hope or anything that his films have taught us, in fact, I am most grateful for those films. However, along with everything good comes a bad and possibly, even an ugly. Even though, we are yet to see the ugly one, we very much have seen the bad one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mediocre beginnings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have come too far, the concept is too distilled in our souls to now have an exorcism. We simply have to accept that we aren’t unique geniuses. Maybe, a moderate, uneventful life will be all that we ever get. Maybe, we will never be anyone’s first choice, but there are great benefits to being an average that must not be discounted. To begin with, if you’re mediocre, most people can relate to you. Sure, a genius is looked up to, but up there he’s all alone. A great example of this is the film &lt;em&gt;Green Book&lt;/em&gt;, based on a trip taken to the south of the Mason-Dixon Line by Don Shirley, a famous black classical pianist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a remarkable scene, Mahershala Ali who plays Don Shirley says to his valet, Tony Lip, “Yes, I live in a castle, Tony. Alone! And rich people pay me to play piano for them because it makes them feel cultured, but as soon I step off that step, I go back to being just another n&lt;em&gt;**** to them. Because that is their true culture. But I suffer that slight alone because I am not like by my own people ‘cause I am not like them either.” This is a classic example of the kind of isolation a genius feels and it is common people like Tony Lip, the classic mediocre who lives a more fulfilled life, which is not to say that being a genius is bad and you should avoid it all costs (but if you were one you probably wouldn’t be reading this article right now). Taking a bit more from the example of *Green Book&lt;/em&gt;, Tony Lip lived a life of equilibrium, where he earned sufficiently, had the love of his friends and family, and was well received by the people around him. That kept him happy. At the end of the day, we cannot deny our most basic urge of socialising and wanting to be loved. Being a genius, more often than not, creates a distance between the admirer and the admired. As a mediocre, it is easier to strike a balance in life and to keep a clear and simple vision of it, something most geniuses struggle with. Leaf through the pages of history, and you’ll see that the most revered personalities also suffered the most through their lifetime. Your name living on, hundreds of years after your death, might sound like a golden prospect but what is the point, if your life has been nothing but suffering and despair? Look at it from a different angle, as a genius, you could have been the next Hitler. Hitler was an extremist with strong beliefs and it doesn’t matter if we agree to it or not, he was a genius; a genius too caught up in his own ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The complaisant man&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, it is not easy to be a genius, but it also isn’t easy to be mediocre. A genius progresses in life and eventually finds meaninglessness. We, on the other hand, are mostly stagnant, and have to generate and believe in meanings to live by. We need to be ignorant, sometimes knowingly, to our conditions because being aware is not of much help. The genius, however, gets to be enlightened. He is a Sisyphus, aware of the futility of his actions, yet forced to carry the burden of changing the course of history. Whenever history is reshaped, by a single force, there live people who partake in that change and, in a way, make that change possible. They are the average Joes, the mediocres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take no shame in being a mediocre. Unlike a genius, being average requires denying a lot of our basic wants as curious beings and I am willing to trade those curiosities for a more fulfilled life. In the end, we’re all ignorant, what matters is how you exercise your ignorance to live more pleasantly. Just as the world needs the greats, it needs the averages. So, do not fret about not having a personal worth, because you do. Life is not short, as some say, it’s long enough to fill our lives with misery. It is, however, not in the pursuit of excellence but in the pursuit of absolute happiness, which albeit unattainable, that we can find liberation.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A prisoner’s affliction</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
