<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/society/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-06-14T00:25:15+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/society/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Can Effective Altruism Truly Work?</title>
      <link href="/Effective-Altruism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can Effective Altruism Truly Work?" />
      <published>2019-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Effective-Altruism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Effective-Altruism">&lt;p&gt;If I told you about a $60 million project aimed at providing water pumps for villages in Africa to 10 million people backed by the US government and various celebrities, you would probably think it’s a sound idea. The way the project actually works, is that the pump is connected to a merry-go-round and as children play on the apparatus, the energy is used to power the pump. It sounds like a great idea, which is why in 2006 this very project was put into place. However, it turned out to be a complete disaster. After some number crunching, it was calculated that children would have to be playing on the roundabout non-stop for 27 hours each day to reach the water production targets set by the initiative. Moreover, simply investing the money into regular water pumps would have been far less expensive and more efficient. As a different water NGO put it; “their marketing is perfect, but the final idea does not work.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The takeaway here is not about water pumps, or even water aid in general. This is but one of hundreds of examples of &lt;em&gt;heart over head&lt;/em&gt; charity. In a world which is inundated with people who need help, it is becoming increasingly hard to know how and where we should give our time and money. Indeed, I would argue that we all experience “charity fatigue”; with so many causes available, it becomes increasingly difficult for an individual charity to stand out. Consequently, charities turn to shock advertising to draw our attention – think of heart-breaking pictures of starving children. By using this visceral imagery, the charities are appealing directly to your heart, to your emotions. They are not asking you to think about the cause, but to believe in it; two very different propositions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, giving any sort of charity is better than giving none at all. However, for those looking for a more critical and rational approach to charity, I would highly suggest examining effective altruism. Simply put, effective altruism is a quasi-utilitarian form of charity. It aims to do the most good possible with the resources available. As Peter Singer, one of the gurus of the theory, puts it;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s important because it combines both the heart and the head. The heart, of course, you feel… But it’s really important to use the head as well to make sure that what you do is effective and well-directed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example that Singer gives, that I think concisely explains how one would practically apply the theory. In this instance, he talks about service dogs for blind people, a cause which most definitely fits the criteria of ‘pulling at the heartstrings.’ It costs about $40,000 in the US to train a guide dog and to train the recipient so that the guide dog can be of effective help to the blind person. It costs somewhere between $20 and $50 to cure a blind person in a developing country, if they have trachoma. After doing the maths, it works out that you could provide one guide dog for one blind American, or you could cure between 400 and 2,000 people of blindness. He finishes by stating that he thinks it’s perfectly clear what the better thing to do is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find his argument truly compelling, and in recent years it has become increasingly relevant in my own personal life. After completing various volunteer roles, I became fully aware of the importance and necessity of critically examining and evaluating our altruistic efforts. Indeed, volunteering serves as a very good example of ineffective altruism. International volunteers are usually low-skilled, studying or recently graduated young people from affluent countries. Often, they come for short periods of time, do not speak the local language, and do not have expertise in the field of work that they are helping in. A particular issue in South America and other developing parts of the world, these volunteers are frequently assumed to have more knowledge and relevant skills, purely because they come from more developed countries. Add into the mix the issues of voluntourism, and what you are left with is a situation where volunteers do not benefit, or even harm the local community. We all love the idea of helping other people, but unfortunately it is not so simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economics of volunteering are unconvincing at best, and I am going to use myself as an example to demonstrate it. A bit of background first; I spent five months volunteering in an NGO in a very small town near Cusco, Peru. The NGO works with disabled and disadvantaged children, and my work specifically consisted of helping out at a school for disabled children and also a care home for children who cannot live with their parents. I speak Spanish and have relevant work experience with children, so I, at least, was able to offset some of the issues that I mentioned earlier. However, a deeper look at the money is where problems start to arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost of return flights = £600&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accommodation costs for 5 months= £1,600&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living costs = £40/week x 20 = £800&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total = £3000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, even without taking into account my various trips to other South American countries whilst I was there, and any other additional costs, we are looking at a value of at least £3,000. When people ask me about the experience, I always say that it is one of the best things I have done in my life, and I felt that I made a real positive impact on the people I worked with. But asking about my experience is not the question that should be asked. As an effective altruist, the real question is, was the help I gave worth what a £3,000 investment could have done in my local area? In my mind, the answer is clearly no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Herein lies one of the main problems with effective altruism. Altruism is, inevitably, emotional and personal. It is very hard to simply give without caring at all. A consequence of this is that we, the giver, also gain something through the act of giving. I would argue, therefore, that it is impossible to be altruistic in a purely selfless way. Whether personal gain is your primary aim or not, some part of giving away your time or your money positively benefits yourself. And here it gets complicated. How can we possibly be effective altruists, if we are at the same time, emotional altruists? How is it possible to analyse and calculate the best possible use of your money, without letting your subconscious emotions affect this decision? Peter Singer does come up with an answer for this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Many effective altruists say that in doing good, they feel good. Effective altruists directly benefit others, but indirectly they often benefit themselves. If doing the most you can for others means that you are also flourishing, then that is the best possible outcome for everyone.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not disagree with him, but like most things, this is far simpler in theory than in practice. It is near-impossible to act without any self-interest, and the line between benefiting ourselves and benefiting other people is very thin. Once the giver starts to achieve their own goals through giving to charity, then it is hard for the process to not become emotional rather than rational. Moreover, it is human nature to generally favour ourselves and people similar to us, instead of others who may need and deserve the help more. It is easier to relate to somebody with whom we share common traits or experiences; another potential pitfall of where our emotions interfere with the aim of being rational and critical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory also suffers from the same critiques that utilitarianism faces. Strictly adhering to benefitting the greatest number of people, instead of individual cases, can lead to some particularly troubling moral decisions. A good example of this was given in the Guardian; “would you really save a large bag of cash from a burning building rather than your neighbour’s terrified child, even if you could donate that cash and save the lives of a thousand strangers?” It’s good food for thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with these two valid criticisms, I am still a firm believer in effective altruism. Perhaps its applications are limited in practice, and not everyone has the luxury of being able to take the time or have the money, to give to charity in such a specific way. Yet, I believe that many people would greatly benefit by at least being aware of the theory and taking inspiration from it. The more rational and critical we can be, the better equipped we are to make informed, successful and effective altruistic decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An image that helps visualise the theory of effective altruism -&amp;gt; https://blog.ted.com/why-how-effective-altruism-peter-singer-visualized/ (Blog)&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Daniel Harris</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">If I told you about a $60 million project aimed at providing water pumps for villages in Africa to 10 million people backed by the US government and various celebrities, you would probably think it’s a sound idea. The way the project actually works, is that the pump is connected to a merry-go-round and as children play on the apparatus, the energy is used to power the pump. It sounds like a great idea, which is why in 2006 this very project was put into place. However, it turned out to be a complete disaster. After some number crunching, it was calculated that children would have to be playing on the roundabout non-stop for 27 hours each day to reach the water production targets set by the initiative. Moreover, simply investing the money into regular water pumps would have been far less expensive and more efficient. As a different water NGO put it; “their marketing is perfect, but the final idea does not work.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">On the Ethics of Immigration: The Morality behind Closed Borders</title>
      <link href="/Ethics-of-Immigration" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the Ethics of Immigration: The Morality behind Closed Borders" />
      <published>2019-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Ethics-of-Immigration</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Ethics-of-Immigration">&lt;p&gt;In a world that is witnessing an unprecedented range of humanitarian crises, can it be ethical for states to shut their doors on victims of war, armed conflict, sexual violence or organized crime? Do these countries have the right to close their borders in the absence of such calamities alike? Notwithstanding, do all humans have a moral right to cross borders at will? While immigration has emerged as an important subject of debate and policies have been argued extensively in economic, political, and cultural contexts, the need for a nuanced understanding of the ethics of immigration has received little attention. There is an urgent need to address such questions whilst discussing the moral implications of immigration policies in light of global ethics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This essay argues that legitimate states, regardless of reason, have a moral right to close their borders to potential immigrants, and that these would-be immigrants do not have a moral right to cross borders at will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part of my essay argues that &lt;em&gt;“legitimate states are morally entitled to unilaterally design and enforce their own immigration policies,”&lt;/em&gt; even if such intensive policies restrict the entry of prospective immigrants. Every state, by virtue of its territorial integrity and sovereignty, is entitled to have dominion over deciding who may enter and who may not, a view deeply rooted in the moral right of countries to be politically self-determining over self-regarding affairs. In numerous instances, the United States has been pulled up for promoting violent coups in Middle-Eastern countries or been accused of meddling with autonomous elections in Central and Latin American nations. Interestingly, it isn’t the illegitimacy and immorality of the interference itself that provokes the rightful criticism and censure of the United States but the &lt;em&gt;very act of intrusion&lt;/em&gt;, that violates the territorial integrity and sovereignty of the targeted states. The essence of such criticism seems to stem from our expectation of political self-determination from the targeted countries. Therefore, political self-determination is an indispensable part of a state’s autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though it is for individuals and groups that international law prescribes self-determination and not states, I believe stripping a country of its political self-determination takes away the right of its citizens and groups to control their self-interested affairs as well. A country’s immigration policy determines who may contribute to shaping the future of that nation: economically, politically and culturally, among other ways. Such a policy holds deep importance because it has the potential to determine the political course of that country and hence the course of its citizens’ lives in turn. The right to political self-determination of a country is simply the collection of individual and group self-determining rights of its citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the politically self-determining nature of legitimate states is sufficient moral ground to let them make their own immigration policies &lt;em&gt;regardless&lt;/em&gt; of the nature of such policies, whether restrictive or liberal, egalitarian or utilitarian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second dimension of my argument suggests that legitimate states have a right to freedom of association that includes the right to refuse association too. For instance, the freedom of association of an unmarried man emanates from his dominion over his own affairs, like any other person. While he may choose to marry a particular woman, he may choose not to marry that woman as well. At the same time, it is at the discretion of that woman as well, to marry him or not; it is a two-way process. While one may join a particular partner by virtue of one’s freedom of association, one may also not join that partner on accord of the same freedom. Similarly, legitimate states should be allowed to associate themselves with potential immigrants as well as refuse association.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might argue that such an analogy is flawed since a matrimonial relationship is discretionary and can be avoided, while statelessness is not. Therefore, one does not have control over one’s citizenship as one does over a voluntary relationship such as marriage. Nevertheless, a different approach to the same argument could give us a clearer picture. What if we compared a state to property? International law requires a state to control a well-defined area under its jurisdiction for it to be called a state. Now, the right to property inherently includes the right to exclude others from its ownership. It can hence be inferred that a legitimate state, or more appropriately, a legitimate property, reserves the right to freedom of association with potential owners, and can deny such ownership by virtue of that freedom. While existent owners in the guise of citizens may rightfully denounce their ownership in the form of emigration, it is not obligatory for the state to entertain new ownership to its property in the form of immigration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the right to exclude prospective immigrants is a right born of the state’s indisputable jurisdiction over the property within its internationally recognized borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final facet of my argument justifies that the previous two hypotheses are not adverse to the moral rights of potential immigrants by any means. The right of a country to reject association with would-be immigrants does not violate their rights as liberalists and egalitarians often try to portray. The main reason is that human beings do not have a moral right to freedom of movement beyond the territory of their citizenship in the first place! Article 13 of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights grants us the right to freedom of movement within our own state only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, arguments in favour of open borders often advocate that ‘humanity is equal’ and that ‘every human has an equal right to the natural resources on the planet’. Liberalists are of the view that it is terribly unjust for a person’s life prospects to be so greatly dependent on something as uncontrollable as the country she is born in. However, my views are more in harmony with &lt;em&gt;The Law of Peoples&lt;/em&gt; by John Rawls, who concedes to the inevitability of inequalities among states. As per Michael Blake, it is more thoughtful to accept that &lt;em&gt;“membership is not itself a good whose distribution is to be evaluated by distributive justice; rather, membership in a territorial state is required before [the] theory of distributive justice [can] have applicability”&lt;/em&gt;. The goods at stake when discussing immigration are connected more to better political institutions and social opportunities rather than a yearning for natural resources. These prospects include better lifestyles, progressive education, developed healthcare, and assured safety among others. Citizens of countries rich in oil are fleeing to havens in Europe without blinking an eye. Why? They value their safety more than their natural reserves, so do the Rohingya Muslims of forest-rich Myanmar that are ever-increasing as refugees in India. Abundantly resource-decorated Chinese and Indian nationals number highest as immigrants in the United States. Why? They value better economic opportunity more than the natural resources back home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, this explanation clearly corroborates that immigration today is applied as a technique to avail of better opportunities or safer sanctuaries, and not as a means to ensure moral equality among human beings. Thus, it cannot be judged a moral human right by any means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To recapitulate my argument, I firstly assert that legitimate states have a right to political self-determination by virtue of their territorial integrity and sovereignty, and on accord of the right to self-determination of its people. Successively, I prove how the freedom of association is an important component of a state’s right to political self-determination, adjudicating next that it is the sole owner of all political institutions within its recognized borders. Therefore, the first two facets of my arguments help me justify why legitimate states have a moral right to close their borders to potential immigrants, regardless of a specific reason. Finally, the concluding facet of my hypotheses helps me validate that human beings do not have a moral right to cross borders at will. I rest my case by affirming that a state’s right to exclude potential immigrants is not detrimental to their individual freedom and states need not present reasons to exercise this innately moral right.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shivang Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In a world that is witnessing an unprecedented range of humanitarian crises, can it be ethical for states to shut their doors on victims of war, armed conflict, sexual violence or organized crime? Do these countries have the right to close their borders in the absence of such calamities alike? Notwithstanding, do all humans have a moral right to cross borders at will? While immigration has emerged as an important subject of debate and policies have been argued extensively in economic, political, and cultural contexts, the need for a nuanced understanding of the ethics of immigration has received little attention. There is an urgent need to address such questions whilst discussing the moral implications of immigration policies in light of global ethics.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">“It’s hard to be down when you’re up” – Control, Understanding and The City.</title>
      <link href="/Control-Understanding-and-The-City" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“It’s hard to be down when you’re up” – Control, Understanding and The City." />
      <published>2019-05-14T23:18:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-14T23:18:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Control-Understanding-and-The-City</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Control-Understanding-and-The-City">&lt;p&gt;“I wonder what is the source of this pleasure of “seeing the whole,” of looking
down on, totalizing the most immoderate of human texts. To be lifted to the
summit of the World Trade Center is to be lifted out of the city’s grasp… It’s
hard to be down when you’re up.” Michel de Certeau&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This quote from French psychoanalyst Michel de Certeau condenses a feeling that
many will have had, though cannot quite fully explain: Why do we take pleasure
in viewpoints, lookouts and the top floors of skyscrapers? What is it about
these vantage points that give us that ‘larger than life’ feeling?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city is a confusing entity. Whether it has been meticulously planned, or has
simply developed naturally over centuries, it is often incredibly difficult to
truly understand. When arriving for the first time, we are hit with a barrage of
new sights, smells, people and culture. Indeed, the first reaction is usually to
find something to orient ourselves, finding a system or service that we know
exists in other similar cities that we have already inhabited, and then working
from there. Examples of this could be a train station, bank, church,
supermarket; by finding universal facilities that exist in nearly all cities, it
becomes easier to navigate a new environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Settling in to a new urban environment can be seen as matching and modifying an
old system of living to fit a new and different place. The building blocks of
how we live, work and function will be similar, but the specificities of how we
do it must adapt. Once you are settled, you solidify this routine until it
becomes second nature. You might even forget the way that you used to live, the
consequence of becoming accustomed to a new style of living, in a city that you
now call home. When eventually you move on, the same process is repeated. Now
you may draw on multiple past experiences, but the process is essentially the
same. By using tried and tested formulas, we manage our inherent human desire
for routine, and implement these plans on whatever the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The city also falls into this dual scripting. It is often branded as
  “evil”, harbouring the underbelly of modern society, while at the same time,
  it is heralded as the pinnacle of civilization, as man’s triumph over the
  barbarism of uncivilized earlier times and as a hallmark of the success of
  the project for pushing forwards the frontier of a wild and untamed nature.”
  Maria Kaika&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawing on what Kaika comments, it can be argued that the city, in its most
basic form, is the representation of the human need to exercise control over
their surroundings. We do not wish to simply live in nature but to tame it,
master it, and modify it for our own desires. Moreover, this does not only apply
to the design of cities themselves but the way in which an individual chooses to
inhabit cities. We create routines, schedules and centre our whole way of living
around having control. The very thought of being out of control can lead to
serious mental health consequences, anxiety and a lack of self-worth. Although,
as stated before in this article, the building blocks of our lives are generally
constant and non-changeable, having the autonomy to decide the details, the
small things, is absolutely key. Your choice of supermarket, regular coffee
shop, the route you take to work; all of these are small but significant ways in
which we exert control over our schedules. Our habits are not just customs we
coincidentally act out, but an integral part of how we inhabit a city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning to de Certeau, it is this relationship between control, understanding
and the city, that explains our love for skyscrapers, viewpoints and lookouts.
By simply being above all of the chaos of the city, above of all the individuals
going about their normal routines, we exercise control not just of ourselves,
but of the very city itself. New York, La Paz and Lisbon all provide perfect
examples of confusing, alive, bustling cities, with spectacular and stunning
lookouts. Suddenly, all of the confusion and anxiety of occupying the city is
lost, and the city is legible and intelligible. We transform into, as de Certeau
explains, a ‘god’, gaining the omniscient perspective that is simply not
possible from the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“His elevation transfigures him into a voyeur. It puts him at a distance. It
  transforms the bewitching world by which one was “possessed” into a text
  that lies before one’s eyes. It allows one to read it, to be a solar Eye,
  looking down like a god.” Michel de Certeau&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, power is the key dynamic at play. Rather than the being the
inhabitant, the apprehensive pedestrian who is just trying to survive in a
confusing and ever-changing environment, all of us wish to be, at least for a
while, sitting up on high reading and understanding the beauty and confusion of
the city. It sure is hard to be down when you are up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//harris_image1.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//harris_image2.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//harris_image3.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//harris_image4.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//harris_image5.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;A selection of my own photos, demonstrating how elevation helps to understand
the city.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Daniel Harris</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“I wonder what is the source of this pleasure of “seeing the whole,” of looking down on, totalizing the most immoderate of human texts. To be lifted to the summit of the World Trade Center is to be lifted out of the city’s grasp… It’s hard to be down when you’re up.” Michel de Certeau This quote from French psychoanalyst Michel de Certeau condenses a feeling that many will have had, though cannot quite fully explain: Why do we take pleasure in viewpoints, lookouts and the top floors of skyscrapers? What is it about these vantage points that give us that ‘larger than life’ feeling? The city is a confusing entity. Whether it has been meticulously planned, or has simply developed naturally over centuries, it is often incredibly difficult to truly understand. When arriving for the first time, we are hit with a barrage of new sights, smells, people and culture. Indeed, the first reaction is usually to find something to orient ourselves, finding a system or service that we know exists in other similar cities that we have already inhabited, and then working from there. Examples of this could be a train station, bank, church, supermarket; by finding universal facilities that exist in nearly all cities, it becomes easier to navigate a new environment. Settling in to a new urban environment can be seen as matching and modifying an old system of living to fit a new and different place. The building blocks of how we live, work and function will be similar, but the specificities of how we do it must adapt. Once you are settled, you solidify this routine until it becomes second nature. You might even forget the way that you used to live, the consequence of becoming accustomed to a new style of living, in a city that you now call home. When eventually you move on, the same process is repeated. Now you may draw on multiple past experiences, but the process is essentially the same. By using tried and tested formulas, we manage our inherent human desire for routine, and implement these plans on whatever the environment. “The city also falls into this dual scripting. It is often branded as “evil”, harbouring the underbelly of modern society, while at the same time, it is heralded as the pinnacle of civilization, as man’s triumph over the barbarism of uncivilized earlier times and as a hallmark of the success of the project for pushing forwards the frontier of a wild and untamed nature.” Maria Kaika Drawing on what Kaika comments, it can be argued that the city, in its most basic form, is the representation of the human need to exercise control over their surroundings. We do not wish to simply live in nature but to tame it, master it, and modify it for our own desires. Moreover, this does not only apply to the design of cities themselves but the way in which an individual chooses to inhabit cities. We create routines, schedules and centre our whole way of living around having control. The very thought of being out of control can lead to serious mental health consequences, anxiety and a lack of self-worth. Although, as stated before in this article, the building blocks of our lives are generally constant and non-changeable, having the autonomy to decide the details, the small things, is absolutely key. Your choice of supermarket, regular coffee shop, the route you take to work; all of these are small but significant ways in which we exert control over our schedules. Our habits are not just customs we coincidentally act out, but an integral part of how we inhabit a city. Returning to de Certeau, it is this relationship between control, understanding and the city, that explains our love for skyscrapers, viewpoints and lookouts. By simply being above all of the chaos of the city, above of all the individuals going about their normal routines, we exercise control not just of ourselves, but of the very city itself. New York, La Paz and Lisbon all provide perfect examples of confusing, alive, bustling cities, with spectacular and stunning lookouts. Suddenly, all of the confusion and anxiety of occupying the city is lost, and the city is legible and intelligible. We transform into, as de Certeau explains, a ‘god’, gaining the omniscient perspective that is simply not possible from the ground. “His elevation transfigures him into a voyeur. It puts him at a distance. It transforms the bewitching world by which one was “possessed” into a text that lies before one’s eyes. It allows one to read it, to be a solar Eye, looking down like a god.” Michel de Certeau Once again, power is the key dynamic at play. Rather than the being the inhabitant, the apprehensive pedestrian who is just trying to survive in a confusing and ever-changing environment, all of us wish to be, at least for a while, sitting up on high reading and understanding the beauty and confusion of the city. It sure is hard to be down when you are up. A selection of my own photos, demonstrating how elevation helps to understand the city.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Shutting Out The Sun? On a New Kind of Loneliness</title>
      <link href="/Shutting-Out-The-Sun" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shutting Out The Sun? On a New Kind of Loneliness" />
      <published>2019-05-03T02:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-03T02:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Shutting-Out-The-Sun</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Shutting-Out-The-Sun">&lt;p&gt;I’m sure we’ve all had days when we don’t want to leave the house, perhaps even
our rooms. It’s not unheard of for a person to take a day off and do nothing,
but then, we all have a limit to all or any of it. After a while, someone is
probably going to call out for you, you’ll probably have made a plan you forgot
about, or someone just visits you. It’d be a surprise if you said you had not
talked to anyone all day, whether virtually or in real life. But, that’s exactly
what is going on in several countries, most notably in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t heard of the word &lt;em&gt;hikikomori&lt;/em&gt; before, don’t worry, I hadn’t
either. Just the other day, I was made aware of how our generation is the most
depressed one and I went surfing on the web to check the validity of that
statement. What I found was this ominous term. When one mentions “&lt;em&gt;hikikomori&lt;/em&gt;”,
the immediate image that comes to mind is a young Japanese man, who has isolated
himself within a bedroom in his parents’ house for years on end, refusing to
speak, interact, or even be seen by anyone – sometimes including his own family.
Meals are brought to the door a few times a day, and garbage and other refuse
are left out in return. He might have started off spending his time playing
video games or chatting online, but those activities have lost their charm long
ago. He now simply stares off into space. &lt;em&gt;Hikikomori&lt;/em&gt;. The world of perfect
isolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the diversity of traits and characteristics accompanying
&lt;em&gt;hikikomori&lt;/em&gt;, much effort has been put into defining the term in a way that
consolidates the condition that we are examining.  It is a term that describes
both the state and the sufferer of acute social withdrawal. It means the
behaviour in which adolescents and young adults refuse all contact with society
and withdraw from all social activities. First coined by psychiatrist Tamaki
Saito in 1998 in his book &lt;em&gt;Social Withdrawal – Adolescence Without End&lt;/em&gt;, the
term and the condition gained immense popularity in Japan following several
newspaper articles and television interviews with Saito. The Japanese government
officially defines hikikomori as people who haven’t left their homes or
interacted with others for at least six months. They’re often dubbed as
modern-day hermits. The best behavioural definition to date was proposed by Teo
and Gaw in 2010, this definition of &lt;em&gt;hikikomori&lt;/em&gt; captures the core constructs
associated with the condition in six criteria. For one, most of the day, nearly
every day, is spent at home. The person persistently avoids social situations
and social relationships. They are bound to have experienced distress or
impairment in their normal routine, for a duration of at least six months. The
last, but an important criterion is that the condition is not better explained
by another psychiatric disorder such as social phobia, major depressive
disorders, schizophrenia, or avoidant personality disorder. We define this kind
of hikikomori as “primary hikikomori”, i.e. one manifestation of the hikikomori
phenomenon that cannot be described using current concepts in psychiatric
disease. Primary hikikomori youth do not have any serious diagnosable
psychopathology, yet they are unable to enter society or adapt to their
surroundings. Hikikomori can also include individuals suffering from a variety
of severe mental disorders including affective disorder, anxiety disorder,
obsessive-compulsive disorder, personality disorders, and pervasive
developmental disorders, but they are classified as “secondary hikikomori”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally, hikikomori was simply a general term referring to a condition in
which people withdrew from relationships with others. It was also used as a
psychiatric term describing the symptom of withdrawal in autistic,
schizophrenic, depressive or aged patients. After 1990, hikikomori among youth
received increasing attention from psychiatrists and society-at-large and came
to be used mainly for describing young adults. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/15/magazine/shutting-themselves-in.html&quot;&gt;According to The New York
Times&lt;/a&gt;,
doctors began to observe hikikomori as a social phenomenon around the mid-1980s,
when young men exhibited signs of lethargy, refusing to communicate and spending
most of their time in their rooms. Canadian journalist Michael Zielenziger’s
book &lt;em&gt;Shutting Out the Sun&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt;’ article “Shutting
Themselves In” put the word on the map for the rest of us. The Saito book –
&lt;em&gt;Social Withdrawal – Adolescence Without End&lt;/em&gt;, in itself, gives us a good idea
about how the word came to be. The hikikomori are rebellious, they need to be
cared for and they’re financially dependent on their parents. It is difficult to
find one cause or reason behind this condition. They are troubled by their
future and are unable to cope with the uncertainty. They may have been triggered
by some trauma; statistics suggest bullying as a major cause. The pressure of it
all: to maintain the family name, to maintain your own dignity, everything may
be a trigger and also a facilitator. The phenomenon can come in various forms: A
person’s condition can be so severe that they lack the energy to leave their
sofa to go to the toilet, another could suffer from obsessive-compulsive
disorders so serious that they shower several hours a day or scrub their shower
tiles for hours, some may just play video games all day- “as if it would
tranquilise me.” Some just lay in wait for ‘energy’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A community‐based survey published in 2010 reported that the prevalence of
hikikomori stood at approximately 1.2% of the Japanese population, and in 2016 a
Japanese cabinet report estimated people with hikikomori to be number over half
a million within the age range of 15‐39 years. The country now hopes to identify
older hikikomori and understand the assistance their families need. As
hikikomori grow older and their parents become too elderly to care for them,
questions over their fate will become more urgent. There’s also an implied
consensus that hikikomori are generally men, which might not be true. In fact,
the very number mentioned might be incorrect. Several families don’t like to
accept the reality and call it what it is and instead just say that their
children are being ‘selfish’ for some time. The females, in Japanese culture,
are already supposed to be shy and introverted, so when they shirk away from
social interaction, nobody views it as anything out of the ordinary. What is
absurd is how many parents albeit aware of what’s occurring channel the truth in
a fashion that fits right with their reality. In Japanese, there’s a very famous
saying, “A protruding nail will be hammered down.” And that is what may be the
reason why this phenomenon is overtaking the Japanese population. Japan is soon
to face what they call the “2030 problem”. As many with the condition are
getting older and staying withdrawn for longer, the concern is that in 12 years
many hikikomori will approach their
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gq-magazine.co.uk/article/men-how-to-dress-your-age-60s-and-beyond&quot;&gt;60s&lt;/a&gt;
and will have no family to support them – making reintegration into society much
harder. Additionally, as more people withdraw from society and stop working, the
fear is that Japan’s economy will also suffer—which it is already doing.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, when there is a problem, there is a solution. Psychiatrists have
tried to treat hikikomori with individual therapy, group therapy, family
therapy, and family group therapy. Solutions have also come in the form of a
non-profit organisation called New Start, which runs a programme called Rental
Sister, where volunteers visit hikikomori houses. It’s been said that it can
take up to two years of visits to get some cases to leave their homes.
Currently, there are more than fifty government‐funded community support centres
for hikikomori located throughout the prefectures of Japan, providing services
such as telephone consultations for family members, the creation of “meeting
spaces” for affected people, and job placement support. In addition, various
private institutions provide treatment for hikikomori sufferers. However, there
is yet to be a unified evidence‐based method for these public/private
interventions. A four‐step intervention is recommended by the government
guidelines for hikikomori, including family support and first contact with the
individual followed by his/her evaluation; individual support; training through
an intermediate‐transient group situation (such as group therapy); and social
participation trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Japanese sociocultural background has been traditionally permeated by
“&lt;em&gt;amae”&lt;/em&gt; (accepting over-dependent behaviours) and shame, which may underlie
hikikomori. Parent‐child relationships in Japan have long been considered less
oedipal than in Western societies. They can be marked by an absent father and an
extremely prolonged and close bond with the mother, which may result in
difficulties when it comes to becoming independent. Especially in hikikomori,
the development of basic interpersonal skills during the early stages of life
seems to be insufficient, which can induce vulnerability to stress in later
school/workplace environments and lead to escape from social situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hikikomori‐like cases have recently been reported in other countries of varying
sociocultural and economic backgrounds such as Hong Kong, Oman, was and Spain,
and studies have revealed its existence in India, South Korea, and the US. Thus,
one can say that hikikomori has now crossed the limits of a culture‐bound
phenomenon to become an increasingly prevalent international condition. A major
contributing factor may be the evolution of communication from direct to
increasingly indirect and physically-isolating forms. This is especially the
case for social interactions which hitherto required face‐to‐face contacts in a
mutual physical space but can now occur, at least partially, in a virtual world.
Internet addiction has been reported in several countries. In South Korea, for
example, it is said to be a serious problem among adolescents. It is said that
the “recluse type” Internet addicts do not leave home not only because they are
totally absorbed in the Internet, but also because they have a tendency to avoid
communication with others. In England, young people not in full-time education,
employment or training (NEET) are the subject of policy concern.  This
phenomenon is similar to hikikomori behaviourally in that the NEET do not work
or study. Japan is very different from India so one cannot actually say that
Indians suffer through what can be construed as exactly Hikikomori. However,
there are several similarities. Indians, too are &lt;a href=&quot;https://qz.com/india/1030594/indian-millennials-are-overworked-and-sick-of-office-politics/&quot;&gt;increasingly
overworked&lt;/a&gt;,
with most of the workers &lt;a href=&quot;https://qz.com/india/1401250/indias-unhealthy-workforce-stands-in-the-way-of-economic-growth/&quot;&gt;burning
out&lt;/a&gt;
from unhealthy conditions. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.abc.net.au/news/2016-10-04/india-obsession-with-sons-millions-of-lonely-men-after-dowry/7903134&quot;&gt;Indians too are
lonely&lt;/a&gt;
and many millions will, statistically, die alone. This is not to count the
actual problem that the dating culture in India is heavily flawed, and the fact
that most men are unlikely to be well-socialised with women – who watch movies
about romance and start to wonder why their lives don’t match up with what’s on
screen. Like the Japanese, Indians also have strong family structures, so that
an unemployed youth staying at home and slowly rotting away isn’t uncommon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we hear the word, we don’t sense that it may be a confusing, cluster-f*ck
of a phenomenon. There’s no one way for us to discern this or solve it. There
are people who’ve recovered and gone on to get married, some even to their
‘rental-sisters.’ But then there are also hikikomori who have been in this
condition for the last 20 years and do not have any desire to come out of it.
The worst case scenario is that there are more than half a million people who
aren’t even aware of their condition. Animes like &lt;em&gt;Welcome to NHK&lt;/em&gt; and movies
about Hikikomori may give us a visual on how hikikomori may feel. One of the
quotes from &lt;em&gt;Welcome to NHK&lt;/em&gt; especially made a mark on me- &lt;em&gt;“To a hikikomori,
winter is painful because everything feels cold, frozen over, and lonely. To a
hikikomori, spring is also painful because everyone is in a good mood and
therefore enviable. Summer, of course, is especially painful…”&lt;/em&gt; Maika Elan has
an amazing range of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/amp/s/relay.nationalgeographic.com/proxy/distribution/public/amp/photography/proof/2018/february/japan-hikikomori-isolation-society&quot;&gt;photographs&lt;/a&gt;
which showcase a spectrum of this phenomenon—from the ones who are new, the ones
who have faced it for decades, to the ones who have recovered. It’s worth a
glance and may give you a lot of fodder for thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a scary time for all of us. Even though we have measures to have constant
communication, it almost seems like we are stepping away from socialising. And
the more that we do so, the more it seems to do more harm than good. It is true
for all of us that we keep touch in ways that may come as shallow. The world has
always been a machine but the ‘chewing out’ and ‘burning out’ cycle seems to
have increased its pace. It is a positive step that social impairment or
problems with social connections are finally being looked at as health issues.
But that’s the best one can ask for, for now.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I’m sure we’ve all had days when we don’t want to leave the house, perhaps even our rooms. It’s not unheard of for a person to take a day off and do nothing, but then, we all have a limit to all or any of it. After a while, someone is probably going to call out for you, you’ll probably have made a plan you forgot about, or someone just visits you. It’d be a surprise if you said you had not talked to anyone all day, whether virtually or in real life. But, that’s exactly what is going on in several countries, most notably in Japan. If you haven’t heard of the word hikikomori before, don’t worry, I hadn’t either. Just the other day, I was made aware of how our generation is the most depressed one and I went surfing on the web to check the validity of that statement. What I found was this ominous term. When one mentions “hikikomori”, the immediate image that comes to mind is a young Japanese man, who has isolated himself within a bedroom in his parents’ house for years on end, refusing to speak, interact, or even be seen by anyone – sometimes including his own family. Meals are brought to the door a few times a day, and garbage and other refuse are left out in return. He might have started off spending his time playing video games or chatting online, but those activities have lost their charm long ago. He now simply stares off into space. Hikikomori. The world of perfect isolation. Because of the diversity of traits and characteristics accompanying hikikomori, much effort has been put into defining the term in a way that consolidates the condition that we are examining.  It is a term that describes both the state and the sufferer of acute social withdrawal. It means the behaviour in which adolescents and young adults refuse all contact with society and withdraw from all social activities. First coined by psychiatrist Tamaki Saito in 1998 in his book Social Withdrawal – Adolescence Without End, the term and the condition gained immense popularity in Japan following several newspaper articles and television interviews with Saito. The Japanese government officially defines hikikomori as people who haven’t left their homes or interacted with others for at least six months. They’re often dubbed as modern-day hermits. The best behavioural definition to date was proposed by Teo and Gaw in 2010, this definition of hikikomori captures the core constructs associated with the condition in six criteria. For one, most of the day, nearly every day, is spent at home. The person persistently avoids social situations and social relationships. They are bound to have experienced distress or impairment in their normal routine, for a duration of at least six months. The last, but an important criterion is that the condition is not better explained by another psychiatric disorder such as social phobia, major depressive disorders, schizophrenia, or avoidant personality disorder. We define this kind of hikikomori as “primary hikikomori”, i.e. one manifestation of the hikikomori phenomenon that cannot be described using current concepts in psychiatric disease. Primary hikikomori youth do not have any serious diagnosable psychopathology, yet they are unable to enter society or adapt to their surroundings. Hikikomori can also include individuals suffering from a variety of severe mental disorders including affective disorder, anxiety disorder, obsessive-compulsive disorder, personality disorders, and pervasive developmental disorders, but they are classified as “secondary hikikomori”. Originally, hikikomori was simply a general term referring to a condition in which people withdrew from relationships with others. It was also used as a psychiatric term describing the symptom of withdrawal in autistic, schizophrenic, depressive or aged patients. After 1990, hikikomori among youth received increasing attention from psychiatrists and society-at-large and came to be used mainly for describing young adults. According to The New York Times, doctors began to observe hikikomori as a social phenomenon around the mid-1980s, when young men exhibited signs of lethargy, refusing to communicate and spending most of their time in their rooms. Canadian journalist Michael Zielenziger’s book Shutting Out the Sun and the New York Times’ article “Shutting Themselves In” put the word on the map for the rest of us. The Saito book – Social Withdrawal – Adolescence Without End, in itself, gives us a good idea about how the word came to be. The hikikomori are rebellious, they need to be cared for and they’re financially dependent on their parents. It is difficult to find one cause or reason behind this condition. They are troubled by their future and are unable to cope with the uncertainty. They may have been triggered by some trauma; statistics suggest bullying as a major cause. The pressure of it all: to maintain the family name, to maintain your own dignity, everything may be a trigger and also a facilitator. The phenomenon can come in various forms: A person’s condition can be so severe that they lack the energy to leave their sofa to go to the toilet, another could suffer from obsessive-compulsive disorders so serious that they shower several hours a day or scrub their shower tiles for hours, some may just play video games all day- “as if it would tranquilise me.” Some just lay in wait for ‘energy’. A community‐based survey published in 2010 reported that the prevalence of hikikomori stood at approximately 1.2% of the Japanese population, and in 2016 a Japanese cabinet report estimated people with hikikomori to be number over half a million within the age range of 15‐39 years. The country now hopes to identify older hikikomori and understand the assistance their families need. As hikikomori grow older and their parents become too elderly to care for them, questions over their fate will become more urgent. There’s also an implied consensus that hikikomori are generally men, which might not be true. In fact, the very number mentioned might be incorrect. Several families don’t like to accept the reality and call it what it is and instead just say that their children are being ‘selfish’ for some time. The females, in Japanese culture, are already supposed to be shy and introverted, so when they shirk away from social interaction, nobody views it as anything out of the ordinary. What is absurd is how many parents albeit aware of what’s occurring channel the truth in a fashion that fits right with their reality. In Japanese, there’s a very famous saying, “A protruding nail will be hammered down.” And that is what may be the reason why this phenomenon is overtaking the Japanese population. Japan is soon to face what they call the “2030 problem”. As many with the condition are getting older and staying withdrawn for longer, the concern is that in 12 years many hikikomori will approach their 60s and will have no family to support them – making reintegration into society much harder. Additionally, as more people withdraw from society and stop working, the fear is that Japan’s economy will also suffer—which it is already doing.   Of course, when there is a problem, there is a solution. Psychiatrists have tried to treat hikikomori with individual therapy, group therapy, family therapy, and family group therapy. Solutions have also come in the form of a non-profit organisation called New Start, which runs a programme called Rental Sister, where volunteers visit hikikomori houses. It’s been said that it can take up to two years of visits to get some cases to leave their homes. Currently, there are more than fifty government‐funded community support centres for hikikomori located throughout the prefectures of Japan, providing services such as telephone consultations for family members, the creation of “meeting spaces” for affected people, and job placement support. In addition, various private institutions provide treatment for hikikomori sufferers. However, there is yet to be a unified evidence‐based method for these public/private interventions. A four‐step intervention is recommended by the government guidelines for hikikomori, including family support and first contact with the individual followed by his/her evaluation; individual support; training through an intermediate‐transient group situation (such as group therapy); and social participation trial. The Japanese sociocultural background has been traditionally permeated by “amae” (accepting over-dependent behaviours) and shame, which may underlie hikikomori. Parent‐child relationships in Japan have long been considered less oedipal than in Western societies. They can be marked by an absent father and an extremely prolonged and close bond with the mother, which may result in difficulties when it comes to becoming independent. Especially in hikikomori, the development of basic interpersonal skills during the early stages of life seems to be insufficient, which can induce vulnerability to stress in later school/workplace environments and lead to escape from social situations. Hikikomori‐like cases have recently been reported in other countries of varying sociocultural and economic backgrounds such as Hong Kong, Oman, was and Spain, and studies have revealed its existence in India, South Korea, and the US. Thus, one can say that hikikomori has now crossed the limits of a culture‐bound phenomenon to become an increasingly prevalent international condition. A major contributing factor may be the evolution of communication from direct to increasingly indirect and physically-isolating forms. This is especially the case for social interactions which hitherto required face‐to‐face contacts in a mutual physical space but can now occur, at least partially, in a virtual world. Internet addiction has been reported in several countries. In South Korea, for example, it is said to be a serious problem among adolescents. It is said that the “recluse type” Internet addicts do not leave home not only because they are totally absorbed in the Internet, but also because they have a tendency to avoid communication with others. In England, young people not in full-time education, employment or training (NEET) are the subject of policy concern.  This phenomenon is similar to hikikomori behaviourally in that the NEET do not work or study. Japan is very different from India so one cannot actually say that Indians suffer through what can be construed as exactly Hikikomori. However, there are several similarities. Indians, too are increasingly overworked, with most of the workers burning out from unhealthy conditions. Indians too are lonely and many millions will, statistically, die alone. This is not to count the actual problem that the dating culture in India is heavily flawed, and the fact that most men are unlikely to be well-socialised with women – who watch movies about romance and start to wonder why their lives don’t match up with what’s on screen. Like the Japanese, Indians also have strong family structures, so that an unemployed youth staying at home and slowly rotting away isn’t uncommon. When we hear the word, we don’t sense that it may be a confusing, cluster-f*ck of a phenomenon. There’s no one way for us to discern this or solve it. There are people who’ve recovered and gone on to get married, some even to their ‘rental-sisters.’ But then there are also hikikomori who have been in this condition for the last 20 years and do not have any desire to come out of it. The worst case scenario is that there are more than half a million people who aren’t even aware of their condition. Animes like Welcome to NHK and movies about Hikikomori may give us a visual on how hikikomori may feel. One of the quotes from Welcome to NHK especially made a mark on me- “To a hikikomori, winter is painful because everything feels cold, frozen over, and lonely. To a hikikomori, spring is also painful because everyone is in a good mood and therefore enviable. Summer, of course, is especially painful…” Maika Elan has an amazing range of photographs which showcase a spectrum of this phenomenon—from the ones who are new, the ones who have faced it for decades, to the ones who have recovered. It’s worth a glance and may give you a lot of fodder for thought. It’s a scary time for all of us. Even though we have measures to have constant communication, it almost seems like we are stepping away from socialising. And the more that we do so, the more it seems to do more harm than good. It is true for all of us that we keep touch in ways that may come as shallow. The world has always been a machine but the ‘chewing out’ and ‘burning out’ cycle seems to have increased its pace. It is a positive step that social impairment or problems with social connections are finally being looked at as health issues. But that’s the best one can ask for, for now.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How to Talk About Islam</title>
      <link href="/How-to-Talk-about-Islam" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Talk About Islam" />
      <published>2019-04-25T14:05:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-25T14:05:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/How-to-Talk-about-Islam</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/How-to-Talk-about-Islam">&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt that Islam is by far the most powerful religion in the world
today. With a presence on almost every continent inhabited by man, a powerful
theocratic political influence in countries dominated by its adherents, a
rapidly increasing immigrant population in post-Christian European countries, an
ever-strengthening missionary influence, and a global following of more than a
billion people, it has come to influence much of the modern world. In 2008, the
Vatican revealed that Muslims have overtaken Catholics as far as the number of
members is concerned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, it is no longer possible for people to simply ignore the Islamic
phenomenon, no matter what their opinion of it might be. The reason is that
Islam is quite unavoidable. There is hardly a place on earth when the &lt;em&gt;adhan&lt;/em&gt;
cannot be heard. There is a hardly a skyline which does not have a minaret
reaching up to the heavens. No matter where you go, Islam is there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a convert from Hinduism to orthodox Catholicism, there is much in Islam that
I admire, despite the deeply troubled history that my Church has shared with the
followers of Muhammad. I deeply admire, for instance, Islam’s teachings on
modesty. I am appreciative of many of the values which Islam inculcates in its
adherents – the devotion to one’s parents and the respect for elders.
Catholicism and Islam both profess to be monotheistic and eschew the joining of
partners with Almighty God, although our views about the nature of Almighty God
are radically different. And it goes without saying that I condemn any and all
forms of violence, hatred, and bigotry towards Muslims on the basis of their
religious affiliation as unethical, immoral and – above all – un-Christian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are also elements in Islam that I find deeply troubling. Now,
notice that I use the word “elements in Islam”, rather than simply “Islam”.
After all, there are many different groups that profess to be Muslim and which
have different interpretations of Islam. For instance, the Ahmadiyya Muslim
Community is entirely pacifistic in nature and condemns any and all forms of
religious terrorism. There are also many Sufis, Salafis, and mainstream Sunnis
who have condemned violence against non-Muslims and advocate a more apolitical
form of Islam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I acknowledge and respect the fact that the texts which &lt;em&gt;seem&lt;/em&gt; to call for
violence – in the Quran and the Hadith – are open to interpretation. As such, it
is not my intention to paint all Muslims with a broad brush, or to pretend that
Islam is monolithic. Just as it would be disingenuous for someone to paint my
faith or any other faith with gross overgeneralizations, so would be to do the
same with Islam. However, there are certainly some trends in the modern media
that are problematic and need to be addressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a tendency (among many secularists, liberals and the left-leaning) to
classify all critics of Islam as part of the far-right. This is not only
inaccurate, but also extremely dangerous, and contrary to the principle of the
freedom of expression. The act of criticising a particular
ideology/proposition/belief system is not the same as advocating violence,
hatred, discrimination or bigotry against proponents of that
ideology/proposition/belief system&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is true that all those who advocate violence against proponents of a
particular ideology/proposition/belief system also happen to be critics of that
particular ideology/proposition/belief system. But not all who criticise the
ideology/proposition/belief system are calling for violence against proponents
of that ideology/proposition/belief system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give an example from everyday life: all oranges are fruits, but not all
fruits are oranges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oranges might be bad, and all oranges might be fruits, but the fact that all
oranges are bad does not imply that all fruits are bad, even though all oranges
are fruits. This is because of the very simple fact that there are some fruits
which are not oranges. In other words, all anti-Muslim bigots are critics of
Islam, but not all critics of Islam are anti-Muslim bigots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider, for example, the case of David Wood, a convert from atheism to
Christianity. Wood is a fairly prominent critic of Islam. He has criticised the
teachings of Islam as inherently violent, the founder of Islam as an immoral
man, and the claims of Islam as intellectually deficient. However, I am yet to
come across a single video in which he has called for hatred against Muslims. On
the contrary, I follow him regularly and can testify that, as far as I can see,
he has nothing in his heart but love for Muslims, whom he believes to be in
error. This he has demonstrated on numerous occasions in many ways. One of the
best examples I can give is when he actually attempted to meet with someone who
had threatened to kill him. He recorded the occasion on camera when he visited
the agreed-upon venue and found that his would-be assassin hadn’t turned up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a professed Christian evangelist, Wood’s goal is not to spread bigotry
against Muslims, but to show Muslims (what he considers to be) the defects in
Islam, and to invite them to (what he believes to be) a better way:
Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what has been the response to his criticism? Intelligent, counter-critiques
from Muslims? On occasion, yes, as we see in the case of the Islamic scholar
(and gentleman) Shabir Ally who has debated him on numerous occasions and who
has always treated him with dignity, respect, and goodwill. However, much of the
backlash against his work has been neither intelligent, nor reasoned, nor
humane. Much of the responses to his criticism include death threats and the
mockery of his disabled children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, not every Muslim has responded in this manner. Of course, there are
many Muslims who would consider such barbaric behaviour to be un-Islamic. Of
course, such aforementioned peaceful Muslims may (and probably do) have peaceful
interpretations of Islam. But what we must realise is that there is a powerful
party within the religion of Islam which is violent, intolerant of criticism,
aggressively imperialist and which bases their beliefs not on political
convictions but on religiously motivated interpretations of Quranic and Hadithic
texts. And it is these hyper-fundamentalists who are making use of the
atmosphere of ‘tolerance’ and political correctness to advance an agenda that is
diabolical and toxic. Attempts to suppress peaceful, intelligent critics of
Islam is not ‘tolerance’. It is intolerance. And such attempts play right into
the hands of the Islamists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interesting thing that we see in the case of Wood is that a number of these
internet jihadis have started false-flagging his content. The shocking result
has been that Facebook has notified him that some of his posts “go against”
their community guidelines. These include posts in which Wood simply informed
his audiences of the most recent threats he had gotten from jihadis! Not a
single one of them included a call to violence, but only an appeal to keep-up
the criticism and satire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems, at times, that the people running Facebook have an extremely warped
idea of what hate speech is. Criticising an ideology as intellectually and
morally deficient is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; hate speech, but threatening someone for making those
criticisms certainly is. Indeed, as I have been at pains to emphasise: we have
to love our Muslim friends, condemn acts of violence against Muslims and fight
anti-Muslim discrimination. But that doesn’t mean we must be naïve and pretend
that Islam is a wholly pacifistic religion and that all the IS terrorists are
merely politically-motivated people using religion as a cover to gain support
for their cause. Such an analysis is not only painfully ignorant of the facts,
but is also dangerous since it encourages complacency against what is clearly a
rising tide of religiously-motivated Islamic fundamentalism in the world today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should we similarly pretend that the founder of Islam was a feminist and a
pacifist? No. If the historical evidence does not indicate that he was such, we
should not pretend that he was such. We should portray him in as historically
accurate a manner as possible – even if that portrayal is deemed offensive and
blasphemous by violent cyber-jihadists who have only one goal: the violent
promulgation of a religious system and the suppression of all criticism of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many peaceful, kind, gentlemanly and dignified people in the Muslim
community who would consider themselves orthodox and who would, in fact, agree
with what I am saying today. Yet, that still begs the question: how &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; we
talk about Islam? We should seek to honestly evaluate the religion itself. But
how should we judge what the religion is? There are peaceful Muslims and violent
Muslims, just as there are peaceful Christians and violent Christians. Which are
the true followers, and which are more influenced by other ideologies rather
than the doctrine itself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience (having extensively and intensively studied religion for around
ten years now), we should always judge a religion on the basis of its &lt;em&gt;Sources&lt;/em&gt;
and its &lt;em&gt;Heroes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I mean by this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Sources&lt;/em&gt; of a religion are essentially its authorities and/or sources of
doctrine. In Protestant Christianity, the &lt;em&gt;Source&lt;/em&gt; is Scripture alone, and its
plain perspicuous teaching. In Catholic Christianity, the source is Scripture
and Apostolic Tradition as received and interpreted by the Magisterium (i.e.,
the Church itself).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Heroes&lt;/em&gt; of a religion are those figures which have been deemed by the
Sources/Authorities as having followed the religion well (though not necessarily
perfectly, and there are different grades of heroes in every religion). The
ultimate Hero of all Christianity is Jesus Himself, who is believed to be the
perfect man. In Catholicism, the heroes are (to a certain degree) the saints.
Although it is generally agreed that the canonisation process only grants us
certainty that the deceased is in heaven, not that the person always lived an
exemplary life. This gives room for the believing Catholic to criticise even the
acts of saints, as many traditionalists have done with St. Mother Teresa, to
give an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Islam, the greatest hero is Muhammad himself, who is considered to be the
perfect example for all mankind. In Sunni Islam, Muhammad is closely followed by
the Four Rightly Guided Caliphs, whereas in Shia Islam, Muhammad is but one of
Fourteen Infallibles, which include – besides the founder himself – Fatima and
the Twelve Imams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, when we judge Islam, we should first distinguish between the various schools
of Islam. Sunni Islam is not the same as Shia Islam or Ibadi Islam or Ahmadi
Islam. There are, so to speak, quite a few ‘Islams’, just as there are different
interpretations of Marxism, democracy, libertarianism, capitalism, feminism and
just about everything else. In other words, the next time you see some act of
violence perpetrated by fundamentalists of any religion or sect, ask yourself
the question: is this act of violence commanded by the Sources of the faith in
question? Is there any precedent for this sort of terror in the behaviour of its
heroes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should ask the same question when it comes to the good actions of peaceful
adherents. When you see followers of a religion endorsing pacifism or separation
of religion and state, are they acting faithfully according to their Sources and
Heroes? Or are there more influenced by other ideologies, in light of which they
interpret their religion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I end this article with a comparison between the Christian Crusades and the
Islamic Mujahideen. The Crusades were an administrative decision, in part made
by the Pope. Catholicism does not require its adherents to consider Papal
administrative decisions as infallible – the only infallible things coming out
of the Pope are his ratifications of ecumenical councils and ex-cathedra
statements; that is to say, matters which &lt;em&gt;solely&lt;/em&gt; concern doctrine and dogma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Administrative decisions, as per Catholic ecclesiology, are &lt;em&gt;entirely&lt;/em&gt; fallible.
As a matter of fact, it is the conservatives in the Church who are very loud in
criticising the administrative decisions of recent Popes, such as the decision
of Pope Paul VI to allow the priest to celebrate the Mass facing the
congregation (&lt;em&gt;versus populum&lt;/em&gt;) rather than the East (&lt;em&gt;ad orientem&lt;/em&gt;) as has
traditionally been practised. So, largely, the Crusades are not part of Catholic
doctrine, if at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not say this in order to “wash my hands clean” of the Crusades, so to
speak. Personally, I think the Crusades had a noble intent in &lt;em&gt;theory&lt;/em&gt; (i.e.,
that of defending Christendom), but I lament the fact that in &lt;em&gt;practice&lt;/em&gt; many of
the Crusaders became too extreme. Rather than simply defeating enemy military
forces, they committed unspeakable atrocities upon civilians which are
horrendous, lamentable and condemnable. As a traditional and orthodox Catholic,
I am &lt;em&gt;ashamed&lt;/em&gt; of the misdeeds that were perpetrated in the name of the
Crusades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here’s the thing: my religion gives me the liberty to say this. My faith
does not compel me to believe that the Crusaders were “inspired by God”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when you study the early Muslim invasions of neighbouring civilisations, ask
yourself the question: can we say the same about Islam? Who led these invasions?
Were these figures deemed by Islam to be inspired by God in their acts and to
be, in some sense, infallible? Do the chief sources command its adherents to
consider their acts of war as virtuous on the part of a ruler? Our judgment of
Islam should be based on these facts. I will leave you to make up your own mind.
It may turn out that, in fact, Islam is an extremely peaceful and humane
religion. Or it may turn out another way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only ask you to use sound judgment in your study and to not be afraid of the
truth, however hard it may turn out to be. However, in all our critique or
appraisal, we must remember that our analysis of a doctrine should not seep into
a generalisation of the moral character of the adherents of that doctrine. This
attitude allows me to be extremely kind and respectful to my Muslim friends
while, at the same time, giving me total liberty to analyse and evaluate the
religion as my conscience commands me. And that is how we should talk about
Islam today, condemning it where we see condemnation due, fighting for and
respecting its adherents when they so require, and accepting or rejecting it for
what it is when truth so demands.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There is no doubt that Islam is by far the most powerful religion in the world today. With a presence on almost every continent inhabited by man, a powerful theocratic political influence in countries dominated by its adherents, a rapidly increasing immigrant population in post-Christian European countries, an ever-strengthening missionary influence, and a global following of more than a billion people, it has come to influence much of the modern world. In 2008, the Vatican revealed that Muslims have overtaken Catholics as far as the number of members is concerned. As such, it is no longer possible for people to simply ignore the Islamic phenomenon, no matter what their opinion of it might be. The reason is that Islam is quite unavoidable. There is hardly a place on earth when the adhan cannot be heard. There is a hardly a skyline which does not have a minaret reaching up to the heavens. No matter where you go, Islam is there. As a convert from Hinduism to orthodox Catholicism, there is much in Islam that I admire, despite the deeply troubled history that my Church has shared with the followers of Muhammad. I deeply admire, for instance, Islam’s teachings on modesty. I am appreciative of many of the values which Islam inculcates in its adherents – the devotion to one’s parents and the respect for elders. Catholicism and Islam both profess to be monotheistic and eschew the joining of partners with Almighty God, although our views about the nature of Almighty God are radically different. And it goes without saying that I condemn any and all forms of violence, hatred, and bigotry towards Muslims on the basis of their religious affiliation as unethical, immoral and – above all – un-Christian. However, there are also elements in Islam that I find deeply troubling. Now, notice that I use the word “elements in Islam”, rather than simply “Islam”. After all, there are many different groups that profess to be Muslim and which have different interpretations of Islam. For instance, the Ahmadiyya Muslim Community is entirely pacifistic in nature and condemns any and all forms of religious terrorism. There are also many Sufis, Salafis, and mainstream Sunnis who have condemned violence against non-Muslims and advocate a more apolitical form of Islam. I acknowledge and respect the fact that the texts which seem to call for violence – in the Quran and the Hadith – are open to interpretation. As such, it is not my intention to paint all Muslims with a broad brush, or to pretend that Islam is monolithic. Just as it would be disingenuous for someone to paint my faith or any other faith with gross overgeneralizations, so would be to do the same with Islam. However, there are certainly some trends in the modern media that are problematic and need to be addressed. There is a tendency (among many secularists, liberals and the left-leaning) to classify all critics of Islam as part of the far-right. This is not only inaccurate, but also extremely dangerous, and contrary to the principle of the freedom of expression. The act of criticising a particular ideology/proposition/belief system is not the same as advocating violence, hatred, discrimination or bigotry against proponents of that ideology/proposition/belief system Yes, it is true that all those who advocate violence against proponents of a particular ideology/proposition/belief system also happen to be critics of that particular ideology/proposition/belief system. But not all who criticise the ideology/proposition/belief system are calling for violence against proponents of that ideology/proposition/belief system. To give an example from everyday life: all oranges are fruits, but not all fruits are oranges. Oranges might be bad, and all oranges might be fruits, but the fact that all oranges are bad does not imply that all fruits are bad, even though all oranges are fruits. This is because of the very simple fact that there are some fruits which are not oranges. In other words, all anti-Muslim bigots are critics of Islam, but not all critics of Islam are anti-Muslim bigots. Consider, for example, the case of David Wood, a convert from atheism to Christianity. Wood is a fairly prominent critic of Islam. He has criticised the teachings of Islam as inherently violent, the founder of Islam as an immoral man, and the claims of Islam as intellectually deficient. However, I am yet to come across a single video in which he has called for hatred against Muslims. On the contrary, I follow him regularly and can testify that, as far as I can see, he has nothing in his heart but love for Muslims, whom he believes to be in error. This he has demonstrated on numerous occasions in many ways. One of the best examples I can give is when he actually attempted to meet with someone who had threatened to kill him. He recorded the occasion on camera when he visited the agreed-upon venue and found that his would-be assassin hadn’t turned up. As a professed Christian evangelist, Wood’s goal is not to spread bigotry against Muslims, but to show Muslims (what he considers to be) the defects in Islam, and to invite them to (what he believes to be) a better way: Christianity. But what has been the response to his criticism? Intelligent, counter-critiques from Muslims? On occasion, yes, as we see in the case of the Islamic scholar (and gentleman) Shabir Ally who has debated him on numerous occasions and who has always treated him with dignity, respect, and goodwill. However, much of the backlash against his work has been neither intelligent, nor reasoned, nor humane. Much of the responses to his criticism include death threats and the mockery of his disabled children. Of course, not every Muslim has responded in this manner. Of course, there are many Muslims who would consider such barbaric behaviour to be un-Islamic. Of course, such aforementioned peaceful Muslims may (and probably do) have peaceful interpretations of Islam. But what we must realise is that there is a powerful party within the religion of Islam which is violent, intolerant of criticism, aggressively imperialist and which bases their beliefs not on political convictions but on religiously motivated interpretations of Quranic and Hadithic texts. And it is these hyper-fundamentalists who are making use of the atmosphere of ‘tolerance’ and political correctness to advance an agenda that is diabolical and toxic. Attempts to suppress peaceful, intelligent critics of Islam is not ‘tolerance’. It is intolerance. And such attempts play right into the hands of the Islamists. The interesting thing that we see in the case of Wood is that a number of these internet jihadis have started false-flagging his content. The shocking result has been that Facebook has notified him that some of his posts “go against” their community guidelines. These include posts in which Wood simply informed his audiences of the most recent threats he had gotten from jihadis! Not a single one of them included a call to violence, but only an appeal to keep-up the criticism and satire. It seems, at times, that the people running Facebook have an extremely warped idea of what hate speech is. Criticising an ideology as intellectually and morally deficient is not hate speech, but threatening someone for making those criticisms certainly is. Indeed, as I have been at pains to emphasise: we have to love our Muslim friends, condemn acts of violence against Muslims and fight anti-Muslim discrimination. But that doesn’t mean we must be naïve and pretend that Islam is a wholly pacifistic religion and that all the IS terrorists are merely politically-motivated people using religion as a cover to gain support for their cause. Such an analysis is not only painfully ignorant of the facts, but is also dangerous since it encourages complacency against what is clearly a rising tide of religiously-motivated Islamic fundamentalism in the world today. Should we similarly pretend that the founder of Islam was a feminist and a pacifist? No. If the historical evidence does not indicate that he was such, we should not pretend that he was such. We should portray him in as historically accurate a manner as possible – even if that portrayal is deemed offensive and blasphemous by violent cyber-jihadists who have only one goal: the violent promulgation of a religious system and the suppression of all criticism of it. There are many peaceful, kind, gentlemanly and dignified people in the Muslim community who would consider themselves orthodox and who would, in fact, agree with what I am saying today. Yet, that still begs the question: how should we talk about Islam? We should seek to honestly evaluate the religion itself. But how should we judge what the religion is? There are peaceful Muslims and violent Muslims, just as there are peaceful Christians and violent Christians. Which are the true followers, and which are more influenced by other ideologies rather than the doctrine itself? In my experience (having extensively and intensively studied religion for around ten years now), we should always judge a religion on the basis of its Sources and its Heroes. What do I mean by this? The Sources of a religion are essentially its authorities and/or sources of doctrine. In Protestant Christianity, the Source is Scripture alone, and its plain perspicuous teaching. In Catholic Christianity, the source is Scripture and Apostolic Tradition as received and interpreted by the Magisterium (i.e., the Church itself). The Heroes of a religion are those figures which have been deemed by the Sources/Authorities as having followed the religion well (though not necessarily perfectly, and there are different grades of heroes in every religion). The ultimate Hero of all Christianity is Jesus Himself, who is believed to be the perfect man. In Catholicism, the heroes are (to a certain degree) the saints. Although it is generally agreed that the canonisation process only grants us certainty that the deceased is in heaven, not that the person always lived an exemplary life. This gives room for the believing Catholic to criticise even the acts of saints, as many traditionalists have done with St. Mother Teresa, to give an example. In Islam, the greatest hero is Muhammad himself, who is considered to be the perfect example for all mankind. In Sunni Islam, Muhammad is closely followed by the Four Rightly Guided Caliphs, whereas in Shia Islam, Muhammad is but one of Fourteen Infallibles, which include – besides the founder himself – Fatima and the Twelve Imams. So, when we judge Islam, we should first distinguish between the various schools of Islam. Sunni Islam is not the same as Shia Islam or Ibadi Islam or Ahmadi Islam. There are, so to speak, quite a few ‘Islams’, just as there are different interpretations of Marxism, democracy, libertarianism, capitalism, feminism and just about everything else. In other words, the next time you see some act of violence perpetrated by fundamentalists of any religion or sect, ask yourself the question: is this act of violence commanded by the Sources of the faith in question? Is there any precedent for this sort of terror in the behaviour of its heroes? You should ask the same question when it comes to the good actions of peaceful adherents. When you see followers of a religion endorsing pacifism or separation of religion and state, are they acting faithfully according to their Sources and Heroes? Or are there more influenced by other ideologies, in light of which they interpret their religion? I end this article with a comparison between the Christian Crusades and the Islamic Mujahideen. The Crusades were an administrative decision, in part made by the Pope. Catholicism does not require its adherents to consider Papal administrative decisions as infallible – the only infallible things coming out of the Pope are his ratifications of ecumenical councils and ex-cathedra statements; that is to say, matters which solely concern doctrine and dogma. Administrative decisions, as per Catholic ecclesiology, are entirely fallible. As a matter of fact, it is the conservatives in the Church who are very loud in criticising the administrative decisions of recent Popes, such as the decision of Pope Paul VI to allow the priest to celebrate the Mass facing the congregation (versus populum) rather than the East (ad orientem) as has traditionally been practised. So, largely, the Crusades are not part of Catholic doctrine, if at all. I do not say this in order to “wash my hands clean” of the Crusades, so to speak. Personally, I think the Crusades had a noble intent in theory (i.e., that of defending Christendom), but I lament the fact that in practice many of the Crusaders became too extreme. Rather than simply defeating enemy military forces, they committed unspeakable atrocities upon civilians which are horrendous, lamentable and condemnable. As a traditional and orthodox Catholic, I am ashamed of the misdeeds that were perpetrated in the name of the Crusades. But here’s the thing: my religion gives me the liberty to say this. My faith does not compel me to believe that the Crusaders were “inspired by God”. But when you study the early Muslim invasions of neighbouring civilisations, ask yourself the question: can we say the same about Islam? Who led these invasions? Were these figures deemed by Islam to be inspired by God in their acts and to be, in some sense, infallible? Do the chief sources command its adherents to consider their acts of war as virtuous on the part of a ruler? Our judgment of Islam should be based on these facts. I will leave you to make up your own mind. It may turn out that, in fact, Islam is an extremely peaceful and humane religion. Or it may turn out another way. I only ask you to use sound judgment in your study and to not be afraid of the truth, however hard it may turn out to be. However, in all our critique or appraisal, we must remember that our analysis of a doctrine should not seep into a generalisation of the moral character of the adherents of that doctrine. This attitude allows me to be extremely kind and respectful to my Muslim friends while, at the same time, giving me total liberty to analyse and evaluate the religion as my conscience commands me. And that is how we should talk about Islam today, condemning it where we see condemnation due, fighting for and respecting its adherents when they so require, and accepting or rejecting it for what it is when truth so demands.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The (Un)faithfuls</title>
      <link href="/The-Unfaithfuls" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The (Un)faithfuls" />
      <published>2019-04-10T11:30:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-10T11:30:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Unfaithfuls</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Unfaithfuls">&lt;p&gt;I recently had a breakdown of sorts, and the stifling confines of my room
tightened its shadows on me, as I desperately tried to get out of that place.
But where would I have gone? I certainly had no means to a Tesla or the unending
country roads to hit like BoJack Horseman, so I ended up quietly muffling my
screams in my pillow. And while I was grappling with desperation to end my life,
my eyes met God’s. Before I venture any further with the narrative, I must tell
you that I am the son of a devout Hindu, so it is quite natural for the walls of
my room to be installed not with posters of cool bands and stuff but with
posters of cool swagger Gods. My mother, who I dearly adore, has tried her fair
share and beyond to turn me into a devout as herself, but has not fared so well
yet. The least I could do was not frustrate her attempt at installing Durga’s (a
Hindu Warrior Goddess) poster in the most visible spot in my room. Initially,
her belief was that it would aid me to gradually turn into a god-fearing inmate
as herself, but now she has given up all hopes on me and doesn’t care as long as
I do no harm to her or society in general―especially by spreading or committing
blasphemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, when my eyes met God’s, I felt the excruciating urge to ask for her
help–putting myself in another struggle with my rational self–which clearly has
not yet accredited any credibility to the existence of any such deity and
considers it a sham. There, in the midst of this struggle, both my selves
settled on a critical question: why is faith important if it is a scam? To
answer this, I had to first address the victims of atheism: the millennial or
Generation Y. As evidenced by memes, a more than qualified instrument to gauge
the collective mindset of the globalised culture of the millennial, we are all
pseudo-nihilists and pseudo-existentialists with no particular belief system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This culture of disbelief is a stark characteristic of this generation and is so
as a consequence of science, which has with all its enigma deinstitutionalised
the notion of religion or anything that it entails. Now, what I have to ask here
is, if it has deinstitutionalised the institutions of faith, what does it
provide us in return? What does it offer us to cling on to when we are at our
worst? Does it offer itself us a replacement or does it offer the idea that we
are apex beings and nothing is higher than us? Now, although I am not in denial
of science’s contributions towards human society, what my problem is that
science is at the end of the day esoteric, exclusive. It is not everyone’s club
to join, and so the multitude with all its disillusionment is without a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science has taught us that we exist for no purpose and our existence is more of
a chance happening than something in the blueprint of a god. Science has since
its birth marshalled forward to perish existing belief systems, appropriating
the office of the apex belief system to itself. No wonder why such extreme
efforts are made for space expeditions, it is because science has run out of
things to unravel; science has run out of purpose as well but is simply
continuing with the faith in its purpose of serving mankind in ways greater than
itself. Ironically enough, while science has robbed us of the notion of faith
and belief and has left us naked to the vile truth of the universe, it has
itself nestled in the belief of something greater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we understand the importance of faith or communal belief systems. I am not
a student of theology so pardon my ill-service towards what I am going to say,
but, in my belief, communions or religions have existed since societies were
conceived for a very real reason. A society just like any organisation is
unmanageable without a fixed set of rules and morality that everyone who is a
part of such has to adhere to. This fixed set of rules and conduct of morality
has with time festered into unquestionable beliefs called religions. Now, where
religions came in handy back in the day was that they gave men a sense of
purpose. And, as is evident, man needs a purpose to go on in life. The piety
towards those set of rules existed because men believed that we exist for a
purpose and by following those rules we would have served that purpose and at
last be in the hands of Nirvana or whatever it is called around the world. I am
not at all bailing religion out of the many evils it has committed, but what
good it has reaped has to be stated. Religion’s greatest victory was that it
took the human psyche into consideration, unlike science, and pandered to our
greatest need, the need for validation. Now, this might seem like a coarse
conclusion, but this is what it is. Human species, in general, has the vehement
need to be validated, of our deeds in particular and existence in general. It is
this need for validation that gave birth to the question of “What is the purpose
of life?” And that is where many irrational beliefs of religion come into aid.
Reason gives us the validation we require in life and also places us in the
hands of faith which can get us through our most devastating times—giving us
meaning and purpose throughout all of it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, it may seem like I am antagonising science and making religion the
protagonist, but that is not the case. I am simply defending the case of
religion where it is due: it has given men a purpose and a belief in the fallacy
that there is something higher than us who is watching over us in our thinnest
of times. Some might argue here that it is better to be out of the shackles of
religion and feel liberated at being able to create our own purpose as Nietzsche
proposed, I argue otherwise.  What Nietzsche has proposed doesn’t apply to the
multitude; the multitude isn’t capable enough to create their own purpose in
life and requires a master to guide them. Imagine a herd of sheep bound by
fences - they stay in it, they work in it, and one day, a novel sheep kills the
master and breaks the fence and opens the sheep to an unending expanse. Although
at first, the change might enthral them, slowly they’d start feeling lost and
purposeless, because now they do not serve anything or anyone and are simply
roaming free. After a while, they scamper in insanity to find a purpose, but due
to their limited intelligence and faculties, they fall short. It goes fairly
Orwellian from there, the sheep, tired of such liberty again hands themselves
over to a new master, and that master in our case is science. Although science
has done great services to the society and we have enjoyed such for a long time,
we now have come to a standstill where nothing makes sense anymore and our
existence is boiled down to absurdity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, although religion has propagated many evils, it has time and again given men
purpose and a much needed coping mechanism to deal with their problems. And now
that we are disillusioned and hopeless, it might not do us much harm to commit
the psychological suicide that Albert Camus proposed, because unlike those
thinkers, we are a herd of simpletons with limited faculties. But that is not
possible at this stage, so I guess we are simply doomed with depression. All we
can simply do is stall our time by looking at memes.  &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I recently had a breakdown of sorts, and the stifling confines of my room tightened its shadows on me, as I desperately tried to get out of that place. But where would I have gone? I certainly had no means to a Tesla or the unending country roads to hit like BoJack Horseman, so I ended up quietly muffling my screams in my pillow. And while I was grappling with desperation to end my life, my eyes met God’s. Before I venture any further with the narrative, I must tell you that I am the son of a devout Hindu, so it is quite natural for the walls of my room to be installed not with posters of cool bands and stuff but with posters of cool swagger Gods. My mother, who I dearly adore, has tried her fair share and beyond to turn me into a devout as herself, but has not fared so well yet. The least I could do was not frustrate her attempt at installing Durga’s (a Hindu Warrior Goddess) poster in the most visible spot in my room. Initially, her belief was that it would aid me to gradually turn into a god-fearing inmate as herself, but now she has given up all hopes on me and doesn’t care as long as I do no harm to her or society in general―especially by spreading or committing blasphemies. Now, when my eyes met God’s, I felt the excruciating urge to ask for her help–putting myself in another struggle with my rational self–which clearly has not yet accredited any credibility to the existence of any such deity and considers it a sham. There, in the midst of this struggle, both my selves settled on a critical question: why is faith important if it is a scam? To answer this, I had to first address the victims of atheism: the millennial or Generation Y. As evidenced by memes, a more than qualified instrument to gauge the collective mindset of the globalised culture of the millennial, we are all pseudo-nihilists and pseudo-existentialists with no particular belief system. This culture of disbelief is a stark characteristic of this generation and is so as a consequence of science, which has with all its enigma deinstitutionalised the notion of religion or anything that it entails. Now, what I have to ask here is, if it has deinstitutionalised the institutions of faith, what does it provide us in return? What does it offer us to cling on to when we are at our worst? Does it offer itself us a replacement or does it offer the idea that we are apex beings and nothing is higher than us? Now, although I am not in denial of science’s contributions towards human society, what my problem is that science is at the end of the day esoteric, exclusive. It is not everyone’s club to join, and so the multitude with all its disillusionment is without a purpose. Science has taught us that we exist for no purpose and our existence is more of a chance happening than something in the blueprint of a god. Science has since its birth marshalled forward to perish existing belief systems, appropriating the office of the apex belief system to itself. No wonder why such extreme efforts are made for space expeditions, it is because science has run out of things to unravel; science has run out of purpose as well but is simply continuing with the faith in its purpose of serving mankind in ways greater than itself. Ironically enough, while science has robbed us of the notion of faith and belief and has left us naked to the vile truth of the universe, it has itself nestled in the belief of something greater. Here we understand the importance of faith or communal belief systems. I am not a student of theology so pardon my ill-service towards what I am going to say, but, in my belief, communions or religions have existed since societies were conceived for a very real reason. A society just like any organisation is unmanageable without a fixed set of rules and morality that everyone who is a part of such has to adhere to. This fixed set of rules and conduct of morality has with time festered into unquestionable beliefs called religions. Now, where religions came in handy back in the day was that they gave men a sense of purpose. And, as is evident, man needs a purpose to go on in life. The piety towards those set of rules existed because men believed that we exist for a purpose and by following those rules we would have served that purpose and at last be in the hands of Nirvana or whatever it is called around the world. I am not at all bailing religion out of the many evils it has committed, but what good it has reaped has to be stated. Religion’s greatest victory was that it took the human psyche into consideration, unlike science, and pandered to our greatest need, the need for validation. Now, this might seem like a coarse conclusion, but this is what it is. Human species, in general, has the vehement need to be validated, of our deeds in particular and existence in general. It is this need for validation that gave birth to the question of “What is the purpose of life?” And that is where many irrational beliefs of religion come into aid. Reason gives us the validation we require in life and also places us in the hands of faith which can get us through our most devastating times—giving us meaning and purpose throughout all of it.   Now, it may seem like I am antagonising science and making religion the protagonist, but that is not the case. I am simply defending the case of religion where it is due: it has given men a purpose and a belief in the fallacy that there is something higher than us who is watching over us in our thinnest of times. Some might argue here that it is better to be out of the shackles of religion and feel liberated at being able to create our own purpose as Nietzsche proposed, I argue otherwise.  What Nietzsche has proposed doesn’t apply to the multitude; the multitude isn’t capable enough to create their own purpose in life and requires a master to guide them. Imagine a herd of sheep bound by fences - they stay in it, they work in it, and one day, a novel sheep kills the master and breaks the fence and opens the sheep to an unending expanse. Although at first, the change might enthral them, slowly they’d start feeling lost and purposeless, because now they do not serve anything or anyone and are simply roaming free. After a while, they scamper in insanity to find a purpose, but due to their limited intelligence and faculties, they fall short. It goes fairly Orwellian from there, the sheep, tired of such liberty again hands themselves over to a new master, and that master in our case is science. Although science has done great services to the society and we have enjoyed such for a long time, we now have come to a standstill where nothing makes sense anymore and our existence is boiled down to absurdity. So, although religion has propagated many evils, it has time and again given men purpose and a much needed coping mechanism to deal with their problems. And now that we are disillusioned and hopeless, it might not do us much harm to commit the psychological suicide that Albert Camus proposed, because unlike those thinkers, we are a herd of simpletons with limited faculties. But that is not possible at this stage, so I guess we are simply doomed with depression. All we can simply do is stall our time by looking at memes.  </summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Not Peace but a Sword: The New Religious War in Ukraine</title>
      <link href="/Religious-War-In-Ukraine" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Not Peace but a Sword: The New Religious War in Ukraine" />
      <published>2019-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Religious-War-In-Ukraine</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Religious-War-In-Ukraine">&lt;p&gt;The year is 2014. Violent protests have erupted across Ukraine. President Viktor Yanukovych’s perceived pro-Russian policies have angered a large section of the population, who have firmly come out in support of closer ties with the European Union. However, the predominantly Russian-speaking East is not that happy about the prospect of a European alliance. Unfortunately for them, Yanukovych is soon ousted from power by a violent revolution. This new development is not, however, universally acclaimed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly afterwards, armed revolutionaries seize control of the Crimean Parliament and allegedly install a pro-Russian Prime Minister, who quickly calls upon Vladimir Putin for military assistance. Cries of “Putin is my President!” are now commonly heard in the streets of Crimea. Eventually, a referendum is held and the results indicate that the people of Crimea have overwhelmingly voted for union with Russia. Crimea then becomes a part of the Russian Federation, a development condemned by the European Union, the United States and much of the rest of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia and Ukraine share a long inter-woven history. Both of them look upon Kievan Rus as their cultural ancestor – the monarchy that once included much of the East Slavic and Finnic peoples of Europe, and which lasted from the late 9th to the mid-13th century. However, over time, their relationship has grown steadily worse. The events of 2014 are but a modern manifestation of a long-festering division that has only been exacerbated as the years have passed by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, Ukraine is a part of Eastern Europe, a region many people consider to be the heartland of the Eastern Orthodox Church. Known for its hardline stances on many issues of faith and morals, this ancient federation of ecclesiastical communities claims a line of unbroken continuity with the Church of the Apostles. Proponents call it a relatively pure Church, undefiled by the erroneous ideologies of the modern world. Critics call it a reactionary, patriarchal organisation, which still refuses to ordain women and considers abortion to be immoral and sinful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the vast majority of Western European culture and society – the historic stronghold of the Roman Church – has been usurped by the forces of liberalism, secularism and the sexual revolution, the same cannot be said about Eastern Orthodoxy. This is highly ironic, given that the Russian Orthodox Church, in particular, was strongly persecuted by the Soviet Union, as were as the other Slavic Orthodox Churches, such the Serbian, Bulgarian and Romanian Patriarchates. However, since the fall of the USSR, the Orthodox Church has come to wield a level of influence over local politics unseen since the time of the Tsars. While the Russian Federation continues to claim non-affiliation with any religious body as such, the alliance between Putin and the Moscow Patriarchate is the &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religion is a very strong preserver. After all, the Roman Catholic Church – the world’s largest, most powerful and longest-running monarchy – is, in many ways, the only remaining bastion of medieval Western culture. This is easily apparent especially if you visit traditionalist monasteries which still follow the rules in all their strictness. It is, of course, true that even many Roman Catholic priests and bishops don’t practice their faith well and have become lax, but there are still many strongholds of conservatism within that Church―despite the forces of liberalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is true also of the Eastern Orthodox Church, which, in general, suffers much less from the plague of liberals within their hierarchy. Some observers have noted the remarkable similarity between the alliance of Putin and Patriarch Kirill of Moscow today and the traditional diarchy of Byzantium, in which the Emperor and the Patriarch would be the most powerful political figures in the land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, while the Russian Federation may no longer possess the territorial jurisdiction of Kievan Rus, the Patriarchate of Moscow has a much stronger boast to that. The Russian Church claims jurisdiction not merely over Russia but also over all of Ukraine. In fact, the single largest Church in Ukraine continues to be under the jurisdiction of Moscow. It is called the Ukrainian Orthodox Church of the Moscow Patriarchate. It is autonomous, but not autocephalous. In other words, it is mostly self-governing, but not wholly independent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, many of the nationalists of Ukraine have despised what they see as the continued intrusion of Russian imperialist influence in their homeland. And it is precisely such sentiments as these that were responsible, in part, for the splintering of the Orthodox Church in Ukraine into two new denominations – the Ukrainian Orthodox Church of the Kievan Patriarchate and the Ukrainian Autocephalous Orthodox Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to this, there is the Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church, which looks like the Orthodox Church, prays like the Orthodox Church, smells like the Orthodox Church, but is – in fact – a Catholic Church in full communion with Rome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, the Kiev Patriarchate and the Ukrainian Autocephalous Orthodox Church were considered by the rest of the Orthodox world to be nationalist fanatics and schismatics who have damaged the unity of Orthodoxy. The Metropolitan Onufriy, under the authority of the Moscow Patriarch, was considered to be the rightful primate of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, quite recently, the situation has taken a sharp turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Patriarch of Constantinople Bartholomew I, long considered the “first among equals” of the Orthodox Patriarchs has taken it upon himself to grant the Church of Ukraine (specifically the two splinter groups from Moscow) complete independence from Russia. While it is true that the Patriarch of Constantinople does not enjoy the same authority in Orthodoxy that the Pope does in Catholicism, he does have some prerogatives – among them is the responsibility of hearing appeals from the rest of the Orthodox world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has led to the Patriarchate of Moscow excommunicating the Patriarch of Constantinople. And the vast majority of the Orthodox Churches have sided with Moscow. Bartholomew, however, has been undeterred. As a result of his efforts, the two splinter groups have now been united as the “Orthodox Church of Ukraine” with the full blessing and support of Ukrainian President Petro Poroshenko. Their new leader calls himself Metropolitan Epiphany (Dumenko). As of now, no Orthodox Church has given recognition to this new Church apart from Constantinople itself, and it has received heated condemnation not only from Moscow but also from the Primate of Serbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What implications could this have for the political situation? First of all, it is almost without question that the new Orthodox Church will come to represent the face of Ukrainian nationalism against “Russian imperialism”. It is no wonder that President Poroshenko is such an avid supporter of the move. Millions of Ukrainians still consider the Patriarch of Moscow to be their spiritual leaders. This new move represents an opportunity to break that perception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the new Church has also received surprising support from sectors of the Roman Catholic Church. It is very ironic indeed – four centuries ago, nationalism played a very important role in rousing extreme opposition to the Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church, members of which were looked upon as traitors who had defected to Rome. Now, it is the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religious freedom still remains strongly restricted in many parts of Eastern Europe. Russia, for instance, has banned the Jehovah’s Witnesses. There was also a famous attempt to ban the &lt;em&gt;Bhagavad Gita As It Is&lt;/em&gt; in 2011. In 2016, the premises of a Vedic monastery in Nizhny Novgorod were demolished by local authorities, after having been declared illegal a year back. Meanwhile, the Russian Orthodox Church is busy rebuilding Churches demolished during the time of the Soviet Union and is enjoying the presence of Putin at Church services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does the future hold for Russia and Ukraine? Will Russia try to resurrect its orthodox heritage, perhaps even, as some suggest, restore the monarchy? Will we see a new cold war, between Russia and the West, with Ukraine caught in the middle? What is the future for the Orthodox faithful?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, my friends, only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The year is 2014. Violent protests have erupted across Ukraine. President Viktor Yanukovych’s perceived pro-Russian policies have angered a large section of the population, who have firmly come out in support of closer ties with the European Union. However, the predominantly Russian-speaking East is not that happy about the prospect of a European alliance. Unfortunately for them, Yanukovych is soon ousted from power by a violent revolution. This new development is not, however, universally acclaimed.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Feminist? No, of course not.</title>
      <link href="/Feminist-No-of-course-not" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Feminist? No, of course not." />
      <published>2019-03-28T01:33:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-28T01:33:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Feminist-No-of-course-not</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Feminist-No-of-course-not">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I don’t want to get into it! No, not me.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very recently, after a long conversation about everything ranging from Paganism
to Masculinity with some very articulate people, I was offered to put my words
to use in talk of feminism. I didn’t know what to make of the instantaneous
rejection that came out of me, I recall thinking I don’t want to dip my feet
into that pool. One of the conversationalists (a very openly-proclaimed
feminist) took it upon herself to tell me that I was welcome to voice my
opinions, that ‘they’ are open to one and all. I never did talk about whether or
not I identified as a feminist, however, her welcome led me to think about why
someone would not want to be a part of this ‘them.’ The new F-word in the market
that people are so scared of had, I think, tied me up in knots too. Not
believing that you could be a part of this movement of feminism would be absurd,
right? How can I, a woman, remove myself from a movement of and about all women?
I am not here to tell you which way to tilt or which fashion to conform to. This
is just me talking about what I’ve dug up in relation to the aforementioned
conversation. My attempt here is only to explore one simple question: why do
some women not want to be ‘feminists’?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the #MeToo movement barrels forward, as record numbers of women seek office,
with the #everydaysexism trending, feminism is reaching a level of cultural
relevance it hasn’t enjoyed in years. It’s now a major object of cultural
discourse–which has led to some very confusing conversations because not
everyone is familiar with or agrees on the basic terminology of feminism. The
&lt;em&gt;Oxford Dictionary&lt;/em&gt; suggests that feminism is the advocacy of women’s rights on
the ground of the equality of the sexes. But when the term feminism entered the
English language, towards the mid-19th century, it meant “feminine qualities or
character”, a meaning no longer in use, obviously. However, the late 19th
century unfolded and feminism unambiguously took on its modern meanings.
Moreover, one of the most basic and most confusing terminologies has to do with
the waves of feminism. I don’t know of one person who is sure of what wave
belongs to which specific timeline. The wave metaphor, over time, has become a
way to describe and distinguish between different eras and generations of
feminism. However, the metaphor can be reductive, it can suggest that each wave
of feminism is a monolith with a single unified agenda, when in fact the history
of feminism is a history of different ideas in wild conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, the first wave (1848-1920) refers to the West’s first
sustained political movement dedicated to achieving political equality for
women: the Suffragettes of the late 19th and early 20th centuries. The second
wave’s (1963-1980) focus was on changing the way society thought about women.
The second wave cared deeply about the casual, systemic sexism ingrained in
society, fighting it by proving that women were no less than men. It cared about
racism too, but it could be clumsy in working with people of colour . The image
of feminists as angry, man-hating and lonely would become canonical as the
second wave began to lose its momentum, and it continues to haunt the way we
talk about feminism today. It would also become foundational to the way the
third wave would position itself as it emerged. It is almost impossible to talk
with any clarity about the third wave because few people agree on exactly what
the third wave is, when it started, or if it’s still going on. “The confusion
surrounding what constitutes third wave feminism,” writes feminist scholar
Elizabeth Evans, “is in some respects its defining feature.” Early third wave
activism tended to involve fighting against workplace sexual harassment and
working to increase the number of women in positions of power. While a lot of
people believe we’re still into the third wave, a new vision of feminism as an
online movement has caught on as the “fourth wave”. This wave is seen to have
begun to hold our culture’s most powerful men accountable for their behaviour.
It has begun a radical critique of the systems of power that allow predators to
target women with impunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, with all of these great accomplishments (despite the confusions), why then,
would a person, especially a woman, not want to be a part of this movement?
Remember those women I talked about: Several were keen on their identity as
feminists, explicitly so. But the ones who weren’t, their answers held my
interest. The top answer would usually be: “I prescribe to egalitarianism and
not feminism.” But saying you’re not a feminist and an egalitarian may come off
as moot from the outset because there’s not one without the other. Feminism is
verily the mechanism and egalitarianism, the goal.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A close second was the idea that a feminist corresponds to a man-hating,
lesbian, non-shaving, free-the-nipple woman. Of course, when put in this manner,
it sounds abhorrent, but a large part of the world believes that every feminist
has to hate men or that feminists need to shirk away from being feminine. This
viewpoint is hardly new. In the 1920’s, feminists were called spinsters, and
speculations on their sexuality were rife. The fact that this view still holds
sway is very telling. To put everything in categories is human nature, but to
understand a spectrum is just as important. The scapegoating of femininity might
as well be the albatross around the feminist movement’s neck. The idea of women
wanting to stay at home and caring for their children, wearing a pink dress,
while serving their husbands breakfast is said to portray a woman who cannot be
a feminist or a bad one at that. These categorical notions make people not
wanting to be hitched to the identity of a feminist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s another reason—that being God. Some suggest that God didn’t want women
and men to be equal. Which is why he made them different. I quote from one of my
acquaintances, “That’s why ideal women are dainty, while men are hunky.” On
this, all I could say was a living, 4-5 kg organism (sometimes, multiple) comes
out of a woman’s most vulnerable area, well, they sure are made to be dainty and
fragile! Again, this is not me trying to fight against someone’s beliefs–I’m
aware that, physiologically, we’re different, but the concept of what our
physicality has to do with our rights still confounds me. Other reasonings
included the idea of ‘Feminazis’. How can a term signifying the systematic
genocide of millions of innocent individuals get conflated with a term that in
all its spirit aims to demolish social hierarchies? You may ask. Well, just like
that the Bra-Burning-Woman imagery was born.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google made me aware of how Katy Perry, the year she received the Woman of the
Year award, showed an unwillingness to be called a feminist. Her reasoning, from
what I could gather was how it’d affect her fan base. Or perhaps, she was scared
of its radicality. Yahoo’s CEO also doesn’t abide by the concept. With the
reasons placed above, and a great multitude of others, one can see how it’d make
sense to be happy to live in a neutral place than to choose somewhat of a
position that may make you seem extremist. The way one may see feminism, now, in
this very moment, is so far from how it was supposed to be. But that’s a very
small percentage. Or, is it? If you’re a part of the magical world of Tumblr,
you’re already aware of the womenagainstfeminism tag. And all the other subtags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come to think about it, if a man proclaims himself as a feminist–he’s applauded,
even favoured. He carries the stereotypical image of being understanding of
women’s dilemmas and struggles, of him being by their side. But a feminist woman
is seen as someone who’ll lecture you at turns, go on rants about issues at the
drop of a hat whilst wearing androgynous clothes. The duality of what we’ve been
taught is traced in every stitch of our social fragmentation. I read something a
while back, “Men are afraid women will laugh at them, and women are afraid men
will kill them.” Hold me wrong if you may, but the issue may not be in how all
of us see feminism, but how we perceive it. The fear of being called a feminist
really rests in the assumed social consequences and implications of being called
one. It is difficult to undertake the personal accountability required to trace
out one’s own position in the multiple systems of domination and oppression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All, I, as a laywoman, can say is that we should see the aversion as a sign, not
of feminism’s failures, but of its continuing relevance. It would be better if
feminism were more widely accepted, sure, but failing that, the least a movement
for radical social change can do is to freak people out a little. Feminism still
provokes resistance; it still has enemies; it still makes many people in the
mainstream nervous. And that, in itself, seems like a victory. Just like the
feminist who welcomed my aversion, feminism too welcomes us all. After all, you
don’t have to understand everything, you just have to try to not be a d*ck!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“I don’t want to get into it! No, not me.” Very recently, after a long conversation about everything ranging from Paganism to Masculinity with some very articulate people, I was offered to put my words to use in talk of feminism. I didn’t know what to make of the instantaneous rejection that came out of me, I recall thinking I don’t want to dip my feet into that pool. One of the conversationalists (a very openly-proclaimed feminist) took it upon herself to tell me that I was welcome to voice my opinions, that ‘they’ are open to one and all. I never did talk about whether or not I identified as a feminist, however, her welcome led me to think about why someone would not want to be a part of this ‘them.’ The new F-word in the market that people are so scared of had, I think, tied me up in knots too. Not believing that you could be a part of this movement of feminism would be absurd, right? How can I, a woman, remove myself from a movement of and about all women? I am not here to tell you which way to tilt or which fashion to conform to. This is just me talking about what I’ve dug up in relation to the aforementioned conversation. My attempt here is only to explore one simple question: why do some women not want to be ‘feminists’? As the #MeToo movement barrels forward, as record numbers of women seek office, with the #everydaysexism trending, feminism is reaching a level of cultural relevance it hasn’t enjoyed in years. It’s now a major object of cultural discourse–which has led to some very confusing conversations because not everyone is familiar with or agrees on the basic terminology of feminism. The Oxford Dictionary suggests that feminism is the advocacy of women’s rights on the ground of the equality of the sexes. But when the term feminism entered the English language, towards the mid-19th century, it meant “feminine qualities or character”, a meaning no longer in use, obviously. However, the late 19th century unfolded and feminism unambiguously took on its modern meanings. Moreover, one of the most basic and most confusing terminologies has to do with the waves of feminism. I don’t know of one person who is sure of what wave belongs to which specific timeline. The wave metaphor, over time, has become a way to describe and distinguish between different eras and generations of feminism. However, the metaphor can be reductive, it can suggest that each wave of feminism is a monolith with a single unified agenda, when in fact the history of feminism is a history of different ideas in wild conflict. Generally speaking, the first wave (1848-1920) refers to the West’s first sustained political movement dedicated to achieving political equality for women: the Suffragettes of the late 19th and early 20th centuries. The second wave’s (1963-1980) focus was on changing the way society thought about women. The second wave cared deeply about the casual, systemic sexism ingrained in society, fighting it by proving that women were no less than men. It cared about racism too, but it could be clumsy in working with people of colour . The image of feminists as angry, man-hating and lonely would become canonical as the second wave began to lose its momentum, and it continues to haunt the way we talk about feminism today. It would also become foundational to the way the third wave would position itself as it emerged. It is almost impossible to talk with any clarity about the third wave because few people agree on exactly what the third wave is, when it started, or if it’s still going on. “The confusion surrounding what constitutes third wave feminism,” writes feminist scholar Elizabeth Evans, “is in some respects its defining feature.” Early third wave activism tended to involve fighting against workplace sexual harassment and working to increase the number of women in positions of power. While a lot of people believe we’re still into the third wave, a new vision of feminism as an online movement has caught on as the “fourth wave”. This wave is seen to have begun to hold our culture’s most powerful men accountable for their behaviour. It has begun a radical critique of the systems of power that allow predators to target women with impunity. Now, with all of these great accomplishments (despite the confusions), why then, would a person, especially a woman, not want to be a part of this movement? Remember those women I talked about: Several were keen on their identity as feminists, explicitly so. But the ones who weren’t, their answers held my interest. The top answer would usually be: “I prescribe to egalitarianism and not feminism.” But saying you’re not a feminist and an egalitarian may come off as moot from the outset because there’s not one without the other. Feminism is verily the mechanism and egalitarianism, the goal.   A close second was the idea that a feminist corresponds to a man-hating, lesbian, non-shaving, free-the-nipple woman. Of course, when put in this manner, it sounds abhorrent, but a large part of the world believes that every feminist has to hate men or that feminists need to shirk away from being feminine. This viewpoint is hardly new. In the 1920’s, feminists were called spinsters, and speculations on their sexuality were rife. The fact that this view still holds sway is very telling. To put everything in categories is human nature, but to understand a spectrum is just as important. The scapegoating of femininity might as well be the albatross around the feminist movement’s neck. The idea of women wanting to stay at home and caring for their children, wearing a pink dress, while serving their husbands breakfast is said to portray a woman who cannot be a feminist or a bad one at that. These categorical notions make people not wanting to be hitched to the identity of a feminist. There’s another reason—that being God. Some suggest that God didn’t want women and men to be equal. Which is why he made them different. I quote from one of my acquaintances, “That’s why ideal women are dainty, while men are hunky.” On this, all I could say was a living, 4-5 kg organism (sometimes, multiple) comes out of a woman’s most vulnerable area, well, they sure are made to be dainty and fragile! Again, this is not me trying to fight against someone’s beliefs–I’m aware that, physiologically, we’re different, but the concept of what our physicality has to do with our rights still confounds me. Other reasonings included the idea of ‘Feminazis’. How can a term signifying the systematic genocide of millions of innocent individuals get conflated with a term that in all its spirit aims to demolish social hierarchies? You may ask. Well, just like that the Bra-Burning-Woman imagery was born.     Google made me aware of how Katy Perry, the year she received the Woman of the Year award, showed an unwillingness to be called a feminist. Her reasoning, from what I could gather was how it’d affect her fan base. Or perhaps, she was scared of its radicality. Yahoo’s CEO also doesn’t abide by the concept. With the reasons placed above, and a great multitude of others, one can see how it’d make sense to be happy to live in a neutral place than to choose somewhat of a position that may make you seem extremist. The way one may see feminism, now, in this very moment, is so far from how it was supposed to be. But that’s a very small percentage. Or, is it? If you’re a part of the magical world of Tumblr, you’re already aware of the womenagainstfeminism tag. And all the other subtags. Come to think about it, if a man proclaims himself as a feminist–he’s applauded, even favoured. He carries the stereotypical image of being understanding of women’s dilemmas and struggles, of him being by their side. But a feminist woman is seen as someone who’ll lecture you at turns, go on rants about issues at the drop of a hat whilst wearing androgynous clothes. The duality of what we’ve been taught is traced in every stitch of our social fragmentation. I read something a while back, “Men are afraid women will laugh at them, and women are afraid men will kill them.” Hold me wrong if you may, but the issue may not be in how all of us see feminism, but how we perceive it. The fear of being called a feminist really rests in the assumed social consequences and implications of being called one. It is difficult to undertake the personal accountability required to trace out one’s own position in the multiple systems of domination and oppression. All, I, as a laywoman, can say is that we should see the aversion as a sign, not of feminism’s failures, but of its continuing relevance. It would be better if feminism were more widely accepted, sure, but failing that, the least a movement for radical social change can do is to freak people out a little. Feminism still provokes resistance; it still has enemies; it still makes many people in the mainstream nervous. And that, in itself, seems like a victory. Just like the feminist who welcomed my aversion, feminism too welcomes us all. After all, you don’t have to understand everything, you just have to try to not be a d*ck!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Cl*t Wants What it Wants</title>
      <link href="/The-Clit-Wants-What-it-Wants" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Cl*t Wants What it Wants" />
      <published>2019-03-21T10:52:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-21T10:52:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Clit-Wants-What-it-Wants</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Clit-Wants-What-it-Wants">&lt;p&gt;Manically cross-checking to ensure that your search history is finally cleared
of every &lt;em&gt;flogging&lt;/em&gt; and every &lt;em&gt;caning&lt;/em&gt; or suddenly having no faith in
technology’s ability to truly remain incognito: People will go to any length to
avoid the embarrassment of enjoying kink. Interestingly, it’s not the idea that
one consumes porn that one feels the need to hide but the kind or &lt;em&gt;category&lt;/em&gt; of
porn, especially the moment it starts deviating from the missionary position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anxiety of being caught watching BDSM is no different from the anxiety one
feels when telling friends about a new crush. “Oh, but he looks better in
person!”, “His meme game isn’t strong but I swear he’s hilarious when you talk
to him.” Crushes are people we aren’t even emotionally invested in (yet), so why
do we care about what our friends think of them? It’s because of what we &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt;,
we perceive as an extension of us. And this applies to kinky porn as well. We’re
scared of what it says about us, we are scared of the fact that &lt;em&gt;these&lt;/em&gt; are our
innermost cravings and desires, that this is who we are. We’re not only scared
of how others see us but also of how we see ourselves, we’re scared of being a
certain person. And this fear magnifies when how we feel is in conflict with how
we think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, the brain just can’t accept what the clitoris wants. One could detest
the word ‘slut’ otherwise, but love being called one during sex. What’s
offensive in daylight is often a turn-on at night. And while there is definitely
a context of consent to any healthy form of kink and acts like &lt;em&gt;choking&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;slapping&lt;/em&gt; cannot be seen in isolation, consent is not the whole answer to why
we want something, it’s not the answer to why we crave something. I think that’s
the hauntingly beautiful role sex plays in our lives because it is the place
where we confront the distinction between what we believe and what we feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the undeniability of the desire, (people will literally have sex even if
there’s a risk of getting stoned to death) that makes sex as scary as it is
wonderful. Sex scandalises the very proprieties and ideas of self we hold so
dear while also feeling good enough to incentivise us to navigate through those
same discomforting ideas and get to the G(ood) spot. Sex is frightening because
it betrays us. In an era of intellectual dissection and analysis of every topic,
we think we have a certain degree of control over who we are, we think our sense
of self arises from all that we know, we think that our thoughts can control
what we do or do not &lt;strong&gt;desire&lt;/strong&gt;. We think we can choose to want or not want
something. But that’s exactly how it does not work. Ultimately, it is the
dominance of the subconscious that manifests in yearning and in longing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is notable how fantasies often play around concepts of morality that are
borrowed from the traditional cultural fabric. For instance, what underlies the
‘good girl’ fantasy? It entails punishing a girl during sex for liking sex or
craving it, judged by indicators such as having an engorged clitoris or a wet
pussy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems rather counterintuitive to shame the girl for liking sex as a way to
further arouse her, but there’s a reason it works. The ‘good girl’ trope in
role-plays exploits the archaic idea of how a woman is not supposed to want sex,
and the notion of how in order to be a ‘good woman’, a woman must never want sex
for her own physical gratification but only for the purpose of pleasing a man.
The moment (in role-play) the man is able to make her feel like she isn’t the
one seeking sex she feels she is fulfilling her &lt;em&gt;role&lt;/em&gt; by serving only his
needs. When she is punished for enjoying something she isn’t supposed to, the
appeal lies in the justice of getting what she deserves (the punishment) for
betraying the rule (women not desiring sex).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spirit behind it is the idea: am I finally being what a woman is supposed to
be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of forms of kink revolve around power, specifically the distortions in its
proportions. There is a whole spectrum to kink and the spectrum is so wide that
most of us fall somewhere in it. It isn’t just about chains and straps in sex
dungeons, it could be something as simple as liking it when a guy takes your
hair by his fists. Cravings for power distortions are much more relatable for an
average individual than one might realise. And like in every other discussion, a
discussion about sexual kink too will reek of naivete if it doesn’t take into
account the politics of gender. The overwhelming overlap of women with
submission and men with dominance has more to it than just men being ‘on top’.
Seizing sovereignty in a sexual scenario is quite territorial in nature. To
claim and to be claimed both give the same kind of comfort, that we’re someone
else’s. For instance, tying your partner’s hands during sex and being able to
restrain them is attached to the thrill of owning them, even if only in fantasy
or even if only for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a romance to that, because it screams the message, “You and only you
can do that with me because I love you and I’m yours, just yours.” After all, we
are all just frazzled souls looking to belong to other humans. While we try to
understand and get to the heart of these fantasies, the important thing to
remember is: &lt;em&gt;desires don’t cease to exist just because you can’t make sense of
them.&lt;/em&gt; No logic or its absence thereof can ever invalidate something that has
been felt. In fact, I think it’s comforting that there’s at least one part of
life which is ruled by the subconscious and there is peace in the knowledge that
this has already been determined for us and it’s not something that needs to be
built and established. It is an exercise in futility to try and tamper with
these desires. Desires arise from within, what happens on the outside is merely
the manifestation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let sexuality be outside the realm of your control. Let your fantasies betray
you.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Stuti Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Manically cross-checking to ensure that your search history is finally cleared of every flogging and every caning or suddenly having no faith in technology’s ability to truly remain incognito: People will go to any length to avoid the embarrassment of enjoying kink. Interestingly, it’s not the idea that one consumes porn that one feels the need to hide but the kind or category of porn, especially the moment it starts deviating from the missionary position. The anxiety of being caught watching BDSM is no different from the anxiety one feels when telling friends about a new crush. “Oh, but he looks better in person!”, “His meme game isn’t strong but I swear he’s hilarious when you talk to him.” Crushes are people we aren’t even emotionally invested in (yet), so why do we care about what our friends think of them? It’s because of what we want, we perceive as an extension of us. And this applies to kinky porn as well. We’re scared of what it says about us, we are scared of the fact that these are our innermost cravings and desires, that this is who we are. We’re not only scared of how others see us but also of how we see ourselves, we’re scared of being a certain person. And this fear magnifies when how we feel is in conflict with how we think. Sometimes, the brain just can’t accept what the clitoris wants. One could detest the word ‘slut’ otherwise, but love being called one during sex. What’s offensive in daylight is often a turn-on at night. And while there is definitely a context of consent to any healthy form of kink and acts like choking and slapping cannot be seen in isolation, consent is not the whole answer to why we want something, it’s not the answer to why we crave something. I think that’s the hauntingly beautiful role sex plays in our lives because it is the place where we confront the distinction between what we believe and what we feel. It is the undeniability of the desire, (people will literally have sex even if there’s a risk of getting stoned to death) that makes sex as scary as it is wonderful. Sex scandalises the very proprieties and ideas of self we hold so dear while also feeling good enough to incentivise us to navigate through those same discomforting ideas and get to the G(ood) spot. Sex is frightening because it betrays us. In an era of intellectual dissection and analysis of every topic, we think we have a certain degree of control over who we are, we think our sense of self arises from all that we know, we think that our thoughts can control what we do or do not desire. We think we can choose to want or not want something. But that’s exactly how it does not work. Ultimately, it is the dominance of the subconscious that manifests in yearning and in longing. It is notable how fantasies often play around concepts of morality that are borrowed from the traditional cultural fabric. For instance, what underlies the ‘good girl’ fantasy? It entails punishing a girl during sex for liking sex or craving it, judged by indicators such as having an engorged clitoris or a wet pussy. It seems rather counterintuitive to shame the girl for liking sex as a way to further arouse her, but there’s a reason it works. The ‘good girl’ trope in role-plays exploits the archaic idea of how a woman is not supposed to want sex, and the notion of how in order to be a ‘good woman’, a woman must never want sex for her own physical gratification but only for the purpose of pleasing a man. The moment (in role-play) the man is able to make her feel like she isn’t the one seeking sex she feels she is fulfilling her role by serving only his needs. When she is punished for enjoying something she isn’t supposed to, the appeal lies in the justice of getting what she deserves (the punishment) for betraying the rule (women not desiring sex). The spirit behind it is the idea: am I finally being what a woman is supposed to be? A lot of forms of kink revolve around power, specifically the distortions in its proportions. There is a whole spectrum to kink and the spectrum is so wide that most of us fall somewhere in it. It isn’t just about chains and straps in sex dungeons, it could be something as simple as liking it when a guy takes your hair by his fists. Cravings for power distortions are much more relatable for an average individual than one might realise. And like in every other discussion, a discussion about sexual kink too will reek of naivete if it doesn’t take into account the politics of gender. The overwhelming overlap of women with submission and men with dominance has more to it than just men being ‘on top’. Seizing sovereignty in a sexual scenario is quite territorial in nature. To claim and to be claimed both give the same kind of comfort, that we’re someone else’s. For instance, tying your partner’s hands during sex and being able to restrain them is attached to the thrill of owning them, even if only in fantasy or even if only for a while. There is a romance to that, because it screams the message, “You and only you can do that with me because I love you and I’m yours, just yours.” After all, we are all just frazzled souls looking to belong to other humans. While we try to understand and get to the heart of these fantasies, the important thing to remember is: desires don’t cease to exist just because you can’t make sense of them. No logic or its absence thereof can ever invalidate something that has been felt. In fact, I think it’s comforting that there’s at least one part of life which is ruled by the subconscious and there is peace in the knowledge that this has already been determined for us and it’s not something that needs to be built and established. It is an exercise in futility to try and tamper with these desires. Desires arise from within, what happens on the outside is merely the manifestation. Let sexuality be outside the realm of your control. Let your fantasies betray you.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Be a Man: a Discourse on 21st Century Masculinity</title>
      <link href="/Be-a-Man" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Be a Man: a Discourse on 21st Century Masculinity" />
      <published>2019-03-14T01:45:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-14T01:45:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Be-a-Man</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Be-a-Man">&lt;p&gt;The Gillette Advert has, for reasons I do not fully understand, caused a
sensation. There are people who are praising it for sending out the right
message on toxic masculinity, and there are people condemning it vociferously
for portraying masculinity as inherently evil. The fact, however, is that an
advert really matters little—they are ultimately paid promotions of products,
not vehicles of social change, and the people who are quick to heap praise or
criticism on it (especially in this case) are either pretentious or simply
b*tthurt. Yet, even in what I consider to be an overreaction about a simple
advert on shaving products, there’s a deeper discussion that is going on. For
more than a couple of thousand years, men across the world have been told that
they are stronger, better and smarter; it has been their job to be responsible
for ‘their’ women and ‘their’ children; it has been their duty to die first in
battle and it has been their job to take charge without shedding a tear and
without ever doubting oneself. But now, in these feminist times, assumptions
about masculinity are not only being challenged but also being designated as
evil—and for a good reason. But with all of this change, masculinity is being
radically redefined. The question is &lt;em&gt;what should it be redefined into?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One has to appreciate the difficulty of this question to even begin to answer
it. There are so many issues, from the plain-fact biological to the unwittingly
socio-cultural, that one does not know what to address first. This means all
thoughts about what masculinity ought to be cannot be discussed in the abstract, for we
simply do not know what the source of masculinity as a social or perhaps natural
construct really is. All we can try to do is pragmatically accept its existence
and move on to see how we can mould it to suit our times—in both a moral and
philosophical sense. And that again reinforces the fact that instead of some
grand theory of what it &lt;em&gt;must mean to be a man&lt;/em&gt;, we must develop more specific
guidelines on what it &lt;em&gt;should mean to be a man&lt;/em&gt;.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fairly good place to begin would be in the surprisingly simple but
controversial question of who should pay for a date between heterosexual
couples. One can easily see why “old-world masculinity” would always make the
man pay: Men were supposed to have the financial resources which they would use
to ‘woo’ women. With women possessing little financial independence (or any
independence, really), and depending on men for nearly everything material, men
paying for dates made sense—even if it was due to unjust laws and the fantasies
of the patriarchy with regard to its own benevolence. But all of that has
changed now and women are (at least on paper) not denied basic rights like the
one to property, a voice and to work. So, the idea that men should have an
obligation to pay for food and alcohol as a projection of their ability to give
a damn when seeing someone seems morally bankrupt, not to mention unfair as
well. Yet, a change of the rules to equal sharing seems ham-handed. It does not
take into account that sometimes people are feeling rich or bound to old-school
values for no discernible reason. More importantly, it simply denies agency to
people, instead of letting them negotiate it with each other. A better kind of
masculinity that truly involves an end to male presumptions of power and
responsibility cannot simply say: &lt;em&gt;Thou shalt split the bill for thou art equal&lt;/em&gt;.
That is only a sign of compromising pride; it is a technical solution to a
psychological problem. The rules on dating must be an expression of true
cooperation, and they can only begin to be so when people recognise that
independent, equal individuals decide matters among themselves. To say that
people must split the bill all the time is to mould a masculinity that need not
actually listen or cooperate, for it feels that there is a simple rule in place.
But to say: there are no rules, you must exercise self-respect and empathy when
negotiating who pays, re-enforces a most important aspect of what modern
masculinity should be. It symbolises an attempt to outgrow the need for the
patriarchy itself as a balm to one’s self-esteem. A contextualised, no
overarching rules approach encourages real interaction, it forces both men and
women to actually ask the question of what is fair when two people, equal in
dignity, decide to strike a settlement for mutual benefit.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masculinity is undeniably linked to &lt;em&gt;how good men feel about themselves&lt;/em&gt;. I don’t
know if there is something biological to it or if it is purely cultural, but the
male to female ratio of suicides is proof to me that men not feeling good about
themselves has some serious consequences. Many people identify the root of this
problem to be toxic masculinity, but that only addresses the surface of the
issue. Of course, a man being forced to bottle all emotion save aggression is
bound to be attracted to suicide in the face of life’s sh*t. But conversely,
without a feeling of independence and strength in the face of one’s fears,
they’re not bound to feel very good about themselves either. The old patriarchal
notion of masculinity is not entirely wrong in wanting men to weather things
stoically. It is simply important for both men and women to try and take control
of their lives when in crisis, rather than near-constantly crying about it. The
only thing a new masculinity needs to do is stop emasculating an expression of
emotion, whilst certainly rewarding personal fortitude and the ability to
skilfully (and quietly) manage one’s misery. Without this positive change,
masculinity risks either being dependent on the fragile male ego of being ‘hard’
or being a source of emotional release that does not provide courage. This new
notion of male self-belief tells us that boys should cry, that they should not
be unwilling to admit to sadness and dejection. However, it cautions us that
crying should not replace men’s self-worth by perpetuating avoidance and
self-doubt. In other words, modern masculinity must give men a better way to
cry: it must tell them they must be “man enough” to be able to do so, and “man
enough” to be able to overcome the urge to only do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the crying bit set aside, the more difficult questions put forward by the
&lt;em&gt;#metoo&lt;/em&gt; movement need to be addressed. It is clear that old-world masculinity
has either failed to deal with an oppressive culture in the workplace or in
enforcing rules of consent. The problem is obvious: the patriarchy does make
women objects. But that misses the forest for the trees, for it does not ask the
difficult question of &lt;em&gt;why society decided to have the patriarchy in the first
place&lt;/em&gt;. I would contend the answer to that question is tantalisingly simple. As
Devdutt Pattanaik, a popular Indian mythologist contends, human beings have “the
patriarchy” verily because nature doesn’t consider males to be that important.
In nature, all that a whole pride of lionesses requires is one (perhaps two)
male lions to produce the next generation of cubs. Human society is entirely
different, even if it has polygamy or polyandry, it tries to value every virile
male as a prospective husband or partner for his ability to care for and produce
human offspring. Practically speaking, this translates into the notion of the
patriarchy, where a literal race for being an alpha male is replaced with the
notion that every male who can find a female(s) has rights and obligations in
relation to that female—which other males are restricted from having. This
creates some kind of social order, but it makes men, whether fathers, brothers,
husbands or lovers, believe that they can (and must) control what happens to the
females associated with them. And this leads to the inevitable manifestation of
the patriarchy that the #metoo movement has so clearly exposed. Men will (if
they choose) assert what they consider “sexual rights” over the women who are
associated with them because they believe their association with them, whether
at the workplace or inside a marriage, gives them that right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cultural paradigm so described is the source of all problems discussed in
the previous paragraphs, it is this fundamental insecurity of not being an alpha
male that leads to men wanting to own, protect and control the women they have
around them. They have to do so, there must be rules that enforce so, otherwise
all of us ‘inadequate’ men will be naturally selected out. We must ensure “our
property” understands who they belong to, whether it be through non-disclosure
agreements or entertaining our putrid pick-up lines at the workplace. One can
combat the patriarchy as a construct, but that hardly addresses the fragile male
ego that underpins this socio-cultural construct. To combat that, men need to be
told that their honour and their power doesn’t reside in their control of the
women around them. Men need to be reminded that it is okay if they feel
inadequate, that they must never seek subjugation of women (or anyone) as a
therapy for low self-esteem and an absurd “will to power”. How does one
crystallise that abstract notion in a practical context? Simple: to quote a
friend, we must remind men that &lt;em&gt;“life is an embarrassment, and we’re going to
die anyway”&lt;/em&gt;. So, if we find ourselves being unable to get the women we want, it
really matters little. The fundamental mortality and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Understanding-the-Absurdity-of-Life&quot;&gt;absurdity of life&lt;/a&gt; mean that
our need to define our self-worth through our power over women (or anything) is
futile—for we’re already inadequate, to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, that is the existential reality that stares at us men every time we
discuss what it means to be a man. We men already realise, deep down, that we
are pathetically inadequate. If we weren’t, we wouldn’t have to construct so
many fallacies to make ourselves feel better, whether they be rules that project
our wealth, rules on not crying, or rules that state: “boys will be boys”.
My conception of masculinity expresses a core desire to do away with all those
stupid rules that are completely unfit for a most egalitarian age. A new kind of
masculinity must rely on fostering an inner strength that lets men outgrow our
base fears. Self-esteem, in any moral or philosophical sense, cannot come from
the outside; it cannot come from protecting or subjugating others. Self-esteem
or the belief in oneself must be exuded, it must be a source of impregnable
strength from within. A modern definition of masculinity must reflect this deep
truth, it must seek to give men the ability to outgrow their weaknesses (and,
therefore, the patriarchy) and to embrace a more complete personality that is a
result of true internal self-belief.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      
        <category term="trending" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Gillette Advert has, for reasons I do not fully understand, caused a sensation. There are people who are praising it for sending out the right message on toxic masculinity, and there are people condemning it vociferously for portraying masculinity as inherently evil. The fact, however, is that an advert really matters little—they are ultimately paid promotions of products, not vehicles of social change, and the people who are quick to heap praise or criticism on it (especially in this case) are either pretentious or simply b*tthurt. Yet, even in what I consider to be an overreaction about a simple advert on shaving products, there’s a deeper discussion that is going on. For more than a couple of thousand years, men across the world have been told that they are stronger, better and smarter; it has been their job to be responsible for ‘their’ women and ‘their’ children; it has been their duty to die first in battle and it has been their job to take charge without shedding a tear and without ever doubting oneself. But now, in these feminist times, assumptions about masculinity are not only being challenged but also being designated as evil—and for a good reason. But with all of this change, masculinity is being radically redefined. The question is what should it be redefined into? One has to appreciate the difficulty of this question to even begin to answer it. There are so many issues, from the plain-fact biological to the unwittingly socio-cultural, that one does not know what to address first. This means all thoughts about what masculinity ought to be cannot be discussed in the abstract, for we simply do not know what the source of masculinity as a social or perhaps natural construct really is. All we can try to do is pragmatically accept its existence and move on to see how we can mould it to suit our times—in both a moral and philosophical sense. And that again reinforces the fact that instead of some grand theory of what it must mean to be a man, we must develop more specific guidelines on what it should mean to be a man.    A fairly good place to begin would be in the surprisingly simple but controversial question of who should pay for a date between heterosexual couples. One can easily see why “old-world masculinity” would always make the man pay: Men were supposed to have the financial resources which they would use to ‘woo’ women. With women possessing little financial independence (or any independence, really), and depending on men for nearly everything material, men paying for dates made sense—even if it was due to unjust laws and the fantasies of the patriarchy with regard to its own benevolence. But all of that has changed now and women are (at least on paper) not denied basic rights like the one to property, a voice and to work. So, the idea that men should have an obligation to pay for food and alcohol as a projection of their ability to give a damn when seeing someone seems morally bankrupt, not to mention unfair as well. Yet, a change of the rules to equal sharing seems ham-handed. It does not take into account that sometimes people are feeling rich or bound to old-school values for no discernible reason. More importantly, it simply denies agency to people, instead of letting them negotiate it with each other. A better kind of masculinity that truly involves an end to male presumptions of power and responsibility cannot simply say: Thou shalt split the bill for thou art equal. That is only a sign of compromising pride; it is a technical solution to a psychological problem. The rules on dating must be an expression of true cooperation, and they can only begin to be so when people recognise that independent, equal individuals decide matters among themselves. To say that people must split the bill all the time is to mould a masculinity that need not actually listen or cooperate, for it feels that there is a simple rule in place. But to say: there are no rules, you must exercise self-respect and empathy when negotiating who pays, re-enforces a most important aspect of what modern masculinity should be. It symbolises an attempt to outgrow the need for the patriarchy itself as a balm to one’s self-esteem. A contextualised, no overarching rules approach encourages real interaction, it forces both men and women to actually ask the question of what is fair when two people, equal in dignity, decide to strike a settlement for mutual benefit.      Masculinity is undeniably linked to how good men feel about themselves. I don’t know if there is something biological to it or if it is purely cultural, but the male to female ratio of suicides is proof to me that men not feeling good about themselves has some serious consequences. Many people identify the root of this problem to be toxic masculinity, but that only addresses the surface of the issue. Of course, a man being forced to bottle all emotion save aggression is bound to be attracted to suicide in the face of life’s sh*t. But conversely, without a feeling of independence and strength in the face of one’s fears, they’re not bound to feel very good about themselves either. The old patriarchal notion of masculinity is not entirely wrong in wanting men to weather things stoically. It is simply important for both men and women to try and take control of their lives when in crisis, rather than near-constantly crying about it. The only thing a new masculinity needs to do is stop emasculating an expression of emotion, whilst certainly rewarding personal fortitude and the ability to skilfully (and quietly) manage one’s misery. Without this positive change, masculinity risks either being dependent on the fragile male ego of being ‘hard’ or being a source of emotional release that does not provide courage. This new notion of male self-belief tells us that boys should cry, that they should not be unwilling to admit to sadness and dejection. However, it cautions us that crying should not replace men’s self-worth by perpetuating avoidance and self-doubt. In other words, modern masculinity must give men a better way to cry: it must tell them they must be “man enough” to be able to do so, and “man enough” to be able to overcome the urge to only do so. With the crying bit set aside, the more difficult questions put forward by the #metoo movement need to be addressed. It is clear that old-world masculinity has either failed to deal with an oppressive culture in the workplace or in enforcing rules of consent. The problem is obvious: the patriarchy does make women objects. But that misses the forest for the trees, for it does not ask the difficult question of why society decided to have the patriarchy in the first place. I would contend the answer to that question is tantalisingly simple. As Devdutt Pattanaik, a popular Indian mythologist contends, human beings have “the patriarchy” verily because nature doesn’t consider males to be that important. In nature, all that a whole pride of lionesses requires is one (perhaps two) male lions to produce the next generation of cubs. Human society is entirely different, even if it has polygamy or polyandry, it tries to value every virile male as a prospective husband or partner for his ability to care for and produce human offspring. Practically speaking, this translates into the notion of the patriarchy, where a literal race for being an alpha male is replaced with the notion that every male who can find a female(s) has rights and obligations in relation to that female—which other males are restricted from having. This creates some kind of social order, but it makes men, whether fathers, brothers, husbands or lovers, believe that they can (and must) control what happens to the females associated with them. And this leads to the inevitable manifestation of the patriarchy that the #metoo movement has so clearly exposed. Men will (if they choose) assert what they consider “sexual rights” over the women who are associated with them because they believe their association with them, whether at the workplace or inside a marriage, gives them that right. The cultural paradigm so described is the source of all problems discussed in the previous paragraphs, it is this fundamental insecurity of not being an alpha male that leads to men wanting to own, protect and control the women they have around them. They have to do so, there must be rules that enforce so, otherwise all of us ‘inadequate’ men will be naturally selected out. We must ensure “our property” understands who they belong to, whether it be through non-disclosure agreements or entertaining our putrid pick-up lines at the workplace. One can combat the patriarchy as a construct, but that hardly addresses the fragile male ego that underpins this socio-cultural construct. To combat that, men need to be told that their honour and their power doesn’t reside in their control of the women around them. Men need to be reminded that it is okay if they feel inadequate, that they must never seek subjugation of women (or anyone) as a therapy for low self-esteem and an absurd “will to power”. How does one crystallise that abstract notion in a practical context? Simple: to quote a friend, we must remind men that “life is an embarrassment, and we’re going to die anyway”. So, if we find ourselves being unable to get the women we want, it really matters little. The fundamental mortality and absurdity of life mean that our need to define our self-worth through our power over women (or anything) is futile—for we’re already inadequate, to begin with. In fact, that is the existential reality that stares at us men every time we discuss what it means to be a man. We men already realise, deep down, that we are pathetically inadequate. If we weren’t, we wouldn’t have to construct so many fallacies to make ourselves feel better, whether they be rules that project our wealth, rules on not crying, or rules that state: “boys will be boys”. My conception of masculinity expresses a core desire to do away with all those stupid rules that are completely unfit for a most egalitarian age. A new kind of masculinity must rely on fostering an inner strength that lets men outgrow our base fears. Self-esteem, in any moral or philosophical sense, cannot come from the outside; it cannot come from protecting or subjugating others. Self-esteem or the belief in oneself must be exuded, it must be a source of impregnable strength from within. A modern definition of masculinity must reflect this deep truth, it must seek to give men the ability to outgrow their weaknesses (and, therefore, the patriarchy) and to embrace a more complete personality that is a result of true internal self-belief.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
