<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/society/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-11-04T20:42:24+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/society/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Retelling of Childhood</title>
      <link href="/A-Retelling-of-Childhood" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Retelling of Childhood" />
      <published>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Retelling-of-Childhood</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Retelling-of-Childhood">&lt;p&gt;All of us have grown up with stories and tales aplenty - that our parents, grandparents and older siblings used to read to us. I had a little corner in my chest of drawers where I kept my A-3 sized colourfully illustrated books about the &lt;em&gt;Little Mermaid, Beauty and the Beast, Thumbelina, Cinderella&lt;/em&gt; and many others. I would take out one copy of those thin, 15-paged books and ask someone to read them to me or even give it a go at reading myself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a kid, I was fascinated with that world and maybe still haven’t lost my touch with it - because who doesn’t enjoy a good Disney&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;movie and some hot chocolate to go with it? Disney&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;is one such institution that has cemented and eternalised the stories that were written hundreds of years ago for children, now told and retold through years, they have changed into a different form - liked by people of all age groups.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A while back, I came across the writer behind these beloved stories - Hans Christian Anderson. Even though he revolutionised the world of storytelling through his selected works like - &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;em&gt; The Snow Queen &lt;/em&gt;(now adapted into the Disney production of &lt;em&gt;Frozen&lt;/em&gt;) and&lt;em&gt; The Ugly Duckling &lt;/em&gt;- his work is criticised for being unfit for children. Now that his work, that dates back to 1835, has been adapted into so many plays, productions and movies, one would think that he used to write perfect fairy tales for a blissful childhood. However, the truth is a bit far from that. Anderson is known for his dark and bitter tales that were written for children but without any filters - just blatant truth and atrocities staring oneself in the face.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anderson was born and raised in Denmark in a poor family to a shoemaker father and an illiterate washerwoman mother. Still, he persisted with his education at the local school for the poor, and at night used to listen to the tales of the &lt;em&gt;Arabian Nights&lt;/em&gt; from his father. He had a rough go at childhood and had to move out and provide for himself at an early age - the pain of which is reflected in his early-written pieces. The first and original edition of his stories is unlike the retold versions of them in many ways. For starters, his stories were not as happy-go-lucky as we see them now to be. &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt;, a classic tale of love and redemption, was actually a disturbing and morbid tale about a mermaid who makes a diabolical bargain with a sea witch and suffers her tongue to be cut out and her tail to be lost, all for the love of a prince. Unfortunately, he completely fails to recognise the enormity of her sacrifice and love for him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Disney film adaption of this tale was morphed into a story about love which always unites, as Ariel and Eric get together in the end, and she leaves her world to be with him. Even though Anderson’s story was bitter, it was realistic because it told you that life doesn’t always give you what or whom you desire, and that it’s not okay to give up your life and the things that make you who you are for anyone - because that never ends well. It reflected that no sacrifice will get you eternal love but maybe patience, time and consent would. Even the tale of &lt;em&gt;Thumbelina&lt;/em&gt; was that of grave pain and a torturous existence, unlike the popular idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might not have understood that as a kid, but if something is repeatedly told, from a young age then it can have an impact on you in many ways. The debate around protecting kids from bad and traumatic things is acceptable and justified, but only as long as the truth is harmful to them. If not, even kids have a right to be exposed to the right and wrong of life, to disappointment and failure - so that they learn to take something from it instead of thinking of it as the end. A lot of Anderson’s stories were changed for this reason alone. Because his stories did not twist the truth into entangled sentences about a utopian world but told them things that everyone should know - the reality of this harsh world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only Anderson’s, but many of children’s tales and stories are moulded according to what adults deem right; in fact, some are banned or censored too. A children’s book by the name of &lt;em&gt;And Tango Makes Three&lt;/em&gt; written by Parnell and Richardson was published in 2005, after a real-life incident that occurred in the Central Park Zoo of New York, where two male, chinstrap penguins, Roy and Silo fell in love. The book tells the story of these two male penguins who&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;create a family together. With the help of the zookeeper, Mr Gramsay, Roy and Silo are given an egg which they help hatch. The female chick, that completes their family, is consequently named 'Tango' by the zookeepers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book wasn’t received well by many parents, because according to them, homosexuality in animals suggested homosexuality in humans as well. They argued that they weren’t able to explain to their kids as to why “&lt;em&gt;a male penguin has a baby with another male penguin instead of a mommy penguin&lt;/em&gt;”. After retaliation from parents across the world, the book was consequently banned in Singapore, Hong Kong and places across the United States, like Utah, Missouri and Massachusetts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ql-cursor&quot;&gt;﻿It is these ingrained notions and our discomfort with the truth that anything different from what we consider ‘normal’, we try to hide from kids instead of having a conversation with them which they might be completely open to.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;p&gt;The question that wavers in my mind is, ‘how much of reality is too much’ to be introduced to children? The reason those stories were changed is that it was considered unfit and inappropriate for a child’s brains. Which might be true from one vantage point, however, why must children be veiled from the realities of the world until a certain age only to be exposed to them suddenly at one go? What is really the right age to see the world in its face?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve always wondered how fair it is to concoct a picture of a world that only disappoints you when you grow up. One, it creates unreal expectations from the world and two, it teaches you things that should be shattered as a concept early on while growing up - be it a princess being saved by the valiant hero at the end, kissing someone without their consent (&lt;em&gt;The Sleeping Beauty&lt;/em&gt;) or having to be perfect for people to like you.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I go back and forth in my mind as to why we think of children as weak or want to shield them from the truth? According to many child psychologists, the impulse to protect kids from unpleasant facts is similar to the self-esteem fad practised by educators. The idea rests on the assumption, not backed by any evidence, that high self-esteem must lead to high academic achievement. Similarly, the instinct to protect children from anything unpleasant is simply out of one’s idea of what a child should and shouldn’t know.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But if one asks themselves, is this reality protecting your child from long-term pain or is just an area of discussion that you don’t want to deal with, or better answer, and so you choose what is convenient - that is, to digress, to lie and to manoeuvre. You leave your children to figure out the jarring and upsetting realities of life by themselves as they grow up. And more often than not, the sources through which your children consume all the things that were hidden from them during their nascent years are not the most reliable or truthful sources. Thus, as we grow up, we are ambushed with facts and to find answers to them we tend to rely on treacherous sources which skew our ideas all the more. Instead of nurturing our kids with righteousness and practicality from the beginning, we try to mask them from facts, for as long as possible - which might not help them as much as one would hope.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The thing about the ‘real’ world is that unlike fairytales, it’s flawed and filled with imperfections. Which is what drives life ahead, the little or large hiccups in the flow of life. From Anderson’s stories to the truth about sexuality, identity, religion and relationships - a lot is made inconspicuous for the kids so that the information dissemination is controlled according to the norms that we have constructed and reaches them in a palatable form. But the question remains: who gets to decide what is right or wrong for these kids? Are flowery stories with morals sieved through our model of heteronormativity, appropriate culture and paradigms of acceptable behaviour the way to go about raising our kids? Only to impel them later into a world where they stumble as they go through life deconstructing their thoughts and knowledge, indoctrinated throughout childhood and then rebuilding it in a frenzy of emotions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wonder if it would’ve been better, had my parents read me stories of women who didn’t enforce ideals of self-sacrifice to find the truest form of love or tales of women and people in general, who didn’t settle for anything less than what they deserved, did not change themselves only to be accepted by society, and stories that told that life’s utmost purpose was not to find a perfect partner but to find yourself. And in the process of that, you will meet people who will make life worthwhile. But not one of the stories told us, that it is very much okay, even if you don’t. Because in life, there is no blueprint or algorithm like in stories - all the milestones of life are supposed to make your journey easier and not all the more pressurizing. So the moral of this article is maybe that it is okay to chart your own path - because if you find yourself not fitting in with any of the existing stories, you can always write a new one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">All of us have grown up with stories and tales aplenty - that our parents, grandparents and older siblings used to read to us. I had a little corner in my chest of drawers where I kept my A-3 sized colourfully illustrated books about the Little Mermaid, Beauty and the Beast, Thumbelina, Cinderella and many others. I would take out one copy of those thin, 15-paged books and ask someone to read them to me or even give it a go at reading myself.&amp;nbsp; As a kid, I was fascinated with that world and maybe still haven’t lost my touch with it - because who doesn’t enjoy a good Disney movie and some hot chocolate to go with it? Disney is one such institution that has cemented and eternalised the stories that were written hundreds of years ago for children, now told and retold through years, they have changed into a different form - liked by people of all age groups.&amp;nbsp; A while back, I came across the writer behind these beloved stories - Hans Christian Anderson. Even though he revolutionised the world of storytelling through his selected works like - The Little Mermaid, The Snow Queen (now adapted into the Disney production of Frozen) and The Ugly Duckling - his work is criticised for being unfit for children. Now that his work, that dates back to 1835, has been adapted into so many plays, productions and movies, one would think that he used to write perfect fairy tales for a blissful childhood. However, the truth is a bit far from that. Anderson is known for his dark and bitter tales that were written for children but without any filters - just blatant truth and atrocities staring oneself in the face.&amp;nbsp; Anderson was born and raised in Denmark in a poor family to a shoemaker father and an illiterate washerwoman mother. Still, he persisted with his education at the local school for the poor, and at night used to listen to the tales of the Arabian Nights from his father. He had a rough go at childhood and had to move out and provide for himself at an early age - the pain of which is reflected in his early-written pieces. The first and original edition of his stories is unlike the retold versions of them in many ways. For starters, his stories were not as happy-go-lucky as we see them now to be. The Little Mermaid, a classic tale of love and redemption, was actually a disturbing and morbid tale about a mermaid who makes a diabolical bargain with a sea witch and suffers her tongue to be cut out and her tail to be lost, all for the love of a prince. Unfortunately, he completely fails to recognise the enormity of her sacrifice and love for him. The Disney film adaption of this tale was morphed into a story about love which always unites, as Ariel and Eric get together in the end, and she leaves her world to be with him. Even though Anderson’s story was bitter, it was realistic because it told you that life doesn’t always give you what or whom you desire, and that it’s not okay to give up your life and the things that make you who you are for anyone - because that never ends well. It reflected that no sacrifice will get you eternal love but maybe patience, time and consent would. Even the tale of Thumbelina was that of grave pain and a torturous existence, unlike the popular idea. I might not have understood that as a kid, but if something is repeatedly told, from a young age then it can have an impact on you in many ways. The debate around protecting kids from bad and traumatic things is acceptable and justified, but only as long as the truth is harmful to them. If not, even kids have a right to be exposed to the right and wrong of life, to disappointment and failure - so that they learn to take something from it instead of thinking of it as the end. A lot of Anderson’s stories were changed for this reason alone. Because his stories did not twist the truth into entangled sentences about a utopian world but told them things that everyone should know - the reality of this harsh world. Not only Anderson’s, but many of children’s tales and stories are moulded according to what adults deem right; in fact, some are banned or censored too. A children’s book by the name of And Tango Makes Three written by Parnell and Richardson was published in 2005, after a real-life incident that occurred in the Central Park Zoo of New York, where two male, chinstrap penguins, Roy and Silo fell in love. The book tells the story of these two male penguins who create a family together. With the help of the zookeeper, Mr Gramsay, Roy and Silo are given an egg which they help hatch. The female chick, that completes their family, is consequently named 'Tango' by the zookeepers.&amp;nbsp; This book wasn’t received well by many parents, because according to them, homosexuality in animals suggested homosexuality in humans as well. They argued that they weren’t able to explain to their kids as to why “a male penguin has a baby with another male penguin instead of a mommy penguin”. After retaliation from parents across the world, the book was consequently banned in Singapore, Hong Kong and places across the United States, like Utah, Missouri and Massachusetts. ﻿It is these ingrained notions and our discomfort with the truth that anything different from what we consider ‘normal’, we try to hide from kids instead of having a conversation with them which they might be completely open to.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;The question that wavers in my mind is, ‘how much of reality is too much’ to be introduced to children? The reason those stories were changed is that it was considered unfit and inappropriate for a child’s brains. Which might be true from one vantage point, however, why must children be veiled from the realities of the world until a certain age only to be exposed to them suddenly at one go? What is really the right age to see the world in its face?&amp;nbsp;I’ve always wondered how fair it is to concoct a picture of a world that only disappoints you when you grow up. One, it creates unreal expectations from the world and two, it teaches you things that should be shattered as a concept early on while growing up - be it a princess being saved by the valiant hero at the end, kissing someone without their consent (The Sleeping Beauty) or having to be perfect for people to like you.&amp;nbsp;I go back and forth in my mind as to why we think of children as weak or want to shield them from the truth? According to many child psychologists, the impulse to protect kids from unpleasant facts is similar to the self-esteem fad practised by educators. The idea rests on the assumption, not backed by any evidence, that high self-esteem must lead to high academic achievement. Similarly, the instinct to protect children from anything unpleasant is simply out of one’s idea of what a child should and shouldn’t know.&amp;nbsp;But if one asks themselves, is this reality protecting your child from long-term pain or is just an area of discussion that you don’t want to deal with, or better answer, and so you choose what is convenient - that is, to digress, to lie and to manoeuvre. You leave your children to figure out the jarring and upsetting realities of life by themselves as they grow up. And more often than not, the sources through which your children consume all the things that were hidden from them during their nascent years are not the most reliable or truthful sources. Thus, as we grow up, we are ambushed with facts and to find answers to them we tend to rely on treacherous sources which skew our ideas all the more. Instead of nurturing our kids with righteousness and practicality from the beginning, we try to mask them from facts, for as long as possible - which might not help them as much as one would hope.&amp;nbsp;The thing about the ‘real’ world is that unlike fairytales, it’s flawed and filled with imperfections. Which is what drives life ahead, the little or large hiccups in the flow of life. From Anderson’s stories to the truth about sexuality, identity, religion and relationships - a lot is made inconspicuous for the kids so that the information dissemination is controlled according to the norms that we have constructed and reaches them in a palatable form. But the question remains: who gets to decide what is right or wrong for these kids? Are flowery stories with morals sieved through our model of heteronormativity, appropriate culture and paradigms of acceptable behaviour the way to go about raising our kids? Only to impel them later into a world where they stumble as they go through life deconstructing their thoughts and knowledge, indoctrinated throughout childhood and then rebuilding it in a frenzy of emotions.I wonder if it would’ve been better, had my parents read me stories of women who didn’t enforce ideals of self-sacrifice to find the truest form of love or tales of women and people in general, who didn’t settle for anything less than what they deserved, did not change themselves only to be accepted by society, and stories that told that life’s utmost purpose was not to find a perfect partner but to find yourself. And in the process of that, you will meet people who will make life worthwhile. But not one of the stories told us, that it is very much okay, even if you don’t. Because in life, there is no blueprint or algorithm like in stories - all the milestones of life are supposed to make your journey easier and not all the more pressurizing. So the moral of this article is maybe that it is okay to chart your own path - because if you find yourself not fitting in with any of the existing stories, you can always write a new one.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Do People Still Listen to Radio in 2020?: A Decentralised Understanding of Radio Broadcasting in India</title>
      <link href="/Do-People-Still-Listen-to-Radio-in-2020" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do People Still Listen to Radio in 2020?: A Decentralised Understanding of Radio Broadcasting in India " />
      <published>2020-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Do-People-Still-Listen-to-Radio-in-2020</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Do-People-Still-Listen-to-Radio-in-2020">&lt;p&gt;Mass media is generally used to disseminate information through various modes of communication. It helps in the exchange of ideas and information to large segments of society. Broadcast is a field of mass communication that transmits information, imparts knowledge and helps in creating a dialogue between the news agency and the audience via mediums like radio and television. The term ‘broadcast’ refers to visual or audio content dispersion to the people through electronic communication in a one-to-many module.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Radio as a Mass Medium&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Known as the ‘theatre of mind’, radio is the most pervasive, accessible and affordable mass media available in the developing world. It networks developing programmes to diverse populations and connects them all on the national and international levels. It is a cheap alternative to the glamourous mediums that have evolved with technology. The radio still remains a potential driver of information and entertainment to highly targeted audiences such as the rural population. Especially in a developing country, like India, this plays a major role in spreading information because most of the rural population is generally left bereft of the newer mechanisms.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evolution of Radio&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objective of the first radio program in India which was transmitted by the Madras Presidency Radio Club (MPRC) and led by C V Krishnaswami Cheti, was to stimulate interest, inform and instruct the public, and to foster the study of radio communications in the presidency. With the approval being given for the privatisation of radio media organisations by the British colonial government, the Indian Broadcasting Company set up radio stations in Calcutta and Bombay. In 1936, this corporation was renamed All India Radio (AIR), and when India became independent in 1947, AIR became a separate department under the Ministry of Information and Broadcasting. Presently, radio broadcasting gets coverage in 24 languages and 146 dialects all across India. 111 million households own a radio set in the country. Regional radio has reached all states individually, catering to its colloquial audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://d2r2ijn7njrktv.cloudfront.net/IL/uploads/2017/02/community-radio.jpg&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/community-radio.jpg&quot; /&gt;Community Radio stations are popular among all age groups and used extensively to spread awareness.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local Broadcasting: Community Radio&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It refers to a type of radio service that caters to the interests of a particular person in an area. The primary focus is on the local population and issues concerning them. Use of broadcast here acts as a link between the community problems and the authorities who can do something about the resolution of the same. Community radio is a broadcast tool that is of the people, by the people and for the people. It is a decentralised use of the larger medium of communication, that is, the radio. It is important to talk about community radio in today’s times as it provides a platform to the local people to become citizen journalists and educate themselves and their fellow beings. While FM Radio caters to the urban population mostly, community radio’s target audience includes rural, urban, suburban, regional and sectional communities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Radio Udaan &lt;/strong&gt;is an example of community radio. Launched in 2014, it is an online radio station developed by and for specially-abled people. &amp;nbsp;It is the only type of radio station that is run by visually challenged people and is widely listened to in more than 115 countries. The vision of the radio station is broad and its agendas are diverse, which is- “&lt;em&gt;To entertain, empower and elevate the listeners. Radio Udaan aims to reach out to maximum possible people. It wants to become not only a supplier of entertainment and knowledge to the listeners but also a part of their daily routine, family and lifestyle. The station seeks to shoulder the burdens of its listeners by empowering them and listening to their stories and problems, and eventually catering them solutions&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apno Radio, 90.4 MHz, Rajasthan &lt;/strong&gt;was launched in 2005 and is Rajasthan’s first community radio station. The station’s objective is to promote self-reliance and women's empowerment. It focuses on several social issues ailing the rural communities of the state such as education, health, nutrition, environment, agriculture, depicting folk, art, culture, rural and community development.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is Radio Dying?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the millennials in urban life devote their maximum time to Apple Music and Spotify, this question often pops up with “yes” as an answer to it. However, that is not true. Radio is not dying but rather it is evolving. The term ‘Tradigital’ (traditional plus digital) is assigned to this evolution wherein traditional radio stations are using digital media platforms for two reasons - one, to expand their audience reach and two, to keep up with the technology and not let the broadcasting medium which has a reach of over 100 million people in India die because of the takeover by bigger and international online streaming platforms, television and satellite revolution. The newer versions of mass communications generally caters to a literate population with access to higher-end devices and it must be acknowledged that radio initially started to educate the uneducated and still plays a pivotal role in doing this duty as a medium of communication. Recognition of local broadcasting is crucial to its development and as we talk more about ‘Communication as a Development Source’ in the 21st century, community reach can boost the country’s process to achieve 2030 Sustainable Development Goals by imparting knowledge in a decentralised manner to the regional sections. Moreover, radio acts as a tool for both development and freedom which provides a platform for people to exercise their freedom of speech and expression, uphold the liberty of thought, especially with the growth of community radio.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand this better, I would like to connect this with a media theory called the Knowledge Gap Theory of 1970. It is the brainchild of Philip J Tichenor, George A Donohue and Clarice N Olien. They explained the Knowledge Gap theory as “&lt;em&gt;the infusion of mass media information into a social system where higher socioeconomic status segments tend to acquire this information faster than lower socioeconomic status population segments. Hence&amp;nbsp;the&amp;nbsp;gap between the two tends to increase rather than decrease.&lt;/em&gt;” In 2020, these faster modes of communication can be through the accessibility of various sources of information. The availability of these mediums come with a price tag and not everyone can afford it. Radio and especially the growing community radio has revolutionised news delivery in various parts of the country that do not get the proper mainstream coverage in the primetime and are highly underrepresented and neglected in the little coverage that they receive. The only way to connect to the grassroots is by reducing this knowledge gap with a tool of communication. This is where the power of radio lies, in the heart of the community people who use this broadcasting medium to connect and embrace positive change in their society. A boost to a media platform which caters to the lower rungs of the socio-economic ladder is necessary in these times when inequality and unemployment are raging and the youth is being fed with narratives filled with hatred and bigotry. This medium can be the harbinger of change in the society for the better, we just have to care enough about the people left behind to dedicate ourselves to such discourse. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Himanshi Saini</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Mass media is generally used to disseminate information through various modes of communication. It helps in the exchange of ideas and information to large segments of society. Broadcast is a field of mass communication that transmits information, imparts knowledge and helps in creating a dialogue between the news agency and the audience via mediums like radio and television. The term ‘broadcast’ refers to visual or audio content dispersion to the people through electronic communication in a one-to-many module.&amp;nbsp; Radio as a Mass Medium Known as the ‘theatre of mind’, radio is the most pervasive, accessible and affordable mass media available in the developing world. It networks developing programmes to diverse populations and connects them all on the national and international levels. It is a cheap alternative to the glamourous mediums that have evolved with technology. The radio still remains a potential driver of information and entertainment to highly targeted audiences such as the rural population. Especially in a developing country, like India, this plays a major role in spreading information because most of the rural population is generally left bereft of the newer mechanisms.&amp;nbsp; Evolution of Radio The objective of the first radio program in India which was transmitted by the Madras Presidency Radio Club (MPRC) and led by C V Krishnaswami Cheti, was to stimulate interest, inform and instruct the public, and to foster the study of radio communications in the presidency. With the approval being given for the privatisation of radio media organisations by the British colonial government, the Indian Broadcasting Company set up radio stations in Calcutta and Bombay. In 1936, this corporation was renamed All India Radio (AIR), and when India became independent in 1947, AIR became a separate department under the Ministry of Information and Broadcasting. Presently, radio broadcasting gets coverage in 24 languages and 146 dialects all across India. 111 million households own a radio set in the country. Regional radio has reached all states individually, catering to its colloquial audience. Community Radio stations are popular among all age groups and used extensively to spread awareness. Local Broadcasting: Community Radio&amp;nbsp; It refers to a type of radio service that caters to the interests of a particular person in an area. The primary focus is on the local population and issues concerning them. Use of broadcast here acts as a link between the community problems and the authorities who can do something about the resolution of the same. Community radio is a broadcast tool that is of the people, by the people and for the people. It is a decentralised use of the larger medium of communication, that is, the radio. It is important to talk about community radio in today’s times as it provides a platform to the local people to become citizen journalists and educate themselves and their fellow beings. While FM Radio caters to the urban population mostly, community radio’s target audience includes rural, urban, suburban, regional and sectional communities.&amp;nbsp; Radio Udaan is an example of community radio. Launched in 2014, it is an online radio station developed by and for specially-abled people. &amp;nbsp;It is the only type of radio station that is run by visually challenged people and is widely listened to in more than 115 countries. The vision of the radio station is broad and its agendas are diverse, which is- “To entertain, empower and elevate the listeners. Radio Udaan aims to reach out to maximum possible people. It wants to become not only a supplier of entertainment and knowledge to the listeners but also a part of their daily routine, family and lifestyle. The station seeks to shoulder the burdens of its listeners by empowering them and listening to their stories and problems, and eventually catering them solutions.” Apno Radio, 90.4 MHz, Rajasthan was launched in 2005 and is Rajasthan’s first community radio station. The station’s objective is to promote self-reliance and women's empowerment. It focuses on several social issues ailing the rural communities of the state such as education, health, nutrition, environment, agriculture, depicting folk, art, culture, rural and community development.&amp;nbsp; Is Radio Dying? While the millennials in urban life devote their maximum time to Apple Music and Spotify, this question often pops up with “yes” as an answer to it. However, that is not true. Radio is not dying but rather it is evolving. The term ‘Tradigital’ (traditional plus digital) is assigned to this evolution wherein traditional radio stations are using digital media platforms for two reasons - one, to expand their audience reach and two, to keep up with the technology and not let the broadcasting medium which has a reach of over 100 million people in India die because of the takeover by bigger and international online streaming platforms, television and satellite revolution. The newer versions of mass communications generally caters to a literate population with access to higher-end devices and it must be acknowledged that radio initially started to educate the uneducated and still plays a pivotal role in doing this duty as a medium of communication. Recognition of local broadcasting is crucial to its development and as we talk more about ‘Communication as a Development Source’ in the 21st century, community reach can boost the country’s process to achieve 2030 Sustainable Development Goals by imparting knowledge in a decentralised manner to the regional sections. Moreover, radio acts as a tool for both development and freedom which provides a platform for people to exercise their freedom of speech and expression, uphold the liberty of thought, especially with the growth of community radio.&amp;nbsp; To understand this better, I would like to connect this with a media theory called the Knowledge Gap Theory of 1970. It is the brainchild of Philip J Tichenor, George A Donohue and Clarice N Olien. They explained the Knowledge Gap theory as “the infusion of mass media information into a social system where higher socioeconomic status segments tend to acquire this information faster than lower socioeconomic status population segments. Hence&amp;nbsp;the&amp;nbsp;gap between the two tends to increase rather than decrease.” In 2020, these faster modes of communication can be through the accessibility of various sources of information. The availability of these mediums come with a price tag and not everyone can afford it. Radio and especially the growing community radio has revolutionised news delivery in various parts of the country that do not get the proper mainstream coverage in the primetime and are highly underrepresented and neglected in the little coverage that they receive. The only way to connect to the grassroots is by reducing this knowledge gap with a tool of communication. This is where the power of radio lies, in the heart of the community people who use this broadcasting medium to connect and embrace positive change in their society. A boost to a media platform which caters to the lower rungs of the socio-economic ladder is necessary in these times when inequality and unemployment are raging and the youth is being fed with narratives filled with hatred and bigotry. This medium can be the harbinger of change in the society for the better, we just have to care enough about the people left behind to dedicate ourselves to such discourse.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Jewish Persecution Through the Ages</title>
      <link href="/Jewish-Persecution-Through-the-Ages" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jewish Persecution Through the Ages" />
      <published>2020-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Jewish-Persecution-Through-the-Ages</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Jewish-Persecution-Through-the-Ages">&lt;p&gt;By our very nature, we humans have the tendency to adapt and mould everything to suit our purpose. We have razed mountains to rubble, developed sustainable civilisations, and harnessed various forces of nature to our service. We need to see the world in a way that makes sense to us because not knowing what’s out there is one of the worst fears of humankind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anomalously, this theory also explains both the cause of developments and the inevitable resistance a society poses to them. Some individuals through their efforts generate new and more plausible explanations of existing phenomena. However, society generally fixates on the traditional notions and feels somewhat threatened by the existence of a new answer - something they’re completely ignorant of.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, advancement in human society is also characterised by free-will and greater acceptance of one’s beliefs and perception. So, the only thing that needs to be decided upon is - do the benefits and costs of clinging onto traditionality and remaining in the comfort zone outweigh that of adapting to developments and being more receptive?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after considering the sentiment of people and the factor of coincidence in the associated events and stories, all the scientific evidence points to the fact that religion is a product of human psychology. People want to make sense of the immeasurable number of interdependent or independent events that take place in the world around them and when they believe they have hit a dead end, they instinctively correlate them with the supernatural or the divine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this theory in its own capacity poses a very interesting philosophical question - why are people willing to mortify, hurt, torture or even kill fellow human beings when there is a very high chance that the argument which they believe absolves them of these crimes may be rooted in ignorance?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ql-cursor&quot;&gt;﻿Jews, throughout history, have been one of the most abused communities around the world. The Greeks did it, the Roman did it, even fellow monothesitics like Christians and Muslims did it, but they were all eventually put to shame by Hitler.&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;p&gt;Monotheistic cultures are widely popular today. When it comes to suitability to the highly dynamic lifestyle of the modern world, they check almost all the boxes. Yet, the forerunners of the bunch - Christianity and Islam - made meagre efforts for upliftment of the Jewish community in their respective reigns over the Middle East and Europe. Also, an important point to mention is that Judaism, Christianity and Islam are highly analogous. Christianity revamped the Jewish ideologies and labeled them as their own, and Islam did the same to Christianity. The fundamental religious doctrine is the same in all three of them, and concepts like prophets, heaven, hell, etc. are fairly consistent. This further intensifies the nefariousness of the former's actions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moreover, it won’t be completely fair to blame this history of blatant inhumanity on poor governance as the laws of that time made no clear cut distinction between the state and the apex religious body. Therefore, it is the medieval thought process of these communities that is to be blamed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ancient Greek and Roman societies were governed by a class of strong believers in polytheism. They prayed to their gods in temples, made blood sacrifices, and tried their best to live their lives by the stories they heard about them. The arrival of monotheistic faith, whose beliefs and practices were not even remotely close to theirs, was not well received by them. Public executions, selective poll tax, and defilement of synagogues were a common method to overrule the other belief system. Jews were expelled from the city and some Roman emperors went to the length of declaring the possession of Jewish scriptures a capital crime. Such acts of hostility, though morally incoherent, can be justified rationally by the fundamental pattern of society's initial reaction to change in any case whatsoever. Moreover, Jews were not the only monotheists being harassed, the Romans reacted similarly to Christianity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moving up the timeline, Rome was Christianised in the late 300 AD and the capital of the Christian stronghold was established in Constantinople, Byzantine. In the late 600 AD, Islam came into being in the Arabian region of the Middle East and started growing rapidly owing to the expansionary crusades of Mohammad and the succeeding Muslim leaders. Jewish groups in Byzantine were treated as aliens for their disbelief in the absolution of Christianity. Their social standing and religious liberty varied with the ruler. Eventually, Islamic leaders reached the borders of Byzantine (Christianized Rome) and toppled the rule of Christians who retaliated with a series of crusades to reclaim the holy lands. All of the conflict lasted for about 200 years and the Jewish community was dishevelled as a byproduct. Muslim rulers aggressively imposed Islamic credo upon them and whenever Christians invaded as a result of the crusades, they wiped entire Jewish colonies off the map.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The situation was especially bad in Persia, as under the prejudice of being spiritually unclean, Jews were forced to live in ghettos outside of towns. They were not allowed to enter shops, and even if they managed to, they were not allowed to touch or inspect any item. If the latter was to happen, the laws clearly stated that the Jew was obligated to buy the product and the seller had an absolute right of charging as much as they wanted. Also, Jews were not allowed to roam the cities during rain, as it was believed that the&amp;nbsp; dirt of their spirituality would wash down with the raindrops and rub off on the locals who walked the same paths.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the middle ages rolled in, anti-semitic groups evolved their methods of suppression, as they started destroying the political standing of the Jews and catalysed it for their physical extermination. During the Black Death period, orthodox Crhritian and Muslim groups in the middle east accused Jews of poisoning the wells within cities and orchestrating the plague. These accusations were used to make initial arrests, upon which the prisoners were tortured and threatened into confessing to crimes that they never committed. Even for executions, slow death methods like public stoning &amp;amp; death by fire were used. As a final touch of cruelty, their respective properties and places of worship were seized without cause and converted into churches, mosques, and libraries.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to the 1940’s. Religious and racial fanaticism had poisoned Germany. Almost everyone is aware of the horrific ordeal that Hitler and his racial political agendas put Jews through - pogroms, mass shootings, concentration camps and the gas chambers. When the dust settled, two-thirds of the European Jewish population had been exterminated- “genocide” in the perfect sense of the word. The scapegoating does not end there, as Jews were also blamed for capitalism and excessively controlling the american financial market via their dominance of the premiere financial institutions of the time like Rothschilds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even today, the other communities prey on Jews for conversions. Their faith is still undermined and their rights as members of the society are still kept subservient to those of other cultures. It is imperative to understand that the concept of “sustainability”- a term which is amassing a lot of popularity lately- is not selective. Developing a world where everyone is willing to live their life of their own volition is the very foundation of the term. Therefore, security and free will for some and impositions on others is a betrayal to the very essence of sustainability as it makes the society more prone to implosion rather than consolidation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aryaman Dhiman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">By our very nature, we humans have the tendency to adapt and mould everything to suit our purpose. We have razed mountains to rubble, developed sustainable civilisations, and harnessed various forces of nature to our service. We need to see the world in a way that makes sense to us because not knowing what’s out there is one of the worst fears of humankind. Anomalously, this theory also explains both the cause of developments and the inevitable resistance a society poses to them. Some individuals through their efforts generate new and more plausible explanations of existing phenomena. However, society generally fixates on the traditional notions and feels somewhat threatened by the existence of a new answer - something they’re completely ignorant of.&amp;nbsp; In retrospect, advancement in human society is also characterised by free-will and greater acceptance of one’s beliefs and perception. So, the only thing that needs to be decided upon is - do the benefits and costs of clinging onto traditionality and remaining in the comfort zone outweigh that of adapting to developments and being more receptive? Even after considering the sentiment of people and the factor of coincidence in the associated events and stories, all the scientific evidence points to the fact that religion is a product of human psychology. People want to make sense of the immeasurable number of interdependent or independent events that take place in the world around them and when they believe they have hit a dead end, they instinctively correlate them with the supernatural or the divine. Now, this theory in its own capacity poses a very interesting philosophical question - why are people willing to mortify, hurt, torture or even kill fellow human beings when there is a very high chance that the argument which they believe absolves them of these crimes may be rooted in ignorance?&amp;nbsp; ﻿Jews, throughout history, have been one of the most abused communities around the world. The Greeks did it, the Roman did it, even fellow monothesitics like Christians and Muslims did it, but they were all eventually put to shame by Hitler.&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;Monotheistic cultures are widely popular today. When it comes to suitability to the highly dynamic lifestyle of the modern world, they check almost all the boxes. Yet, the forerunners of the bunch - Christianity and Islam - made meagre efforts for upliftment of the Jewish community in their respective reigns over the Middle East and Europe. Also, an important point to mention is that Judaism, Christianity and Islam are highly analogous. Christianity revamped the Jewish ideologies and labeled them as their own, and Islam did the same to Christianity. The fundamental religious doctrine is the same in all three of them, and concepts like prophets, heaven, hell, etc. are fairly consistent. This further intensifies the nefariousness of the former's actions.&amp;nbsp;Moreover, it won’t be completely fair to blame this history of blatant inhumanity on poor governance as the laws of that time made no clear cut distinction between the state and the apex religious body. Therefore, it is the medieval thought process of these communities that is to be blamed.&amp;nbsp;Ancient Greek and Roman societies were governed by a class of strong believers in polytheism. They prayed to their gods in temples, made blood sacrifices, and tried their best to live their lives by the stories they heard about them. The arrival of monotheistic faith, whose beliefs and practices were not even remotely close to theirs, was not well received by them. Public executions, selective poll tax, and defilement of synagogues were a common method to overrule the other belief system. Jews were expelled from the city and some Roman emperors went to the length of declaring the possession of Jewish scriptures a capital crime. Such acts of hostility, though morally incoherent, can be justified rationally by the fundamental pattern of society's initial reaction to change in any case whatsoever. Moreover, Jews were not the only monotheists being harassed, the Romans reacted similarly to Christianity.&amp;nbsp;Moving up the timeline, Rome was Christianised in the late 300 AD and the capital of the Christian stronghold was established in Constantinople, Byzantine. In the late 600 AD, Islam came into being in the Arabian region of the Middle East and started growing rapidly owing to the expansionary crusades of Mohammad and the succeeding Muslim leaders. Jewish groups in Byzantine were treated as aliens for their disbelief in the absolution of Christianity. Their social standing and religious liberty varied with the ruler. Eventually, Islamic leaders reached the borders of Byzantine (Christianized Rome) and toppled the rule of Christians who retaliated with a series of crusades to reclaim the holy lands. All of the conflict lasted for about 200 years and the Jewish community was dishevelled as a byproduct. Muslim rulers aggressively imposed Islamic credo upon them and whenever Christians invaded as a result of the crusades, they wiped entire Jewish colonies off the map.&amp;nbsp;The situation was especially bad in Persia, as under the prejudice of being spiritually unclean, Jews were forced to live in ghettos outside of towns. They were not allowed to enter shops, and even if they managed to, they were not allowed to touch or inspect any item. If the latter was to happen, the laws clearly stated that the Jew was obligated to buy the product and the seller had an absolute right of charging as much as they wanted. Also, Jews were not allowed to roam the cities during rain, as it was believed that the&amp;nbsp; dirt of their spirituality would wash down with the raindrops and rub off on the locals who walked the same paths.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;As the middle ages rolled in, anti-semitic groups evolved their methods of suppression, as they started destroying the political standing of the Jews and catalysed it for their physical extermination. During the Black Death period, orthodox Crhritian and Muslim groups in the middle east accused Jews of poisoning the wells within cities and orchestrating the plague. These accusations were used to make initial arrests, upon which the prisoners were tortured and threatened into confessing to crimes that they never committed. Even for executions, slow death methods like public stoning &amp;amp; death by fire were used. As a final touch of cruelty, their respective properties and places of worship were seized without cause and converted into churches, mosques, and libraries.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Fast forward to the 1940’s. Religious and racial fanaticism had poisoned Germany. Almost everyone is aware of the horrific ordeal that Hitler and his racial political agendas put Jews through - pogroms, mass shootings, concentration camps and the gas chambers. When the dust settled, two-thirds of the European Jewish population had been exterminated- “genocide” in the perfect sense of the word. The scapegoating does not end there, as Jews were also blamed for capitalism and excessively controlling the american financial market via their dominance of the premiere financial institutions of the time like Rothschilds.Even today, the other communities prey on Jews for conversions. Their faith is still undermined and their rights as members of the society are still kept subservient to those of other cultures. It is imperative to understand that the concept of “sustainability”- a term which is amassing a lot of popularity lately- is not selective. Developing a world where everyone is willing to live their life of their own volition is the very foundation of the term. Therefore, security and free will for some and impositions on others is a betrayal to the very essence of sustainability as it makes the society more prone to implosion rather than consolidation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Weaponised Words: A Tale of Hate Speech</title>
      <link href="/Weaponised-Words-A-Tale-of-Hate-Speech" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Weaponised Words: A Tale of Hate Speech" />
      <published>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Weaponised-Words-A-Tale-of-Hate-Speech</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Weaponised-Words-A-Tale-of-Hate-Speech">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&quot;There is a fine line between free speech and hate speech. Free speech encourages debate whereas hate speech incites violence&quot; -&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Newton Lee,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/work/quotes/24289059&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Counterterrorism and Cybersecurity: Total Information Awareness&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quotation is a constant reminder of how easily hate speech overlaps with the idea of freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp;Over the past few months, the challenge of separating hate speech from the Indian citizen’s right to ‘Freedom of Expression’ has increased tremendously. Recently, several citizens including journalists, political party leaders and activists have been charged with hate speech, inflammatory speech and sedition. On one hand, offended plaintiffs file complaints due to hurt caused to their sentiments by the comments of the accused people. On the other hand, the defendants perceive it as a violation of their right to Freedom of Speech.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the light of recent incidents in India, a crucial question arises.&amp;nbsp;Should hate speech be incorporated as a part of Freedom of Speech, or should hate speech be legally regulated?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to scrutinise the idea of ‘free, hate speech’, it is important to distinguish between the two ideas of hate speech and free speech.&amp;nbsp;'Freedom of Expression or Speech' is a principle supporting the idea of an individual or a community articulating their opinions and ideas freely. It ensures such freedom “without the fear of retaliation, censorship, or legal sanction.” On the other hand, hate speech is clearly defined by the &lt;em&gt;Cambridge Dictionary&lt;/em&gt; as a &quot;public speech that expresses hate or encourages violence towards a person or a group based on something such as race, religion, sex, or sexual orientation”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get a sense of how hate speech is treated by legislation, we must take a look at a few examples. While hate speech is not a legal term in some countries, victims of hate speech may seek redressal under civil law, criminal law, or both in other nations. For instance, in the United States, hate speech is constitutionally protected. On the contrary, de jure, freedom of expression is promised in North Korea but there is no de facto right to free speech as asserted by Amnesty International, a human rights group.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In India, hate speech is regulated. While ‘Freedom of Speech and Expression’ is a fundamental right of the Indian Constitution, under Article 19(2) &quot;reasonable restrictions&quot; can be imposed on this right. This is in order to protect &quot;the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of the State, friendly relations with foreign States, public order, decency or morality, or in relation to contempt of court, defamation or incitement to an offence&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hurdle of Hate&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hate speech is a threat to humankind because words have the power to influence people to take action. It causes instability and agitation across the society. It can lead to reduced motivation, lower tolerance, emotional trauma or in extreme cases, depression.&amp;nbsp;Raising this concern, Joyce Arthur, a Canadian activist, in an article titled 'Should Hate Speech be a Crime?' underlines the importance of hate speech legislation. She elucidates that hate speech needs to be regulated as it has a huge impact on people’s dignity and human rights. Hate speech is often derogatory to the sentiments of a particular caste, creed, sex or religion as it is often rooted in stereotypes, prejudices and personal experiences which may be an inaccurate perception of the group or community as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A product of hate speech is hate crime&lt;/strong&gt;. Hate crimes are dangerous as they jeopardise amity in society, instigate precarity among communities, and foster a sense of animosity in the democracy.&amp;nbsp;In the technological era, hate speech over social media causes a tremendous amount of intolerance and violence leading to hate crimes. For instance, the perpetrator of the 2019 New Zealand mosque shootings killed 49 Muslims at prayer and sought to broadcast the attack on YouTube. In Germany, a correlation was observed between anti-refugee Facebook posts by the Alternative for Germany party and increasing attacks on refugees. In India, the recent case of Delhi violence due to hate speech and rumors on social media is also another instance.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hate Speech in India&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While 2020 has been a relatively inactive year for India in terms of business and functioning of institutions, the story is very different when it comes to hate speech laws. Starting from January 2020, there have been 10+ cases involving charges for sedition and hate speech.&amp;nbsp;Among journalists, Arnab Goswami, Amish Devgan and Vinod Dua are a few who&amp;nbsp; have faced FIRs or First Information Reports against them. On one hand, Amish Devgan was accused of injuring religious sentiments on his show. On the other hand, Goswami and Dua faced charges for criticising the State in different forms. FIRs against Goswami have been filed in relation to his questioning opposition leader Sonia Gandhi regarding mob lynching in the Palghar district of Western India. And Dua has been charged with sedition for a Youtube broadcast wherein he said that the State failed to implement the lockdown.&amp;nbsp;Sharjeel Imam, an Indian activist, has been charged with sedition, hate speech and promoting religious antagonism for his speeches against the Citizenship Amendment Act.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These diverse cases point out that it is also challenging and important to define specifically what can be categorized as hate speech.&amp;nbsp;A striking point has been stated in one of the articles in &lt;em&gt;Indian Express&lt;/em&gt;. It says that out of the ten hate speech cases that were scrutinised, including the ones mentioned above, the cases where the State and the petitioner contended on the same side, relief was provided. However, in six cases, where the State was accused, no relief was granted to the petitioner. A ‘telling pattern’ of this sort indicates a fresh challenge of violation of the right to equality before the law.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of this is the regulation of hate speech over social media. While trolling is only the tip of the iceberg, Facebook has recently faced challenges concerning hate speech rules. The &lt;em&gt;Wall Street Journal&lt;/em&gt; has accused Facebook of having failed to apply hate speech regulations on content posted by a BJP leader from the state of Telangana. Three other party leaders’ posts have also been overlooked.&amp;nbsp;A great initiative to combat such challenges is Facebook’s Oversight Board. The Oversight Board is an entity vested with the power to moderate and make independent decisions regarding content over social media sites like Facebook and Instagram. Its purpose is the protection of Facebook users. Hate speech and cases related to ‘political bias’ are within the purview of the board.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Watershed Verdicts&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1962 Indian Supreme Court judgement in &lt;em&gt;Kedar Nath Singh vs State of Bihar&lt;/em&gt; is a landmark judgement concerning the right to Freedom of Expression. The defendant faced charges of sedition and inciting public mischief due to a criticism of the then ruling party, the Indian National Congress in his speech. The defendant argued that the provisions on sedition in the Indian Penal Code (IPC) violated the right to Freedom of Expression under Article 19(1)(a) of the Indian Constitution.&amp;nbsp;The Court asserted that these were not under the purview of “reasonable restrictions” under Article 19(2). It explained that the phrase “Government established by law” under section 124A is different from the criticism of a political party or political leaders.&amp;nbsp;Yet sedition continues to be criminalised under the IPC. However, its provision has been narrowed down to only criminalise expression that intends to jeopardize public order and peace through violence, thereby protecting the right to freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another remarkable judgement in the field of online free speech is &lt;em&gt;Shreya Singhal vs Union of India (UOI).&lt;/em&gt; Two women were arrested under Section 66A of the Information Technology Act, 2000 for ‘posting allegedly offensive comments on Facebook’. As per the section, any person who sends “grossly offensive information” or information “to cause insult, injury or ill will” can be punished. These women filed a petition arguing that Section 66A was constitutionally invalid on the grounds of violation of the right to freedom of speech.&amp;nbsp;In 2015, the Supreme Court declared Section 66A to be unconstitutional and it was struck down. This was because Section 66A was not recognized as a “reasonable restriction” under Article 19(2). Thus, this was a turning point for online free speech.&amp;nbsp;These landmark judgements are useful to cite in cases relating to hate speech and freedom of expression for stronger established arguments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above-mentioned arguments and instances indicate that hate speech needs to be tackled through a balanced approach. While the right to freedom of expression needs to be upheld, hate speech intending to cause violence, disturb public order and promote unrest can prove to be detrimental for humankind.&amp;nbsp;A study by the Pew Research Center reveals that 67% and 27% of people in the United States and Asia-Pacific, respectively, agree with free hate speech. Nonetheless, as the saying goes, “Hate begets more hate”, hate speech causes a vicious cycle of hatred that has no end.&amp;nbsp;Thus, to balance respectful and considerate free speech without hampering the true essence of the Freedom of Expression, regulation of hate speech and uniform implementation of such rules is the need of the hour.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Nirikta Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">&quot;There is a fine line between free speech and hate speech. Free speech encourages debate whereas hate speech incites violence&quot; - Newton Lee, Counterterrorism and Cybersecurity: Total Information Awareness This quotation is a constant reminder of how easily hate speech overlaps with the idea of freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp;Over the past few months, the challenge of separating hate speech from the Indian citizen’s right to ‘Freedom of Expression’ has increased tremendously. Recently, several citizens including journalists, political party leaders and activists have been charged with hate speech, inflammatory speech and sedition. On one hand, offended plaintiffs file complaints due to hurt caused to their sentiments by the comments of the accused people. On the other hand, the defendants perceive it as a violation of their right to Freedom of Speech.&amp;nbsp; In the light of recent incidents in India, a crucial question arises.&amp;nbsp;Should hate speech be incorporated as a part of Freedom of Speech, or should hate speech be legally regulated?&amp;nbsp; In order to scrutinise the idea of ‘free, hate speech’, it is important to distinguish between the two ideas of hate speech and free speech.&amp;nbsp;'Freedom of Expression or Speech' is a principle supporting the idea of an individual or a community articulating their opinions and ideas freely. It ensures such freedom “without the fear of retaliation, censorship, or legal sanction.” On the other hand, hate speech is clearly defined by the Cambridge Dictionary as a &quot;public speech that expresses hate or encourages violence towards a person or a group based on something such as race, religion, sex, or sexual orientation”. To get a sense of how hate speech is treated by legislation, we must take a look at a few examples. While hate speech is not a legal term in some countries, victims of hate speech may seek redressal under civil law, criminal law, or both in other nations. For instance, in the United States, hate speech is constitutionally protected. On the contrary, de jure, freedom of expression is promised in North Korea but there is no de facto right to free speech as asserted by Amnesty International, a human rights group.&amp;nbsp; In India, hate speech is regulated. While ‘Freedom of Speech and Expression’ is a fundamental right of the Indian Constitution, under Article 19(2) &quot;reasonable restrictions&quot; can be imposed on this right. This is in order to protect &quot;the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of the State, friendly relations with foreign States, public order, decency or morality, or in relation to contempt of court, defamation or incitement to an offence&quot;. Hurdle of Hate&amp;nbsp; Hate speech is a threat to humankind because words have the power to influence people to take action. It causes instability and agitation across the society. It can lead to reduced motivation, lower tolerance, emotional trauma or in extreme cases, depression.&amp;nbsp;Raising this concern, Joyce Arthur, a Canadian activist, in an article titled 'Should Hate Speech be a Crime?' underlines the importance of hate speech legislation. She elucidates that hate speech needs to be regulated as it has a huge impact on people’s dignity and human rights. Hate speech is often derogatory to the sentiments of a particular caste, creed, sex or religion as it is often rooted in stereotypes, prejudices and personal experiences which may be an inaccurate perception of the group or community as a whole. A product of hate speech is hate crime. Hate crimes are dangerous as they jeopardise amity in society, instigate precarity among communities, and foster a sense of animosity in the democracy.&amp;nbsp;In the technological era, hate speech over social media causes a tremendous amount of intolerance and violence leading to hate crimes. For instance, the perpetrator of the 2019 New Zealand mosque shootings killed 49 Muslims at prayer and sought to broadcast the attack on YouTube. In Germany, a correlation was observed between anti-refugee Facebook posts by the Alternative for Germany party and increasing attacks on refugees. In India, the recent case of Delhi violence due to hate speech and rumors on social media is also another instance.&amp;nbsp; Hate Speech in India&amp;nbsp; While 2020 has been a relatively inactive year for India in terms of business and functioning of institutions, the story is very different when it comes to hate speech laws. Starting from January 2020, there have been 10+ cases involving charges for sedition and hate speech.&amp;nbsp;Among journalists, Arnab Goswami, Amish Devgan and Vinod Dua are a few who&amp;nbsp; have faced FIRs or First Information Reports against them. On one hand, Amish Devgan was accused of injuring religious sentiments on his show. On the other hand, Goswami and Dua faced charges for criticising the State in different forms. FIRs against Goswami have been filed in relation to his questioning opposition leader Sonia Gandhi regarding mob lynching in the Palghar district of Western India. And Dua has been charged with sedition for a Youtube broadcast wherein he said that the State failed to implement the lockdown.&amp;nbsp;Sharjeel Imam, an Indian activist, has been charged with sedition, hate speech and promoting religious antagonism for his speeches against the Citizenship Amendment Act.&amp;nbsp; These diverse cases point out that it is also challenging and important to define specifically what can be categorized as hate speech.&amp;nbsp;A striking point has been stated in one of the articles in Indian Express. It says that out of the ten hate speech cases that were scrutinised, including the ones mentioned above, the cases where the State and the petitioner contended on the same side, relief was provided. However, in six cases, where the State was accused, no relief was granted to the petitioner. A ‘telling pattern’ of this sort indicates a fresh challenge of violation of the right to equality before the law.&amp;nbsp; Another aspect of this is the regulation of hate speech over social media. While trolling is only the tip of the iceberg, Facebook has recently faced challenges concerning hate speech rules. The Wall Street Journal has accused Facebook of having failed to apply hate speech regulations on content posted by a BJP leader from the state of Telangana. Three other party leaders’ posts have also been overlooked.&amp;nbsp;A great initiative to combat such challenges is Facebook’s Oversight Board. The Oversight Board is an entity vested with the power to moderate and make independent decisions regarding content over social media sites like Facebook and Instagram. Its purpose is the protection of Facebook users. Hate speech and cases related to ‘political bias’ are within the purview of the board.&amp;nbsp; Watershed Verdicts&amp;nbsp; The 1962 Indian Supreme Court judgement in Kedar Nath Singh vs State of Bihar is a landmark judgement concerning the right to Freedom of Expression. The defendant faced charges of sedition and inciting public mischief due to a criticism of the then ruling party, the Indian National Congress in his speech. The defendant argued that the provisions on sedition in the Indian Penal Code (IPC) violated the right to Freedom of Expression under Article 19(1)(a) of the Indian Constitution.&amp;nbsp;The Court asserted that these were not under the purview of “reasonable restrictions” under Article 19(2). It explained that the phrase “Government established by law” under section 124A is different from the criticism of a political party or political leaders.&amp;nbsp;Yet sedition continues to be criminalised under the IPC. However, its provision has been narrowed down to only criminalise expression that intends to jeopardize public order and peace through violence, thereby protecting the right to freedom of expression.&amp;nbsp; Another remarkable judgement in the field of online free speech is Shreya Singhal vs Union of India (UOI). Two women were arrested under Section 66A of the Information Technology Act, 2000 for ‘posting allegedly offensive comments on Facebook’. As per the section, any person who sends “grossly offensive information” or information “to cause insult, injury or ill will” can be punished. These women filed a petition arguing that Section 66A was constitutionally invalid on the grounds of violation of the right to freedom of speech.&amp;nbsp;In 2015, the Supreme Court declared Section 66A to be unconstitutional and it was struck down. This was because Section 66A was not recognized as a “reasonable restriction” under Article 19(2). Thus, this was a turning point for online free speech.&amp;nbsp;These landmark judgements are useful to cite in cases relating to hate speech and freedom of expression for stronger established arguments.&amp;nbsp; The above-mentioned arguments and instances indicate that hate speech needs to be tackled through a balanced approach. While the right to freedom of expression needs to be upheld, hate speech intending to cause violence, disturb public order and promote unrest can prove to be detrimental for humankind.&amp;nbsp;A study by the Pew Research Center reveals that 67% and 27% of people in the United States and Asia-Pacific, respectively, agree with free hate speech. Nonetheless, as the saying goes, “Hate begets more hate”, hate speech causes a vicious cycle of hatred that has no end.&amp;nbsp;Thus, to balance respectful and considerate free speech without hampering the true essence of the Freedom of Expression, regulation of hate speech and uniform implementation of such rules is the need of the hour.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Caustic Crass of Casteism</title>
      <link href="/Caustic-Crass-of-Casteism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Caustic Crass of Casteism" />
      <published>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Caustic-Crass-of-Casteism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Caustic-Crass-of-Casteism">&lt;p&gt;Facebook in India is incessantly flooded with memes — pictures or videos of casteist slurs against the marginalised communities, as those who belong to ‘upper caste’ per se, lament against caste-based reservations in public institutes and government jobs. Their rationale, more prominently since the implementation of the Mandal Commission in 1990, has been that it ‘kills’ the merit factor, i.e. meritorious students who belong to the namesake ‘General’ category are deprived of opportunities that marginalised communities get due to reservation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the mind of every student in this country is filled with this narrative even before they burn the midnight oil to crack the draconian entrance exams. Such a hate-spewing narrative naturally brings a certain anathema towards the ‘reserved’ categories of students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This hatred is evident from the repetitive use of &lt;em&gt;cham**r&lt;/em&gt;, a word used as a casteist expletive which generalises all the marginalised communities under a derogative umbrella term, by many students studying in various educational institutions, sub-consciously fuming their exasperation against reservation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author of this article, who has been through the rat-race of preparing for the draconian engineering entrance exams, also blindly believed in this narrative. In hindsight, he now sees how it actually culminated with him profiling classmates and batchmates in the coaching classes, based on whether they could reap the benefits of reservation or not. His time also coincided with the ascendancy of Hindu-supremacist BJP at the centre, which also made him look slyly at Dr Ambedkar and the entire anti-caste movement. Of course, he found little sense in those rallying against casteism — for he only saw from a prism which showed them ‘entitled’ to higher-education in prestigious institutes without ‘merit’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This anecdote supports the aforementioned argument of how upper-caste propaganda embarks students on a path of discrimination and hatred — the wrongdoings of which are extremely difficult, if not impossible, to undo. What is even more concerning is that this propaganda under the garb of ‘merit’ and ‘equality’ brings a certain wind of legitimacy, the whiff of which is often hard to resist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, ‘merit’ is the key working word in this debate. However, it has been painstakingly dissected and presented in “Does ‘Merit’ have a Caste?” on &lt;em&gt;The Wire&lt;/em&gt; and it would be a great disservice to the author if it is reiterated only for the sake of argumentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The duopoly of casteism and classism are the biggest yet the most obscure threat to India’s Xanadu, the liveable manifestation of the promulgations of the Indian Constitution. Caste and class inequalities, on the contrary, are being pushed further into obscurity by a rising intolerance towards monotheistic religions, Islam in particular. Hindu vigilantes are often in what could be a self-perceived duel against their Muslim counterparts and vice versa. The macabre riots in Delhi are a testament to this intolerance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any conflict between religious communities obviously takes precedence over atrocities committed in the name of caste. In fact, the growing divide between monotheistic Islam and polytheistic Hinduism has given the latter a very powerful rationale for a ‘war cry’ of sorts, exhorting Hindus to ‘unite’ to ‘protect’ their sacrosanct religion. In reality, such exhortations culminate only with upper-caste Hindus to make a more impregnable clout and thereby, pushing the marginalised communities further away into oblivion. The upper echelons of public life in India are still largely dominated by upper-caste Hindus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, the author also believes that caste-based politicking is another reason for this growing divide. Whilst the government has brought upon the reformist measures to alleviate centuries of oppression, it still isn’t a step towards abolishing caste altogether. Many upper-caste Hindus often accuse political parties of caste-based political skullduggery for the marginalised communities have always been of a ‘vote-bank’, a sizeable population whose vote is crucial to win elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the author himself was led to strongly believe in the upper-caste narrative which denounces the existence of caste-based oppression altogether and accuses the marginalised communities to raise the caste question only to ‘cling’ onto the reservations that they are entitled to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an opinion of caste comes from a selective reading of society. In order to subscribe to this narrative, one must have class privilege, where the society is so-called ‘westernised’ enough to not bother knowing one’s caste as long as everyone belongs to the same economic class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it would be unfair to assume that being on top of the class pyramid saves one from the caste question, such selective perception of caste also comes from denial and ignorance; to put it crudely, one cannot deny the existence of casteism if one has never been subjected to caste-based discrimination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The caste dynamics in India are so precariously balanced that leaders such as Mahatma Gandhi are also accused of ensuring that the caste hierarchy remains. Man Booker-prize winning author Arundhati Roy in her essay ‘The Doctor and the Saint’ has opined that Gandhi supported the caste hierarchy only to appease the high-caste Marwari businessmen who, financially or otherwise, supported his &lt;em&gt;satyagraha&lt;/em&gt; (policy of nonviolent resistance) movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If probably the greatest statesman of this country paid his obeisance to casteism, it would be foolish to assume that a Hindu-supremacist government like the BJP would uproot this anachronistic practice. On the contrary, many Dalit activists are wary of the party’s intentions, and accuse it of ethnic profiling and cleansing with their divisive Citizenship Amendment Act (CAA) and the draconian National Register of Citizens (NRC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legacy of Dr B R Ambedkar, who perhaps was the most profound Dalit thinker, is also thrown in the cesspool of profanities and slurs, hurled by the upper-caste, the propaganda of hate deeply entrenched in their minds. The Indian education system, among its many inherent flaws, also fails to elucidate students about Dr Ambedkar as much as it embellishes Gandhi, which again reeks of the politics behind how impressionable minds are moulded to perceive the history and ethos of the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Xanadu which was envisaged by those who broke the shackles of an oppressive colonial rule is questioned and dissected now. Despite Dr Ambedkar’s tribulations for a more egalitarian and just society, the existence of marginalised communities is reduced to a transactional relationship where ‘reservation’ is given in exchange for their suffrage. Whether the doors of an independent India were open for Dalits and tribals is a question that remains unanswered even after 73 years.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rishi Kant</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Facebook in India is incessantly flooded with memes — pictures or videos of casteist slurs against the marginalised communities, as those who belong to ‘upper caste’ per se, lament against caste-based reservations in public institutes and government jobs. Their rationale, more prominently since the implementation of the Mandal Commission in 1990, has been that it ‘kills’ the merit factor, i.e. meritorious students who belong to the namesake ‘General’ category are deprived of opportunities that marginalised communities get due to reservation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Clout of A New World Order</title>
      <link href="/Clout-of-A-New-World-Order" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Clout of A New World Order" />
      <published>2020-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Clout-of-A-New-World-Order</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Clout-of-A-New-World-Order">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Social psychologists believe that feelings of frailty and uncertainty associate an individual with a tendency to believe in conspiracies”&lt;/em&gt;, said Karen M Douglas, Professor of Social Psychology at the University of Kent in the United Kingdom. Conceivably, it is true, to have something to lean on is an instinct to regain a sense of control, even if the conspiracy is unrelated to what caused the lack of control in an individual’s life. But what if this is just another conspiracy theory to dwarf all the other conspiracy theories?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you remember watching &lt;em&gt;The Matrix&lt;/em&gt;, you would probably remember Mr Anderson (Keanu Reaves), an otherwise rational person making the leap from prudent paranoia to a not so illogical conspiracy, which led him to the dilemma of choosing between the red and the blue pill. There exists a gnawing feeling of not having control over your life - the dissatisfaction which hinders you from living your life to the fullest. And that is what happened with Adam Weishaupt, founder of The Illuminati.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Born in 1748 in Ingolstadt, Bavaria, Weishaupt was a descendant of Jewish converts to Christianity. Orphaned at a young age, his uncle took care of his education. After completing his studies, Weishaupt became a Professor of canon law at the University of Ingolstadt, got married and started a family. He seemed to have a conventional career until 1784 when the Bavarian state learned about his distinct and provocative ideas. Since childhood, being an avid reader, Weishaupt was convinced that religious ideas were no longer an adequate belief system and hence, he decided to find another form of illumination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May 1, 1776 saw the first Illuminati meet in a forest near Ingolstadt to find the order and there, they established the rules that were to govern the order. The order was a set of scientific ideas and practices that could be applied to radically change the way European states were run. By the end of 1784, Weishaupt’s secret order grew considerably to 3,000 members and by the mid 1780’s, theIlluminati caught the Bavarian government’s attention, which put an end to the secret society. Weishaupt fled and gave up the secret shenanigans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does the Illuminati want?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conspiracy theorists obsessively analyse public events for evidence of Illuminati infiltration in the modern-day world. There have been many events which are said to be proof of the fact that the Illuminati has infiltrated the ranks of prominent leaders, celebrities, clergymen, business tycoons and pharmaceutical companies around the globe, who are affiliated with it and are collectively working to secure their main objective. Back in 2013, when Beyonce performed at superbowl and flashed a pyramid (believed to be the Illuminati’s symbol) with her hands, the internet was lit up with conjectures that she was a member of the secret society. While this might be a baseless conspiracy theory on the grounds of impracticality, it is logical for many who believe they have seen things. Moreover, there exists a condition called Pareidolia, which causes humans to see objective patterns in random stimuli, often attaching humane characteristics to non-living objects, for instance, seeing the face of Jesus in a cream cracker or the date of Apocalypse in Trump’s social security number. Though rationality makes conditions like Pareidolia seem utter nonsense, one can argue that wild-imagination has always fuelled pragmatic creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conspiracy theorists have been warning about a New World Order for decades, going all the way back to the isolationist critics of Franklin Delano Roosevelt. The New World Order or NWO is claimed to be a totalitarian world government led by a secretive power elite conspiring to rule the planet. Though it holds little significance whether any secret society wants to instigate a new world order or a group of power-hungry humans who want to control the world, it nonetheless merits some investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the New World Order?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New World Order is a supposedly autocratic world government (or a Cosmocratic government), which signifies the idea of having ONE central government for every country, institution and state in the world. A Cosmocratic style of government can come to power either through violent world domination or voluntary supranational union. Cosmocracy is a polity made up with recombinant structures that are themselves products of constantly changing, yet permanently unfolding processes. It is a moving target that produces unexpected and highly unstable targets. Though that is one way to look at it, there are numerous ways to perceive this form of world order. Having a single government for everybody will result in absolute harmony among different nations implying that most likely there will be no trade and nuclear wars, rather homogeneity will breed bonhomie between countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single government at the world stage may also ensure that after people become unbound from nature, they will create more anthropocentric forms of organizations, and one among them is democracy. Cosmocracy brings this cycle to a close and leads us back to the essential unity of all things - nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is something like the NWO feasible?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The likeliness of a Cosmocratic government’s rise to power is undoubtedly negligible, given the severe political and socio-economic turmoil it may bring. Any leader who is at the top of the world’s power structure and wields enormous power has a good chance of indulging in malpractices and corruption. The world surely cannot afford to give such power to a small group of individuals, because at the end of the day, they are just humans and have a good chance of becoming corrupt because of the unlimited power the position entails. Also, in the status quo, we live in a world in which people are inherently very proud of their cultural practices, which naturally results in any of their actions (at a macro level) aimed towards making their ‘nation’ great. In such a scenario, if we elect people from a particular country or even if we ensure that the Cosmocratic government is such which consists of equal representation from all parts of the world, there is no way we can eradicate personal bias towards their nations. This is a factor which defeats the purpose of having one government at a global level because if the leaders do not work to cater to the interests of all people across the world, the implementation of this new order will be futile. Moreover, setting up such a government is not pragmatic at all. We have around 200 countries in the world, albeit we cannot have 200 leaders at the world centre, so there has to be some type of filtration system to see from where the leaders are to be elected, which will naturally give the leaders from the first world nations an upper-hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, such a type of government may surely be beneficial in a post-apocalyptic scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the course of history, the most powerful advocates of change have emerged out of destructive circumstances. Citing some examples from history - the nation-state to geopolitics emerged from the Peace of Westphalia, which marked the end of the Thirty Years’ War (1618-48) in Central Europe. The political concept of balance of power gained greater importance with the Congress of Vienna, which emerged in the aftermath of the French Revolution and Napoleonic Wars (1792-1815). Besides, The League of Nations, a noble, yet short-lived experiment in circumscribing power competition, emerged from the First World War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transformation of the world order into a new world order may result from extremely farsighted diplomacy, for which diplomats and policymakers around the world will have to do more than push for incremental improvements within an inadequate system. A possibility entails that if not from diplomacy, the NWO may arise from an apocalypse, though it is terrifying to consider what might have to occur for a new order to emerge in this way, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Anshdeep Singh Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Social psychologists believe that feelings of frailty and uncertainty associate an individual with a tendency to believe in conspiracies”, said Karen M Douglas, Professor of Social Psychology at the University of Kent in the United Kingdom. Conceivably, it is true, to have something to lean on is an instinct to regain a sense of control, even if the conspiracy is unrelated to what caused the lack of control in an individual’s life. But what if this is just another conspiracy theory to dwarf all the other conspiracy theories? If you remember watching The Matrix, you would probably remember Mr Anderson (Keanu Reaves), an otherwise rational person making the leap from prudent paranoia to a not so illogical conspiracy, which led him to the dilemma of choosing between the red and the blue pill. There exists a gnawing feeling of not having control over your life - the dissatisfaction which hinders you from living your life to the fullest. And that is what happened with Adam Weishaupt, founder of The Illuminati. Born in 1748 in Ingolstadt, Bavaria, Weishaupt was a descendant of Jewish converts to Christianity. Orphaned at a young age, his uncle took care of his education. After completing his studies, Weishaupt became a Professor of canon law at the University of Ingolstadt, got married and started a family. He seemed to have a conventional career until 1784 when the Bavarian state learned about his distinct and provocative ideas. Since childhood, being an avid reader, Weishaupt was convinced that religious ideas were no longer an adequate belief system and hence, he decided to find another form of illumination. May 1, 1776 saw the first Illuminati meet in a forest near Ingolstadt to find the order and there, they established the rules that were to govern the order. The order was a set of scientific ideas and practices that could be applied to radically change the way European states were run. By the end of 1784, Weishaupt’s secret order grew considerably to 3,000 members and by the mid 1780’s, theIlluminati caught the Bavarian government’s attention, which put an end to the secret society. Weishaupt fled and gave up the secret shenanigans. What does the Illuminati want?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Role of Caste in Indian Elections</title>
      <link href="/The-Role-of-Caste" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Role of Caste in Indian Elections" />
      <published>2020-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Role-of-Caste</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Role-of-Caste">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Jaati na Poocho Sadhu ki, Pooch lijiye gyaan’&lt;/em&gt; is a part of a &lt;em&gt;doha&lt;/em&gt; (couplet) by an Indian mystic, poet and saint Kabir Das, which directly translates to – ‘Do not judge a saint by their caste, but ask for their knowledge’. Yet, this &lt;em&gt;doha&lt;/em&gt; is categorically ignored in Indian elections, when the most-asked question during an election is about the candidate’s surname, caste or religion and not what they have to offer or the values they will bring to the table. From political analysts to voters, everyone has this question on their mind, which is why the candidates standing in an election want to play their caste game right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what do you think of, when you first hear the word &lt;em&gt;caste&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be anything, literally. Albeit in the contemporary world, it mostly has a negative connotation attached to itself; being the sole reason for many ills which impair the world’s largest democracy. And, what is the caste system? It is an old social-stratification system that provides a hierarchy of social roles which hold inherent characteristics and, more importantly, are supposed to remain fixed throughout life. Even though Indian politicians didn’t create the mighty caste system, they surely know how to exploit this fault-line, exacerbating the caste animosities to build vote banks. In India, caste (and religion) is something people are very sensitive about and hence political parties face a difficult choice – they try to woo the oppressed castes in order to collect more votes. And in doing so, they antagonize some of the upper castes. Religiosity and tradition expect them to respect the caste boundaries, which is way too tempting to not exploit. A large number of parties draw up their poll strategies on the basis of the constituency’s caste demographic. Messages in the election speeches are tailored to suit the dominant caste of that constituency, and ideological coherence is sacrificed. And that’s why, while making the decision of choosing a candidate to represent them, voters tend to focus on caste and tend to overlook how adequately he/she would be able to represent them and focus on key issues. If a candidate belongs to caste X, his rival belonging to caste Y fields dummy candidates of caste X to divide the opponent’s votes. Caste determines the nature, organisation and working of most political parties, interest groups, and their functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of caste for gaining political popularity is not a new phenomenon and pre-Independence Indian politics also involved the use of caste, in different ways. The British Imperialists used religion as well as caste for political division of the nation. Unfortunately, even after Independence, India could not stop caste from becoming a factor that would influence politics. Even though the scenario is changing in urban India as voters are becoming more educated and aware about important issues, a large part of India still resides in rural areas, where people are not so much aware; for them, caste still plays a very important role in the election processes. Now, what can be the reason that people prefer to choose someone for their representation who belongs to their own caste rather than choosing someone who guarantees good work, amenities and development? It is because of an emotion – the feeling of belongingness. People tend to have an inherent desire to belong and be an important part of something that is greater than themselves; a relationship that is greater than simple acquaintance. This is a strong and inevitable feeling that exists in human nature. And due to this feeling, people have a strange natural trust that someone from their community, from their social group would be the apt representative for them; that he/she would protect them, provide them with opportunities and take care of them because after all, they belong to one big family, right? Sadly, that is not the case. Most of the times, this trust is taken for granted. Many political parties take advantage of these sentiments and fracture the society in such a manner that they gain from the divisions hence created; not to forget how deeply these divisions can damage the society. Politicians appeal to the sentiments of the voters of their respective caste groups and try to mobilize votes on that basis so as to capture and retain political power. Not only this, politicians have also managed to divert the attention of voters from issues relating to jobs, development, education, etc. by portraying caste as the paramount metric they should keep in mind while voting. The biggest harms of caste being involved in India’s electoral processes? There are many – incompetent leadership, ineffective governance, failed public policies, and most importantly, stagnancy. In a country where more than half of its population lives on less than 2$/day, it becomes highly important to make people realise the importance of proper representation and how it can change their lives. However, people are beginning to understand how such superficial factors are good for nothing and only poison the society at large. As is the case with any social evil, this is something which will require a lot of time and effort to be flushed out from the society, but that doesn’t mean it is impossible at all, right?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Anshdeep Singh Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">‘Jaati na Poocho Sadhu ki, Pooch lijiye gyaan’ is a part of a doha (couplet) by an Indian mystic, poet and saint Kabir Das, which directly translates to – ‘Do not judge a saint by their caste, but ask for their knowledge’. Yet, this doha is categorically ignored in Indian elections, when the most-asked question during an election is about the candidate’s surname, caste or religion and not what they have to offer or the values they will bring to the table. From political analysts to voters, everyone has this question on their mind, which is why the candidates standing in an election want to play their caste game right.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Stranded by the Sea</title>
      <link href="/Stranded-by-the-Sea" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stranded by the Sea" />
      <published>2020-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Stranded-by-the-Sea</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Stranded-by-the-Sea">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;Refugee&lt;/em&gt; is a term we read and hear about often, on the internet or the news and dissect into it like any other topic that we came across on a particular day. Be it the Syrian refugee crisis, the Afghanistan refugee crisis, people displaced in the Middle East fleeing to Europe for desperate rehabilitation, the partition of India or the result of a civil war. These are all issues originating in different parts of the world, delineated by boundaries and separated based on geography or the cause or origin of conflict. However, even though conflicts might vary in terms of nature- political, economic or social - it’s corollary remains immutable across borders and religion, that is, displacement of people and wreckage of homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve fled your country (or have been chased out by the majority population/authoritarian government), it’s nearly impossible to come back. The unsafe and riotous situation in certain countries caused by wars or feud creates conditions that make it fatal to a come back to a place they once called home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rohingya are one such community, facing persecution and fleeing from one place to another since 58 years, circa 1962.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of the persecution of the Rohingyas can be traced back to the colonization of India by the British, which endured for over 200 years. Tracing back to the British colonial period in the 1800’s, many people from India and Bangladesh were brought to Myanmar to work in the British led administration, doubling the Muslim community in Myanmar. This decision was received with acrimony by the local Myanmar people. This stands as one of the root cause of the animosity against the Rohingyas. During the World Wars, this hostility further deepened its roots since the majority of the Muslim population supported the British whereas the Buddhist population was predisposed towards the Japanese. This incongruity, as a result of the disparity between The Allies and The Axis Powers, aggravated the situation for the Muslim population in Myanmar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The official status of “refugee” is something the Rohingya people have struggled with for years now. In 1962, military rule became the norm and law throughout Myanmar. As a result, the Muslim population in Rakhine State was overpowered by militants and the Buddhist majority, thus causing the refugees to flee to Bangladesh. Since then, from 1962 to 2017 a large number of Rohingya people have migrated to the neighbouring countries, especially Bangladesh, having faced oppression in their own country. In 1982, an official Myanmar announcement declared 135 nationally recognized ethnic groups and the Rohingya were not included in the list, leaving them stateless and without citizenship. Further, in 2012 riots were waged against the Rohingyas and 200 people were killed while leaving 15,000 homeless and displaced. The Myanmar government even prohibited them from participating in the national census and the voting procedure during the elections. These acts of negligence, violence and repression continued till 2017 causing more than 600,000 Rohingya people to flee the Rakhine State since their communities were destroyed. But that doesn’t mean that things are any safer for them now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, there are some 860,000 Rohingya people seeking refuge in Bangladesh and at least 1.3 million people — Rohingya refugees and Bangladeshi host communities — who rely on humanitarian assistance to meet their basic needs. More than half of them are children. These populations live in desperately overcrowded camps and communities, highly vulnerable to oncoming monsoon and cyclone seasons, violence, sexual harassment and unhygienic environment. These camps provide them with less than the meagre amenities, leaving them to live a life of ignorance, in a vicious cycle of poverty, violence and substandard living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) and Médecins Sans Frontières (MSF) (also known as Doctors without Borders) describes the Rohingya as one of the most persecuted people in the world. The world we live in prides itself on its safety and peacekeeping system at the international level. Since after the Second World War, many nations came together and pledged to save vulnerable people and nations in crises. Yet, their (Rohingyas) struggle and oppression has been one of the most under-reported humanitarian crises in the world. The international media and community have practically ignored the situation of these people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all of this because of one reason, deeply entrenched in our parochial minds: ethnic animosity and conflict on the grounds of religion and historical beliefs of territory and ownership. This practice has left the Rohingya people without a beacon of hope for a better future. It has normalized a humanitarian crisis of this gravity, leading us to believe that it’s okay to treat a community of people with mindless hostility and utter disregard for their lives. (Because they might’ve done something to deserve it)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having faced persecution even in the camps of Bangladesh’s Cox Bazaar (and Myanmar, of course) the Rohingya people have made attempts to reach Malaysia, Thailand, Indonesia and other countries for years now. Since they lack visas, travel documents and are subjected to strict restrictions, boats are often the only option left for them to undertake transnational crossing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to MSF, it is estimated that around 167 countries across the world have fully or partially closed their borders during COVID-19 pandemic and 57 states made no exception for people seeking asylum. Even though closing borders is an acceptable reaction to the pandemic, not providing a concession for people looking for a refugee status amidst these tough times, stranded by the sea and in between nations is unacceptable. Countries such as Italy and Malta closed their ports for refugees and are using the excuse of the pandemic to reject refugees from entering their land and water borders. Several hundred Rohingyas fleeing persecution at home and refugee camps in Bangladesh have been stranded for months after countries sealed their borders to block the spread of the coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have reported that their relatives are stranded by the sea and their traffickers, holding hundreds of Rohingya refugees, are demanding money to release them from boats that have been off Southeast Asia since February, trying to find a place to land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Material cupidity has yet again taken precedence over humanity in a situation of a deadly life-crisis. The refugees travelling on these boats could hardly gather the money and documents to take this journey across the sea, and now with the pandemic having engulfed the world, they’re stuck on these boats, suffering, starving and seething in pain, waiting to get across any border to find some refuge and shelter from these treacherous circumstances. On top of this, they are being exploited for money in a situation of utmost helplessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To think why these people landed in such a chronic crisis, which has persisted for over five decades now; to think why we as a community allow and tolerate a humanitarian crisis at such a cosmic level. It is because somewhere deep down, we all have our own set of ideas and beliefs tied by social norms of caste, creed and culture. Because we all have ingrained the idea of &lt;em&gt;Us vs Them&lt;/em&gt;, so concretely in our heads that it’s almost impossible to break down those walls around us. But if there’s something that this pandemic has taught us, it’s that we’re all in this together. No problem is a standalone issue - it’s always linked to a larger affliction and it’s not outside the ambit of possibility for it to find its way to you. If we don’t untangle this issue as a community and for the community, it’ll always remain unresolved and will surface time and again.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A Refugee is a term we read and hear about often, on the internet or the news and dissect into it like any other topic that we came across on a particular day. Be it the Syrian refugee crisis, the Afghanistan refugee crisis, people displaced in the Middle East fleeing to Europe for desperate rehabilitation, the partition of India or the result of a civil war. These are all issues originating in different parts of the world, delineated by boundaries and separated based on geography or the cause or origin of conflict. However, even though conflicts might vary in terms of nature- political, economic or social - it’s corollary remains immutable across borders and religion, that is, displacement of people and wreckage of homes.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Western Media Texts</title>
      <link href="/Western-Media-Texts" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Western Media Texts" />
      <published>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Western-Media-Texts</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Western-Media-Texts">&lt;p&gt;The digital revolution of old media into new media has taken shape very rapidly. Old media has seldom been given its due recognition. Traditional sources of information like newspapers and radio have sustained their quality in truth telling for ages. Its comparison is unparalleled when it comes to new media, which is why it still has a wide market and is almost irreplaceable. On the other hand, new media rose to power because of its instantaneous quality to connect and communicate. News became easy to deliver as new media defined its timeliness. It has definitely changed the dynamics of public consumption of news, heralding a phase in humanity where everything can be reported, by anyone, and at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this has caused a severe decline in the ethics and philosophies of news providers. The power of creating news and gathering information is privy to distortion. Popularising preconceived notions as news is an emerging norm. This leads to misrepresentation and unfortunate consequences. The multiplicity of perspectives, opinions, and beliefs, entailing even factual wrongdoings, mixed with propaganda, has corrupted what was once considered an industry full of good samaritans. It is now a blotch on the entire concept of truth, information and news. Even traditional media faced this deterioration. The downward spiral of media credibility first footed at the advent of selling sensational news. The entire concept of ‘tabloidisation’ in garnering an audience, for the sake of business growth by corporations, led to a complete dilution in the way the public’s sensibilities allowed them to evaluate news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the media’s very history has dictated cultural behaviour throughout the course of time, it has become a core part of our lives. From newspapers to television networks to the abundance of information disseminated on social media, different types of media have both evolved and learnt to coexist. Thus, understanding the people and corporations behind these media networks, and the faces that decide news value, will further provide transparency in this respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Television is a writer’s playground, and online platforms only widen this space. The artistic freedom and the creative liberty that comes with it, was hitherto unheard of. So what would earlier be written for network audience traction is now developing into its own qualitative entity. All shows based on varied walks of life, using diverse plots, and being highly representative, have a loyal audience. Film and television also influence us in the most impactful ways. Therefore, the story and the way of storytelling employed is imperative to the niche audience it targets. When we talk about journalism and media, it is easy to assume how its machine functions. However, we hardly know the works behind the scenes. That is news nobody can tell us. We are oblivious to what goes into reporting a two minute segment, or a five page article. It always varies depending on the story, the source, the journalist, the editor, and the thousand inbetweeners that it takes to put a story out there. There have been innumerable assumptions around what a media workplace should be or how a journalistic practice must work, usually tied around speculation and hearsay. There’s seldom any representation within media texts portraying the media itself. Let us analyse two stand out accomplishments that tried to do it right, and well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Newsroom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Aaron Sorkin original, HBO’s &lt;em&gt;The Newsroom&lt;/em&gt; revolves around the dramatisation of a fictional news broadcast media network - Atlantis Cable Network. The name itself suggests that it is a fictional, idealistic world of the media elite. It is essentially a newsroom drama, a tale only seen panned out in movies before. Therefore, the scope for incorporating real time journalistic stories is high. And Sorkin knows how to merge that plethora of opportunity through witty dialogue and righteous ethical commentary. The plot revolves around some passionate workaholic journalists who only live by their virtues of delivering the unfiltered truth, without being bothered about the network ratings or audience commands. It is representative of what every journalist wants to be - equally intellectual and ethical - despite being held back by outside forces. The show reiterates that the value of journalistic integrity is above all else. It is a stark contrast to broadcast networks in real life, which are constantly required to entertain rather than provide information. In this day and age, ratings and viewership is highly important for a network to sustain itself. Thus, this show posits itself as an ideal of how every journalist wants to work and does not delve into a practical solution for how broadcast may allow its journalists to change that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The show tends to remain positive even during the darkest stories that have plagued the United States of America, by the up and coming celebration of democracy that the nation prevails to be. Its coverage of real time political events and serious stories, is not only well written but amazingly performed by the ensemble cast. While the show does not accurately portray broadcast networks in the West (and is especially inaccurate in doing that), it sure lives up to the narrative it is trying to convey - that which every network must strive to achieve. The show also satires and ridicules networks that have different ideologies and functions. Its constant snarky digs at &lt;em&gt;Thirty Mile Zone (TMZ)&lt;/em&gt; for exploitation, and &lt;em&gt;Cable News Network (CNN)&lt;/em&gt; for false reporting, is well-handled and brave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorkin’s masterful writing aids him in articulating some narratives within the media industry that need to be heard. For networks not just in the US, but even worldwide. Even if it’s not an accurate representation, the technical representation and the chaotic nuance of a newsroom workplace is on point. With some admirable takeaways from beloved performances of some truly heroic characters, the show does its job and does it well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Morning Show&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Apple TV+ venture, &lt;em&gt;The Morning Show&lt;/em&gt; represents a morning broadcast media show and what the happy rosy environment actually masks. Its script originally dealt with a common plot threading various stories in between, but it ended up changing to accentuate the overarching common storyline due to its relevance. Entailing the #MeToo movement, the show focuses on the alleged sexual harassment cases that women at the media house workplace suffered at the hands of a powerful lead anchor. The anchor is fired and denies the claims. While fictionalised, this premise is taken from what happened to Matt Lauer at the &lt;em&gt;Today Show&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It shows the complicity of the workplace environment in perpetuating the harassment. This is representative of not just media organisations but of any working environment. Through its complex characters, and dramatic plot twists, the first season does justice in representing the consequences of such unfortunate workplace incidents. It humanises every character involved and doesn’t judge through its writing. It’s everything that is expected from a gripping drama. The story explores the nuanced details of the #MeToo movement, but leaves the audience in suspense about the actual truth until the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its course, the show is riddled with characters that are dayside journalists, so the media premise is naturally different. Everything from the type of stories covered, to the positivity that it propagates, it is accurately representative of that broadcast niche. The lead anchors are shown being vain and self absorbed. But the entrance of a righteous journalist who enters this feel-good world, shakes the flow of the show. She has doubts about the kind of journalism this media group stands for. She has constant outbursts of journalistic integrity (much like she’s plucked out of the Sorkin universe), is absolutely apprehended by the overly narcissistic environment, and continually calls out the hypocrisies of the organisation. She acts as a conscience trope for journalism as a virtue. The news producer, and the owner have their own tensions and roles at the backdrop of the story. They show is well-balanced in its media representation that way and does for the media industry, what was long overdue. Gearing up for its second season, the show can further elevate or deteriorate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were some of the representations of new broadcast media in the West, and of the West, that were worth analysing due to their brilliant execution. The developing countries of the East, like India, are still short of well-made media representations. Recent releases like &lt;em&gt;Paatal Lok&lt;/em&gt; have stirred this conversation in a much-needed direction, by accurately representing the dichotomies and hypocrisies of Indian journalism and media. Being a fourth pillar to democracy, we mustn’t infuriatingly bash our media sources. A way of portraying gratitude is through such media texts, and encouraging that is reinstating our belief in journalism and truth-telling.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The digital revolution of old media into new media has taken shape very rapidly. Old media has seldom been given its due recognition. Traditional sources of information like newspapers and radio have sustained their quality in truth telling for ages. Its comparison is unparalleled when it comes to new media, which is why it still has a wide market and is almost irreplaceable. On the other hand, new media rose to power because of its instantaneous quality to connect and communicate. News became easy to deliver as new media defined its timeliness. It has definitely changed the dynamics of public consumption of news, heralding a phase in humanity where everything can be reported, by anyone, and at any time.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Against a Liberal Anti-racism</title>
      <link href="/Against-a-Liberal-Anti-racism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Against a Liberal Anti-racism" />
      <published>2020-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Against-a-Liberal-Anti-racism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Against-a-Liberal-Anti-racism">&lt;p&gt;The months following the killing of George Floyd saw sales of books about race increase by up to 6,800%. The top seller was Robin DiAngelo’s &lt;em&gt;White Fragility&lt;/em&gt;, which increased sales by over 400,000 copies from May to June this year, a startling increase of over 2,000%. DiAngelo, a ‘diversity consultant’, has since been invited to deliver keynote speeches, charging up to $35,000 for a two-hour workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DiAngelo’s central premise, that white Americans must reckon with their own implicit biases and engage in rigorous introspection to remedy them, appears less of a repudiation of centuries-old institutional racism than it does an instructional manual for white liberals working in corporate jobs to avoid getting into trouble with HR. It characterises racism merely as an antipathy felt by individuals towards other individuals, leaving untouched the edifice of America’s racist socio-economic structure. It fails to acknowledge that white supremacy is not simply the supremacy of white over black, but also the supremacy of rich whites over poorer whites who can be trusted to vote themselves into economic ruin in return for the illusion of superiority. And even more egregiously, it focuses attention on the self-aggrandising antics of the white liberal, repackaging the fight against racism as a culture war between educated white liberals and less educated whites, many of whom do not view themselves as the beneficiaries of ‘privilege’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the first Africans arrived in Virginia in 1619, there were no ‘white’ people there. It would be another 60 years before colonial records would describe the settlers as ‘white’, as the idea of the ‘white’ race was deliberately constructed by the ruling class as a form of social control, dividing poor European indentured servants and African chattel-bond labourers, assimilating the Europeans into the ‘middle class’, and preventing the likelihood of the reemergence of an event such as Bacon’s Rebellion (1676). Europeans and Africans had jointly demanded the imposition of a land tax and Virginia’s transition from a large plantation economy to a diversified economy of small freeholders, chasing the planter bourgeoisie to the shore and burning Jamestown to the ground. Ira Berlin stated that in the aftermath of Bacon’s Rebellion &lt;em&gt;“they enact laws which say that people of African descent are hereditary slaves. And they increasingly give some power to the independent white farmers and land holders”&lt;/em&gt;. Therefore, rather than being simply a form of prejudice on the basis of skin colour, racism can be understood as a complex form of social control. Theodore W Allen’s book &lt;em&gt;The Invention of the White Race&lt;/em&gt; made a similar argument that racism is a “sociogenic” rather than a “phylogenic” phenomenon, analysing how the (phenotypically similar) British used racial oppression against Irish Catholics, later allowing the Irish Catholic bourgeoisie to assimilate into the oppressive structure, accepting the disenfranchisement of the forty-shilling freeholders in return for meagre ‘emancipation’ in 1829.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, liberal anti-racism of the DiAngelo variety, largely devoid of this analysis, becomes an exercise in narcissistic self-indulgence on the part of white liberals, who reframe discussions about race in terms of how they can be better people, and how it is incumbent on all whites to unlearn their white privilege. As this approach to anti-racism fails to acknowledge how racism functions as a tool of socioeconomic disenfranchisement by the ruling class, it assumes that all whites benefit equally from white privilege, ignoring and minimising the plight of working-class whites. A 2019 sociological study by E Cooley, etc. found that learning about white privilege did nothing to increase empathy for people of colour among white liberals, but simply made them less likely to empathise with poorer whites, placing greater personal blame on them on the basis that their privilege outweighed other social factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, reactionary and racist ideology abounds among the white working class, and this article is not intended to downplay such attitudes or pretend that they do not exist. It is to argue that if there is a hope that cross-racial solidarity can be achieved, and these reactionary tendencies extinguished, it will not be accomplished by lecturing working-class whites who are beset by low wages, deindustrialisation, and the opioid epidemic about their ‘privilege’, but by encouraging them to recognise that they have more in common with other races than with elites of the same race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term ‘class reductionist’ is consistently deployed against socialists who recognise that racism and capitalism are intimately connected as if this recognition downplays the significance of racism. But some of the most pernicious forms of American institutional racism, such as redlining and the prison-industrial complex, have explicitly capitalistic imperatives. For example, exclusion from ‘prime’ credit has forced black communities to secure housing through subprime loans and substandard rental accommodation. During the subprime lending boom, predatory loans were five times more likely to be made in black neighbourhoods than in white neighbourhoods, while black Americans were four times as likely as white Americans to be denied loans from the Bank of America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations such as the Blackstone Group have conspired to engage in predatory lending practices, buying up houses at cheap prices and selling them on for higher prices or charging exorbitant rents. Invitation Homes, a subsidiary of the Blackstone Group and a prominent lender to black communities, may have broken laws to give tenants loans that maximised profits as they could easily outbid first time buyers. It is issues such as these, the pervasive, material disparities which have concentrated generational wealth in the hands of white communities and generational disadvantage in the hands of black communities that should be the focus of anti-racists, not trivial ideas such as ‘white fragility’. These are not injustices that can be solved simply by more representation of black people within the highest echelons of power, but only through the de-privatisation and de-commodification of housing at a minimum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another consequence of viewing racism through a reductive, individualistic lens is the over-medicalisation of the problem, which treats racism as a pathology on the part of its perpetrators. As Kenan Malik writes, &lt;em&gt;“It was not unconscious bias that made a police officer place his knee on George Floyd’s neck”&lt;/em&gt;. A meta-analysis of nearly 500 studies found that unconscious bias training only had a “weak” effect on the behaviour of individuals. Reframing racism as a product of original sin, an aberration that could never be held by ‘normal’ people simply absolves those who are responsible for perpetuating it, as racial bigotry can, and often is, the product of a sound mind. The Nazi war criminals at Nuremberg, for instance, all tested as medically sane, had high IQs, and included a disproportionate number of PhDs. Far from being the irrational judgement of an insane mind, racism is the mendacious, calculated judgement of the elites who perpetuate it, to provide a constant stream of alienated unfree labour from those they impoverish, to divide and conquer and to subjugate. Only an approach that acknowledges the systemic and institutional manifestations of racism can grasp this central point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The systemic racism on which the United States was founded, that still exists today, cannot be expunged with ‘unconscious bias training’ or the recognition of white fragility. The injustices will remain, but white corporate consultants such as Robin DiAngelo will become very rich. What is required is not white guilt but white solidarity on a mass scale, such as has been seen in the recent protests, and a recognition that, as Karl Marx stated, &lt;em&gt;“Labour in the white skin cannot emancipate itself where in the black it is branded.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The months following the killing of George Floyd saw sales of books about race increase by up to 6,800%. The top seller was Robin DiAngelo’s White Fragility, which increased sales by over 400,000 copies from May to June this year, a startling increase of over 2,000%. DiAngelo, a ‘diversity consultant’, has since been invited to deliver keynote speeches, charging up to $35,000 for a two-hour workshop.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
