<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/society/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-04-23T17:33:01+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/society/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Puppets of Patriarchy</title>
      <link href="/Puppets-of-Patriarchy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Puppets of Patriarchy" />
      <published>2020-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Puppets-of-Patriarchy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Puppets-of-Patriarchy">&lt;p&gt;I wake up every morning as a woman in this society, a child of the upper-middle-class, privileged and comfortable in my warm bed. I have the option to choose the course of my day as I like, as do most of the women in my surroundings. However, a lot of us forget amidst the warmth of our mornings that our choices or rather the right to choose weren’t granted to us on a platter of silverware. It has been a long, arduous, gory fight since the beginning of time. From colossal watershed moments like wars and suffrage to societal acceptance, from voting rights and the combat against harassment to as minuscule a subject as walking freely on the streets in a pair of your favourite blue jeans. The world hasn’t been a wish-granting factory for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most men &lt;em&gt;used to, still do, and always will&lt;/em&gt; wake up every day in a society that doesn’t refer to them as ‘The Second Sex’. They don’t have to walk the face of the earth with gills to breathe with on land. And in those moments when you forget what the millions of women, forgotten and faded through history, gave up, the ones who asked &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; and refuted with a staunch &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;, take a swift sift through the past that screams for you to protect this privilege. Yes, it’s a privilege, even if it shouldn’t have been because respecting another human being and walking with them instead of trooping ahead should be as easy as shutting your eyes close and lapsing into sleep. Instead of morphing this system into a more accepting and wholesome one, it might just be easier in a parallel world, where we can go back 200,000 years in time and reset the trail of human life on earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is my statement to everyone who has ever questioned me as to why we need feminism anymore. To those who still foolishly think of it as a process with an end date, a time when everything will be idyllic and we’ll stop the ‘train of feminism’. To those who question the label that it has gained over the last few decades, mindless of the fact that it was them who pejoratively stamped in that way- both men and women. Men, who are scared and alarmed at the thought of a world where their kind doesn’t dominate and take precedence anymore but exists in an unruffled state with the environment with all people, all genders. And the women who have so long been repressed and rewired that they don’t think that openly breathing is an option anymore. And to everybody who thinks that feminism is a struggle against men,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I vehemently disagree, for these people are way off-target. For two reasons- because I reckon women aren’t in the least powerless, let alone tenuous in front of any gender. And secondly, for those who think that men aren’t subjugated in this society are starkly mistaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patriarchy is a friend to none, no gender; be it men, women or non-binary. It feeds and thrives on the politics of power and authority and throttles whatever comes in its way. Men who aren’t ‘masculine’ enough, women who are too ‘brazen’, ‘impure’ castes and races, and everyone who doesn’t fit inside their box; the icy-cold, suffocating box with pores impossible to permeate, into which it shoves all who refuse to conform to the beliefs of gender. Gender, which is just a socially constructed idea, gradually fabricated into a sheath of rules and norms, which in actuality is as abstract an idea as complex numbers, perhaps. Apart from the normal human physiology that describes a person’s sex, no science explains the attributes we innocently anoint to the ‘two’ genders. They say women are calm and understanding, whereas men are temperamental and impulsive. &lt;em&gt;Of pinks and blues, cooking and driving, dominant and submissive, on top, on the bottom, floral and solid;&lt;/em&gt; gender is a &lt;em&gt;role&lt;/em&gt; perfected intricately over years, contingent on patriarchy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judith Butler, a renowned gender theorist, contends that being female is not “natural” and that it appears natural only through repeated performances of gender; these performances in turn reproduce and define the traditional categories of gender. Maybe Shakespeare was right, maybe the world is a stage and we’re all mere players, nay, puppets of patriarchy. These roles assigned to us are bolstered into a cemented building, so tightly plastered that any attempt to subvert that structure is considered a convulsion of the society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stereotyping is the soul food of human civilisation, especially when it comes to gender. And a simple explanation for it could be the fact that it is easier on the brain to stereotype, in other words, a heuristic. When faced with a decision to be made quickly, our brain doesn’t have the time or resources to compare all the information before making a choice, and so people often rely on mental shortcuts known as representative heuristics. Stereotyping stems from these heuristics and when inculcated as a habit or unwittingly imbibed since an early age, can be spotted in children as young as six years old. If you take a neutral environment and raise two different sexes with the same treatment and knowledge, bereft of these norms, they will grow up to be free of gender stereotypes. The girl might not necessarily pick up the doll and the boy the copter, but if they do, it will be out of a liking, a choice and not a manoeuvred stereotype that the society has comfortably sunk into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patriarchal violence is not solely against women but nature as well, and when we stand up against the Satanic cousin that is patriarchy, tearing down this concrete-helix structure, we emerge loyal to the posterity and to the planet itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the foundation of ‘Eco-Feminism’, first ideated in the late 1970’s and early 1980’s. Eco-feminism is about connectedness and wholeness of the abstract and the actual. It asserts a special strength and integrity of every living thing. Vandana Shiva, a radical eco-feminist from India has changed the conception of this idea in her analysis of links between the degradation of women and the exploitation of nature in modern social setups. It highlights the gall of patriarchy to dominate and destroy not just ‘anything that isn’t masculine’ but the environment we’re living in. Both women and the environment are undervalued in our global system and economies and both are very essential elements of our world, if we are to see a changeover to a more inclusive and sustainable economy. Better use of the world’s female population would increase economic growth, reduce poverty, enhance societal well-being, and help ensure sustainable development in all countries since women have a smaller ecological footprint than men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fight hasn’t gotten any easier than it was before. It started with earning the rights and the place we deserved. And after a good 100 years, only six countries in the world give other genders absolute equal rights, the World Bank found out. And they ask what more do we need? Others do state those (hollow) rights in their constitution, but they don’t uphold them. So now it is about taking those values into everyday life and making them as real and tangible as possible. The fight now is to break down the barrier of being referred to as ‘The Second Sex’ and locomote to a non-ordinal world, where genders aren’t ranked, defined, suffocated, and bifurcated into pink and blue. Instead, they can breathe and identify themselves through the way that they feel and not necessarily their sex, manifesting through a rainbow of colours.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I wake up every morning as a woman in this society, a child of the upper-middle-class, privileged and comfortable in my warm bed. I have the option to choose the course of my day as I like, as do most of the women in my surroundings. However, a lot of us forget amidst the warmth of our mornings that our choices or rather the right to choose weren’t granted to us on a platter of silverware. It has been a long, arduous, gory fight since the beginning of time. From colossal watershed moments like wars and suffrage to societal acceptance, from voting rights and the combat against harassment to as minuscule a subject as walking freely on the streets in a pair of your favourite blue jeans. The world hasn’t been a wish-granting factory for us.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Echoes of the Estates-General: A Comparison between Ancient Regime France and 21st Century America (Part II)</title>
      <link href="/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Echoes of the Estates-General: A Comparison between Ancient Regime France and 21st Century America (Part II)" />
      <published>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General-II</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General-II">&lt;p&gt;The similarities between 18th century France and modern America apply not only to the background to the French Revolution but to the early stages of the Revolution in which a moderate, professional bourgeoisie sought to consolidate their power and stem the tide of economic and political radicalism emanating from the peasantry and sans-culottes. This article chronicles the various aspects of this divide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Representative Problem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tim Blanning, writing in &lt;em&gt;The Pursuit of Glory&lt;/em&gt;, argued that the French Revolution “wrapped into one explosive package the three great abstractions of modern politics: the People, the State, and the Nation”, and that “the French people announced their arrival as the main actors in the nation’s political life.” That sovereignty resided in the nation and that Louis XVI was answerable not to God but to the constitutional law of the State (for the first part of the Revolution anyway), were principles that would lead to the self-assertion of the French people, as mass participation in assemblies and demonstrations and universal conscription under the Jacobins meant that they could no longer be ignored. But for the first part of the Revolution, representation was monopolised by the most middle-class, reformist elements of the French society. America today suffers from a similar problem, as the DNC continuously props up Joe Biden’s campaign, and acts as an obstacle to any substantive change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Estates-General sat on May 5, 1789, Louis XVI having had little choice over its convocation following the difficulties in levying taxes and rents on an increasingly recalcitrant peasantry, coupled with the fears of the bourgeoisie that the loans they had made to the State might not be paid back. The Third Estate was represented by 610 men, about 1/6th of whom were capitalists and bankers, and many of whom were lawyers, indicating that despite representing 95% of the French people, the Third Estate exclusively advanced the interests of the educated middle classes. As such, the Declaration of the Rights of Man and the Citizen, which Lafayette consulted Thomas Jefferson in drawing up, was a crystallisation of Enlightenment principles that affirmed the universal power of reason, the ability of man to surmount all obstacles and control his own government and society, and the principle of equality before the law with noble privileges abolished. Article IV of the Declaration stated that liberty constituted anything that did not harm others by infringing on the rights to liberty, property and security and that only the rule of law could delineate these boundaries. Private property remained a ‘natural right’, and the unchecked ability to accumulate capital and influence the political process did not infringe any of the aforementioned negatively-defined ‘rights’, and so was sanctified by law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Eric Hobsbawm, “A constitutional monarchy based on a propertied oligarchy expressing itself through a representative assembly was more congenial to most bourgeois liberals than the democratic republic which might have seemed a more logical expression of their theoretical aspirations.” The demands articulated by the peasantry for the restoration of communal lands and material prosperity could be ignored, and by August 10, 1789, the bourgeoisie had taken up arms against the peasantry in Dauphine and Burgundy. Characterising peasant agitations as the work of ‘brigands’, the troops were called out to crush all men without professions and domiciles. This brutality saw 160 prisoners killed at Cluny, and 80 hanged in Lyon. Following the storming of the Bastille and the August 4 reforms that established equality in taxation and admission to public office, in addition to the redemption of manorial lands, it was clear that the peasantry and sans-culottes were the vessels of social change, repelled by bourgeois anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The glaring flaws in a supposedly ‘representative’ system have also shown themselves in the recent Democratic primaries, where Bernie Sanders’ campaign has cratered. In Iowa last month, the app meant to coordinate the results of the Caucus mysteriously crashed, and it later transpired that the app was built by a for-profit company named Shadow Inc. that Pete Buttigieg’s campaign had paid millions of dollars. The US Constitution, like France’s Declaration of the Rights of Man, protects the rights of private business to hike prices, depress wages and lock other competitors out of the market, and the rights of political institutions such as the DNC to sabotage the electoral process in favour of candidates who are more conducive to a capitalist economic setting. Nothing legally prevents the DNC from limiting the number of debates and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/us-politics/bernie-sanders-democratic-primary-dnc-convention-superdelegates-nomination-2020-election-a9363626.html&quot;&gt;blocking Bernie Sanders from winning the nomination.&lt;/a&gt; The freedoms of speech and voluntary exchange are theoretical abstractions that give way to the realities of market competition and the profit motive, as while individuals enjoy the superficial freedoms to participate in democracy, the real power lies in the hands of multinational corporations or nepotistic political behemoths like the DNC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two Shades of Moderation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moderate voices within the National Assembly, who would later go on to form the Legislative Assembly in 1791, recognised that their interests were broadly in line with a limited monarchy, rather than a democratic republic. In what became the National Constituent Assembly, a class of propertied ‘active citizens’ formed a constitutional monarchy that banned trade unions and guild corporations, instituted the enclosure of communal lands and sold off ecclesiastical domains. These reforms were designed to create an internal market for goods, rather than to satiate the demands of the peasantry, as the ensuing price fluctuations led to agitations in rural areas. The distinction between the property-owning moderates of the Legislative Assembly who favoured opening up internal markets and creating a class of landless agrarian wage-labourers, and the peasantry and sans-culottes who favoured the communal ownership of land and higher income and inheritance tax was becoming more evident. The storming of the Tuileries and the establishment of the National Convention in 1792 was the apotheosis of this struggle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The incompatibility of moderate defenders of the status quo with the vast numbers demanding transformative change is also characteristic of the schisms between Bernie Sanders and his supporters with the centrist Democrats. Much like the Girondins and moderates in the National Constituent Assembly, Joe Biden and his supporters pretend to rail against the corruption and despotism of the Trump administration while obscuring how much they have in common with the Republicans. In addition to his already disastrous record of voting in favour of NAFTA, supporting the war in Iraq and playing a key role in the war on drugs that has devastated many families (particularly Black and Hispanic), Biden continues to oppose Medicare for All, even suggesting that he would &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politifact.com/factchecks/2020/mar/10/facebook-posts/when-biden-was-asked-if-he-would-veto-medicare-all/&quot;&gt;veto it if it passed both houses and came to his desk.&lt;/a&gt; Furthermore, the centrist Democrats and Bernie Sanders’ supporters are separated not only by policy disagreements but a profound and seemingly irreconcilable divergence in worldview. The centrist Democrats are consequentialist; it is unsurprising that a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2020/03/suburbanites-are-backing-biden/607726/&quot;&gt;base of primarily middle-class professionals&lt;/a&gt; are concerned with results and efficacy above all else, and maintain that the ends (beating Trump) justify the means (nominating Biden). Much like the bureaucratic moderates in the Legislative Assembly, the centrist Democrats view capitalism as a natural accompaniment to their utilitarian, consequentialist worldview. If one believes that man is a rational, utility maximising agent entering into voluntary exchanges with others, then the consequences of mutual trade and transaction are all that matters, and anything not amenable to the rationalist calculus of profitability can be discarded. Bernie Sanders’ supporters are more ideological (and, indeed, deontological), advocating for transformative measures such as Medicare for all and the abolition of ICE as ends in themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must be mentioned, however, that the situation in France that enabled the storming of the Bastille in 1789 and the Tuileries in 1792 is not entirely analogous to the modern American situation, as the peasantry and sans-culottes in France represented a broadly unified coalition, committed to establishing communally-owned land and preventing monopolisation and speculation. They had both suffered the effects of inflation and famine during the 1770’s and 1780’s, and both saw their enemy as the nobility and bourgeois professionals. The American working class, by contrast, remains divided along racial lines, as well as on geographic and occupational lines. &lt;a href=&quot;https://aese.psu.edu/directory/smm67/Election16.pdf?wpisrc=nl_daily202&amp;amp;wpmm=1&quot;&gt;A study from Penn State University&lt;/a&gt; showed that Donald Trump performed best in swing states that were worst affected by deindustrialisation and the opioid epidemic, and had experienced employment losses over recent decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The political divisions between professional, liberal capitalists who sought to make an existing system more amenable to their interests and the disaffected masses who sought radical change are common to both late Ancien Regime France and 21st century America. The disillusionment with the machinery of governance that led the sans-culottes to believe that the Estates General did not represent them also motivates many Bernie Sanders supporters who view the DNC as an obstacle to power. If the French Revolution was the time for the French people to assert themselves as a prominent force, then the coming economic depression may foreground the schism between unrepresentative political institutions and the people they have disenfranchised.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The similarities between 18th century France and modern America apply not only to the background to the French Revolution but to the early stages of the Revolution in which a moderate, professional bourgeoisie sought to consolidate their power and stem the tide of economic and political radicalism emanating from the peasantry and sans-culottes. This article chronicles the various aspects of this divide.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Chaos and Order—How to Bring the Ego to Equilibrium Through an Act of Metamorphosis</title>
      <link href="/Chaos-and-Order" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chaos and Order—How to Bring the Ego to Equilibrium Through an Act of Metamorphosis" />
      <published>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Chaos-and-Order</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Chaos-and-Order">&lt;p&gt;I would like to begin this article by an act of meditation, and would also like to humbly ask you to participate in this process by allowing your mind to freely explore the depth of your imagination and to make links, connections and associations between the following words. Please allow the following words to gently hover in your mind as you are reading this article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;chaos, order, uncertainty, self-discovery, death, rebirth, transcendence, the ego, your grounding, metamorphosis, culture, creation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As human beings, we are all struck by existential problems—we do not know where we come from, we do not know why we are here in this mysterious world, and we also do not know where we are going. All the advances in knowledge should not lead one to be deceived about how much we don’t know. Far too often we like to claim knowledge or understanding because certainty keeps us sane and helps us in our survival. If we all wake up in the morning and start questioning our lives and our choices really honestly as we go through our days, we will be held suspended in a state of inertia and existential angst. There is a point where we act on our beliefs even though we are not sure about them. And, herein lies the conundrum of our lives: we all know that we don’t know but we act as if we know. What is the solution? Or a question to be asked first, is that, why is it that most people from the learned to the unlearned, from the sane to the insane, from the poor to the rich, often act and behave in a manner as if they somehow know the ‘truth’?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As animals, human beings are part of the fabric of the evolutionary processes, and as such, much of what we refer to as ‘me’ is simply the by-product of the evolutionary processes. Specifically, in the cortex of the human brain, even though we don’t understand it fully, there are a few observations we can make. Firstly, that in its process of evolution, the two hemispheres of the brain have been both specialised for certain specific functions, with the right hemisphere being the one that is involved in the acts of exploration that opens us up to possibilities, and the left hemisphere being the one that seeks to tie itself down to certainty (see &lt;em&gt;The Master and his Emissary&lt;/em&gt; by Iain McGilchrist). And, the constant interplay of these two hemispheres can be understood as the brain trying to balance between chaos and order. With chaos being that which is beyond our understanding, or that which we do not understand; and order being the polar opposite, that which is within our grasp, or that which we do understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already we can see from evolution’s point of view that it would be overwhelming for the human mind to perceive all the realities surrounding it, and just like the importance of forgetting, it is also important that we only receive certain sensory data from the world in the form of perceptions. And, as evolution is concerned with our survival, the brain also evolved such that it only perceives realities that concerns it for its survival, and as we have already observed, the left hemisphere, and indeed about 25% of the entire brain’s context acts as an inhibitory mechanism. In other words, the brain as observed by Huxley (see &lt;em&gt;The Doors of Perception&lt;/em&gt; by Aldous Huxley) blocks off much of the sensory data produced by the surrounding environment. Now we have addressed the first question, which was that, why do humans act as if they know the truth—simply because our brains give us a very convincing illusion of reality (an incomplete picture of reality, not inaccurate!). Here also lies the problem of the ego, as much of the ego is the result of complex evolutionary processes which formed for a multiplicity of reasons such as self-defense, survival, dominance, self-identify and many more factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, from the very moment we are born, we are inhabited by the spirit of our ancestors, so to speak - a metaphor of this long evolutionary process. The brain of a human child is then nourished and developed through one’s upbringing into his family, society and above all into his culture. This is where the biological foundations of the ego are then built on by the culture. A simple example is the universal thirst for economic prosperity; once a biological drive for survival, it is now transformed to a culturally ego-driven desire to consume with ever-more new products being created for such desire, and with much emphasis being placed upon the acquisition of objects, and sometimes people for that matter! In fact, most aspects of culture are about the creation and maintenance of boundaries and order—and what is the driving mechanism that fuels culture? — The ego of course! It is as deep as the dawn of humanity, it is ancient and present in every single human being. The ego is self-centered, it advocated for its own growth at the cost of everything including nature herself—no reference is needed in the current ecological disaster where man cannot stop himself from constant exploitation of the environment. In short, as Terence McKenna once said, “The ego will become like a cyst if left untreated”, and I actually think that the ego is more like a tumor, that if untreated, it will lead to collective seizures which gets manifested in forms of natural disasters, human bloodshed, exploitation of others, and ultimately, the destruction of our world. And, culture far from balancing this toxic order as fuelled by the ego with the feminine spirit, it further strengthens the ego and advocates for the continuation of its survival. Only after the times of major collective disasters (eg: global pandemics), will we see major change in our attitude towards each other and towards our environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But parts of the ego is necessary. In the book, &lt;em&gt;Thus Spoke Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt;, Nietzsche explores the necessity of the first stage of human metamorphosis, which he represents as the camel. He writes: “the weight-bearing spirit takes upon itself all these heaviest things: like a camel hurrying laden into the desert, thus hurries into its desert”. Understanding the camel as human beings and the weight that is being carried as tradition and culture, it is a natural stage of man’s development where we acquire our self-identity and become a slave to our cultural values. However, the solution as advocated by Nietzsche’s character as represented in the second and third state of man’s metamorphosis is that of the lion, and then the child. Once we have nourished and developed our ego and learnt the wisdom of the past, it is time to doubt them with a spirit of courage (the lion stage), and then, finally, we must participate in a process of self-discovery, self-exploration, and above all to create one’s own values (the child stage). Thus, the act of creation, and constant death and rebirth of one’s values and beliefs is necessary for the final stage of man’s metamorphosis. But Nietzsche’s abstract ideas can also lead to the re-growth of the ego as one is in total freedom to create one’s values, so why not to create novel ego-driven values? This is where man’s true and complete act of metamorphosis must be in direct harmony with the spirit of nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, I have delineated the history and the origin of the ego and its processes of development within culture, and explained how the ego becomes not only toxic to ourselves but also to nature herself. But, I also indicated why the ego is necessary and inevitable, it need not be destroyed but it requires to be treated through acts of metamorphosis. Now a question which we asked in the beginning, what is the solution? All these abstract ideas of self-transformation seem all well and good but none are of any practical use. And, that is why the practice of ego-dissolving activity in shamanism is necessary if the ego is to be treated. The other solution as we already alluded to is to wait for major disasters so that the ego can observe the effects of himself, and in an act of pathetic self-preservation, mutate and change course, but don’t be fooled, this is only for the short term. Whereas, activities like community, love, caring and connecting to nature and each other, connection and the bringing together of people on the internet, the use of psychedelic plant medicines all act as a cure for the toxic elements of the ego. Particularly, the proper use of psychedelics in its shamanic context with right intentions can bring about a shift in consciousness and a dissolution of the ego such that our values become aligned with planetary values—that of care and love for nature and one another. The chaos that psychedelics introduce into the cultural machinery is one reliable way to bring the ego to equilibrium. But, as I have already indicated, the ego need not be completely dissolved but only treated, as we do need our personal identities and we should be grateful for some of the achievement of the ego like our advanced civilization, or my act of writing this very article until 5 am in the morning for a girl that I have a crush on.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Omidvar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I would like to begin this article by an act of meditation, and would also like to humbly ask you to participate in this process by allowing your mind to freely explore the depth of your imagination and to make links, connections and associations between the following words. Please allow the following words to gently hover in your mind as you are reading this article:</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Sexism and the City</title>
      <link href="/Sexism-and-the-City" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sexism and the City" />
      <published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Sexism-and-the-City</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Sexism-and-the-City">&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that this big bad world is biased towards the people with both the X and Y chromosomes, thanks to the patriarchy that has upheld the ideas of male superiority. These biases further suggest that women are inferior because of their sex. Thus, any expression upholding these biases can be termed as — ‘sexist.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sexism can affect anyone, however, there have been few men on the receiving end. It affects men and boys when they don’t conform to gender roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this article, we will restrict the ambit of our discussion to only the University level in India. Sexist attitudes are not just limited to boys rating girls on a scale of 0-10 based on their physical appearances. It has transcended into limiting the opportunities for women, imposing draconian rules and observing traditions that are misogynistic and chauvinist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often consider academia as the citadel of everything fair and progressive. However, we don’t live in a utopian world. Just like other institutions that have these notions of male superiority deep-rooted in their practices and norms, so does education. Many people benefit from these power dynamics in the status quo, and thus, have no incentive to change it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a stark imbalance in the male to female ratio in many courses such as law, management, and STEM disciplines. Considered the holy grail of education and achievement, Indian Institutes of Technology (IITs), suffer from the worst gender imbalance with only 9.3% of females. This gap further increases with progression in these careers, with an utter lack of women in leadership positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see this trend across central universities in India. Out of 46 central universities, only 5 have women placed as the heads of the institutions. Even in India’s most liberal universities, like Jawaharlal Nehru University (JNU), no women has ever been the head of the institute. The selection committees are dominated by men, who give little weightage to women candidates as many view women as someone who has stolen a job a man was entitled to do. This perception has risen from the cultural view that men are the bread-earners of the family while women are the homemakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In colleges with extreme gender disproportion, the environment becomes testosterone-driven, leading to women students being subjected to sexual innuendos and sexist remarks. Language and communication make people recognise or demean their contribution to society. Our language shapes our thoughts, and the way we think influences our actions. Gender-discriminatory language reinforces sexist attitudes and behaviours. Thus, female students become conditioned to accept subtle sexism and lewd remarks as the norm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sexism in Indian universities isn’t just limited to leadership positions but encompasses norms that affect the day-to-day lives of many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many colleges across India, dress codes are imposed on women. For example, The Government Medical College, Kerala issued a dress code for its female students instructing them not to wear jeans, leggings, short tops or noisy ornaments. Many girls’ hostels also follow curfews, thus increasing the red tape for them to step out. Many institutions like Jamia Milia University, IITs and the University of Delhi have come under the light in the past for such rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such draconian measures show how expecting equality remains a far-off dream for girls. These rules concretise the notion that the price for the safety of women is curbing their freedom rather than bringing a systemic change in the attitude of men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Symbiosis Center for Media and Communication (SCMC) Pune is widely recognised for its option of ‘film and television’ specialisation as a part of its three-year undergraduate program. In her article for &lt;em&gt;The Print&lt;/em&gt;, Vaishnavi Suresh, an SCMC alumnus highlights the rampant sexism in the coveted institution. Being a media college, the students spend a large amount of time in classes watching films. Vaishnavi, however, notes how the students barely had any female filmmakers as role models. In an incident where some people from her class suggested they study a female filmmaker, the professor shot down their requests and instead taught them about another male filmmaker. She also noted how by the time they came to their 3rd year, only 2 women out of her batch were still invested in the camera by practising photography or videography. She cites the reason for this to be the “reality of the industry drilled into them constantly.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A college that prides itself on being liberal lacks showing its students that women could be role models too. Having female role models is important for breaking the stereotype of men being better than women to propagate for a more inclusive world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016, while the #MeToo movement was still in its nascent stage, the students of Women Centred Practices at Tata Institute of Social Sciences (TISS), Mumbai organised a ‘Gender Sensitisation Week’ in their campus. Amidst the gender sensitisation week, a signed comment was noticed on a banner that was put up for people to anonymously share accounts of sexist instances on campus. It read, “Sexism is an accusation, sluts level against dissenting voices for recognising that a slut is a slut.” Instances like these make one realise that the notion of some campuses being ‘more sensitive and liberal than the rest of the world’, is nothing but a facade. People still trivialise sexual harassment, use the word ‘slut’ as a derogatory term and push aside voices of dissent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2019, a few pre-university colleges in Bengaluru set higher cut-off marks for girls for admission into the courses. On inquiring about the reason behind this move, the Vice-Chancellor of Christ PU College, Fr Abraham VM, commented - “Girls are smart, and this is not a new trend. If there is no higher cut-off, the college will have only girls. The higher cut-off is to bring in gender balance.” Subsequently, the cut-off for science stream in Christ college was fixed at 93.92% for girls and 91.04% for boys. This move begs the question that in a society where historically almost every classroom has been dominated by men, why do we fear if women step into those shoes. It seems like a move to &lt;em&gt;punish&lt;/em&gt; women for breaking the glass ceiling despite being on the worse off end of the access to opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the most famous sexist tradition would be the regressive Virgin Tree ‘Pooja’ on Valentine’s Day at Hindu College (University of Delhi). The Pooja is a customary tradition wherein the boys’ hostel decorates a ‘virgin tree’ on campus with condoms and posters of an actress naming her the Damdami Mai. This actress, seen as a sex symbol, is ‘worshipped’ on Valentine’s Day and according to legend, the people partaking in this practice lose their virginity in the coming six months or at least get into a relationship. In a university space, where we regard sexuality-related conversations as a taboo, they often term such a celebration as ‘liberatory.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The V-Day pooja, which has been taking place since 1953, is ridden in a Brahmanical and casteist notion of prayer and reward. Highly offensive and misogynistic, the pooja follows a hollow notion of ‘sex-positivity’ while overlooking homosexual relationships. The celebration reinforces the existing patriarchal structures which have ingrained insecurity in the minds of young women by reducing their value to just the pleasure of and determined by an external male gaze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;College is the first encounter of the young adults with reality by giving them a peek into the larger world out there. It introduces us to the workings of the ‘real world’ and underpins many of our perspectives and expectations in a social context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sexist practices create a climate of fear and insecurity by producing feelings of worthlessness, self-censorship, and changes in behaviour. This further leads to the deterioration of people’s mental health and makes them acceptable to violence, as they now think they &lt;em&gt;deserve&lt;/em&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When students are exposed to these ideas in college, it either normalises these ideas for many by ingraining notions of male superiority. Or it makes people recognise and fight the problem. The wave of social consciousness and woke culture have made the youth today more liberal than their predecessors, leading to more inclusive spaces for women and homosexuals in institutions. They, however, remain a minority faction and their wokeness hasn’t led to a ripple effect big enough to shake down sexism on a bigger level. The boy’s hostel at Hindu College plans to host the Virgin Tree Pooja in 2021, many girls’ hostels continue to follow the archaic dress codes and curfews, and conversations among men will continue to be casually sexist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All over the world, people have celebrated 46 International Women’s Days and 6 Zero Discrimination Days and will celebrate many more, but until we abolish all discriminatory and sexist practices, we won’t be celebrating these days in their true essence.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It’s no secret that this big bad world is biased towards the people with both the X and Y chromosomes, thanks to the patriarchy that has upheld the ideas of male superiority. These biases further suggest that women are inferior because of their sex. Thus, any expression upholding these biases can be termed as — ‘sexist.’</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Pink: The Hated Colour of Love</title>
      <link href="/Pink-The-Hated-Colour-of-Love" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pink: The Hated Colour of Love" />
      <published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Pink-The-Hated-Colour-of-Love</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Pink-The-Hated-Colour-of-Love">&lt;p&gt;The first image that props up in your mind when you think of the word ‘pink’ is probably a dainty young lady wearing a pretty pink dress. Indeed, for many people, especially girls, this colour represents weakness or ‘girly-ness’ because of what it has been associated with in recent years. The negative connotations associated with being ‘girly’ are very similar to the way in which we perceive most of the other so-called feminine words or traits. We have always associated the female gender with characteristics that are intrinsically inferior to those associated with the male gender. While females are seen as weak, submissive, caring and sensitive, males are seen as brash, well built, hard-working people with strong control over their emotions. “You fight like a girl”, “stop crying like a girl” and so on and so forth are very common in our conversations even today and they reflect the inherent mindset of the people in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pink represents a lot of rather adverse aspects of society in the eyes of many. One of the most important among them is the pink aisle in toy stores. This lane is meant only for young girls and is thus decorated accordingly, using the colour pink. Similarly, the lane meant for boys is decorated primarily using blue. A closer look at the items on display and for sale reveals a lot about us and our society. The blue lane has miniature construction kits, motor cars and so on: all toys that boys are ‘supposed’ to play with. Likewise, the pink lane houses a collection of kitchen sets, dolls and miniature makeup kits. What is happening here is subtle but significant. Not only are we, as a society, pushing a conventional binary structure of the gender system on our children, but we are also dictating what each gender is meant to be like. In other words, we are laying down the basis of gender roles from a very early age. Laura Bates, the founder of ‘Everyday Sexism’ believes ‘pinkification’ spreads the message that “women cook, men work”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While girls are expected to be obsessed with makeup, enjoying cooking and babysitting dolls, boys are directed towards tech using gender-specific toys. Research by the Institute of Engineering and Technology in 2016 suggests that STEM-based toys are three times more likely to target boys than girls. Jess Day of ‘Let Toys be Toys’ actively advocates for toys to be not categorised by gender for the same reason. In 2016, she was quoted saying: “We previously asked women engineers and scientists about the toys they played with as children and the most interesting find was not that they all played with construction or science toys, but they didn’t recall being aware of a distinction between girls’ and boys’ toys at all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This problem has been well addressed by Debbie Sterling in her TEDxPSU speech. She started her presentation by asking the audience to close their eyes and to imagine an engineer. She then asked them to tell her by a show of hands how many imagined a woman in that role. The number was underwhelming. In her roughly 17 minute long talk that followed, she quoted different researches to drive home the point that the problem of the astonishingly low number of women in STEM careers is not a biological issue but a cultural one. She attributed the loss in interest in science and technology among girls to the pink aisle. Sterling explained how she came to this conclusion by sharing stories of her own struggle as an engineering student. Being a very creative girl, she did not expect to find a course titled Engineering Drawing to be difficult and yet she did find it so. This course involved drawing in perspective and the guys in class excelled at it. She, however, had to put in a lot more effort to pass the course. Sterling explained that this is a rather common phenomenon and can be attributed to the fact that most girls have under-developed spatial skills. The majority of those who do well in spatial skills tests grew up with construction toys, irrespective of gender. The market did not, however, have construction toys targeted at girls. It was just not seen and is still popularly not seen as a ‘girly’ thing to do. Sterling went on to build an extremely popular construction toy for girls named GoldieBlox which featured the world’s first girl engineer character in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another such pink related thing that women are not very happy about is the Pink Tax. This tax is not always a literal tax. It is a form of gender-based price discrimination observed today. Feminine versions of everyday items like razors and deodorants usually cost more than those meant for males. In fact, feminine hygiene products are astonishingly expensive in most countries. This includes menstruation hygiene products like sanitary pads and tampons. Research in the USA in 2019 by the New York City Department of Consumer Affairs revealed that women pay 13% more for personal health care products, 8% more for adult clothing, 7% more for toys and accessories and 4% more for children’s clothing than men. There are a lot of issues with this pink tax, especially since it seems as if the structure is penalising one for being born female. Menstruation is an essential human bodily process just like any other and to pay such high amounts for menstruation hygiene products is borderline oppressive. The main economic impact of this phenomenon is that women have less purchasing power, especially considering the fact that a gender-based pay gap already exists. Although recent activism in this matter has seen some positive outcomes in terms of repealing the pink tax in certain places like in Ohio, the price discrimination continues to exist in most other places in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is apparent that there are abundant instances where pink has been associated with something that not many are happy about. One thing that is bluntly clear is that this colour has been largely used to describe things, both positive and negative, that are related to the female gender. This notion of pink being only for girls is pushed on us over and over again. The pink ribbon is used to symbolise and raise awareness for breast cancer. The teenage section of Victoria’s Secret is named ‘Pink’. A 2016 Indian film about a molestation case filed by a woman was titled &lt;em&gt;Pink&lt;/em&gt;. This recurring appearance of pink in connection with the female gender has successfully established this shade as a predominantly feminine colour. Women are almost expected to like and wear pink and its variations and yet, there are conditions that come with it. People often criticise dark-skinned women seen wearing pink and other related shades. This really does not make any sense and might just be an expression of an additional stereotype that dark-skinned women are loud and confrontational, characteristics that the society does not believe goes well with the feminine gender. Conversely, women who do love pink and sparkles, as the stereotype suggests, are seen as weak, submissive, obsessed with appearance and unprofessional. Many have tried to destroy this image over the years. In 2019, a female scientist named Rita J King opted for an eye-catching sparkly ensemble to give a talk at NASA. This evoked both positive and negative responses from across the world. King later explained her decision later by stating “I came across this gown and remembered the little girls who sent me a letter and asked me to wear something sparkly… so they could believe that scientists could also be sparkly.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of all this, movies popularly continue to portray women who love wearing pink as rather dumb, mean or maternal and any exception to this rule becomes a big deal - the idea is treated as the most important aspect of the plot and the movie is deemed as unusual and female-centric. All this is in spite of the fact that the nerd of the class, irrespective of gender, in any random school, can be a pink lover. It is almost an unspoken crime to portray them in the regular teen flicks that way and the female lead as a blue lover. The Pink Ranger is always the ‘girliest’ female in the group. The high school princesses who have spent their entire lives waiting to be crowned the Prom Queen and are always mean to other girls are more often than not seen wearing pink. Somehow in the movie world, blue and black lovers are never popular or ‘girly’. Have a look at the posters of &lt;em&gt;Mean Girls&lt;/em&gt; and other similar teen flicks for proof of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notable exceptions include movies like &lt;em&gt;Legally Blonde&lt;/em&gt;, where a pink loving, makeup obsessed, popular and beautiful fashion student named Elle goes on to become a successful lawyer. However, this transition happens only after she is dumped by her boyfriend, Warner Huntington III. Warner prefers to be with an all-blue or black wearing ‘serious’ woman who is studying law as it would improve his image in the real world. Elle cracks the LSATs and joins her ex-boyfriend’s college, Harvard Law School to win him over. Over the course of time, she realises how much of a terrible person her ex-boyfriend was and the sexism that exists in the world of law. One thing that is praiseworthy about this movie is that although Elle goes on to become a successful lawyer, she does not give up on her fashion-obsessed side-love for pink. In fact, Elle wins her first case using her knowledge of how a specific beauty procedure and its maintenance work and a fashion stereotype involving the gay community. Now, this might seem like she is being portrayed as someone whose knowledge is strictly restricted to the domain of fashion and that her winning the case was a fluke but she is previously shown as a hardworking and knowledgeable law student.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have established the popular notions about the colour, let us talk about the several problems associated with this narrow view of pink. The laundry list begins with the fact that pink was a masculine colour for a very long time. It was established as a feminine colour only around the 1940’s. In 20th century Europe, the most common practice was to assign colour based on the complexion of the child and thus, any of the genders could be associated with pink or blue. Paintings from the 19th century show young boys wearing pink. In the 18th century, pink was actually seen primarily as a masculine colour as it is related to the ‘war-like’ red colour. A 1918 article published in &lt;em&gt;The Infants’ Department&lt;/em&gt; titled ‘Pink or Blue’ stated that the generally-accepted rule was that pink was for boys and blue for girls. It said, “The reason is that pink, being a decided and stronger colour is more suitable for the boy, while blue, which is more delicate and dainty, is prettier for the girl.” It is actually very difficult to pin-point when in history this role reversal of the colours took place. Baby boomers were probably the first to be dressed in the modern sex-specific coloured clothing that we are familiar with today. This took a hard hit during the women’s liberation movements of the 1960’s-70’s when the female participants of the movement started developing a view that dressing up stereotypically ‘girly’ would limit their opportunities and consequently, parents started preferring gender-neutral colours. However, the practices involving gender-specific colours are pretty prevalent even today and the numerous fancy gender reveal videos on social media bears testimony to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another very popular pink symbol from the past is the pink triangle. Back in the Germany of the 1930’s and 1940’s, the Nazis not only prosecuted the Jews but also several other groups of people. Homosexuals were one of them and this symbol was used for identification just as the David’s Star was used for the Jews. Bisexuals and transgenders were also included in this category. Back then, it was a symbol of utter shame. Later, in the 1970’s, it was revived as a symbol of protest against homophobia. Its popularity increased manifold in the 1980’s as the pink triangle established its place as a positive icon: a symbol of self and community identity. It commonly represented both the gay and the lesbian communities. The rainbow pride flag that we have come to popularly associate with the LGBTQIA+ community was originally designed by Gilbert Baker for the 1978 San Francisco Gay Freedom Day and had eight stripes. This version was soon replaced by the seven stripe version that we use and see today. The original flag had an additional pink stripe that was symbolic of sexuality. In fact, pink is very popularly associated with all kinds of love. No wonder Taylor Swift’s Lover era pieces are an explosion of pink. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, pink is fast-tracking its way to become a symbol of the feminist movement. Various activists and artists have made generous use of this colour to complement their views and activism. Let us take an example: American singer, P!nk aka Alecia Moore. She declared herself as a feminist long before any other popular artist, long before it was ‘in’. In 2006, she criticised Republican President, George Bush in her song titled, &lt;em&gt;Dear Mr President&lt;/em&gt;. The song’s lyrics like “What kind of father (parent) would take his own daughter’s rights away? What kind of father (parent) might hate his own daughter (child) if she were gay?” is an expression of her beliefs, her support for women’s rights activism and her support for the LGBTQIA+ community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, she has shared several stories of struggle and change on different platforms. The most memorable of these is perhaps her 2017 MTV Video Music Awards speech after she won the Michael Jackson Vanguard Award. She shared a story of her daughter who had once conveyed to her, “I’m the ugliest girl I know” and that she thought that she looked like a boy with long hair. That day, Pink sat down with her and talked to her about great artists who look very different especially androgynous artists, like Freddie Mercury, David Bowie, Prince, Michael Jackson, Kurt Cobain, Janis Joplin and so on. She also told her about the negative comments that she herself receives about her rather boyish look and the fact that that does not stop her from making great music and selling out arenas. Her message is clear: how one looks or dresses has nothing to do with one’s capacity to excel at something. Similarly, wearing pink does not make anyone any less of a capable person or any less of a feminist as the title of Scarlett Curtis’s book, &lt;em&gt;Feminists Don’t Wear Pink and Other Lies’&lt;/em&gt; suggests. By extension, being fashionable and ‘girly’ does not intellectually handicap anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alas, we are pretty far away from this realisation. In 2016, a young graphic designer named Katherine Young re-created the cover of &lt;em&gt;Girls’ Life&lt;/em&gt; magazine. The original cover that featured Olivia Holt and articles like ‘Your Dream Hair’ and ‘The ‘New’ Denim Checklist’ changed into one that featured Olivia Hallisey (2015 Google Science Fair winner) and articles like ‘Your Dream Career’ and ‘The ‘New’ Dreamer Checklist’. This was widely appreciated. However, what I don’t understand is this: why can’t a life magazine targeted at young females feature both ends of the spectrum- articles on fashion and other career choices? Secondly, it seems rather demeaning to view a successful actress with perfectly done make-up and fashion-forward outfit less accomplished or symbolic of an empowered woman than a girl with a successful STEM career. I agree that STEM girls are fewer in number and they do not get as much support, but bringing down one girl to pull up another is a bad strategy. What is required is a balance - women should be represented in all fields and all kinds of interests should be equally catered to and appreciated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that most of the pink related problems that exist today exist because of our distorted perceptions of the colour and the undertones that cling onto the word. Associating the colour with conservative notions of gender is an utter disrespect of a shade that for years has symbolised love of all kinds and has represented all genders. While the issue will continue to persist until men start wearing pink casually in movies and in real life and women proudly wear feminine clothing in pastel shades without getting undermined, a lot of progress has been made over the last decade. Only time can tell us if we are capable of reaching a pedestal where we no longer associate a specific colour with a particular gender or certain traits&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The first image that props up in your mind when you think of the word ‘pink’ is probably a dainty young lady wearing a pretty pink dress. Indeed, for many people, especially girls, this colour represents weakness or ‘girly-ness’ because of what it has been associated with in recent years. The negative connotations associated with being ‘girly’ are very similar to the way in which we perceive most of the other so-called feminine words or traits. We have always associated the female gender with characteristics that are intrinsically inferior to those associated with the male gender. While females are seen as weak, submissive, caring and sensitive, males are seen as brash, well built, hard-working people with strong control over their emotions. “You fight like a girl”, “stop crying like a girl” and so on and so forth are very common in our conversations even today and they reflect the inherent mindset of the people in general.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Women are Under-represented? Not News.</title>
      <link href="/Women-are-Under-represented-Not-News" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Women are Under-represented? Not News." />
      <published>2020-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Women-are-Under-represented-Not-News</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Women-are-Under-represented-Not-News">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I only go to a movie if it satisfies three basic requirements. One, it has to have at least two women in it, who, two, talk to each other about, three, something besides a man.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1985, a new edition of the comic strip &lt;em&gt;Dykes to Watch Out For&lt;/em&gt;, called ‘The Rule’, first introduced the ‘Bechdel Test’ to the film industry. The writers portrayed the character as avoiding cinema with an extreme male bias, with the character in the script claiming that she hasn’t been able to watch a movie since the 1979 space horror film &lt;em&gt;Alien&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a society where patriarchy has been the dominating narrative, it’s no surprise that women’s representation in the film industry (or any industry, for that matter) is lacking. Looking at statistics from the past few years, women play only about 37% of roles on television (2015). In films, the percentage of speaking roles for women drops to 28% (2012). Women make up a mere 16% of directors, writers, producers, and editors (2013).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many are unaware that gender stereotypes are not just linked to the costumes but are intrinsic to a character’s conversations, actions and traits. To understand how grave the situation is, the Test proves to be helpful. The Bechdel Test is a convenient way to gauge the active presence of female characters in films and just how well-rounded and complete those roles are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On listening to what it takes for the movies to pass the test, one might think: “This seems easy, I bet most movies pass it.” And that’s what I expected. But on researching more on the topic, the number of popular movies that couldn’t pass this simple test turned out to be astonishing. At the 2014 Academy Awards, only three out of the eight nominees for Best Picture passed the Bechdel Test: &lt;em&gt;Boyhood&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Theory of Everything&lt;/em&gt;. Corresponding to research by Duke University in 2017, over 40% of all the films in the US failed the test. The team used data from the bechdeltest.com website, a user-compiled database of over 7,000 movies where volunteers rate films based on the Bechdel criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These results show the under-representation of women’s complex lives in the film industry. The Bechdel Test’s demands set a low bar for the filmmakers to meet and they start a conversation about gender inequality in film. The test has brought to light the importance of shifting the focus from men to the other things in a woman’s life: career goals, friendships, inner troubles, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the test comes with its own set of problems. A film passing the test doesn’t mean the movie automatically becomes one that the feminists support. The Bechdel Test can be a misleading gauge of ‘feminism’ in movies. Films with a strong female lead don’t provide a supporting female character who holds enough importance to converse with the lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many movies that pass the test, do so based on a ‘technicality’: in some inconsequential scene, the women have a small conversation about something other than men, therefore fulfilling the criteria. For example, &lt;em&gt;Gravity&lt;/em&gt; featuring a female astronaut doesn’t pass the test. However, &lt;em&gt;Legally Blonde&lt;/em&gt; does because Elle and her friend talk about their dogs in a scene or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female characters have followed the same tropes. The movies make women damsels in distress or a ‘manic pixie dream girl.’ They also sexualise women, forcing them to wear tight-fitting clothes and heels throughout the movie. Adjectives about physical attributes like beautiful, gorgeous and pretty are used to describe the female characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another common trope used is called ‘fridging’ wherein the female characters are injured, raped, killed, or depowered, sometimes to stimulate ‘protective’ traits in men, and often as a plot device intended to move a male character’s story arc forward. &lt;em&gt;Women in Refrigerators&lt;/em&gt;, a website created in 1999 by a group of feminist comic-book fans lists examples of this trope. It refers to an incident in &lt;em&gt;Green Lantern #54&lt;/em&gt; (1994), in which, the title hero, Kyle Rayner, comes home to his apartment to find that his girlfriend had been killed and stuffed into a refrigerator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, however, is not the sole test. The ‘Mako Mori Test’ requires that: The film must feature at least one female character, who has her narrative arc that does not depend on supporting a man’s story. Likewise, the ‘DuVernay Test’ determines a film’s racial diversity. It checks if the minorities have realised lives rather than serving as scenery in the stories of the whites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these tests prove to be like the Bechdel Test as they provide data about representation but cannot provide a coherent picture if the film is feminist enough. Some critics argue that the problem lies in the disagreement about what it means to be a ‘feminist film.’ Because of this, forming a one-size-fits-all test for judging feminism has been difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female representation worsens across intersectionality. Under the broader umbrella of female characters, there are even fewer black females, Latina females, Lesbians or Transgenders. Hollywood executives have knocked dark-skinned women to the side in favour of those with European features and pale complexions. ‘Colourism’ isn’t, however, unique to the black community. In the Bollywood film industry, too, the starring roles go to lighter-skinned actors. Many of them also endorse fairness creams and other similar products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the 2018 USC Annenberg Inclusion Initiative study, out of the top 100 films in 2017, 43 films didn’t include any African-American female character. Sixty-five films were missing Asian or Asian-American female characters, and 64 didn’t include a Latina character. Ninety-four didn’t feature characters with disabilities and LGBTQ characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representation is significant for all communities. However, more than representation, it’s accurate representation that is important. Accurate and well-rounded representation allows people to see a world outside of themselves, fostering critical thinking and empathy with those who are different. The stereotypes don’t allow for the representation to portray the full picture of the complexities of the surrounding people. Because of the aspirational value that pop culture holds, it becomes a cunning, persuasive and pervasive educator. As an educator, it has the power to shape views and opinions about how people look at themselves and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representation in the film industry, however, isn’t just limited to on-screen representation but also extends to those who are working behind the camera. Figures published by &lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt; have revealed that only 22% of the crew involved in making 2,000 of the biggest grossing films over the past 20 years were women. Further, the report revealed a split in responsibilities: women made up a majority only in costume and wardrobe departments and casting. These departments have been perceived as feminine workplaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue deepens when you take into consideration the wage gap between the actors and actresses. &lt;em&gt;Forbes’&lt;/em&gt; analysis of American acting salaries in 2013 determined that the top-paid actors for that year made 2½ times as much money as the top-paid actresses. This means that Hollywood’s best-compensated actresses made just 40 cents for every dollar that the best-compensated men made. Women who have spoken about the issue explain the reason for not demanding higher pay as “they worry about seeming difficult or spoiled.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her 2018 Oscar speech, Frances McDormand suggested an ‘inclusion rider’, a clause in contracts meant to stipulate that 50% of a film crew had to be female. If A-list actors put this clause into practice, the film industry could portray the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Film producers and showrunners have, however, started to take charge. In 2015, the film professionals started the “Bechdel Bill” campaign, who pledged that 80% of their films will pass the test. CW also incorporated the Bechdel Test in two of its shows: &lt;em&gt;Crazy Ex-Girlfriend&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Jane the Virgin&lt;/em&gt;. Despite both shows not passing the test, the move was symbolic as the network constructed a space in which discourse could take place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This discourse can challenge Hollywood to do more than settle for the status quo and to question the absences of many types of people from the movie-making process. These people could potentially enrich our entertainment in countless ways, both on the screen and behind the lens. A post &lt;em&gt;#&lt;/em&gt;MeToo and #TimesUp world has the potential to hold Hollywood accountable and challenge the oppressive structure to demand a more inclusive industry that isn’t hegemonised by cis-white-men.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“I only go to a movie if it satisfies three basic requirements. One, it has to have at least two women in it, who, two, talk to each other about, three, something besides a man.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Explo-Consciousness: The Science, Phenomenology and the Implications of Psychedelic Experience</title>
      <link href="/Explo-Consciousness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Explo-Consciousness: The Science, Phenomenology and the Implications of Psychedelic Experience" />
      <published>2020-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Explo-Consciousness</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Explo-Consciousness">&lt;p&gt;Since the 1930’s, with the discovery of LSD (Lysergic Acid Diethylamide) by Albert Hoffmann, and much later, with the introduction of Psilocybin mushrooms (magic mushrooms) to the west by Gordon Wasson, there has been much heated debate on the topic from all disciplines. The true history of psychedelics is as old as our evolution, and some like Terrence McKenna have even proposed that human beings developed their unique characteristics, especially that of our deep awareness and self-consciousness as a result of the consumption of varieties of psychedelic plants, especially the psilocybin mushrooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, the advent of many religions is also very likely associated with the experience of psychedelics due to the similar character of religious experiences. This view is further confirmed by the fact that, evolutionary speaking, almost all primates consume mushrooms found in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My purpose here is not to draw attention to the medical benefits of these substances; that is the job of the scientist, but I am mostly here to describe what we call ‘the psychedelic experience’, and to finally go into a theory that I have been deeply thinking about, which is called: ‘Explo-Consciousness’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before anything, it is of great importance to explore the science of these substances. Both LSD and Psilocybin are psychedelics, meaning, mind-manifesting or mind-expanding substances. These substances, unlike most recreational drugs, do not increase ‘the pleasure chemicals’ like dopamine, and as such, they do not possess any addictive properties. Instead, they are called serotonergic substances; meaning that they bind with serotonin (the receptor responsible for mood and sleep regulation). When ingested, they alter the user’s perception, and interestingly they bring about hyper-connectivity within the brain as the following diagrams show:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//brain-connectivity.png&quot; style=&quot;display:inline; text-align: left; width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two diagrams are the representation of the brain state; (a) is the state of someone who has been given the placebo with few neuro-connectivity, whereas (b) is the brain on psilocybin. This research, carried out by the Imperial College Centre for Psychedelics, is the first time we have understood, using brain scans, that, on psilocybin, the brain becomes hyper-connected. This hyper-connectivity is also understood to suspend the brain’s ‘Default Mode Network’, which is somewhat equivalent to the ‘ego’ or the ‘self’. The DMN is what provides you with a theory of who you are, and it is particularly active when one thinks about the past or plans for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The over-activity of the DMN is closely correlated with mental illnesses like depression and anxiety, as, roughly stated, the former is in relation to being stuck in the past, and the latter is in relation to worrying about the future. This is, perhaps, what explains the experimental medical use of psychedelic substances to treat anxiety and depression, as for a short while a patient is, simply put, taken out of the prison of the judging and destructive self. As a result, they develop new perspectives about themselves. Such results could also be novel and life-changing for older people, as they too become imprisoned by deeply structured patterns of behaviour and belief. In short, ego dissolution or the suspension of the DMN is not only good for treating mental illnesses but could provide most people with new perspectives in extremely profound life-changing experiences. Such profound experiences were observed in many studies carried out by the John Hopkins Institute, for those of you interested to look further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, when describing the psychedelic experience, one must necessarily possess a new language or form of expression, if one is to truly communicate these experiences. And, this is only possible if one enters through ‘the doors of perception’ and arrives in the place, beautifully described by Rudolph Otto, as “the wholly other” with a unique sense of “&lt;em&gt;Mysterium tremendum et fascinans&lt;/em&gt;”. This is a place where all previous beliefs become trivial and one is then struck by a sense of mystery that is infused by feeling of the holy; both imitating love and terror. One feels in union with God, if God means anything! There cannot be anything in the realm of visual and emotional experience that is more spiritual or religious than the psychedelic experience. The experience, for many, takes the turn of a true and meaningful conversation with this energy or cosmic-consciousness. As a result, if the experience is integrated, the profundity of the experience, whether positive or life-changing, can remain with the voyager. And, if negative, it can be managed with integration; hence why it is necessary to have an experienced guide when taking these sacred substances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own experiences with mushrooms have always been profound; especially the second time when I took a huge dose of 6 grams of dried Liberty Caps&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; I probably should have taken less, perhaps 4 grams. As with any psychedelics, ‘&lt;em&gt;set and setting&lt;/em&gt;’ is more important than the substance itself. My ‘set’ (state of mind) was that of a readiness to have a spiritual experience but it also expected to be terrified. And, my setting was a dark quiet room with a comfortable bed that I laid on after ingesting the mushrooms. Indeed, I was alone…and it was in this environment that I experienced the wholly other. This was my fourth time, so I saw no need for a sitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about 20 minutes, I felt like my body was warming-up, in a strange spiritual sense. It was as if my body was preparing to travel to another dimension; I felt uneasy and excited at the same time. I was like a snake shedding its old skin, and subsequently after 1 hour, all my recent life-choices came in front of me from a different angle. I saw where I went wrong…. I saw and understood my recent errors or areas in life that I had not paid attention to. All of us know our weaknesses and faults but the DMN or the ego stops us from truly accepting, comprehending and feeling them. We may even admit to other people that we are in the wrong but deep in the foundation of our beliefs, we always manage to convince ourselves that the other is in the wrong. But, this time was different. This time, I gained the power to truly separate myself from my ego, and then from those eyes looked and analysed my mistakes and weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This internal feeling was neither judging nor merciful. It was, rather, like being able to look at all my infirmities with a naked eye that was free from all contaminant lenses, so pure and honest! Imagine looking through the window and seeing the disorderly garden of one’s house. Normally, we are moved by emotions such as disgust, sadness or even perhaps the urgency to clean and organise one’s garden. In my experience, there was only the observable garden and its disorganised state, I was like God just observing… After some time of seeing and understanding all my faults, I was then touched by this divine sensation of love that communicated to me that “it’s ok”. This was the most profound moment in the entire experience where I deeply felt that I didn’t have to be oppressed by my past faults and mistakes. The experience was not only meaningfully self-exploratory but deeply healing and transformative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a long time, the purpose of human beings has transcended survival. It seems that all human cultures have understood the importance of knowledge, whether practical or theoretical. Similarly, all cultures have also understood the importance of experience not only as an activity that is fun and enjoyable but also as something that is deeply related to the human essence. In fact, these two things are not separated, but it is clearly observable that knowledge is also a derivation of either direct experience or reflections of experience. As such, the meaning and purpose of human beings is directly intertwined with experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, the more we have access to different repertoire of experiences and the more we live as humans, the closer we get to completeness of what humanness really means. It is also likely that the process of becoming more human is akin to transcending the current reality of the essence of man. In other words, such an evolution or transformation pushes one to become more than a human. One who has more, has more and is perhaps more prosperous, but one who ‘becomes’ more, he transcends himself, even surpassing God himself. For God supposedly created man…now man can constantly re-create himself and ascend at a place that God himself could never attain. For God’s essence is fixed and his nature unchangeable. All varieties of human experiences offered to us by the world (both positive and negative) is a necessary condition if one were to attain such transformation. It occurs to me after my own study and experience that the ‘psychedelic experience’ is the most profound of all possible human experiences; and yet most modern societies have demonised these sacred substances. The function of the ‘mushroom’ and other sacred plants is teaching and they are the wisest of all teachers as they teach you to think for yourself. Other than this, and many other profound functions that these plants play, they also freely gift you the most challenging and life-changing experiences, and these are not only healing but also what one needs for a true spiritual awakening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;em&gt;Explo-consciousness&lt;/em&gt; simply means the explosion of consciousness, and this seems to be the essence of the psychedelic experience. In an explosion, there is death and rebirth and hence why we can participate in a constant process of becoming and hence the human being can attains such transformation that even God himself cannot. In every explosion, there is death and destruction but with the explosion of consciousness, death gives way for the resurrection of something new, of something spectacularly novel and beautiful. With the explosion of consciousness, one realises that one is in union with everything and is nothing at the same time; this is the place of the mystic…it is where they live and breathe…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the question is, do you prefer a life full of indoctrination and culturally sanctioned values; a life whose contents have been determined by others? Such a life is comfortable as it requires no self-examination and self-exploration of one’s authentic self. When one enters in the psychedelic realm, one realises that the essence of man is so much more than just the ego, which is the construction of society and culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, true enlightenment is a lifestyle and not a destination; true enlightenment is the process of constant death and rebirth of the self and what we refer to as the psychedelic experience does just that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Terrence-McKenna.png&quot; style=&quot;display:inline; text-align: left; width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;I want to dedicate this piece to the great Terrence McKenna whose ideas have helped me integrate my psychedelic experiences!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Omidvar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Since the 1930’s, with the discovery of LSD (Lysergic Acid Diethylamide) by Albert Hoffmann, and much later, with the introduction of Psilocybin mushrooms (magic mushrooms) to the west by Gordon Wasson, there has been much heated debate on the topic from all disciplines. The true history of psychedelics is as old as our evolution, and some like Terrence McKenna have even proposed that human beings developed their unique characteristics, especially that of our deep awareness and self-consciousness as a result of the consumption of varieties of psychedelic plants, especially the psilocybin mushrooms.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Televising a Revolution: How Fiction Animates Reality</title>
      <link href="/Televising-a-Revolution" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Televising a Revolution: How Fiction Animates Reality" />
      <published>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Televising-a-Revolution</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Televising-a-Revolution">&lt;p&gt;In the past two weeks, the city of Delhi saw the rise of a mass movement of agitation and protest against India’s controversial new law, the Citizenship Amendment Act (CAA). This movement also reacted strongly against the proposed National Register of Citizens which the Indian Home Minister Amit Shah promised would eventually be implemented across the country. In many of these cities, students were the torch-bearers of these protests. Not long after it became crystal clear that a large section of the populace, especially the youth, was extremely dissatisfied with these decisions by the Indian government, violence broke out primarily &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; students at Jamia Milia University in Delhi, a premier, sought-after institution for humanities in the country. Reports began to pour in of instances of extreme police brutality against the rising protesters, not only in Jamia, but also in other institutions as well as outside colleges and universities. A large part of the student fraternity, not just in Delhi, but all across India, took this to heart and attempted to take a peaceful stand against what they believed was a clear instance of abuse of power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is not meant to be an analysis of the Act or the social implications that follow. More able people have done it, and I feel no need for me to add to them at present. What stood out to me, though, was how largely mainstream pop culture was being co-opted to make a point about how problematic the Act was, or why you could never justify the violence against students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big criticism of my generation, the millennials, has been our unhealthy obsession with binge-watching, and a subsequent laziness to do anything else as a result of that. It is often perceived as a valueless activity, because all you are signing up for is your entertainment. More often than not, you will sacrifice either sleep or studies to watch the next episode of your favourite show on Netflix or some other streaming website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This month, however, not only did students take to the streets, often in defiance of the wishes of their parents and relatives, but they also synthesised their image of being slaves to digitalisation along with rebellion. They proved that they were never really glued to the television for the sake of it. Rather, they were constantly learning what was better about the rest of the world through these shows. They formed better ideals of what was socially acceptable, and decided to carve a narrative that argued for more equality. To be fair, this change has been occurring for a long time in social media. The passing of this Act was the nudge that propelled even those people who would otherwise rather not speak their minds to take a public stand for what they believed was the right thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest example of this was how many people drew parallels between the current government and the attitude of the erstwhile headmaster of Hogwarts, Dolores Umbridge from &lt;em&gt;Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix&lt;/em&gt;. A few pages from the book were mass-shared on Instagram and Twitter, when today’s teenagers, who may not have felt politically charged before the violence, realised that fictional ideas could still have possibly real-life origins. Memes took the front when it came to creative ways of taking out frustration. “Ok boomer” spread like wildfire, when our generation was trying to bridge the gap between their elders and them when it came to truly understanding the government’s intentions. ‘This episode of Black Mirror sucks’ was too close to home. ‘Orange is the New Black’ had become an apt phrase. And, since it was Christmas time, Mariah Carey and vines from a time gone by (&lt;em&gt;Merry Crisis&lt;/em&gt;) decided to feature into the parade. This author’s personal favourite was one that drew from one of those HBO shows. Staying true to the graphic novel, with the yellow and black template, a poster said, “Who watches the watchmen?” I blame myself for letting pop culture necessitate my need to be political, and not have it be an organic process. I also credit it in the same vein, since there wasn’t really an organic process to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we leave out the ways in which pop culture betrayed this generation? Twitterati took nearly all of India’s film industry to task for not using its influence to say anything about the protests. Most notably, Ranveer Singh was a major target, since he played the lead role in &lt;em&gt;Gully Boy&lt;/em&gt; - a movie that was about a marginalised person trying to escape his reality by forging a new one through rapping about his struggles. Shah Rukh Khan, who is an alumnus of Jamia Milia University, met a similar plight. Actors were accused of not having any spine; those who seemed ‘woke’ on the surface through their movies but took a selfie with current Prime Minister Narendra Modi became a symbol of shallowness in the eyes of many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My generation is often called the most depressed set of people to exist. It seems like every concern they have ever had about work, society, themselves, their careers, their grades, has collectivised together to make known to everyone that the government is to blame for much of it. This is not to say that they may be entirely wrong, either. Unsure job prospects, a disgusting lack of reverence for the humanities that also manifests itself in ad hominem jibes about people from supposedly ‘anti-national’ but surely excellent institutions like JNU, passage of oppressive bills like the Rights of Transgender Persons Bill, and the general treatment of marginalised groups do not provide any kind of conducive environment for positivity on the part of India’s youth. An escapist resort from the pressures of this world then becomes pop culture - a feel-good substitute for the real world. Of course, with time, pop culture has begun to mirror society more and more. Yet, we still feel that we can treat movies and shows as they are, and not as something that affects our environment beyond what is on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the mirror does exist. This article may not have been the need of the hour, because in the grand scheme of things, it feels unimportant to discuss pop culture. However, it has definitely been one of the ways that people used to make aware to others around them the true impact of the government’s actions. It became a common language to understand something so big, and then eventually be the platform for educating oneself more about the happenings in the country. Even beyond Delhi, the protests are getting worse and people need help. The truth is that the revolution was televised and it’s an episode every day.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pranav Manie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In the past two weeks, the city of Delhi saw the rise of a mass movement of agitation and protest against India’s controversial new law, the Citizenship Amendment Act (CAA). This movement also reacted strongly against the proposed National Register of Citizens which the Indian Home Minister Amit Shah promised would eventually be implemented across the country. In many of these cities, students were the torch-bearers of these protests. Not long after it became crystal clear that a large section of the populace, especially the youth, was extremely dissatisfied with these decisions by the Indian government, violence broke out primarily against students at Jamia Milia University in Delhi, a premier, sought-after institution for humanities in the country. Reports began to pour in of instances of extreme police brutality against the rising protesters, not only in Jamia, but also in other institutions as well as outside colleges and universities. A large part of the student fraternity, not just in Delhi, but all across India, took this to heart and attempted to take a peaceful stand against what they believed was a clear instance of abuse of power.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Colourism: An Introduction</title>
      <link href="/Colourism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Colourism: An Introduction" />
      <published>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Colourism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Colourism">&lt;p&gt;Colourism is a term increasingly mentioned in recent, modern racial discourse and is enjoying some much-needed attention during the current political climate. Colourism, by definition, is the “prejudice or discrimination against individuals with a dark skin tone, typically among people of the same ethnic or racial group” (&lt;em&gt;Oxford English Dictionary&lt;/em&gt;); but does this mean that this problem is something that is in fact conceived, and perpetuated, by black communities?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, no. Colourism is an overhang from slavery. It’s some form of diaspora from within your own diasporic community; where darker-skinned women, in particular, suffer poor treatment, fewer job opportunities and less representation in the film, television and music industries. Lighter skinned-artists such as Beyoncé Knowles, Robin ‘Rihanna’ Fenty, Jorja Smith and racially ambiguous artists like Cardi B, enjoy mainstream success, largely straddling both sides of the Black Atlantic (a concept developed by Paul Gilroy). On the other hand, artists like Nina Simone, Grace Jones and Azealia Banks have enjoyed lower levels of success or heightened criticism for their artistic choices. (Banks is admittedly a contentious choice to some, but still valid in demonstrating the wider point.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowles’ father, Matthew, conceded in an interview, when quizzed about whether the success of his daughters was in part down to their skin colour, that it was no ‘accident’ that the two were this way, elaborating further and revealing a greater attraction to lighter-skinned women. Mr Knowles admitted that his now ex-wife – Tina – seemed white to him when they first met. This was something that clearly was attractive to him and that he had been told by his mother to not bring home a “nappy headed black girl”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The negative portrait painted of women with darker skin seems to be a perpetuated tale of self-loathing from darker-skinned men and women reaching back over generations, since slavery – where white masters did show preferential treatment to and force themselves upon the lighter-skinned female slaves. Mr Knowles’ testimony, simultaneously explains that these ideas were ‘conditioned’ into him by his mother, yet this does no favours to the stereotypes of black women being angry and abusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyoncé Knowles’ &lt;em&gt;Lemonade&lt;/em&gt; visual album in 2016 was her third album away from the management of her father, who orchestrated her entire early career and her first three solo albums. On &lt;em&gt;Lemonade&lt;/em&gt;, Beyoncé sampled speeches from Malcolm X, notably in the music video for &lt;em&gt;Don’t’ Hurt Yourself&lt;/em&gt;: “The most disrespected person in America is the Black woman. The most unprotected person in America, is the Black woman. The most neglected woman in America is the Black Woman”. In addition, the promotional appearance at the 2016 Superbowl Half-time Show referenced the Black Panther movement in costume and staging, much to the shock and dismay of ‘White America’. US comedy show &lt;em&gt;Saturday Night Live&lt;/em&gt; even parodied the national reaction, joking that Beyoncé had become such a successful household name, that ‘they’ (‘White America’) had forgotten that she was in fact a black woman expressing – amongst other more personal things – her diasporic place in America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some would argue that the only way that this music was ever heard on a mainstream stage was due to her complexion and preferential treatment as a lighter-skinned woman, and as an established popular artist, with considerable influence and artistic independence thanks to signing with her husband’s label. Since then, Beyoncé also wrote a song for the &lt;em&gt;Lion King&lt;/em&gt; soundtrack &lt;em&gt;Brown Skinned Girl&lt;/em&gt; to empower and uplift women of darker shades—thereby using her privilege to uplift others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that this particular colouristic scrutiny doesn’t affect men in the same way, not to say it does not affect them at all. Black men in entertainment are seen in all shades, from Childish Gambino to the darker Kendrick Lamar, to the problematic Chris Brown who, despite several instances of abuse, continues to make music. Clearly the issue is not about representation, it’s about male privilege and a lack of self-worth or self-esteem that is passed down generations, which further marginalises women who do not enjoy the same privileges as their male counterparts in any ethnic group of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also about being held to a different standard to both men and people of lighter complexions. My earlier acknowledgement of Azealia Banks’ notorious spats serves a wider point. Many artists express un-savoury opinions about others, or are insensitive around hot-button issues: like Gina Rodriguez’s continued maligning of black women and throwaway use of the ‘N-word’; Cardi B’s abhorrent attitudes towards trans people, whilst appropriating LGBT+ turns of phrase; or Kanye West’s musings on slavery and support of Donald Trump under the guise of ‘free thought’. These are all people who swathes of people online have called out and ‘cancelled’ but who also mysteriously continue to enjoy success whilst remaining largely unscathed. It appears separating the artist from the art has qualifying factors and one of them is clearly skin tone – or at least when it comes to women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colourism itself highlights the complexities of ethnic minorities’ relationships with one another. It is perpetuated – at its root – by a form of white supremacy, that has filtered into various communities and left dark-skinned women feeling marginalised and unappreciated. Here, the term black is far from simple, as it does not encompass the inner prejudices within a diverse community of billions. Colourism is being discussed exponentially more in recent months and years; and hopefully, continues to get the attention it deserves for whom Malcom X described as the most ‘disrespected’, the most ‘unprotected’ and the most ‘neglected’ group in American society – and indeed the wider world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nat Richards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nat Richards is a freelance musician with a post-graduate degree from the University of Bristol.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Nat</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Colourism is a term increasingly mentioned in recent, modern racial discourse and is enjoying some much-needed attention during the current political climate. Colourism, by definition, is the “prejudice or discrimination against individuals with a dark skin tone, typically among people of the same ethnic or racial group” (Oxford English Dictionary); but does this mean that this problem is something that is in fact conceived, and perpetuated, by black communities?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Labour’s Tale of Woe: Reflections on the British General Election</title>
      <link href="/Labour-s-Tale-of-Woe-Reflections-on-the-British-General-Election" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Labour's Tale of Woe: Reflections on the British General Election" />
      <published>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Labour-s-Tale-of-Woe-Reflections-on-the-British-General-Election</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Labour-s-Tale-of-Woe-Reflections-on-the-British-General-Election">&lt;p&gt;In last Thursday’s British general election, the Conservative Party won a resounding majority of 356 seats to Labour’s 203, in what proved to be the Labour Party’s worst election defeat since 1935. The Conservatives saw significant gains in Britain’s Leave-voting constituencies in the North East and the Midlands, as Boris Johnson’s promise to ‘get Brexit done’ clearly resonated with many voters in traditional Labour strongholds. The certainty of an exit from the EU, coupled with the SNP gaining 13 seats in Scotland including that of the Liberal Democrat leader Jo Swinson, has also left many contemplating the future of the Union and the probability of a Scottish secession. But the most striking aspect of the election was the collapse of the Labour Party, which lost 59 seats from their 2017 results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boris Johnson, in pledging not only to deliver Brexit but to increase public expenditure by £13.4 billion in 2020–2021, which would be the largest increase in spending in 15 years, clearly provided a theoretical break from the austerity policies and supply-side economics which had characterised the Conservatives’ previous administrations in the wake of the Financial Crisis, enabling him to win over voters in Labour strongholds. It is unclear, however, if this ‘One-Nation Conservative’ rhetoric will translate into policy, as Boris Johnson has voted consistently in favour of austerity policies since being returned as an MP in 2015. Moreover, it is entirely probable that having won a demonstrable majority, the Conservatives may use their relative unaccountability to continue the same cuts to income tax and spending that they were previously committed to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Labour, a schism between the Europhile, metropolitan, London-centric PLP and the Eurosceptic so-called ‘Red Wall’ of Northern, working class seats was the main source of their undoing. Labour lost 10.4% of the vote share in seats where 60% or more people voted Leave, as seats such as Sedgefield, Bolsover and Workington fell to the Conservatives. Dennis Skinner, a veteran Labour MP and former miner, lost his Bolsover seat after 49 years in Parliament. In 2017, when Labour had promised to honour the result of the referendum, they held 72 of the 100 constituencies in the most working class (C2DE) households. In 2019, this figure fell to 53, and the Conservatives increased their share from 13 to 31. Labour’s decision to cleave towards the centre to placate the Blairite elements of the Party was, therefore, an unmitigated catastrophe. Ian Lavery MP, who held onto his seat in Wansbeck in Northumberland by an unfathomably slender majority of just 800 votes, stated: “Ignore democracy and to be quite honest the consequences will come back and bite you up the backside.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many voters in the aforementioned deindustrialised Northern towns now beset by a dismal combination of unemployment and precarious, low-wage service sector work, the fact that Labour had failed to completely acknowledge their Eurosceptic stance eroded their faith in democracy. Devoid for the most part of media influence or capital, the vote was the only way of making their voices heard. Having been neglected by a London-centric party and a political consensus dominated for decades by financialisation, the City of London and an obsession with GDP as the sole indicator of the prosperity of the nation, they struck a lethal blow against those who purported but failed to represent them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perception of Jeremy Corbyn as an inadequate leader was another prevalent theme both on the doorstep and in mainstream political coverage throughout the election. Media coverage of Corbyn was relentlessly brutal. The virulent anti-Corbyn rhetoric even predated the election, as during the past 3 years, he has been referred to as a Czech spy, a Russian agent, an anti-semite and a Communist. It is undeniable that there are antisemitic elements within the Labour Party that Corbyn has been indecisive in removing, and that the British Left has a long and disgraceful history of indulging antisemitism, aptly described by August Bebel as “the socialism of fools”. Keir Hardie, the first ever Labour leader, blamed Jewish financial houses for the outbreak of the First World War. However, Corbyn himself has a long and understated history of opposing antisemitism. As far back as 1977, for example, Corbyn organised a counter-demonstration in defence of London’s Jewish community against 1,000 National Front members who attempted to march through Wood Green.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blairites and moderate voices within the Labour movement continue to portray this election as proof that it is left wing policies that are unpopular rather than the party’s Brexit stance and alienation of its core voting bloc. They suggest that the Labour Party must revert to a pro-corporate ideology, being at ease with privatisation, marketisation and a bellicose foreign policy. Yet this is directly contradicted by the available evidence: a 2017 YouGov poll found that 60% of the British public support renationalising the railways, 59% support taking water into public ownership, and 53% supported public ownership of the energy companies. 60% also back higher levels of taxation and spending. To argue that the statistical success of Tony Blair compared to Jeremy Corbyn represents a necessity to return to a Blairite brand of politics is to misunderstand that the political context has changed significantly since 1997. A global financial crash, the longest squeeze in wages since the Napoleonic Wars, and house prices rising to 7.8 times the amount of annual salaries demonstrate that a significantly greater amount of fiscal intervention is required to alleviate the crises of the present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The technocratic, Blairite conception of politics, which focuses entirely on winning power for its own sake and ignores the broader contexts in which new political and economic ideas come to the fore, has subsided. It has been proposed, therefore, that the future of the Labour Party is a combination of a culturally conservative, patriotic communitarianism with economic leftism of the kind espoused by figures such as Clement Attlee and George Lansbury. The resurgence of ‘Blue Labour’ attests to this. However, it must be acknowledged that Labour is a party that, for decades, has attempted to straddle a coalition of voters with fundamentally different outlooks and views of the world that may be considered irreconcilable. Socially-liberal graduates in Manchester and London, harbouring an instinctual aversion to the monarchy and the nation-state, on whom the Labour Party also depends, would be alienated by such a platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reconnect with its core vote, and to pull together its fractured coalition of voters, Labour will need a sustained and coordinated presence within areas of the country which perceive them to be London-centric and elitist, rather than merely turning up a week prior to the election and expecting votes. The neoliberal atomisation and individualism which characterise the present political era have torn asunder many community institutions which once fostered political dialogue and enabled people to become involved with politics. Therefore, much of the impetus must come from the grassroots elements of the party, with a priority placed on engaging in programmes such as the National Food Service and serving the concerns of local residents regarding ordinary issues such as education, housing and healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that the schisms and fissures within the Labour Party, and between the party and the electorate have been destructive and have led to the party’s near annihilation. There is a significant amount of soul-searching to be done, as the Labour Party desperately attempts to avoid decades in political oblivion. Reconnection with the party’s Northern heartlands will be a clear priority, as will grassroots level organising and education. But some of these ideological vicissitudes, such as the gap between voters in the Northern heartlands and those in the major cities, run so deep that it is difficult to see the party recovering from them.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In last Thursday’s British general election, the Conservative Party won a resounding majority of 356 seats to Labour’s 203, in what proved to be the Labour Party’s worst election defeat since 1935. The Conservatives saw significant gains in Britain’s Leave-voting constituencies in the North East and the Midlands, as Boris Johnson’s promise to ‘get Brexit done’ clearly resonated with many voters in traditional Labour strongholds. The certainty of an exit from the EU, coupled with the SNP gaining 13 seats in Scotland including that of the Liberal Democrat leader Jo Swinson, has also left many contemplating the future of the Union and the probability of a Scottish secession. But the most striking aspect of the election was the collapse of the Labour Party, which lost 59 seats from their 2017 results.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
