<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/society/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-01-15T00:52:25+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/society/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why ‘Hindutva’ Should be a Good Word</title>
      <link href="/Why-Hindutva-Should-be-a-Good-Word" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why 'Hindutva’ Should be a Good Word" />
      <published>2019-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-Hindutva-Should-be-a-Good-Word</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-Hindutva-Should-be-a-Good-Word">&lt;p&gt;The term ‘Hindutva’ has a bad reputation and not without good reason. A most unholy concoction of unscientific claims by right-wing leaders, mob lynchings, casteism and communal hatred has come to define Hindutva. The term has become so contemptible, especially to the well-educated and well-to-do of Indian society, that anyone who has slightly Hindutvavadi inclinations is automatically branded a ‘Bigoted Bhakt’ or ‘Sanghi’. This is, however, a sad state-of-affairs, for a political ideology like ‘Hindutva’ can be so much more than ‘Mandir Wahin Banayenge’. This article is an attempt at defining (not revising) Hindutva. It is our attempt at showing the world that Hindutva can be a profoundly positive contributor to our lives and to the life of this diverse and great nation called India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindutva as a political ideology manifests the ‘Hinduness’ of the Indian people. On a primitive level, Hindutva means the ‘Inherent Hinduness’  of all Indian people. Savarkar, who coined the term Hindutva, was an atheist himself and defined Hindutva in a strictly geographical and cultural sense. The word ‘Hindu’ comes from ‘Indus’ (the river around which we started off as a civilization) and the common bond which all Indians inherently share is hence called ‘Hindutva’. Simply put, any person born within the boundaries of the subcontinent is a Hindu and his inherent ‘Bharatiyata’ is called Hindutva.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This definition of Hindutva is, historically, the only true answer for Indians to the question “Who are we?” All other answers divided Indians into different religions, castes, regions and even races. In fact, the Hindu Code Bill defined a Hindu as someone who is “NOT a Christian, Jew, Parsi or Muslim”! Clearly, we need this ‘Bharatiya’ definition of Hindutva to have a true, positive consciousness of our identity as an extremely diverse nation. Socially, the concept of Hindutva, or there being a certain kind of Hinduness which we inherit from the fact of us being born in this holy land looks beyond divisions of caste and religion to unify the Indian masses. It brilliantly distinguishes Indians from the rest of the world. An American does not start possessing Hindutva if he converts to Hinduism (Sorry David Frawley). But an Indian Muslim has an inherent Hindutva and is very distinct from an Arabic or South-east Asian Muslim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not fashioning an artificial answer here on the question of Indian identity based only in geography. Instead, we are verily identifying the common culture and syncretic tradition that exists only within that geography. The Hindutva we speak of is not simply due to the happenstance of people living in a piece of land, it’s due to the overarching unity among diversity they have developed, the story they have told themselves. This Hindutva is manifested in the numerous public holidays of Eid, Christmas and Diwali we Indians enjoy together― whether we are Hindu, Christian, or Muslim. It is found in the consistent requests for Biryani by Hindus to their Muslim friends. From the Rig Veda’s declaration (RV 1.164.46) that “Indra, Mitra, Varuna, Agni…The wise speak of what is One in many ways” to Kabir’s elegant verses on religious unity, Hindutva is about the rich cultural inheritance of all Indians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first key aspect of Hindutva is the fact that we have overcome so many foibles and problems, skirmishes and conflicts to emerge as one nation. Yes, there was once a time we officially designated people as ‘untouchable’ but still, our Constitution was written by a ‘Dalit’ man. Yes, Mahmud Ghazni plundered the Somnath Temple 17 times, but Ghalib’s verses would be non-existent without Muslims. It is through the schisms between us that we have developed this complex and unique identity. We have been through multiple disagreements on grounds of caste, faith, state and language. And in overcoming them we have discovered our underlying unity. Therefore, the first theme of Hindutva involves a sense of Indian pride, a feeling of common triumph of having risen above so many conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second aspect of Hindutva is religion, or rather the peculiar part it plays in making us so distinct. Religion is very strongly present in India’s public life, from the raucous dispute surrounding the Babri Masjid to the controversy on beef and mob lynchings. However, even if religion is a cause of conflict in India, it is undeniably the bedrock of its cultural identity too. Without Hinduism and its multiple gods, esoteric texts and ancient hymns, India is unimaginable. Without the Buddha its culture is barren; and without an Indian version of Islam, there would be no Sufism, no qawwalis. Faith is a wonderful thing in India that makes us separate from the barren West. In the West, as Nietzsche states (in The Gay Science), “God is dead, he remains dead, and [they] have killed him”. In India, the ‘Samudra Manthan’ of religions yields the nectar of meaning, whether it be in the form of Khwajaji’s sermons, Adi Shankara’s works, or Lalan Fakir’s songs, all we need to do is share it equally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third historical aspect of Hindutva explains how our unity exists through our diversity, and not despite it. We Indians may have had our problems, but just like a big Indian joint family, we are one. Hindutva ideologues like Golwalkar (in his Bunch of Thoughts) and Deendayal Upadhyaya (in his Integral Humanism) have time and again emphasised how Hindutva is broader than Hinduism because Indians following ‘Avaidik’ Dharmas like Sikhism, Jainism, Buddhism and even religions like Islam and Christianity have Hindutva in them. The reason for that is cultural intermingling. Arjuna’s marriage to Naga princess Ulupi and Manipuri princess Chitrangada in The Mahabharata is a classical and literary example of how we Indians cherish a mixing of traditions in our rich mythology. Even the Indian Supreme Court noted in 1995 that Hindutva is a way of life (and a ‘state of mind’). This way of life has been accepting of all people (both the oppressed and the oppressors), and even ‘foreign-origin’ rulers like the towering Mughal Emperor Akbar have patronised this way of life that epitomises a unity that stems from diversity. While the Parsis immigrated to both China and India, it was the latter where they finally found refuge in. The Jews have thanked us enough for being the only country without an instance of anti-Semitism. In fact, the Jewish quarters of Kochi stand right next to the Palace of the King of Kochi. The Hindu philosophical idea of every creature being a part of the Supreme Brahman (irrespective of his faith) has made us an all-welcoming people. And the word Hindutva embodies that openness of mind ever so poignantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line of this article is to tell the reader to embrace Hindutva. Why? Because Hindutva is India’s gift to the world. It was Hindutva which ‘Indianized’ parts of Iran, Afghanistan, Tibet, South-East Asia and even Japan. Thailand’s erstwhile capital is named Ayutthaya, after Lord Ram’s capital Ayodhya. What makes India stand out is not its history, its philosophy or its many religions, but an optimum combination  of all three. Once upon a time, European merchants wanted to trade with us, hence the mad pursuits by Columbus and Vasco Da Gama to ‘discover’ the magical land called India. But what do we find today? Growing westernization and inferiority complex amongst Indians! The same India which was a shining example of an ideal country to the world is now restyling itself based on western ‘isms’ like Capitalism and Socialism. This cannot happen. Hindutva is India’s ‘Soft Power’. All Indians have to be proud of Hindutva, for we can’t expect the world to respect us if we don’t respect ‘who we are’. Unless India becomes ‘Indianized’ again, ‘Superpower 2020’ (realistically speaking, ‘Superpower 2050’), will remain a distant dream.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>The Oxy Moron</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The term ‘Hindutva’ has a bad reputation and not without good reason. A most unholy concoction of unscientific claims by right-wing leaders, mob lynchings, casteism and communal hatred has come to define Hindutva. The term has become so contemptible, especially to the well-educated and well-to-do of Indian society, that anyone who has slightly Hindutvavadi inclinations is automatically branded a ‘Bigoted Bhakt’ or ‘Sanghi’. This is, however, a sad state-of-affairs, for a political ideology like ‘Hindutva’ can be so much more than ‘Mandir Wahin Banayenge’. This article is an attempt at defining (not revising) Hindutva. It is our attempt at showing the world that Hindutva can be a profoundly positive contributor to our lives and to the life of this diverse and great nation called India.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">On Space and Loneliness</title>
      <link href="/On-Space-and-Loneliness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Space and Loneliness" />
      <published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/On-Space-and-Loneliness</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/On-Space-and-Loneliness">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The whole conviction of my life now rests upon the belief that loneliness, far from being a rare and curious phenomenon, is the central and inevitable fact of human existence.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taxi Driver’s principle character Travis Bickle outlines these very principles as espoused by the great American author (who I happen to be a big fan of) Thomas Wolfe. Loneliness is a derivative of several complex emotions which arise within the spheres of our consciousness. This article however will not stress on our individual perspective of loneliness but rather a collective sense of loneliness, i.e. the feeling that we could be the only civilization to breed conscious life in a whole goddamn universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1961, Frank Drake, in his very famous equation, discussed the possibility of the existence of the extraterrestrial beings and our chances of actually finding them and making contact with them. This was not to quantify the number of civilizations in the universe but rather a way to stimulate scientific dialogue on the search for extraterrestrial beings. It is just an estimation technique which is popularly known in the scientific community as the Fermi Problem. It provides a back-of-the-envelope solution to the entire problem at hand. The Drake equation features 7 unknown parameters which can be treated as variables in order to find an answer. This includes variables like the number of civilisations in our galaxy with which communication might be possible (i.e. which are on our current past light cone); the average rate of star formation in our galaxy; the fraction of those stars that have planets; the average number of planets that can potentially support life per star that has planets; and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inspirations behind these variables was actually an article in the &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; journal that was provocatively titled: “Searching for Interstellar Communications”. One of the first known attempts to connect with the extraterrestrial beings was made by the 1977 American Scientific program that employed the use of 2 robotic satellite probes, namely, Voyager 1 and Voyager 2, respectively. It was actually intended to study the outer solar system, i.e. the outer planets of Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus and Neptune. It was launched under conditions of a favourable alignment of the four planets. The initial plan was to study the four planets, but currently, the Voyagers explore the outer boundary of the heliosphere in interstellar space and the mission has been extended way above it’s time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spacecrafts contain very advanced technological instruments in order to collect and transmit proper, accurate data back home. The Voyagers have stabilized guidance systems, controlled by computers, to point their high gain antennas to Earth for efficient transfer of important results and data. The message transmission is also helped by the use of an electronic photography system which has been an instrumental part of the satellites. One thing of immense interest in the spacecraft, however, is the Voyager Golden Record. These records are phonograph records which contain sounds and images , “selected to portray the diversity and culture on Earth” to any intelligent extraterrestrial life that may come across it. Carl Sagan, the renowned astrophysicist who was allocated the duty to decide which records to include on the disk noted that “the spacecrafts will be encountered and the record played only if there are advanced space-faring civilisations in interstellar space”. But the launching of this “bottle” into the cosmic ocean says something very hopeful about life on our planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carl Sagan chose and assembled 115 images and varieties of natural sounds. There are collections of songs and spoken greetings and printed messages from the likes of US President Jimmy Carter and UN Secretary General Kurt Waldheim. It includes an inspirational message which is “per aspera ad astra” or “ through hardships to the stars”, which is what this entire struggle of choices is supposed to signify. There are several photographs from the notable photographer Ansel Adams along with the recorded brain waves of Ann Druyan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, one song which resonates with this entire struggle is the simple choice of a gospel blues song written and performed by American musician Blind Willie Johnson that was recorded in 1927. The song was named: “Dark was the Night. Cold was the Ground”. It is basically an instrumental song with the self-taught slide style used by Willie and accompanied by his moaning and humming. Johnson was not blind when he was born, but it is speculated that he was blinded by his stepmother when was only 7 years old. Apparently, during an argument, she splashed Willie with a caustic solution of lye water which ended up permanently blinding him. However, that was not the end of his suffering. He used to perform on the streets and had a tin cup tied to his neck to collect money. During his career, he was praised for his style which became quite popular but he was never financially well off. Post the Great Depression, his audience was completely wiped off, and he never recorded again. And in strange series of circumstances in 1945, his home got destroyed in a fire and he continued to live within the ruins of his house, where he was exposed to humidity and dampness, following which he contracted Malaria. His health steadily worsened due to several other factors and hospitals were not willing to admit him owing to his visual impairment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He passed away on September 18, 1945. His life has been a true testimony of his song, which has immortalized humankind’s search to cure loneliness. His song truly represents the primal feeling which we all have, whether individually or collectively, for a greater purpose and a direction to every event. Floating in the endless space, it represents a sign of hope and a possibility on how loneliness could be a feature which could give us a new path to our existence. But maybe being alone is not bad after all. Maybe we could all be God’s lonely men. I guess we simply need a few aliens to tell us what the truth is.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“The whole conviction of my life now rests upon the belief that loneliness, far from being a rare and curious phenomenon, is the central and inevitable fact of human existence.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">“A Strange Game. The only Winning Move is to not Play.”</title>
      <link href="/A-Strange-Game-The-only-Winning-Move-is-to-not-Play" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“A Strange Game. The only Winning Move is to not Play.”" />
      <published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Strange-Game-The-only-Winning-Move-is-to-not-Play</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Strange-Game-The-only-Winning-Move-is-to-not-Play">&lt;p&gt;The cold war science fiction movie War Games had a very cold yet direct message to its audiences and the dispatch remains important to us, even more so, at this point of time too. A nuclear war has no clear winners and thereby, referring to Sun Tzu’s key principle in the Art of War, “a battle where no one wins must be avoided.” A nuclear war and its implications have always been a source of inspiration for several authors and filmmakers. It stems from a deep fear of a “mutually assured destruction” of civilization as we know it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Doomsday Clock has been a representative of how far we are from a situation of nuclear war. The Doomsday Clock is updated by the Bulletin of Atomic Scientists based in Chicago and it has been maintained since 1947. The hypothetical global catastrophe is represented as “midnight” and the minute hand represents how far we are from that midnight. In 1991, post the Soviet collapse, it was the furthest away from the midnight, 17 minutes. The clock has been turned and has changed positions several times, 23 times to be precise, but never has it been more alarming than recently. In 2018, the clock was said to be only 2 minutes away from midnight due to the “looming possibility of climate change and nuclear war”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is funny how Metal fans can relate to it, as epitomised by a famous Iron Maiden song which was quite rightly called “2 minutes to midnight”. The chorus of the song carries a blatant warning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The Hands that threaten Doom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two minutes to midnight&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To kill the unborn in the womb”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I will not be referring to any political commentary by any world leader in reference to why this has been the most alarming period of human history. But this opportunity will be used to highlight why exactly we are not going to survive a nuclear holocaust if such a situation does arise in the future. We have come a long way since Dr. Oppenheimer’s infamous commentary after the success of the nuclear bomb testing, when he is supposed to have said (allegedly quoting the Bhagavad Gita) , &lt;em&gt;“I am become death, the destroyer of worlds”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, we have become destroyers of worlds. The rate of development of nuclear technology peaked amidst the rising tensions during the Cold War, when certain ideologies involving the then Soviet Russia and United States put both of them in a collision course. It was an alarming period of time, but the tension peaked during the testing of the Soviet RDS-220 hydrogen Bomb, commonly known as the Tsar Bomba. The aspect which was truly alarming was that the bomb was named, in a rather unpopular manner, as Kuzma’s mother. This was believed to be a reference to Nikita Khrushchev’s statement in United Nations General Assembly in 1960, when he claimed that he would “show United States Kuzma’s mother”. He was intending to broach a Russian idiom which translates to, “we will show them”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tsar Bomba was the most powerful explosive ever detonated, yielding a staggering 50 megatons of TNT. In fact, the initial plan envisioned of 100 megatons of TNT but that never happened, fortunately. The bomb was detonated at Sukhoy Nos cape of Severny Island, part of Novaya Zemlya. It was too big to be placed in a missile and too heavy for the planes to carry it with enough fuel. It was thereby carried in a release plane and the pilot Durnotsev and his crew were only given a dismal 50% chance of survival. The surprising fact was that the bomb which was expected to hit the ground was prevented from doing so by its own shockwave which reflected it back. The fireball was 8 km wide and was visible almost 1000 km away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mushroom cloud was about 64 km high—that is around 8 times the size of Mt. Everest. All buildings around a 55 km radius of ground zero were completely annihilated. It is said that a participant saw the bright flash from 270 km away with dark goggles and still felt the thermal pulse. In fact, the shockwave travelled the world around 3 times before it finally subsided. It was truly an alarming period of time in the midst of the show of power between nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is where the truly sinister shock is found. If an evaluation of the true capabilities of the Tsar Bomba is done, using the NUKEMAP software by Alex Wellerstein, if 10 of these bombs are used at key locations all around the world, around 2 billion of world’s population would get eliminated almost immediately. This does not even account for the long lasting effects of radiation and 3rd degree burns which several people will, inevitably, ultimately succumb to. Even a small scale nuclear war would have devastating effects on the planet. A research article by Dr. Mills proposes that even a local regional nuclear conflict, such as the India-Pakistan conflict would have devastating tolls on the planet’s ozone retention and protection capability. The ozone level would inevitably get decreased to alarming levels never before seen in human history, which would lead to a sudden fall in the Earth’s temperature, leading to possible frosts. Surface temperatures would go on decreasing for more than 25 years due to thermal inertia. This combination of cooling and less protection from the ozone layer would lead to enhanced UV rays from the sun, putting pressure on global food supplies that could lead to a global famine. This is only based on the assumption on equal use of artillery from both the sides though—which is clearly a very generous conjecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nuclear war would have devastating effects on the planet’s resources and thereby would have a range of climatic effects which would surely spell doom for human civilisation. It is time we finally realized that there are no victors in this war. However, even the eradication of nuclear weapons places us in a catch-22 situation: There are no ways for the safe disposal of these weapons and a failure to handle them would only place them in the wrong hands. The technology which was expected to solve the energy crisis during the initial days of research has ended up being a nuisance of its own. War Games resonates with us as a cold reminder of a dystopia which lies beyond a nuclear catastrophe, that is if we survive it at all. Maybe with all the words and warnings, we could finally strive to push within us a sense of realization and maybe avoid the danger while there is still 2 minutes to the midnight.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The cold war science fiction movie War Games had a very cold yet direct message to its audiences and the dispatch remains important to us, even more so, at this point of time too. A nuclear war has no clear winners and thereby, referring to Sun Tzu’s key principle in the Art of War, “a battle where no one wins must be avoided.” A nuclear war and its implications have always been a source of inspiration for several authors and filmmakers. It stems from a deep fear of a “mutually assured destruction” of civilization as we know it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Editorial: On The Importance of Sex</title>
      <link href="/Importance-of-sex" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Editorial: On The Importance of Sex" />
      <published>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Importance-of-sex</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Importance-of-sex">&lt;p&gt;It is most certainly not easy writing about sex. To begin with, you have to deal with the fact that once you start talking about orgasms, breasts, penises and foot fetishes (the human mind is an unholy place), it is very easy to sound like you are writing plain-old erotica—cheap, unsophisticated, and yet very arousing. At the same time though, if you try to distance yourself from the human depravity of sex, you could sound more like a plumber describing a u-bend when exploring whether the G-Spot really exists. I want to avoid making such serious stylistic errors, but I don’t want to forget that any conversation about sex has to be both erotic and exciting whilst being decidedly technical about a topic that is so serious. I remember watching an interview of Philip Roth (you kind of have to read and listen to him when thinking about sex and literature), where he declared quite hilariously that when he and his friends were sixteen they had only question about sex: &lt;em&gt;“WHEN? WHEN? WHEN?!!”&lt;/em&gt; That kind of desperation was not simply because of an animal drive within us, according to Roth. If his book &lt;i&gt;Portnoy’s Complaint&lt;/i&gt; (which is about a mother-obsessed, masturbation addict) is any indication, the want for sex in human beings can lead to all kinds of things both disgusting and sexy. The power that sex holds over our lives can lead to all sorts of problems, from the relatively benign but hideous (think Diogenes masturbating in the open streets) to the debauched (think Marquis De Sade’s &lt;i&gt;120 Days of Sodom&lt;/i&gt;) and to even wholesale exploitation (think prostitution). There is a reason why “sex sells” and there’s a reason why clerics don’t want even the ankles of women to be visible to men. Sex lies at the very human intersection of patriarchy, fulfilment, love, exploitation, power and everything else in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think a brilliant place to find a conversation about sex that is stimulating (in the right way) is the comments section of any porn video (it’s also a good way of ensuring the video is a good one!). The things people say (and don’t say) about sex in these comments is so profoundly revealing (never thought I’d use the word profound when writing about sex!). These comments tell us that people don’t just watch porn to simply &lt;em&gt;“bust a nut or yaw yaw the sisterhood”&lt;/em&gt;. Masturbation is a very sensuous thing in our lives: It relieves boredom, which is perennially the human mind’s most wicked enemy and it gives us the opportunity to enjoy the feelings (and hormones) that sex brings with the most important person in our erotic lives: ourselves. Therefore, it is no wonder that people have such strikingly specific criticisms of the acting in the video, or the stilettos of the female porn star, or the absolutely unrealistic time for which the male porn star lasts. People put up comments stating all sorts of things, from the things they found funny like the orgasm face of the actors or the scenes they felt where outright bizarre like one where they felt the porn star’s screaming was extremely unappealing as it sounded like a &lt;em&gt;“donkey braying”&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Porn is about the deep voyeurism that inhabits the human mind, it is about finding release (literally) and for that one needs a good experience. Put it this way: when we want to release our bowels we want a clean toilet that smells good, when we want to fulfil our hunger we want food that tastes good, and when we want to avoid the cold we want a jumper that looks good. If we want quality in all other things, should it surprise anyone that we want porn to be more than just people “doing it” with each other? Good pornography is important for the same reason that anything is important to human beings, we are not just Plato’s “featherless birds” and we don’t just have sex in caves (HA!). Unlike the plots and scripts of most porn movies, human beings are interesting in nature, and their erotic lives reflect that via their desires from pornography. There’s a reason why &lt;i&gt;Playboy&lt;/i&gt; Magazine, instead of just having any other nudes, had Marilyn Monroe’s nudes. And there is a reason why Pornhub has reported a phenomenal rise in the consumption of incest porn by…(drum-roll)…millennials!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sex as an activity is about satisfying the human imagination—otherwise, a few grunts and no foreplay would have kept everyone happy. On the issue of ‘grunts’, we all know that men can have very few problems when it ‘comes’ to (pardon the pun) reaching climax, whereas there is a whole body of feminist literature on how women don’t really climax at all most of the time. The common form that the female orgasm takes is due to clitoral stimulation, and the reason why women do not really come due to vaginal stimulation is because, well, men don’t usually last long enough. This creates an obviously skewered power dynamic in sex, where men are able to “unload” ever so easily and women are left feeling constantly under-appreciated. I don’t mean to say that this means men are near-constantly aroused pigs who pay no heed to the needs of their female partners, although there is truth in that contention. My point here is simply that without a good amount of foreplay and some good oral sex, our sexual activities with all their imaginative passion can simply end up being a dull series of painful thrusts for one whole half of the human population—and sex must be far more than that if in these feminist times we men are to redeem ourselves for having treated women as objects of sex for thousands of years. Ancient India, being a culture at a stupendous height of civilisation, was acutely aware of the consequences of denying women the beauty of an orgasm. As Wendy Doniger, a controversial yet revered Indologist, points out, even the legendary &lt;i&gt;Kama Sutra&lt;/i&gt; is clear on the fact that women must orgasm first, given how easy it is for men to do so. The message is clear and has been clear for more than a thousand years: boys, at least try to find the fabled G-spot once in a while instead of just seeking blowjobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power dynamics of sex bring up a very curious issue with specific regard to sex between homosexual men. It is difficult to accurately describe how significantly being either a ‘top’ or a ‘bottom’ has an effect on the masculinity of gay men (MEN!!). The power politics in that part of human sexuality has assumed new proportions with the world’s gay community bidding adieu to the stereotype of the “camp” gay man and welcoming a more traditionally masculine homosexual male as more desirable. As Kevin Troughton &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/nov/30/the-end-of-camp-straight-acting-gay&quot;&gt;writes&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;i&gt;The Guardian&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;em&gt;“very few find [camp] sexually attractive. That limp-wristed, bitchy queen might be hilarious, but you wouldn’t want him as a boyfriend, or even as a one-night stand.”&lt;/em&gt; The fact is “bottoming” gay men have always been stereotyped into the camp category, facing potentially even internalised homophobia due to their perceived passivity in the gay community. And now with the rise in the desirability of the straight-acting gay alpha male, it would appear that all men who wish to receive anal sex will potentially have greater issues relating to dominance and estimations of their own masculinity. Funny enough, all of this simply reinforces the words of Oscar Wilde: &lt;em&gt;“Everything in the world is about sex except sex. Sex is about power”&lt;/em&gt;. It is slightly hilarious but definitely unsurprising that men having sex with other men is where power dynamics take centre stage, after all, the ‘male ego’ manifests itself most strongly in front of other men!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between love and sex is complicated (well, of course). And if you have read a bit of Freud (he has to be mentioned in a discussion on sex, you know, #respect), sex and love are both about your mum. Obviously, his Oedipus Complex and theories on the development of libido are a bit bogus, but his underlying assertion that we learn how to have relationships primarily from our parents makes a lot of intuitive sense. Parents give their children a reality, they define what human interaction means for them and they do so simply because that’s how it is, for good or for bad. This means people’s relationships are (to a degree) shaped by the experiences given to them by their childhood and their parents. The problem is that people fall in love with the people they have sex with quite often and vice versa! And people falling in love leads to all sorts of problems like marriage, infidelity, drama and the responsibility to take care of children. The very point of sex leads to relationships that are determined on factors outside your control (your mum!), and lead to a sexual rut (your children) with added responsibilities of bringing up another human being—so that the cycle can continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is definitely weird talking about sex and extremely difficult to treat it with the sensitivity and respect it deserves. But it certainly is fun to think about and research on something that is so goddamn brilliant. I mean, my research showed me that orgasms could be had by brain dead people if the right nerves are stimulated! And it was facts and observations like this that made my task ever so out-of-control. Yes, sex is important, I could see that, but what is the common thread that makes it all ever so important? And why? I think I have chanced upon a simple answer to these questions: sex is humanity’s deepest desires manifested in the most physical of acts, and for that very reason it’s going to be more than just a simple act. Adieu!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>The Oxy Moron</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is most certainly not easy writing about sex. To begin with, you have to deal with the fact that once you start talking about orgasms, breasts, penises and foot fetishes (the human mind is an unholy place), it is very easy to sound like you are writing plain-old erotica—cheap, unsophisticated, and yet very arousing. At the same time though, if you try to distance yourself from the human depravity of sex, you could sound more like a plumber describing a u-bend when exploring whether the G-Spot really exists. I want to avoid making such serious stylistic errors, but I don’t want to forget that any conversation about sex has to be both erotic and exciting whilst being decidedly technical about a topic that is so serious. I remember watching an interview of Philip Roth (you kind of have to read and listen to him when thinking about sex and literature), where he declared quite hilariously that when he and his friends were sixteen they had only question about sex: “WHEN? WHEN? WHEN?!!” That kind of desperation was not simply because of an animal drive within us, according to Roth. If his book Portnoy’s Complaint (which is about a mother-obsessed, masturbation addict) is any indication, the want for sex in human beings can lead to all kinds of things both disgusting and sexy. The power that sex holds over our lives can lead to all sorts of problems, from the relatively benign but hideous (think Diogenes masturbating in the open streets) to the debauched (think Marquis De Sade’s 120 Days of Sodom) and to even wholesale exploitation (think prostitution). There is a reason why “sex sells” and there’s a reason why clerics don’t want even the ankles of women to be visible to men. Sex lies at the very human intersection of patriarchy, fulfilment, love, exploitation, power and everything else in between.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Beauty and the Beast</title>
      <link href="/Beauty-and-the-Beast" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beauty and the Beast" />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Beauty-and-the-Beast</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Beauty-and-the-Beast">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Beauty is an enormous, unmerited gift given randomly, stupidly.”&lt;/em&gt; – K. Hosseini&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stealthily and openly, invisibly and brazenly, beauty snakes through conversations, decisions and opinions. The discussion of beauty is not just the domain of subjects like narcissism or nature’s trickery to perpetuate a species. Beauty is a matter to be discussed sociologically, for beauty is far more than just how we perceive ourselves, it is also how we perceive each other. In a world that paints less with words and more with filters, it becomes important to examine the intrusion of physical appearances into how one thinks, and leads life. No longer just a measure of what one finds visually or aesthetically soothing, beauty has now become a socially approved metric for the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; we place on people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Indian matrimonial advertisements that yearn for ‘fair’ and ‘slim’ brides and show business boosting looks over talent; right from the start it is ingrained and embedded into us that society fosters a reward mechanism that favours the handsome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps beauty is an enormous, unmerited gift but is it really given &lt;em&gt;randomly&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What truly needs to be pondered upon is, how is it that there is a set of bodily and facial attributes that have been magically fixed as attractive and thereby high value? Why is light skin preferred to dark skin in most cultures? Why are perky breasts seen as more attractive as compared to breasts that sag? Why is it easier for one to find a woman with straight blonde hair aesthetically pleasing but not a woman with frizzy black hair?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fraud in beauty is that we have been made to believe that there is something &lt;em&gt;inherently beautiful&lt;/em&gt; about certain attributes, such as having fair skin. We do not find fair skin beautiful because it is embedded into our genetic constitution to find it so, it is not an innate characteristic of our species to find fair skin beautiful. We find it beautiful because society has deemed it to be beautiful. We find it beautiful because society tells us to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“She had perfect features, with her eye, nose, lips, and ears the right size and in right places. That is all it takes to make people beautiful, normal body parts – yet why does nature mess it up so many times?”&lt;/em&gt; – an un-ironic quote from a Chetan Bhagat novel. Society manufactures and dictates the way we feel about beauty while making us believe that those feelings and judgements arise organically from within. Beauty, is a social construct and this construct too rests upon a farce, which revolves around Eurocentricity and gendered expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Yeh chaand sa roshan chehra, zulfon ka rang sunehra, yeh jheel si neeli aakhein, koi raaz hai inmein gehra, tareef karun kya uski, jisne tumhe banaya?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This song, from a 1964 film in India, casting Indian actors to be watched largely by people living in India, glorifies white skin, blonde hair and blue eyes and people actually &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;related&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to this song to the extent that today it is considered to be a classic. How does this make sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;European standards of beauty are living proof that colonialism once prevailed. When European countries colonised African and Asian nations they did not just see the people they subjugated as &lt;em&gt;‘different’&lt;/em&gt; from themselves but also as inferior, as subhuman. Colonialists glorified everything European as a superior, more civilised and refined way of leading life. They attached ‘disgust’ to everything native and indigenous. Idealisation of European beauty was a by-product of colonisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The skewed power dynamics of the world allowed white people to narrate the norms for beauty. Colourism today, grips cultures across the world. From black women who look at their skin and wonder how much black is too black, to a nation of brown people being marketed skin lightening creams under the brand of ‘Fair &amp;amp; Lovely’. Colourism grips us both by the bane of society and the bane of our selfhood. And while beauty standards affect everyone, they affect people of colour way more. Because it has made us forget what we actually look like. Through the alchemy of Eurocentric standards of beauty, the untamed wavy black hair on the heads of Indian goddesses look mythical to Indians, yet somehow Cameron Diaz’s blonde hair looks more &lt;em&gt;natural&lt;/em&gt; and more &lt;em&gt;attainable&lt;/em&gt;. The conventional archetypes of beauty do not even coincide with traditional looks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The normativity extends to gendered expectations too, as society and media continue to be obsessed with narrow waisted women and tall, brawny men. Once again, the sham lies in the fact that these expectations are &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;assumed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and not &lt;em&gt;intrinsic&lt;/em&gt; to any gender. In a day and age when media is ever present and more dominant than anything else, when one does not see a single woman having body hair on screen, it’s almost as if society wants us to pretend that women do not have body hair. This promotes a form of normativity that borders on delusion! Media latches on a sense of disgust to chest hair, and sells us the lie that it is ‘gross’ and ‘repulsive’ for men to have it. Media strips away what is natural, and in its place synthesises a new ‘normal’. This new ordinary makes the state of nature seem abnormal, if it didn’t it would be easier to picture Chris Evans with chest hair. Ah! Never mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These imposed standards are so deeply entrenched in us that even when one is aware of the sham surrounding beauty, they visit one in private moments. Like the inward rejoice of having hair straightened because it feels as if frizz was something to be corrected, and straight just looks more ‘normal’. Or stopping a porn video midway because the woman having a tuft of pubic hair made it ‘uncomfortable’ to watch, or because watching people of colour have sex ‘feels wrong’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even when faced with these inner hypocrisies, one must remember that these dilemmas too are imposed and injected into the people by a media that rests upon the commoditization of beauty and reinforces the same toxic ideas. But ah! To hell with norms! It is the era for shaking up normativity and outraging beauty ideals!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beauty, in all its failing and its glory, is subjective. “Beauty is subjective” is not a lie meant to console people who do not fall within conventional archetypes of beauty. On the contrary, &lt;em&gt;‘subjective beauty’&lt;/em&gt; is the only truth, for beauty cannot and should not be standardised. Beauty does not conform, why then should its ideals do the same?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Stuti Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Beauty is an enormous, unmerited gift given randomly, stupidly.” – K. Hosseini</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A House Divided: The Secret Civil War of the Catholic Church</title>
      <link href="/A-House-Divided-The-Secret-Civil-War-of-the-Catholic-Church" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A House Divided: The Secret Civil War of the Catholic Church" />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-House-Divided-The-Secret-Civil-War-of-the-Catholic-Church</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-House-Divided-The-Secret-Civil-War-of-the-Catholic-Church">&lt;p&gt;The Catholic Church is perhaps the most troubled religious organization in modern times. No other sect or group is going through the same crisis Catholics are undergoing today, although this is not immediately apparent to those on the outside. This century – the 21st century – will truly determine the shape of the faith for generations to come. But before we move on, a bit of background information is welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1960’s, the Catholic Church held a worldwide council of bishops, called the Second Vatican Council. This was the 21st of the so-called Ecumenical Councils, the deliberations and decrees of which are meant to expound and explain Catholic doctrine in light of contemporary challenges to the faith whilst seeking unity with all other Christian sects. This youngest of the councils was meant to be the Church’s response to the modern world—an attempt at providing a modern discourse not unlike the philosophical consolidation provided by the great Thomas Aquinas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, the Church has focused more on dialogue rather than debate, collaboration rather than conflict. After nearly a thousand years of separation, Pope Paul VI met with Patriarch Athenagoras of the Greek Orthodox Church, and the two hierarchs lifted excommunications which had been in force since 1054. After centuries of war and bloodshed, the Church reached out to the Lutherans and the two groups even drafted a joint declaration on the most controversial point of doctrinal difference between Catholicism and Protestantism. Hopes are high for an eventual reunion of all Christians. And the more general calls for dialogue and peace have been extended not merely to other Christians but even to the various religions of the world, from the folk traditions of North America to the now-resurgent Islam. The Church has not, of course, diluted a single point of Church teaching (both Popes John Paul II and Benedict XVI make that abundantly clear), but the practice of the Church has changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the outside, things might appear to be warm and merry. But under the appearance of serenity lies a harsh reality. The Church is in a state of great turmoil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early 20th century, Pope Pius X spent much of his time and energy as head of the Catholic Church to combat a movement called “Modernism”. The Modernists were clerics and laypeople who, while professing to be Catholics and uniting themselves with the external structures of the Church, nevertheless watered down and diluted several elements of Church doctrine and teaching. Pius X was particularly ruthless – he ordered that all priests and seminary professors take the “Oath Against Modernism”. Needless to say, under his pontificate, the modernists were forced to go underground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, after the Second Vatican Council, under the guise of “pastoral reforms”, the Modernists have had a remarkable resurgence. While they have failed utterly to change official Church teaching, they nonetheless hold opinions at variance with what many consider to unchanging dogma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the Popes post the Vatican II have been very strict against this newly resuscitated trend. John Paul II, in particular, reaffirmed orthodox doctrine in his catechism and encyclicals and Benedict promulgated reforms that led to a revival of traditionalism among clerics and laypeople. But the most recent ascendant to the Throne of Peter does not appear to be in the same vein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Is the Pope Catholic?” was considered to be a joke English Catholics said to themselves in the 19th century. It isn’t funny anymore as the current pontiff, Pope Francis, repeatedly makes ambiguous statements that appear to: firstly, question the necessity of faith for salvation; secondly, allow for divorced and remarried couples to receive Communion; thirdly, imply that Catholic couples should control the number of children they have (which some might interpret as a contradiction of age-old Church doctrine on contraception); and fourthly, call for a change in the teaching on the death penalty and sympathy for homosexuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these statements are ambiguously worded, and it is not always clear if a denial has taken place or if it is simply yet another case of authentic doctrine being stated in a slipshod manner. But what is certainly without question is that this is the most controversial pontificate in recent memory. The situation became so bad that it prompted four high-ranking Church leaders to make public an appeal (called “dubia”) to the Pope seeking clarification on his statements – an appeal which, since then, has gone unanswered. There was even talk of a “public fraternal correction” of the Pope, and there has already been a more grass-roots level “filial correction” involving scores of distinguished signatories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what is even more worrying is the Holy Father’s response to his critics. When calls for clarification come, the Pope is silent. Subtle attacks on his critics and dissenters abound in his Sunday homilies. Conservative laypeople are up in arms, not least among them being the historian Henry Sire, author of the controversial bestseller The Dictator Pope. While Francis tries his level best to maintain an image of compassion, can that really square with what many are now calling a tyrannical method of internal governance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On August 25, 2018, a prominent prelate, Archbishop Carlo Maria Vigano, released a damning 11-page letter describing a network of sexual abuse cover-ups that had spread its tentacles all the way to upper echelons of power. In a move virtually unprecedented in recent history, the bishop called upon the pontiff and the others complicit to resign. This is more than a question of moral corruption. In the eyes of countless conservatives, the laxity of moral standards among prelates and priests is not separate from but is rather a direct result of the “Modernist conspiracy” to liberalize Catholic doctrine. The fact that the majority of these abuse cases are instances of homosexual abuse has only added fuel to the fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not just a regional crisis. This is a battle for the very heart of the Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a conservative Christian with deep sympathy for the Catholic Church’s mission and an appreciation of the richness of her theological heritage, I propose a three-point programme to deal with this crisis once and for all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initiate a Church-wide search-and-destroy operation – better still, if this is handled by outside non-ecclesiastical bodies. Defrock priests found guilty of sexual abuse and hand them over to the secular authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Allow, for the time being, married men to become priests, in accordance with the historical precedents of the Byzantine and other Oriental traditions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Renovate the formation process in theological seminaries
– restore traditional practices abandoned since Vatican II and work to foster ascetic rigour among candidates for the priesthood.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these three points are successfully implemented, we may find ourselves with a smaller Catholic Church. But this will not be a loss. It will be a victory, and the Church will finally have a chance to reclaim her former glory in the modern world.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Catholic Church is perhaps the most troubled religious organization in modern times. No other sect or group is going through the same crisis Catholics are undergoing today, although this is not immediately apparent to those on the outside. This century – the 21st century – will truly determine the shape of the faith for generations to come. But before we move on, a bit of background information is welcome.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
