<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/society/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-01-16T17:58:35+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/society/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Labour’s Tale of Woe: Reflections on the British General Election</title>
      <link href="/Labour-s-Tale-of-Woe-Reflections-on-the-British-General-Election" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Labour's Tale of Woe: Reflections on the British General Election" />
      <published>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Labour-s-Tale-of-Woe-Reflections-on-the-British-General-Election</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Labour-s-Tale-of-Woe-Reflections-on-the-British-General-Election">&lt;p&gt;In last Thursday’s British general election, the Conservative Party won a resounding majority of 356 seats to Labour’s 203, in what proved to be the Labour Party’s worst election defeat since 1935. The Conservatives saw significant gains in Britain’s Leave-voting constituencies in the North East and the Midlands, as Boris Johnson’s promise to ‘get Brexit done’ clearly resonated with many voters in traditional Labour strongholds. The certainty of an exit from the EU, coupled with the SNP gaining 13 seats in Scotland including that of the Liberal Democrat leader Jo Swinson, has also left many contemplating the future of the Union and the probability of a Scottish secession. But the most striking aspect of the election was the collapse of the Labour Party, which lost 59 seats from their 2017 results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boris Johnson, in pledging not only to deliver Brexit but to increase public expenditure by £13.4 billion in 2020–2021, which would be the largest increase in spending in 15 years, clearly provided a theoretical break from the austerity policies and supply-side economics which had characterised the Conservatives’ previous administrations in the wake of the Financial Crisis, enabling him to win over voters in Labour strongholds. It is unclear, however, if this ‘One-Nation Conservative’ rhetoric will translate into policy, as Boris Johnson has voted consistently in favour of austerity policies since being returned as an MP in 2015. Moreover, it is entirely probable that having won a demonstrable majority, the Conservatives may use their relative unaccountability to continue the same cuts to income tax and spending that they were previously committed to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Labour, a schism between the Europhile, metropolitan, London-centric PLP and the Eurosceptic so-called ‘Red Wall’ of Northern, working class seats was the main source of their undoing. Labour lost 10.4% of the vote share in seats where 60% or more people voted Leave, as seats such as Sedgefield, Bolsover and Workington fell to the Conservatives. Dennis Skinner, a veteran Labour MP and former miner, lost his Bolsover seat after 49 years in Parliament. In 2017, when Labour had promised to honour the result of the referendum, they held 72 of the 100 constituencies in the most working class (C2DE) households. In 2019, this figure fell to 53, and the Conservatives increased their share from 13 to 31. Labour’s decision to cleave towards the centre to placate the Blairite elements of the Party was, therefore, an unmitigated catastrophe. Ian Lavery MP, who held onto his seat in Wansbeck in Northumberland by an unfathomably slender majority of just 800 votes, stated: “Ignore democracy and to be quite honest the consequences will come back and bite you up the backside.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many voters in the aforementioned deindustrialised Northern towns now beset by a dismal combination of unemployment and precarious, low-wage service sector work, the fact that Labour had failed to completely acknowledge their Eurosceptic stance eroded their faith in democracy. Devoid for the most part of media influence or capital, the vote was the only way of making their voices heard. Having been neglected by a London-centric party and a political consensus dominated for decades by financialisation, the City of London and an obsession with GDP as the sole indicator of the prosperity of the nation, they struck a lethal blow against those who purported but failed to represent them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perception of Jeremy Corbyn as an inadequate leader was another prevalent theme both on the doorstep and in mainstream political coverage throughout the election. Media coverage of Corbyn was relentlessly brutal. The virulent anti-Corbyn rhetoric even predated the election, as during the past 3 years, he has been referred to as a Czech spy, a Russian agent, an anti-semite and a Communist. It is undeniable that there are antisemitic elements within the Labour Party that Corbyn has been indecisive in removing, and that the British Left has a long and disgraceful history of indulging antisemitism, aptly described by August Bebel as “the socialism of fools”. Keir Hardie, the first ever Labour leader, blamed Jewish financial houses for the outbreak of the First World War. However, Corbyn himself has a long and understated history of opposing antisemitism. As far back as 1977, for example, Corbyn organised a counter-demonstration in defence of London’s Jewish community against 1,000 National Front members who attempted to march through Wood Green.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blairites and moderate voices within the Labour movement continue to portray this election as proof that it is left wing policies that are unpopular rather than the party’s Brexit stance and alienation of its core voting bloc. They suggest that the Labour Party must revert to a pro-corporate ideology, being at ease with privatisation, marketisation and a bellicose foreign policy. Yet this is directly contradicted by the available evidence: a 2017 YouGov poll found that 60% of the British public support renationalising the railways, 59% support taking water into public ownership, and 53% supported public ownership of the energy companies. 60% also back higher levels of taxation and spending. To argue that the statistical success of Tony Blair compared to Jeremy Corbyn represents a necessity to return to a Blairite brand of politics is to misunderstand that the political context has changed significantly since 1997. A global financial crash, the longest squeeze in wages since the Napoleonic Wars, and house prices rising to 7.8 times the amount of annual salaries demonstrate that a significantly greater amount of fiscal intervention is required to alleviate the crises of the present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The technocratic, Blairite conception of politics, which focuses entirely on winning power for its own sake and ignores the broader contexts in which new political and economic ideas come to the fore, has subsided. It has been proposed, therefore, that the future of the Labour Party is a combination of a culturally conservative, patriotic communitarianism with economic leftism of the kind espoused by figures such as Clement Attlee and George Lansbury. The resurgence of ‘Blue Labour’ attests to this. However, it must be acknowledged that Labour is a party that, for decades, has attempted to straddle a coalition of voters with fundamentally different outlooks and views of the world that may be considered irreconcilable. Socially-liberal graduates in Manchester and London, harbouring an instinctual aversion to the monarchy and the nation-state, on whom the Labour Party also depends, would be alienated by such a platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reconnect with its core vote, and to pull together its fractured coalition of voters, Labour will need a sustained and coordinated presence within areas of the country which perceive them to be London-centric and elitist, rather than merely turning up a week prior to the election and expecting votes. The neoliberal atomisation and individualism which characterise the present political era have torn asunder many community institutions which once fostered political dialogue and enabled people to become involved with politics. Therefore, much of the impetus must come from the grassroots elements of the party, with a priority placed on engaging in programmes such as the National Food Service and serving the concerns of local residents regarding ordinary issues such as education, housing and healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that the schisms and fissures within the Labour Party, and between the party and the electorate have been destructive and have led to the party’s near annihilation. There is a significant amount of soul-searching to be done, as the Labour Party desperately attempts to avoid decades in political oblivion. Reconnection with the party’s Northern heartlands will be a clear priority, as will grassroots level organising and education. But some of these ideological vicissitudes, such as the gap between voters in the Northern heartlands and those in the major cities, run so deep that it is difficult to see the party recovering from them.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In last Thursday’s British general election, the Conservative Party won a resounding majority of 356 seats to Labour’s 203, in what proved to be the Labour Party’s worst election defeat since 1935. The Conservatives saw significant gains in Britain’s Leave-voting constituencies in the North East and the Midlands, as Boris Johnson’s promise to ‘get Brexit done’ clearly resonated with many voters in traditional Labour strongholds. The certainty of an exit from the EU, coupled with the SNP gaining 13 seats in Scotland including that of the Liberal Democrat leader Jo Swinson, has also left many contemplating the future of the Union and the probability of a Scottish secession. But the most striking aspect of the election was the collapse of the Labour Party, which lost 59 seats from their 2017 results.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Atheism Destroys Science and Progress. Here’s How.</title>
      <link href="/Atheism-Destroys" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Atheism Destroys Science and Progress. Here’s How." />
      <published>2019-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Atheism-Destroys</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Atheism-Destroys">&lt;p&gt;It might sound strange to say that atheism destroys science. Indeed, many will laugh merely upon reading the heading of this article. However, my interactions with sceptics and postmodernists have convinced me that while it may seem to many that atheism leads to science and moral progress, the truth is exactly the opposite. Rather than upholding science, atheism destroys the foundations that underlie science; and far from promoting human progress, atheism degrades humanity and inevitably leads to moral decay in society. Not only that, I am also deeply convinced that a postmodernist attitude is simply the result of centuries of atheist influence upon the West; a true atheist will, in my opinion, adopt a postmodern outlook sooner or later. In this article, I hope to show why I think this is the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am a Christian, let’s talk about Christianity for a moment. As the Oxford mathematician and Christian thinker John Lennox has remarked multiple times, many of the scientists of the early Modern era were Christians because their faith in God led them to expect order and stability in the universe. Indeed, many of the very people who laid the foundations of science in the post-Reformation West were devoutly Christian people, believing that the study of the creation was a kind of worship to God. Indeed, that is my own opinion as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Christian, I believe that God gave us rationality so that we could use it to study and learn more about the world in which we live. My belief that my mind and my sense organs are a gift of God gives me sufficient ground to trust it as being reliable in giving me information about this wonderful universe which we are privileged to call home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, an atheist cannot say the same thing. For suppose that we live in a world that is merely a cosmic accident, and suppose – for the sake of argument – that the material reality is all that exists and there is no spiritual dimension whatsoever. Under this view, the mind is purely a material phenomenon and is directly equivalent to the brain. There is no aspect whatsoever to the mind that is immaterial under this view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the brain is merely a conglomeration of nerves and chemicals. In a purely physical, materialistic world, what we perceive as emotions, thoughts and feelings are merely the result of chemicals firing around in our brain. Even our deepest moral sentiments are simply the products of how our brain has been evolved to think and perceive reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if this is true, then how can the atheist say that his senses and rational powers are capable of giving him an accurate depiction of reality? If the mind is simply a physical organ that is determined to function and act in a particular way (because of the evolutionary path that it happened to take), then there are no rational grounds for trusting your perception or your ability to reason. After all, everything – in an atheistic worldview – is a cosmic accident and the way your brain thinks and perceives something to be ‘rational’ or ‘logical’ or ‘reasonable’ is merely an accident as well. If evolution had taken a different path, then your brain might not even have existed… or it would have existed, but it would be operating in a different manner, giving you a different perception of what you call ‘reality’. But in that situation, you would have had radically different beliefs and ways of perceiving the world. What you today call ‘reasonable’ might under that circumstance appear absurd or farcical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is here that the atheist falls into a bit of a quandary. One alternative is that he can admit the fact and say that he simply ‘trusts’ his ability to reason and operates with that as his basic epistemological presupposition. But if this is so, then he cannot in good conscience criticize religious faith, since that too is a kind of trust in things we might not be able to “prove” with mathematical accuracy. Another alternative is that he can admit the fact I have mentioned and collapse into a kind of postmodernism, looking at all things – science included! – with scepticism, since even scientific observations are dependant upon human perception, which cannot be ‘proven’ per se to be reliable!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, if we were living in the Matrix, chances are we wouldn’t know that we were!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same thing holds true for morality. We all – atheists and Christians included – have basic moral instincts. From a Christian point of view, I believe that God is perfect and he gives us a basic knowledge of what is right and wrong. Thus, as a Christian, I can say with conviction that certain things are basically right and others are basically wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But can the atheist say such a thing? Certainly, atheists have moral beliefs, but can they justify those beliefs? After all, if there is no God and if materialistic naturalism is true, then there are no objective moral principles. Whatever morality we might have is purely subjective. Our mind is conditioned to think in a particular way – morally speaking - because of external accidental circumstances. Morality, in an atheistic worldview, inevitably becomes either a psychological construct or a societal one. On the former view, it is primarily evolution that conforms us to have certain moral instincts – and, remember, there is no guarantee that evolution would have taken the path it ultimately took! On the latter view, morality is primarily the result of societal conditioning – we happen to live in a society that values liberty and freedom; therefore, we have learned to value them as well. Had we lived in a cannibalistic society we would have had different moral values. This is called the doctrine of Cultural Relativism, and in this philosophy, no particular moral code is intrinsically superior to another, since they are all cultural constructs and all cultures are equally true and equally false.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is not that atheists don’t have a sense of morality – they certainly do. The problem, rather, is that their metaphysical worldview cripples them from having an objective foundation for their morality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is heart-breaking for me as a Christian to see prominent thinkers and philosophers encourage people to embrace a worldview in which everything is fundamentally meaningless and to “get used to it” (quoting Dr Susan Blackwood in her dialogue with Professor Jordan Peterson on the &lt;em&gt;Unbelievable?&lt;/em&gt; radio podcast). It is just as upsetting to see the rise of postmodern thinking in our world. I am convinced that such a mode of looking at the world will inevitably give birth to a society of depression and despair. And this observation vindicates my deeply Christian belief that only God can give true meaning and value to our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People might find it similarly shocking that I claim atheism degrades human beings. After all, don’t many atheists identify as ‘humanists’? Don’t so many atheists fight so vigorously for human rights and don’t humanists try and oppose oppression around the world? An atheist friend of mine once quipped to me that the modern West is proof that we can have morality without God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t disagree more. And here’s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give one example: most atheists don’t, as far as I know, fight for the rights of the unborn. In fact, prominent atheists like Sam Harris complain that religious bigots such as myself still try to stop embryonic stem cell research. Similarly, I have never heard an atheist oppose the recent legislations that have effectively allowed the monstrosity of late-term abortions in New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not only the unborn who are being marginalized. Peter Singer, a prominent atheist ethicist, openly declares that – like unborn foetuses – new-born infants similarly lack what he calls the essential characteristics of personhood. The troubling implications of such a horrendous line of thinking are so alarming that words fail to convey the emotions that stir up in my heart as I write this article. And what is even more scandalous is that Singer is a vegan, although – as he would put it – a ‘flexible vegan’. In other words, he goes to great lengths to ensure that cows and buffaloes don’t suffer because of him… but that same privilege is not extended even to new-born babies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here’s the thing. I believe that deep down, everyone has a sense of right and wrong. And this sense has been given to them by God. If you want proof that a Divine Law does indeed exist, then turn to your own conscience. I believe that deep down, everyone knows that good and evil are real, but over time they manufacture philosophies and ideologies to rationalise away what they do not want to be true. Because if there is a Divine Law, you are not ‘free’ to enjoy things that are evil, however attractive or pleasurable that might be. And if there is a Divine Law, there must also be a Divine Law-giver before whom we are all accountable for our actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not saying that you can’t be good without fear of punishment. On the contrary, I believe that the good should be sought for its own sake, rather than merely out of servile fear. Rather, what I am saying is that if there is no God, then good and evil are both illusions and have no real existence. And if that is so, then everything is permitted, since all things are then morally equal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the disastrous implications of the revolution that our world has initiated against God. And you will then forgive me when I say that atheism is not a boon. It is, in fact, poison.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It might sound strange to say that atheism destroys science. Indeed, many will laugh merely upon reading the heading of this article. However, my interactions with sceptics and postmodernists have convinced me that while it may seem to many that atheism leads to science and moral progress, the truth is exactly the opposite. Rather than upholding science, atheism destroys the foundations that underlie science; and far from promoting human progress, atheism degrades humanity and inevitably leads to moral decay in society. Not only that, I am also deeply convinced that a postmodernist attitude is simply the result of centuries of atheist influence upon the West; a true atheist will, in my opinion, adopt a postmodern outlook sooner or later. In this article, I hope to show why I think this is the case.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Memoirs of an Ex-Muslim: Lies, Propaganda and Truth</title>
      <link href="/Memoirs-of-an-Ex-Muslim" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Memoirs of an Ex-Muslim: Lies, Propaganda and Truth" />
      <published>2019-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Memoirs-of-an-Ex-Muslim</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Memoirs-of-an-Ex-Muslim">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following is an opinion piece submitted by a contributor who wishes to remain anonymous.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My time in Iran as a Muslim now seems like the distant past. The beautiful and almost transcendent experience of being a Muslim comes with its costs. But what are these costs, some people ask? Is it not true that having a religious foundation helps society and isn’t Islam the religion of peace?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the answers to those questions are all ‘yes’ if you are a typical person living in Iran. However, let’s not forget that belief - or even fanatical conviction - is not the same as truth. At the time, I was only 16 and was certainly influenced by the constant Islamic propaganda that pervaded every aspect of the Iranian society. I now ask myself whether it was even possible not to believe in the Islamic doctrines at the time since everything ranging from music to media and books were heavily shaped by Islamic beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, our epistemology was based on supposedly revealed scriptures and doctrines. In schools, for instance, the humanities were taught from a purely Islamic perspective, as though these were objective facts alongside science. Any criticism of these would be like saying that atoms do not exist. I am not exaggerating. It is extremely important for non-Iranians to understand how much of an independent thinker one must be in order to go against Islamic doctrines in Iran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why did I leave Islam? Well, after my migration to the UK in 2014, the Islamic propaganda was no longer present in my life. There was this sense of mental liberation that had begun to manifest itself. Despite this, the toxicity and the virus-like the behavior of Islamic ideas made it such that it took me two years to abandon all of my faith in Islam. So for those of you who are reading this, the first step is to understand your religion from within. In my case, I started educating myself about the &lt;em&gt;Hadith&lt;/em&gt; and the history of Islam and the more I investigated, the more disillusioned I became with the faith. It was as though I was walking in a dark tunnel, and soon enough I realised that my expectation of the existing light at the end of the tunnel was illusory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a 16 year old Iranian studying these texts and the history of Islam, I soon became aware that it was not that difficult to lose faith in Islam. Why was it so easy? It would not have been easy in Iran but here in the UK I had access to a vast number of resources and was being exposed to various points of view. In Iran, all I was taught was that the &lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt; was a text filled with amazing scientific truths as well as accurate historical facts. Conversely, it was only in the UK that for the first time I had heard criticism against Muhammad’s character. Surely he was the perfect human being, right? Well, with some study, I realised that that was not the case at all. In fact, all I found was that in the Islamic sources themselves such as in Bukhari and other Hadiths, Muhammad was not only a prophet without any prophecy, but that his actions and beliefs utterly and precisely mirrors that of those in the so-called Islamic State of Iraq and Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, the clue is in the name ‘The Islamic State’ and I am not naïve enough to think that a name could on its own make this proposition true. But, when one looks at the history of Islam and learns about Muhammad who had, on many occasions, committed acts of genocide, pedophilia and had engaged in the institution of sex slavery, one need not go any further. Are those accusations accurate? It depends on what sources you think are credible and statistically speaking, the &lt;em&gt;Hadiths&lt;/em&gt; especially by Bukhari  are believed by Muslims to provide the life of Prophet Muhammad with a fair amount of accuracy. And, for those who do not subscribe to the credibility of these texts, there is an even more challenging problem; which is that, they do not have any credible source of even making the proposition that Muhammad existed as a person in history. So either, Muhammad was a morally repugnant human being or he never existed, and even if he did, there is not enough historical evidence to render that belief plausible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something even more embarrassing is that Muhammad is actually rarely mentioned in the &lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt;, which is, also a book filled with commands for sex slavery and genocide; in addition to that, the &lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt; clearly places women on a far lower pedestal than men. All these are not mere assertions. Those who study these texts are well aware of the existence of these commands and events but they try to contextualise them and give reasons for why they happened. Here, I think I am completely justified to compare this to someone who justifies the crimes committed by Hitler by giving reasons as to why they happened, in order to provide a moral account for the actions committed by him. There is no excuse for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the most reprehensible of all crimes against humanity: to justify the evils of the past and to not recognise them. For if we don’t recognise them, we are doomed to repeat them. The fact that Muhammad (PeACE Be UPoN hIM) married a six year old should not be something up for contextualisation or debate. The fact that Muhammad took sex slaves should not be a matter for contextualisation or debate. Some actions are just so intrinsically wrong that no reasoning could render them moral&lt;/em&gt;. Similarly, there is absolutely no situation under which Muhammad was justified to take sex slaves (&lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt; 33:50, &lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt; 4:24). Let’s look at the latter example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;And all married women (are forbidden unto you) save those (captives) whom your right hands possess.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, we see that slaves regardless of their marital status are basically the property of those who capture them, as Nadia Murad was. In essence, the deity of the &lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt; clearly permits rape for war slaves. This is what I mean when I say that there are actions which are never justified. And hopefully, now you see why I lost my faith so rapidly after reading these texts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really hope that Muslims start to read and educate themselves with their own sources, for if not, history is bound to repeat itself as it is repeating itself now and no one is paying attention.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>anon.anon</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The following is an opinion piece submitted by a contributor who wishes to remain anonymous.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Uncomfortable Parallels: The Revenge of the Anglophone Elites</title>
      <link href="/Uncomfortable-Parallels" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Uncomfortable Parallels: The Revenge of the Anglophone Elites" />
      <published>2019-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Uncomfortable-Parallels</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Uncomfortable-Parallels">&lt;p&gt;The political elite of the United States, in the form of Democrats in the Congress, Democrats in the media, and jealous Republicans in the political establishment, are all upset that the people rejected them in favour of a populist man with zero political experience or connections, and have now united together for the first time since the bomb that was the Mueller testimony to try and overturn the election of 2016. They have announced they will support the impeachment of the American President, although House Speaker Pelosi’s ‘announcement’ of an ‘impeachment inquiry’ thus far has no actual effect because there hasn’t been a vote taken in the House on the issue. However, by September 26, 2019, there were 217 Democrats announcing they’d vote in favour of such an inquiry plus former Republican Justin Amash of Michigan, giving the majority of 218 needed if a vote were brought to the floor. So what did the bad orange man do that finally pushed a majority of the oldest democratic legislative body in the world to declare their official attempts to prematurely remove the chief executive, elected independently of themselves by the people? He talked to a foreign president about trying to end corruption in said President’s nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, a majority of members of the US House of Representatives want to now overturn an election of over 120,000,000 voters and 538 electors because the President that process produced talked to President Vladimir Zelensky of Ukraine to ask him what he was doing to fight corruption. Nothing about threats, nothing about money, and nothing about the election. In fact, while the media and the left all across the world have been screaming about the ‘fact’ that there is a ‘coverup’ or that there was ‘quid pro quo’ or even ‘election interference’ in the form of investigating Trump’s ‘opponent’, they have completely missed that the transcript of the call in question was released and says nothing of the sort. Joe Biden is not Trump’s opponent and there is corruption in the Ukraine that Trump wants to look at, which could possibly include Vice President Joe Biden actually withholding money from Ukraine until they fired a prosecutor looking into a company involving his son, Hunter. Finally, and probably most importantly, not a single mention of aid appears, nor are there any threats. In total, it is a nothingburger, but the leftists in all spheres, from media to Congress, have organised to move forward in the next attempt to throw out the president for the crime of winning the 2016 election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could very well spell trouble for the Democrats in 2020, with Speaker Pelosi going so far as to say “we have to impeach him, even if it means we lose the House in 2020.” The left knows very well the fire it is playing with and this will most likely backfire on them gloriously. However, for the time being, they are playing their hand and doing everything they can to ensure that Trump is taken out somehow. While this effort is doomed to fail like previous efforts, to see them so united in such a hostile manner, essentially unmasking themselves for the radicals they really are, it becomes clear how big the fight for the future of the United States and its culture will be in the coming years. They don’t just want to get rid of Trump, but they would also like to force everyone who supported him to witness his overthrow as an example of what happens when you upset their little club by getting uppity and thinking you should have a voice in government. That type of mentality leads to dark roads and must be rejected and defeated at every turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings me across the pond to Britain, going through its own democratic crisis due to its own 2016 middle finger to the elites, Brexit. Since that day, the elite Remainers in all parties had been fighting long and hard to overturn the results, however they just could not unite to do it. Not that Brexiteers in power have been the most united, however, their message has been consistent throughout: deliver Brexit with a good deal or leave the EU on World Trade Organisation rules two years after the invocation of Article 50. Theresa May, a Remainer at heart, extended the current deadline of October 31 due to her abysmal withdrawal treaty suffering three humiliating defeats in the House of Commons before the original deadline. So when she was finally deposed and more upbeat, can do, ‘we will leave, do or die’ Boris Johnson took her place, it seemed things would be going okay for the Brexiteers, and Remainers would finally be on the path to the dustbin of history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the Parliament first met under PM Johnson and votes started happening, after his announcement of the prorogation of Parliament to put a fresh Queen’s Speech down and finally end the longest Parliament since the Rump Parliament during the English Civil War. This reasonable request was met by Remainer elites in the media, Labour Party, Liberal Democrats, Scottish National Party, and bitter, anti democratic, Conservatives with screeches of “Stop the coup” and “this is a dictatorship.” They declared the reduction of the session by four days was designed to take away debate for the apocalypse they think would be a no-deal Brexit. The fact that they have been debating and fear-mongering on for over three years at this point has not seemed to occur to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next came the fact that PM Johnson started losing every vote put to the floor, including one which effectively called for the formation of a new government by the back door and was made a motion of confidence in the Conservative Party, and resulted in the loss of the majority to where it currently stands at -44. Because of the ungovernability of such a position, Johnson asked for an election to be had under the Fixed Terms Parliaments Act…twice. Both times, it was rejected by the opposition and the former Conservative members of Parliament. They then claimed it was undemocratic what Johnson was doing and they would not abide so long as no-deal was still an option. Their rejection of an election was hailed by their friends in the media as them standing up to the declared disdain for democracy Johnson supposedly has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prorogation finally went into effect, however, and the legal battles were to continue on whether the PM had to seek an extension. Then came the Supreme Court of the United Kingdom, squarely and officially inserting themselves into the political process by declaring the entire thing unlawful and ordering Parliament back. They did come back, just to further show their absolute ineffectiveness as they currently stand. They have essentially thrown out the government and inserted themselves as the government without asking the people or through a motion of no-confidence. They continue to reject an election to be held because they know the people can see right through their nonsense and would reject them at the ballot box for this. However, like in America, they currently have united and will work tirelessly to show to the people who dared vote against them in 2016 that they are to never rise up and do it again—a state-of-affairs that could be fatal to the deal negotiated by Johnson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Anglophone leftist/Remainer elites are now a united force once again, reinvigorated by a media class who have as much an interest in overturning the greatest political mandate in British history and the biggest electoral upset in modern American history. They have the reigns of government for the time being in both nations and are ramping up their efforts to put down these uprisings once and for all, presumably as one final big push as they know they will lose. In their desperate last grasps at power, they do not care if they destroy the greatest democratic organisations in the world. They will lie about those who dared choose Brexit or Trump. They will destroy the lives of anybody who helped in making those momentous occasions to happen. They will only be emboldened if they are able to complete their missions in destroying the idea of democratic governance. We must not let them do so. They need to be soundly rejected and defeated at the ballot box and need to be stopped from overturning previous election results they do not like. If we fail to do so, the uncomfortable parallels between the two great Anglophone nations will go from uncomfortable to disastrous.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sam Valk</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The political elite of the United States, in the form of Democrats in the Congress, Democrats in the media, and jealous Republicans in the political establishment, are all upset that the people rejected them in favour of a populist man with zero political experience or connections, and have now united together for the first time since the bomb that was the Mueller testimony to try and overturn the election of 2016. They have announced they will support the impeachment of the American President, although House Speaker Pelosi’s ‘announcement’ of an ‘impeachment inquiry’ thus far has no actual effect because there hasn’t been a vote taken in the House on the issue. However, by September 26, 2019, there were 217 Democrats announcing they’d vote in favour of such an inquiry plus former Republican Justin Amash of Michigan, giving the majority of 218 needed if a vote were brought to the floor. So what did the bad orange man do that finally pushed a majority of the oldest democratic legislative body in the world to declare their official attempts to prematurely remove the chief executive, elected independently of themselves by the people? He talked to a foreign president about trying to end corruption in said President’s nation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What Feminism Ought To Be?</title>
      <link href="/What-Feminism-Ought-To-Be" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Feminism Ought To Be?" />
      <published>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-Feminism-Ought-To-Be</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-Feminism-Ought-To-Be">&lt;p&gt;There is no reason why one shouldn’t be a feminist in this day and age. Any suggestion that is contrary to the notion that women’s rights ought to be protected and that patriarchy ought to be completely dismantled is, ipso facto, foolish and thoroughly immoral. But, post the #metoo movement and torrents of online rage from ‘feminists’, one is bound to ask: is this supposed collective expression of anger against societal discrimination, sexual harrasment and patriarchal structures, well-intentioned as it may be, leading to a material change in the status of women in society? To answer that question in the affirmative seems disingenuous at best and nefarious at worst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The #metoo movement has been both shocking yet brilliant in exposing the rot beneath the veneer of equality. But has this exposition led to meaningful change? Or, for that matter, do passionate supporters of the #metoo movement really seek to bring about changes in, say, sexual harassment legislation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent seminar organised by the Calcutta High Court and American embassy in Calcutta, I was woken up to the reality of how precious little had changed with regard to America’s Civil Rights Act of 1964 or India’s Sexual Harassment of Women at Workplace (Prevention, Prohibition and Redressal) Act, 2013 in the wake of the #metoo movement. There are umpteen criticisms that can be made of both these laws, but one with regard to each should suffice to illustrate why these laws are programmed to protect the Harvey Weinsteins of our age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian Act contemplates an Internal Complaints Committee to function as a redressal mechanism for aggrieved women in a workplace of more than ten employees. The Committee does require an external member who is familiar with issues relating to sexual assault or from an organisation committed to the cause of women, but the nagging sense that this is a mechanism where the “fox is guarding the hen’s house” disturbingly remains. In the case of the American Civil Rights Act, the same ends up happening even though complaints are supposed to be filed with the external US Equal Employment Opportunity Commission. This is because of two American Supreme Court decisions in &lt;em&gt;Faragher v. City of Boca Raton&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Burlington v. Ellerth&lt;/em&gt;. While both these decisions attempted to clarify the law, they inadvertently laid down a point of law that has, in the words of &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5319966/sexual-harassment-scotus-anniversary/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; magazine, “contributed to a key reason why workplace sexual harassment lawsuits are still hard to file today”. The Supreme Court ruled in these cases that an employer may not be liable under the Civil Rights Act for sexual harassment if, inter alia, the complainant fails to take advantage of any internal mechanisms for redressal of the complaint provided by the employer. In other words, we have a situation not dissimilar to the state of the Indian law, where a potential victim of sexual harassment must reckon with the fox before she can truly reach the hen’s house. This, quite obviously, means that numerous sexual harassment claims simply go unnoticed and are, quite simply, suppressed in America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That these and other legal issues have been significant contributors to the extent of harassment and abuse exposed by the #metoo movement ought to be apparent to anyone with a brain. However, a call for reforms to such laws is hardly the defining conversation of today’s feminist movements. Indeed, one can appreciate that perhaps the nitty-gritties of legal reform cannot form part of an exoteric conversation. But one cannot deny that if feminists engaged in advocating meaningful legislative reform with half the passion that they use to ‘destroy’ incels and dudebros online, we would be living in a better world. This is not an anti-feminist rant from a privileged little boy, it is a Greta Thunbergesque (&lt;em&gt;bless her&lt;/em&gt;) “how dare you?!” to all those who claim to stand for women’s rights but are so pathetic at delivering those rights to women. Of course, it is important that society evolves to develop zero tolerance for misogynistic bigots, but to pay more attention to a hurtful tweet instead of the silent suffering of so many working women is rather dystopian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of misplaced priorities, we must address the representation of women in the workplace, and, of course, the feminist’s refusal to do anything real about it. As was pointed out by Baroness Arden of Heswall, Deputy President of the UK Supreme Court, in a guest lecture at the University of Bristol (which I had the privilege to attend), the percentage of women who were partners in London law firms in 2019, 100 years after women got the right to practice law in England, was a mere 29%. What’s more, Lady Arden stated that when she, as a Judge of the English Court of Appeal, proposed that a daycare centre be set up for women barristers near the Royal Courts of Justice, the other male Judges simply dismissed her by stating that this would be a nuisance to male barristers. That Lady Arden was a Judge of the Court of Appeal from 2000-2018 should serve to indicate that such horrendous attitudes are definitely not from some distant age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern feminist’s response to these facts and realities is not very different from the dialogues delivered by Samuel L Jackson in &lt;em&gt;Pulp Fiction&lt;/em&gt;, they are expressions of “furious anger” that seek to lay their vengeance upon men. But these responses are, to quote The Merovingian from the second &lt;em&gt;Matrix&lt;/em&gt; movie, “so boring, so obvious, so bourgeoisie.” They very simply ignore the import of Lady Arden’s arguments: that the next step towards a greater representation of women in the workplace requires some important tangible changes. For instance, one needs to ensure mandatory maternity leave as well as paternity leave is a reality in all big organisations—something that is far from being a reality in a country as developed as America. Secondly, one needs to concentrate on making daycare cheaper and more accessible to women so that the beauty of becoming a mother doesn’t end up penalising a booming career. Thirdly, one needs to change office culture and, sorry right-wing crackpots, that includes ensuring that air conditioning is not set in accordance with the metabolism of middle-aged men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, battling against the patriarchy to implement such changes sounds awfully hard, it is far easier to just obsess over cats (okay, fair enough, they are amazing) and share disgustingly bad feminist slam poetry. Why challenge patriarchs to be better and to do better when one can simply raise one’s hands and declare that they’re trash. And not to mention, how could we possibly change attitudes surrounding women without changing the colour of people’s toys. All of this is not for some comedic effect, it is to expose the Goebbellian lie that is modern feminism, a movement (if it can be called one) that concentrates less on change and more on empty expressions of supposed solidarity with the numerous problems faced by women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most dangerous effects of this is borne out by the feminist’s treatment of rape culture. Speaking logically, one would presume that the only way to destroy an oppressive social construct like rape culture is to teach people to know better. But that definitely is not what today’s feminist does. Today’s feminist hardly seeks to bat for rigorous consent classes in universities and schools. They rarely seek to educate people on understanding the humanity of women and they are loathe to contemplate on how men can be used as allies in combating rape culture. This not only fails to go to the root of the problem by dealing with the cultural rot that a priori drives men’s most problematic behaviours, it has far more nefarious effects. This misandry-is-feminism attitude of so many feminists incentivises a lot of men to simply pretend to be feminists in a bid to get sex. And it should go without saying that this is a most poisonous kind of objectification that relies on its antithesis to survive and grow. This verily means that feminists end up giving traction to a very fundamental sabotage of their own movement by refusing to actually deal with a problem and by stooping to lowly instinct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of that being said, credit must be given where credit is due, modern feminism has been very sharp in changing broader culture to simply not be accommodative of abusers and bigots. It has created a rightfully hostile environment for those who would dare say that women are lesser than men and it has clarified that sexist attitudes are simply not going to fly anymore. However, that is simply not enough. One has to go beyond a great grand shriek about how sexist and patriarchal the world is to actually contemplate upon how it could look better. And one has to understand that without such a constructive contemplation, one is going to have a world with a smokescreen of verbose activism but with a ground reality of festering oppression.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There is no reason why one shouldn’t be a feminist in this day and age. Any suggestion that is contrary to the notion that women’s rights ought to be protected and that patriarchy ought to be completely dismantled is, ipso facto, foolish and thoroughly immoral. But, post the #metoo movement and torrents of online rage from ‘feminists’, one is bound to ask: is this supposed collective expression of anger against societal discrimination, sexual harrasment and patriarchal structures, well-intentioned as it may be, leading to a material change in the status of women in society? To answer that question in the affirmative seems disingenuous at best and nefarious at worst.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Groupthink: A World-Governing Herd Mentality</title>
      <link href="/A-World-Governing-Herd-Mentality" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Groupthink: A World-Governing Herd Mentality" />
      <published>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-World-Governing-Herd-Mentality</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-World-Governing-Herd-Mentality">&lt;p&gt;We’ve all followed the pack at some points of time in our lives. Be it decisions
about what kind of studies to pursue, which rat race to run, which Beyblade to
buy or which new friend to include in our otherwise exclusive gang. Why we like
to do so is because it’s easier than thinking for oneself. Once you figure out
how this same thought process affects government policies, major industries,
workplace regulations, national elections, and other such important-sounding
things, you realise that maybe even important people, unlike us, have an
inherent laziness seen in their readiness to accept the easiest narrative. This,
however, is just the tip of the iceberg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what Irving L Janis, a research psychologist from Yale University, set
out to establish when he pioneered the initial research on groupthink - a term
inspired by doublethink, the phenomenon of accepting two contradictory beliefs
because of political propaganda (the term was coined by George Orwell in his
novel &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt;). Janis believed that groups that suffered from groupthink had some
common characteristics among them. He identified 8 common symptoms in his
original paper: &lt;em&gt;invulnerability&lt;/em&gt; in the belief that they can never be defeated,
&lt;em&gt;rationalising&lt;/em&gt; all sorts of warnings that hint towards an adversity that the
group wouldn’t prefer, blind faith in the group’s &lt;em&gt;moral high ground&lt;/em&gt; without
actually considering the consequences, &lt;em&gt;stereotyping&lt;/em&gt; the enemy, &lt;em&gt;peer
pressure&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;self-censorship&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;unanimity&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;mindguards&lt;/em&gt; that prevent
unfavourable but true information from changing the group leader’s decision.
It’s also very interesting to think of group dynamics in this way. Ideally being
in a circle of friends must mean that you find solace in it and you can
gleefully say anything without feeling the need to censor yourself. If this
circle has some unspoken ideals that are conditions for you to remain in it, the
phenomenon of groupthink arises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink offers a sense of comfort. Think of the first time you left for
college, unshackled by the rules that bound you in school. You were probably
afraid of the amount of freedom you had, of how alone you were. You would rather
go back to a time when you were governed by rules, at home, because at the very
least there was someone who would take care of you, every step of the way. You
don’t want to be part of this ugly, competitive world and instead of sorting
life out for yourself, you’d rather have someone else do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting how many instances from history one can draw in order to fit
this model. Janis advances his argument about groupthink, primarily, by talking
about the Bay of Pigs invasion that inevitably led to the defeat of the CIA-led
American personnel. Janis provided proof of the mechanisms that the Kennedy
administration had in place, such that only the anti-communist narrative could
prevail in their decisions, with little space left for dissent. They believed
that, as a communist nation, Cuba had very little firepower against the
capitalist might of the US. Arthur Schlesinger, one of the members of Kennedy’s
circle, was an active dissenter but he was constantly suppressed. In a similar
vein but far worse off is the Vietnam War. The Nixon administration truly
believed they could ride the wave of American integrity being threatened abroad
and communists being inherently evil despite being told that it was unlikely
that they could defeat the Viet Cong. Not only did they end up losing horribly
but also lost the trust of the soldiers, who had been sent on government orders,
and the American public that saw very little wrong in having leftist leanings.
The government earned the wrath of a generation that decided to pour their pain
into anti-war music, psychedelics and alternative living. Lesson learnt: don’t
piss off people who can become the future Rolling Stones or Black Sabbath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US isn’t the only nation to have fallen prey to this. The Chernobyl tragedy
speaks for why unwavering belief in any ideology, especially one that
prioritises the nation over its citizens, is the surest route to disaster. The
Soviet Union’s adherence to not leaking any information about the nuclear power
plant, its belief that it was virtually impossible for any Soviet construction
to fail, let alone one that displayed its true might in a cold war, and
immediate dismissal of scientific backing behind what could happen was what
caused Mikhail Gorbachev to proclaim the Chernobyl disaster as the event that
led to the collapse of the USSR. Nazi Germany is an even better example; people
were wilfully ignorant of the dictatorship’s treatment of Jews in concentration
camps. They believed that the power of the fatherland could extend everywhere
without consequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink is not a thing of the past either. In the present, groupthink is how
groups of people become alienated from other ideas. Elite, educated liberals of
the day choose not to explain their stance to people who oppose them, assuming
the opposition to be &lt;em&gt;inherently stupid&lt;/em&gt;. The same ‘inherently stupid’ then
collectivise and assume majority power. Thereafter, even if someone from this
group is presented with an alternative rationale, they will choose to reject it
due to the distrust that has already been formed. This is best exemplified in
how, in an age where political correctness has become a ‘necessity’, anyone with
a contrary view of things is bashed instead of educated. This is not to say that
all political correctness is unwarranted. However, if liberals choose to deride
rather than increase awareness then they are simply contributing to the
aforementioned alienation. On the other hand, conservatives around the world
(who often overlap with the aforementioned ‘inherently stupid’) stick to
societal norms that have existed for ages, even if they’re regressive.
Groupthink is often the basis for dinner table conversations that revolve around
politics; opposition to the favourite narrative, if any, will be met with loud,
sharp words. These dynamics are used to the advantage of politicians like Donald
Trump, who know how to appeal to their voter base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink extends beyond politics. It led to the subprime crisis in 2008. The
financial industry ardently believed that no rational human being would ever
default on his/her home loan. However, they took this to mean that loans could
be given to anyone and everyone, and then they built complex securities based on
these loans that were dependent on each other. The dot-com bubble in the early
2000’s is a good example too. The internet was the hottest property that was
virtual, and people were naturally excited about its potential. This sentiment
led to massive overvaluation of companies that merely had a website which
combined with tech companies prioritising growth over profit and cash flow
stability, led to the downfall of a number of firms. It is happening even today,
with startups like Uber and WeWork launching their initial public offerings.
WeWork is currently burning cash, and it has been subject to lots of scrutiny by
the market. Adam Neumann, the founder, was recently ousted from the post of CEO.
Uber took a huge plunge on its first day of going public. This shows how
groupthink is responsible for hype value. Brands like Supreme, that rely simply
on their logo being printed on what would otherwise be a plain white T-shirt,
have the power of hype working in their favour. This hype has no concrete basis
like quality. It builds up through targeted marketing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does one escape groupthink? Most articles state one method right off the
bat: create awareness of critical thinking skills that lead to thoughtful
criticism. It might just be the case that what we do not wish to hear is what
truly makes sense to us at times. Silence isn’t proof of consent from members.
People who do not speak up must be encouraged to talk, since it’s entirely
possible that they don’t want to only out of the fear of being chastised.
Another way is to have the leader of the group take a poll before they announce
their opinion. In that way, especially if the poll is anonymous, those who were
not comfortable providing a perspective contrarian to the existing status quo
can freely say what they want to. Another way is to appoint a devil’s advocate
specifically for this purpose, or a red-team that makes a B-plan in contrast to
yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink offers a comfortable seat where you may not have to do a lot of
thinking, or take a lot of responsibility. If a decision goes horribly wrong,
then no &lt;em&gt;single&lt;/em&gt; individual can be held accountable. However, if everyone in a
group feels a heightened sense of pride towards the goal of a group, and can be
made to believe that their actions have a large impact, positive or negative,
then decisions will be taken with greater forethought and discussion. In times
that value nuanced discussions over various ideas, we must be heading towards
the ideal of free-flowing thought instead succumbing to peer pressure.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pranav Manie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">We’ve all followed the pack at some points of time in our lives. Be it decisions about what kind of studies to pursue, which rat race to run, which Beyblade to buy or which new friend to include in our otherwise exclusive gang. Why we like to do so is because it’s easier than thinking for oneself. Once you figure out how this same thought process affects government policies, major industries, workplace regulations, national elections, and other such important-sounding things, you realise that maybe even important people, unlike us, have an inherent laziness seen in their readiness to accept the easiest narrative. This, however, is just the tip of the iceberg. This is what Irving L Janis, a research psychologist from Yale University, set out to establish when he pioneered the initial research on groupthink - a term inspired by doublethink, the phenomenon of accepting two contradictory beliefs because of political propaganda (the term was coined by George Orwell in his novel 1984). Janis believed that groups that suffered from groupthink had some common characteristics among them. He identified 8 common symptoms in his original paper: invulnerability in the belief that they can never be defeated, rationalising all sorts of warnings that hint towards an adversity that the group wouldn’t prefer, blind faith in the group’s moral high ground without actually considering the consequences, stereotyping the enemy, peer pressure, self-censorship, unanimity and mindguards that prevent unfavourable but true information from changing the group leader’s decision. It’s also very interesting to think of group dynamics in this way. Ideally being in a circle of friends must mean that you find solace in it and you can gleefully say anything without feeling the need to censor yourself. If this circle has some unspoken ideals that are conditions for you to remain in it, the phenomenon of groupthink arises. Groupthink offers a sense of comfort. Think of the first time you left for college, unshackled by the rules that bound you in school. You were probably afraid of the amount of freedom you had, of how alone you were. You would rather go back to a time when you were governed by rules, at home, because at the very least there was someone who would take care of you, every step of the way. You don’t want to be part of this ugly, competitive world and instead of sorting life out for yourself, you’d rather have someone else do it. It’s interesting how many instances from history one can draw in order to fit this model. Janis advances his argument about groupthink, primarily, by talking about the Bay of Pigs invasion that inevitably led to the defeat of the CIA-led American personnel. Janis provided proof of the mechanisms that the Kennedy administration had in place, such that only the anti-communist narrative could prevail in their decisions, with little space left for dissent. They believed that, as a communist nation, Cuba had very little firepower against the capitalist might of the US. Arthur Schlesinger, one of the members of Kennedy’s circle, was an active dissenter but he was constantly suppressed. In a similar vein but far worse off is the Vietnam War. The Nixon administration truly believed they could ride the wave of American integrity being threatened abroad and communists being inherently evil despite being told that it was unlikely that they could defeat the Viet Cong. Not only did they end up losing horribly but also lost the trust of the soldiers, who had been sent on government orders, and the American public that saw very little wrong in having leftist leanings. The government earned the wrath of a generation that decided to pour their pain into anti-war music, psychedelics and alternative living. Lesson learnt: don’t piss off people who can become the future Rolling Stones or Black Sabbath. The US isn’t the only nation to have fallen prey to this. The Chernobyl tragedy speaks for why unwavering belief in any ideology, especially one that prioritises the nation over its citizens, is the surest route to disaster. The Soviet Union’s adherence to not leaking any information about the nuclear power plant, its belief that it was virtually impossible for any Soviet construction to fail, let alone one that displayed its true might in a cold war, and immediate dismissal of scientific backing behind what could happen was what caused Mikhail Gorbachev to proclaim the Chernobyl disaster as the event that led to the collapse of the USSR. Nazi Germany is an even better example; people were wilfully ignorant of the dictatorship’s treatment of Jews in concentration camps. They believed that the power of the fatherland could extend everywhere without consequence. Groupthink is not a thing of the past either. In the present, groupthink is how groups of people become alienated from other ideas. Elite, educated liberals of the day choose not to explain their stance to people who oppose them, assuming the opposition to be inherently stupid. The same ‘inherently stupid’ then collectivise and assume majority power. Thereafter, even if someone from this group is presented with an alternative rationale, they will choose to reject it due to the distrust that has already been formed. This is best exemplified in how, in an age where political correctness has become a ‘necessity’, anyone with a contrary view of things is bashed instead of educated. This is not to say that all political correctness is unwarranted. However, if liberals choose to deride rather than increase awareness then they are simply contributing to the aforementioned alienation. On the other hand, conservatives around the world (who often overlap with the aforementioned ‘inherently stupid’) stick to societal norms that have existed for ages, even if they’re regressive. Groupthink is often the basis for dinner table conversations that revolve around politics; opposition to the favourite narrative, if any, will be met with loud, sharp words. These dynamics are used to the advantage of politicians like Donald Trump, who know how to appeal to their voter base. Groupthink extends beyond politics. It led to the subprime crisis in 2008. The financial industry ardently believed that no rational human being would ever default on his/her home loan. However, they took this to mean that loans could be given to anyone and everyone, and then they built complex securities based on these loans that were dependent on each other. The dot-com bubble in the early 2000’s is a good example too. The internet was the hottest property that was virtual, and people were naturally excited about its potential. This sentiment led to massive overvaluation of companies that merely had a website which combined with tech companies prioritising growth over profit and cash flow stability, led to the downfall of a number of firms. It is happening even today, with startups like Uber and WeWork launching their initial public offerings. WeWork is currently burning cash, and it has been subject to lots of scrutiny by the market. Adam Neumann, the founder, was recently ousted from the post of CEO. Uber took a huge plunge on its first day of going public. This shows how groupthink is responsible for hype value. Brands like Supreme, that rely simply on their logo being printed on what would otherwise be a plain white T-shirt, have the power of hype working in their favour. This hype has no concrete basis like quality. It builds up through targeted marketing. How does one escape groupthink? Most articles state one method right off the bat: create awareness of critical thinking skills that lead to thoughtful criticism. It might just be the case that what we do not wish to hear is what truly makes sense to us at times. Silence isn’t proof of consent from members. People who do not speak up must be encouraged to talk, since it’s entirely possible that they don’t want to only out of the fear of being chastised. Another way is to have the leader of the group take a poll before they announce their opinion. In that way, especially if the poll is anonymous, those who were not comfortable providing a perspective contrarian to the existing status quo can freely say what they want to. Another way is to appoint a devil’s advocate specifically for this purpose, or a red-team that makes a B-plan in contrast to yours. Groupthink offers a comfortable seat where you may not have to do a lot of thinking, or take a lot of responsibility. If a decision goes horribly wrong, then no single individual can be held accountable. However, if everyone in a group feels a heightened sense of pride towards the goal of a group, and can be made to believe that their actions have a large impact, positive or negative, then decisions will be taken with greater forethought and discussion. In times that value nuanced discussions over various ideas, we must be heading towards the ideal of free-flowing thought instead succumbing to peer pressure.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What Makes Bengal Bangla?</title>
      <link href="/What-Makes-Bengal-Bangla" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Makes Bengal Bangla?" />
      <published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-Makes-Bengal-Bangla</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-Makes-Bengal-Bangla">&lt;p&gt;This year, on our (India’s) Independence Day, a group of my friends were talking
about the celebrations when one of them mentioned that he feels that Bengalis
are the most patriotic of all in India. I had never really given this a lot of
thought before but the comment got me thinking: do we Bengalis really put our
country before everything? Do we put India before Bengal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always lived in the state of West Bengal, India. Now that I am studying
in Goa with people of different backgrounds and from different states, I see a
lot of differences between our culture and that of the rest of the country.
While we do share similar sentiments of pride towards our culture as the other
Indian states, the way our love for our traditions and heritage finds
manifestation is wildly different from anywhere else, possibly in the whole
world. For the longest time, India has taken pride in its diversity. The country
seeks unity in acknowledging, respecting and preserving the diversity in
culture, lineage and heritage. When politicians come up with ideas involving
linguistic homogenization of the country, India and her people respond with
passionate protests. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Language, an integral part of an ethnic group’s culture and an essence of their
non-material heritage, is a powerful political tool. It has the power to unify
nations like it did for Italy and Germany and on the other hand, create
conflicts like Catalonia and Spain. Language has been a central factor in the
demarcation of states in India. The ethno-linguistic divisions are definitely
not perfect for there exists over a hundred languages and more of their dialects
in the country. As a result, the political map of India is forever changing with
Telangana being born in 2014 and the fight for the Nepali majority Darjeeling
district of West Bengal’s fight for a separate state, Gorkhaland, still being
on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way Bengalis feel about their language is slightly different though. They
have never been afraid of giving up their lives to preserve their
mother-language, Bangla (or Bangali as non-Bengalis would call it). Unlike
France and groups of Gandhian ideologues, Bengalis do not seek to elevate their
mother-tongue to a higher pedestal only to counter the supremacy of English
(colonial language for the Indians). It is our love for our language,
literature, art and so on and so forth that make us do so, all thanks to the
Bangali Renaissance of the 1700s-1900s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1947, when British India was partitioned into the Republic of India and the
Islamic Republic of Pakistan right before their independence from colonial rule,
East Bengal became East Pakistan, solely because of the fact that it was home to
a majority of the Muslim population. Besides, the 200 years of the British
colonial policy of ‘Divide and Rule’ had proven to be remarkably efficacious,
resulting in alienating and pitting the Hindus and Muslims against each other in
the erstwhile state of Bengal. This helped in the Partition of Bengal into East
and West Bengal by the then British viceroy, Lord Curzon in 1905. Various
movements sprung up against the partition. Famous freedom fighter and future
Nobel-laureate, Rabindranath Tagore encouraged the celebration of
Raksha-Bandhan, a Hindu festival to honour the bond between a brother and a
sister, between Hindus and Muslims instead. Songs celebrating the unity between
the two religions found popularity as battle-cries of the energetic protests
against the actions of the English. However, Indians failed to stop what in my
personal opinion has been one of the most strategic ways to destroy Bengal’s
unity and a future as a unified state. The Partition of Bengal was later
annulled in 1911 but the province was never to be the same again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India was similarly partitioned, yet again, right before the transfer of power
in 1947. East Bengal was handed over to Prime Minister Jinnah’s Pakistan in a
platter that year. 55% of Pakistan’s population resided in East Pakistan and
yet, the distant minority residing in West Pakistan was to rule over them. This
lead to a great deal of resentment and problems, and they were not just limited
to the communication issues resulting from the uncomfortable fact that the two
halves of the country were separated by the state of India. Urdu was to be given
the status of the national language, effectively making it a language superior
to East Pakistan’s beloved mother-tongue Bangla. The Bangladesh Liberation
Movement, which finally concluded with the birth of yet another country,
Bangladesh in 1971, found momentum because of the Bangali population’s love for
their &lt;em&gt;Bangaliayana&lt;/em&gt;- the Bangali culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dhaka University played a central role in this movement. No wonder it had to see
blood spilt multiple times. One of the most shocking incidents of this movement,
fuelled by the love for Bangla also happens to be one of those incidents that
Bangalis, across borders, hold very close to heart. It took place on February
21st, 1952, when 4 students of Dhaka University were killed by the Pakistani
forces for opposing the sole use of Urdu in educational institutions across the
Bangali majority region. Today, the UN commemorates this day (21st of February)
as the International Mother Language Day every year. Every Bangali looks back at
this massacre with pride and respect because it symbolises the fact that their
love for their language is stronger than anything else can ever be.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, Bangalis have always been a very politically active culture. They
have never shied away from a revolution. The fact that most revolutionaries of
the Independence Movement were Bangali bears testimony to this fact. Even today,
West Bengal finds itself amidst protests and revolutions against what it
considers wrong throughout the year. It has already witnessed the &lt;em&gt;Doctor’s
Revolution&lt;/em&gt; and the protest against ABVP and RSS’s Hindutva-centric actions in
Jadavpur University this year itself. People of West Bengal’s love for
revolutions, change and socialism lies in stark contrast to the political
compass of most of the other parts of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sentimental views of how Bangladesh and the Bangali majority regions of India
ought to be a single country has existed for quite some time now. In fact, Prime
Minister Clement Attlee of UK predicted that Bengal would want to be united
under a single banner- it would want to rise above the religious demarcations
that virtually defined the rest of the country and unify for the love of Bangla
in 1946. HS Suhrawardy, the then premier of Bengal explained his stance in
support of an ‘independent, undivided and sovereign Bengal’ and appealed to the
masses on April 27th of 1947:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Let us pause for a moment to consider what Bengal can be if it remains united.
It will be a great country, indeed the richest and the most prosperous in India
capable of giving to its people a high standard of living, where a great people
will be able to rise to the fullest height of their stature, a land that will
truly be plentiful. It will be rich in agriculture, rich in industry and
commerce and in the course of time it will be one of the most powerful and
progressive states of the world. If Bengal remains united this will be no dream,
no fantasy.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the appeal to the Bangali exceptionalism, left-wingers supported this
cause, blaming all of Bengal’s ills on the non-Bangali capitalists. GD Birla was
quoted saying: “I am in favour of separation, and I do not think it is
impracticable or against the interest of Hindus” as early as 1942, on behalf of
the Marwari business community in Kolkata. If only the plan for Bengal
unification had been all about catering to the sole interests of Hindus. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even MA Jinnah supported the cause instead of wanting Bengal for Pakistan
although he had a slightly different reasoning, stating: “what is the use of
Bengal without Calcutta?” The most influential supporter of the plan to make
Bengal a separate nation was Sarat Chandra Bose, a popular congressman and the
elder brother of the celebrated freedom fighter, Subhash Chandra Bose. The
proposal for United Bengal involved equal quotas for Hindus and Muslims in the
military and the police, which were to be indigenised and ‘manned by Bangalis’.
The plan that was eventually made public on May 24th of 1947, 10 days before the
final Partition plan was announced, provided for a Hindu-Muslim coalition
Government in Unified Bengal. The Prime Minister was to be a Muslim and the Home
Minister a Hindu. However, the Hindu-Muslim riots in Kolkata around the same
time and the open opposition to the unification of Bengal by Sardar Vallabhai
Patil, Jawaharlal Nehru and later even Gandhiji, eventually led to this plan
being discarded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why most non-Bangali Indian leaders failed to support the idea of the
formation of a third country is because they thought that it would lay down a
precedent for other states to follow and demand independence. On May 27th, 1947,
Nehru made a formal declaration that he would support the unification only if
Bengal was to remain as a part of the Indian Union. This sparked a response from
the last British Governor of Bengal, Sir Frederick Burrows: “Bengal will be
sacrificed at the altar of Nehru’s all-India outlook.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sentiments did not, however, die with the failure of the plan to unify
Bengal in 1947. The Brihot Bangla or Bishal Bangla Movement (Greater Bengal
Movement) is a nationalist political ideology which seeks to unite all bangali
speaking regions of today’s India, Bangladesh and Myanmar into a single nation.
If I am to draw an analogy (although it is very difficult to find one for it is
as unique as it can possibly get), I would say that it is like Kurdistan. The
Kurds are a nation without a state. The Bangalis too are unified by their
language but not by land. bangali literature has always referred to their
country as ‘Bangla’, the same word as they use to refer to their language.
However, Bangla does not refer to either India or Bangladesh, it refers to the
Unified Bengal. So yes, Bangalis are patriotic. But, they are patriotic towards
Bangla before any country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Nehru thought Bengal was just like other Indian states and that the
unification of Bengal and a consequent separate state would result in similar
sentiments in other states like Tamil Nadu, I disagree. The sentiments are
stronger among Bangalis because half of our own state (or country, for a
Bangladeshi) is a separate country. People from West Bengal have grown up with
stories of Bangla and how some of our ancestors had to cross borders during the
Partition and how they still long to go back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nostalgia, the resentment of the Hindu-Muslim divide and the love for
Bangla, both the language and the motherland keeps the emotions and nationalist
sentiments alive even today. For every Bangali, half of their identity lies in
West Bengal and the remaining half lies in Bangladesh. For every Bangali,
language is the identity- not religion, not dialects but Bangla. Whether or not
we are destined to ever be unified is a question yet to be answered. What
doesn’t change is the fact that even though we do not have a separate country of
Bangla, we are still unified as Bangalis.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This year, on our (India’s) Independence Day, a group of my friends were talking about the celebrations when one of them mentioned that he feels that Bengalis are the most patriotic of all in India. I had never really given this a lot of thought before but the comment got me thinking: do we Bengalis really put our country before everything? Do we put India before Bengal? I have always lived in the state of West Bengal, India. Now that I am studying in Goa with people of different backgrounds and from different states, I see a lot of differences between our culture and that of the rest of the country. While we do share similar sentiments of pride towards our culture as the other Indian states, the way our love for our traditions and heritage finds manifestation is wildly different from anywhere else, possibly in the whole world. For the longest time, India has taken pride in its diversity. The country seeks unity in acknowledging, respecting and preserving the diversity in culture, lineage and heritage. When politicians come up with ideas involving linguistic homogenization of the country, India and her people respond with passionate protests.  Language, an integral part of an ethnic group’s culture and an essence of their non-material heritage, is a powerful political tool. It has the power to unify nations like it did for Italy and Germany and on the other hand, create conflicts like Catalonia and Spain. Language has been a central factor in the demarcation of states in India. The ethno-linguistic divisions are definitely not perfect for there exists over a hundred languages and more of their dialects in the country. As a result, the political map of India is forever changing with Telangana being born in 2014 and the fight for the Nepali majority Darjeeling district of West Bengal’s fight for a separate state, Gorkhaland, still being on.  The way Bengalis feel about their language is slightly different though. They have never been afraid of giving up their lives to preserve their mother-language, Bangla (or Bangali as non-Bengalis would call it). Unlike France and groups of Gandhian ideologues, Bengalis do not seek to elevate their mother-tongue to a higher pedestal only to counter the supremacy of English (colonial language for the Indians). It is our love for our language, literature, art and so on and so forth that make us do so, all thanks to the Bangali Renaissance of the 1700s-1900s.  In 1947, when British India was partitioned into the Republic of India and the Islamic Republic of Pakistan right before their independence from colonial rule, East Bengal became East Pakistan, solely because of the fact that it was home to a majority of the Muslim population. Besides, the 200 years of the British colonial policy of ‘Divide and Rule’ had proven to be remarkably efficacious, resulting in alienating and pitting the Hindus and Muslims against each other in the erstwhile state of Bengal. This helped in the Partition of Bengal into East and West Bengal by the then British viceroy, Lord Curzon in 1905. Various movements sprung up against the partition. Famous freedom fighter and future Nobel-laureate, Rabindranath Tagore encouraged the celebration of Raksha-Bandhan, a Hindu festival to honour the bond between a brother and a sister, between Hindus and Muslims instead. Songs celebrating the unity between the two religions found popularity as battle-cries of the energetic protests against the actions of the English. However, Indians failed to stop what in my personal opinion has been one of the most strategic ways to destroy Bengal’s unity and a future as a unified state. The Partition of Bengal was later annulled in 1911 but the province was never to be the same again. India was similarly partitioned, yet again, right before the transfer of power in 1947. East Bengal was handed over to Prime Minister Jinnah’s Pakistan in a platter that year. 55% of Pakistan’s population resided in East Pakistan and yet, the distant minority residing in West Pakistan was to rule over them. This lead to a great deal of resentment and problems, and they were not just limited to the communication issues resulting from the uncomfortable fact that the two halves of the country were separated by the state of India. Urdu was to be given the status of the national language, effectively making it a language superior to East Pakistan’s beloved mother-tongue Bangla. The Bangladesh Liberation Movement, which finally concluded with the birth of yet another country, Bangladesh in 1971, found momentum because of the Bangali population’s love for their Bangaliayana- the Bangali culture. Dhaka University played a central role in this movement. No wonder it had to see blood spilt multiple times. One of the most shocking incidents of this movement, fuelled by the love for Bangla also happens to be one of those incidents that Bangalis, across borders, hold very close to heart. It took place on February 21st, 1952, when 4 students of Dhaka University were killed by the Pakistani forces for opposing the sole use of Urdu in educational institutions across the Bangali majority region. Today, the UN commemorates this day (21st of February) as the International Mother Language Day every year. Every Bangali looks back at this massacre with pride and respect because it symbolises the fact that their love for their language is stronger than anything else can ever be.    Historically, Bangalis have always been a very politically active culture. They have never shied away from a revolution. The fact that most revolutionaries of the Independence Movement were Bangali bears testimony to this fact. Even today, West Bengal finds itself amidst protests and revolutions against what it considers wrong throughout the year. It has already witnessed the Doctor’s Revolution and the protest against ABVP and RSS’s Hindutva-centric actions in Jadavpur University this year itself. People of West Bengal’s love for revolutions, change and socialism lies in stark contrast to the political compass of most of the other parts of India. Sentimental views of how Bangladesh and the Bangali majority regions of India ought to be a single country has existed for quite some time now. In fact, Prime Minister Clement Attlee of UK predicted that Bengal would want to be united under a single banner- it would want to rise above the religious demarcations that virtually defined the rest of the country and unify for the love of Bangla in 1946. HS Suhrawardy, the then premier of Bengal explained his stance in support of an ‘independent, undivided and sovereign Bengal’ and appealed to the masses on April 27th of 1947: “Let us pause for a moment to consider what Bengal can be if it remains united. It will be a great country, indeed the richest and the most prosperous in India capable of giving to its people a high standard of living, where a great people will be able to rise to the fullest height of their stature, a land that will truly be plentiful. It will be rich in agriculture, rich in industry and commerce and in the course of time it will be one of the most powerful and progressive states of the world. If Bengal remains united this will be no dream, no fantasy.” Besides the appeal to the Bangali exceptionalism, left-wingers supported this cause, blaming all of Bengal’s ills on the non-Bangali capitalists. GD Birla was quoted saying: “I am in favour of separation, and I do not think it is impracticable or against the interest of Hindus” as early as 1942, on behalf of the Marwari business community in Kolkata. If only the plan for Bengal unification had been all about catering to the sole interests of Hindus.  Even MA Jinnah supported the cause instead of wanting Bengal for Pakistan although he had a slightly different reasoning, stating: “what is the use of Bengal without Calcutta?” The most influential supporter of the plan to make Bengal a separate nation was Sarat Chandra Bose, a popular congressman and the elder brother of the celebrated freedom fighter, Subhash Chandra Bose. The proposal for United Bengal involved equal quotas for Hindus and Muslims in the military and the police, which were to be indigenised and ‘manned by Bangalis’. The plan that was eventually made public on May 24th of 1947, 10 days before the final Partition plan was announced, provided for a Hindu-Muslim coalition Government in Unified Bengal. The Prime Minister was to be a Muslim and the Home Minister a Hindu. However, the Hindu-Muslim riots in Kolkata around the same time and the open opposition to the unification of Bengal by Sardar Vallabhai Patil, Jawaharlal Nehru and later even Gandhiji, eventually led to this plan being discarded.  The reason why most non-Bangali Indian leaders failed to support the idea of the formation of a third country is because they thought that it would lay down a precedent for other states to follow and demand independence. On May 27th, 1947, Nehru made a formal declaration that he would support the unification only if Bengal was to remain as a part of the Indian Union. This sparked a response from the last British Governor of Bengal, Sir Frederick Burrows: “Bengal will be sacrificed at the altar of Nehru’s all-India outlook.”  The sentiments did not, however, die with the failure of the plan to unify Bengal in 1947. The Brihot Bangla or Bishal Bangla Movement (Greater Bengal Movement) is a nationalist political ideology which seeks to unite all bangali speaking regions of today’s India, Bangladesh and Myanmar into a single nation. If I am to draw an analogy (although it is very difficult to find one for it is as unique as it can possibly get), I would say that it is like Kurdistan. The Kurds are a nation without a state. The Bangalis too are unified by their language but not by land. bangali literature has always referred to their country as ‘Bangla’, the same word as they use to refer to their language. However, Bangla does not refer to either India or Bangladesh, it refers to the Unified Bengal. So yes, Bangalis are patriotic. But, they are patriotic towards Bangla before any country.   While Nehru thought Bengal was just like other Indian states and that the unification of Bengal and a consequent separate state would result in similar sentiments in other states like Tamil Nadu, I disagree. The sentiments are stronger among Bangalis because half of our own state (or country, for a Bangladeshi) is a separate country. People from West Bengal have grown up with stories of Bangla and how some of our ancestors had to cross borders during the Partition and how they still long to go back. The nostalgia, the resentment of the Hindu-Muslim divide and the love for Bangla, both the language and the motherland keeps the emotions and nationalist sentiments alive even today. For every Bangali, half of their identity lies in West Bengal and the remaining half lies in Bangladesh. For every Bangali, language is the identity- not religion, not dialects but Bangla. Whether or not we are destined to ever be unified is a question yet to be answered. What doesn’t change is the fact that even though we do not have a separate country of Bangla, we are still unified as Bangalis.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Modern Slavery: Inside the Transgender Communities of India and Pakistan</title>
      <link href="/Modern-Slavery" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modern Slavery: Inside the Transgender Communities of India and Pakistan" />
      <published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Modern-Slavery</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Modern-Slavery">&lt;p&gt;Our world is imbued with contradictions and opposing realities which inform our lives. Nowhere is this more evident than in our social setting. While some reap benefits of the rights and privileges bestowed upon them, others remain tangled in the subjugating mesh of society. The trapped transgenders either end up mangled under the massive burden of gender roles or end up conforming to the gender expectations ascribed to the sex in which they were &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; born, as a means of expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accident of birth has had serious ramifications on many, but none have been affected as gravely as the transgender. Betrayed by their bodies, and disowned by their families and communities, the transgender (including the eunuch and the intersex), popularly termed as &lt;em&gt;hijras&lt;/em&gt; in India and Pakistan, live as social outcasts, misfits for committing the grave crime of expressing their identities. Their existence itself poses a great threat to social conceptions of gender and sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living in such countries, especially Pakistan where a manic obsession with gender roles reigns over every soul, certainly isn’t easy. The slightest deviation from societal conventions may result in ostracisation and humiliation; primarily the reason why the community is forced into darkness, into total seclusion. The expression of individuality comes at the great price of losing honour and respect. Having been stripped of all rights and dignity, they are forced into begging, prostitution, dancing as a means to earn their living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of mankind has largely revolved around freedom, power and recognition. It is a human need to be recognised and respected by others. Our identities form the very basis of our personhood. This is primarily why we assert ourselves wherever we go. We want our presence to be felt. But what if somebody just takes it all away from us? It would cause a massive dent on our personhood. This is precisely what the transgender community undergoes. Society robs them of their personhood. Life for them is suffering; it begins with gender dysphoria and their struggle to recognise themselves and ends with society deeming them as weeds unfit to be with others; the &lt;em&gt;normal&lt;/em&gt; lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forced to remain hidden from the public eye, they form secret communities that observe their own mysterious codes and customs. One such custom is the rite of initiation, where every new transgender wishing to join the community must go through the painful procedure of emasculation and then be accepted by a &lt;em&gt;guru&lt;/em&gt;, who assumes a paternalistic role in the life of the newly initiated novice. The guru – novice relationship forms the bedrock of the transgender community. This is where things start turning really dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initiate or the novice, who is purchased in exchange of money, is literally at the mercy of the guru. She is penalised and punished severely if she fails to discharge the duties imposed on her. And if at all she decides to leave, she is shunned from the entire community. After being purchased, the novice is then forced by the guru into performing professions like begging, dancing, etc. to earn money; a major chunk of which goes to the guru. This practice almost seems like a modern form of slavery, but because of how inherent it is to the culture, it goes unquestioned and unopposed. Sadly, the tradition which was created to protect starts fettering them and taking away their freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the tremendous pressure imposed by the gurus, the novices at times may even have to indulge in sex work for money. Since they are denied all respectable jobs, several transgenders have to undergo this torment. They are coerced, tortured, raped- all under the knowledge of their gurus. Unable to complain to the authorities and fearing further harassment, they are forced to remain silent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the young transgender, there remains no respite. On one end, they have to deal with repression from society and on the other, the monopoly of the greedy gurus. Another threat looming over their reality is the possibility of acquiring sexually transmitted diseases. Living in denial, they refuse to get themselves medically examined and continue living in unsafe conditions. They, nevertheless, continue existing, because for them nothing can surpass the feeling of power that comes along with expressing oneself and getting acknowledged as the person one wishes to be. The exhibition of identity becomes the sole purpose of their existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back to the guru-novice relationship, it’s important to understand that no cultural practice is free of fault. As in the case of this relationship, every cultural practice harbours in itself certain forms of darkness, often hidden from the rest of the world. The only way out here, is for change to come from the outside, so that these cultural practices automatically dismantle and disintegrate, without being meddled with. Change is slowly coming about; transgenders in India and Pakistan are being recognised as a third gender. With a state-issued identity of their own, they can now avail opportunities previously known only to the two genders, and therefore, reduce their dependence on the guru-novice practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acceptance in society can only come with greater visibility. For an all-inclusive world, the transgender community, with all its eccentricity and richness, must be integrated into the mainstream of society. There exists a need to create space for identity to breathe, which must then be recognised and respected. Especially in Asian countries where these groups are attached to labels of abnormality, there is a necessity to uproot the social stigma surrounding their existence. This can only happen when we begin to recognise them as humans before ascribing a gender identity to them.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Our world is imbued with contradictions and opposing realities which inform our lives. Nowhere is this more evident than in our social setting. While some reap benefits of the rights and privileges bestowed upon them, others remain tangled in the subjugating mesh of society. The trapped transgenders either end up mangled under the massive burden of gender roles or end up conforming to the gender expectations ascribed to the sex in which they were not born, as a means of expression.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Watch Me Watch You Watch Me</title>
      <link href="/Watch-Me-Watch-You-Watch-Me" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Watch Me Watch You Watch Me" />
      <published>2019-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Watch-Me-Watch-You-Watch-Me</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Watch-Me-Watch-You-Watch-Me">&lt;p&gt;Most of us in some way, shape or form love social media. We spend hours
scrolling through content, liking and commenting as we go along. All of our
actions generate data which is then collected by these social media companies
and used, to encourage us to use their platforms more: the so-called addictive
factor. The more data a social media platform collects, the larger their profit
margins. Not only do we consume content, but we also partake in the creation of
content which further keeps users on these platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take Instagram for example. When you upload a photo of yourself on a beach
holiday in Mauritius, it is added to the collective of all posts by Instagram.
Now Instagram is going to do its best to get as many people to view, like and
comment on your post. This brings two benefits to them. One, it learns about the
consumer’s preferences and interests based on what they look at. Two, each
notification you receive about that post will trigger a dopamine response making
you more likely to click on it and get back on the app. Now you can see from
just one post, Instagram is able to keep your followers on the app as well as
yourself. And every additional action carried out on Instagram generates a data
point on us to be sold to the highest bidder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media sites are also designed to make it as easy as possible for us to
post something. By studying how we use the app, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/habits-five-ways-to-help-users-change-them&quot;&gt;UI/UX designers are further
improving apps to make creating content a force of
habit&lt;/a&gt;.
These habits slowly meld into our lives to the point we don’t even have to think
before carrying out all the actions required to open Facebook on our phones and
get onto a Livestream. Now that we have come full circle, we realise the
horrible truth, that we are the creators of our own downfall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;em&gt;“Social media, it’s just the market’s answer to a generation that demanded to
perform. So the market said, ‘Here, perform everything to each other, all the
time, for no reason.’ It’s prison. It’s horrific. It is performer and audience
melded together,”&lt;/em&gt; He then goes on to add, &lt;em&gt;“I know very little about anything,
but what I do know is that if you can live your life without an audience, you
should do it.”&lt;/em&gt; - Bo Burnham's comedy special &lt;em&gt;Make Happy&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does this mean for us? Once you understand how social media works, you
begin to realise that the platforms only have power because we give it to them.
And if we can give them the power, we can also take it back. Sometimes it feels
like one person can’t make a difference, but much like democracy, every single
person counts. The next time you find yourself appalled by Facebook’s unethical
data practices. Just stop and think for a little, how much of an accomplice are
you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media is a great tool to connect, discover and learn but failure to
understand the machinations behind how social media works can lead us down a
vicious cycle of consumption. Sometimes all we need to take control… is to
take a step back.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Avinash Naidu</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Most of us in some way, shape or form love social media. We spend hours scrolling through content, liking and commenting as we go along. All of our actions generate data which is then collected by these social media companies and used, to encourage us to use their platforms more: the so-called addictive factor. The more data a social media platform collects, the larger their profit margins. Not only do we consume content, but we also partake in the creation of content which further keeps users on these platforms. Let’s take Instagram for example. When you upload a photo of yourself on a beach holiday in Mauritius, it is added to the collective of all posts by Instagram. Now Instagram is going to do its best to get as many people to view, like and comment on your post. This brings two benefits to them. One, it learns about the consumer’s preferences and interests based on what they look at. Two, each notification you receive about that post will trigger a dopamine response making you more likely to click on it and get back on the app. Now you can see from just one post, Instagram is able to keep your followers on the app as well as yourself. And every additional action carried out on Instagram generates a data point on us to be sold to the highest bidder. Social media sites are also designed to make it as easy as possible for us to post something. By studying how we use the app, UI/UX designers are further improving apps to make creating content a force of habit. These habits slowly meld into our lives to the point we don’t even have to think before carrying out all the actions required to open Facebook on our phones and get onto a Livestream. Now that we have come full circle, we realise the horrible truth, that we are the creators of our own downfall. “Social media, it’s just the market’s answer to a generation that demanded to perform. So the market said, ‘Here, perform everything to each other, all the time, for no reason.’ It’s prison. It’s horrific. It is performer and audience melded together,” He then goes on to add, “I know very little about anything, but what I do know is that if you can live your life without an audience, you should do it.” - Bo Burnham's comedy special Make Happy. So what does this mean for us? Once you understand how social media works, you begin to realise that the platforms only have power because we give it to them. And if we can give them the power, we can also take it back. Sometimes it feels like one person can’t make a difference, but much like democracy, every single person counts. The next time you find yourself appalled by Facebook’s unethical data practices. Just stop and think for a little, how much of an accomplice are you? Social media is a great tool to connect, discover and learn but failure to understand the machinations behind how social media works can lead us down a vicious cycle of consumption. Sometimes all we need to take control… is to take a step back.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">On TikTok and The Breathlessness of Social Climbing</title>
      <link href="/The-Breathlessness-of-Social-Climbing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On TikTok and The Breathlessness of Social Climbing" />
      <published>2019-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Breathlessness-of-Social-Climbing</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Breathlessness-of-Social-Climbing">&lt;p&gt;As he fishhooks his worn-out khaki &lt;em&gt;jhola&lt;/em&gt; (bag) for keys and reaches out arm
deep to the floor of his bag, the peculiar lines on his forehead curl up into a
sweaty keyhole around his sandalwood &lt;em&gt;tilak&lt;/em&gt;, and it is with some pensive
exertion that he says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“You cannot ever erase your caste. But you sure can pretend to change it. &lt;br /&gt;
The rules of the game are pretty simple back in my village. &lt;br /&gt;
If you have a hearth and nothing else, you count on god. &lt;br /&gt;
If you have a hearth and a cow, you can negotiate with your god. &lt;br /&gt;
If you have a hearth and a cow and a land, you are your own god.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ronge Kumar is a 39-year-old sweeper and errand guy at the local temple near my
place of domicile in North Delhi, India. His favourite sport, second only to
knowing all the Hindu gods’ genealogy trivia like the back of his hand, is
stealing time for his almost ritualistic TikTok consumption in the slimy
contours between the work-home binary at the temple.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I conjecture up an introduction for him in foresight of a biographical
essay I might someday write about him, he overruns my train of thought to
continue his monologue: “One of the greatest pieces of unwitting disclosure is
your father’s name. Your father might not leave you an inheritance but he sure
will leave you a family name as a mortgage against your self respect. How do you
go on pretending to be a different person while carrying your family tree on
your shoulder? The city, with all its noise, is easy on you, because it does not
have time to care.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If all identity is indeed a performance, Kumar’s predicament really leaves me
questioning the semantics of visibility in a society that, at once, implicates
us as performers of our everyday identities and an audience to others’. This, I
intend not as much in a Shakespearean sense of the word as much in a social
constructionist sort of way. The fact that I ‘pass’ as a normal, functional unit
of the social context, is but a deliberate, concerted project of everyday
performance. However, when the context is all too familiar and the performer too
visible, it is hard to ‘pass’ without being held to public scrutiny for
everything you do. Thus, the respite Kumar attributes to the city is the
relative autonomy that his anonymity here can afford for him. This anonymity is
only augmented when he enters the internet, to a point of discord, if not
dissociation from his identities back home and in the city. This is not to say
that the internet exists in a social vacuum, free from the social categories
that define our identity on the ground, but that it offers every new entrant a
clean slate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kumar’s TikTok profile, then, is an embodiment of his existential anxieties of
upward social mobility. His TikTok username, ‘Pandit’ Ronge, above everything,
enables him to attach a Brahminical prefix to his name, something that is
inaccessible to him in the material world. What we see with Kumar then is a more
universal tendency to use the virtual world to live one’s aspirations
vicariously, as in when a 5-year-old chooses a conventionally attractive gaming
avatar to represent themself to the other players, but more so, a social desire
for upward movement. The caste system in India, like most hierarchies, can be
understood as a classic game of Jenga, wherein each participant takes a turn
removing one of the blocks not located on the top three levels and places it on
top of the tower without knocking it down. One’s participation in the game not
only presupposes but also actively ensures that the larger structure of
hierarchical arrangement of the blocks stays in place. An inevitable consequence
of the mobility of the blocks, however, is that the base of the tower
progressively becomes more unstable and struggles to support its heavy top until
it eventually collapses, with the loser being the participant who pulled the
block that caused the demolition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How caste operates in India is much like the rules of Jenga, in that it is as
self preservatory as it is self-destructive. This is to say that while the rules
of the game ensure that the larger structure stays in place, acting out those
very rules also creates possibilities of change within it. But nobody wants to
be singled out as the loser who upset the structure. Thus, mobility desires, if
not demands, anonymity. Most social systems, in that sense, are a long
negotiation of social position within the structure. In negotiating this place,
it puts forth its end of the bargain, creates new fiction to support its claim,
and gradually acquires cultural practices of those above it in the hierarchy.
Social mobility is a cumbersome summit. You spend most days social climbing and
other days catching your breath from all the climbing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in the true Foucauldian sense, what Pandit Ronge also does is that in order
of being represented, ends up subjectifying himself by the very presupposition
of representation. That is, while you start with a clean slate, the moment you
start representing yourself, you also start creating fiction about yourself and
the group people associate you with. This idea approximates the terrain this
essay attempts to explore. Most of what I am trying to say then lies in the
contours of being the butt of a joke and cracking a joke, which is to say, “Are
we laughing at a person or with a person?” or “Is the person less subject, more
object of humour?” This is not to say that performance of humorous content
cannot be funny but the fact that something that is being performed diligently
by one, comes across as funny to another, is an act of violence to the
performer’s diligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ways in which TikTok is consumed today, like most entertainment, is an idiom
for our social existence. For the uninitiated, TikTok is a video app for
creating and sharing short lip-sync, comedy, and talent videos. Previously known
as ‘Musical.ly’, it was acquired in 2018 by a Chinese tech firm and merged with
its Asian counterpart to become TikTok. Currently, with over 800 million active
users, the app has snowballed into an online entertainment giant with popular
creators on the app burgeoning into social media influencers. How then is TikTok
any different from its American short-form video counterpart ‘Vine’, except that
it is not shutting down anytime soon? Social context, mostly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TikTok in India has seeped into Indian houses through the creaks in our
ceilings, and the damp in our walls, strumming the iron bars on our windows like
an amateur guitarist mindlessly learning to toy around with a guitar. From the
iconisation of the Indian mother butting out her kid from the frame to invite
people for tea with her catchphrase, “Hello friends, chai peelo”, to
impassioned, young, brown men, bawling their eyes out in classic misogynistic
Bollywood bereavement fashion; from drought-hit farmers in Maharashtra
lip-syncing to colloquial protest songs and unionising on the internet to
teenagers turned lip-syncing social media influencers, landing modelling
contracts, TikTok has captured the popular imagination in India, with no
precedent. While humour is one of the top genres of content creation on the app,
a larger source of humour is that which is unintended. While the content of most
of these videos reinstates heteronormative, fat-phobic, often hyper nationalist
semantics of Indian households, the performers are also, more often than not,
rampantly fat-shamed and trolled in casteist, classist ways by the elite, the
ignorant, the woke and the conservative, alike. Meme pages on Facebook and
Instagram create targeted content laughing away what they call the ‘chapri’
TikToker. ‘Chapri’, as defined by the urban dictionary is a colloquial slur in
Bombay for ‘low-tier wannabe fuckboys, characterised by ripped jeans, neon
flip-flops, coloured hair, and speeding motorcycles. Mostly found within the
Bandra-Kurla-Andheri triad.’ Given how hyperlocal it is, the context of the
‘chapri’ performers is that the Kurla- Andheri region houses some of the
largest, most densely populated slums in the country. We cannot thus, begin to
understand the violence of humour without politicising identities. TikTok in
India is as much about entertainment and trolling, characteristic of the rest of
the internet, as it is about reclamation and ownership of entertainment. While
it lets some live a Bollywood dream or a social mobility dream, it is also
implicated in the meanings that construct it. This is to say that the liberation
it affords comes from a presupposed bargain of socio-cultural capital, where a
17-year-old with a ring light and an iPhone will pivot an influencer career, &lt;em&gt;in
spite&lt;/em&gt; of trolls, while a 19-year-old ‘gully boy’ becomes a one-hit wonder
&lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of trolls or is jettisoned in the hyperspace of the internet. But,
again, it is not as binary as my last sentence makes it sound and the
eclecticism is where the heart of internet democratisation lies. As I sit musing
the politics of humour in the temple backyard, the large clock in the temple
ticks six and Ronge calls me out from through the large iron gate of the temple
asking if I want to watch him record his prayers for TikTok. I relent and call
it a day.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Yashna Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As he fishhooks his worn-out khaki jhola (bag) for keys and reaches out arm deep to the floor of his bag, the peculiar lines on his forehead curl up into a sweaty keyhole around his sandalwood tilak, and it is with some pensive exertion that he says, “You cannot ever erase your caste. But you sure can pretend to change it.  The rules of the game are pretty simple back in my village.  If you have a hearth and nothing else, you count on god. If you have a hearth and a cow, you can negotiate with your god. If you have a hearth and a cow and a land, you are your own god.” Ronge Kumar is a 39-year-old sweeper and errand guy at the local temple near my place of domicile in North Delhi, India. His favourite sport, second only to knowing all the Hindu gods’ genealogy trivia like the back of his hand, is stealing time for his almost ritualistic TikTok consumption in the slimy contours between the work-home binary at the temple.   While I conjecture up an introduction for him in foresight of a biographical essay I might someday write about him, he overruns my train of thought to continue his monologue: “One of the greatest pieces of unwitting disclosure is your father’s name. Your father might not leave you an inheritance but he sure will leave you a family name as a mortgage against your self respect. How do you go on pretending to be a different person while carrying your family tree on your shoulder? The city, with all its noise, is easy on you, because it does not have time to care.” If all identity is indeed a performance, Kumar’s predicament really leaves me questioning the semantics of visibility in a society that, at once, implicates us as performers of our everyday identities and an audience to others’. This, I intend not as much in a Shakespearean sense of the word as much in a social constructionist sort of way. The fact that I ‘pass’ as a normal, functional unit of the social context, is but a deliberate, concerted project of everyday performance. However, when the context is all too familiar and the performer too visible, it is hard to ‘pass’ without being held to public scrutiny for everything you do. Thus, the respite Kumar attributes to the city is the relative autonomy that his anonymity here can afford for him. This anonymity is only augmented when he enters the internet, to a point of discord, if not dissociation from his identities back home and in the city. This is not to say that the internet exists in a social vacuum, free from the social categories that define our identity on the ground, but that it offers every new entrant a clean slate. Kumar’s TikTok profile, then, is an embodiment of his existential anxieties of upward social mobility. His TikTok username, ‘Pandit’ Ronge, above everything, enables him to attach a Brahminical prefix to his name, something that is inaccessible to him in the material world. What we see with Kumar then is a more universal tendency to use the virtual world to live one’s aspirations vicariously, as in when a 5-year-old chooses a conventionally attractive gaming avatar to represent themself to the other players, but more so, a social desire for upward movement. The caste system in India, like most hierarchies, can be understood as a classic game of Jenga, wherein each participant takes a turn removing one of the blocks not located on the top three levels and places it on top of the tower without knocking it down. One’s participation in the game not only presupposes but also actively ensures that the larger structure of hierarchical arrangement of the blocks stays in place. An inevitable consequence of the mobility of the blocks, however, is that the base of the tower progressively becomes more unstable and struggles to support its heavy top until it eventually collapses, with the loser being the participant who pulled the block that caused the demolition. How caste operates in India is much like the rules of Jenga, in that it is as self preservatory as it is self-destructive. This is to say that while the rules of the game ensure that the larger structure stays in place, acting out those very rules also creates possibilities of change within it. But nobody wants to be singled out as the loser who upset the structure. Thus, mobility desires, if not demands, anonymity. Most social systems, in that sense, are a long negotiation of social position within the structure. In negotiating this place, it puts forth its end of the bargain, creates new fiction to support its claim, and gradually acquires cultural practices of those above it in the hierarchy. Social mobility is a cumbersome summit. You spend most days social climbing and other days catching your breath from all the climbing.  But, in the true Foucauldian sense, what Pandit Ronge also does is that in order of being represented, ends up subjectifying himself by the very presupposition of representation. That is, while you start with a clean slate, the moment you start representing yourself, you also start creating fiction about yourself and the group people associate you with. This idea approximates the terrain this essay attempts to explore. Most of what I am trying to say then lies in the contours of being the butt of a joke and cracking a joke, which is to say, “Are we laughing at a person or with a person?” or “Is the person less subject, more object of humour?” This is not to say that performance of humorous content cannot be funny but the fact that something that is being performed diligently by one, comes across as funny to another, is an act of violence to the performer’s diligence. The ways in which TikTok is consumed today, like most entertainment, is an idiom for our social existence. For the uninitiated, TikTok is a video app for creating and sharing short lip-sync, comedy, and talent videos. Previously known as ‘Musical.ly’, it was acquired in 2018 by a Chinese tech firm and merged with its Asian counterpart to become TikTok. Currently, with over 800 million active users, the app has snowballed into an online entertainment giant with popular creators on the app burgeoning into social media influencers. How then is TikTok any different from its American short-form video counterpart ‘Vine’, except that it is not shutting down anytime soon? Social context, mostly.  TikTok in India has seeped into Indian houses through the creaks in our ceilings, and the damp in our walls, strumming the iron bars on our windows like an amateur guitarist mindlessly learning to toy around with a guitar. From the iconisation of the Indian mother butting out her kid from the frame to invite people for tea with her catchphrase, “Hello friends, chai peelo”, to impassioned, young, brown men, bawling their eyes out in classic misogynistic Bollywood bereavement fashion; from drought-hit farmers in Maharashtra lip-syncing to colloquial protest songs and unionising on the internet to teenagers turned lip-syncing social media influencers, landing modelling contracts, TikTok has captured the popular imagination in India, with no precedent. While humour is one of the top genres of content creation on the app, a larger source of humour is that which is unintended. While the content of most of these videos reinstates heteronormative, fat-phobic, often hyper nationalist semantics of Indian households, the performers are also, more often than not, rampantly fat-shamed and trolled in casteist, classist ways by the elite, the ignorant, the woke and the conservative, alike. Meme pages on Facebook and Instagram create targeted content laughing away what they call the ‘chapri’ TikToker. ‘Chapri’, as defined by the urban dictionary is a colloquial slur in Bombay for ‘low-tier wannabe fuckboys, characterised by ripped jeans, neon flip-flops, coloured hair, and speeding motorcycles. Mostly found within the Bandra-Kurla-Andheri triad.’ Given how hyperlocal it is, the context of the ‘chapri’ performers is that the Kurla- Andheri region houses some of the largest, most densely populated slums in the country. We cannot thus, begin to understand the violence of humour without politicising identities. TikTok in India is as much about entertainment and trolling, characteristic of the rest of the internet, as it is about reclamation and ownership of entertainment. While it lets some live a Bollywood dream or a social mobility dream, it is also implicated in the meanings that construct it. This is to say that the liberation it affords comes from a presupposed bargain of socio-cultural capital, where a 17-year-old with a ring light and an iPhone will pivot an influencer career, in spite of trolls, while a 19-year-old ‘gully boy’ becomes a one-hit wonder because of trolls or is jettisoned in the hyperspace of the internet. But, again, it is not as binary as my last sentence makes it sound and the eclecticism is where the heart of internet democratisation lies. As I sit musing the politics of humour in the temple backyard, the large clock in the temple ticks six and Ronge calls me out from through the large iron gate of the temple asking if I want to watch him record his prayers for TikTok. I relent and call it a day.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
