<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/society/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-03-23T13:34:37+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/society/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Women are Under-represented? Not News.</title>
      <link href="/Women-are-Under-represented-Not-News" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Women are Under-represented? Not News." />
      <published>2020-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Women-are-Under-represented-Not-News</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Women-are-Under-represented-Not-News">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I only go to a movie if it satisfies three basic requirements. One, it has to have at least two women in it, who, two, talk to each other about, three, something besides a man.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1985, a new edition of the comic strip &lt;em&gt;Dykes to Watch Out For&lt;/em&gt;, called ‘The Rule’, first introduced the ‘Bechdel Test’ to the film industry. The writers portrayed the character as avoiding cinema with an extreme male bias, with the character in the script claiming that she hasn’t been able to watch a movie since the 1979 space horror film &lt;em&gt;Alien&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a society where patriarchy has been the dominating narrative, it’s no surprise that women’s representation in the film industry (or any industry, for that matter) is lacking. Looking at statistics from the past few years, women play only about 37% of roles on television (2015). In films, the percentage of speaking roles for women drops to 28% (2012). Women make up a mere 16% of directors, writers, producers, and editors (2013).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many are unaware that gender stereotypes are not just linked to the costumes but are intrinsic to a character’s conversations, actions and traits. To understand how grave the situation is, the Test proves to be helpful. The Bechdel Test is a convenient way to gauge the active presence of female characters in films and just how well-rounded and complete those roles are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On listening to what it takes for the movies to pass the test, one might think: “This seems easy, I bet most movies pass it.” And that’s what I expected. But on researching more on the topic, the number of popular movies that couldn’t pass this simple test turned out to be astonishing. At the 2014 Academy Awards, only three out of the eight nominees for Best Picture passed the Bechdel Test: &lt;em&gt;Boyhood&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Selma&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Theory of Everything&lt;/em&gt;. Corresponding to research by Duke University in 2017, over 40% of all the films in the US failed the test. The team used data from the bechdeltest.com website, a user-compiled database of over 7,000 movies where volunteers rate films based on the Bechdel criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These results show the under-representation of women’s complex lives in the film industry. The Bechdel Test’s demands set a low bar for the filmmakers to meet and they start a conversation about gender inequality in film. The test has brought to light the importance of shifting the focus from men to the other things in a woman’s life: career goals, friendships, inner troubles, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the test comes with its own set of problems. A film passing the test doesn’t mean the movie automatically becomes one that the feminists support. The Bechdel Test can be a misleading gauge of ‘feminism’ in movies. Films with a strong female lead don’t provide a supporting female character who holds enough importance to converse with the lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many movies that pass the test, do so based on a ‘technicality’: in some inconsequential scene, the women have a small conversation about something other than men, therefore fulfilling the criteria. For example, &lt;em&gt;Gravity&lt;/em&gt; featuring a female astronaut doesn’t pass the test. However, &lt;em&gt;Legally Blonde&lt;/em&gt; does because Elle and her friend talk about their dogs in a scene or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female characters have followed the same tropes. The movies make women damsels in distress or a ‘manic pixie dream girl.’ They also sexualise women, forcing them to wear tight-fitting clothes and heels throughout the movie. Adjectives about physical attributes like beautiful, gorgeous and pretty are used to describe the female characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another common trope used is called ‘fridging’ wherein the female characters are injured, raped, killed, or depowered, sometimes to stimulate ‘protective’ traits in men, and often as a plot device intended to move a male character’s story arc forward. &lt;em&gt;Women in Refrigerators&lt;/em&gt;, a website created in 1999 by a group of feminist comic-book fans lists examples of this trope. It refers to an incident in &lt;em&gt;Green Lantern #54&lt;/em&gt; (1994), in which, the title hero, Kyle Rayner, comes home to his apartment to find that his girlfriend had been killed and stuffed into a refrigerator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, however, is not the sole test. The ‘Mako Mori Test’ requires that: The film must feature at least one female character, who has her narrative arc that does not depend on supporting a man’s story. Likewise, the ‘DuVernay Test’ determines a film’s racial diversity. It checks if the minorities have realised lives rather than serving as scenery in the stories of the whites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these tests prove to be like the Bechdel Test as they provide data about representation but cannot provide a coherent picture if the film is feminist enough. Some critics argue that the problem lies in the disagreement about what it means to be a ‘feminist film.’ Because of this, forming a one-size-fits-all test for judging feminism has been difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female representation worsens across intersectionality. Under the broader umbrella of female characters, there are even fewer black females, Latina females, Lesbians or Transgenders. Hollywood executives have knocked dark-skinned women to the side in favour of those with European features and pale complexions. ‘Colourism’ isn’t, however, unique to the black community. In the Bollywood film industry, too, the starring roles go to lighter-skinned actors. Many of them also endorse fairness creams and other similar products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the 2018 USC Annenberg Inclusion Initiative study, out of the top 100 films in 2017, 43 films didn’t include any African-American female character. Sixty-five films were missing Asian or Asian-American female characters, and 64 didn’t include a Latina character. Ninety-four didn’t feature characters with disabilities and LGBTQ characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representation is significant for all communities. However, more than representation, it’s accurate representation that is important. Accurate and well-rounded representation allows people to see a world outside of themselves, fostering critical thinking and empathy with those who are different. The stereotypes don’t allow for the representation to portray the full picture of the complexities of the surrounding people. Because of the aspirational value that pop culture holds, it becomes a cunning, persuasive and pervasive educator. As an educator, it has the power to shape views and opinions about how people look at themselves and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representation in the film industry, however, isn’t just limited to on-screen representation but also extends to those who are working behind the camera. Figures published by &lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt; have revealed that only 22% of the crew involved in making 2,000 of the biggest grossing films over the past 20 years were women. Further, the report revealed a split in responsibilities: women made up a majority only in costume and wardrobe departments and casting. These departments have been perceived as feminine workplaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue deepens when you take into consideration the wage gap between the actors and actresses. &lt;em&gt;Forbes’&lt;/em&gt; analysis of American acting salaries in 2013 determined that the top-paid actors for that year made 2½ times as much money as the top-paid actresses. This means that Hollywood’s best-compensated actresses made just 40 cents for every dollar that the best-compensated men made. Women who have spoken about the issue explain the reason for not demanding higher pay as “they worry about seeming difficult or spoiled.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her 2018 Oscar speech, Frances McDormand suggested an ‘inclusion rider’, a clause in contracts meant to stipulate that 50% of a film crew had to be female. If A-list actors put this clause into practice, the film industry could portray the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Film producers and showrunners have, however, started to take charge. In 2015, the film professionals started the “Bechdel Bill” campaign, who pledged that 80% of their films will pass the test. CW also incorporated the Bechdel Test in two of its shows: &lt;em&gt;Crazy Ex-Girlfriend&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Jane the Virgin&lt;/em&gt;. Despite both shows not passing the test, the move was symbolic as the network constructed a space in which discourse could take place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This discourse can challenge Hollywood to do more than settle for the status quo and to question the absences of many types of people from the movie-making process. These people could potentially enrich our entertainment in countless ways, both on the screen and behind the lens. A post &lt;em&gt;#&lt;/em&gt;MeToo and #TimesUp world has the potential to hold Hollywood accountable and challenge the oppressive structure to demand a more inclusive industry that isn’t hegemonised by cis-white-men.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“I only go to a movie if it satisfies three basic requirements. One, it has to have at least two women in it, who, two, talk to each other about, three, something besides a man.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Explo-Consciousness: The Science, Phenomenology and the Implications of Psychedelic Experience</title>
      <link href="/Explo-Consciousness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Explo-Consciousness: The Science, Phenomenology and the Implications of Psychedelic Experience" />
      <published>2020-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Explo-Consciousness</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Explo-Consciousness">&lt;p&gt;Since the 1930’s, with the discovery of LSD (Lysergic Acid Diethylamide) by Albert Hoffmann, and much later, with the introduction of Psilocybin mushrooms (magic mushrooms) to the west by Gordon Wasson, there has been much heated debate on the topic from all disciplines. The true history of psychedelics is as old as our evolution, and some like Terrence McKenna have even proposed that human beings developed their unique characteristics, especially that of our deep awareness and self-consciousness as a result of the consumption of varieties of psychedelic plants, especially the psilocybin mushrooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, the advent of many religions is also very likely associated with the experience of psychedelics due to the similar character of religious experiences. This view is further confirmed by the fact that, evolutionary speaking, almost all primates consume mushrooms found in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My purpose here is not to draw attention to the medical benefits of these substances; that is the job of the scientist, but I am mostly here to describe what we call ‘the psychedelic experience’, and to finally go into a theory that I have been deeply thinking about, which is called: ‘Explo-Consciousness’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before anything, it is of great importance to explore the science of these substances. Both LSD and Psilocybin are psychedelics, meaning, mind-manifesting or mind-expanding substances. These substances, unlike most recreational drugs, do not increase ‘the pleasure chemicals’ like dopamine, and as such, they do not possess any addictive properties. Instead, they are called serotonergic substances; meaning that they bind with serotonin (the receptor responsible for mood and sleep regulation). When ingested, they alter the user’s perception, and interestingly they bring about hyper-connectivity within the brain as the following diagrams show:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//brain-connectivity.png&quot; style=&quot;display:inline; text-align: left; width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two diagrams are the representation of the brain state; (a) is the state of someone who has been given the placebo with few neuro-connectivity, whereas (b) is the brain on psilocybin. This research, carried out by the Imperial College Centre for Psychedelics, is the first time we have understood, using brain scans, that, on psilocybin, the brain becomes hyper-connected. This hyper-connectivity is also understood to suspend the brain’s ‘Default Mode Network’, which is somewhat equivalent to the ‘ego’ or the ‘self’. The DMN is what provides you with a theory of who you are, and it is particularly active when one thinks about the past or plans for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The over-activity of the DMN is closely correlated with mental illnesses like depression and anxiety, as, roughly stated, the former is in relation to being stuck in the past, and the latter is in relation to worrying about the future. This is, perhaps, what explains the experimental medical use of psychedelic substances to treat anxiety and depression, as for a short while a patient is, simply put, taken out of the prison of the judging and destructive self. As a result, they develop new perspectives about themselves. Such results could also be novel and life-changing for older people, as they too become imprisoned by deeply structured patterns of behaviour and belief. In short, ego dissolution or the suspension of the DMN is not only good for treating mental illnesses but could provide most people with new perspectives in extremely profound life-changing experiences. Such profound experiences were observed in many studies carried out by the John Hopkins Institute, for those of you interested to look further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, when describing the psychedelic experience, one must necessarily possess a new language or form of expression, if one is to truly communicate these experiences. And, this is only possible if one enters through ‘the doors of perception’ and arrives in the place, beautifully described by Rudolph Otto, as “the wholly other” with a unique sense of “&lt;em&gt;Mysterium tremendum et fascinans&lt;/em&gt;”. This is a place where all previous beliefs become trivial and one is then struck by a sense of mystery that is infused by feeling of the holy; both imitating love and terror. One feels in union with God, if God means anything! There cannot be anything in the realm of visual and emotional experience that is more spiritual or religious than the psychedelic experience. The experience, for many, takes the turn of a true and meaningful conversation with this energy or cosmic-consciousness. As a result, if the experience is integrated, the profundity of the experience, whether positive or life-changing, can remain with the voyager. And, if negative, it can be managed with integration; hence why it is necessary to have an experienced guide when taking these sacred substances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own experiences with mushrooms have always been profound; especially the second time when I took a huge dose of 6 grams of dried Liberty Caps&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; I probably should have taken less, perhaps 4 grams. As with any psychedelics, ‘&lt;em&gt;set and setting&lt;/em&gt;’ is more important than the substance itself. My ‘set’ (state of mind) was that of a readiness to have a spiritual experience but it also expected to be terrified. And, my setting was a dark quiet room with a comfortable bed that I laid on after ingesting the mushrooms. Indeed, I was alone…and it was in this environment that I experienced the wholly other. This was my fourth time, so I saw no need for a sitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about 20 minutes, I felt like my body was warming-up, in a strange spiritual sense. It was as if my body was preparing to travel to another dimension; I felt uneasy and excited at the same time. I was like a snake shedding its old skin, and subsequently after 1 hour, all my recent life-choices came in front of me from a different angle. I saw where I went wrong…. I saw and understood my recent errors or areas in life that I had not paid attention to. All of us know our weaknesses and faults but the DMN or the ego stops us from truly accepting, comprehending and feeling them. We may even admit to other people that we are in the wrong but deep in the foundation of our beliefs, we always manage to convince ourselves that the other is in the wrong. But, this time was different. This time, I gained the power to truly separate myself from my ego, and then from those eyes looked and analysed my mistakes and weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This internal feeling was neither judging nor merciful. It was, rather, like being able to look at all my infirmities with a naked eye that was free from all contaminant lenses, so pure and honest! Imagine looking through the window and seeing the disorderly garden of one’s house. Normally, we are moved by emotions such as disgust, sadness or even perhaps the urgency to clean and organise one’s garden. In my experience, there was only the observable garden and its disorganised state, I was like God just observing… After some time of seeing and understanding all my faults, I was then touched by this divine sensation of love that communicated to me that “it’s ok”. This was the most profound moment in the entire experience where I deeply felt that I didn’t have to be oppressed by my past faults and mistakes. The experience was not only meaningfully self-exploratory but deeply healing and transformative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a long time, the purpose of human beings has transcended survival. It seems that all human cultures have understood the importance of knowledge, whether practical or theoretical. Similarly, all cultures have also understood the importance of experience not only as an activity that is fun and enjoyable but also as something that is deeply related to the human essence. In fact, these two things are not separated, but it is clearly observable that knowledge is also a derivation of either direct experience or reflections of experience. As such, the meaning and purpose of human beings is directly intertwined with experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, the more we have access to different repertoire of experiences and the more we live as humans, the closer we get to completeness of what humanness really means. It is also likely that the process of becoming more human is akin to transcending the current reality of the essence of man. In other words, such an evolution or transformation pushes one to become more than a human. One who has more, has more and is perhaps more prosperous, but one who ‘becomes’ more, he transcends himself, even surpassing God himself. For God supposedly created man…now man can constantly re-create himself and ascend at a place that God himself could never attain. For God’s essence is fixed and his nature unchangeable. All varieties of human experiences offered to us by the world (both positive and negative) is a necessary condition if one were to attain such transformation. It occurs to me after my own study and experience that the ‘psychedelic experience’ is the most profound of all possible human experiences; and yet most modern societies have demonised these sacred substances. The function of the ‘mushroom’ and other sacred plants is teaching and they are the wisest of all teachers as they teach you to think for yourself. Other than this, and many other profound functions that these plants play, they also freely gift you the most challenging and life-changing experiences, and these are not only healing but also what one needs for a true spiritual awakening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;em&gt;Explo-consciousness&lt;/em&gt; simply means the explosion of consciousness, and this seems to be the essence of the psychedelic experience. In an explosion, there is death and rebirth and hence why we can participate in a constant process of becoming and hence the human being can attains such transformation that even God himself cannot. In every explosion, there is death and destruction but with the explosion of consciousness, death gives way for the resurrection of something new, of something spectacularly novel and beautiful. With the explosion of consciousness, one realises that one is in union with everything and is nothing at the same time; this is the place of the mystic…it is where they live and breathe…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the question is, do you prefer a life full of indoctrination and culturally sanctioned values; a life whose contents have been determined by others? Such a life is comfortable as it requires no self-examination and self-exploration of one’s authentic self. When one enters in the psychedelic realm, one realises that the essence of man is so much more than just the ego, which is the construction of society and culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, true enlightenment is a lifestyle and not a destination; true enlightenment is the process of constant death and rebirth of the self and what we refer to as the psychedelic experience does just that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Terrence-McKenna.png&quot; style=&quot;display:inline; text-align: left; width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;I want to dedicate this piece to the great Terrence McKenna whose ideas have helped me integrate my psychedelic experiences!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Omidvar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Since the 1930’s, with the discovery of LSD (Lysergic Acid Diethylamide) by Albert Hoffmann, and much later, with the introduction of Psilocybin mushrooms (magic mushrooms) to the west by Gordon Wasson, there has been much heated debate on the topic from all disciplines. The true history of psychedelics is as old as our evolution, and some like Terrence McKenna have even proposed that human beings developed their unique characteristics, especially that of our deep awareness and self-consciousness as a result of the consumption of varieties of psychedelic plants, especially the psilocybin mushrooms.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Televising a Revolution: How Fiction Animates Reality</title>
      <link href="/Televising-a-Revolution" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Televising a Revolution: How Fiction Animates Reality" />
      <published>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Televising-a-Revolution</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Televising-a-Revolution">&lt;p&gt;In the past two weeks, the city of Delhi saw the rise of a mass movement of agitation and protest against India’s controversial new law, the Citizenship Amendment Act (CAA). This movement also reacted strongly against the proposed National Register of Citizens which the Indian Home Minister Amit Shah promised would eventually be implemented across the country. In many of these cities, students were the torch-bearers of these protests. Not long after it became crystal clear that a large section of the populace, especially the youth, was extremely dissatisfied with these decisions by the Indian government, violence broke out primarily &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; students at Jamia Milia University in Delhi, a premier, sought-after institution for humanities in the country. Reports began to pour in of instances of extreme police brutality against the rising protesters, not only in Jamia, but also in other institutions as well as outside colleges and universities. A large part of the student fraternity, not just in Delhi, but all across India, took this to heart and attempted to take a peaceful stand against what they believed was a clear instance of abuse of power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is not meant to be an analysis of the Act or the social implications that follow. More able people have done it, and I feel no need for me to add to them at present. What stood out to me, though, was how largely mainstream pop culture was being co-opted to make a point about how problematic the Act was, or why you could never justify the violence against students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big criticism of my generation, the millennials, has been our unhealthy obsession with binge-watching, and a subsequent laziness to do anything else as a result of that. It is often perceived as a valueless activity, because all you are signing up for is your entertainment. More often than not, you will sacrifice either sleep or studies to watch the next episode of your favourite show on Netflix or some other streaming website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This month, however, not only did students take to the streets, often in defiance of the wishes of their parents and relatives, but they also synthesised their image of being slaves to digitalisation along with rebellion. They proved that they were never really glued to the television for the sake of it. Rather, they were constantly learning what was better about the rest of the world through these shows. They formed better ideals of what was socially acceptable, and decided to carve a narrative that argued for more equality. To be fair, this change has been occurring for a long time in social media. The passing of this Act was the nudge that propelled even those people who would otherwise rather not speak their minds to take a public stand for what they believed was the right thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest example of this was how many people drew parallels between the current government and the attitude of the erstwhile headmaster of Hogwarts, Dolores Umbridge from &lt;em&gt;Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix&lt;/em&gt;. A few pages from the book were mass-shared on Instagram and Twitter, when today’s teenagers, who may not have felt politically charged before the violence, realised that fictional ideas could still have possibly real-life origins. Memes took the front when it came to creative ways of taking out frustration. “Ok boomer” spread like wildfire, when our generation was trying to bridge the gap between their elders and them when it came to truly understanding the government’s intentions. ‘This episode of Black Mirror sucks’ was too close to home. ‘Orange is the New Black’ had become an apt phrase. And, since it was Christmas time, Mariah Carey and vines from a time gone by (&lt;em&gt;Merry Crisis&lt;/em&gt;) decided to feature into the parade. This author’s personal favourite was one that drew from one of those HBO shows. Staying true to the graphic novel, with the yellow and black template, a poster said, “Who watches the watchmen?” I blame myself for letting pop culture necessitate my need to be political, and not have it be an organic process. I also credit it in the same vein, since there wasn’t really an organic process to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we leave out the ways in which pop culture betrayed this generation? Twitterati took nearly all of India’s film industry to task for not using its influence to say anything about the protests. Most notably, Ranveer Singh was a major target, since he played the lead role in &lt;em&gt;Gully Boy&lt;/em&gt; - a movie that was about a marginalised person trying to escape his reality by forging a new one through rapping about his struggles. Shah Rukh Khan, who is an alumnus of Jamia Milia University, met a similar plight. Actors were accused of not having any spine; those who seemed ‘woke’ on the surface through their movies but took a selfie with current Prime Minister Narendra Modi became a symbol of shallowness in the eyes of many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My generation is often called the most depressed set of people to exist. It seems like every concern they have ever had about work, society, themselves, their careers, their grades, has collectivised together to make known to everyone that the government is to blame for much of it. This is not to say that they may be entirely wrong, either. Unsure job prospects, a disgusting lack of reverence for the humanities that also manifests itself in ad hominem jibes about people from supposedly ‘anti-national’ but surely excellent institutions like JNU, passage of oppressive bills like the Rights of Transgender Persons Bill, and the general treatment of marginalised groups do not provide any kind of conducive environment for positivity on the part of India’s youth. An escapist resort from the pressures of this world then becomes pop culture - a feel-good substitute for the real world. Of course, with time, pop culture has begun to mirror society more and more. Yet, we still feel that we can treat movies and shows as they are, and not as something that affects our environment beyond what is on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the mirror does exist. This article may not have been the need of the hour, because in the grand scheme of things, it feels unimportant to discuss pop culture. However, it has definitely been one of the ways that people used to make aware to others around them the true impact of the government’s actions. It became a common language to understand something so big, and then eventually be the platform for educating oneself more about the happenings in the country. Even beyond Delhi, the protests are getting worse and people need help. The truth is that the revolution was televised and it’s an episode every day.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pranav Manie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In the past two weeks, the city of Delhi saw the rise of a mass movement of agitation and protest against India’s controversial new law, the Citizenship Amendment Act (CAA). This movement also reacted strongly against the proposed National Register of Citizens which the Indian Home Minister Amit Shah promised would eventually be implemented across the country. In many of these cities, students were the torch-bearers of these protests. Not long after it became crystal clear that a large section of the populace, especially the youth, was extremely dissatisfied with these decisions by the Indian government, violence broke out primarily against students at Jamia Milia University in Delhi, a premier, sought-after institution for humanities in the country. Reports began to pour in of instances of extreme police brutality against the rising protesters, not only in Jamia, but also in other institutions as well as outside colleges and universities. A large part of the student fraternity, not just in Delhi, but all across India, took this to heart and attempted to take a peaceful stand against what they believed was a clear instance of abuse of power.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Colourism: An Introduction</title>
      <link href="/Colourism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Colourism: An Introduction" />
      <published>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Colourism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Colourism">&lt;p&gt;Colourism is a term increasingly mentioned in recent, modern racial discourse and is enjoying some much-needed attention during the current political climate. Colourism, by definition, is the “prejudice or discrimination against individuals with a dark skin tone, typically among people of the same ethnic or racial group” (&lt;em&gt;Oxford English Dictionary&lt;/em&gt;); but does this mean that this problem is something that is in fact conceived, and perpetuated, by black communities?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, no. Colourism is an overhang from slavery. It’s some form of diaspora from within your own diasporic community; where darker-skinned women, in particular, suffer poor treatment, fewer job opportunities and less representation in the film, television and music industries. Lighter skinned-artists such as Beyoncé Knowles, Robin ‘Rihanna’ Fenty, Jorja Smith and racially ambiguous artists like Cardi B, enjoy mainstream success, largely straddling both sides of the Black Atlantic (a concept developed by Paul Gilroy). On the other hand, artists like Nina Simone, Grace Jones and Azealia Banks have enjoyed lower levels of success or heightened criticism for their artistic choices. (Banks is admittedly a contentious choice to some, but still valid in demonstrating the wider point.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowles’ father, Matthew, conceded in an interview, when quizzed about whether the success of his daughters was in part down to their skin colour, that it was no ‘accident’ that the two were this way, elaborating further and revealing a greater attraction to lighter-skinned women. Mr Knowles admitted that his now ex-wife – Tina – seemed white to him when they first met. This was something that clearly was attractive to him and that he had been told by his mother to not bring home a “nappy headed black girl”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The negative portrait painted of women with darker skin seems to be a perpetuated tale of self-loathing from darker-skinned men and women reaching back over generations, since slavery – where white masters did show preferential treatment to and force themselves upon the lighter-skinned female slaves. Mr Knowles’ testimony, simultaneously explains that these ideas were ‘conditioned’ into him by his mother, yet this does no favours to the stereotypes of black women being angry and abusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyoncé Knowles’ &lt;em&gt;Lemonade&lt;/em&gt; visual album in 2016 was her third album away from the management of her father, who orchestrated her entire early career and her first three solo albums. On &lt;em&gt;Lemonade&lt;/em&gt;, Beyoncé sampled speeches from Malcolm X, notably in the music video for &lt;em&gt;Don’t’ Hurt Yourself&lt;/em&gt;: “The most disrespected person in America is the Black woman. The most unprotected person in America, is the Black woman. The most neglected woman in America is the Black Woman”. In addition, the promotional appearance at the 2016 Superbowl Half-time Show referenced the Black Panther movement in costume and staging, much to the shock and dismay of ‘White America’. US comedy show &lt;em&gt;Saturday Night Live&lt;/em&gt; even parodied the national reaction, joking that Beyoncé had become such a successful household name, that ‘they’ (‘White America’) had forgotten that she was in fact a black woman expressing – amongst other more personal things – her diasporic place in America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some would argue that the only way that this music was ever heard on a mainstream stage was due to her complexion and preferential treatment as a lighter-skinned woman, and as an established popular artist, with considerable influence and artistic independence thanks to signing with her husband’s label. Since then, Beyoncé also wrote a song for the &lt;em&gt;Lion King&lt;/em&gt; soundtrack &lt;em&gt;Brown Skinned Girl&lt;/em&gt; to empower and uplift women of darker shades—thereby using her privilege to uplift others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that this particular colouristic scrutiny doesn’t affect men in the same way, not to say it does not affect them at all. Black men in entertainment are seen in all shades, from Childish Gambino to the darker Kendrick Lamar, to the problematic Chris Brown who, despite several instances of abuse, continues to make music. Clearly the issue is not about representation, it’s about male privilege and a lack of self-worth or self-esteem that is passed down generations, which further marginalises women who do not enjoy the same privileges as their male counterparts in any ethnic group of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also about being held to a different standard to both men and people of lighter complexions. My earlier acknowledgement of Azealia Banks’ notorious spats serves a wider point. Many artists express un-savoury opinions about others, or are insensitive around hot-button issues: like Gina Rodriguez’s continued maligning of black women and throwaway use of the ‘N-word’; Cardi B’s abhorrent attitudes towards trans people, whilst appropriating LGBT+ turns of phrase; or Kanye West’s musings on slavery and support of Donald Trump under the guise of ‘free thought’. These are all people who swathes of people online have called out and ‘cancelled’ but who also mysteriously continue to enjoy success whilst remaining largely unscathed. It appears separating the artist from the art has qualifying factors and one of them is clearly skin tone – or at least when it comes to women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colourism itself highlights the complexities of ethnic minorities’ relationships with one another. It is perpetuated – at its root – by a form of white supremacy, that has filtered into various communities and left dark-skinned women feeling marginalised and unappreciated. Here, the term black is far from simple, as it does not encompass the inner prejudices within a diverse community of billions. Colourism is being discussed exponentially more in recent months and years; and hopefully, continues to get the attention it deserves for whom Malcom X described as the most ‘disrespected’, the most ‘unprotected’ and the most ‘neglected’ group in American society – and indeed the wider world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nat Richards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nat Richards is a freelance musician with a post-graduate degree from the University of Bristol.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Nat</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Colourism is a term increasingly mentioned in recent, modern racial discourse and is enjoying some much-needed attention during the current political climate. Colourism, by definition, is the “prejudice or discrimination against individuals with a dark skin tone, typically among people of the same ethnic or racial group” (Oxford English Dictionary); but does this mean that this problem is something that is in fact conceived, and perpetuated, by black communities?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Labour’s Tale of Woe: Reflections on the British General Election</title>
      <link href="/Labour-s-Tale-of-Woe-Reflections-on-the-British-General-Election" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Labour's Tale of Woe: Reflections on the British General Election" />
      <published>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Labour-s-Tale-of-Woe-Reflections-on-the-British-General-Election</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Labour-s-Tale-of-Woe-Reflections-on-the-British-General-Election">&lt;p&gt;In last Thursday’s British general election, the Conservative Party won a resounding majority of 356 seats to Labour’s 203, in what proved to be the Labour Party’s worst election defeat since 1935. The Conservatives saw significant gains in Britain’s Leave-voting constituencies in the North East and the Midlands, as Boris Johnson’s promise to ‘get Brexit done’ clearly resonated with many voters in traditional Labour strongholds. The certainty of an exit from the EU, coupled with the SNP gaining 13 seats in Scotland including that of the Liberal Democrat leader Jo Swinson, has also left many contemplating the future of the Union and the probability of a Scottish secession. But the most striking aspect of the election was the collapse of the Labour Party, which lost 59 seats from their 2017 results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boris Johnson, in pledging not only to deliver Brexit but to increase public expenditure by £13.4 billion in 2020–2021, which would be the largest increase in spending in 15 years, clearly provided a theoretical break from the austerity policies and supply-side economics which had characterised the Conservatives’ previous administrations in the wake of the Financial Crisis, enabling him to win over voters in Labour strongholds. It is unclear, however, if this ‘One-Nation Conservative’ rhetoric will translate into policy, as Boris Johnson has voted consistently in favour of austerity policies since being returned as an MP in 2015. Moreover, it is entirely probable that having won a demonstrable majority, the Conservatives may use their relative unaccountability to continue the same cuts to income tax and spending that they were previously committed to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Labour, a schism between the Europhile, metropolitan, London-centric PLP and the Eurosceptic so-called ‘Red Wall’ of Northern, working class seats was the main source of their undoing. Labour lost 10.4% of the vote share in seats where 60% or more people voted Leave, as seats such as Sedgefield, Bolsover and Workington fell to the Conservatives. Dennis Skinner, a veteran Labour MP and former miner, lost his Bolsover seat after 49 years in Parliament. In 2017, when Labour had promised to honour the result of the referendum, they held 72 of the 100 constituencies in the most working class (C2DE) households. In 2019, this figure fell to 53, and the Conservatives increased their share from 13 to 31. Labour’s decision to cleave towards the centre to placate the Blairite elements of the Party was, therefore, an unmitigated catastrophe. Ian Lavery MP, who held onto his seat in Wansbeck in Northumberland by an unfathomably slender majority of just 800 votes, stated: “Ignore democracy and to be quite honest the consequences will come back and bite you up the backside.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many voters in the aforementioned deindustrialised Northern towns now beset by a dismal combination of unemployment and precarious, low-wage service sector work, the fact that Labour had failed to completely acknowledge their Eurosceptic stance eroded their faith in democracy. Devoid for the most part of media influence or capital, the vote was the only way of making their voices heard. Having been neglected by a London-centric party and a political consensus dominated for decades by financialisation, the City of London and an obsession with GDP as the sole indicator of the prosperity of the nation, they struck a lethal blow against those who purported but failed to represent them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perception of Jeremy Corbyn as an inadequate leader was another prevalent theme both on the doorstep and in mainstream political coverage throughout the election. Media coverage of Corbyn was relentlessly brutal. The virulent anti-Corbyn rhetoric even predated the election, as during the past 3 years, he has been referred to as a Czech spy, a Russian agent, an anti-semite and a Communist. It is undeniable that there are antisemitic elements within the Labour Party that Corbyn has been indecisive in removing, and that the British Left has a long and disgraceful history of indulging antisemitism, aptly described by August Bebel as “the socialism of fools”. Keir Hardie, the first ever Labour leader, blamed Jewish financial houses for the outbreak of the First World War. However, Corbyn himself has a long and understated history of opposing antisemitism. As far back as 1977, for example, Corbyn organised a counter-demonstration in defence of London’s Jewish community against 1,000 National Front members who attempted to march through Wood Green.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blairites and moderate voices within the Labour movement continue to portray this election as proof that it is left wing policies that are unpopular rather than the party’s Brexit stance and alienation of its core voting bloc. They suggest that the Labour Party must revert to a pro-corporate ideology, being at ease with privatisation, marketisation and a bellicose foreign policy. Yet this is directly contradicted by the available evidence: a 2017 YouGov poll found that 60% of the British public support renationalising the railways, 59% support taking water into public ownership, and 53% supported public ownership of the energy companies. 60% also back higher levels of taxation and spending. To argue that the statistical success of Tony Blair compared to Jeremy Corbyn represents a necessity to return to a Blairite brand of politics is to misunderstand that the political context has changed significantly since 1997. A global financial crash, the longest squeeze in wages since the Napoleonic Wars, and house prices rising to 7.8 times the amount of annual salaries demonstrate that a significantly greater amount of fiscal intervention is required to alleviate the crises of the present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The technocratic, Blairite conception of politics, which focuses entirely on winning power for its own sake and ignores the broader contexts in which new political and economic ideas come to the fore, has subsided. It has been proposed, therefore, that the future of the Labour Party is a combination of a culturally conservative, patriotic communitarianism with economic leftism of the kind espoused by figures such as Clement Attlee and George Lansbury. The resurgence of ‘Blue Labour’ attests to this. However, it must be acknowledged that Labour is a party that, for decades, has attempted to straddle a coalition of voters with fundamentally different outlooks and views of the world that may be considered irreconcilable. Socially-liberal graduates in Manchester and London, harbouring an instinctual aversion to the monarchy and the nation-state, on whom the Labour Party also depends, would be alienated by such a platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reconnect with its core vote, and to pull together its fractured coalition of voters, Labour will need a sustained and coordinated presence within areas of the country which perceive them to be London-centric and elitist, rather than merely turning up a week prior to the election and expecting votes. The neoliberal atomisation and individualism which characterise the present political era have torn asunder many community institutions which once fostered political dialogue and enabled people to become involved with politics. Therefore, much of the impetus must come from the grassroots elements of the party, with a priority placed on engaging in programmes such as the National Food Service and serving the concerns of local residents regarding ordinary issues such as education, housing and healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that the schisms and fissures within the Labour Party, and between the party and the electorate have been destructive and have led to the party’s near annihilation. There is a significant amount of soul-searching to be done, as the Labour Party desperately attempts to avoid decades in political oblivion. Reconnection with the party’s Northern heartlands will be a clear priority, as will grassroots level organising and education. But some of these ideological vicissitudes, such as the gap between voters in the Northern heartlands and those in the major cities, run so deep that it is difficult to see the party recovering from them.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In last Thursday’s British general election, the Conservative Party won a resounding majority of 356 seats to Labour’s 203, in what proved to be the Labour Party’s worst election defeat since 1935. The Conservatives saw significant gains in Britain’s Leave-voting constituencies in the North East and the Midlands, as Boris Johnson’s promise to ‘get Brexit done’ clearly resonated with many voters in traditional Labour strongholds. The certainty of an exit from the EU, coupled with the SNP gaining 13 seats in Scotland including that of the Liberal Democrat leader Jo Swinson, has also left many contemplating the future of the Union and the probability of a Scottish secession. But the most striking aspect of the election was the collapse of the Labour Party, which lost 59 seats from their 2017 results.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Atheism Destroys Science and Progress. Here’s How.</title>
      <link href="/Atheism-Destroys" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Atheism Destroys Science and Progress. Here’s How." />
      <published>2019-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Atheism-Destroys</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Atheism-Destroys">&lt;p&gt;It might sound strange to say that atheism destroys science. Indeed, many will laugh merely upon reading the heading of this article. However, my interactions with sceptics and postmodernists have convinced me that while it may seem to many that atheism leads to science and moral progress, the truth is exactly the opposite. Rather than upholding science, atheism destroys the foundations that underlie science; and far from promoting human progress, atheism degrades humanity and inevitably leads to moral decay in society. Not only that, I am also deeply convinced that a postmodernist attitude is simply the result of centuries of atheist influence upon the West; a true atheist will, in my opinion, adopt a postmodern outlook sooner or later. In this article, I hope to show why I think this is the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am a Christian, let’s talk about Christianity for a moment. As the Oxford mathematician and Christian thinker John Lennox has remarked multiple times, many of the scientists of the early Modern era were Christians because their faith in God led them to expect order and stability in the universe. Indeed, many of the very people who laid the foundations of science in the post-Reformation West were devoutly Christian people, believing that the study of the creation was a kind of worship to God. Indeed, that is my own opinion as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Christian, I believe that God gave us rationality so that we could use it to study and learn more about the world in which we live. My belief that my mind and my sense organs are a gift of God gives me sufficient ground to trust it as being reliable in giving me information about this wonderful universe which we are privileged to call home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, an atheist cannot say the same thing. For suppose that we live in a world that is merely a cosmic accident, and suppose – for the sake of argument – that the material reality is all that exists and there is no spiritual dimension whatsoever. Under this view, the mind is purely a material phenomenon and is directly equivalent to the brain. There is no aspect whatsoever to the mind that is immaterial under this view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the brain is merely a conglomeration of nerves and chemicals. In a purely physical, materialistic world, what we perceive as emotions, thoughts and feelings are merely the result of chemicals firing around in our brain. Even our deepest moral sentiments are simply the products of how our brain has been evolved to think and perceive reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if this is true, then how can the atheist say that his senses and rational powers are capable of giving him an accurate depiction of reality? If the mind is simply a physical organ that is determined to function and act in a particular way (because of the evolutionary path that it happened to take), then there are no rational grounds for trusting your perception or your ability to reason. After all, everything – in an atheistic worldview – is a cosmic accident and the way your brain thinks and perceives something to be ‘rational’ or ‘logical’ or ‘reasonable’ is merely an accident as well. If evolution had taken a different path, then your brain might not even have existed… or it would have existed, but it would be operating in a different manner, giving you a different perception of what you call ‘reality’. But in that situation, you would have had radically different beliefs and ways of perceiving the world. What you today call ‘reasonable’ might under that circumstance appear absurd or farcical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is here that the atheist falls into a bit of a quandary. One alternative is that he can admit the fact and say that he simply ‘trusts’ his ability to reason and operates with that as his basic epistemological presupposition. But if this is so, then he cannot in good conscience criticize religious faith, since that too is a kind of trust in things we might not be able to “prove” with mathematical accuracy. Another alternative is that he can admit the fact I have mentioned and collapse into a kind of postmodernism, looking at all things – science included! – with scepticism, since even scientific observations are dependant upon human perception, which cannot be ‘proven’ per se to be reliable!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, if we were living in the Matrix, chances are we wouldn’t know that we were!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same thing holds true for morality. We all – atheists and Christians included – have basic moral instincts. From a Christian point of view, I believe that God is perfect and he gives us a basic knowledge of what is right and wrong. Thus, as a Christian, I can say with conviction that certain things are basically right and others are basically wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But can the atheist say such a thing? Certainly, atheists have moral beliefs, but can they justify those beliefs? After all, if there is no God and if materialistic naturalism is true, then there are no objective moral principles. Whatever morality we might have is purely subjective. Our mind is conditioned to think in a particular way – morally speaking - because of external accidental circumstances. Morality, in an atheistic worldview, inevitably becomes either a psychological construct or a societal one. On the former view, it is primarily evolution that conforms us to have certain moral instincts – and, remember, there is no guarantee that evolution would have taken the path it ultimately took! On the latter view, morality is primarily the result of societal conditioning – we happen to live in a society that values liberty and freedom; therefore, we have learned to value them as well. Had we lived in a cannibalistic society we would have had different moral values. This is called the doctrine of Cultural Relativism, and in this philosophy, no particular moral code is intrinsically superior to another, since they are all cultural constructs and all cultures are equally true and equally false.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is not that atheists don’t have a sense of morality – they certainly do. The problem, rather, is that their metaphysical worldview cripples them from having an objective foundation for their morality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is heart-breaking for me as a Christian to see prominent thinkers and philosophers encourage people to embrace a worldview in which everything is fundamentally meaningless and to “get used to it” (quoting Dr Susan Blackwood in her dialogue with Professor Jordan Peterson on the &lt;em&gt;Unbelievable?&lt;/em&gt; radio podcast). It is just as upsetting to see the rise of postmodern thinking in our world. I am convinced that such a mode of looking at the world will inevitably give birth to a society of depression and despair. And this observation vindicates my deeply Christian belief that only God can give true meaning and value to our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People might find it similarly shocking that I claim atheism degrades human beings. After all, don’t many atheists identify as ‘humanists’? Don’t so many atheists fight so vigorously for human rights and don’t humanists try and oppose oppression around the world? An atheist friend of mine once quipped to me that the modern West is proof that we can have morality without God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t disagree more. And here’s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give one example: most atheists don’t, as far as I know, fight for the rights of the unborn. In fact, prominent atheists like Sam Harris complain that religious bigots such as myself still try to stop embryonic stem cell research. Similarly, I have never heard an atheist oppose the recent legislations that have effectively allowed the monstrosity of late-term abortions in New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not only the unborn who are being marginalized. Peter Singer, a prominent atheist ethicist, openly declares that – like unborn foetuses – new-born infants similarly lack what he calls the essential characteristics of personhood. The troubling implications of such a horrendous line of thinking are so alarming that words fail to convey the emotions that stir up in my heart as I write this article. And what is even more scandalous is that Singer is a vegan, although – as he would put it – a ‘flexible vegan’. In other words, he goes to great lengths to ensure that cows and buffaloes don’t suffer because of him… but that same privilege is not extended even to new-born babies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here’s the thing. I believe that deep down, everyone has a sense of right and wrong. And this sense has been given to them by God. If you want proof that a Divine Law does indeed exist, then turn to your own conscience. I believe that deep down, everyone knows that good and evil are real, but over time they manufacture philosophies and ideologies to rationalise away what they do not want to be true. Because if there is a Divine Law, you are not ‘free’ to enjoy things that are evil, however attractive or pleasurable that might be. And if there is a Divine Law, there must also be a Divine Law-giver before whom we are all accountable for our actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not saying that you can’t be good without fear of punishment. On the contrary, I believe that the good should be sought for its own sake, rather than merely out of servile fear. Rather, what I am saying is that if there is no God, then good and evil are both illusions and have no real existence. And if that is so, then everything is permitted, since all things are then morally equal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the disastrous implications of the revolution that our world has initiated against God. And you will then forgive me when I say that atheism is not a boon. It is, in fact, poison.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It might sound strange to say that atheism destroys science. Indeed, many will laugh merely upon reading the heading of this article. However, my interactions with sceptics and postmodernists have convinced me that while it may seem to many that atheism leads to science and moral progress, the truth is exactly the opposite. Rather than upholding science, atheism destroys the foundations that underlie science; and far from promoting human progress, atheism degrades humanity and inevitably leads to moral decay in society. Not only that, I am also deeply convinced that a postmodernist attitude is simply the result of centuries of atheist influence upon the West; a true atheist will, in my opinion, adopt a postmodern outlook sooner or later. In this article, I hope to show why I think this is the case.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Memoirs of an Ex-Muslim: Lies, Propaganda and Truth</title>
      <link href="/Memoirs-of-an-Ex-Muslim" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Memoirs of an Ex-Muslim: Lies, Propaganda and Truth" />
      <published>2019-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Memoirs-of-an-Ex-Muslim</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Memoirs-of-an-Ex-Muslim">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following is an opinion piece submitted by a contributor who wishes to remain anonymous.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My time in Iran as a Muslim now seems like the distant past. The beautiful and almost transcendent experience of being a Muslim comes with its costs. But what are these costs, some people ask? Is it not true that having a religious foundation helps society and isn’t Islam the religion of peace?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the answers to those questions are all ‘yes’ if you are a typical person living in Iran. However, let’s not forget that belief - or even fanatical conviction - is not the same as truth. At the time, I was only 16 and was certainly influenced by the constant Islamic propaganda that pervaded every aspect of the Iranian society. I now ask myself whether it was even possible not to believe in the Islamic doctrines at the time since everything ranging from music to media and books were heavily shaped by Islamic beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, our epistemology was based on supposedly revealed scriptures and doctrines. In schools, for instance, the humanities were taught from a purely Islamic perspective, as though these were objective facts alongside science. Any criticism of these would be like saying that atoms do not exist. I am not exaggerating. It is extremely important for non-Iranians to understand how much of an independent thinker one must be in order to go against Islamic doctrines in Iran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why did I leave Islam? Well, after my migration to the UK in 2014, the Islamic propaganda was no longer present in my life. There was this sense of mental liberation that had begun to manifest itself. Despite this, the toxicity and the virus-like the behavior of Islamic ideas made it such that it took me two years to abandon all of my faith in Islam. So for those of you who are reading this, the first step is to understand your religion from within. In my case, I started educating myself about the &lt;em&gt;Hadith&lt;/em&gt; and the history of Islam and the more I investigated, the more disillusioned I became with the faith. It was as though I was walking in a dark tunnel, and soon enough I realised that my expectation of the existing light at the end of the tunnel was illusory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a 16 year old Iranian studying these texts and the history of Islam, I soon became aware that it was not that difficult to lose faith in Islam. Why was it so easy? It would not have been easy in Iran but here in the UK I had access to a vast number of resources and was being exposed to various points of view. In Iran, all I was taught was that the &lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt; was a text filled with amazing scientific truths as well as accurate historical facts. Conversely, it was only in the UK that for the first time I had heard criticism against Muhammad’s character. Surely he was the perfect human being, right? Well, with some study, I realised that that was not the case at all. In fact, all I found was that in the Islamic sources themselves such as in Bukhari and other Hadiths, Muhammad was not only a prophet without any prophecy, but that his actions and beliefs utterly and precisely mirrors that of those in the so-called Islamic State of Iraq and Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, the clue is in the name ‘The Islamic State’ and I am not naïve enough to think that a name could on its own make this proposition true. But, when one looks at the history of Islam and learns about Muhammad who had, on many occasions, committed acts of genocide, pedophilia and had engaged in the institution of sex slavery, one need not go any further. Are those accusations accurate? It depends on what sources you think are credible and statistically speaking, the &lt;em&gt;Hadiths&lt;/em&gt; especially by Bukhari  are believed by Muslims to provide the life of Prophet Muhammad with a fair amount of accuracy. And, for those who do not subscribe to the credibility of these texts, there is an even more challenging problem; which is that, they do not have any credible source of even making the proposition that Muhammad existed as a person in history. So either, Muhammad was a morally repugnant human being or he never existed, and even if he did, there is not enough historical evidence to render that belief plausible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something even more embarrassing is that Muhammad is actually rarely mentioned in the &lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt;, which is, also a book filled with commands for sex slavery and genocide; in addition to that, the &lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt; clearly places women on a far lower pedestal than men. All these are not mere assertions. Those who study these texts are well aware of the existence of these commands and events but they try to contextualise them and give reasons for why they happened. Here, I think I am completely justified to compare this to someone who justifies the crimes committed by Hitler by giving reasons as to why they happened, in order to provide a moral account for the actions committed by him. There is no excuse for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the most reprehensible of all crimes against humanity: to justify the evils of the past and to not recognise them. For if we don’t recognise them, we are doomed to repeat them. The fact that Muhammad (PeACE Be UPoN hIM) married a six year old should not be something up for contextualisation or debate. The fact that Muhammad took sex slaves should not be a matter for contextualisation or debate. Some actions are just so intrinsically wrong that no reasoning could render them moral&lt;/em&gt;. Similarly, there is absolutely no situation under which Muhammad was justified to take sex slaves (&lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt; 33:50, &lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt; 4:24). Let’s look at the latter example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;And all married women (are forbidden unto you) save those (captives) whom your right hands possess.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, we see that slaves regardless of their marital status are basically the property of those who capture them, as Nadia Murad was. In essence, the deity of the &lt;em&gt;Quran&lt;/em&gt; clearly permits rape for war slaves. This is what I mean when I say that there are actions which are never justified. And hopefully, now you see why I lost my faith so rapidly after reading these texts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really hope that Muslims start to read and educate themselves with their own sources, for if not, history is bound to repeat itself as it is repeating itself now and no one is paying attention.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>anon.anon</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The following is an opinion piece submitted by a contributor who wishes to remain anonymous.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Uncomfortable Parallels: The Revenge of the Anglophone Elites</title>
      <link href="/Uncomfortable-Parallels" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Uncomfortable Parallels: The Revenge of the Anglophone Elites" />
      <published>2019-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Uncomfortable-Parallels</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Uncomfortable-Parallels">&lt;p&gt;The political elite of the United States, in the form of Democrats in the Congress, Democrats in the media, and jealous Republicans in the political establishment, are all upset that the people rejected them in favour of a populist man with zero political experience or connections, and have now united together for the first time since the bomb that was the Mueller testimony to try and overturn the election of 2016. They have announced they will support the impeachment of the American President, although House Speaker Pelosi’s ‘announcement’ of an ‘impeachment inquiry’ thus far has no actual effect because there hasn’t been a vote taken in the House on the issue. However, by September 26, 2019, there were 217 Democrats announcing they’d vote in favour of such an inquiry plus former Republican Justin Amash of Michigan, giving the majority of 218 needed if a vote were brought to the floor. So what did the bad orange man do that finally pushed a majority of the oldest democratic legislative body in the world to declare their official attempts to prematurely remove the chief executive, elected independently of themselves by the people? He talked to a foreign president about trying to end corruption in said President’s nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, a majority of members of the US House of Representatives want to now overturn an election of over 120,000,000 voters and 538 electors because the President that process produced talked to President Vladimir Zelensky of Ukraine to ask him what he was doing to fight corruption. Nothing about threats, nothing about money, and nothing about the election. In fact, while the media and the left all across the world have been screaming about the ‘fact’ that there is a ‘coverup’ or that there was ‘quid pro quo’ or even ‘election interference’ in the form of investigating Trump’s ‘opponent’, they have completely missed that the transcript of the call in question was released and says nothing of the sort. Joe Biden is not Trump’s opponent and there is corruption in the Ukraine that Trump wants to look at, which could possibly include Vice President Joe Biden actually withholding money from Ukraine until they fired a prosecutor looking into a company involving his son, Hunter. Finally, and probably most importantly, not a single mention of aid appears, nor are there any threats. In total, it is a nothingburger, but the leftists in all spheres, from media to Congress, have organised to move forward in the next attempt to throw out the president for the crime of winning the 2016 election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could very well spell trouble for the Democrats in 2020, with Speaker Pelosi going so far as to say “we have to impeach him, even if it means we lose the House in 2020.” The left knows very well the fire it is playing with and this will most likely backfire on them gloriously. However, for the time being, they are playing their hand and doing everything they can to ensure that Trump is taken out somehow. While this effort is doomed to fail like previous efforts, to see them so united in such a hostile manner, essentially unmasking themselves for the radicals they really are, it becomes clear how big the fight for the future of the United States and its culture will be in the coming years. They don’t just want to get rid of Trump, but they would also like to force everyone who supported him to witness his overthrow as an example of what happens when you upset their little club by getting uppity and thinking you should have a voice in government. That type of mentality leads to dark roads and must be rejected and defeated at every turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings me across the pond to Britain, going through its own democratic crisis due to its own 2016 middle finger to the elites, Brexit. Since that day, the elite Remainers in all parties had been fighting long and hard to overturn the results, however they just could not unite to do it. Not that Brexiteers in power have been the most united, however, their message has been consistent throughout: deliver Brexit with a good deal or leave the EU on World Trade Organisation rules two years after the invocation of Article 50. Theresa May, a Remainer at heart, extended the current deadline of October 31 due to her abysmal withdrawal treaty suffering three humiliating defeats in the House of Commons before the original deadline. So when she was finally deposed and more upbeat, can do, ‘we will leave, do or die’ Boris Johnson took her place, it seemed things would be going okay for the Brexiteers, and Remainers would finally be on the path to the dustbin of history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the Parliament first met under PM Johnson and votes started happening, after his announcement of the prorogation of Parliament to put a fresh Queen’s Speech down and finally end the longest Parliament since the Rump Parliament during the English Civil War. This reasonable request was met by Remainer elites in the media, Labour Party, Liberal Democrats, Scottish National Party, and bitter, anti democratic, Conservatives with screeches of “Stop the coup” and “this is a dictatorship.” They declared the reduction of the session by four days was designed to take away debate for the apocalypse they think would be a no-deal Brexit. The fact that they have been debating and fear-mongering on for over three years at this point has not seemed to occur to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next came the fact that PM Johnson started losing every vote put to the floor, including one which effectively called for the formation of a new government by the back door and was made a motion of confidence in the Conservative Party, and resulted in the loss of the majority to where it currently stands at -44. Because of the ungovernability of such a position, Johnson asked for an election to be had under the Fixed Terms Parliaments Act…twice. Both times, it was rejected by the opposition and the former Conservative members of Parliament. They then claimed it was undemocratic what Johnson was doing and they would not abide so long as no-deal was still an option. Their rejection of an election was hailed by their friends in the media as them standing up to the declared disdain for democracy Johnson supposedly has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prorogation finally went into effect, however, and the legal battles were to continue on whether the PM had to seek an extension. Then came the Supreme Court of the United Kingdom, squarely and officially inserting themselves into the political process by declaring the entire thing unlawful and ordering Parliament back. They did come back, just to further show their absolute ineffectiveness as they currently stand. They have essentially thrown out the government and inserted themselves as the government without asking the people or through a motion of no-confidence. They continue to reject an election to be held because they know the people can see right through their nonsense and would reject them at the ballot box for this. However, like in America, they currently have united and will work tirelessly to show to the people who dared vote against them in 2016 that they are to never rise up and do it again—a state-of-affairs that could be fatal to the deal negotiated by Johnson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Anglophone leftist/Remainer elites are now a united force once again, reinvigorated by a media class who have as much an interest in overturning the greatest political mandate in British history and the biggest electoral upset in modern American history. They have the reigns of government for the time being in both nations and are ramping up their efforts to put down these uprisings once and for all, presumably as one final big push as they know they will lose. In their desperate last grasps at power, they do not care if they destroy the greatest democratic organisations in the world. They will lie about those who dared choose Brexit or Trump. They will destroy the lives of anybody who helped in making those momentous occasions to happen. They will only be emboldened if they are able to complete their missions in destroying the idea of democratic governance. We must not let them do so. They need to be soundly rejected and defeated at the ballot box and need to be stopped from overturning previous election results they do not like. If we fail to do so, the uncomfortable parallels between the two great Anglophone nations will go from uncomfortable to disastrous.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sam Valk</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The political elite of the United States, in the form of Democrats in the Congress, Democrats in the media, and jealous Republicans in the political establishment, are all upset that the people rejected them in favour of a populist man with zero political experience or connections, and have now united together for the first time since the bomb that was the Mueller testimony to try and overturn the election of 2016. They have announced they will support the impeachment of the American President, although House Speaker Pelosi’s ‘announcement’ of an ‘impeachment inquiry’ thus far has no actual effect because there hasn’t been a vote taken in the House on the issue. However, by September 26, 2019, there were 217 Democrats announcing they’d vote in favour of such an inquiry plus former Republican Justin Amash of Michigan, giving the majority of 218 needed if a vote were brought to the floor. So what did the bad orange man do that finally pushed a majority of the oldest democratic legislative body in the world to declare their official attempts to prematurely remove the chief executive, elected independently of themselves by the people? He talked to a foreign president about trying to end corruption in said President’s nation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What Feminism Ought To Be?</title>
      <link href="/What-Feminism-Ought-To-Be" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Feminism Ought To Be?" />
      <published>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-Feminism-Ought-To-Be</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-Feminism-Ought-To-Be">&lt;p&gt;There is no reason why one shouldn’t be a feminist in this day and age. Any suggestion that is contrary to the notion that women’s rights ought to be protected and that patriarchy ought to be completely dismantled is, ipso facto, foolish and thoroughly immoral. But, post the #metoo movement and torrents of online rage from ‘feminists’, one is bound to ask: is this supposed collective expression of anger against societal discrimination, sexual harrasment and patriarchal structures, well-intentioned as it may be, leading to a material change in the status of women in society? To answer that question in the affirmative seems disingenuous at best and nefarious at worst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The #metoo movement has been both shocking yet brilliant in exposing the rot beneath the veneer of equality. But has this exposition led to meaningful change? Or, for that matter, do passionate supporters of the #metoo movement really seek to bring about changes in, say, sexual harassment legislation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent seminar organised by the Calcutta High Court and American embassy in Calcutta, I was woken up to the reality of how precious little had changed with regard to America’s Civil Rights Act of 1964 or India’s Sexual Harassment of Women at Workplace (Prevention, Prohibition and Redressal) Act, 2013 in the wake of the #metoo movement. There are umpteen criticisms that can be made of both these laws, but one with regard to each should suffice to illustrate why these laws are programmed to protect the Harvey Weinsteins of our age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian Act contemplates an Internal Complaints Committee to function as a redressal mechanism for aggrieved women in a workplace of more than ten employees. The Committee does require an external member who is familiar with issues relating to sexual assault or from an organisation committed to the cause of women, but the nagging sense that this is a mechanism where the “fox is guarding the hen’s house” disturbingly remains. In the case of the American Civil Rights Act, the same ends up happening even though complaints are supposed to be filed with the external US Equal Employment Opportunity Commission. This is because of two American Supreme Court decisions in &lt;em&gt;Faragher v. City of Boca Raton&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Burlington v. Ellerth&lt;/em&gt;. While both these decisions attempted to clarify the law, they inadvertently laid down a point of law that has, in the words of &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5319966/sexual-harassment-scotus-anniversary/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; magazine, “contributed to a key reason why workplace sexual harassment lawsuits are still hard to file today”. The Supreme Court ruled in these cases that an employer may not be liable under the Civil Rights Act for sexual harassment if, inter alia, the complainant fails to take advantage of any internal mechanisms for redressal of the complaint provided by the employer. In other words, we have a situation not dissimilar to the state of the Indian law, where a potential victim of sexual harassment must reckon with the fox before she can truly reach the hen’s house. This, quite obviously, means that numerous sexual harassment claims simply go unnoticed and are, quite simply, suppressed in America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That these and other legal issues have been significant contributors to the extent of harassment and abuse exposed by the #metoo movement ought to be apparent to anyone with a brain. However, a call for reforms to such laws is hardly the defining conversation of today’s feminist movements. Indeed, one can appreciate that perhaps the nitty-gritties of legal reform cannot form part of an exoteric conversation. But one cannot deny that if feminists engaged in advocating meaningful legislative reform with half the passion that they use to ‘destroy’ incels and dudebros online, we would be living in a better world. This is not an anti-feminist rant from a privileged little boy, it is a Greta Thunbergesque (&lt;em&gt;bless her&lt;/em&gt;) “how dare you?!” to all those who claim to stand for women’s rights but are so pathetic at delivering those rights to women. Of course, it is important that society evolves to develop zero tolerance for misogynistic bigots, but to pay more attention to a hurtful tweet instead of the silent suffering of so many working women is rather dystopian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of misplaced priorities, we must address the representation of women in the workplace, and, of course, the feminist’s refusal to do anything real about it. As was pointed out by Baroness Arden of Heswall, Deputy President of the UK Supreme Court, in a guest lecture at the University of Bristol (which I had the privilege to attend), the percentage of women who were partners in London law firms in 2019, 100 years after women got the right to practice law in England, was a mere 29%. What’s more, Lady Arden stated that when she, as a Judge of the English Court of Appeal, proposed that a daycare centre be set up for women barristers near the Royal Courts of Justice, the other male Judges simply dismissed her by stating that this would be a nuisance to male barristers. That Lady Arden was a Judge of the Court of Appeal from 2000-2018 should serve to indicate that such horrendous attitudes are definitely not from some distant age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern feminist’s response to these facts and realities is not very different from the dialogues delivered by Samuel L Jackson in &lt;em&gt;Pulp Fiction&lt;/em&gt;, they are expressions of “furious anger” that seek to lay their vengeance upon men. But these responses are, to quote The Merovingian from the second &lt;em&gt;Matrix&lt;/em&gt; movie, “so boring, so obvious, so bourgeoisie.” They very simply ignore the import of Lady Arden’s arguments: that the next step towards a greater representation of women in the workplace requires some important tangible changes. For instance, one needs to ensure mandatory maternity leave as well as paternity leave is a reality in all big organisations—something that is far from being a reality in a country as developed as America. Secondly, one needs to concentrate on making daycare cheaper and more accessible to women so that the beauty of becoming a mother doesn’t end up penalising a booming career. Thirdly, one needs to change office culture and, sorry right-wing crackpots, that includes ensuring that air conditioning is not set in accordance with the metabolism of middle-aged men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, battling against the patriarchy to implement such changes sounds awfully hard, it is far easier to just obsess over cats (okay, fair enough, they are amazing) and share disgustingly bad feminist slam poetry. Why challenge patriarchs to be better and to do better when one can simply raise one’s hands and declare that they’re trash. And not to mention, how could we possibly change attitudes surrounding women without changing the colour of people’s toys. All of this is not for some comedic effect, it is to expose the Goebbellian lie that is modern feminism, a movement (if it can be called one) that concentrates less on change and more on empty expressions of supposed solidarity with the numerous problems faced by women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most dangerous effects of this is borne out by the feminist’s treatment of rape culture. Speaking logically, one would presume that the only way to destroy an oppressive social construct like rape culture is to teach people to know better. But that definitely is not what today’s feminist does. Today’s feminist hardly seeks to bat for rigorous consent classes in universities and schools. They rarely seek to educate people on understanding the humanity of women and they are loathe to contemplate on how men can be used as allies in combating rape culture. This not only fails to go to the root of the problem by dealing with the cultural rot that a priori drives men’s most problematic behaviours, it has far more nefarious effects. This misandry-is-feminism attitude of so many feminists incentivises a lot of men to simply pretend to be feminists in a bid to get sex. And it should go without saying that this is a most poisonous kind of objectification that relies on its antithesis to survive and grow. This verily means that feminists end up giving traction to a very fundamental sabotage of their own movement by refusing to actually deal with a problem and by stooping to lowly instinct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of that being said, credit must be given where credit is due, modern feminism has been very sharp in changing broader culture to simply not be accommodative of abusers and bigots. It has created a rightfully hostile environment for those who would dare say that women are lesser than men and it has clarified that sexist attitudes are simply not going to fly anymore. However, that is simply not enough. One has to go beyond a great grand shriek about how sexist and patriarchal the world is to actually contemplate upon how it could look better. And one has to understand that without such a constructive contemplation, one is going to have a world with a smokescreen of verbose activism but with a ground reality of festering oppression.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There is no reason why one shouldn’t be a feminist in this day and age. Any suggestion that is contrary to the notion that women’s rights ought to be protected and that patriarchy ought to be completely dismantled is, ipso facto, foolish and thoroughly immoral. But, post the #metoo movement and torrents of online rage from ‘feminists’, one is bound to ask: is this supposed collective expression of anger against societal discrimination, sexual harrasment and patriarchal structures, well-intentioned as it may be, leading to a material change in the status of women in society? To answer that question in the affirmative seems disingenuous at best and nefarious at worst.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Groupthink: A World-Governing Herd Mentality</title>
      <link href="/A-World-Governing-Herd-Mentality" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Groupthink: A World-Governing Herd Mentality" />
      <published>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-World-Governing-Herd-Mentality</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-World-Governing-Herd-Mentality">&lt;p&gt;We’ve all followed the pack at some points of time in our lives. Be it decisions
about what kind of studies to pursue, which rat race to run, which Beyblade to
buy or which new friend to include in our otherwise exclusive gang. Why we like
to do so is because it’s easier than thinking for oneself. Once you figure out
how this same thought process affects government policies, major industries,
workplace regulations, national elections, and other such important-sounding
things, you realise that maybe even important people, unlike us, have an
inherent laziness seen in their readiness to accept the easiest narrative. This,
however, is just the tip of the iceberg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what Irving L Janis, a research psychologist from Yale University, set
out to establish when he pioneered the initial research on groupthink - a term
inspired by doublethink, the phenomenon of accepting two contradictory beliefs
because of political propaganda (the term was coined by George Orwell in his
novel &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt;). Janis believed that groups that suffered from groupthink had some
common characteristics among them. He identified 8 common symptoms in his
original paper: &lt;em&gt;invulnerability&lt;/em&gt; in the belief that they can never be defeated,
&lt;em&gt;rationalising&lt;/em&gt; all sorts of warnings that hint towards an adversity that the
group wouldn’t prefer, blind faith in the group’s &lt;em&gt;moral high ground&lt;/em&gt; without
actually considering the consequences, &lt;em&gt;stereotyping&lt;/em&gt; the enemy, &lt;em&gt;peer
pressure&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;self-censorship&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;unanimity&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;mindguards&lt;/em&gt; that prevent
unfavourable but true information from changing the group leader’s decision.
It’s also very interesting to think of group dynamics in this way. Ideally being
in a circle of friends must mean that you find solace in it and you can
gleefully say anything without feeling the need to censor yourself. If this
circle has some unspoken ideals that are conditions for you to remain in it, the
phenomenon of groupthink arises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink offers a sense of comfort. Think of the first time you left for
college, unshackled by the rules that bound you in school. You were probably
afraid of the amount of freedom you had, of how alone you were. You would rather
go back to a time when you were governed by rules, at home, because at the very
least there was someone who would take care of you, every step of the way. You
don’t want to be part of this ugly, competitive world and instead of sorting
life out for yourself, you’d rather have someone else do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting how many instances from history one can draw in order to fit
this model. Janis advances his argument about groupthink, primarily, by talking
about the Bay of Pigs invasion that inevitably led to the defeat of the CIA-led
American personnel. Janis provided proof of the mechanisms that the Kennedy
administration had in place, such that only the anti-communist narrative could
prevail in their decisions, with little space left for dissent. They believed
that, as a communist nation, Cuba had very little firepower against the
capitalist might of the US. Arthur Schlesinger, one of the members of Kennedy’s
circle, was an active dissenter but he was constantly suppressed. In a similar
vein but far worse off is the Vietnam War. The Nixon administration truly
believed they could ride the wave of American integrity being threatened abroad
and communists being inherently evil despite being told that it was unlikely
that they could defeat the Viet Cong. Not only did they end up losing horribly
but also lost the trust of the soldiers, who had been sent on government orders,
and the American public that saw very little wrong in having leftist leanings.
The government earned the wrath of a generation that decided to pour their pain
into anti-war music, psychedelics and alternative living. Lesson learnt: don’t
piss off people who can become the future Rolling Stones or Black Sabbath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US isn’t the only nation to have fallen prey to this. The Chernobyl tragedy
speaks for why unwavering belief in any ideology, especially one that
prioritises the nation over its citizens, is the surest route to disaster. The
Soviet Union’s adherence to not leaking any information about the nuclear power
plant, its belief that it was virtually impossible for any Soviet construction
to fail, let alone one that displayed its true might in a cold war, and
immediate dismissal of scientific backing behind what could happen was what
caused Mikhail Gorbachev to proclaim the Chernobyl disaster as the event that
led to the collapse of the USSR. Nazi Germany is an even better example; people
were wilfully ignorant of the dictatorship’s treatment of Jews in concentration
camps. They believed that the power of the fatherland could extend everywhere
without consequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink is not a thing of the past either. In the present, groupthink is how
groups of people become alienated from other ideas. Elite, educated liberals of
the day choose not to explain their stance to people who oppose them, assuming
the opposition to be &lt;em&gt;inherently stupid&lt;/em&gt;. The same ‘inherently stupid’ then
collectivise and assume majority power. Thereafter, even if someone from this
group is presented with an alternative rationale, they will choose to reject it
due to the distrust that has already been formed. This is best exemplified in
how, in an age where political correctness has become a ‘necessity’, anyone with
a contrary view of things is bashed instead of educated. This is not to say that
all political correctness is unwarranted. However, if liberals choose to deride
rather than increase awareness then they are simply contributing to the
aforementioned alienation. On the other hand, conservatives around the world
(who often overlap with the aforementioned ‘inherently stupid’) stick to
societal norms that have existed for ages, even if they’re regressive.
Groupthink is often the basis for dinner table conversations that revolve around
politics; opposition to the favourite narrative, if any, will be met with loud,
sharp words. These dynamics are used to the advantage of politicians like Donald
Trump, who know how to appeal to their voter base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink extends beyond politics. It led to the subprime crisis in 2008. The
financial industry ardently believed that no rational human being would ever
default on his/her home loan. However, they took this to mean that loans could
be given to anyone and everyone, and then they built complex securities based on
these loans that were dependent on each other. The dot-com bubble in the early
2000’s is a good example too. The internet was the hottest property that was
virtual, and people were naturally excited about its potential. This sentiment
led to massive overvaluation of companies that merely had a website which
combined with tech companies prioritising growth over profit and cash flow
stability, led to the downfall of a number of firms. It is happening even today,
with startups like Uber and WeWork launching their initial public offerings.
WeWork is currently burning cash, and it has been subject to lots of scrutiny by
the market. Adam Neumann, the founder, was recently ousted from the post of CEO.
Uber took a huge plunge on its first day of going public. This shows how
groupthink is responsible for hype value. Brands like Supreme, that rely simply
on their logo being printed on what would otherwise be a plain white T-shirt,
have the power of hype working in their favour. This hype has no concrete basis
like quality. It builds up through targeted marketing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does one escape groupthink? Most articles state one method right off the
bat: create awareness of critical thinking skills that lead to thoughtful
criticism. It might just be the case that what we do not wish to hear is what
truly makes sense to us at times. Silence isn’t proof of consent from members.
People who do not speak up must be encouraged to talk, since it’s entirely
possible that they don’t want to only out of the fear of being chastised.
Another way is to have the leader of the group take a poll before they announce
their opinion. In that way, especially if the poll is anonymous, those who were
not comfortable providing a perspective contrarian to the existing status quo
can freely say what they want to. Another way is to appoint a devil’s advocate
specifically for this purpose, or a red-team that makes a B-plan in contrast to
yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink offers a comfortable seat where you may not have to do a lot of
thinking, or take a lot of responsibility. If a decision goes horribly wrong,
then no &lt;em&gt;single&lt;/em&gt; individual can be held accountable. However, if everyone in a
group feels a heightened sense of pride towards the goal of a group, and can be
made to believe that their actions have a large impact, positive or negative,
then decisions will be taken with greater forethought and discussion. In times
that value nuanced discussions over various ideas, we must be heading towards
the ideal of free-flowing thought instead succumbing to peer pressure.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pranav Manie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">We’ve all followed the pack at some points of time in our lives. Be it decisions about what kind of studies to pursue, which rat race to run, which Beyblade to buy or which new friend to include in our otherwise exclusive gang. Why we like to do so is because it’s easier than thinking for oneself. Once you figure out how this same thought process affects government policies, major industries, workplace regulations, national elections, and other such important-sounding things, you realise that maybe even important people, unlike us, have an inherent laziness seen in their readiness to accept the easiest narrative. This, however, is just the tip of the iceberg. This is what Irving L Janis, a research psychologist from Yale University, set out to establish when he pioneered the initial research on groupthink - a term inspired by doublethink, the phenomenon of accepting two contradictory beliefs because of political propaganda (the term was coined by George Orwell in his novel 1984). Janis believed that groups that suffered from groupthink had some common characteristics among them. He identified 8 common symptoms in his original paper: invulnerability in the belief that they can never be defeated, rationalising all sorts of warnings that hint towards an adversity that the group wouldn’t prefer, blind faith in the group’s moral high ground without actually considering the consequences, stereotyping the enemy, peer pressure, self-censorship, unanimity and mindguards that prevent unfavourable but true information from changing the group leader’s decision. It’s also very interesting to think of group dynamics in this way. Ideally being in a circle of friends must mean that you find solace in it and you can gleefully say anything without feeling the need to censor yourself. If this circle has some unspoken ideals that are conditions for you to remain in it, the phenomenon of groupthink arises. Groupthink offers a sense of comfort. Think of the first time you left for college, unshackled by the rules that bound you in school. You were probably afraid of the amount of freedom you had, of how alone you were. You would rather go back to a time when you were governed by rules, at home, because at the very least there was someone who would take care of you, every step of the way. You don’t want to be part of this ugly, competitive world and instead of sorting life out for yourself, you’d rather have someone else do it. It’s interesting how many instances from history one can draw in order to fit this model. Janis advances his argument about groupthink, primarily, by talking about the Bay of Pigs invasion that inevitably led to the defeat of the CIA-led American personnel. Janis provided proof of the mechanisms that the Kennedy administration had in place, such that only the anti-communist narrative could prevail in their decisions, with little space left for dissent. They believed that, as a communist nation, Cuba had very little firepower against the capitalist might of the US. Arthur Schlesinger, one of the members of Kennedy’s circle, was an active dissenter but he was constantly suppressed. In a similar vein but far worse off is the Vietnam War. The Nixon administration truly believed they could ride the wave of American integrity being threatened abroad and communists being inherently evil despite being told that it was unlikely that they could defeat the Viet Cong. Not only did they end up losing horribly but also lost the trust of the soldiers, who had been sent on government orders, and the American public that saw very little wrong in having leftist leanings. The government earned the wrath of a generation that decided to pour their pain into anti-war music, psychedelics and alternative living. Lesson learnt: don’t piss off people who can become the future Rolling Stones or Black Sabbath. The US isn’t the only nation to have fallen prey to this. The Chernobyl tragedy speaks for why unwavering belief in any ideology, especially one that prioritises the nation over its citizens, is the surest route to disaster. The Soviet Union’s adherence to not leaking any information about the nuclear power plant, its belief that it was virtually impossible for any Soviet construction to fail, let alone one that displayed its true might in a cold war, and immediate dismissal of scientific backing behind what could happen was what caused Mikhail Gorbachev to proclaim the Chernobyl disaster as the event that led to the collapse of the USSR. Nazi Germany is an even better example; people were wilfully ignorant of the dictatorship’s treatment of Jews in concentration camps. They believed that the power of the fatherland could extend everywhere without consequence. Groupthink is not a thing of the past either. In the present, groupthink is how groups of people become alienated from other ideas. Elite, educated liberals of the day choose not to explain their stance to people who oppose them, assuming the opposition to be inherently stupid. The same ‘inherently stupid’ then collectivise and assume majority power. Thereafter, even if someone from this group is presented with an alternative rationale, they will choose to reject it due to the distrust that has already been formed. This is best exemplified in how, in an age where political correctness has become a ‘necessity’, anyone with a contrary view of things is bashed instead of educated. This is not to say that all political correctness is unwarranted. However, if liberals choose to deride rather than increase awareness then they are simply contributing to the aforementioned alienation. On the other hand, conservatives around the world (who often overlap with the aforementioned ‘inherently stupid’) stick to societal norms that have existed for ages, even if they’re regressive. Groupthink is often the basis for dinner table conversations that revolve around politics; opposition to the favourite narrative, if any, will be met with loud, sharp words. These dynamics are used to the advantage of politicians like Donald Trump, who know how to appeal to their voter base. Groupthink extends beyond politics. It led to the subprime crisis in 2008. The financial industry ardently believed that no rational human being would ever default on his/her home loan. However, they took this to mean that loans could be given to anyone and everyone, and then they built complex securities based on these loans that were dependent on each other. The dot-com bubble in the early 2000’s is a good example too. The internet was the hottest property that was virtual, and people were naturally excited about its potential. This sentiment led to massive overvaluation of companies that merely had a website which combined with tech companies prioritising growth over profit and cash flow stability, led to the downfall of a number of firms. It is happening even today, with startups like Uber and WeWork launching their initial public offerings. WeWork is currently burning cash, and it has been subject to lots of scrutiny by the market. Adam Neumann, the founder, was recently ousted from the post of CEO. Uber took a huge plunge on its first day of going public. This shows how groupthink is responsible for hype value. Brands like Supreme, that rely simply on their logo being printed on what would otherwise be a plain white T-shirt, have the power of hype working in their favour. This hype has no concrete basis like quality. It builds up through targeted marketing. How does one escape groupthink? Most articles state one method right off the bat: create awareness of critical thinking skills that lead to thoughtful criticism. It might just be the case that what we do not wish to hear is what truly makes sense to us at times. Silence isn’t proof of consent from members. People who do not speak up must be encouraged to talk, since it’s entirely possible that they don’t want to only out of the fear of being chastised. Another way is to have the leader of the group take a poll before they announce their opinion. In that way, especially if the poll is anonymous, those who were not comfortable providing a perspective contrarian to the existing status quo can freely say what they want to. Another way is to appoint a devil’s advocate specifically for this purpose, or a red-team that makes a B-plan in contrast to yours. Groupthink offers a comfortable seat where you may not have to do a lot of thinking, or take a lot of responsibility. If a decision goes horribly wrong, then no single individual can be held accountable. However, if everyone in a group feels a heightened sense of pride towards the goal of a group, and can be made to believe that their actions have a large impact, positive or negative, then decisions will be taken with greater forethought and discussion. In times that value nuanced discussions over various ideas, we must be heading towards the ideal of free-flowing thought instead succumbing to peer pressure.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
