<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/priyanshi.mehra/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-08-02T13:32:04+01:00</updated>
  <id>/author/priyanshi.mehra/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Virtual Classrooms and Open Book Examinations</title>
      <link href="/Virtual-Classrooms-and-Open-Book-Examinations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Virtual Classrooms and Open Book Examinations" />
      <published>2020-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Virtual-Classrooms-and-Open-Book-Examinations</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Virtual-Classrooms-and-Open-Book-Examinations">&lt;p&gt;Virtual classrooms is a phrase that has become an important part of the new normal, and along with it comes the infamous open-book examinations. Who would have thought that in 2020, the mainstream physical examinations would be replaced by open book examinations. But then again, who in their wildest dreams would have thought that the whole world will be stuck inside their homes, or away from it, for almost a year. The pandemic has clearly uprooted the lives of many, and the students, all across the globe, are no different.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students have been forced to stay within the four walls of their houses, and attend digital schooling. In a country like India or the UK, it was March or April when the lockdown started as a result of the pandemic, and honestly, at that time no one thought it would go on for this long. In fact, no one was prepared for this pandemic and surely wasn’t ready to adapt to it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was clear from the start that the educational institutions were going to make decisions that might not be suited for the heterogeneous society that we are. Too many debates, discussions and uncertainty led to all sorts of discussions on what to do for the students who had their exams approaching. Thus, emerged the idea of open-book examinations for final year college students. This was initially taken up by Delhi University. The exams got postponed so many times that by the time we took the test we had lost the count. But when these examinations did take place, they happened at a definite, not-so-unclear cost.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, as a person, who could afford to have a separate room and a laptop to take the exams in peace, I was still drowned in intense amounts of anxiety. For, as a student since the past 17 years, all I had to focus on was my paper. Anything from a wrong question, to doubts, to submission of sheets was to be taken care of by the invigilators. The usage of any sort of technology wasn't even a part of the discussion. So these 17 years taught me to dedicate my whole three hours to write the exam. But with this pandemic and open-book examinations, it meant that for once I was required to do all the tasks by myself, using technology, an approach that many of us were clueless about, the added stress being whether the sheets were being uploaded and were the scanned images even clear. All this made me wonder about those who did not have all these layers of privilege I had, and the added stress levels they had to deal with. Obviously, by no means can I even come close to understanding how dreadful all this would have been for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is in times like these where the only source of interaction and schooling is through technology, people are forced to be left out, just because they cannot afford such a luxury. Thus, in such situations, something like education that we consider a necessity, in fact, becomes a luxury for many people.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the past few months, all the classes are being taken online. Within the span of these months, the mode of examinations has expanded to become MCQ-based or assignment-based. Despite all of this, looking at the state of students, it all doesn't look so different from the idea of a zero academic year, which many people find absurd. The students are constantly stuck onto the screens to study and then to do their homework and assignments, no wonder they are so tired from it all. From teachers figuring out how to make it all understandable to a class with no video and microphone on, to the students attending the class but sleeping through most of it. There is little to no education taking place.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this seems like it was bound to happen because our teaching methods have been developed for face-to-face interactions and not for video-call sessions. Moreover, Indian education systems aren't even reformed enough to focus on teaching the concepts, rather than focusing on exams, which clearly doesn't sit well with the condition we are in currently. Hence, it really makes no sense to have open-book examinations or any form of virtual examinations for that matter, when our whole education system is based on seeing how well you remember what you have learnt, and not really how well you grasp the concept.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pandemic has already increased our anxiety levels, and an education like this just adds to it all. This is only the state of the ones who are privileged enough to actually have access to such resources and means of education. There are so many students out there who due to different reasons cannot take up online classes. And hence have no other option but to skip this year, in the hopes that they'll get to join next year. No one can imagine the stress of these children and the huge loss to their mental health as a result of not being able to take up classes this year. We did see one such incident come forth from Lady Shri Ram College, Delhi University, where a brilliant student was so burdened by the stress of her family's financial incapability that it made her take her own life. It was only then that the college decided to take action towards reducing fees and providing help to those in need. But is it really the lack of financial capability of the family, or the lack of concern of the people sitting on the other end, who refuse to look into how the pandemic could be affecting the students and their families?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking around we do see differences when it comes to how the private institutions and government institutions have dealt with digital schooling. And definitely, there is a clear difference between nations across the globe. However, despite these differences, with some institutions clearly having a better grasp of virtual classroom systems, none of the institutions were prepared to shift their entire curriculum fully online for a whole year, or maybe even more. And even though, for once I am willing to believe that all the educational institutions took the most suitable option in the current scenario, there are still aspects which they just chose to ignore. While they adapted to the new normal, they forgot to look into the students who too had to adapt to it. From lack of concern towards the cash crunch that people are facing, to the effects of the pandemic on the mental and physical well-being of students — all of this is far from being discussed. There are still students left who haven't taken examinations due to various reasons, and they are constantly under stress, with the uncertainty of when they'll actually take them only growing. Every day my Instagram stories are filled with students crying over the extensive amount of pressure from the deadlines of assignments and the upcoming exams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this makes us wonder what is the point of such an education that only focuses on finishing the curriculum and not even on making sure that each and every student is actually able to attend these classes. Even if it seems that digital schooling is the only possible option right now, is it really worth it if it is at the expense of the sanity of the students, especially with so many students being left out of it altogether?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Priyanshi Mehra</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Virtual classrooms is a phrase that has become an important part of the new normal, and along with it comes the infamous open-book examinations. Who would have thought that in 2020, the mainstream physical examinations would be replaced by open book examinations. But then again, who in their wildest dreams would have thought that the whole world will be stuck inside their homes, or away from it, for almost a year. The pandemic has clearly uprooted the lives of many, and the students, all across the globe, are no different.&amp;nbsp; Students have been forced to stay within the four walls of their houses, and attend digital schooling. In a country like India or the UK, it was March or April when the lockdown started as a result of the pandemic, and honestly, at that time no one thought it would go on for this long. In fact, no one was prepared for this pandemic and surely wasn’t ready to adapt to it.&amp;nbsp; It was clear from the start that the educational institutions were going to make decisions that might not be suited for the heterogeneous society that we are. Too many debates, discussions and uncertainty led to all sorts of discussions on what to do for the students who had their exams approaching. Thus, emerged the idea of open-book examinations for final year college students. This was initially taken up by Delhi University. The exams got postponed so many times that by the time we took the test we had lost the count. But when these examinations did take place, they happened at a definite, not-so-unclear cost.&amp;nbsp; You see, as a person, who could afford to have a separate room and a laptop to take the exams in peace, I was still drowned in intense amounts of anxiety. For, as a student since the past 17 years, all I had to focus on was my paper. Anything from a wrong question, to doubts, to submission of sheets was to be taken care of by the invigilators. The usage of any sort of technology wasn't even a part of the discussion. So these 17 years taught me to dedicate my whole three hours to write the exam. But with this pandemic and open-book examinations, it meant that for once I was required to do all the tasks by myself, using technology, an approach that many of us were clueless about, the added stress being whether the sheets were being uploaded and were the scanned images even clear. All this made me wonder about those who did not have all these layers of privilege I had, and the added stress levels they had to deal with. Obviously, by no means can I even come close to understanding how dreadful all this would have been for them. It is in times like these where the only source of interaction and schooling is through technology, people are forced to be left out, just because they cannot afford such a luxury. Thus, in such situations, something like education that we consider a necessity, in fact, becomes a luxury for many people.&amp;nbsp; Since the past few months, all the classes are being taken online. Within the span of these months, the mode of examinations has expanded to become MCQ-based or assignment-based. Despite all of this, looking at the state of students, it all doesn't look so different from the idea of a zero academic year, which many people find absurd. The students are constantly stuck onto the screens to study and then to do their homework and assignments, no wonder they are so tired from it all. From teachers figuring out how to make it all understandable to a class with no video and microphone on, to the students attending the class but sleeping through most of it. There is little to no education taking place.&amp;nbsp; All of this seems like it was bound to happen because our teaching methods have been developed for face-to-face interactions and not for video-call sessions. Moreover, Indian education systems aren't even reformed enough to focus on teaching the concepts, rather than focusing on exams, which clearly doesn't sit well with the condition we are in currently. Hence, it really makes no sense to have open-book examinations or any form of virtual examinations for that matter, when our whole education system is based on seeing how well you remember what you have learnt, and not really how well you grasp the concept.&amp;nbsp; The pandemic has already increased our anxiety levels, and an education like this just adds to it all. This is only the state of the ones who are privileged enough to actually have access to such resources and means of education. There are so many students out there who due to different reasons cannot take up online classes. And hence have no other option but to skip this year, in the hopes that they'll get to join next year. No one can imagine the stress of these children and the huge loss to their mental health as a result of not being able to take up classes this year. We did see one such incident come forth from Lady Shri Ram College, Delhi University, where a brilliant student was so burdened by the stress of her family's financial incapability that it made her take her own life. It was only then that the college decided to take action towards reducing fees and providing help to those in need. But is it really the lack of financial capability of the family, or the lack of concern of the people sitting on the other end, who refuse to look into how the pandemic could be affecting the students and their families?&amp;nbsp; Looking around we do see differences when it comes to how the private institutions and government institutions have dealt with digital schooling. And definitely, there is a clear difference between nations across the globe. However, despite these differences, with some institutions clearly having a better grasp of virtual classroom systems, none of the institutions were prepared to shift their entire curriculum fully online for a whole year, or maybe even more. And even though, for once I am willing to believe that all the educational institutions took the most suitable option in the current scenario, there are still aspects which they just chose to ignore. While they adapted to the new normal, they forgot to look into the students who too had to adapt to it. From lack of concern towards the cash crunch that people are facing, to the effects of the pandemic on the mental and physical well-being of students — all of this is far from being discussed. There are still students left who haven't taken examinations due to various reasons, and they are constantly under stress, with the uncertainty of when they'll actually take them only growing. Every day my Instagram stories are filled with students crying over the extensive amount of pressure from the deadlines of assignments and the upcoming exams. All of this makes us wonder what is the point of such an education that only focuses on finishing the curriculum and not even on making sure that each and every student is actually able to attend these classes. Even if it seems that digital schooling is the only possible option right now, is it really worth it if it is at the expense of the sanity of the students, especially with so many students being left out of it altogether?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Present Bias: Focus on the Now but maybe Not Always</title>
      <link href="/Present-Bias-Focus-on-the-Now-but-maybe-Not-Always" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Present Bias: Focus on the Now but maybe Not Always" />
      <published>2020-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Present-Bias-Focus-on-the-Now-but-maybe-Not-Always</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Present-Bias-Focus-on-the-Now-but-maybe-Not-Always">&lt;p&gt;Many times we wonder, what is it that makes us procrastinate? Why do we spend the whole day scrolling through Instagram instead of finishing the assignment that is due tomorrow? Apart from the fact that social media is designed to distract us, procrastinating isn't as simple as just being lazy. It isn't only about not wanting to do the task at hand, but more about how we humans are wired.&amp;nbsp; Procrastination is in fact related to a cognitive bias called the &lt;em&gt;present bias&lt;/em&gt;. As the name in itself suggests, it is the tendency of humans to be biased towards the present. This means that we tend to go for short-term rewards that provide us instant gratification rather than choosing long-term benefits. Thus, even though the benefit of finishing that assignment is clearly more than simply being on Instagram, the sense of gratification is achieved faster in the latter. Therefore, our brain might as well trick us into choosing the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to understand why humans are actually biased towards the present. The answer lies in how our ancestors lived their lives. The times they lived in, it only made sense that they focused on the present. With the uncertainty of the future and the environment they lived in, they had no other option but to be short-sighted in their decision making. This present bias allowed them to survive and deal with the immediate threats that existed around them. Over the centuries, this outlook of theirs seems to have been so well engraved in our brains that even today we have a similar mindset. Despite us having a far more stable lifestyle and a future to actually look forward to, our brain still makes us biased towards our present. It still makes us believe that the future is a scary avenue that one shouldn't be focusing much on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of the present bias has been studied by many researchers over the years, in order to understand to what extent such a bias can affect the lives of individuals. An interesting experiment in this field was conducted by Walter Mischel. This experiment that goes by the name of &lt;em&gt;Marshmallow Test &lt;/em&gt;is a famous experiment which involved finding out whether children delayed gratification. It involved children being asked to either choose a marshmallow now or wait for 15-20 minutes to get two of them. This experiment, however, did not end here only. After a few years, these very children, who were by then adolescents, were traced and it was seen that the children who delayed gratification at a younger age were able to be more successful in the later period of their lives. Thus, shedding light on the connection between small decisions turning into a lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting aspect of present bias is that it is not just limited to the field of psychology but also equally important for economics. Take for an example, if you were to choose between getting a job of ₹15,000/month now, or interning for free for a year and getting a job of ₹30,000/month. You are more likely to choose the former. But if you were asked to either complete your 3 years of Bachelor's and get a job starting at ₹15,000/month or to choose an integrated programme of 4 years that would allow you to get a package starting at ₹30,000/month, then you are most likely to choose the second option. Even though there isn’t a difference between these two cases other than the time periods, your choice would potentially differ. This is because our brain can only distinguish between the present and the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether the future is three or four years down the lane, our brain fails to distinguish between them, because both are considered as far-sighted. Since our mind takes the future as uncertain it wants to make decisions for now, even though they might not be as beneficial. In economics, present bias is used when we talk about time inconsistency and discounting. Time inconsistency refers to the fact that individuals are inconsistent over time. That is, for instance, you decide to hit the gym next month, but when next month arrives, you are more likely to postpone it to another month. Thus, meaning that people aren't as rational in making decisions, but there are various social and psychological factors that govern their decisions. People have the tendency to change their choices, over different time periods even though the benefits remain the same. Richard H Thaler (a Nobel Prize Winner for his work in the field of behavioural economics) has conducted researches that show that economics and psychology are far more closely related than one can imagine, thus expanding the scope and importance of behavioural economics. He along with H M Shefrin wrote a paper titled &lt;em&gt;An Economic Theory of Self-control&lt;/em&gt; that introduced an economic model of self-control. This model explains that people aren't only lacking self-control when it comes to not buying new clothes, or when it comes to stopping with just another episode. But the lack of self-control can also be seen towards how people handle their finances, especially saving for their retirements before it gets late. To us, saving money seems more like a loss now even though it’ll benefit us in future, and thus people tend to postpone saving money. In fact, this research has led to various social policies to emerge to help people with saving their money from early days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since it is wired into our system to focus on what could harm us immediately, rather than what could harm us in the long-term, present bias manifests itself in many of our actions. The concept of present bias explains why we humans tend to make self-harming choices that provide us instant gratification but clearly have harmful consequences in the future. It also explains why we tend to ignore the importance of climate change, since it doesn't seem like an instant harm to our minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living in the present is important, but it isn't all we should be focused on. In reality, our lives are a combination of the past, present and future and therefore it becomes equally important to realise that the present is only a small piece in the puzzle of life. Understanding what present bias is, and how strongly it can control our decision making, allows us to be more aware of our own selves. It makes us realise that our brains aren't always thinking what's best for us and can quite a few times make impulsive decisions that might not seem so right in the years to come. Clearly, our brains are guided by the fear of the future, because of all the uncertainty it brings. So it only makes sense that we continue to ignore the future, and be in a more comfortable zone, the present. And honestly, instant gratification, no matter for how little of a time, does feel good. But it also feels fulfilling to make decisions that'll help our future selves. This is the dilemma that present bias poses. Whether to choose the time that we know of or to choose the time that'll come. It isn't easy to break away from our habits, especially the ones that are so well engraved in our nerves. Self-control and will power aren't as easily attained as we are likely to believe. But what we can do is to be more aware of how our brains have a tendency of fooling our own selves, and maybe for once not trust whatever our brain has to say.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Priyanshi Mehra</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Many times we wonder, what is it that makes us procrastinate? Why do we spend the whole day scrolling through Instagram instead of finishing the assignment that is due tomorrow? Apart from the fact that social media is designed to distract us, procrastinating isn't as simple as just being lazy. It isn't only about not wanting to do the task at hand, but more about how we humans are wired.&amp;nbsp; Procrastination is in fact related to a cognitive bias called the present bias. As the name in itself suggests, it is the tendency of humans to be biased towards the present. This means that we tend to go for short-term rewards that provide us instant gratification rather than choosing long-term benefits. Thus, even though the benefit of finishing that assignment is clearly more than simply being on Instagram, the sense of gratification is achieved faster in the latter. Therefore, our brain might as well trick us into choosing the latter. It is important to understand why humans are actually biased towards the present. The answer lies in how our ancestors lived their lives. The times they lived in, it only made sense that they focused on the present. With the uncertainty of the future and the environment they lived in, they had no other option but to be short-sighted in their decision making. This present bias allowed them to survive and deal with the immediate threats that existed around them. Over the centuries, this outlook of theirs seems to have been so well engraved in our brains that even today we have a similar mindset. Despite us having a far more stable lifestyle and a future to actually look forward to, our brain still makes us biased towards our present. It still makes us believe that the future is a scary avenue that one shouldn't be focusing much on it. The idea of the present bias has been studied by many researchers over the years, in order to understand to what extent such a bias can affect the lives of individuals. An interesting experiment in this field was conducted by Walter Mischel. This experiment that goes by the name of Marshmallow Test is a famous experiment which involved finding out whether children delayed gratification. It involved children being asked to either choose a marshmallow now or wait for 15-20 minutes to get two of them. This experiment, however, did not end here only. After a few years, these very children, who were by then adolescents, were traced and it was seen that the children who delayed gratification at a younger age were able to be more successful in the later period of their lives. Thus, shedding light on the connection between small decisions turning into a lifestyle. An interesting aspect of present bias is that it is not just limited to the field of psychology but also equally important for economics. Take for an example, if you were to choose between getting a job of ₹15,000/month now, or interning for free for a year and getting a job of ₹30,000/month. You are more likely to choose the former. But if you were asked to either complete your 3 years of Bachelor's and get a job starting at ₹15,000/month or to choose an integrated programme of 4 years that would allow you to get a package starting at ₹30,000/month, then you are most likely to choose the second option. Even though there isn’t a difference between these two cases other than the time periods, your choice would potentially differ. This is because our brain can only distinguish between the present and the future. Whether the future is three or four years down the lane, our brain fails to distinguish between them, because both are considered as far-sighted. Since our mind takes the future as uncertain it wants to make decisions for now, even though they might not be as beneficial. In economics, present bias is used when we talk about time inconsistency and discounting. Time inconsistency refers to the fact that individuals are inconsistent over time. That is, for instance, you decide to hit the gym next month, but when next month arrives, you are more likely to postpone it to another month. Thus, meaning that people aren't as rational in making decisions, but there are various social and psychological factors that govern their decisions. People have the tendency to change their choices, over different time periods even though the benefits remain the same. Richard H Thaler (a Nobel Prize Winner for his work in the field of behavioural economics) has conducted researches that show that economics and psychology are far more closely related than one can imagine, thus expanding the scope and importance of behavioural economics. He along with H M Shefrin wrote a paper titled An Economic Theory of Self-control that introduced an economic model of self-control. This model explains that people aren't only lacking self-control when it comes to not buying new clothes, or when it comes to stopping with just another episode. But the lack of self-control can also be seen towards how people handle their finances, especially saving for their retirements before it gets late. To us, saving money seems more like a loss now even though it’ll benefit us in future, and thus people tend to postpone saving money. In fact, this research has led to various social policies to emerge to help people with saving their money from early days. Since it is wired into our system to focus on what could harm us immediately, rather than what could harm us in the long-term, present bias manifests itself in many of our actions. The concept of present bias explains why we humans tend to make self-harming choices that provide us instant gratification but clearly have harmful consequences in the future. It also explains why we tend to ignore the importance of climate change, since it doesn't seem like an instant harm to our minds. Living in the present is important, but it isn't all we should be focused on. In reality, our lives are a combination of the past, present and future and therefore it becomes equally important to realise that the present is only a small piece in the puzzle of life. Understanding what present bias is, and how strongly it can control our decision making, allows us to be more aware of our own selves. It makes us realise that our brains aren't always thinking what's best for us and can quite a few times make impulsive decisions that might not seem so right in the years to come. Clearly, our brains are guided by the fear of the future, because of all the uncertainty it brings. So it only makes sense that we continue to ignore the future, and be in a more comfortable zone, the present. And honestly, instant gratification, no matter for how little of a time, does feel good. But it also feels fulfilling to make decisions that'll help our future selves. This is the dilemma that present bias poses. Whether to choose the time that we know of or to choose the time that'll come. It isn't easy to break away from our habits, especially the ones that are so well engraved in our nerves. Self-control and will power aren't as easily attained as we are likely to believe. But what we can do is to be more aware of how our brains have a tendency of fooling our own selves, and maybe for once not trust whatever our brain has to say.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">SKY Castle: What Happens When Adults Don’t Act Like Adults?</title>
      <link href="/SKY-Castle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SKY Castle: What Happens When Adults Don't Act Like Adults?" />
      <published>2020-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/SKY-Castle</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/SKY-Castle">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;We all lie&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tell you the truths&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sometimes we laugh and easily lie&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;SKY Castle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is a satirical, dark comedy-drama that revolves around the lives of four elite families living in the SKY Castle neighbourhood, situated in the suburbs of Seoul. In reality, &lt;em&gt;SKY&lt;/em&gt; is an acronym for the three renowned colleges of South Korea, namely, Seoul National University (SNU), Korea University and Yonsei University. SKY neighbourhood is home to top doctors and a prosecutor turned professor, who all want their children to live a worthy life, which according to them, can only be achieved if they get into one of these above-mentioned colleges. Thus, the story revolves around the Korean National College Exam, &lt;em&gt;Suneung&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The show, like most K-drama shows, starts with a straightforward story but manages to leave the audience baffled with its twists and turns. It's a really well-crafted show that makes its audience grip to their screens since the first episode itself. What is commendable about &lt;em&gt;SKY Castle&lt;/em&gt; is that despite its twists, never once does it distract itself from the main plot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first episode opens with a party being thrown to celebrate the Park family; whose son got into the Seoul National Medical School. But more than being happy, the other families are interested in knowing the methods that led to his admission. As it turns out, an expensive entrance exam coordinator made this possible. Therefore, this information starts a fight to hire her at an exclusive VVIP party. This coordinator who goes by the name of Kim Joo-Young chooses to teach Ye-Seo, whose only dream has been to get admission in Seoul National Medical College.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A dark cloud falls over the Park family when Lee Myung-Joo, the mother, decides to take her own life. We notice that Kim Joo-Young, the exceptional coordinator, definitely had something to do with it. However, Ye-Seo’s mother, even after finding it all out, is willing to look past all this because all she wants is to see her daughter get into SNU. With such a tragedy, Park family decides to move out and this opens the door for a new family to move in. This new family, Hwang family, have a simple and relaxed outlook towards life which clearly doesn't sit well with the other families. From questioning Lee So Im’s teaching methods to constantly treating her as an outsider, they really do give the Hwang family a hard time. Even at the hospital, Dr Hwang, who wants to treat the patients and interns with utmost respect, is criticised by Dr Kang, Ye-Seo’s father, who is more inclined towards making money and asserting his authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With each passing episode, we realise that Joo-Young’s flawless result isn’t a work of her own credibility, but her ability to cheat her ways through. Besides, all the families who have hired her have faced consequences similar to the Park family. But by the time Ye-Seo or her mother became aware of this, they are in too deep in to take a step back. What further unfolds is the lie that Joo-Young managed to hide for all these years, which is also the reason behind her desire to destroy each and every family that hires her. At this point, I thought I couldn't possibly dislike this character more, but what happens in the remaining episodes clearly left me speechless.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other two families living in the SKY Castle neighbourhood include the Cha and Woo families, who have more of a side role to play. In the&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Cha family, Min-Hyuk (the head of the family) being the prosecutor turned professor, wants his kids to reach the “&lt;em&gt;top of the pyramid&lt;/em&gt;” which he himself failed to do. He forces his dreams on his kids through means that only bear negative results. With the twin boys being average at school, which is obviously something that Min-Hyuk cannot deal with, to the eldest daughter lying about being in Harvard, all of it is a result of him constantly pressuring them. On the other hand, Noh Seung-Hye is an understanding mother who clearly sees through Min-Hyuk’s methods and is willing to end her marriage if that is what it takes to save her children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last is the Woo family, and here we see a mother struggling to find a balance between keeping her child happy but also wanting him to study hard and get into SKY. With Dr Woo working under Dr Kang, we constantly see them trying to be on the good side of the Kang family. Not to mention, this family really adds the much-needed elements of comedy that takes this show on another tangent altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fifth episode, we come across a new character Kim Hye-na, a bold kid studying in the same class as Ye-Seo. Despite her being a poor child, with a sick mother admitted in the hospital, she still manages to surpass Ye-Seo in academics. Ye-Seo, being a child who cannot stand failure, and her mother, who cannot see her child upset, clearly don't take this well. Ye-Seo’s mother even goes out of her way to tell Hye-na to not mess with Ye-Seo and her goal. To be honest, initially, I didn’t think that her role could be any more than a classmate, but the story that revolves around Hye-na's life leaves Ye-Seo’s goal of SNU Medical School, shaken to its very core.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This show started with a rating of as low as 1%, and halfway through the show, it managed to reach skyrocketing numbers. It has nothing common with the popular K-dramas that revolve around romance, which is also why it is my favourite show. &lt;em&gt;SKY Castle &lt;/em&gt;is rather a series that very smartly raises some of the darkest issues that exist in societies all across the globe, especially around Korea’s Scholastic Ability Test, &lt;em&gt;Suneung&lt;/em&gt;. With a cast so carefully chosen, and with every actor being true to their role, this show really proves why it received such high ratings. From highlighting the harsh reality of the Korean educational system and how it can take a toll on the mental health of children (since all of them are told is to get into SKY), it also portrays how the elite families are willing to go beyond their means to get their children into a good college, by spending huge sums of money or even adopting ways not available to a normal family. It constantly emphasises how parents tend to force their unachieved dreams and ambitions on their children without asking them what they really want, which can have unforeseen consequences. The other thing that needs to be mentioned is the original soundtrack, &quot;&lt;em&gt;We all lie&lt;/em&gt;&quot;. This soundtrack is so brilliantly curated that it works perfectly with the storyline. And it is definitely one of those songs I found myself going back to. Also, the added bonus being that it's entirely an English song, strategically used to pull international audiences to the show.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I agree with the majority audience that the last episode could have been better, but by no means does it destroy the very essence of the show and what it's trying to put forward. Throughout the show, we are made to realise that if Ye-Seo's mother wasn't so selfish towards her child's goal, this all could have been easily avoided. But then, we wouldn't have gotten this masterpiece to binge-watch. Therefore, I recommend this show to the audiences as it has a message relevant to all age groups. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Priyanshi Mehra</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“We all lie Tell you the truths Sometimes we laugh and easily lie” &amp;nbsp;SKY Castle is a satirical, dark comedy-drama that revolves around the lives of four elite families living in the SKY Castle neighbourhood, situated in the suburbs of Seoul. In reality, SKY is an acronym for the three renowned colleges of South Korea, namely, Seoul National University (SNU), Korea University and Yonsei University. SKY neighbourhood is home to top doctors and a prosecutor turned professor, who all want their children to live a worthy life, which according to them, can only be achieved if they get into one of these above-mentioned colleges. Thus, the story revolves around the Korean National College Exam, Suneung. The show, like most K-drama shows, starts with a straightforward story but manages to leave the audience baffled with its twists and turns. It's a really well-crafted show that makes its audience grip to their screens since the first episode itself. What is commendable about SKY Castle is that despite its twists, never once does it distract itself from the main plot. The first episode opens with a party being thrown to celebrate the Park family; whose son got into the Seoul National Medical School. But more than being happy, the other families are interested in knowing the methods that led to his admission. As it turns out, an expensive entrance exam coordinator made this possible. Therefore, this information starts a fight to hire her at an exclusive VVIP party. This coordinator who goes by the name of Kim Joo-Young chooses to teach Ye-Seo, whose only dream has been to get admission in Seoul National Medical College. A dark cloud falls over the Park family when Lee Myung-Joo, the mother, decides to take her own life. We notice that Kim Joo-Young, the exceptional coordinator, definitely had something to do with it. However, Ye-Seo’s mother, even after finding it all out, is willing to look past all this because all she wants is to see her daughter get into SNU. With such a tragedy, Park family decides to move out and this opens the door for a new family to move in. This new family, Hwang family, have a simple and relaxed outlook towards life which clearly doesn't sit well with the other families. From questioning Lee So Im’s teaching methods to constantly treating her as an outsider, they really do give the Hwang family a hard time. Even at the hospital, Dr Hwang, who wants to treat the patients and interns with utmost respect, is criticised by Dr Kang, Ye-Seo’s father, who is more inclined towards making money and asserting his authority. With each passing episode, we realise that Joo-Young’s flawless result isn’t a work of her own credibility, but her ability to cheat her ways through. Besides, all the families who have hired her have faced consequences similar to the Park family. But by the time Ye-Seo or her mother became aware of this, they are in too deep in to take a step back. What further unfolds is the lie that Joo-Young managed to hide for all these years, which is also the reason behind her desire to destroy each and every family that hires her. At this point, I thought I couldn't possibly dislike this character more, but what happens in the remaining episodes clearly left me speechless.&amp;nbsp; The other two families living in the SKY Castle neighbourhood include the Cha and Woo families, who have more of a side role to play. In the Cha family, Min-Hyuk (the head of the family) being the prosecutor turned professor, wants his kids to reach the “top of the pyramid” which he himself failed to do. He forces his dreams on his kids through means that only bear negative results. With the twin boys being average at school, which is obviously something that Min-Hyuk cannot deal with, to the eldest daughter lying about being in Harvard, all of it is a result of him constantly pressuring them. On the other hand, Noh Seung-Hye is an understanding mother who clearly sees through Min-Hyuk’s methods and is willing to end her marriage if that is what it takes to save her children. The last is the Woo family, and here we see a mother struggling to find a balance between keeping her child happy but also wanting him to study hard and get into SKY. With Dr Woo working under Dr Kang, we constantly see them trying to be on the good side of the Kang family. Not to mention, this family really adds the much-needed elements of comedy that takes this show on another tangent altogether. In the fifth episode, we come across a new character Kim Hye-na, a bold kid studying in the same class as Ye-Seo. Despite her being a poor child, with a sick mother admitted in the hospital, she still manages to surpass Ye-Seo in academics. Ye-Seo, being a child who cannot stand failure, and her mother, who cannot see her child upset, clearly don't take this well. Ye-Seo’s mother even goes out of her way to tell Hye-na to not mess with Ye-Seo and her goal. To be honest, initially, I didn’t think that her role could be any more than a classmate, but the story that revolves around Hye-na's life leaves Ye-Seo’s goal of SNU Medical School, shaken to its very core. This show started with a rating of as low as 1%, and halfway through the show, it managed to reach skyrocketing numbers. It has nothing common with the popular K-dramas that revolve around romance, which is also why it is my favourite show. SKY Castle is rather a series that very smartly raises some of the darkest issues that exist in societies all across the globe, especially around Korea’s Scholastic Ability Test, Suneung. With a cast so carefully chosen, and with every actor being true to their role, this show really proves why it received such high ratings. From highlighting the harsh reality of the Korean educational system and how it can take a toll on the mental health of children (since all of them are told is to get into SKY), it also portrays how the elite families are willing to go beyond their means to get their children into a good college, by spending huge sums of money or even adopting ways not available to a normal family. It constantly emphasises how parents tend to force their unachieved dreams and ambitions on their children without asking them what they really want, which can have unforeseen consequences. The other thing that needs to be mentioned is the original soundtrack, &quot;We all lie&quot;. This soundtrack is so brilliantly curated that it works perfectly with the storyline. And it is definitely one of those songs I found myself going back to. Also, the added bonus being that it's entirely an English song, strategically used to pull international audiences to the show.&amp;nbsp; While I agree with the majority audience that the last episode could have been better, but by no means does it destroy the very essence of the show and what it's trying to put forward. Throughout the show, we are made to realise that if Ye-Seo's mother wasn't so selfish towards her child's goal, this all could have been easily avoided. But then, we wouldn't have gotten this masterpiece to binge-watch. Therefore, I recommend this show to the audiences as it has a message relevant to all age groups.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
