<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/shreyansh.verma/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2022-10-30T11:08:13+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/shreyansh.verma/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Economic Sanctions: A Silent Weapon of War</title>
      <link href="/Economic-Sanctions-A-Silent-Weapon-of-War" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Economic Sanctions: A Silent Weapon of War" />
      <published>2022-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Economic-Sanctions-A-Silent-Weapon-of-War</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Economic-Sanctions-A-Silent-Weapon-of-War">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘The United States has imposed severe sanctions over the state of North Korea for their new ballistic missile test.’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This is how a typical headline in global politics looks like when a jaw-dropping geopolitically motivated event occurs. At first glance, one might wonder why a country such as the US is so vested in the fund allocation of the North Korean treasury. It all essentially boils down to the degree of influence that a superpower (assumption being that the US is the lone superpower) has over nation states when it comes to their economy and people.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The US does so in the larger interest of the world, and considers itself to be the saviour of our generation when it comes to averting a nuclear catastrophe. Since it cannot (and must not) threaten war on many already poverty stricken and poor states, it imposes a series of Keynesian tool-based economic sanctions that prohibit the economic growth of the nation state, as they directly affect the demand and supply chains of the economy and tend to cut them off from more states that are members of ‘the bloc’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The unsettling reality is that disasters similar to Hiroshima and Nagasaki continue to occur in Middle Eastern countries, where war has been raging for decades, and yet we've been so oblivious to their occurrences when we accidentally switch to &lt;em&gt;BBC International&lt;/em&gt; after cheering for our football team on the previous channel. But beneath the thick glorious boasts of killing ISIS leaders, annihilating Sanaa (again), and killing millions, there is the far more destructive layer of economic sanctions imposed on seemingly rogue states that disagree with the ideology of the world's leading nation state. The inconvenient reality is that those sanctions, in a roundabout way, have an effect on the health of citizens and frequently bring about devastating consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Economic sanctions are of three types: (1) suspension of loans or aid withdrawal by the sender; (2) denial of access to international financial markets; and (3) bans on capital investment in the targeted state. They often involve a sector-specific ban such as an oil ban, textile ban, a ban on using a particular currency or engaging with particular financial operators (such as banks). Intended to impose constraints on the economic activities of the targeted state, economic sanctions aim to prevent a state from importing certain goods or services. They may also prevent a state from exporting its natural resources, agricultural, or manufactured products.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another type of economic sanction specifically targets the banking and financial sectors. Overseas assets, for example, can be frozen or transactions put on hold. Foreign aid may be withheld as well. Economic sanctions are most likely to be detrimental to a country. Refusing to import goods or services from a country can act as a kind of protectionist policy for the target country. This can create a constituency for such policies, making them difficult to repeal. A ban on exporting certain goods and services to a country, such as agricultural products, on the other hand, can harm influential sectors of the target country and make it difficult to impose or sustain such measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to Farrokh Habibzadeh's paper &lt;em&gt;Economic sanction: a weapon of mass destruction&lt;/em&gt;, the UN Security Council Resolution 661-3 imposed a multilateral sanction on Iraq in 1990, prohibiting the import of all substances other than those intended for scientific purposes, food, and various humanitarian items. The sanction killed approximately 1.5 million people (including more than half a million children) in Iraq - more than the number of people killed in Hiroshima in the aftermath of the nuclear bomb detonation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Many critical life-saving tablets become unavailable due to the imposition of sanctions. Even the production of a few drugs is reduced, if not halted, due to a scarcity of basic substances or spare device components required for drug production. The cost of medicines rises to a point that people with low incomes can only afford a small portion of it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This results in growth of black markets as locations where medicines (occasionally forged) are illegally traded. Additionally, the lack of spare components tends to affect not only medical devices, but also different critical infrastructures such as electric powered generators. Consequently, frequent power outages result in severe problems such as lack of vaccines, tablets, ventilators, monitors, etc. Thus, hundreds of thousands of people die in silence as a result of diseases.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;This quiet mass homicide in a tumultuous sector is not always noticed, and may even be overlooked. The same can be said about the current COVID crisis, in which the US refused to lift sanctions against Iran despite the fact that it was dealing with COVID-19 and low vaccination rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Seen in this light, sanctions act as a terrifying mechanism for bringing a country to its knees. There are many ways to deal with 'rogue' states, but depriving people of their humanity is not one of them.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shreyansh Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">‘The United States has imposed severe sanctions over the state of North Korea for their new ballistic missile test.’ This is how a typical headline in global politics looks like when a jaw-dropping geopolitically motivated event occurs. At first glance, one might wonder why a country such as the US is so vested in the fund allocation of the North Korean treasury. It all essentially boils down to the degree of influence that a superpower (assumption being that the US is the lone superpower) has over nation states when it comes to their economy and people.&amp;nbsp; The US does so in the larger interest of the world, and considers itself to be the saviour of our generation when it comes to averting a nuclear catastrophe. Since it cannot (and must not) threaten war on many already poverty stricken and poor states, it imposes a series of Keynesian tool-based economic sanctions that prohibit the economic growth of the nation state, as they directly affect the demand and supply chains of the economy and tend to cut them off from more states that are members of ‘the bloc’. The unsettling reality is that disasters similar to Hiroshima and Nagasaki continue to occur in Middle Eastern countries, where war has been raging for decades, and yet we've been so oblivious to their occurrences when we accidentally switch to BBC International after cheering for our football team on the previous channel. But beneath the thick glorious boasts of killing ISIS leaders, annihilating Sanaa (again), and killing millions, there is the far more destructive layer of economic sanctions imposed on seemingly rogue states that disagree with the ideology of the world's leading nation state. The inconvenient reality is that those sanctions, in a roundabout way, have an effect on the health of citizens and frequently bring about devastating consequences. Economic sanctions are of three types: (1) suspension of loans or aid withdrawal by the sender; (2) denial of access to international financial markets; and (3) bans on capital investment in the targeted state. They often involve a sector-specific ban such as an oil ban, textile ban, a ban on using a particular currency or engaging with particular financial operators (such as banks). Intended to impose constraints on the economic activities of the targeted state, economic sanctions aim to prevent a state from importing certain goods or services. They may also prevent a state from exporting its natural resources, agricultural, or manufactured products.&amp;nbsp; Another type of economic sanction specifically targets the banking and financial sectors. Overseas assets, for example, can be frozen or transactions put on hold. Foreign aid may be withheld as well. Economic sanctions are most likely to be detrimental to a country. Refusing to import goods or services from a country can act as a kind of protectionist policy for the target country. This can create a constituency for such policies, making them difficult to repeal. A ban on exporting certain goods and services to a country, such as agricultural products, on the other hand, can harm influential sectors of the target country and make it difficult to impose or sustain such measures. According to Farrokh Habibzadeh's paper Economic sanction: a weapon of mass destruction, the UN Security Council Resolution 661-3 imposed a multilateral sanction on Iraq in 1990, prohibiting the import of all substances other than those intended for scientific purposes, food, and various humanitarian items. The sanction killed approximately 1.5 million people (including more than half a million children) in Iraq - more than the number of people killed in Hiroshima in the aftermath of the nuclear bomb detonation.&amp;nbsp; Many critical life-saving tablets become unavailable due to the imposition of sanctions. Even the production of a few drugs is reduced, if not halted, due to a scarcity of basic substances or spare device components required for drug production. The cost of medicines rises to a point that people with low incomes can only afford a small portion of it.&amp;nbsp; This results in growth of black markets as locations where medicines (occasionally forged) are illegally traded. Additionally, the lack of spare components tends to affect not only medical devices, but also different critical infrastructures such as electric powered generators. Consequently, frequent power outages result in severe problems such as lack of vaccines, tablets, ventilators, monitors, etc. Thus, hundreds of thousands of people die in silence as a result of diseases.&amp;nbsp; This quiet mass homicide in a tumultuous sector is not always noticed, and may even be overlooked. The same can be said about the current COVID crisis, in which the US refused to lift sanctions against Iran despite the fact that it was dealing with COVID-19 and low vaccination rates. Seen in this light, sanctions act as a terrifying mechanism for bringing a country to its knees. There are many ways to deal with 'rogue' states, but depriving people of their humanity is not one of them.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Rise of the Far Right in Europe</title>
      <link href="/The-Rise-of-the-Far-Right-in-Europe" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rise of the Far Right in Europe" />
      <published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Rise-of-the-Far-Right-in-Europe</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Rise-of-the-Far-Right-in-Europe">&lt;p&gt;For decades in our world, the far-right and Nazism have been almost synonymous. Horrific visuals of trains carrying naked Jews (or for the pop-culture loving generation of ours: the red jacket from &lt;em&gt;Schindler’s List&lt;/em&gt;) are nothing but absolute reminders of the terrible turns things can take if propaganda and falsehoods are left unchecked. Such ideologies are malignant tumours and deserve nothing but condemnation. While this has been the norm of moral and ethical conduct (even legal in the case of Eastern Europe), the world also has seen words like Neo-Nazism come into existence. The worst part is that it is not just Germany but the entire world, and particularly Europe, that is witnessing a rise in far-right activities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with the basics, what exactly is the political representation of the ‘far-right’? Far-right ideologies are political philosophies that call for unification, ultra-nationalism and nativist cultures and seek the exodus of migrants, they are against inter-racial unions and believe in the supremacy of their people against others. When the Allied powers annihilated the Axis powers and their unjust crimes came to light, everyone believed that the re-occurrence of such a strong belief in the far-right would be unlikely. However, smaller far-right units have existed ever since the end of the Second World War. Recently, such parties have seen a huge rise in their popularity and have gained a foothold in legislatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Central to this issue is the spilling out of migrants from the Middle East. “Europe is becoming another Islamic Caliphate”, claimed the then Interior Minister of Italy, Matteo Salvini, in a rally with thousands of people back in 2019. Soon, we saw the Prime Minister of Hungary Viktor Orban claiming in public that “Islamic invaders have reached Europe”.&amp;nbsp; More prominent problems can be seen in the patterns of how such groups have reached decision-making bodies. One such example is the Golden Dawn, a political outfit based out of Greece. In the 2019 elections, it was the seventh largest political party and once had around 7.0% acceptance around Greece, setting a very dangerous precedent. Fortunately enough, the outfit was banned, and its leadership was imprisoned in 2020.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a trend in Europe as political parties such as PEGIDA and AfD (Germany), the British National Party, Jobbik (Hungary), National Rally (France) have seen massive crowds being drawn to their events, their candidates have become lead runners to key positions in governments and policy formulation platforms, and access to social media has further intensified their anti-migration, anti-Islamic and, in general, fascist overtones and increased their reach multiple times. Apart from outfits openly cheering fascist literature, one can also observe a shift in preference for far-right politics in the general mindset of people, possibly due to higher unemployment (due to COVID-19) and rapidly rising anti-establishment thoughts. The COVID-19 pandemic has also provoked the general population to align themselves with far-right ideologies due to anti-lockdown sentiment, protests, and mandatory COVID-19 vaccinations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numerous studies and surveys have positively concluded that most people who associate with this violent form of right-wing politics are unemployed, anti-vaxxers and generally have shown idealisation of the Nazi Party. It is very concerning to note that many people have openly praised Adolf Hitler during anti-lockdown protests.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Governments have not been mute spectators in this either. The German government recently cracked down on Alternative for Germany (AfD), a political outfit known for its Euro-scepticism, anti-Islamic positions and anti-migrant stances. Interestingly, AfD has 82 seats in the Federal Parliament of Germany, so one can imagine the political opposition and accusations that the German government faced as it placed a prominent political opposition under strict surveillance for being an extremist outfit. Shortly after major media outlets reported the surveillance, courts blocked the move. Likewise, governments across Europe are taking significant actions to destroy these movements and preserve their cultural balance.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can see how the rhetoric of ultra-nationalism is on the rise and how elections are becoming an affair of migrant scepticism and a centre-stage show where migrants are the bait. Policies of selectively leaving Muslims out, changing the way they live by forcing them to integrate into western society and trying to change their religious texts institutionally are more spillovers of the entire crises that probably started with an inflammatory speech. Policymaking and such discourses in public light are intimately connected.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Union needs to accept the multiple changes that have led to the rise in far-right movements of Europe and decisively work with constituent governments to take corrective action. The threat of the far-right resurgence is evolving as many outfits are gaining a stronghold in rural and ill-kept areas of Europe. This transitional shift is very similar to how Hitler brainwashed millions: by giving them hope for a better and more equal future. The COVID-19 pandemic is easily comparable to World War I in this situation, where it feeds the people of the republic anti-establishment thoughts which they seek through far-right extremist outfits who champion themselves as their saviours and have a common enemy to pin the blame on (Jews back then, Muslims and migrants now). The political landscape is very volatile right now and a back-slide of Europe into its darkest age will only lead to spillovers to other countries in both political and economic ways.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shreyansh Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For decades in our world, the far-right and Nazism have been almost synonymous. Horrific visuals of trains carrying naked Jews (or for the pop-culture loving generation of ours: the red jacket from Schindler’s List) are nothing but absolute reminders of the terrible turns things can take if propaganda and falsehoods are left unchecked. Such ideologies are malignant tumours and deserve nothing but condemnation. While this has been the norm of moral and ethical conduct (even legal in the case of Eastern Europe), the world also has seen words like Neo-Nazism come into existence. The worst part is that it is not just Germany but the entire world, and particularly Europe, that is witnessing a rise in far-right activities.&amp;nbsp; Starting with the basics, what exactly is the political representation of the ‘far-right’? Far-right ideologies are political philosophies that call for unification, ultra-nationalism and nativist cultures and seek the exodus of migrants, they are against inter-racial unions and believe in the supremacy of their people against others. When the Allied powers annihilated the Axis powers and their unjust crimes came to light, everyone believed that the re-occurrence of such a strong belief in the far-right would be unlikely. However, smaller far-right units have existed ever since the end of the Second World War. Recently, such parties have seen a huge rise in their popularity and have gained a foothold in legislatures. Central to this issue is the spilling out of migrants from the Middle East. “Europe is becoming another Islamic Caliphate”, claimed the then Interior Minister of Italy, Matteo Salvini, in a rally with thousands of people back in 2019. Soon, we saw the Prime Minister of Hungary Viktor Orban claiming in public that “Islamic invaders have reached Europe”.&amp;nbsp; More prominent problems can be seen in the patterns of how such groups have reached decision-making bodies. One such example is the Golden Dawn, a political outfit based out of Greece. In the 2019 elections, it was the seventh largest political party and once had around 7.0% acceptance around Greece, setting a very dangerous precedent. Fortunately enough, the outfit was banned, and its leadership was imprisoned in 2020.&amp;nbsp; This has been a trend in Europe as political parties such as PEGIDA and AfD (Germany), the British National Party, Jobbik (Hungary), National Rally (France) have seen massive crowds being drawn to their events, their candidates have become lead runners to key positions in governments and policy formulation platforms, and access to social media has further intensified their anti-migration, anti-Islamic and, in general, fascist overtones and increased their reach multiple times. Apart from outfits openly cheering fascist literature, one can also observe a shift in preference for far-right politics in the general mindset of people, possibly due to higher unemployment (due to COVID-19) and rapidly rising anti-establishment thoughts. The COVID-19 pandemic has also provoked the general population to align themselves with far-right ideologies due to anti-lockdown sentiment, protests, and mandatory COVID-19 vaccinations.&amp;nbsp; Numerous studies and surveys have positively concluded that most people who associate with this violent form of right-wing politics are unemployed, anti-vaxxers and generally have shown idealisation of the Nazi Party. It is very concerning to note that many people have openly praised Adolf Hitler during anti-lockdown protests.&amp;nbsp; Governments have not been mute spectators in this either. The German government recently cracked down on Alternative for Germany (AfD), a political outfit known for its Euro-scepticism, anti-Islamic positions and anti-migrant stances. Interestingly, AfD has 82 seats in the Federal Parliament of Germany, so one can imagine the political opposition and accusations that the German government faced as it placed a prominent political opposition under strict surveillance for being an extremist outfit. Shortly after major media outlets reported the surveillance, courts blocked the move. Likewise, governments across Europe are taking significant actions to destroy these movements and preserve their cultural balance.&amp;nbsp; One can see how the rhetoric of ultra-nationalism is on the rise and how elections are becoming an affair of migrant scepticism and a centre-stage show where migrants are the bait. Policies of selectively leaving Muslims out, changing the way they live by forcing them to integrate into western society and trying to change their religious texts institutionally are more spillovers of the entire crises that probably started with an inflammatory speech. Policymaking and such discourses in public light are intimately connected.&amp;nbsp; The European Union needs to accept the multiple changes that have led to the rise in far-right movements of Europe and decisively work with constituent governments to take corrective action. The threat of the far-right resurgence is evolving as many outfits are gaining a stronghold in rural and ill-kept areas of Europe. This transitional shift is very similar to how Hitler brainwashed millions: by giving them hope for a better and more equal future. The COVID-19 pandemic is easily comparable to World War I in this situation, where it feeds the people of the republic anti-establishment thoughts which they seek through far-right extremist outfits who champion themselves as their saviours and have a common enemy to pin the blame on (Jews back then, Muslims and migrants now). The political landscape is very volatile right now and a back-slide of Europe into its darkest age will only lead to spillovers to other countries in both political and economic ways.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
