<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/reuben.pritchard/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-11-04T21:28:53+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/reuben.pritchard/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Dreaming of a Good Dictator and Watching Tiger King</title>
      <link href="/Dreaming-of-a-Good-Dictator-and-Watching-Tiger-King" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dreaming of a Good Dictator and Watching Tiger King" />
      <published>2020-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Dreaming-of-a-Good-Dictator-and-Watching-Tiger-King</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Dreaming-of-a-Good-Dictator-and-Watching-Tiger-King">&lt;p&gt;One of the saddest patterns of Western discourse is believing an up and coming dictator when he claims to be a reformist liberal. In 2001, George Bush looked into Vladimir Putin’s soul and saw a good man, he didn’t feel the need to look into the eyes of the 20,000 civilians killed in the Second Chechen War. Brutally suppressing the Chechen’s dream of independence, which had been Putin’s first act as a President, established his tough law and order persona. But that was an inconvenient truth for Western leaders who wanted to believe Putin represented a new liberal Russia. Until recently, I mocked George W Bush for this and wondered how our governing elites could be so willfully blind. Then I watched &lt;em&gt;Tiger King&lt;/em&gt; on Netflix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It follows a medley of cult leaders and psychopaths in America’s bizarre and horrifying big cat grooming industry. How crazy are these people? One of the less morally reprehensible of the bunch was probably the inspiration for &lt;em&gt;Scarface&lt;/em&gt;. And yet, I couldn’t help but find myself rooting for the central figure of the piece, Joe Exotic, who has the same irresistible charisma made up of overconfidence mixed with insecurity hiding just below the surface which Robert Downey Jr brought to Iron Man. Watching the Tiger King, I wanted to believe he was a good person. Coming to terms with him being a cult leader who abused animals and people alike, gave me a newfound grudging respect for George.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1980’s, the press heralded Mugabe as ‘Africa’s Clem Attlee’ and ‘the thinking man’s guerrilla’. Unsurprisingly, this continued up to the point when Mugabe began seizing land off white settlers in the late 90’s. During the 80’s, when his regime brutally suppressed the defenceless Ndebele people, he continued to be heralded as a liberal reformer by the West. Recently Mohammad Bin Salman (or MBS to his fans) was heralded as a young liberal reformer in Saudi Arabia. Boris Johnson called him the “most exciting thing happening in the Middle East”, it was hoped he would liberalise the press and relax the kingdom’s sexist laws. The murder of Jamal Khashoggi in 2018 ended Bin Salman’s applauding headlines. However, this wasn’t a unique act by the young autocrat. Much like Putin, who he famously high-fived at a G20 summit, he had built his domestic image through a violent war. He ordered the kingdom’s intervention in the Yemeni civil war, which has so far killed over 10,000 civilians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there’s Xi Jinping, who was feted in the Western press at the time of his inauguration in 2012 as a liberal reformer based on only the most resounding evidence. You see, his father had been a liberal reformer, exiled by Chairman Mao in the 1970’s, and throughout human history, sons have never rebelled against their fathers. He had spoken about the importance of free trade and a rules-based international order, lambasted senior party members for their corruption, and promised change. As if any world leader stands up and praises global chaos, adding that they’re a great fan of corruption and greed. Actions, not words will always define a leader. What have Xi’s actions been in the last eight years? Over a million Uyghur Muslims in concentration camps, organ harvesting of political dissidents, and the strangulation of Hong Kong’s democracy movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t all my fault that I feel for Joe Exotic. &lt;em&gt;Tiger King&lt;/em&gt; brilliantly humanises him by showing us his tragic early life. A gay man rejected by his father, who set out with a dream to create a sanctuary both for the animals he loved and people who had been left behind. He employed anyone at his zoo, giving them accommodation, food and a job to care for the most beautiful animals. It was only when one of his senior lieutenants revealed that Joe would purposely hire people who had nothing, that I realised I was watching a cult leader. He thought they would work harder since without him they’d be destitute and back on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel for the idea, Joe was helping save these endangered animals through breeding them. Happily ignoring the reality that he fed them expired meat from Walmart. Or how everyone ominously talks about how the cats are most appealing to visitors when they’re less than two years old and young enough to pet. The older cats aren’t as profitable, not worth keeping for long. I wanted to believe this charismatic weirdo was a good person. That while his world wasn’t mine, he was helping his people and moving them in a positive direction. Of course, it was nonsense. One of Joe’s two husbands admitted he often felt afraid Joe would violently attack his rival Carole Baskin, an animal rights campaigner. She had successfully sued Joe, leaving him in a financially ruinous position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, Joe is in jail for the attempted murder of Carole. Xi, Vladimir and Bin Salman are all still world leaders with thousands of their critics in jail. Might might not make right, but it is powerful. Those of us who live in the free world must take to heart not to fall for the lies and spins of the world’s tyrants and remember to look for the ugly truth of charismatic leaders’ actions, no matter how attractive the alternative may be.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reuben Pritchard</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the saddest patterns of Western discourse is believing an up and coming dictator when he claims to be a reformist liberal. In 2001, George Bush looked into Vladimir Putin’s soul and saw a good man, he didn’t feel the need to look into the eyes of the 20,000 civilians killed in the Second Chechen War. Brutally suppressing the Chechen’s dream of independence, which had been Putin’s first act as a President, established his tough law and order persona. But that was an inconvenient truth for Western leaders who wanted to believe Putin represented a new liberal Russia. Until recently, I mocked George W Bush for this and wondered how our governing elites could be so willfully blind. Then I watched Tiger King on Netflix.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Drunk Parable of The Tech Age</title>
      <link href="/Pubcast-of-the-Tech-Age" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Drunk Parable of The Tech Age" />
      <published>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Pubcast-of-the-Tech-Age</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Pubcast-of-the-Tech-Age">&lt;p&gt;The first of The Pangean’s &lt;em&gt;pubcasts&lt;/em&gt; is with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/mirandamowbray/&quot;&gt;Dr Miranda Mowbray&lt;/a&gt;, a Lecturer in Computer Science at the University of Bristol. After having graduated from the University of Cambridge and completing her PhD in Mathematics at Queen Mary University of London, Dr Mowbray gained several years of experience in industry and is now pursuing research into data science for cybersecurity, and ethics for big data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this podcast, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/harsh.tiwari/&quot;&gt;Harsh Tiwari&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/reuben.pritchard/&quot;&gt;Reuben Pritchard&lt;/a&gt; sit down with Dr Miranda Mowbray and, over lunch and a couple of pints, discuss some pressing matters surrounding the age of technology. Listen below to part 1 of the full uncut recording or skip ahead to the following topics of interest:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(0)&quot;&gt;00:00&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology as a replacement for human interaction&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(60)&quot;&gt;01:00&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology in business and politics&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(1203)&quot;&gt;20:03&lt;/a&gt;), or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The accessibility of technology&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(2142)&quot;&gt;35:42&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;audio id=&quot;pubcast-1&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; controlsList=&quot;nodownload&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/Podcast1-final.mp3&quot;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    var aud = document.getElementById(&quot;pubcast-1&quot;);
    function setTime(x) {
      aud.currentTime = x;
    }

&lt;/script&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>harsh.tiwari reuben.pritchard</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="podcast" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The first of The Pangean’s pubcasts is with Dr Miranda Mowbray, a Lecturer in Computer Science at the University of Bristol. After having graduated from the University of Cambridge and completing her PhD in Mathematics at Queen Mary University of London, Dr Mowbray gained several years of experience in industry and is now pursuing research into data science for cybersecurity, and ethics for big data. In this podcast, Harsh Tiwari and Reuben Pritchard sit down with Dr Miranda Mowbray and, over lunch and a couple of pints, discuss some pressing matters surrounding the age of technology. Listen below to part 1 of the full uncut recording or skip ahead to the following topics of interest: Introduction (00:00), Technology as a replacement for human interaction (01:00), Technology in business and politics (20:03), or The accessibility of technology (35:42). Your browser does not support the audio element.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why Haven’t We Left Yet?</title>
      <link href="/Why-Havent-We-Left-Yet" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Haven’t We Left Yet?" />
      <published>2019-04-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-Havent-We-Left-Yet</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-Havent-We-Left-Yet">&lt;p&gt;How did it end up like this? It was only a dream. An independent Britain; free to strike its own trade deals with the world; free of the tyranny of the European Union’s tyrannical Commission. This was the dream behind Brexit. Only it hasn’t worked out that way. Today, Great Britain is trapped in a quagmire, from which its ancient and prestigious Parliament can’t find an escape. The pitiful Prime Minister Theresa May finds herself leading a government but without much power, after the failure of her Withdrawal Agreement, and the three votes vainly trying to pass it. If Theresa can take any solace, it will be in the fact that following Commons’ MP Oliver Letwin’s backbench coup, a solution to the Brexit mess still can’t be found. All the while, the British people wonder how did a great nation find itself in such a mess that it has had to beg the European Union for the second time for an extension of the Article 50 exit process. The European Union have been magnanimous in response to Britain’s self-humiliation, granting it another six months to figure out what type of Brexit it actually wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, it is worth remembering that the crisis Britain now faces shouldn’t have even been possible under the old Constitution. Britain’s tradition of Parliamentary Sovereignty is an anathema to referendums. Margaret Thatcher once called them “the tools of dictators and tyrants”. It all began in 1975, when the then Prime Minister Harold Wilson gave the British people a referendum on being a part of the European Economic Community (as the EU then was). Wilson won his referendum in favour of membership of the European Community by over 30%, a majority large enough to end the issue for a generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, by introducing the practice of referendums to British politics, he had forever changed the unwritten Constitution of the sceptered Isle, in ways nobody could possibly foresee. The second strike, the anti-European strike, against Britain’s ancient Constitution would be self-inflicted. Back in 1999, the European Commission decreed that henceforth, all elections to the European Parliament would use ‘proportional representation’, a practise Britain’s dominant political parties had resisted. This had radical repercussions which neither the British establishment nor the European elite could expect. By introducing proportional representation to British politics, the European Commission broke the stranglehold that the two great parties had held on British politics since 1945. In 2009, Nigel Farage led the United Kingdom Independence Party (UKIP) to second place in the European Parliament elections. Then in 2014, UKIP came first in the European Parliament elections. For the first time, a party other than the Conservative or Labour Party had won a national poll since 1945.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The delicate balance of Britain’s Constitution had been disturbed, leading David Cameron to promise that if he won the 2015 general elections, then he would hold a referendum on the membership of the European Union. Cameron lost, Britain voted to leave European Union and become independent of … something, which isn’t so clear. Today, the Parliament is broken into four factions neither of which is interested in compromise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most extreme faction is the &lt;em&gt;Hard Brexiteers&lt;/em&gt; who can’t accept anything but a complete Brexit. Where Britain would be completely separated from the European Union’s regulatory framework, and then trade with the EU, under the terms of the World Trade Organisation. They consider this as restoring Britain’s rightful place as a free buccaneering nation, arguing any short term pain would be more than worthwhile. This would involve a rough and hard separation from the EU’s single market—an idea Most British companies find terrifying. This option is prefered by a core group of less than fifty Brexit-extremist Members of Parliament led by Boris Johnson and Jacob Rees-Mogg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theresa May’s preferred option is unsurprisingly her &lt;em&gt;Withdrawal Agreement&lt;/em&gt; which manages the difficult task of both upsetting the &lt;em&gt;remainers and leavers&lt;/em&gt;, coming short on both their desires. Nevertheless, it is still supported by a majority of the Conservative Party, which struggles with those rebelling against their Prime Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third faction, within the House of Commons, support the &lt;em&gt;Soft Brexit&lt;/em&gt;, which would involve Britain remaining in the European Union’s Customs Union and regulatory framework. This group includes most of the Labour party and many Conservative party rebels. However, it’s ambition of a soft Brexit is undermined by the House of Commons fourth group: the &lt;em&gt;anti-Brexiteers&lt;/em&gt;. This final group lead by Nicola Sturgeon (of the Scottish National Party) desires the complete revocation of the referendum, and the end of Brexit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, there lies the problem of the four groups who can’t compromise with one another. And if they don’t, then a Parliamentary majority for any response to Brexit won’t be found. In the last two weeks, Theresa May has seemed to motion towards a compromise with the Labour Party’s position of a Customs Union between Britain and the EU. But any compromise with Jeremy Corbyn’s Labour Party faces stiff opposition from the Conservative backbenchers and grassroots. May and Corbyn are both incentivised to not walk away from the compromise talks to show the electorate that they are trying to find a solution. But they also can’t actually agree to one without alienating both their party’s grassroots. Hard Brexiteers thought that these stablemates would result in Britain crashing out of the EU without a deal on March 29, the original Brexit deadline. However, the European political elite has showed themselves to be just as worried about a no-deal, as the British establishment. Hence, their decision to give Britain another six-month extension, without any requirements from the British, wasn’t surprising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the Parliament can’t finally agree to a solution to Brexit, the only solution will be to dissolve it and elect again. However, following May’s previous disastrous election performance, when the Conservatives lost their majority to the Conservative backbenchers in marginal seats, it will be unlikely for her to call another one. Therefore, until May can be replaced as the Tory leader, another election seems off the table. This would be difficult, given that May has promised to resign the Conservative Party leadership only after her Withdrawal Agreement is passed in the Commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, the British Parliament is split between four opposing factions with different responses to Brexit. No one can command a majority in the current Parliament, whether it’s a &lt;em&gt;Hard, Soft or No Brexit&lt;/em&gt;. Theresa May once promised that Britain would leave on the 29th of March, that date is now three weeks past, and no end to the Brexit is in sight. Britain now faces another a six months of uncertainty as the Parliament squabbles over what to do. The current Brexit chaos is reminiscent of an old joke: a traveler asked a man how to find the local tavern, the man replied “Well, I wouldn’t start from here”.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reuben Pritchard</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">How did it end up like this? It was only a dream. An independent Britain; free to strike its own trade deals with the world; free of the tyranny of the European Union’s tyrannical Commission. This was the dream behind Brexit. Only it hasn’t worked out that way. Today, Great Britain is trapped in a quagmire, from which its ancient and prestigious Parliament can’t find an escape. The pitiful Prime Minister Theresa May finds herself leading a government but without much power, after the failure of her Withdrawal Agreement, and the three votes vainly trying to pass it. If Theresa can take any solace, it will be in the fact that following Commons’ MP Oliver Letwin’s backbench coup, a solution to the Brexit mess still can’t be found. All the while, the British people wonder how did a great nation find itself in such a mess that it has had to beg the European Union for the second time for an extension of the Article 50 exit process. The European Union have been magnanimous in response to Britain’s self-humiliation, granting it another six months to figure out what type of Brexit it actually wants.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Mueller Report is a Damp Squib, What Do The Democrats Do Now?</title>
      <link href="/What-Do-The-Democrats-Do-Now" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Mueller Report is a Damp Squib, What Do The Democrats Do Now?" />
      <published>2019-04-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-Do-The-Democrats-Do-Now</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-Do-The-Democrats-Do-Now">&lt;p&gt;It was meant to be liberal Christmas, the day of the revelations, when the Messiah would come and smite the Antichrist. Robert Mueller is everything Trump isn’t, a modest do-gooder who was awarded the ‘Purple Heart’ and a public servant with a formidable 20-year record of true service to America. He would save us all from the tyranny of the ‘orange Hitler’, a draft dodging, bumptious braggart who has earned a life of privileged excess by the virtue of his name. The Republic would be saved from his tyranny, and the office of Washington, Jefferson, and Lincoln redeemed of this brief stain. ‘Russiagate’ may have sounded too good to be true, but after losing the first female president to a pervert, goddamit that b*tch karma owed us this one. But as Trump’s favourite rally anthem goes, “you can’t always get what you want”. So what do the Dems do now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mueller has given America a scrupulously researched report into the 2016 Trump election campaign, which found a lack of significant evidence for any criminal proceedings against the President or his family. At the moment, some Democrats are banking on the fact that the report doesn’t fully exonerate Trump, hoping and praying that a full release of the report will give them the nuggets they need to build a criminal case against the President. But they miss the point of the Special Counsel’s report. It wasn’t to prove that the Donald was some kind of crook, any American could tell you Trump’s business dealings have been sketchy for decades, it was to find a case for criminal proceedings and, later, impeachment. Without concrete evidence of such wrongdoing, the leader of the world’s greatest power cannot be toppled. If you come for the king, you best land a s*cker punch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sad irony in that if the roles were reversed, one could imagine Special Counsel Donnie using every dirty trick in the book to bring President Mueller down. But as the Democrats must soon learn if they want any hope of making Trump a one-term President, we live in the real world [sad :(]. Any further attempts by the Democrats to impeach Trump will merely ensure his reelection. They will confirm the suspicions of many middle Americans that a distant coastal elite can’t stomach their decision to exercise their constitutional right to vote for any d*mn fool they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Democrats still have hope. In 2020, they will have several key advantages that they lacked in 2016. Instead of an establishment fix up by the Clinton crime family in the upcoming elections, the Democrats will have an open primary, in which dozens of talented candidates will have their chance to win the nomination. Currently, the strongest candidates are Bernie Sanders and Joe Biden (the progressive party looks set to elect another straight white male dinosaur). Despite coming from opposite ends of their parties ideological spectrum, they share many of the same qualities: an easy-going working-class charm, the ability to empathise with rust belt voters whom Hillary alienated in 2016, and the good sense to not call millions of American ‘deplorables’. Of the two, Biden probably has the edge, the Obama connection gives him a hefty poll boost with African-American voters who dominate the Democrats’ southern primaries. He currently polls higher than both the declared African-American candidates, Cory Booker, and Kamala Harris, combined. Although recent “sexual assault” allegations against Biden could seriously undermine him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the wings of the Democratic primaries, there’s a plethora of has-beens and never-weres. Julian Castro and Kirsten Gillibrand missed their moment if there ever was one. Elizabeth Warren’s desperate attempts to prove that she is a Native American, smacks of an ugly white guilt that repulses minority and white voters alike. Corey Booker’s a progressive poser who isn’t fooling anyone but his New York donors. Beto O’Rourke, the Kennedy for gym buddies, could have clinched it had he won his Senate race last year. Kamala Harris is the strongest candidate outside of the big two, but her career as a prosecutor alienates her from the progressives, and picking a Californian candidate isn’t exactly a smart tactic when the state has been overwhelmingly Democratic for the last 20 years. My personal crushes are Tulsi Gabbard and Pete Buttigieg, both of whom are exciting fresh candidates with innovative ideas, but they lack the profile to win. I’d say look out for them in 2024, but they’re both so young that they could still run in 2040–when they are 70–after all it worked so well for Trump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny enough, the Mueller report might actually strengthen the Democrats in the 2020 election. By ending their foolish crusade to impeach Trump, they could focus on the issues that matter to American voters: the economy, healthcare, civil rights, and national security. In just seven months, we will be a decade from Obama’s 2008 triumph, in which the Democrats swept the rust belt. That 2008 coalition of disaffected white working-class voters, young progressives and minorities hoping for a better future is still out there. Millions of these voters chose Obama in 2008 and 2012, and then Trump in 2016. These were Democratic voters, and then the Democrats nominated the establishment standard-bearer with the charisma of a damp rag, Hillary Clinton. In 2020, the Democrats have the chance to win back these voters, but a campaign focusing on Russia will make that impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russiagate was meant to be the 21st century’s Watergate. Instead, it now seems more like this generation’s hunt for the WMDs in Iraq. After years of media speculation and major hype that promised a revelation which would legitimise radical action to topple a leader, nothing has been found. However, this time, rather than undermining the administration, it’s the opposition and the media who have embarrassed themselves. For the past two years, senior Democrats and media pundits have promised the American people that Trump colluded with Russia. This won’t be forgotten by American voters coming into the 2020 elections. When Trump will yell that the media is nothing but fake news, far more Americans will now be inclined to agree with him. If the Democrats want to win in 2020, they will need a strong candidate and a message focused on the real anxieties affecting American voters. Russiagate has served to distract many from Trump’s actual failures as President, his inability to pass healthcare reform, a tax cut which overwhelmingly benefits the rich and muddled foreign policy which has alienated America’s allies. Can they do it? If past performance is anything to go on, the rest of the world may have to get ready to put up with four more years of Trump. Nonetheless, it would be a critical race determining America’s future. The people must decide whether they want a unified world with America at the helm or a bunch of bickering nations who at the end will lose all that they have built over the years.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reuben Pritchard</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It was meant to be liberal Christmas, the day of the revelations, when the Messiah would come and smite the Antichrist. Robert Mueller is everything Trump isn’t, a modest do-gooder who was awarded the ‘Purple Heart’ and a public servant with a formidable 20-year record of true service to America. He would save us all from the tyranny of the ‘orange Hitler’, a draft dodging, bumptious braggart who has earned a life of privileged excess by the virtue of his name. The Republic would be saved from his tyranny, and the office of Washington, Jefferson, and Lincoln redeemed of this brief stain. ‘Russiagate’ may have sounded too good to be true, but after losing the first female president to a pervert, goddamit that b*tch karma owed us this one. But as Trump’s favourite rally anthem goes, “you can’t always get what you want”. So what do the Dems do now?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Rwanda the Real Wakanda?</title>
      <link href="/Rwanda-Real-Wakanda" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rwanda the Real Wakanda?" />
      <published>2019-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Rwanda-Real-Wakanda</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Rwanda-Real-Wakanda">&lt;p&gt;Last year, the film &lt;em&gt;Black Panther&lt;/em&gt; broke box office records and challenged the Hollywood consensus. For the first time ever, an ‘all black’ cast had headlined a major motion picture. One which made over a billion dollars worldwide and more in the United States than &lt;em&gt;Avengers Infinity War&lt;/em&gt;. The film imagined a world, home to the advanced African nation of Wakanda, which thanks to its monopoly over the unique resource of Vibranium, had managed to avoid the horrors of colonialism and become a prosperous, independent African nation. As an economics student, I believe that this premise seems to be painfully false. There is an African nation blessed with unique natural resources, so important that every person reading this article will have it in their pocket. It’s the Democratic Republic of the Congo, which is home to more than half of the world’s supply of cobalt. A mineral used to create smartphones’ rechargeable batteries. But the Democratic Republic of the Congo remains one of the world’s poorest nations, despite having rich resources of cobalt as well as copper, diamonds, tantalum, and tin. In reality Wakanda, just like the DRC, would suffer from a nasty case of “Dutch disease”, inhibiting industrialisation and a diversified economy. The real vibranium, as economists will tell you, is the “World Bank’s’ Ease of Doing Business Index”. Score higher than your neighbours in this, and your economy will soar through an influx in that magical blessing of foreign direct investment (FDI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what makes Rwanda the real Wakanda? For starters, Rwanda is a small landlocked nation within the African interior with far higher living standards than all of its neighbours. Also, just like the fictional Wakanda, it owes its wealth to a warrior king. While Rwanda’s president Paul Kagame isn’t a superhero, he is quite possibly the world’s greatest living general. At the age of twenty-eight, he helped overthrow the Ugandan regime, and at thirty-six, he toppled the Rwandan regime and ended the genocide. But his journey of martial brilliance didn’t stop here. He further went on to oust the government of the DRC, at the age of thirty-nine. Since 2000 he has ruled Rwanda as a warrior king, the rare autocrat who proved his martial credentials in a total war. After eighteen years of leading his nation, he has dramatically increased its GDP per capita from $200 to over $750. In 2000, the foreign direct investment into Rwanda was less than US$20 million. However, today it averages $232 million a year. The Kagame regime is a peaceful one with only 2.5 murders per thousand residents per year, much less than the United States, and far lower than its neighbour, the Democratic Republic of the Congo, with 13.5 murders per thousand people a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the mandatory question is how has Rwanda’s despot achieved so much. It is not through democracy or liberalism. Rwanda has severe limitations on freedom of speech and assembly. It’s a police state, with opposition leaders frequently being harassed and jailed. Former intelligence leaders have been mysteriously strangled to death in a South African hotel, and strangely, a former Interior Minister was shot dead in Kenya. In the most recent presidential election in 2017, Kagame won over 98% of the popular vote, a number even Stalin would blush at. It should be noted that the Rwandan population is over 85% Hutu, while Kagame hails from the market-dominant minority Tutsi ethnic group. It’s a little unlikely that a member of an unpopular minority could receive such overwhelming support in free elections. However, Kagame’s authoritarian tendencies are in keeping with the &lt;em&gt;Black Panther&lt;/em&gt; comparison. Like King T’Challa from the film, Kagame gained his throne through martial prowess (while not in quite as grand a personal challenge as the film version). He also maintains his throne for the good of his people without actually asking for their input on his rule. The film is notable both for its stereotype breaking all-black cast and for its status as the rare Hollywood film which advocates for an absolute monarchical government instead of one based on the ideals of American liberty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon his election, Kagame declared he would turn Rwanda into the “Singapore of Africa” and that the country would be the business and financial hub of the world’s developing continent. Just as Singapore had once gone from a small city on the edge of a Royal Navy base to the business hub of Asia in less than 50 years. Under Kagame, Rwanda has adopted English as its’ ‘lingua franca’ and become the second nation not associated with the British Empire to join the ‘Commonwealth of Nations’. Since 2000, Rwanda has liberalised its economy, cutting regulations and opening the markets to foreign businesses. The result of this is that now Rwanda ranks 29th in the ‘World Bank’s Ease of Doing Business Index’, by far the highest in Africa and higher than nations such as the Netherlands, Japan, and Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So is Rwanda the real-life Wakanda? If you accept that in the real world resource wealth almost never leads to sustained national wealth, and instead view vibranium as perhaps a metaphor for a liberal economic policy and uncorrupt courts and institutions, then Rwanda becomes the most obvious example of a real-world African nation which has achieved economic success, in spite of European colonialism in the past. Of course, through a policy of austere economic exceptionalism under the leadership of a great warrior monarch. However, while the fictional Wakanda was ruled by a benign dynasty, the very real Rwanda isn’t so lucky. In 2005, Kagame said that if by 2017 he hadn’t found a successor and made “a post me Rwanda possible”, then he would deem himself a failed leader. Contrary to that, in 2017, Kagame bullied the supreme court into allowing him to run for a third term. With the strict regulations and life-threatening challenges, to this day no possible successor has emerged. Today Rwanda sits at a crossroads. Its success has been remarkable, but if it can’t find a solution to the terrifying question of succession then its golden age might be a short-lived one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wakanda forever and we hope Rwanda too.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reuben Pritchard</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Last year, the film Black Panther broke box office records and challenged the Hollywood consensus. For the first time ever, an ‘all black’ cast had headlined a major motion picture. One which made over a billion dollars worldwide and more in the United States than Avengers Infinity War. The film imagined a world, home to the advanced African nation of Wakanda, which thanks to its monopoly over the unique resource of Vibranium, had managed to avoid the horrors of colonialism and become a prosperous, independent African nation. As an economics student, I believe that this premise seems to be painfully false. There is an African nation blessed with unique natural resources, so important that every person reading this article will have it in their pocket. It’s the Democratic Republic of the Congo, which is home to more than half of the world’s supply of cobalt. A mineral used to create smartphones’ rechargeable batteries. But the Democratic Republic of the Congo remains one of the world’s poorest nations, despite having rich resources of cobalt as well as copper, diamonds, tantalum, and tin. In reality Wakanda, just like the DRC, would suffer from a nasty case of “Dutch disease”, inhibiting industrialisation and a diversified economy. The real vibranium, as economists will tell you, is the “World Bank’s’ Ease of Doing Business Index”. Score higher than your neighbours in this, and your economy will soar through an influx in that magical blessing of foreign direct investment (FDI).</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">From Corbyn to Podemos, Don’t Forgive Maduro’s Cheerleaders</title>
      <link href="/From-Corbyn-to-Podemos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Corbyn to Podemos, Don't Forgive Maduro’s Cheerleaders" />
      <published>2019-03-07T04:30:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-07T04:30:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/From-Corbyn-to-Podemos</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/From-Corbyn-to-Podemos">&lt;p&gt;Venezuela is on fire. Two decades of mismanagement by a corrupt regime has left
its people starving, fleeing, and cowering from government death squads. Venezuela,
the world’s most oil-rich state is in ruins. The extent of the spoil has been so
thorough that it now imports more oil from the United States than it produces.
Much of this is because of the severe deficiency of refinement infrastructure.
In addition, hyperinflation has been a major battle for the administration. For
a nation which does not print its own currency, this surely is a cruel fate.
Cash money has become a rare sight. Probably due to the fact that the government
can barely afford to buy new currency. Last Christmas, a plane from Basingstoke
(a quaint Hampshire town) touched down in Caracas, filled with newly printed
Bolivars. The lowest valued note onboard was already worth less than a single US
cent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the problems for the Venezuelans weren’t just limited to financial setbacks.
It includes corruption, violence, and extreme disparity within the economic
classes―which fueled tensions. In 2016, the incumbent President, Nicolas Maduro
created a new wing of the police, the Special Action Force or FAES. Various
human rights groups have accused them of acting as Death Squads. They have
allegedly entered low-income neighbourhoods to harass and, sometimes, execute
the rivals and competitors of the regime. Since the beginning of the year,
forty-three protestors have been confirmed to have died in clashes with the
police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nicolas Maduro and his predecessor, Hugo Chavez have taken actions that have had
a tragic effect on the lives of ordinary Venezuelans. Over 3.4 million people
now live as refugees, desperately trying to flee poverty. The wealthiest nation
of South America, just a few decades ago, is now a page out of a book and
nothing more. But what makes the Maduro regime so unique is the support it gets
from many useful idiots across the developed world. While dictators like Robert
Mugabe in Zimbabwe and Bashar Al-Assad in Syria have arguably committed far more
heinous crimes against their own people, neither can boast such a committed fan
base in wealthy nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeremy Corbyn, the leader of the UK Labour Party and Her Majesty’s Most Loyal
Opposition is an avid fan of the Chavez-Maduro regime. He has personally called
Maduro to congratulate him on an election victory in 2016. This is the very
election which was decried as unfair by Human Rights Watch. The Labour Party is
the second largest party in the United Kingdom’s House of Commons and the
largest political movement in Europe by membership. Its prominent members
include Owen Jones who wrote in 2012, “Chavez’s critics in the West are entitled
to passionately disagree with him. But it’s time they stopped pretending he is a
dictator”. That was 4 years after Chavez expelled Human Rights Watch from the
country. In 2014, Corbyn’s top lieutenant John Mcdonnell said, “Here you had the
contrast between capitalism in crisis, and socialism in action.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this article isn’t about the asinine debate on whether the Venezuelan
economy can truly be considered socialist or not. I personally doubt a regime as
corrupt as Chavez’s could have ever carried out the necessary reforms to
institute a socialist economy. But we should remember the man who may soon be
the UK Chancellor of The Exchequer (Finance Minister), lauded Venezuela a
‘socialist’ regime, saying it was a nation worth emulating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Greek Prime Minister, Alexis Tsipras, was the only European head of
government who had attended Hugo Chavez’s funeral, way back in 2012. There he
praised Venezuela as an anti-capitalist model country, and has since remained
friendly with the Venezuelan regime. This has continued over the current crisis.
It should be noted that Tsipras hasn’t instituted the type of authoritarian
reforms of the Chavez and Maduro regimes for his own country. But his fondness
for their government begs the question: what would he have done if Syriza had
achieved a majority in the Greek Parliament or if he didn’t have the European
Union overseeing his administration ready to sanction it for anti-democratic
policies. Jean-Luc Melancon, the leader of the French Left, also in the past,
praised the Chavez regime. In 2013, he described it as a “source of
inspiration”. However, since then, he has changed his mind claiming that he
doesn’t “support dictatorship”, and that he has “never supported dictatorship
anywhere in the world”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there is Podemos, the Spanish Left-wing party. Since, its foundation, it
has had a special relationship with the Bolivarian regime in Venezuela. Several
of its founders, including its leader Pablo Iglesia, have been economic advisors
to the Venezuelan government. Iglesia once called Venezuela “one of the most
consolidated democracies in the world”. According to a think tank, which is
close to the party, Podemos has received millions in funding from the regime, as
published in the Spanish newspaper ABC. Nevertheless, Iglesia has now u-turned
on his support for the dictatorship. Earlier this year, he was caught on record
saying, “I don’t agree with some of the things I said in the past, and I believe
that the political and economic situation in Venezuela is disastrous. To rectify
in politics is a good thing”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a few months, voters all across Europe will have the chance to vote, in free
and fair elections, for who they want as their representatives in the European
Parliament. Voting is a hard-fought privilege held by far less than half of the
world’s population. It was once the right that the people of Venezuela had. If
the European Left’s radical leaders, who supported Chavez and Maduro, win the
elections they are, of course, unlikely to institute the authoritarian policies
as seen in Venezuela. This is because Europe’s civic institutions are strong and
it’s people remember what a dictator looks like. Having said that though, we
must remember that the support of the radical Left for the Venezuelan regime is
a cause for grave concern to the lovers of democracy. It resonates the hard
truth, as to what type of policies all these leaders would like to introduce, if
only they had the power they believe they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reuben Pritchard</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Venezuela is on fire. Two decades of mismanagement by a corrupt regime has left its people starving, fleeing, and cowering from government death squads. Venezuela, the world’s most oil-rich state is in ruins. The extent of the spoil has been so thorough that it now imports more oil from the United States than it produces. Much of this is because of the severe deficiency of refinement infrastructure. In addition, hyperinflation has been a major battle for the administration. For a nation which does not print its own currency, this surely is a cruel fate. Cash money has become a rare sight. Probably due to the fact that the government can barely afford to buy new currency. Last Christmas, a plane from Basingstoke (a quaint Hampshire town) touched down in Caracas, filled with newly printed Bolivars. The lowest valued note onboard was already worth less than a single US cent. But the problems for the Venezuelans weren’t just limited to financial setbacks. It includes corruption, violence, and extreme disparity within the economic classes―which fueled tensions. In 2016, the incumbent President, Nicolas Maduro created a new wing of the police, the Special Action Force or FAES. Various human rights groups have accused them of acting as Death Squads. They have allegedly entered low-income neighbourhoods to harass and, sometimes, execute the rivals and competitors of the regime. Since the beginning of the year, forty-three protestors have been confirmed to have died in clashes with the police. Nicolas Maduro and his predecessor, Hugo Chavez have taken actions that have had a tragic effect on the lives of ordinary Venezuelans. Over 3.4 million people now live as refugees, desperately trying to flee poverty. The wealthiest nation of South America, just a few decades ago, is now a page out of a book and nothing more. But what makes the Maduro regime so unique is the support it gets from many useful idiots across the developed world. While dictators like Robert Mugabe in Zimbabwe and Bashar Al-Assad in Syria have arguably committed far more heinous crimes against their own people, neither can boast such a committed fan base in wealthy nations. Jeremy Corbyn, the leader of the UK Labour Party and Her Majesty’s Most Loyal Opposition is an avid fan of the Chavez-Maduro regime. He has personally called Maduro to congratulate him on an election victory in 2016. This is the very election which was decried as unfair by Human Rights Watch. The Labour Party is the second largest party in the United Kingdom’s House of Commons and the largest political movement in Europe by membership. Its prominent members include Owen Jones who wrote in 2012, “Chavez’s critics in the West are entitled to passionately disagree with him. But it’s time they stopped pretending he is a dictator”. That was 4 years after Chavez expelled Human Rights Watch from the country. In 2014, Corbyn’s top lieutenant John Mcdonnell said, “Here you had the contrast between capitalism in crisis, and socialism in action.” Now, this article isn’t about the asinine debate on whether the Venezuelan economy can truly be considered socialist or not. I personally doubt a regime as corrupt as Chavez’s could have ever carried out the necessary reforms to institute a socialist economy. But we should remember the man who may soon be the UK Chancellor of The Exchequer (Finance Minister), lauded Venezuela a ‘socialist’ regime, saying it was a nation worth emulating. The Greek Prime Minister, Alexis Tsipras, was the only European head of government who had attended Hugo Chavez’s funeral, way back in 2012. There he praised Venezuela as an anti-capitalist model country, and has since remained friendly with the Venezuelan regime. This has continued over the current crisis. It should be noted that Tsipras hasn’t instituted the type of authoritarian reforms of the Chavez and Maduro regimes for his own country. But his fondness for their government begs the question: what would he have done if Syriza had achieved a majority in the Greek Parliament or if he didn’t have the European Union overseeing his administration ready to sanction it for anti-democratic policies. Jean-Luc Melancon, the leader of the French Left, also in the past, praised the Chavez regime. In 2013, he described it as a “source of inspiration”. However, since then, he has changed his mind claiming that he doesn’t “support dictatorship”, and that he has “never supported dictatorship anywhere in the world”. Then there is Podemos, the Spanish Left-wing party. Since, its foundation, it has had a special relationship with the Bolivarian regime in Venezuela. Several of its founders, including its leader Pablo Iglesia, have been economic advisors to the Venezuelan government. Iglesia once called Venezuela “one of the most consolidated democracies in the world”. According to a think tank, which is close to the party, Podemos has received millions in funding from the regime, as published in the Spanish newspaper ABC. Nevertheless, Iglesia has now u-turned on his support for the dictatorship. Earlier this year, he was caught on record saying, “I don’t agree with some of the things I said in the past, and I believe that the political and economic situation in Venezuela is disastrous. To rectify in politics is a good thing”. In a few months, voters all across Europe will have the chance to vote, in free and fair elections, for who they want as their representatives in the European Parliament. Voting is a hard-fought privilege held by far less than half of the world’s population. It was once the right that the people of Venezuela had. If the European Left’s radical leaders, who supported Chavez and Maduro, win the elections they are, of course, unlikely to institute the authoritarian policies as seen in Venezuela. This is because Europe’s civic institutions are strong and it’s people remember what a dictator looks like. Having said that though, we must remember that the support of the radical Left for the Venezuelan regime is a cause for grave concern to the lovers of democracy. It resonates the hard truth, as to what type of policies all these leaders would like to introduce, if only they had the power they believe they deserve.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Conservative Party’s Internal Squabbles Created Brexit and Divided a Nation</title>
      <link href="/The-Conservative-Party's-Internal-Squabbles" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Conservative Party's Internal Squabbles Created Brexit and Divided a Nation" />
      <published>2019-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Conservative-Party's-Internal-Squabbles</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Conservative-Party's-Internal-Squabbles">&lt;p&gt;Brexit is a bit of a mess. It threatens to have dire effects on the British and European economies, permanently undermine the continent’s security institutions, and leave behind a culture war which could divide Britain for decades to come. The old are pitted against the young, the elites against the working class and the ‘Brexiteers’ against the ‘Remainiacs’. A marginal Brexit victory of only 4% two years ago has fatally undermined any attempt to form a consensus about which Brexit (hard or soft) should be attempted, resulting in Prime Minister May’s kerfuffle negotiations. This has left Britain with a choice of: (1) no-deal Brexit (which Remainers dread); (2) remaining in the EU (which outrages Brexiteers); or (3) May’s deal (which is happily despised by all). This wasn’t what David Cameron expected. Brexit began as a bit of internal housekeeping within Cameron’s Conservative Party and as an attempt to finally settle the decades-old rift which had kept the Tories out of government for 13 years. But this intellectual dispute within the Conservative Party led to a most serious outcome that may now change Britain beyond recognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of Brexit goes deep. It is underpinned by the memory of the Blitz spirit and Churchill, the triumph of Trafalgar against the wee Napoleon and the very first Brexit, when King Henry VIII separated with the Church of Rome. But for brevity’s sake, we begin in 1990, when Britain’s first female Prime Minister, Baroness Thatcher, said “No, No, No” to the radical European integration agenda of Commission President Jacques Delors. She feared an erosion of British sovereignty. The speech was a reversal of her earlier support for the creation of the European Single Market (Customs Union) in 1987, and it injected euroscepticism into the Conservative Party. Strange as it sounds now, in the 1980’s, the Conservatives had been Britain’s pro-European party, while the Labour Party had proposed leaving the European superstate at the 1983 election. Thatcher’s new found euroscepticism was one of the key factors leading to her forced resignation, alongside the poll tax scandal and poor popularity polls. Her successor as leader of the country and the Conservative Party was John Major, who would now have to navigate the passing of the Maastricht Treaty through Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Maastricht Treaty formally transformed the European Economic Community into the European Union, replacing a club for economic cooperation with a political union that had an ominous commitment to “ever closer union”. Major was committed to a shared European future but knew many on the Conservative Parties’ backbenches saw it as affront to national sovereignty, meanwhile many Thatcher loyalists were angry at the new regime. Major negotiated a series of opt-outs for the UK, including the right to not adopt the Euro or the European Workers’ Directive. This was enough for most of the party, and the Maastricht Treaty was ratified by Parliament in 1992. However, as the magnitude of the competences Britain had acceded to the EU became clear, a large faction grew in the Conservative backbenches of eurosceptics angry with Major’s ‘betrayal’ of Britain. Major branded this group “the bastards” and they would be a constant thorn in Major’s side until his crushing defeat to Tony Blair in 1997. It must be noted that through all this (and upto 2014) very few members of the public really noticed that the European Union existed at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, two of Brexit’s greatest characters enter the story: Boris and Nigel. Nigel Farage had been a market trader and Tory party member who quit both following the betrayal of the Maastricht Treaty, choosing to devote his life to the recently formed United Kingdom Independence Party (UKIP). Meanwhile, Boris Johnson was a young Telegraph journalist based in Brussels who began building his fame with a series of spectacularly witty articles lampooning the ridiculousness of EU regulations. Nevermind the articles were full of distortions and half-truths, Boris had began his path to stardom. In 2016, Boris and Nigel would find themselves the public faces of the Brexit campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2005, David Cameron was elected Conservative Party leader, promising to get the party to “shut up about Europe”, and to end the constant infighting that had undermined the party during the Major era. Thereafter, riding a wave of political disillusionment, UKIP (lead by Farage) won the the 2014 British elections to the European Parliament. Cameron considered UKIP to be a party of Conservative voters in rebellion, and he thought that by promising a referendum he could win voters back from UKIP in the 2015 election. It was all so simple, then the Brexit campaign began.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moment the Leave campaign became real was when Boris Johnson and Michael Gove announced their support, Cameron had expected both to begrudgingly support Remain. The support of two of the Conservative Party’s “big beasts” gave the Leave campaign the legitimacy needed to make Brexit believable to the public. For the first time in 30 years, leaving the European Union was a decision supported by major politicians, not fringe figures such as Farage or Enoch Powell. The campaign focused on the simple message of “take back control”, which hit a chord with the left behind of British society. The Brexit battle bus was decorated with the immortal line “we send 350 million to the EU a week, let’s give it to our NHS instead”. A brilliant lie. Britain’s contribution to the EU is offset by millions of EU development funds and subsidies, the real figure would have been around 80 million. But all the British people heard was that millions were sent to Brussels. Exactly what the Leave campaign wanted them to hear. In the end, Britain voted by a narrow margin of 52% to 48% to leave the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the chaos began. Hoping to encourage support for Remain during the referendum, Cameron had prevented contingency planning for a Leave victory by the Civil Service. And the day after the referendum, the British political class was in crisis. For 30 years, support for the European Union had been a consensus across the ruling elite in London. None had expected a Brexit and none were ready to accept it. Following Cameron’s resignation on the day of the vote, the Conservative Party turned to Theresa May (a Remain supporter) to be the next Prime Minister. She was seen as the only adult in the room, a safe pair of hands who could solve the crisis of a nation voting for a policy which none of its social, political or business elite supported. That was was 2016, two years later after a litany of mistakes: the failed general election, a ‘dementia’ tax and the European backstop, it has become clear she was not up to the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Britain is paralysed. Experts rightly warn that a no-deal Brexit could cause food shortages, power outages and grounded planes. But if Britain chooses to stay in the EU now, after all that’s happened, something greater could be lost. I’ve spoken to family members who say that if Brexit is cancelled they will never vote again. The working class and their long running suspicion that democracy was ‘bollocks’, that no matter what happened, the elite would always have the power, would be horrifically confirmed. Britain was arguably the world’s first true democracy, its Parliament is the mother of the world’s legislative bodies. Brexit began as an internal squabble within the Conservative Party. But now, if it’s abandoned, the legitimacy of British democracy itself might be permanently undone. There are no easy solutions to this crisis. At the very least this article may have given you a idea of how we got here, what happened and who to blame.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reuben Pritchard</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Brexit is a bit of a mess. It threatens to have dire effects on the British and European economies, permanently undermine the continent’s security institutions, and leave behind a culture war which could divide Britain for decades to come. The old are pitted against the young, the elites against the working class and the ‘Brexiteers’ against the ‘Remainiacs’. A marginal Brexit victory of only 4% two years ago has fatally undermined any attempt to form a consensus about which Brexit (hard or soft) should be attempted, resulting in Prime Minister May’s kerfuffle negotiations. This has left Britain with a choice of: (1) no-deal Brexit (which Remainers dread); (2) remaining in the EU (which outrages Brexiteers); or (3) May’s deal (which is happily despised by all). This wasn’t what David Cameron expected. Brexit began as a bit of internal housekeeping within Cameron’s Conservative Party and as an attempt to finally settle the decades-old rift which had kept the Tories out of government for 13 years. But this intellectual dispute within the Conservative Party led to a most serious outcome that may now change Britain beyond recognition.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Only Turkey can Save the European Dream, but Not in the Way you Think.</title>
      <link href="/Only-Turkey-can-save-the-European-dream" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Only Turkey can Save the European Dream, but Not in the Way you Think." />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Only-Turkey-can-save-the-European-dream</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Only-Turkey-can-save-the-European-dream">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To unite the EU needs a common enemy and only the wanker from Ankara is ready to play the role.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is Europe, where are its borders, who are its people, and why should I die for it? These are the questions the European Union has desperately grappled with since the 2008 crash. National governments derive power from the willingness of their citizens to make sacrifices. Whether its paying an extra 2.9 cents for a litre of petrol, or traveling across the seas to get shot for Uncle Sam, a government’s power comes from the support of its people. But while the idea of the EU remains popular amongst the European people, with over 60% support across the block in 2017 Eurobarometer surveys, few are willing to make sacrifices for the EU. Northern Europeans don’t want to pay for the ‘greedy’ Southerners. Meanwhile, the Western Europeans don’t see the need to defend Eastern Europe against the Russians. It seems as though the EU has millions of supporters, but very few citizens ready to make the sacrifice necessary for a truly united Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So will Europe ever unite? Can the European Union potentially become a single federalised state, or a superpower capable of challenging China or America? Such a force could defeat the Russians over a long weekend and potentially upset the balance of global politics like no event since the unification of Germany or the French revolution. But the EU needs a threat to give the extra push needed for federalisation. Once that would’ve been Russia, but with an aging population and a declining economy, Russia is today truly only a threat to the Baltic republics: Belarus and the Ukraine. From the beaches of Barcelona or Palermo, the idea of Russia as a serious threat is due to Europe’s ‘special relationship’. Even so is the idea of sending their young lads to fight for Estonian sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily an Armenian phrase tells us who could provide the necessary threat to Europe: “when dealing with the Turk, don’t let go of the stick”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only power capable of convincing European nations to unify is the threat of a rising Turkey with an expansionist government. It has two key advantages over Russia: Firstly, by a matter of its geography it is able to threaten far more of the European continent than Russia can. Secondly, because in a conflict between Turkey and Europe, the United States would likely remain neutral (as it did in the Falklands War), Turkey would force the EU to take the leadership position during the conflict. This would be a cold conflict only though, likely to result in direct confrontation only through proxies in hotspots such as Cyprus or North Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the boom years, European integration seemed both logical and inevitable. The EU expanded its influence both geographically and politically, incorporating the A8 nations of eastern Europe in 2004 and increasing the authority of the Commission with the Treaties of Nice (2007) and Lisbon (2007). Then the bad times came. In 2008, the Great Recession began, since then the EU has lumbered from crisis to crisis. The Greek debt crisis, the migrant crisis and Brexit have all rocked the continent. Through it all, the EU Commision has struggled to act decisively and has lost the support of people across the continent, resulting in the surge of populist and eurosceptic parties. In Poland, Italy and Austria, pro-EU governments have been replaced with eurosceptic regemes unafraid of challenging the Commission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new hope appeared in 2017 in the form of Emmanuel Macron, who sweeped to power, defeated Le Penn and promised to reform Europe and save the Union from irrelevance. At first it seemed to work, Macron faced down protestors in France with a neo-liberal zeal, and Merkel made statements to support Macron’s vision. However, following severe losses for the ruling coalition in the 2017 German election and the populist AFD entering the Bundestag, Merkel’s political capital dried-up. Meanwhile, resentment grew in France at the so called “president of the rich”, culminating in the recent Gilets Jaunes protests which may have permanently crippled Macron’s Presidency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A decade on from the 2008 crash, it’s now perfectly clear that in a vacuum European states will continue to squabble likely forever. But Europe does not exist in a vacuum. The Republic of Turkey has a population of over 80 million of which over half are under 25, it has the largest army in Europe and will soon be home to the world’s largest airport. Also, it has done a good job of challenging Europe in the past, the Ottoman Empire once touched Vienna, Malta and the Moroccan coast opposite southern Spain. As it became clear that the EU could never allow Turkey to join, the nation has become increasingly hostile to Europe. In 2012, French diplomats were expelled following France’s formal recognition of the Armenian Genocide. In 2016, German Parliamentarians were banned from visiting their own pilots at a NATO airbase in Turkey. And in 2017, President Erdogan called the Dutch government “fascist”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Turkish Navy and Airforce can pose a direct threat to Southern and Eastern Europe, the Turkish also have the capability to threaten violence on the streets of Western Europe. Most of Western Europe’s great cities (Berlin, Rotterdam, Brussels) have large impoverished Turkish minorities which the Europeans have utterly failed to integrate or provide economic opportunity to. Amongst the Turkish diaspora, support for President Erdogan is strong, giving Ankara the capability to ignite social unrest on the streets of European capitals. Moreover, Turkey has a strong relationship with the United States, which hopes to use Turkey to check Russian and Iranian influence, and is willing to sidestep allies in order to do so (as we all saw last week when America abandoned the Syria Kurds). While the USA supporting Turkey against Europe remains unthinkable, if the Turks were able to make a confrontation appear to be at least partly the fault of the Europeans, America could be convinced to take a neutral position as it did during the Cyprus Crisis in 1964. In this scenario, Turkey becomes a threat capable of scaring the Europeans like none other, perhaps even enough to form a federation in resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern definition of Europe comes from the time of the Carolingian Renaissance when the word was used to refer to the union of Latin and Germanic Catholic peoples. This was in contrast to the Islamic Al Andalus in the south and the Orthodox Byzantine Empire in the east. From the beginning Europe was about uniting different peoples to face an enemy from outside. This Union formed under Charlemagne was not to last long after his demise, but the idea of a common people without a shared language, but owing a shared civilisation continues. Globalisation has given Europe a common language, even post Brexit over 51% percent of EU citizens can hold a conversation in English and that number will only grow. A United States of Europe is today more possible than ever before, but it will require a rival to give it shape and purpose. And Europe’s old enemy Turkey is going to be that rival.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reuben Pritchard</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">To unite the EU needs a common enemy and only the wanker from Ankara is ready to play the role.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
