<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/reema.singh/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-06-15T21:56:30+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/reema.singh/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Behind the Veil of Economic Growth</title>
      <link href="/Behind-the_Veil-of-Economic-Growth" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Behind the Veil of Economic Growth" />
      <published>2019-02-07T04:15:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T04:15:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Behind-the_Veil-of-Economic-Growth</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Behind-the_Veil-of-Economic-Growth">&lt;p&gt;India’s short period of fast economic growth has been considerably eulogized. We are now the fastest growing economy in the world—an achievement that we pat ourselves on the back for. Yet, this shred of data is difficult to embrace after being a witness to ground realities. The rapid growth has manifested itself in a plethora of opportunities for many while leaving many others in conditions that seem to be helpless. One can’t help but feel something’s amiss in the “Indian Growth Story” narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the 21st century, there will be 1.5 billion Indians and 1.1 billion Chinese. Simply as a consequence of the number of people, India will continue to be among the world’s biggest economic powers. This will hold true even if the economy stagnates sometime in the future, or even if India’s efforts to become a middle-income country fall behind. In fact, we could be the largest economy with slightly more than two-thirds of China’s current per capita GDP by that time. It is well established that economic prosperity doesn’t imply people lead satisfied lives. The aspect which has failed to come to the forefront is how rapid economic growth doesn’t necessarily translate to better living standards. Their relationship hinges on how the government employs public revenue generated from economic growth. Unless the expenditure facilitates advancement in human capabilities, it isn’t really ‘growth’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While India is climbing up the ladder of per capita income, it is slipping down when it comes to social indicators. Public revenue generated from economic growth has not been used to expand social and physical infrastructure in a well-planned manner. While the middle and upper-middle classes have fared extremely well in terms of improved standards of living during the last three decades, the same cannot be said for those employed in the informal sector, who make up to 81% of India’s 487 million person workforce. For them, the pace of growth has been excruciatingly slow. Growth in real wages for poorer sections of the population has been severely lacking when compared to other developing economies. The reason lies in the failure to generate adequate employment, in what is best described as “jobless growth”. Rapid economic growth was led by the services sector. Since growth was concentrated in skill-intensive sectors rather than labour-intensive sectors, the educated labour force has been able to earn much higher wages and salaries. The rest of the workforce is employed in activities where wages and productivity have remained very low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Official poverty estimates tell us that the poverty rate in the country has nearly halved in the ten years between 2006 and 2016. This appears to be a huge leap at first. However, as the density effect explains, since there are so many people just a little below the poverty line in India, a tiny increase in per capita income is enough to lift large numbers above the poverty line. It also explains why the official poverty line is so low (₹32 per day for rural India and ₹47 per day for urban India, which is equivalent to less than a US dollar per day). One may argue that India cannot rely on income growth alone to transform living conditions. But, the concern remains that India is not doing well in many respects even in comparison with some of the poorest countries in the world. India’s Human Development Index (HDI) ranking is 130 out of 189 countries, with a score of 0.64. Moreover, when inequality-adjusted HDI is considered, this value further falls by another 26.8%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “big brother” of the South Asian subcontinent is falling behind every other South Asian country in terms of many social indicators, notwithstanding it does much better in the growth of per capita income. Despite being much poorer than India, Bangladesh does better in terms of life expectancy, Infant Mortality Rate (IMR), immunization rates, Total Fertility Rate (TFR) and access to improved sanitation. It also fares better in the data on mean years of schooling and female literacy. Perhaps more intriguing is the case of Nepal, a country enmeshed in unstable politics and governance. In 1990, Nepal was severely lagging behind in terms of every development indicator. Over the years it has caught up with India and even overtaken it in maternal mortality, infant immunization, and female literacy. The comparison with Pakistan is more favourable to India, but not particularly flattering either. In 1990, only Sri Lanka had better social indicators than India. Now India appears to be the second worst in the region, ahead of Pakistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although India is the poorest among the BRICS countries, much more needs to be done to bridge these gaps than to catch up in terms of per capita income. When compared with other BRICS countries which have the commonality of large populations, India lags abysmally behind in every social indicator, especially undernourishment among children below 5, child immunization rates, and universal literacy. Experiences within the country itself have been starkly contrasting. The Multi-Dimensional Poverty Index (MPI) places the North Indian states of Bihar and Jharkhand in the same category as Mozambique and Sierra Leone. However, the growth model in states like Kerala, Himachal Pradesh and Tamil Nadu continue to serve as examples of how economic growth can be complemented with sustained successful social policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What clearly works for rapid social progress is the universal provision of essential public services: school education, primary health care, electricity connections, sanitation and drinking water. Their provision has to be facilitated by an efficient administration that takes into account the structure of social inequality in the area while ensuring the involvement of local communities. Among BRICS countries, India is the only one that hasn’t gone through a phase of expansion of public support (elementary education, health care, social security) or economic redistribution. It also has the lowest expenditure on education and health, which have yet again taken a back seat in the face of a populist budget. The nation has much to learn from the policies and achievements of two of its neighbouring countries. From Bangladesh, it must learn female literacy programmes, microcredit and community mobilization to bring about social change. And from Sri Lanka, it should adopt the health care and public schooling system. India can have a serious advantage over these countries in implementing these same programmes. As Amartya Sen phrased it, “A poor country may have less money to spend on healthcare but it also needs to spend less to provide the same labour-intensive services.” Healthcare and education are primarily labour-intensive activities. Since wages are low in populous and poor India, these community building services can be provided at low costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions about the nature of economic growth require much greater attention than they receive. Recently, a leaked government report put India’s unemployment rate on a 45-year high. Prominent NSSO employees (the institution who had prepared the report) had resigned in protest because the government was not releasing the report. The government’s reply to the leaked report? “You can’t be growing at 7.2% and say no jobs are being created.” A discussion on India’s economy lacks sufficient inquiry on the provision of jobs to the 1 million people who reach working age &lt;i&gt;every month&lt;/i&gt;, or the transparency on data for economic indicators, or the massive improvement required in malnutrition indicators. Unless we end our obsession with GDP numbers, we cannot expect our governments to focus on social indicators. After all, what a democratic system achieves depends largely on the issues that are brought into political engagement.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reema Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">India’s short period of fast economic growth has been considerably eulogized. We are now the fastest growing economy in the world—an achievement that we pat ourselves on the back for. Yet, this shred of data is difficult to embrace after being a witness to ground realities. The rapid growth has manifested itself in a plethora of opportunities for many while leaving many others in conditions that seem to be helpless. One can’t help but feel something’s amiss in the “Indian Growth Story” narrative.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Understanding Surplus Transfers between Central Banks and Governments</title>
      <link href="/Understanding-Surplus-Transfers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding Surplus Transfers between Central Banks and Governments" />
      <published>2019-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Understanding-Surplus-Transfers</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-Surplus-Transfers">&lt;p&gt;The trend over the last few decades for greater independence of central banks has raised the question of their financial independence. There has been increasing discussion on whether central banks require capital and if so, how much? The central bank (CB) mainly has two functions: print currency notes that are held by the public, and issue deposits to commercial banks. These are liabilities for which it does not have to pay any interest. At the same time, it purchases financial assets in the form of domestic and foreign government bonds on which it gets interest. As the cost of printing currency is on average 1/7th of the net interest income, the result is a large net interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any time the CB issues currency, undertakes foreign exchange operations, investments, conducts monetary policy operations, or provides liquidity assistance, its net worth is impacted. For central banks, much like commercial banks, the capital buffer or net worth on balance sheets allows them to absorb any potential losses. This means that it’s net worth impacts its ability to achieve monetary policy objectives, which include keeping the inflation rate within the set target. But there are no rules that dictate the amount of capital a central bank must possess. And different countries have taken different approaches based on their unique circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt; Up until the 1980’s, CBs in most countries weren’t as independent as we know them to be today. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CBs usually served under the government. They had myriad roles like financing government expenditure, maintaining financial stability, ensuring stability of prices and stimulating economic activity. But they did not have independence. The 90’s and 2000’s saw a trend in favour of independence for central banks to improve long run economic performance. This resulted from a consensus that a central bank independent from the government would be more capable of conducting a credible monetary policy. Market expectations that are more responsive to its actions will make it easier to achieve the monetary policy objectives. The main role of the CBs became the maintenance of price stability, although it was still expected to safeguard financial stability in the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When central banks served as an arm of the Ministry of Finance/Treasury, the level of CB capital and rules for distribution of profits to governments weren’t of consequence. As and when CBs across countries were allowed to set a monetary policy without interference from the government, these questions came under contention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When capital becomes sufficiently negative, there are two ways for the central bank to move forward: it has to either be recapitalised; or it has to cover losses on a cash-flow basis from the government. In latter case, which is most common, the government can insist it have discretion over the time and magnitude of the transfer, which effectively places the monetary policy in its hands. Now, the former case may seem more appealing. However, in countries that have negative capital as well as budget deficits, concerns for government interference resurface with recapitalisation as well. A government that is cash-strapped itself would not be able to render a large amount of capital to a CB in need. This was seen in the case of Argentina, where CB losses were 23.5% of the GDP in 1989 and in Jamaica, where losses were 53% of the GDP from 1988 to 1991. Financing these losses implied abandonment of monetary policy objectives that were conflicting with the government’s objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to all these issues plaguing banks with negative capital, central banks with positive amounts of capital and legal independence have been able to resist such pressures. Moreover, it is during banking crises that the CB’s demonstration of its ability to maintain financial stability becomes of utmost importance. A market that believes the central bank may change its policy to avoid losses undermines its credibility. This deters investors and delays restructuring of distressed assets, suppressing fiscal revenue and growth in the process. Indeed, in cases like Peru, Bolivia, and Chile, recapitalisation has led to a gradual improvement in financial position. But it is important to note that in these case studies, recapitalisation was brought about in conjunction with new central bank laws and economic reforms that sought to restore the public’s faith. So, it appears that if credibility is important for success of the monetary policy, the central bank must be financially strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The next question that arises is how much capital do CBs need?&lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Peter Stella in a paper written in 2005 identified four different ways that central banks have determined their level of capital:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An absolute nominal value of capital. (e.g. Bank of Canada)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A target ratio of capital to another central bank balance sheet item. (e.g. Bank of Japan)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A target ratio of capital to a macroeconomic variable. (e.g. US Federal Reserve)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Based on the perceived risks to the solvency of the bank.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, the optimal level of capital depends on a large number of factors, such as the macroeconomic environment, how vulnerable the CB is to large financial shocks, its historical legacy, policy obligations (like a fixed or pegged exchange rate) and the volatility of profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(e.g. Reserve Bank of India, Reserve Bank of New Zealand)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also follows that in developing countries and countries with narrow capital markets, the CB should have larger capital. Countries where governments have frequent or constant budget deficits and those with fixed or pegged exchange rates should pursue the same path. It is only after taking into consideration policy objectives, such as price or exchange rate stability, can an ideal level of capital be determined. The determination of the minimum financial strength should also take into account the exposure to risk. Finally, a mechanism and sufficient resources must to be available to absorb the risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the determination of an ideal level of capital, profit in excess of what is required by the central bank has to be transferred to the government. This is another source of discord. Usually the amount to be transferred is decided by both the parties before the budget for the year is set. In some cases, such as Japan, the government decides the quantum. Governments want a higher surplus in order to reduce fiscal deficit or provide assistance to distressed financial institutions, while CBs want to be cautious and keep reserves from profits for unforeseen risk. A debate follows on whether the CB is holding more capital than it requires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is little doubt that clear rules for allocation of profits would alleviate some of the strain between the CB and the government. Since the amount is subject to much fluctuation, it is also advisable to have a committee that reviews the surplus distribution policy. The rules should also contain contingencies for cases in which CB capital becomes negative. Clearly specified and transparent principles will safeguard the bank’s independence in the event that CB capital is seriously depleted. Most important of all, it would enhance the credibility of commitment to price stability on the part of both the government and the CB in the public eye.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reema Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The trend over the last few decades for greater independence of central banks has raised the question of their financial independence. There has been increasing discussion on whether central banks require capital and if so, how much? The central bank (CB) mainly has two functions: print currency notes that are held by the public, and issue deposits to commercial banks. These are liabilities for which it does not have to pay any interest. At the same time, it purchases financial assets in the form of domestic and foreign government bonds on which it gets interest. As the cost of printing currency is on average 1/7th of the net interest income, the result is a large net interest.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Market and Politics: The New Separation</title>
      <link href="/Market-and-politics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Market and Politics: The New Separation" />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Market-and-politics</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Market-and-politics">&lt;p&gt;The system of production established in the 1920’s, Fordism, entailed mass standardization of goods for societies that were increasingly headed towards urbanization. The demand was for consumer durables that were cheap and reliable, such as televisions and refrigerators. The market, therefore, was run by a few oligopolistic firms and consumers were used to waiting for a long time before getting the goods they had ordered. This period involved the initiation of assembly lines in production. Factories employed unskilled workers who were regarded as a cog in the machine within the capitalist mode of production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time the 70’s rolled around, many workers in industrialized economies refused to subject themselves to alienation under the Taylorist factory regime, demanding shorter working hours and a higher pay. Another setback to capitalist accumulation was posed by the changing products market. In the West, basic needs had largely been covered by this time and the market for standardized consumer durables was undergoing a secular saturation. What resulted was a restructuring of the production process, and the product lines. Capital responded by re-engineering its products and making them less standardized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Products had become differentiated and customized to cater to the preferences of the smallest groups of potential customers. Like never before, markets allowed customers to pay attention to their individual wants, thereby boosting the move towards customization. The two decades of 1980’s and 1990’s ushered in a period of new consumerism. As products got closer to satisfying idiosyncratic preferences, customers became more willing to work harder or borrow to attain the purchasing power required to acquire them. The growth of the industry for luxury goods, which included perfumes, watches and fashion, followed an identical pattern. Global food chains like McDonald’s incorporated aspects of local cuisines in their menus for different countries. Marketing, on one hand, discovered the commercially untapped wants, and on the other hand, it developed consumer wants. When consumer desires exceeded income, upscale emulation resulted in increasing levels of indebtedness and decreased savings. This marked a transition of markets from those that satisfied needs to those that satisfied wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By developing market niches, commercialized diversification allowed the individual to differentiate himself from some social groups and at the same time associate with others, conveying a desire for upward social mobility. The act of shopping is a way of socializing with others. Moreover, specific kinds of clothing and brands can be used to create a sense of group membership. In fact, rejecting consumer brands in itself establishes quasi-group identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What differentiates this from traditional social integration is that this is voluntary. In well-developed post-Fordist markets, collective identities can be formed through a purchase and abandoned without much ado. In one sense, this signifies liberation from the identity associated with one’s family, community and nation, which the individual is born into and does not have much choice in. It also means that social ties have become much more fragile and weaker as individuals shift identities and desert them as per their convenience. Market forces in this sense writhed their way deeper into social life under a capitalist mode of production. Social media acts as another mode to form these voluntary ties. Twitter, Facebook, Instagram and the likes allow for the formation of a community of followers who interact with each other. Companies use this to further their individualized marketing. Celebrities use it to promote their works and stay relevant. Politicians use it to prevent the increasing weakening of traditional party organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markets that seek to cater to the idiosyncrasies of consumers have resulted in the development of a political system best described as “politainment”. Since purchasing power in affluent societies allow the average citizens to get what they want, their interest in the political process begins to fade as there is no vested interest. Participation in traditional politics no longer seems worthwhile. Although people continue to follow the news and pay emphasis on being informed, politics is gradually turning into a form of entertainment, and the citizen is made a spectator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we move forward, we find ourselves diverting from a vision for social and economic progress to an overemphasis on individual political decisions. Politics, in effect is becoming de-contextualized. Political participation becomes like an act of consumption, something that can be abandoned or replaced if it ceases to be exciting, much like the T-shirt you bought a few months ago. A consequence is that the public begins to perceive politics as a cumulation of antics resulting from a game of power grabbing. What becomes the focus are the scandals, the petty statements made by opposing sides against each other and representatives focus on managing their appearances rather than serving the public interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;An argument for a separation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what has been discussed, it is evident that goods aren’t merely for consumption, but also a status symbol. Underlying consumer behaviour is a desire for emulation and differentiation. In advanced industrial societies, consumption of a good serves a dual purpose: It should allow the consumer to distinguish himself or herself from other social groups and classes, while simultaneously allowing for the retention of a sense of individuality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This affects the allocation of resources between the public and private sphere. Government goods, those produced by government authorities, are designed to be standardized to ensure a sense of equality among those who consume them. In doing so, they fail to serve the purpose of status differentiation. Their inability to allow the consumer to derive a personal status benefit causes government goods to suffer in cases where the consumer is the decision maker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once it became well accepted that only private firms could satisfy expectations of the consumer for more customized products, the private sector began to be seen as inherently more superior to the public sector. The public sector reforms of the 90’s followed suit. They involved privatisation of government industries that produced consumer goods, decentralisation of government activities, the use of private producers to sell government produced goods and, a change in the mix of government activities, with a greater focus towards education and healthcare. Formerly public functions moved to the private sphere and even in mixed governments, the balance shifted in favour of the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The role of politics, regardless of how romanticised it may seem in today’s day and age, is the maintenance of social order and parity. Political communities are built on the idea of accepting a collective identity rather than focusing on one’s individuality. They do not allow for the flexibility of choice as in the markets of highly industrialized economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The employment of a democratic procedure entails that one must accept decisions that they don’t personally prefer, even if they aren’t optimal from an individual’s perspective. In its essence, Politics cannot cater to hedonistic individual desires. Rather, it assesses them to form a general idea that supersedes an individual’s wants. Similarly, social goods cannot be diversified at the rate of customization in the consumer market. As a result they will always seem unfavourable in comparison to private goods. Eventually, the incentive to contribute to the provision of public goods and civil services will dry up. Moreover, paying taxes for financing government activities without having prior knowledge of how they are to be used is in contrast to any other market purchase. This decline in interest in collective projects by people with sufficient purchasing power will ensue an increase in tax resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a shift from public to private consumption, those who continue to depend on public provisions will also get affected. In commercial markets that effectively oust the poorer segments, the only effective means to promote their requirements is their power to affect the electoral outcome. When the political system is starved of legitimacy and financial resources, the lower classes will refrain from voting and even symbolically participating in the political process; Consequently, the state’s ability to ensure public order will slowly evaporate. The reorganization of social life under capitalism, culminates today in a dual crisis of the global financial system and the creation of a ‘minimalist’ democracy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reema Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The system of production established in the 1920’s, Fordism, entailed mass standardization of goods for societies that were increasingly headed towards urbanization. The demand was for consumer durables that were cheap and reliable, such as televisions and refrigerators. The market, therefore, was run by a few oligopolistic firms and consumers were used to waiting for a long time before getting the goods they had ordered. This period involved the initiation of assembly lines in production. Factories employed unskilled workers who were regarded as a cog in the machine within the capitalist mode of production.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
