<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/sponsored/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-09-04T09:19:29+01:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/sponsored/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Art for Thought</title>
      <link href="/Art-for-Thought" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Art for Thought" />
      <published>2021-09-03T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Art-for-Thought</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Art-for-Thought">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It would be a no-brainer today to say that the world is lacking in beauty and happiness. COVID-19 has wreaked havoc on our lives. So many people have lost their jobs. So many people have succumbed to the plague. So much despair colours the air. In all of this turmoil, it is not only easy to believe that there is no light at the end of the tunnel but also stupid to think that happiness can be more than a dream. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Nevertheless, we know that we cannot give in to the demons that beset the path of our whole species. We already know that we must give ourselves hope. For without hope there can be no survival. But the question is how? How can we overcome our human limitations? How do we convince a mind so affected by malaise to believe in a better tomorrow? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The answer lies in art. Art is the yearning of the human soul for something greater than itself. Art screams out to every human being out there that no matter how small they may be, they’re capable of wonderful things. Art is salvation for our restless minds in these times, when our bodies stay caged within four walls.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;We need art not just in some magnificent Da Vinci painting, but in every-day items: small but necessary things which remind us that life is worth living and that all is not lost. It is here that Vantheshoe comes to our aid. This small start-up, run by a charming young lady, by definition, refuses to give up on the soul of humanity. With charming floral prints and vivacious colours on all kinds of items like handbags, phone covers, and so on, Vantheshoe reminds you that this pandemic cannot take away the beauty that is within you. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;No, this is not just some pithy advertorial trying to sell you a product by exploiting your deeper unhappiness. Rather, it is a heartfelt article telling you about the work of someone who is genuinely interested in giving you something that you can truly cherish. We are here not to sell Vantheshoes’s products, but to tell you why at all they are worth buying. In other words, we’re here in true solidarity with the depth of human feeling. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Thus, we implore you to explore &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vantheshoe.com/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Vantheshoe’s products&lt;/a&gt;, to appreciate the designs and the hours of work that have gone into making them. We will not ask you to buy the products, that would be presumptuous, but we will ask you to see for yourselves that in every mobile cover, in every handbag, every coaster, there is the soul of an artist trapped inside waiting to be adored by the right person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/vantheshoe1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/vantheshoe2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>.</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      
        <category term="sponsored" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It would be a no-brainer today to say that the world is lacking in beauty and happiness. COVID-19 has wreaked havoc on our lives. So many people have lost their jobs. So many people have succumbed to the plague. So much despair colours the air. In all of this turmoil, it is not only easy to believe that there is no light at the end of the tunnel but also stupid to think that happiness can be more than a dream. Nevertheless, we know that we cannot give in to the demons that beset the path of our whole species. We already know that we must give ourselves hope. For without hope there can be no survival. But the question is how? How can we overcome our human limitations? How do we convince a mind so affected by malaise to believe in a better tomorrow? The answer lies in art. Art is the yearning of the human soul for something greater than itself. Art screams out to every human being out there that no matter how small they may be, they’re capable of wonderful things. Art is salvation for our restless minds in these times, when our bodies stay caged within four walls.&amp;nbsp; We need art not just in some magnificent Da Vinci painting, but in every-day items: small but necessary things which remind us that life is worth living and that all is not lost. It is here that Vantheshoe comes to our aid. This small start-up, run by a charming young lady, by definition, refuses to give up on the soul of humanity. With charming floral prints and vivacious colours on all kinds of items like handbags, phone covers, and so on, Vantheshoe reminds you that this pandemic cannot take away the beauty that is within you. No, this is not just some pithy advertorial trying to sell you a product by exploiting your deeper unhappiness. Rather, it is a heartfelt article telling you about the work of someone who is genuinely interested in giving you something that you can truly cherish. We are here not to sell Vantheshoes’s products, but to tell you why at all they are worth buying. In other words, we’re here in true solidarity with the depth of human feeling. Thus, we implore you to explore Vantheshoe’s products, to appreciate the designs and the hours of work that have gone into making them. We will not ask you to buy the products, that would be presumptuous, but we will ask you to see for yourselves that in every mobile cover, in every handbag, every coaster, there is the soul of an artist trapped inside waiting to be adored by the right person.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Doxxing: Everything You Should Know About Not Falling Victim</title>
      <link href="/Doxxing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Doxxing: Everything You Should Know About Not Falling Victim" />
      <published>2021-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Doxxing</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Doxxing">&lt;p&gt;Doxxing has been around for a long time. You might have been a victim of doxxing – on a smaller or larger scale – and you didn't even know it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this piece, we discuss what doxxing is and what you can do to prevent it from happening in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is Doxxing?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also known as doxxing, it refers to a specific form of cyber-attack where an internet user's details are revealed and made publicly available.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doxing often occurs as a personal attack launched on a specific internet user to make them uncomfortable in their own homes. It is also a way to let the internet user know that they are not safe from their attacker's reach, no matter where they might go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to prevent doxxing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth about doxxing is that nothing you didn't put out there will be found. Thus, it can be prevented in its entirety if you know what you are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the ways to keep off the radar of this damaging attack include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Watching Social Media Activity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media is an information mine that you are not considering as much as you should be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From constant updates, picture uploads, random tweets, and more, you might be letting on bits and pieces of personal information which could be pieced together to uncover your identity online. Here, details such as your email address, home address, personal cell number, and more can be revealed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do well to limit the kind of information that you share online. If possible, make your social media accounts private such that only friends and family can follow your updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Masking your IP Address&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The internet works on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wpbeginner.com/glossary/ip-address/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;a system of IP addresses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which are uniquely assigned to each computer. Just like a physical address, the IP address is used to approximate or pinpoint the location where your computer is accessing the internet from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, anyone with access to your IP address information can extract where you are reaching the web from. Hence, they have your location also.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good measure against this is to use the Tor browser or get &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.expressvpn.com&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;a VPN app to protect your identity online&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Both services are excellent for assigning a new IP address to you whenever you access the web. Thus, anyone tracking you will always be sent on a wild goose chase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preventing Packet Sniffing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, make sure your internet network is as secure as it can be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, the hacker can break the Wi-Fi protocols and access the computers on that network. From there, there is no limit to the amount of personal information that they can get on you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An excellent place to start here is to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inc.com/comcast/risks-of-using-public-wifi.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;avoid public and free Wi-Fi networks altogether&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. When on a personal router network also, ensure the best practices at all times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a sponsored article from &lt;a href=&quot;https://techwarn.com/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TechWarn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>tech.warn</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="sponsored" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Doxxing has been around for a long time. You might have been a victim of doxxing – on a smaller or larger scale – and you didn't even know it. In this piece, we discuss what doxxing is and what you can do to prevent it from happening in the first place. What is Doxxing? Also known as doxxing, it refers to a specific form of cyber-attack where an internet user's details are revealed and made publicly available.&amp;nbsp; Doxing often occurs as a personal attack launched on a specific internet user to make them uncomfortable in their own homes. It is also a way to let the internet user know that they are not safe from their attacker's reach, no matter where they might go. How to prevent doxxing The truth about doxxing is that nothing you didn't put out there will be found. Thus, it can be prevented in its entirety if you know what you are doing. Some of the ways to keep off the radar of this damaging attack include: Watching Social Media Activity Social media is an information mine that you are not considering as much as you should be. From constant updates, picture uploads, random tweets, and more, you might be letting on bits and pieces of personal information which could be pieced together to uncover your identity online. Here, details such as your email address, home address, personal cell number, and more can be revealed. Do well to limit the kind of information that you share online. If possible, make your social media accounts private such that only friends and family can follow your updates. Masking your IP Address The internet works on a system of IP addresses which are uniquely assigned to each computer. Just like a physical address, the IP address is used to approximate or pinpoint the location where your computer is accessing the internet from. In other words, anyone with access to your IP address information can extract where you are reaching the web from. Hence, they have your location also. A good measure against this is to use the Tor browser or get a VPN app to protect your identity online. Both services are excellent for assigning a new IP address to you whenever you access the web. Thus, anyone tracking you will always be sent on a wild goose chase. Preventing Packet Sniffing In other words, make sure your internet network is as secure as it can be. Otherwise, the hacker can break the Wi-Fi protocols and access the computers on that network. From there, there is no limit to the amount of personal information that they can get on you. An excellent place to start here is to avoid public and free Wi-Fi networks altogether. When on a personal router network also, ensure the best practices at all times. This is a sponsored article from TechWarn.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
