<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/ashima.makhija/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-01-19T11:50:37+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/ashima.makhija/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Jan Lokpal: The half-waged war for anti-corruption</title>
      <link href="/The-half-waged-war-for-anti-corruption" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jan Lokpal: The half-waged war for anti-corruption" />
      <published>2019-01-03T21:01:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T21:01:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-half-waged-war-for-anti-corruption</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-half-waged-war-for-anti-corruption">&lt;p&gt;India’s “war on corruption”, which erupted in 2011 with the hunger strikes of the activist Anna Hazare in New Delhi, seems to have lost itself underneath a mountain of bureaucratic jargon and political propaganda. Over seven years ago, Anna Hazare, with his unflinching voice and grit, demanded the formulation and approval of the Jan Lokpal Bill, a citizen’s ombudsman bill, that requires the appointment of a Jan Lokpal, an independent body that would investigate corruption cases, complete the investigation within a year and ensure that the trial in the case gets over in the next one year. The Jan Lokpal Bill was passed after the protests started by Hazare spread across the country in 2013. However, the vision of an India rid of corrupt officials and leaders is still quite distant simply because the Lokpal bill was never implemented. Over the years, along with political activists and India’s Central and State governments, the judiciary has also become involved in the process of the appointment of the Jan Lokpal. Yet, national policy has come to a standstill on the issue, and no remarkable progress has been made in over five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lokpal issue has been raging in the country since 1968, when the bill was first introduced in the Indian Parliament. The need for this reform is certainly apparent. In a fast-developing economy like India, which is emerging as a powerful player of the future, accountability and transparency can no longer be compromised. And so, Anna Hazare began his revolution of a “Swachh” or “Clean” economy and polity for the country. His protests in Delhi became a historic symbol of the country’s battle against corruption. In fact, the formulation of the Aam Aadmi Party (AAP), which constitutes the current government of Delhi, is viewed as a product of these protests. It was Mr Hazare’s protests that led to the Jan Lokpal, a committee of eight headed by a chairperson as the country’s ultimate anti-corruption watchdog. The Jan Lokpal bill provides for special protection of the whistleblower and covers all categories of public servants, including the Prime Minister, with only the armed forces being exempted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the ineffective executive mechanisms that run the nation, have once again, proved themselves. Due to vested interests of significant parties and leaders, the Jan Lokpal is not even solving corruption theoretically. The first issue to spark up was related to the procedure of appointment of the Lokpal itself. According to the provisions of the Bill, The Lokpal is appointed by a five-member committee including the Prime Minister, the Parliamentary Speaker, the Chief Justice of India, the Leader of Opposition and a member appointed by the Prime Minister. The problem is India doesn’t have a Leader of Opposition as of now. By definition, the Leader of Opposition is from a party that has 10 percent seats in the Lok Sabha or Lower House and no party satisfies this criterion. Thus, an amendment was introduced that called for the leader of the largest opposition party to be on the panel for selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in 2017, the Indian Supreme Court ruled that the absence of the Leader of the Opposition should not become a hindrance to the appointment of the Jan Lokpal. But this has evidently been ineffective. And the Court was dragged into the matter again in 2018 when the government had made no notable progress. The petition was filed by an NGO called Common Cause, which was represented by senior lawyer Prashant Bhushan. The petition questioned why the Lokpal has not been appointed as yet, despite an order by the apex court in April last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we now move onto January 2019, the Supreme Court has sought a response from the Centre on a plea that the leader of the single largest opposition party be treated as the Leader of the Opposition and be included in high-level committees involved in the appointment of heads of statutory bodies like CBI, CVC, CIC and Lokpal. NGO Common Cause has even suggested that the SC should appoint the Lokpal. But it only seems that with so many layers of executive, legislative and judicial interventions, India has become tangled in an all-too-familiar web of stagnation. The activist Anna Hazare, after a long period of silence, has decided to step up again and restart his hunger strike. He is expected to fast again from January 30, 2019. This can mark a crucial turning point for the Lokpal law, and the half-waged war on corruption. His aura may once again be successful in bringing people together. But can the man, who awed the public once, five years ago, repeat his own feat? Only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till then, Indians, like always, have to simply cope with a sad reality brought about by perennial administrative bottlenecks. The Jan Lokpal, that once became the torchbearer of India’s struggle for freedom from black money and corruption, has now become a distant issue. The media seems to have “moved on”. But what remains is the fact that the Jan Lokpal is the need of the hour. Public awareness and intervention alone can help save the cause for Lokpal and develop the economically “Swachh Bharat”.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">India’s “war on corruption”, which erupted in 2011 with the hunger strikes of the activist Anna Hazare in New Delhi, seems to have lost itself underneath a mountain of bureaucratic jargon and political propaganda. Over seven years ago, Anna Hazare, with his unflinching voice and grit, demanded the formulation and approval of the Jan Lokpal Bill, a citizen’s ombudsman bill, that requires the appointment of a Jan Lokpal, an independent body that would investigate corruption cases, complete the investigation within a year and ensure that the trial in the case gets over in the next one year. The Jan Lokpal Bill was passed after the protests started by Hazare spread across the country in 2013. However, the vision of an India rid of corrupt officials and leaders is still quite distant simply because the Lokpal bill was never implemented. Over the years, along with political activists and India’s Central and State governments, the judiciary has also become involved in the process of the appointment of the Jan Lokpal. Yet, national policy has come to a standstill on the issue, and no remarkable progress has been made in over five years.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Trump’s ‘New African Policy’: Can US weave diplomatic tapestries using Chinese threads?</title>
      <link href="/trumps-new-african-policy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trump’s ‘New African Policy’: Can US weave diplomatic tapestries using Chinese threads?" />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/trumps-new-african-policy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/trumps-new-african-policy">&lt;p&gt;On December 14, 2018, the US National Security Adviser, John Bolton revealed Trump’s ‘New African Strategy’, which aims to advance U.S. trade and investment, suppress terrorism and conflict, and ensure that US aid in the continent is well spent. This policy, entitled &lt;i&gt;Prosper Africa&lt;/i&gt;, is perhaps the Trump administration’s biggest policy decision vis-à-vis the African continent. Yet, many critics detected the familiar rhetoric of the Cold War return in subtle hues with this policy. This is because, rather than focusing on developing Africa, this policy has taken the narrative of simply countering China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his speech at the Heritage Foundation, Bolton spoke of the “predatory” policies of China in Africa, which are led by opaque terms of loans and have given China unfair leverage over the national governments in Africa. Over the last two years, American foreign policy had turned into a listless farce, with no meaning or purpose, as far as Africa was concerned. Contrary to previous administrations, Trump’s inward-looking politics left no space for new initiatives to be launched and left existing partnerships lurching in confusion, disarray, and disregard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Chinese Threat&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no question about the fact that a renewed and rigorous policy towards Africa was long overdue. According to the African Development Bank, African states need to invest $68 billion to $108 billion more each year in infrastructure to boost growth and create enough jobs for their booming populations. Thus, when China came knocking on Africa’s doors, with ambitions of infrastructural development, large-scale investments, cultural exchange, trade and prosperity, Africa didn’t go over the terms and conditions as well as one would hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being orphaned by the US and adopted by China simultaneously, Africa witnessed an immense growth in Chinese capital. According to the consulting firm McKinsey, more than 10,000 Chinese companies now do business on the continent, earning approximately $180 billion each year. Although the United States still has more foreign direct investment stock in Africa, Chinese investment in the region is growing fast. In 2009, China overtook the United States to become Africa’s biggest trading partner. It has also taken over the Western superpower as the largest creditor of the continent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Belt and Road Initiative (BRI) underway, the Chinese global trading zones are bound to increase many-fold. With even greater lending to developing countries and promises of trade, exports and economic growth, China is fulfilling its destiny of being a superpower of the East. And, to reclaim Africa, the US’s strategy has finally been kick-started. Even Bolton’s words at the conference were foreboding and warned of foreign threats, instead of being optimistic and growth-driven.  Particularly, he said that “Great power competitors, namely China and Russia, are rapidly expanding their financial and political influence across Africa. They are deliberately and aggressively targeting their investments in the region to gain a competitive advantage over the United States.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Flight to dominance via Africa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trump’s policy has the following three major objectives:
Advancing U.S. trade and commercial ties with nations across the region to the benefit of both the United States and Africa;
Countering the threat from Radical Islamic Terrorism and violent conflict.
Ensuring that U.S. taxpayer dollars for aid are used efficiently and effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This announcement has followed the signing of the BUILD Act by President Trump. The Act provides new authorities to the Overseas Private Investment Corporation (OPIC), including doubling its lending cap to 60 billion USD. ‘Prosper Africa’ will lead to over 1 billion USD in new investments and greater private-public partnerships in the region to flourish growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the policy is well suited to the situation, it is still being viewed as ‘poorly targeted’. This is because Bolton’s speech missed all the usual cries of human rights, democracy and freedom. Instead of posing as the harbinger of liberty and peace, as US policy has done since the end of Cold War, this one blatantly stands against the advances of Russia and China. Throughout his speech, Bolton mentioned the evils of China and Russia, which are making enormous investments by fooling African nations with opaque credit terms, bribes and strategic use of debt. He also criticised several UN peacekeeping missions, which have received enormous American funds, but to no fruition. His speech, thus, disregarded the commercial, economic, political and military advances of China and Russia and admitted that the US’s efforts in the region have yielded no substantial political or economic results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the Trump administration views this policy as the best way to secure American interests in the region while ensuring sustained development, previous governments have used multilateral approaches instead. This means that in order to achieve peace and economic growth, previous governments saw China as a partner, instead of a global adversary. Obama, in particular, saw China’s interest in the region, even via American initiatives, as a medium to further bolster growth. Many experts feel that a triangular approach to the African question, wherein both U.S and China could invest in partnership, rather than in competition, would have been more desirable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, one cannot ignore that there has been a significant shift in the positions of both, the US and China, on the global stage. China indeed has been aggressively advancing its economic and military interests in Africa and Asia and perhaps, a strong political move like this was what the US needed to reiterate its own position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;America has finally built a concrete structure for its African policy. Although there are still many blanks that need to be filled, there are several desirable changes that are coming about, especially, reduction in expenditure on UN projects that have not led to any tangible results and increase in investment-driven projects, led by economic and commercial interests. With the trade war first and the African policy now, it seems that U.S. and China are diverging on their paths to achieve global growth and prosperity. Globalisation and planetary collaboration are increasingly taking a back seat and national superiority is coming to the forefront again. Whether or not this works out for Africa, China and the US is yet to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On December 14, 2018, the US National Security Adviser, John Bolton revealed Trump’s ‘New African Strategy’, which aims to advance U.S. trade and investment, suppress terrorism and conflict, and ensure that US aid in the continent is well spent. This policy, entitled Prosper Africa, is perhaps the Trump administration’s biggest policy decision vis-à-vis the African continent. Yet, many critics detected the familiar rhetoric of the Cold War return in subtle hues with this policy. This is because, rather than focusing on developing Africa, this policy has taken the narrative of simply countering China.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
