<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/harsh.tiwari/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-08-04T13:52:51+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/harsh.tiwari/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Are Britain’s Regulators Too Good to Fail?</title>
      <link href="/Too-Good-to-Fail" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are Britain's Regulators Too Good to Fail?" />
      <published>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Too-Good-to-Fail</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Too-Good-to-Fail">&lt;p&gt;Not long ago, the Bank of England cancelled the annual stress tests of different UK banks this year due to the COVID-19 pandemic. The Prudential Regulatory Authority (PRA), Britain’s prudential regulator for all systemically important financial firms, signalled its willingness to reevaluate the timetable for the new Basel norms on international banking regulation. These relaxations in regulatory scrutiny and planning were based on the health check of UK banks conducted last year, which, according to the Bank of England, “showed that the UK banking system was resilient to deep simultaneous recessions in the UK and global economies that are more severe overall than the global financial crisis, combined with large falls in asset prices and a separate stress of misconduct costs”. Despite the use of dry language, the sheer optimism of this outlook is undeniable, which obviously begs the question of its veracity. More specifically, it is worthwhile to ask: are the UK’s regulatory policies really that good? Can the Bank of England really have that much faith in the stewardship of the financial regulators?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good starting point for exploring the issues that are thematic and recurrent in the UK’s broader regulatory ideology is its handling of competition and innovation. The Financial Conduct Authority (FCA), Britain’s financial services consumer champion, has been explicitly mandated by the Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 (FSMA 2000) to promote competition and to ensure the removal of market barriers and encourage innovation in pursuance of the same. The PRA also has the competition objective as its secondary objective. The FCA and PRA have worked together to set-up the New Bank Start-up Unit and the FCA has set-up the Regulatory Sandbox for fintech firms. Prima facie, these measures seem to be very successful. Under cohort 5 of the Regulatory Sandbox, 29 businesses have gained entry with 99 applications— the highest so far. The rise of the new banks has been impressive as well: 1 in every 4 millennials is the customer of a challenger bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it would be glib to argue that the rise of fintech and challenger banks represents a true policy success. For instance, the Regulatory Sandbox, rather than being a hub of clinical trials for new financial products, is becoming a way for firms to gain funding and legitimacy before their product is deemed safe. As &lt;a href=&quot;http://ftalphaville.ft.com/2018/12/05/1543986004000/A--fintech-sandbox--might-sound-like-a-harmless-idea--It-s-not/&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Financial Times&lt;/em&gt;, in the 2018 cohort, around 40% of the Sandbox entrants gained funding just after entry. Moreover, around half of the start-ups that did gain entry had something to do with crypto-currency— a dangerous financial product, to say the least. This should be the cause for grave concern as it exposes that promoting innovation for the sake of innovation creates critical risks for a financial system, after all, payment protection insurance and subprime mortgages were the results of cutting edge innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A deeper analysis of the regulators’ policies on challenger banks exposes the tensions inherent in trying to keep a system both safe and competitive. While challenger banks have grown, they have not really posed a threat to traditional lenders. In 2000, the top six firms had 80% personal current accounts, by 2017 that figure rose to 87%. The reason for this is the high regulatory burden on challenger banks, such as the higher ‘minimum requirement for own funds and eligible liabilities’ or MREL put forth by the Bank of England under the Banking Act 2009. The MREL, as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bba.org.uk/news/bba-voice/mrel-the-home-straight/#.XvuI08ZX40M&quot;&gt;explained&lt;/a&gt; by Mark Russell of the British Bankers Association, is necessary to prevent government bail-outs, but it requires smaller banks on an average to have an MREL that is 22% of their risk-weighted liabilities, which is too heavy a burden. So, while the New Bank Start-up Unit is not itself a failure, there is a lack of policies accompanying it that would achieve greater stability through optimal competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another key set of measures that dominates the current regulatory landscape is the change from a ‘light touch’ and ‘tick box’ approach to a more ‘judgment-based’ and ‘outcomes-based’ style of regulation. This kind of regulation ensures that instead of mechanically following certain procedures or protocols that are merely presumed to ensure the safety of the financial system and consumer protection, firms actively engage in adopting strategies and policies which actually achieve the outcomes of better consumer protection and greater systemic stability. This regulatory approach is based on the notion that a one-size-fits-all kind of regulation is ill-suited to the financial and banking sector and that, practically speaking, firms have to be trusted to regulate themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implications of this approach, which incorporates influences from behavioural economics, is that there is a greater emphasis on banking culture and individual responsibility. In addition, there is an understanding that firms are free to develop their own innovative methods on how to reach certain outcomes. While all of this represents a significant and welcome departure from the pre-2008 approach, problems do exist. Two issues are worth highlighting. First, there is the issue of technology. Regulators lack the technical know-how that firms have and they may find it difficult to assess whether a product is safe. They could be &lt;a href=&quot;https://minnesotalawreview.org/2017/05/17/the-algorithm-made-me-do-it-and-other-bad-excuses/&quot;&gt;duped&lt;/a&gt; by an algorithm supplied by the firm, given algorithms, like human decisions, are made on incomplete data and imperfect logic. Moreover, firms could deliberately seek to mislead regulators using algorithms. As Miranda Mowbray, a former lecturer of computer science at the University of Bristol pointed out in a podcast to &lt;em&gt;The Pangean&lt;/em&gt;, algorithms could lead to the next VW scandal. To the regulator, the algorithm may appear regulation-compliant, whereas, in reality, it may not be so. The consequences of a regulator being duped or misled may remain invisible, quietly wreaking havoc until it is too late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other issue is that cultural change can be exceedingly difficult. While individual responsibility is important and can go a long way, culture is bigger than any single individual. The attitude people have towards risk and the extent to which they value regulatory compliance and customer protection is something that a regulator has minimum control over. Regulators can ensure management is well-qualified but they cannot stop the idolisation of Gordon Gekko in &lt;em&gt;Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; and Jordan Belfort in &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; by the whole industry. Moreover, the regulatory culture and banking culture go hand-in-hand. If a regulator arguably starts prioritising innovation for the sake of it by routinely encouraging crypto startups (see above), then it signals its willingness to support potentially dangerous ideas, which inevitably has the effect of engendering a similar openness to exceedingly risky ideas in the banking industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final policy approach worth discussing is the elephant in the room, i.e. stress testing. Indeed, stress testing is a laudable policy measure and practice. Last year’s stress test even involved checking if firms could weather a climate catastrophe. But no policy measure is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stress tests are published as part of the financial stability report prepared by the Financial Policy Committee, a committee of the Bank of England that is headed by its Governor, under the Financial Services Act. This report is published after approval in a meeting of the Committee, where the Governor of the Bank of England is required to maintain consensus. The effect of this is that the voices of those who may strongly dissent with the majority’s (likely) positive assessment are suppressed. As we know from past experience, this is a bad idea simply because, to quote Alastair Hudson, &lt;em&gt;“there is as much a need for Eeyore as there is Piglet in macro-prudential regulation”&lt;/em&gt;. Besides, the only accountability that the Governor has for the financial stability report is ‘tea’ with the Chancellor of the Exchequer, i.e. a meeting with him, which, undeniably, is not ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, it would seem that the UK’s broad regulatory policies are far from fool-proof and adequately robust. While on the surface they seem to be doing their task of ensuring a stronger, more stable financial system, a closer analysis exposes serious problems brewing beneath the surface. These problems present a strong warning against any sense of complacency and remind us that a lot of work remains to be done. This is not to say that the Bank of England was wrong to cancel this year’s stress tests or that the PRA was wrong in delaying the implementation of Basel IV, it is only to say that the (over) confidence with which regulatory oversight has been eschewed is deeply misplaced. Britain’s regulatory architecture, to put it bluntly, is simply not as strong as it thinks it is. And it better recognise that before things come crashing down once again.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Not long ago, the Bank of England cancelled the annual stress tests of different UK banks this year due to the COVID-19 pandemic. The Prudential Regulatory Authority (PRA), Britain’s prudential regulator for all systemically important financial firms, signalled its willingness to reevaluate the timetable for the new Basel norms on international banking regulation. These relaxations in regulatory scrutiny and planning were based on the health check of UK banks conducted last year, which, according to the Bank of England, “showed that the UK banking system was resilient to deep simultaneous recessions in the UK and global economies that are more severe overall than the global financial crisis, combined with large falls in asset prices and a separate stress of misconduct costs”. Despite the use of dry language, the sheer optimism of this outlook is undeniable, which obviously begs the question of its veracity. More specifically, it is worthwhile to ask: are the UK’s regulatory policies really that good? Can the Bank of England really have that much faith in the stewardship of the financial regulators?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">American Psycho, Capitalism and the Hindu Gods</title>
      <link href="/American-Psycho-Capitalism-and-the-Hindu-Gods" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="American Psycho, Capitalism and the Hindu Gods" />
      <published>2020-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/American-Psycho-Capitalism-and-the-Hindu-Gods</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/American-Psycho-Capitalism-and-the-Hindu-Gods">&lt;p&gt;The morning routine scene in &lt;em&gt;American Psycho&lt;/em&gt; is, without a doubt, ensnaring. The intricate detail with which Patrick Bateman describes the various toiletries he uses, the near-artistic manner in which he applies facemask, and the way in which he innocently cautions against using alcohol-based aftershave is hauntingly beautiful. The question is: apart from the obvious aesthetics of the scene (and Christian Bale’s perfect physique and looks), why is a bloody personal hygiene tutorial so enchanting? Is the scene so surreal that it somehow reminds us of our own reality?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;American Psycho&lt;/em&gt;, it is acknowledged across the board, takes a dig at the hyper materialism and obsessive image-consciousness of 80’s American yuppie culture. But its relevance to today’s advanced capitalist society is unmistakable. Patrick Bateman’s obsessive beauty regimen is a mirror for the multiple ways in which we craft detailed masks to project an image that conforms to certain appearances of wealth, happiness and even ‘liberalism’. It mirrors Elon Musk’s workaholism, which seeks to portray him as a self-made man, when in fact his father was the owner of multiple emerald mines. It mirrors the life of many Instagram models whose very source of income is a self-objectification of their bodies. It mirrors Pride Month, which is nothing more than liberal hogwash, and it mirrors us, the people who check-in on Facebook when visiting an expensive restaurant or put up such perfect pictures when visiting sweaty, crowded, dirty and drug-filled music festivals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, the morning routine scene in &lt;em&gt;American Psycho&lt;/em&gt; serves as a perfect allegory for the way in which society immaculately creates the face of capitalism. In providing this allegory, it serves as a starting point for a much more profound idea: that ‘capitalism’, instead of being a mere economic system is actually an elaborate socio-psychological construct that moulds human beings in a certain way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference between capitalism per se and an economic system merely involving private ownership of material wealth is, rather curiously, provided by the Hindu tale of Ganesha and Kubera. For those who may not be aware, Ganesha, typically portrayed with an elephant head and pot belly, is the lord of wealth in Hinduism, he is traditionally associated with all things related to business and commerce and is the favourite god of all traders and merchants. Kubera, is a &lt;em&gt;yaksha&lt;/em&gt;, he is a ‘lesser being’ when compared to a ‘god’, but still one among the divine. Kubera is known for his fabulous wealth and rotund figure, he is known for being a great hoarder of riches and fine things, from perfumes and food to mythical flying chariots and gold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/6/64/Ganesha_Basohli_miniature_circa_1730_Dubost_p73.jpg/472px-Ganesha_Basohli_miniature_circa_1730_Dubost_p73.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Ganesha_Basohli.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Ganesha, the Hindu god of wealth.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day, Kubera decided to host a grand feast in his opulent home to please all the gods, the intellectuals and other beings. He invited Ganesha as well. At the same time, he taunted Ganesha for living with his parents, the gods Shiva and Kali, who represent the destruction of all material reality, stating that the latter must not get well-fed in a household of literal destroyers. Ganesha accepted the invitation, and when he turned up to the feast, he ate like no other. Kubera was initially pleased to feed such an important god, but Ganesha kept on devouring the food, eating more and more and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Ganesha had consumed all that was in the kitchen, he began to eat all of Kubera’s possessions: his gold, his furniture, his home, everything. Kubera ran to lord Shiva, the destroyer of the universe and Ganesha’s father, seeking help. Shiva calmly instructed Kubera to carry with him a small pot of plain rice to the lord of wealth and to offer it up in all humility. Kubera did as told, the lord of wealth was placated. After finishing his rice, the lord of wealth asked Kubera if he had finally understood the rationale behind Ganesha’s actions, Kubera confessed he had not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/0/03/Jambhala.jpg/435px-Jambhala.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Jambhala.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Kubera, the wealthy yaksha.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ganesha explained that Kubera was a hoarder of wealth, that he saw material pleasure not as the part and parcel of life but as the end in itself, while Ganesha was the lord of wealth, he ate not to blindly chase more food but to appreciate the goodness that good food and wealth brings. Kubera’s feast, Ganesha said, was made to honour excess, and Ganesha was only seeking to illustrate the folly of believing in excess—by showing Kubera the true meaning of consuming for the sake of consuming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that it is Ganesha—the child of the destroyer god—who is the lord of wealth instead of Kubera. Being the lord of wealth means one has mastery over it, and Kubera, instead of having mastery over wealth has wealth itself as his master. And this is what capitalism is: not a mastery of wealth but of service to it, of slavery to it. It is this slavery to wealth which is making us literally consume like Ganesha consuming Kubera’s vanity feast. Corporations are prepared to destroy our whole planet in order to create products for our consumption. While we do not go killing and eating people like Patrick Bateman because of our envy of another’s slightly different business card, we do, in our desire to have more and to be recognised as having more, devour goods like sharks frenzied by chum. We’re all Kuberas today, unable to understand that it is the sumptuousness of plain rice we must cherish over the newest (and-not-at-all-upgraded) iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the story of Brahma, the creator god of Hinduism, comes in. After Brahma created the universe, he ventured to create the first woman, once he created her, he did the most egregious thing: he fell in love with her, his own daughter. He tried to chase her wherever she went, sprouting four heads to keep an eye on her in every direction. He even sprouted a fifth head when his daughter tried to jump over him to avoid his lecherous gaze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/1/13/Brahma_sarawati.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Brahma_sarawati.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Brahma, the creator god of Hinduism.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story represents what capitalism does to the human mind. The act of creating the woman involves Brahma carrying out complex fire sacrifices and reciting great hymns, much like the creation of goods in an industrialised, capitalist society involves complex contractual and credit arrangements along with the furnaces of factories and the sacrifice of the millions who contribute their labour. The fire sacrifice has a &lt;em&gt;yajaman&lt;/em&gt;, the declared officiator of the fire sacrifice, the one who must reap the benefits, in other words, the capitalist and all of society itself. Brahma’s taboo act of falling in love with his own daughter represents our love for everything capitalism has to provide. It represents our yearning to dominate and control everything by gaining full control of the material world through the means of production. Brahma’s fifth head represents our ego, our narcissistic belief in having subdued all of creation through the fire sacrifice of capitalism. It must be noted here that Kubera, i.e. the one who invited Ganesha to his feast, is a direct descendant of Brahma, very clearly implying that Brahma’s will to create and consume literally gives birth to a servitude towards wealth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parallels of Brahma’s lustful and forbidden act are drawn even more starkly in &lt;em&gt;American Psycho&lt;/em&gt;. Patrick Bateman looks at himself with great admiration when he engages in that threesome with two prostitutes, much like capitalism looks at its billboards and high rises with awe. He video records himself having sex and then proceeds to inflict very serious wounds on the women as a declaration of his might, much like the capitalist overworks and abuses the labour that gives him his profits. In killing one of the prostitutes later on, he declares his will to power, much like Brahma sprouting a fifth head, illustrating the extent to which he will go to fulfill his bloodlust and hunger for the allegorical carnal pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is after this point that the parallels between &lt;em&gt;American Psycho&lt;/em&gt; and Brahma’s story end.* American Psycho* ends with Patrick Bateman declaring that there’s no escape even when he has confessed to his crimes. In a way, it reflects the quagmire that the Marxist accuses the Liberal of being in, i.e. that the Liberal has no way to escape capitalism even if he recognises it is bad because capitalism itself animates him so fully. To the Marxist, true escape lies in the ending of capitalism itself, it lies in ending the superstructures and narratives (like private property) that sustain our reality and justify the idiotic sum of material relations, so that we may have true common ownership of wealth. And it is here that the story of Brahma arrives again to educate us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once Brahma’s fifth head grows, Shiva, the destroyer god, who is usually lost in meditation awakens. He takes the most fearsome form, called Kala Bhairav (literally ‘dark frightful creature’). Kala Bhairav rides dogs, which are unclean animals according to Hindu priests, and has great talons. It is with these talons that he hacks off Brahma’s head, which he then turns it into a cup for drinking hemp. The symbolism of this act should not be lost on anybody, Shiva here is literally beheading the human ego, dramatically forcing contemplation. In converting the head into a drinking cup, he’s reminding humans of the falsehood of capitalism that leaves them lost in an unreality of their own making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e1/Kala_Bhairava_in_the_night.JPG/425px-Kala_Bhairava_in_the_night.JPG&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Kala_Bhairava_in_the_night.jpeg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Kala Bhairav, the frightful form of Shiva.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, Shiva’s act, even if seemingly mirroring Marx’s call for the death of capitalism, is radically different from it. Marx’s dialectic materialism is, ultimately, that only, it is materialism. Marx’s philosophy, by putting economic relations or property relations as the base, stupidly puts Brahma’s fifth head as the one true thing, calling for the other four to be cut off. Marxism does not go to the very thing that drives the fire sacrifice of capitalism and the sprouting of the fifth head: the human desire to dominate material reality, the human ego which seeks to consume, create and serve wealth as an extension of itself. Shiva’s act seeks to destroy that very thing, to release the human being from his need for capitalism, to release the human being from his need to control material reality in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moment we stop conceiving capitalism as an economic theory but rather as a psychological, social and even spiritual state of society is the moment we understand what it truly is. Capitalism is an outgrowth of our very consciousness, it is an attempt at fashioning reality itself, which places the material as paramount. It represents our need to control the world around us, to subdue the elements to do our bidding, and in the process to create goods and services that will give our lives meaning and worth. But it is in the process of creating meaning that the human ego rears itself, seeing its petty creation as all that matters, when reality is much larger than we would realise. To overcome capitalism, we must destroy it at its roots which lie deep within the human psyche, we must cut off our heads, allowing a better one to take its place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*I owe my gratitude to Devdutt Pattanaik, Slavoj Zizek and Adi Shankara for this article, without their ideas and teachings I would not have even conceived of this article. *&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The morning routine scene in American Psycho is, without a doubt, ensnaring. The intricate detail with which Patrick Bateman describes the various toiletries he uses, the near-artistic manner in which he applies facemask, and the way in which he innocently cautions against using alcohol-based aftershave is hauntingly beautiful. The question is: apart from the obvious aesthetics of the scene (and Christian Bale’s perfect physique and looks), why is a bloody personal hygiene tutorial so enchanting? Is the scene so surreal that it somehow reminds us of our own reality?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Pubcast on the Indian Economy</title>
      <link href="/Pubcast-on-the-Indian-Econoomy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Pubcast on the Indian Economy" />
      <published>2019-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Pubcast-on-the-Indian-Econoomy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Pubcast-on-the-Indian-Econoomy">&lt;p&gt;The second of The Pangean’s pubcasts is with Mr Achyut Chandra, an MSME businessman engaged in the field of manufacturing printing and packaging solutions. Mr Chandra is the Chairman of the New Market Development Committee of the Federation of Corrugated Box Manufacturers’ Association of India, an umbrella organisation of box manufacturing organisations in India. He’s also the current Vice-President of the Corrugated Box Manufacturers’ Association of Eastern India and is an active member of the Bharat Chambers of Commerce. The pubcast with Mr Chandra is in two parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part I&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(0)&quot;&gt;00:00&lt;/a&gt;) - an on-ground overview of what is going wrong with the Indian economy, i.e. the current slowdown, and a brief overview of the state of the MSME sector, in particular&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part II&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(2246)&quot;&gt;37:26&lt;/a&gt;) - a vision for India’s economy, including a broad roadmap for future prosperity and for unleashing the potential of India’s small businesses&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;audio id=&quot;pubcast-2&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; controlsList=&quot;nodownload&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/Podcast2-final.mp3&quot;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    var aud = document.getElementById(&quot;pubcast-2&quot;);
    function setTime(x) {
      aud.currentTime = x;
    }

&lt;/script&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The second of The Pangean’s pubcasts is with Mr Achyut Chandra, an MSME businessman engaged in the field of manufacturing printing and packaging solutions. Mr Chandra is the Chairman of the New Market Development Committee of the Federation of Corrugated Box Manufacturers’ Association of India, an umbrella organisation of box manufacturing organisations in India. He’s also the current Vice-President of the Corrugated Box Manufacturers’ Association of Eastern India and is an active member of the Bharat Chambers of Commerce. The pubcast with Mr Chandra is in two parts: Part I (00:00) - an on-ground overview of what is going wrong with the Indian economy, i.e. the current slowdown, and a brief overview of the state of the MSME sector, in particular Part II (37:26) - a vision for India’s economy, including a broad roadmap for future prosperity and for unleashing the potential of India’s small businesses Your browser does not support the audio element.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What Feminism Ought To Be?</title>
      <link href="/What-Feminism-Ought-To-Be" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Feminism Ought To Be?" />
      <published>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-Feminism-Ought-To-Be</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-Feminism-Ought-To-Be">&lt;p&gt;There is no reason why one shouldn’t be a feminist in this day and age. Any suggestion that is contrary to the notion that women’s rights ought to be protected and that patriarchy ought to be completely dismantled is, ipso facto, foolish and thoroughly immoral. But, post the #metoo movement and torrents of online rage from ‘feminists’, one is bound to ask: is this supposed collective expression of anger against societal discrimination, sexual harrasment and patriarchal structures, well-intentioned as it may be, leading to a material change in the status of women in society? To answer that question in the affirmative seems disingenuous at best and nefarious at worst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The #metoo movement has been both shocking yet brilliant in exposing the rot beneath the veneer of equality. But has this exposition led to meaningful change? Or, for that matter, do passionate supporters of the #metoo movement really seek to bring about changes in, say, sexual harassment legislation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent seminar organised by the Calcutta High Court and American embassy in Calcutta, I was woken up to the reality of how precious little had changed with regard to America’s Civil Rights Act of 1964 or India’s Sexual Harassment of Women at Workplace (Prevention, Prohibition and Redressal) Act, 2013 in the wake of the #metoo movement. There are umpteen criticisms that can be made of both these laws, but one with regard to each should suffice to illustrate why these laws are programmed to protect the Harvey Weinsteins of our age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian Act contemplates an Internal Complaints Committee to function as a redressal mechanism for aggrieved women in a workplace of more than ten employees. The Committee does require an external member who is familiar with issues relating to sexual assault or from an organisation committed to the cause of women, but the nagging sense that this is a mechanism where the “fox is guarding the hen’s house” disturbingly remains. In the case of the American Civil Rights Act, the same ends up happening even though complaints are supposed to be filed with the external US Equal Employment Opportunity Commission. This is because of two American Supreme Court decisions in &lt;em&gt;Faragher v. City of Boca Raton&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Burlington v. Ellerth&lt;/em&gt;. While both these decisions attempted to clarify the law, they inadvertently laid down a point of law that has, in the words of &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5319966/sexual-harassment-scotus-anniversary/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; magazine, “contributed to a key reason why workplace sexual harassment lawsuits are still hard to file today”. The Supreme Court ruled in these cases that an employer may not be liable under the Civil Rights Act for sexual harassment if, inter alia, the complainant fails to take advantage of any internal mechanisms for redressal of the complaint provided by the employer. In other words, we have a situation not dissimilar to the state of the Indian law, where a potential victim of sexual harassment must reckon with the fox before she can truly reach the hen’s house. This, quite obviously, means that numerous sexual harassment claims simply go unnoticed and are, quite simply, suppressed in America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That these and other legal issues have been significant contributors to the extent of harassment and abuse exposed by the #metoo movement ought to be apparent to anyone with a brain. However, a call for reforms to such laws is hardly the defining conversation of today’s feminist movements. Indeed, one can appreciate that perhaps the nitty-gritties of legal reform cannot form part of an exoteric conversation. But one cannot deny that if feminists engaged in advocating meaningful legislative reform with half the passion that they use to ‘destroy’ incels and dudebros online, we would be living in a better world. This is not an anti-feminist rant from a privileged little boy, it is a Greta Thunbergesque (&lt;em&gt;bless her&lt;/em&gt;) “how dare you?!” to all those who claim to stand for women’s rights but are so pathetic at delivering those rights to women. Of course, it is important that society evolves to develop zero tolerance for misogynistic bigots, but to pay more attention to a hurtful tweet instead of the silent suffering of so many working women is rather dystopian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of misplaced priorities, we must address the representation of women in the workplace, and, of course, the feminist’s refusal to do anything real about it. As was pointed out by Baroness Arden of Heswall, Deputy President of the UK Supreme Court, in a guest lecture at the University of Bristol (which I had the privilege to attend), the percentage of women who were partners in London law firms in 2019, 100 years after women got the right to practice law in England, was a mere 29%. What’s more, Lady Arden stated that when she, as a Judge of the English Court of Appeal, proposed that a daycare centre be set up for women barristers near the Royal Courts of Justice, the other male Judges simply dismissed her by stating that this would be a nuisance to male barristers. That Lady Arden was a Judge of the Court of Appeal from 2000-2018 should serve to indicate that such horrendous attitudes are definitely not from some distant age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern feminist’s response to these facts and realities is not very different from the dialogues delivered by Samuel L Jackson in &lt;em&gt;Pulp Fiction&lt;/em&gt;, they are expressions of “furious anger” that seek to lay their vengeance upon men. But these responses are, to quote The Merovingian from the second &lt;em&gt;Matrix&lt;/em&gt; movie, “so boring, so obvious, so bourgeoisie.” They very simply ignore the import of Lady Arden’s arguments: that the next step towards a greater representation of women in the workplace requires some important tangible changes. For instance, one needs to ensure mandatory maternity leave as well as paternity leave is a reality in all big organisations—something that is far from being a reality in a country as developed as America. Secondly, one needs to concentrate on making daycare cheaper and more accessible to women so that the beauty of becoming a mother doesn’t end up penalising a booming career. Thirdly, one needs to change office culture and, sorry right-wing crackpots, that includes ensuring that air conditioning is not set in accordance with the metabolism of middle-aged men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, battling against the patriarchy to implement such changes sounds awfully hard, it is far easier to just obsess over cats (okay, fair enough, they are amazing) and share disgustingly bad feminist slam poetry. Why challenge patriarchs to be better and to do better when one can simply raise one’s hands and declare that they’re trash. And not to mention, how could we possibly change attitudes surrounding women without changing the colour of people’s toys. All of this is not for some comedic effect, it is to expose the Goebbellian lie that is modern feminism, a movement (if it can be called one) that concentrates less on change and more on empty expressions of supposed solidarity with the numerous problems faced by women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most dangerous effects of this is borne out by the feminist’s treatment of rape culture. Speaking logically, one would presume that the only way to destroy an oppressive social construct like rape culture is to teach people to know better. But that definitely is not what today’s feminist does. Today’s feminist hardly seeks to bat for rigorous consent classes in universities and schools. They rarely seek to educate people on understanding the humanity of women and they are loathe to contemplate on how men can be used as allies in combating rape culture. This not only fails to go to the root of the problem by dealing with the cultural rot that a priori drives men’s most problematic behaviours, it has far more nefarious effects. This misandry-is-feminism attitude of so many feminists incentivises a lot of men to simply pretend to be feminists in a bid to get sex. And it should go without saying that this is a most poisonous kind of objectification that relies on its antithesis to survive and grow. This verily means that feminists end up giving traction to a very fundamental sabotage of their own movement by refusing to actually deal with a problem and by stooping to lowly instinct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of that being said, credit must be given where credit is due, modern feminism has been very sharp in changing broader culture to simply not be accommodative of abusers and bigots. It has created a rightfully hostile environment for those who would dare say that women are lesser than men and it has clarified that sexist attitudes are simply not going to fly anymore. However, that is simply not enough. One has to go beyond a great grand shriek about how sexist and patriarchal the world is to actually contemplate upon how it could look better. And one has to understand that without such a constructive contemplation, one is going to have a world with a smokescreen of verbose activism but with a ground reality of festering oppression.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There is no reason why one shouldn’t be a feminist in this day and age. Any suggestion that is contrary to the notion that women’s rights ought to be protected and that patriarchy ought to be completely dismantled is, ipso facto, foolish and thoroughly immoral. But, post the #metoo movement and torrents of online rage from ‘feminists’, one is bound to ask: is this supposed collective expression of anger against societal discrimination, sexual harrasment and patriarchal structures, well-intentioned as it may be, leading to a material change in the status of women in society? To answer that question in the affirmative seems disingenuous at best and nefarious at worst.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Drunk Parable of The Tech Age</title>
      <link href="/Pubcast-of-the-Tech-Age" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Drunk Parable of The Tech Age" />
      <published>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Pubcast-of-the-Tech-Age</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Pubcast-of-the-Tech-Age">&lt;p&gt;The first of The Pangean’s &lt;em&gt;pubcasts&lt;/em&gt; is with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/mirandamowbray/&quot;&gt;Dr Miranda Mowbray&lt;/a&gt;, a Lecturer in Computer Science at the University of Bristol. After having graduated from the University of Cambridge and completing her PhD in Mathematics at Queen Mary University of London, Dr Mowbray gained several years of experience in industry and is now pursuing research into data science for cybersecurity, and ethics for big data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this podcast, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/harsh.tiwari/&quot;&gt;Harsh Tiwari&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/reuben.pritchard/&quot;&gt;Reuben Pritchard&lt;/a&gt; sit down with Dr Miranda Mowbray and, over lunch and a couple of pints, discuss some pressing matters surrounding the age of technology. Listen below to part 1 of the full uncut recording or skip ahead to the following topics of interest:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(0)&quot;&gt;00:00&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology as a replacement for human interaction&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(60)&quot;&gt;01:00&lt;/a&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology in business and politics&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(1203)&quot;&gt;20:03&lt;/a&gt;), or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The accessibility of technology&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot; onclick=&quot;setTime(2142)&quot;&gt;35:42&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;audio id=&quot;pubcast-1&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; controlsList=&quot;nodownload&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/Podcast1-final.mp3&quot;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    var aud = document.getElementById(&quot;pubcast-1&quot;);
    function setTime(x) {
      aud.currentTime = x;
    }

&lt;/script&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>harsh.tiwari reuben.pritchard</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The first of The Pangean’s pubcasts is with Dr Miranda Mowbray, a Lecturer in Computer Science at the University of Bristol. After having graduated from the University of Cambridge and completing her PhD in Mathematics at Queen Mary University of London, Dr Mowbray gained several years of experience in industry and is now pursuing research into data science for cybersecurity, and ethics for big data. In this podcast, Harsh Tiwari and Reuben Pritchard sit down with Dr Miranda Mowbray and, over lunch and a couple of pints, discuss some pressing matters surrounding the age of technology. Listen below to part 1 of the full uncut recording or skip ahead to the following topics of interest: Introduction (00:00), Technology as a replacement for human interaction (01:00), Technology in business and politics (20:03), or The accessibility of technology (35:42). Your browser does not support the audio element.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Indian Elections, A Hindu Zeitgeist and ‘Pattanaikism’</title>
      <link href="/The-Indian-Elections-A-Hindu-Zeitgeist-and-Pattanaikism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Indian Elections, A Hindu Zeitgeist and 'Pattanaikism'" />
      <published>2019-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Indian-Elections-A-Hindu-Zeitgeist-and-Pattanaikism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Indian-Elections-A-Hindu-Zeitgeist-and-Pattanaikism">&lt;p&gt;It is now a truism that faith divides people, engenders identities, perpetuates meaningless violence and places stupid restrictions on human behaviour. Whether it be Islamophobic attacks or the rise of the Islamic State, religion, rather than making us better human beings, can drive us towards all kinds of mindless evil. So it is no wonder that people think religion is (or ought to be) a dying institution or social phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the fight it is putting up by seeking to tie-up with politics means that it is not going away anytime soon. Nowhere is this more apparent than in the Indian general election results of 2019, which saw India’s Hindu Nationalist party being swept back into power after a fiery, divisive and communally-charged campaign. But to say that this election result is the endorsement of a militant, monolithic kind of Hinduism would be disingenuous. Hinduism is, ultimately, a complex and chaotic faith that has multiple aspects and ever-changing dialectics in every age. And the Hindu Nationalist’s victory is countered by numerous different perspectives, both correct and incorrect. These narratives serve to show us a faith that is alive, and, more importantly, learning to find a sweet spot in a modern world that may see religion as a relic of human stupidity. The zeitgeist of Hinduism today lies not in the polarising voices of Prime Minister Modi and his minions, but in the vast extent of all the different ideas that dominate Hinduism’s current cultural landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an animistic, possibly agnostic faith that was centred around animal sacrifice and elaborate fire rituals over 3,000 years ago, Hinduism has come a long way. It now has an organised chaos, in every sense of the phrase, with multiple strands of theistic and atheistic philosophies, grand epics, a notorious caste system and 330 million ‘gods’. Prima facie, one can see how the &lt;em&gt;Sanatan Dharma&lt;/em&gt; (or The Eternal Faith, as so many Hindus call it) is ever so different from Christianity, Islam or Judaism. However, given Hinduism’s openness to new ideas, an analysis of some of the broad socio-political strands currently prevailing within (and without) the faith reveals many similarities with Abrahamic religions. In fact, it is the “Hindu revivalism” championed by (what can only be called) India’s Hindu Nationalists that seems to have the strongest resemblance to Abrahamic faiths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindu Nationalist organisations, collectively known as the “&lt;em&gt;Sangh Parivar&lt;/em&gt;” (Family of Associations), which form the ideological bedrock of PM Modi’s party, explicitly subscribe to a kind of “Hindu Zionism”. They believe that, like Israel, the glue that should bind India is the idea of a Hindu motherland, where a great Temple is built (in place of an existing mosque) that is dedicated to Lord Ram. Lord Ram is a Hindu god king from the epic &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt;, and his rule is seen as the most perfect model for good governance and nation-building. Hindu Nationalists paint Lord Ram and the idea of India with brushstrokes that evidently transplant ideas from the Christian, Islamic or Israeli far right. They have major problems with the presence of another faith in their own ‘backyard’, they rely heavily on spiritual ‘gurus’ and religious leadership to spread their message, and they cling on to “older, truer” values like an opposition to the LGBTQ movement. While these groups have usually been a noisy minority with a record of some major violence like the vandalism of the mosque which allegedly stood in Lord Ram’s birthplace, they are now a formidable force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all their faults, the Hindu Nationalists have sparked a true debate on the nature of Hinduism. They have forced people to ask: What makes Hinduism ‘different’? What is the difference between the ‘right’ or ‘wrong’ kind of Hinduism? How important is it for a Hindu to not consume beef? Should Hinduism seek some level of organisation like Abrahamic faiths? Is the idea of India inextricably linked to a fundamentally “Hindu identity”? The import of these questions extends far beyond their relevance to Hindu dogma (if there is one).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although not from a strictly Hindu perspective, the political criticism of Hindu Nationalism comes from India’s broad cross-section of left-wing intellectuals and politicians. Their first major criticism being that PM Modi and his coterie of fanatic backers have perpetuated greater communal violence and intolerance. This is certainly not untrue. In a country which prides itself on having a composite culture, the recent increase in lynchings of people belonging to minority faiths is a complete and utter travesty. If there’s one thing a faith or ideology should not have is a penchant for violence. If the Hinduism of tomorrow or the India of tomorrow is run by people who resemble the Taliban, then Hinduism must rightly die as a faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, the second major criticism hurled at the Hindu Nationalist is more ideological than factual. The Indian left-wing sees Hindu Nationalism as contrary both to the idea of India and the demands of a more modern world. The idea of India put forward by the Indian Left is very significantly influenced by the ideas of Jawaharlal Nehru, India’s first Prime Minister. Nehru argues that India is a composite culture that has forever lived in harmony verily because of the immense spiritual diversity of Hinduism. Consequently, the Nehruvian vision of India dreams of a secular Indian state that stands in support of all faiths and respects all minorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are great internal flaws in these ideas. It is completely counterfactual to suggest that India has ever had true harmony in its history. The histories are replete with examples of Islamic rulers exploiting their Hindu subjects and vice versa. And it is undeniably a cheap political lie to suggest that Hinduism has, historically, been a tolerant faith that has always accepted outsiders. The history of Hinduism is plagued both by strands of profound pluralism and horrific clashes. For instance, the burning and pillaging of Buddhist monasteries has been a feature of Hinduism since the rise of the former as an alternative to a faith that thinks it’s okay (desirable, even) to label someone an ‘Untouchable’. The works of Dr B.R. Ambedkar, the architect of India’s Constitution are filled with examples of Hinduism terrorising all kinds of people―especially those who are untouchable. I fail to see how a faith that has denied ‘lower’ people the right to share clean water with some ‘higher’ people on the basis of birthright can be considered tolerant, especially when it ironically says each person possesses an immanent, infinite and transcendental soul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian left-wing seems to always ignore these truths, taking refuge instead in the apologetic argument that Hindu Nationalist ideology is a hangover from a colonial past or that it is a high caste conspiracy. While this argument makes sense in part, its implications are far more problematic. Yes, it is true that the coloniser’s view of Hinduism’s fearsome, naked goddesses and shamanic traditions drove it to embrace more Victorian trends like prudishness about sex or LGBTQ people (in the land of the &lt;em&gt;Kama Sutra&lt;/em&gt;!). But that ominously suggests that if Hinduism were rid of colonial influences then it could return to some kind of earlier purity. Quite obviously, that ignores what Hinduism was before colonisation―a religion that burned widows alive. And, moreover, it implies that cultures can reverse history, which quite clearly is impossible. Faiths today cannot rely on the smokescreen of a heyday of yesteryear to redeem themselves, they must seek to move forward, not backwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as blaming the higher castes for Hinduism’s social evils is concerned, that argument seems both malicious and futile. No one can deny that the Brahmins played an active role in engendering the dehumanising aspects of the caste system. And, of course, ex post rationalisations of caste as a division of labour are deeply troublesome. But to confuse fighting against the caste system with fighting against the Brahmins entails a society that is fraught with acrimonious divisions. Nowhere is this truer than in South India, where movements led by the late thinker Periyar have created an environment that is hostile to Brahmins–leading to a slow death of their culture. The Left’s view of the caste system as a symptom of Brahmin hegemony, rather than the other way around, blames a group of people following Hinduism over the religion itself―which is the source of this rot. Instead of finding positive solutions it only presents arguments on whom to blame, making it extremely unhelpful to those who actually require emancipation and empowerment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidently, the back and forth between India’s Hindu Right and Secular Left seems very poor in providing either a vision of Hinduism that is ready for a modern age or an idea of India that is historically accurate. While one side sees Hinduism as the be-all and end-all of 1.3 billion people, the other trivialises it by white-washing the faith to provide a rather deceptive vision. The Hindu Indian voter in the 2019 election was forced to stand between a rock and a hard place. And the predicament of the Indian voter reveals the confusion that animates all of society today in regards to religion. The Hindu may have chosen the Hindu Nationalists, but they did so only because the other parties didn’t really give two hoots about their faith, which obviously defines their identity. Like the American Evangelical, the Hindu voter knows that Modi, like Trump, doesn’t actually care about faith and god. After all, to the Hindu Nationalist, Lord Ram isn’t a god who provides deep spiritual enhancement, he’s a political tool. To the Indian Secularist, Hinduism is only relevant or important in so far as it helps their idea of India. All movements that seem to use religion for politics, seem to do verily that, use it for politics. And to think the Hindu Indian voter doesn’t know that, or that he’s going to let the Hindu Nationalist define his faith post this election victory reeks of naivety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for the Hindu Indian voter, a new, more philosophical movement seems emergent amidst all of these political debates. While no movement of this kind is attributable to a single person, this “new age Hinduism” does have an unofficial leader: Devdutt Pattanaik. Pattanaik has written over forty books and hundreds of columns on Hinduism and has been a management consultant to many large corporates―where he has ingeniously combined mythology to put forth &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/I7QwxbImhZI&quot;&gt;new ideas&lt;/a&gt; on management. His writings provide both scathing critiques and poignant praise of all that is found in Hinduism, unravelling how the mythology of Indian culture shapes its people. Most radically, the Pattanaikist worldview &lt;a href=&quot;https://mumbaimirror.indiatimes.com/others/sunday-read/defining-hinduism/articleshow/60897762.cms&quot;&gt;shatters&lt;/a&gt; the illusion that Hinduism can provide any singular answer to what it is and what it should be. Instead, it suggests that Hinduism is truly about embracing the diversity of opinions it allows and accepting that the Eternal Faith is so because &lt;a href=&quot;https://devdutt.com/articles/applied-mythology/society/who-is-a-hindu-hinduisms-diy-kit.html&quot;&gt;nothing in it is eternally true&lt;/a&gt;. Pattanaik illustrates this by contrasting the two versions of the same god Vishnu in his books &lt;em&gt;Sita&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Jaya&lt;/em&gt;, which are his takes on the Hindu epics the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Mahabharata&lt;/em&gt;. In one age, Vishnu, the preserver of &lt;em&gt;Dharma&lt;/em&gt; (that which is right) is Lord Ram, who is the perfect man because he upholds social rules, no matter how distasteful they are. While, in another age, Vishnu is Lord Krishna, who is the perfect man because he upholds what is right by disregarding social rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although not readily apparent, Pattanaik’s philosophy has certain very optimistic implications for the plight of the Hindu post the 2019 Indian general elections. Firstly, it serves to remind the Hindu that his faith is richer than shibboleths like beef bans and Ram Temples. Of course, this doesn’t mean that the Pattnaikist view provides any political clarion call against India’s Hindu Nationalists. Rather, it does something far more impactful: it brings the devoted Hindu a way of psychologically divorcing his faith from those who would claim a monopoly on it in the name of nationalism or politics. The Hindu, being enlightened by the multilayered and complex nature of his religion, is able to rise above the politics of the Hindu Nationalist to worship Lord Ram for who he is: a perfect god, instead of some pithy political totem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the Pattanaik worldview, quite counterintuitively, provides what I think is a truer understanding of Hinduism and its place in the “idea of India”. It recognises where Hinduism must change to fit a secular Indian society while continuing to grow. Instead of the Indian Left’s apologetic or misleading narratives, Pattanaik provides a very positive but limited argument. And unlike the Hindu Nationalist’s strident dogmatism, his view entails a very comforting kind of ambiguity. Pattanaik writes in in the Introduction to Jaya: “Within infinite lies, lies a truth. Who sees it all? Varuna [the god of the waters] has but a thousand eyes, Indra [the god of rain], a hundred, you and I, only two.” The liberating quality of this short mantra cannot be emphasised enough, stemming from the depths of Upanishadic Hindu philosophy. It reminds Hindus and, more broadly, Indians that it is difficult to always see the truth. So, to blame anyone for what we consider different, or misguided, or, perhaps, plain wrong is rather hypocritical. This means that Hindus and India must learn, as part of kind of national introspection, to not only tolerate differences, but to accept them as alternative truths one may not be able to fully see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this doesn’t mean that Hinduism ought to be a ‘lolbertarian’ religion. But it does mean that Hinduism in the age of Kali must learn to live with other religions and with the variations in its own nature. And that applies, contrary to Popperian ‘mythologies’, even if it is found that there is a view that opposes that very truth―as Hindu Nationalism ostensibly does. To put it in Pattanaik’s own &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/sNCpWECSGR4&quot;&gt;words&lt;/a&gt;, “Everybody has beliefs, and most beliefs are stupid”, and that clearly means no one is really in the position to evaluate if another’s belief is based on falsehoods or not. We are simply not that wise. A Hindu by definition is supposed to believe that he has not the moral or epistemic authority to disrespect anyone’s views. And that makes for an undeniably marvellous faith that is willing to coexist with others, with more than just tolerance, even if there is disagreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideas of Pattanaik and their growing popularity offer respite to anyone who thinks this Indian election has set Hinduism on a course towards fanaticism. It provides a template for how religions, by having both a healthy measure of empathy towards all those who ‘twist’ its tenets and trivialise its significance, can survive in a modern world. Religions have lost much due to their inability to adapt and put forward a zeitgeist that is brimming with new ideas. Pattanaik’s view gives us a Hinduism whose true zeitgeist today, far from being restricted to Modi’s Lotus flags (even if inclusive of it), is animated by a hotbed of new ideas. And all these ideas are rising up to the challenge of making the Hindu life more meaningful and enriching at a very interesting time. Pattanaik’s view of Hinduism gives us more than a reason to believe that Hinduism shall continue to be rich and complex, it tells us why that’s a very good thing.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is now a truism that faith divides people, engenders identities, perpetuates meaningless violence and places stupid restrictions on human behaviour. Whether it be Islamophobic attacks or the rise of the Islamic State, religion, rather than making us better human beings, can drive us towards all kinds of mindless evil. So it is no wonder that people think religion is (or ought to be) a dying institution or social phenomenon.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">There is No Going Back on Brexit</title>
      <link href="/No-Going-Back" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="There is No Going Back on Brexit" />
      <published>2019-03-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/No-Going-Back</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/No-Going-Back">&lt;p&gt;Dear Bremainers,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Julius Caesar crossed the Rubicon with his armies, in defiance of the Senate and to start a civil war against Pompey, he is supposed to have said: “Alea Iacta Est” or “The die is cast”. Of course, politicians like Nigel Farage or Boris Johnson or Jacob Rees-Mogg (despite his Latin) are far from being Caesar, but they may have led Britain on a path of no return. British Prime Minister Theresa May’s consistent ability to disappoint but not surprise, whether it be in negotiating a deal with the EU, getting Brexit legislation through Parliament, or actually holding on to office, has destroyed all the fantasies Brexiteers sold and upheld all the nightmares Bremainers dreaded. So much so, that a petition to effectively stop Brexit has reportedly reached three million signatures whilst hilariously causing the government website to crash too! The big question is: should Britain really implement that referendum vote, especially after seeing the absolute chimera that has already emerged? Or has the die truly been cast?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arguments made by those in favour of this petition or those demanding a second referendum are very compelling: The Irish border issue is simply too complicated to be resolvable after two years of worthless back-and-forth. Even notional agreement on a future relationship with the EU is hard to find, whether in Parliament or in government. The consequences of a no-deal Brexit will be severe and, with a weak government, it is bound to be more so. Clearly, staying on or asking the people again seem to be the least worst ways out of this mess. Moreover, Parliament is not technically bound by the referendum results. It is a Sovereign institution, as the UK Supreme Court so recently affirmed in the Miller case, and it can certainly choose to not make an Act of Parliament to implement Brexit plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as a patriotic foreign national having lived in this wet, grim, sad yet hauntingly beautiful country, I find this defeatist attitude hard to accept. Britain was once an Empire on which the sun never set, it was the country that ruled mine. This country has survived two World Wars and assisted in unleashing hell on Iraq and Afghanistan (read the Chilcot Report), it has a history of being aggressive and not backing down from a fight. So, sure, I may smile a little when I see its ignominious decline, but as someone who can’t help but love this country, I feel saddened too. How can Britain’s Parliament, which has been described as the “Mother of all Parliaments” ever seek to ignore the results of a referendum? How can a country that was once ready to find “Victory! Victory, at all costs” at the bidding of a drunk now find itself so easily losing? Have things really gotten so out of hand that even democracy finds itself being questioned?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the British Parliament can certainly accept the demands of those who want another referendum or those who want Brexit stopped altogether, it would completely violate the ethos of what can be called Britain’s Constitution. Britain’s Constitution is ultimately political, it rests on tradition and time-tested conventions, and not on “Constitutional Acts” or the opinions of judges. The British Constitution reveals its core tenets through rituals and crowns and maces. It shows its fundamentally democratic nature through peculiar rituals like the House of Commons closing the door on the Black Rod’s face, when he (an official of the House of Lords) approaches the Commons to invite them for the Queen’s Speech every year at the first sitting of Parliament. Britain’s Constitution, in some senses, is an evolving agreement between its aristocracy and masses, from the Magna Carta, to the Petition of Right 1628, to the Bill of Rights 1688, and to the European Union Act 2011―which requires all big EU decisions to be put to a referendum. It is these ‘agreements’ that ensure the replacement of imperial authority with the rule of law and it is these agreements which ensure that Parliament simply does not “make or unmake any law whatever”. Through its age-old traditions and expensive rituals, the British Constitution ensures that the voice of the people is never ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, one may contend here, and do so not in futility, that the people spoke in favour of Brexit due to severe misinformation and propaganda, (arguably) electoral malpractice and racism. One may also say that ignoring the 48% would be undemocratic too. But all of this simply ignores something very important about democracy: it is not supposed to give us the right answer all the time.Vox Populi Vox Dei (the voice of the people is the voice of God) does not mean God gets it right all the time, otherwise he would have made Eden snake-proof and without the Tree of Knowledge. But the fact still remains that when God commands you leave Eden (and the EU is far from Eden), you have to leave Eden. The nature of democracy is such that a popular vote on something can very well lead to bad decision-making. But one can do very little about that, this is a systemic flaw of democracy itself. One can seek to prevent misinformation or hateful propaganda before people step into the ballot box, but once the votes are counted and sorted according to all legal strictures, and the results declared, Caesar’s horse crosses the Rubicon. To try and go back is to threaten the ‘agreement’ on which British Constitutional Democracy rests, it is to say democracy shall only be sacrosanct when it is ‘right’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spirit of the EU Act 2011 was to ensure the public had the ultimate say in matters that majorly concerned the European Union. While it did not mandate Parliament be bound by what the public said, it seems nonsensical to assume it wanted umpteen referendums conducted in futility till the time those in power had the results they think they wanted. The EU Act does not imply anywhere that referendum results can ever be trivialised. Democracy has to be upheld. The referendum result has to be accepted. Britain has to leave the EU. Or else, it will tear itself apart, with chaos and anarchy―exactly the way in which it would fall apart in the event of no-deal. Those seeking to sabotage Brexit now will find themselves going from the frying pan and into the fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A student whose country fought the British in order to have democracy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Dear Bremainers,</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Be a Man: a Discourse on 21st Century Masculinity</title>
      <link href="/Be-a-Man" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Be a Man: a Discourse on 21st Century Masculinity" />
      <published>2019-03-14T01:45:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-14T01:45:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Be-a-Man</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Be-a-Man">&lt;p&gt;The Gillette Advert has, for reasons I do not fully understand, caused a
sensation. There are people who are praising it for sending out the right
message on toxic masculinity, and there are people condemning it vociferously
for portraying masculinity as inherently evil. The fact, however, is that an
advert really matters little—they are ultimately paid promotions of products,
not vehicles of social change, and the people who are quick to heap praise or
criticism on it (especially in this case) are either pretentious or simply
b*tthurt. Yet, even in what I consider to be an overreaction about a simple
advert on shaving products, there’s a deeper discussion that is going on. For
more than a couple of thousand years, men across the world have been told that
they are stronger, better and smarter; it has been their job to be responsible
for ‘their’ women and ‘their’ children; it has been their duty to die first in
battle and it has been their job to take charge without shedding a tear and
without ever doubting oneself. But now, in these feminist times, assumptions
about masculinity are not only being challenged but also being designated as
evil—and for a good reason. But with all of this change, masculinity is being
radically redefined. The question is &lt;em&gt;what should it be redefined into?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One has to appreciate the difficulty of this question to even begin to answer
it. There are so many issues, from the plain-fact biological to the unwittingly
socio-cultural, that one does not know what to address first. This means all
thoughts about what masculinity ought to be cannot be discussed in the abstract, for we
simply do not know what the source of masculinity as a social or perhaps natural
construct really is. All we can try to do is pragmatically accept its existence
and move on to see how we can mould it to suit our times—in both a moral and
philosophical sense. And that again reinforces the fact that instead of some
grand theory of what it &lt;em&gt;must mean to be a man&lt;/em&gt;, we must develop more specific
guidelines on what it &lt;em&gt;should mean to be a man&lt;/em&gt;.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fairly good place to begin would be in the surprisingly simple but
controversial question of who should pay for a date between heterosexual
couples. One can easily see why “old-world masculinity” would always make the
man pay: Men were supposed to have the financial resources which they would use
to ‘woo’ women. With women possessing little financial independence (or any
independence, really), and depending on men for nearly everything material, men
paying for dates made sense—even if it was due to unjust laws and the fantasies
of the patriarchy with regard to its own benevolence. But all of that has
changed now and women are (at least on paper) not denied basic rights like the
one to property, a voice and to work. So, the idea that men should have an
obligation to pay for food and alcohol as a projection of their ability to give
a damn when seeing someone seems morally bankrupt, not to mention unfair as
well. Yet, a change of the rules to equal sharing seems ham-handed. It does not
take into account that sometimes people are feeling rich or bound to old-school
values for no discernible reason. More importantly, it simply denies agency to
people, instead of letting them negotiate it with each other. A better kind of
masculinity that truly involves an end to male presumptions of power and
responsibility cannot simply say: &lt;em&gt;Thou shalt split the bill for thou art equal&lt;/em&gt;.
That is only a sign of compromising pride; it is a technical solution to a
psychological problem. The rules on dating must be an expression of true
cooperation, and they can only begin to be so when people recognise that
independent, equal individuals decide matters among themselves. To say that
people must split the bill all the time is to mould a masculinity that need not
actually listen or cooperate, for it feels that there is a simple rule in place.
But to say: there are no rules, you must exercise self-respect and empathy when
negotiating who pays, re-enforces a most important aspect of what modern
masculinity should be. It symbolises an attempt to outgrow the need for the
patriarchy itself as a balm to one’s self-esteem. A contextualised, no
overarching rules approach encourages real interaction, it forces both men and
women to actually ask the question of what is fair when two people, equal in
dignity, decide to strike a settlement for mutual benefit.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masculinity is undeniably linked to &lt;em&gt;how good men feel about themselves&lt;/em&gt;. I don’t
know if there is something biological to it or if it is purely cultural, but the
male to female ratio of suicides is proof to me that men not feeling good about
themselves has some serious consequences. Many people identify the root of this
problem to be toxic masculinity, but that only addresses the surface of the
issue. Of course, a man being forced to bottle all emotion save aggression is
bound to be attracted to suicide in the face of life’s sh*t. But conversely,
without a feeling of independence and strength in the face of one’s fears,
they’re not bound to feel very good about themselves either. The old patriarchal
notion of masculinity is not entirely wrong in wanting men to weather things
stoically. It is simply important for both men and women to try and take control
of their lives when in crisis, rather than near-constantly crying about it. The
only thing a new masculinity needs to do is stop emasculating an expression of
emotion, whilst certainly rewarding personal fortitude and the ability to
skilfully (and quietly) manage one’s misery. Without this positive change,
masculinity risks either being dependent on the fragile male ego of being ‘hard’
or being a source of emotional release that does not provide courage. This new
notion of male self-belief tells us that boys should cry, that they should not
be unwilling to admit to sadness and dejection. However, it cautions us that
crying should not replace men’s self-worth by perpetuating avoidance and
self-doubt. In other words, modern masculinity must give men a better way to
cry: it must tell them they must be “man enough” to be able to do so, and “man
enough” to be able to overcome the urge to only do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the crying bit set aside, the more difficult questions put forward by the
&lt;em&gt;#metoo&lt;/em&gt; movement need to be addressed. It is clear that old-world masculinity
has either failed to deal with an oppressive culture in the workplace or in
enforcing rules of consent. The problem is obvious: the patriarchy does make
women objects. But that misses the forest for the trees, for it does not ask the
difficult question of &lt;em&gt;why society decided to have the patriarchy in the first
place&lt;/em&gt;. I would contend the answer to that question is tantalisingly simple. As
Devdutt Pattanaik, a popular Indian mythologist contends, human beings have “the
patriarchy” verily because nature doesn’t consider males to be that important.
In nature, all that a whole pride of lionesses requires is one (perhaps two)
male lions to produce the next generation of cubs. Human society is entirely
different, even if it has polygamy or polyandry, it tries to value every virile
male as a prospective husband or partner for his ability to care for and produce
human offspring. Practically speaking, this translates into the notion of the
patriarchy, where a literal race for being an alpha male is replaced with the
notion that every male who can find a female(s) has rights and obligations in
relation to that female—which other males are restricted from having. This
creates some kind of social order, but it makes men, whether fathers, brothers,
husbands or lovers, believe that they can (and must) control what happens to the
females associated with them. And this leads to the inevitable manifestation of
the patriarchy that the #metoo movement has so clearly exposed. Men will (if
they choose) assert what they consider “sexual rights” over the women who are
associated with them because they believe their association with them, whether
at the workplace or inside a marriage, gives them that right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cultural paradigm so described is the source of all problems discussed in
the previous paragraphs, it is this fundamental insecurity of not being an alpha
male that leads to men wanting to own, protect and control the women they have
around them. They have to do so, there must be rules that enforce so, otherwise
all of us ‘inadequate’ men will be naturally selected out. We must ensure “our
property” understands who they belong to, whether it be through non-disclosure
agreements or entertaining our putrid pick-up lines at the workplace. One can
combat the patriarchy as a construct, but that hardly addresses the fragile male
ego that underpins this socio-cultural construct. To combat that, men need to be
told that their honour and their power doesn’t reside in their control of the
women around them. Men need to be reminded that it is okay if they feel
inadequate, that they must never seek subjugation of women (or anyone) as a
therapy for low self-esteem and an absurd “will to power”. How does one
crystallise that abstract notion in a practical context? Simple: to quote a
friend, we must remind men that &lt;em&gt;“life is an embarrassment, and we’re going to
die anyway”&lt;/em&gt;. So, if we find ourselves being unable to get the women we want, it
really matters little. The fundamental mortality and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Understanding-the-Absurdity-of-Life&quot;&gt;absurdity of life&lt;/a&gt; mean that
our need to define our self-worth through our power over women (or anything) is
futile—for we’re already inadequate, to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, that is the existential reality that stares at us men every time we
discuss what it means to be a man. We men already realise, deep down, that we
are pathetically inadequate. If we weren’t, we wouldn’t have to construct so
many fallacies to make ourselves feel better, whether they be rules that project
our wealth, rules on not crying, or rules that state: “boys will be boys”.
My conception of masculinity expresses a core desire to do away with all those
stupid rules that are completely unfit for a most egalitarian age. A new kind of
masculinity must rely on fostering an inner strength that lets men outgrow our
base fears. Self-esteem, in any moral or philosophical sense, cannot come from
the outside; it cannot come from protecting or subjugating others. Self-esteem
or the belief in oneself must be exuded, it must be a source of impregnable
strength from within. A modern definition of masculinity must reflect this deep
truth, it must seek to give men the ability to outgrow their weaknesses (and,
therefore, the patriarchy) and to embrace a more complete personality that is a
result of true internal self-belief.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Gillette Advert has, for reasons I do not fully understand, caused a sensation. There are people who are praising it for sending out the right message on toxic masculinity, and there are people condemning it vociferously for portraying masculinity as inherently evil. The fact, however, is that an advert really matters little—they are ultimately paid promotions of products, not vehicles of social change, and the people who are quick to heap praise or criticism on it (especially in this case) are either pretentious or simply b*tthurt. Yet, even in what I consider to be an overreaction about a simple advert on shaving products, there’s a deeper discussion that is going on. For more than a couple of thousand years, men across the world have been told that they are stronger, better and smarter; it has been their job to be responsible for ‘their’ women and ‘their’ children; it has been their duty to die first in battle and it has been their job to take charge without shedding a tear and without ever doubting oneself. But now, in these feminist times, assumptions about masculinity are not only being challenged but also being designated as evil—and for a good reason. But with all of this change, masculinity is being radically redefined. The question is what should it be redefined into? One has to appreciate the difficulty of this question to even begin to answer it. There are so many issues, from the plain-fact biological to the unwittingly socio-cultural, that one does not know what to address first. This means all thoughts about what masculinity ought to be cannot be discussed in the abstract, for we simply do not know what the source of masculinity as a social or perhaps natural construct really is. All we can try to do is pragmatically accept its existence and move on to see how we can mould it to suit our times—in both a moral and philosophical sense. And that again reinforces the fact that instead of some grand theory of what it must mean to be a man, we must develop more specific guidelines on what it should mean to be a man.    A fairly good place to begin would be in the surprisingly simple but controversial question of who should pay for a date between heterosexual couples. One can easily see why “old-world masculinity” would always make the man pay: Men were supposed to have the financial resources which they would use to ‘woo’ women. With women possessing little financial independence (or any independence, really), and depending on men for nearly everything material, men paying for dates made sense—even if it was due to unjust laws and the fantasies of the patriarchy with regard to its own benevolence. But all of that has changed now and women are (at least on paper) not denied basic rights like the one to property, a voice and to work. So, the idea that men should have an obligation to pay for food and alcohol as a projection of their ability to give a damn when seeing someone seems morally bankrupt, not to mention unfair as well. Yet, a change of the rules to equal sharing seems ham-handed. It does not take into account that sometimes people are feeling rich or bound to old-school values for no discernible reason. More importantly, it simply denies agency to people, instead of letting them negotiate it with each other. A better kind of masculinity that truly involves an end to male presumptions of power and responsibility cannot simply say: Thou shalt split the bill for thou art equal. That is only a sign of compromising pride; it is a technical solution to a psychological problem. The rules on dating must be an expression of true cooperation, and they can only begin to be so when people recognise that independent, equal individuals decide matters among themselves. To say that people must split the bill all the time is to mould a masculinity that need not actually listen or cooperate, for it feels that there is a simple rule in place. But to say: there are no rules, you must exercise self-respect and empathy when negotiating who pays, re-enforces a most important aspect of what modern masculinity should be. It symbolises an attempt to outgrow the need for the patriarchy itself as a balm to one’s self-esteem. A contextualised, no overarching rules approach encourages real interaction, it forces both men and women to actually ask the question of what is fair when two people, equal in dignity, decide to strike a settlement for mutual benefit.      Masculinity is undeniably linked to how good men feel about themselves. I don’t know if there is something biological to it or if it is purely cultural, but the male to female ratio of suicides is proof to me that men not feeling good about themselves has some serious consequences. Many people identify the root of this problem to be toxic masculinity, but that only addresses the surface of the issue. Of course, a man being forced to bottle all emotion save aggression is bound to be attracted to suicide in the face of life’s sh*t. But conversely, without a feeling of independence and strength in the face of one’s fears, they’re not bound to feel very good about themselves either. The old patriarchal notion of masculinity is not entirely wrong in wanting men to weather things stoically. It is simply important for both men and women to try and take control of their lives when in crisis, rather than near-constantly crying about it. The only thing a new masculinity needs to do is stop emasculating an expression of emotion, whilst certainly rewarding personal fortitude and the ability to skilfully (and quietly) manage one’s misery. Without this positive change, masculinity risks either being dependent on the fragile male ego of being ‘hard’ or being a source of emotional release that does not provide courage. This new notion of male self-belief tells us that boys should cry, that they should not be unwilling to admit to sadness and dejection. However, it cautions us that crying should not replace men’s self-worth by perpetuating avoidance and self-doubt. In other words, modern masculinity must give men a better way to cry: it must tell them they must be “man enough” to be able to do so, and “man enough” to be able to overcome the urge to only do so. With the crying bit set aside, the more difficult questions put forward by the #metoo movement need to be addressed. It is clear that old-world masculinity has either failed to deal with an oppressive culture in the workplace or in enforcing rules of consent. The problem is obvious: the patriarchy does make women objects. But that misses the forest for the trees, for it does not ask the difficult question of why society decided to have the patriarchy in the first place. I would contend the answer to that question is tantalisingly simple. As Devdutt Pattanaik, a popular Indian mythologist contends, human beings have “the patriarchy” verily because nature doesn’t consider males to be that important. In nature, all that a whole pride of lionesses requires is one (perhaps two) male lions to produce the next generation of cubs. Human society is entirely different, even if it has polygamy or polyandry, it tries to value every virile male as a prospective husband or partner for his ability to care for and produce human offspring. Practically speaking, this translates into the notion of the patriarchy, where a literal race for being an alpha male is replaced with the notion that every male who can find a female(s) has rights and obligations in relation to that female—which other males are restricted from having. This creates some kind of social order, but it makes men, whether fathers, brothers, husbands or lovers, believe that they can (and must) control what happens to the females associated with them. And this leads to the inevitable manifestation of the patriarchy that the #metoo movement has so clearly exposed. Men will (if they choose) assert what they consider “sexual rights” over the women who are associated with them because they believe their association with them, whether at the workplace or inside a marriage, gives them that right. The cultural paradigm so described is the source of all problems discussed in the previous paragraphs, it is this fundamental insecurity of not being an alpha male that leads to men wanting to own, protect and control the women they have around them. They have to do so, there must be rules that enforce so, otherwise all of us ‘inadequate’ men will be naturally selected out. We must ensure “our property” understands who they belong to, whether it be through non-disclosure agreements or entertaining our putrid pick-up lines at the workplace. One can combat the patriarchy as a construct, but that hardly addresses the fragile male ego that underpins this socio-cultural construct. To combat that, men need to be told that their honour and their power doesn’t reside in their control of the women around them. Men need to be reminded that it is okay if they feel inadequate, that they must never seek subjugation of women (or anyone) as a therapy for low self-esteem and an absurd “will to power”. How does one crystallise that abstract notion in a practical context? Simple: to quote a friend, we must remind men that “life is an embarrassment, and we’re going to die anyway”. So, if we find ourselves being unable to get the women we want, it really matters little. The fundamental mortality and absurdity of life mean that our need to define our self-worth through our power over women (or anything) is futile—for we’re already inadequate, to begin with. In fact, that is the existential reality that stares at us men every time we discuss what it means to be a man. We men already realise, deep down, that we are pathetically inadequate. If we weren’t, we wouldn’t have to construct so many fallacies to make ourselves feel better, whether they be rules that project our wealth, rules on not crying, or rules that state: “boys will be boys”. My conception of masculinity expresses a core desire to do away with all those stupid rules that are completely unfit for a most egalitarian age. A new kind of masculinity must rely on fostering an inner strength that lets men outgrow our base fears. Self-esteem, in any moral or philosophical sense, cannot come from the outside; it cannot come from protecting or subjugating others. Self-esteem or the belief in oneself must be exuded, it must be a source of impregnable strength from within. A modern definition of masculinity must reflect this deep truth, it must seek to give men the ability to outgrow their weaknesses (and, therefore, the patriarchy) and to embrace a more complete personality that is a result of true internal self-belief.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why ‘Hindutva’ Should be a Good Word</title>
      <link href="/Why-Hindutva-Should-be-a-Good-Word" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why 'Hindutva’ Should be a Good Word" />
      <published>2019-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-Hindutva-Should-be-a-Good-Word</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-Hindutva-Should-be-a-Good-Word">&lt;p&gt;The term ‘Hindutva’ has a bad reputation and not without good reason. A most unholy concoction of unscientific claims by right-wing leaders, mob lynchings, casteism and communal hatred has come to define Hindutva. The term has become so contemptible, especially to the well-educated and well-to-do of Indian society, that anyone who has slightly Hindutvavadi inclinations is automatically branded a ‘Bigoted Bhakt’ or ‘Sanghi’. This is, however, a sad state-of-affairs, for a political ideology like ‘Hindutva’ can be so much more than ‘Mandir Wahin Banayenge’. This article is an attempt at defining (not revising) Hindutva. It is our attempt at showing the world that Hindutva can be a profoundly positive contributor to our lives and to the life of this diverse and great nation called India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindutva as a political ideology manifests the ‘Hinduness’ of the Indian people. On a primitive level, Hindutva means the ‘Inherent Hinduness’  of all Indian people. Savarkar, who coined the term Hindutva, was an atheist himself and defined Hindutva in a strictly geographical and cultural sense. The word ‘Hindu’ comes from ‘Indus’ (the river around which we started off as a civilization) and the common bond which all Indians inherently share is hence called ‘Hindutva’. Simply put, any person born within the boundaries of the subcontinent is a Hindu and his inherent ‘Bharatiyata’ is called Hindutva.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This definition of Hindutva is, historically, the only true answer for Indians to the question “Who are we?” All other answers divided Indians into different religions, castes, regions and even races. In fact, the Hindu Code Bill defined a Hindu as someone who is “NOT a Christian, Jew, Parsi or Muslim”! Clearly, we need this ‘Bharatiya’ definition of Hindutva to have a true, positive consciousness of our identity as an extremely diverse nation. Socially, the concept of Hindutva, or there being a certain kind of Hinduness which we inherit from the fact of us being born in this holy land looks beyond divisions of caste and religion to unify the Indian masses. It brilliantly distinguishes Indians from the rest of the world. An American does not start possessing Hindutva if he converts to Hinduism (Sorry David Frawley). But an Indian Muslim has an inherent Hindutva and is very distinct from an Arabic or South-east Asian Muslim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not fashioning an artificial answer here on the question of Indian identity based only in geography. Instead, we are verily identifying the common culture and syncretic tradition that exists only within that geography. The Hindutva we speak of is not simply due to the happenstance of people living in a piece of land, it’s due to the overarching unity among diversity they have developed, the story they have told themselves. This Hindutva is manifested in the numerous public holidays of Eid, Christmas and Diwali we Indians enjoy together― whether we are Hindu, Christian, or Muslim. It is found in the consistent requests for Biryani by Hindus to their Muslim friends. From the Rig Veda’s declaration (RV 1.164.46) that “Indra, Mitra, Varuna, Agni…The wise speak of what is One in many ways” to Kabir’s elegant verses on religious unity, Hindutva is about the rich cultural inheritance of all Indians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first key aspect of Hindutva is the fact that we have overcome so many foibles and problems, skirmishes and conflicts to emerge as one nation. Yes, there was once a time we officially designated people as ‘untouchable’ but still, our Constitution was written by a ‘Dalit’ man. Yes, Mahmud Ghazni plundered the Somnath Temple 17 times, but Ghalib’s verses would be non-existent without Muslims. It is through the schisms between us that we have developed this complex and unique identity. We have been through multiple disagreements on grounds of caste, faith, state and language. And in overcoming them we have discovered our underlying unity. Therefore, the first theme of Hindutva involves a sense of Indian pride, a feeling of common triumph of having risen above so many conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second aspect of Hindutva is religion, or rather the peculiar part it plays in making us so distinct. Religion is very strongly present in India’s public life, from the raucous dispute surrounding the Babri Masjid to the controversy on beef and mob lynchings. However, even if religion is a cause of conflict in India, it is undeniably the bedrock of its cultural identity too. Without Hinduism and its multiple gods, esoteric texts and ancient hymns, India is unimaginable. Without the Buddha its culture is barren; and without an Indian version of Islam, there would be no Sufism, no qawwalis. Faith is a wonderful thing in India that makes us separate from the barren West. In the West, as Nietzsche states (in The Gay Science), “God is dead, he remains dead, and [they] have killed him”. In India, the ‘Samudra Manthan’ of religions yields the nectar of meaning, whether it be in the form of Khwajaji’s sermons, Adi Shankara’s works, or Lalan Fakir’s songs, all we need to do is share it equally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third historical aspect of Hindutva explains how our unity exists through our diversity, and not despite it. We Indians may have had our problems, but just like a big Indian joint family, we are one. Hindutva ideologues like Golwalkar (in his Bunch of Thoughts) and Deendayal Upadhyaya (in his Integral Humanism) have time and again emphasised how Hindutva is broader than Hinduism because Indians following ‘Avaidik’ Dharmas like Sikhism, Jainism, Buddhism and even religions like Islam and Christianity have Hindutva in them. The reason for that is cultural intermingling. Arjuna’s marriage to Naga princess Ulupi and Manipuri princess Chitrangada in The Mahabharata is a classical and literary example of how we Indians cherish a mixing of traditions in our rich mythology. Even the Indian Supreme Court noted in 1995 that Hindutva is a way of life (and a ‘state of mind’). This way of life has been accepting of all people (both the oppressed and the oppressors), and even ‘foreign-origin’ rulers like the towering Mughal Emperor Akbar have patronised this way of life that epitomises a unity that stems from diversity. While the Parsis immigrated to both China and India, it was the latter where they finally found refuge in. The Jews have thanked us enough for being the only country without an instance of anti-Semitism. In fact, the Jewish quarters of Kochi stand right next to the Palace of the King of Kochi. The Hindu philosophical idea of every creature being a part of the Supreme Brahman (irrespective of his faith) has made us an all-welcoming people. And the word Hindutva embodies that openness of mind ever so poignantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line of this article is to tell the reader to embrace Hindutva. Why? Because Hindutva is India’s gift to the world. It was Hindutva which ‘Indianized’ parts of Iran, Afghanistan, Tibet, South-East Asia and even Japan. Thailand’s erstwhile capital is named Ayutthaya, after Lord Ram’s capital Ayodhya. What makes India stand out is not its history, its philosophy or its many religions, but an optimum combination  of all three. Once upon a time, European merchants wanted to trade with us, hence the mad pursuits by Columbus and Vasco Da Gama to ‘discover’ the magical land called India. But what do we find today? Growing westernization and inferiority complex amongst Indians! The same India which was a shining example of an ideal country to the world is now restyling itself based on western ‘isms’ like Capitalism and Socialism. This cannot happen. Hindutva is India’s ‘Soft Power’. All Indians have to be proud of Hindutva, for we can’t expect the world to respect us if we don’t respect ‘who we are’. Unless India becomes ‘Indianized’ again, ‘Superpower 2020’ (realistically speaking, ‘Superpower 2050’), will remain a distant dream.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>harsh.tiwari tushar.singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      
        <category term="trending" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The term ‘Hindutva’ has a bad reputation and not without good reason. A most unholy concoction of unscientific claims by right-wing leaders, mob lynchings, casteism and communal hatred has come to define Hindutva. The term has become so contemptible, especially to the well-educated and well-to-do of Indian society, that anyone who has slightly Hindutvavadi inclinations is automatically branded a ‘Bigoted Bhakt’ or ‘Sanghi’. This is, however, a sad state-of-affairs, for a political ideology like ‘Hindutva’ can be so much more than ‘Mandir Wahin Banayenge’. This article is an attempt at defining (not revising) Hindutva. It is our attempt at showing the world that Hindutva can be a profoundly positive contributor to our lives and to the life of this diverse and great nation called India.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Editorial: On The Importance of Sex</title>
      <link href="/Importance-of-sex" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Editorial: On The Importance of Sex" />
      <published>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Importance-of-sex</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Importance-of-sex">&lt;p&gt;It is most certainly not easy writing about sex. To begin with, you have to deal with the fact that once you start talking about orgasms, breasts, penises and foot fetishes (the human mind is an unholy place), it is very easy to sound like you are writing plain-old erotica—cheap, unsophisticated, and yet very arousing. At the same time though, if you try to distance yourself from the human depravity of sex, you could sound more like a plumber describing a u-bend when exploring whether the G-Spot really exists. I want to avoid making such serious stylistic errors, but I don’t want to forget that any conversation about sex has to be both erotic and exciting whilst being decidedly technical about a topic that is so serious. I remember watching an interview of Philip Roth (you kind of have to read and listen to him when thinking about sex and literature), where he declared quite hilariously that when he and his friends were sixteen they had only question about sex: &lt;em&gt;“WHEN? WHEN? WHEN?!!”&lt;/em&gt; That kind of desperation was not simply because of an animal drive within us, according to Roth. If his book &lt;i&gt;Portnoy’s Complaint&lt;/i&gt; (which is about a mother-obsessed, masturbation addict) is any indication, the want for sex in human beings can lead to all kinds of things both disgusting and sexy. The power that sex holds over our lives can lead to all sorts of problems, from the relatively benign but hideous (think Diogenes masturbating in the open streets) to the debauched (think Marquis De Sade’s &lt;i&gt;120 Days of Sodom&lt;/i&gt;) and to even wholesale exploitation (think prostitution). There is a reason why “sex sells” and there’s a reason why clerics don’t want even the ankles of women to be visible to men. Sex lies at the very human intersection of patriarchy, fulfilment, love, exploitation, power and everything else in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think a brilliant place to find a conversation about sex that is stimulating (in the right way) is the comments section of any porn video (it’s also a good way of ensuring the video is a good one!). The things people say (and don’t say) about sex in these comments is so profoundly revealing (never thought I’d use the word profound when writing about sex!). These comments tell us that people don’t just watch porn to simply &lt;em&gt;“bust a nut or yaw yaw the sisterhood”&lt;/em&gt;. Masturbation is a very sensuous thing in our lives: It relieves boredom, which is perennially the human mind’s most wicked enemy and it gives us the opportunity to enjoy the feelings (and hormones) that sex brings with the most important person in our erotic lives: ourselves. Therefore, it is no wonder that people have such strikingly specific criticisms of the acting in the video, or the stilettos of the female porn star, or the absolutely unrealistic time for which the male porn star lasts. People put up comments stating all sorts of things, from the things they found funny like the orgasm face of the actors or the scenes they felt where outright bizarre like one where they felt the porn star’s screaming was extremely unappealing as it sounded like a &lt;em&gt;“donkey braying”&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Porn is about the deep voyeurism that inhabits the human mind, it is about finding release (literally) and for that one needs a good experience. Put it this way: when we want to release our bowels we want a clean toilet that smells good, when we want to fulfil our hunger we want food that tastes good, and when we want to avoid the cold we want a jumper that looks good. If we want quality in all other things, should it surprise anyone that we want porn to be more than just people “doing it” with each other? Good pornography is important for the same reason that anything is important to human beings, we are not just Plato’s “featherless birds” and we don’t just have sex in caves (HA!). Unlike the plots and scripts of most porn movies, human beings are interesting in nature, and their erotic lives reflect that via their desires from pornography. There’s a reason why &lt;i&gt;Playboy&lt;/i&gt; Magazine, instead of just having any other nudes, had Marilyn Monroe’s nudes. And there is a reason why Pornhub has reported a phenomenal rise in the consumption of incest porn by…(drum-roll)…millennials!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sex as an activity is about satisfying the human imagination—otherwise, a few grunts and no foreplay would have kept everyone happy. On the issue of ‘grunts’, we all know that men can have very few problems when it ‘comes’ to (pardon the pun) reaching climax, whereas there is a whole body of feminist literature on how women don’t really climax at all most of the time. The common form that the female orgasm takes is due to clitoral stimulation, and the reason why women do not really come due to vaginal stimulation is because, well, men don’t usually last long enough. This creates an obviously skewered power dynamic in sex, where men are able to “unload” ever so easily and women are left feeling constantly under-appreciated. I don’t mean to say that this means men are near-constantly aroused pigs who pay no heed to the needs of their female partners, although there is truth in that contention. My point here is simply that without a good amount of foreplay and some good oral sex, our sexual activities with all their imaginative passion can simply end up being a dull series of painful thrusts for one whole half of the human population—and sex must be far more than that if in these feminist times we men are to redeem ourselves for having treated women as objects of sex for thousands of years. Ancient India, being a culture at a stupendous height of civilisation, was acutely aware of the consequences of denying women the beauty of an orgasm. As Wendy Doniger, a controversial yet revered Indologist, points out, even the legendary &lt;i&gt;Kama Sutra&lt;/i&gt; is clear on the fact that women must orgasm first, given how easy it is for men to do so. The message is clear and has been clear for more than a thousand years: boys, at least try to find the fabled G-spot once in a while instead of just seeking blowjobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power dynamics of sex bring up a very curious issue with specific regard to sex between homosexual men. It is difficult to accurately describe how significantly being either a ‘top’ or a ‘bottom’ has an effect on the masculinity of gay men (MEN!!). The power politics in that part of human sexuality has assumed new proportions with the world’s gay community bidding adieu to the stereotype of the “camp” gay man and welcoming a more traditionally masculine homosexual male as more desirable. As Kevin Troughton &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/nov/30/the-end-of-camp-straight-acting-gay&quot;&gt;writes&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;i&gt;The Guardian&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;em&gt;“very few find [camp] sexually attractive. That limp-wristed, bitchy queen might be hilarious, but you wouldn’t want him as a boyfriend, or even as a one-night stand.”&lt;/em&gt; The fact is “bottoming” gay men have always been stereotyped into the camp category, facing potentially even internalised homophobia due to their perceived passivity in the gay community. And now with the rise in the desirability of the straight-acting gay alpha male, it would appear that all men who wish to receive anal sex will potentially have greater issues relating to dominance and estimations of their own masculinity. Funny enough, all of this simply reinforces the words of Oscar Wilde: &lt;em&gt;“Everything in the world is about sex except sex. Sex is about power”&lt;/em&gt;. It is slightly hilarious but definitely unsurprising that men having sex with other men is where power dynamics take centre stage, after all, the ‘male ego’ manifests itself most strongly in front of other men!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between love and sex is complicated (well, of course). And if you have read a bit of Freud (he has to be mentioned in a discussion on sex, you know, #respect), sex and love are both about your mum. Obviously, his Oedipus Complex and theories on the development of libido are a bit bogus, but his underlying assertion that we learn how to have relationships primarily from our parents makes a lot of intuitive sense. Parents give their children a reality, they define what human interaction means for them and they do so simply because that’s how it is, for good or for bad. This means people’s relationships are (to a degree) shaped by the experiences given to them by their childhood and their parents. The problem is that people fall in love with the people they have sex with quite often and vice versa! And people falling in love leads to all sorts of problems like marriage, infidelity, drama and the responsibility to take care of children. The very point of sex leads to relationships that are determined on factors outside your control (your mum!), and lead to a sexual rut (your children) with added responsibilities of bringing up another human being—so that the cycle can continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is definitely weird talking about sex and extremely difficult to treat it with the sensitivity and respect it deserves. But it certainly is fun to think about and research on something that is so goddamn brilliant. I mean, my research showed me that orgasms could be had by brain dead people if the right nerves are stimulated! And it was facts and observations like this that made my task ever so out-of-control. Yes, sex is important, I could see that, but what is the common thread that makes it all ever so important? And why? I think I have chanced upon a simple answer to these questions: sex is humanity’s deepest desires manifested in the most physical of acts, and for that very reason it’s going to be more than just a simple act. Adieu!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is most certainly not easy writing about sex. To begin with, you have to deal with the fact that once you start talking about orgasms, breasts, penises and foot fetishes (the human mind is an unholy place), it is very easy to sound like you are writing plain-old erotica—cheap, unsophisticated, and yet very arousing. At the same time though, if you try to distance yourself from the human depravity of sex, you could sound more like a plumber describing a u-bend when exploring whether the G-Spot really exists. I want to avoid making such serious stylistic errors, but I don’t want to forget that any conversation about sex has to be both erotic and exciting whilst being decidedly technical about a topic that is so serious. I remember watching an interview of Philip Roth (you kind of have to read and listen to him when thinking about sex and literature), where he declared quite hilariously that when he and his friends were sixteen they had only question about sex: “WHEN? WHEN? WHEN?!!” That kind of desperation was not simply because of an animal drive within us, according to Roth. If his book Portnoy’s Complaint (which is about a mother-obsessed, masturbation addict) is any indication, the want for sex in human beings can lead to all kinds of things both disgusting and sexy. The power that sex holds over our lives can lead to all sorts of problems, from the relatively benign but hideous (think Diogenes masturbating in the open streets) to the debauched (think Marquis De Sade’s 120 Days of Sodom) and to even wholesale exploitation (think prostitution). There is a reason why “sex sells” and there’s a reason why clerics don’t want even the ankles of women to be visible to men. Sex lies at the very human intersection of patriarchy, fulfilment, love, exploitation, power and everything else in between.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
