<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/culture/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-08-28T21:55:41+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/culture/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Mind-Numbingness of Black Mirror</title>
      <link href="/The-Mind-Numbingness-of-Black-Mirror" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Mind-Numbingness of Black Mirror" />
      <published>2019-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Mind-Numbingness-of-Black-Mirror</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Mind-Numbingness-of-Black-Mirror">&lt;p&gt;I remember being flabbergasted and mesmerised by &lt;em&gt;The National Anthem&lt;/em&gt; - the
very first episode of Charlie Brooker’s surreal and maddening piece of art that
we call &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;. It took me a while to understand why it was called that,
and the revelation hit me like a brick. The idea of calling a screen ‘black
mirror’ because it reflects your image is not just genius on the surface but is
also a teaser for the show’s intention: to tell you about yourself through
technology. It is exceedingly difficult to watch the show one episode at a time.
&lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; is discomforting due to the darkness in its content; dark enough
to send any brain on a whirlwind spin. It is potent, razor-sharp, and
brilliantly critical of the ways in which we abuse technology. If I ever had a
horror recommendation for someone, movie or TV show, &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; was what I
would first go with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It isn’t the first time that Charlie Brooker has scathingly criticised
technology. He previously wrote &lt;em&gt;Deadset&lt;/em&gt; - a show where a zombie apocalypse
breaks out in the &lt;em&gt;Big Brother&lt;/em&gt; (or as Indians call it, &lt;em&gt;Bigg Boss&lt;/em&gt;) house. It
is often called a precursor to &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;. He’s also hosted &lt;em&gt;How TV Ruined
Your Life&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;TVGoHome&lt;/em&gt; - very self-explanatory titles about his disdain for
reality television’s outlandish premises. That is not to say he hates everything
about mainstream media. He is quite the pop culture and video game buff, having
hosted shows on both. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; was the culmination of all of his thought
processes from earlier shows. It was prophetic and innovative, and told us
things about ourselves we did not wish to hear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not a problem, as long as you do not become the very thing you had hoped
to destroy. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; was picked up by Netflix after two seasons and one
Christmas special, and since then, it has run on for three seasons with one
groundbreaking style of narration in the form of the interactive film,
&lt;em&gt;Bandersnatch&lt;/em&gt;. Undoubtedly, it gave us too much to think about again; the power
of technology to affect relationships, rattle politics, reveal sexual subtext,
create near-dystopian scenarios with social credit scores, prove that free will
is a myth, and show how the head of a state can be blackmailed into having sex
with a pig are on full display in this show. Surely, many would agree that, of
late, the episodes have been lacklustre as compared to the first few seasons.
However, that isn’t my concern here, because there is still enough food for
thought in those episodes. I’m concerned with why we find them lacklustre and
the entire culture that has formed around the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Netflix acquired the rights to Channel 4 production, one might have noted
a growing anxiety in people to want the streaming giant to release one more
season of the show. It ends too quickly for viewers, partly because of the
binge-watching culture that has engulfed the experience of &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;. Irony
kicks in strong here. We are willing to subject ourselves to the control of
technology because it has us hooked like a tight fishing rod. Sure, you get
quite a lot to think about, but you end up not realising the ridiculousness of
what you are doing. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; then becomes a show about how much it can
surprise and shock you, which, in all fairness, it continues to do in cruel and
sometimes gruesome ways. But the real question remains, to what extent have we
been able to grasp what those episodes imply about the future or the present.
This is also where the discomfort attached to the show matters. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;
is not here to spare your feelings, it is unafraid of destroying the lives of
all the protagonists in a single stroke, after around 40 minutes of intense
build up. How does one watch so many episodes of gruesome emotional intensity
and brutal philosophies, all in one go? It contributes to the culture of
incessant, mindless consumption of pop culture, without a pause. Our willingness
to consume such uncomfortable subject matter with such ease and speed is
indicative of how much we have let pop culture consume us, instead of the other
way round. Brooker himself said that bingeing the show is like getting hit by a
car, and that’s just one season worth of episodes. One might even argue that
&lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;, like all else, is just a show and it isn’t meant to convince or
change status quo vastly. However, it feels really preachy, especially once you
consider Charlie Brooker’s own beliefs. He wants to sell to us why our
increasing reliance on technology won’t get us too far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I also find discouraging is the idea of Netflix backing this show. It’s a
terrible idea to pressurise your content creators to churning out further
content. I believe that is, in part, why the show has been declining in quality
lately. Netflix is still trying to find footing in this vast market that has now
been opened up due to the entry of giants like Disney and WarnerBros, not to
mention the existence of Amazon. It’s trying its hardest to keep subscribers
hooked by releasing new series and films continuously. In the midst of companies
taking back their content from Netflix, to host on their own sites, Netflix has
no choice but to create a niche of its own as soon as it can, like HBO, which is
perceived by many as one of the best content producers. A glaring example of
this strategy’s volatility was when Netflix purchased streaming rights to
&lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt; for $100 million. Months later, this year, Warner Media took the
rights back when they announced the entry of their own streaming site. Netflix
has progressed in that sphere very well - originals like &lt;em&gt;Orange Is The New
Black, Narcos, House of Cards,&lt;/em&gt; etc. have carved their own space in the internet
sphere. However, at the end of the day, Netflix is run primarily on data
analytics, and every operation is based on that concept. While it’s the right
way to go about understanding your audience, increasing competition may worsen
the pace at which it wants to expand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does this strategy have such a paramount effect on a show? It’s because of
the resources that Netflix has put in for just this show alone. Before a season
launch, it would release a trailer for every single episode, which isn’t the
usual practice. A heavy marketing campaign will then follow, for engagement with
users on Twitter, YouTube and Facebook; something Netflix is really good at
because it has &lt;em&gt;humanised&lt;/em&gt; itself by replying to comments. Under Channel 4,
&lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; was relatively obscure. Now, it’s Netflix’s marquee signing. More
funds also mean more high-profile celebrities act in the show, some of which
include Miley Cyrus and Jodie Foster. It also means smarter programming, like
the choose-your-own-adventure &lt;em&gt;Bandersnatch&lt;/em&gt;. However, the flip side of this
means that time doesn’t wait for quality, or the overall delivery of the
message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With escalating technological developments, there’s no way to tell whether we
will really use virtual reality or artificial intelligence the way the show
depicts. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; is definitely a glimpse of the most vulnerable
tendencies of the human mind, because behind all the gizmo, it’s really a show
about what it means to be human and not about the hi-fi stuff itself.
Unfortunately, in the millennial age, we’re losing our human connections, and
&lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; is just being co-opted into this stream of unconsciousness that
includes being stuck to some form of a screen. The show is prophetic for sure,
but is it going to impact how we approach technology? The use of apps like
FaceApp by a population unaware of the privacy policy or the unwanted potential
of machine learning, does not bode well for this question. We will no doubt have
more seasons of &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; in the future, which will be different than the
previous ones. Despite all the meta-level, self-aware marketing Netflix might do
when it parodies itself as being part of the &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; universe, we all
know what it really means. We’ll just absorb more of it with gleeful abandon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we really need another screen to tell us not to be hooked to one?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pranav Manie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I remember being flabbergasted and mesmerised by The National Anthem - the very first episode of Charlie Brooker’s surreal and maddening piece of art that we call Black Mirror. It took me a while to understand why it was called that, and the revelation hit me like a brick. The idea of calling a screen ‘black mirror’ because it reflects your image is not just genius on the surface but is also a teaser for the show’s intention: to tell you about yourself through technology. It is exceedingly difficult to watch the show one episode at a time. Black Mirror is discomforting due to the darkness in its content; dark enough to send any brain on a whirlwind spin. It is potent, razor-sharp, and brilliantly critical of the ways in which we abuse technology. If I ever had a horror recommendation for someone, movie or TV show, Black Mirror was what I would first go with. It isn’t the first time that Charlie Brooker has scathingly criticised technology. He previously wrote Deadset - a show where a zombie apocalypse breaks out in the Big Brother (or as Indians call it, Bigg Boss) house. It is often called a precursor to Black Mirror. He’s also hosted How TV Ruined Your Life, and TVGoHome - very self-explanatory titles about his disdain for reality television’s outlandish premises. That is not to say he hates everything about mainstream media. He is quite the pop culture and video game buff, having hosted shows on both. Black Mirror was the culmination of all of his thought processes from earlier shows. It was prophetic and innovative, and told us things about ourselves we did not wish to hear. That is not a problem, as long as you do not become the very thing you had hoped to destroy. Black Mirror was picked up by Netflix after two seasons and one Christmas special, and since then, it has run on for three seasons with one groundbreaking style of narration in the form of the interactive film, Bandersnatch. Undoubtedly, it gave us too much to think about again; the power of technology to affect relationships, rattle politics, reveal sexual subtext, create near-dystopian scenarios with social credit scores, prove that free will is a myth, and show how the head of a state can be blackmailed into having sex with a pig are on full display in this show. Surely, many would agree that, of late, the episodes have been lacklustre as compared to the first few seasons. However, that isn’t my concern here, because there is still enough food for thought in those episodes. I’m concerned with why we find them lacklustre and the entire culture that has formed around the show. Since Netflix acquired the rights to Channel 4 production, one might have noted a growing anxiety in people to want the streaming giant to release one more season of the show. It ends too quickly for viewers, partly because of the binge-watching culture that has engulfed the experience of Black Mirror. Irony kicks in strong here. We are willing to subject ourselves to the control of technology because it has us hooked like a tight fishing rod. Sure, you get quite a lot to think about, but you end up not realising the ridiculousness of what you are doing. Black Mirror then becomes a show about how much it can surprise and shock you, which, in all fairness, it continues to do in cruel and sometimes gruesome ways. But the real question remains, to what extent have we been able to grasp what those episodes imply about the future or the present. This is also where the discomfort attached to the show matters. Black Mirror is not here to spare your feelings, it is unafraid of destroying the lives of all the protagonists in a single stroke, after around 40 minutes of intense build up. How does one watch so many episodes of gruesome emotional intensity and brutal philosophies, all in one go? It contributes to the culture of incessant, mindless consumption of pop culture, without a pause. Our willingness to consume such uncomfortable subject matter with such ease and speed is indicative of how much we have let pop culture consume us, instead of the other way round. Brooker himself said that bingeing the show is like getting hit by a car, and that’s just one season worth of episodes. One might even argue that Black Mirror, like all else, is just a show and it isn’t meant to convince or change status quo vastly. However, it feels really preachy, especially once you consider Charlie Brooker’s own beliefs. He wants to sell to us why our increasing reliance on technology won’t get us too far. What I also find discouraging is the idea of Netflix backing this show. It’s a terrible idea to pressurise your content creators to churning out further content. I believe that is, in part, why the show has been declining in quality lately. Netflix is still trying to find footing in this vast market that has now been opened up due to the entry of giants like Disney and WarnerBros, not to mention the existence of Amazon. It’s trying its hardest to keep subscribers hooked by releasing new series and films continuously. In the midst of companies taking back their content from Netflix, to host on their own sites, Netflix has no choice but to create a niche of its own as soon as it can, like HBO, which is perceived by many as one of the best content producers. A glaring example of this strategy’s volatility was when Netflix purchased streaming rights to Friends for $100 million. Months later, this year, Warner Media took the rights back when they announced the entry of their own streaming site. Netflix has progressed in that sphere very well - originals like Orange Is The New Black, Narcos, House of Cards, etc. have carved their own space in the internet sphere. However, at the end of the day, Netflix is run primarily on data analytics, and every operation is based on that concept. While it’s the right way to go about understanding your audience, increasing competition may worsen the pace at which it wants to expand.  Why does this strategy have such a paramount effect on a show? It’s because of the resources that Netflix has put in for just this show alone. Before a season launch, it would release a trailer for every single episode, which isn’t the usual practice. A heavy marketing campaign will then follow, for engagement with users on Twitter, YouTube and Facebook; something Netflix is really good at because it has humanised itself by replying to comments. Under Channel 4, Black Mirror was relatively obscure. Now, it’s Netflix’s marquee signing. More funds also mean more high-profile celebrities act in the show, some of which include Miley Cyrus and Jodie Foster. It also means smarter programming, like the choose-your-own-adventure Bandersnatch. However, the flip side of this means that time doesn’t wait for quality, or the overall delivery of the message. With escalating technological developments, there’s no way to tell whether we will really use virtual reality or artificial intelligence the way the show depicts. Black Mirror is definitely a glimpse of the most vulnerable tendencies of the human mind, because behind all the gizmo, it’s really a show about what it means to be human and not about the hi-fi stuff itself. Unfortunately, in the millennial age, we’re losing our human connections, and Black Mirror is just being co-opted into this stream of unconsciousness that includes being stuck to some form of a screen. The show is prophetic for sure, but is it going to impact how we approach technology? The use of apps like FaceApp by a population unaware of the privacy policy or the unwanted potential of machine learning, does not bode well for this question. We will no doubt have more seasons of Black Mirror in the future, which will be different than the previous ones. Despite all the meta-level, self-aware marketing Netflix might do when it parodies itself as being part of the Black Mirror universe, we all know what it really means. We’ll just absorb more of it with gleeful abandon. Do we really need another screen to tell us not to be hooked to one?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why So Bad *rse?</title>
      <link href="/Why-So-Bad-Arse" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why So Bad *rse?" />
      <published>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-So-Bad-Arse</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-So-Bad-Arse">&lt;p&gt;Raise your hand if you remember the &lt;em&gt;Frozen&lt;/em&gt; fever that gripped Hollywood - and
pretty much the rest of the world too - in the fall of 2013. If you remember the
glittering reviews and the innumerable times ‘&lt;em&gt;shattered the glass ceiling&lt;/em&gt;’,
‘&lt;em&gt;badass princesses&lt;/em&gt;’ or ‘&lt;em&gt;Oscar worthy&lt;/em&gt;’ flashed before your eyes, till you
were made certain that all of life was meaningless unless you booked first-day,
deluxe seat tickets. If you remember how Disney Renaissance enthusiasts, across
the globe, made sure you knew that Anna and Elsa were &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt;, unlike the
&lt;em&gt;girly-girls&lt;/em&gt; you see in other princess movies. They are &lt;em&gt;empowered,&lt;/em&gt; with their
M-slit gowns and absence of a romantic wedding for an ending, jot that down. If
you remember how you found yourself at the theatre, semi-guilt tripped into
watching the movie, and finally realised that Jennifer Lee’s retelling of &lt;em&gt;The
Snow Queen&lt;/em&gt; to be, at most, a well-intentioned but weak tea nod as to what made
a woman ‘badass’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s funny, actually, because when one sits down to look back upon this legacy
of retconning traditionally feminine roles as &lt;em&gt;weak&lt;/em&gt;, so as to prop up
tomboyish, often desensitised heroines, it’s not just the creators, critics and
audience of present day showbiz media who are to blame. Even adored and revered
works like those of C S Lewis and Rowling, &lt;em&gt;yes, Rowling&lt;/em&gt;, have often sought to
perpetuate this trope, often under a carefully arranged veneer of offering
simple didactic messages in children’s literature. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let’s talk about &lt;em&gt;these girly-girls&lt;/em&gt;. Not just the predecessor Disney
princesses, no, but the so-called wimpy girls in the media, the featherbrained
airheads, the wet blankets. The ones who can’t and won’t punch assassins, knife
through captors or ride horses into sandstorms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For as long as I can remember, it was a struggle for me to find feminine,
unapologetically girly characters in literature and media, who were not
dismissed as prissy, uppity damsels or useless, shivering waifs whose plethora
of interests - sewing, fashion, painting, music, and so forth - were not
dismissed as completely decorative and impractical in the general context of the
storyline. Worse still, if I did manage to find a rare favourite, it was quite
the feat to avoid the barrage of snide remarks from acquaintances, friends, and
even more terrible - overenthusiastic vloggers and literary dissenters who were
sure to hammer home the fact that Sansa Stark and Amy March are, in fact,
horrible sinners doomed to burn in eternal hellfire for their crimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sansa Stark, from George R R Martin’s &lt;em&gt;A Song of Ice and Fire,&lt;/em&gt; is a textbook
example of the stern fact that a non-tomboyish, non-sexualised female lead can
do nothing without being written off as a wimp. A young, naive lady of merely
eleven&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; when the series begins, Sansa is held captive, forced to endure the
slaughter of her family and shoulders through being a political pawn and a
hostage with kindness, bravery and resilience. She has no dragons and no swords,
she loves lemon cakes, ballads and handsome knights, and is therefore, by
default, painted by the &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt; fandom as a wet blanket airhead. She’s
even seen as a veritable ableist demon for not feeling sexually attracted
towards a man thrice her age (and he hails from the house that murdered her
family, no less). She only manages to garner some sympathy after she is violated
in the TV adaptation, a scene that doesn’t even exist in the books. It is hardly
surprising that many male characters in the series, who do much worse, get away
with their misdeeds way easily. &lt;em&gt;Thrones’&lt;/em&gt; treatment of non-warrior women is
particularly repulsive. Sansa is made to mouth lines showing stoic gratitude
towards her assaulters for teaching her strength, and another female character,
who is often praised for being the snarky cool kid, demurely announces that she
doesn’t plan to be useless during battle, namely ‘sit knitting by the fire’.
Non-canonical lines, inserted because of the directors’ knowledge that they
specifically pander to the audience’s needs and explicit scenes where women
condemn softness and acts of ‘predictable’ ladyship, thereby metamorphosing into
&lt;em&gt;badasses,&lt;/em&gt; are aplenty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is alarming that such scenes, in books and films, are often revered and
portrayed as a sort of phoenix-from-the-ashes-moment, worthy of wolf-whistles
and printed merchandise. Even more alarming is how the notion of empowerment has
grown so utterly distorted that nothing, save for panning people who do not go
against the grain, can properly qualify as a wholesome depiction of strong
women. Why, after all, is knitting by the fire, or working in the kitchen so
problematic? Do soldiers magically grow their uniforms? Does food come to us
without the contribution of those who make it? Demeaning the choice of a woman
to do as she pleases or act as she wants, is but an elaborately twisted route,
ultimately ending in degrading womanhood itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When C S Lewis published &lt;em&gt;The Last Battle&lt;/em&gt; in 1956 the final instalment of his
Narnia series, there was quite a bit of hue and outcry over his decision to
close the gates of Narnia upon Susan Pevensie, the older, calmer, more beautiful
and ladylike of the Pevensie sisters. After her family is killed in a car
accident and the souls of her siblings find eternal refuge in Narnia, (a clear
metaphor of an Eden-like realm) Susan is left alone, literally and figuratively
locked out of heaven, her dismissal most summarily executed by Lewis in a couple
of lines: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;My sister Susan,” answered Peter shortly and gravely, “is no longer a friend
of Narnia.&lt;/em&gt;” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this a problem? Because it’s not so much a question of &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; her fate
was, as it is of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; she deserved such a peremptory conclusion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Oh Susan!” said Jill. “She’s interested in nothing nowadays except nylons and
lipsticks and invitations. She always was a jolly sight too keen on being
grown-up&lt;/em&gt;…” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, yes, of course. Dresses and makeup, wanting to socialise and have peers;
what could be more heinous a crime for an adolescent? Surely, a crime worthy of
being unpardonable, in a book replete with Biblical imagery and repeated
emphasis on the need to keep the innocence in children untainted, with a fervour
that would make Blake proud. If you are shaking your head at this, slightly
unconvinced, here’s a snippet from Lewis himself, where he makes it clear that
our lipstick-wearing, nylon-loving lady is not enjoying the fruits of the
Promised Land anytime soon:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The books don’t tell us what happened to Susan. She is left alive in this
world at the end, having by then turned into a rather silly, conceited young
woman. But there’s plenty of time for her to mend and perhaps she will get to
Aslan’s country in the end… in her own way&lt;/em&gt;…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even while he offers us a glimmer of hope, one can’t help but wince at the last
lines. ‘Plenty of time for her to mend’ what, exactly? What is so indisputably
repulsive about Susan craving extremely normal things, for a girl of her age?
Why is there an immediate need to demonise a female character who chooses to
beautify herself with makeup and pretty clothes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, Susan’s crisis has attracted plenty of sympathetic voices from the
literary community: Philip Pullman, Neil Gaiman, J K Rowling - to name a few,
with Gaiman even creating a sort of spinoff short story with a very Susan-esque
protagonist, giving her a much-needed voice and agency. Still, the older
Pevensie sister remains an outcast of Narnia, a scarring reminder of what
happens to girls who dare to be…well, just be. The ugly implications of
girlish existence in Lewis’ ramrod world of old laws and deep magic are proof
enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of Rowling, an interesting and somewhat ironic fact is that while the
&lt;em&gt;Harry Potter&lt;/em&gt; series, on the forefront, seems chock-full of strong,
three-dimensional female characters, there is something slightly problematic in
the way she treats any character that teeters dangerously into &lt;em&gt;girly-girl&lt;/em&gt;
territory. Two classic examples are Cho Chang, Harry’s first girlfriend, who is
constantly vilified for being ‘too emotional’ and too mopey over her dead
boyfriend, and Fleur Delacour, who while she gets a much better conclusion, is
still written off as the shallow dumb blonde, with a subpar performance in the
Triwizard tournament where she’s the only female competitor. Cho is eventually
cast aside for Ginny, whom Harry considers wonderful because she is ‘rarely
weepy’. Constant misogynistic and slightly racist jabs are directed at Fleur by
none other than Molly and Ginny Weasley, two of the most glorified and
celebrated women in Harry’s life. Not even the minor characters escape
judgement: the Patil twins and Lavender Brown, bubblier and more extroverted
classmates of Hermione, are often reduced to nothing but cartoonish caricatures
vying for Harry and Ron’s affections in the movies. Besides the evocation of
unpleasant racial overtones, it’s something to think about, really. Where does
mild, school cliché-centric humour end and perpetual bracketing-and-bashing of
softness and &lt;em&gt;generic&lt;/em&gt; girlishness begin?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My personal favourite though, is the much-hated Amy March from &lt;em&gt;Little Women&lt;/em&gt;.
Amy’s case is particularly interesting because Alcott never meant to malign her,
no, it’s the audience, unable to look past their ‘JO x LAURIE ENDGAME’ stupor,
who miss the whole point of Amy’s arc - the resourcefulness in her choice to
work within the conventions of traditional femininity instead of rebelling
against it, the raw honesty in her desire as an impoverished girl to enjoy
pretty material pleasures, the flaws and petty mistakes she succumbs to, because
she is not written to be liked, she is written to be &lt;em&gt;real.&lt;/em&gt; Jo’s struggles are
very earthy and very honest, and her staunch refusal to fit in and fulfil
societal expectations is admirable, but Amy’s willingness to maintain a sort of
harmony with her community and work towards self-fulfilment…how is that, in
any way, less gratifying?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for that matter, what do all these endless debates actually uncover? What
does this hollow classification system of girls into &lt;em&gt;badasses&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;girly-girls&lt;/em&gt; entail?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is uncertain, but it’s surely not an easy one. One cannot simply go
for a shallow deconstruction of the &lt;em&gt;not-like-other-girls syndrome&lt;/em&gt; without
looking into why this syndrome had to arise at all. And then one finds that the
root of this bizarre phenomenon lies in square one: the &lt;em&gt;trivialisation&lt;/em&gt; of
tenderness in girls and women, leading many to think that female voices and
characters might not be taken seriously unless they are stripped away of all
that could possibly hint at compassion and clemency. While Katniss Everdeen,
Merida and the warrior heroines of some of the later Young Adult franchises may
have arrived at exactly the right moment to prevent oversaturation of the market
by the same kind of feminine representation, the boomerang effect that arose out
of this is girls, in the younger demographic, seeking validation by rejecting
and loudly denouncing traits that could possibly mark them as girly. This
denunciation shows an almost vitriolic hatred in harmless things, marked out as
extremely feminine motifs: anything pink and/or coded as &lt;em&gt;princessy&lt;/em&gt; being the
commonest examples. It’s alarming, it’s potentially harmful that the psyche of
girls is shaped by what they &lt;em&gt;shouldn’t&lt;/em&gt; be as opposed to what they prefer to
be, it leans towards the patriarchy having the last laugh at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, as hackneyed as this sounds, there is nothing more
reproachable than the actions and behaviour of one woman being tainted so as to
glorify another. Feminism and badassery don’t spring &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; from elaborate fight
sequences or by being completely stone-cold or perpetually displeased and in a
fighting stance. Yes, female characters so portrayed are valid, beautiful, even
necessary. But they are not the beginning and end of all that’s marvellous and
awe-inspiring about women. It’s definitely heartening to see a much more
positive and varied portrayal of sharp and brilliant women in contemporary
media, who don’t always depend on brawn or magic to achieve unanimous approval,
take the famous Elle Woods (&lt;em&gt;Legally Blonde)&lt;/em&gt; for example, a wonderful
subversion of the dumb blonde stereotype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while we praise Arya for knifing through her tormentors, we cannot forget
Sansa, who comforts children and women with songs during a battle; we can
celebrate angry, rebellious spirits without coming for gentle, tranquil hearts.
We can cherish both sides of the spectrum. We can appreciate that some
rebellions happen quietly, in utter tranquillity, glossed with pink and flowers.
We can, for once, not let the patriarchy win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And maybe, just maybe at the end, Susan, the outcast of Narnia, no longer a
powerful queen but just gloriously and heartbreakingly a human girl, will have
the last laugh.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sritama Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Raise your hand if you remember the Frozen fever that gripped Hollywood - and pretty much the rest of the world too - in the fall of 2013. If you remember the glittering reviews and the innumerable times ‘shattered the glass ceiling’, ‘badass princesses’ or ‘Oscar worthy’ flashed before your eyes, till you were made certain that all of life was meaningless unless you booked first-day, deluxe seat tickets. If you remember how Disney Renaissance enthusiasts, across the globe, made sure you knew that Anna and Elsa were different, unlike the girly-girls you see in other princess movies. They are empowered, with their M-slit gowns and absence of a romantic wedding for an ending, jot that down. If you remember how you found yourself at the theatre, semi-guilt tripped into watching the movie, and finally realised that Jennifer Lee’s retelling of The Snow Queen to be, at most, a well-intentioned but weak tea nod as to what made a woman ‘badass’. It’s funny, actually, because when one sits down to look back upon this legacy of retconning traditionally feminine roles as weak, so as to prop up tomboyish, often desensitised heroines, it’s not just the creators, critics and audience of present day showbiz media who are to blame. Even adored and revered works like those of C S Lewis and Rowling, yes, Rowling, have often sought to perpetuate this trope, often under a carefully arranged veneer of offering simple didactic messages in children’s literature.  So, let’s talk about these girly-girls. Not just the predecessor Disney princesses, no, but the so-called wimpy girls in the media, the featherbrained airheads, the wet blankets. The ones who can’t and won’t punch assassins, knife through captors or ride horses into sandstorms.  For as long as I can remember, it was a struggle for me to find feminine, unapologetically girly characters in literature and media, who were not dismissed as prissy, uppity damsels or useless, shivering waifs whose plethora of interests - sewing, fashion, painting, music, and so forth - were not dismissed as completely decorative and impractical in the general context of the storyline. Worse still, if I did manage to find a rare favourite, it was quite the feat to avoid the barrage of snide remarks from acquaintances, friends, and even more terrible - overenthusiastic vloggers and literary dissenters who were sure to hammer home the fact that Sansa Stark and Amy March are, in fact, horrible sinners doomed to burn in eternal hellfire for their crimes. Sansa Stark, from George R R Martin’s A Song of Ice and Fire, is a textbook example of the stern fact that a non-tomboyish, non-sexualised female lead can do nothing without being written off as a wimp. A young, naive lady of merely eleven, when the series begins, Sansa is held captive, forced to endure the slaughter of her family and shoulders through being a political pawn and a hostage with kindness, bravery and resilience. She has no dragons and no swords, she loves lemon cakes, ballads and handsome knights, and is therefore, by default, painted by the Game of Thrones fandom as a wet blanket airhead. She’s even seen as a veritable ableist demon for not feeling sexually attracted towards a man thrice her age (and he hails from the house that murdered her family, no less). She only manages to garner some sympathy after she is violated in the TV adaptation, a scene that doesn’t even exist in the books. It is hardly surprising that many male characters in the series, who do much worse, get away with their misdeeds way easily. Thrones’ treatment of non-warrior women is particularly repulsive. Sansa is made to mouth lines showing stoic gratitude towards her assaulters for teaching her strength, and another female character, who is often praised for being the snarky cool kid, demurely announces that she doesn’t plan to be useless during battle, namely ‘sit knitting by the fire’. Non-canonical lines, inserted because of the directors’ knowledge that they specifically pander to the audience’s needs and explicit scenes where women condemn softness and acts of ‘predictable’ ladyship, thereby metamorphosing into badasses, are aplenty. It is alarming that such scenes, in books and films, are often revered and portrayed as a sort of phoenix-from-the-ashes-moment, worthy of wolf-whistles and printed merchandise. Even more alarming is how the notion of empowerment has grown so utterly distorted that nothing, save for panning people who do not go against the grain, can properly qualify as a wholesome depiction of strong women. Why, after all, is knitting by the fire, or working in the kitchen so problematic? Do soldiers magically grow their uniforms? Does food come to us without the contribution of those who make it? Demeaning the choice of a woman to do as she pleases or act as she wants, is but an elaborately twisted route, ultimately ending in degrading womanhood itself. When C S Lewis published The Last Battle in 1956 the final instalment of his Narnia series, there was quite a bit of hue and outcry over his decision to close the gates of Narnia upon Susan Pevensie, the older, calmer, more beautiful and ladylike of the Pevensie sisters. After her family is killed in a car accident and the souls of her siblings find eternal refuge in Narnia, (a clear metaphor of an Eden-like realm) Susan is left alone, literally and figuratively locked out of heaven, her dismissal most summarily executed by Lewis in a couple of lines:  “My sister Susan,” answered Peter shortly and gravely, “is no longer a friend of Narnia.”  Why is this a problem? Because it’s not so much a question of what her fate was, as it is of why she deserved such a peremptory conclusion: “Oh Susan!” said Jill. “She’s interested in nothing nowadays except nylons and lipsticks and invitations. She always was a jolly sight too keen on being grown-up…”  Ah, yes, of course. Dresses and makeup, wanting to socialise and have peers; what could be more heinous a crime for an adolescent? Surely, a crime worthy of being unpardonable, in a book replete with Biblical imagery and repeated emphasis on the need to keep the innocence in children untainted, with a fervour that would make Blake proud. If you are shaking your head at this, slightly unconvinced, here’s a snippet from Lewis himself, where he makes it clear that our lipstick-wearing, nylon-loving lady is not enjoying the fruits of the Promised Land anytime soon: “The books don’t tell us what happened to Susan. She is left alive in this world at the end, having by then turned into a rather silly, conceited young woman. But there’s plenty of time for her to mend and perhaps she will get to Aslan’s country in the end… in her own way…” Even while he offers us a glimmer of hope, one can’t help but wince at the last lines. ‘Plenty of time for her to mend’ what, exactly? What is so indisputably repulsive about Susan craving extremely normal things, for a girl of her age? Why is there an immediate need to demonise a female character who chooses to beautify herself with makeup and pretty clothes? Since then, Susan’s crisis has attracted plenty of sympathetic voices from the literary community: Philip Pullman, Neil Gaiman, J K Rowling - to name a few, with Gaiman even creating a sort of spinoff short story with a very Susan-esque protagonist, giving her a much-needed voice and agency. Still, the older Pevensie sister remains an outcast of Narnia, a scarring reminder of what happens to girls who dare to be…well, just be. The ugly implications of girlish existence in Lewis’ ramrod world of old laws and deep magic are proof enough. Speaking of Rowling, an interesting and somewhat ironic fact is that while the Harry Potter series, on the forefront, seems chock-full of strong, three-dimensional female characters, there is something slightly problematic in the way she treats any character that teeters dangerously into girly-girl territory. Two classic examples are Cho Chang, Harry’s first girlfriend, who is constantly vilified for being ‘too emotional’ and too mopey over her dead boyfriend, and Fleur Delacour, who while she gets a much better conclusion, is still written off as the shallow dumb blonde, with a subpar performance in the Triwizard tournament where she’s the only female competitor. Cho is eventually cast aside for Ginny, whom Harry considers wonderful because she is ‘rarely weepy’. Constant misogynistic and slightly racist jabs are directed at Fleur by none other than Molly and Ginny Weasley, two of the most glorified and celebrated women in Harry’s life. Not even the minor characters escape judgement: the Patil twins and Lavender Brown, bubblier and more extroverted classmates of Hermione, are often reduced to nothing but cartoonish caricatures vying for Harry and Ron’s affections in the movies. Besides the evocation of unpleasant racial overtones, it’s something to think about, really. Where does mild, school cliché-centric humour end and perpetual bracketing-and-bashing of softness and generic girlishness begin? My personal favourite though, is the much-hated Amy March from Little Women. Amy’s case is particularly interesting because Alcott never meant to malign her, no, it’s the audience, unable to look past their ‘JO x LAURIE ENDGAME’ stupor, who miss the whole point of Amy’s arc - the resourcefulness in her choice to work within the conventions of traditional femininity instead of rebelling against it, the raw honesty in her desire as an impoverished girl to enjoy pretty material pleasures, the flaws and petty mistakes she succumbs to, because she is not written to be liked, she is written to be real. Jo’s struggles are very earthy and very honest, and her staunch refusal to fit in and fulfil societal expectations is admirable, but Amy’s willingness to maintain a sort of harmony with her community and work towards self-fulfilment…how is that, in any way, less gratifying? And for that matter, what do all these endless debates actually uncover? What does this hollow classification system of girls into badasses and girly-girls entail? The answer is uncertain, but it’s surely not an easy one. One cannot simply go for a shallow deconstruction of the not-like-other-girls syndrome without looking into why this syndrome had to arise at all. And then one finds that the root of this bizarre phenomenon lies in square one: the trivialisation of tenderness in girls and women, leading many to think that female voices and characters might not be taken seriously unless they are stripped away of all that could possibly hint at compassion and clemency. While Katniss Everdeen, Merida and the warrior heroines of some of the later Young Adult franchises may have arrived at exactly the right moment to prevent oversaturation of the market by the same kind of feminine representation, the boomerang effect that arose out of this is girls, in the younger demographic, seeking validation by rejecting and loudly denouncing traits that could possibly mark them as girly. This denunciation shows an almost vitriolic hatred in harmless things, marked out as extremely feminine motifs: anything pink and/or coded as princessy being the commonest examples. It’s alarming, it’s potentially harmful that the psyche of girls is shaped by what they shouldn’t be as opposed to what they prefer to be, it leans towards the patriarchy having the last laugh at the end. Most importantly, as hackneyed as this sounds, there is nothing more reproachable than the actions and behaviour of one woman being tainted so as to glorify another. Feminism and badassery don’t spring just from elaborate fight sequences or by being completely stone-cold or perpetually displeased and in a fighting stance. Yes, female characters so portrayed are valid, beautiful, even necessary. But they are not the beginning and end of all that’s marvellous and awe-inspiring about women. It’s definitely heartening to see a much more positive and varied portrayal of sharp and brilliant women in contemporary media, who don’t always depend on brawn or magic to achieve unanimous approval, take the famous Elle Woods (Legally Blonde) for example, a wonderful subversion of the dumb blonde stereotype. So while we praise Arya for knifing through her tormentors, we cannot forget Sansa, who comforts children and women with songs during a battle; we can celebrate angry, rebellious spirits without coming for gentle, tranquil hearts. We can cherish both sides of the spectrum. We can appreciate that some rebellions happen quietly, in utter tranquillity, glossed with pink and flowers. We can, for once, not let the patriarchy win. And maybe, just maybe at the end, Susan, the outcast of Narnia, no longer a powerful queen but just gloriously and heartbreakingly a human girl, will have the last laugh.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Beauty And Brazen: The World Of Berserk</title>
      <link href="/Beauty-and-Brazen" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beauty And Brazen: The World Of Berserk" />
      <published>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Beauty-and-Brazen</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Beauty-and-Brazen">&lt;p&gt;“No matter how strong, for a human to fight a monster means he has submerged his
humanity and transformed himself into a greater monster.” – Schierke in
&lt;em&gt;Berserk.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friedrich Nietzsche was a philosopher who was well beyond the comprehension of
other philosophers of his time or even those of modern times. He had, to say the
least, an interesting childhood, which transformed him into what he was as an
adult, and also metamorphosed him into a lunatic during the later stages of his
life. His biography largely signifies what it is to be a human dangerously close
to the &lt;strong&gt;Truth&lt;/strong&gt; and yet so far away. This is what makes his works all the more
interesting and true gems in the realm of literary masterpieces. Little did he
know how much he was going to inspire a certain mangaka named Kentaro Miura to
script a saga. This saga is Miura’s visualisation of the struggle Nietzsche
refers to as the journey of a man to defy his limits and be, what he considered
to be, the future of humanity, &lt;em&gt;Ubermensch&lt;/em&gt;, roughly translated to ‘Over Man’.
Thus begins the journey of &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; and its protagonist, the most bad*rse
anime/manga character in history, &lt;em&gt;Guts&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; is a story which encompasses the journey of an individual, against the
very flow of his fate. Causality plays an integral part in the tale. The story
is clear on how a man is bound by his fate and whether he likes it or not, fate
&lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; overtake him and he &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be entwined with his future, with what is
already pre-decided for him. It is a brutal reminder that our free will is not
always free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche was a sceptic about causality and his views are well illustrated in
&lt;em&gt;Twilight of the Idols&lt;/em&gt;, where he referred to causality as the cause of
humankind’s general inability to accept the unknown. Humans are always yearning
to explain the ‘logic and reason’ behind events. Nietzsche calls this the cause
behind ‘The Four Great Errors’; arguing that causes are reimagined in order to
support the reason for our existence. Nietzsche denied in &lt;em&gt;Twilight&lt;/em&gt; that free
will is free at all and rather argued that it is a method by which theologians
exert their control over humanity. The invention of a human free will, Nietzsche
thought, was rooted in a human drive to punish and judge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; challenges the very concept of faith or judgement through a
protagonist who faces the vicious current of fate and still goes on defying it,
at every turn. Guts was born from the corpse of his dead mother, who had been
hanged. He was found by a mercenary and his wife, who then took care of him.
When his adoptive mother passes away, his adoptive father tries to kill him.
Guts is forced to escape the mercenary camp and the only family he has known, to
survive in the wild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironic though it may be, our protagonist, Guts ends up joining another mercenary
group that was under the leadership of a charming leader called Griffith. He
falls in love with a female soldier named Casca. Several events take place, and
the ‘causality’ of events ultimately leads to a betrayal, whereby Griffith
sacrifices all the members of his group in order to gain power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sacrificial event, commonly referred to as &lt;em&gt;Eclipse&lt;/em&gt;, is a momentous image
of Nietzsche’s views on human struggle. Guts helplessly watches his comrades get
killed and devoured by monsters and is forced to watch the love of his life get
violated by the same person he once considered to be his friend, Griffith. He
does eventually find his way out of the situation but not without sustaining
several scars of his own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guts’ story is a struggle of achieving the unimaginable. Nietzsche in, arguably
his most interesting piece of work, &lt;em&gt;Thus Spoke Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt; introduced the
concept of the ‘Overman’. He discusses how we are spiritually and
philosophically entwined with the struggles of our mind and overcoming them is
an integral part of one’s journey. He discusses man’s journey in three steps:
The Camel, The Lion and The Child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Camel is the first step of one’s journey. The Camel yearns to gain the
knowledge of the &lt;em&gt;Dragon&lt;/em&gt; (the essence of the ultimate knowledge) and therefore
listens to whatever everyone says and acts on it, without listening to himself.
As Guts put it himself, “One who does something he hates just because he is told
to…is called an errand boy.” This is the nature of the Camel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Camel finally sees how futile it is to lose one’s own will to others’
demands and begins to challenge himself is when the transformation to become a
Lion takes place. The Lion is a symbol of aggression and rage against the system
in order to challenge the themes which are generally considered rightful. The
Lion challenges concepts of right and wrong and is a passive aggressor, most of
the time presenting his views against the system, whilst remaining within the
system himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is until the final transition to being a Child takes place. According to
Nietzsche, this is the final transition, when the Lion transcends into a being
who is above the constraints of society, and is therefore powerful enough to
struggle and overcome. I believe this is how Kentaro Miura too visualises Guts’
transition, whose change from a person who fought for no reason and wanted to
integrate with society to someone who is ready to challenge everyone else who
defies his goal, which is to protect the person closest to him. Guts is the very
epitome of the Overman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very interesting philosophy of Nietzsche is presented in the dynamics of the
Higher Man and the Common. According to Nietzsche, all company is bad company,
unless it is the company of the equal. Nietzsche stressed on the philosophy of a
society being divided into two parts; the Higher Man and the Common Man.
Nietzsche says that it is very difficult for either of them to understand the
other, however, the Common Man places his trust in the Higher Man as a part of
this ambition. &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt;, in the same manner, brings about the reference of
Higher Man, which is Griffith. The men, who are led by Griffith, do not
understand him completely and Griffith, in the same manner, does not understand
the wants of his own men. The only thing that mattered was Griffith’s goal, the
light of which is “strong enough for every one of them to bring together all
their goals and dreams as one.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche once said, “There have been two great narcotics in the history of
Europe. Christianity and Alcohol.” He saw religion as a restriction to
resentment and envy, which he believed to be the driving source of one’s true
goals in life. He saw religion as a way for Common Men to cling to their beliefs
and demonise and ostracise whatever they could not gain. This symbolism has been
highlighted in &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt;, where we are informed of the existence of a
monotheistic religion, termed as the &lt;em&gt;Holy See&lt;/em&gt;, whose ideals bear similarity to
Christianity. The greatest proponents of the Holy See were hideous creatures who
could go to any lengths in order to protect their faith (duh much). Kentaro
Miura, yet again, portrays the meanings of resentment and struggling against all
odds, through Guts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; has given us a character whom we all can understand, someone who is
all too human; made up of faults like the rest of us, truly embodying the spirit
of a fighter. &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt;, in its own uncanny ways, could be discussed and
deliberated upon as a testament of Nietzsche’s greatest influences, all compiled
under a single saga: a struggle of one who is always destined to be the ‘Higher
Man’, despite not being from the nobility. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“No matter how strong, for a human to fight a monster means he has submerged his humanity and transformed himself into a greater monster.” – Schierke in Berserk. Friedrich Nietzsche was a philosopher who was well beyond the comprehension of other philosophers of his time or even those of modern times. He had, to say the least, an interesting childhood, which transformed him into what he was as an adult, and also metamorphosed him into a lunatic during the later stages of his life. His biography largely signifies what it is to be a human dangerously close to the Truth and yet so far away. This is what makes his works all the more interesting and true gems in the realm of literary masterpieces. Little did he know how much he was going to inspire a certain mangaka named Kentaro Miura to script a saga. This saga is Miura’s visualisation of the struggle Nietzsche refers to as the journey of a man to defy his limits and be, what he considered to be, the future of humanity, Ubermensch, roughly translated to ‘Over Man’. Thus begins the journey of Berserk and its protagonist, the most bad*rse anime/manga character in history, Guts. Berserk is a story which encompasses the journey of an individual, against the very flow of his fate. Causality plays an integral part in the tale. The story is clear on how a man is bound by his fate and whether he likes it or not, fate will overtake him and he will be entwined with his future, with what is already pre-decided for him. It is a brutal reminder that our free will is not always free. Nietzsche was a sceptic about causality and his views are well illustrated in Twilight of the Idols, where he referred to causality as the cause of humankind’s general inability to accept the unknown. Humans are always yearning to explain the ‘logic and reason’ behind events. Nietzsche calls this the cause behind ‘The Four Great Errors’; arguing that causes are reimagined in order to support the reason for our existence. Nietzsche denied in Twilight that free will is free at all and rather argued that it is a method by which theologians exert their control over humanity. The invention of a human free will, Nietzsche thought, was rooted in a human drive to punish and judge. Berserk challenges the very concept of faith or judgement through a protagonist who faces the vicious current of fate and still goes on defying it, at every turn. Guts was born from the corpse of his dead mother, who had been hanged. He was found by a mercenary and his wife, who then took care of him. When his adoptive mother passes away, his adoptive father tries to kill him. Guts is forced to escape the mercenary camp and the only family he has known, to survive in the wild. Ironic though it may be, our protagonist, Guts ends up joining another mercenary group that was under the leadership of a charming leader called Griffith. He falls in love with a female soldier named Casca. Several events take place, and the ‘causality’ of events ultimately leads to a betrayal, whereby Griffith sacrifices all the members of his group in order to gain power. The sacrificial event, commonly referred to as Eclipse, is a momentous image of Nietzsche’s views on human struggle. Guts helplessly watches his comrades get killed and devoured by monsters and is forced to watch the love of his life get violated by the same person he once considered to be his friend, Griffith. He does eventually find his way out of the situation but not without sustaining several scars of his own. Guts’ story is a struggle of achieving the unimaginable. Nietzsche in, arguably his most interesting piece of work, Thus Spoke Zarathustra introduced the concept of the ‘Overman’. He discusses how we are spiritually and philosophically entwined with the struggles of our mind and overcoming them is an integral part of one’s journey. He discusses man’s journey in three steps: The Camel, The Lion and The Child. The Camel is the first step of one’s journey. The Camel yearns to gain the knowledge of the Dragon (the essence of the ultimate knowledge) and therefore listens to whatever everyone says and acts on it, without listening to himself. As Guts put it himself, “One who does something he hates just because he is told to…is called an errand boy.” This is the nature of the Camel. When the Camel finally sees how futile it is to lose one’s own will to others’ demands and begins to challenge himself is when the transformation to become a Lion takes place. The Lion is a symbol of aggression and rage against the system in order to challenge the themes which are generally considered rightful. The Lion challenges concepts of right and wrong and is a passive aggressor, most of the time presenting his views against the system, whilst remaining within the system himself. That is until the final transition to being a Child takes place. According to Nietzsche, this is the final transition, when the Lion transcends into a being who is above the constraints of society, and is therefore powerful enough to struggle and overcome. I believe this is how Kentaro Miura too visualises Guts’ transition, whose change from a person who fought for no reason and wanted to integrate with society to someone who is ready to challenge everyone else who defies his goal, which is to protect the person closest to him. Guts is the very epitome of the Overman. A very interesting philosophy of Nietzsche is presented in the dynamics of the Higher Man and the Common. According to Nietzsche, all company is bad company, unless it is the company of the equal. Nietzsche stressed on the philosophy of a society being divided into two parts; the Higher Man and the Common Man. Nietzsche says that it is very difficult for either of them to understand the other, however, the Common Man places his trust in the Higher Man as a part of this ambition. Berserk, in the same manner, brings about the reference of Higher Man, which is Griffith. The men, who are led by Griffith, do not understand him completely and Griffith, in the same manner, does not understand the wants of his own men. The only thing that mattered was Griffith’s goal, the light of which is “strong enough for every one of them to bring together all their goals and dreams as one.” Nietzsche once said, “There have been two great narcotics in the history of Europe. Christianity and Alcohol.” He saw religion as a restriction to resentment and envy, which he believed to be the driving source of one’s true goals in life. He saw religion as a way for Common Men to cling to their beliefs and demonise and ostracise whatever they could not gain. This symbolism has been highlighted in Berserk, where we are informed of the existence of a monotheistic religion, termed as the Holy See, whose ideals bear similarity to Christianity. The greatest proponents of the Holy See were hideous creatures who could go to any lengths in order to protect their faith (duh much). Kentaro Miura, yet again, portrays the meanings of resentment and struggling against all odds, through Guts. Berserk has given us a character whom we all can understand, someone who is all too human; made up of faults like the rest of us, truly embodying the spirit of a fighter. Berserk, in its own uncanny ways, could be discussed and deliberated upon as a testament of Nietzsche’s greatest influences, all compiled under a single saga: a struggle of one who is always destined to be the ‘Higher Man’, despite not being from the nobility. </summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Lived Experience Through The Lens of Pop Culture</title>
      <link href="/The-Lens-of-Pop-Culture" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Lived Experience Through The Lens of Pop Culture" />
      <published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Lens-of-Pop-Culture</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Lens-of-Pop-Culture">&lt;p&gt;Pop culture was never meant to be therapeutic for the conscience. It was merely
an escape from reality, a make-believe world where you could imagine yourself as
Clint Eastwood on a horse, or as Sylvester Stallone being one hell of a southpaw
boxer. Or, it could have been you taking acid during a Jimi Hendrix concert, or
raging with the grunge bands of the 90’s. It was only in the 2000’s, the
millennial age, when mainstream pop culture became a place for the reclamation
of maligned narratives. Finally, a space on the global stage for those with
little social capital. Be it non-cisgender people, African-Americans, Latinos or
people with clinical depression; the millennial age did more than take note of
these problems, it made sure that they were heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to strip the periods before that of credit for their art. Movies
like &lt;em&gt;Forrest Gump&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Platoon&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Apocalypse Now&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Deer Hunter&lt;/em&gt; surely
gave an insight into the prevailing anti-war sentiment in the USA and the
protests by soldiers’ families. These movies could, however, very well be termed
‘Oscar bait’, and they got swept away in the same instead of provoking perhaps
finer, more nuanced details of, say, military life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a movie like &lt;em&gt;Driving Miss Daisy&lt;/em&gt;, for example. It won the Best Picture
Oscar in 1980, but its premise might make one skeptical about the award. Apart
from the hailing of a  ‘white saviour’, the film also promoted stereotypes about
Afro-Americans; illiterate, not self dependent, helpless people who don’t know
what to do in the face of problems. They’re undermined in their own stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference between that time and today, however, is that our generation
won’t shy away from criticising such films. The films of yore too are
scrutinised under the modern lens of how an ideal world must be; a
post-postmodern critique, if you will. That’s how the image of &lt;em&gt;James Bond&lt;/em&gt; has
evolved. There is no denying that people did not take to a one-dimensional
womanizer spy with cheeky sensibilities and a way to escape every situation
effortlessly. They wanted someone more vulnerable and mortal, and possibly not a
man, which is evident in the recent wave of Bond movies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, take a look at the movies and shows of today. &lt;em&gt;Get Out&lt;/em&gt; was a pivotal
movie that took shots at liberals for ‘acting black’, thinking that that would
solve racism. A less-talked-about but incredibly influential show was the Donald
Glover show &lt;em&gt;Atlanta&lt;/em&gt;, that was hailed by many Atlanta natives as a true
portrayal of life and culture in the city. The show humanised Afro-Americans.
This trend extends to a lot of shows, like &lt;em&gt;Orange Is The New Black&lt;/em&gt;, that
eventually went beyond the lead character and ended up becoming one of the most
inclusive shows in recent times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mainstream music has also changed drastically over the past two decades. Hip-hop&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a genre often criticised for the use of homophobic slurs as a metric for
masculinity - has now included artists like Tyler, The Creator, and more
recently, Lil Nas X who thought it was safe enough to reveal their sexualities
and talk about their experiences through their music. Notably, Tyler was accused
of using one such slur. Musicians such as St Vincent and Troye Sivan have been
much more open about the same throughout their discography.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conscious hip-hop has also gained popularity, with the advent of artists like
Kendrick Lamar and Kanye West, who wrap messages and lived experiences in ear
candy. Even pop stars like Beyonce and Lady Gaga have been using their global
influence to further discussions that several years ago would have been
considered too taboo to even be talked about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does this increasing demand for inclusivity tell us? We, the
millennials, want our screens to show us something that evokes not merely
sympathy but also empathy. We want to see lived experiences. We do not want
tokenistic gestures of inclusivity, but full-blooded accounts of stories about
people that are not necessarily us. The idea that racism is over simply because
a privileged character learns about the struggles of the ostracised minority,
has been running for all of Hollywood’s existence; Hollywood’s systemic Oscar
bait and guaranteed cash churning mechanism. Authentic stories, like real life,
are possibly boring to them. They also forget the one rule of moviemaking: do
not underestimate the audience. The same goes for music: concept albums exist to
tell a story that’s beyond our imagination. Millennials, especially those who
are part of the minority have become fed up of the fact that they can not see
any entertainment that resembles them. They expect human depictions of what it
means to belong to their race, religion, caste or gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might even argue that the severance of human connection has left us seeking
something &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; in our cinema. The millennial is looking for relatability and
human fallibility more than he is looking for fantasy. The craving to feel is
seen in how much readership emo Tumblr experiences achieve or in how much shows
like BoJack Horseman shine. BoJack Horseman is highly acclaimed primarily
because it really touches a nerve, in millennials, in the domain of mental
health. It lets its viewers comprehend the consequences of such actions that
already might have happened to them. Besides, the idea then also becomes about
combining reality and fantasy, brutality and comedy, to make more high-end
surreal art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is definitely the tough question that all of this poses: do we really need
more and more art to get us to empathise with something? Isn’t once enough? To
be honest, we are all guilty of it, including this writer here. It becomes a
global statement, that our inaction, or our perception is part of the problem,
if not the actual problem. But it has been done before, with resounding success.
During the #BlackLivesMatter movement in 2015, Kendrick Lamar released his hit
song &lt;em&gt;Alright&lt;/em&gt;. The refrain “We gon’ be alright” became the cry of the rally for
some time and unified the protestors. We do not need conscious art to feel good
about ourselves because we have seen/heard it; we need it to make us better
people, if at all we really need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that inclusion and adequate representation in media has taken a
much higher priority today as compared to earlier times. A UCLA study on
diversity in Hollywood states that people of colour have quadrupled their share
of broadcast television from 5.1% in 2011-12 to 21.5% in 2017-18.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennials are better educated as compared to previous generations, with 39% of
people having a bachelor’s degree or higher; to compare, at the same age, the
same statistic was 29% for Gen X, around 25% for baby boomers, and 15% for the
Silent Generation. Higher education is becoming accessible to people of various
cultures. The Deloitte Global Millennial Survey talks about how millennials only
like firms that abide by their values, and any non-adherence to consumer values
on their part will make them or break them. People are more receptive to
personal and social problems, and while there are a myriad of surveys pointing
to how millennials are becoming less empathetic, one can not deny that it is the
millennials who are shaping narratives about intersectionality, privilege, class
and race amongst other things. Call it political correctness or call it
sensitivity, it has arguably bettered the debate. It is this nuance that is
slowly but surely influencing content around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quintessential to this is the scenario of Indian stand-up comedy. After the
calling out of the prevalence of sexual harassment in what was perceived as a
circle that was &lt;em&gt;woke just for show&lt;/em&gt;, female comedians have been earning what’s
due to them. Their jokes are a lot more oriented towards the female experience,
quite naturally, whilst their other observations are arguably spot on. In
another example, TVF’s &lt;em&gt;Kota Factory&lt;/em&gt; created ripples across the student
community in India for its bleak but true depiction of the city. Engineering
students possibly shed tears at the time the show was released because they saw
their life reflected in it. Millennials are both creating and consuming bold
content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studios understand the importance of discourse for long-term retention of the
millennial as a consumer. This is evident in the shifts in strategy by platforms
such as Netflix towards creating content that is politically or socially
charged. These shifts in strategy betray how they see their consumers; as a
generation that wants to confront socio-politico realities head on. As a
generation that is so desperate to connect to the characters on screen, to view
life through the lens of cinema as a way of trying to make sense of our own
troubles and our trauma. We seek a lot fewer heroes and a lot more flawed humans
in our cinema.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pranav Manie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Pop culture was never meant to be therapeutic for the conscience. It was merely an escape from reality, a make-believe world where you could imagine yourself as Clint Eastwood on a horse, or as Sylvester Stallone being one hell of a southpaw boxer. Or, it could have been you taking acid during a Jimi Hendrix concert, or raging with the grunge bands of the 90’s. It was only in the 2000’s, the millennial age, when mainstream pop culture became a place for the reclamation of maligned narratives. Finally, a space on the global stage for those with little social capital. Be it non-cisgender people, African-Americans, Latinos or people with clinical depression; the millennial age did more than take note of these problems, it made sure that they were heard. This is not to strip the periods before that of credit for their art. Movies like Forrest Gump, Platoon, Apocalypse Now and The Deer Hunter surely gave an insight into the prevailing anti-war sentiment in the USA and the protests by soldiers’ families. These movies could, however, very well be termed ‘Oscar bait’, and they got swept away in the same instead of provoking perhaps finer, more nuanced details of, say, military life.   Take a movie like Driving Miss Daisy, for example. It won the Best Picture Oscar in 1980, but its premise might make one skeptical about the award. Apart from the hailing of a  ‘white saviour’, the film also promoted stereotypes about Afro-Americans; illiterate, not self dependent, helpless people who don’t know what to do in the face of problems. They’re undermined in their own stories. The difference between that time and today, however, is that our generation won’t shy away from criticising such films. The films of yore too are scrutinised under the modern lens of how an ideal world must be; a post-postmodern critique, if you will. That’s how the image of James Bond has evolved. There is no denying that people did not take to a one-dimensional womanizer spy with cheeky sensibilities and a way to escape every situation effortlessly. They wanted someone more vulnerable and mortal, and possibly not a man, which is evident in the recent wave of Bond movies. Moreover, take a look at the movies and shows of today. Get Out was a pivotal movie that took shots at liberals for ‘acting black’, thinking that that would solve racism. A less-talked-about but incredibly influential show was the Donald Glover show Atlanta, that was hailed by many Atlanta natives as a true portrayal of life and culture in the city. The show humanised Afro-Americans. This trend extends to a lot of shows, like Orange Is The New Black, that eventually went beyond the lead character and ended up becoming one of the most inclusive shows in recent times. Mainstream music has also changed drastically over the past two decades. Hip-hop a genre often criticised for the use of homophobic slurs as a metric for masculinity - has now included artists like Tyler, The Creator, and more recently, Lil Nas X who thought it was safe enough to reveal their sexualities and talk about their experiences through their music. Notably, Tyler was accused of using one such slur. Musicians such as St Vincent and Troye Sivan have been much more open about the same throughout their discography. Conscious hip-hop has also gained popularity, with the advent of artists like Kendrick Lamar and Kanye West, who wrap messages and lived experiences in ear candy. Even pop stars like Beyonce and Lady Gaga have been using their global influence to further discussions that several years ago would have been considered too taboo to even be talked about. But what does this increasing demand for inclusivity tell us? We, the millennials, want our screens to show us something that evokes not merely sympathy but also empathy. We want to see lived experiences. We do not want tokenistic gestures of inclusivity, but full-blooded accounts of stories about people that are not necessarily us. The idea that racism is over simply because a privileged character learns about the struggles of the ostracised minority, has been running for all of Hollywood’s existence; Hollywood’s systemic Oscar bait and guaranteed cash churning mechanism. Authentic stories, like real life, are possibly boring to them. They also forget the one rule of moviemaking: do not underestimate the audience. The same goes for music: concept albums exist to tell a story that’s beyond our imagination. Millennials, especially those who are part of the minority have become fed up of the fact that they can not see any entertainment that resembles them. They expect human depictions of what it means to belong to their race, religion, caste or gender. One might even argue that the severance of human connection has left us seeking something real in our cinema. The millennial is looking for relatability and human fallibility more than he is looking for fantasy. The craving to feel is seen in how much readership emo Tumblr experiences achieve or in how much shows like BoJack Horseman shine. BoJack Horseman is highly acclaimed primarily because it really touches a nerve, in millennials, in the domain of mental health. It lets its viewers comprehend the consequences of such actions that already might have happened to them. Besides, the idea then also becomes about combining reality and fantasy, brutality and comedy, to make more high-end surreal art. There is definitely the tough question that all of this poses: do we really need more and more art to get us to empathise with something? Isn’t once enough? To be honest, we are all guilty of it, including this writer here. It becomes a global statement, that our inaction, or our perception is part of the problem, if not the actual problem. But it has been done before, with resounding success. During the #BlackLivesMatter movement in 2015, Kendrick Lamar released his hit song Alright. The refrain “We gon’ be alright” became the cry of the rally for some time and unified the protestors. We do not need conscious art to feel good about ourselves because we have seen/heard it; we need it to make us better people, if at all we really need it. The good news is that inclusion and adequate representation in media has taken a much higher priority today as compared to earlier times. A UCLA study on diversity in Hollywood states that people of colour have quadrupled their share of broadcast television from 5.1% in 2011-12 to 21.5% in 2017-18. Millennials are better educated as compared to previous generations, with 39% of people having a bachelor’s degree or higher; to compare, at the same age, the same statistic was 29% for Gen X, around 25% for baby boomers, and 15% for the Silent Generation. Higher education is becoming accessible to people of various cultures. The Deloitte Global Millennial Survey talks about how millennials only like firms that abide by their values, and any non-adherence to consumer values on their part will make them or break them. People are more receptive to personal and social problems, and while there are a myriad of surveys pointing to how millennials are becoming less empathetic, one can not deny that it is the millennials who are shaping narratives about intersectionality, privilege, class and race amongst other things. Call it political correctness or call it sensitivity, it has arguably bettered the debate. It is this nuance that is slowly but surely influencing content around us.   Quintessential to this is the scenario of Indian stand-up comedy. After the calling out of the prevalence of sexual harassment in what was perceived as a circle that was woke just for show, female comedians have been earning what’s due to them. Their jokes are a lot more oriented towards the female experience, quite naturally, whilst their other observations are arguably spot on. In another example, TVF’s Kota Factory created ripples across the student community in India for its bleak but true depiction of the city. Engineering students possibly shed tears at the time the show was released because they saw their life reflected in it. Millennials are both creating and consuming bold content. Studios understand the importance of discourse for long-term retention of the millennial as a consumer. This is evident in the shifts in strategy by platforms such as Netflix towards creating content that is politically or socially charged. These shifts in strategy betray how they see their consumers; as a generation that wants to confront socio-politico realities head on. As a generation that is so desperate to connect to the characters on screen, to view life through the lens of cinema as a way of trying to make sense of our own troubles and our trauma. We seek a lot fewer heroes and a lot more flawed humans in our cinema.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Rise of the Screen Thriller</title>
      <link href="/Rise-of-the-Screen-Killer" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rise of the Screen Thriller" />
      <published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Rise-of-the-Screen-Killer</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Rise-of-the-Screen-Killer">&lt;p&gt;Internet culture has pervaded scriptwriting in various ways. It has provided
useful ways of releasing information to the audience. Meme culture, ways of
writing texts, or communication through a certain type of media reveals a
subtext previously unknown, but in every conversation that follows, you consider
these subtexts to figure out how the situation will unfold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the BBC masterpiece, &lt;em&gt;Sherlock&lt;/em&gt;, for example. Sherlock is quite often in
contact with his arch-nemesis Jim Moriarty, and we know that through the message
bubbles which pop up on the screen for us to see whilst we simultaneously
observe Sherlock’s expressions. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; portrays the internet the best -
take an episode like &lt;em&gt;Nosedive&lt;/em&gt;; a brutal, horrifying account of what happens if
we introduce a social credit rating for humans or &lt;em&gt;Shut Up And Dance&lt;/em&gt;; an
episode that’ll instantly make you cover your webcam with some tape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These, however, are still conventional ways of storytelling. Even though the
aforementioned devices make use of internet culture, they still fall short of
being able to harness the full power of what someone experiences when online.
The need to harness and depict that is what led to the &lt;em&gt;computer screen
thriller&lt;/em&gt; being born - a stylish new method of movie-making. Most or all of the
film takes place on some kind of a screen be it the computer, phone or
television. This subgenre of films made its biggest splash with the release of
&lt;em&gt;Searching&lt;/em&gt;, a movie with John Cho playing the lead, about a father searching
for his missing daughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the roots of this subgenre go back way before 2018. The first
documented screen-only movie was &lt;em&gt;The Collingswood Story&lt;/em&gt;, which is about an
online long-distance relationship gone wrong. It takes place through webcams.
The real wave of this subgenre started about a decade later with the movie
&lt;em&gt;Unfriended&lt;/em&gt;, which revolved around cyberbullying among high-school students. It
made $64 million in revenue against a budget of $1 million. A Russian
director, Timur Bekmambetov co-produced it, thereby beginning his dedication to
this subgenre that he calls &lt;em&gt;Screen Life&lt;/em&gt;. He produced a sequel to the movie, as
well as &lt;em&gt;Searching,&lt;/em&gt; and directed one of his own called &lt;em&gt;Profile.&lt;/em&gt; There were
other short films in and around 2013-2015, which seemingly inspired the TV show
&lt;em&gt;Modern Family&lt;/em&gt; to go the same route with one of their episodes. It is hailed by
many as one of the best episodes of the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real question, however, is this: is there something much deeper to the
Screen Life or is it just a gimmick to make things flashy? Much of the
information can be revealed without using screens throughout. &lt;em&gt;Sherlock&lt;/em&gt; was
able to demonstrate it well. The TV show &lt;em&gt;American Vandal&lt;/em&gt; was themed around
internet culture, and used it to its advantage. Even &lt;em&gt;13 Reasons Why&lt;/em&gt; could be
credited for the same; one can see that this trend is directed towards
millennials, because their lives revolve around screens the most. Modern
film-making has allowed the blending of actions on the web and reactions to it
for us to simultaneously consume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These films have much smaller budgets. The return on investment can be immense.
&lt;em&gt;Searching&lt;/em&gt; made $75 million against a budget of $1 million, and &lt;em&gt;Unfriended&lt;/em&gt;
made 64 times its budget. But is there more to this subgenre than meets the eye?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first glance, one can see that this style expresses a lot by saying little.
Social media tells us about habits, likes and desires not just of the user but
also of people engaging with said user. It is the rapidity with which the story
gets out that makes screen thrillers this gripping. When people are online and
texting each other, the messages, the time taken to reply, or the choice to not
reply at all, everything leads to some assumptions in both the audience and the
characters. This technique plays upon our conditioning to believe that tiny
things are indicators of something large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to hide porn from your parents, you naturally put it in some folder
in an extreme corner of the depths of your desktop. And when your parents find
out they are shocked and upset. The way those reactions get captured in a screen
thriller is unparalleled. The screen need not resort to edits or cut-aways to
show the reaction; it is right there. The actor reacts at the same time as the
audience does, they are as much the spectator as we are. The lesser reliance on
cut-aways directly takes the audience on the protagonist’s journey. While not
exclusive to the genre, Screen Life films surely help bring out the often
shocking difference that exists between our lives and our personas, in real life
and online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These films come attached with a sense of claustrophobia, to say the least. The
screen is crowded with pop-ups, the user keeps switching between tabs and
windows. This adds to not only the pace of the film but also the paranoia of the
viewer. Every step of the way, there lurks a  fear, it is like you are always
waiting for the next development. You are excited for what comes next, no matter
how deeply personal or confidential it might be for the victim. Not that that is
wrong; it is a story, after all. But it does explain something about the human
desire to voyeur over others’ lives; both the good and the bad. As David
Fincher, the director of &lt;em&gt;The Social Network&lt;/em&gt; says, “People are perverts.” They
want to know the truth, but the kicker is that it will be ugly. Nevertheless,
they will love it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pranav Manie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Internet culture has pervaded scriptwriting in various ways. It has provided useful ways of releasing information to the audience. Meme culture, ways of writing texts, or communication through a certain type of media reveals a subtext previously unknown, but in every conversation that follows, you consider these subtexts to figure out how the situation will unfold. Take the BBC masterpiece, Sherlock, for example. Sherlock is quite often in contact with his arch-nemesis Jim Moriarty, and we know that through the message bubbles which pop up on the screen for us to see whilst we simultaneously observe Sherlock’s expressions. Black Mirror portrays the internet the best - take an episode like Nosedive; a brutal, horrifying account of what happens if we introduce a social credit rating for humans or Shut Up And Dance; an episode that’ll instantly make you cover your webcam with some tape. These, however, are still conventional ways of storytelling. Even though the aforementioned devices make use of internet culture, they still fall short of being able to harness the full power of what someone experiences when online. The need to harness and depict that is what led to the computer screen thriller being born - a stylish new method of movie-making. Most or all of the film takes place on some kind of a screen be it the computer, phone or television. This subgenre of films made its biggest splash with the release of Searching, a movie with John Cho playing the lead, about a father searching for his missing daughter. However, the roots of this subgenre go back way before 2018. The first documented screen-only movie was The Collingswood Story, which is about an online long-distance relationship gone wrong. It takes place through webcams. The real wave of this subgenre started about a decade later with the movie Unfriended, which revolved around cyberbullying among high-school students. It made $64 million in revenue against a budget of $1 million. A Russian director, Timur Bekmambetov co-produced it, thereby beginning his dedication to this subgenre that he calls Screen Life. He produced a sequel to the movie, as well as Searching, and directed one of his own called Profile. There were other short films in and around 2013-2015, which seemingly inspired the TV show Modern Family to go the same route with one of their episodes. It is hailed by many as one of the best episodes of the show. The real question, however, is this: is there something much deeper to the Screen Life or is it just a gimmick to make things flashy? Much of the information can be revealed without using screens throughout. Sherlock was able to demonstrate it well. The TV show American Vandal was themed around internet culture, and used it to its advantage. Even 13 Reasons Why could be credited for the same; one can see that this trend is directed towards millennials, because their lives revolve around screens the most. Modern film-making has allowed the blending of actions on the web and reactions to it for us to simultaneously consume. These films have much smaller budgets. The return on investment can be immense. Searching made $75 million against a budget of $1 million, and Unfriended made 64 times its budget. But is there more to this subgenre than meets the eye? At first glance, one can see that this style expresses a lot by saying little. Social media tells us about habits, likes and desires not just of the user but also of people engaging with said user. It is the rapidity with which the story gets out that makes screen thrillers this gripping. When people are online and texting each other, the messages, the time taken to reply, or the choice to not reply at all, everything leads to some assumptions in both the audience and the characters. This technique plays upon our conditioning to believe that tiny things are indicators of something large. If you want to hide porn from your parents, you naturally put it in some folder in an extreme corner of the depths of your desktop. And when your parents find out they are shocked and upset. The way those reactions get captured in a screen thriller is unparalleled. The screen need not resort to edits or cut-aways to show the reaction; it is right there. The actor reacts at the same time as the audience does, they are as much the spectator as we are. The lesser reliance on cut-aways directly takes the audience on the protagonist’s journey. While not exclusive to the genre, Screen Life films surely help bring out the often shocking difference that exists between our lives and our personas, in real life and online. These films come attached with a sense of claustrophobia, to say the least. The screen is crowded with pop-ups, the user keeps switching between tabs and windows. This adds to not only the pace of the film but also the paranoia of the viewer. Every step of the way, there lurks a  fear, it is like you are always waiting for the next development. You are excited for what comes next, no matter how deeply personal or confidential it might be for the victim. Not that that is wrong; it is a story, after all. But it does explain something about the human desire to voyeur over others’ lives; both the good and the bad. As David Fincher, the director of The Social Network says, “People are perverts.” They want to know the truth, but the kicker is that it will be ugly. Nevertheless, they will love it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Millennials and Meme Culture</title>
      <link href="/Millennials-and-Meme-Culture" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Millennials and Meme Culture" />
      <published>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Millennials-and-Meme-Culture</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Millennials-and-Meme-Culture">&lt;p&gt;Art has existed for about 30,000 years now. And although art has no practical utility, it is one of those things that puts humans at the apex of the food chain. At first, art was strictly an extension of the artist’s speculation, and slowly it branched out to imagination. It slowly evolved into a tool to form friendships and solidarities, establish authority, form groups, bands, tribes, civilisations, and societies. Societies as big as Russia were formed through art. And, unlike the other extension of human cognitive faculty, i.e. science, art has evolved on its own through vessels called artists. It has endured through time and adapted itself to epochal changes and cultural diversifications like a living, breathing organism. If there’s one thing on the planet that could come close to humans, it would be art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time and the intent behind it shape the adaptability of art. Art can be used as a mouthpiece for personal vexation, for political propaganda, as a romantic sonnet, a rebellious speech, or even as satire. The possibilities are endless and the means to propagate them have a few malleable forms. The very beginning of art was through illustrations, statuettes, and fictional stories. As our ancestors developed their faculties, so did art. It has since then taken several forms, namely illustration, text, sculpting, acting, dance, song, cinema and now, memes. Like innumerable developments in the field of art, memes too betray a thing or two about the period to which they are relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;em&gt;meme&lt;/em&gt; originally comes from the Greek word ‘&lt;em&gt;mimema&lt;/em&gt;’, meaning imitation. The term was coined by Richard Dawkins in his book &lt;em&gt;The Selfish Gene&lt;/em&gt; in 1976. Back then, however, the word didn’t gain a lot of recognition. A few decades later, after the emergence of the Internet, memes have surged to be an art form most characteristic of the millennials or Gen Y.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand how a meme is a form of art, we need to understand other art forms. The key idea behind any art is to freeze or compress a particular thought or vision, a whole infinity into a finite space. It confronts our consciousness with matters that we miss out on due to activities essential to survival. If rendered well enough, it takes hold of our spirits and colonises it with whatever it wanted to. Consuming art is a conscious effort and has always been, until the arrival of memes. Memes have gone astray from this principle of art. Memes are consumed in an unstudied manner, seldom requiring cognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memes are symbolic of millennials. They symbolise the hyperactive lifestyle of our generation. They betray the cultural degradation we are going through. A degradation that makes us ponder and say less and less and passively consume more and more. Our vocabulary is riddled with buzzwords which lose meaning with every passing day. Abundance has made us fall out of our practice of thinking. Time has shortened itself relatively, and we constantly seek to escape reality. On average, in a single day, a person goes through a hundred different thoughts, which are &lt;em&gt;not his own&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are losing the originality of thought, the creativity that we are born with. It is in the nature of words and of our human selves to make it difficult to say just about anything. It is momentous to experience the bittersweetness of struggling for words to express how we feel, to lose words just as they are clawing at the base of one’s throat. But with meme culture we lose that. My broken expression and my efforts give way to tagging my friends in memes and to what Buzzfeed tells me describes me and the culture of my generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The erosion of human cognition is alarming and evermore because of the manner of consumption. As mentioned before, memes are consumed quite absently not requiring a conscious effort. This leaves us unguarded, vulnerable to what the memes represent. And, as the practice of conscious thinking ebbs away, so does our consciousness towards life. We are gradually turning apathetic, normalising things that should evoke deep concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Phil Kaye tells us, “If you repeat something over and over again it loses its meaning.” The words ‘climate change’ turn into a category of memes you share, people’s mental traumas become a ‘&lt;em&gt;mood&lt;/em&gt;’ to us and bashing capitalist exploitation just something we do for the kick of feeling edgy. The outrageous loses the ability to outrage us anymore. We think we feel so much that we end up feeling very little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A generation distinguished by a mental health crisis, an existential crisis, a crisis of faith, and a crisis of belief requires, above all, empathy and a careful understanding of the self to counter all our crises. But with the emergence of memes, the probability of countering them is plummeting. Memes that represent cultures and societies, on both micro and macro levels, qualify as phenomenal and path-breaking. Memes have helped us understand our kind better, they’ve taken away the alienation we feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, memes have ended up normalising, without us realising, a lot that is worrisome. The apathy we feel towards ourselves and our actions is of grave concern. The manifestation of this apathy is seen in the increasing streak of nihilism in our generation. Memes are blurring the lines and lies constructed through fiction over the ages and slowly lifting our trust from certain systems of belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But enough about the villainy of memes. Memes are an extension of postmodernism. One can’t discount all of the good that memes have brought. They’ve made us aware of things we otherwise would have remained oblivious of: culture, people, politics, ideologies, sports, our favourite celebrities. Memes are reaching to form a global culture, unparalleled by any art form before. Millennials understand diversity better than any of our previous generations. Millennials are aware of and understand the climate crisis, the water crisis and in general the humanitarian crisis breathing heavily down our necks. With the hyperactivity and the pace of things, it is difficult to take time out to be aware, to seek information, but with memes, it is no longer an arduous task. The simplicity of it is probably its greatest feature. It psychologically functions on the need to remain simple. Perhaps why we keep returning to memes in the face of rising complexities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memes represent a milestone in the evolution of art, a point at which human art has transcended from a confrontation of our inner consciousness to an unguarded passive intake of what lies before one. For better or for worse, meme culture has a sinister ability to both reveal and shape the people who consume it the most, namely the Millennials.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Art has existed for about 30,000 years now. And although art has no practical utility, it is one of those things that puts humans at the apex of the food chain. At first, art was strictly an extension of the artist’s speculation, and slowly it branched out to imagination. It slowly evolved into a tool to form friendships and solidarities, establish authority, form groups, bands, tribes, civilisations, and societies. Societies as big as Russia were formed through art. And, unlike the other extension of human cognitive faculty, i.e. science, art has evolved on its own through vessels called artists. It has endured through time and adapted itself to epochal changes and cultural diversifications like a living, breathing organism. If there’s one thing on the planet that could come close to humans, it would be art.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">On Codes and Ciphers; The Imitation Game</title>
      <link href="/On-Codes-and-Ciphers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Codes and Ciphers; The Imitation Game" />
      <published>2019-07-12T17:45:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-12T17:45:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/On-Codes-and-Ciphers</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/On-Codes-and-Ciphers">&lt;p&gt;“Are you paying attention? Good. If you are not listening carefully, you will
miss things, important things. I will not pause, I will not repeat myself, and
you will not interrupt me. You think that because you’re sitting where you are
and I am sitting where I am, that you are in control of what is about to happen.
You’re mistaken. I am in control, because I know things that you do not know.” - &lt;em&gt;The Imitation Game&lt;/em&gt;, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/a1/Alan_Turing_Aged_16.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Alan_Turing_Aged_16.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan Turing was a revolutionary mathematician, a pioneer among computer
scientists and, most importantly, one of the key players in resolving World War
II through his immense contribution to the decoding of the Enigma cipher. The
Allied forces were in a near-constant state of perplexion over how to crack the
Enigma, the cipher used by the Germans, in order to encrypt messages. Though the
Enigma was reported to have been decoded by the Polish well before him, Turing’s
original method of decrypting the cipher was instrumental in predicting German
movements during the War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/_dchris/19612913884&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//enigma-machine.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Enigma was believed to be impossible to crack. Ultimately, however, it was
broken, bearing testimony to how nothing is truly unbreakable, and every system
has a catch attached to it; a principle well highlighted by modern cryptologists
like Shamir and Bonhe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conceptualisation of codes and ciphers is well-documented alongside the
history of warfare and the development of language, as we know it. A very famous
cipher, the Caesar Cipher, was supposedly used by the famous Roman general to
communicate messages from one camp to another whilst maintaining the
authenticity of commands. In the cipher, the first letter of the alphabet is
replaced with any chosen letter, the subsequent letters then get replaced in a
similar order. For example, in the ‘G Cipher’, A gets replaced by G, B gets
replaced by H and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://s4scoding.com/images/caesar-cipher-left-shift-of-3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//caesar-cipher-left-shift-of-3.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key aspects of codes and ciphers comes from the concept of
steganography. Even though steganography is considered to be a part of
cryptology, it actually isn’t, it is simply a method of hiding information,
using pictures. This method is said to be foolproof. It was even used in the
very famous or rather infamous case of Cicada 3301, when an unknown group of
people claimed to hide information within certain images, and challenged someone
to crack it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another prominent cipher is the Vigenere Cipher; a key-controlled Caesar Cipher.
A key is a system through which one can encode or decode anything, like messages
or warnings. Vigenere Ciphers have been instrumental during war communication
even during the era of the Napoleonic Wars and have stood the test of time, 
being one of the most recognisable of ciphers today. However, the claim to the
throne of the most illustrious cipher would, undisputedly, go to the Morse Code.
The concept behind the Morse Code, (which despite the misnomer of being a code,
is actually a cipher) is also behind the invention of the telegraph by, you
guessed it, Samuel Morse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/b/b5/International_Morse_Code.svg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//International_Morse_Code.svg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For almost half a century, the Telegraph was the only means by which electronic
messages could be sent and received. The Morse Code expresses words, i.e. the
letters and numbers that constitute them, in the form of ‘dots and dashes’ and
it is in this form that it is sent to the receiver. Morse Code, however, has
been, quite interestingly, used in several other forms such as taps and untaps;
tapping signifying a dot, and pausing a dash. (Yes, Sherlock fans, you guessed
it, didn’t you)? The Morse Code is quite a reliable form of masking data, if
masked properly that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny enough, codes and ciphers have been an integral part of artistic movements
in Europe. One of the most renowned ciphers was developed by one of the most
talented men in Europe. Although his name is obscure, he is considered to have
talent comparable to the likes of Leonardo Da Vinci. Most of the relics of that
age have been protected using this very cipher. The cipher in question is the
Alberti Cipher, conceptualised by the revolutionary, Alberti. This cipher
replaces words according to a disk which helps encrypt and decrypt the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The famous author David Kahn notes in his book &lt;em&gt;The Codebreakers&lt;/em&gt; that history
has forgotten several of the other famous ciphers, such as the ones used by many
mathematicians in the Middle-East during the Oriental age, the Scytale Cipher
used by the Spartans during their Golden Age, and so on. There has been no
dearth in the human ability to innovate. In order to create a foolproof cipher
system, all has been done, ranging from methods of transposition (that is to
replace one word with another, as was utilised by the famous Gronsfeld Cipher)
to the generation of intelligent schemes to make decryption difficult without
the key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when the Enigma was built, it was almost as if the pinnacle of human
comprehension was reached and it was presumed that it could not be broken, no
matter what the Allies did. However, a group of people in Bletchley Park refused
to give up and the rest, as they say, is history. Alan Turing has been an
inspiration for the greatest of modern cryptographers, from Adi Shamir to
Malcolm Williamson. In an age in which it is predicted that computers might rule
the world, the authenticity of information and security are some of the biggest
concerns. Cryptography and its application are only going to get more complex
and esoteric, to the extent that we may not be able to comprehend even abstract
concepts on the quantum nature of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information, they say, is key. The philosophy behind the establishment, setting
up and the consequent breaking of codes signifies the ultimate nature of how we
are. It signifies the essence of humankind. It is in the nature of man to build
and then eventually destroy, to construct and then ultimately deconstruct, only
for a better possibility to be explored. Human nature tells us that nothing is
truly unbreakable and that everything, which is part of human effort, can be
brought down, thanks to humans themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Codes help us express ourselves in a niche manner, truly being an indication of
the creativity and perseverance, we as humans, are able to display and put into
effect.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Are you paying attention? Good. If you are not listening carefully, you will miss things, important things. I will not pause, I will not repeat myself, and you will not interrupt me. You think that because you’re sitting where you are and I am sitting where I am, that you are in control of what is about to happen. You’re mistaken. I am in control, because I know things that you do not know.” - The Imitation Game, 2014. Alan Turing was a revolutionary mathematician, a pioneer among computer scientists and, most importantly, one of the key players in resolving World War II through his immense contribution to the decoding of the Enigma cipher. The Allied forces were in a near-constant state of perplexion over how to crack the Enigma, the cipher used by the Germans, in order to encrypt messages. Though the Enigma was reported to have been decoded by the Polish well before him, Turing’s original method of decrypting the cipher was instrumental in predicting German movements during the War. The Enigma was believed to be impossible to crack. Ultimately, however, it was broken, bearing testimony to how nothing is truly unbreakable, and every system has a catch attached to it; a principle well highlighted by modern cryptologists like Shamir and Bonhe. The conceptualisation of codes and ciphers is well-documented alongside the history of warfare and the development of language, as we know it. A very famous cipher, the Caesar Cipher, was supposedly used by the famous Roman general to communicate messages from one camp to another whilst maintaining the authenticity of commands. In the cipher, the first letter of the alphabet is replaced with any chosen letter, the subsequent letters then get replaced in a similar order. For example, in the ‘G Cipher’, A gets replaced by G, B gets replaced by H and so on. One of the key aspects of codes and ciphers comes from the concept of steganography. Even though steganography is considered to be a part of cryptology, it actually isn’t, it is simply a method of hiding information, using pictures. This method is said to be foolproof. It was even used in the very famous or rather infamous case of Cicada 3301, when an unknown group of people claimed to hide information within certain images, and challenged someone to crack it. Another prominent cipher is the Vigenere Cipher; a key-controlled Caesar Cipher. A key is a system through which one can encode or decode anything, like messages or warnings. Vigenere Ciphers have been instrumental during war communication even during the era of the Napoleonic Wars and have stood the test of time,  being one of the most recognisable of ciphers today. However, the claim to the throne of the most illustrious cipher would, undisputedly, go to the Morse Code. The concept behind the Morse Code, (which despite the misnomer of being a code, is actually a cipher) is also behind the invention of the telegraph by, you guessed it, Samuel Morse. For almost half a century, the Telegraph was the only means by which electronic messages could be sent and received. The Morse Code expresses words, i.e. the letters and numbers that constitute them, in the form of ‘dots and dashes’ and it is in this form that it is sent to the receiver. Morse Code, however, has been, quite interestingly, used in several other forms such as taps and untaps; tapping signifying a dot, and pausing a dash. (Yes, Sherlock fans, you guessed it, didn’t you)? The Morse Code is quite a reliable form of masking data, if masked properly that is. Funny enough, codes and ciphers have been an integral part of artistic movements in Europe. One of the most renowned ciphers was developed by one of the most talented men in Europe. Although his name is obscure, he is considered to have talent comparable to the likes of Leonardo Da Vinci. Most of the relics of that age have been protected using this very cipher. The cipher in question is the Alberti Cipher, conceptualised by the revolutionary, Alberti. This cipher replaces words according to a disk which helps encrypt and decrypt the text. The famous author David Kahn notes in his book The Codebreakers that history has forgotten several of the other famous ciphers, such as the ones used by many mathematicians in the Middle-East during the Oriental age, the Scytale Cipher used by the Spartans during their Golden Age, and so on. There has been no dearth in the human ability to innovate. In order to create a foolproof cipher system, all has been done, ranging from methods of transposition (that is to replace one word with another, as was utilised by the famous Gronsfeld Cipher) to the generation of intelligent schemes to make decryption difficult without the key. However, when the Enigma was built, it was almost as if the pinnacle of human comprehension was reached and it was presumed that it could not be broken, no matter what the Allies did. However, a group of people in Bletchley Park refused to give up and the rest, as they say, is history. Alan Turing has been an inspiration for the greatest of modern cryptographers, from Adi Shamir to Malcolm Williamson. In an age in which it is predicted that computers might rule the world, the authenticity of information and security are some of the biggest concerns. Cryptography and its application are only going to get more complex and esoteric, to the extent that we may not be able to comprehend even abstract concepts on the quantum nature of information. Information, they say, is key. The philosophy behind the establishment, setting up and the consequent breaking of codes signifies the ultimate nature of how we are. It signifies the essence of humankind. It is in the nature of man to build and then eventually destroy, to construct and then ultimately deconstruct, only for a better possibility to be explored. Human nature tells us that nothing is truly unbreakable and that everything, which is part of human effort, can be brought down, thanks to humans themselves. Codes help us express ourselves in a niche manner, truly being an indication of the creativity and perseverance, we as humans, are able to display and put into effect.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Fleabag: A Tale of Clumsy Womanhood</title>
      <link href="/Fleabag" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fleabag: A Tale of Clumsy Womanhood" />
      <published>2019-07-12T16:30:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-12T16:30:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Fleabag</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Fleabag">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fleabag&lt;/em&gt;, a dark comedy, is a television show for every chaotic feminist out
there. It is a brutally honest account of a dysfunctional yet nonchalant woman,
who is clearly failing at life with her passive-aggressive family, dead business
and meaningless sexual relationships. The show, set in contemporary London,
speaks the mind of a modern woman through a feminist lens. Phoebe Waller-Bridge,
the writer of the show, also stars as the protagonist and plays her unnamed
character with utter brilliance, whom we call Fleabag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The viewers take a ride through Fleabag’s mind, quite literally, when she talks
to them by breaking the fourth wall. She, conceitedly, predicts the actions of
the people she meets and talks to her audience about it. In the very first
scene, she presumes exactly what is going to happen after she has sex with an
immensely attractive man, and does so throughout the series. She seems to
understand the routine behaviour of the men who she sleeps with, and is seldom
fascinated by them. As viewers, we do not see Fleabag’s story, we see Fleabag.
She is present in every scene of every episode and is almost constantly talking.
The audience is not provided with other characters’ stories, and Fleabag’s
encounters and perceptions form the plot of the entire series. In fact, a few
interesting events in the characters’ lives build up to form the narrative of a
rather bigger story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first episode, Fleabag and her sister, Claire, attend a feminist lecture,
the tickets of which were given to them by their father. Fleabag called this
“[her] dad’s way of coping with two motherless daughters”, who is now in a
relationship with their godmother and has minimised contact with them. The
lecturer asks the audience to “raise [their] hands if you would trade five years
of your life for the so-called perfect body”, to which the sisters promptly
raise their hands, followed by Fleabag calling themselves ‘bad feminists.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through a lot of instances in the show, we come to understand how Fleabag uses
sex to validate her own body and desirability, once even explicitly saying, “I
know that my body is the only thing I have left, and when that gets old and
unfuckable, I may as well kill it.” We later see how the complexities of
Fleabag’s anguish over the death of her mother and her best friend are
intertwined with her sexual encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Season 1 is an entry into the mayhem of Fleabag’s life, whereas season 2 is what
she calls her love story. Andrew Scott enters season 2 as &lt;em&gt;Sexy Priest&lt;/em&gt; and one
cannot take eyes off him. As Fleabag says ‘his arm’, ‘his beautiful neck’, ‘I
found myself pining &lt;em&gt;YES, YES, YES!&lt;/em&gt;’ But glass shatters, it’s not as much a
love story between Fleabag and ‘Sexy Priest’, as it is Fleabag’s
self-introspection and overcoming her disruptive behaviour. She learns to love
and to let go. Her cafe business thrives, and so does her relationship with
Claire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A magnificent scene in season 2, with guest star Kristin Scott Thomas, playing
the role of Belinda who wins an award for women in business, might just be the
monologue of the year, and will absolutely pierce through your heart. Belinda
says, “I was in an aeroplane the other day, and I realised – I’ve been longing
to say this out loud – women are born with pain built-in. It’s our physical
destiny. Period pain, sore boobs, childbirth, you know. We carry it within
ourselves throughout our lives.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Men don’t. They have to seek it out. They invent all these Gods and demons and
things just so they can feel guilty about things, which is something we do very
well on our own. Then they create wars so they can feel things and touch each
other, and when there aren’t any wars they can play rugby.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And we have it all going on in here, inside. We have pain on a cycle for years
and years and years. And then, just as you feel you’re making peace with it all,
what happens? The menopause comes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Men capitalise to feel alive, but women bring things to life. She protected even
when she suffered, while he created violence to be able to restore peace. Women
built walls to nurture, not to divide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an interview with &lt;em&gt;The Hollywood Reporter&lt;/em&gt;, Phoebe Waller-Bridge confirmed
that &lt;em&gt;Fleabag&lt;/em&gt; is not autobiographical. “A lot of the time when I was being
asked about the show, it was through the prism of feminism which was an
important part of the show for me…I just started feeling like I was suddenly
being moved into a different position that it wasn’t so much that I was a
writer, it was that I was a feminist writer, which of course I am, but that
becomes a category of writing”, added Phoebe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I would say, watch this for the love of clumsy womanhood, for learning to be
strong in this modern feminist world even when your entire life is crumbling
down. &lt;em&gt;Fleabag&lt;/em&gt; taught me that feminism is hope, even if its standards you
cannot seem to reach, and women (dead or alive) will be your strength.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Hrishita Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Fleabag, a dark comedy, is a television show for every chaotic feminist out there. It is a brutally honest account of a dysfunctional yet nonchalant woman, who is clearly failing at life with her passive-aggressive family, dead business and meaningless sexual relationships. The show, set in contemporary London, speaks the mind of a modern woman through a feminist lens. Phoebe Waller-Bridge, the writer of the show, also stars as the protagonist and plays her unnamed character with utter brilliance, whom we call Fleabag. The viewers take a ride through Fleabag’s mind, quite literally, when she talks to them by breaking the fourth wall. She, conceitedly, predicts the actions of the people she meets and talks to her audience about it. In the very first scene, she presumes exactly what is going to happen after she has sex with an immensely attractive man, and does so throughout the series. She seems to understand the routine behaviour of the men who she sleeps with, and is seldom fascinated by them. As viewers, we do not see Fleabag’s story, we see Fleabag. She is present in every scene of every episode and is almost constantly talking. The audience is not provided with other characters’ stories, and Fleabag’s encounters and perceptions form the plot of the entire series. In fact, a few interesting events in the characters’ lives build up to form the narrative of a rather bigger story. In the first episode, Fleabag and her sister, Claire, attend a feminist lecture, the tickets of which were given to them by their father. Fleabag called this “[her] dad’s way of coping with two motherless daughters”, who is now in a relationship with their godmother and has minimised contact with them. The lecturer asks the audience to “raise [their] hands if you would trade five years of your life for the so-called perfect body”, to which the sisters promptly raise their hands, followed by Fleabag calling themselves ‘bad feminists.’ Through a lot of instances in the show, we come to understand how Fleabag uses sex to validate her own body and desirability, once even explicitly saying, “I know that my body is the only thing I have left, and when that gets old and unfuckable, I may as well kill it.” We later see how the complexities of Fleabag’s anguish over the death of her mother and her best friend are intertwined with her sexual encounters. Season 1 is an entry into the mayhem of Fleabag’s life, whereas season 2 is what she calls her love story. Andrew Scott enters season 2 as Sexy Priest and one cannot take eyes off him. As Fleabag says ‘his arm’, ‘his beautiful neck’, ‘I found myself pining YES, YES, YES!’ But glass shatters, it’s not as much a love story between Fleabag and ‘Sexy Priest’, as it is Fleabag’s self-introspection and overcoming her disruptive behaviour. She learns to love and to let go. Her cafe business thrives, and so does her relationship with Claire. A magnificent scene in season 2, with guest star Kristin Scott Thomas, playing the role of Belinda who wins an award for women in business, might just be the monologue of the year, and will absolutely pierce through your heart. Belinda says, “I was in an aeroplane the other day, and I realised – I’ve been longing to say this out loud – women are born with pain built-in. It’s our physical destiny. Period pain, sore boobs, childbirth, you know. We carry it within ourselves throughout our lives.” “Men don’t. They have to seek it out. They invent all these Gods and demons and things just so they can feel guilty about things, which is something we do very well on our own. Then they create wars so they can feel things and touch each other, and when there aren’t any wars they can play rugby.” “And we have it all going on in here, inside. We have pain on a cycle for years and years and years. And then, just as you feel you’re making peace with it all, what happens? The menopause comes.” Men capitalise to feel alive, but women bring things to life. She protected even when she suffered, while he created violence to be able to restore peace. Women built walls to nurture, not to divide. In an interview with The Hollywood Reporter, Phoebe Waller-Bridge confirmed that Fleabag is not autobiographical. “A lot of the time when I was being asked about the show, it was through the prism of feminism which was an important part of the show for me…I just started feeling like I was suddenly being moved into a different position that it wasn’t so much that I was a writer, it was that I was a feminist writer, which of course I am, but that becomes a category of writing”, added Phoebe. So, I would say, watch this for the love of clumsy womanhood, for learning to be strong in this modern feminist world even when your entire life is crumbling down. Fleabag taught me that feminism is hope, even if its standards you cannot seem to reach, and women (dead or alive) will be your strength.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Review: ‘The Book of Ram’ by Devdutt Pattanaik</title>
      <link href="/The-Book-of-Ram" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review: 'The Book of Ram' by Devdutt Pattanaik" />
      <published>2019-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Book-of-Ram</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Book-of-Ram">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Book of Ram&lt;/em&gt; is the outcome of Pattanaik’s endeavour to weave magic into the timeless Indian epic tale of the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt;. As the title suggests, the book brings to light, the story of &lt;em&gt;Maryada Purushottam&lt;/em&gt; Ram, the seventh ‘avatar’ of Lord Vishnu (the one who nurtures and maintains balance in the worldly life), the scion of the Raghu clan, the worthy heir, the jewel of the Solar dynasty, the Prince and the Supreme Upholder of social norms and values, the warrior and the ideal king. The author admits that he felt compelled to write the book when he realised that the epic in question was being used as a tool to fuel anger, animosity, hatred, and violence. Pattanaik’s &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; is as informative as it is gripping and riveting. Pattanaik’s simple yet exceedingly well-written book explores the relevance of Shri Ram, the only Hindu deity to be worshipped as The King in the contemporary world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book very rightly portrays Lord Ram as ‘&lt;em&gt;Eka-Vachani&lt;/em&gt;’: A king who is always true to his words; ‘&lt;em&gt;Ek-bani&lt;/em&gt;’: a supreme archer who strikes his target with the first arrow, and ‘&lt;em&gt;Ek-Patni&lt;/em&gt;’: A man who is eternally devoted to one woman. Censured by feminists and appropriated by innumerable politicians, Ram still remains pious and serene in his majesty. Hindus firmly believe that in times of turmoil, by chanting Lord Ram’s name and his tales, one can achieve peace, stability, hope, and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pattanaik’s story is through the eyes of Sita, Ram’s wife and the avatar of Vishnu’s consort Lakshmi. The book glimpses through all the different versions of the revered epic starting from before the 1st century CE to the 19th century, including the versions popular in South East Asian cultures. The author meticulously shows the contrast between different mini &lt;em&gt;Ramayanas&lt;/em&gt;, ranging from Kamban’s &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; to Valmiki’s, from Maya Sita to Devi Sita. All these versions speak a different tale but eventually converge into a singular point that reflects the grandeur of the creator(s) and an ancient faith. It also becomes crucial to note that &lt;em&gt;Sanatan Dharma&lt;/em&gt; (Eternal Order, as so many Hindus refer to Hinduism) does not subscribe to the idea of differentiating between the male and the female along a strict line. Pattanaik makes the use of symbols, metaphors, patterns, and motifs to convey his message. The fact that Ram painstakingly fulfils his duty as a king and ultimately walks into the Sarayu river chanting Sita’s name to bring him solace, stands crucial. In the Indian context, a God is always accompanied by a Goddess, thus reflecting the need to maintain a balance between the two. The existence of &lt;em&gt;Adi Shakti&lt;/em&gt; (Primal Female Energy) points to the same and brings in a much-needed fluidity in modern society. Ram as a God is dependable and Sita as a Goddess is independent. Pattanaik asks, isn’t this what we all aspire to be, dependable but independent? The author scholastically delves into the spirit of the religious text. Rather than drawing superficial inferences from the literal aspects of the text, which has led to myriad misinterpretations from time immemorial, Pattanaik understands an important truth about the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt;, it is not about the words but the essence behind them. He also brings to light how the binary, didactic Abrahamic Western thought process has discredited the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; or, for that matter, all our religious texts by only taking into account the literal aspects of our vast literature and culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is crucial to note that parts of this epic and many other Hindu religious scriptures have been changed by authors, in accordance with the time they lived in and the perils that faced their society. Even in this book, Pattanaik admits to using his vivid imagination and thereby perpetuates the long-standing tradition of adding personal stories to the great epic. As a consequence, it becomes difficult for a lay reader to distinguish between the facts mentioned in the epic and those that have been woven into it by the author’s imagination. Even though this makes Pattanaik’s book slightly unscholarly it’s still not completely discreditable, for it only makes it a tad bit more Hindu in spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book also, very rightly, criticises the manipulation and distortion of religion by Hindu extremist groups. It gives out a message of peace and unity for achieving true &lt;em&gt;Ram Rajya&lt;/em&gt;, which is not restricted to a time or place but is to be found &lt;strong&gt;within&lt;/strong&gt;. To quote Pattanaik, “He [Ram] is our soul.” He criticises the modern education system for teaching one to respect only that which can be proved empirically. He provokes one to think of the debate between religion and science. He also makes a much-needed distinction between linear and cyclical history. However, the book adopts a very idealistic stand which is difficult to grasp in a modern materialistic world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindu religious scriptures tell us something crucial through its characters. Humans are made of conflicting truths; there isn’t either a positive side or a negative side to one, Pattanaik shows how one person can be a martyr, a villain, a hero, and a victim. Our books are about diverse human characters; humans of wisdom and of folly who are unpredictable and dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pattanaik also draws a parallel between Prince Ram and Lord Krishna. The epic, he rightly states, teaches us that a world governed only by law and not by emotions is not ideal. He talks about the supreme sacrifice made by Lord Ram and Goddess Sita to impart this lesson to a not-so-humane world. The strong, wise and independent hero, the warrior princess, Sita also fulfils her duties and departs leaving Ram on Earth to fulfill his kingly duty and return to the &lt;em&gt;Vaikuntha Loka&lt;/em&gt;, the abode of Vishnu where he sleeps on the Snake of Time, dreaming of creation. The epic, via its protagonist Shri Ram, thus imparts essential lessons of democracy and the beauty of living for people. It imparts valuable lessons of humanity also through King Ram’s character: His supreme uprightness in the face of the darkest of adversities offers peace, stability and hope to all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pattanaik stands by the statement that liberals today will find their perfect ally in Hindu thought and philosophy. The nonexistence of a Sanskrit word for blasphemy also points to the same. The book speaks of fluidity and inclusivity of the Hindu religion by talking about the acceptance of LGBTQ people in the social order, linking this fact back to Hinduism’s comfort with fluidity in its seemingly gendered motifs and totems. The book also states that in the Hindu religion, one’s &lt;em&gt;Karma&lt;/em&gt; (Action) is supreme and overshadows all else. The &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; is primarily a tale of emotions, be it filial affection, a sense of duty and loyalty, love, lust or malice. It also shows the ill outcome of ego, ambition, and arrogance. Thus, the retelling of the epic provokes profound thought, it expands one’s consciousness inspiring them to cultivate and realise one’s potential by overcoming the fallacies of human nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pattanaik’s &lt;em&gt;Book of Ram&lt;/em&gt; is a well-researched one. Simplifying the philosophical connotations, it can be said that the author believes that in each person there is a part of Ram-Sita, a Ravan, an Ahilya, a Mandodri or a Surupnakha. Human nature and destiny are determined by the part a human decides to give precedence to. Thus, in essence, it can be said, the Ramayana has never been a tale of Ram’s life. It has always been a tale of how Ram lived for others. Here, I am compelled to reiterate, that the interpretation of Ram’s character will invariably be an interpretation of one’s own character. Isn’t how we see others a reflection of how we see ourselves? Perhaps, the answer is best left untold!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Book of Ram is the outcome of Pattanaik’s endeavour to weave magic into the timeless Indian epic tale of the Ramayana. As the title suggests, the book brings to light, the story of Maryada Purushottam Ram, the seventh ‘avatar’ of Lord Vishnu (the one who nurtures and maintains balance in the worldly life), the scion of the Raghu clan, the worthy heir, the jewel of the Solar dynasty, the Prince and the Supreme Upholder of social norms and values, the warrior and the ideal king. The author admits that he felt compelled to write the book when he realised that the epic in question was being used as a tool to fuel anger, animosity, hatred, and violence. Pattanaik’s Ramayana is as informative as it is gripping and riveting. Pattanaik’s simple yet exceedingly well-written book explores the relevance of Shri Ram, the only Hindu deity to be worshipped as The King in the contemporary world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Turkish Diaries</title>
      <link href="/Turkish-Diaries" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Turkish Diaries" />
      <published>2019-07-06T14:40:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-06T14:40:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Turkish-Diaries</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Turkish-Diaries">&lt;p&gt;Before writing this piece, I had a couple of rather conflicting thoughts, that
made me resist the urge to write a personal account of my visit to Turkey. My
initial enthusiasm to pen down my extraordinary experience was soon met by a
greater impediment when I searched the internet to gather more information about
Turkey, as I will explain later. I would not have done justice to myself if I
would have written an article instead of a personal account. And so, I have
decided to shut down those thoughts and do what I wanted to do anyway, i.e. to
enlighten you about my journey, along with the aftermath, as it was in Turkey.
Nothing more and nothing less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turkey, one of the five countries to be a part of both Europe and Asia, was a
journey of a lifetime. Having visited five cities and towns over a course of
twelve days, I experienced breath-taking architecture (mosques, museums,
palaces, theatres and natural beauty), talked to Turks and ate traditional
Turkish delicacies. I consider myself to be in a position to form an opinion
about the country and its citizens. An Islamic country, where 99.8% of the
population follows Islam as its religion, Turkey was truly a blend of modernity
and cultural heritage, where people had accepted the reality of the modern era
while remaining true to their own roots. It rightfully stood in the middle
ground, embodying the qualities of both Europe and Asia. The country’s two
wonders of the ancient world: The Temple of Artemis and The Mausoleum of
Halicarnassus, its rich traditional architecture, a blend of Islam and
Christianity, was intellectually stimulating and visually captivating at the
same time. The cherry on top was the state-of-the-art infrastructure, pristine
surroundings, the technologically-advanced society and the open-minded people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a little hard to digest that an Islamic society can be so advanced and
modern, isn’t it? Turkey certainly broke the few stereotypes I might have had
against Muslims and reinforced the sense of respect I had for the religion.
There were some incidents that took place during the journey that compelled me
to think highly of Islam. In Islam, women are often expected to wear traditional
dresses (like burqa, hijab, niqab, etc.), look after the domestic chores, and
behave in a modest and polite way. However, men and women in Turkey wore western
attire; jeans and t-shirts among other dresses. In the entirety of my journey,
from a big city like Istanbul to a small town like Selcuk, I did not see more
than 20% of the women with headscarves, let alone garments fully covering their
body. The work culture was inclusive and women were financially independent. I
remember eating at restaurants and cafes where women waited tables, even at
night, a phenomenon uncommon in my supposedly more liberal home country, India.
Furthermore, unlike India, smoking in public was not considered a taboo in
Turkey and both men and women openly smoked in the streets. Although smoking
does not imply modernity, yet to experience it in an Islamic country is a big
deal.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was one incident that stood out from the rest and acted as an ‘inception’
for my exploration of the Islamic world. It was when I visited the Suleymaniye
Mosque in Istanbul, where a college student had volunteered to explain the
history of the mosque to visitors. While explaining the prayer pattern, he said
that women stood at the back during Namaz so as to ensure that men do not get
distracted during prayer. I found this absurd and initiated a discussion on the
point. My father was apprehensive that the discussion might turn into a heated
argument and tried to stop me. To this, the gentleman instantly replied, “I want
to hear her opinion. She (Muslim women, not me) is the disadvantaged one.” This
incident indicated both a positive as well as a negative point for Turkish
Islam: positive because the younger generations were open-minded and negative
because the religion put women in a position of disadvantage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To further my proposition, let us take a look at some statistics. According to
the Central Intelligence Agency of the USA, Turkey is a developed country and is
considered advanced in terms of infrastructure, technology, industrialisation,
per capita income and standards of living. For a better understanding of
Turkey’s economic and social situation, let us compare it with India:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turkey&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Male-Female percentage of population&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;49.1% - 50.9%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;51.8% - 48.2%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Population density&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;104.5 people/sq km&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;415.63 people/ sq km&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literacy Rate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;95.6%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;74.04%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Male literacy rate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;98%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;80.9%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Female literacy rate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;92%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;64.6%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quality of Life Index (Rank)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;44/70&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;52/70&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Population living in Urban areas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;70%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;33%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Source:&lt;/b&gt; World Population Review, 2019&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of some troublesome trends like rising unemployment and inflation, the
above statistics provide enough evidence that Turkey is a developed nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My curiosity to learn more about Turkish Islam and to uphold my findings led me
to collect pamphlets everywhere I went and undertake an in-depth search on the
internet. But, what I read online was in stark contrast to what I saw through my
eyes. I was appalled by the negative portrayal of Turkey in almost all of the
articles I read! All of them had some common themes: economic and political
instability, humanitarian crisis, disputes based on religion, and so on. I was
distressed to find out that a staggering 477 women were killed and another 232
injured at the hands of violent men in Turkey in 2018. It was only when one of
Turkey’s biggest pop stars Sıla Gencoglu filed abuse charges against her actor
boyfriend in 2018 that a media frenzy was set off, which sparked the
long-awaited national debate about violence against women. Furthermore, the
&lt;em&gt;Women in Statistics 2017&lt;/em&gt; report stated that only 28% of women above 15 years
of age were part of the Turkish labour force. These incidences reduced the
confidence I had in Turkish Islam. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthering my research, I found out that Turkey’s current President Recep Tayyip
Erdogan and his AK party have made the constitutionally secular country more
conservative and religious. The pro-Islamic authoritarian President aims to
raise a ‘pious generation’ and thus promotes the growth of state-funded
religious education in the country. Although the AK party claims to be secular,
it seeks to change the country’s laws to greater reflect its growing Muslim
identity. So, why did the modern people of Turkey elect Erdogan into power in
the first place? This is because, in the first decade of his rule starting from
2003, he initiated several rapid economic and democratic reforms in the country.
However, legal and democratic standards quickly deteriorated after 2013, and his
focus shifted to the promotion of Islam. As a result, people became fearful that
the President might slowly erase the line between Religion and the State, and
make Turkey a non-secular country, upsetting the great balance put in place by
the great Atatürk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These steps have received a backlash from the Turks, especially the younger
generation, and the level of piety has declined over the years, despite an
increase in religious education. There has been a significant drop in people
calling themselves ‘religious conservative’, from 32% in 2008 to 25% in 2018.
People who say they fast during the Muslim holy month of Ramadan declined from
77% to 65%. Figures for ‘nonbeliever’ and ‘atheist’, which had been barely
registered in 2008, increased to 2% and 3% respectively. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now comes the final question. Is Turkey a modern or a conservative Islamic
nation? The internet is full of Turkey’s past, which lost its way under
President Erdogan, both economically and socially. However, what I saw was
Turkey’s future, where the so-called ‘pious generation’ is changing course and
embracing people from all religions and backgrounds. There is no chance that the
AK party will come back to power in the next Parliamentary elections if it
continues with the same narrow mindset of making Turkey an Islamist nation. I
would urge the readers to develop a positive outlook towards Turkey, a country
adapting itself with the changing times while retaining its cultural heritage.
There’s more to this beautiful nation than what meets the internet!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sanjana Chandaliya</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Before writing this piece, I had a couple of rather conflicting thoughts, that made me resist the urge to write a personal account of my visit to Turkey. My initial enthusiasm to pen down my extraordinary experience was soon met by a greater impediment when I searched the internet to gather more information about Turkey, as I will explain later. I would not have done justice to myself if I would have written an article instead of a personal account. And so, I have decided to shut down those thoughts and do what I wanted to do anyway, i.e. to enlighten you about my journey, along with the aftermath, as it was in Turkey. Nothing more and nothing less. Turkey, one of the five countries to be a part of both Europe and Asia, was a journey of a lifetime. Having visited five cities and towns over a course of twelve days, I experienced breath-taking architecture (mosques, museums, palaces, theatres and natural beauty), talked to Turks and ate traditional Turkish delicacies. I consider myself to be in a position to form an opinion about the country and its citizens. An Islamic country, where 99.8% of the population follows Islam as its religion, Turkey was truly a blend of modernity and cultural heritage, where people had accepted the reality of the modern era while remaining true to their own roots. It rightfully stood in the middle ground, embodying the qualities of both Europe and Asia. The country’s two wonders of the ancient world: The Temple of Artemis and The Mausoleum of Halicarnassus, its rich traditional architecture, a blend of Islam and Christianity, was intellectually stimulating and visually captivating at the same time. The cherry on top was the state-of-the-art infrastructure, pristine surroundings, the technologically-advanced society and the open-minded people.  It’s a little hard to digest that an Islamic society can be so advanced and modern, isn’t it? Turkey certainly broke the few stereotypes I might have had against Muslims and reinforced the sense of respect I had for the religion. There were some incidents that took place during the journey that compelled me to think highly of Islam. In Islam, women are often expected to wear traditional dresses (like burqa, hijab, niqab, etc.), look after the domestic chores, and behave in a modest and polite way. However, men and women in Turkey wore western attire; jeans and t-shirts among other dresses. In the entirety of my journey, from a big city like Istanbul to a small town like Selcuk, I did not see more than 20% of the women with headscarves, let alone garments fully covering their body. The work culture was inclusive and women were financially independent. I remember eating at restaurants and cafes where women waited tables, even at night, a phenomenon uncommon in my supposedly more liberal home country, India. Furthermore, unlike India, smoking in public was not considered a taboo in Turkey and both men and women openly smoked in the streets. Although smoking does not imply modernity, yet to experience it in an Islamic country is a big deal.   There was one incident that stood out from the rest and acted as an ‘inception’ for my exploration of the Islamic world. It was when I visited the Suleymaniye Mosque in Istanbul, where a college student had volunteered to explain the history of the mosque to visitors. While explaining the prayer pattern, he said that women stood at the back during Namaz so as to ensure that men do not get distracted during prayer. I found this absurd and initiated a discussion on the point. My father was apprehensive that the discussion might turn into a heated argument and tried to stop me. To this, the gentleman instantly replied, “I want to hear her opinion. She (Muslim women, not me) is the disadvantaged one.” This incident indicated both a positive as well as a negative point for Turkish Islam: positive because the younger generations were open-minded and negative because the religion put women in a position of disadvantage.  To further my proposition, let us take a look at some statistics. According to the Central Intelligence Agency of the USA, Turkey is a developed country and is considered advanced in terms of infrastructure, technology, industrialisation, per capita income and standards of living. For a better understanding of Turkey’s economic and social situation, let us compare it with India: &amp;nbsp; Turkey India Male-Female percentage of population 49.1% - 50.9% 51.8% - 48.2% Population density 104.5 people/sq km 415.63 people/ sq km Literacy Rate 95.6% 74.04% Male literacy rate 98% 80.9% Female literacy rate 92% 64.6% Quality of Life Index (Rank) 44/70 52/70 Population living in Urban areas 70% 33% Source: World Population Review, 2019 In spite of some troublesome trends like rising unemployment and inflation, the above statistics provide enough evidence that Turkey is a developed nation. My curiosity to learn more about Turkish Islam and to uphold my findings led me to collect pamphlets everywhere I went and undertake an in-depth search on the internet. But, what I read online was in stark contrast to what I saw through my eyes. I was appalled by the negative portrayal of Turkey in almost all of the articles I read! All of them had some common themes: economic and political instability, humanitarian crisis, disputes based on religion, and so on. I was distressed to find out that a staggering 477 women were killed and another 232 injured at the hands of violent men in Turkey in 2018. It was only when one of Turkey’s biggest pop stars Sıla Gencoglu filed abuse charges against her actor boyfriend in 2018 that a media frenzy was set off, which sparked the long-awaited national debate about violence against women. Furthermore, the Women in Statistics 2017 report stated that only 28% of women above 15 years of age were part of the Turkish labour force. These incidences reduced the confidence I had in Turkish Islam.  Furthering my research, I found out that Turkey’s current President Recep Tayyip Erdogan and his AK party have made the constitutionally secular country more conservative and religious. The pro-Islamic authoritarian President aims to raise a ‘pious generation’ and thus promotes the growth of state-funded religious education in the country. Although the AK party claims to be secular, it seeks to change the country’s laws to greater reflect its growing Muslim identity. So, why did the modern people of Turkey elect Erdogan into power in the first place? This is because, in the first decade of his rule starting from 2003, he initiated several rapid economic and democratic reforms in the country. However, legal and democratic standards quickly deteriorated after 2013, and his focus shifted to the promotion of Islam. As a result, people became fearful that the President might slowly erase the line between Religion and the State, and make Turkey a non-secular country, upsetting the great balance put in place by the great Atatürk.  These steps have received a backlash from the Turks, especially the younger generation, and the level of piety has declined over the years, despite an increase in religious education. There has been a significant drop in people calling themselves ‘religious conservative’, from 32% in 2008 to 25% in 2018. People who say they fast during the Muslim holy month of Ramadan declined from 77% to 65%. Figures for ‘nonbeliever’ and ‘atheist’, which had been barely registered in 2008, increased to 2% and 3% respectively.  Now comes the final question. Is Turkey a modern or a conservative Islamic nation? The internet is full of Turkey’s past, which lost its way under President Erdogan, both economically and socially. However, what I saw was Turkey’s future, where the so-called ‘pious generation’ is changing course and embracing people from all religions and backgrounds. There is no chance that the AK party will come back to power in the next Parliamentary elections if it continues with the same narrow mindset of making Turkey an Islamist nation. I would urge the readers to develop a positive outlook towards Turkey, a country adapting itself with the changing times while retaining its cultural heritage. There’s more to this beautiful nation than what meets the internet!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
