<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/culture/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-06-14T00:48:23+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/culture/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Is Eternal Life a Good Thing?</title>
      <link href="/Eternal-Life" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Eternal Life a Good Thing?" />
      <published>2019-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Eternal-Life</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Eternal-Life">&lt;p&gt;It is basic human nature to mourn the death of our loved ones for they are no longer with us. Similarly, death seems to be a loss for the ones who die, at least in the human imagination, since the dead no longer exist for themselves or for others. In this context, death can be considered overwhelmingly ‘bad’ or harmful to human existence. So, if death is ‘bad’, then not dying must be ‘good’. Would this mean immortality is, in some ways, good because life itself is the essence of ‘goodness’ or the antithesis of death?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the above exposition might be a common assumption where immortality seems desirable, we can answer the question posed above only if we have an accurate evaluation of what is actually good. This essay investigates the metaphysical nature of death and its moral implications only to argue that death is better than an immortal existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Battle of Defining Death&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medical professionals today command consensus over the scientific dogma that “human death is the irreversible cessation of the functioning of the brain including the brainstem”– as argued by Mr Thomas in the journal called &lt;em&gt;Bioethics&lt;/em&gt;. But there still exists a vibrancy of contentions that scholars often include in their respective theories of death. One school of thought considers death to be the inevitable end of a person’s existence, while another believes that only the body perishes on dying, for the soul lives forever. Deductions from the latter argument open doors for discussions on salvation, Heaven, Hell and the beyond. But, how much do we actually know about them for us to discuss them fruitfully? Great spiritual gratification may be found in death by those who believe in the latter, however, it is more convincing to approve of the former argument, given the limited knowledge we have about death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our current knowledge at least verifies a universal truth that death is the common fate of all human beings, post which they stop existing physically. There is no concrete evidence to support any concept of another life, an after-life, or a reincarnation, among other divine hypotheses. Though a few mythological and religious texts support supernatural theories like these, the scientific age has turned them down on grounds of insufficiency of rationale and absence of proof. Also, even if we were to agree that there is an aftermath to death, it is certainly devoid of one’s original identity, thus terminating that particular life anyhow. The seemingly eternal soul will find a new body to sustain in, and leave that too one day before finding another body for a cycle of death to continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, if we analyse only the knowledge we are certain of, it is easy to accept death as a state of individual non-existence and nothing more. Consequently, it is a permanent annihilation of a person (at least as we know him/her) from the face of the earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nature of Death: The Deprivation Account of Badness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philosophical discussions surrounding the nature of death – good or bad – has been in a constant argument among diverse schools of thought for several centuries now. My belief resonates with the ideas of deprivation theorists like Thomas Nagel and Shelly Kagan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deprivation Theory elucidates that death is bad because we can no longer experience the good things in life by virtue of our non-existence. When we cease to exist, we are naturally deprived of the good things in life. Therefore, being dead may not be intrinsically bad, but, it is relatively bad when compared to a situation that could allow us to continue watching the sunset, keep playing with our children and keep eating favorite delicacies, among other fortunes. Hence, the state of death makes us worse off than we were alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, some may argue that a person who was suffering when alive is better off once dead. He does not need to feel the pain and agony anymore. While the context of this argument may seem reasonable, even in this case we are worse off dead since we have no knowledge of what awaits us after death. For all we know, one might end up suffering to a greater extent than he already was when alive. A known devil is better than an unknown angel: we are better off being a part of what we know than walking into oblivion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second, stronger rebuttal can be drawn from the Epicurean argument that suggests we be indifferent to death. It explains that death cannot be good or bad since there is no existing person who can describe or value its pleasant or harmful nature. However, if an existing person were to be stripped of all the good things in his life, he would curse whoever did that. Similarly, if it were ever possible, he would curse death as well. Just because he exists no more is no reason for us to disregard the harm that death did to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, a Roman philosopher named Lucretius offers yet another contention to my viewpoint. He believes that our non-existence after dying is just like the non-existence we underwent before birth. Since the latter is not bad, the former should not be bad either. To answer his claim, it can be expounded that our prenatal period did not involve any loss. On the contrary, death is a result of the loss of our life. Losing the good things in life is attached to a negative connotation. This way, we have proved yet again that death is a bad venture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Mortal’s Assessment of Immortality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the introduction of this essay, I had questioned if life was a good thing, provided death is bad. Now that we have established “death is bad,” we must assess immortality to see what life actually is. In order for immortality to be good, says Bernard Williams, two conditions need to be met simultaneously: the ‘Attractiveness Condition’ and the ‘Identity Condition’. Therefore, in order for immortality to be bad, or worse than death, these two conditions must not get fulfilled simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Attractiveness Condition requires a life to have attractive meaning forever. Imagine doing something you love for one month straight. Then a year. Then a decade. Then a century. Then millions and billions of years. Regardless of how much you love that experience inherently, it will eventually lose its attractiveness when done repeatedly over a significant length of time. Such repetition will only lead to boredom and monotony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, a counter-argument could be that an immortal person would have a diverse routine, doing everything immortally possible. So, let Monday be music day, Tuesday – singing day, Wednesday – travelling day, and so on… Furthermore, imagine the schedule changes every week with new activities every day. Still, how long before we exhaust doing the things we like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take the argument to an all new level, let us take Robert Nozick’s Experience Machine. Even if we were to feel a variety of pleasures, every single day of our lives, over and over again, ultimately all our desires would lose meaning, leaving nothing for us to live for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may also delay participating in activities that we were keen to be a part of when mortally alive. Immortality might swing us towards a ‘will-do-it-tomorrow’ attitude because our days are no longer numbered. The ambition that a finite life instills in us would be lost to the drudgery of time, hence compromising the attractiveness of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us also discuss the Identity Condition, which requires that our personality and uniqueness always stay intact. It is difficult to consciously fulfill this condition, given the human mind is easily prone to tedium and ennui. In order to prevent this, an immortal person could attempt to transform himself in a way that divests him of his real-self and creates an existential crisis. Such attempts could include a ‘removal of higher consciousness’ so as to become ignorant towards an unending life or ‘inducing mental forgetfulness’ so as to experience every activity as if it were the first time, even if it were the millionth. This would artificially preserve the attractiveness of life but compromise our true identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, it can be concluded that the Attractiveness Condition and the Identity Condition cannot be met simultaneously because of a clearly presented dilemma: If we live forever as our true selves, boredom will eventually set in and life would not remain as attractive; and if boredom does not set in, then it is not our true self that is living immortally; in both ways making immortality bad or in fact worse than death. While a finite existence promotes ambition, passion, motivation, and determination, an infinite life endorses dispiritedness, indifference, and lethargy over time. The balance of nature makes sure an unnatural phenomenon like immortality is worse than the natural principle of death. In other words, it is verily because of death that life becomes good, and it is verily because of life that death becomes bad. It is this metaphysical dichotomy and the epistemic limitations to a true understanding of death which makes life better than death. But, at the same time, this is what makes an unending life valueless too, for, without death, life is, quite unironically, pointless.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shivang Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is basic human nature to mourn the death of our loved ones for they are no longer with us. Similarly, death seems to be a loss for the ones who die, at least in the human imagination, since the dead no longer exist for themselves or for others. In this context, death can be considered overwhelmingly ‘bad’ or harmful to human existence. So, if death is ‘bad’, then not dying must be ‘good’. Would this mean immortality is, in some ways, good because life itself is the essence of ‘goodness’ or the antithesis of death?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">On the Curator of Girlhood: An Ode to Olivia Gatwood</title>
      <link href="/On-the-Curator-of-Girlhood" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the Curator of Girlhood: An Ode to Olivia Gatwood" />
      <published>2019-05-03T02:10:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-03T02:10:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/On-the-Curator-of-Girlhood</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/On-the-Curator-of-Girlhood">&lt;p&gt;Olivia Gatwood was a name I stumbled upon in a vast sea of slam poetry videos on
YouTube. Out of the hundreds of videos of finger-snapping and rants over love,
loss, oppression, and identity, it was her name that stuck, long after my fiery
infatuation with spoken word poetry had mellowed to a flicker. I always
gravitate back to this opinionated, curly-haired woman who writes about Manic
Pixie Dream Girls, resting b*tch faces, period underwear and stories of girls
putting in tampons for their friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her writing reflects a wave of feminism which has a ferocious insistence on
&lt;em&gt;reclaiming&lt;/em&gt; femininity with unwavering pride. Olivia doesn’t spend time
clarifying that pink isn’t every woman’s favourite colour, she would much rather
illustrate through poetry the beauty and loveliness of pink, and how there
cannot be shame in loving something that is beautiful. The idea behind
reclamation is to tell-off the patriarchy, by stripping away the shame,
weakness, and unimportance that it attaches to womanliness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Imagine, the teen girls gone from our world and how quickly we would beg for
their return.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By writing about girlhood, Olivia advocates for the fact that stories of
girlhood are in fact important enough to be given a name, to be archived and
shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have had a love affair with Olivia’s poetry and with her determined conviction
to speak to the teenage girl in me or in any woman. And in all their might,
those words have loved me back too, by bringing me tales of valiant and
interesting women in a world that has only ever painted us as meek and doe-eyed,
and by bringing pride to places that had only known shame. Olivia tells me how
uniquely wonderful the friendship between two teen girls is and I recall all of
those moments of unbelievable intimacy that I had taken for granted. She tells
me about the careless trust she places on old period underwear and my mind
wanders back to every red splotch, together with the vicious scrubbing and the
unnecessary hiding. She talks of the profoundness of female rituals and suddenly
nothing about my existence as a teen girl is mundane to me. With her poetry,
every mundane experience of girlhood evolves into a sacrosanct ceremony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;I had never pined, so badly,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;for denim to slip down her lower back,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;upon taking a seat,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;to reveal the fuzz along her spine,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;that which she likely wished to remove,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;begged her mother for hot wax like we all did&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olivia paints a collage of details, she doesn’t &lt;em&gt;tell&lt;/em&gt; you that queerness is a
beautiful thing, instead she makes you feel a thousand flapping butterflies for
a girl’s fuzzy lower back, and by the end of it you have &lt;em&gt;felt&lt;/em&gt; that queerness
is indeed a beautiful thing, you don’t have to be told anymore. It’s not a poem
of some gigantic struggle for LGBTQ emancipation. Instead, it is one that
combines the smallest of elements, eliciting the most primitive, the most human
of responses, and establishing connectedness in the process. The constant
non-linearity in her writing is what sets her apart from the surge of spoken
word poets, whose poems are more declarative in form. Olivia will let her words
find you at a leisurely pace and gradually engulf you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a world of excessive interaction with content, it is easy to become
desensitised to words. Words, as they are, fall short in being able to evoke
fury or love or even solidarity. What then, induces one to drop one’s thoughts
and feel something? Olivia speaks to that desensitised reader/listener through
the entangling net of stories that she weaves. She reminds one that poetry isn’t
a dish to be served on a platter but rather a recipe to be navigated through,
half the fun lies in disentangling the net that the author weaves. Quite unlike
the Rupi Kaur brand of poetry. For Kaur gives a perfectly fitting feminist
message, but that’s it. Her poetry exists merely on the surface, there is
nothing to delve into, to be submerged in. This narrative moves forward in a
straight line, such that there is no space left &lt;em&gt;between&lt;/em&gt; the lines, which is
also the space where the magic happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The last time we made love you asked me if I was scared,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I think you wanted me to say yes”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subtlety is also Olivia’s distinguishing quality. Even in poems with darker
undertones, in stories of pain and abuse, she often speaks about the abuse
without ever outrightly addressing it. And strangely enough, the indistinction
encapsulates the very nature of abuse itself, to be so subtle that we wish to
ignore it. How abuse isn’t usually isolated and identifiable, but it’s in words,
actions and behaviours interlaced with all else, how it is indistinguishable to
the extent that it almost resembles normalcy. She brings out the imperceptible
fears that lurk within us. Olivia gets the grey nature of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The boy doesn’t ask if he can choke me, so I pretend to die while he’s doing
it”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She is the curator to the museum of all our stories, some lost and some broken,
what’s different is the light that she uses to guide us through them. A light of
pride. She leaves one with not only the feeling that poetry is magical but that
being a girl itself is so so wondrous and sensationally beautiful in nature.
Olivia is about the details, about the fears and insecurities in the experiences
of girlhood, and the understanding that from the smallest instances emerges the
greatest solidarity. Being a girl can be a constant struggle for selfhood.
Everything teenage girls do and are is under constant attack and ridicule. And
that is precisely how patriarchy is structured, that even a single moment of
uninterrupted female existence is unendurable for them. And to that, she says,
f*ck you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“When the boy said, he liked my hair the other way, I shaved my head instead of
my p*ssy.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Stuti Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Olivia Gatwood was a name I stumbled upon in a vast sea of slam poetry videos on YouTube. Out of the hundreds of videos of finger-snapping and rants over love, loss, oppression, and identity, it was her name that stuck, long after my fiery infatuation with spoken word poetry had mellowed to a flicker. I always gravitate back to this opinionated, curly-haired woman who writes about Manic Pixie Dream Girls, resting b*tch faces, period underwear and stories of girls putting in tampons for their friends. Her writing reflects a wave of feminism which has a ferocious insistence on reclaiming femininity with unwavering pride. Olivia doesn’t spend time clarifying that pink isn’t every woman’s favourite colour, she would much rather illustrate through poetry the beauty and loveliness of pink, and how there cannot be shame in loving something that is beautiful. The idea behind reclamation is to tell-off the patriarchy, by stripping away the shame, weakness, and unimportance that it attaches to womanliness. “Imagine, the teen girls gone from our world and how quickly we would beg for their return.” By writing about girlhood, Olivia advocates for the fact that stories of girlhood are in fact important enough to be given a name, to be archived and shared. I have had a love affair with Olivia’s poetry and with her determined conviction to speak to the teenage girl in me or in any woman. And in all their might, those words have loved me back too, by bringing me tales of valiant and interesting women in a world that has only ever painted us as meek and doe-eyed, and by bringing pride to places that had only known shame. Olivia tells me how uniquely wonderful the friendship between two teen girls is and I recall all of those moments of unbelievable intimacy that I had taken for granted. She tells me about the careless trust she places on old period underwear and my mind wanders back to every red splotch, together with the vicious scrubbing and the unnecessary hiding. She talks of the profoundness of female rituals and suddenly nothing about my existence as a teen girl is mundane to me. With her poetry, every mundane experience of girlhood evolves into a sacrosanct ceremony. “I had never pined, so badly, for denim to slip down her lower back, upon taking a seat, to reveal the fuzz along her spine, that which she likely wished to remove, begged her mother for hot wax like we all did.” Olivia paints a collage of details, she doesn’t tell you that queerness is a beautiful thing, instead she makes you feel a thousand flapping butterflies for a girl’s fuzzy lower back, and by the end of it you have felt that queerness is indeed a beautiful thing, you don’t have to be told anymore. It’s not a poem of some gigantic struggle for LGBTQ emancipation. Instead, it is one that combines the smallest of elements, eliciting the most primitive, the most human of responses, and establishing connectedness in the process. The constant non-linearity in her writing is what sets her apart from the surge of spoken word poets, whose poems are more declarative in form. Olivia will let her words find you at a leisurely pace and gradually engulf you. In a world of excessive interaction with content, it is easy to become desensitised to words. Words, as they are, fall short in being able to evoke fury or love or even solidarity. What then, induces one to drop one’s thoughts and feel something? Olivia speaks to that desensitised reader/listener through the entangling net of stories that she weaves. She reminds one that poetry isn’t a dish to be served on a platter but rather a recipe to be navigated through, half the fun lies in disentangling the net that the author weaves. Quite unlike the Rupi Kaur brand of poetry. For Kaur gives a perfectly fitting feminist message, but that’s it. Her poetry exists merely on the surface, there is nothing to delve into, to be submerged in. This narrative moves forward in a straight line, such that there is no space left between the lines, which is also the space where the magic happens. “The last time we made love you asked me if I was scared, I think you wanted me to say yes” Subtlety is also Olivia’s distinguishing quality. Even in poems with darker undertones, in stories of pain and abuse, she often speaks about the abuse without ever outrightly addressing it. And strangely enough, the indistinction encapsulates the very nature of abuse itself, to be so subtle that we wish to ignore it. How abuse isn’t usually isolated and identifiable, but it’s in words, actions and behaviours interlaced with all else, how it is indistinguishable to the extent that it almost resembles normalcy. She brings out the imperceptible fears that lurk within us. Olivia gets the grey nature of things. “The boy doesn’t ask if he can choke me, so I pretend to die while he’s doing it” She is the curator to the museum of all our stories, some lost and some broken, what’s different is the light that she uses to guide us through them. A light of pride. She leaves one with not only the feeling that poetry is magical but that being a girl itself is so so wondrous and sensationally beautiful in nature. Olivia is about the details, about the fears and insecurities in the experiences of girlhood, and the understanding that from the smallest instances emerges the greatest solidarity. Being a girl can be a constant struggle for selfhood. Everything teenage girls do and are is under constant attack and ridicule. And that is precisely how patriarchy is structured, that even a single moment of uninterrupted female existence is unendurable for them. And to that, she says, f*ck you. “When the boy said, he liked my hair the other way, I shaved my head instead of my p*ssy.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Jadis the Bells: The Pyres of Notre Dame</title>
      <link href="/The-Pyres-of-Notre-Dame" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jadis the Bells: The Pyres of Notre Dame" />
      <published>2019-04-25T14:05:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-25T14:05:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Pyres-of-Notre-Dame</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Pyres-of-Notre-Dame">&lt;p&gt;Jadis, the bells. Paris is in flames. Notre de Dame de Paris, my dearest, most
cherished Cathedral, our Lady of Paris, is burning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or certainly, it was when I began writing. Now it sits, an exhausted carcass,
divested of that eldest of jewels from the Parisian skyline. Much of the stained
glass is ruined. And the windows have been blinded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is particularly painful for all French people. I, like many of them, have a
long, difficult and passionate relationship with Notre Dame, mostly because of
how much I have sung about it. I remember the first time I saw the Cathedral
itself depicted, in the Disney film, &lt;em&gt;The Hunchback of Notre Dame&lt;/em&gt;. The most
gothic, the darkest piece in the mouse’s repertoire, it marked me as a child.
The first time I heard those voices, coupled with those spires, stabbing into
that sky, I was terrified, I was exhilarated, I was amazed at the power of the
artistic and dark marvel. It stayed with me forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The passion people can have for something so immortal as a building can truly
show how they can bring out the personhood within our creations, the moral in
the static. Anthropology has much to say about such things, particularly in the
works of Michel Foucault, especially on how architecture affects peoples’
feelings; how their surroundings affect their moods; how buildings can be so
evocative, purely because of this integral intransitive nature of the human
spirit, because of this very ghost within the shell. And what ghosts do haunt
our cities now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Victor Hugo knew this, in fact he published that famous hunchback’s tale in an
effort to generate public interest in the Cathedral, which was at the time
Paris’s local, dilapidated and forgotten ruin. His book, in time, helped garner
enough interest to pay for the restorations we saw crumble and part into dust
and smoke in the wind. And so that spirit passes. And so passes the old Europe,
into oblivion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I ever sang a solo in our rural town’s music conservatoire young
choir, at say 12 or 13, I knew what I would sing about. I still remember my name
being called, as I stepped out from behind the curtain to expectant applause,
and the bells shook, and the voices did swell, until my queue, on a little
accordion…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Morning in Paris, the city awakes to the Bells of Notre Dame. The fisherman
fishes, the bakerman bakes, to the Bells of Notre Dame. From the big bells as
LOUD as the Thunder, to the little bells as -soft- as a psalm, and SOME say the
SOUL of the city’s the TOLL of the bells… The Bells of Notre Dame. Kyrie
eleison…”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it was never the same for me again. I still remember sitting in the cellar
of our old 15th century house, in France, intermittently watching the musical
Notre Dame de Paris, waiting for my calls to help with the dinners we would host
at the Manor. I sat in awe as Bruneau Pelletier sang away about “a time of
Cathedrals”, becoming one of my vocal heroes, the song becoming one of my go-to
standards. That famous song of the successful musical show touches on the advent
of the Cathedral as a symbol of man’s growing ambition in Europe, heralded by
the Gothic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the passage from Romanesque to Gothic architecture, in making the buildings
bigger, European architecture had looked to nature to make the inside of
churches resemble the outside world and was inspired by the natural landscape
for decoration and adaptation of space. The very term ‘gothic’ itself was used
derogatively by writers like Molière to criticise a barbarous, pagan style
called monstrous by association with a less ‘civilised’ age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By very virtue of worshipping a ‘pagus’, a local spirit of nature, the earlier
pagans venerated nature, and medieval Christian churches began to take on
aspects emulative of the ‘nemetons’, sacred groves of the heathens from Europe
of yore. Greeks and Romans themselves had their ‘tenemos’, areas of vegetation
or clearings separated from public use, for a religious purpose (associated with
the female Oracle at Delphi; perhaps related to the Greek &lt;em&gt;delphus&lt;/em&gt;, ‘womb’).
The Norse Poetic &lt;em&gt;Edda&lt;/em&gt; features the open-air ‘hörgr’ (harrow, etymologically
related to ‘heathen’). D. Wilson notes that for the Anglo-Saxons, the hörgr is
specifically a “special type of religious site, that occupied a prominent
position on high land and was a communal place of worship for a specific group
of people”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon, almost as if inspired by a divine, pagan purpose sleeping within them, as
if it had been dictated to them by an ancestral wisdom, the medieval European
builders of gothic churches beheld the truly sacred, the natural world, and made
of it a cold, stone creation. They took the magical outside, brought it inside,
and made of it the prerogative of their one god and the possession of the mortal
man. All of this, in simple architecture, in ancient stone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the veneration of fertility in the form of resplendent, beautiful goddesses
was retained somehow by the Europeans of old Paris, for though referring to the
Virgin Mary, they made of this now presently wounded cathedral, ‘Our Lady’, of
the city.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I saw the place in person was in 2017 on a much belated visit to
the capital, I was shy and nervous about the city, like an estranged friend,
like a lost lover, but when I arrived with a companion acting as guide at the
station of the Isle de la Cité, then I knew. Then I felt it. The soul of Paris.
It was about time. It was about the enduring, deepest European aspect. And then
we went upstairs, and to the street. And I heard it. I heard them. The bells of
Notre Dame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I finally did go inside, it was a deeply spiritual experience, but not for
Christian reasons. For only then did I feel and know Paris. The high ceilings
and high halls, evoking Europe’s ancient sacred groves of tall trees, oak, pine
and poplar. The Cathedral’s small park by the Seine, watching the people of the
city go by, young people, young students, people from intelligent cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People love their cities, and they love the buildings which they and their kin
have woken up to and walked past for centuries. Such a paysage of human
construction acts to support a sort of consistency of a nation’s spirit. These
buildings are a skeleton, they are the frameworks which contain and maintain the
very culture of the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so everywhere, on our social media platforms, on our video-streaming
services, all that can be heard is that “Europe is dying!”. It is not the first
time a great fire having devastated a great edifice of cultural import has
prompted reactions of national significance. Most significantly, comparisons can
be drawn to the 1933 Reichstag Fire, when the burning of the historic German
Parliament building in Berlin allowed Adolf Hitler to put the country into a
state of national alert. This was the first and most conclusive step towards
seizing power on a national scale for Hitler, and it sealed Germany’s future
forever.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conspiracies have abounded for decades and ever will as to the cause of such
fires. But the consequences of such fires are inarguable: grim, dejected locals,
suddenly feeling a great need to protect what is theirs for pride and for
sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, poor Notre Dame. If her bells do not sound, Paris is made mute. If her
glass does not shine, Paris is blinded. But we must not forget that as long as
her children live, Our Lady of Paris survives. And so we must look to future
truth, and future Europeans. If their spirit built her, their spirit can do and
ought to do so much more than this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jadis, les cloches. Adieux Notre Dame. Adieux Paris. I owe you the letters after
my name. And I hear you forever in my heart. Jadis, the bells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this comes now, when we see ourselves go mad, when a black hole is seen for
the first time, and we stare into it; the abyss stares back, and smiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw fire, and as it presides over us now, the black hole sun dawns. A vile
rictus upon us. How destiny does smile, sickeningly. How the fates, as the
vates, do seem to have a sense of humour. Clown World begins. A Circle of fire
forms.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Morgan Black</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Jadis, the bells. Paris is in flames. Notre de Dame de Paris, my dearest, most cherished Cathedral, our Lady of Paris, is burning. Or certainly, it was when I began writing. Now it sits, an exhausted carcass, divested of that eldest of jewels from the Parisian skyline. Much of the stained glass is ruined. And the windows have been blinded. This is particularly painful for all French people. I, like many of them, have a long, difficult and passionate relationship with Notre Dame, mostly because of how much I have sung about it. I remember the first time I saw the Cathedral itself depicted, in the Disney film, The Hunchback of Notre Dame. The most gothic, the darkest piece in the mouse’s repertoire, it marked me as a child. The first time I heard those voices, coupled with those spires, stabbing into that sky, I was terrified, I was exhilarated, I was amazed at the power of the artistic and dark marvel. It stayed with me forever. The passion people can have for something so immortal as a building can truly show how they can bring out the personhood within our creations, the moral in the static. Anthropology has much to say about such things, particularly in the works of Michel Foucault, especially on how architecture affects peoples’ feelings; how their surroundings affect their moods; how buildings can be so evocative, purely because of this integral intransitive nature of the human spirit, because of this very ghost within the shell. And what ghosts do haunt our cities now. Victor Hugo knew this, in fact he published that famous hunchback’s tale in an effort to generate public interest in the Cathedral, which was at the time Paris’s local, dilapidated and forgotten ruin. His book, in time, helped garner enough interest to pay for the restorations we saw crumble and part into dust and smoke in the wind. And so that spirit passes. And so passes the old Europe, into oblivion. The first time I ever sang a solo in our rural town’s music conservatoire young choir, at say 12 or 13, I knew what I would sing about. I still remember my name being called, as I stepped out from behind the curtain to expectant applause, and the bells shook, and the voices did swell, until my queue, on a little accordion… “Morning in Paris, the city awakes to the Bells of Notre Dame. The fisherman fishes, the bakerman bakes, to the Bells of Notre Dame. From the big bells as LOUD as the Thunder, to the little bells as -soft- as a psalm, and SOME say the SOUL of the city’s the TOLL of the bells… The Bells of Notre Dame. Kyrie eleison…”. And it was never the same for me again. I still remember sitting in the cellar of our old 15th century house, in France, intermittently watching the musical Notre Dame de Paris, waiting for my calls to help with the dinners we would host at the Manor. I sat in awe as Bruneau Pelletier sang away about “a time of Cathedrals”, becoming one of my vocal heroes, the song becoming one of my go-to standards. That famous song of the successful musical show touches on the advent of the Cathedral as a symbol of man’s growing ambition in Europe, heralded by the Gothic. In the passage from Romanesque to Gothic architecture, in making the buildings bigger, European architecture had looked to nature to make the inside of churches resemble the outside world and was inspired by the natural landscape for decoration and adaptation of space. The very term ‘gothic’ itself was used derogatively by writers like Molière to criticise a barbarous, pagan style called monstrous by association with a less ‘civilised’ age. By very virtue of worshipping a ‘pagus’, a local spirit of nature, the earlier pagans venerated nature, and medieval Christian churches began to take on aspects emulative of the ‘nemetons’, sacred groves of the heathens from Europe of yore. Greeks and Romans themselves had their ‘tenemos’, areas of vegetation or clearings separated from public use, for a religious purpose (associated with the female Oracle at Delphi; perhaps related to the Greek delphus, ‘womb’). The Norse Poetic Edda features the open-air ‘hörgr’ (harrow, etymologically related to ‘heathen’). D. Wilson notes that for the Anglo-Saxons, the hörgr is specifically a “special type of religious site, that occupied a prominent position on high land and was a communal place of worship for a specific group of people”. Soon, almost as if inspired by a divine, pagan purpose sleeping within them, as if it had been dictated to them by an ancestral wisdom, the medieval European builders of gothic churches beheld the truly sacred, the natural world, and made of it a cold, stone creation. They took the magical outside, brought it inside, and made of it the prerogative of their one god and the possession of the mortal man. All of this, in simple architecture, in ancient stone. Even the veneration of fertility in the form of resplendent, beautiful goddesses was retained somehow by the Europeans of old Paris, for though referring to the Virgin Mary, they made of this now presently wounded cathedral, ‘Our Lady’, of the city.   The first time I saw the place in person was in 2017 on a much belated visit to the capital, I was shy and nervous about the city, like an estranged friend, like a lost lover, but when I arrived with a companion acting as guide at the station of the Isle de la Cité, then I knew. Then I felt it. The soul of Paris. It was about time. It was about the enduring, deepest European aspect. And then we went upstairs, and to the street. And I heard it. I heard them. The bells of Notre Dame. When I finally did go inside, it was a deeply spiritual experience, but not for Christian reasons. For only then did I feel and know Paris. The high ceilings and high halls, evoking Europe’s ancient sacred groves of tall trees, oak, pine and poplar. The Cathedral’s small park by the Seine, watching the people of the city go by, young people, young students, people from intelligent cities. People love their cities, and they love the buildings which they and their kin have woken up to and walked past for centuries. Such a paysage of human construction acts to support a sort of consistency of a nation’s spirit. These buildings are a skeleton, they are the frameworks which contain and maintain the very culture of the people. And so everywhere, on our social media platforms, on our video-streaming services, all that can be heard is that “Europe is dying!”. It is not the first time a great fire having devastated a great edifice of cultural import has prompted reactions of national significance. Most significantly, comparisons can be drawn to the 1933 Reichstag Fire, when the burning of the historic German Parliament building in Berlin allowed Adolf Hitler to put the country into a state of national alert. This was the first and most conclusive step towards seizing power on a national scale for Hitler, and it sealed Germany’s future forever.    Conspiracies have abounded for decades and ever will as to the cause of such fires. But the consequences of such fires are inarguable: grim, dejected locals, suddenly feeling a great need to protect what is theirs for pride and for sovereignty. And so, poor Notre Dame. If her bells do not sound, Paris is made mute. If her glass does not shine, Paris is blinded. But we must not forget that as long as her children live, Our Lady of Paris survives. And so we must look to future truth, and future Europeans. If their spirit built her, their spirit can do and ought to do so much more than this. Jadis, les cloches. Adieux Notre Dame. Adieux Paris. I owe you the letters after my name. And I hear you forever in my heart. Jadis, the bells. And this comes now, when we see ourselves go mad, when a black hole is seen for the first time, and we stare into it; the abyss stares back, and smiles. I saw fire, and as it presides over us now, the black hole sun dawns. A vile rictus upon us. How destiny does smile, sickeningly. How the fates, as the vates, do seem to have a sense of humour. Clown World begins. A Circle of fire forms.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Circle of Fire: A Lament and Lesson for Europe</title>
      <link href="/Circle-of-Fire" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Circle of Fire: A Lament and Lesson for Europe" />
      <published>2019-04-11T04:29:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-11T04:29:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Circle-of-Fire</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Circle-of-Fire">&lt;p&gt;1818, in a dusty, dawn-cast attic of a stately home, a statue begins to turn
from the grey of shaped limestone to the radiant gold of marble. It is a copy of
a very old Roman copy, of a Greek sculpture: “The Dying Gaul”, as commissioned
by Attalus I of Pergamon while celebrating his victory over the Celts of Turkey
in the 3rd Century BCE. In the dusty room, at daybreak, an amber light shines on
the torque tightly clasping the statue’s neck, a circle somehow proud, yet
broken, beneath his downcast brow. The “Dying Gaul” is depicted as so dismal, so
dejected a thing that many observe an inherent sadness in him. Admiring the
skill of the artist, even Lord Byron himself writes about the pathos engendered
by the scene. However, he dubs him &lt;em&gt;The Dying Gladiator&lt;/em&gt;, and so even as an art
piece, this lost, false picture of a man is, like his race, truly forgotten.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many miles away, in Lahore, modern-day Pakistan, a Sikh wears a “Chakram” as he
prepares for a wedding ceremony. These metal rings recalling the mythological
weapon of the Hindu god Krishna, the disc-bearer. Despite having lost their
practical functionality after the British arrived, “chakrams” retain their
symbolic importance. Even in a Punjabi wedding, Indo-European Vedic traditions
remain, as a bride to be wedded has her feet painted in Mehndi by a woman older
than herself and already happily married.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So telling, how these traits of myth may endure, even through the ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The role of mythology, of all “divine poetry”, is to act as superlative verse to
the layman’s consideration of the passing day, to act as sacred words which fill
colour into the profane of our world. In fact, we might see our culture itself
as a sort of divine consort, as a partner to our existence, and determine that
an individual divested of culture is lonely. Our cultural identity is,
therefore, our spouse and it is given to us by our heritage. Ultimately, the
only thing which separates one group of people from another is the place they
are situated in, and religious beliefs are formed dependent on the surroundings
of said people. You would only pray for the sorts of things your lands made
plentiful or precious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, what follows is this: all mythology encompasses the relationship of a
people with their geological environment. This makes all religion, all cultural
heritage an ontological understanding of one’s surroundings. We process the
existence we know. That is the truly pagan way of being in oneself, that is the
truly human way. Nature will teach you; it will teach you everything. Nature has
many faces, but one voice and we must remember that Mother Nature has no
obligation to be fair to you. Neither do natural forces. But you can try to
understand them. Even, dare I say, try to communicate with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All religion serves to reconcile the distance between the earthly and the
heavenly, and it seems one patch of Earth, lived upon by one people in
opposition to another, becomes a different Earth. And the force which marries us
to our geographically-defined culture, religion, etc., is the same which would
bind one person to another. Once, what was called Sati in one place was observed
in different forms in others. Accounts from Ibn Fadlan and the verses from the
&lt;em&gt;Sigurðarkviða hin skamma&lt;/em&gt; assert that Norse people would offer up a wealthy
Chieftain’s &lt;em&gt;thralls&lt;/em&gt; or slaves, to his funeral pyre after his passing, and
Julius Caesar says the same of the Celts in &lt;em&gt;De Bello Gallico&lt;/em&gt;. This Roman
account is the origin of the ‘Wicker Man’ stereotype, where beloved ‘dependants’
of the deceased are given up along with other offerings to be purified into
something others would call &lt;em&gt;Agni&lt;/em&gt;, the sacred fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be more virtuous to plaster all discourse pertaining to such things
with comments on the barbarous vestiges of a less appropriately enlightened
past, but it might be more useful still to understand why people would do such
things. And so go from “ignorance to truth, darkness to light, and death to
immortality,” as per that enigmatic mantra echoed in Hindu Yagna rituals, it
would seem. If truth could be light. If that light could be immortality, it
would take the shape of a fire fed by and specified by one’s very beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how our belief ties us to our people, to our lands. We live and die by
them. We do not simply have our culture follow us into the fire. We go because
of it. And whether that is ethically speaking without blemish or not, it is
certainly powerful. We do things which seem illogical, which other animals do
not do. A culture is a truth, it is an understanding of the world. In such a
way, it considers rules and identifies what is to be prized in this
understanding of the world, and what is to be deemed more unsightly. And this is
the nature of our identities, as humans, as ethnicities. This is how we are
married to our cultures, not in bondage, but in heritage, as per a hypernatural,
proto-legal contract. This is us. &lt;em&gt;Alive&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Europe is becoming even less alive itself, because it is becoming less
Christian, which in and of itself would not necessitate unfortunate
circumstances, if only it did not entail the rise of Atheism. As a consequence,
Europe becomes ‘more lonely’. It manages the extraordinary feat of being somehow
formed of so many countries which remain so impossibly isolated from each other.
Yet, indeed, it is natural that this continent should have no faith, and no
faith in itself, for such things were bored out of it by the Romans and
Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is my customary finding that things usually succeed in doing what they were
designed to do, and Christianity was designed to make the European people
complacent and easy to control. No wonder that as it falls, as the Church
awakens to every nightmare about paedophilia accusations in this hypocritical
bed it has made for itself, Europeans are not only impossible to control, but
they are directionless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christianity is more impactful from a cultural perspective than a spiritual one;
it served as a device of enforcing the Roman rule and extending the duration of
their Empire, supplanting an enduring (arguably militant) presence in their
lands as an oppressive crushing of culture on a local scale, imposing a single
identity-defining dogma. It was applied to control, and now the people are
uncontrollable, and inconsolably unruly since the Roman rule has decayed. Yet,
it is the state of the dominated to retain their chains after their master has
met their demise. It is surprising Europe has taken so long to throw off the
very yoke of Christendom in the first place. Albeit, Christianity had been
unknowingly preserving truly European, pagan culture. And, as it falls, so does
its inherited identity. Atheism has come and it brings with it a cold, stark
divestment of the European spirit from the European body. This makes every man
and woman less than human, for all different world cultures, all at least have a
notion of the spirit, and a cornered animal lashes out because it is afraid,
outnumbered, perhaps. &lt;em&gt;Alone&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a time of division. Even as we speak, conversations are cracking open
about the consequences of Brexit in regards to Ireland’s relationship with
Northern Ireland, and while a united Éire may seem like a step forward, it also
indicates the breaking down of a much older order. One thing upon which we all
can agree is that changes are afoot. For better or for worse, it seems this
great and old continent will never be the same again. The end of individual
difference, so surely the end of our differences altogether, no? Ultimate unity
through ultimate, violent equity. Of course, it is rather beneficial for Church
and State alike to have its people be without identity; they are so much easier
to pra(e)y upon! And so, behold the touted saviour: &lt;em&gt;Socialism&lt;/em&gt;. It is at the
heart of globalisation, but socialism was purely and only an advent of chaos, a
machine designed to destroy. Karl Marx did not want to help the working classes,
but he did want to make them kill people, often each other.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marx believed a great change was on the horizon, but the problem with his ideas
was that he believed the change could only and must be reached via great
conflict. He believed society was on the verge of collapse, he never incited
peaceful resolution or the empowerment of workers and always sought only to arm
them rather than communicate with them. When he visited the German Workers’
Education Society of London in 1845, he found self-educated, self-made men. They
were anti-liberal, anti-bohemian and practically-minded, and he saw them as
lowly for not sharing his apocalyptic ambitions for the future. They engaged in
practical discussion, though without academic training in philosophy (which is
why he disliked working men and thought them beneath himself). This was not what
he wanted. He wanted revolution and chaos, for as he stated: “Socialism cannot
be brought into existence without revolution”. When his father died in 1838, he
spent much of his inheritance of 6000 ₣ on arming Belgian workers with guns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly, the violent revolutions of the country I grew up in, France, have a
long history indeed of upheaving everything and distracting from the country’s
problems until they go away, but they ultimately benefited slightly wealthier
men seizing power, only to be deposed by men slightly less wealthy than
themselves. Every time, it is the slightly less hard-working man who gains
leadership at the expense of the slightly harder working man. The same can be
seen in the French-backed American Revolution, a systematic upheaval which
allowed wealthy English landowners in the New World to detach themselves from
their colonial control of ‘The British’ under the new identity of ‘The
American’, and they profited and suffered immensely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, marrying oneself to a new culture, a new identity, will dictate one’s
destiny. And so come into focus the fires of modern-day Paris, lit by the Gilets
Jaunes. Fire once more presides the times of chaos, the times of change. So how,
I ask, can this, revolution, be the answer? I cannot agree that Marx was right
in the larger sense that it is necessary, but I must wonder as to his related
belief that it is inevitable. Visions of fire, revolution and chaos, and one
must think of the Wheel of Fire, a Greek mythological image originating in the
punishment of Ixion after his lusting for Zeus’s divine consort, Hera. It
signifies a torturous chain of events leading to dire consequences, in result of
personal actions or flaws which are ultimately the victim’s fault. It provides a
caveat to be considered, in matters of want and misplaced ambition. It is the
fall from grace, and it is engendered by the foreboding betrayal of a sacred
matrimony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I attend a concert by the folk-rock band Faun, at the end, a skaldic
lutist/mandolin player speaks as a grandiose orator, transforming from the
humble, weaselly man he has been every other time we hear him speak into
something approaching the divine musician we have seen play, as when he
performs, as when he sings. His band’s spectacle reaches an emotive pinnacle as
he speaks, almost preaching now, but with such zeal the likes of which a
hurricane could not bring any modern Christian priest to muster, with the
passion not seen since they were not merely excused by the burning of our wise
women but corralled it. The kind of power not seen unless truth and conviction
bolster the rightful in their unextinguished focus; he says we must remember who
we are. Remember nature. Our own nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As he speaks in his complete form, finally, but only once, is mentioned the
creature who is the namesake of the band, the faun, the Pan figure, who just
like Krishna plays the flute and sits surrounded by the animals, a Master of
Beasts. And then he says how it was known by another name to the Celts, as
Cernunnos. Thus begins the cycle. A vision of a devil. A vision of nature,
personified. A herald of flame to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I contemplate this apple of my eye which I see on the horizon. Knowledge
of paganism is the knowledge of how to live and connect with our environment of
Europe, and so I say that, for the West, to transcend Christendom via the
produce of the trees of knowledge is the only way that we will be able to live
in this garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The serpent penetrates the apple. Perhaps, it is to be seized, like the
Snake-Witch Stone shows, perhaps it is to be defeated like the biblical
Leviathan. But it is no primitive return to nature which will save us now, but a
mature and learned taking into oneself the ways of yore. We must make of
ourselves ergonomic beings. A form of cultural bio-mimicry will be observed in
ancient lore, and this will tell us how to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, there are philosophies and facts to be observed in the natural
world, echoed in mythology, which can inform us on how to live our lives, so we
can be healthier, but also on how we should think, so we can be &lt;em&gt;holier&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I think on this vision, I must wonder what ‘true spiritual sun’ will be
unveiled to us, ‘hidden by a disc of golden light’. What truth will be known,
what duty done? What sacred feet, anointed now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking to the future, for Europe, for the world? &lt;em&gt;Fire&lt;/em&gt;. But will it be a wheel
or a dawn? This will depend on the nature, the aspect and, I fear, upon the
reception of this, the &lt;em&gt;Truth&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These tales of myth and history weave in and out of each other, they remind us
of our inherent shared heritage defined not as humans, but as people. For, in
commiseration with history, mythology serves not only to grant us stories from
the past where we may learn how to rise, but also stories of the soul, that we
may learn not to fall. And what these similarities do tell us is that Europe
should be united under common ground, regardless of any Union - so long as it
remains European. As such, it is time Europe decided to whom it would be married
and what is to be the philosophical companion to its destiny, what identity will
accompany it towards an uncertain future. Some would say we look outside, or
without. I merely say we look within.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Morgan Black</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">1818, in a dusty, dawn-cast attic of a stately home, a statue begins to turn from the grey of shaped limestone to the radiant gold of marble. It is a copy of a very old Roman copy, of a Greek sculpture: “The Dying Gaul”, as commissioned by Attalus I of Pergamon while celebrating his victory over the Celts of Turkey in the 3rd Century BCE. In the dusty room, at daybreak, an amber light shines on the torque tightly clasping the statue’s neck, a circle somehow proud, yet broken, beneath his downcast brow. The “Dying Gaul” is depicted as so dismal, so dejected a thing that many observe an inherent sadness in him. Admiring the skill of the artist, even Lord Byron himself writes about the pathos engendered by the scene. However, he dubs him The Dying Gladiator, and so even as an art piece, this lost, false picture of a man is, like his race, truly forgotten.   Many miles away, in Lahore, modern-day Pakistan, a Sikh wears a “Chakram” as he prepares for a wedding ceremony. These metal rings recalling the mythological weapon of the Hindu god Krishna, the disc-bearer. Despite having lost their practical functionality after the British arrived, “chakrams” retain their symbolic importance. Even in a Punjabi wedding, Indo-European Vedic traditions remain, as a bride to be wedded has her feet painted in Mehndi by a woman older than herself and already happily married. So telling, how these traits of myth may endure, even through the ages. The role of mythology, of all “divine poetry”, is to act as superlative verse to the layman’s consideration of the passing day, to act as sacred words which fill colour into the profane of our world. In fact, we might see our culture itself as a sort of divine consort, as a partner to our existence, and determine that an individual divested of culture is lonely. Our cultural identity is, therefore, our spouse and it is given to us by our heritage. Ultimately, the only thing which separates one group of people from another is the place they are situated in, and religious beliefs are formed dependent on the surroundings of said people. You would only pray for the sorts of things your lands made plentiful or precious. Therefore, what follows is this: all mythology encompasses the relationship of a people with their geological environment. This makes all religion, all cultural heritage an ontological understanding of one’s surroundings. We process the existence we know. That is the truly pagan way of being in oneself, that is the truly human way. Nature will teach you; it will teach you everything. Nature has many faces, but one voice and we must remember that Mother Nature has no obligation to be fair to you. Neither do natural forces. But you can try to understand them. Even, dare I say, try to communicate with them. All religion serves to reconcile the distance between the earthly and the heavenly, and it seems one patch of Earth, lived upon by one people in opposition to another, becomes a different Earth. And the force which marries us to our geographically-defined culture, religion, etc., is the same which would bind one person to another. Once, what was called Sati in one place was observed in different forms in others. Accounts from Ibn Fadlan and the verses from the Sigurðarkviða hin skamma assert that Norse people would offer up a wealthy Chieftain’s thralls or slaves, to his funeral pyre after his passing, and Julius Caesar says the same of the Celts in De Bello Gallico. This Roman account is the origin of the ‘Wicker Man’ stereotype, where beloved ‘dependants’ of the deceased are given up along with other offerings to be purified into something others would call Agni, the sacred fire. It might be more virtuous to plaster all discourse pertaining to such things with comments on the barbarous vestiges of a less appropriately enlightened past, but it might be more useful still to understand why people would do such things. And so go from “ignorance to truth, darkness to light, and death to immortality,” as per that enigmatic mantra echoed in Hindu Yagna rituals, it would seem. If truth could be light. If that light could be immortality, it would take the shape of a fire fed by and specified by one’s very beliefs. This is how our belief ties us to our people, to our lands. We live and die by them. We do not simply have our culture follow us into the fire. We go because of it. And whether that is ethically speaking without blemish or not, it is certainly powerful. We do things which seem illogical, which other animals do not do. A culture is a truth, it is an understanding of the world. In such a way, it considers rules and identifies what is to be prized in this understanding of the world, and what is to be deemed more unsightly. And this is the nature of our identities, as humans, as ethnicities. This is how we are married to our cultures, not in bondage, but in heritage, as per a hypernatural, proto-legal contract. This is us. Alive. But Europe is becoming even less alive itself, because it is becoming less Christian, which in and of itself would not necessitate unfortunate circumstances, if only it did not entail the rise of Atheism. As a consequence, Europe becomes ‘more lonely’. It manages the extraordinary feat of being somehow formed of so many countries which remain so impossibly isolated from each other. Yet, indeed, it is natural that this continent should have no faith, and no faith in itself, for such things were bored out of it by the Romans and Christianity. It is my customary finding that things usually succeed in doing what they were designed to do, and Christianity was designed to make the European people complacent and easy to control. No wonder that as it falls, as the Church awakens to every nightmare about paedophilia accusations in this hypocritical bed it has made for itself, Europeans are not only impossible to control, but they are directionless. Christianity is more impactful from a cultural perspective than a spiritual one; it served as a device of enforcing the Roman rule and extending the duration of their Empire, supplanting an enduring (arguably militant) presence in their lands as an oppressive crushing of culture on a local scale, imposing a single identity-defining dogma. It was applied to control, and now the people are uncontrollable, and inconsolably unruly since the Roman rule has decayed. Yet, it is the state of the dominated to retain their chains after their master has met their demise. It is surprising Europe has taken so long to throw off the very yoke of Christendom in the first place. Albeit, Christianity had been unknowingly preserving truly European, pagan culture. And, as it falls, so does its inherited identity. Atheism has come and it brings with it a cold, stark divestment of the European spirit from the European body. This makes every man and woman less than human, for all different world cultures, all at least have a notion of the spirit, and a cornered animal lashes out because it is afraid, outnumbered, perhaps. Alone. This is a time of division. Even as we speak, conversations are cracking open about the consequences of Brexit in regards to Ireland’s relationship with Northern Ireland, and while a united Éire may seem like a step forward, it also indicates the breaking down of a much older order. One thing upon which we all can agree is that changes are afoot. For better or for worse, it seems this great and old continent will never be the same again. The end of individual difference, so surely the end of our differences altogether, no? Ultimate unity through ultimate, violent equity. Of course, it is rather beneficial for Church and State alike to have its people be without identity; they are so much easier to pra(e)y upon! And so, behold the touted saviour: Socialism. It is at the heart of globalisation, but socialism was purely and only an advent of chaos, a machine designed to destroy. Karl Marx did not want to help the working classes, but he did want to make them kill people, often each other.   Marx believed a great change was on the horizon, but the problem with his ideas was that he believed the change could only and must be reached via great conflict. He believed society was on the verge of collapse, he never incited peaceful resolution or the empowerment of workers and always sought only to arm them rather than communicate with them. When he visited the German Workers’ Education Society of London in 1845, he found self-educated, self-made men. They were anti-liberal, anti-bohemian and practically-minded, and he saw them as lowly for not sharing his apocalyptic ambitions for the future. They engaged in practical discussion, though without academic training in philosophy (which is why he disliked working men and thought them beneath himself). This was not what he wanted. He wanted revolution and chaos, for as he stated: “Socialism cannot be brought into existence without revolution”. When his father died in 1838, he spent much of his inheritance of 6000 ₣ on arming Belgian workers with guns. Certainly, the violent revolutions of the country I grew up in, France, have a long history indeed of upheaving everything and distracting from the country’s problems until they go away, but they ultimately benefited slightly wealthier men seizing power, only to be deposed by men slightly less wealthy than themselves. Every time, it is the slightly less hard-working man who gains leadership at the expense of the slightly harder working man. The same can be seen in the French-backed American Revolution, a systematic upheaval which allowed wealthy English landowners in the New World to detach themselves from their colonial control of ‘The British’ under the new identity of ‘The American’, and they profited and suffered immensely. Again, marrying oneself to a new culture, a new identity, will dictate one’s destiny. And so come into focus the fires of modern-day Paris, lit by the Gilets Jaunes. Fire once more presides the times of chaos, the times of change. So how, I ask, can this, revolution, be the answer? I cannot agree that Marx was right in the larger sense that it is necessary, but I must wonder as to his related belief that it is inevitable. Visions of fire, revolution and chaos, and one must think of the Wheel of Fire, a Greek mythological image originating in the punishment of Ixion after his lusting for Zeus’s divine consort, Hera. It signifies a torturous chain of events leading to dire consequences, in result of personal actions or flaws which are ultimately the victim’s fault. It provides a caveat to be considered, in matters of want and misplaced ambition. It is the fall from grace, and it is engendered by the foreboding betrayal of a sacred matrimony. As I attend a concert by the folk-rock band Faun, at the end, a skaldic lutist/mandolin player speaks as a grandiose orator, transforming from the humble, weaselly man he has been every other time we hear him speak into something approaching the divine musician we have seen play, as when he performs, as when he sings. His band’s spectacle reaches an emotive pinnacle as he speaks, almost preaching now, but with such zeal the likes of which a hurricane could not bring any modern Christian priest to muster, with the passion not seen since they were not merely excused by the burning of our wise women but corralled it. The kind of power not seen unless truth and conviction bolster the rightful in their unextinguished focus; he says we must remember who we are. Remember nature. Our own nature. As he speaks in his complete form, finally, but only once, is mentioned the creature who is the namesake of the band, the faun, the Pan figure, who just like Krishna plays the flute and sits surrounded by the animals, a Master of Beasts. And then he says how it was known by another name to the Celts, as Cernunnos. Thus begins the cycle. A vision of a devil. A vision of nature, personified. A herald of flame to come. And so I contemplate this apple of my eye which I see on the horizon. Knowledge of paganism is the knowledge of how to live and connect with our environment of Europe, and so I say that, for the West, to transcend Christendom via the produce of the trees of knowledge is the only way that we will be able to live in this garden. The serpent penetrates the apple. Perhaps, it is to be seized, like the Snake-Witch Stone shows, perhaps it is to be defeated like the biblical Leviathan. But it is no primitive return to nature which will save us now, but a mature and learned taking into oneself the ways of yore. We must make of ourselves ergonomic beings. A form of cultural bio-mimicry will be observed in ancient lore, and this will tell us how to be. Simply put, there are philosophies and facts to be observed in the natural world, echoed in mythology, which can inform us on how to live our lives, so we can be healthier, but also on how we should think, so we can be holier. As I think on this vision, I must wonder what ‘true spiritual sun’ will be unveiled to us, ‘hidden by a disc of golden light’. What truth will be known, what duty done? What sacred feet, anointed now? Looking to the future, for Europe, for the world? Fire. But will it be a wheel or a dawn? This will depend on the nature, the aspect and, I fear, upon the reception of this, the Truth. These tales of myth and history weave in and out of each other, they remind us of our inherent shared heritage defined not as humans, but as people. For, in commiseration with history, mythology serves not only to grant us stories from the past where we may learn how to rise, but also stories of the soul, that we may learn not to fall. And what these similarities do tell us is that Europe should be united under common ground, regardless of any Union - so long as it remains European. As such, it is time Europe decided to whom it would be married and what is to be the philosophical companion to its destiny, what identity will accompany it towards an uncertain future. Some would say we look outside, or without. I merely say we look within.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘Halloween’ in 2018: Missing the Point of Its Predecessor’s Pointed Social Criticism</title>
      <link href="/Halloween-In-2018" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘Halloween’ in 2018: Missing the Point of Its Predecessor’s Pointed Social Criticism" />
      <published>2019-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Halloween-In-2018</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Halloween-In-2018">&lt;p&gt;Director David Gordon Green’s 2018 sequel to John Carpenter’s 1978 classic splattered across big screens last fall, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.slashfilm.com/halloween-box-office-opening-slasher-records/&quot;&gt;breaking&lt;/a&gt; box office records for opening weekends for the long-running franchise and for the slasher genre as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But financial success is rarely a barometer for artistic success, and a film as rich in meaning as the original &lt;em&gt;Halloween&lt;/em&gt; deserves a comparative review alongside its shiny sequel. As we shall see, Green’s film stays faithful to the original’s atmosphere and structure but does little with the film’s underlying social commentary on sex and suburbia, opting instead to play it safe and only offer a few, mainly cosmetic feminist reversals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one, this sequel does not in any way address the controversial topic of sex like its predecessor did. Although John Carpenter has gone to great pains to insist that his 1978 film does not offer commentary on teenage sexuality, countless film critics have spilled much ink on the original’s unique relationship to sex. Michael Myers kills his naked sister after she has sex; he also kills babysitters and their paramour boyfriends as they engage in lovemaking or immediately after it (harkening back to an earlier association between sex and murder made in Italian thrillers known as &lt;em&gt;Gialli&lt;/em&gt;, most prominently Mario Bava’s 1971 picture &lt;em&gt;Bay of Blood&lt;/em&gt;). Many critics have seen Myers’ killings as allegorical of Middle-American and middle-class anxiety over burgeoning teenage sexuality, unleashed by the Sexual Revolution a decade before the original film’s release. Myers appears in the absence of parental supervision, acting as a nightmarish father figure in addition to being the boogeyman. By making Myers both a symbol of society’s condemnation of premarital sex and its superego, Carpenter’s film also makes teenage sexuality not just “problematic” (to use contemporary academic lingo) but transgressive, something that must be repressed by any means necessary–even violent ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Green’s &lt;em&gt;Halloween&lt;/em&gt; dispenses entirely with the transgressive teenage sexuality of the late 1970’s, instead importing contemporary America’s lax moral strictures on the subject. Allyson (granddaughter of female protagonist Laurie Strode) and her boyfriend Cameron Elam break up because Cameron drunkenly kisses another girl at a Halloween-themed dance at their high school; their mutual friend Drew Scheid drunkenly tries to hit on her afterwards and fails; babysitter Vicky begins making love with her boyfriend Dave but never gets anywhere with it. The last two episodes are interrupted by the appearance of The Shape, who promptly kills the men and the babysitter. But make no mistake, the movie offers no special Freudian connection between sex and death, eros and thanatos–the sex is incidental to the killings, and nothing more. More often than not humour interrupts otherwise romantic or steamy scenes, making it seem like the movie has nothing important to say on the subject of sex. In fact, sex features so little in the film, you would be forgiven if you mistook this &lt;em&gt;Halloween&lt;/em&gt; for a sanitised version of the original. The newest installment in the franchise merely includes sex because it was a feature of the original, which it mistook for a bug rather than an integral part of the film. The updated sexuality of Green’s film is in all likelihood an attempt to make it relatable to younger audiences, who rarely sleep with a guilty conscience–or the fear of being killed by the boogeyman–just because they’ve slept with someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of society which Green’s &lt;em&gt;Halloween&lt;/em&gt; refuses to comment upon is the decline of social trust in American society and suburbia. The original &lt;em&gt;Halloween&lt;/em&gt; was so shocking to 70’s theatregoers because of the sleepy suburb of Haddonfield, Illinois―a microcosm of Middle America, and some might say ‘real’ America―was ravaged by a faceless killer who weaved through unlocked door after unlocked door. None of the residents of Haddonfield expected the intrusion of evil into their &lt;em&gt;Halloween&lt;/em&gt; night precisely because they were embedded in a social system where neighbours not only looked out for one another but babysat each other’s children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contemporary Americans no longer trust their neighbours. Americans’ trust in their fellow citizens and trust in government have &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/trust&quot;&gt;reached&lt;/a&gt; all-time lows. One University of Minnesota &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/3792177?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; suggested that “materialistic values may be undermining young people’s views about the trustworthiness of others.” The researchers found that “the rapid rise of materialistic value orientations that occurred among American youth in the 1970s and 1980s severely eroded levels of social trust.” This is in line with the theories of French sociologist Emile Durkheim and especially French political theorist Alexis de Tocqueville, who predicted in &lt;em&gt;Democracy in America&lt;/em&gt; that democracy impels people to materialistic worldviews and pursuits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent spurt in widely publicised mass shootings, as well as the continuous coverage of assaults and rapes and all manner of affronts to civil society by an increasingly negative news media, has eroded that trust. (If anyone doubts this trend, they need only look at the media’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2017/10/02/555092743/study-news-coverage-of-trump-more-negative-than-for-other-presidents&quot;&gt;coverage&lt;/a&gt; of Donald Trump alone, which is three times as negative as the coverage of the Obama and Bush presidencies.) But instead of taking note of and commenting upon this decisive social change, the new &lt;em&gt;Halloween&lt;/em&gt; film thoughtlessly assumes the social situation of its 1978 forbearer. True, cosmetically the film boasts the reversal of gender roles by its characters―Allyson and Cameron dress as Bonnie and Clyde with the genders reversed, and Laurie Strode hunts Michael Myers in the final act of the film. But it tellingly leaves its premise–the violation of social trust–unmodified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Green’s film pathologises Laurie Strode’s prepper mindset as paranoia and a trauma which she can only work through by confronting and killing Michael Myers, when in fact in contemporary America, Strode’s fears are not so far beyond the pale as the director would like us to think. Americans, especially mothers, do fear for the safety of their children, especially in an age of widely televised mass shootings and terrorist attacks. Fewer and fewer children use public transportation and fewer and fewer states &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/03/29/well/family/utah-passes-free-range-parenting-law.html&quot;&gt;allow&lt;/a&gt; the “free-range parenting” of children. The state instead criminalises the very act of allowing one’s children to play outside unsupervised. Laurie Strode is the modern helicopter mom par excellence, and can we begrudge her for her fears given our own times and perceptions? Of all the characters in this ostensibly feminist-themed sequel, Laurie Strode and her particular brand of psychology is done the least justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green appears far more interested in merely perpetuating a franchise and duplicating its financial success, rather than actually engaging with the original film were it counts, that is, at the level of setting. The setting of &lt;em&gt;Halloween&lt;/em&gt; is what makes the idea of Michael Myers possible; gender roles have little to do with the horror of The Shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put things simply, Michael Myers would be a lot less scarier if the film had placed him in contemporary American suburbia, helicopter moms and all.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Troy Worden</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Director David Gordon Green’s 2018 sequel to John Carpenter’s 1978 classic splattered across big screens last fall, breaking box office records for opening weekends for the long-running franchise and for the slasher genre as a whole.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Dialectic on Cultural Relativism</title>
      <link href="/A-Dialectic-on-Cultural-Relativism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Dialectic on Cultural Relativism" />
      <published>2019-03-28T01:45:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-28T01:45:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Dialectic-on-Cultural-Relativism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Dialectic-on-Cultural-Relativism">&lt;p&gt;In this kaleidoscopic world, cultural diversity is a phenomenon that is standard
to every institution and organisation. Adorned with a plethora of societies and
people dressed in almost every colour on the palette, communicating in different
languages, and following all sorts of customs and traditions, the world
certainly is a beautiful place to live in. Wherever you go, whatever you do, you
are bound to encounter differences and unfamiliarity in the form of people and
the cultures they manifest. With every nook and corner characterised by its own
uniqueness, diversity has certainly become an undeniable reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we are always taught to appreciate and embrace this diversity, we must
also be cautious of its potential to cause morally problematic situations.
Consider for instance, how would you feel if someone sticks out their tongue at
you? I am sure humiliated would be the answer. But, what if I tell you that it’s
the way people greet each other in Tibet. This would certainly change things a
little bit, however, still, the whole idea of sticking out your tongue to greet
others would seem unnatural or rather weird to you, something you’ll never dare
to do to out of fear of embarrassment, unless you’re from Tibet of course! This
becomes very troubling. With divergent practices exclusive to each culture,
often questions pertaining to the “ideal conduct” are raised. One may, in fact,
be inclined to ask “Is there an ideal way at all?” And this is where the theory
of cultural relativism steps in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans have always been very intimately linked with the culture they’re brought
up in, to the extent that their choices, tastes and behaviours resonate with the
spirit and essence of their culture. Especially with respect to actions and
demeanours, culture is believed to exercise a profound influence on the lives of
people. Therefore, it is quite natural for them to cling onto their own cultural
standards and view other cultures with suspicion. Activities like the
recreational use of cemeteries in Denmark, or the Greek practice of pretending
to spit on a married couple for good luck, or the exhuming of dead bodies by
Trojan tribes, long-ringed necks in Thailand, foot binding in China, etc. might
seem a little strange to hear at first and even impel us to pass a negative
judgement. But, according to the idea of cultural relativism, such judgements
would be wrong and irrational, as they are evaluated on the basis of our own
cultural sense and sensibilities, which fail to cover the moral codes of other
cultures. According to the theory of cultural relativism, the conception of good
and evil, right and wrong, is relative to cultures and so there can never be any
universal moral code of judgment. In other words, we can’t asses other cultures
by employing our own cultural standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This becomes immensely important, given the phenomenal rise in ethnocentrism and
intolerance. With culture assuming supremacy over our lives in governing our
views and judgements, often acceptance of others becomes a little challenging.
In the face of such strict cultural conditioning, it would seem the theory of
cultural relativism is our only way out to advance towards a world characterised
by harmony and brotherhood. This seems to make cultural relativism an impeccable
theory. But is it so?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider a world with strict cultural relativism. Here, there shall be no
cross-cultural judgements; humanity would function on the principle of
tolerance, almost to the extent that everything would be approved. All cultures,
with their boons and banes, would be embraced blindly, without any reservation.
As a result, if a culture commands its male members to rape women as a
traditional custom, then cultural relativism would be able to do very little
about it. And this is where the theory takes a problematic turn. Blind
acceptance of practices paves way for certain evil tendencies to proliferate,
and since no culture is immune to defects, the theory would essentially place
the entire humanity under a grave threat. For example, women in parts of Africa
are robbed of sexual pleasure by the age-old barbaric custom of female
circumcision. But, because of cultural relativism, it becomes almost impossible
to eradicate this ill practice. While the theory does leave some scope for
intra-cultural judgements, very seldom are people seen raising voices of dissent
against their own cultures, given it is something that pulsates through their
veins. Like any other theory, cultural relativism is not a viable solution for
all situations. However, before rejecting the theory completely, it’s also
important to appreciate certain aspects of it, so that one can find a more
nuanced version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution here could be perhaps to design a new relativism altogether, one
which is based on respect, not just for the culture as a whole, but also for
individual subjects belonging to the culture. This new relativism can have a
separate mechanism to address the issues of members, who get victimised in the
name of cultural customs. With people’s participation (and not interference) in
a peaceful, rational dialogue, the seeds of change can be sown in any culture to
do away with the inherent ferocity in it. Whatever be the case, it is difficult
to deny that cultural relativism promotes an atmosphere of tolerance and amity.
By eliminating the views of dogmatism surrounding one’s culture, it makes a
person more grounded and open to greater acceptance by others. Further, it
strengthens the intercultural relationships and builds a world based on the
principles of universal brotherhood. With communities being able to understand
and empathise with each other, the world certainly becomes a better place. Of
course, cultural relativism like any theory is harmful at its logical extreme,
but so long as it is caveated with a spirit of earnest dialogue, critique, and
individual respect, it works as a theory that makes a better world.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In this kaleidoscopic world, cultural diversity is a phenomenon that is standard to every institution and organisation. Adorned with a plethora of societies and people dressed in almost every colour on the palette, communicating in different languages, and following all sorts of customs and traditions, the world certainly is a beautiful place to live in. Wherever you go, whatever you do, you are bound to encounter differences and unfamiliarity in the form of people and the cultures they manifest. With every nook and corner characterised by its own uniqueness, diversity has certainly become an undeniable reality. While we are always taught to appreciate and embrace this diversity, we must also be cautious of its potential to cause morally problematic situations. Consider for instance, how would you feel if someone sticks out their tongue at you? I am sure humiliated would be the answer. But, what if I tell you that it’s the way people greet each other in Tibet. This would certainly change things a little bit, however, still, the whole idea of sticking out your tongue to greet others would seem unnatural or rather weird to you, something you’ll never dare to do to out of fear of embarrassment, unless you’re from Tibet of course! This becomes very troubling. With divergent practices exclusive to each culture, often questions pertaining to the “ideal conduct” are raised. One may, in fact, be inclined to ask “Is there an ideal way at all?” And this is where the theory of cultural relativism steps in. Humans have always been very intimately linked with the culture they’re brought up in, to the extent that their choices, tastes and behaviours resonate with the spirit and essence of their culture. Especially with respect to actions and demeanours, culture is believed to exercise a profound influence on the lives of people. Therefore, it is quite natural for them to cling onto their own cultural standards and view other cultures with suspicion. Activities like the recreational use of cemeteries in Denmark, or the Greek practice of pretending to spit on a married couple for good luck, or the exhuming of dead bodies by Trojan tribes, long-ringed necks in Thailand, foot binding in China, etc. might seem a little strange to hear at first and even impel us to pass a negative judgement. But, according to the idea of cultural relativism, such judgements would be wrong and irrational, as they are evaluated on the basis of our own cultural sense and sensibilities, which fail to cover the moral codes of other cultures. According to the theory of cultural relativism, the conception of good and evil, right and wrong, is relative to cultures and so there can never be any universal moral code of judgment. In other words, we can’t asses other cultures by employing our own cultural standards. This becomes immensely important, given the phenomenal rise in ethnocentrism and intolerance. With culture assuming supremacy over our lives in governing our views and judgements, often acceptance of others becomes a little challenging. In the face of such strict cultural conditioning, it would seem the theory of cultural relativism is our only way out to advance towards a world characterised by harmony and brotherhood. This seems to make cultural relativism an impeccable theory. But is it so? Consider a world with strict cultural relativism. Here, there shall be no cross-cultural judgements; humanity would function on the principle of tolerance, almost to the extent that everything would be approved. All cultures, with their boons and banes, would be embraced blindly, without any reservation. As a result, if a culture commands its male members to rape women as a traditional custom, then cultural relativism would be able to do very little about it. And this is where the theory takes a problematic turn. Blind acceptance of practices paves way for certain evil tendencies to proliferate, and since no culture is immune to defects, the theory would essentially place the entire humanity under a grave threat. For example, women in parts of Africa are robbed of sexual pleasure by the age-old barbaric custom of female circumcision. But, because of cultural relativism, it becomes almost impossible to eradicate this ill practice. While the theory does leave some scope for intra-cultural judgements, very seldom are people seen raising voices of dissent against their own cultures, given it is something that pulsates through their veins. Like any other theory, cultural relativism is not a viable solution for all situations. However, before rejecting the theory completely, it’s also important to appreciate certain aspects of it, so that one can find a more nuanced version. The solution here could be perhaps to design a new relativism altogether, one which is based on respect, not just for the culture as a whole, but also for individual subjects belonging to the culture. This new relativism can have a separate mechanism to address the issues of members, who get victimised in the name of cultural customs. With people’s participation (and not interference) in a peaceful, rational dialogue, the seeds of change can be sown in any culture to do away with the inherent ferocity in it. Whatever be the case, it is difficult to deny that cultural relativism promotes an atmosphere of tolerance and amity. By eliminating the views of dogmatism surrounding one’s culture, it makes a person more grounded and open to greater acceptance by others. Further, it strengthens the intercultural relationships and builds a world based on the principles of universal brotherhood. With communities being able to understand and empathise with each other, the world certainly becomes a better place. Of course, cultural relativism like any theory is harmful at its logical extreme, but so long as it is caveated with a spirit of earnest dialogue, critique, and individual respect, it works as a theory that makes a better world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">And the Academy Award goes to…Mexico?</title>
      <link href="/Academy-Award-Mexico" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="And the Academy Award goes to…Mexico?" />
      <published>2019-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Academy-Award-Mexico</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Academy-Award-Mexico">&lt;p&gt;I love the Oscars. I acknowledge this without a hint of shame and I’m more than happy to admit it. With the television ratings slumping to 26.6 million in 2018 (a 39% decrease from 2014), and remaining below 30 million for this year’s broadcast, it’s safe to say that I am part of a rare breed – a young person still interested in the Academy Awards. However, the caveat is that I watch the show ‘almost completely ironically’. Every year for the past four years, myself and another film buff nit-pick the entirety of the marathon show. We do have a few reasons for it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, to make the near 240-minute programme bearable, you have to do something a bit more exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, if you think that the Academy Awards are merely a ‘celebration of cinematic excellence’, then you are truly mistaken. There are many different film festivals and ceremonies that take place during the awards season, and there is definitely a debate to be had over which is the most prestigious or important. Whether the Oscars will admit it or not, they feast on the grand spectacle as much as, or perhaps even more than, simply rewarding genuine talent. From #oscarssowhite, to &lt;em&gt;La La Land&lt;/em&gt; winning by mistake, to this year’s host debacle. It is these controversies which make people watch the Oscars. So, by critiquing it, we subconsciously embrace the farce and fanfare of the show. Thus, we make the whole experience of watching it far more enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly and finally, predicting the Oscars is an artform and each year we have just one opportunity to test our skills. I highly recommend Insider’s Youtube Video: “Are the Oscars Rigged?” if you’ve never thought about the logistics of winning Best Picture, or any Academy Award for that matter. To state the obvious, it doesn’t just simply happen on merit. There are tried and tested formulas on how the system works, with each critic or film buff having their own method of guessing the winners. As the great film critic Roger Ebert wrote in 2005:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Shhhhhh. Don’t tell a soul. Close Oscar-watchers (and Academy insiders) know that what you are about to read is true but few like to talk about these things. When it comes to picking Oscar winners, you can study the statistics of the past Oscars in search of patterns and clues, but there are certain influential paradigms that defy and transcend conventional statistical analysis.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He goes on to give a few examples, all of which are worth a read, but my favourite is definitely the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;Having a Period&lt;/strong&gt;: The showiest way to flaunt your budget (besides spending it on astronomical marquee names) is to set your movie in the past, so you can see all the departments – costumes, production design, cinematography, makeup – working hard all the time. It’s astonishing, but the only Best Picture winners in the last 20 years to be set in contemporary times (real or fantasy) were “Rain Man,” “The Silence of the Lambs,” and “American Beauty” – which are also among the few that weren’t historical biographies.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you know (or think you know) the formula, guessing all of the 24 awards is simple…or so it seems. As Ebert notes, “&lt;em&gt;count on at least one surprise, off-the-wall winner&lt;/em&gt;”, and in my experience it is not usually the obscure categories that trip you up, usually it is one of the big ones, such as Best Supporting Actor/Actress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cynic might say that by watching the Oscars, in this manner, we are just making a mockery of the Academy Awards; and, despite its over-exuberance, by ridiculing the show we are also ridiculing the pieces of art that the show is rewarding. Now, I do partially agree with this; the Oscars will, for a lot of people, always be the watermark of good cinema. Moreover, in recent years the Oscars have helped promote smaller indie films that without the Best Picture nomination or win, would never have achieved such success. Indeed, in a world where five films made over US$1 billion in 2018, the past six Best Picture Winners all grossed under US$100 million in the United States. To cite some prime examples, films such as &lt;em&gt;Birdman&lt;/em&gt; (2014) and the &lt;em&gt;Shape of Water&lt;/em&gt; (2017) would never have gotten the exposure that they did, without the Academy Awards, or more specifically, the Academy’s reputation as representing prestigious cinema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said earlier that I watch the Oscars “almost completely ironically” and it is time to address the ‘almost’ part of that statement. There is one part of the annual broadcast that I do take seriously, namely the meteoric rise of ‘New Mexican Cinema’ that surely would have gone largely unnoticed by the general public, but for the Oscars. Now, if you’re thinking, “I am an average film-goer, and I have literally no idea what New Mexican Cinema is”, that’s fine. In fact, I think this is the beauty of this movement; it has quietly infiltrated Hollywood, and apart from film buffs and industry experts, nobody was even aware it was happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I deliberately listed the examples of &lt;em&gt;Birdman&lt;/em&gt; (2014) and the &lt;em&gt;Shape of Water&lt;/em&gt; (2017) earlier, and both of these have Mexican directors: Alejandro González Iñárritu and Guillermo Del Toro, who along with Alfonso Cuarón make ‘Los Tres Amigos’, the leading lights of the second wave of this movement. Incredibly, between the three of them they have won five of the past six Academy Awards for Best Director. They have an astonishing ten Academy Awards between them and show no signs of slowing down. Yet, perhaps what is more impressive is how they have been able to blend this critical success with commercial “Hollywood” box office hits. Remember, these are the very same directors that made &lt;em&gt;Hellboy&lt;/em&gt; (2004), &lt;em&gt;Pacific Rim&lt;/em&gt; (2013), &lt;em&gt;Children of Men&lt;/em&gt; (2006), &lt;em&gt;The Revenant&lt;/em&gt; (2015) and &lt;em&gt;*Harry Potter&lt;/em&gt; and the Prisoner of Azkaban* (2004). Yet, the three have stayed true to their roots as well. They continue to make Spanish language films, with the best and most recent example being Cuarón’s &lt;em&gt;Roma&lt;/em&gt; (2018), winner of three Oscars this year and, in my opinion, robbed of Best Picture. It is available to view on Netflix, and whilst a black and white Spanish language drama about a maid for a middle-class Mexican family might not be everybody’s cup of tea, it is definitely my favourite film of the past few months and worth a watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as a Spanish and Portuguese student, foreign language films have always been more accessible to me than they might be for the average viewer. I know that subtitles can be a little unpalatable for some people, and it is usually easier to relate to something if you have shared culture or understanding. That said, despite all I may critique about the Oscars, they have actually taken note of the genuine movement of foreign cinematic talent that has hijacked the awards over the past few years. By recognising these directors, it validates the movement as a whole, bringing respect and recognition from a global audience. Films such as &lt;em&gt;Y tu Mamá También&lt;/em&gt; (2001), &lt;em&gt;El Laberinto del Fauno&lt;/em&gt; (2006) and &lt;em&gt;Amores Perros&lt;/em&gt; (2001) were all nominated for Oscars in various categories; they were just the first indication of what was to come. Moreover, it is not just directors that are receiving recognition. The cinematographer Emmanuel Lubezki won Best Achievement in Cinematography, three years running from 2013 to 2015, and actors such as Gael García Bernal (&lt;em&gt;Coco&lt;/em&gt;, 2017) and Diego Luna (&lt;em&gt;Rogue One&lt;/em&gt;, 2016) are stepping into the spotlight of Western cinema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I do make fun of the Academy, perhaps a little too much. However, I am somewhat part of the snobbery that make the Oscars what it is; I love the inside jokes, the awards scandals, the predicting of formulas. Even if I critique the ridiculous nature of it, that in and of itself just contributes to the grand annual spectacle. With all the said, what brings me back to the Academy is the small belief that it still does do what it should do; reward some of the best cinema that the world has to offer. And maybe the success of New Mexican Cinema is a sign that the Academy is getting back on track.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Daniel Harris</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I love the Oscars. I acknowledge this without a hint of shame and I’m more than happy to admit it. With the television ratings slumping to 26.6 million in 2018 (a 39% decrease from 2014), and remaining below 30 million for this year’s broadcast, it’s safe to say that I am part of a rare breed – a young person still interested in the Academy Awards. However, the caveat is that I watch the show ‘almost completely ironically’. Every year for the past four years, myself and another film buff nit-pick the entirety of the marathon show. We do have a few reasons for it:</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The ‘Bhakt’ and The Bhakti</title>
      <link href="/The-Bhakt-and-The-Bhakti" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The ‘Bhakt’ and The Bhakti" />
      <published>2019-03-21T11:01:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-21T11:01:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Bhakt-and-The-Bhakti</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Bhakt-and-The-Bhakti">&lt;p&gt;There comes a time in history when a nation as a whole needs to stop, take a
step back, reflect and re-examine its assumptions and perceptions about
language. We forget the value that words hold. It doesn’t cross our minds when
they are too cheap to type, tweet, post, and share. We quite wilfully forget the
degree of social investment that was poured into empowering the different
factions and sections of the world population with literacy, technology, and
vast infrastructure. Was it endowed upon us so that we could hurl abuses at each
other using these mediums or platforms of communication?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent times, the public discourse in India has witnessed one of the greatest
concepts of our civilisation turn into a meaningless word, an insult, even.
However, the context in which this has happened has been within a debate about
‘civility’ on the internet. Quite ironic as one might say. Yet it has failed to
realise how easily it has turned something as sacred and pious an idea as
‘bhakti’ into a currency of political, electoral and communal invective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complete ease with which the word ‘bhakt’ (devotee) is being hurled around,
like a derogatory term, an abuse, should be seen as a warning by us. It depicts
the extent to which our imagination, our thought process, has been colonised. It
portrays how distant we’ve become from our deeply spiritual, life-affirming and
non-violent sensibilities. After all, &lt;em&gt;‘bhakti’&lt;/em&gt;(devotion) is not just some
‘trait’ of Indian culture that needs to be protected and fought over like some
religious symbol that might offend some group or the other. It goes beyond that.
It is way deeper than that. It is at the very core of what it means to be human,
and what it means to live and not just exist. Bhakti means to live for love in
the face of formidable political, economic and social challenges. Only when we
acknowledge the widespread existence of its opposite, the value of ‘bhakti’ will
be understood. The opposite is lovelessness. This is a monster. If you are
privileged enough to not have encountered it yet, thank your stars. Even if you
have not experienced it personally, it does exist in this brutal, so-called
‘modern’ chaotic world where violence penetrates every sphere of society and
spares none.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue, of course, lies in the fact that too often we perceive lovelessness
as a personal problem. But we forget that it is also a systemic social and
cultural failure. We need to ask ourselves: if at all today’s media environment
with its enormous miasma of stories, images, and words, teaches us to cultivate
love, whether human, non-human, divine, call it what you will. Sadly, it does
not. What the media and the educational system mostly has to offer primarily
centres around being efficient (or inefficient). These platforms are formed on
the basis of the principle of lovelessness by managers, professors, narcissists
and consumers―mutually adjusting self-interests, nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet, in this land, in this great civilisation called India, there still is a
better way to live. And this, the people have been doing, for several centuries
now, against the greatest odds. India’s religiosity, its culture of ‘bhakti’ has
been fighting a relentless battle for the idea of love in ways that the scholars
of today can barely even decipher, let alone understand. After all, what do you
do when the facade of emptiness stares you down coldly, almost like a rapacious
army circling your house or a tyrannical boss stabbing out your sense of worth?
You pray. What do you do, but sing your soul out to the different manifestations
of the divine, to Lord Rama, to Jesus, to Allah or whoever it is who you think
is listening to your faint whispers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of this sense of desperation, this feeling of
urgency, this flight from a disastrous world beyond our control to a moment of
agency when we can say, I will still see You, I will still feel love, and I will
be okay. When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of the voice of my Guru, and the
philosophy of Mahatma Gandhi—who through the “love force” of peaceful agitation
reversed centuries of colonisation. When I think of bhakti, I think of the
profound truth hidden in the anonymity of these words, which for a moment make a
friendship between you and me that for a gives us the hope that language in its
decency and communion, in its &lt;em&gt;bhaava&lt;/em&gt; (emotion), will one day become something
more real and meaningful than any of our policies, and manifestos, and op-eds
can ever be. The late modern world with its refined, idealistic and now
contorted words like pluralism and secularism can only pitter-patter around the
idea of ‘bhakti’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bhakti is a very precious word, it simply &lt;strong&gt;CANNOT&lt;/strong&gt; be denigrated. Far from
mocking bhakti, what we really ought to be cultivating now, here in the
wilderness of the digital spaces in which we live and seethe, is a little more
bhakti in practice too; perhaps a sense of bhakti towards language itself. After
all, just a few generations ago our elders learned to write with a finger
tracing imperishable symbols into hot sand. Would they have found it so easy to
trivialise language itself the way we do today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Censoring words and ideas is a meaningless solution. However, thinking of this
differently, resolving to grow in understanding, kindness, and love–through
language–is the way civilisation can restore itself in its wild new frontiers
too. I really hope therefore that all those in India who think ‘bhakt’ is some
primitive mindset or an insult will seriously rethink their assumptions. You
need to take it as a surrender of what you might feel is a principled resistance
against a political figure or his boisterous fans. You need to do better with
your criticism, and perhaps yourself.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There comes a time in history when a nation as a whole needs to stop, take a step back, reflect and re-examine its assumptions and perceptions about language. We forget the value that words hold. It doesn’t cross our minds when they are too cheap to type, tweet, post, and share. We quite wilfully forget the degree of social investment that was poured into empowering the different factions and sections of the world population with literacy, technology, and vast infrastructure. Was it endowed upon us so that we could hurl abuses at each other using these mediums or platforms of communication? In recent times, the public discourse in India has witnessed one of the greatest concepts of our civilisation turn into a meaningless word, an insult, even. However, the context in which this has happened has been within a debate about ‘civility’ on the internet. Quite ironic as one might say. Yet it has failed to realise how easily it has turned something as sacred and pious an idea as ‘bhakti’ into a currency of political, electoral and communal invective. The complete ease with which the word ‘bhakt’ (devotee) is being hurled around, like a derogatory term, an abuse, should be seen as a warning by us. It depicts the extent to which our imagination, our thought process, has been colonised. It portrays how distant we’ve become from our deeply spiritual, life-affirming and non-violent sensibilities. After all, ‘bhakti’(devotion) is not just some ‘trait’ of Indian culture that needs to be protected and fought over like some religious symbol that might offend some group or the other. It goes beyond that. It is way deeper than that. It is at the very core of what it means to be human, and what it means to live and not just exist. Bhakti means to live for love in the face of formidable political, economic and social challenges. Only when we acknowledge the widespread existence of its opposite, the value of ‘bhakti’ will be understood. The opposite is lovelessness. This is a monster. If you are privileged enough to not have encountered it yet, thank your stars. Even if you have not experienced it personally, it does exist in this brutal, so-called ‘modern’ chaotic world where violence penetrates every sphere of society and spares none. The issue, of course, lies in the fact that too often we perceive lovelessness as a personal problem. But we forget that it is also a systemic social and cultural failure. We need to ask ourselves: if at all today’s media environment with its enormous miasma of stories, images, and words, teaches us to cultivate love, whether human, non-human, divine, call it what you will. Sadly, it does not. What the media and the educational system mostly has to offer primarily centres around being efficient (or inefficient). These platforms are formed on the basis of the principle of lovelessness by managers, professors, narcissists and consumers―mutually adjusting self-interests, nothing more. And yet, in this land, in this great civilisation called India, there still is a better way to live. And this, the people have been doing, for several centuries now, against the greatest odds. India’s religiosity, its culture of ‘bhakti’ has been fighting a relentless battle for the idea of love in ways that the scholars of today can barely even decipher, let alone understand. After all, what do you do when the facade of emptiness stares you down coldly, almost like a rapacious army circling your house or a tyrannical boss stabbing out your sense of worth? You pray. What do you do, but sing your soul out to the different manifestations of the divine, to Lord Rama, to Jesus, to Allah or whoever it is who you think is listening to your faint whispers? When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of this sense of desperation, this feeling of urgency, this flight from a disastrous world beyond our control to a moment of agency when we can say, I will still see You, I will still feel love, and I will be okay. When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of the voice of my Guru, and the philosophy of Mahatma Gandhi—who through the “love force” of peaceful agitation reversed centuries of colonisation. When I think of bhakti, I think of the profound truth hidden in the anonymity of these words, which for a moment make a friendship between you and me that for a gives us the hope that language in its decency and communion, in its bhaava (emotion), will one day become something more real and meaningful than any of our policies, and manifestos, and op-eds can ever be. The late modern world with its refined, idealistic and now contorted words like pluralism and secularism can only pitter-patter around the idea of ‘bhakti’. Bhakti is a very precious word, it simply CANNOT be denigrated. Far from mocking bhakti, what we really ought to be cultivating now, here in the wilderness of the digital spaces in which we live and seethe, is a little more bhakti in practice too; perhaps a sense of bhakti towards language itself. After all, just a few generations ago our elders learned to write with a finger tracing imperishable symbols into hot sand. Would they have found it so easy to trivialise language itself the way we do today? Censoring words and ideas is a meaningless solution. However, thinking of this differently, resolving to grow in understanding, kindness, and love–through language–is the way civilisation can restore itself in its wild new frontiers too. I really hope therefore that all those in India who think ‘bhakt’ is some primitive mindset or an insult will seriously rethink their assumptions. You need to take it as a surrender of what you might feel is a principled resistance against a political figure or his boisterous fans. You need to do better with your criticism, and perhaps yourself.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Picture of Dorian Gray – Final Thoughts from the Composer’s Desk</title>
      <link href="/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray-2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Picture of Dorian Gray – Final Thoughts from the Composer’s Desk" />
      <published>2019-03-07T03:30:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-07T03:30:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray-2</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray-2">&lt;p&gt;It strikes me that whenever I announced to people that I had set about writing
an opera, I never actually received that reaction I expected. I was certain I’d
be met with derision – “What makes you think YOU can write one, Bowes?” Up to
the point that I began working on &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt;, I had only really written choral
music and a few songs. My only forays into purely instrumental music consisted
of a piano quintet I concocted for my A-level coursework, an arrangement of a
school song (&lt;em&gt;Bedford by the River&lt;/em&gt; – won a cash prize for it, to be fair), and
a frankly ridiculous setting of the &lt;em&gt;Requiem Mass&lt;/em&gt;, which I hope will never be
performed in its current state. Yet, the reaction, especially when I told
everyone of the subject-matter of this opera, Wilde’s seminal novella &lt;em&gt;The
Picture of Dorian Gray&lt;/em&gt;, was unanimously positive. A few more knowledgeable
friends asked whether it had been done before, to which I ask: how many versions
of &lt;em&gt;Faust&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Romeo and Juliet&lt;/em&gt; are there? Answer: frankly too many, not that I
wouldn’t consider doing a &lt;em&gt;Faust&lt;/em&gt;-related one at some point – indeed, one can
see &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt; itself as a Faustian tale. Nevertheless, the reception to the idea
was that I ought to push on, and so I did. Thus, I have reached the end of the
compositional process (barring edits after the fact) and I have more than enough
time to sit and worry about the show. Which I do – all too often, in fact. And
which also led me to write this pair of articles for &lt;em&gt;The Pangean&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray&quot;&gt;last
article&lt;/a&gt;, I had reflected on
the music of the first Act, but I came to realize after its publication that I
had failed to actually discuss compositional process, which I suppose is far
more interesting than simply taking you, arm-in-arm, on a promenade through what
you will, in just a matter of months, be able to hear for yourself. Therefore,
while I will still move chronologically through the final Act, wouldn’t you
rather hear about how I did the composing, rather than what composing I did?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all honesty, I have not been composing for long enough to have entirely
unified a process. Different pieces require different things from me. Some
pieces can go from just the little scribblings in a notebook straight into my
computer, where I will transform them from the idea into an actual functioning
piece. Others, such as the song-cycle I am currently working on, &lt;em&gt;Crow&lt;/em&gt;, needed
to be mapped out in full-score on paper first, and in ink – it felt particularly
necessary for &lt;em&gt;Crow&lt;/em&gt;, as it lent a sparseness to the writing that was very
helpful (although, I must say that it has been an absolute b*tch to write up on
my computer.) These are the two ends of a sliding scale upon which &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt; sat
somewhere in the middle. Or, in fact, off of either end. Some scenes, such as
the theatre scene in Act One went straight from my brain into the computer, as
the nature of the scurrying accompaniment made it a real bore to hand-write,
without the joy of copy-and-paste and editing after the fact. Others, such as
the entire last scene, were almost entirely drafted on paper first and then
written up – although I admit that at least part of the reason for hand-writing
the entire last scene was that my laptop was on the blink and I was 3,000 miles
from home. But, it keeps the romantic notion of the composer scribbling away
with pen and ink alive, so I’ve got to keep up appearances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so we come to the last Act. Although much of this was drafted last, the
prelude to the first scene was, in fact, finished long before most of Act One,
as it gave me, frankly, a nice compositional break from the Prologue. My
librettist Jamie and I had to come up with some way to symbolise several years
of debauchery that the audience missed by swanning out for their interval drinks
in the bar. I assume that the debauched years will be lived through in the minds
of our performers during this interval; it would be nicely ‘method’ of them. But
how to illustrate it in music? I gave the audience a brief, slow moment in which
to mourn Basil and Sybil, both brutally killed at the end of the first Act,
before setting about the musical debauchery. Decadence and wild abandon are
often achieved in music through the use of rowdy dances. Ravel was a master of
this, especially in the finale of &lt;em&gt;La Valse&lt;/em&gt;, or consider Stravinsky’s &lt;em&gt;Rite of
Spring&lt;/em&gt; – the poor girl dances herself to death at the end. But, as those of you
who know me can testify, I am no dancer. So how should I go after the same
effects? It’s actually fairly obvious: the thing that makes a dance a dance is
the rhythm, with which I have very little issue (getting the legs to do what
they’re told on the other hand…). Therefore, I took one of the rhythmic motifs
that described the den of iniquity that was the theatre in Act One, and laid it
underneath a pulsating Yoruba-inspired cross-rhythm from a pair of drums to
create a heady mix of open fifths and driving rhythms that symbolises Dorian’s
embracing of Harry’s lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the segue into the first scene, which itself takes place in an opium
den, takes its influences from Debussy’s use of the quartal harmony to lend an
air of intentionally fake orientalism, with added xylophonic twinkling. This is
undercut by the following chorus ‘number’ – Dorian, his mind full of a romantic
poems, hallucinates that the other patrons of this establishment all begin
singing, in French, about the beauty of Venice, at odds with both the Chinese-y
music of the den, as well as with the general dinginess of London at the end of
the 19th century. And, as a unifying feature of this scene, the music is still
Debussy-inspired. With a French poem, especially by a poet such as Théophile
Gautier, one can’t not look to Debussy, I feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Sur une gamme chromatique, &lt;br /&gt;

Le sein de perles ruisselant, &lt;br /&gt;

La Vénus de l’Adriatique, &lt;br /&gt;

Sort de l’eau son corps rose et blanc.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remainder of the first scene is dominated by the one appearance of Sybil’s
brother James, who rages like a bull in a china-shop while attempting to pursue
Dorian. His aria was one for which I did the most planning – James had to be
able to arrive on the scene and make enough of an impact to make him feel like a
threat for the remainder of the show, despite not having been seen in the
previous acts. Thus, he demanded a full-on show-stopper of an aria. What makes
music sound angry? It’s much the same as that which makes music sound debauched,
as both violent anger and wild abandon stray from the comfortable emotional
spectrum. Thus, I focused on rhythm again. I wrote out his words, some of the
most violent I have read in Wilde, and began to speak them to myself over and
over again. Individual lines became something of a rapid chant, savagely
thumping away, until I was able to write down specific rhythms I had associated
with them. The aria became very caballetic, with compound rhythms driving
underneath the singer’s howling. And then I worked out the melody. It’s not
greatly complicated, just arpeggiating through the chords underneath. Far more
important is the tessitura: James was, in my head, a Bass, albeit one with a
very solid top range, and this aria is one that exploits it, as I push the
singer to the upper extreme, bellowing away in righteous fury, while the
orchestra churns away tempestuously around him, until he disappears into the
night to hunt his sister’s ‘killer’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second scene, the last scene to be written, and not appearing in the
novella, we return to Lord Henry’s house. Yet the house has a much darker aspect
than when we had seen it in the first Act. For one thing, it is about three in
the morning. But, more importantly, Henry’s wife has made a decision that will
cast a pall on the man for the rest of the show. To give a sense of this
foreboding, I searched back through her brief appearance in Act One for melodies
associated with Lady Victoria, finally picking the languorous downwardly
meandering tune she uses to describe her enjoyment of pianists to manipulate
into a mournful prelude to the scene, descending through the strings in a canon,
before a quote from Tchaikovsky’s &lt;em&gt;Eugene Onegin&lt;/em&gt; foreshadows the fateful letter
that she has written for Harry. Harry’s music, on the other hand, is much
brighter and jolly – he’s drunk, and he sings in a drunkenly twisted patter,
while Victoria drums up the courage to tell him she is leaving. When she finally
pours forth all her upset, we move from twisted patter into a driving
baroque-esque raging, reminiscent of Handel’s more overtly furious moments, most
particularly Dejanira’s aria, &lt;em&gt;Where Shall I Fly&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;Hercules,&lt;/em&gt; in which the
overwrought Dejanira is driven mad by guilt, having caused the death of her
god-like husband. But, for me, there was a deeper meaning behind the baroque
façade that I had Victoria put up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jamie and I discussed this scene at great length, deliberating over how to stop
Victoria from seeming like a shrewish, nagging wife, and more like the bright,
free woman she ought to be. Neither of us understand women (or, in my case,
people in general) as well as we’d like to think, I suspect, but I truly believe
we have drawn here a very human event: Victoria pretends, in her baroque raging,
that her divorce is for all sorts of moral and societal reasons, citing Harry’s
insalubrious behaviour as more than enough reason for her to leave him. Yet, she
ultimately confesses that this is a pretence. She married him because that
behaviour, fuelled as it was by his Byronic intelligence, was highly attractive.
However, he has now ceased being Byronic, and is simply being indulgent and
destructive whilst ignoring her as a wife. All the romance has gone from his
behaviour. It’s a far more interesting character that Jamie has drawn through
this dichotomy than what could have been there: a shrew reprimanding a wastrel
for his wastefulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We finally return to Dorian, still suffering shock from his encounter with James
Vane, on retreat in the country. We find him alone in the grounds of the Duchess
of Monmouth’s house, musing on the events of the previous few days. For this
scene, we took full advantage of the non-linear storytelling we had introduced
with the appearance of Sybil at the end of Act One. There is, in Wilde’s
original, a scintillating scene of witty repartee between Harry and several
other pillars of society after a dinner hosted by the Duchess. However, in
streamlining the show, we feared we would lose this in order to focus more
clearly on Dorian himself. That is, we feared until one of us realised we could
just do another pseudo-flashback, as Dorian recalls the events of the previous
evening. Therefore, we have another moment of lighthearted patter from Harry,
who is joined by the chorus – I felt I was channelling all of my love for &lt;em&gt;Die
Fledermaus&lt;/em&gt; or even the great Victorian partnership of Gilbert and Sullivan,
trying to create some feeling of effervescence in the midst of the terror that
is consuming Dorian here. This continues into the next big chorus moment, after
the flashback, when these society lords and ladies enter the field in which
Dorian has been sitting in order to go shooting, singing words by Rudyard
Kipling, from his &lt;em&gt;Verses on Games&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Peace upon Earth, Goodwill to men” &lt;br /&gt;

So greet we Christmas Day! &lt;br /&gt;

Oh, Christian, load your gun and then &lt;br /&gt;

Oh, Christian, out and slay.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This joyful entrance is set to a reharmonisation of Sullivan’s tune Noel, known
to most of us as &lt;em&gt;It Came Upon A Midnight Clear.&lt;/em&gt; At the same time, something of
RVW’s &lt;em&gt;Antiphon&lt;/em&gt; or Bruckner’s &lt;em&gt;Te Deum&lt;/em&gt; was never far from my mind, in terms of
the orchestration. It may have become obvious to you that I am always thinking
of other things to relate my music to. It is a problem I run into occasionally –
am I being influenced, which is fine: music does not exist in a vacuum; or am I
simply copying? Quoting things is fine, especially in such a long work as this
(there are many quotes in &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt;, most of which I have not pointed out, but
all of which make me irrationally, self-indulgently happy), but copying is not
just plagiaristic but, personally, pointless – even if my original thought, at
the inception of this opera, was that “I wish Britten had written a Dorian
Gray.” Hopefully, my style has become distinct enough from just “a kid copying
Britten”. Hopefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving on, there is so much to point to in the final scene. Therefore, I will
keep my comments limited to two particular moments. In this last scene, we see
Dorian and Harry finally alone in Dorian’s living room. Dorian is by now
incredibly stressed – Vane hunted him all the way to the Duchess’ estate, and,
in trying to creep up on him, was shot by one of the Lords on their morning
shoot – which Dorian took as a terribly ill omen. Returning to London, Harry has
been keeping tabs on his young protégé, making sure the fear and stress doesn’t
get to him. Therefore, he ups the levels of inane babble. The treatment of his
final moment of inane babble is possibly one of my favourite bits of composition
I’ve done to date. I say my composition, but actually, Harry’s last aria is
founded entirely upon a piece by Alexander Scriabin, who, although I mention him
very infrequently, is one of my favourite composers, if only for his absolutely
insane theories about the end of the world (and attempts to bring said end
about) and his pretence at having synaesthesia, which he tried to use to create
a light-organ or ‘&lt;em&gt;clavier à lumières&lt;/em&gt;’ with which to compose for the
colour-spectrum―which is, I think you’ll agree, fairly bonkers. Nevertheless, I
got it into my head to use this moment at the end of the piece to highlight
musically a big change in Dorian: before we meet Dorian in the Prologue, we hear
him from offstage, playing a snippet from Schumann’s &lt;em&gt;Waldszenen&lt;/em&gt;, a very calm,
nature-themed work for the piano – a piece of innocence, if you will. But now,
at the end of the evening, many years later for the two remaining characters,
Dorian returns to the piano to ignore Harry’s inanities, and plays Scriabin’s
&lt;em&gt;Nocturne&lt;/em&gt; for the left hand. This highlights a change in Dorian in several
ways. Firstly, it is significantly more technically and harmonically challenging
than the Schumann, in part because it is specifically for the left hand, but
also because of Scriabin’s tense, dense harmonic language, which is
significantly more discordant and much less innocent than Schumann’s. Moreover,
Schumann published &lt;em&gt;Waldszenen&lt;/em&gt; in 1849, whereas the &lt;em&gt;Nocturne&lt;/em&gt; was composed in
1894; there is nearly half a century of musical development, pushing the
boundaries of tonality and taste, between the two, indicative of the passage of
time within the show, perhaps, and certainly indicative again of the corruption
of Dorian’s innocence over that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we come to the grand collapse that is the ending. I shan’t spoil the
last few pages by discussing exactly how the show closes, because that would
undoubtedly be a travesty. What I would like to discuss is the allegorical use
of the story of &lt;em&gt;Belshazzar&lt;/em&gt; in the closing moments. In my first plan of the
end, I had refused the idea of an off-stage chorus as too ‘operatic’ for an
intimate close to this show, much too close to the end of &lt;em&gt;Don Giovanni&lt;/em&gt; or the
countless other shows that copied that dramatic close, with the lecher dragged
into hell by an immaterial chorus. However, one chat with Jamie transformed my
conception entirely: I was not overly keen on my first draft’s ending, and he
wrote some new words to close the show – they were splendid. In a tangent to
Dorian’s flashback or his vision of Sybil, Jamie brought up an off-stage chorus,
symbolic perhaps of Dorian’s frantic brain or of heavenly judgement (I’m
inclined to think one particular way, but others may disagree), singing the
&lt;em&gt;“writing on the wall”&lt;/em&gt; that appeared at &lt;em&gt;Belshazzar’s Feast&lt;/em&gt;: “&lt;em&gt;Mene Mene Tekel
Upharsin&lt;/em&gt;” or, as Jamie put it, “&lt;em&gt;Thou art in the balances, and art found
wanting.&lt;/em&gt;” Dorian, in his desperate bid to redeem himself after his years of
immorality, cannot help but hear these words, directly paralleling the
condemnation that is his own portrait hanging upon the wall. Thus, in
composition, I had to avoid not just the links to Don Giovanni but also to
Walton’s own &lt;em&gt;Belshazzar’s Feast&lt;/em&gt;, again a favourite work of mine. Fortunately,
context saved me here, as the chorus slowly makes itself known, crescendoing slowly to become just about audible on-stage, before making a final fortissimo
statement and leaving Dorian to contemplate his fate – with little over a minute
left of the opera.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Olly Bowes</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It strikes me that whenever I announced to people that I had set about writing an opera, I never actually received that reaction I expected. I was certain I’d be met with derision – “What makes you think YOU can write one, Bowes?” Up to the point that I began working on Dorian, I had only really written choral music and a few songs. My only forays into purely instrumental music consisted of a piano quintet I concocted for my A-level coursework, an arrangement of a school song (Bedford by the River – won a cash prize for it, to be fair), and a frankly ridiculous setting of the Requiem Mass, which I hope will never be performed in its current state. Yet, the reaction, especially when I told everyone of the subject-matter of this opera, Wilde’s seminal novella The Picture of Dorian Gray, was unanimously positive. A few more knowledgeable friends asked whether it had been done before, to which I ask: how many versions of Faust or Romeo and Juliet are there? Answer: frankly too many, not that I wouldn’t consider doing a Faust-related one at some point – indeed, one can see Dorian itself as a Faustian tale. Nevertheless, the reception to the idea was that I ought to push on, and so I did. Thus, I have reached the end of the compositional process (barring edits after the fact) and I have more than enough time to sit and worry about the show. Which I do – all too often, in fact. And which also led me to write this pair of articles for The Pangean. At the end of my last article, I had reflected on the music of the first Act, but I came to realize after its publication that I had failed to actually discuss compositional process, which I suppose is far more interesting than simply taking you, arm-in-arm, on a promenade through what you will, in just a matter of months, be able to hear for yourself. Therefore, while I will still move chronologically through the final Act, wouldn’t you rather hear about how I did the composing, rather than what composing I did? In all honesty, I have not been composing for long enough to have entirely unified a process. Different pieces require different things from me. Some pieces can go from just the little scribblings in a notebook straight into my computer, where I will transform them from the idea into an actual functioning piece. Others, such as the song-cycle I am currently working on, Crow, needed to be mapped out in full-score on paper first, and in ink – it felt particularly necessary for Crow, as it lent a sparseness to the writing that was very helpful (although, I must say that it has been an absolute b*tch to write up on my computer.) These are the two ends of a sliding scale upon which Dorian sat somewhere in the middle. Or, in fact, off of either end. Some scenes, such as the theatre scene in Act One went straight from my brain into the computer, as the nature of the scurrying accompaniment made it a real bore to hand-write, without the joy of copy-and-paste and editing after the fact. Others, such as the entire last scene, were almost entirely drafted on paper first and then written up – although I admit that at least part of the reason for hand-writing the entire last scene was that my laptop was on the blink and I was 3,000 miles from home. But, it keeps the romantic notion of the composer scribbling away with pen and ink alive, so I’ve got to keep up appearances. And so we come to the last Act. Although much of this was drafted last, the prelude to the first scene was, in fact, finished long before most of Act One, as it gave me, frankly, a nice compositional break from the Prologue. My librettist Jamie and I had to come up with some way to symbolise several years of debauchery that the audience missed by swanning out for their interval drinks in the bar. I assume that the debauched years will be lived through in the minds of our performers during this interval; it would be nicely ‘method’ of them. But how to illustrate it in music? I gave the audience a brief, slow moment in which to mourn Basil and Sybil, both brutally killed at the end of the first Act, before setting about the musical debauchery. Decadence and wild abandon are often achieved in music through the use of rowdy dances. Ravel was a master of this, especially in the finale of La Valse, or consider Stravinsky’s Rite of Spring – the poor girl dances herself to death at the end. But, as those of you who know me can testify, I am no dancer. So how should I go after the same effects? It’s actually fairly obvious: the thing that makes a dance a dance is the rhythm, with which I have very little issue (getting the legs to do what they’re told on the other hand…). Therefore, I took one of the rhythmic motifs that described the den of iniquity that was the theatre in Act One, and laid it underneath a pulsating Yoruba-inspired cross-rhythm from a pair of drums to create a heady mix of open fifths and driving rhythms that symbolises Dorian’s embracing of Harry’s lessons. Similarly, the segue into the first scene, which itself takes place in an opium den, takes its influences from Debussy’s use of the quartal harmony to lend an air of intentionally fake orientalism, with added xylophonic twinkling. This is undercut by the following chorus ‘number’ – Dorian, his mind full of a romantic poems, hallucinates that the other patrons of this establishment all begin singing, in French, about the beauty of Venice, at odds with both the Chinese-y music of the den, as well as with the general dinginess of London at the end of the 19th century. And, as a unifying feature of this scene, the music is still Debussy-inspired. With a French poem, especially by a poet such as Théophile Gautier, one can’t not look to Debussy, I feel. “Sur une gamme chromatique, Le sein de perles ruisselant, La Vénus de l’Adriatique, Sort de l’eau son corps rose et blanc.” The remainder of the first scene is dominated by the one appearance of Sybil’s brother James, who rages like a bull in a china-shop while attempting to pursue Dorian. His aria was one for which I did the most planning – James had to be able to arrive on the scene and make enough of an impact to make him feel like a threat for the remainder of the show, despite not having been seen in the previous acts. Thus, he demanded a full-on show-stopper of an aria. What makes music sound angry? It’s much the same as that which makes music sound debauched, as both violent anger and wild abandon stray from the comfortable emotional spectrum. Thus, I focused on rhythm again. I wrote out his words, some of the most violent I have read in Wilde, and began to speak them to myself over and over again. Individual lines became something of a rapid chant, savagely thumping away, until I was able to write down specific rhythms I had associated with them. The aria became very caballetic, with compound rhythms driving underneath the singer’s howling. And then I worked out the melody. It’s not greatly complicated, just arpeggiating through the chords underneath. Far more important is the tessitura: James was, in my head, a Bass, albeit one with a very solid top range, and this aria is one that exploits it, as I push the singer to the upper extreme, bellowing away in righteous fury, while the orchestra churns away tempestuously around him, until he disappears into the night to hunt his sister’s ‘killer’. In the second scene, the last scene to be written, and not appearing in the novella, we return to Lord Henry’s house. Yet the house has a much darker aspect than when we had seen it in the first Act. For one thing, it is about three in the morning. But, more importantly, Henry’s wife has made a decision that will cast a pall on the man for the rest of the show. To give a sense of this foreboding, I searched back through her brief appearance in Act One for melodies associated with Lady Victoria, finally picking the languorous downwardly meandering tune she uses to describe her enjoyment of pianists to manipulate into a mournful prelude to the scene, descending through the strings in a canon, before a quote from Tchaikovsky’s Eugene Onegin foreshadows the fateful letter that she has written for Harry. Harry’s music, on the other hand, is much brighter and jolly – he’s drunk, and he sings in a drunkenly twisted patter, while Victoria drums up the courage to tell him she is leaving. When she finally pours forth all her upset, we move from twisted patter into a driving baroque-esque raging, reminiscent of Handel’s more overtly furious moments, most particularly Dejanira’s aria, Where Shall I Fly from Hercules, in which the overwrought Dejanira is driven mad by guilt, having caused the death of her god-like husband. But, for me, there was a deeper meaning behind the baroque façade that I had Victoria put up. Jamie and I discussed this scene at great length, deliberating over how to stop Victoria from seeming like a shrewish, nagging wife, and more like the bright, free woman she ought to be. Neither of us understand women (or, in my case, people in general) as well as we’d like to think, I suspect, but I truly believe we have drawn here a very human event: Victoria pretends, in her baroque raging, that her divorce is for all sorts of moral and societal reasons, citing Harry’s insalubrious behaviour as more than enough reason for her to leave him. Yet, she ultimately confesses that this is a pretence. She married him because that behaviour, fuelled as it was by his Byronic intelligence, was highly attractive. However, he has now ceased being Byronic, and is simply being indulgent and destructive whilst ignoring her as a wife. All the romance has gone from his behaviour. It’s a far more interesting character that Jamie has drawn through this dichotomy than what could have been there: a shrew reprimanding a wastrel for his wastefulness. We finally return to Dorian, still suffering shock from his encounter with James Vane, on retreat in the country. We find him alone in the grounds of the Duchess of Monmouth’s house, musing on the events of the previous few days. For this scene, we took full advantage of the non-linear storytelling we had introduced with the appearance of Sybil at the end of Act One. There is, in Wilde’s original, a scintillating scene of witty repartee between Harry and several other pillars of society after a dinner hosted by the Duchess. However, in streamlining the show, we feared we would lose this in order to focus more clearly on Dorian himself. That is, we feared until one of us realised we could just do another pseudo-flashback, as Dorian recalls the events of the previous evening. Therefore, we have another moment of lighthearted patter from Harry, who is joined by the chorus – I felt I was channelling all of my love for Die Fledermaus or even the great Victorian partnership of Gilbert and Sullivan, trying to create some feeling of effervescence in the midst of the terror that is consuming Dorian here. This continues into the next big chorus moment, after the flashback, when these society lords and ladies enter the field in which Dorian has been sitting in order to go shooting, singing words by Rudyard Kipling, from his Verses on Games: “Peace upon Earth, Goodwill to men” So greet we Christmas Day! Oh, Christian, load your gun and then Oh, Christian, out and slay.” This joyful entrance is set to a reharmonisation of Sullivan’s tune Noel, known to most of us as It Came Upon A Midnight Clear. At the same time, something of RVW’s Antiphon or Bruckner’s Te Deum was never far from my mind, in terms of the orchestration. It may have become obvious to you that I am always thinking of other things to relate my music to. It is a problem I run into occasionally – am I being influenced, which is fine: music does not exist in a vacuum; or am I simply copying? Quoting things is fine, especially in such a long work as this (there are many quotes in Dorian, most of which I have not pointed out, but all of which make me irrationally, self-indulgently happy), but copying is not just plagiaristic but, personally, pointless – even if my original thought, at the inception of this opera, was that “I wish Britten had written a Dorian Gray.” Hopefully, my style has become distinct enough from just “a kid copying Britten”. Hopefully. Moving on, there is so much to point to in the final scene. Therefore, I will keep my comments limited to two particular moments. In this last scene, we see Dorian and Harry finally alone in Dorian’s living room. Dorian is by now incredibly stressed – Vane hunted him all the way to the Duchess’ estate, and, in trying to creep up on him, was shot by one of the Lords on their morning shoot – which Dorian took as a terribly ill omen. Returning to London, Harry has been keeping tabs on his young protégé, making sure the fear and stress doesn’t get to him. Therefore, he ups the levels of inane babble. The treatment of his final moment of inane babble is possibly one of my favourite bits of composition I’ve done to date. I say my composition, but actually, Harry’s last aria is founded entirely upon a piece by Alexander Scriabin, who, although I mention him very infrequently, is one of my favourite composers, if only for his absolutely insane theories about the end of the world (and attempts to bring said end about) and his pretence at having synaesthesia, which he tried to use to create a light-organ or ‘clavier à lumières’ with which to compose for the colour-spectrum―which is, I think you’ll agree, fairly bonkers. Nevertheless, I got it into my head to use this moment at the end of the piece to highlight musically a big change in Dorian: before we meet Dorian in the Prologue, we hear him from offstage, playing a snippet from Schumann’s Waldszenen, a very calm, nature-themed work for the piano – a piece of innocence, if you will. But now, at the end of the evening, many years later for the two remaining characters, Dorian returns to the piano to ignore Harry’s inanities, and plays Scriabin’s Nocturne for the left hand. This highlights a change in Dorian in several ways. Firstly, it is significantly more technically and harmonically challenging than the Schumann, in part because it is specifically for the left hand, but also because of Scriabin’s tense, dense harmonic language, which is significantly more discordant and much less innocent than Schumann’s. Moreover, Schumann published Waldszenen in 1849, whereas the Nocturne was composed in 1894; there is nearly half a century of musical development, pushing the boundaries of tonality and taste, between the two, indicative of the passage of time within the show, perhaps, and certainly indicative again of the corruption of Dorian’s innocence over that time. Finally, we come to the grand collapse that is the ending. I shan’t spoil the last few pages by discussing exactly how the show closes, because that would undoubtedly be a travesty. What I would like to discuss is the allegorical use of the story of Belshazzar in the closing moments. In my first plan of the end, I had refused the idea of an off-stage chorus as too ‘operatic’ for an intimate close to this show, much too close to the end of Don Giovanni or the countless other shows that copied that dramatic close, with the lecher dragged into hell by an immaterial chorus. However, one chat with Jamie transformed my conception entirely: I was not overly keen on my first draft’s ending, and he wrote some new words to close the show – they were splendid. In a tangent to Dorian’s flashback or his vision of Sybil, Jamie brought up an off-stage chorus, symbolic perhaps of Dorian’s frantic brain or of heavenly judgement (I’m inclined to think one particular way, but others may disagree), singing the “writing on the wall” that appeared at Belshazzar’s Feast: “Mene Mene Tekel Upharsin” or, as Jamie put it, “Thou art in the balances, and art found wanting.” Dorian, in his desperate bid to redeem himself after his years of immorality, cannot help but hear these words, directly paralleling the condemnation that is his own portrait hanging upon the wall. Thus, in composition, I had to avoid not just the links to Don Giovanni but also to Walton’s own Belshazzar’s Feast, again a favourite work of mine. Fortunately, context saved me here, as the chorus slowly makes itself known, crescendoing slowly to become just about audible on-stage, before making a final fortissimo statement and leaving Dorian to contemplate his fate – with little over a minute left of the opera.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Hard Reality of Hardcopies</title>
      <link href="/The-Hard-Reality-on-Hardcopies" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Hard Reality of Hardcopies" />
      <published>2019-03-07T03:15:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-07T03:15:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Hard-Reality-on-Hardcopies</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Hard-Reality-on-Hardcopies">&lt;p&gt;Spring, which has almost become non-existential in Calcutta, is a much revered
and coveted time of the year for any of us living in the tropical zone,
especially when it precedes a season of pig-like sweating. The breezy streets
are a delight to the souls dampened by the winter, and a walk through those
streets with an old friend hits just the right note on the Spring Symphony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An old friend and I have shared a long, uneven but all the more enjoyable
friendship over the years, and our unending love for books has still, with old,
straining strings, held our friendship. Here, I must mention, with much
gratitude, that she was the person to introduce me to the vast, unending, and
marvellous land of books, lending me the first book I ever read by Sidney
Sheldon. When I raised my reservations about the unappealing demeanour of a
book, she just asked me to read for only thirty minutes every day before sleep,
and stated that if after a week I still found it ‘uninteresting’, I could drop
it and return it to her, with her promising to never again insist that I read a
book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprise! Surprise! I finished the book within a week, returned it to her, told
her I finished it and was prized with a look of priceless shock from her. I am
not such an active reader anymore, but what occurred to me then was how
immensely romantic holding the spine of a book is; and of the many sins that our
education system and technology has caused, one is causing a holocaust on the
romance of holding a book. Needless to say, books, since then, became an
inseparable part of my regime and my birthday gifts. But I must confess, after
my first read, I was still sceptical whether this enchantment I felt was
ephemeral or actually enduring. It persisted. Even though initially, I raised
doubts about the ‘unappealing’ demeanour of a book, it was that which drove me
most to the habit of reading books: the mellow chirps of the pages, the letters
marching on the beige field, the weaving and unravelling of tales, and the
hundreds of lives coming to life on those very seemingly lifeless pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, coming back to the spring evening of breezy streets: it was an occasion of
me returning my friend her long-given books, and as we were merrily discussing
things of grave concern to us, something graver ambushed us – what is the future
of hardcopies? I have always been troubled by the growing popularity of ebooks,
but it did not hit harder than when I heard her saying that she has to do her
college’s research work from an ebook. The general argument here would be that
an ebook offers almost everything that a book does, but god forbid the day when
writers romanticise reading an ebook by the window on a rainy day in their
novels or their Instagram posts per se. Leaving aside the romantic values, how
would an ebook ever satiate the bourgeois need of the book-hoarding class? Who
do you think would be impressed by your listless list of books on your device,
instead of the piles of webbed and tattered books with missing pages and
crumpled edges? How can looking up from your well-lit Kindle be the same as a
distracted stare into the distance as Tolstoy drones on in a thick copy of &lt;em&gt;War
and Peace&lt;/em&gt;? What would be more charming, lending book by just a few taps, or
rummaging through the hundreds of dust sprinkled books, whilst being cast under
the perverse magic of nostalgia?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a not so recent finding in 2017, it was published that the United States of
America recorded a greater sale of ebooks compared to hardcopies. I became
fairly unstable after reading this and looked with greater awe than ever at my
meagre collection of whatever hardcopies I possess. I, too, am guilty of
possessing ebooks. Of course, I am not all against ebooks (this article is being
published online, after all), it does provide many the opportunity to read
things that otherwise would be inaccessible to them and it certainly is a great
aid when travelling. Although the emergence of ebooks feels like a personal
defeat to me, I concede to the importance of ebooks in times of such great
distress to nature and society. And in fear that I might be misconstrued as a
privileged brat, let me tell you, I buy books using fees earned from part-time
teaching, which most assuredly isn’t much. Yet, still, for me, books and their
essence lies in their old-school charm that keeps us turning actual pages.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrei Tarkovsky once said that artists are there because the world is not
perfect, and such imperfection is reminded to us by those hardcopies that seem
frayed and old and decaying just like our world. The ebook is too perfect a
vessel for works that are born out of imperfection. It swerves us into a path
away from nature, away from reality into a dark realm of complete machine
dominance. In the end, maybe I am simply a hopeless romantic stuck in the past
when the world is aggressively progressing into the future, but I hope my voice
of unreason reaches a few romantic hearts so that we can keep the lineage of
hardcopies from dying a most ignominious and unromantic death.  &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Spring, which has almost become non-existential in Calcutta, is a much revered and coveted time of the year for any of us living in the tropical zone, especially when it precedes a season of pig-like sweating. The breezy streets are a delight to the souls dampened by the winter, and a walk through those streets with an old friend hits just the right note on the Spring Symphony. An old friend and I have shared a long, uneven but all the more enjoyable friendship over the years, and our unending love for books has still, with old, straining strings, held our friendship. Here, I must mention, with much gratitude, that she was the person to introduce me to the vast, unending, and marvellous land of books, lending me the first book I ever read by Sidney Sheldon. When I raised my reservations about the unappealing demeanour of a book, she just asked me to read for only thirty minutes every day before sleep, and stated that if after a week I still found it ‘uninteresting’, I could drop it and return it to her, with her promising to never again insist that I read a book. Surprise! Surprise! I finished the book within a week, returned it to her, told her I finished it and was prized with a look of priceless shock from her. I am not such an active reader anymore, but what occurred to me then was how immensely romantic holding the spine of a book is; and of the many sins that our education system and technology has caused, one is causing a holocaust on the romance of holding a book. Needless to say, books, since then, became an inseparable part of my regime and my birthday gifts. But I must confess, after my first read, I was still sceptical whether this enchantment I felt was ephemeral or actually enduring. It persisted. Even though initially, I raised doubts about the ‘unappealing’ demeanour of a book, it was that which drove me most to the habit of reading books: the mellow chirps of the pages, the letters marching on the beige field, the weaving and unravelling of tales, and the hundreds of lives coming to life on those very seemingly lifeless pages. Now, coming back to the spring evening of breezy streets: it was an occasion of me returning my friend her long-given books, and as we were merrily discussing things of grave concern to us, something graver ambushed us – what is the future of hardcopies? I have always been troubled by the growing popularity of ebooks, but it did not hit harder than when I heard her saying that she has to do her college’s research work from an ebook. The general argument here would be that an ebook offers almost everything that a book does, but god forbid the day when writers romanticise reading an ebook by the window on a rainy day in their novels or their Instagram posts per se. Leaving aside the romantic values, how would an ebook ever satiate the bourgeois need of the book-hoarding class? Who do you think would be impressed by your listless list of books on your device, instead of the piles of webbed and tattered books with missing pages and crumpled edges? How can looking up from your well-lit Kindle be the same as a distracted stare into the distance as Tolstoy drones on in a thick copy of War and Peace? What would be more charming, lending book by just a few taps, or rummaging through the hundreds of dust sprinkled books, whilst being cast under the perverse magic of nostalgia? In a not so recent finding in 2017, it was published that the United States of America recorded a greater sale of ebooks compared to hardcopies. I became fairly unstable after reading this and looked with greater awe than ever at my meagre collection of whatever hardcopies I possess. I, too, am guilty of possessing ebooks. Of course, I am not all against ebooks (this article is being published online, after all), it does provide many the opportunity to read things that otherwise would be inaccessible to them and it certainly is a great aid when travelling. Although the emergence of ebooks feels like a personal defeat to me, I concede to the importance of ebooks in times of such great distress to nature and society. And in fear that I might be misconstrued as a privileged brat, let me tell you, I buy books using fees earned from part-time teaching, which most assuredly isn’t much. Yet, still, for me, books and their essence lies in their old-school charm that keeps us turning actual pages.   Andrei Tarkovsky once said that artists are there because the world is not perfect, and such imperfection is reminded to us by those hardcopies that seem frayed and old and decaying just like our world. The ebook is too perfect a vessel for works that are born out of imperfection. It swerves us into a path away from nature, away from reality into a dark realm of complete machine dominance. In the end, maybe I am simply a hopeless romantic stuck in the past when the world is aggressively progressing into the future, but I hope my voice of unreason reaches a few romantic hearts so that we can keep the lineage of hardcopies from dying a most ignominious and unromantic death.  </summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
