<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/culture/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-07-26T18:40:29+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/culture/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Lived Experience Through The Lens of Pop Culture</title>
      <link href="/The-Lens-of-Pop-Culture" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Lived Experience Through The Lens of Pop Culture" />
      <published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Lens-of-Pop-Culture</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Lens-of-Pop-Culture">&lt;p&gt;Pop culture was never meant to be therapeutic for the conscience. It was merely
an escape from reality, a make-believe world where you could imagine yourself as
Clint Eastwood on a horse, or as Sylvester Stallone being one hell of a southpaw
boxer. Or, it could have been you taking acid during a Jimi Hendrix concert, or
raging with the grunge bands of the 90’s. It was only in the 2000’s, the
millennial age, when mainstream pop culture became a place for the reclamation
of maligned narratives. Finally, a space on the global stage for those with
little social capital. Be it non-cisgender people, African-Americans, Latinos or
people with clinical depression; the millennial age did more than take note of
these problems, it made sure that they were heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to strip the periods before that of credit for their art. Movies
like &lt;em&gt;Forrest Gump&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Platoon&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Apocalypse Now&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Deer Hunter&lt;/em&gt; surely
gave an insight into the prevailing anti-war sentiment in the USA and the
protests by soldiers’ families. These movies could, however, very well be termed
‘Oscar bait’, and they got swept away in the same instead of provoking perhaps
finer, more nuanced details of, say, military life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a movie like &lt;em&gt;Driving Miss Daisy&lt;/em&gt;, for example. It won the Best Picture
Oscar in 1980, but its premise might make one skeptical about the award. Apart
from the hailing of a  ‘white saviour’, the film also promoted stereotypes about
Afro-Americans; illiterate, not self dependent, helpless people who don’t know
what to do in the face of problems. They’re undermined in their own stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference between that time and today, however, is that our generation
won’t shy away from criticising such films. The films of yore too are
scrutinised under the modern lens of how an ideal world must be; a
post-postmodern critique, if you will. That’s how the image of &lt;em&gt;James Bond&lt;/em&gt; has
evolved. There is no denying that people did not take to a one-dimensional
womanizer spy with cheeky sensibilities and a way to escape every situation
effortlessly. They wanted someone more vulnerable and mortal, and possibly not a
man, which is evident in the recent wave of Bond movies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, take a look at the movies and shows of today. &lt;em&gt;Get Out&lt;/em&gt; was a pivotal
movie that took shots at liberals for ‘acting black’, thinking that that would
solve racism. A less-talked-about but incredibly influential show was the Donald
Glover show &lt;em&gt;Atlanta&lt;/em&gt;, that was hailed by many Atlanta natives as a true
portrayal of life and culture in the city. The show humanised Afro-Americans.
This trend extends to a lot of shows, like &lt;em&gt;Orange Is The New Black&lt;/em&gt;, that
eventually went beyond the lead character and ended up becoming one of the most
inclusive shows in recent times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mainstream music has also changed drastically over the past two decades. Hip-hop&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a genre often criticised for the use of homophobic slurs as a metric for
masculinity - has now included artists like Tyler, The Creator, and more
recently, Lil Nas X who thought it was safe enough to reveal their sexualities
and talk about their experiences through their music. Notably, Tyler was accused
of using one such slur. Musicians such as St Vincent and Troye Sivan have been
much more open about the same throughout their discography.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conscious hip-hop has also gained popularity, with the advent of artists like
Kendrick Lamar and Kanye West, who wrap messages and lived experiences in ear
candy. Even pop stars like Beyonce and Lady Gaga have been using their global
influence to further discussions that several years ago would have been
considered too taboo to even be talked about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does this increasing demand for inclusivity tell us? We, the
millennials, want our screens to show us something that evokes not merely
sympathy but also empathy. We want to see lived experiences. We do not want
tokenistic gestures of inclusivity, but full-blooded accounts of stories about
people that are not necessarily us. The idea that racism is over simply because
a privileged character learns about the struggles of the ostracised minority,
has been running for all of Hollywood’s existence; Hollywood’s systemic Oscar
bait and guaranteed cash churning mechanism. Authentic stories, like real life,
are possibly boring to them. They also forget the one rule of moviemaking: do
not underestimate the audience. The same goes for music: concept albums exist to
tell a story that’s beyond our imagination. Millennials, especially those who
are part of the minority have become fed up of the fact that they can not see
any entertainment that resembles them. They expect human depictions of what it
means to belong to their race, religion, caste or gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might even argue that the severance of human connection has left us seeking
something &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; in our cinema. The millennial is looking for relatability and
human fallibility more than he is looking for fantasy. The craving to feel is
seen in how much readership emo Tumblr experiences achieve or in how much shows
like BoJack Horseman shine. BoJack Horseman is highly acclaimed primarily
because it really touches a nerve, in millennials, in the domain of mental
health. It lets its viewers comprehend the consequences of such actions that
already might have happened to them. Besides, the idea then also becomes about
combining reality and fantasy, brutality and comedy, to make more high-end
surreal art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is definitely the tough question that all of this poses: do we really need
more and more art to get us to empathise with something? Isn’t once enough? To
be honest, we are all guilty of it, including this writer here. It becomes a
global statement, that our inaction, or our perception is part of the problem,
if not the actual problem. But it has been done before, with resounding success.
During the #BlackLivesMatter movement in 2015, Kendrick Lamar released his hit
song &lt;em&gt;Alright&lt;/em&gt;. The refrain “We gon’ be alright” became the cry of the rally for
some time and unified the protestors. We do not need conscious art to feel good
about ourselves because we have seen/heard it; we need it to make us better
people, if at all we really need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that inclusion and adequate representation in media has taken a
much higher priority today as compared to earlier times. A UCLA study on
diversity in Hollywood states that people of colour have quadrupled their share
of broadcast television from 5.1% in 2011-12 to 21.5% in 2017-18.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennials are better educated as compared to previous generations, with 39% of
people having a bachelor’s degree or higher; to compare, at the same age, the
same statistic was 29% for Gen X, around 25% for baby boomers, and 15% for the
Silent Generation. Higher education is becoming accessible to people of various
cultures. The Deloitte Global Millennial Survey talks about how millennials only
like firms that abide by their values, and any non-adherence to consumer values
on their part will make them or break them. People are more receptive to
personal and social problems, and while there are a myriad of surveys pointing
to how millennials are becoming less empathetic, one can not deny that it is the
millennials who are shaping narratives about intersectionality, privilege, class
and race amongst other things. Call it political correctness or call it
sensitivity, it has arguably bettered the debate. It is this nuance that is
slowly but surely influencing content around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quintessential to this is the scenario of Indian stand-up comedy. After the
calling out of the prevalence of sexual harassment in what was perceived as a
circle that was &lt;em&gt;woke just for show&lt;/em&gt;, female comedians have been earning what’s
due to them. Their jokes are a lot more oriented towards the female experience,
quite naturally, whilst their other observations are arguably spot on. In
another example, TVF’s &lt;em&gt;Kota Factory&lt;/em&gt; created ripples across the student
community in India for its bleak but true depiction of the city. Engineering
students possibly shed tears at the time the show was released because they saw
their life reflected in it. Millennials are both creating and consuming bold
content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studios understand the importance of discourse for long-term retention of the
millennial as a consumer. This is evident in the shifts in strategy by platforms
such as Netflix towards creating content that is politically or socially
charged. These shifts in strategy betray how they see their consumers; as a
generation that wants to confront socio-politico realities head on. As a
generation that is so desperate to connect to the characters on screen, to view
life through the lens of cinema as a way of trying to make sense of our own
troubles and our trauma. We seek a lot fewer heroes and a lot more flawed humans
in our cinema.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pranav Manie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Pop culture was never meant to be therapeutic for the conscience. It was merely an escape from reality, a make-believe world where you could imagine yourself as Clint Eastwood on a horse, or as Sylvester Stallone being one hell of a southpaw boxer. Or, it could have been you taking acid during a Jimi Hendrix concert, or raging with the grunge bands of the 90’s. It was only in the 2000’s, the millennial age, when mainstream pop culture became a place for the reclamation of maligned narratives. Finally, a space on the global stage for those with little social capital. Be it non-cisgender people, African-Americans, Latinos or people with clinical depression; the millennial age did more than take note of these problems, it made sure that they were heard. This is not to strip the periods before that of credit for their art. Movies like Forrest Gump, Platoon, Apocalypse Now and The Deer Hunter surely gave an insight into the prevailing anti-war sentiment in the USA and the protests by soldiers’ families. These movies could, however, very well be termed ‘Oscar bait’, and they got swept away in the same instead of provoking perhaps finer, more nuanced details of, say, military life.   Take a movie like Driving Miss Daisy, for example. It won the Best Picture Oscar in 1980, but its premise might make one skeptical about the award. Apart from the hailing of a  ‘white saviour’, the film also promoted stereotypes about Afro-Americans; illiterate, not self dependent, helpless people who don’t know what to do in the face of problems. They’re undermined in their own stories. The difference between that time and today, however, is that our generation won’t shy away from criticising such films. The films of yore too are scrutinised under the modern lens of how an ideal world must be; a post-postmodern critique, if you will. That’s how the image of James Bond has evolved. There is no denying that people did not take to a one-dimensional womanizer spy with cheeky sensibilities and a way to escape every situation effortlessly. They wanted someone more vulnerable and mortal, and possibly not a man, which is evident in the recent wave of Bond movies. Moreover, take a look at the movies and shows of today. Get Out was a pivotal movie that took shots at liberals for ‘acting black’, thinking that that would solve racism. A less-talked-about but incredibly influential show was the Donald Glover show Atlanta, that was hailed by many Atlanta natives as a true portrayal of life and culture in the city. The show humanised Afro-Americans. This trend extends to a lot of shows, like Orange Is The New Black, that eventually went beyond the lead character and ended up becoming one of the most inclusive shows in recent times. Mainstream music has also changed drastically over the past two decades. Hip-hop a genre often criticised for the use of homophobic slurs as a metric for masculinity - has now included artists like Tyler, The Creator, and more recently, Lil Nas X who thought it was safe enough to reveal their sexualities and talk about their experiences through their music. Notably, Tyler was accused of using one such slur. Musicians such as St Vincent and Troye Sivan have been much more open about the same throughout their discography. Conscious hip-hop has also gained popularity, with the advent of artists like Kendrick Lamar and Kanye West, who wrap messages and lived experiences in ear candy. Even pop stars like Beyonce and Lady Gaga have been using their global influence to further discussions that several years ago would have been considered too taboo to even be talked about. But what does this increasing demand for inclusivity tell us? We, the millennials, want our screens to show us something that evokes not merely sympathy but also empathy. We want to see lived experiences. We do not want tokenistic gestures of inclusivity, but full-blooded accounts of stories about people that are not necessarily us. The idea that racism is over simply because a privileged character learns about the struggles of the ostracised minority, has been running for all of Hollywood’s existence; Hollywood’s systemic Oscar bait and guaranteed cash churning mechanism. Authentic stories, like real life, are possibly boring to them. They also forget the one rule of moviemaking: do not underestimate the audience. The same goes for music: concept albums exist to tell a story that’s beyond our imagination. Millennials, especially those who are part of the minority have become fed up of the fact that they can not see any entertainment that resembles them. They expect human depictions of what it means to belong to their race, religion, caste or gender. One might even argue that the severance of human connection has left us seeking something real in our cinema. The millennial is looking for relatability and human fallibility more than he is looking for fantasy. The craving to feel is seen in how much readership emo Tumblr experiences achieve or in how much shows like BoJack Horseman shine. BoJack Horseman is highly acclaimed primarily because it really touches a nerve, in millennials, in the domain of mental health. It lets its viewers comprehend the consequences of such actions that already might have happened to them. Besides, the idea then also becomes about combining reality and fantasy, brutality and comedy, to make more high-end surreal art. There is definitely the tough question that all of this poses: do we really need more and more art to get us to empathise with something? Isn’t once enough? To be honest, we are all guilty of it, including this writer here. It becomes a global statement, that our inaction, or our perception is part of the problem, if not the actual problem. But it has been done before, with resounding success. During the #BlackLivesMatter movement in 2015, Kendrick Lamar released his hit song Alright. The refrain “We gon’ be alright” became the cry of the rally for some time and unified the protestors. We do not need conscious art to feel good about ourselves because we have seen/heard it; we need it to make us better people, if at all we really need it. The good news is that inclusion and adequate representation in media has taken a much higher priority today as compared to earlier times. A UCLA study on diversity in Hollywood states that people of colour have quadrupled their share of broadcast television from 5.1% in 2011-12 to 21.5% in 2017-18. Millennials are better educated as compared to previous generations, with 39% of people having a bachelor’s degree or higher; to compare, at the same age, the same statistic was 29% for Gen X, around 25% for baby boomers, and 15% for the Silent Generation. Higher education is becoming accessible to people of various cultures. The Deloitte Global Millennial Survey talks about how millennials only like firms that abide by their values, and any non-adherence to consumer values on their part will make them or break them. People are more receptive to personal and social problems, and while there are a myriad of surveys pointing to how millennials are becoming less empathetic, one can not deny that it is the millennials who are shaping narratives about intersectionality, privilege, class and race amongst other things. Call it political correctness or call it sensitivity, it has arguably bettered the debate. It is this nuance that is slowly but surely influencing content around us.   Quintessential to this is the scenario of Indian stand-up comedy. After the calling out of the prevalence of sexual harassment in what was perceived as a circle that was woke just for show, female comedians have been earning what’s due to them. Their jokes are a lot more oriented towards the female experience, quite naturally, whilst their other observations are arguably spot on. In another example, TVF’s Kota Factory created ripples across the student community in India for its bleak but true depiction of the city. Engineering students possibly shed tears at the time the show was released because they saw their life reflected in it. Millennials are both creating and consuming bold content. Studios understand the importance of discourse for long-term retention of the millennial as a consumer. This is evident in the shifts in strategy by platforms such as Netflix towards creating content that is politically or socially charged. These shifts in strategy betray how they see their consumers; as a generation that wants to confront socio-politico realities head on. As a generation that is so desperate to connect to the characters on screen, to view life through the lens of cinema as a way of trying to make sense of our own troubles and our trauma. We seek a lot fewer heroes and a lot more flawed humans in our cinema.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Rise of the Screen Thriller</title>
      <link href="/Rise-of-the-Screen-Killer" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rise of the Screen Thriller" />
      <published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Rise-of-the-Screen-Killer</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Rise-of-the-Screen-Killer">&lt;p&gt;Internet culture has pervaded scriptwriting in various ways. It has provided
useful ways of releasing information to the audience. Meme culture, ways of
writing texts, or communication through a certain type of media reveals a
subtext previously unknown, but in every conversation that follows, you consider
these subtexts to figure out how the situation will unfold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the BBC masterpiece, &lt;em&gt;Sherlock&lt;/em&gt;, for example. Sherlock is quite often in
contact with his arch-nemesis Jim Moriarty, and we know that through the message
bubbles which pop up on the screen for us to see whilst we simultaneously
observe Sherlock’s expressions. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; portrays the internet the best -
take an episode like &lt;em&gt;Nosedive&lt;/em&gt;; a brutal, horrifying account of what happens if
we introduce a social credit rating for humans or &lt;em&gt;Shut Up And Dance&lt;/em&gt;; an
episode that’ll instantly make you cover your webcam with some tape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These, however, are still conventional ways of storytelling. Even though the
aforementioned devices make use of internet culture, they still fall short of
being able to harness the full power of what someone experiences when online.
The need to harness and depict that is what led to the &lt;em&gt;computer screen
thriller&lt;/em&gt; being born - a stylish new method of movie-making. Most or all of the
film takes place on some kind of a screen be it the computer, phone or
television. This subgenre of films made its biggest splash with the release of
&lt;em&gt;Searching&lt;/em&gt;, a movie with John Cho playing the lead, about a father searching
for his missing daughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the roots of this subgenre go back way before 2018. The first
documented screen-only movie was &lt;em&gt;The Collingswood Story&lt;/em&gt;, which is about an
online long-distance relationship gone wrong. It takes place through webcams.
The real wave of this subgenre started about a decade later with the movie
&lt;em&gt;Unfriended&lt;/em&gt;, which revolved around cyberbullying among high-school students. It
made $64 million in revenue against a budget of $1 million. A Russian
director, Timur Bekmambetov co-produced it, thereby beginning his dedication to
this subgenre that he calls &lt;em&gt;Screen Life&lt;/em&gt;. He produced a sequel to the movie, as
well as &lt;em&gt;Searching,&lt;/em&gt; and directed one of his own called &lt;em&gt;Profile.&lt;/em&gt; There were
other short films in and around 2013-2015, which seemingly inspired the TV show
&lt;em&gt;Modern Family&lt;/em&gt; to go the same route with one of their episodes. It is hailed by
many as one of the best episodes of the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real question, however, is this: is there something much deeper to the
Screen Life or is it just a gimmick to make things flashy? Much of the
information can be revealed without using screens throughout. &lt;em&gt;Sherlock&lt;/em&gt; was
able to demonstrate it well. The TV show &lt;em&gt;American Vandal&lt;/em&gt; was themed around
internet culture, and used it to its advantage. Even &lt;em&gt;13 Reasons Why&lt;/em&gt; could be
credited for the same; one can see that this trend is directed towards
millennials, because their lives revolve around screens the most. Modern
film-making has allowed the blending of actions on the web and reactions to it
for us to simultaneously consume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These films have much smaller budgets. The return on investment can be immense.
&lt;em&gt;Searching&lt;/em&gt; made $75 million against a budget of $1 million, and &lt;em&gt;Unfriended&lt;/em&gt;
made 64 times its budget. But is there more to this subgenre than meets the eye?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first glance, one can see that this style expresses a lot by saying little.
Social media tells us about habits, likes and desires not just of the user but
also of people engaging with said user. It is the rapidity with which the story
gets out that makes screen thrillers this gripping. When people are online and
texting each other, the messages, the time taken to reply, or the choice to not
reply at all, everything leads to some assumptions in both the audience and the
characters. This technique plays upon our conditioning to believe that tiny
things are indicators of something large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to hide porn from your parents, you naturally put it in some folder
in an extreme corner of the depths of your desktop. And when your parents find
out they are shocked and upset. The way those reactions get captured in a screen
thriller is unparalleled. The screen need not resort to edits or cut-aways to
show the reaction; it is right there. The actor reacts at the same time as the
audience does, they are as much the spectator as we are. The lesser reliance on
cut-aways directly takes the audience on the protagonist’s journey. While not
exclusive to the genre, Screen Life films surely help bring out the often
shocking difference that exists between our lives and our personas, in real life
and online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These films come attached with a sense of claustrophobia, to say the least. The
screen is crowded with pop-ups, the user keeps switching between tabs and
windows. This adds to not only the pace of the film but also the paranoia of the
viewer. Every step of the way, there lurks a  fear, it is like you are always
waiting for the next development. You are excited for what comes next, no matter
how deeply personal or confidential it might be for the victim. Not that that is
wrong; it is a story, after all. But it does explain something about the human
desire to voyeur over others’ lives; both the good and the bad. As David
Fincher, the director of &lt;em&gt;The Social Network&lt;/em&gt; says, “People are perverts.” They
want to know the truth, but the kicker is that it will be ugly. Nevertheless,
they will love it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pranav Manie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Internet culture has pervaded scriptwriting in various ways. It has provided useful ways of releasing information to the audience. Meme culture, ways of writing texts, or communication through a certain type of media reveals a subtext previously unknown, but in every conversation that follows, you consider these subtexts to figure out how the situation will unfold. Take the BBC masterpiece, Sherlock, for example. Sherlock is quite often in contact with his arch-nemesis Jim Moriarty, and we know that through the message bubbles which pop up on the screen for us to see whilst we simultaneously observe Sherlock’s expressions. Black Mirror portrays the internet the best - take an episode like Nosedive; a brutal, horrifying account of what happens if we introduce a social credit rating for humans or Shut Up And Dance; an episode that’ll instantly make you cover your webcam with some tape. These, however, are still conventional ways of storytelling. Even though the aforementioned devices make use of internet culture, they still fall short of being able to harness the full power of what someone experiences when online. The need to harness and depict that is what led to the computer screen thriller being born - a stylish new method of movie-making. Most or all of the film takes place on some kind of a screen be it the computer, phone or television. This subgenre of films made its biggest splash with the release of Searching, a movie with John Cho playing the lead, about a father searching for his missing daughter. However, the roots of this subgenre go back way before 2018. The first documented screen-only movie was The Collingswood Story, which is about an online long-distance relationship gone wrong. It takes place through webcams. The real wave of this subgenre started about a decade later with the movie Unfriended, which revolved around cyberbullying among high-school students. It made $64 million in revenue against a budget of $1 million. A Russian director, Timur Bekmambetov co-produced it, thereby beginning his dedication to this subgenre that he calls Screen Life. He produced a sequel to the movie, as well as Searching, and directed one of his own called Profile. There were other short films in and around 2013-2015, which seemingly inspired the TV show Modern Family to go the same route with one of their episodes. It is hailed by many as one of the best episodes of the show. The real question, however, is this: is there something much deeper to the Screen Life or is it just a gimmick to make things flashy? Much of the information can be revealed without using screens throughout. Sherlock was able to demonstrate it well. The TV show American Vandal was themed around internet culture, and used it to its advantage. Even 13 Reasons Why could be credited for the same; one can see that this trend is directed towards millennials, because their lives revolve around screens the most. Modern film-making has allowed the blending of actions on the web and reactions to it for us to simultaneously consume. These films have much smaller budgets. The return on investment can be immense. Searching made $75 million against a budget of $1 million, and Unfriended made 64 times its budget. But is there more to this subgenre than meets the eye? At first glance, one can see that this style expresses a lot by saying little. Social media tells us about habits, likes and desires not just of the user but also of people engaging with said user. It is the rapidity with which the story gets out that makes screen thrillers this gripping. When people are online and texting each other, the messages, the time taken to reply, or the choice to not reply at all, everything leads to some assumptions in both the audience and the characters. This technique plays upon our conditioning to believe that tiny things are indicators of something large. If you want to hide porn from your parents, you naturally put it in some folder in an extreme corner of the depths of your desktop. And when your parents find out they are shocked and upset. The way those reactions get captured in a screen thriller is unparalleled. The screen need not resort to edits or cut-aways to show the reaction; it is right there. The actor reacts at the same time as the audience does, they are as much the spectator as we are. The lesser reliance on cut-aways directly takes the audience on the protagonist’s journey. While not exclusive to the genre, Screen Life films surely help bring out the often shocking difference that exists between our lives and our personas, in real life and online. These films come attached with a sense of claustrophobia, to say the least. The screen is crowded with pop-ups, the user keeps switching between tabs and windows. This adds to not only the pace of the film but also the paranoia of the viewer. Every step of the way, there lurks a  fear, it is like you are always waiting for the next development. You are excited for what comes next, no matter how deeply personal or confidential it might be for the victim. Not that that is wrong; it is a story, after all. But it does explain something about the human desire to voyeur over others’ lives; both the good and the bad. As David Fincher, the director of The Social Network says, “People are perverts.” They want to know the truth, but the kicker is that it will be ugly. Nevertheless, they will love it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Millennials and Meme Culture</title>
      <link href="/Millennials-and-Meme-Culture" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Millennials and Meme Culture" />
      <published>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Millennials-and-Meme-Culture</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Millennials-and-Meme-Culture">&lt;p&gt;Art has existed for about 30,000 years now. And although art has no practical utility, it is one of those things that puts humans at the apex of the food chain. At first, art was strictly an extension of the artist’s speculation, and slowly it branched out to imagination. It slowly evolved into a tool to form friendships and solidarities, establish authority, form groups, bands, tribes, civilisations, and societies. Societies as big as Russia were formed through art. And, unlike the other extension of human cognitive faculty, i.e. science, art has evolved on its own through vessels called artists. It has endured through time and adapted itself to epochal changes and cultural diversifications like a living, breathing organism. If there’s one thing on the planet that could come close to humans, it would be art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time and the intent behind it shape the adaptability of art. Art can be used as a mouthpiece for personal vexation, for political propaganda, as a romantic sonnet, a rebellious speech, or even as satire. The possibilities are endless and the means to propagate them have a few malleable forms. The very beginning of art was through illustrations, statuettes, and fictional stories. As our ancestors developed their faculties, so did art. It has since then taken several forms, namely illustration, text, sculpting, acting, dance, song, cinema and now, memes. Like innumerable developments in the field of art, memes too betray a thing or two about the period to which they are relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;em&gt;meme&lt;/em&gt; originally comes from the Greek word ‘&lt;em&gt;mimema&lt;/em&gt;’, meaning imitation. The term was coined by Richard Dawkins in his book &lt;em&gt;The Selfish Gene&lt;/em&gt; in 1976. Back then, however, the word didn’t gain a lot of recognition. A few decades later, after the emergence of the Internet, memes have surged to be an art form most characteristic of the millennials or Gen Y.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand how a meme is a form of art, we need to understand other art forms. The key idea behind any art is to freeze or compress a particular thought or vision, a whole infinity into a finite space. It confronts our consciousness with matters that we miss out on due to activities essential to survival. If rendered well enough, it takes hold of our spirits and colonises it with whatever it wanted to. Consuming art is a conscious effort and has always been, until the arrival of memes. Memes have gone astray from this principle of art. Memes are consumed in an unstudied manner, seldom requiring cognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memes are symbolic of millennials. They symbolise the hyperactive lifestyle of our generation. They betray the cultural degradation we are going through. A degradation that makes us ponder and say less and less and passively consume more and more. Our vocabulary is riddled with buzzwords which lose meaning with every passing day. Abundance has made us fall out of our practice of thinking. Time has shortened itself relatively, and we constantly seek to escape reality. On average, in a single day, a person goes through a hundred different thoughts, which are &lt;em&gt;not his own&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are losing the originality of thought, the creativity that we are born with. It is in the nature of words and of our human selves to make it difficult to say just about anything. It is momentous to experience the bittersweetness of struggling for words to express how we feel, to lose words just as they are clawing at the base of one’s throat. But with meme culture we lose that. My broken expression and my efforts give way to tagging my friends in memes and to what Buzzfeed tells me describes me and the culture of my generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The erosion of human cognition is alarming and evermore because of the manner of consumption. As mentioned before, memes are consumed quite absently not requiring a conscious effort. This leaves us unguarded, vulnerable to what the memes represent. And, as the practice of conscious thinking ebbs away, so does our consciousness towards life. We are gradually turning apathetic, normalising things that should evoke deep concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Phil Kaye tells us, “If you repeat something over and over again it loses its meaning.” The words ‘climate change’ turn into a category of memes you share, people’s mental traumas become a ‘&lt;em&gt;mood&lt;/em&gt;’ to us and bashing capitalist exploitation just something we do for the kick of feeling edgy. The outrageous loses the ability to outrage us anymore. We think we feel so much that we end up feeling very little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A generation distinguished by a mental health crisis, an existential crisis, a crisis of faith, and a crisis of belief requires, above all, empathy and a careful understanding of the self to counter all our crises. But with the emergence of memes, the probability of countering them is plummeting. Memes that represent cultures and societies, on both micro and macro levels, qualify as phenomenal and path-breaking. Memes have helped us understand our kind better, they’ve taken away the alienation we feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, memes have ended up normalising, without us realising, a lot that is worrisome. The apathy we feel towards ourselves and our actions is of grave concern. The manifestation of this apathy is seen in the increasing streak of nihilism in our generation. Memes are blurring the lines and lies constructed through fiction over the ages and slowly lifting our trust from certain systems of belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But enough about the villainy of memes. Memes are an extension of postmodernism. One can’t discount all of the good that memes have brought. They’ve made us aware of things we otherwise would have remained oblivious of: culture, people, politics, ideologies, sports, our favourite celebrities. Memes are reaching to form a global culture, unparalleled by any art form before. Millennials understand diversity better than any of our previous generations. Millennials are aware of and understand the climate crisis, the water crisis and in general the humanitarian crisis breathing heavily down our necks. With the hyperactivity and the pace of things, it is difficult to take time out to be aware, to seek information, but with memes, it is no longer an arduous task. The simplicity of it is probably its greatest feature. It psychologically functions on the need to remain simple. Perhaps why we keep returning to memes in the face of rising complexities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memes represent a milestone in the evolution of art, a point at which human art has transcended from a confrontation of our inner consciousness to an unguarded passive intake of what lies before one. For better or for worse, meme culture has a sinister ability to both reveal and shape the people who consume it the most, namely the Millennials.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Art has existed for about 30,000 years now. And although art has no practical utility, it is one of those things that puts humans at the apex of the food chain. At first, art was strictly an extension of the artist’s speculation, and slowly it branched out to imagination. It slowly evolved into a tool to form friendships and solidarities, establish authority, form groups, bands, tribes, civilisations, and societies. Societies as big as Russia were formed through art. And, unlike the other extension of human cognitive faculty, i.e. science, art has evolved on its own through vessels called artists. It has endured through time and adapted itself to epochal changes and cultural diversifications like a living, breathing organism. If there’s one thing on the planet that could come close to humans, it would be art.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">On Codes and Ciphers; The Imitation Game</title>
      <link href="/On-Codes-and-Ciphers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Codes and Ciphers; The Imitation Game" />
      <published>2019-07-12T17:45:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-12T17:45:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/On-Codes-and-Ciphers</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/On-Codes-and-Ciphers">&lt;p&gt;“Are you paying attention? Good. If you are not listening carefully, you will
miss things, important things. I will not pause, I will not repeat myself, and
you will not interrupt me. You think that because you’re sitting where you are
and I am sitting where I am, that you are in control of what is about to happen.
You’re mistaken. I am in control, because I know things that you do not know.” - &lt;em&gt;The Imitation Game&lt;/em&gt;, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/a1/Alan_Turing_Aged_16.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Alan_Turing_Aged_16.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan Turing was a revolutionary mathematician, a pioneer among computer
scientists and, most importantly, one of the key players in resolving World War
II through his immense contribution to the decoding of the Enigma cipher. The
Allied forces were in a near-constant state of perplexion over how to crack the
Enigma, the cipher used by the Germans, in order to encrypt messages. Though the
Enigma was reported to have been decoded by the Polish well before him, Turing’s
original method of decrypting the cipher was instrumental in predicting German
movements during the War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/_dchris/19612913884&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//enigma-machine.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Enigma was believed to be impossible to crack. Ultimately, however, it was
broken, bearing testimony to how nothing is truly unbreakable, and every system
has a catch attached to it; a principle well highlighted by modern cryptologists
like Shamir and Bonhe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conceptualisation of codes and ciphers is well-documented alongside the
history of warfare and the development of language, as we know it. A very famous
cipher, the Caesar Cipher, was supposedly used by the famous Roman general to
communicate messages from one camp to another whilst maintaining the
authenticity of commands. In the cipher, the first letter of the alphabet is
replaced with any chosen letter, the subsequent letters then get replaced in a
similar order. For example, in the ‘G Cipher’, A gets replaced by G, B gets
replaced by H and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://s4scoding.com/images/caesar-cipher-left-shift-of-3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//caesar-cipher-left-shift-of-3.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key aspects of codes and ciphers comes from the concept of
steganography. Even though steganography is considered to be a part of
cryptology, it actually isn’t, it is simply a method of hiding information,
using pictures. This method is said to be foolproof. It was even used in the
very famous or rather infamous case of Cicada 3301, when an unknown group of
people claimed to hide information within certain images, and challenged someone
to crack it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another prominent cipher is the Vigenere Cipher; a key-controlled Caesar Cipher.
A key is a system through which one can encode or decode anything, like messages
or warnings. Vigenere Ciphers have been instrumental during war communication
even during the era of the Napoleonic Wars and have stood the test of time, 
being one of the most recognisable of ciphers today. However, the claim to the
throne of the most illustrious cipher would, undisputedly, go to the Morse Code.
The concept behind the Morse Code, (which despite the misnomer of being a code,
is actually a cipher) is also behind the invention of the telegraph by, you
guessed it, Samuel Morse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/b/b5/International_Morse_Code.svg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//International_Morse_Code.svg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For almost half a century, the Telegraph was the only means by which electronic
messages could be sent and received. The Morse Code expresses words, i.e. the
letters and numbers that constitute them, in the form of ‘dots and dashes’ and
it is in this form that it is sent to the receiver. Morse Code, however, has
been, quite interestingly, used in several other forms such as taps and untaps;
tapping signifying a dot, and pausing a dash. (Yes, Sherlock fans, you guessed
it, didn’t you)? The Morse Code is quite a reliable form of masking data, if
masked properly that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny enough, codes and ciphers have been an integral part of artistic movements
in Europe. One of the most renowned ciphers was developed by one of the most
talented men in Europe. Although his name is obscure, he is considered to have
talent comparable to the likes of Leonardo Da Vinci. Most of the relics of that
age have been protected using this very cipher. The cipher in question is the
Alberti Cipher, conceptualised by the revolutionary, Alberti. This cipher
replaces words according to a disk which helps encrypt and decrypt the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The famous author David Kahn notes in his book &lt;em&gt;The Codebreakers&lt;/em&gt; that history
has forgotten several of the other famous ciphers, such as the ones used by many
mathematicians in the Middle-East during the Oriental age, the Scytale Cipher
used by the Spartans during their Golden Age, and so on. There has been no
dearth in the human ability to innovate. In order to create a foolproof cipher
system, all has been done, ranging from methods of transposition (that is to
replace one word with another, as was utilised by the famous Gronsfeld Cipher)
to the generation of intelligent schemes to make decryption difficult without
the key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when the Enigma was built, it was almost as if the pinnacle of human
comprehension was reached and it was presumed that it could not be broken, no
matter what the Allies did. However, a group of people in Bletchley Park refused
to give up and the rest, as they say, is history. Alan Turing has been an
inspiration for the greatest of modern cryptographers, from Adi Shamir to
Malcolm Williamson. In an age in which it is predicted that computers might rule
the world, the authenticity of information and security are some of the biggest
concerns. Cryptography and its application are only going to get more complex
and esoteric, to the extent that we may not be able to comprehend even abstract
concepts on the quantum nature of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information, they say, is key. The philosophy behind the establishment, setting
up and the consequent breaking of codes signifies the ultimate nature of how we
are. It signifies the essence of humankind. It is in the nature of man to build
and then eventually destroy, to construct and then ultimately deconstruct, only
for a better possibility to be explored. Human nature tells us that nothing is
truly unbreakable and that everything, which is part of human effort, can be
brought down, thanks to humans themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Codes help us express ourselves in a niche manner, truly being an indication of
the creativity and perseverance, we as humans, are able to display and put into
effect.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Are you paying attention? Good. If you are not listening carefully, you will miss things, important things. I will not pause, I will not repeat myself, and you will not interrupt me. You think that because you’re sitting where you are and I am sitting where I am, that you are in control of what is about to happen. You’re mistaken. I am in control, because I know things that you do not know.” - The Imitation Game, 2014. Alan Turing was a revolutionary mathematician, a pioneer among computer scientists and, most importantly, one of the key players in resolving World War II through his immense contribution to the decoding of the Enigma cipher. The Allied forces were in a near-constant state of perplexion over how to crack the Enigma, the cipher used by the Germans, in order to encrypt messages. Though the Enigma was reported to have been decoded by the Polish well before him, Turing’s original method of decrypting the cipher was instrumental in predicting German movements during the War. The Enigma was believed to be impossible to crack. Ultimately, however, it was broken, bearing testimony to how nothing is truly unbreakable, and every system has a catch attached to it; a principle well highlighted by modern cryptologists like Shamir and Bonhe. The conceptualisation of codes and ciphers is well-documented alongside the history of warfare and the development of language, as we know it. A very famous cipher, the Caesar Cipher, was supposedly used by the famous Roman general to communicate messages from one camp to another whilst maintaining the authenticity of commands. In the cipher, the first letter of the alphabet is replaced with any chosen letter, the subsequent letters then get replaced in a similar order. For example, in the ‘G Cipher’, A gets replaced by G, B gets replaced by H and so on. One of the key aspects of codes and ciphers comes from the concept of steganography. Even though steganography is considered to be a part of cryptology, it actually isn’t, it is simply a method of hiding information, using pictures. This method is said to be foolproof. It was even used in the very famous or rather infamous case of Cicada 3301, when an unknown group of people claimed to hide information within certain images, and challenged someone to crack it. Another prominent cipher is the Vigenere Cipher; a key-controlled Caesar Cipher. A key is a system through which one can encode or decode anything, like messages or warnings. Vigenere Ciphers have been instrumental during war communication even during the era of the Napoleonic Wars and have stood the test of time,  being one of the most recognisable of ciphers today. However, the claim to the throne of the most illustrious cipher would, undisputedly, go to the Morse Code. The concept behind the Morse Code, (which despite the misnomer of being a code, is actually a cipher) is also behind the invention of the telegraph by, you guessed it, Samuel Morse. For almost half a century, the Telegraph was the only means by which electronic messages could be sent and received. The Morse Code expresses words, i.e. the letters and numbers that constitute them, in the form of ‘dots and dashes’ and it is in this form that it is sent to the receiver. Morse Code, however, has been, quite interestingly, used in several other forms such as taps and untaps; tapping signifying a dot, and pausing a dash. (Yes, Sherlock fans, you guessed it, didn’t you)? The Morse Code is quite a reliable form of masking data, if masked properly that is. Funny enough, codes and ciphers have been an integral part of artistic movements in Europe. One of the most renowned ciphers was developed by one of the most talented men in Europe. Although his name is obscure, he is considered to have talent comparable to the likes of Leonardo Da Vinci. Most of the relics of that age have been protected using this very cipher. The cipher in question is the Alberti Cipher, conceptualised by the revolutionary, Alberti. This cipher replaces words according to a disk which helps encrypt and decrypt the text. The famous author David Kahn notes in his book The Codebreakers that history has forgotten several of the other famous ciphers, such as the ones used by many mathematicians in the Middle-East during the Oriental age, the Scytale Cipher used by the Spartans during their Golden Age, and so on. There has been no dearth in the human ability to innovate. In order to create a foolproof cipher system, all has been done, ranging from methods of transposition (that is to replace one word with another, as was utilised by the famous Gronsfeld Cipher) to the generation of intelligent schemes to make decryption difficult without the key. However, when the Enigma was built, it was almost as if the pinnacle of human comprehension was reached and it was presumed that it could not be broken, no matter what the Allies did. However, a group of people in Bletchley Park refused to give up and the rest, as they say, is history. Alan Turing has been an inspiration for the greatest of modern cryptographers, from Adi Shamir to Malcolm Williamson. In an age in which it is predicted that computers might rule the world, the authenticity of information and security are some of the biggest concerns. Cryptography and its application are only going to get more complex and esoteric, to the extent that we may not be able to comprehend even abstract concepts on the quantum nature of information. Information, they say, is key. The philosophy behind the establishment, setting up and the consequent breaking of codes signifies the ultimate nature of how we are. It signifies the essence of humankind. It is in the nature of man to build and then eventually destroy, to construct and then ultimately deconstruct, only for a better possibility to be explored. Human nature tells us that nothing is truly unbreakable and that everything, which is part of human effort, can be brought down, thanks to humans themselves. Codes help us express ourselves in a niche manner, truly being an indication of the creativity and perseverance, we as humans, are able to display and put into effect.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Fleabag: A Tale of Clumsy Womanhood</title>
      <link href="/Fleabag" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fleabag: A Tale of Clumsy Womanhood" />
      <published>2019-07-12T16:30:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-12T16:30:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Fleabag</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Fleabag">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fleabag&lt;/em&gt;, a dark comedy, is a television show for every chaotic feminist out
there. It is a brutally honest account of a dysfunctional yet nonchalant woman,
who is clearly failing at life with her passive-aggressive family, dead business
and meaningless sexual relationships. The show, set in contemporary London,
speaks the mind of a modern woman through a feminist lens. Phoebe Waller-Bridge,
the writer of the show, also stars as the protagonist and plays her unnamed
character with utter brilliance, whom we call Fleabag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The viewers take a ride through Fleabag’s mind, quite literally, when she talks
to them by breaking the fourth wall. She, conceitedly, predicts the actions of
the people she meets and talks to her audience about it. In the very first
scene, she presumes exactly what is going to happen after she has sex with an
immensely attractive man, and does so throughout the series. She seems to
understand the routine behaviour of the men who she sleeps with, and is seldom
fascinated by them. As viewers, we do not see Fleabag’s story, we see Fleabag.
She is present in every scene of every episode and is almost constantly talking.
The audience is not provided with other characters’ stories, and Fleabag’s
encounters and perceptions form the plot of the entire series. In fact, a few
interesting events in the characters’ lives build up to form the narrative of a
rather bigger story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first episode, Fleabag and her sister, Claire, attend a feminist lecture,
the tickets of which were given to them by their father. Fleabag called this
“[her] dad’s way of coping with two motherless daughters”, who is now in a
relationship with their godmother and has minimised contact with them. The
lecturer asks the audience to “raise [their] hands if you would trade five years
of your life for the so-called perfect body”, to which the sisters promptly
raise their hands, followed by Fleabag calling themselves ‘bad feminists.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through a lot of instances in the show, we come to understand how Fleabag uses
sex to validate her own body and desirability, once even explicitly saying, “I
know that my body is the only thing I have left, and when that gets old and
unfuckable, I may as well kill it.” We later see how the complexities of
Fleabag’s anguish over the death of her mother and her best friend are
intertwined with her sexual encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Season 1 is an entry into the mayhem of Fleabag’s life, whereas season 2 is what
she calls her love story. Andrew Scott enters season 2 as &lt;em&gt;Sexy Priest&lt;/em&gt; and one
cannot take eyes off him. As Fleabag says ‘his arm’, ‘his beautiful neck’, ‘I
found myself pining &lt;em&gt;YES, YES, YES!&lt;/em&gt;’ But glass shatters, it’s not as much a
love story between Fleabag and ‘Sexy Priest’, as it is Fleabag’s
self-introspection and overcoming her disruptive behaviour. She learns to love
and to let go. Her cafe business thrives, and so does her relationship with
Claire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A magnificent scene in season 2, with guest star Kristin Scott Thomas, playing
the role of Belinda who wins an award for women in business, might just be the
monologue of the year, and will absolutely pierce through your heart. Belinda
says, “I was in an aeroplane the other day, and I realised – I’ve been longing
to say this out loud – women are born with pain built-in. It’s our physical
destiny. Period pain, sore boobs, childbirth, you know. We carry it within
ourselves throughout our lives.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Men don’t. They have to seek it out. They invent all these Gods and demons and
things just so they can feel guilty about things, which is something we do very
well on our own. Then they create wars so they can feel things and touch each
other, and when there aren’t any wars they can play rugby.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And we have it all going on in here, inside. We have pain on a cycle for years
and years and years. And then, just as you feel you’re making peace with it all,
what happens? The menopause comes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Men capitalise to feel alive, but women bring things to life. She protected even
when she suffered, while he created violence to be able to restore peace. Women
built walls to nurture, not to divide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an interview with &lt;em&gt;The Hollywood Reporter&lt;/em&gt;, Phoebe Waller-Bridge confirmed
that &lt;em&gt;Fleabag&lt;/em&gt; is not autobiographical. “A lot of the time when I was being
asked about the show, it was through the prism of feminism which was an
important part of the show for me…I just started feeling like I was suddenly
being moved into a different position that it wasn’t so much that I was a
writer, it was that I was a feminist writer, which of course I am, but that
becomes a category of writing”, added Phoebe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I would say, watch this for the love of clumsy womanhood, for learning to be
strong in this modern feminist world even when your entire life is crumbling
down. &lt;em&gt;Fleabag&lt;/em&gt; taught me that feminism is hope, even if its standards you
cannot seem to reach, and women (dead or alive) will be your strength.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Hrishita Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Fleabag, a dark comedy, is a television show for every chaotic feminist out there. It is a brutally honest account of a dysfunctional yet nonchalant woman, who is clearly failing at life with her passive-aggressive family, dead business and meaningless sexual relationships. The show, set in contemporary London, speaks the mind of a modern woman through a feminist lens. Phoebe Waller-Bridge, the writer of the show, also stars as the protagonist and plays her unnamed character with utter brilliance, whom we call Fleabag. The viewers take a ride through Fleabag’s mind, quite literally, when she talks to them by breaking the fourth wall. She, conceitedly, predicts the actions of the people she meets and talks to her audience about it. In the very first scene, she presumes exactly what is going to happen after she has sex with an immensely attractive man, and does so throughout the series. She seems to understand the routine behaviour of the men who she sleeps with, and is seldom fascinated by them. As viewers, we do not see Fleabag’s story, we see Fleabag. She is present in every scene of every episode and is almost constantly talking. The audience is not provided with other characters’ stories, and Fleabag’s encounters and perceptions form the plot of the entire series. In fact, a few interesting events in the characters’ lives build up to form the narrative of a rather bigger story. In the first episode, Fleabag and her sister, Claire, attend a feminist lecture, the tickets of which were given to them by their father. Fleabag called this “[her] dad’s way of coping with two motherless daughters”, who is now in a relationship with their godmother and has minimised contact with them. The lecturer asks the audience to “raise [their] hands if you would trade five years of your life for the so-called perfect body”, to which the sisters promptly raise their hands, followed by Fleabag calling themselves ‘bad feminists.’ Through a lot of instances in the show, we come to understand how Fleabag uses sex to validate her own body and desirability, once even explicitly saying, “I know that my body is the only thing I have left, and when that gets old and unfuckable, I may as well kill it.” We later see how the complexities of Fleabag’s anguish over the death of her mother and her best friend are intertwined with her sexual encounters. Season 1 is an entry into the mayhem of Fleabag’s life, whereas season 2 is what she calls her love story. Andrew Scott enters season 2 as Sexy Priest and one cannot take eyes off him. As Fleabag says ‘his arm’, ‘his beautiful neck’, ‘I found myself pining YES, YES, YES!’ But glass shatters, it’s not as much a love story between Fleabag and ‘Sexy Priest’, as it is Fleabag’s self-introspection and overcoming her disruptive behaviour. She learns to love and to let go. Her cafe business thrives, and so does her relationship with Claire. A magnificent scene in season 2, with guest star Kristin Scott Thomas, playing the role of Belinda who wins an award for women in business, might just be the monologue of the year, and will absolutely pierce through your heart. Belinda says, “I was in an aeroplane the other day, and I realised – I’ve been longing to say this out loud – women are born with pain built-in. It’s our physical destiny. Period pain, sore boobs, childbirth, you know. We carry it within ourselves throughout our lives.” “Men don’t. They have to seek it out. They invent all these Gods and demons and things just so they can feel guilty about things, which is something we do very well on our own. Then they create wars so they can feel things and touch each other, and when there aren’t any wars they can play rugby.” “And we have it all going on in here, inside. We have pain on a cycle for years and years and years. And then, just as you feel you’re making peace with it all, what happens? The menopause comes.” Men capitalise to feel alive, but women bring things to life. She protected even when she suffered, while he created violence to be able to restore peace. Women built walls to nurture, not to divide. In an interview with The Hollywood Reporter, Phoebe Waller-Bridge confirmed that Fleabag is not autobiographical. “A lot of the time when I was being asked about the show, it was through the prism of feminism which was an important part of the show for me…I just started feeling like I was suddenly being moved into a different position that it wasn’t so much that I was a writer, it was that I was a feminist writer, which of course I am, but that becomes a category of writing”, added Phoebe. So, I would say, watch this for the love of clumsy womanhood, for learning to be strong in this modern feminist world even when your entire life is crumbling down. Fleabag taught me that feminism is hope, even if its standards you cannot seem to reach, and women (dead or alive) will be your strength.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Review: ‘The Book of Ram’ by Devdutt Pattanaik</title>
      <link href="/The-Book-of-Ram" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review: 'The Book of Ram' by Devdutt Pattanaik" />
      <published>2019-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Book-of-Ram</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Book-of-Ram">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Book of Ram&lt;/em&gt; is the outcome of Pattanaik’s endeavour to weave magic into the timeless Indian epic tale of the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt;. As the title suggests, the book brings to light, the story of &lt;em&gt;Maryada Purushottam&lt;/em&gt; Ram, the seventh ‘avatar’ of Lord Vishnu (the one who nurtures and maintains balance in the worldly life), the scion of the Raghu clan, the worthy heir, the jewel of the Solar dynasty, the Prince and the Supreme Upholder of social norms and values, the warrior and the ideal king. The author admits that he felt compelled to write the book when he realised that the epic in question was being used as a tool to fuel anger, animosity, hatred, and violence. Pattanaik’s &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; is as informative as it is gripping and riveting. Pattanaik’s simple yet exceedingly well-written book explores the relevance of Shri Ram, the only Hindu deity to be worshipped as The King in the contemporary world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book very rightly portrays Lord Ram as ‘&lt;em&gt;Eka-Vachani&lt;/em&gt;’: A king who is always true to his words; ‘&lt;em&gt;Ek-bani&lt;/em&gt;’: a supreme archer who strikes his target with the first arrow, and ‘&lt;em&gt;Ek-Patni&lt;/em&gt;’: A man who is eternally devoted to one woman. Censured by feminists and appropriated by innumerable politicians, Ram still remains pious and serene in his majesty. Hindus firmly believe that in times of turmoil, by chanting Lord Ram’s name and his tales, one can achieve peace, stability, hope, and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pattanaik’s story is through the eyes of Sita, Ram’s wife and the avatar of Vishnu’s consort Lakshmi. The book glimpses through all the different versions of the revered epic starting from before the 1st century CE to the 19th century, including the versions popular in South East Asian cultures. The author meticulously shows the contrast between different mini &lt;em&gt;Ramayanas&lt;/em&gt;, ranging from Kamban’s &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; to Valmiki’s, from Maya Sita to Devi Sita. All these versions speak a different tale but eventually converge into a singular point that reflects the grandeur of the creator(s) and an ancient faith. It also becomes crucial to note that &lt;em&gt;Sanatan Dharma&lt;/em&gt; (Eternal Order, as so many Hindus refer to Hinduism) does not subscribe to the idea of differentiating between the male and the female along a strict line. Pattanaik makes the use of symbols, metaphors, patterns, and motifs to convey his message. The fact that Ram painstakingly fulfils his duty as a king and ultimately walks into the Sarayu river chanting Sita’s name to bring him solace, stands crucial. In the Indian context, a God is always accompanied by a Goddess, thus reflecting the need to maintain a balance between the two. The existence of &lt;em&gt;Adi Shakti&lt;/em&gt; (Primal Female Energy) points to the same and brings in a much-needed fluidity in modern society. Ram as a God is dependable and Sita as a Goddess is independent. Pattanaik asks, isn’t this what we all aspire to be, dependable but independent? The author scholastically delves into the spirit of the religious text. Rather than drawing superficial inferences from the literal aspects of the text, which has led to myriad misinterpretations from time immemorial, Pattanaik understands an important truth about the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt;, it is not about the words but the essence behind them. He also brings to light how the binary, didactic Abrahamic Western thought process has discredited the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; or, for that matter, all our religious texts by only taking into account the literal aspects of our vast literature and culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is crucial to note that parts of this epic and many other Hindu religious scriptures have been changed by authors, in accordance with the time they lived in and the perils that faced their society. Even in this book, Pattanaik admits to using his vivid imagination and thereby perpetuates the long-standing tradition of adding personal stories to the great epic. As a consequence, it becomes difficult for a lay reader to distinguish between the facts mentioned in the epic and those that have been woven into it by the author’s imagination. Even though this makes Pattanaik’s book slightly unscholarly it’s still not completely discreditable, for it only makes it a tad bit more Hindu in spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book also, very rightly, criticises the manipulation and distortion of religion by Hindu extremist groups. It gives out a message of peace and unity for achieving true &lt;em&gt;Ram Rajya&lt;/em&gt;, which is not restricted to a time or place but is to be found &lt;strong&gt;within&lt;/strong&gt;. To quote Pattanaik, “He [Ram] is our soul.” He criticises the modern education system for teaching one to respect only that which can be proved empirically. He provokes one to think of the debate between religion and science. He also makes a much-needed distinction between linear and cyclical history. However, the book adopts a very idealistic stand which is difficult to grasp in a modern materialistic world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindu religious scriptures tell us something crucial through its characters. Humans are made of conflicting truths; there isn’t either a positive side or a negative side to one, Pattanaik shows how one person can be a martyr, a villain, a hero, and a victim. Our books are about diverse human characters; humans of wisdom and of folly who are unpredictable and dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pattanaik also draws a parallel between Prince Ram and Lord Krishna. The epic, he rightly states, teaches us that a world governed only by law and not by emotions is not ideal. He talks about the supreme sacrifice made by Lord Ram and Goddess Sita to impart this lesson to a not-so-humane world. The strong, wise and independent hero, the warrior princess, Sita also fulfils her duties and departs leaving Ram on Earth to fulfill his kingly duty and return to the &lt;em&gt;Vaikuntha Loka&lt;/em&gt;, the abode of Vishnu where he sleeps on the Snake of Time, dreaming of creation. The epic, via its protagonist Shri Ram, thus imparts essential lessons of democracy and the beauty of living for people. It imparts valuable lessons of humanity also through King Ram’s character: His supreme uprightness in the face of the darkest of adversities offers peace, stability and hope to all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pattanaik stands by the statement that liberals today will find their perfect ally in Hindu thought and philosophy. The nonexistence of a Sanskrit word for blasphemy also points to the same. The book speaks of fluidity and inclusivity of the Hindu religion by talking about the acceptance of LGBTQ people in the social order, linking this fact back to Hinduism’s comfort with fluidity in its seemingly gendered motifs and totems. The book also states that in the Hindu religion, one’s &lt;em&gt;Karma&lt;/em&gt; (Action) is supreme and overshadows all else. The &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; is primarily a tale of emotions, be it filial affection, a sense of duty and loyalty, love, lust or malice. It also shows the ill outcome of ego, ambition, and arrogance. Thus, the retelling of the epic provokes profound thought, it expands one’s consciousness inspiring them to cultivate and realise one’s potential by overcoming the fallacies of human nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pattanaik’s &lt;em&gt;Book of Ram&lt;/em&gt; is a well-researched one. Simplifying the philosophical connotations, it can be said that the author believes that in each person there is a part of Ram-Sita, a Ravan, an Ahilya, a Mandodri or a Surupnakha. Human nature and destiny are determined by the part a human decides to give precedence to. Thus, in essence, it can be said, the Ramayana has never been a tale of Ram’s life. It has always been a tale of how Ram lived for others. Here, I am compelled to reiterate, that the interpretation of Ram’s character will invariably be an interpretation of one’s own character. Isn’t how we see others a reflection of how we see ourselves? Perhaps, the answer is best left untold!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Book of Ram is the outcome of Pattanaik’s endeavour to weave magic into the timeless Indian epic tale of the Ramayana. As the title suggests, the book brings to light, the story of Maryada Purushottam Ram, the seventh ‘avatar’ of Lord Vishnu (the one who nurtures and maintains balance in the worldly life), the scion of the Raghu clan, the worthy heir, the jewel of the Solar dynasty, the Prince and the Supreme Upholder of social norms and values, the warrior and the ideal king. The author admits that he felt compelled to write the book when he realised that the epic in question was being used as a tool to fuel anger, animosity, hatred, and violence. Pattanaik’s Ramayana is as informative as it is gripping and riveting. Pattanaik’s simple yet exceedingly well-written book explores the relevance of Shri Ram, the only Hindu deity to be worshipped as The King in the contemporary world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Turkish Diaries</title>
      <link href="/Turkish-Diaries" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Turkish Diaries" />
      <published>2019-07-06T14:40:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-06T14:40:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Turkish-Diaries</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Turkish-Diaries">&lt;p&gt;Before writing this piece, I had a couple of rather conflicting thoughts, that
made me resist the urge to write a personal account of my visit to Turkey. My
initial enthusiasm to pen down my extraordinary experience was soon met by a
greater impediment when I searched the internet to gather more information about
Turkey, as I will explain later. I would not have done justice to myself if I
would have written an article instead of a personal account. And so, I have
decided to shut down those thoughts and do what I wanted to do anyway, i.e. to
enlighten you about my journey, along with the aftermath, as it was in Turkey.
Nothing more and nothing less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turkey, one of the five countries to be a part of both Europe and Asia, was a
journey of a lifetime. Having visited five cities and towns over a course of
twelve days, I experienced breath-taking architecture (mosques, museums,
palaces, theatres and natural beauty), talked to Turks and ate traditional
Turkish delicacies. I consider myself to be in a position to form an opinion
about the country and its citizens. An Islamic country, where 99.8% of the
population follows Islam as its religion, Turkey was truly a blend of modernity
and cultural heritage, where people had accepted the reality of the modern era
while remaining true to their own roots. It rightfully stood in the middle
ground, embodying the qualities of both Europe and Asia. The country’s two
wonders of the ancient world: The Temple of Artemis and The Mausoleum of
Halicarnassus, its rich traditional architecture, a blend of Islam and
Christianity, was intellectually stimulating and visually captivating at the
same time. The cherry on top was the state-of-the-art infrastructure, pristine
surroundings, the technologically-advanced society and the open-minded people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a little hard to digest that an Islamic society can be so advanced and
modern, isn’t it? Turkey certainly broke the few stereotypes I might have had
against Muslims and reinforced the sense of respect I had for the religion.
There were some incidents that took place during the journey that compelled me
to think highly of Islam. In Islam, women are often expected to wear traditional
dresses (like burqa, hijab, niqab, etc.), look after the domestic chores, and
behave in a modest and polite way. However, men and women in Turkey wore western
attire; jeans and t-shirts among other dresses. In the entirety of my journey,
from a big city like Istanbul to a small town like Selcuk, I did not see more
than 20% of the women with headscarves, let alone garments fully covering their
body. The work culture was inclusive and women were financially independent. I
remember eating at restaurants and cafes where women waited tables, even at
night, a phenomenon uncommon in my supposedly more liberal home country, India.
Furthermore, unlike India, smoking in public was not considered a taboo in
Turkey and both men and women openly smoked in the streets. Although smoking
does not imply modernity, yet to experience it in an Islamic country is a big
deal.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was one incident that stood out from the rest and acted as an ‘inception’
for my exploration of the Islamic world. It was when I visited the Suleymaniye
Mosque in Istanbul, where a college student had volunteered to explain the
history of the mosque to visitors. While explaining the prayer pattern, he said
that women stood at the back during Namaz so as to ensure that men do not get
distracted during prayer. I found this absurd and initiated a discussion on the
point. My father was apprehensive that the discussion might turn into a heated
argument and tried to stop me. To this, the gentleman instantly replied, “I want
to hear her opinion. She (Muslim women, not me) is the disadvantaged one.” This
incident indicated both a positive as well as a negative point for Turkish
Islam: positive because the younger generations were open-minded and negative
because the religion put women in a position of disadvantage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To further my proposition, let us take a look at some statistics. According to
the Central Intelligence Agency of the USA, Turkey is a developed country and is
considered advanced in terms of infrastructure, technology, industrialisation,
per capita income and standards of living. For a better understanding of
Turkey’s economic and social situation, let us compare it with India:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turkey&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Male-Female percentage of population&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;49.1% - 50.9%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;51.8% - 48.2%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Population density&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;104.5 people/sq km&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;415.63 people/ sq km&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literacy Rate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;95.6%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;74.04%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Male literacy rate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;98%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;80.9%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Female literacy rate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;92%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;64.6%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quality of Life Index (Rank)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;44/70&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;52/70&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Population living in Urban areas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;70%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;33%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Source:&lt;/b&gt; World Population Review, 2019&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of some troublesome trends like rising unemployment and inflation, the
above statistics provide enough evidence that Turkey is a developed nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My curiosity to learn more about Turkish Islam and to uphold my findings led me
to collect pamphlets everywhere I went and undertake an in-depth search on the
internet. But, what I read online was in stark contrast to what I saw through my
eyes. I was appalled by the negative portrayal of Turkey in almost all of the
articles I read! All of them had some common themes: economic and political
instability, humanitarian crisis, disputes based on religion, and so on. I was
distressed to find out that a staggering 477 women were killed and another 232
injured at the hands of violent men in Turkey in 2018. It was only when one of
Turkey’s biggest pop stars Sıla Gencoglu filed abuse charges against her actor
boyfriend in 2018 that a media frenzy was set off, which sparked the
long-awaited national debate about violence against women. Furthermore, the
&lt;em&gt;Women in Statistics 2017&lt;/em&gt; report stated that only 28% of women above 15 years
of age were part of the Turkish labour force. These incidences reduced the
confidence I had in Turkish Islam. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthering my research, I found out that Turkey’s current President Recep Tayyip
Erdogan and his AK party have made the constitutionally secular country more
conservative and religious. The pro-Islamic authoritarian President aims to
raise a ‘pious generation’ and thus promotes the growth of state-funded
religious education in the country. Although the AK party claims to be secular,
it seeks to change the country’s laws to greater reflect its growing Muslim
identity. So, why did the modern people of Turkey elect Erdogan into power in
the first place? This is because, in the first decade of his rule starting from
2003, he initiated several rapid economic and democratic reforms in the country.
However, legal and democratic standards quickly deteriorated after 2013, and his
focus shifted to the promotion of Islam. As a result, people became fearful that
the President might slowly erase the line between Religion and the State, and
make Turkey a non-secular country, upsetting the great balance put in place by
the great Atatürk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These steps have received a backlash from the Turks, especially the younger
generation, and the level of piety has declined over the years, despite an
increase in religious education. There has been a significant drop in people
calling themselves ‘religious conservative’, from 32% in 2008 to 25% in 2018.
People who say they fast during the Muslim holy month of Ramadan declined from
77% to 65%. Figures for ‘nonbeliever’ and ‘atheist’, which had been barely
registered in 2008, increased to 2% and 3% respectively. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now comes the final question. Is Turkey a modern or a conservative Islamic
nation? The internet is full of Turkey’s past, which lost its way under
President Erdogan, both economically and socially. However, what I saw was
Turkey’s future, where the so-called ‘pious generation’ is changing course and
embracing people from all religions and backgrounds. There is no chance that the
AK party will come back to power in the next Parliamentary elections if it
continues with the same narrow mindset of making Turkey an Islamist nation. I
would urge the readers to develop a positive outlook towards Turkey, a country
adapting itself with the changing times while retaining its cultural heritage.
There’s more to this beautiful nation than what meets the internet!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sanjana Chandaliya</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Before writing this piece, I had a couple of rather conflicting thoughts, that made me resist the urge to write a personal account of my visit to Turkey. My initial enthusiasm to pen down my extraordinary experience was soon met by a greater impediment when I searched the internet to gather more information about Turkey, as I will explain later. I would not have done justice to myself if I would have written an article instead of a personal account. And so, I have decided to shut down those thoughts and do what I wanted to do anyway, i.e. to enlighten you about my journey, along with the aftermath, as it was in Turkey. Nothing more and nothing less. Turkey, one of the five countries to be a part of both Europe and Asia, was a journey of a lifetime. Having visited five cities and towns over a course of twelve days, I experienced breath-taking architecture (mosques, museums, palaces, theatres and natural beauty), talked to Turks and ate traditional Turkish delicacies. I consider myself to be in a position to form an opinion about the country and its citizens. An Islamic country, where 99.8% of the population follows Islam as its religion, Turkey was truly a blend of modernity and cultural heritage, where people had accepted the reality of the modern era while remaining true to their own roots. It rightfully stood in the middle ground, embodying the qualities of both Europe and Asia. The country’s two wonders of the ancient world: The Temple of Artemis and The Mausoleum of Halicarnassus, its rich traditional architecture, a blend of Islam and Christianity, was intellectually stimulating and visually captivating at the same time. The cherry on top was the state-of-the-art infrastructure, pristine surroundings, the technologically-advanced society and the open-minded people.  It’s a little hard to digest that an Islamic society can be so advanced and modern, isn’t it? Turkey certainly broke the few stereotypes I might have had against Muslims and reinforced the sense of respect I had for the religion. There were some incidents that took place during the journey that compelled me to think highly of Islam. In Islam, women are often expected to wear traditional dresses (like burqa, hijab, niqab, etc.), look after the domestic chores, and behave in a modest and polite way. However, men and women in Turkey wore western attire; jeans and t-shirts among other dresses. In the entirety of my journey, from a big city like Istanbul to a small town like Selcuk, I did not see more than 20% of the women with headscarves, let alone garments fully covering their body. The work culture was inclusive and women were financially independent. I remember eating at restaurants and cafes where women waited tables, even at night, a phenomenon uncommon in my supposedly more liberal home country, India. Furthermore, unlike India, smoking in public was not considered a taboo in Turkey and both men and women openly smoked in the streets. Although smoking does not imply modernity, yet to experience it in an Islamic country is a big deal.   There was one incident that stood out from the rest and acted as an ‘inception’ for my exploration of the Islamic world. It was when I visited the Suleymaniye Mosque in Istanbul, where a college student had volunteered to explain the history of the mosque to visitors. While explaining the prayer pattern, he said that women stood at the back during Namaz so as to ensure that men do not get distracted during prayer. I found this absurd and initiated a discussion on the point. My father was apprehensive that the discussion might turn into a heated argument and tried to stop me. To this, the gentleman instantly replied, “I want to hear her opinion. She (Muslim women, not me) is the disadvantaged one.” This incident indicated both a positive as well as a negative point for Turkish Islam: positive because the younger generations were open-minded and negative because the religion put women in a position of disadvantage.  To further my proposition, let us take a look at some statistics. According to the Central Intelligence Agency of the USA, Turkey is a developed country and is considered advanced in terms of infrastructure, technology, industrialisation, per capita income and standards of living. For a better understanding of Turkey’s economic and social situation, let us compare it with India: &amp;nbsp; Turkey India Male-Female percentage of population 49.1% - 50.9% 51.8% - 48.2% Population density 104.5 people/sq km 415.63 people/ sq km Literacy Rate 95.6% 74.04% Male literacy rate 98% 80.9% Female literacy rate 92% 64.6% Quality of Life Index (Rank) 44/70 52/70 Population living in Urban areas 70% 33% Source: World Population Review, 2019 In spite of some troublesome trends like rising unemployment and inflation, the above statistics provide enough evidence that Turkey is a developed nation. My curiosity to learn more about Turkish Islam and to uphold my findings led me to collect pamphlets everywhere I went and undertake an in-depth search on the internet. But, what I read online was in stark contrast to what I saw through my eyes. I was appalled by the negative portrayal of Turkey in almost all of the articles I read! All of them had some common themes: economic and political instability, humanitarian crisis, disputes based on religion, and so on. I was distressed to find out that a staggering 477 women were killed and another 232 injured at the hands of violent men in Turkey in 2018. It was only when one of Turkey’s biggest pop stars Sıla Gencoglu filed abuse charges against her actor boyfriend in 2018 that a media frenzy was set off, which sparked the long-awaited national debate about violence against women. Furthermore, the Women in Statistics 2017 report stated that only 28% of women above 15 years of age were part of the Turkish labour force. These incidences reduced the confidence I had in Turkish Islam.  Furthering my research, I found out that Turkey’s current President Recep Tayyip Erdogan and his AK party have made the constitutionally secular country more conservative and religious. The pro-Islamic authoritarian President aims to raise a ‘pious generation’ and thus promotes the growth of state-funded religious education in the country. Although the AK party claims to be secular, it seeks to change the country’s laws to greater reflect its growing Muslim identity. So, why did the modern people of Turkey elect Erdogan into power in the first place? This is because, in the first decade of his rule starting from 2003, he initiated several rapid economic and democratic reforms in the country. However, legal and democratic standards quickly deteriorated after 2013, and his focus shifted to the promotion of Islam. As a result, people became fearful that the President might slowly erase the line between Religion and the State, and make Turkey a non-secular country, upsetting the great balance put in place by the great Atatürk.  These steps have received a backlash from the Turks, especially the younger generation, and the level of piety has declined over the years, despite an increase in religious education. There has been a significant drop in people calling themselves ‘religious conservative’, from 32% in 2008 to 25% in 2018. People who say they fast during the Muslim holy month of Ramadan declined from 77% to 65%. Figures for ‘nonbeliever’ and ‘atheist’, which had been barely registered in 2008, increased to 2% and 3% respectively.  Now comes the final question. Is Turkey a modern or a conservative Islamic nation? The internet is full of Turkey’s past, which lost its way under President Erdogan, both economically and socially. However, what I saw was Turkey’s future, where the so-called ‘pious generation’ is changing course and embracing people from all religions and backgrounds. There is no chance that the AK party will come back to power in the next Parliamentary elections if it continues with the same narrow mindset of making Turkey an Islamist nation. I would urge the readers to develop a positive outlook towards Turkey, a country adapting itself with the changing times while retaining its cultural heritage. There’s more to this beautiful nation than what meets the internet!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Understanding Jihad</title>
      <link href="/Understanding-Jihad" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding Jihad" />
      <published>2019-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Understanding-Jihad</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-Jihad">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jihad&lt;/em&gt;; possibly the most polarising word in the Arabic language. It provokes a range of varied reactions, depending on the perspective through which one looks at it. And it is true to say that the word has largely been misunderstood in non-Muslim circles. So before I even begin said analysis, I must make a series of clarifications and preliminary disclaimers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, my article is not intended to be an attack upon the Muslim community. Nor is it meant to be a criticism of individual Muslims. Some of the most kind, brotherly and loving people I have met are devout practicing Muslims and I am grateful to God for their friendship. I also recognise that there are countless members of the Islamic &lt;em&gt;ummah&lt;/em&gt; who are peaceful and humane people, truly worthy of our respect as fellow human beings. My article is not meant to be an indictment of the entire Muslim people. Rather, my goal is to analyse the concept of &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt;, and how it has been understood by most of the mainstream Islamic schools of thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I recognise and mourn the tragedies and persecutions which Muslim people have had to endure. I condemn in no uncertain terms the attacks upon innocent Muslims that have taken place on account of their faith. No one should ever be harmed or attacked or despised or be held in suspicion simply for being a Muslim. Indeed, my goal is not to spread suspicion against Muslims. I invite all people to extend their arms wide open in welcome for their Muslim friends, neighbours and fellow human beings, especially to Muslim refugees in need, and to give them the love and the affection that we indeed owe them as fellow citizens of this Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, my criticisms will not apply to quite a few schools of thought in Islam. They do not apply, for example, to the Ahmadi Muslim Community, which I consider to be the most peaceful sect of Islam. Nor do they apply to the Ibadis, who have proven themselves to be very tolerant and welcoming, and regarding their theology I have little knowledge and have no wish to pontificate. My criticisms mostly apply to Sunni and Shia schools of thought, but even among them there are exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I do not pretend to be a scholar of Islam. I am merely an interested layperson. So take all my claims with a grain of salt. Fact-check them and see if they are correct. I write with little formal authority on the subject, but with the firmest of convictions that I am right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourthly, please don’t be surprised that the views I document, describe and criticise in this article are not held by many of the average Muslims. Laypeople of all religions are known to have a poor track record of understanding what their religion actually teaches, and it is not uncommon to see that at times the views of laypeople are significantly at variance with the views of their own religious leaders. A good example is seen among some ‘Catholics’ in North America, many of whom practice contraception and have no problem with abortion, both of which are strongly condemned by the leaders of the Church they belong to and claim to profess faith in. Similarly, many ‘Protestants’ in England and Northern Europe don’t even believe in a physical Resurrection anymore, a belief which is absolutely central to historic Protestant orthodoxy. The views of laypeople are rarely barometers for the beliefs of the religion they follow, though, of course, there are exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all that said, let us press on the main subject matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you are me and you hail from a liberal background and you’ve had the same experience I’ve had, one of the first things you would have heard about Islam – especially from Westernised non-Muslim liberals – is how wonderful it truly is. You would have been told that Islam promotes peace, harmony, cultural diversity, coexistence and the emancipation of women. You would even have been informed that the word ‘Islam’ has its roots in a word which means ‘peace’. And, of course, you would have been told that the word ‘jihad’ does not mean ‘terrorism’ or ‘holy war’ but rather ‘struggle’. And don’t we all struggle against something or the other, especially against the faults in our own personality?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, much of these claims are true, to some degree or the other. However, the problem is that this narrative, although it certainly has a grain of truth, does not tell the whole story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is true that ‘jihad’ does not mean ‘terrorism’ or ‘violence’ but ‘struggle’. But what many people aren’t told is that the ‘struggle’ in Islam is not merely against personal faults, but also against injustice in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, some of you might be wondering, “Well, what’s wrong with that? Surely, we all have a duty to fight injustice?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem, of course, is not that Islam exhorts war against injustice. The issue, however, is how Islam defines injustice. And injustice, in the Islamic context, is quite different from the SJW conception of ‘injustice’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Islamic word for this is &lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt;. It literally means ‘corruption’ or ‘rottenness’. Consider, for instance, the following passage from the Quran, which talks about people who promote &lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;When they are told, ‘Do not cause corruption on the earth,’ they say, ‘We are only reformers!’
Look! They are themselves the agents of corruption, but they are not aware.”&lt;/em&gt; (Quran 2:11-12).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To whom does this passage refer? To corruption in general? To things like stealing, murder, adultery, etc., which most human beings would agree are corrupt deeds? No doubt, in Islam, these things are certainly sinful and are also part of corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in the context of this particular passage, the corruption refers not to sin in general, but very specifically to the sin of unbelief. Here’s what the preceding five verses say. I have added some emphasis to bring out the major themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As for the &lt;strong&gt;faithless&lt;/strong&gt;, it is the same to them whether you warn them or do not warn them, &lt;strong&gt;they will not have faith&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allah has set a seal on their hearts and their hearing, and there is a blindfold on their sight, and there is a great punishment for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And among the people are those who say, ‘We have faith in Allah and the Last Day,’ but &lt;strong&gt;they have no faith&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They seek to deceive Allah and those who have faith, yet they deceive no one but themselves, but they are not aware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sickness in their hearts; then Allah increased their sickness, and there is a painful punishment for them &lt;strong&gt;because of the lies they used to tell.&lt;/strong&gt;” (Quran 2:6-10)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this passage is condemning a very specific form of &lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt; – the sin of &lt;em&gt;kufr&lt;/em&gt; or unbelief, and the telling of lies based upon this &lt;em&gt;kufr&lt;/em&gt;. The word &lt;em&gt;kufr&lt;/em&gt; is the one from which comes the word &lt;em&gt;kafir&lt;/em&gt; or non-believer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the point even clearer, here is what the Quranic passage says right after verse 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;And when they are told, ‘Believe like the people who have believed,’ they say, &lt;strong&gt;‘Shall we believe like the fools who have believed?’&lt;/strong&gt; Look! They are themselves the fools, but they do not know.
When they meet the faithful, they say, ‘We believe,’ &lt;strong&gt;but when they are alone with their devils, they say, ‘We are with you; we were only deriding [them].&lt;/strong&gt;’
It is Allah who derides them, and leaves them bewildered in their rebellion.&lt;/em&gt;” (Quran 2:13-15).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So not only is the passage condemning a particular form of &lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt; (corruption) – &lt;em&gt;kufr&lt;/em&gt; (unbelief) – it is condemning a very specific kind of &lt;em&gt;kufr&lt;/em&gt;: the sin of pretending to be a Muslim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As noted before, Islam places a lot of emphasis upon justice (&lt;em&gt;adl&lt;/em&gt;). Striving to achieve justice is a virtue in Islam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, once more, the simple fact is that justice is defined very differently in Islam from the way a liberal might understand justice. Justice in Islam is, to put it simply, &lt;em&gt;Islam itself&lt;/em&gt;, and anything which detracts from Islam or diverges from Islam is, in some sense, to varying degrees, injustice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the struggle (&lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt;) against corruption (&lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt;) in order to achieve justice (&lt;em&gt;adl&lt;/em&gt;) is nothing more and nothing less than a struggle to achieve the triumph of Islam, in every sphere of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, there are different kinds of &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt; in Islam. And there are many interpretations of jihad. Hardly any of these interpretations are pacifistic, but not all of them are hyper-militaristic. Let’s stop there for a moment and consider some important facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Islamic theology and jurisprudence are based upon the Quran (believed to be the Word of God) and the Sunnah (the path of the Prophet). The latter is known from the various &lt;em&gt;hadith&lt;/em&gt;. These are narrations, orally transmitted across several centuries, which relate stories about or quotations from the Prophet and/or his family (the &lt;em&gt;Ahlul Bayt&lt;/em&gt;) and/or his companions. Sunnis and Shias have different Hadith collections. The Sunnis have the six books, chief among them being Sahih Bukhari and Sahih Muslim. The Shias have the Kitab-al-Kafi and three others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all hadith are uncritically accepted. Some are strong (that is, believed to be reliable narrations). Others are thought weak and unreliable. And contradictions among them abound, thereby producing a variety of schools of thought and interpretations thereof. Generally speaking, however, there are three main classifications of &lt;em&gt;hadith&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;em&gt;sahih&lt;/em&gt; (authentic), &lt;em&gt;hasan&lt;/em&gt; (good) and &lt;em&gt;da’if&lt;/em&gt; (weak). &lt;em&gt;Sahih&lt;/em&gt; is the highest epithet that can be applied to a hadith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Islamic theology about &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt; comes from the Quran. But the Quran is not written like other books. For one, it is not arranged chronologically in the order in which it was written. The first chapter of the Quran that was allegedly revealed to Muhammad was Chapter 96, &lt;em&gt;Surah Al-Alaq&lt;/em&gt;. Even the different passages in the Quran were sometimes revealed at different times and in very specific contexts. All of these are haphazard in arrangement. This can be seen especially in &lt;em&gt;Surah Maryam&lt;/em&gt;, in which several Biblical prophets are mentioned, but in a mixed up order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why on the one hand you have passages which seem to call for peace and others which seem to urge violence. Unless we want to affirm that the author(s) of the Quran was/were confused, we must realise that there is great ambiguity in understanding the intent, purposes and context of these conflicting verses. Some scholars even say that if commands in the Quran contradict, the one which was revealed later repeals the one which came before. This interpretation is quite common and well-known among scholars in the Muslim world (though not, thankfully, universally accepted) and is itself based upon a Quranic verse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Whatever communications We abrogate or cause to be forgotten, We bring one better than it or like it. Do you not know that Allah has power over all things?&lt;/em&gt;” (Quran 2:106)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with this interpretation, of course, is that many of the violent passages seem to have popped up at a later date than the more peaceful ones, according to Islam’s own sources! If this interpretation is to be followed, we would perhaps have to adopt a more violent form of Islam, because the more militaristic-sounding verses would then repeal the more peaceful and tolerant-sounding ones and become, as David Wood says, “the final marching orders” of that religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, of course, interpretations are manifold and varied. As stated before, while &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt; is an integral part of Islam, it is certainly true that not every school of thought takes a hyper-militaristic view of it. In many schools, &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt; is non-violent for the most part. However, once &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt; becomes successful and Islam gains dominance in society, a different picture emerges. Most of the mainstream Islamic schools of jurisprudence affirm that if Islam manages to take hold of a society, it should become the state religion and the entire country – both Muslims and non-Muslims - should be governed according to the law of Allah. It is now that the persecution of minorities becomes almost inescapable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider for instance what is considered one of the most peaceful verses in the Quran:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;On that account: We ordained for the Children of Israel that if any one slew a person - unless it be for murder or for spreading mischief in the land - it would be as if he slew the whole people: and if any one saved a life, it would be as if he saved the life of the whole people.&lt;/em&gt;” (Qur’an 5:32)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberals often cite this verse as an evidence of the peaceful and tolerant nature of Islam, but what they fail to understand is that “spreading mischief in the land” (the word originally used in Arabic, again, is &lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt;) means a whole host of things in Islam, and many Islamic scholars and theologians would gladly agree that insulting the religion, mocking the prophet or preaching other religions to Muslims is a part of &lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt;. In other words, rather than being an exhortation to promote equality and egalitarianism as some silly liberals vainly imagine, the exhortation would actually justify the killing and/or incarceration of Christian missionaries who preach Christianity in Muslim lands!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another good example is the case of apostasy. What if there is a Muslim who has lost faith and wishes to leave the &lt;em&gt;ummah&lt;/em&gt;? Here again, the Islamic testimony seems contradictory. Qur’an 2:256 literally states that there is ‘no compulsion in religion’. For many ears, this sounds pretty peaceful. However, can this text be applied to apostates, or does it refer only to the non-Muslim embracing Islam (for the first time)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain &lt;em&gt;hadith&lt;/em&gt; seem to indicate that it is the latter. Consider for instance the following citation from Sahih Bukhari, one of the most respected Sunni Hadith collections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Narrated Abdullah:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allah’s Messenger said, “The blood of a Muslim who confesses that none has the right to be worshipped but Allah and that I am His Apostle, cannot be shed except in three cases: In Qisas for murder, a married person who commits illegal sexual intercourse and the one who reverts from Islam (apostate) and leaves the Muslims.” Sahih Bukhari 9:83:17&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar Hadith are also found in Sahih Muslim 16:4152 and 4154. And all three of these &lt;em&gt;hadith&lt;/em&gt; are considered authentic (&lt;em&gt;sahih&lt;/em&gt;) which, as stated earlier, is the highest epithet that can be given to a &lt;em&gt;hadith&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As noted before, the evidence seems ambiguous and difficult to interpret. However, historically, most of the major Islamic schools of jurisprudence have indeed advocated the death penalty for apostasy. Even a peaceful liberal Muslim who interprets the texts in a different way cannot deny this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once one understands this, one will realise why Muslim countries tend to be more religiously intolerant than non-Muslim countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is true that many Muslim scholars and theologians advocate a non-violent form of Jihad which mostly involves prayer, memorising the Quran, fasting and preaching Islam in a peaceful, non-coercive manner. However, once Islam gains dominance and a large portion of the population has embraced the faith, most schools of jurisprudence would gladly advocate the setting up of an Islamic state. And one need only look at the Middle East to see what that would be like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One must also realise that Islam is quite stringently theocratic. Except in certain less influential schools of thought, setting up a religious state is always considered the ideal. The only thing is, setting up an Islamic state is not always possible for Muslims, especially in lands where Islam has little influence. It is only in these settings that puritanical Muslims advocate secularism. The separation of mosque and state is always considered a compromise by the mainstream schools of jurisprudence, never the ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideal is always an Islamic state. And all jihad – even the most peaceful forms of it – is ultimately meant to accomplish the ideal. And I will only leave the reader to contemplate the ominous implications that entails.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Jihad; possibly the most polarising word in the Arabic language. It provokes a range of varied reactions, depending on the perspective through which one looks at it. And it is true to say that the word has largely been misunderstood in non-Muslim circles. So before I even begin said analysis, I must make a series of clarifications and preliminary disclaimers.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Celebrating Darkness Through Style: Yami Kawaii</title>
      <link href="/Celebrating-Darkness-Through-Style" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Celebrating Darkness Through Style: Yami Kawaii" />
      <published>2019-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Celebrating-Darkness-Through-Style</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Celebrating-Darkness-Through-Style">&lt;p&gt;The streets of Harajuku have witnessed it all; the shifts, blends and twists that have gone into making Japan’s street fashion what it is today. As part of one of the world’s most exciting fashion capitals, Tokyo, Harajuku’s streets have given birth to diverse fashion trends, which stem from an interplay of western elements and unique individual tastes. With a splendid array of authentic styles, characterised by heavy accessorisation and experimentation, Harajuku has garnered attention from designers worldwide. The youth of Harajuku, in particular, has begun creating a free space of expression for themselves through the clothes they don. Vibrant and quirky, the Harajuku youth culture, both as a trend in fashion and a lifestyle reflects the constant struggle to break free from mainstream culture, which is marked by order and discipline and leaves little space for people to play with their style and fashion choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world’s obsession with &lt;em&gt;kawaii&lt;/em&gt; (meaning cute) is not new and with growing fame, &lt;em&gt;kawaii&lt;/em&gt; has expanded beyond Hello Kitty products and plushies (which as a matter of fact draw their inspiration from fierce beasts!) to enter the world of fashion. As phrases like “&lt;em&gt;that’s so kawaii!&lt;/em&gt;” emerged, adolescents embraced styles that gave them an innocent, childlike air. Against the backdrop of Japan’s mental health crisis and a cultural unwillingness to speak about it, some even went a step ahead to give their own twist to the idea of kawaii. Thus emerged a new look in the streets of Harajuku, called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;yami kawaii&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Literally translating to ‘sick cute’, yami kawaii wasn’t the normal, conventional kawaii. Something dark and profound pervaded it. It dealt with sickness, a sickness that even though plagued the whole of Japan was one that nobody was and is still ready to talk about. It dealt with depression and suicide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By fusion of the cute and the dark, yami kawaii produced fashion of a freakish nature, involving soft pastels and anime juxtaposed with guns, syringes, bandages. Underneath the facade of kawaii, the tshirts illustrated chilling messages such as ‘Kill You’, ‘I want to die’ and ‘F*ck You’. What makes such fashion intense is not the frightening imagery that it employs but the implication that underlies that imagery; these clothes were a desperate last resort for people to express themselves, an attempt at catharsis of a deep, deep pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Menhera Chan, a manga character, came to be seen as an important figure in the yami kawaii movement. This is primarily because Menhera chan is different from other manga characters. She has a dark cynical vibe to her, her arms are bandaged, she carries a blade with her and harms herself, she is anxious and depressed. Her despair and agony are what make her a strangely relatable figure to countless others, who experience a similar pain but have to shroud it with their silence. They see her as the personification of the feelings and desires buried in the depths of their hearts, a therapeutic mechanism to pour out the pain of hiding the miserable state they’re in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uncannily enough, yami kawaii has opened doors for a healthy dialogue in a society where profession and education overwhelmingly dictate every aspect of an individual’s life, where seeking help in order to tackle mental illness is still labelled a weakness. In the difficulty of having to reshape one’s life during the hard times, expression seems the only recourse, something that yami kawaii offers as a style. This, however, is not to be misunderstood as the glorification of suicide or depression. Personally, I find this style to be emboldening, simply because it marks a dissent from the ongoing discourse that reeks of bigotry and seeks to forbid individuals from expressing what they truly feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With negativity looming over the topic of mental health (which again, is partly responsible for the lack of dialogue) one remains fettered to live a life of lies. Constantly in the shackles of keeping up appearances, one has to project oneself as something they’re not. Those unable to take it anymore, seek their emancipation in suicide. Against the stifling expectations of society, where abiding by rules and etiquette are a must, yami kawaii offers a way out to people, in the form of catharsis. Yami kawaii gives a release to the inner turbulence they experience while helping one connect with others who feel the same way. It possesses a healing power of sorts, alleviating all those enduring the pain of masking their true feelings and enabling their style to speak for them. This makes yami kawaii empowering, fostering a new hope in the world for greater acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using fashion as an instrument of their liberation, the youngsters of Harajuku have certainly begun to lay down the foundations of change, to break silence against this raging catastrophe. By providing an outlet to vent complex emotions through style, an embodiment of the self, they seek to urge others who are suffering like them to join this movement towards self-love. Yami kawaii tells one and all that they have nothing to hide and nothing to fear. Bold and beautiful, these youths, go about announcing their identity in the streets of Harajuku.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The streets of Harajuku have witnessed it all; the shifts, blends and twists that have gone into making Japan’s street fashion what it is today. As part of one of the world’s most exciting fashion capitals, Tokyo, Harajuku’s streets have given birth to diverse fashion trends, which stem from an interplay of western elements and unique individual tastes. With a splendid array of authentic styles, characterised by heavy accessorisation and experimentation, Harajuku has garnered attention from designers worldwide. The youth of Harajuku, in particular, has begun creating a free space of expression for themselves through the clothes they don. Vibrant and quirky, the Harajuku youth culture, both as a trend in fashion and a lifestyle reflects the constant struggle to break free from mainstream culture, which is marked by order and discipline and leaves little space for people to play with their style and fashion choices.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Martin Scorsese and The American Dream</title>
      <link href="/Martin-Scorsese-and-The-American-Dream" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Martin Scorsese and The American Dream" />
      <published>2019-06-16T23:13:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-16T23:13:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Martin-Scorsese-and-The-American-Dream</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Martin-Scorsese-and-The-American-Dream">&lt;p&gt;(Spoilers ahead for &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other day, I was looking at reviews of &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;, a film
that I love a lot. Upon noticing a lot of negative comments I decided to rewatch
it and watching it reminded me of why I loved that film so much; not because of
how the film manages to spill excess into every scene, but because of how in the
midst of it all, a message lies hidden. The same message that Martin Scorsese
has always tried to illustrate throughout his filmography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scorsese loves to show the downfall of the Man in the high castle. Be it
&lt;em&gt;Goodfellas&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Raging Bull&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;The Aviator&lt;/em&gt;, and this 3-hour debauchery act
that I’ll be focusing on primarily, Scorsese focuses quite a lot on male ego.
What ties his stories together is how his characters’ life choices are
influenced by their dreamland. In other words, the protagonists in all of his
movies and shows wanted to live the &lt;em&gt;American Dream&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;America has always been seen as a land of opportunity. Throughout the history of
the USA, one can observe immigrants from various European countries finding a
place in this glorious nation to make a living. It continues even today, as seen
in students coming from all over the world to America to study or in Silicon
Valley, where a sizeable percentage of the workforce is of quasi-American
heritage, that too only by a generation or so. The immigrants’ aim to get a
coveted degree, a top job at a quant firm or under a tech mogul, or to kickstart
their venture into a high-life which they always wanted. Microsoft is headed by
an Indian today, Facebook was founded by multiple Jewish-Americans with other
mixed heritages, and these are just the biggest examples in a vast sea of such
cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the kicker: America hasn’t necessarily been kind to a lot of outsiders.
The cases in the limelight were stories of success that create a narrative that
you could be anyone, you could be dirt poor, but you’ll always find a way to
make something out of the land of the brave and the free. But in reality, one’s
likelihood to succeed is rigged by factors such as race and appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early 20th century, there was mass immigration of Italians to America.
Many of them were very poor and lived in neighbourhoods characterised by
poverty. Gradually, they grew out of it but, initially, life was rather too
hard. They were involved in low-paying blue-collar jobs, had difficulty
adjusting to their surroundings as they faced issues like the inability to speak
English and considerable discrimination during World War II by the US
government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the face of such adversity, the definition of the American Dream had become
slightly skewed. It became an end in itself and the means to attain it was left
open to a fair extent. This is where my example of Italian-Americans comes in
(I’m well aware that this could be advancing a stereotypical narrative about
them which is not my intention, but nonetheless, it surely is a sociological
factor). In Italy, the institution of family was very important, to the extent
that they would do anything to protect and advance the interests of their own
kind. Italian-Americans organized themselves in places like New York, and
created communities around them where they had control over the socio-economic
conditions of their people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This particular example of Italian-Americans is pertinent because of Scorsese’s
focus on it. &lt;em&gt;Goodfellas&lt;/em&gt; is a movie about how Italian gangsters in New York
made their profession look cool and aspirational around their neighbourhood;
their display of power enticed anybody who wanted to make the American Dream a
reality. The idea of a family also becomes important here; Henry Hill had said
that being an Italian mobster was better than being the President of the United
States of America because of how relaxed these mobsters are. They have shady but
steady sources of income, and no one to trouble them. The reason I can see
behind this is that the Italian mobster feels no responsibility towards others.
With this, the idea of the American Dream shifted from making use of the
opportunity to succeed in the land of the American Dream without responsibility
towards anyone or anything at all, at least for those who feel the need to
resort to illegitimate means, even if in limited quantities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; exemplifies that philosophy to perfection. Leading a
normal life is a frustrating ordeal for Jordan Belfort. It all begins with one
morally ambiguous choice. Jordan Belfort started selling stocks of companies
that were not financially sound enough to get themselves listed on a legitimate
stock exchange. He overlooked the fact that consumers might be adversely
affected by such a deal with the misguided assurance that every company makes
profits in the long run! Belfort has sex with everyone but his wife. She won’t
find out, problem sorted! &lt;em&gt;Goodfellas&lt;/em&gt; advances its story in the same vein;
let’s bribe the cops, so everyone is happy. People get what they want, if only
they put in the ‘effort’ to acquire it. So, everything could be hacked. But all
of it becomes a problem when you want more, or when you find the need to sustain
that lifestyle. You get sucked in, and you can’t find a way out. Stockbroking
was a highly focused job that requires one to remain calm at all times.
Substance usage provided that enhanced ability. Promiscuous sex provided the
relief after. Home life provided the anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;, this conception of the American Dream was most
magnified when money-crazed kids read a &lt;em&gt;Forbes&lt;/em&gt; piece that was actually critical
of Jordan Belfort and decided to join his firm, Stratton Oakmont. Drugs, women,
capital, a need for the high life. It was everything that an average American
male needed; a break from the monotony of merely existing and working an
unexciting job to feel larger than life. The middle-class could now profit off
of the impulsiveness of the 1%, which was what Leonardo DiCaprio’s character
initially set out to do. In part, this obsession can be attributed to the huge
amounts of investment flowing through the economy, and mass media like the
Michael Douglas-starrer &lt;em&gt;Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; glorifying the “greed is good” image. With
corporate raiders gaining infamy on the scene, the market being generally
bullish, and huge leveraged buyouts being made (case in point being RJR
Nabisco), Wall Street was a party. What is more interesting is that you could be
a college dropout, an illiterate beggar, and Wall Street will still let you make
your own fortune. That was where the appeal lay; selling is an art that can be
learned irrespective of where you are in life. It primarily became a game of
convincing American citizens that they wanted to shift their capital elsewhere,
without holding any responsibility for their investments in the future. And why
not this game? It was a comparatively easy and a quick way to make money. “Sell
me a pen” became quotable as a line later on, because it was an exhibition of
the idea that doing this much was enough to signify one’s potential for success,
the main determinant of which was wealth. The product was not necessarily the
seller’s own, he/she was just a middleman who won a fat commission on each sale.
No responsibility, no accountability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He did not just have this art of selling people things they didn’t want. What
Jordan Belfort was most successful at was selling the perfect life to his
employees. In the scene where he makes the motivational speech before the Steve
Madden IPO, he draws a contrast between the women that men desire (“with big
voluptuous tits”), and the women that are “disgusting wildebeests with three
days of razor stubble”. That was his best sale ever, not the penny stocks that
were essentially scams. What Scorsese really wanted to show here was how toxic
masculinity began to shape the American Dream, mainly by saying that money can
buy everything, including your happiness. One may argue that Belfort knew that
it was all a crime, so he could have backed out by striking a deal with the FBI
when they offered him a back door. But no, he felt too attached to this baby of
his; this company that he had started from scratch after a disastrous stock
market crash had left him unemployed. A parallel to this could be how attached
&lt;em&gt;Breaking Bad’s&lt;/em&gt; Walter White felt for his Baby Blue - his meth empire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Departed&lt;/em&gt; contains streaks of this American Dream. The opening lines of
Jack Nicholson’s crazed, senile Irish gangster character says that he wants his
environment to be a product of him, and not the other way round. He criticises
the Afro-American community, calling them the N-word, saying that they were
where they were because they could never “take it”. Nobody would give it to
them. This idea of carving out your own environment to survive, no matter how
illegitimate, defined the American Dream as presented in Scorsese’s films. It is
safe to say that as the son of Americans with Italian heritage himself, he has
seen the dream suck people into an abyss. This is not to say he doesn’t thank
America for being so kind to him; &lt;em&gt;Gangs of New York&lt;/em&gt; was a celebration of that.
However, the thought of taking matters into one’s own hands became such an
obsession for Americans that it eventually led to the downfall of prominent,
wealthy people. They may have started from the bottom, but they definitely
forgot their roots because that was always their intention. No one wants to
remember painful beginnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martin Scorsese has always evoked extreme reactions from his viewers. The
surface viewer might just think that &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; was a 3-hour
grossed-out porno-comedy without any message. That person misses a lot of the
important shots that convey a deeper meaning, like that of the federal agent
tasked with bringing Belfort to justice or shots of dull-faced middle-class
people in a metro train. According to the film, the federal agent wanted to be a
broker sometime in the past. And despite nailing such a huge arrest, he felt
empty inside. He could never live the life Belfort did, even when he had the
choice to. All it remained for him was a dream.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pranav Manie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">(Spoilers ahead for The Wolf of Wall Street). The other day, I was looking at reviews of The Wolf of Wall Street, a film that I love a lot. Upon noticing a lot of negative comments I decided to rewatch it and watching it reminded me of why I loved that film so much; not because of how the film manages to spill excess into every scene, but because of how in the midst of it all, a message lies hidden. The same message that Martin Scorsese has always tried to illustrate throughout his filmography. Scorsese loves to show the downfall of the Man in the high castle. Be it Goodfellas, Raging Bull or The Aviator, and this 3-hour debauchery act that I’ll be focusing on primarily, Scorsese focuses quite a lot on male ego. What ties his stories together is how his characters’ life choices are influenced by their dreamland. In other words, the protagonists in all of his movies and shows wanted to live the American Dream. America has always been seen as a land of opportunity. Throughout the history of the USA, one can observe immigrants from various European countries finding a place in this glorious nation to make a living. It continues even today, as seen in students coming from all over the world to America to study or in Silicon Valley, where a sizeable percentage of the workforce is of quasi-American heritage, that too only by a generation or so. The immigrants’ aim to get a coveted degree, a top job at a quant firm or under a tech mogul, or to kickstart their venture into a high-life which they always wanted. Microsoft is headed by an Indian today, Facebook was founded by multiple Jewish-Americans with other mixed heritages, and these are just the biggest examples in a vast sea of such cases. Here’s the kicker: America hasn’t necessarily been kind to a lot of outsiders. The cases in the limelight were stories of success that create a narrative that you could be anyone, you could be dirt poor, but you’ll always find a way to make something out of the land of the brave and the free. But in reality, one’s likelihood to succeed is rigged by factors such as race and appearance. In the early 20th century, there was mass immigration of Italians to America. Many of them were very poor and lived in neighbourhoods characterised by poverty. Gradually, they grew out of it but, initially, life was rather too hard. They were involved in low-paying blue-collar jobs, had difficulty adjusting to their surroundings as they faced issues like the inability to speak English and considerable discrimination during World War II by the US government. In the face of such adversity, the definition of the American Dream had become slightly skewed. It became an end in itself and the means to attain it was left open to a fair extent. This is where my example of Italian-Americans comes in (I’m well aware that this could be advancing a stereotypical narrative about them which is not my intention, but nonetheless, it surely is a sociological factor). In Italy, the institution of family was very important, to the extent that they would do anything to protect and advance the interests of their own kind. Italian-Americans organized themselves in places like New York, and created communities around them where they had control over the socio-economic conditions of their people. This particular example of Italian-Americans is pertinent because of Scorsese’s focus on it. Goodfellas is a movie about how Italian gangsters in New York made their profession look cool and aspirational around their neighbourhood; their display of power enticed anybody who wanted to make the American Dream a reality. The idea of a family also becomes important here; Henry Hill had said that being an Italian mobster was better than being the President of the United States of America because of how relaxed these mobsters are. They have shady but steady sources of income, and no one to trouble them. The reason I can see behind this is that the Italian mobster feels no responsibility towards others. With this, the idea of the American Dream shifted from making use of the opportunity to succeed in the land of the American Dream without responsibility towards anyone or anything at all, at least for those who feel the need to resort to illegitimate means, even if in limited quantities. The Wolf of Wall Street exemplifies that philosophy to perfection. Leading a normal life is a frustrating ordeal for Jordan Belfort. It all begins with one morally ambiguous choice. Jordan Belfort started selling stocks of companies that were not financially sound enough to get themselves listed on a legitimate stock exchange. He overlooked the fact that consumers might be adversely affected by such a deal with the misguided assurance that every company makes profits in the long run! Belfort has sex with everyone but his wife. She won’t find out, problem sorted! Goodfellas advances its story in the same vein; let’s bribe the cops, so everyone is happy. People get what they want, if only they put in the ‘effort’ to acquire it. So, everything could be hacked. But all of it becomes a problem when you want more, or when you find the need to sustain that lifestyle. You get sucked in, and you can’t find a way out. Stockbroking was a highly focused job that requires one to remain calm at all times. Substance usage provided that enhanced ability. Promiscuous sex provided the relief after. Home life provided the anxiety. In The Wolf of Wall Street, this conception of the American Dream was most magnified when money-crazed kids read a Forbes piece that was actually critical of Jordan Belfort and decided to join his firm, Stratton Oakmont. Drugs, women, capital, a need for the high life. It was everything that an average American male needed; a break from the monotony of merely existing and working an unexciting job to feel larger than life. The middle-class could now profit off of the impulsiveness of the 1%, which was what Leonardo DiCaprio’s character initially set out to do. In part, this obsession can be attributed to the huge amounts of investment flowing through the economy, and mass media like the Michael Douglas-starrer Wall Street glorifying the “greed is good” image. With corporate raiders gaining infamy on the scene, the market being generally bullish, and huge leveraged buyouts being made (case in point being RJR Nabisco), Wall Street was a party. What is more interesting is that you could be a college dropout, an illiterate beggar, and Wall Street will still let you make your own fortune. That was where the appeal lay; selling is an art that can be learned irrespective of where you are in life. It primarily became a game of convincing American citizens that they wanted to shift their capital elsewhere, without holding any responsibility for their investments in the future. And why not this game? It was a comparatively easy and a quick way to make money. “Sell me a pen” became quotable as a line later on, because it was an exhibition of the idea that doing this much was enough to signify one’s potential for success, the main determinant of which was wealth. The product was not necessarily the seller’s own, he/she was just a middleman who won a fat commission on each sale. No responsibility, no accountability. He did not just have this art of selling people things they didn’t want. What Jordan Belfort was most successful at was selling the perfect life to his employees. In the scene where he makes the motivational speech before the Steve Madden IPO, he draws a contrast between the women that men desire (“with big voluptuous tits”), and the women that are “disgusting wildebeests with three days of razor stubble”. That was his best sale ever, not the penny stocks that were essentially scams. What Scorsese really wanted to show here was how toxic masculinity began to shape the American Dream, mainly by saying that money can buy everything, including your happiness. One may argue that Belfort knew that it was all a crime, so he could have backed out by striking a deal with the FBI when they offered him a back door. But no, he felt too attached to this baby of his; this company that he had started from scratch after a disastrous stock market crash had left him unemployed. A parallel to this could be how attached Breaking Bad’s Walter White felt for his Baby Blue - his meth empire. The Departed contains streaks of this American Dream. The opening lines of Jack Nicholson’s crazed, senile Irish gangster character says that he wants his environment to be a product of him, and not the other way round. He criticises the Afro-American community, calling them the N-word, saying that they were where they were because they could never “take it”. Nobody would give it to them. This idea of carving out your own environment to survive, no matter how illegitimate, defined the American Dream as presented in Scorsese’s films. It is safe to say that as the son of Americans with Italian heritage himself, he has seen the dream suck people into an abyss. This is not to say he doesn’t thank America for being so kind to him; Gangs of New York was a celebration of that. However, the thought of taking matters into one’s own hands became such an obsession for Americans that it eventually led to the downfall of prominent, wealthy people. They may have started from the bottom, but they definitely forgot their roots because that was always their intention. No one wants to remember painful beginnings. Martin Scorsese has always evoked extreme reactions from his viewers. The surface viewer might just think that The Wolf of Wall Street was a 3-hour grossed-out porno-comedy without any message. That person misses a lot of the important shots that convey a deeper meaning, like that of the federal agent tasked with bringing Belfort to justice or shots of dull-faced middle-class people in a metro train. According to the film, the federal agent wanted to be a broker sometime in the past. And despite nailing such a huge arrest, he felt empty inside. He could never live the life Belfort did, even when he had the choice to. All it remained for him was a dream.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
