<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/culture/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-01-23T22:57:35+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/culture/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">New Heroes for a New Age?</title>
      <link href="/New-Heroes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Heroes for a New Age?" />
      <published>2019-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/New-Heroes</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/New-Heroes">&lt;p&gt;Our age has produced a new kind of disillusionment with heroism. Every decade that comes overshadows heroism as we know it. The new age Hero is what one may call an Anti-hero. He or she is a protagonist but without the traditional heroic traits. How we see heroes—as characters driven by creative energies, who are deeply motivated by the desire to seize the day, to be creative and virtuous, courageous and just—is not exactly how the new heroes are seen. An antihero is driven by the physical and animal side of his nature. They are earthbound selves who pursue earthly things instead of lofty goals. Yet in doing all of this, the antiheroes only seek to overcome themselves. They have conscious or unconscious appreciation of human limitations, and in their unpretentious actions directed towards fulfilling their motives, they reveal to us the meaning of true heroism for imperfect beings in an imperfect world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hallmark of a hero is personal sacrifice and a personification of the positive, unselfish side of the Freudian Ego. But the &lt;i&gt;modus operandi&lt;/i&gt; of an antihero is the antisocial act. They personify the negative, selfish side of the Id, the one that warrants immediate gratification, and their journey reveals the dark downside of the human mind. The hero represents that part of us that recognizes problems and accepts responsibility. However, the antihero is the will to power and insatiable greed, the materialistic, power hungry, tyrannical side of our natures; the side that wants to possess everything it desires, without limit, and control everything it needs. In real life, this is Hitler, Stalin and Mao Tse-tung. In story, it is Little Caesar, Michael Corleone and Commodus in ‘Gladiator.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can go as far back as Greek Mythology or look into 18th Century literature to find examples of an unconventional model for a hero. Defoe’s Moll Flanders (1722), for instance, is a poignant example of an antihero/protagonist in the conventional sense, since the main character is a thief and a prostitute. According to &lt;i&gt;Encyclopaedia Britannicai&lt;/i&gt;, Henry Fielding’s Tom Jones is also one of the prototypes of an antihero that belongs to the tradition of picaresque narration in the 18th century. However, more recently, the popular Hollywood films and genres from the mid-1940’s through the 1970’s have epitomised the antihero and made him ubiquitous. Film Noir, Westerns, Outlaw Biker Films, Cop Dramas, Mob Films and Sci-Fi Films have featured antiheroes (like Taxi Driver’s Travis Bickle) who have become some of the most iconic movie characters of all time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stages for a hero, usually include: separation, initiation, integration and rebirth. One can easily take the example of Mr. Harry Potter himself to see this. In the seven years of his life that we know of, we see Harry turn from the “boy who lived in the cupboard under the stairs” to the “one who defeats He-Who-Must-Not-Be-Named.” We know of his separation from his parents, of how he loses them and yearns for their presence, and of how he’s ignorant of the Wizarding World. But then, as he steps into Hogwarts, unaware of his own significance, he slowly becomes aware of his destiny. With this Boy, we all take a leap into a world of turmoil that he wins over with his wisdom and bravery, defeating great evil. Of course, he many-a-time has the bravery of a fool, and needs a lot of help to accomplish his monumental task. But he ultimately triumphs, literally being reborn after rising from the dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the stages for antiheroes are- attachment, regression, alienation and death. We can take the example of the character of Tyrion Lannister (from the TV Adaptation of &lt;i&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/i&gt;). Tyrion, unlike Harry, is not a novice in this cruel world, he is a witty, hedonistic insider: one who is protected by his family’s status but is still the object of humiliation. One sees not Tyrion holding the moral flag high, he soothes his inadequacies with wine, women, wit and self-indulgence. His entire life, Tyrion seeks his father’s approval and throughout the storyline it’s his father that haunts him, dead and/or alive. There’s no such attribute of Tyrion that can be highly complimented—other than how extremely intelligent and cunning he is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Tyrion cannot in any way be described as, ultimately, a bad person. Tyrion’s had to pave his own way, almost without any allies. His life is threatened a multitude of times, and yet, somehow, whining about his captors like Jorah Mormont not having wine, he is able to keep his head whilst preventing a siege of King’s Landing. Despite giving in to excess, he puts his weight behind the Targaryens in the sincere belief that Daenerys will bring about good. Tyrion assumes his role as an anti-hero almost slyly. One doesn’t realize that he has managed to make you admire and respect him, but he proves his heroism with acts none see, like his treatment of Sansa. Harry has no proverbial sins on his hand, while Tyrion’s are painted with them. Yet, what brings Tyrion and Harry to the same lane is their ability to overcome. In fact, one may even say Harry appears a little too bland, a little too ‘straight-laced’ and a little too not-relatable compared to Tyrion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is what is it about our age that makes us fall in love with these Tyrions? Historically, we have to take into consideration the various wars, whether it be the World Wars, the controversial Vietnam War, the Cold War, and most recently, the Middle Eastern conflict. Not only have people seen some of the worst acts in human history committed during this time, but many of us have experienced it first-hand. Further, endless cultural progress has become Modernism’s empty promise, and it has resulted in a Post-modernist deep-seated mistrust of the establishment, including its boundaries between right and wrong. The world now has far more shades of gray, and the characters on the silver screen reflect a broader view of morally acceptable behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we consider the 21st century so far—9/11 terrorist attacks, the Iraq War, Enron, Hurricane Katrina, the economic recession, Hurricane Sandy, the Newtown shootings, the Boston Marathon attacks—there’s been a steady stream of terrible events to shake our faith in humanity. Characters who shine as morally pure and upright don’t ring true to us anymore, because it’s not who we see around us in the world. Neither is it what we see when we look in the mirror. After all, a believable and relatable character is one of the single-most important elements of an enjoyable story. In truth, we owe a great debt to fictional villains and antiheroes. They create the problems the heroes have to solve and that creates the need for a story that reveals the inner workings of the dark side of ourselves. Without the actions of the negative forces, there would be very few stories to tell, and the forces that motivated Hitler and Jack the Ripper would remain forever a mystery to us. “Everyone carries a shadow,” Jung wrote, “and the less it is embodied in the individual’s conscious life, the blacker and denser it is.” In this new age, in this new world, the modern hero dares to heed the call of his shadow. He casts off his slough of pride, fear, rationalized avarice, and sanctified misunderstanding to reach atonement and true growth.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Our age has produced a new kind of disillusionment with heroism. Every decade that comes overshadows heroism as we know it. The new age Hero is what one may call an Anti-hero. He or she is a protagonist but without the traditional heroic traits. How we see heroes—as characters driven by creative energies, who are deeply motivated by the desire to seize the day, to be creative and virtuous, courageous and just—is not exactly how the new heroes are seen. An antihero is driven by the physical and animal side of his nature. They are earthbound selves who pursue earthly things instead of lofty goals. Yet in doing all of this, the antiheroes only seek to overcome themselves. They have conscious or unconscious appreciation of human limitations, and in their unpretentious actions directed towards fulfilling their motives, they reveal to us the meaning of true heroism for imperfect beings in an imperfect world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Winter Solstice Ceremony at Stanton Drew Stone Circle</title>
      <link href="/Winter-Solstice-Ceremony" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winter Solstice Ceremony at Stanton Drew Stone Circle" />
      <published>2019-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Winter-Solstice-Ceremony</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Winter-Solstice-Ceremony">&lt;p&gt;How I wish, dear reader, that I might tell you of how blemishless this ceremony was, how perfectly it did unfold, but sadly, it rather unravelled to dismal disappointment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so it was, on Friday, December 21, 2018 at 5 o’clock in the morning, that myself, a cohort, a witch and two accidentally encountered friends (plucked completely by chance as we crossed paths with them on the way to an uber pick-up point) did become companions in the most bizarre but heartwarming of undertakings; there was to be a Druidic ceremony, at sunrise, at a Neolithic stone circle near the village of Stanton Drew on the outskirts of Bristol, UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are greeted by a film crew and a small contingency of middle-aged women cloaked in long robes and walking with staffs at their sides. The filmographic team will be shooting a documentary for National Geographic, with the footage of the ceremony to be narrated by Morgan Freeman (who sadly would not be attending our English rural romp in person).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Battered by wind and rain, we moved all of us through the emptiness of this winter night’s morning and into a dark field. Trundling across the expanse, it seemed our numbers did increase as if by magical apparitions of many who came from all directions, all to converge in a central mass, to become a large group, to surround and step into the circle which was the Stanton Drew Stones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The megaliths loomed out of the darkness as scars of grey, with rippling light, rain running across their listless and ancient surfaces as we shuffled, bustled and edged our way into position. Lights were erected by the film crew but were torn from their hinges by the furious wind, leaving whole swarms of people consumed in pitch black. Thankfully, as if by command, after half an hour, the elements lessened and eased upon us. Shivering in our boots, we were told by the Head Druid assembled with perhaps six or seven of his entourage that the ceremony would soon commence. A single bodhrán (a kind of drum) began playing a steady beat which seemed somehow suddenly louder than the heaviest of the weather—leaving us only with a harsh breeze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We formed, as instructed, a great circle of possibly seventy people all holding hands. The Head Druid came through the only passage of free movement in and out the circle, a parting at the Western stones reminiscent of the passages often seen in Neolithic round barrows. Followed by the others, this leader of neo-pagan priests began a song with simple words by which all could soon join-in, a pleasant if contrived jaunt of a hymn with text and melody likely an oft-heard ditty in such Neo-Pagan communities, mentioning personification of animals and land with a shared spiritual connection, but probably dating back no further than the New Age movement in the 1970’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This man proclaimed the start of this public ritual and the start of a new phase in time, telling us of how this is, at the solstice, a time for new beginnings and rebirth. Our druids then distributed, in perhaps one of the only truly ‘sacred’ moments of the proceeding, branches of mistletoe which had not yet touched the ground. Such a ritual for their procurement, performed by a druid who must climb an oak tree to cut the mistletoe with a golden sickle and allow it to be caught by others in a white cloak, is the only religious practice for which we have definite knowledge, coming to us from the Roman writings of Pliny the Elder. Coupled with the sacrifice of two white bulls, a brew made from this undertaking on the 6th day of the moon was heralded to bestow fertility and cure all ailments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This connection to mistletoe was later perhaps a little misconstrued at our ceremony—one of the druids giving speeches on behalf of the directions, light, darkness, etc, mentions Baldr, the beautiful god, son of Odin and Frigg, who was slain by Loki with an arrow of mistletoe, for though his mother had endeavoured to ask all things in the land to never harm her beloved child, she had neglected this harmless plant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In comparative mythology, one might see a link to the Llew of Welsh legends, who is nigh-unkillable until his beloved Blodeuwedd, the maiden made of flowers, betrays his weakness to an enemy. But this would be the only motif we might connect in this narrative to the ‘Celtic’ identity promulgated by these neo-druids. And until we see evidence of this legend being related to the winter solstice, reader, this punter of the ancient, the eldritch and the occult will not be convinced. In considering the fertility aspect of the divine associated with Celtic festivals, one druid opted to describe the passionate and sexual embrace of his male partner, complete with graphic descriptions of everything they would with their tongues and bodies. He also went about anointing this circular congregation with water, many times, even through the speeches of other druids, saying that water was life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, along with various (unsuccessful) attempts to set alight a soaked pile of bushes in the centre of the circle, multiple wishes that there be ‘peace throughout all the world’, and the gathering being generally unable to fully hear the druids speaking at a pathetically moderate volume on this magnificently windy morning (a far cry indeed from the thunderous tones of Christopher Lee’s operatic chanting atop the tower of Isengard) made the entire affair seem really rather tame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a drab conclusion, having closed once more the gates of the North, the East and company (but mistaking one for the other), the circle, now blessed by dim, grey daylight, concluded the happenings with probably the best part of that morning, this being a great skipping and hopping, a roving of the congregation that so that we became a revolving set of linked lines in a disorganised but joyful dance set to traditional music. We thence went our separate, hitch-hiking ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you ask me – and in fact, ask anyone you like – paganism ought to be something wild. Raw and uncompromising, within reason of course, and putting us in-mind at least in spirit of the fierce pre-Christian people who did once inhabit this noble and ancient land. And yet, bearing in consideration the words of these, in truth, well-meaning hippies, I begin to wonder, as a man must if he is to mean anything to himself and his close ones, what is it I must give up, in the new year? What is it that I must sacrifice? As my ancestors did before. And what is it I hope for in return?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I leave you with this; the solstice is a time of loss. With thoughts drawn as to what we must gain and what we cannot live without. In place of new year’s resolutions, let us have new year’s dissolutions, in considering the sacrifices we may make, and perhaps must make, in our personal lives. Here is hoping that one day, we will in the South of Britain be able to put on a show in a ritualistic, religious context the likes of which our friends in the North, the Scots, have achieved every year on April, 30 since 1988 at the Beltane Fire Festival, in Edinburgh. Scantily-clad, red-body-painted dancers, revellers and all. I will look for you in the slithy toves and among the bracken and the rough. I will be there in that wind-scathed paysage, upon yonder scraggy and leering hill. Will I see you?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Morgan Black</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">How I wish, dear reader, that I might tell you of how blemishless this ceremony was, how perfectly it did unfold, but sadly, it rather unravelled to dismal disappointment.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Understanding the Absurdity of Life</title>
      <link href="/Understanding-the-Absurdity-of-Life" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding the Absurdity of Life" />
      <published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Understanding-the-Absurdity-of-Life</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-the-Absurdity-of-Life">&lt;p&gt;What is the meaning of life? This has been perhaps one of the most vexing questions of all time which has transformed several ordinary men into brooding intellectuals. While the world has seen the emergence of diverse theories propounded by the greatest of philosophers, none seem to have completely quenched the ultimate thirst for an objective analysis of life and its meaning. It was in the pursuit of this meaning that philosophers like Sartre, Kierkegaard and Albert Camus sowed the seeds from which eventually sprang a full grown tree of a new philosophical discourse on absurdism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Albert Camus, in particular, has spoken at length about absurdity in his manuscript called the “Myth of Sisyphus”. Here, he has endeavoured to explicate the futility of investigating for the absolute meaning of life—which doesn’t really exist. “The absurd” for Camus stems from the discord between “the human need and the unreasonable silence of the universe”. This ultimately culminates into a sense of hopelessness and despair in the human heart. Camus addresses what he considers the most crucial problem of philosophy: suicide, and whether the absurdity of life is a good reason for committing suicide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Men, by their very nature, are seekers of meanings, and in this pursuit, turn to religion and dogmatism to explain a world which in reality is characterised by sheer indifference and ‘irrationality’. An illusionary world embellished with meanings serves as a major source of comfort to humans as it offers false hope and reassurance, but once this world is stripped of all its meanings, man is thrown in an abyss of chaos and upheaval. Men continue to live in their robotic way, pursuing goals and ambitions mindlessly as if they are in a never-ending race. Then comes a day when they suddenly wake up from this deep slumber of ignorance after receiving a huge blow from the absurdity of life. An alien feeling of disharmony dawns upon them, and life, with all its essence and beauty, loses significance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try to imagine yourself as an invisible person and look at the world around you. It’s nothing but a mechanical interplay of relations with people chasing temporary materialistic pleasures and associating their very being with these short-lived passions. Such an existence is like an exile or punishment, just like the one awarded to the Greek mythological character named Sisyphus who was condemned by the Gods to perform the futile labour of rolling a massive boulder up the hill only to watch it fall down again and again till eternity. It begs Camus’ ever-so-important question: should we live life at all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human understanding is only limited to their own standards. Efforts to reduce the enormity of the universe into a set of uniform principles is futile. In an attempt to content himself, man attaches humanistic feelings of love and suffering to the apathetic universe. While a man’s craving for certainty persists, the universe remains still. And, it is from this relationship between the truth-seeking man and an unfeeling universe that the feeling of absurdity emanates. Science, the most authentic form of inquiry is itself based on hypothesis and conjectures. The claims believed to be true centuries ago are being altered and disproved now. In the face of such dynamism, certainty becomes a far-fetched dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, it is not the individual or the world that is absurd, but the incongruous relation between the two. The absurd originates from comparisons and confrontation. In the case of man and the world, the absurd lies in the clash between the human desire to look for meanings in a meaningless universe. Although a little baffling to comprehend, once man develops faith in the absurd, it plays an active role in guiding his life’s choices. Apart from accepting the absurd, the other option open to men is to either physically end their lives once and for all, or commit a philosophical suicide, where they assume artificial meanings and purpose of life by resorting to theology or religion. While suicide may seem a reasonable option, it simply negates the problem and does not answer it. Camus staunchly denies suicide and refers to it as ‘a repudiation’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is to embrace this absurdity and live with it. This produces three consequences - &lt;strong&gt;Revolt, Freedom, and Passion&lt;/strong&gt;. The revolt is identified by the relentless longing for an objective meaning, which is impossible to achieve. Freedom, on the other hand, is characterised by the realisation that an absurd man is free to act and doesn’t have to submit to the restrictions imposed by life. And finally, consequence or passion arises as a result of living life to the fullest by accepting the absurd and caring only about the present rather than the future or past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us now go back to our ‘absurd hero’, Sisyphus. His perpetual toil of pushing the boulder up and watching it roll down enables us to acknowledge the melancholic truth of absurdity. And the only way to remove this anguish is by imagining Sisyphus as a happy person, who despite all the struggle, is enjoying the whole process. Likewise, we must also contemplate the absurd and accept the inevitable drudgery of existence, which can only happen when we conquer our fate without expecting anything in return. So, what are you thinking? Go, enjoy your life, so what if you’ve failed a test, missed a deadline or many deadlines. Such occurrences are insignificant in the grand scheme of things. Appreciate and observe the grandeur of the world around you. Feel the sunlight, the delicate touch of petals, the cold droplets of rain and the beauty of nature, and maybe even derive a meaning out of it (bearing in the mind that it’s absurd of course!). Live your life passionately, and above all, cherish every moment. Stay happy because, at the end of the day, that’s what matters the most!!!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">What is the meaning of life? This has been perhaps one of the most vexing questions of all time which has transformed several ordinary men into brooding intellectuals. While the world has seen the emergence of diverse theories propounded by the greatest of philosophers, none seem to have completely quenched the ultimate thirst for an objective analysis of life and its meaning. It was in the pursuit of this meaning that philosophers like Sartre, Kierkegaard and Albert Camus sowed the seeds from which eventually sprang a full grown tree of a new philosophical discourse on absurdism.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Morality, the Clash of Civilizations and the Democratic Dilemma</title>
      <link href="/Morality-the-Clash-of-Civilizations-and-the-Democratic-Dilemma" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Morality, the Clash of Civilizations and the Democratic Dilemma" />
      <published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Morality-the-Clash-of-Civilizations-and-the-Democratic-Dilemma</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Morality-the-Clash-of-Civilizations-and-the-Democratic-Dilemma">&lt;p&gt;“Civilization will not attain to its perfection until the last stone from the last church falls on the last priest.” Émile Zola&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Freedom consists not in doing what we like, but in having the right to do what we ought.” Pope John Paul II&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mid-1900s, hundreds of millions hoped (and feared) that the “spectre of Communism” would overshadow the world. Less than 100 years later, this hope appears to have all but vanished. The Soviet Union has collapsed. Communism is either dying or dead. Liberal democracy is considered the norm, and societies which deviate from it are considered either barbaric or backward (sometimes both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what is all this in aid of? Well, proponents argue, liberal democracy ensures that each person will have an infallible guarantee of their most intrinsic human rights, and that, if they are violated, the guilty party will be swiftly brought to justice. The problem, of course, arises when we consider the question of what constitutes “human rights”. The phrase is rather nebulous and subject to a wide range of possible interpretations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, consider the so-called “Right to Life”. To whom does this extend? Well, the human being, obviously. But can the unborn foetus be considered a “human being”? Who gets to define this term “human being”? At what stage does an entity start to be “human”? And what about criminals? Do they also enjoy the right to life, or have they – by their transgressions and woeful iniquities (again, a very debatable issue at times) – forfeited that right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the problem. There are 1.3 billion Catholics in the world who (if they are good Catholics) affirm that human life begins at conception. They also have (so their apologists claim) a number of medical experts and embryologists to back them up on that. On the other hand, there are countless self-professed “feminists” who believe that to protect without exception the foetus from being aborted would be to endanger the life of the mother. One is, the argument goes, trying to prioritize the life of an unborn, half-developed “creature” over that of a fully developed, free citizen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is clearly a clash of civilizations, a war of opposing ideologies. If the pro-choice crowd is in the right, then the right to abortion is an intrinsic right of the woman. If the pro-life factions are correct, then abortion is the biggest cause of genocide since the Holocaust. Both sides agree that human rights are being violated to this day. This brings us to a very pressing question: Is Liberal Democracy even realistic? Or does it try to bite off more than it can chew? It tries to keep the “religious busybodies” out of government, but at the same time imposes a morality on the rest of the population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a philosophical perspective, can non-religious people even have objective moral values? According to a sizeable number of atheists and naturalists, morality is simply a human construct, created by societies in order to facilitate greater synergy and efficiency of operation. Each tribe of people, the story goes, tries over time to organize its own affairs and, in order to do so, “invents” a moral code to better facilitate that purpose. But if it is purely a human construct, then it has no intrinsic value – only imparted value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Jews, Christians and Muslims all believe (and together, they constitute more than 3 billion people), that morality is ordained by God. Some go even further and say that morality is nothing other than God’s own eternal, immutable nature. With the rise of postmodernism, moral relativism has been skyrocketing, and the old-school atheists are desperately scrambling to produce a scientific basis for objective moral values. The religious camp is claiming that such an operation is in vain since science (they say) cannot possibly adjudicate on matters on ethics. Only time will tell which side wins out in the end. But both factions are united in an affirmation that relativism is dangerous and toxic. Here is why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If morality is purely a human construct, then there is no universal moral code everyone has to abide by. Each person gets to invent his/her own moral rules and one would have no objective basis to refute that. In a relativistic worldview, if one disagrees with someone else, one cannot say that the other side is “wrong” – merely that they disagree. Now imagine if the Nazis suddenly had a worldwide resurgence. The Christian, Muslim and Jew would be able to unite and condemn them on the basis that they are violating God’s eternal unchangeable law and are &lt;em&gt;ipso facto&lt;/em&gt; condemned. But what can the relativist say? Only that he/she disagrees with their moral code, but since – according to his/her own definition – morality is merely a human construct, he/she cannot make an objective claim that they are “wrong” in an absolute sense of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Democracy must be better delineated. The fact is that there exist in the world irreconcilable worldviews. People of different ethnicities, races, communities and genders might coexist, but can a pro-lifer eat at the same table as an abortionist, when the fact is – according to the pro-lifer – the latter is nothing other than a murderer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One cannot live in two worlds. Liberal Democracy cannot not take a stand, but if it does take a stand, it ceases to be liberal. And when it ceases to be liberal, can it be called democracy? In a world of exclusive ideologies, absolute inclusivism is an impossibility. And in a world of conflicting moral systems, the state and the law cannot act as impartial umpires. Either abortion is legal, or it isn’t. The question then remains, that if the state is ready to impose its own moral values on the rest of the populace, then it must ask itself a question: does it have any objective basis for those values or not? If it does not, it undermines its own authority. And if it is non-religious, it is hard to see how it’s ethical code can have any objective basis at all.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Civilization will not attain to its perfection until the last stone from the last church falls on the last priest.” Émile Zola</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Siddis: The Black Rulers of India</title>
      <link href="/Siddis-The-Black-Rulers-of-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Siddis: The Black Rulers of India" />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Siddis-The-Black-Rulers-of-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Siddis-The-Black-Rulers-of-India">&lt;p&gt;Deep in the annals of Indian history, there lies a long-forgotten tale of daring heroes, who, although foreign to the land, quickly got assimilated into her blood and added to her magnificence. This is the story of the first African rulers of India, the Siddis. India has long been acting as a magnet, drawing to her shores communities from lands afar which have flourished and prospered in her. Amongst these communities were the Africans who although arrived as slaves, still emerged as the mightiest of rulers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Journeying all the way from Abyssinia, their motherland, through the treacherous waters, the ‘habshis’ (another term used for addressing the Siddis, descendants of the Bantu people) arrived at the Deccan as a part of the ongoing lucrative slave trade by the Arab merchants. The very distinguished Moroccan scholar, Ibn Batutta recounts how the habshis were reputed for being formidable, such that the presence of even a single habshi in a ship would make the pirates turn away from it. While most of the habshis arrived as slaves and soldiers for the armies of the Delhi Sultanate, not all remained so, and some even climbed the social ladder to become dignified nobles. One of such nobles was Jamal-ud-din Yakut, a close confidant of Razia Sultan (the first female monarch to assume the ascendancy over the Delhi Sultanate), who enjoyed a privileged position as the Amir al-Umara (Amir of Amirs), under her patronage. His growing proximity with the Sultana, along with his racial humbleness, earned him great spite from the Turkish clerics, especially Malik Ikhtiar-ud-din Altunia, who led a violent rebellion against the two, ultimately culminating in his tragic end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were also other Abyssinian men like the governor general Malik Sarwar who even went to the extent of laying down the foundation of a sovereign state called Jaunpur, which survived for nearly a century as a symbol of cultural amity and unity. Furthermore, some even established themselves in the eastern part of the subcontinent by dethroning the Sultans of Bengal. The very impressive Siddi Sayed mosque in Ahmedabad was also sanctioned for construction by a Habshi in 1572. Other noteworthy cases of Abyssinians entering the political limelight include Suhail Khan, saviour of the beleaguered Queen of Ahmadnagar, Chand Bibi, who was at war with the Mughals, and Yakut Khan, a navy admiral commissioned by the great Mughal emperor, Aurangzeb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these achievements are indeed great, nowhere had the habshis thrived as much as they did in the Deccan region. Many soared up sky-high, attaining extraordinary heights in the administration and military, because of their physical competency and fidelity. They no longer remained subdued, and with social ascendency, came greater power and privilege at their disposal. Such is the story of another Habshi, Malik Ambar, who held the post of the prime minister of the Ahmadnagar Sultanate. Born in the Oromo tribe, he was sold out at a very young age to an Arab merchant and passed through the hands of several owners to ultimately arrive at India and write his own destiny, where he converted to Islam and was renamed Ambar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was around 1571 that Ambar arrived at the Deccan where he served under a new master, the Peshwa of Ahmadnagar, who was himself a black man. This must have presented to Ambar a tempting prospect of rising above slavery to cease power and wealth. After the death of his master, he established an independent army (with the help of other habshi lords) and provided his valuable services to Adil Shah for which he was even conferred the title of Malik. But his most impressive accomplishment by far was during the invasions of the 1590’s, where he led a pluralistic force of several thousands under his command against the Mughals. His animosity towards the Mughals was especially long drawn, against whom he fought bravely to establish Nizam Shah on the throne of Ahmadnagar as the lawful monarch. Apart from being an able administrator, Malik Ambar is also accredited with engineering the military tactic of guerrilla warfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donning Indian clothes and speaking the language of the land, the Siddis over time have coalesced into the culture and tradition of the subcontinent. However, contrary to the honour and fame attained as a part of history, the Siddis of present-day India remain a secluded community. Maintaining their distance from the mainstream culture and society, they live in tiny clusters scattered around the states of Karnataka, Maharashtra, and Gujarat. Having been reduced to mere outsiders in a country of their own, the Siddis have to continuously battle against the evils of racism and poverty. The only positive step taken by the government towards their upliftment was the establishment of the Special Area Games Project, in the hope of nurturing the raw talent for athletics which runs in their blood. This initiative, however, could not sustain for long and the dream of having Indo-African athletes run for the country in the Olympics was lost. Sports being the only way out of their deplorable condition, the Siddi community now dwells in the hope of the revival of SAG project and creation of many such opportunities&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With xenophobia and racial attacks on the rise all over the country, there is a dire need to spread greater awareness about this community. The government, especially, needs to shoulder some responsibility and formulate comprehensive policies to harness the enormous potential lying in the Siddi community. This can come in the form of better employment, education, and opportunities in sports, and most importantly, acceptance from the rest of the countrymen. The time has come for us to uproot this deep-seated feeling of prejudice against the Indo-African community and truly embrace them to the core in an attempt to learn from the glorious past and shape a bright future based on mutual recognition and brotherhood.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Deep in the annals of Indian history, there lies a long-forgotten tale of daring heroes, who, although foreign to the land, quickly got assimilated into her blood and added to her magnificence. This is the story of the first African rulers of India, the Siddis. India has long been acting as a magnet, drawing to her shores communities from lands afar which have flourished and prospered in her. Amongst these communities were the Africans who although arrived as slaves, still emerged as the mightiest of rulers.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Cynical Circus</title>
      <link href="/A-Cynical-Circus" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Cynical Circus" />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Cynical-Circus</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Cynical-Circus">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Greatest Showman Betrays Barnum’s Legacy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Greatest Showman&lt;/em&gt; has swept across the cinematic landscape, garnering praise from almost every audience-member (young and old), whilst being generally panned by any critic going. Most were swift to point blame at the score, whose music, I agree, is largely an unchanging series of generic music-theatre-lite pop songs punctuated by a couple of ballads to swell the emotions, all backed by RnB-style beats to make it seem accessible for all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, while I don’t actually have too many issues with the score outside of its genericness (there are even a few that really caught my attention!), the idea of being ‘accessible for all’ pervades this show in an extremely insidious manner. It’s almost as if the composers Benj Pasek and Justin Paul (&lt;em&gt;James and the Giant Peach, Dear Evan Hansen&lt;/em&gt;) embraced the idea of making this score so generic to better reel in their paying audience—and there’s the rub with the entire film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right from the end of the opening song (“The Greatest Show” – one of the few that stands out as being genuinely individual as it introduces Barnum’s Circus in an eye- and ear-catching festival of light and sound), we are introduced to characters whose every purpose is to force the audience to either pity or love them – usually both. The boy, Barnum’s younger self, suffers abuse from all sides – his father shoves him about; his father’s rich client, unfortunately the father of the girl, Charity, slaps the lad out of hand. Charity and Barnum are ultimately left to explore their young love in secret in the most frustratingly clichéd and tedious songs of the film (“A Million Dreams”), wherein the pair grow up apart, writing letters as she (as per) goes off to finishing-school and he grows up on the streets, an American Oliver, eventually becoming respectable… somehow? The teenaged Barnum over-hears someone calling for people to work on the railway, and then suddenly we see middle-aged Hugh Jackman asking for Charity’s hand – and, shock-horror, the father is not pleased. But off they go anyway, declaring that “however big, however small / let me be a part of it all.” Adorable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so are their children, who are just too perfect: one ballet-dances and the other plays with her dollhouse – both agonisingly cute, setting off a quiet, childlike reprise of “A Million Dreams”. So, in a sequence that ought to be about family struggling against poverty, we miss every chance offered to have some angst over their inability to live the life Barnum wants to give them – which ought to be the driving factor for him to found the Circus in the first place! Instead, the writers, Jenny Bicks and Bill Condon (&lt;em&gt;Men in Trees, Chicago&lt;/em&gt;), allow the family to get by on being cute and seemingly glitter their way through poverty. Compared to &lt;em&gt;Oliver!&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;Fiddler&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;In The Heights&lt;/em&gt;, the struggle against poverty that ought to be central to the film is entirely lacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is worse, though, than the manipulation of the audience with cute children and a sob-story past, is the exploitation of the characters in Barnum’s Circus; not by Barnum himself, but by the writers. Barnum himself was fairly charitable towards his ‘freaks’, practicing ‘profitable philanthropy’ – making both himself and their-selves richer by dint of the public’s fascination with them. But every character we see in his Circus is not real. They are all, without fault, amalgams of several historical persons, simplified and made to seem less exploited by Barnum and more empowered. Charles, the dwarf, one of the few allowed to keep his own name, was not in his twenties when he joined Barnum. He was four – and within a year he was drinking and smoking to entertain the audience. Insidiously, the producers are making money by exploiting not just the ‘freaks’, but the age of #MeToo and of #blacklivesmatter, following the current trend of films that provide empowerment, without truly empowering the audience itself. They are mining the feel-good factor itself in a very obvious and distasteful manner through the generic score and through the freedom and empowerment that Barnum appears to offer his ‘freaks’ (even that term is taken and made empowering) And that is to say nothing of the ‘White Man’s Burden’ that goes unaddressed in this film; Hugh Jackman empowering all these people by showing them how they can make money off of other people’s macabre fascination with them? It struck me as a great white elephant in the room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we come to my pet-hate from this film? Oh, Ms Bicks, what did you do to Jenny Lind? You’ve destroyed her defining feature: her voice. In terms of singing, the Swedish Nightingale is reduced to a pop-music mezzo rather than a sparkling operatic soprano. Accent-wise, she is bizarrely British. And narratively? They construct an affair between Lind and Barnum to try and provoke some familial angst at a point in the story where there is already enough circus-based angst, and where we could have had some real familial angst as Barnum historically fell into debt again after Lind’s tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That all being said, there are positives: the performances are stellar. Hugh Jackman is masterful as Barnum. Zac Efron rises above a poorly-constructed amalgam role designed to give some class-tension, and is an excellent foil to Jackman. Paul Sparks as Bennett, the nasty newspaper critic, oddly provides a final moral to the piece that doesn’t feel false. Similarly, the choreography is amazing: “The Other Side” duet is mesmeric in its staging. The dancing in general is fantastic, especially during the Circus performances and in “A Million Dreams”. And the cinematography is broadly very good – a misstep with a CGI elephant notwithstanding. The use of colour I find particularly notable to separate the circus from the outside world, reminding one of Baz Luhrmann’s &lt;em&gt;Moulin Rouge&lt;/em&gt; in its carnival pomp. Ultimately, however, &lt;em&gt;The Greatest Showman&lt;/em&gt; is simply a well-made spectacle that looks good but feels terribly, terribly wrong.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Olly Bowes</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Greatest Showman Betrays Barnum’s Legacy</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
