<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/culture/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-11-20T00:44:08+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/culture/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Stand Up and Economics</title>
      <link href="/Stand-Up-and-Economics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stand Up and Economics" />
      <published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Stand-Up-and-Economics</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Stand-Up-and-Economics">&lt;p&gt;Who would be a perfect partner for a tub of Popcorn and a day drowned in gloom? For me, it has always been Kenny Sebastian cracking jokes on coffee or biscuits. Not just Kenny Sebastian, but as a matter of fact, stand-up comedians in general have been my saviour in times of crisis. The giggles and the laughs indeed help one escape from reality and live in the moment. However, there is one not so known fact about stand-ups - they share a close relationship with everybody’s favourite subject, economics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This relationship between Economics and Stand Ups is bilateral, and however funny and astonishing it may sound, we have someone with the title of 'Stand-up Economist'. Yoram Bauman is deemed to be the first Stand up Economist in the world. He is a microeconomist and his key focus area is the environment. He once wrote a parody on the 'ten principles of Economics'&amp;nbsp; by N Mankiw which kick-started his side-career in comedy. Now, he regularly performs at colleges, clubs and institutes&lt;em&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;&quot;The difference, of course, being that microeconomists are people who are wrong about specific things and macroeconomists are wrong about things in general&quot; &lt;/em&gt;was one of his lines at a 45- minute comedy show performed at Mission College which made the audience burst into laughter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving ahead, while we look at the first half of the relationship, we will be looking at stand-ups as economics. A lot of people have drawn similarities between jokes and currency. Some went overboard and termed jokes as a 'Strange Currency'. The value of this currency rests on a shared agreement and it keeps fluctuating, i.e., increases or decreases, over time. Moreover, if we visualise stand-up as a market, the market does have a point of saturation wherein the joke becomes so diffused that it no longer pleases the audience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And again, like everything else, jokes react to the principles of supply and demand. Jokes, in this market, are characterised as investments. Not everyone can wake up one day, go on the stage and become a stand up comedian. There’s a lot of refinement and honing that goes behind a successful joke (or investment) which can be presented to a paid audience and in turn yield money. &lt;a href=&quot;http://marknormandcomedy.com/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mark Normand&lt;/a&gt;’s line “&lt;em&gt;If I can get a joke to work on [a free] show, that joke is worth money” &lt;/em&gt;sums up the idea pretty well. These jokes have a lasting or terminal value like any other investment. However, when does the value of a joke fade away? The lasting value depends on the person who’s making the joke. For example, stand-up comedians who have been in the business for as long as decades can dig out old jokes and please the audience with the reference. Thus, the jokes still have a lasting value for them even after decades. Generally, it is considered that non-conventional jokes have a longer lasting value than the conventional ones.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we have walked through the streets of the stand-up industry, there’s another visualisation of the joke market which was proposed by Yoram Bauman. Instead of considering jokes as a currency, Bauman considers jokes to be like public goods such as fresh air, water, etc. If one of the members enjoys the joke, it doesn’t take away the right of enjoying it from any other member. However, even estimating the value of a public good is difficult, as no one puts equal value on a nice view or a nice joke. Again like any other goods, jokes face saturation in the market. If a comedy show has the same specific bit of jokes about the same things, the value of the jokes would reduce. Ultimately the audience would refuse to buy these jokes by either not laughing at them or worse by heckling. However, one fundamental question that still remains is how one puts a value on a creative intangible hobby because a lot of stand up comedians don’t really want money in exchange for their “goods” but are satisfied by the giggles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now exploring the second half of the relationship, a lot of stand-ups have economic concepts entwined in them. Stand ups provide a really holistic view of human behavior. Since most of the jokes are centered on everyday life; these comedians analyze our behavior to derive jokes out of them. Hence, economics lovers should definitely watch stand ups apart from reading the usual microeconomics textbook. As was noted in one of the articles by Mint, there are various instances where stand-up comedians have explained complex economics issues through jokes. For example, when in one of his gigs, Abhishek Upmanyu said that, in his childhood, on his grandmother’s death anniversary, his mother used to request him to offer food to poor people. While he agrees that it is a noble deed to do, he also states that it creates an unwanted incentive. If poor people get to know that elderly people dying means food, they’ll start hurting elderly people. This, in economics, is called ‘The Cobra Effect’.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it’s stand-up comedy in economics or economics in stand-up comedy, there’s one thing clear that there is a relationship between the two. So, the next time you sit with a tub of popcorn and Kenny Sebastian, you can skip your microeconomics tuition!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shiksha Mody</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Who would be a perfect partner for a tub of Popcorn and a day drowned in gloom? For me, it has always been Kenny Sebastian cracking jokes on coffee or biscuits. Not just Kenny Sebastian, but as a matter of fact, stand-up comedians in general have been my saviour in times of crisis. The giggles and the laughs indeed help one escape from reality and live in the moment. However, there is one not so known fact about stand-ups - they share a close relationship with everybody’s favourite subject, economics. This relationship between Economics and Stand Ups is bilateral, and however funny and astonishing it may sound, we have someone with the title of 'Stand-up Economist'. Yoram Bauman is deemed to be the first Stand up Economist in the world. He is a microeconomist and his key focus area is the environment. He once wrote a parody on the 'ten principles of Economics'&amp;nbsp; by N Mankiw which kick-started his side-career in comedy. Now, he regularly performs at colleges, clubs and institutes. &quot;The difference, of course, being that microeconomists are people who are wrong about specific things and macroeconomists are wrong about things in general&quot; was one of his lines at a 45- minute comedy show performed at Mission College which made the audience burst into laughter. Moving ahead, while we look at the first half of the relationship, we will be looking at stand-ups as economics. A lot of people have drawn similarities between jokes and currency. Some went overboard and termed jokes as a 'Strange Currency'. The value of this currency rests on a shared agreement and it keeps fluctuating, i.e., increases or decreases, over time. Moreover, if we visualise stand-up as a market, the market does have a point of saturation wherein the joke becomes so diffused that it no longer pleases the audience.&amp;nbsp; And again, like everything else, jokes react to the principles of supply and demand. Jokes, in this market, are characterised as investments. Not everyone can wake up one day, go on the stage and become a stand up comedian. There’s a lot of refinement and honing that goes behind a successful joke (or investment) which can be presented to a paid audience and in turn yield money. Mark Normand’s line “If I can get a joke to work on [a free] show, that joke is worth money” sums up the idea pretty well. These jokes have a lasting or terminal value like any other investment. However, when does the value of a joke fade away? The lasting value depends on the person who’s making the joke. For example, stand-up comedians who have been in the business for as long as decades can dig out old jokes and please the audience with the reference. Thus, the jokes still have a lasting value for them even after decades. Generally, it is considered that non-conventional jokes have a longer lasting value than the conventional ones.&amp;nbsp; While we have walked through the streets of the stand-up industry, there’s another visualisation of the joke market which was proposed by Yoram Bauman. Instead of considering jokes as a currency, Bauman considers jokes to be like public goods such as fresh air, water, etc. If one of the members enjoys the joke, it doesn’t take away the right of enjoying it from any other member. However, even estimating the value of a public good is difficult, as no one puts equal value on a nice view or a nice joke. Again like any other goods, jokes face saturation in the market. If a comedy show has the same specific bit of jokes about the same things, the value of the jokes would reduce. Ultimately the audience would refuse to buy these jokes by either not laughing at them or worse by heckling. However, one fundamental question that still remains is how one puts a value on a creative intangible hobby because a lot of stand up comedians don’t really want money in exchange for their “goods” but are satisfied by the giggles. Now exploring the second half of the relationship, a lot of stand-ups have economic concepts entwined in them. Stand ups provide a really holistic view of human behavior. Since most of the jokes are centered on everyday life; these comedians analyze our behavior to derive jokes out of them. Hence, economics lovers should definitely watch stand ups apart from reading the usual microeconomics textbook. As was noted in one of the articles by Mint, there are various instances where stand-up comedians have explained complex economics issues through jokes. For example, when in one of his gigs, Abhishek Upmanyu said that, in his childhood, on his grandmother’s death anniversary, his mother used to request him to offer food to poor people. While he agrees that it is a noble deed to do, he also states that it creates an unwanted incentive. If poor people get to know that elderly people dying means food, they’ll start hurting elderly people. This, in economics, is called ‘The Cobra Effect’.&amp;nbsp; While it’s stand-up comedy in economics or economics in stand-up comedy, there’s one thing clear that there is a relationship between the two. So, the next time you sit with a tub of popcorn and Kenny Sebastian, you can skip your microeconomics tuition!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Revolutionary Force of K-Pop</title>
      <link href="/The-Revolutionary-Force-of-K-Pop" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Revolutionary Force of K-Pop" />
      <published>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Revolutionary-Force-of-K-Pop</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Revolutionary-Force-of-K-Pop">&lt;p&gt;This year, K-pop accelerated its expansion into all sorts of mediums — &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5892708/jessica-jung-shine-interview/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;novels&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.billboard.com/articles/news/international/9342105/k-pop-podcasts-coronavirus-quarantine/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;podcasts&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.billboard.com/articles/news/movies/9446222/netflix-blackpink-documentary&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;documentaries&lt;/a&gt;. And yet, for all the satisfaction these new forms brought with them, the music remained the heart of this global phenomenon. Despite the pandemic’s impact on the worldwide recording industry, releases from&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/entertainer-of-the-year-2020-bts/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;South Korea&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;saw no decline in quantity or quality, and a slew of artists produced their best work to date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The K-pop songs and albums that defined the year transported us to places we miss most—from&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5912807/best-broadway-shows-to-stream/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the theat&lt;/a&gt;re&amp;nbsp;to the jazz bar to the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5870462/rick-steves-coronavirus-quarantine/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;island vacation&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;that lives only in our memories or imaginations. Some prompted nostalgia for things we&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5902420/hugging-coronavirus-amy-ephron/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;once took for granted&lt;/a&gt;, while others inspired hope for their return. Through these releases, many of our favorite artists experimented with their sounds, all while building deeper connections with an&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5912998/bts-army/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;audience&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;they could only interact with from a distance. A talented rookie class experimented with retro sounds, while K-pop's most successful women brazenly defied expectations. Disco completely took over, and noise music prevailed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was also a year for career breakthroughs and major milestones, as the world's biggest superstars&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.papermag.com/tag/bts&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;BTS&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;continued to shatter records left and right and break new ground for Korean artists. They're going into the new year with three number-one singles on the&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Billboard&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;Hot 100, a whole quarantine album, and a Grammy nomination. And while the world got smaller, K-pop went bigger and bolder — sonically and aesthetically.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the global coronavirus pandemic put an end to live touring, the K-pop industry brought the spectacle to our screens with&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.teenvogue.com/story/k-pop-future-of-live-music-immersive-online-concerts&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;immersive live concert&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;experiences. The music never stopped, not even for a second&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you're a casual listener, a stan, or someone who's just genuinely curious to see what K-pop is all about,&amp;nbsp;here are 10 songs from the heat of KPOP that made the hard 2020 much easier and eventually took the world by storm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1)&lt;strong&gt; BTS, 'Black Swan' (&lt;em&gt;Map of the Soul: 7&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BTS has connected with a worldwide fanbase in large part thanks to the universal-but-still-personal themes of their music, and 'Black Swan' represents one of their most intimate confessions. Dreamy, gloomy hip-hop soundscapes lay the backdrop for the chart-toppers to open up about their darkest fears: that they may one day fall out of love with music. Using the title as a metaphor – to represent both the one-of-a-kind phenomenon they are and the 2010 movie where a ballerina makes the ultimate sacrifice for her art – the superstar septet investigates their underlying anxieties whilst declaring that they won’t let fear win over passion in the end. It’s a full-fledged motion picture-packed into just over three minutes to tell a rare, real-life story of one of the world’s biggest stars&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2)&lt;strong&gt; TXT, 'Can’t You See Me' (&lt;em&gt;The Dream Chapter: ETERNITY&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 'Can’t You See Me' TXT pulls the dark undercurrent of their youthful whimsy out from under the bed. Crunchy electric guitars and a jaunty whistle add a refreshing contrast to the track’s trap underpinnings, but where it best exposes its murkiness is through the quintet's vocal performances. Alternating between distorted tremolo vocals, hushed whisper-raps, and delicate verses wisping like curls of smoke, the members’ voices lurch between dulcet and disorienting as they reveal the cracks in a friendship. Through unsettling sounds and an idyllic music video that devolves into something frightening, TXT lay bare a horror rarely spoken of: watching a friendship fade before your eyes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3)&lt;strong&gt; &amp;nbsp;Twice, “I CAN’T STOP ME” (&lt;em&gt;Eyes Wide Open)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Dua Lipa and Lady Gaga, Twice were hip to electro basslines this year in “I CAN’T STOP ME.” The girl group bask in the elastic, strobing synth that pulses under the glamorous nu-disco track, and it snaps into formation with the chorus. The song calls for a grand celebration, but they’re too distracted trying not to indulge in their own treacherous desires: “I just can’t go back anymore/ Out of control,” Chaeyoung sings before the rest of the group fully surrender to temptation. Twice fight to keep cool, though it’s hard to notice when they nail such a spotless performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4) WOODZ, “BUMP BUMP” (&lt;em&gt;WOOPS!&lt;/em&gt;)&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a great year for soloists in K-pop, and no one was more honest with themselves than WOODZ. The push-and-pull of any romance is often the most enticing yet stressful aspect of it all. Amidst airy promises from his lover is the dreary prospect of being left alone, but he approaches this mixed-messaging with a refreshing candour. In our own whirlpools of flirting and call backs, IG-reels and missed messages, “BUMP BUMP” was comfortingly straightforward – with WOODZ relaying what he wants, exactly how he wants it. It was the wrong year to be young and in love in 2020, but at least we had WOODZ to keep us company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5) Weki Meki, “COOL” (&lt;em&gt;NEW RULES&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weki Meki revamp their approach in 'Cool' by swapping their preppy dance-pop for steely electro. The group’s demeanor is as spartan as the icy beat, and they amplify their bratty voices to assert their flawlessness. Their cockiness peaks in the chorus, which doubles as a taunt and a mantra: &quot;Be hotter/ Beyond the control,” they sing like a drill instructor. “Get out of all the boring rules.” If “Cool” sounds standoffish, then the song succeeds at what it sets out to do. Weki Meki don’t aspire to be a role model for attainable, girl-crush cool but instead point out the gap between you and them. “Cool” is a conceited celebration of self, though sometimes it just feels satisfying to flaunt what you got.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6). GFRIEND, 'MAGO' (&lt;em&gt;回:Walpurgis Night&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'MAGO' distils disco to its very best qualities, shimmering – quite literally – with synths and steady beats, building a heady, atmospheric high. As cohesive as it is musically, its magic lies in how perfectly it fits into the ethos of&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;回:Walpurgis Night.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;The album&amp;nbsp;is built on the idea of modern witches, at the centre of which are women who exercise the same agency and power of the song’s namesake, and GFRIEND has fun while doing it. Interspersed with images of the girls dancing the night away – not what you’d expect from a concept dealing with the occult – are lyrics that brim with confidence and ambition. Instead of believing in fairy tales and waiting for a Prince Charming, their only love is the images of themselves smiling in the mirror. It’s a cheeky way to poke fun at how society perceives self-assured women since the title itself translates to 'wizard.' In celebrating their limitless ambition, 'MAGO' casts a spell that keeps you coming back for more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7) SEVENTEEN, 'Left &amp;amp; Right' (&lt;em&gt;Heng:garæ&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'LEFT &amp;amp; RIGHT' is so exuberant that every sound – from doorbell chimes to 808 cowbells, organ synth riffs to full-bodied brass&amp;nbsp; –&amp;nbsp; bursts forth like aural confetti. One could readily claim SEVENTEEN have made their own 'Cupid Shuffle' but they’re aiming for something beyond mere dance instructional: this is a song for transforming every moment into a cause for celebration. In a time when in-person parties aren’t possible, 'LEFT &amp;amp; RIGHT' converts bedrooms into dancefloors. And with exultant shouts and energized rapping, they tell you to keep your chin up, to run down red carpets, to&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;dance&lt;/em&gt;. SEVENTEEN act as leaders and hype men here, but the role they fill best is that of life coaches: despite their talk of races and finish lines, they exclaim that “not running is an answer too / who cares what we do.”&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They grant permission to simply be: a reminder that surviving every day is enough right now. And after all, if you’re not moving forward, why not move &quot;LEFT &amp;amp; RIGHT,”&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt;? They understand something that should be taught in schools around the world: busting your ass should be supplemented with time spent shaking it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8) Apink, 'Dumhdurum' (&lt;em&gt;LOOK&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;K-pop tends to be a young person's game – both the industry and its labels regularly shift their priorities to younger artists – but Apink’s 'Dumhdurum' makes an exceptional case for the continuing effort and investment in senior acts. The track opens with a swirling synth-pop hook strong enough to stand as a chorus on its own, before diving into verses and choruses that strike pop gold with just the right amount of catchy repetition and melancholy longing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apink detail the complexity of remaining calm in the presence of a past love, even when one’s heart's still beating&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;dumhdurum&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;for them – a concept that could be difficult for younger groups to believably pull off. This mature message successfully connected with a large audience, and 'Dumhdurum' became a knockout success in both Korea (topping all local music charts) and the&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Billboard&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;charts (tying for their longest-running hit on&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.billboard.com/charts/world-digital-song-sales&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;World Digital Song Sales&lt;/a&gt;).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nine years into their career, Apink are still more than equipped to bring their A-Game, and that deserves larger recognition all in itself for the industry to pay equal attention to both its senior and developing artists. Matured musical magic awaits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9). EVERGLOW, 'LA DI DA' (&lt;em&gt;-77.82x-78.29&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to a virtual flattening of borders, musical trends in the States now get reflected in&amp;nbsp;K-pop in real-time. Throughout 2020 – in both the U.S. and South Korea – throwback sounds were ubiquitous. This year’s K-pop magnum opus, EVERGLOW’s 'LA DI DA' mirrored the US’ pop magnum opus, The Weeknd’s 'Blinding Lights' only months after its release. But where The Weeknd’s work is chilling and sinister in its search for love, EVERGLOW’s is a spry kiss-off to all the haters, the bad guys, and the players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A successful pastiche of the 80's that’s crafted by producer Ollipop, 'LA DI DA' blends myriad influences: the&amp;nbsp;layered cheerleader chants of Toni Basil's '&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0aqLwHP4y6Q&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mickey&lt;/a&gt;' the spunky girl power of Cyndi Lauper and the Go-Go's, the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HnYWmgSZdlM&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;na-na-nas&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;of Bananarama, and above all, the shimmering synth-pop sound that permeated the top half of that decade. 'LA DI DA' melds these all together, with K-pop twists: a killing part punctuated by handclaps, a tempo-shifting rap section carried by leader E:U, and an earworm of a melody evocative of early 2010's K-pop – a time when choruses were packed with hooky vocal melodies instead of hollow drops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10) 'Lovesick Girls', BLACKPINK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arrival of BLACKPINK’s first&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5896487/blackpink-the-album/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;full-length album&lt;/a&gt; — so highly anticipated at the project was simply titled&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;The Album&lt;/em&gt;—was one of K-pop’s biggest news events in 2020. While the pre-release singles&amp;nbsp;'&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5859277/blackpink-how-you-like-that/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;How You Like That&lt;/a&gt;'&amp;nbsp;and 'Ice Cream' with Selena Gomez charted higher on the &lt;em&gt;Billboard&lt;/em&gt; Hot 100, 'Lovesick Girls' is the true gem on the album. The heavy electronic production characteristic of BLACKPINK’s crowd-riling bops remains intact, but it’s stripped back to accentuate sung melodies from the four members. Their voices are layered over an acoustic guitar to create a breezy and mellow ambience, taking a more pensive and melancholic turn from the hard-hitting nature of the group’s 2018 and 2019 title track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While 2020 has been far from a banner year for K-pop, with the coronavirus pandemic impacting the industry through disbandments, cancelled tours, and shelved comebacks, there have been enough pleasant surprises to keep fans plugged in. BTS’ success these days can make it hard to recall that they were once considered the underdogs of the K-pop industry. The seven-piece group didn’t come from a big management firm, and at the time of their debut, they stood out for not sounding (or looking) overly packaged or produced. Instead, BTS was built by their fans — the 'Army' — who rallied behind the group. This month, the Army’s influence has extended beyond music and into social justice, when the loyal fanbase helped to match the group’s&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-news/bts-black-lives-matter-donation-1011198/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$1 million donation to Black Lives Matter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. That followed a&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-news/white-lives-matter-k-pop-1009581/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;coordinated campaign&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;by K-pop fans just days earlier, when fans came together to drown out the racist #WhiteLivesMatter hashtag on Twitter by spamming it with irreverent memes and fan cams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone who still thought K-pop was a passing fad or a niche subset best left to the 'world music' fringes, the recent rallying of the fandoms (not to mention a host of spirited new releases) has underlined the fact that K-pop is more than just another overseas import — it’s officially a global force.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tejasvi Joshi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This year, K-pop accelerated its expansion into all sorts of mediums — novels,&amp;nbsp;podcasts,&amp;nbsp;documentaries. And yet, for all the satisfaction these new forms brought with them, the music remained the heart of this global phenomenon. Despite the pandemic’s impact on the worldwide recording industry, releases from&amp;nbsp;South Korea&amp;nbsp;saw no decline in quantity or quality, and a slew of artists produced their best work to date. The K-pop songs and albums that defined the year transported us to places we miss most—from&amp;nbsp;the theatre&amp;nbsp;to the jazz bar to the&amp;nbsp;island vacation&amp;nbsp;that lives only in our memories or imaginations. Some prompted nostalgia for things we&amp;nbsp;once took for granted, while others inspired hope for their return. Through these releases, many of our favorite artists experimented with their sounds, all while building deeper connections with an&amp;nbsp;audience&amp;nbsp;they could only interact with from a distance. A talented rookie class experimented with retro sounds, while K-pop's most successful women brazenly defied expectations. Disco completely took over, and noise music prevailed.&amp;nbsp; It was also a year for career breakthroughs and major milestones, as the world's biggest superstars&amp;nbsp;BTS&amp;nbsp;continued to shatter records left and right and break new ground for Korean artists. They're going into the new year with three number-one singles on the&amp;nbsp;Billboard&amp;nbsp;Hot 100, a whole quarantine album, and a Grammy nomination. And while the world got smaller, K-pop went bigger and bolder — sonically and aesthetically.&amp;nbsp; When the global coronavirus pandemic put an end to live touring, the K-pop industry brought the spectacle to our screens with&amp;nbsp;immersive live concert&amp;nbsp;experiences. The music never stopped, not even for a second&amp;nbsp; Whether you're a casual listener, a stan, or someone who's just genuinely curious to see what K-pop is all about,&amp;nbsp;here are 10 songs from the heat of KPOP that made the hard 2020 much easier and eventually took the world by storm. 1) BTS, 'Black Swan' (Map of the Soul: 7) BTS has connected with a worldwide fanbase in large part thanks to the universal-but-still-personal themes of their music, and 'Black Swan' represents one of their most intimate confessions. Dreamy, gloomy hip-hop soundscapes lay the backdrop for the chart-toppers to open up about their darkest fears: that they may one day fall out of love with music. Using the title as a metaphor – to represent both the one-of-a-kind phenomenon they are and the 2010 movie where a ballerina makes the ultimate sacrifice for her art – the superstar septet investigates their underlying anxieties whilst declaring that they won’t let fear win over passion in the end. It’s a full-fledged motion picture-packed into just over three minutes to tell a rare, real-life story of one of the world’s biggest stars 2) TXT, 'Can’t You See Me' (The Dream Chapter: ETERNITY) On 'Can’t You See Me' TXT pulls the dark undercurrent of their youthful whimsy out from under the bed. Crunchy electric guitars and a jaunty whistle add a refreshing contrast to the track’s trap underpinnings, but where it best exposes its murkiness is through the quintet's vocal performances. Alternating between distorted tremolo vocals, hushed whisper-raps, and delicate verses wisping like curls of smoke, the members’ voices lurch between dulcet and disorienting as they reveal the cracks in a friendship. Through unsettling sounds and an idyllic music video that devolves into something frightening, TXT lay bare a horror rarely spoken of: watching a friendship fade before your eyes 3) &amp;nbsp;Twice, “I CAN’T STOP ME” (Eyes Wide Open) Like Dua Lipa and Lady Gaga, Twice were hip to electro basslines this year in “I CAN’T STOP ME.” The girl group bask in the elastic, strobing synth that pulses under the glamorous nu-disco track, and it snaps into formation with the chorus. The song calls for a grand celebration, but they’re too distracted trying not to indulge in their own treacherous desires: “I just can’t go back anymore/ Out of control,” Chaeyoung sings before the rest of the group fully surrender to temptation. Twice fight to keep cool, though it’s hard to notice when they nail such a spotless performance. 4) WOODZ, “BUMP BUMP” (WOOPS!)&amp;nbsp; This was a great year for soloists in K-pop, and no one was more honest with themselves than WOODZ. The push-and-pull of any romance is often the most enticing yet stressful aspect of it all. Amidst airy promises from his lover is the dreary prospect of being left alone, but he approaches this mixed-messaging with a refreshing candour. In our own whirlpools of flirting and call backs, IG-reels and missed messages, “BUMP BUMP” was comfortingly straightforward – with WOODZ relaying what he wants, exactly how he wants it. It was the wrong year to be young and in love in 2020, but at least we had WOODZ to keep us company. 5) Weki Meki, “COOL” (NEW RULES) Weki Meki revamp their approach in 'Cool' by swapping their preppy dance-pop for steely electro. The group’s demeanor is as spartan as the icy beat, and they amplify their bratty voices to assert their flawlessness. Their cockiness peaks in the chorus, which doubles as a taunt and a mantra: &quot;Be hotter/ Beyond the control,” they sing like a drill instructor. “Get out of all the boring rules.” If “Cool” sounds standoffish, then the song succeeds at what it sets out to do. Weki Meki don’t aspire to be a role model for attainable, girl-crush cool but instead point out the gap between you and them. “Cool” is a conceited celebration of self, though sometimes it just feels satisfying to flaunt what you got. 6). GFRIEND, 'MAGO' (回:Walpurgis Night) 'MAGO' distils disco to its very best qualities, shimmering – quite literally – with synths and steady beats, building a heady, atmospheric high. As cohesive as it is musically, its magic lies in how perfectly it fits into the ethos of&amp;nbsp;回:Walpurgis Night.&amp;nbsp;The album&amp;nbsp;is built on the idea of modern witches, at the centre of which are women who exercise the same agency and power of the song’s namesake, and GFRIEND has fun while doing it. Interspersed with images of the girls dancing the night away – not what you’d expect from a concept dealing with the occult – are lyrics that brim with confidence and ambition. Instead of believing in fairy tales and waiting for a Prince Charming, their only love is the images of themselves smiling in the mirror. It’s a cheeky way to poke fun at how society perceives self-assured women since the title itself translates to 'wizard.' In celebrating their limitless ambition, 'MAGO' casts a spell that keeps you coming back for more. 7) SEVENTEEN, 'Left &amp;amp; Right' (Heng:garæ) 'LEFT &amp;amp; RIGHT' is so exuberant that every sound – from doorbell chimes to 808 cowbells, organ synth riffs to full-bodied brass&amp;nbsp; –&amp;nbsp; bursts forth like aural confetti. One could readily claim SEVENTEEN have made their own 'Cupid Shuffle' but they’re aiming for something beyond mere dance instructional: this is a song for transforming every moment into a cause for celebration. In a time when in-person parties aren’t possible, 'LEFT &amp;amp; RIGHT' converts bedrooms into dancefloors. And with exultant shouts and energized rapping, they tell you to keep your chin up, to run down red carpets, to&amp;nbsp;dance. SEVENTEEN act as leaders and hype men here, but the role they fill best is that of life coaches: despite their talk of races and finish lines, they exclaim that “not running is an answer too / who cares what we do.”&amp;nbsp; They grant permission to simply be: a reminder that surviving every day is enough right now. And after all, if you’re not moving forward, why not move &quot;LEFT &amp;amp; RIGHT,”&amp;nbsp;right? They understand something that should be taught in schools around the world: busting your ass should be supplemented with time spent shaking it.&amp;nbsp; 8) Apink, 'Dumhdurum' (LOOK) K-pop tends to be a young person's game – both the industry and its labels regularly shift their priorities to younger artists – but Apink’s 'Dumhdurum' makes an exceptional case for the continuing effort and investment in senior acts. The track opens with a swirling synth-pop hook strong enough to stand as a chorus on its own, before diving into verses and choruses that strike pop gold with just the right amount of catchy repetition and melancholy longing. Apink detail the complexity of remaining calm in the presence of a past love, even when one’s heart's still beating&amp;nbsp;dumhdurum&amp;nbsp;for them – a concept that could be difficult for younger groups to believably pull off. This mature message successfully connected with a large audience, and 'Dumhdurum' became a knockout success in both Korea (topping all local music charts) and the&amp;nbsp;Billboard&amp;nbsp;charts (tying for their longest-running hit on&amp;nbsp;World Digital Song Sales).&amp;nbsp; Nine years into their career, Apink are still more than equipped to bring their A-Game, and that deserves larger recognition all in itself for the industry to pay equal attention to both its senior and developing artists. Matured musical magic awaits. 9). EVERGLOW, 'LA DI DA' (-77.82x-78.29) Thanks to a virtual flattening of borders, musical trends in the States now get reflected in&amp;nbsp;K-pop in real-time. Throughout 2020 – in both the U.S. and South Korea – throwback sounds were ubiquitous. This year’s K-pop magnum opus, EVERGLOW’s 'LA DI DA' mirrored the US’ pop magnum opus, The Weeknd’s 'Blinding Lights' only months after its release. But where The Weeknd’s work is chilling and sinister in its search for love, EVERGLOW’s is a spry kiss-off to all the haters, the bad guys, and the players. A successful pastiche of the 80's that’s crafted by producer Ollipop, 'LA DI DA' blends myriad influences: the&amp;nbsp;layered cheerleader chants of Toni Basil's 'Mickey' the spunky girl power of Cyndi Lauper and the Go-Go's, the&amp;nbsp;na-na-nas&amp;nbsp;of Bananarama, and above all, the shimmering synth-pop sound that permeated the top half of that decade. 'LA DI DA' melds these all together, with K-pop twists: a killing part punctuated by handclaps, a tempo-shifting rap section carried by leader E:U, and an earworm of a melody evocative of early 2010's K-pop – a time when choruses were packed with hooky vocal melodies instead of hollow drops. 10) 'Lovesick Girls', BLACKPINK The arrival of BLACKPINK’s first&amp;nbsp;full-length album — so highly anticipated at the project was simply titled&amp;nbsp;The Album—was one of K-pop’s biggest news events in 2020. While the pre-release singles&amp;nbsp;'How You Like That'&amp;nbsp;and 'Ice Cream' with Selena Gomez charted higher on the Billboard Hot 100, 'Lovesick Girls' is the true gem on the album. The heavy electronic production characteristic of BLACKPINK’s crowd-riling bops remains intact, but it’s stripped back to accentuate sung melodies from the four members. Their voices are layered over an acoustic guitar to create a breezy and mellow ambience, taking a more pensive and melancholic turn from the hard-hitting nature of the group’s 2018 and 2019 title track. While 2020 has been far from a banner year for K-pop, with the coronavirus pandemic impacting the industry through disbandments, cancelled tours, and shelved comebacks, there have been enough pleasant surprises to keep fans plugged in. BTS’ success these days can make it hard to recall that they were once considered the underdogs of the K-pop industry. The seven-piece group didn’t come from a big management firm, and at the time of their debut, they stood out for not sounding (or looking) overly packaged or produced. Instead, BTS was built by their fans — the 'Army' — who rallied behind the group. This month, the Army’s influence has extended beyond music and into social justice, when the loyal fanbase helped to match the group’s&amp;nbsp;$1 million donation to Black Lives Matter. That followed a&amp;nbsp;coordinated campaign&amp;nbsp;by K-pop fans just days earlier, when fans came together to drown out the racist #WhiteLivesMatter hashtag on Twitter by spamming it with irreverent memes and fan cams. For anyone who still thought K-pop was a passing fad or a niche subset best left to the 'world music' fringes, the recent rallying of the fandoms (not to mention a host of spirited new releases) has underlined the fact that K-pop is more than just another overseas import — it’s officially a global force.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Critical Look at Female Representation in the Queen’s Gambit, Fate: The Winx Saga and Bridgerton</title>
      <link href="/A-Critical-Look-at-Female-Representation-in-the-Queen-s-Gambit-Fate-The-Winx-Saga-and-Bridgerton" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Critical Look at Female Representation in the Queen’s Gambit, Fate: The Winx Saga and Bridgerton" />
      <published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Critical-Look-at-Female-Representation-in-the-Queen-s-Gambit-Fate-The-Winx-Saga-and-Bridgerton</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Critical-Look-at-Female-Representation-in-the-Queen-s-Gambit-Fate-The-Winx-Saga-and-Bridgerton">&lt;p&gt;Female representation in cinema has been an area of contention for a while now. One of the most popular measures used to look for equality in representation of the sexes in movies is the Bechdel-Wallace test. To pass the test, the film under consideration has to have at least two female characters that have names and who converse with each other about anything other than men. It sounds very simple but unfortunately, a surprisingly large number of productions fail, even today. My time in quarantine over the past year gave me an opportunity to explore a variety of films and TV series; and in doing so, another issue made itself very prominent amongst countless others - misrepresentation of women and the relationships among them. In this article, I’ll be pointing out the absurd depiction and storylines involving female characters in &lt;em&gt;The Queen’s Gambit, Fate: The Winx Saga a&lt;/em&gt;nd &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Queen’s Gambit&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Queen’s Gambit is probably one of the best TV series that I have watched over the past year. However, it does have a glaring problem, one that is common in many modern day movies - the male gaze. “Male gaze” is a phrase coined by feminist thinker Laura Mulvey and in the context of cinema, it refers to the depiction of women as seen through a heterosexual male lens. The most commonly used example of this is the portrayal of female superheroes in unrealistic hypersexualised and non-functional costumes, such as the Black Widow or Wonder Woman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A girlboss character is one who is seen as a feminist, with talents and powers at par with or more than her male counterparts, yet still are characterised by the male gaze. For example, while Black Widow is a fan-favourite character with unparalleled combat skills and iconic one-liners, she is still a hypersexualised girlboss character, waiting to be elevated beyond her almost side-kick like status by her individual movie to be released next month after a decade of being a part of the MCU.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise Elizabeth “Beth” Harmon in &lt;em&gt;The Queen’s&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Gambit&lt;/em&gt; is a girlboss character. Depictions of “rock bottom” faced by women in cinema have been criticised for being sexist, eroticised and, overall, unrealistic throughout history. Beth is shown struggling with addiction and her past trauma throughout the miniseries. In one scene she is dancing around in her underwear, with perfectly shaved legs and with the camera following her rear end; apart from her indulging in alcoholic drinks or smoking cigarettes in order to showcase her version of “rock bottom”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to remember that mental health issues manifest in a spectrum of different ways in different people and this can be used to justify the artistic choices involved in the depiction of Beth’s struggles. However, it is easy to note that a man’s struggles with alcoholism or any other form of addiction would probably not have been portrayed similarly, and a conscious choice was involved in trying to make Harmon and her mental illness sexy - a gorgeous damsel in distress. In terms of entertainment, hyperbole and embellishment are common. But, unrealistic depictions of struggles of characters meant to be reflections of reality over and over again makes real people question their own struggles, and this often isolates them. Accurate representation is important, especially in a world where so many struggle with mental illnesses.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fate: The Winx Saga&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; is a Netflix remake of the beloved Italian animated TV series &lt;em&gt;Winx Club&lt;/em&gt;. The original series was extremely popular because of its colour palette, the fashion sense of the characters, the diversity and, of course, the friendship between the titular characters, all of whom were female.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; was meant to cater to the now 20+ year olds who grew up watching the iconic show as kids. However, as soon as the trailer dropped, fans of the original series were more than disappointed. It featured a very “&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'aged' sense of fashion, one that many described as far too old for fashionable teenagers of 2020/21. In addition, blatant whitewashing of the beloved characters like Musa (originally, East Asian coded) and Flora (originally, Latin coded but replaced in the new series with a white character named Terra) left viewers disappointed. There were various other issues with the trailer too like the lack of wings in spite of the characters being fairies, the absence of one of the lead characters, Tecna and so on.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the series finally aired early this year, the audience was left divided - some enjoyed the series while most others, who grew up watching the original, were not satisfied with the Netflix show. There are many reasons why I personally did not enjoy the series, but in this article I shall confine myself to discussions regarding the portrayal of women.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original series portrayed female characters as fairies or witches; and male characters as warriors designated as the “specialists”. These three categories of magical creatures attended three different schools located in Magix. The new TV series makes it abundantly clear right from the start that anyone can be a fairy or a specialist (witches don’t find a place in the franchise), which is a welcome change. However, my approval of the series probably ends here.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The series tries to portray itself as a story of very woke characters but fails at every step in actually living up to the claim. For example, in the very first scene, the protagonist Bloom, who is from Earth and is visiting the 'Other World' (where the school for fairies and specialists known as &lt;em&gt;Alfea&lt;/em&gt; is located for the first time), comes face to face with Sky, a specialist, who is Bloom’s love interest in both the original and the Netflix adaptation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sky offers help after noticing that Bloom is new to the school and is facing difficulty in finding her way around. Bloom tags this as 'mansplaining'. The choice of words sound almost like someone who is attempting to make fun of feminism by trying to give terms like mansplaining a meaning very different from what it really is in a way to undermine women’s experiences. Had Bloom known what she was doing, was aware of what Sky said about the school beforehand and didn't actually need help, then the use of the phrase 'mansplaining' would make sense. But she did in fact need help as Bloom was in a world that she admittedly didn't know existed up until a few months ago.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One striking difference between the original and &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; is the relationship between the lead characters: Bloom, Stella, Aisha, Terra and Musa. In &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt;, they are shown to be mean to each other before even getting to know each other. Their hurtful comments make no sense. They are seen trying to avoid being friends with each other and even crossing paths, again, without a reason. In the original, they enjoyed each other’s company, appreciated their individualities and supported each other through everything that life threw at them. In fact, the 'Winx Club' is what they named their friend group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt;, however, Winx is simply the name of the suite that they unfortunately had to share. Real life interactions between women (or anyone for that matter) who are meeting for the first time are rarely ever the way &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; describes it and is definitely much closer to the animation, except when internalised misogyny plays a role. &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt;’s version of a broken relationship between all female characters is unfortunately not uncommon in cinema. Animosity between women, shown to be a result of jealousy, is used as a plot line, even the main plot line, in shows very often. The lack of friendship and the chaotic energy that the audience of the original series so loved was painfully apparent and a punch in the face of those who were looking forward to the adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stella, clearly, absolutely despised Bloom. The show would let us know eventually that it is because Sky, who is now interested in Bloom, is Stella’s ex boyfriend - a standard love triangle trope. This trope is not only tired but also is solely created to cause friction between the female characters and reduce all their interactions. This, however, did not exist in the original. In &lt;em&gt;Winx Club&lt;/em&gt;, Stella was the one to discover Bloom on Earth and take her to &lt;em&gt;Alfea&lt;/em&gt;. The two were the closest of friends.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best friend’s position in &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; is taken up by Aisha, the only person of colour in the show. She is stripped of her extremely celebrated original storyline, much like all of the other characters, and reduced to an overachieving mother-like character to Bloom - serving yet another common and tired trope - the ‘Black best friend’. All of the characters were stripped of their individualities - their style, their backgrounds, their struggles and their personalities; in a weak attempt to make Bloom look like an interesting character. Unfortunately, the original &lt;em&gt;Winx Club&lt;/em&gt; was celebrated because of the diversity and extensive storyline, which the creators of &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; obviously failed to realise.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The series does make a feeble effort to overcome the biggest criticism of the original series: the lack of diversity in body shapes as each female character was portrayed with an unattainable hourglass figure while simultaneously being extremely thin. On the other hand, the male characters were tall, built and had very broad shoulders. There were very few exceptions to this. &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; introduced a singular plus size character through Terra - a token plus size character.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that the extras were also very thin made her standout. In addition, her entire storyline was reduced to a young girl always conscious and embarrassed of her size and as a result, always opting to cover up. Winx was a perfect opportunity to have a confident plus sized character with an incredible fashion sense and not make everything in her story revolve around her size, in contrast to almost all of the stories told by movies today that involve a curvy character.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My final criticism is about &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt;’s protagonist, Bloom and her unbearably annoying personality that again, is in stark contrast to the original Bloom. She comes across as a “I am not like the other girls'' type of female protagonist as she herself makes it clear to the show's audience by repeatedly mentioning how she is not very social or in any way like a cheerleader from Earth; and somehow that is indicative of her fairy ancestry.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, even while she is at &lt;em&gt;Alfea&lt;/em&gt;, her antics, attitude and sharp words make her come across as a, for the lack of a better phrase, self-important brat. She certainly doesn’t know how to treat those around herself including her suite mates well, and often makes rather dumb choices inspite of having Aisha always trying to babysit her. She however does realise this herself, only after she has caused more than enough trouble and the series has shown her to be indeed different from the others in the sense that she, someone who has been unaware of magic her entire life and has a meagre few months of training, is the most powerful fairy in the realm and has wings! Everyone loves a chosen one trope, but this particular instance has been handled terribly. Being rude does not make anyone cool or dark and mysterious, it just makes them super annoying.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, this entire series was a weak amalgamation of tired, problematic tropes that did not exist in the original series resulting in an absolute train wreck of a show that many were looking forward to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bridgerton has amassed an almost cult-like following with both commoners and celebrities repeatedly expressing their love for the show since its release in December, 2020. The series is based on the 2000 book &lt;em&gt;The Duke and I &lt;/em&gt;written by Julia Quinn. There have been a variety of critiques that have come up over the past few months, and rightfully so. Most of these are about how the show was marketed as one with a diverse cast but 'diverse', for the showrunners of &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt;, meant having only white and black characters. The show's queer baiting (due to gay sex scene in the trailer but a lack of a queer storyline in the actual show) and tone deaf handling of race as an issue (addressed only once in the series through an interaction between the Duke and Lady Danbury) has also been criticised.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rarely does it happen that Black characters are played by those of full black heritage. This is very evident in the case of &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; too. Marina Thompson and Simon Basset who are to be perceived as desirable are light skinned while the Duke’s late abusive father, Lady Danbury (a much older woman) and Will Mondrich (who fights for a living) are dark-skinned. Colourism, although not as highly discussed or debated as racism, is a very important issue, even within individual minority communities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My main criticism of the show is how the series is seen as empowering to women when in fact, it glamourises sexual assault. The titular female character, Daphne Bridgerton rapes her husband as she tries to get impregnated by him without his consent and in spite of him repeatedly asking her to stop. The following scenes make it look like Simon is at fault for lying when, in fact, he had been very clear in his intentions right from the beginning about not wanting to have kids. Whether it is that he cannot or does not want to have children is immaterial and Daphne should have respected his choice.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The show fails to call out Daphne for her act and she is shown to be mad at the Duke for “lying” to her. The scenes are set in a way that the audience is meant to take her side and view Simon’s anger at his wife as unjustified. It was a missed opportunity to actually call Daphne out and acknowledge that men can be victims of rape, women can rape men and marital rape is just as prevalent and unforgiveable. None of these discussions take place and when the Duke explains to Daphne about the abuse he experienced at the hands of his father, she simply sees it as not sufficient a reason to “lie” to her. The relationship between the two is very toxic and everything seems to be rectified by the two simply reiterating their love for each other and deciding that if they have a child, “nothing else will matter”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this is problematic enough in itself but the series takes it a step further by drawing a parallel between Daphne’s situation and that of Marina, a Black woman who at this point in the story believes that she has been abandoned by her lover and the father of her unborn child. Daphne offers to help her out - the, unfortunately, very common white saviour trope wherein white characters are portrayed as selfless saviours of characters of colour, an idea deep rooted in white supremacy. When Daphne comes to know that her efforts did not bear any fruit, she is seen crying. At no point in the series whatsoever is Simon’s position as a survivor of abuse and a victim of sexual assault viewed with sympathy and the show ends without Daphne apologising.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another women-related issue with the series is the treatment of period health. The portrayal might be true to the Regency era but frankly it is difficult to keep up with what is or isn’t meant to be accurate or morally right as per the Regency era in the show. Throughout the season Daphne and Marina are shown to check their bedsheets for bloodstains that would indicate periods. This, in their knowledge, would suggest that they are not pregnant. However, biologically, this is not the best way to check for pregnancy. Spotting or light bleeding during the first trimester, that is, implantation bleeding, is very common.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, implantation bleeding is a definitive proof of pregnancy contrary to what the characters believed. In addition, when the Duke talks to Daphne about self pleasure, he asks her to touch in between her legs. This in itself is a very vague instruction and seems to be made under an assumption that vaginal penetration is the only way, all or at least most, women experience orgasm. However, only 18% of women actually experience orgasm through vaginal penetration alone and thus, it is an abject misrepresentation of female pleasure. Of course, this has been an issue with video based media for a long time now. Pornography too is often criticised for being inaccurate when it comes to female pleasure and for setting unrealistic standards for women. Again, such notions were justified under the mask of the Regency era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, many of the issues discussed above can be easily done away with without affecting the main storyline too much. Errors associated with representation of women can be avoided to a large extent by ensuring that women tell women’s stories (&lt;em&gt;The Queen’s Gambit&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Fate: The Winx Saga&lt;/em&gt; have male showrunners and &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; has female showrunners). Most widely used tropes that have been discussed here are deeply-rooted in sexism, racism and homophobia. These tropes are tired and do not have a place in a world undergoing radical changes through the MeToo movement, the Black Lives Matter movement, Pride and so on and so forth. It is important that TV series and movies not only pass the Bechdel-Wallace test, which is the most basic requirement, but also accurately represent women, their problems, aspirations, desires and relationships.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Female representation in cinema has been an area of contention for a while now. One of the most popular measures used to look for equality in representation of the sexes in movies is the Bechdel-Wallace test. To pass the test, the film under consideration has to have at least two female characters that have names and who converse with each other about anything other than men. It sounds very simple but unfortunately, a surprisingly large number of productions fail, even today. My time in quarantine over the past year gave me an opportunity to explore a variety of films and TV series; and in doing so, another issue made itself very prominent amongst countless others - misrepresentation of women and the relationships among them. In this article, I’ll be pointing out the absurd depiction and storylines involving female characters in The Queen’s Gambit, Fate: The Winx Saga and Bridgerton.&amp;nbsp; The Queen’s Gambit The Queen’s Gambit is probably one of the best TV series that I have watched over the past year. However, it does have a glaring problem, one that is common in many modern day movies - the male gaze. “Male gaze” is a phrase coined by feminist thinker Laura Mulvey and in the context of cinema, it refers to the depiction of women as seen through a heterosexual male lens. The most commonly used example of this is the portrayal of female superheroes in unrealistic hypersexualised and non-functional costumes, such as the Black Widow or Wonder Woman. A girlboss character is one who is seen as a feminist, with talents and powers at par with or more than her male counterparts, yet still are characterised by the male gaze. For example, while Black Widow is a fan-favourite character with unparalleled combat skills and iconic one-liners, she is still a hypersexualised girlboss character, waiting to be elevated beyond her almost side-kick like status by her individual movie to be released next month after a decade of being a part of the MCU.&amp;nbsp; Likewise Elizabeth “Beth” Harmon in The Queen’s Gambit is a girlboss character. Depictions of “rock bottom” faced by women in cinema have been criticised for being sexist, eroticised and, overall, unrealistic throughout history. Beth is shown struggling with addiction and her past trauma throughout the miniseries. In one scene she is dancing around in her underwear, with perfectly shaved legs and with the camera following her rear end; apart from her indulging in alcoholic drinks or smoking cigarettes in order to showcase her version of “rock bottom”.&amp;nbsp; It is important to remember that mental health issues manifest in a spectrum of different ways in different people and this can be used to justify the artistic choices involved in the depiction of Beth’s struggles. However, it is easy to note that a man’s struggles with alcoholism or any other form of addiction would probably not have been portrayed similarly, and a conscious choice was involved in trying to make Harmon and her mental illness sexy - a gorgeous damsel in distress. In terms of entertainment, hyperbole and embellishment are common. But, unrealistic depictions of struggles of characters meant to be reflections of reality over and over again makes real people question their own struggles, and this often isolates them. Accurate representation is important, especially in a world where so many struggle with mental illnesses.&amp;nbsp; Fate: The Winx Saga Fate is a Netflix remake of the beloved Italian animated TV series Winx Club. The original series was extremely popular because of its colour palette, the fashion sense of the characters, the diversity and, of course, the friendship between the titular characters, all of whom were female.&amp;nbsp; Fate was meant to cater to the now 20+ year olds who grew up watching the iconic show as kids. However, as soon as the trailer dropped, fans of the original series were more than disappointed. It featured a very “ 'aged' sense of fashion, one that many described as far too old for fashionable teenagers of 2020/21. In addition, blatant whitewashing of the beloved characters like Musa (originally, East Asian coded) and Flora (originally, Latin coded but replaced in the new series with a white character named Terra) left viewers disappointed. There were various other issues with the trailer too like the lack of wings in spite of the characters being fairies, the absence of one of the lead characters, Tecna and so on.&amp;nbsp; When the series finally aired early this year, the audience was left divided - some enjoyed the series while most others, who grew up watching the original, were not satisfied with the Netflix show. There are many reasons why I personally did not enjoy the series, but in this article I shall confine myself to discussions regarding the portrayal of women.&amp;nbsp; The original series portrayed female characters as fairies or witches; and male characters as warriors designated as the “specialists”. These three categories of magical creatures attended three different schools located in Magix. The new TV series makes it abundantly clear right from the start that anyone can be a fairy or a specialist (witches don’t find a place in the franchise), which is a welcome change. However, my approval of the series probably ends here.&amp;nbsp; The series tries to portray itself as a story of very woke characters but fails at every step in actually living up to the claim. For example, in the very first scene, the protagonist Bloom, who is from Earth and is visiting the 'Other World' (where the school for fairies and specialists known as Alfea is located for the first time), comes face to face with Sky, a specialist, who is Bloom’s love interest in both the original and the Netflix adaptation.&amp;nbsp; Sky offers help after noticing that Bloom is new to the school and is facing difficulty in finding her way around. Bloom tags this as 'mansplaining'. The choice of words sound almost like someone who is attempting to make fun of feminism by trying to give terms like mansplaining a meaning very different from what it really is in a way to undermine women’s experiences. Had Bloom known what she was doing, was aware of what Sky said about the school beforehand and didn't actually need help, then the use of the phrase 'mansplaining' would make sense. But she did in fact need help as Bloom was in a world that she admittedly didn't know existed up until a few months ago.&amp;nbsp; One striking difference between the original and Fate is the relationship between the lead characters: Bloom, Stella, Aisha, Terra and Musa. In Fate, they are shown to be mean to each other before even getting to know each other. Their hurtful comments make no sense. They are seen trying to avoid being friends with each other and even crossing paths, again, without a reason. In the original, they enjoyed each other’s company, appreciated their individualities and supported each other through everything that life threw at them. In fact, the 'Winx Club' is what they named their friend group. In Fate, however, Winx is simply the name of the suite that they unfortunately had to share. Real life interactions between women (or anyone for that matter) who are meeting for the first time are rarely ever the way Fate describes it and is definitely much closer to the animation, except when internalised misogyny plays a role. Fate’s version of a broken relationship between all female characters is unfortunately not uncommon in cinema. Animosity between women, shown to be a result of jealousy, is used as a plot line, even the main plot line, in shows very often. The lack of friendship and the chaotic energy that the audience of the original series so loved was painfully apparent and a punch in the face of those who were looking forward to the adaptation. Stella, clearly, absolutely despised Bloom. The show would let us know eventually that it is because Sky, who is now interested in Bloom, is Stella’s ex boyfriend - a standard love triangle trope. This trope is not only tired but also is solely created to cause friction between the female characters and reduce all their interactions. This, however, did not exist in the original. In Winx Club, Stella was the one to discover Bloom on Earth and take her to Alfea. The two were the closest of friends.&amp;nbsp; The best friend’s position in Fate is taken up by Aisha, the only person of colour in the show. She is stripped of her extremely celebrated original storyline, much like all of the other characters, and reduced to an overachieving mother-like character to Bloom - serving yet another common and tired trope - the ‘Black best friend’. All of the characters were stripped of their individualities - their style, their backgrounds, their struggles and their personalities; in a weak attempt to make Bloom look like an interesting character. Unfortunately, the original Winx Club was celebrated because of the diversity and extensive storyline, which the creators of Fate obviously failed to realise.&amp;nbsp; The series does make a feeble effort to overcome the biggest criticism of the original series: the lack of diversity in body shapes as each female character was portrayed with an unattainable hourglass figure while simultaneously being extremely thin. On the other hand, the male characters were tall, built and had very broad shoulders. There were very few exceptions to this. Fate introduced a singular plus size character through Terra - a token plus size character.&amp;nbsp; The fact that the extras were also very thin made her standout. In addition, her entire storyline was reduced to a young girl always conscious and embarrassed of her size and as a result, always opting to cover up. Winx was a perfect opportunity to have a confident plus sized character with an incredible fashion sense and not make everything in her story revolve around her size, in contrast to almost all of the stories told by movies today that involve a curvy character.&amp;nbsp; My final criticism is about Fate’s protagonist, Bloom and her unbearably annoying personality that again, is in stark contrast to the original Bloom. She comes across as a “I am not like the other girls'' type of female protagonist as she herself makes it clear to the show's audience by repeatedly mentioning how she is not very social or in any way like a cheerleader from Earth; and somehow that is indicative of her fairy ancestry.&amp;nbsp; However, even while she is at Alfea, her antics, attitude and sharp words make her come across as a, for the lack of a better phrase, self-important brat. She certainly doesn’t know how to treat those around herself including her suite mates well, and often makes rather dumb choices inspite of having Aisha always trying to babysit her. She however does realise this herself, only after she has caused more than enough trouble and the series has shown her to be indeed different from the others in the sense that she, someone who has been unaware of magic her entire life and has a meagre few months of training, is the most powerful fairy in the realm and has wings! Everyone loves a chosen one trope, but this particular instance has been handled terribly. Being rude does not make anyone cool or dark and mysterious, it just makes them super annoying.&amp;nbsp; Clearly, this entire series was a weak amalgamation of tired, problematic tropes that did not exist in the original series resulting in an absolute train wreck of a show that many were looking forward to. Bridgerton Bridgerton has amassed an almost cult-like following with both commoners and celebrities repeatedly expressing their love for the show since its release in December, 2020. The series is based on the 2000 book The Duke and I written by Julia Quinn. There have been a variety of critiques that have come up over the past few months, and rightfully so. Most of these are about how the show was marketed as one with a diverse cast but 'diverse', for the showrunners of Bridgerton, meant having only white and black characters. The show's queer baiting (due to gay sex scene in the trailer but a lack of a queer storyline in the actual show) and tone deaf handling of race as an issue (addressed only once in the series through an interaction between the Duke and Lady Danbury) has also been criticised.&amp;nbsp; Rarely does it happen that Black characters are played by those of full black heritage. This is very evident in the case of Bridgerton too. Marina Thompson and Simon Basset who are to be perceived as desirable are light skinned while the Duke’s late abusive father, Lady Danbury (a much older woman) and Will Mondrich (who fights for a living) are dark-skinned. Colourism, although not as highly discussed or debated as racism, is a very important issue, even within individual minority communities.&amp;nbsp; My main criticism of the show is how the series is seen as empowering to women when in fact, it glamourises sexual assault. The titular female character, Daphne Bridgerton rapes her husband as she tries to get impregnated by him without his consent and in spite of him repeatedly asking her to stop. The following scenes make it look like Simon is at fault for lying when, in fact, he had been very clear in his intentions right from the beginning about not wanting to have kids. Whether it is that he cannot or does not want to have children is immaterial and Daphne should have respected his choice.&amp;nbsp; The show fails to call out Daphne for her act and she is shown to be mad at the Duke for “lying” to her. The scenes are set in a way that the audience is meant to take her side and view Simon’s anger at his wife as unjustified. It was a missed opportunity to actually call Daphne out and acknowledge that men can be victims of rape, women can rape men and marital rape is just as prevalent and unforgiveable. None of these discussions take place and when the Duke explains to Daphne about the abuse he experienced at the hands of his father, she simply sees it as not sufficient a reason to “lie” to her. The relationship between the two is very toxic and everything seems to be rectified by the two simply reiterating their love for each other and deciding that if they have a child, “nothing else will matter”.&amp;nbsp; All this is problematic enough in itself but the series takes it a step further by drawing a parallel between Daphne’s situation and that of Marina, a Black woman who at this point in the story believes that she has been abandoned by her lover and the father of her unborn child. Daphne offers to help her out - the, unfortunately, very common white saviour trope wherein white characters are portrayed as selfless saviours of characters of colour, an idea deep rooted in white supremacy. When Daphne comes to know that her efforts did not bear any fruit, she is seen crying. At no point in the series whatsoever is Simon’s position as a survivor of abuse and a victim of sexual assault viewed with sympathy and the show ends without Daphne apologising.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Another women-related issue with the series is the treatment of period health. The portrayal might be true to the Regency era but frankly it is difficult to keep up with what is or isn’t meant to be accurate or morally right as per the Regency era in the show. Throughout the season Daphne and Marina are shown to check their bedsheets for bloodstains that would indicate periods. This, in their knowledge, would suggest that they are not pregnant. However, biologically, this is not the best way to check for pregnancy. Spotting or light bleeding during the first trimester, that is, implantation bleeding, is very common.&amp;nbsp; In fact, implantation bleeding is a definitive proof of pregnancy contrary to what the characters believed. In addition, when the Duke talks to Daphne about self pleasure, he asks her to touch in between her legs. This in itself is a very vague instruction and seems to be made under an assumption that vaginal penetration is the only way, all or at least most, women experience orgasm. However, only 18% of women actually experience orgasm through vaginal penetration alone and thus, it is an abject misrepresentation of female pleasure. Of course, this has been an issue with video based media for a long time now. Pornography too is often criticised for being inaccurate when it comes to female pleasure and for setting unrealistic standards for women. Again, such notions were justified under the mask of the Regency era. Clearly, many of the issues discussed above can be easily done away with without affecting the main storyline too much. Errors associated with representation of women can be avoided to a large extent by ensuring that women tell women’s stories (The Queen’s Gambit and Fate: The Winx Saga have male showrunners and Bridgerton has female showrunners). Most widely used tropes that have been discussed here are deeply-rooted in sexism, racism and homophobia. These tropes are tired and do not have a place in a world undergoing radical changes through the MeToo movement, the Black Lives Matter movement, Pride and so on and so forth. It is important that TV series and movies not only pass the Bechdel-Wallace test, which is the most basic requirement, but also accurately represent women, their problems, aspirations, desires and relationships.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Makeup Conundrum</title>
      <link href="/The-Makeup-Conundrum" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Makeup Conundrum" />
      <published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Makeup-Conundrum</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Makeup-Conundrum">&lt;p&gt;Makeup is a very fascinating mode of self-expression. It is also a central part of many cultures across the globe. It is beautiful and is respected, but only within certain unspoken limits that are decided by the society in question.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People often judge one’s personality by the amount and kind of makeup they are wearing. It can be either 'feminine’ and beautiful or unprofessional and frivolous. Not to mention, this is applicable only to one gender and everyone else is expected to not understand anything about it. In fact, they are expected to stay away from makeup, and when they do not follow this rule, they are seen as “unnatural”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Indians, like many other cultures, makeup is auspicious. A specific kind of makeup is reserved for each occasion or milestone in one’s life like engagement or wedding and of course, this varies from culture to culture. If you have, by any chance, come across an Indian TV serial or movie, you will know that more often than not, makeup is used to express certain character traits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, the female protagonist, who is shown to be a rather innocent and naive person, characteristics that we see being appreciated in female characters almost globally, has natural makeup on. On the other hand, the female antagonist tends to have very heavy makeup on, often playing with darker shades of red and black. This results in and is born out of an unconscious association of heavy or dark makeup with being promiscuous or a bad person.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moral policing in schools, especially in India, where I am from, is not rare. The administration and teachers often question the character of female students who choose to express themselves through different hairstyles or even just a simple eyeliner. It has been so ingrained in our psyche that most of us never even questioned it and in fact, were, to a large extent, in agreement with the policing. Makeup is simply a form of expression and associating it with not being serious about education is simply baseless and a way to control women. If a simple eyeliner is 'disruptive', we are definitely going wrong somewhere in our education system.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An extension of this is the idea that women wear makeup solely to attract men. In fact, this is often used to shame girls in schools (at least, in India) who are found wearing anything that can be remotely associated with makeup. Honestly, if a little makeup distracts boys and men, they need to be taught to not sexualise anything and everything that is considered 'feminine' by society. Instead, school girls face punishment, sometimes to the extent of getting suspended.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When someone with authority suspends someone over wearing makeup, with the reason that it deviates attention from what is the main purpose of school, that is education, and more importantly, that it distracts the 'boys', it is a clear proclamation that they are unwilling to put an effort to teach boys to be respectful and are more satisfied with sending the person wearing makeup home, because their education is simply not as important as that of the boys.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point of the matter is that makeup is simply a form of art. Neither should it be gendered nor should it be associated with a certain intention or personality trait. Some people wear makeup because of insecurities, some wear it because they enjoy it, some do it as a form of art and expression, some do it because it makes them feel confident - there is a myriad of reasons for wearing makeup.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This association of makeup with being frivolous or in other words, 'girly', a trait usually seen as negative and associated with not being serious, hardworking or trustworthy, has been around for a while now. In fact, many women who are victims of internalised misogyny fail to notice the problem.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2016, a young graphic designer, Katherine Young re-created the cover of &lt;em&gt;Girls’ Life&lt;/em&gt; magazine. The original cover that featured Olivia Holt and articles like ‘Your Dream Hair’ and ‘The ‘New’ Denim Checklist’ changed into one that featured Olivia Hallisey (2015 Google Science Fair winner) and articles like ‘Your Dream Career’ and ‘The ‘New’ Dreamer Checklist’. This was widely appreciated. However, what I don’t understand is this: why can’t a life magazine targeted at young females feature both ends of the spectrum - articles on fashion and makeup, as well as other career choices?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, it seems rather demeaning to view a successful actress with perfectly done make-up and a fashion-forward outfit as less accomplished or not symbolic of an empowered woman, than a girl with a successful STEM career. I agree that STEM girls are fewer in number and they do not get as much support, but bringing down one girl to pull up another is a bad strategy. What is required is a balance - women should be represented in all fields and all kinds of interests should be equally catered to and appreciated.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cultures, women are expected to wear heavy makeup to conform to a very restrictive standard of beauty. This is, more often than not, influenced by Western ideals: sharp nose, fair skin, straight hair, oval face, etc. Women face societal pressure to use makeup to live up to these standards, lest they be misunderstood as not being serious or worth listening to or, worst of all, ugly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cultures, women’s worth is defined by how easy it is to “marry her off” and being conventionally pretty helps the process. Yet, when they post their own pictures on social media looking absolutely gorgeous with makeup on, they are swarmed with messages about how she would look prettier without makeup or how a certain person prefers women who don't wear makeup. In male-dominated office spaces, women who dress up or wear makeup often find it difficult to be taken seriously and are repeatedly sexualised - makeup is seen as unprofessional. Yet, when they don’t, they are not seen as well put together or are questioned if they are sick. The double standards are quite frankly, astonishing and hilarious.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of Hollywood’s beloved movies with 'ugly duckling transformation' sequences continue to propagate the idea that someone who isn't wearing makeup, is not really taking care of themselves and so, is not taken seriously. Until of course, the transformation sequence takes place and suddenly, everything she says makes sense and is worth listening to. Yet, the same movie has a jealous female character, portrayed as someone who understands only clothes and makeup, hell-bent upon making the protagonist’s life miserable for no apparent reason. The amount of knowledge concerning makeup makes all the difference in the personalities in these movies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In South Korea, beauty standards are very strict and this often pushes youngsters to opt for plastic surgery simply to make their lives easier by being able to conform to the unrealistic Korean beauty standards. Over the last couple of years, K-beauty has made a mark on the Western world. However, it is now facing backlash from within Korea’s borders. Influencers and commoners alike want to see a shift in the standards that pressurise women to go to extreme lengths to attain an unrealistic youthful look appreciated by society.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Escape the Corset, #metoo and other similar feminist movements have seen Korean women openly expressing their dissatisfaction with the highly unequal and unfair societal norms through demonstrations like cutting their hair short and destroying makeup, among others. In June of 2018, Lina Bae, a former beauty Youtuber, posted a video titled 'I am not pretty'. The video concludes with her asking her audience to not compare themselves to what the media portrays as beautiful because they are special just the way they are.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This message was appreciated by a large audience and the video went viral and was watched several million times. However, Korean media continues to worship a very specific look, a look that Korean idols continue to feel pressured to starve themselves and go under the knife to achieve. There are very few popular exceptions like Hwasa and Jessi, and they are treated as just that, exceptions in their place because idols are meant to be thin, tall and fair.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is more interesting is that society sometimes tends to have different expectations, in terms of beauty, from people of different races or ethnic backgrounds. For example, big lips and dark skin is not appreciated on black girls and yet, that seems to be the most appreciated 'look' on white women. Kim Kardashian and Kylie Jenner are frequently called out for their choices that are best described as blackfishing or black faces. However, the impact is short lived and the same mistakes are made over and over again. Blackface was a popular form of makeup used by white actors to portray a caricature of a black person for a long time. The portrayals were nowhere near accurate and were primarily meant to dehumanise and make fun of black people. So, you can see why people are not fond of such trends and rightfully so.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fox eyes are all the rage right now, with Bella Hadid making several magazine covers and fashion shows with the look, while East Asians, with monolids and natural fox eyes are frequently attacked and criticised for their looks. The 'migraine pose' that these models often use to pull the eyes up to give a fox eye effect is identical to the racially charged gesture made to make fun of East Asians. It is important to remember that this is not a recent issue.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 1930's, Cecil Holland, a Hollywood makeup artist used various techniques to simulate East Asian fox eyes on white actors to portray Asian characters, often villains. This was practised for a very long time and gave us characters like Fu Manchu and I Y Yunioshi (&lt;em&gt;Breakfast at Tiffany’s&lt;/em&gt;), both played by white actors.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to genders other than cis-females, makeup is treated very differently. It's very clear from Candance Owen’s remarks on Harry Styles’ &lt;em&gt;Vogue&lt;/em&gt; cover wearing traditionally feminine garments: “Bring back manly men”, that the conservative world is not very appreciative of makeup on men. They are often victims of homophobic slurs, when love for creative expression through makeup has absolutely nothing to do with one’s sexuality. Drag makeup is often criticised too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disagreement often comes in the form of a claim that makeup was meant to be feminine and thus, should be reserved for women. This is actually objectively false, because it was only in the mid-1800's when makeup started to be associated with a particular gender. Queen Victoria I of Britain and the Church agreed that makeup was an “abomination” resulting in a widespread and long-standing association of it with femininity and the “Devil’s Work”. These ideas were exported with imperialism and colonialism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, prior to that, men were often seen dawning makeup. In ancient Egypt, makeup was an integral part of the culture and had various religious connotations and so, makeup was worn, irrespective of gender. In ancient Rome, men often used makeup to cover up bald spots, lightened their skin using white powder, applied red pigment on their cheeks and so on and so forth. Even in Elizabethan England, makeup was popular among men. The influence of the Victorian age would start dying out only when Hollywood started using makeup on actors. However, they were still not mainstream. In the late 20th century, rock and roll artists started expressing themselves through makeup. Even today, as multiple male makeup gurus dominate the internet, many are wary of men wearing makeup in everyday life. However, this gendered aspect of makeup is clearly very new and for thousands of years, starting around 4000 BC to the mid-1800's, makeup was very common among men.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, a lot of associations, often negative, made with makeup are baseless and are only an attempt to control women and demean those who do not agree with the modern societal interpretations of 'femininity' and 'masculinity'. Most of these are a result of internalised misogyny and perception of anything “girly” as frivolous and not serious. These have long-standing consequences in terms of forcing women to opt for extreme measures to adhere to beauty standards and to escape the constant scrutiny based on their looks, and alternatively, toning it down to be taken seriously in certain male-dominated spaces. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Makeup is a very fascinating mode of self-expression. It is also a central part of many cultures across the globe. It is beautiful and is respected, but only within certain unspoken limits that are decided by the society in question.&amp;nbsp; People often judge one’s personality by the amount and kind of makeup they are wearing. It can be either 'feminine’ and beautiful or unprofessional and frivolous. Not to mention, this is applicable only to one gender and everyone else is expected to not understand anything about it. In fact, they are expected to stay away from makeup, and when they do not follow this rule, they are seen as “unnatural”.&amp;nbsp; For Indians, like many other cultures, makeup is auspicious. A specific kind of makeup is reserved for each occasion or milestone in one’s life like engagement or wedding and of course, this varies from culture to culture. If you have, by any chance, come across an Indian TV serial or movie, you will know that more often than not, makeup is used to express certain character traits.&amp;nbsp; Generally, the female protagonist, who is shown to be a rather innocent and naive person, characteristics that we see being appreciated in female characters almost globally, has natural makeup on. On the other hand, the female antagonist tends to have very heavy makeup on, often playing with darker shades of red and black. This results in and is born out of an unconscious association of heavy or dark makeup with being promiscuous or a bad person.&amp;nbsp; Moral policing in schools, especially in India, where I am from, is not rare. The administration and teachers often question the character of female students who choose to express themselves through different hairstyles or even just a simple eyeliner. It has been so ingrained in our psyche that most of us never even questioned it and in fact, were, to a large extent, in agreement with the policing. Makeup is simply a form of expression and associating it with not being serious about education is simply baseless and a way to control women. If a simple eyeliner is 'disruptive', we are definitely going wrong somewhere in our education system.&amp;nbsp; An extension of this is the idea that women wear makeup solely to attract men. In fact, this is often used to shame girls in schools (at least, in India) who are found wearing anything that can be remotely associated with makeup. Honestly, if a little makeup distracts boys and men, they need to be taught to not sexualise anything and everything that is considered 'feminine' by society. Instead, school girls face punishment, sometimes to the extent of getting suspended.&amp;nbsp; When someone with authority suspends someone over wearing makeup, with the reason that it deviates attention from what is the main purpose of school, that is education, and more importantly, that it distracts the 'boys', it is a clear proclamation that they are unwilling to put an effort to teach boys to be respectful and are more satisfied with sending the person wearing makeup home, because their education is simply not as important as that of the boys.&amp;nbsp; The point of the matter is that makeup is simply a form of art. Neither should it be gendered nor should it be associated with a certain intention or personality trait. Some people wear makeup because of insecurities, some wear it because they enjoy it, some do it as a form of art and expression, some do it because it makes them feel confident - there is a myriad of reasons for wearing makeup.&amp;nbsp; This association of makeup with being frivolous or in other words, 'girly', a trait usually seen as negative and associated with not being serious, hardworking or trustworthy, has been around for a while now. In fact, many women who are victims of internalised misogyny fail to notice the problem.&amp;nbsp; In 2016, a young graphic designer, Katherine Young re-created the cover of Girls’ Life magazine. The original cover that featured Olivia Holt and articles like ‘Your Dream Hair’ and ‘The ‘New’ Denim Checklist’ changed into one that featured Olivia Hallisey (2015 Google Science Fair winner) and articles like ‘Your Dream Career’ and ‘The ‘New’ Dreamer Checklist’. This was widely appreciated. However, what I don’t understand is this: why can’t a life magazine targeted at young females feature both ends of the spectrum - articles on fashion and makeup, as well as other career choices?&amp;nbsp; Secondly, it seems rather demeaning to view a successful actress with perfectly done make-up and a fashion-forward outfit as less accomplished or not symbolic of an empowered woman, than a girl with a successful STEM career. I agree that STEM girls are fewer in number and they do not get as much support, but bringing down one girl to pull up another is a bad strategy. What is required is a balance - women should be represented in all fields and all kinds of interests should be equally catered to and appreciated.&amp;nbsp; In some cultures, women are expected to wear heavy makeup to conform to a very restrictive standard of beauty. This is, more often than not, influenced by Western ideals: sharp nose, fair skin, straight hair, oval face, etc. Women face societal pressure to use makeup to live up to these standards, lest they be misunderstood as not being serious or worth listening to or, worst of all, ugly. In many cultures, women’s worth is defined by how easy it is to “marry her off” and being conventionally pretty helps the process. Yet, when they post their own pictures on social media looking absolutely gorgeous with makeup on, they are swarmed with messages about how she would look prettier without makeup or how a certain person prefers women who don't wear makeup. In male-dominated office spaces, women who dress up or wear makeup often find it difficult to be taken seriously and are repeatedly sexualised - makeup is seen as unprofessional. Yet, when they don’t, they are not seen as well put together or are questioned if they are sick. The double standards are quite frankly, astonishing and hilarious.&amp;nbsp; Many of Hollywood’s beloved movies with 'ugly duckling transformation' sequences continue to propagate the idea that someone who isn't wearing makeup, is not really taking care of themselves and so, is not taken seriously. Until of course, the transformation sequence takes place and suddenly, everything she says makes sense and is worth listening to. Yet, the same movie has a jealous female character, portrayed as someone who understands only clothes and makeup, hell-bent upon making the protagonist’s life miserable for no apparent reason. The amount of knowledge concerning makeup makes all the difference in the personalities in these movies. In South Korea, beauty standards are very strict and this often pushes youngsters to opt for plastic surgery simply to make their lives easier by being able to conform to the unrealistic Korean beauty standards. Over the last couple of years, K-beauty has made a mark on the Western world. However, it is now facing backlash from within Korea’s borders. Influencers and commoners alike want to see a shift in the standards that pressurise women to go to extreme lengths to attain an unrealistic youthful look appreciated by society.&amp;nbsp; The Escape the Corset, #metoo and other similar feminist movements have seen Korean women openly expressing their dissatisfaction with the highly unequal and unfair societal norms through demonstrations like cutting their hair short and destroying makeup, among others. In June of 2018, Lina Bae, a former beauty Youtuber, posted a video titled 'I am not pretty'. The video concludes with her asking her audience to not compare themselves to what the media portrays as beautiful because they are special just the way they are.&amp;nbsp; This message was appreciated by a large audience and the video went viral and was watched several million times. However, Korean media continues to worship a very specific look, a look that Korean idols continue to feel pressured to starve themselves and go under the knife to achieve. There are very few popular exceptions like Hwasa and Jessi, and they are treated as just that, exceptions in their place because idols are meant to be thin, tall and fair.&amp;nbsp; What is more interesting is that society sometimes tends to have different expectations, in terms of beauty, from people of different races or ethnic backgrounds. For example, big lips and dark skin is not appreciated on black girls and yet, that seems to be the most appreciated 'look' on white women. Kim Kardashian and Kylie Jenner are frequently called out for their choices that are best described as blackfishing or black faces. However, the impact is short lived and the same mistakes are made over and over again. Blackface was a popular form of makeup used by white actors to portray a caricature of a black person for a long time. The portrayals were nowhere near accurate and were primarily meant to dehumanise and make fun of black people. So, you can see why people are not fond of such trends and rightfully so.&amp;nbsp; Fox eyes are all the rage right now, with Bella Hadid making several magazine covers and fashion shows with the look, while East Asians, with monolids and natural fox eyes are frequently attacked and criticised for their looks. The 'migraine pose' that these models often use to pull the eyes up to give a fox eye effect is identical to the racially charged gesture made to make fun of East Asians. It is important to remember that this is not a recent issue.&amp;nbsp; In the 1930's, Cecil Holland, a Hollywood makeup artist used various techniques to simulate East Asian fox eyes on white actors to portray Asian characters, often villains. This was practised for a very long time and gave us characters like Fu Manchu and I Y Yunioshi (Breakfast at Tiffany’s), both played by white actors.&amp;nbsp; When it comes to genders other than cis-females, makeup is treated very differently. It's very clear from Candance Owen’s remarks on Harry Styles’ Vogue cover wearing traditionally feminine garments: “Bring back manly men”, that the conservative world is not very appreciative of makeup on men. They are often victims of homophobic slurs, when love for creative expression through makeup has absolutely nothing to do with one’s sexuality. Drag makeup is often criticised too.&amp;nbsp; The disagreement often comes in the form of a claim that makeup was meant to be feminine and thus, should be reserved for women. This is actually objectively false, because it was only in the mid-1800's when makeup started to be associated with a particular gender. Queen Victoria I of Britain and the Church agreed that makeup was an “abomination” resulting in a widespread and long-standing association of it with femininity and the “Devil’s Work”. These ideas were exported with imperialism and colonialism.&amp;nbsp; However, prior to that, men were often seen dawning makeup. In ancient Egypt, makeup was an integral part of the culture and had various religious connotations and so, makeup was worn, irrespective of gender. In ancient Rome, men often used makeup to cover up bald spots, lightened their skin using white powder, applied red pigment on their cheeks and so on and so forth. Even in Elizabethan England, makeup was popular among men. The influence of the Victorian age would start dying out only when Hollywood started using makeup on actors. However, they were still not mainstream. In the late 20th century, rock and roll artists started expressing themselves through makeup. Even today, as multiple male makeup gurus dominate the internet, many are wary of men wearing makeup in everyday life. However, this gendered aspect of makeup is clearly very new and for thousands of years, starting around 4000 BC to the mid-1800's, makeup was very common among men.&amp;nbsp; Clearly, a lot of associations, often negative, made with makeup are baseless and are only an attempt to control women and demean those who do not agree with the modern societal interpretations of 'femininity' and 'masculinity'. Most of these are a result of internalised misogyny and perception of anything “girly” as frivolous and not serious. These have long-standing consequences in terms of forcing women to opt for extreme measures to adhere to beauty standards and to escape the constant scrutiny based on their looks, and alternatively, toning it down to be taken seriously in certain male-dominated spaces.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">SKY Castle: What Happens When Adults Don’t Act Like Adults?</title>
      <link href="/SKY-Castle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SKY Castle: What Happens When Adults Don't Act Like Adults?" />
      <published>2020-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/SKY-Castle</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/SKY-Castle">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;We all lie&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tell you the truths&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sometimes we laugh and easily lie&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;SKY Castle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is a satirical, dark comedy-drama that revolves around the lives of four elite families living in the SKY Castle neighbourhood, situated in the suburbs of Seoul. In reality, &lt;em&gt;SKY&lt;/em&gt; is an acronym for the three renowned colleges of South Korea, namely, Seoul National University (SNU), Korea University and Yonsei University. SKY neighbourhood is home to top doctors and a prosecutor turned professor, who all want their children to live a worthy life, which according to them, can only be achieved if they get into one of these above-mentioned colleges. Thus, the story revolves around the Korean National College Exam, &lt;em&gt;Suneung&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The show, like most K-drama shows, starts with a straightforward story but manages to leave the audience baffled with its twists and turns. It's a really well-crafted show that makes its audience grip to their screens since the first episode itself. What is commendable about &lt;em&gt;SKY Castle&lt;/em&gt; is that despite its twists, never once does it distract itself from the main plot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first episode opens with a party being thrown to celebrate the Park family; whose son got into the Seoul National Medical School. But more than being happy, the other families are interested in knowing the methods that led to his admission. As it turns out, an expensive entrance exam coordinator made this possible. Therefore, this information starts a fight to hire her at an exclusive VVIP party. This coordinator who goes by the name of Kim Joo-Young chooses to teach Ye-Seo, whose only dream has been to get admission in Seoul National Medical College.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A dark cloud falls over the Park family when Lee Myung-Joo, the mother, decides to take her own life. We notice that Kim Joo-Young, the exceptional coordinator, definitely had something to do with it. However, Ye-Seo’s mother, even after finding it all out, is willing to look past all this because all she wants is to see her daughter get into SNU. With such a tragedy, Park family decides to move out and this opens the door for a new family to move in. This new family, Hwang family, have a simple and relaxed outlook towards life which clearly doesn't sit well with the other families. From questioning Lee So Im’s teaching methods to constantly treating her as an outsider, they really do give the Hwang family a hard time. Even at the hospital, Dr Hwang, who wants to treat the patients and interns with utmost respect, is criticised by Dr Kang, Ye-Seo’s father, who is more inclined towards making money and asserting his authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With each passing episode, we realise that Joo-Young’s flawless result isn’t a work of her own credibility, but her ability to cheat her ways through. Besides, all the families who have hired her have faced consequences similar to the Park family. But by the time Ye-Seo or her mother became aware of this, they are in too deep in to take a step back. What further unfolds is the lie that Joo-Young managed to hide for all these years, which is also the reason behind her desire to destroy each and every family that hires her. At this point, I thought I couldn't possibly dislike this character more, but what happens in the remaining episodes clearly left me speechless.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other two families living in the SKY Castle neighbourhood include the Cha and Woo families, who have more of a side role to play. In the&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Cha family, Min-Hyuk (the head of the family) being the prosecutor turned professor, wants his kids to reach the “&lt;em&gt;top of the pyramid&lt;/em&gt;” which he himself failed to do. He forces his dreams on his kids through means that only bear negative results. With the twin boys being average at school, which is obviously something that Min-Hyuk cannot deal with, to the eldest daughter lying about being in Harvard, all of it is a result of him constantly pressuring them. On the other hand, Noh Seung-Hye is an understanding mother who clearly sees through Min-Hyuk’s methods and is willing to end her marriage if that is what it takes to save her children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last is the Woo family, and here we see a mother struggling to find a balance between keeping her child happy but also wanting him to study hard and get into SKY. With Dr Woo working under Dr Kang, we constantly see them trying to be on the good side of the Kang family. Not to mention, this family really adds the much-needed elements of comedy that takes this show on another tangent altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fifth episode, we come across a new character Kim Hye-na, a bold kid studying in the same class as Ye-Seo. Despite her being a poor child, with a sick mother admitted in the hospital, she still manages to surpass Ye-Seo in academics. Ye-Seo, being a child who cannot stand failure, and her mother, who cannot see her child upset, clearly don't take this well. Ye-Seo’s mother even goes out of her way to tell Hye-na to not mess with Ye-Seo and her goal. To be honest, initially, I didn’t think that her role could be any more than a classmate, but the story that revolves around Hye-na's life leaves Ye-Seo’s goal of SNU Medical School, shaken to its very core.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This show started with a rating of as low as 1%, and halfway through the show, it managed to reach skyrocketing numbers. It has nothing common with the popular K-dramas that revolve around romance, which is also why it is my favourite show. &lt;em&gt;SKY Castle &lt;/em&gt;is rather a series that very smartly raises some of the darkest issues that exist in societies all across the globe, especially around Korea’s Scholastic Ability Test, &lt;em&gt;Suneung&lt;/em&gt;. With a cast so carefully chosen, and with every actor being true to their role, this show really proves why it received such high ratings. From highlighting the harsh reality of the Korean educational system and how it can take a toll on the mental health of children (since all of them are told is to get into SKY), it also portrays how the elite families are willing to go beyond their means to get their children into a good college, by spending huge sums of money or even adopting ways not available to a normal family. It constantly emphasises how parents tend to force their unachieved dreams and ambitions on their children without asking them what they really want, which can have unforeseen consequences. The other thing that needs to be mentioned is the original soundtrack, &quot;&lt;em&gt;We all lie&lt;/em&gt;&quot;. This soundtrack is so brilliantly curated that it works perfectly with the storyline. And it is definitely one of those songs I found myself going back to. Also, the added bonus being that it's entirely an English song, strategically used to pull international audiences to the show.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I agree with the majority audience that the last episode could have been better, but by no means does it destroy the very essence of the show and what it's trying to put forward. Throughout the show, we are made to realise that if Ye-Seo's mother wasn't so selfish towards her child's goal, this all could have been easily avoided. But then, we wouldn't have gotten this masterpiece to binge-watch. Therefore, I recommend this show to the audiences as it has a message relevant to all age groups. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Priyanshi Mehra</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“We all lie Tell you the truths Sometimes we laugh and easily lie” &amp;nbsp;SKY Castle is a satirical, dark comedy-drama that revolves around the lives of four elite families living in the SKY Castle neighbourhood, situated in the suburbs of Seoul. In reality, SKY is an acronym for the three renowned colleges of South Korea, namely, Seoul National University (SNU), Korea University and Yonsei University. SKY neighbourhood is home to top doctors and a prosecutor turned professor, who all want their children to live a worthy life, which according to them, can only be achieved if they get into one of these above-mentioned colleges. Thus, the story revolves around the Korean National College Exam, Suneung. The show, like most K-drama shows, starts with a straightforward story but manages to leave the audience baffled with its twists and turns. It's a really well-crafted show that makes its audience grip to their screens since the first episode itself. What is commendable about SKY Castle is that despite its twists, never once does it distract itself from the main plot. The first episode opens with a party being thrown to celebrate the Park family; whose son got into the Seoul National Medical School. But more than being happy, the other families are interested in knowing the methods that led to his admission. As it turns out, an expensive entrance exam coordinator made this possible. Therefore, this information starts a fight to hire her at an exclusive VVIP party. This coordinator who goes by the name of Kim Joo-Young chooses to teach Ye-Seo, whose only dream has been to get admission in Seoul National Medical College. A dark cloud falls over the Park family when Lee Myung-Joo, the mother, decides to take her own life. We notice that Kim Joo-Young, the exceptional coordinator, definitely had something to do with it. However, Ye-Seo’s mother, even after finding it all out, is willing to look past all this because all she wants is to see her daughter get into SNU. With such a tragedy, Park family decides to move out and this opens the door for a new family to move in. This new family, Hwang family, have a simple and relaxed outlook towards life which clearly doesn't sit well with the other families. From questioning Lee So Im’s teaching methods to constantly treating her as an outsider, they really do give the Hwang family a hard time. Even at the hospital, Dr Hwang, who wants to treat the patients and interns with utmost respect, is criticised by Dr Kang, Ye-Seo’s father, who is more inclined towards making money and asserting his authority. With each passing episode, we realise that Joo-Young’s flawless result isn’t a work of her own credibility, but her ability to cheat her ways through. Besides, all the families who have hired her have faced consequences similar to the Park family. But by the time Ye-Seo or her mother became aware of this, they are in too deep in to take a step back. What further unfolds is the lie that Joo-Young managed to hide for all these years, which is also the reason behind her desire to destroy each and every family that hires her. At this point, I thought I couldn't possibly dislike this character more, but what happens in the remaining episodes clearly left me speechless.&amp;nbsp; The other two families living in the SKY Castle neighbourhood include the Cha and Woo families, who have more of a side role to play. In the Cha family, Min-Hyuk (the head of the family) being the prosecutor turned professor, wants his kids to reach the “top of the pyramid” which he himself failed to do. He forces his dreams on his kids through means that only bear negative results. With the twin boys being average at school, which is obviously something that Min-Hyuk cannot deal with, to the eldest daughter lying about being in Harvard, all of it is a result of him constantly pressuring them. On the other hand, Noh Seung-Hye is an understanding mother who clearly sees through Min-Hyuk’s methods and is willing to end her marriage if that is what it takes to save her children. The last is the Woo family, and here we see a mother struggling to find a balance between keeping her child happy but also wanting him to study hard and get into SKY. With Dr Woo working under Dr Kang, we constantly see them trying to be on the good side of the Kang family. Not to mention, this family really adds the much-needed elements of comedy that takes this show on another tangent altogether. In the fifth episode, we come across a new character Kim Hye-na, a bold kid studying in the same class as Ye-Seo. Despite her being a poor child, with a sick mother admitted in the hospital, she still manages to surpass Ye-Seo in academics. Ye-Seo, being a child who cannot stand failure, and her mother, who cannot see her child upset, clearly don't take this well. Ye-Seo’s mother even goes out of her way to tell Hye-na to not mess with Ye-Seo and her goal. To be honest, initially, I didn’t think that her role could be any more than a classmate, but the story that revolves around Hye-na's life leaves Ye-Seo’s goal of SNU Medical School, shaken to its very core. This show started with a rating of as low as 1%, and halfway through the show, it managed to reach skyrocketing numbers. It has nothing common with the popular K-dramas that revolve around romance, which is also why it is my favourite show. SKY Castle is rather a series that very smartly raises some of the darkest issues that exist in societies all across the globe, especially around Korea’s Scholastic Ability Test, Suneung. With a cast so carefully chosen, and with every actor being true to their role, this show really proves why it received such high ratings. From highlighting the harsh reality of the Korean educational system and how it can take a toll on the mental health of children (since all of them are told is to get into SKY), it also portrays how the elite families are willing to go beyond their means to get their children into a good college, by spending huge sums of money or even adopting ways not available to a normal family. It constantly emphasises how parents tend to force their unachieved dreams and ambitions on their children without asking them what they really want, which can have unforeseen consequences. The other thing that needs to be mentioned is the original soundtrack, &quot;We all lie&quot;. This soundtrack is so brilliantly curated that it works perfectly with the storyline. And it is definitely one of those songs I found myself going back to. Also, the added bonus being that it's entirely an English song, strategically used to pull international audiences to the show.&amp;nbsp; While I agree with the majority audience that the last episode could have been better, but by no means does it destroy the very essence of the show and what it's trying to put forward. Throughout the show, we are made to realise that if Ye-Seo's mother wasn't so selfish towards her child's goal, this all could have been easily avoided. But then, we wouldn't have gotten this masterpiece to binge-watch. Therefore, I recommend this show to the audiences as it has a message relevant to all age groups.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Photograph</title>
      <link href="/The-Photograph" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Photograph" />
      <published>2020-09-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Photograph</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Photograph">&lt;p&gt;The field of journalism is constantly evolving in today’s times. Originating from the medium of print, the news media and the internet have revolutionised it in many ways. The press is no more just a one-way delivery machine of information but it has also encouraged feedback and communication which have led to a change in its style of gathering news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photojournalism is a subset of broadcast journalism, referring to the presentation of a news story through photographs. The use of the medium of photography to compliment a news article or fully tell a story on its own has been a major source of authentic information and facts presentation. However, in order to understand the meaning of ‘photojournalism’, it is important to trace the legacy of it and examine the ways in which it was used in the period when we did not have a term to define this type of art. Here is one such early news story that made it to the headlines and grabbed the attention of its target audience by the camera’s capture:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/f/fe/W._Eugene_Smith_-_Tomoko_Uemura_in_Her_Bath.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/tomokobath.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setup of this photograph is a Japanese, black and white image captured in 1971.  American photojournalist W Eugene Smith captured ‘Tomoko Uemura in Her Bath’, a photograph of a mother holding her severely deformed and naked child in a bathroom. The photojournalist wanted to depict the severity of the disease, Minamata, which is caused by mercury poisoning. It was first discovered in Minamata city of Japan, in 1956. Loss of peripheral vision, numbness in body muscles, and damage of speech and hearing are some of the symptoms. In extreme cases, it also affects foetuses in the womb.  This was not the only photograph that Smith picked to depict the trauma and condition of the people affected in Japan. He picked several photos that even made it to some of the publications, but he was searching for one striking photograph to gain the attention of the entire world. Smith had a symbolic vision of this photograph in his mind before he actually captured it and turned it into a reality. He explained his idea to Tomoko Uemura’s parents and when they agreed to get their daughter clicked, Smith began working on the set up of the photograph. Tomoko Uemura wanted the photo to depict the reality and plight of the people affected and dying in Minamata because of the pollution. Ryoko Uemura (mother) wanted a sympathetic portrayal of the photograph of her daughter and helped Smith in developing his ideas for the shots. She herself suggested the bathing chamber as the location of the photograph. The final capture was done on a chilly evening in December 1971.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first publication of the photograph was done in 1972 in the American magazine, &lt;em&gt;Life&lt;/em&gt;, as a centrepiece for a short photo essay on Minamata. Smith developed an entire book featuring all his clicks of the disease. This photo became famous globally and shed light on the victims, raising their concerns of compensation. With this attention came rumours that Ryoko Uemura’s family was financially benefiting from all the interviews as the photograph had brought them into the spotlight. This intensified worries that the rumours might have an impact on Tomoko’s mental health. Tomoko died at the age of 21 in 1977. The photograph was withdrawn from publication in 1997, 20 years after Tomoko’s death, as per the wishes of the family. They refused the copyright on the photograph and interviews as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tokomo’s father said &lt;em&gt;“I wanted Tomoko to be laid to rest and this feeling was growing steadily”&lt;/em&gt; in a refusal to permit exploitation of his daughter’s photo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tokomo’s capture brings to light a lot of aspects involved in the field of photojournalism, both from the reporter’s side and the victim’s side. There is always a story that is carried by an image on a news media platform and there are hundreds of stories behind that one capture. Only a photojournalist is remotely close to knowing them in detail. Photojournalism is a globally recognised and much-appreciated form of journalism today. It is an artistic presentation based on the recognition of realism in stories that are constantly changing and evolving as the audience awaits new concepts of storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W Eugene Smith’s journey provides us with insights of photojournalism in the western nations, whereas when talking specifically about the Indian context, many consider Kulwant Roy as a pioneer of Indian Photojournalism. He was one of the photographers who captured the birth of independent India and documented the freedom struggle. Digital photography and online editing have been revolutionary evolutions in photography, but realism is what attaches the term journalism and ethics to these captures. This is one of the major reasons why archival photos of Eugene Smith and Kulwant Roy are till date found to be inspirational to many growing photojournalists. It is interesting to see how far the camera’s click can deliver the news to its target audiences and whether or not it will take over the conventional mediums of journalism reporting in the digital era.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Himanshi Saini</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The field of journalism is constantly evolving in today’s times. Originating from the medium of print, the news media and the internet have revolutionised it in many ways. The press is no more just a one-way delivery machine of information but it has also encouraged feedback and communication which have led to a change in its style of gathering news.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Candid Midnight Talks</title>
      <link href="/Candid-Midnight-Talks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Candid Midnight Talks" />
      <published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Candid-Midnight-Talks</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Candid-Midnight-Talks">&lt;p&gt;George Bernard Shaw’s works generally dealt with the themes of politics, human and social relationships, and the influence that society has on people’s lives. A staunch critic, he often expressed his views and opinions subtly through incidents and characters in his plays. &lt;em&gt;Candida&lt;/em&gt; can be regarded as one of Shaw’s controversial plays, where he gives a strong criticism of the Catholic clergy, the oppression of women in the Victorian society, the prominent socio-economic class divide and the underwhelming graduate education system. The choice which Candida makes in the end between her husband and her admirer, is dependent on several factors - Morell’s political and religious ideologies, the status of a woman in a marriage and in society, and the love and, eventually, respect which she receives in her marriage. Morell’s political and economic ideologies are interesting considerations as the First Act ensues a heated debate between Morell, a socialist and his father-in-law Burgess - a shrewd, capitalist businessman. Furthermore, his notions on marriage are largely based on the patriarchal mindset prevalent in the religion he preaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Linklater, on the other hand, is a filmmaker whose films occasionally deal with themes like relationships, loneliness, adolescence, modern life and politics of current American society. His 2013 film &lt;em&gt;Before Midnight&lt;/em&gt; follows a couple, Jesse and Celine, spending the last day of their summer vacation in southern Greece with Jesse’s intellectual friends. The film begins with Jesse dropping Henry, his fourteen-year-old son from his previous marriage, at the airport. As they travel around the Greek Peloponnese island on their way to a hotel room that another couple has gifted them for another one-night stay, the couple discuss the choices they had made in life and whether their romance still persists after nine years of courtship or has gradually been replaced by spousal obligations. When they reach the hotel, a passionate sexual moment soon turns into a row, where a conversation on Henry and his well-being, leads to a confrontation where they spill out their resentments, insecurities and the factors which affect their courtship. Like Candida, the couple also make a choice in the end after examining the turbulence in their relationship: the choice to make their relationship work. Therefore, both these works explore the problems in a relationship in their unique ways - while &lt;em&gt;Candida&lt;/em&gt; weaves capitalism and money, religion and sex with the institution of marriage, &lt;em&gt;Before Midnight&lt;/em&gt; also portrays the effect of these factors on a courtship with a stepchild involved. What links the two works is the fact that, despite the differences in opinions, the couples at the centre of these works choose to carry on with their relationships, signifying that the hardest part of any relationship is compromising and staying together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“When there is money to give, he gives it; when there is money to refuse, I refuse it”&lt;/em&gt;, Candida declares this in the final act of the play. She is the wife of a Socialist clergyman who preaches how life is bigger than money. The comment, however, cleverly indicates that Morell acts as a concerned altruist who gives money to the poor, but only if he receives the opposite publicity. When it comes to undetected private revenue, Shaw suggests that Morell doesn’t seem to know where to draw the line, and it is always Candida who intervenes, preventing Morell from unfairly accepting donations and charging the gullible followers of the Church. This line can be interpreted in many ways, but ‘money’ is a crucial factor behind Candida’s choice. In the first Act, Morell has a heated conversation over money with his father-in-law, Burgess. He despises Burgess’ networking with the elite, and his exploitative methods of profit generation and underpayment of the women workers in his factory. Morell is against such profit-making business ventures and calls Burgess a ‘scoundrel’ for his short-term gain tactics. Shaw tries to show the conflict between socialism and capitalism through this debate. Furthermore, he later tells Candida that his religious lectures are aimed to dissuade people from making profitable money, as he abhors the philosophy of capitalism and the money-hungry businessmen who propel such institutions. Candida points out that Morell lives in an illusion. The survival in any society depends on economic power, which Burgess possesses. Candida has compromised on the frugality in their marriage but points out how he is oblivious to her feelings. She tells him that religion doesn’t act as a deterrent as the very same audience goes out and makes more money, and, thus, implies that Morell promotes idealism, which can never be attained. These political ideologies are equated with their marriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as a capitalist like Burgess exploits his workers, Morell (a socialist) exploits his followers to believe in the ideology of equality. However, there is no equality in their marriage. Morell believes Candida is economically dependent on him, and that is how marriages should work. He despises Candida’s confrontational speech in the second Act where she says that Morell does bother about money, and he does have chauvinistic, patriarchal notions despite masquerading as a progressive clergyman in public. In fact, his hypocrisy is shown by the preferential treatment and attention which Lexy, an Oxford graduate from a wealthy family, gets over Proserpine, his loyal middle-class typist. Shaw criticises this attitude of self-proclaimed ‘liberals’ like Morell who believe in an ideal world and live in a bubble, far away from reality. Candida’s choice is governed by economics. She chooses to stay with the person who can provide her economic stability, as she knows well that women can never be given jobs that guarantee financial autonomy. &lt;em&gt;Before Midnight&lt;/em&gt; has a similar messaging, the difference here being that both the spouses are working. The film, being the third in the trilogy, is unique in its treatment of the protagonists’ relationship. Unlike the other two installments, where the audience have seen them fall in love, here the spousal future they had fantasised about and dreaded in their youth has arrived. For better or worse, they are a functioning couple. Here, Linklater is not concerned with the youthful romance associated with curiosity and blind love, but the wisdom one imbibes with age and the effect of that wisdom on several matters of the relationship. In this case, money is an important factor when Jesse asks Celine to move to Chicago to spend their lives with Henry. She has her ‘dream job’ in Paris and she feels threatened when Jesse asks if there is any possibility in her quitting this job and finding a ‘comparable job’ in America. Linklater, like Shaw, points out the chauvinism which still exists in a modern relationship where a woman is expected to compromise at the professional or financial front. Shaw and Linklater successfully connect economics, money and capitalism with marriage, and drive the point home that despite longing for economic independence, the thought of a woman compromising on the professional front has been cultured into the general mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Candida&lt;/em&gt; also gives a perspective on culture and religion. The Catholic clergy in Victorian London is occupied with sermons and gospel speeches - a discourse or a lecture on religion rather than a dialogue with the audience. The setting itself has several religious connotations- the picture of Virgin Mary on the wall, the religious pamphlets and the books on the library shelves. Shaw tries to draw a parallel between Jesus and Morell, the distinction being that Morell does not practice or follow what he preaches. He talks of the liberation of women as an important doctrine of the religion. On the other hand, he privately boasts of how a woman is essential for the maintenance of a house and that a woman can make one’s home and marriage into a ‘paradise’. Several other cultural and mythological references are used in the play. Eugene compares Morell with ‘King David’. The comparison is interesting due to Shaw’s choice of this Biblical character. The King would get drunk and dance in front of his audience, while his wife ‘despised’ him. Shaw seems to imply that the clergyman is no less than David, inebriated with self-contentment and moral superiority such that the audience would amuse themselves by attending his sermons. This allegory in fact rings so true that Morell brutally assaults Eugene. The words hit hard to both Morell and the readers. Linklater also uses Greek mythology to bring out pathos between the couple. Before they visit the hotel, they enter a traditional Greek Chapel, dimly lit with candles. They pray for a few seconds, perhaps for a happy relationship, only to find themselves questioning the basis and the future of their companionship a few hours later. When Celine accuses Jesse of always blaming her for the reason Henry doesn’t stay with them, she uses the reference of Medea (a mythological figure who had killed her children to punish her husband). She hints that his accusations of her trying to sever ties and mar his relationship with his son is similar to Medea’s attempts to punish her partner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sexual references and innuendos are also used to illustrate the obstacles in a marriage. At the beginning of the Third Act in the play, Morell spots Candida and Eugene within close physical proximity. As Eugene recites romantic poems, Candida amusingly listens while observing a ‘brass poker’ by the fireplace. Shaw specifically chooses this object due to the phallic nature of the poker, which Candida gazes at intensely with ‘rapt absorption’. Shaw never explicitly states whether there was any affair at all between the two, as Candida is often referred to as a woman with maternal instincts and care. Shaw might be hinting at the lack of intimacy in their marriage, which she considers as she makes a choice. She reminds Morell that although she does provide him the care of his ‘mother and sisters’, she is also a wife and hints that no relationship could suffice without intimacy. The message might be construed as problematic by some, who often ask whether Candida’s choice would have been the same had there been a physical relation with Eugene. Linklater takes a similar approach. While the issue of Henry serves as a trigger to introspect on their relationship, lust and insecurities also become a topic of discussion. Both the spouses allege the infidelity of the other - she alleges that he has an illicit affair with a female student, he alleges that she had oral sex with her former partner. Celine even condescendingly declares that Jesse always makes love to her in the exact same way, and she hates it. Sex builds up further tensions and insecurities within the relationship, and both Shaw and Linklater examine this aspect astutely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both their works, the couples at the centre of these works, however, decide to continue with their relationship. Candida chooses her husband over her passionate admirer, and Celine decides to go ahead with her relationship. As Jesse explains, life is “real”- &lt;em&gt;“It’s not perfect, but it’s real”&lt;/em&gt;. The reality of marriage and relationships is what has been depicted in these two works. In &lt;em&gt;Candida&lt;/em&gt;, there is a statement- &lt;em&gt;“There are no delightful marriages, only convenient ones.”&lt;/em&gt; Both these works show that the quotient of delight in a marriage (or a spousal relation) gradually fades away with time. Although Morell had refuted or countered this statement in the play, it dawns on the readers that Morell’s marriage was a ‘convenient’ marriage with marked boundaries and no flexibility in their spousal roles. &lt;em&gt;Before Midnight&lt;/em&gt; might not exactly portray the courtship as absolutely convenient for the spouses, as they are both struggling with certain aspects in life - however, the talk of shifting to the States itself shows that there is a definite routine, and distortion of this routine would deteriorate their relationship. These works are, thus, left to the interpretation of the viewers and the readers - how they perceive the joy and the drudgery in these two relationships. It must be noted though, that these works show that marriages and relationships are based on sacrifices and compromises, and both Shaw and Linklater are uncompromising in showing how relationships are affected by several peripheral factors surrounding it. But both couples decide to work towards it and move on in life, in the pursuit of further happiness.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sarbesh Chaudhury</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">George Bernard Shaw’s works generally dealt with the themes of politics, human and social relationships, and the influence that society has on people’s lives. A staunch critic, he often expressed his views and opinions subtly through incidents and characters in his plays. Candida can be regarded as one of Shaw’s controversial plays, where he gives a strong criticism of the Catholic clergy, the oppression of women in the Victorian society, the prominent socio-economic class divide and the underwhelming graduate education system. The choice which Candida makes in the end between her husband and her admirer, is dependent on several factors - Morell’s political and religious ideologies, the status of a woman in a marriage and in society, and the love and, eventually, respect which she receives in her marriage. Morell’s political and economic ideologies are interesting considerations as the First Act ensues a heated debate between Morell, a socialist and his father-in-law Burgess - a shrewd, capitalist businessman. Furthermore, his notions on marriage are largely based on the patriarchal mindset prevalent in the religion he preaches.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Amongst The Living: Review of the TV Series ‘After Life’</title>
      <link href="/Amongst-The-Living" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amongst The Living: Review of the TV Series 'After Life'" />
      <published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Amongst-The-Living</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Amongst-The-Living">&lt;p&gt;There’s no earthly medicine, nor any amount of therapy or escape from the grief that engulfs you completely from head to toe after the demise of a loved one, especially a spouse. Someone you’ve spent more than half of your life with and expected to share the rest of your old and fragile years, sprawled under the sun with a classic and some iced-tea. Someone who becomes not just a habit but as ingrained in your mind as muscle memory - the way a writer’s fingertips move across a keyboard, gliding through without a mere thought - as necessary as breathing and as easy too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Losing that person, (if you’re lucky enough to find them in the first place), is something I thought could not be expressed or filmed, but Ricky Gervais’ character Tony in &lt;em&gt;After Life&lt;/em&gt; did just that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tony, after losing his wife whom he was married to for 25 years had forgone the will to live. He had unabashedly submitted to death and wasn’t afraid of anything that was to come his way. He didn’t think death was the hard part anymore; it was life that stung him every day. In simpler terms - he wanted to die, or at least he thought he did. After several attempts at it, he still found himself waking up each morning to a hollow life - most times for his beloved dog Brandy whom he thought he couldn’t leave alone and other times to watch the videotapes of his wife from their bygone life. His day started with the clips of Lisa (his wife) talking and laughing, and he succumbed to sleep with them too. I think dying wasn’t a part of his plan at all, or he would have done that a long time back, and we wouldn’t have a two-season-long series of &lt;em&gt;After Life&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, his pain was equivalent to the effect that made him attempt to kill himself. When the series commenced, his attitude could be described in his own words as - &lt;em&gt;“Here’s what’s what: humanity is a plague. We’re a disgusting, narcissistic, selfish parasite, and the world would be a better place without us.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ricky Gervais is probably the only person who can turn a macabre series about death and depression into a heartwarming and hilarious tale of love and redemption that friendship can offer. Written, directed and starred by this multi-talented actor (who also wrote the original version of &lt;em&gt;The Office&lt;/em&gt; UK), you will find yourself on an inundating journey of emotions throughout this show. He normalises mourning, grief and depression in an unprecedented way. He tells us it’s okay to be wrought up because, &lt;em&gt;“We’re all screwed up in one way or the other, that’s what makes us normal.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often after we lose a loved one, we’re sympathised with for a while, maybe for a couple of months, but after that, you’re expected to move on with your normal life. But is there an end-date to the grief that death taints your heart with? You can move on from a bad-hair-day or a lull in your career, but how do you fill a hole cratered by death?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, in my opinion, you don’t. And that is one of the reasons I fell in love with this beautiful yet realistic show. It doesn’t end with a colossal epiphany where you find that life is still beautiful and move on, back to being the person you were, because you cannot ever go back to that version of yourself that you were - in this case, what he was with his wife. That part of him might exist somewhere passively but it was put to sleep with the person who brought it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People aren’t whole or made up of a monolithic tenor; people are the sum of their parts. Sometimes it does so happen that you might lose an irreplaceable part of yourself, and so did Tony. But he didn’t “move on” from his wife, just because she was no more with him. Even though he knew he had lost that part of himself to her, he accepted it. They were very slow days but he got there. He learnt to live a life without forgoing Lisa. Why do we have to let go of the things and the memories left behind by the demised anyway? Tony definitely didn’t because he believes “love is everything”  and that he had experienced the purest form of it; a love which won’t ever feel the same way again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the 2 seasons, he struggles with an impertinence of character and apathy for life. Tony lives in a fictional town of Tambury and writes for the local newspaper, &lt;em&gt;The Tambury Gazette&lt;/em&gt;. He works with his brother-in-law, opposite to him in nature, who stood by him throughout his journey of dealing with something that can be vaguely referred to as &lt;em&gt;life&lt;/em&gt;, after Lisa. Their newspaper showcases stories of the local people and their quirky, crazy little tales- from an old man who had been posting his letters in a dog-poop box, to a 50-year-old man who identifies as an 8-year-old girl (which according to his wife was clearly a nervous breakdown). Tony hates his job, including meeting all these people and recording their inane and frothy stories. But towards the turn of Season 1, this formerly despised routine makes his life just a tad more bearable for him. He starts relating to these people, realising that they are all either lonely or going through something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The keenness with which Gervais has worked on his characters individually is laudable. Each role brings something to the table, has a unique personality and contributes to pacifying Tony’s seething soul. Tony, who hated any social interaction, comes out of this vortex with a few special relationships. Be it the candid postman Pat (who clearly doesn’t understand boundaries), his coworker Sandy who looks up to him and shares a sweet relationship with him, his infirm father whom he visits daily or his father’s nurse Emma with whom unfolds an inexplicable relationship towards the culmination of the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The portrayal of his unbiased friendship with a sex worker who goes by the name of Roxy whom he met across the street unfurls into a sweet friendship, where she cares and worries for him a lot. He tells her that he sees a reflection of his wife in her; that even Lisa couldn’t go to sleep until everyone around her was okay. These little anecdotes, entwined in his memory is what keeps him going and concurrently pains him too. But these moments reinforce my faith in his undying love for his wife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of Season 2, Tony turns a corner and thinks that the least he can do is be a better person for the people he loves, who have constantly been there for him to rely on. He introspects as to how selfish he has been, and that life necessarily doesn’t need to be about him. If he doesn’t want to live for himself anymore, he can live for others, because &lt;em&gt;“we’re not just here for ourselves”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this had a lot to do with Anne, a woman he met at the graveyard, sitting at a bench close by, whom he found himself visiting everyday and sharing the tiniest, most banal parts of his day. She dressed his wounds with her kind and wise words, and a shared experience of losing her husband. She made him realise that the only way to heal is to let go of his anger for the world, that he can’t ever feel better again without being his intrinsically good self. She told him once that, &lt;em&gt;“Good people do things for other people. That’s it. The end.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you choose to watch this show, I promise you will laugh deliriously, even whilst questioning his coal-like dark humour and cry when he cries for no reason at all when old memories come gushing to him. Even though the development of his character through the two seasons is commendable and leaves you with a sense of warmth in your heart, you will feel this show hitting you hard because of the sheer reality that it emanates even amidst a fictional setting. After all the sadness, despair and the caustic humour, at the end you will agree with the writer on one thing at least - that &lt;em&gt;“hope is everything”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think &lt;em&gt;after life&lt;/em&gt; should be a word attributed to the living instead of the dead, in that once people leave; it is us who grapple to make peace with the reality of it all, amongst the living, in our &lt;strong&gt;After Life&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There’s no earthly medicine, nor any amount of therapy or escape from the grief that engulfs you completely from head to toe after the demise of a loved one, especially a spouse. Someone you’ve spent more than half of your life with and expected to share the rest of your old and fragile years, sprawled under the sun with a classic and some iced-tea. Someone who becomes not just a habit but as ingrained in your mind as muscle memory - the way a writer’s fingertips move across a keyboard, gliding through without a mere thought - as necessary as breathing and as easy too.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Who Really Built the Pyramids?</title>
      <link href="/Who-Really-Built-the-Pyramids" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who Really Built the Pyramids?" />
      <published>2020-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Who-Really-Built-the-Pyramids</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Who-Really-Built-the-Pyramids">&lt;p&gt;Pyramids are arguably among the most recognisable and impressive structures around the world. For millennia this design has been used in various forms of architecture: ceremonial complexes and tombs of the ancient world to the iconic Louvre in France and the Ryugyong Hotel in North Korea, in the modern world. Although the word “pyramid” is bound to conjure up an image of the pyramids at Giza, Egypt, the basic structure is not unique to this ancient civilisation. It has made appearances in various cultures all around the world over the years- Chichen Itza (Mexico), Koh Ker (Cambodia), Ji’an (China), Meroe (Sudan) and Borobudur Temple (Indonesia) are some such examples. But why on Earth did the ancient people decide to drag massive chunks of rocks and stack them up to make the pyramids? Why were the pyramids common to so many of the civilisations in a relatively unconnected ancient world? How did the primitive people even build them, especially in as little time as 20 years, in the case of the Great Pyramid of Giza? Questions like these have baffled historians for years and several theories have been proposed to provide an answer. In this article, I shall be focussing my attention on the most popular examples of the pyramids: the pyramids of the ancient Egyptian civilization and trying to address some of these questions and controversies associated with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the most famous site of the Egyptian pyramids is located in Giza, these pyramids are far from being the oldest examples of such architecture belonging to this early civilisation. The earliest attempt at a pyramidal design resides in Saqqara and dates back to around 2780 BC (almost 4800 years old). This is the Step Pyramid of Pharaoh Djoser. It was built by the pharaoh’s youngest architect, Imhotep, whose revolutionary ideas greatly impressed the king. This pyramid took over 10 years to reach completion and underwent several changes in the initial plan on its way. The final result was a stepped pyramid, a style we usually associate with the Aztecs. It is popularly assumed to symbolise the steps that the Pharaoh would have had to take to move on to his afterlife. The pyramid of Djoser is quite possibly the oldest pyramid in the world and it heralded a long standing tradition of building similar structures to house the sarcophagi of the Pharaohs of Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next greatest attempt at such a feat would come during the reign of Huni, the last pharaoh of the third dynasty and it is located in Meidum, Egypt. It is popularly believed that although this pyramid was originally meant for him, he died before its completion and the process of construction was later taken up by the founder of the fourth dynasty, Sneferu. This pyramid is a type of step pyramid and is the oldest known example of a straight sided pyramid in Egypt. Unfortunately, due to some faults, it partially collapsed during the ancient times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sneferu’s next ambitious endeavour resulted in what is today known as the Bent Pyramid. It is located in Dashur, a necropolis in Lower Egypt. This pyramid is so called because of a very clear “bend” at its belly. However, the reason why this pyramid bears this unusual shape is not exactly known and multiple theories have been put forward to provide an explanation. One of these suggests that the initial plan was to build a structure that looks like what we have come to associate the word “pyramid” with today- a tetrahedron. The final result, however, has a slope of 54°27′44′′ below bend and 43°22′ above it. Clearly, the lower angle corresponds to a much greater total height. It is possible that the pharaoh, due to his rapidly advancing old age, wanted the process of construction to be accelerated. This left the architects with no choice but to reduce the angle to complete the structure faster. Another theory suggests that, as the Meidum Pyramid had already started collapsing, the architects decided that the base angle was way too steep (Meidum Pyramid also had a base angle of 51°50’35’’) and changed it mid-way through the construction process resulting in the infamous bend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sneferu left behind yet another pyramid in Dashur. This one is known as the Red Pyramid. This pyramid bears almost the same base angle as the upper portion of the Bent Pyramid- 43°40’ and is of the shape that we typically call a pyramid today. The Red Pyramid paved the way for the majestic pyramids at Giza during the reign of Sneferu’s successors. They were constructed roughly between 2550 BC and 2490 BC and house the burial chambers of Khafre, Khufu and Menkaure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pyramids of Giza looked very different back in its days than it does now. Firstly, they used to be white in colour owing to the use of locally found limestone on its exterior. In the sunlight, the pyramids would have had a startling and almost blinding glow. Most of this outer layer has fallen off or has eroded away. Another rather astonishing discovery in recent times is the fact that Khufu’s pyramid, also called the Great Pyramid of Giza, does not have a conventional pyramid-shape. In fact, it has eight faces and this is very clear in the aerial pictures of the structure. Each of the four faces has a slight concave split from the base to the top and all the faces have the same base length. Thus, it simply could not have been a mishap. It was planned. The outer walls of the Great Pyramid of Giza showcase the exceptional cutting skills of the builders as the rocks fit in perfectly with each other. The rocks away from the walls however, are shapeless and do not fit in well. It might have been a conscious decision to speed up the process of construction. It is popularly believed that the pyramids are so shaped to represent the rays of the sun. The sun god Ra was a central figure in the ancient Egyptian myths. The rays of the sun, called Aten, often associated with life giving properties, was just as important. In fact, during the reign of Pharaoh Akhenaten, the father of the legendary boy king Tutankhamun, a new monotheistic religion was adopted that involved worshipping only Aten. All these indicate that the pyramids were meticulously planned and they served to reinforce long held beliefs. Besides, the excellent craftsmanship of the workers is very apparent in the magnificent execution of the plans of the ambitious architects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important question that arises at this point is this: how did the people of the ancient world build something as ambitious and remarkable as the pyramids? Egyptologists believe that the ancient Egyptians had not even invented the wheel yet. This adds to the laundry list of problems associated with the construction of such a gigantic structure during a supposedly technologically backward era. In addition, not only are these pyramids grandiose, they have defied the odds of nature and stood the test of time. Besides, the rocks that make up the pyramids of Giza weigh a few tonnes each. Let’s also not forget the fact that the pyramid itself rises to a staggering height of 146.7m (in the case of Khufu’s pyramid). Apart from these, the rocks on the outside of the pyramid and those that make up the burial chamber are so precisely cut that not even a credit card can slip in in between them. In a world where humans had only very primitive tools, this indeed seems like an impossible feat. Some people think that it really was impossible and the ancient Egyptians did not, in fact, build them. Question is, who did then? Their response is just as simple as it is shocking: aliens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There many reasons why one could possibly believe in this theory. This is especially since pyramids are not only an architectural marvel but also a mathematical and scientific masterpiece. The recurrence of pi in different multiplicities in various calculated dimensions of the pyramid has baffled everyone for years. Another such remarkable discovery involves phi. The number whose square is one more than itself is referred to as phi and it is numerically equal to 1.618. Pythagorean Theorem can then be applied to find the values corresponding to any right sided triangle. Assume a triangle that has root phi as the height, 1 as the base and phi as the hypotenuse. The height to base ratio of this triangle, referred to as the Golden Triangle, is equal to 0.636. The Great Pyramid of Giza has a height of 146.7 m and the base perimeter is 230.34 m. The height to base ratio comes out to be 0.636 (approximately). The error is only about 0.025%. In addition, the pyramid is aligned within 1/15th of a degree to true North. These are only three of the numerous examples of astonishing mathematical knowledge that the ancient Egyptians supposedly possessed. The ancient alien theorists do not believe that the Egyptians are capable of having such impeccable command over the understanding of mathematics and honestly, very few disagree. In their view, it is a little too rich to expect people who didn’t know that a circular log could be used as a wheel, to understand astronomy and spend time deriving complicated mathematical equations. Another shocking fact that possibly supports the ancient aliens theory is that no Egyptian text mentions the construction of the pyramids. Egypt has around 120 pyramids and each of them is equally marvellous and unique. Yet, no one decided to write down how they managed the construction of possibly the most impressive set of structures to have been ever built in the history of mankind. There are several such arguments that have been put forward in favour of this theory about aliens being the masterminds behind the pyramids. In fact, there is an American TV series titled “Ancient Aliens” dedicated to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are numerous theories aimed at debunking the hypothesis put forward by the ancient alien theorists. Various proofs have also been found that indicate that the ancient people did in fact build the enormous structures. There are scriptures that show numerous people working together to drag a humongous statue in the form of a seated figure while one person is committed to wetting the path right in front of the sledge with the statue on it. Water does reduce friction and thus, makes dragging the weight easier. Various tools have been found and possible plans on the ground in front of the pyramids prove exceptional architectural, mathematical and engineering skills of the ancient Egyptians. At this point, you might be thinking, how do we even know who commissioned the construction of the Great Pyramid, considering the fact that tomb robbers did not even leave the sarcophagus and the mummy behind for identification, if possible. The answer to this is a series of informally scribbled messages found inside the Great Pyramid of Giza. One of them has been translated and reads: “Friends of Khufu.” It is believed to have been left behind by one of the construction workers. In addition to this, the previous discussion on the evolution of the pyramidal structure in ancient Egypt is a clear indication of the fact that they gradually developed the knowledge and understanding. Everything did not happen all at once; it took centuries for them to perfect the pyramid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of historians, architects and archaeologists have proposed several theories to explain how the gigantic structures of the ancient world like the pyramids were built. One of these theories suggests that a head on slope was employed. However, this hypothesis failed to garner support from the community of Egyptologists as the amount of rocks required to build such a slope would have been greater than that required to build the pyramid itself, in order to reach the full height. This renders the system rather inefficient and thus, unlikely. Others speculate that a slope that spiraled around the pyramid might have been used. This is popularly known as the ramp model. Some even believe that the spiral slope could have been inside the structure itself. Thermal scanning shows unexplained vacant spaces within the walls of the Giza pyramids. An elaborate mechanism has been proposed to support these findings and the theory. It involves the use of a pulley system. Although no concrete proof exists to validate this, possible carvings into the wall that could have been required for such a system to be set up, have been discovered inside the Great Pyramid of Giza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the modern world continues to believe that the ancient world was a dark age where knowledge was scarce and structures and weapons were very primitive, it is clear that we might be gravely wrong. I have also discussed how Egypt was a far more women friendly civilization than many cultures that we know of today, in one of my previous articles. However, very little of either of these is popularly known due to the efficient and long term erasure of non-cis straight male history and our long standing notions of what the ancient and medieval times were like. In fact, it is our conviction that the river valley civilizations were backward that has led us to believe in the possible involvement of aliens or even supernatural beings in the construction of the marvels of the ancient world. Whether aliens are real or not is not the concern here. The point is that we need to give the ancient humans due credit for their meticulous work and preserve history as it is.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Pyramids are arguably among the most recognisable and impressive structures around the world. For millennia this design has been used in various forms of architecture: ceremonial complexes and tombs of the ancient world to the iconic Louvre in France and the Ryugyong Hotel in North Korea, in the modern world. Although the word “pyramid” is bound to conjure up an image of the pyramids at Giza, Egypt, the basic structure is not unique to this ancient civilisation. It has made appearances in various cultures all around the world over the years- Chichen Itza (Mexico), Koh Ker (Cambodia), Ji’an (China), Meroe (Sudan) and Borobudur Temple (Indonesia) are some such examples. But why on Earth did the ancient people decide to drag massive chunks of rocks and stack them up to make the pyramids? Why were the pyramids common to so many of the civilisations in a relatively unconnected ancient world? How did the primitive people even build them, especially in as little time as 20 years, in the case of the Great Pyramid of Giza? Questions like these have baffled historians for years and several theories have been proposed to provide an answer. In this article, I shall be focussing my attention on the most popular examples of the pyramids: the pyramids of the ancient Egyptian civilization and trying to address some of these questions and controversies associated with them.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">O Ray of Truth and Humanity</title>
      <link href="/Ray-of-Truth-and-Humanity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="O Ray of Truth and Humanity" />
      <published>2020-05-03T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Ray-of-Truth-and-Humanity</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Ray-of-Truth-and-Humanity">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Not to have seen the cinema of Ray means existing in the world without seeing the sun or the moon”&lt;/em&gt;- Akira Kurosawa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing up in a Bengali household I was introduced to the world of art, music and cinema at a very early age. My love for cinema started when I watched &lt;em&gt;Sonar Kella&lt;/em&gt;, a film by Satyajit Ray. At that point in time I didn’t even know what direction was or how a movie was made, but somehow I understood that it would be nice to be able to make something like this! Like music in Bengal is tantamount to Rabindra Sangeet (ie. Nobel Laureate Rabindranath Tagore’s collection of songs), intellectual cinema in the state is defined by the artistic excellence of Satyajit Ray. For those of you who do not know who Ray is, I’ll try my best to put down words that might help you to understand him—albeit I am certain that those words will never be able to do justice to this ‘Kohinoor’ among film directors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ray was born in the year 1921 and was present when landslide changes that still affect Indian lives were afoot in the country. Now, cinema before Ray was mostly based on Indian literature. As flourished and as distinct our literature was, Indian cinema was yet to find its distinct voice. We didn’t have a lot of stories to tell, or more precisely, nobody really knew how to talk about their time. Until, of course, Ray’s film &lt;em&gt;Pather Panchali&lt;/em&gt; (The Song of the Road) came along and changed Indian cinema forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pather Panchali&lt;/em&gt; was based on a book of the same name by Bibhutibhushan Bannerjee. Although highly underrated initially, Bannerjee was later considered to be one of the most iconic writers of modern Bengali literature and also one of the most prominent writers in the post-Tagore era. Of course, there were literary works which beautifully expressed the scenario of India but none of those were as brilliant and as true as Bannerjee’s &lt;em&gt;Pather Panchali&lt;/em&gt;. When Bannerjee thought of publishing the novel, he was rejected by most of the publishing houses on the pretext that his story was too long and too upsetting. That used to be the predicament of any artist seeking to depict truth via any medium (that is what it still is).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, after a long time of rejection, at last a small-time publishing house named ‘Ranjan Prakashalay’ (Ranjan Publishers) agreed to publish the book. Without the book there wouldn’t have been a young Satyajit Ray coming out of a movie theatre in London after watching &lt;em&gt;The Bicycle Thief&lt;/em&gt; and thinking “This is what I want to be able to tell, the truth”. Ray decided to turn Bannerjee’s book into a film around 1946-47. Why? To quote Ray, it was because of the certain qualities that “made it a great book: its humanism, its lyricism, and its ring of truth”. It took a tremendous effort to turn this novel into a film, especially when each member of the crew was new to this. A bigger difficulty was funding the film, no producer was willing to finance the film, it lacked stars, songs and it wasn’t entertaining either. It took the film almost 2 years to complete, as the team faced financial crisis more than once. At last, in 1955, the film was released. A completely unorthodox film in Bengali cinema, very few people had any interest in seeing a film based on a village of West Bengal, but those that did see the film were mesmerised by its sheer simplicity. They understood that this new director named Satyajit Ray was something else altogether. The film later became one of the most significant works of art all over the world, winning numerous accolades in film festivals across the world. &lt;em&gt;Pather Panchali&lt;/em&gt; was followed by two more films named &lt;em&gt;Aparajito&lt;/em&gt; (The Unvanquished), and &lt;em&gt;Apur Sansar&lt;/em&gt; (The World of Apu). Together they are known as ‘The Apu Trilogy’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One significant feature of Ray’s films was the city of Kolkata. Due to the partition of India, the Bangladesh Liberation War and bad infrastructure, Kolkata became overly-crowded in the 70’s—which was also a period of nihilistic delusion for the youth of the city. The Naxalite period had just ended, and there was madness and frustration all around. Many people were without jobs, food, or a place to live. ‘The Kolkata Trilogy’ by Ray tells these stories of Kolkata. The trilogy contains the following films: &lt;em&gt;Pratidwandi&lt;/em&gt; (The Adversary), &lt;em&gt;Seemabaddha&lt;/em&gt; (Company Limited) and &lt;em&gt;Jana Aranya&lt;/em&gt; (The Middleman). Ray depicted the stories of three different men from three different social classes in these films, showing how the once-loved city became a nightmare for them, and how it showed them a ‘ray’ of hope as well!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, instead of merely focussing his attention on the lives of the downtrodden or grasping the frenzy of the times plainly, the maverick filmmaker’s Neo-Realism led him to weave his stories into profound human and social documentaries. Watching Ray’s Kolkata Trilogy is still the best way of understanding Kolkata and its history. That apart, the city played a huge part in his movies like &lt;em&gt;Charulata&lt;/em&gt; (The Lonely Wife) and &lt;em&gt;Mahanagar&lt;/em&gt; (The Big City). Both movies exhibit the richness of Ray’s thoughts and his genial ability to transport his audience to an adventurous yet real plethora of emotions. The problems described in Ray’s films are unfortunately still present in Indian society. Be it class struggle, the oppression of women, middle class identity crisis, religion or anything, we are still very much suffering from them. In the end, &lt;em&gt;we might cherish this man’s existence in our society but we couldn’t learn anything from his films&lt;/em&gt;. This man had the courage to talk about the problems of his time in his own way and we all know how difficult it is to talk about the truth through any art. We are becoming more and more stereotypical day-by-day, we are becoming too sensitive to hear and tell the truth each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It won’t be fair to talk about Ray and not mention his love for children, his constant enthusiasm towards creating a different world for children, a world each and every kid in Bengal has been a part of while growing up. If you ever check his work you will see the huge amount of work he has done for children. A lot of it comes from his father, Sukumar Ray, who was a critically-acclaimed poet and writer and probably the first person to write nonsensical comedy for children in Bengali—a thing which is missing from today’s ‘woke’ generation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many directors can tell really serious stories through their work but they cannot and have not made a film for the children. Now, why I’m saying this is because I truly believe that making children happy and showing them something which can inspire them through generations is the most beautiful thing that you can achieve as a filmmaker. Ray has done innumerable things for children; he made films, he wrote stories, he created the first children’s magazine in Bengali, and he created and gifted us our very own Bengali detective named ‘Feluda’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Satyajit Ray single-handedly created such an impact that it inspires generation after generation. Even today, when we watch a film by Satyajit Ray, we are drawn in. Technology was not as developed as today, resources to make a film were not readily available, yet by sheer willpower, talent and his love for the art, Ray created one masterpiece after the other. It won’t be fair to name just a couple of famous filmmakers who have been inspired greatly by Ray, as glimpses of his impact can be seen in every artist. Yesterday, ie. May 2, 2020 was our very own Manikda’s (Ray’s nickname) 99th birthday. I do not know if this article, in any way, does justice to this great human being, but I will always be thankful to Ray for showing me and our generation the truth of life, how can we learn things from our imagination and how to never stop doing what you love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Belated Happy Birthday Manikda. May you always show us the ray of hope!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Satyaki Paul&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Satyaki Paul is a film enthusiast trying to explore the unseen in cinema everyday.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>guest.contributor</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Not to have seen the cinema of Ray means existing in the world without seeing the sun or the moon”- Akira Kurosawa.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
