<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/culture/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-10-31T13:57:53+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/culture/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Photograph</title>
      <link href="/The-Photograph" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Photograph" />
      <published>2020-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Photograph</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Photograph">&lt;p&gt;The field of journalism is constantly evolving in today’s times. Originating from the medium of print, the news media and the internet have revolutionised it in many ways. The press is no more just a one-way delivery machine of information but it has also encouraged feedback and communication which have led to a change in its style of gathering news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photojournalism is a subset of broadcast journalism, referring to the presentation of a news story through photographs. The use of the medium of photography to compliment a news article or fully tell a story on its own has been a major source of authentic information and facts presentation. However, in order to understand the meaning of ‘photojournalism’, it is important to trace the legacy of it and examine the ways in which it was used in the period when we did not have a term to define this type of art. Here is one such early news story that made it to the headlines and grabbed the attention of its target audience by the camera’s capture:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/f/fe/W._Eugene_Smith_-_Tomoko_Uemura_in_Her_Bath.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/tomokobath.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setup of this photograph is a Japanese, black and white image captured in 1971.  American photojournalist W Eugene Smith captured ‘Tomoko Uemura in Her Bath’, a photograph of a mother holding her severely deformed and naked child in a bathroom. The photojournalist wanted to depict the severity of the disease, Minamata, which is caused by mercury poisoning. It was first discovered in Minamata city of Japan, in 1956. Loss of peripheral vision, numbness in body muscles, and damage of speech and hearing are some of the symptoms. In extreme cases, it also affects foetuses in the womb.  This was not the only photograph that Smith picked to depict the trauma and condition of the people affected in Japan. He picked several photos that even made it to some of the publications, but he was searching for one striking photograph to gain the attention of the entire world. Smith had a symbolic vision of this photograph in his mind before he actually captured it and turned it into a reality. He explained his idea to Tomoko Uemura’s parents and when they agreed to get their daughter clicked, Smith began working on the set up of the photograph. Tomoko Uemura wanted the photo to depict the reality and plight of the people affected and dying in Minamata because of the pollution. Ryoko Uemura (mother) wanted a sympathetic portrayal of the photograph of her daughter and helped Smith in developing his ideas for the shots. She herself suggested the bathing chamber as the location of the photograph. The final capture was done on a chilly evening in December 1971.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first publication of the photograph was done in 1972 in the American magazine, &lt;em&gt;Life&lt;/em&gt;, as a centrepiece for a short photo essay on Minamata. Smith developed an entire book featuring all his clicks of the disease. This photo became famous globally and shed light on the victims, raising their concerns of compensation. With this attention came rumours that Ryoko Uemura’s family was financially benefiting from all the interviews as the photograph had brought them into the spotlight. This intensified worries that the rumours might have an impact on Tomoko’s mental health. Tomoko died at the age of 21 in 1977. The photograph was withdrawn from publication in 1997, 20 years after Tomoko’s death, as per the wishes of the family. They refused the copyright on the photograph and interviews as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tokomo’s father said &lt;em&gt;“I wanted Tomoko to be laid to rest and this feeling was growing steadily”&lt;/em&gt; in a refusal to permit exploitation of his daughter’s photo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tokomo’s capture brings to light a lot of aspects involved in the field of photojournalism, both from the reporter’s side and the victim’s side. There is always a story that is carried by an image on a news media platform and there are hundreds of stories behind that one capture. Only a photojournalist is remotely close to knowing them in detail. Photojournalism is a globally recognised and much-appreciated form of journalism today. It is an artistic presentation based on the recognition of realism in stories that are constantly changing and evolving as the audience awaits new concepts of storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W Eugene Smith’s journey provides us with insights of photojournalism in the western nations, whereas when talking specifically about the Indian context, many consider Kulwant Roy as a pioneer of Indian Photojournalism. He was one of the photographers who captured the birth of independent India and documented the freedom struggle. Digital photography and online editing have been revolutionary evolutions in photography, but realism is what attaches the term journalism and ethics to these captures. This is one of the major reasons why archival photos of Eugene Smith and Kulwant Roy are till date found to be inspirational to many growing photojournalists. It is interesting to see how far the camera’s click can deliver the news to its target audiences and whether or not it will take over the conventional mediums of journalism reporting in the digital era.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Himanshi Saini</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The field of journalism is constantly evolving in today’s times. Originating from the medium of print, the news media and the internet have revolutionised it in many ways. The press is no more just a one-way delivery machine of information but it has also encouraged feedback and communication which have led to a change in its style of gathering news.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Candid Midnight Talks</title>
      <link href="/Candid-Midnight-Talks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Candid Midnight Talks" />
      <published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Candid-Midnight-Talks</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Candid-Midnight-Talks">&lt;p&gt;George Bernard Shaw’s works generally dealt with the themes of politics, human and social relationships, and the influence that society has on people’s lives. A staunch critic, he often expressed his views and opinions subtly through incidents and characters in his plays. &lt;em&gt;Candida&lt;/em&gt; can be regarded as one of Shaw’s controversial plays, where he gives a strong criticism of the Catholic clergy, the oppression of women in the Victorian society, the prominent socio-economic class divide and the underwhelming graduate education system. The choice which Candida makes in the end between her husband and her admirer, is dependent on several factors - Morell’s political and religious ideologies, the status of a woman in a marriage and in society, and the love and, eventually, respect which she receives in her marriage. Morell’s political and economic ideologies are interesting considerations as the First Act ensues a heated debate between Morell, a socialist and his father-in-law Burgess - a shrewd, capitalist businessman. Furthermore, his notions on marriage are largely based on the patriarchal mindset prevalent in the religion he preaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Linklater, on the other hand, is a filmmaker whose films occasionally deal with themes like relationships, loneliness, adolescence, modern life and politics of current American society. His 2013 film &lt;em&gt;Before Midnight&lt;/em&gt; follows a couple, Jesse and Celine, spending the last day of their summer vacation in southern Greece with Jesse’s intellectual friends. The film begins with Jesse dropping Henry, his fourteen-year-old son from his previous marriage, at the airport. As they travel around the Greek Peloponnese island on their way to a hotel room that another couple has gifted them for another one-night stay, the couple discuss the choices they had made in life and whether their romance still persists after nine years of courtship or has gradually been replaced by spousal obligations. When they reach the hotel, a passionate sexual moment soon turns into a row, where a conversation on Henry and his well-being, leads to a confrontation where they spill out their resentments, insecurities and the factors which affect their courtship. Like Candida, the couple also make a choice in the end after examining the turbulence in their relationship: the choice to make their relationship work. Therefore, both these works explore the problems in a relationship in their unique ways - while &lt;em&gt;Candida&lt;/em&gt; weaves capitalism and money, religion and sex with the institution of marriage, &lt;em&gt;Before Midnight&lt;/em&gt; also portrays the effect of these factors on a courtship with a stepchild involved. What links the two works is the fact that, despite the differences in opinions, the couples at the centre of these works choose to carry on with their relationships, signifying that the hardest part of any relationship is compromising and staying together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“When there is money to give, he gives it; when there is money to refuse, I refuse it”&lt;/em&gt;, Candida declares this in the final act of the play. She is the wife of a Socialist clergyman who preaches how life is bigger than money. The comment, however, cleverly indicates that Morell acts as a concerned altruist who gives money to the poor, but only if he receives the opposite publicity. When it comes to undetected private revenue, Shaw suggests that Morell doesn’t seem to know where to draw the line, and it is always Candida who intervenes, preventing Morell from unfairly accepting donations and charging the gullible followers of the Church. This line can be interpreted in many ways, but ‘money’ is a crucial factor behind Candida’s choice. In the first Act, Morell has a heated conversation over money with his father-in-law, Burgess. He despises Burgess’ networking with the elite, and his exploitative methods of profit generation and underpayment of the women workers in his factory. Morell is against such profit-making business ventures and calls Burgess a ‘scoundrel’ for his short-term gain tactics. Shaw tries to show the conflict between socialism and capitalism through this debate. Furthermore, he later tells Candida that his religious lectures are aimed to dissuade people from making profitable money, as he abhors the philosophy of capitalism and the money-hungry businessmen who propel such institutions. Candida points out that Morell lives in an illusion. The survival in any society depends on economic power, which Burgess possesses. Candida has compromised on the frugality in their marriage but points out how he is oblivious to her feelings. She tells him that religion doesn’t act as a deterrent as the very same audience goes out and makes more money, and, thus, implies that Morell promotes idealism, which can never be attained. These political ideologies are equated with their marriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as a capitalist like Burgess exploits his workers, Morell (a socialist) exploits his followers to believe in the ideology of equality. However, there is no equality in their marriage. Morell believes Candida is economically dependent on him, and that is how marriages should work. He despises Candida’s confrontational speech in the second Act where she says that Morell does bother about money, and he does have chauvinistic, patriarchal notions despite masquerading as a progressive clergyman in public. In fact, his hypocrisy is shown by the preferential treatment and attention which Lexy, an Oxford graduate from a wealthy family, gets over Proserpine, his loyal middle-class typist. Shaw criticises this attitude of self-proclaimed ‘liberals’ like Morell who believe in an ideal world and live in a bubble, far away from reality. Candida’s choice is governed by economics. She chooses to stay with the person who can provide her economic stability, as she knows well that women can never be given jobs that guarantee financial autonomy. &lt;em&gt;Before Midnight&lt;/em&gt; has a similar messaging, the difference here being that both the spouses are working. The film, being the third in the trilogy, is unique in its treatment of the protagonists’ relationship. Unlike the other two installments, where the audience have seen them fall in love, here the spousal future they had fantasised about and dreaded in their youth has arrived. For better or worse, they are a functioning couple. Here, Linklater is not concerned with the youthful romance associated with curiosity and blind love, but the wisdom one imbibes with age and the effect of that wisdom on several matters of the relationship. In this case, money is an important factor when Jesse asks Celine to move to Chicago to spend their lives with Henry. She has her ‘dream job’ in Paris and she feels threatened when Jesse asks if there is any possibility in her quitting this job and finding a ‘comparable job’ in America. Linklater, like Shaw, points out the chauvinism which still exists in a modern relationship where a woman is expected to compromise at the professional or financial front. Shaw and Linklater successfully connect economics, money and capitalism with marriage, and drive the point home that despite longing for economic independence, the thought of a woman compromising on the professional front has been cultured into the general mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Candida&lt;/em&gt; also gives a perspective on culture and religion. The Catholic clergy in Victorian London is occupied with sermons and gospel speeches - a discourse or a lecture on religion rather than a dialogue with the audience. The setting itself has several religious connotations- the picture of Virgin Mary on the wall, the religious pamphlets and the books on the library shelves. Shaw tries to draw a parallel between Jesus and Morell, the distinction being that Morell does not practice or follow what he preaches. He talks of the liberation of women as an important doctrine of the religion. On the other hand, he privately boasts of how a woman is essential for the maintenance of a house and that a woman can make one’s home and marriage into a ‘paradise’. Several other cultural and mythological references are used in the play. Eugene compares Morell with ‘King David’. The comparison is interesting due to Shaw’s choice of this Biblical character. The King would get drunk and dance in front of his audience, while his wife ‘despised’ him. Shaw seems to imply that the clergyman is no less than David, inebriated with self-contentment and moral superiority such that the audience would amuse themselves by attending his sermons. This allegory in fact rings so true that Morell brutally assaults Eugene. The words hit hard to both Morell and the readers. Linklater also uses Greek mythology to bring out pathos between the couple. Before they visit the hotel, they enter a traditional Greek Chapel, dimly lit with candles. They pray for a few seconds, perhaps for a happy relationship, only to find themselves questioning the basis and the future of their companionship a few hours later. When Celine accuses Jesse of always blaming her for the reason Henry doesn’t stay with them, she uses the reference of Medea (a mythological figure who had killed her children to punish her husband). She hints that his accusations of her trying to sever ties and mar his relationship with his son is similar to Medea’s attempts to punish her partner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sexual references and innuendos are also used to illustrate the obstacles in a marriage. At the beginning of the Third Act in the play, Morell spots Candida and Eugene within close physical proximity. As Eugene recites romantic poems, Candida amusingly listens while observing a ‘brass poker’ by the fireplace. Shaw specifically chooses this object due to the phallic nature of the poker, which Candida gazes at intensely with ‘rapt absorption’. Shaw never explicitly states whether there was any affair at all between the two, as Candida is often referred to as a woman with maternal instincts and care. Shaw might be hinting at the lack of intimacy in their marriage, which she considers as she makes a choice. She reminds Morell that although she does provide him the care of his ‘mother and sisters’, she is also a wife and hints that no relationship could suffice without intimacy. The message might be construed as problematic by some, who often ask whether Candida’s choice would have been the same had there been a physical relation with Eugene. Linklater takes a similar approach. While the issue of Henry serves as a trigger to introspect on their relationship, lust and insecurities also become a topic of discussion. Both the spouses allege the infidelity of the other - she alleges that he has an illicit affair with a female student, he alleges that she had oral sex with her former partner. Celine even condescendingly declares that Jesse always makes love to her in the exact same way, and she hates it. Sex builds up further tensions and insecurities within the relationship, and both Shaw and Linklater examine this aspect astutely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both their works, the couples at the centre of these works, however, decide to continue with their relationship. Candida chooses her husband over her passionate admirer, and Celine decides to go ahead with her relationship. As Jesse explains, life is “real”- &lt;em&gt;“It’s not perfect, but it’s real”&lt;/em&gt;. The reality of marriage and relationships is what has been depicted in these two works. In &lt;em&gt;Candida&lt;/em&gt;, there is a statement- &lt;em&gt;“There are no delightful marriages, only convenient ones.”&lt;/em&gt; Both these works show that the quotient of delight in a marriage (or a spousal relation) gradually fades away with time. Although Morell had refuted or countered this statement in the play, it dawns on the readers that Morell’s marriage was a ‘convenient’ marriage with marked boundaries and no flexibility in their spousal roles. &lt;em&gt;Before Midnight&lt;/em&gt; might not exactly portray the courtship as absolutely convenient for the spouses, as they are both struggling with certain aspects in life - however, the talk of shifting to the States itself shows that there is a definite routine, and distortion of this routine would deteriorate their relationship. These works are, thus, left to the interpretation of the viewers and the readers - how they perceive the joy and the drudgery in these two relationships. It must be noted though, that these works show that marriages and relationships are based on sacrifices and compromises, and both Shaw and Linklater are uncompromising in showing how relationships are affected by several peripheral factors surrounding it. But both couples decide to work towards it and move on in life, in the pursuit of further happiness.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sarbesh Chaudhury</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">George Bernard Shaw’s works generally dealt with the themes of politics, human and social relationships, and the influence that society has on people’s lives. A staunch critic, he often expressed his views and opinions subtly through incidents and characters in his plays. Candida can be regarded as one of Shaw’s controversial plays, where he gives a strong criticism of the Catholic clergy, the oppression of women in the Victorian society, the prominent socio-economic class divide and the underwhelming graduate education system. The choice which Candida makes in the end between her husband and her admirer, is dependent on several factors - Morell’s political and religious ideologies, the status of a woman in a marriage and in society, and the love and, eventually, respect which she receives in her marriage. Morell’s political and economic ideologies are interesting considerations as the First Act ensues a heated debate between Morell, a socialist and his father-in-law Burgess - a shrewd, capitalist businessman. Furthermore, his notions on marriage are largely based on the patriarchal mindset prevalent in the religion he preaches.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Amongst The Living: Review of the TV Series ‘After Life’</title>
      <link href="/Amongst-The-Living" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amongst The Living: Review of the TV Series 'After Life'" />
      <published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Amongst-The-Living</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Amongst-The-Living">&lt;p&gt;There’s no earthly medicine, nor any amount of therapy or escape from the grief that engulfs you completely from head to toe after the demise of a loved one, especially a spouse. Someone you’ve spent more than half of your life with and expected to share the rest of your old and fragile years, sprawled under the sun with a classic and some iced-tea. Someone who becomes not just a habit but as ingrained in your mind as muscle memory - the way a writer’s fingertips move across a keyboard, gliding through without a mere thought - as necessary as breathing and as easy too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Losing that person, (if you’re lucky enough to find them in the first place), is something I thought could not be expressed or filmed, but Ricky Gervais’ character Tony in &lt;em&gt;After Life&lt;/em&gt; did just that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tony, after losing his wife whom he was married to for 25 years had forgone the will to live. He had unabashedly submitted to death and wasn’t afraid of anything that was to come his way. He didn’t think death was the hard part anymore; it was life that stung him every day. In simpler terms - he wanted to die, or at least he thought he did. After several attempts at it, he still found himself waking up each morning to a hollow life - most times for his beloved dog Brandy whom he thought he couldn’t leave alone and other times to watch the videotapes of his wife from their bygone life. His day started with the clips of Lisa (his wife) talking and laughing, and he succumbed to sleep with them too. I think dying wasn’t a part of his plan at all, or he would have done that a long time back, and we wouldn’t have a two-season-long series of &lt;em&gt;After Life&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, his pain was equivalent to the effect that made him attempt to kill himself. When the series commenced, his attitude could be described in his own words as - &lt;em&gt;“Here’s what’s what: humanity is a plague. We’re a disgusting, narcissistic, selfish parasite, and the world would be a better place without us.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ricky Gervais is probably the only person who can turn a macabre series about death and depression into a heartwarming and hilarious tale of love and redemption that friendship can offer. Written, directed and starred by this multi-talented actor (who also wrote the original version of &lt;em&gt;The Office&lt;/em&gt; UK), you will find yourself on an inundating journey of emotions throughout this show. He normalises mourning, grief and depression in an unprecedented way. He tells us it’s okay to be wrought up because, &lt;em&gt;“We’re all screwed up in one way or the other, that’s what makes us normal.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often after we lose a loved one, we’re sympathised with for a while, maybe for a couple of months, but after that, you’re expected to move on with your normal life. But is there an end-date to the grief that death taints your heart with? You can move on from a bad-hair-day or a lull in your career, but how do you fill a hole cratered by death?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, in my opinion, you don’t. And that is one of the reasons I fell in love with this beautiful yet realistic show. It doesn’t end with a colossal epiphany where you find that life is still beautiful and move on, back to being the person you were, because you cannot ever go back to that version of yourself that you were - in this case, what he was with his wife. That part of him might exist somewhere passively but it was put to sleep with the person who brought it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People aren’t whole or made up of a monolithic tenor; people are the sum of their parts. Sometimes it does so happen that you might lose an irreplaceable part of yourself, and so did Tony. But he didn’t “move on” from his wife, just because she was no more with him. Even though he knew he had lost that part of himself to her, he accepted it. They were very slow days but he got there. He learnt to live a life without forgoing Lisa. Why do we have to let go of the things and the memories left behind by the demised anyway? Tony definitely didn’t because he believes “love is everything”  and that he had experienced the purest form of it; a love which won’t ever feel the same way again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the 2 seasons, he struggles with an impertinence of character and apathy for life. Tony lives in a fictional town of Tambury and writes for the local newspaper, &lt;em&gt;The Tambury Gazette&lt;/em&gt;. He works with his brother-in-law, opposite to him in nature, who stood by him throughout his journey of dealing with something that can be vaguely referred to as &lt;em&gt;life&lt;/em&gt;, after Lisa. Their newspaper showcases stories of the local people and their quirky, crazy little tales- from an old man who had been posting his letters in a dog-poop box, to a 50-year-old man who identifies as an 8-year-old girl (which according to his wife was clearly a nervous breakdown). Tony hates his job, including meeting all these people and recording their inane and frothy stories. But towards the turn of Season 1, this formerly despised routine makes his life just a tad more bearable for him. He starts relating to these people, realising that they are all either lonely or going through something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The keenness with which Gervais has worked on his characters individually is laudable. Each role brings something to the table, has a unique personality and contributes to pacifying Tony’s seething soul. Tony, who hated any social interaction, comes out of this vortex with a few special relationships. Be it the candid postman Pat (who clearly doesn’t understand boundaries), his coworker Sandy who looks up to him and shares a sweet relationship with him, his infirm father whom he visits daily or his father’s nurse Emma with whom unfolds an inexplicable relationship towards the culmination of the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The portrayal of his unbiased friendship with a sex worker who goes by the name of Roxy whom he met across the street unfurls into a sweet friendship, where she cares and worries for him a lot. He tells her that he sees a reflection of his wife in her; that even Lisa couldn’t go to sleep until everyone around her was okay. These little anecdotes, entwined in his memory is what keeps him going and concurrently pains him too. But these moments reinforce my faith in his undying love for his wife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of Season 2, Tony turns a corner and thinks that the least he can do is be a better person for the people he loves, who have constantly been there for him to rely on. He introspects as to how selfish he has been, and that life necessarily doesn’t need to be about him. If he doesn’t want to live for himself anymore, he can live for others, because &lt;em&gt;“we’re not just here for ourselves”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this had a lot to do with Anne, a woman he met at the graveyard, sitting at a bench close by, whom he found himself visiting everyday and sharing the tiniest, most banal parts of his day. She dressed his wounds with her kind and wise words, and a shared experience of losing her husband. She made him realise that the only way to heal is to let go of his anger for the world, that he can’t ever feel better again without being his intrinsically good self. She told him once that, &lt;em&gt;“Good people do things for other people. That’s it. The end.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you choose to watch this show, I promise you will laugh deliriously, even whilst questioning his coal-like dark humour and cry when he cries for no reason at all when old memories come gushing to him. Even though the development of his character through the two seasons is commendable and leaves you with a sense of warmth in your heart, you will feel this show hitting you hard because of the sheer reality that it emanates even amidst a fictional setting. After all the sadness, despair and the caustic humour, at the end you will agree with the writer on one thing at least - that &lt;em&gt;“hope is everything”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think &lt;em&gt;after life&lt;/em&gt; should be a word attributed to the living instead of the dead, in that once people leave; it is us who grapple to make peace with the reality of it all, amongst the living, in our &lt;strong&gt;After Life&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There’s no earthly medicine, nor any amount of therapy or escape from the grief that engulfs you completely from head to toe after the demise of a loved one, especially a spouse. Someone you’ve spent more than half of your life with and expected to share the rest of your old and fragile years, sprawled under the sun with a classic and some iced-tea. Someone who becomes not just a habit but as ingrained in your mind as muscle memory - the way a writer’s fingertips move across a keyboard, gliding through without a mere thought - as necessary as breathing and as easy too.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Who Really Built the Pyramids?</title>
      <link href="/Who-Really-Built-the-Pyramids" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who Really Built the Pyramids?" />
      <published>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Who-Really-Built-the-Pyramids</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Who-Really-Built-the-Pyramids">&lt;p&gt;Pyramids are arguably among the most recognisable and impressive structures around the world. For millennia this design has been used in various forms of architecture: ceremonial complexes and tombs of the ancient world to the iconic Louvre in France and the Ryugyong Hotel in North Korea, in the modern world. Although the word “pyramid” is bound to conjure up an image of the pyramids at Giza, Egypt, the basic structure is not unique to this ancient civilisation. It has made appearances in various cultures all around the world over the years- Chichen Itza (Mexico), Koh Ker (Cambodia), Ji’an (China), Meroe (Sudan) and Borobudur Temple (Indonesia) are some such examples. But why on Earth did the ancient people decide to drag massive chunks of rocks and stack them up to make the pyramids? Why were the pyramids common to so many of the civilisations in a relatively unconnected ancient world? How did the primitive people even build them, especially in as little time as 20 years, in the case of the Great Pyramid of Giza? Questions like these have baffled historians for years and several theories have been proposed to provide an answer. In this article, I shall be focussing my attention on the most popular examples of the pyramids: the pyramids of the ancient Egyptian civilization and trying to address some of these questions and controversies associated with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the most famous site of the Egyptian pyramids is located in Giza, these pyramids are far from being the oldest examples of such architecture belonging to this early civilisation. The earliest attempt at a pyramidal design resides in Saqqara and dates back to around 2780 BC (almost 4800 years old). This is the Step Pyramid of Pharaoh Djoser. It was built by the pharaoh’s youngest architect, Imhotep, whose revolutionary ideas greatly impressed the king. This pyramid took over 10 years to reach completion and underwent several changes in the initial plan on its way. The final result was a stepped pyramid, a style we usually associate with the Aztecs. It is popularly assumed to symbolise the steps that the Pharaoh would have had to take to move on to his afterlife. The pyramid of Djoser is quite possibly the oldest pyramid in the world and it heralded a long standing tradition of building similar structures to house the sarcophagi of the Pharaohs of Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next greatest attempt at such a feat would come during the reign of Huni, the last pharaoh of the third dynasty and it is located in Meidum, Egypt. It is popularly believed that although this pyramid was originally meant for him, he died before its completion and the process of construction was later taken up by the founder of the fourth dynasty, Sneferu. This pyramid is a type of step pyramid and is the oldest known example of a straight sided pyramid in Egypt. Unfortunately, due to some faults, it partially collapsed during the ancient times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sneferu’s next ambitious endeavour resulted in what is today known as the Bent Pyramid. It is located in Dashur, a necropolis in Lower Egypt. This pyramid is so called because of a very clear “bend” at its belly. However, the reason why this pyramid bears this unusual shape is not exactly known and multiple theories have been put forward to provide an explanation. One of these suggests that the initial plan was to build a structure that looks like what we have come to associate the word “pyramid” with today- a tetrahedron. The final result, however, has a slope of 54°27′44′′ below bend and 43°22′ above it. Clearly, the lower angle corresponds to a much greater total height. It is possible that the pharaoh, due to his rapidly advancing old age, wanted the process of construction to be accelerated. This left the architects with no choice but to reduce the angle to complete the structure faster. Another theory suggests that, as the Meidum Pyramid had already started collapsing, the architects decided that the base angle was way too steep (Meidum Pyramid also had a base angle of 51°50’35’’) and changed it mid-way through the construction process resulting in the infamous bend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sneferu left behind yet another pyramid in Dashur. This one is known as the Red Pyramid. This pyramid bears almost the same base angle as the upper portion of the Bent Pyramid- 43°40’ and is of the shape that we typically call a pyramid today. The Red Pyramid paved the way for the majestic pyramids at Giza during the reign of Sneferu’s successors. They were constructed roughly between 2550 BC and 2490 BC and house the burial chambers of Khafre, Khufu and Menkaure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pyramids of Giza looked very different back in its days than it does now. Firstly, they used to be white in colour owing to the use of locally found limestone on its exterior. In the sunlight, the pyramids would have had a startling and almost blinding glow. Most of this outer layer has fallen off or has eroded away. Another rather astonishing discovery in recent times is the fact that Khufu’s pyramid, also called the Great Pyramid of Giza, does not have a conventional pyramid-shape. In fact, it has eight faces and this is very clear in the aerial pictures of the structure. Each of the four faces has a slight concave split from the base to the top and all the faces have the same base length. Thus, it simply could not have been a mishap. It was planned. The outer walls of the Great Pyramid of Giza showcase the exceptional cutting skills of the builders as the rocks fit in perfectly with each other. The rocks away from the walls however, are shapeless and do not fit in well. It might have been a conscious decision to speed up the process of construction. It is popularly believed that the pyramids are so shaped to represent the rays of the sun. The sun god Ra was a central figure in the ancient Egyptian myths. The rays of the sun, called Aten, often associated with life giving properties, was just as important. In fact, during the reign of Pharaoh Akhenaten, the father of the legendary boy king Tutankhamun, a new monotheistic religion was adopted that involved worshipping only Aten. All these indicate that the pyramids were meticulously planned and they served to reinforce long held beliefs. Besides, the excellent craftsmanship of the workers is very apparent in the magnificent execution of the plans of the ambitious architects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important question that arises at this point is this: how did the people of the ancient world build something as ambitious and remarkable as the pyramids? Egyptologists believe that the ancient Egyptians had not even invented the wheel yet. This adds to the laundry list of problems associated with the construction of such a gigantic structure during a supposedly technologically backward era. In addition, not only are these pyramids grandiose, they have defied the odds of nature and stood the test of time. Besides, the rocks that make up the pyramids of Giza weigh a few tonnes each. Let’s also not forget the fact that the pyramid itself rises to a staggering height of 146.7m (in the case of Khufu’s pyramid). Apart from these, the rocks on the outside of the pyramid and those that make up the burial chamber are so precisely cut that not even a credit card can slip in in between them. In a world where humans had only very primitive tools, this indeed seems like an impossible feat. Some people think that it really was impossible and the ancient Egyptians did not, in fact, build them. Question is, who did then? Their response is just as simple as it is shocking: aliens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There many reasons why one could possibly believe in this theory. This is especially since pyramids are not only an architectural marvel but also a mathematical and scientific masterpiece. The recurrence of pi in different multiplicities in various calculated dimensions of the pyramid has baffled everyone for years. Another such remarkable discovery involves phi. The number whose square is one more than itself is referred to as phi and it is numerically equal to 1.618. Pythagorean Theorem can then be applied to find the values corresponding to any right sided triangle. Assume a triangle that has root phi as the height, 1 as the base and phi as the hypotenuse. The height to base ratio of this triangle, referred to as the Golden Triangle, is equal to 0.636. The Great Pyramid of Giza has a height of 146.7 m and the base perimeter is 230.34 m. The height to base ratio comes out to be 0.636 (approximately). The error is only about 0.025%. In addition, the pyramid is aligned within 1/15th of a degree to true North. These are only three of the numerous examples of astonishing mathematical knowledge that the ancient Egyptians supposedly possessed. The ancient alien theorists do not believe that the Egyptians are capable of having such impeccable command over the understanding of mathematics and honestly, very few disagree. In their view, it is a little too rich to expect people who didn’t know that a circular log could be used as a wheel, to understand astronomy and spend time deriving complicated mathematical equations. Another shocking fact that possibly supports the ancient aliens theory is that no Egyptian text mentions the construction of the pyramids. Egypt has around 120 pyramids and each of them is equally marvellous and unique. Yet, no one decided to write down how they managed the construction of possibly the most impressive set of structures to have been ever built in the history of mankind. There are several such arguments that have been put forward in favour of this theory about aliens being the masterminds behind the pyramids. In fact, there is an American TV series titled “Ancient Aliens” dedicated to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are numerous theories aimed at debunking the hypothesis put forward by the ancient alien theorists. Various proofs have also been found that indicate that the ancient people did in fact build the enormous structures. There are scriptures that show numerous people working together to drag a humongous statue in the form of a seated figure while one person is committed to wetting the path right in front of the sledge with the statue on it. Water does reduce friction and thus, makes dragging the weight easier. Various tools have been found and possible plans on the ground in front of the pyramids prove exceptional architectural, mathematical and engineering skills of the ancient Egyptians. At this point, you might be thinking, how do we even know who commissioned the construction of the Great Pyramid, considering the fact that tomb robbers did not even leave the sarcophagus and the mummy behind for identification, if possible. The answer to this is a series of informally scribbled messages found inside the Great Pyramid of Giza. One of them has been translated and reads: “Friends of Khufu.” It is believed to have been left behind by one of the construction workers. In addition to this, the previous discussion on the evolution of the pyramidal structure in ancient Egypt is a clear indication of the fact that they gradually developed the knowledge and understanding. Everything did not happen all at once; it took centuries for them to perfect the pyramid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of historians, architects and archaeologists have proposed several theories to explain how the gigantic structures of the ancient world like the pyramids were built. One of these theories suggests that a head on slope was employed. However, this hypothesis failed to garner support from the community of Egyptologists as the amount of rocks required to build such a slope would have been greater than that required to build the pyramid itself, in order to reach the full height. This renders the system rather inefficient and thus, unlikely. Others speculate that a slope that spiraled around the pyramid might have been used. This is popularly known as the ramp model. Some even believe that the spiral slope could have been inside the structure itself. Thermal scanning shows unexplained vacant spaces within the walls of the Giza pyramids. An elaborate mechanism has been proposed to support these findings and the theory. It involves the use of a pulley system. Although no concrete proof exists to validate this, possible carvings into the wall that could have been required for such a system to be set up, have been discovered inside the Great Pyramid of Giza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the modern world continues to believe that the ancient world was a dark age where knowledge was scarce and structures and weapons were very primitive, it is clear that we might be gravely wrong. I have also discussed how Egypt was a far more women friendly civilization than many cultures that we know of today, in one of my previous articles. However, very little of either of these is popularly known due to the efficient and long term erasure of non-cis straight male history and our long standing notions of what the ancient and medieval times were like. In fact, it is our conviction that the river valley civilizations were backward that has led us to believe in the possible involvement of aliens or even supernatural beings in the construction of the marvels of the ancient world. Whether aliens are real or not is not the concern here. The point is that we need to give the ancient humans due credit for their meticulous work and preserve history as it is.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Pyramids are arguably among the most recognisable and impressive structures around the world. For millennia this design has been used in various forms of architecture: ceremonial complexes and tombs of the ancient world to the iconic Louvre in France and the Ryugyong Hotel in North Korea, in the modern world. Although the word “pyramid” is bound to conjure up an image of the pyramids at Giza, Egypt, the basic structure is not unique to this ancient civilisation. It has made appearances in various cultures all around the world over the years- Chichen Itza (Mexico), Koh Ker (Cambodia), Ji’an (China), Meroe (Sudan) and Borobudur Temple (Indonesia) are some such examples. But why on Earth did the ancient people decide to drag massive chunks of rocks and stack them up to make the pyramids? Why were the pyramids common to so many of the civilisations in a relatively unconnected ancient world? How did the primitive people even build them, especially in as little time as 20 years, in the case of the Great Pyramid of Giza? Questions like these have baffled historians for years and several theories have been proposed to provide an answer. In this article, I shall be focussing my attention on the most popular examples of the pyramids: the pyramids of the ancient Egyptian civilization and trying to address some of these questions and controversies associated with them.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">O Ray of Truth and Humanity</title>
      <link href="/Ray-of-Truth-and-Humanity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="O Ray of Truth and Humanity" />
      <published>2020-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Ray-of-Truth-and-Humanity</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Ray-of-Truth-and-Humanity">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Not to have seen the cinema of Ray means existing in the world without seeing the sun or the moon”&lt;/em&gt;- Akira Kurosawa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing up in a Bengali household I was introduced to the world of art, music and cinema at a very early age. My love for cinema started when I watched &lt;em&gt;Sonar Kella&lt;/em&gt;, a film by Satyajit Ray. At that point in time I didn’t even know what direction was or how a movie was made, but somehow I understood that it would be nice to be able to make something like this! Like music in Bengal is tantamount to Rabindra Sangeet (ie. Nobel Laureate Rabindranath Tagore’s collection of songs), intellectual cinema in the state is defined by the artistic excellence of Satyajit Ray. For those of you who do not know who Ray is, I’ll try my best to put down words that might help you to understand him—albeit I am certain that those words will never be able to do justice to this ‘Kohinoor’ among film directors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ray was born in the year 1921 and was present when landslide changes that still affect Indian lives were afoot in the country. Now, cinema before Ray was mostly based on Indian literature. As flourished and as distinct our literature was, Indian cinema was yet to find its distinct voice. We didn’t have a lot of stories to tell, or more precisely, nobody really knew how to talk about their time. Until, of course, Ray’s film &lt;em&gt;Pather Panchali&lt;/em&gt; (The Song of the Road) came along and changed Indian cinema forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pather Panchali&lt;/em&gt; was based on a book of the same name by Bibhutibhushan Bannerjee. Although highly underrated initially, Bannerjee was later considered to be one of the most iconic writers of modern Bengali literature and also one of the most prominent writers in the post-Tagore era. Of course, there were literary works which beautifully expressed the scenario of India but none of those were as brilliant and as true as Bannerjee’s &lt;em&gt;Pather Panchali&lt;/em&gt;. When Bannerjee thought of publishing the novel, he was rejected by most of the publishing houses on the pretext that his story was too long and too upsetting. That used to be the predicament of any artist seeking to depict truth via any medium (that is what it still is).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, after a long time of rejection, at last a small-time publishing house named ‘Ranjan Prakashalay’ (Ranjan Publishers) agreed to publish the book. Without the book there wouldn’t have been a young Satyajit Ray coming out of a movie theatre in London after watching &lt;em&gt;The Bicycle Thief&lt;/em&gt; and thinking “This is what I want to be able to tell, the truth”. Ray decided to turn Bannerjee’s book into a film around 1946-47. Why? To quote Ray, it was because of the certain qualities that “made it a great book: its humanism, its lyricism, and its ring of truth”. It took a tremendous effort to turn this novel into a film, especially when each member of the crew was new to this. A bigger difficulty was funding the film, no producer was willing to finance the film, it lacked stars, songs and it wasn’t entertaining either. It took the film almost 2 years to complete, as the team faced financial crisis more than once. At last, in 1955, the film was released. A completely unorthodox film in Bengali cinema, very few people had any interest in seeing a film based on a village of West Bengal, but those that did see the film were mesmerised by its sheer simplicity. They understood that this new director named Satyajit Ray was something else altogether. The film later became one of the most significant works of art all over the world, winning numerous accolades in film festivals across the world. &lt;em&gt;Pather Panchali&lt;/em&gt; was followed by two more films named &lt;em&gt;Aparajito&lt;/em&gt; (The Unvanquished), and &lt;em&gt;Apur Sansar&lt;/em&gt; (The World of Apu). Together they are known as ‘The Apu Trilogy’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One significant feature of Ray’s films was the city of Kolkata. Due to the partition of India, the Bangladesh Liberation War and bad infrastructure, Kolkata became overly-crowded in the 70’s—which was also a period of nihilistic delusion for the youth of the city. The Naxalite period had just ended, and there was madness and frustration all around. Many people were without jobs, food, or a place to live. ‘The Kolkata Trilogy’ by Ray tells these stories of Kolkata. The trilogy contains the following films: &lt;em&gt;Pratidwandi&lt;/em&gt; (The Adversary), &lt;em&gt;Seemabaddha&lt;/em&gt; (Company Limited) and &lt;em&gt;Jana Aranya&lt;/em&gt; (The Middleman). Ray depicted the stories of three different men from three different social classes in these films, showing how the once-loved city became a nightmare for them, and how it showed them a ‘ray’ of hope as well!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, instead of merely focussing his attention on the lives of the downtrodden or grasping the frenzy of the times plainly, the maverick filmmaker’s Neo-Realism led him to weave his stories into profound human and social documentaries. Watching Ray’s Kolkata Trilogy is still the best way of understanding Kolkata and its history. That apart, the city played a huge part in his movies like &lt;em&gt;Charulata&lt;/em&gt; (The Lonely Wife) and &lt;em&gt;Mahanagar&lt;/em&gt; (The Big City). Both movies exhibit the richness of Ray’s thoughts and his genial ability to transport his audience to an adventurous yet real plethora of emotions. The problems described in Ray’s films are unfortunately still present in Indian society. Be it class struggle, the oppression of women, middle class identity crisis, religion or anything, we are still very much suffering from them. In the end, &lt;em&gt;we might cherish this man’s existence in our society but we couldn’t learn anything from his films&lt;/em&gt;. This man had the courage to talk about the problems of his time in his own way and we all know how difficult it is to talk about the truth through any art. We are becoming more and more stereotypical day-by-day, we are becoming too sensitive to hear and tell the truth each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It won’t be fair to talk about Ray and not mention his love for children, his constant enthusiasm towards creating a different world for children, a world each and every kid in Bengal has been a part of while growing up. If you ever check his work you will see the huge amount of work he has done for children. A lot of it comes from his father, Sukumar Ray, who was a critically-acclaimed poet and writer and probably the first person to write nonsensical comedy for children in Bengali—a thing which is missing from today’s ‘woke’ generation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many directors can tell really serious stories through their work but they cannot and have not made a film for the children. Now, why I’m saying this is because I truly believe that making children happy and showing them something which can inspire them through generations is the most beautiful thing that you can achieve as a filmmaker. Ray has done innumerable things for children; he made films, he wrote stories, he created the first children’s magazine in Bengali, and he created and gifted us our very own Bengali detective named ‘Feluda’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Satyajit Ray single-handedly created such an impact that it inspires generation after generation. Even today, when we watch a film by Satyajit Ray, we are drawn in. Technology was not as developed as today, resources to make a film were not readily available, yet by sheer willpower, talent and his love for the art, Ray created one masterpiece after the other. It won’t be fair to name just a couple of famous filmmakers who have been inspired greatly by Ray, as glimpses of his impact can be seen in every artist. Yesterday, ie. May 2, 2020 was our very own Manikda’s (Ray’s nickname) 99th birthday. I do not know if this article, in any way, does justice to this great human being, but I will always be thankful to Ray for showing me and our generation the truth of life, how can we learn things from our imagination and how to never stop doing what you love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Belated Happy Birthday Manikda. May you always show us the ray of hope!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Satyaki Paul&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Satyaki Paul is a film enthusiast trying to explore the unseen in cinema everyday.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>guest.contributor</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Not to have seen the cinema of Ray means existing in the world without seeing the sun or the moon”- Akira Kurosawa.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">False Hope is a Parasite</title>
      <link href="/False-Hope-is-a-Parasite" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="False Hope is a Parasite" />
      <published>2020-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/False-Hope-is-a-Parasite</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/False-Hope-is-a-Parasite">&lt;p&gt;During his childhood days, director Bong Joon Ho used to hike and traverse the hilly landscapes of his hometown Daegu in the country of South Korea, where he gradually became fond of collecting stones with his father. It must have been one of his favourite pastimes and nostalgia-inducing memories of his early days, for one such mystical rock found its way in his Oscar-winning movie, &lt;em&gt;Parasite&lt;/em&gt;, many years after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based around the lives of two Korean families, &lt;em&gt;Parasite&lt;/em&gt; is a tale about many things. The Kims, a poverty-stricken family living out in a semi-basement, slowly infiltrate the lives of the Parks, a rich family living in the home of a world-renowned architect. The Kims’ son, Ki-woo replaces his friend’s position as a tutor for the Parks’ daughter and hence begins a story about lying, cheating and manipulation as the rest of the Kims’ slowly slither their way into the household of the Parks’ as their domestic help. All of the plotting and scheming, when covered and infused with black comedy, thoroughly amuses all of us; however, it is midway through the movie when it takes a horrifying turn of events and a mirror is placed in front of us, to make us see a hard-hitting image of the class divide we all actively participate in perpetuating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked during one of his interviews about where he got the inspiration for incorporating class-consciousness in his art, director Bong Joon Ho replied, &lt;em&gt;“I think all creators, all artists, and even just everyone, we are always interested in class, 24/7. I think it would actually be strange if we’re not. You know, when we’re seeing people on the subway, on the streets, complete strangers, we wonder,&lt;/em&gt; how rich are they? &lt;em&gt;Or you know, people we encounter in the airports, did they ride economy class, business class? We always wonder about this, because we live in the era of capitalism. I think we all have a very sensitive antennae to class, in general.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was during Ki-woo and his friend’s conversation, when he is gifted a mystifying and eccentric-looking rock by his friend. The rock confuses Ki-woo and he exclaims, &lt;em&gt;“It’s so metaphorical!”&lt;/em&gt; when he shows it to his family. Throughout the movie, Ki-woo is shown to be bedazzled and stumped by this rock’s presence, a sentiment mirroring my own. This rock simply fascinated me. One of the few reasons for this was how strange it looked in the dingy basement of the Kims’. Later on in the movie, when it is used as a murder weapon, it perplexed me even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to dig up symbols in movies and I found plenty in this one. Frequent shots of stairs, basements, ascending roads and alleyways, smell and even &lt;em&gt;noodles&lt;/em&gt;; each one of them were beautifully crafted as symbols for depicting the evils of capitalism and the ever-widening gap between the rich and the poor. The Parks’ are always portrayed climbing up the stairs in their home while the Kims’ are mostly shown descending them. One of the most famous scenes of the film depicting Mrs Park fawning over how blissful and lucky she felt that it rained heavily during the preceding night when that same rain caused the Kims’ to almost lose their house to floods is a testament to just how riddled we’ve all become to act class-ignorant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Ki-woo tightly hugs the gifted rock to his chest at a camp after a dreadful rain displaces hundreds like him and his family, it dawned on me that the rock represented a ‘hope’ for him. Whether it was the hope that he could lead a luxurious life as the rock’s original owner, his friend, or the long-dreamt of vision of a better future for him and his family, this rock meant something to him. It meant the unlikely possibility of a life free from the clutches of poverty, hence why he wanted to cling onto it so badly in times of adversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This false hope of dismantling a system forever uplifting the rich and denigrating the poor, by hook or by crook, takes the form of a malicious scheme initiated by Ki-woo himself, which leads to the Kims’ acting like a &lt;em&gt;parasite&lt;/em&gt;, trying dearly to hold onto the Parks’ for their survival. The Parks’ leech off of the Kims’ hard labour, trying to keep them from ‘crossing the line’, in an attempt to maintain their status quo and respectability in the society. During one of the most realistic scenes in the film - the fight between the Kims’ and other members of the working class, it is reiterated that it’s the false hope of re-establishing one’s superiority over the other that is destroying them, when in reality they are all victims of the same evil and must stand in solidarity with each other. This false hope ultimately leads both the families of Kims’ and Parks’ to a disturbingly sad fate, which makes them go down a downward spiral they can probably never emerge from again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the movie, we are shown an ideal representation of what the Kims’ family turns up like many years afterwards. A slightly older Ki-woo moves in with his mother to the house of the Parks and reunites with his father. It is a version of events too hard to believe but we almost believe it, because humans have a tendency to cling onto every last string of hope available, just like Ki-woo in the movie. Suddenly, the scene shifts to a young Ki-woo still sitting in his semi-basement home. The movie ends with a visual of the rock being placed back in the river, probably where it came from originally. This scene stumped me for words because it signified that Ki-woo was finally letting go of his false hope. Even though the ending of &lt;em&gt;Parasite&lt;/em&gt; is deemed sad by most, for me, it was the ideal one. Maybe Ki-woo finally takes his father’s advice of making it all work by not having a plan at all. Maybe not.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aarushi Mittal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">During his childhood days, director Bong Joon Ho used to hike and traverse the hilly landscapes of his hometown Daegu in the country of South Korea, where he gradually became fond of collecting stones with his father. It must have been one of his favourite pastimes and nostalgia-inducing memories of his early days, for one such mystical rock found its way in his Oscar-winning movie, Parasite, many years after.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Story of Easter</title>
      <link href="/The-Story-of-Easter" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Story of Easter" />
      <published>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Story-of%20Easter</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Story-of-Easter">&lt;p&gt;Everyone has a worldview. This might seem like a controversial assumption, given that many would deny having any concrete belief system of sorts, but I think the claim is warranted. No one truly acts neutrally – however implicitly, they have beliefs and assumptions that drive their day-to-day actions. These assumptions might be unnoticed even by the ones who hold to them, but they are there, working subtly behind the shadows. There might be someone, for example, who says he is disinterested in philosophy and religion, but if he lives in a secular godless manner, then you know that he is living as if God does not exist – and if he is living as if God does not exist, then clearly he has a belief, deep down in his subconscious, that the idea of God is not worth taking seriously, or, at the very least, that there is no good reason to live as if God does exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, everyone has a worldview, a lens through which he/she views the world, however implicit this worldview might be. And every worldview is, ultimately, a story. I don’t mean this in a condescending manner – stories can be true! My mother used to tell me stories about my childhood, and I have no doubt concerning the sincerity of her testimony. In fact, it is stories that drive our world. Everyone has their own story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I write this on the twelfth of April, 2020. It is a Sunday, it is Easter. And what better to write on this occasion than to simply tell the story of Easter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our world is a strange, dark and forsaken world. Even in the midst of apparent joy, there is deep and real suffering. Even the ancient Indian prince Siddhartha could not help but realise that the world was filled with pain and anguish. And this realisation was so shocking and heart-wrenching for him that, as the legend goes, he forsook all royalty in search for the enlightenment that he believed would reveal to him the secret of joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things haven’t changed much. In fact, today’s world is filled with Siddharthas, desperate to discover the secret of happiness. Every advertisement you have ever seen, every product you have been keen to buy, every place you have wanted to visit, every prize you have been ambitious to win – in other words, everything you have ever done, you have done it in the hope that what you are about to do will finally bring you the joy and peace that your heart desires – or at the very least, will increase the joy that you already have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet, here you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I too was a lot like Siddhartha. In fact, my mother wanted to name me Siddhartha, but ultimately decided against it for fear that I would ultimately become a monk. But against all hope, as it turned out, I did have a very ‘monastic’ spirit, even early on. From very early on in my life, I have been searching for answers – answers to the big questions of life. Why am I here? What is my purpose? Why does this world exist? Where am I going?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short: what does it all mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thirst to discover these answers eventually became like a madness, like an obsession that had wormed itself deep into my psyche. I’m certain I was the only person in seventh grade who did not know how to play cricket, but who had, in fact, read the entire Bhagavad Gita cover to cover. I was the only kid in high school who was not a Muslim but who wanted to carry the Qur’an with him to read during the tiffin break. I was, in other words, probably exactly the kind of person my mother had initially dreaded I would become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most people, I sought for something that would give purpose to my life: religion, politics, worldly success as a writer or an actor were high on the list. And yet, the questions remained. At one point in my life, I even contemplated raw, naked materialist atheism. I started reading atheist literature and was initially greatly impressed by the force of the rhetoric. Richard Dawkins, in particular, was a crucial influence. There he stood, marshalling all the powers of reason and science in an intellectual assault upon all forms of religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, for a while, it seemed the candle had been blown out. There was no god. There was no purpose. There was no meaning to anything. There was no good, there was no evil – there was simply matter, endlessly morphing. As Christopher Hitchens wrote, “To the dumb question, ‘Why me?’ the cosmos barely bothers to return the reply: why not?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The atheist ‘enlightenment’ informed me that, at best, I was an accident. I didn’t have to be here, but I was. And I would one day flicker out of existence. I came into being for no reason, and eventually, I would perish for no reason. And all my precious joys, passions, loves, desires, ambitions, fears and sorrows would perish with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the worldview which the atheists presented to me, death was more real than life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was then that I encountered a person who completely changed my life. His name was Dr William Lane Craig. An academic philosopher of religion and a deeply Christian soul, he was a man who had debated leading atheists at universities around the world. He had faced off against big names like Lawrence Krauss, Dan Barker, Sam Harris, Peter Atkins and a whole host of other atheist heavyweights. And with him, for the first time, I saw someone who was able to give a clear and intellectually compelling case in favour of theism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, as I studied more, I came to realise that most militant atheism was more motivated by anger against religion than any careful consideration of the question of whether or not God exists. Many of the arguments atheists had been putting forward, I realised, were extremely poor and shabby, often based upon misunderstandings and caricatures of Christian arguments and theology. And some of the leading atheists like Lawrence Krauss seemed unwilling to even consider the possibility of there being a God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than overthrowing dogmas, at times it seemed that the atheists were championing new dogmas – dogmas based less upon careful intellectual thought and more upon prejudice and hatred for a particular social order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I identify not as an atheist, but as a convinced believer in Jesus Christ. I believe in Jesus – and, even more unthinkably, in the Catholic Church - because I believe Christianity – and Catholicism – are true. And I believe the story of Christianity, which is really the story of Easter, can truly change people’s lives for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bible opens with a very grand and simple line: In the beginning, God created the heavens and earth. In the Biblical worldview, God is the reason why this universe exists. God created us, and we exist because of Him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Bible also tells us that human beings sinned. Though we were originally created holy and good, we turned against God and rebelled against Him. All the evil that exists in the world is merely the outworking of man’s original sin. And the bad news is that none of us is innocent, because we have all participated in this unholy work of sin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the good news that Christianity brings is the proclamation that God did not abandon us. On the contrary, He descended from heaven and became one of us. He shared in our misery, our suffering, our loneliness, our pain and our anguish. But He did not share in our sins. He was crucified by men who hated His claims, but as He was dying on the Cross, He offered His life as a sacrifice – to atone for the sins of man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the powers of evil gathered together and climaxed on the Cross of Jesus 2,000 years ago… because there was no sin more grotesque than the murder of God’s only Son.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in the Christian worldview, death did not have the last word. On the contrary, Jesus Christ rose from the dead, physically, bodily, on the third day, triumphing over the powers of sin and death. Though men murdered Him, death could not hold Him, because He had committed no sin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who hold to materialist dogma will scoff at this idea. For countless souls, miracles and resurrections are the stuff of legend. They cannot happen and do not happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you doubt the Resurrection, then I highly recommend you to take the time to study it, historically. The Oxford atheist philosopher (and later convert to theism, though not to Christianity) Antony Flew admitted in his debate with the historian Gary Habermas that the Resurrection of Jesus had better evidence than claimed miracles in any other religion. I think he is right in this. The Gospels, after all, are not myths written centuries after the time of Jesus, but rather are biographical accounts that can, more or less, all be traced back to the first century. Though written by various authors, they all testify that Jesus rose bodily from the dead. It is the same with the letters of Paul of Tarsus, an anti-Christian Jew who was later converted after seeing a vision of the resurrected Jesus. His letter to the Galatians contains a moving testimony of his conversion, and his story is corroborated by the Book of Acts, written by a man named Luke. These documents I speak of are not fabrications, but rather the writings of real people, who lived at specific times in history, and whose biographical and at times autobiographical claims largely corroborate each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my mind, the Resurrection of Jesus is the single most extraordinary event of human history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I invite you – whoever you may be – to consider the claims of Christianity for yourself. You have nothing at all to lose. If Christianity is true, then you have everything to gain from discovering its truthfulness. But if it’s false, then a careful study will only reveal its falsity, because the truth cannot ultimately be hidden. Either way, you will increase your knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What convinced me was the intellectual arguments in favour of God’s existence, the extraordinary testimony of the resurrection of Jesus, the fulfilled prophecies of the Old Testament, the beauty and power of the very words of the Saviour, and, of course, my personal experience of grace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you might have questions, and you might want to learn more. If this is so, I rejoice in this, and I encourage you wholeheartedly to follow the truth wherever it leads. A good place to start is the YouTube channel Capturing Christianity, which regularly hosts discussions between Christian and atheist intellectuals and scholars. Bishop Robert Barron’s book &lt;em&gt;Catholicism: A Journey to the Heart of the Faith&lt;/em&gt; is also a great place to start. I also highly recommend the work of Edward Feser, an atheist philosopher whose studies in the philosophy of religion and mind eventually led him to convert to Christianity – I especially commend his book &lt;em&gt;Five Proofs of the Existence of God&lt;/em&gt;, which, in my mind, is the best intellectual and reasoned defence of classical theism that has been made in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all, I urge you to take the time out and read the New Testament, which is a collection of these ancient historical writings that testify to the life and works of Jesus of Nazareth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that there are people who will read this article of mine and laugh. Why then do I write? Why then do I spend so much time telling people about a man who lived 2,000 years ago, a man I have never met in person?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I believe this man is no mere man, but rather the incarnate Son of God. I write because this Man has changed my life, and He can change yours as well, if only you allow Him. And if you do, you will come to possess a joy that the world cannot give.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Telling people about the amazing person that is Jesus is worth any sacrifice and any cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the faith that has inspired millions, that has shaken empires, that has changed the course of human history. This is the faith of the martyrs, the confessors and the saints of the Cross. And this is the audacity with which I can stare death in the eye and proclaim that Christ is risen and that He lives forever more.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Everyone has a worldview. This might seem like a controversial assumption, given that many would deny having any concrete belief system of sorts, but I think the claim is warranted. No one truly acts neutrally – however implicitly, they have beliefs and assumptions that drive their day-to-day actions. These assumptions might be unnoticed even by the ones who hold to them, but they are there, working subtly behind the shadows. There might be someone, for example, who says he is disinterested in philosophy and religion, but if he lives in a secular godless manner, then you know that he is living as if God does not exist – and if he is living as if God does not exist, then clearly he has a belief, deep down in his subconscious, that the idea of God is not worth taking seriously, or, at the very least, that there is no good reason to live as if God does exist.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Walk with Me, Through Calcutta</title>
      <link href="/A-Walk-with-Me-through-Calcutta" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Walk with Me, Through Calcutta" />
      <published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Walk-with-Me-through-Calcutta</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Walk-with-Me-through-Calcutta">&lt;p&gt;It’s almost every day that one takes a stroll down the memory lane, but even more so during a heart-wrenching pandemic and lockdown. This is unexplored territory for most of us millennials, who have been living their teens and adulthood through the golden period of India, in terms of economy and culture both. We never had to face the horrors of the 1984 riots, the Emergency or the grotesque wars fought by India, post-Independence. I wonder if we’ll come out of this pandemic a bit more mature and stable, or just more reliant on the virtual world for sustenance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find myself one early morning after the lockdown, woken up by the sheer tirelessness at 6 am; only to witness a swathe of cotton candy shaped clouds and the Sun so calm, for it is March in Delhi. It was unlike anything I had witnessed before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a good half hour of staring at the silence clinging to the walls of my house, I make myself my ritualistic cup of lemon tea and cross another day off of my calendar, until this is all over.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I sit and blow on my tea for the thousandth time, I hear a voice from a recorder coming from my neighbour’s house. They were playing a famous Satyajit Ray song, that they do often but is usually drowned out by the jingling utensils of the neighbourhood and the hasty vehicles. I can faintly put any words together, but the calming music makes me get off my bed and lean against the wall to listen a little more clearly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I clamber on my couch, with my black laptop and fiddle through the folders to finally find the one I was rummaging for, named Kolkata or Calcutta, as most snobby Kolkatans would insist. I look at the pictures nostalgically and I’m back in the streets of the city of joy, where I can almost smell the salty fragrance of fish and the rust adorning Victoria Memorial’s old doors. For a good five years of my life, in fact, for as long as I can remember, I have dreamed of going to Kolkata. Maybe it was &lt;em&gt;Gitanjali&lt;/em&gt; by Rabindranath Tagore, Anupam Roy’s sweet sitar music, the movie &lt;em&gt;Piku&lt;/em&gt;, Kolkata’s iconic yellow taxis or my love for &lt;em&gt;Mishti Doi&lt;/em&gt; (sweet yogurt).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For someone hailing from Delhi, Kolkata hits you like the fresh respite of mint lemonade on a hot summer day. A lot more scanty and calmer than the fast-paced city of Delhi, Kolkata, for me, was a sight out of a Michelangelo painting, an architect’s candy land if you may. Wherever you look, across three-sixty degrees, beautiful colours adorn the old buildings; not one is left white. There is something about the buildings in that city - they’re as old as time, but they stand strong, bold and speak to you if you like all things old. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kolkata is one of the metropolitan cities of India, with the 7th largest population and a bustling cultural milieu, yet it feels as if time has not moved there. The city has heavy influences from its colonial past, which can be seen in the wide roads, intersections, pavements, and the touch of white on the big, stellar monuments and museums. There is a mix of old and modern Indo-Saracenic elements in Kolkata, but a huge part of it dates back to the late 19th century when it was the major cultural, economic and commercial capital of colonial India. From the old rusty doors on its buildings, the yellow taxis around the city, to the cramped markets and street vendors selling the famous street food called* Phuchka*, there are parts of Kolkata surviving still, as authentic to its culture as it could’ve been. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tradition of the &lt;em&gt;hand-pulled rickshaws &lt;/em&gt;is still going strong and extant in the tapered lanes of Kolkata’s &lt;em&gt;Bara Bazar&lt;/em&gt; (literally ‘big market’) where men labour all day long, pulling these rickshaws with people for survival. These rickshaws were introduced in Kolkata by the Chinese Traders around the 1900’s who inhabited the Bara Bazar area  primarily to carry goods. The present-day pullers are either third or fourth generation pullers carrying the colonial heritage with their heredity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government of Kolkata has tried time and again to eradicate this practice, which some consider vile and inhuman, by banning it throughout the city, however, the rickshaws can still be spotted across the town. They say it’s their heritage and legacy, and it’s the only work they know. Hence, Kolkata stands as the only city in India to still have hand-pulled rickshaws in a working environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When talking about a monopoly on things, Kolkata is also the city of the &lt;em&gt;Tram Car&lt;/em&gt;. These trams are the oldest operating electric tram system in Asia, which has been running since 1902. They are little yellow and blue carriages, usually in a pair of two that run on electricity from overhead lines and tracks laid down throughout the city; from right next to Park Street to the Fort William, their expanse is widely spread. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although these trams are old and rough around the edges, they are still chosen as a means of transportation by a significant number of lower-middle-class people, as it costs less than rupees ten to travel in this delightful little vehicle. Sitting in a tram takes you back to the 70’s and you can suddenly hear an old Hindi song playing in your head. They’re slow yet still efficient and environment-friendly and sit right in the heart of Kolkata’s culture, defining the city since time immemorial. And if you’re in Kolkata, I promise you can tell by the metallic tracks hugging the road and the muffled ringing of its bell that you’re near one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, undoubtedly, Kolkata’s culture is what it is known for across the globe. During the late 19th and 20th centuries, Kolkata gave birth to what later came to be known as the Bengal Renaissance. It is said to be initiated by the famous social-religious reformer, Raja Ram Mohan Roy, who led Kolkata to greatness, along with fellow reformers from this period - Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar, Swami Vivekananda, and many others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the British authority over India was incrementing every day, Bengal decided to step out from this period of darkness and towards the light. Reconsideration and reassessment transpired in the culture and philosophy of Kolkata, which is the very soul of a renaissance. This renaissance increased the importance of Kolkata by folds when it became the capital of colonial British India. Education, literacy, and civilisation flourished throughout the city which led to the birth of Kolkata’s literary realm, producing impressive pieces of literature and concurrently writers like the Nobel Prize-winning legend Rabindranath Tagore or Rashsundari Debi who is considered to be one of the first Indian women to write an autobiography and the first Bengali woman to have ever written anything. The Bengal renaissance not only brought literature and knowledge but reforms, technology, science, and enlightenment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise in Bengali culture during the time of colonialism is a watershed for Indian feminism because of the remnants that some of the women have left behind. Kolkata has witnessed women like Begum Rokeya, the author of the feminist utopian story &lt;em&gt;Sultana’s Dream&lt;/em&gt;, Nobel Peace Prize recipient Mother Teresa, Bina Das and Aruna Asaf Ali who laid a firm foundation of a feminist example for India’s posterity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the streets of Kolkata, I was not only staggered by its beautiful museums and churches but the art that lives in every corner of that city. Be it music, books or food, Kolkata aces the chart on every ground. It houses India’s largest library - The National Library of India, which provides a serene environment for any bibliophile, and &lt;em&gt;College Street, &lt;/em&gt;a mile of bookshops and bookstalls spilling over each other, where a large majority of publishers are situated. It became the heart of all-things-books after the &lt;em&gt;Kallol *movement, started around the beginning of the 20th century, witnessed the arrival of postmodernism. One of the greatest achievements of the &lt;/em&gt;Kallol* group was in establishing a new generation of writers and thinkers in Bengal, especially Kolkata. This also gave rise to Kolkata’s cinematic scene theatre and by extension, art films, known worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember seeing the oldest building in Kolkata situated in the centre of a jostling market called Lalbazar, lost and unmarked, shown to me by an old man, a lawyer, whom I met in my Uber-pool. It had red bricks and white pillars with curved white-painted windows. Before he left, he told me the best time to enjoy all that Kolkata has to offer is mid-October, during the period of Durga Pujo, a time of week-long festivities and food. The city lights up like a cluster of fireflies and rejoices with music authentic to the soul of Kolkata. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city lost its colossal importance after the capital of the Indian subcontinent was shifted from Calcutta (back then) to Delhi on December 12, 1911. However, it still strives to mesmerise its inhabitants and travellers from across the globe. It’s unlike any other city, soaked deeply in immense history and culture, which is reflected in every building, every pavement, and every bite of its delectable &lt;em&gt;roshogollas&lt;/em&gt;. The sweet Bengali music from the house adjacent to mine stops as the world wakes up and dives into the everyday hustle of life again. I close the window into my memory jar of Kolkata, rush to the kitchen and pour my nostalgia into a hearty Sunday treat of &lt;em&gt;Mishti Doi.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It’s almost every day that one takes a stroll down the memory lane, but even more so during a heart-wrenching pandemic and lockdown. This is unexplored territory for most of us millennials, who have been living their teens and adulthood through the golden period of India, in terms of economy and culture both. We never had to face the horrors of the 1984 riots, the Emergency or the grotesque wars fought by India, post-Independence. I wonder if we’ll come out of this pandemic a bit more mature and stable, or just more reliant on the virtual world for sustenance. </summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">HER: A Tale of Blurred Lines of Love</title>
      <link href="/HER-A-Tale-of-Blurred-Lines-of-Love" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="HER: A Tale of Blurred Lines of Love" />
      <published>2020-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/HER-A-Tale-of-Blurred-Lines-of-Love</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/HER-A-Tale-of-Blurred-Lines-of-Love">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Theodore Twombly:&lt;/em&gt; What are you doing? &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Samantha:&lt;/em&gt; I'm just sitting here, looking at the world and writing a new piece of music. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Theodore Twombly:&lt;/em&gt; Can I hear it? What's this one about?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Samantha:&lt;/em&gt; Well, I was thinking, we don't really have any photographs of us. And I thought this song could be like a photo that captures us at this moment in our life together.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Theodore Twombly:&lt;/em&gt; Aw, I like our photograph. I can see you in it.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Samantha:&lt;/em&gt; I am.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t watched this movie yet, you need to figure out the most mundane and ordinary day to sit and binge through this cinematic work of art because you’ll need a good two hours later to stare at the wall and think about it. &lt;em&gt;A little later in the week and in all the still and noiseless moments of your life too&lt;/em&gt;. But why are we talking about a six-year-old movie? Primarily because &lt;em&gt;Her&lt;/em&gt; is a movie that stands more relevant today than ever and it will remain so for the next century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story spins around a fairly simple and reclusive guy, Theodore Twombly who writes heartwarming letters for a living at a company called (BeautifulHandwrittenLetters.com)[BeautifulHandwrittenLetters.com], letters that’ll make you feel a tingling sensation in your back and curl your toes. He’s your everyday Joe with a sweet and simple appearance, but if you look closely, he has a broken heart from his ex-wife that he is seen trying to mend throughout the movie. &lt;em&gt;Her&lt;/em&gt; is set in an undisclosed time in the future, where technology has taken over the human life threefold than it does now, trickling down human interaction to its least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, it’s completely normal for us to meet somebody via the internet or social media, talk to them, laugh with them, and maybe even fall in love with them in the process. Meeting the old fashioned way isn’t what you get to see very often- a café, two corner booths and eyes meeting over the same order of Irish coffee from across the room. Instead, it starts with a follow request or a right swipe. If that’s our cultural identity, then it’s not going too far to say that you can fall in love with an operating system; as shown in this ensemble by Spike Jonze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you gulped a little too hard at that, then sit tight because this story is all about the struggle of the self, about thinning the boundaries of the real and the unreal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an adventure of the protagonist Theodore Twombly, who purchases a new operating system to better his life, exclusively designed for the personal needs of each individual. This operating system names herself Samantha, who is an ever-evolving device, learning from humans and picking up on their habits. He carries her around, shares the little and larger things about his day and most importantly- laughs wholeheartedly with her. He befriends her over their shared humour and easiness of being together which ultimately leads to falling in love with her, so much so that he isn’t afraid to accept it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might sound ridiculous to think of someone loving an inanimate object such as an OS but the intricacy with which Spike Jonze has written it and Joaquin Phoenix has flawlessly personified the character would take you on a roller coaster of emotions throughout the two hours of this movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A light banter over the phone becomes their everyday routine and Samantha feels more like a human with every passing minute, and so does their relationship. This delusion is conjured skillfully by the writer through the seclusion of characters from the world and the empathising nature of Theodore’s loneliness. The lightness in him and the calming effect of his presence gives a nice contrast to the brazenly out-there idea of the movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only point of human contact that Theodore has is his neighbour and college best friend, Amy who provides him with little bits of sanity now and then, as most of our friends do for us. Telling them your innermost thoughts that sound beyond normal in your head, somehow begin to gain a sense of sanity as you voice it out to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Amy tells him that she has become best friends with her OS since she left her husband, Theodore gathers the courage to say it out loud for the first time: that he is dating an operating system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He somewhere feels that this is insane but Amy senses that and sympathises with him telling him that, “Falling in love is kind of like a form of socially acceptable insanity”. This one line ties together the essence of the movie and the argument of what is acceptable and what isn’t. As long as you can accommodate and accept an idea in your head and heart, nothing is too far fetched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, you start to believe in their relationship and the genuineness of Samantha; which is the beauty of the screenplay and the one man tussle of Joaquin Phoenix, who carries us with him throughout the movie, never letting us go off the wagon even for a second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this misty canvas of emotions comes washing down when one day he wakes up and calls Samantha, only to find out that she’s not there at the other end of the line. He tries in vain to connect to her repeatedly but it’s as if she vanished from his phone, his life. And in that brief second, their entire relationship flashes before his eyes, he’s panting and almost subliminal. Even though she’s back in the next moment, he realizes how fleetingly real this relationship was. One minute it was everything, and the next there was no trace of it in the world- it fizzled into thin air. For a spectator, this instance was like a snap out of a daydream as a huge underlying reality of the story hits you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to that, Theodore’s ex-wife, whom he has always had unresolved feelings for, learns about his relationship with an operating system, Samantha, and blatantly tells him that he is crazy to pursue such a relationship just because he cannot handle ‘real emotions.’ She even goes on to say that he had always wanted a wife without the challenges of actually dealing with something real. Her reaction gives us an insight into Theodore’s deepest insecurities and a more clear view of why his relationship with Samantha worked out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He goes into a dour state of introspection and starts developing issues with Samantha. They fight, they cry and emotionalise, consummating the final step of their relationship and making it as human as it could have been. But the reality once slipped away, only drifts farther and farther in his mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What finally happens to Samantha and Theodore is something I’d leave up to you to comprehend for yourself. I’d urge you to go and watch the movie, for the feeling that it ends with is not something any writer can pen down in a review, let alone myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what I can comment on is the complex and mind-twisting path chosen by Spike Jonze to portray modern love, the paradox of solipsism and its untwined relationship with technology in the 21st century. It makes us question the boundaries of love? The line that separates the real and the unreal is no more clear to one. This movie toys with the questions we’re too afraid to ask ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is the tangled beauty of this story - it leaves you with an unfamiliar feeling in the pit of your stomach towards the end because we humans like to know the why and how of everything, and that is something that this movie does not promise.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Poorvi Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Theodore Twombly: What are you doing? Samantha: I'm just sitting here, looking at the world and writing a new piece of music. Theodore Twombly: Can I hear it? What's this one about? Samantha: Well, I was thinking, we don't really have any photographs of us. And I thought this song could be like a photo that captures us at this moment in our life together. Theodore Twombly: Aw, I like our photograph. I can see you in it. Samantha: I am.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Regret in The American Dream</title>
      <link href="/The-Regret-in-The-American-Dream" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Regret in The American Dream" />
      <published>2020-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Regret-in-The-American-Dream</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Regret-in-The-American-Dream">&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Martin-Scorsese-and-The-American-Dream&quot;&gt;first article&lt;/a&gt; for The Pangean was on how Martin Scorsese felt about the ‘American Dream’ and expressed the same through the medium of his movies. In 2019, he took another attempt at revising that same theme with &lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt;. It feels like a full-circle moment when I was asked to write on it because the first thing that I thought of when I watched this 3-hour epic was that this was Scorsese looking back introspectively on his own career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right off the bat, I want to note that* The Irishman* has very little similarity to &lt;em&gt;Goodfellas&lt;/em&gt;, or The &lt;em&gt;Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;Mean Streets&lt;/em&gt;, apart from style. The first shot of the movie shows a heavily made-up Robert De Niro, playing an old, wheelchair-ridden Frank Sheeran, narrating his story in flashback-style. If I had known better, this was indication enough that &lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt; is not going to be the type of borderline glorification that Martin Scorsese has been accused of throughout his career. His movies generally start with the energy of youth - Jordan Belfort’s infectious but immature energy to be a bull, Henry Hill with an iconic line about how he always wanted to be a gangster or even the excitement of running casinos mixed with all the sins you can think of in &lt;em&gt;Casino&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt; progresses with showing how Frank Sheeran, an American of Irish descent, started off as a meat truck driver after leaving army service, a possibly traumatic experience where he may have killed unarmed Germans who were willing to surrender, just as a revenge statement. He shows no qualms in joining the Bufalino crime family and doing questionable things for money and, hence, a more stable family life. He would do as he was told, no questions asked. Loyalty took first place above all other ambitions. The violence in the movie was subtle, there was nothing flashy about the editing of the movie in terms of it making the movie more frenetic, and everyone who was killed in the movie was just done off without a lot of hullabaloos, unlike Scorsese’s other films. Mind you,* The Irishman* has lots of killings. The difference was that most of them were hardly shown visually, but merely explained. In stark contrast, &lt;em&gt;Goodfellas&lt;/em&gt; has an entire montage showing how wiseguys Tommy, Jimmy and Henry eliminated people that could have troubled them. In &lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt;, every person who died before Sheeran was accompanied by a text infographic showing their name, date of death and cause of death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It speaks volumes about what Scorsese wants to achieve through the movie. Is it to make the mob life more interesting, and show what attracts people to that side of life? If that was the case, there would really be nothing separating &lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;Goodfellas&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;Casino&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;Mean Streets&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;. Rather, &lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt; has more in common with &lt;em&gt;Raging Bull&lt;/em&gt; than any of his other films. &lt;em&gt;Raging Bull&lt;/em&gt; starts very similarly - after a celebrated, but incredibly rough boxing career marred by relationship issues, anger, abuse, a prison sentence, and a run with the Mafia, Jake LaMotta becomes a stand-up comedian. He looks at himself in the mirror, and monologues about the point of his life. He’s become much fatter compared to his boxer days and looks withered out. Scorsese may often be accused of having extremely stock female characters that aren’t well fleshed out. However, to his credit, he doesn’t spare anything in ripping the character of his male leads to shreds, to the extent that they may be unlikeable. At the same time, the world that they live in draws you, and you can’t resist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt; is not that world. The second hour of the movie focuses on Sheeran’s relationship with Jimmy Hoffa, the leader of the Teamsters Union of workers, and thereby a hugely-respected man. All of the problematic things Hoffa does is for the betterment of his workers. Otherwise, he has a joyful code of conduct in life. He loves his family and turns out to be a better father figure to Sheeran’s younger daughter, Peggy, than Sheeran himself. This hour of the movie is extremely wholesome - Sheeran discovers that you can form personal, endearing relationships with the people you work for. For him, that person was Hoffa. This friendship sounds hardly like any of the partnerships that were present in Scorsese’s filmography. They were based on a code of brotherhood: friendly enough that neither would screw the other over, but professional enough that each knows his boundaries. Sheeran helped Hoffa build his American Dream, where the workers feel empowered and have maximum bargaining power. It wouldn’t take Hoffa one day to shut down operations across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hoffa was jailed for jury tampering in 1963 by the Kennedy administration. According to the movie, he wanted to come back to power in the Union. His replacement, Frank Fitzsimmons, was handing out interest-free loans to the Bufalino family. Hoffa was barred by Nixon from interacting with any labour organisation in any capacity. He also had a prison spat with Anthony Provenzano, former vice-president of the Union and New Jersey mob leader. The Mafia was wary of Hoffa’s rise to power, which may have disrupted their arrangements with the Union. Soon enough, Russell Bufalino called for his head, and ordered Frank Sheeran to do it, at least, according to the movie’s stance: nobody can actually confirm who was involved in Hoffa’s disappearance. The book written by Charles Brandt is vocal about Sheeran’s direct involvement, and hence, the movie as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next 30 minutes are spent in patience, waiting up to the moment where Sheeran shoots Hoffa. The 30 minutes after are spent in Sheeran trying to process the emotion of regret, but possibly failing, or being unable to move on. He goes to confession, brags about Jimmy Hoffa to his hospice care with pride as if he were a rockstar in his time, all the while trying to grapple with what he had truly done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One look at a summary of the movie tells you that it plays about the classic elements of a standard mob movie very subtly. The idea that you could bend your moral code just a little each day so that you could achieve your ideal of the American Dream, got tested with each questionable act, or each emotion that Sheeran was unable to process. The code of loyalty, brotherhood and business, that so tightly binds mobs in gangster movies was broken down in the most emotional way possible. What Scorsese may have done before is show downfall in terms of a sentence served, a physical manifestation of Icarus flying too close to the sun. Nobody was shown to be eaten from the insides, unlike Frank Sheeran here. It wasn’t the prison sentence he served later that was his penance; it was the fact that he had to live with being unable to truly feel for Hoffa, despite wanting to so badly because he loved him. One may argue that the American Dream doesn’t care about how you feel: in a race to consume everything by growing to be the best version of yourself financially, you forget about your mental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, mob movies are tied by familial bonds, which become another foundation for the American Dream as defined by the mafioso, or the genre of movies. Your actions are justified to a fair extent as long as you’re extending the benefits to your family and giving them a happy life. &lt;em&gt;Goodfellas&lt;/em&gt; indulged in that idea for the longest time. In &lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt;, it hardly mattered. Peggy, Sheeran’s youngest daughter, never looked at him as a father. For all the money and stature that he may have earned, he could never gain the trust of someone who arguably mattered more. What is worse was that Sheeran never truly found out why his daughter was so quiet around him. He never figured out it was a resentment of the violence he perpetrated or the fact that his name was in the papers for all the wrong reasons. He didn’t spend too much time with her either. His being around for her was restricted to financial concern and physical protection, or so says the movie. And &lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt; then elaborates on why that in itself is so preposterous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like the movie, rather fittingly, this piece feels like an extended epilogue to the first article I wrote for The Pangean. I had no idea &lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt; would be this entire flip from what old man Marty had done before. I remember laughing so much when I first saw &lt;em&gt;Goodfellas. *I rewatch *The Departed *every time I’m free, *Hugo&lt;/em&gt; was nice too and &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; is also a riot with every viewing. &lt;em&gt;Taxi Driver&lt;/em&gt; is jarring and &lt;em&gt;Raging Bull&lt;/em&gt; is wondrous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then who’s cutting these onions? &lt;em&gt;The Irishman&lt;/em&gt; is easily one of the best movies of last year (second-best in this author’s humble opinion) because it does exactly what no one expected: get you teary-eyed for the life of nonagenarian Irish mobster, based on a story that, while unconfirmed, is most likely true, and was heralded by a boomer that has changed the face of cinema as we have known it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pranav Manie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">My first article for The Pangean was on how Martin Scorsese felt about the ‘American Dream’ and expressed the same through the medium of his movies. In 2019, he took another attempt at revising that same theme with The Irishman. It feels like a full-circle moment when I was asked to write on it because the first thing that I thought of when I watched this 3-hour epic was that this was Scorsese looking back introspectively on his own career.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
