<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/culture/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-10-20T15:42:30+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/culture/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What if Veritaserum was Real?</title>
      <link href="/What-If-Veritaserum-was-Real" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What if Veritaserum was Real?" />
      <published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-If-Veritaserum-was-Real</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-If-Veritaserum-was-Real">&lt;p&gt;For those of you who don’t know what Veritaserum is (seriously?), it is a
magical truth potion from the universe of Harry Potter. As a collegiate debater,
I have faced my fair share of &lt;em&gt;meta&lt;/em&gt; motions. One of the most intriguing ones
that I have come across is: ‘This house prefers a world where no one can lie.’
Although it sounds like a very common, overused motion, it got me thinking, is
it really possible? What would the world be like? And would I want to live in
that world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us start with the first question: can Veritaserum indeed be a reality one
day? Well, let me break this to you- truth serums very much exist. In fact, they
have been available since the 1920’s. They are primarily mind-altering
(psychoactive) drugs which slow down the process of transfer of messages from
the spinal cord to the brain. Lying usually requires a lot of effort, unless you
are a compulsive liar. These drugs simply hinder your capability to concentrate
and thus, make it difficult to lie. They don’t, however, completely inhibit your
ability to lie. Some common examples include &lt;em&gt;sodium thiopental&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;scopolamine&lt;/em&gt;
and &lt;em&gt;sodium amytal&lt;/em&gt;. Historically, they have been used for various other
purposes. During World War II, they were used as anti-anxiety drugs on soldiers.
Until 2011, they were also used as anaesthetics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very rarely have truth serums been used for interrogation though, due to ethical
conflicts. A myriad of historical examples, however, portray the positives of
using such drugs in a criminal investigation. The 2007 Noida serial killer case
(in India) could only be solved when the suspect confessed, under the influence
of &lt;em&gt;sodium amytal&lt;/em&gt;, to the heinous crimes that had been committed by him.
However, the use of truth serums during interrogation is considered to be a
direct violation of the Fifth Amendment of the US Constitution (the Right to
remain silent) and is, thus, illegal in the US. Many consider the administration
of truth serums, in order to extract information, to not only be a violation of
the human right to be free from degrading treatment but also a form of torture.
Besides, these drugs have some serious side-effects, including the development
of false memories, addiction and even death in case of an overdose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of such concerns, research is on to find and develop a drug that can
completely prevent a person from lying, including compulsive liars, without any
grave side-effects: &lt;em&gt;the ultimate Veritaserum&lt;/em&gt;. But just because something can
be done doesn’t mean that it should be done. Whether it is morally right or
wrong requires thinking through a lot of different things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One side of the debate might argue that taking away the right to lie is a severe
encroachment upon the right to choose. At times, it might, in fact, be necessary
to lie- white lies. Thomas Paine once said, “He who dares not offend cannot be
honest”. In a world where being polite is deemed a great virtue, it is
impossible to get by without lying, if one hopes to follow the etiquettes set by
a genteel society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a child, still in the formative years, tries to learn something new, we
provide them encouragement shrouded in little lies. This is necessary to prevent
them from losing interest or giving up. It is also unfortunate that the modern
world isn’t very progressive when it comes to accepting the LGBTQIA+ community,
often forcing people of the community to lie about their sexuality or gender to
save themselves from questions, comments and bullies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At times, lies are crucial to one’s safety. Celebrities lie about where they
live to prevent stalkers from breaking in, spies put on a disguise and lie to
unveil the secrets of underground institutions and terrorist cells, while also
ensuring personal safety against potential harm from the people they spy upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When doctors fail to see alternative options to save a person’s life, they often
resort to placebo. This involves actively lying to the patient about the effects
the drugs have been having on the person’s health- telling them that the
medicines have actually been working well and that they will get well soon when
that is probably not the case. In some cases, patients actually have a positive
response to this. While many see this practice as unethical, owing to the fact
that a doctor has to blatantly lie to a patient, others think that using placebo
as a last resort to help them is justified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most of these cases are rather niche, there are many which are not as
individualistic. Taking a step back and looking at the big picture, reveals
other interesting aspects. The avenues that greatly affect our day to day lives
like politics, religion, media, etc. tend to hurt us mostly when lies in some
form or the other are involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk politics. Populist demagogues, who tend to make fake promises based
on what the majority of the populace desires instead of using rational
arguments, are the biggest disgrace to modern politics. Their campaigns and
popularity are based on lies. Commoners fall prey to their words because these
leaders pander to what people already want to hear. Examples of such leaders
include Adolf Hitler and Benito Mussolini. Stephen Hawking once tagged even
Donald Trump as a demagogue. It isn’t unknown to any of us what their ‘reigns’
have been like. Even though stripping politicians of the ability to lie won’t
solve the problems that pervade politics, it does ensure that commoners do not
get cheated into hoping for something that is never meant to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing to affect our lives immensely is crime. False charges, corruption
and plantation of fake evidence are not unusual. It is common practice among
convicts, facing the possibility of a long sentence, to lie about the severity
of their crimes to hinder the prosecution. Psychopaths and sociopaths are able
to lie without any remorse whatsoever. Most serial killers can be classified as
either of the two and their flawless lying makes them incredibly difficult to
spot. The problems of adjudication, conviction and prosecution will simply fail
to exist in a world where people are unable to lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unethical marketing cheats people into believing that a product provides certain
benefits which it actually doesn’t. Tech giants like Google, Amazon, Facebook,
Qualcomm and so on have come under a lot of heat in recent years. Immense
capital is spent on investigating these companies to find the truth. In a
lie-less world, these problems would simply cease to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cases of fraud often take several years to be solved and have justice served
for, like the Enron scandal. It is easier to live in a world where committing
fraud is an impossibility than to have so many duped before spending big bucks
to rectify the situation. The morality of the work done by certain companies
itself is questionable. Take Ashley Madison for example, it is a dating site
catering to those who are currently in a committed relationship or married. The
profits of this company are based on how well they are able to lie without
taking into consideration the fact that they hurt people in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is widespread misinformation in the world owing to the phenomena of ‘fake
news’. Lies about the intentions of a party creates misunderstandings, leading
to conflict and divided masses. Social media has enabled lying to a whole new
extent. It is fashionable to lie about not having make-up on or not having had
plastic surgery in the past, or even about living perfect lives. These set
unrealisable standards of lifestyle and beauty for everyone. This eventually
culminates in depression among teenagers and adults who fail to achieve these
unreal standards- something that is more common now than ever. In fact,
celebrities, like K-Pop idols, are forced to undergo surgeries to comply with
certain beauty standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that shapes society drastically is religion. Problems arise from
lies about what God desires. While this can be used as a powerful positive tool
too, there exist other alternatives to achieve the same. For example, it is
better to tell a person not to cut a tree because they provide us with oxygen
rather than using some religious reference to drive the point home. This is
because, for one, atheism is on the rise and will, in the future, be the
dominant ‘belief’ (atheism is expected to overtake religion by 2041). These
atheists associate religion with regressiveness of thought and religious
justifications are unacceptable to them. Secondly, religious beliefs do not have
the same appeal among people belonging to different religions or sects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While freedom of choice is essential for everyone, this freedom cannot affect
someone else- hurt the other person or encroach upon their freedom. Social
contract theorists argue that everyone in a society moves into a contract with
each other and the government, and the government can partially take away
certain rights of individuals to ensure greater benefits for society at large.
If this ‘sacrifice’ is what society operates upon, I personally feel that it is
justified to take away the right to lie if greater benefits can be ensured in
the process.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all problems can be solved by just stopping people from lying. A world where
no one can lie is not the ideal world. Crimes will be committed. Bad people will
continue to exist. They will have evil intentions; they just will not be able to
lie about them. While it might seem that taking away the right to lie infringes
upon individual rights, the greater benefits it provides makes me question if
the argument of ‘rights’ is sufficient grounds to argue against it. A world like
this, however, is a reality left in store for those who come after us (unless
someone is secretly preparing for a Nobel Prize). For now, we are doomed to live
in a world of lies, fraud and betrayal where we can only hope that the ones we
trust the most do not lie to us.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For those of you who don’t know what Veritaserum is (seriously?), it is a magical truth potion from the universe of Harry Potter. As a collegiate debater, I have faced my fair share of meta motions. One of the most intriguing ones that I have come across is: ‘This house prefers a world where no one can lie.’ Although it sounds like a very common, overused motion, it got me thinking, is it really possible? What would the world be like? And would I want to live in that world? Let us start with the first question: can Veritaserum indeed be a reality one day? Well, let me break this to you- truth serums very much exist. In fact, they have been available since the 1920’s. They are primarily mind-altering (psychoactive) drugs which slow down the process of transfer of messages from the spinal cord to the brain. Lying usually requires a lot of effort, unless you are a compulsive liar. These drugs simply hinder your capability to concentrate and thus, make it difficult to lie. They don’t, however, completely inhibit your ability to lie. Some common examples include sodium thiopental, scopolamine and sodium amytal. Historically, they have been used for various other purposes. During World War II, they were used as anti-anxiety drugs on soldiers. Until 2011, they were also used as anaesthetics. Very rarely have truth serums been used for interrogation though, due to ethical conflicts. A myriad of historical examples, however, portray the positives of using such drugs in a criminal investigation. The 2007 Noida serial killer case (in India) could only be solved when the suspect confessed, under the influence of sodium amytal, to the heinous crimes that had been committed by him. However, the use of truth serums during interrogation is considered to be a direct violation of the Fifth Amendment of the US Constitution (the Right to remain silent) and is, thus, illegal in the US. Many consider the administration of truth serums, in order to extract information, to not only be a violation of the human right to be free from degrading treatment but also a form of torture. Besides, these drugs have some serious side-effects, including the development of false memories, addiction and even death in case of an overdose. In spite of such concerns, research is on to find and develop a drug that can completely prevent a person from lying, including compulsive liars, without any grave side-effects: the ultimate Veritaserum. But just because something can be done doesn’t mean that it should be done. Whether it is morally right or wrong requires thinking through a lot of different things. One side of the debate might argue that taking away the right to lie is a severe encroachment upon the right to choose. At times, it might, in fact, be necessary to lie- white lies. Thomas Paine once said, “He who dares not offend cannot be honest”. In a world where being polite is deemed a great virtue, it is impossible to get by without lying, if one hopes to follow the etiquettes set by a genteel society. When a child, still in the formative years, tries to learn something new, we provide them encouragement shrouded in little lies. This is necessary to prevent them from losing interest or giving up. It is also unfortunate that the modern world isn’t very progressive when it comes to accepting the LGBTQIA+ community, often forcing people of the community to lie about their sexuality or gender to save themselves from questions, comments and bullies. At times, lies are crucial to one’s safety. Celebrities lie about where they live to prevent stalkers from breaking in, spies put on a disguise and lie to unveil the secrets of underground institutions and terrorist cells, while also ensuring personal safety against potential harm from the people they spy upon. When doctors fail to see alternative options to save a person’s life, they often resort to placebo. This involves actively lying to the patient about the effects the drugs have been having on the person’s health- telling them that the medicines have actually been working well and that they will get well soon when that is probably not the case. In some cases, patients actually have a positive response to this. While many see this practice as unethical, owing to the fact that a doctor has to blatantly lie to a patient, others think that using placebo as a last resort to help them is justified. While most of these cases are rather niche, there are many which are not as individualistic. Taking a step back and looking at the big picture, reveals other interesting aspects. The avenues that greatly affect our day to day lives like politics, religion, media, etc. tend to hurt us mostly when lies in some form or the other are involved. Let’s talk politics. Populist demagogues, who tend to make fake promises based on what the majority of the populace desires instead of using rational arguments, are the biggest disgrace to modern politics. Their campaigns and popularity are based on lies. Commoners fall prey to their words because these leaders pander to what people already want to hear. Examples of such leaders include Adolf Hitler and Benito Mussolini. Stephen Hawking once tagged even Donald Trump as a demagogue. It isn’t unknown to any of us what their ‘reigns’ have been like. Even though stripping politicians of the ability to lie won’t solve the problems that pervade politics, it does ensure that commoners do not get cheated into hoping for something that is never meant to happen. Another thing to affect our lives immensely is crime. False charges, corruption and plantation of fake evidence are not unusual. It is common practice among convicts, facing the possibility of a long sentence, to lie about the severity of their crimes to hinder the prosecution. Psychopaths and sociopaths are able to lie without any remorse whatsoever. Most serial killers can be classified as either of the two and their flawless lying makes them incredibly difficult to spot. The problems of adjudication, conviction and prosecution will simply fail to exist in a world where people are unable to lie. Unethical marketing cheats people into believing that a product provides certain benefits which it actually doesn’t. Tech giants like Google, Amazon, Facebook, Qualcomm and so on have come under a lot of heat in recent years. Immense capital is spent on investigating these companies to find the truth. In a lie-less world, these problems would simply cease to exist. Cases of fraud often take several years to be solved and have justice served for, like the Enron scandal. It is easier to live in a world where committing fraud is an impossibility than to have so many duped before spending big bucks to rectify the situation. The morality of the work done by certain companies itself is questionable. Take Ashley Madison for example, it is a dating site catering to those who are currently in a committed relationship or married. The profits of this company are based on how well they are able to lie without taking into consideration the fact that they hurt people in the process. There is widespread misinformation in the world owing to the phenomena of ‘fake news’. Lies about the intentions of a party creates misunderstandings, leading to conflict and divided masses. Social media has enabled lying to a whole new extent. It is fashionable to lie about not having make-up on or not having had plastic surgery in the past, or even about living perfect lives. These set unrealisable standards of lifestyle and beauty for everyone. This eventually culminates in depression among teenagers and adults who fail to achieve these unreal standards- something that is more common now than ever. In fact, celebrities, like K-Pop idols, are forced to undergo surgeries to comply with certain beauty standards. Another thing that shapes society drastically is religion. Problems arise from lies about what God desires. While this can be used as a powerful positive tool too, there exist other alternatives to achieve the same. For example, it is better to tell a person not to cut a tree because they provide us with oxygen rather than using some religious reference to drive the point home. This is because, for one, atheism is on the rise and will, in the future, be the dominant ‘belief’ (atheism is expected to overtake religion by 2041). These atheists associate religion with regressiveness of thought and religious justifications are unacceptable to them. Secondly, religious beliefs do not have the same appeal among people belonging to different religions or sects. While freedom of choice is essential for everyone, this freedom cannot affect someone else- hurt the other person or encroach upon their freedom. Social contract theorists argue that everyone in a society moves into a contract with each other and the government, and the government can partially take away certain rights of individuals to ensure greater benefits for society at large. If this ‘sacrifice’ is what society operates upon, I personally feel that it is justified to take away the right to lie if greater benefits can be ensured in the process.   Not all problems can be solved by just stopping people from lying. A world where no one can lie is not the ideal world. Crimes will be committed. Bad people will continue to exist. They will have evil intentions; they just will not be able to lie about them. While it might seem that taking away the right to lie infringes upon individual rights, the greater benefits it provides makes me question if the argument of ‘rights’ is sufficient grounds to argue against it. A world like this, however, is a reality left in store for those who come after us (unless someone is secretly preparing for a Nobel Prize). For now, we are doomed to live in a world of lies, fraud and betrayal where we can only hope that the ones we trust the most do not lie to us.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">To Walk Again: On Love In Shinkai’s Anime</title>
      <link href="/To-Walk-Again" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To Walk Again: On Love In Shinkai’s Anime" />
      <published>2019-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/To-Walk-Again</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/To-Walk-Again">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Narukami no sukoshi toyomite&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
(A faint clap of thunder)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;sashi kumori&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
(Clouded skies)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ame mo furanu ka?&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
(Perhaps rain comes)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kimi wo todomemu&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
(If so, will you stay here with me?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fate, sometimes, begets in itself the funniest stories as well as the most
melancholic ones. It writes its own comedies and tragedies. The way we interpret
it, however, is what finalises the effect fate has on us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Makoto Shinkai is a giant in the world of anime. Deservedly and frequently does
he get compared to Miyazaki; a genius in the field. I do not wish to compare two
of the most amazing anime directors. Their work and their storytelling have
always touched a chord in my heart; a reaction spanning all of the people who
have watched their movies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shinkai is, however, criticised due to his lack of versatility in approaching
the themes of stories. &lt;em&gt;Most&lt;/em&gt; of his stories pertain to separation and love,
requited or otherwise. &lt;em&gt;Garden of Words&lt;/em&gt;, one of his works, is not any
different. However, the multitude of perspectives that went behind the making of
the story’s concept is what makes the story stand out, in the midst of a
plethora of influential anime films.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Garden of Words&lt;/em&gt; sets up an atmosphere which most of us can relate to on a
superficial level. Shinkai has never been afraid to work on stuff he personally
connects to, as a result of which three things come forth in his films as
defining motifs: train, rain, and pain, strangely enough they rhyme too. &lt;em&gt;Garden
of words&lt;/em&gt; interweaves a beautiful love story between the two protagonists and
despite their mutual feelings for each other, they remain visibly disconnected
from each other. They remain separated by the immense difference in age that
exists between the two of them. 27-year-old, Yukari Yukino is a teacher in the
same school as the 15-year-old Takao Akizuki, albeit unbeknownst to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a fine rainy day, both of them chance upon each other in a Japanese-themed
garden where they both had sought refuge from the rain. The two share a moment
of connectedness. Yukino leaves him, after sharing with him a cryptic &lt;em&gt;tanka&lt;/em&gt; (a
short Japanese poem). Yukino and Takao end up forming a connection and start
meeting each time it rains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things turn topsy-turvy when Yukino is wrongfully accused of being involved in a
relationship with a student. She is in a soup herself, left with feelings of
remorse and shame even though she had done no wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Takao is an aspiring shoemaker. He comes from a broken family; having been
abandoned by their mother, he and his elder brother lived together. Takao is a
responsible human despite being a mere high school student, he assumes a
part-time job in order to ensure ends meet. Takao, helps Yukino ‘to walk again’
and get back up on her feet. His affection and bond with Yukino make him resolve
to make a shoe for her, a project he works passionately and dedicatedly for.
&lt;em&gt;Love&lt;/em&gt; is the central theme that runs throughout the story. Ultimately, the
rainy season is over and despite wanting each other’s company, they both
hesitate to meet. Takao still continues to work on the shoe. On one particular
day, he realises how Yukino is a teacher in his school and has been wrongfully
accused of something that she did not even commit. Takao decides to take it upon
himself to resolve the issue, and ends up getting involved in a fight. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One certain day, Takao and Yukino get a chance to meet up again. In the midst of
a conversation, Takao confesses his love for her. Yukino, unable to process it,
makes him realise that she is still technically his teacher. Takao and Yukino
share their feelings with each other but realise the limitations of their own
understanding and that of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Garden of Words&lt;/em&gt; provides a unique perspective, a tale of love, which is
unrequited and beautiful in its own way. It was Takao’s behaviour towards her,
and his compassion, respect and love that ultimately heals Yukino. This story
makes one introspect upon a form of love that was much popularised by the
philosopher Plato himself: platonic love. There are no boundaries, no
restrictions and no limitations in platonic love and every form of expressing
this love is pure, considerate and understandable. &lt;em&gt;Garden of Words&lt;/em&gt; gives us a
look into a world of people to whom we can relate, beings we can understand and
sympathise with. It makes us realise the harshness with which society conditions
us and shapes our views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separation is the ultimate form of connection because it provides a &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt; for
two people to connect, and know each others’ places in their lives better than
ever. &lt;em&gt;Garden of Words,&lt;/em&gt; with its sensitively structured soundtracks and
breathtaking animation, helps us make a connection in separation. A separation
of ages does not restrict a human from pacifying and helping the other person
‘learn to walk again’. Japanese culture is founded on the principles of mutual
respect, understanding and love. The story provides us with that and more. One
must learn to enjoy the things one takes for granted, take the opportunity to
understand someone better and maybe heal them as well as ourselves in the
process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the world is a cold place and all we have is ourselves, and the crucial
key to understanding our own selves is to understand the ones who need our help.
Maybe we are all Takao, living in a broken, mundane, disjunctive world but we
can still always try to find someone like ourselves, broken and battered and
unable to walk, and learn to walk together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of trying to search for the love that we seek all our lives, we can try
to help one another and seek acceptance within ourselves. After all, “We all are
humans, we all have our own quirks, don’t we?”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Narukami no sukoshi toyomite (A faint clap of thunder) sashi kumori (Clouded skies) Ame mo furanu ka? (Perhaps rain comes) Kimi wo todomemu (If so, will you stay here with me?) Fate, sometimes, begets in itself the funniest stories as well as the most melancholic ones. It writes its own comedies and tragedies. The way we interpret it, however, is what finalises the effect fate has on us. Makoto Shinkai is a giant in the world of anime. Deservedly and frequently does he get compared to Miyazaki; a genius in the field. I do not wish to compare two of the most amazing anime directors. Their work and their storytelling have always touched a chord in my heart; a reaction spanning all of the people who have watched their movies. Shinkai is, however, criticised due to his lack of versatility in approaching the themes of stories. Most of his stories pertain to separation and love, requited or otherwise. Garden of Words, one of his works, is not any different. However, the multitude of perspectives that went behind the making of the story’s concept is what makes the story stand out, in the midst of a plethora of influential anime films. Garden of Words sets up an atmosphere which most of us can relate to on a superficial level. Shinkai has never been afraid to work on stuff he personally connects to, as a result of which three things come forth in his films as defining motifs: train, rain, and pain, strangely enough they rhyme too. Garden of words interweaves a beautiful love story between the two protagonists and despite their mutual feelings for each other, they remain visibly disconnected from each other. They remain separated by the immense difference in age that exists between the two of them. 27-year-old, Yukari Yukino is a teacher in the same school as the 15-year-old Takao Akizuki, albeit unbeknownst to him. On a fine rainy day, both of them chance upon each other in a Japanese-themed garden where they both had sought refuge from the rain. The two share a moment of connectedness. Yukino leaves him, after sharing with him a cryptic tanka (a short Japanese poem). Yukino and Takao end up forming a connection and start meeting each time it rains. Things turn topsy-turvy when Yukino is wrongfully accused of being involved in a relationship with a student. She is in a soup herself, left with feelings of remorse and shame even though she had done no wrong. Takao is an aspiring shoemaker. He comes from a broken family; having been abandoned by their mother, he and his elder brother lived together. Takao is a responsible human despite being a mere high school student, he assumes a part-time job in order to ensure ends meet. Takao, helps Yukino ‘to walk again’ and get back up on her feet. His affection and bond with Yukino make him resolve to make a shoe for her, a project he works passionately and dedicatedly for. Love is the central theme that runs throughout the story. Ultimately, the rainy season is over and despite wanting each other’s company, they both hesitate to meet. Takao still continues to work on the shoe. On one particular day, he realises how Yukino is a teacher in his school and has been wrongfully accused of something that she did not even commit. Takao decides to take it upon himself to resolve the issue, and ends up getting involved in a fight.  One certain day, Takao and Yukino get a chance to meet up again. In the midst of a conversation, Takao confesses his love for her. Yukino, unable to process it, makes him realise that she is still technically his teacher. Takao and Yukino share their feelings with each other but realise the limitations of their own understanding and that of society. Garden of Words provides a unique perspective, a tale of love, which is unrequited and beautiful in its own way. It was Takao’s behaviour towards her, and his compassion, respect and love that ultimately heals Yukino. This story makes one introspect upon a form of love that was much popularised by the philosopher Plato himself: platonic love. There are no boundaries, no restrictions and no limitations in platonic love and every form of expressing this love is pure, considerate and understandable. Garden of Words gives us a look into a world of people to whom we can relate, beings we can understand and sympathise with. It makes us realise the harshness with which society conditions us and shapes our views. Separation is the ultimate form of connection because it provides a reason for two people to connect, and know each others’ places in their lives better than ever. Garden of Words, with its sensitively structured soundtracks and breathtaking animation, helps us make a connection in separation. A separation of ages does not restrict a human from pacifying and helping the other person ‘learn to walk again’. Japanese culture is founded on the principles of mutual respect, understanding and love. The story provides us with that and more. One must learn to enjoy the things one takes for granted, take the opportunity to understand someone better and maybe heal them as well as ourselves in the process. Perhaps the world is a cold place and all we have is ourselves, and the crucial key to understanding our own selves is to understand the ones who need our help. Maybe we are all Takao, living in a broken, mundane, disjunctive world but we can still always try to find someone like ourselves, broken and battered and unable to walk, and learn to walk together.  Instead of trying to search for the love that we seek all our lives, we can try to help one another and seek acceptance within ourselves. After all, “We all are humans, we all have our own quirks, don’t we?”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Kalām Cosmological Argument for God’s Existence</title>
      <link href="/Cosmological-Argument" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Kalām Cosmological Argument for God’s Existence" />
      <published>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Cosmological-Argument</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Cosmological-Argument">&lt;p&gt;This is the first article that I have been privileged to write for &lt;em&gt;The Pangean&lt;/em&gt; on the existence of God. Some might be surprised at this. &lt;em&gt;The Pangean&lt;/em&gt;,  after all, is not a philosophical quarterly. How is this relevant, some might say? To put it simply: in every way. This is an immensely relevant topic because the question of whether or not God exists is surely one of the most significant questions we can ask (in fact, I consider it the most significant). The answer we give to this question will inevitably impact the rest of our worldview as well as influence how we choose to live our lives. Not merely that, this article shall be a bit of an introduction to the field of natural theology: that branch of philosophy devoted to arguments for the existence of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before we proceed further, a few disclaimers must be made. Here’s the first one: I am not claiming to provide &lt;em&gt;empirical&lt;/em&gt; evidence for God. Some people have quipped to me in the past, “Show me God, and I’ll believe in Him.” But this statement/challenge presupposes that God is an empirical entity that can be ‘shown’. But God is not an empirical entity; I would argue that He is immaterial and transcendent, not enclosed within space and time. As such, it is not possible for anyone to ‘show’ God to you. But empirical evidence is not the only valid source of knowledge. Logical and philosophical reasoning can play a crucial role too. In fact, the idea that only empirical observations are true sources of knowledge (also called Empiricism) is &lt;em&gt;itself&lt;/em&gt; not an empirical observation – it is rather a philosophical assertion, based upon (I imagine) some kind of inductive (probabilistic) reasoning. To claim that only empirical observations can be true sources of knowledge is by its very nature self-defeating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As this is an article tailored for a general audience, this article will not presuppose any prior philosophical or theological training. And thus, the argument that has been chosen for this paper is one of the simplest ones out there – the &lt;em&gt;Kalām&lt;/em&gt; Cosmological Argument. However, its simplicity does not imply a lack of strength – quite the contrary, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now here’s the second disclaimer: this article is also not going to be extremely comprehensive. Yes, it will be to the point, but it is my hope to reach as broad an audience as I can. As such, the article will not be answering every possible objection that can be made to the argument; instead it will focus primarily on seeking to explain what it actually is rather than defend it in excruciating detail. Comprehensive defences of the argument have already been made by Christian philosophers and there is no need for a humble writer, such as myself, to add to the (quite frankly, saturated) bulk of scholarly literature that already exists on this subject. If you want to study deeper, look no further than Chapter 3 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wiley.com/en-us/The+Blackwell+Companion+to+Natural+Theology-p-9781444350852&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Blackwell Companion to Natural Theology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, one of the most elegantly argued natural theology textbooks of our time (though this present author does not agree with everything that is asserted in that work). Or you can look &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reasonablefaith.org/writings/popular-writings/existence-nature-of-god/the-kalam-cosmological-argument/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for an exposition of the argument, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gtfVds8Kn4s&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for responses to the most popular objections that have been made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main purpose of this article is to explain why God exists in as simple a manner as I possibly can. This will also give the reader an idea of how philosophical reasoning normally works and how classical theists have argued for the rationality of their faith in God. For, sadly, many of the popular YouTube ‘vlogs’ on the Kalām argument (usually made by posturing theatrical self-congratulatory millennials and other assorted hippies) clearly betray a pitiful lack of understanding of the argument itself, as well as the reasoning that runs through it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here is a third disclaimer, which may seem trivial, but which I feel must be made for the sake of conscience. While I heartily acclaim the argument itself, I do not endorse every aspect of the philosophy that has been put forward by some of its chief proponents. Particularly, I take issue with the philosopher William Lane Craig’s (one of the argument’s most vocal defenders) denial of God’s intrinsic immutability. However, this does not affect the core of the argument, and so there should be no issue in presenting it as is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, without further ado, let us get into the argument. It can be formulated as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P1.&lt;/strong&gt; Everything which begins to exist must have a cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P2.&lt;/strong&gt; The universe began to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C1.&lt;/strong&gt; (From P1 and P2) Therefore, the universe must have a cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P4.&lt;/strong&gt; If the universe has a cause, then an uncaused, Personal Creator of the universe exists, Who sans the universe is beginningless, changeless, immaterial, timeless, spaceless and enormously powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C2.&lt;/strong&gt; (From C1 and P4) Therefore, an uncaused, Personal Creator of the universe exists, Who sans the universe is beginningless, changeless, immaterial, timeless, spaceless and enormously powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we proceed, something very crucial in &lt;strong&gt;P1&lt;/strong&gt; must be pointed out. It is a common question, often posed by young internet atheists: “If everything which exists must have a cause, then what caused God?” However, this question misses the point of what we are saying. &lt;strong&gt;P1&lt;/strong&gt; does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; say that &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; which exists must have a cause – rather, it simply asserts that &lt;em&gt;everything which &lt;strong&gt;begins&lt;/strong&gt; to exist&lt;/em&gt; must have a cause. On the face of it, the syllogism is extremely simple and straightforward. P1 is obviously true – or, at the very least, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reasonablefaith.org/media/reasonable-faith-podcast/why-think-whatever-begins-to-exist-has-a-cause/&quot;&gt;it is far, far more probable than its alternative&lt;/a&gt;. As for &lt;strong&gt;P2&lt;/strong&gt;, it can be verified by philosophical arguments as well as scientific evidence. Notice also that the argument is what philosophers call a &lt;em&gt;deductive&lt;/em&gt; argument – meaning that if the premises of the argument are true, the conclusion necessarily and inescapably follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the universe has a cause. But, some ask, why does this cause have to be God? Richard Dawkins, for instance, argues that there is no reason at all to believe that this universal cause (if It indeed exists) possesses the attributes that have been traditionally ascribed to It by Jewish, Christian and Muslim theologians. However, in this, Dawkins is thoroughly mistaken. The divine attributes have been rationally argued for and logically defended for centuries now, and they go back all the way &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; to Aristotle and Plotinus, philosophers who lived before the time of Christ and who – although they were neither Jews nor Christians in the formal sense of the term – did come up with a belief in a monotheistic God. It is therefore no wonder that Christian philosophers like St Thomas Aquinas took Aristotle with such enthusiasm (in fact, Catholic theology to this day makes use of Aristotelian terminology to describe spiritual realities).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So, why does the Cause of the Universe have to be God?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument can be laid out as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Firstly&lt;/em&gt;, there must be an Ultimate Uncaused Cause of all things. In other words, we cannot postulate the existence of an infinite regress of causes (the idea that the Universe is caused by A, which is caused by B, which is caused by C… etc. all the way to infinity).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The philosophers William Lane Craig and James D Sinclair offer a simple reason: the reason is that actual infinites cannot exist in reality. Actual infinites do enjoy mathematical existence, that is undeniable. However, mathematical existence does not necessarily equate to metaphysical existence, or existence in the real world. The great German mathematician David Hilbert himself observed, “The infinite is nowhere to be found in reality. It neither exists in nature nor provides a legitimate basis for rational thought… The role that remains for the infinite to play is solely that of an idea”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actual infinites cannot exist in reality simply because, if they did, they would create insoluble absurdities. A good example of this is the famous paradox of Hilbert’s Hotel, an exposition of which you can see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lobeX6ft6PA&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some, however, claim that infinites exist all around us. For example, they point to the fact that any given distance can be infinitely subdivided. However, here we must make the distinction Aristotle made between an actual and a potential infinite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An actual infinite is something which, to put it bluntly, is &lt;em&gt;actually infinite&lt;/em&gt; – that is, it is a completed infinite. For example, the set of all even numbers truly contains an infinite number of members. However, a potential infinite is quite different. It is anything which keeps increasing and which keeps moving towards infinity but which never actualizes or achieves infinity – it always remains an ever-increasing (or ever-decreasing) finitude. For example, the age of the universe which began to exist but which will never cease to exist in the future. The age would be increasing with every passing moment and be forever progressing towards infinity, but it would never actually reach infinity. It is the same with the example of a finite distance being potentially divisible infinitely. To quote Craig and Sinclair: “The only legitimate sense in which one can speak of the infinite is in terms of potentiality: something may be infinitely divisible or susceptible to infinite addition, but this type of infinity is potential only and can never be fully actualized”. So, “While one can continue indefinitely to divide conceptually any distance, the series of subintervals thereby generated is merely potentially infinite, in that infinity serves as a limit that one endlessly approaches but never reaches”. The same goes for time. “This is the thoroughgoing Aristotelian position on the infinite: only the potential infinite exists. This position does not imply that minimal time atoms, or chronons, exist. Rather time, like space, is infinitely divisible in the sense that division can proceed indefinitely, but time is never actually infinitely divided, neither does one arrive at an instantaneous point.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, when we seek to subdivide any given distance, we must remember that the distance we are seeking to divide is strictly finite – it is not infinite. We can keep dividing it for years and years if we please, but we will never actually reach an infinite number of divisions. At any given point in time, the number of divisions we will have created will still be finite, the size of each division will still be finite and the sum total of the divisions will still be what it originally was: the finite distance we set out to divide. We will never arrive at an actually infinite number of divisions; we will keep on moving towards the infinite without realising it. This is a &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; infinite, not an actual one. For more on the paradoxes related to the infinite, readers can refer to the Oxford philosopher A W Moore’s book &lt;em&gt;The Infinite&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, an actual infinite cannot exist in reality. This naturally implies that the regress of causes cannot be actually infinite; it must terminate in a First/Ultimate Cause. And this First/Ultimate Cause must naturally be Uncaused (otherwise, it would not be a First/Ultimate Cause). So, we have established the first premise of all monotheistic religion – that there is an Ultimate Uncaused Cause of all things. Let us continue with the divine attributes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the second place&lt;/em&gt;,  an Uncaused Cause must be beginning-less since everything which is uncaused has no beginning to it (we can derive this by contraposition of &lt;strong&gt;P1&lt;/strong&gt; of the original argument).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thirdly&lt;/em&gt;, there is good reason to believe that the Entity is Immaterial and Timeless. This is powerfully suggested by the fact that it is, in fact, the cause of space and time (causation, it must be remembered, does not itself have to be temporal). But if the Entity is Itself the cause of space and time, it cannot itself be enclosed within space and time. Of course, this assertion itself probably doesn’t clinch the argument on its own. However, there are other arguments by other philosophers which have proven convincing to me that the Ultimate Cause is indeed immaterial and timeless. If you’re interested in reading up on this, refer to Chapters 1 and 3 of philosopher and former atheist Edward Feser’s book &lt;em&gt;Five Proofs for the Existence of God&lt;/em&gt;. However, since the Immateriality and Timelessness of the First Cause is not – strictly speaking – crucial to the core of the argument, we shall carry on without dwelling on it for too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fourthly&lt;/em&gt;, the Entity in question must possess enormous power, since it brought the entirety of the universe into existence quite literally from nothing. This is fairly straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fifthly and finally&lt;/em&gt;, the Ultimate Cause of all Things must be Personal. This is the linchpin. Craig and Sinclair offer three arguments for this (though many, many more can be offered) in &lt;em&gt;The Blackwell Companion to Natural Theology&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first place, as the Oxford philosopher Richard Swinburne notes, there are two types of causal explanations: “scientific explanations in terms of laws and initial conditions and personal explanations in terms of agents and their volitions”. For example, two answers can be given to the question, “Why is the kettle boiling?” We could say: “The heat of the flame is being conducted via the bottom of the kettle to the water, increasing the kinetic energy of the molecules such that they vibrate so violently that they break the surface tension of the water and are thrown off in the form of steam.” Or we could simply say: “I put the kettle on to make a cup of tea.” Both these explanations are true, and one does not necessarily exclude the other. However, one is scientific in nature; the other personal. The ‘First State of the Universe’ cannot have a scientific explanation, since there is nothing before it and it cannot, therefore, be accounted for in terms of laws operating on initial conditions. The only other explanation is in terms of an Agent and His volitions (the personal explanation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the Personhood of the Ultimate/First Cause also seems to follow from the other properties we have laid out in our argumentation. There are only two kinds of things which can be said to be uncaused, beginningless, timeless, spaceless and immaterial – either abstract objects or unembodied minds. However, abstract objects (like numbers for example, or things like roundness, redness, etc.) cannot cause anything at all – that’s part of what it means to be abstract. The only alternative that springs to mind is that of an Unembodied Mind. No other alternatives seem possible, and indeed none have been suggested so far by any major critic of the argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third argument begins by observing that while the cause is clearly eternal, the effect is not. But this seems strange. Is it not reasonable to expect that if the cause is eternal, the effect would also be co-eternal with it? And yet, we see that the effect only came to be a finite time ago, instead of forever existing side-by-side with its eternal cause, like a person and her shadow, or a subject and his/her reflection in the mirror. The easiest way out of this dilemma, Craig and Sinclair argue, is to accept that the Cause is Personal and Free. That way, it can be Eternal, while still being the cause of a temporal and finite effect. God simply chooses eternally to create a temporally finite world. This does not, of course, mean, that God “one day woke up and decided all upon a sudden to create the world”. No, that assertion is deeply problematic philosophically. Rather, the classical theist position is simply to assert that God eternally wills to create/cause the temporal universe. This decision is eternal (as would be expected if God is omniscient and immutable – though that is a topic for another day), but still, free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those were the arguments made by some of the mainstream philosophers. In addition, I would boldly venture a suggestion of my own. Although I myself lack the credentials of an Oxford don, the example I am about to give I have thought about for some time and – so far – have found no flaw in it. You could take it as a personal insight, which is not too different from Swinburne’s argument described in point one above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example is that of a stone. A stone is an inanimate object. It can never think nor freely chose to do things. This means that it cannot do anything at all unless external forces act upon it. If a stone comes flying through the air and hits you on the head, you can legitimately say, “The stone has hit me!” But because the stone is inanimate (it can neither think nor take free will decisions of its own), you must also recognize that it did not hit you by its own strength or power or will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if there is indeed an Ultimate/First Cause of all things, then it must be animate/living, personal, conscious and endowed with free will. Otherwise, it could not do (or, to be more accurate, cause) anything on its own unless external forces acted upon it – much like the stone. However, the Ultimate/First Cause has no such forces to rely upon – that is precisely &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; it is the Ultimate/First Cause to begin with! Therefore, Personhood and Freedom of the Will seem inescapable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, in a nutshell, is the Kalām Cosmological Argument. It is a very old argument, having roots in the Islamic tradition, but it has recently been popularised by philosopher of religion William Lane Craig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is up to you, dear reader, at the end of the day to judge whether or not the argument is sound. You must do your own research and make up your own mind. But even if you ultimately disagree, I hope you can at least see that the Classical Theist philosophical tradition is nothing like what it is so often made out to be by the New Atheists and their enthusiastic YouTube supporters. Al-Ghazali, Aquinas, Anselm, Aristotle, Augustine, Bonaventure, Scotus – these were not like the illiterate country bumpkins they are so often made out to be. They were brilliant and careful thinkers. Centuries later, their insights still remain true and science has, in fact, confirmed many of their philosophical deductions (for example: al-Ghazali argued centuries ago, on the basis of philosophical argumentation, that time is finite; modern cosmology largely seems to have vindicated him). If you want to see how the argument holds up in the context of debate, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0tYm41hb48o&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9JVRy7bR7zI&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I hope has become obvious, although I have peppered this article with hyperlinks that will prove useful to you, I have not taken it upon myself to answer every question or refute every objection. There are others who have done that and this article has already exceeded 3,000 words. You’ll have to be satisfied with this much for now, at least from me. Plus, since this is an extremely provocative topic, what better way to end it than with a provocative and cliff-hanging conclusion?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This is the first article that I have been privileged to write for The Pangean on the existence of God. Some might be surprised at this. The Pangean, after all, is not a philosophical quarterly. How is this relevant, some might say? To put it simply: in every way. This is an immensely relevant topic because the question of whether or not God exists is surely one of the most significant questions we can ask (in fact, I consider it the most significant). The answer we give to this question will inevitably impact the rest of our worldview as well as influence how we choose to live our lives. Not merely that, this article shall be a bit of an introduction to the field of natural theology: that branch of philosophy devoted to arguments for the existence of God.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Stoic’s Path to Happiness</title>
      <link href="/Stoic-Path-to-Happiness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Stoic’s Path to Happiness" />
      <published>2019-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Stoic-Path-to-Happiness</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Stoic-Path-to-Happiness">&lt;p&gt;Call it an endless string of experiences or a series of vivid sensations of the world around, we are all suffering from a mysterious condition, called life or existence. Existence is difficult to define in objective terms. One can only derive a vague understanding of existence through the complex fabric of encounters and experiences that shape how we see the world. But does one’s myopic and vague understanding stop one from expressing one’s subjective take on the matter? Certainly not. Discussions on existence have permeated through the history of humankind. Myriad answers have been proposed and rejected over the years but a solitary troubling question has remained unchanged: what is the best way to live?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the peculiar existential ‘situatedness’ that is exclusive to every individual, there remains one universal narrative that has seemed to establish its grip on everyone. An idea that has been passionately explored by myriad traditions of the past and the present – life is suffering; a meld of ephemeral pleasures and perpetual despair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The murky river of existence, to which we are eternally stuck, is, well, doomed. With every meandering turn it inflicts painful blows, pulverises hopes and leaves us in a state of absolute despondence and melancholia. Sorrow is inextricably linked to existence. Sorrow stems from attachments and poisons our lives; an idea deeply rooted in Buddhist philosophy. This realisation itself is sufficient to make a person depressed for the rest of his life, knowing that whatever he does shall in no way improve his dull existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much deliberation went into the matter, in response to which a Greek man proposed his own tenets to lead a joyful life. This later took the form of a full-fledged school of thought called &lt;em&gt;Stoicism&lt;/em&gt;. Far removed from other philosophies, that expound obscure esoteric questions pertaining to the metaphysics or epistemology of existence, stoicism employs the Socratic approach to discuss practical issues which have a direct bearing on the lives of common people. The idea was to search for the best means to lead a happy life, in the face of the pandemonium that had descended over the political landscape of the Hellenistic period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our tale begins with a sailing merchant by the name of Zeno who, after surviving a major shipwreck, ends up in the city of Athens. During his stay, he visited a bookstore which proved to be the turning point of his life. That was the day he was introduced to the philosophy of Socrates. Fascinated by his findings, Zeno decided to pursue his newly developed interest in philosophy and asked the librarian to suggest a teacher who could guide him. The librarian recommended a man named Crates, who, for the coming years, instructed Zeno on the idea of Cynicism; an outgrowth of Socratic thought. A passionate student, Zeno studied not only Cynicism but also other schools of thought that prevailed during that time. This equipped him with the ability to understand the world through multiple lenses, and much later helped him develop a theory of his own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Cynicism exposed Zeno to a brand new world of naturalistic existence, one that defied all societal norms, it didn’t quite resonate with his own personal beliefs. After all who would want to lie around, naked in broad daylight, disturbing everybody passing by, like the cynic Diogenes? Dissatisfied with whatever knowledge he had acquired so far, he decided to part ways with the school and set out on a new journey. Zeno took up teaching. He lectured pupils on his own precepts, in the middle of the city, which actually turned out to be quite successful. Several students flocked to the beautiful building of Stoa Poikile, to hear their great teacher speak. It is here that the foundations of Stoicism were finally laid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Zeno remains a major player in our story, he isn’t the only one. Several other intellectuals also subscribed and greatly contributed to the doctrine. These thinkers included greats such as Seneca, Marcus Aurelius and Epictetus. They, together with Zeno, spoke in great detail about the various facets of Stoicism. Here, I’ll be discussing aspects of Stoic ethics that surprisingly enough remain relevant till date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that is studied in Ethics today has a very direct connection with the ideas that were propounded by these thinkers. Stoic ethics mainly investigated happy existence and the conditions required to reach that state. The aim is to end suffering and live in harmony with nature. So, how did they achieve it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the core of Stoic ethics lies the idea of &lt;em&gt;Oikeiosis&lt;/em&gt;, loosely translating to orientation. Every living thing in the world has a basic constitution, assigned to it by the natural order. For animals it is self-preservation, but in the case of humans, the oikeiosis is much greater as it involves our extraordinary ability to reason. Thus stoicism takes into account our primitive behaviour along with the potentiality to transcend it, since to be rational one is required to step out of the realm of primitive desires. It ascribes greater importance to the actions that are motivated by reason rather than animalistic desires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very simple doctrine of the Stoics, from which one can derive a massive life lesson is that one needs to make a demarcation between things that fall under one’s control and things which don’t. All that is external to us is, quite naturally, in a state of chaos and something that’s independent of us. We can’t impose ourselves on the mechanisms of nature which remain outside the clutches of our will. However, we can change our perspectives and actions towards it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about it. In a brief session of introspection, we can easily discern that our lives are stranded between regrets of the past and fears of the future. All that stoicism asks is - why give a damn? To be Stoic is to remain indifferent to whatever lies beyond you. And it is when you become indifferent that you begin to act out of reason rather than passion. The Stoics may as well be dubbed the Buddhists of the western tradition, in some respects. Their ethics have a striking resemblance to the 2nd noble truth of the Buddha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever something bothers you, stop a second and ask - “Can I change this situation?” If yes, then strive towards that change otherwise be unfazed by it. This might seem difficult at first but if this little ritual of interrupting negativity is followed, life can transform drastically. The key is to halt expectations and to be at peace with oneself. In the words of Marcus Aurelius:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If you work at that which is before you, following right reason seriously, vigorously, calmly, without allowing anything else to distract you, but keeping your divine part pure, as if you were bound to give it back immediately; if you hold to this, expecting nothing, but satisfied to live now according to nature, speaking heroic truth in every word that you utter, you will live happy. And there is no man able to prevent this.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understand stoicism as a philosophy that prepares you to face the bitter truths of life, without getting affected. It engineers you in a manner such that you can’t help but walk a virtuous path. It imparts the lesson that one must moderate one’s desires and emotions by employing reason, untouched by the highs and lows of life. Stoicism values self-control and an acceptance of whatever comes one’s way. Above all, however, stoicism is about empowering the ‘ruler within you.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is obvious that in the 21st century, the age of despair and silenced voices, humans are drawn towards a philosophy which can offer them tranquillity and order. Ours is a generation being pulled by desire with a force we can’t resist. We end up either letting go of the reins of control, becoming slaves to our passions, or fretting over situations which we can’t possibly control. It, therefore, becomes imperative to adopt Stoicism, because honestly, what is a life without happiness? Stoicism is the emancipatory force to guide us towards the path of a more fulfilled and joyful existence.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Call it an endless string of experiences or a series of vivid sensations of the world around, we are all suffering from a mysterious condition, called life or existence. Existence is difficult to define in objective terms. One can only derive a vague understanding of existence through the complex fabric of encounters and experiences that shape how we see the world. But does one’s myopic and vague understanding stop one from expressing one’s subjective take on the matter? Certainly not. Discussions on existence have permeated through the history of humankind. Myriad answers have been proposed and rejected over the years but a solitary troubling question has remained unchanged: what is the best way to live?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How Hayao Miyazaki Sees The Beauty in The Mundane</title>
      <link href="/Beauty-In-The-Mundane" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Hayao Miyazaki Sees The Beauty in The Mundane" />
      <published>2019-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Beauty-In-The-Mundane</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Beauty-In-The-Mundane">&lt;p&gt;One of the most enjoyed and oft-recounted anecdotes about Hayao Miyazaki- filmmaker, manga author, animator and co-founder of Japan’s Studio Ghibli- is his tussle with Hollywood’s now infamous mascot of predatory behaviour, Harvey Weinstein. Originally printed in &lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt;, the story runs thus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Harvey Weinstein, one of Hollywood’s most belligerent producers, received a samurai sword in the post because his reputation preceded him. It came with a note that said simply: “No cuts.” By 1997, Weinstein’s Miramax Company had been taken over by Disney, which had a distribution deal with Japanese animation revolutionaries Studio Ghibli.  Weinstein became one of Hollywood’s most powerful producers by acquiring and ruthlessly cutting films to make them as commercial as possible. Fearing his masterpiece Princess Mononoke would be butchered, director and animator Hayao Miyazaki sent Weinstein the sword with the note advising him not to do it.
[….]” I did go to New York to meet this man, this Harvey Weinstein, and I was bombarded with this aggressive attack, all these demands for cuts. I defeated him.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot to unpack in this tale. Obviously, it carries all the red flags that would later come to be associated with Weinstein. It is an amusing snippet of a battle between two of the biggest names in the global filmmaking industry. But more poignantly, it is, perhaps, a real-life enactment of Miyazaki’s favourite story to tell in each of his works: the desire to preserve a rapidly fading simplicity, which has its roots in a kind of psycho-emotional-cultural nostalgia, but which also faces the risk of obliteration by the hideous tide of forced Western assimilation and glitzy consumerism that Japanese culture and media faces to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I defeated him. No cuts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While he is often popularly addressed by the epithet &lt;em&gt;Walt Disney of Japan&lt;/em&gt;,  I have personally always disliked this particular comparison between the animators, each a legend in his own right. That is because Studio Ghibli, the Tokyo-based animation house that is often described as Disney’s whimsical Japanese twin in many ways, acts more like a foil as opposed to a mere Eastern counterpart of the former. Where Disney seeks to impress with the opulence of scale and blissfully escapist glamour (think bewitchingly beautiful princesses, operatic songs, almost demonic villains), Ghibli seeks out what’s relatable even in the extraordinary, tries to make a mark in more subtle ways, not through escapism but through its polar opposite really, through well-crafted realism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, if you ask someone to tell you what the best part is about Ghibli films, nine out of ten times the answer will inevitably end up being, either the delightfully animated technicolour food or the painstakingly drawn verdant landscapes of some sort of quasi-utopian, Kyoto countryside-meets-wonderland realm, peopled with mythical beasts and bizarre spirits. Or perhaps it might just be the underlying extended allegories of ethnic traditions and a love for environmentalism, which seeps through pretty much every Ghibli film in the past two and a half decades. Whatever it is, one thing stands out in crystal-sharp clarity: Miyazaki’s philosophy centres not around grandiose but around the mundane, which he moulds to his own liking through the most skillful blending of cinematic, emotive and artistic devices till the ordinary is idyllic and the commonplace enchanting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what constitutes the Hayao Miyazaki school of thought, exactly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his informative visual essay, &lt;em&gt;The Immersive Realism of Studio Ghibli&lt;/em&gt;,  video journalist Asher Isbruker chalks out the main reasons as to why Miyazaki’s creations feel so disarmingly familiar and relevant, despite some of them being as displaced from reality as most of our childhood bedtime tales. “No matter how far-fetched and imaginary [is] the story,” Isbruker emphasizes, “the world of a Ghibli film consistently feels tactile and realistic.” To prove his point, he cites the example of the 2001 Academy Award winning film &lt;em&gt;Spirited Away&lt;/em&gt;, directed and written by Miyazaki. The film revolves around Chihiro, a young human girl forced to work as a servant in a bathhouse frequented and operated by the most incredible array of ghosts and spirits. She does so in an effort to save her parents, who - courtesy of a whirlwind series of unfortunate events - have been turned into pigs by a malevolent witch. While you stop to reread and completely understand that sentence, it is worthwhile to take a look at what Isbruker says about world-building in the film:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…the bathhouse feels alive and real. While it is inherently unbelievable, we believe it exists in the context of the world (of the film) because it’s so well established. There are employees with jobs to do, sleeping quarters, a coal-powered furnace that heats the baths, different kinds of soaps for different clients… If you followed another employee, what would their day be like? That’s fun to imagine.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting that in a story bristling with absolutely wild events (a river becomes a dragon, the dragon becomes a boy, a witch ‘steals’ the names of her employees, thus rendering them disoriented, a faceless spirit materialises gold coins by clenching his fist) what sticks out as the most endearing bits are the little, uncharted moments that could have easily been from any slice-of-life indie film: waking up alone in an unfamiliar room to the view of an ocean, menial-labour employees gathering at the end of the day on a balcony to wistfully share their future plans of moving to the big city where prospects are better, two young children eating rice cakes in a garden full of spring flowers, the simple beauty of a wide-angle animated shot, downpour on the streets of a ghost-town. Nothing grand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isbruker also speaks of the very specific attention Miyazaki devotes to details as unostentatious as personalising the action of running in different characters. “Movement must be used to convey a sense of relative scale and weight,” he says. “Ghibli not only accomplishes this with grace but also conveys the emotions and traits of their characters through attention to minute details of their behaviour.” Instead of using technical shortcuts like pre-generated run cycles or rotoscoping (tracing live action footage), the veteran director and his animating team painstakingly created different patterns of movement to suit the circumstances and motives of every character, major or minor, be it the swift catlike sprint of wild, mountain-bred San and her horde of wolves from &lt;em&gt;Princess Mononoke&lt;/em&gt; (1997), the giddy, happy, flighty run of the innocent Kusakabe sisters joyfully exploring their new house in &lt;em&gt;My Neighbour Totoro&lt;/em&gt; (1988) or the comical, laboured struggles of the young witch from &lt;em&gt;Kiki’s Delivery Service&lt;/em&gt; (1989) to mount an enchanted broom. These details, seemingly unimportant, embellish and enrich the Ghibli cinematic experience, attesting yet again to the importance of the &lt;em&gt;extraordinary&lt;/em&gt;, so to speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there is food. Even those not well acquainted with that particular brand of Japanese animation are largely familiar with the mouth-watering, aesthetically pleasing scenes of food in every single Ghibli film. When we think of a retelling of &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt;, food is not the first thing that comes to mind. Yet, it is the most enduring motif in &lt;em&gt;Ponyo On the Cliff&lt;/em&gt; (2008), Miyazaki’s lightest, brightest film yet. The most iconic scene in his take on Hans Christian Andersen’s Danish fairytale is a simple, homely scene of little importance plot-wise, where Lisa, the mother of Ponyo’s human companion Sōsuke, prepares a wholesome meal for her; ham and a bowl of steaming ramen noodles. It is a slow, drowsy scene, right after an extended, fatiguing driving sequence through the storm; the warmth and gastronomic aspect of it feel deliciously homely. Not just &lt;em&gt;Ponyo&lt;/em&gt;, who can forget the enchanted buffets of &lt;em&gt;Spirited Away&lt;/em&gt;, the mouth-watering Bento boxes from &lt;em&gt;Totoro&lt;/em&gt;, or the eggs-and-bacon breakfast scene in &lt;em&gt;Howl’s Moving Castle&lt;/em&gt; (2004)? None of these movies are wanting for magic and mischief, conflicts and adventures, yet what we take back at the end of the film are these small, humane moments of nurture and domesticity, opportunities to forge reel-to-real kinship with the protagonists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we speak of Ghibli food and Ghibli landscapes, we cannot avoid the underlying theme that Miyazaki strives to emphasise in his craft: romanticising the ordinary and trying to achieve a sense of balance between the magical extravaganzas of spirit-infested bathhouses and flying castles and benevolent cat-bear tree deities. One of Ghibli’s favourite tropes to use is the incomplete or unexplained aspects of its multilayered, kaleidoscopic universes. We are given rich tapestries of magical worlds- enchanted forests, prehistoric oceans, deserted valleys and idyllic small towns, with creatures and people unlike any of our own- but not all of it revealed through exposition, just enough to make us already familiar with, aware of the sensory experience we’re being thrust into. It definitely helps that Miyazaki prefers to work with young, starry-eyed protagonists for most of his films- it helps to convey a sense of newness and wonder at the good in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A section of critics have theorised that Miyazaki’s repeated emphasis on the synthesis of human-nature relationships, traditional and sustainable ways of living versus technology and economic progress, the portrayal of largely pacifist protagonists, ambiguous and somewhat redeemable antagonists, and anti-war motifs have much to do with Hayao Miyazaki’s personal experiences during the Second World War, particularly the 1945 bombings of Utsunomiya. “The characters who pursue war — generally government officials — are portrayed as vainglorious and arrogant schemers who rashly court cataclysm for the sake of their grandiose ambitions,” writes Dan Sanchez in his essay &lt;em&gt;Miyazaki’s Beautiful Anti War Dreams&lt;/em&gt;, while also noting that Miyazaki allows for even such seemingly irredeemable paragons of wickedness their moments to redeem themselves. “The climax of the film comes not with the hero impaling or detonating his foe, as in so many Hollywood movies, or in the villain falling to his doom, as in so many Disney animated films. Miyazaki’s heroes achieve victory, not through the destruction of their enemies, but by foiling their plans enough such that the belligerents finally relent …. sometimes even …. to the point of converting villains into friends.” He adds, “…. (Although) Tolkien’s &lt;em&gt;Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt; is a profound meditation on the corruption of power, its discussion of war and peace is crudely Manichean. Yet on this subject, and so many others, the fantasy of Studio Ghibli — &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; the work of the creative genius Hayao Miyazaki— is wise and deeply moral, as well as exhilarating and achingly beautiful. It is a cultural treasure that stands and soars in a class of its own.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others note that Miyazaki might have been significantly influenced by the ethno-Japanese &lt;em&gt;Shinto&lt;/em&gt; ideology, which attaches great importance to the worship of &lt;em&gt;kami&lt;/em&gt;: the sacred presence that manifests itself everywhere in nature, from rocks to rivers to forests to the creatures that dwell in them. The sacredness and fragility of the Shinto balance is well portrayed in one of Miyazaki’s earliest and most powerful works, &lt;em&gt;Nausicaä of the Valley of Wind&lt;/em&gt; (1984), where the titular protagonist Nausicaä battles fascist forces to establish harmony between the human world and the ancient creatures of the forest- dangerous, insect-like beasts called Ohms- even as Earth teeters on the brink of apocalypse. &lt;em&gt;Mononoke&lt;/em&gt; deals with the same ordeal, when the forest gods are disturbed as their homes are destroyed by an industrial settlement that derives resources from hacking down the pristine mountain foliage. These may sound rather far-fetched in theory, but with the skill that only a Ghibli animator can demonstrate, Miyazaki spreads his messages in a beautiful art-on-celluloid format, preferring to concentrate, as always, more on the ordinary than the other-worldly; not the rampages, or the grand battles, but the lives at the centre of the crossfire between enemies, at the motivations of every character, princess or chieftain or sailor or just a small-town boy with big dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all of Miyazaki’s movies come laden with ladles of fantasy, however. &lt;em&gt;Whisper of the Heart&lt;/em&gt; (1995), written by him, is a heart-warming, lush take on childhood and childish dreams, yearning, hoping, loving and losing, all embodied in the very non-fantastic and yet endearing host of characters, especially Shizuku, the 14 year old, book-smart, imaginative protagonist. It is in these understated and realistic films, that could easily be swapped for live-action works, that Miyazaki’s touch works the best. For it is here that you get to see the legacy of Studio Ghibli. How everything becomes dreamy and magical with just the right dose of attention and love, with just the exact dollops of childish whimsy and adult musings to balance each other out. As Isbruker says, “Pay attention to the ordinary, the inconsequential, seemingly unimportant actions and elements … every single one was a conscious choice.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We depict hatred, but it is to depict that there are more important things. We depict a curse, to depict the joy of liberation,” says Miyazaki himself. He goes on to talk about the joys of hand-drawn animation, “When I think about the way the computer has taken over and eliminated a certain experience of life, that makes me sad. When we were animating fire some staff said they had never seen wood burning. I said, “Go watch!” It has disappeared from their daily lives. Japanese baths used to be made by burning firewood. Now you press a button. I don’t think you can become an animator if you don’t have any experience.” His words bring us full-circle- the Harvey Weinstein episode, the chronicle of the samurai sword, no cuts … a testament to a mind as fresh and transcendental as it was during his first endeavour, a staunch refusal to bow to artificialities and be a cheap copy of the West. No more being the Walt Disney of Japan, thank you very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The celebration of the common is, then, both the hallmark and the most overlooked facet of Studio Ghibli. There is magic in a nighttime flight across a village on the wings of your friendly neighbour forest spirit, or in your everyday battle against evil scheming fascists, but there is also magic enough in the simple pleasures of a bowl of warm, home-cooked food, served at the right time to suit the right mood, in a lilting conversation with a friendly stranger. It is a befitting paradox really, the harmony of opposites brought about with poise and delicacy. For you see, animation isn’t just for dragons and demons and great spectacles. It is also a medium to narrate stories in their purest, most non-distilled state, unfettered by the boundaries of logistics and science. It is the medium of dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what is Hayao Miyazaki after all, but a dreamer?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sritama Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the most enjoyed and oft-recounted anecdotes about Hayao Miyazaki- filmmaker, manga author, animator and co-founder of Japan’s Studio Ghibli- is his tussle with Hollywood’s now infamous mascot of predatory behaviour, Harvey Weinstein. Originally printed in The Guardian, the story runs thus:</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Exploration of Ourselves</title>
      <link href="/Exploration-of-Ourselves" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploration of Ourselves" />
      <published>2019-08-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Exploration-of-Ourselves</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Exploration-of-Ourselves">&lt;p&gt;“What makes you, well, you?”- Michael Stevens, Vsauce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plato in his thesis and conceptualisation of perfect beings, explored and introduced to us the concept of Forms and how the ‘World of Forms’ is the state of perfection of every being in our world, the achievement of which may be well beyond our capabilities, owing to the limitations that bound us. The World of Forms is a utopian disposition, a state of perfection, which exists only in the mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the question which arises from it is: what kind of a being would be a perfect form of us? To understand this, we must question ourselves on our true nature and the most fundamentally important, yet unanswered question we are faced with. The question is: who are we?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re probably thinking that this is another clichéd take on who you are, or on how who someone &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; is can never be defined and yet there will be attempts to explore this subject, leading to countless innovative and daring philosophical initiatives in order to reach a comprehensive definition of our being? Oh blimey! That’s some misplaced and crooked jugular, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, you could be right, this probably is another one of those inquiries that we dive into, modelling ourselves into the Thinker’s pose, trying to figure out what defines us, what it means to &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; us. Rene Descartes once remarked, “I think, therefore I am”, posing keen albeit ambiguous arguments on the definition of a man, on the basis of his consciousness first, after which we can define our being. Sartre took his chance and played with “Cogito, ergo sum” to make his own phrase, “I am, therefore I think” and even though it may seem to be just a play of words which it is (maybe). It does, however, attempt to make more sense from Jean Paul’s version of existentialist propagation, prioritising our being over the form of mind. Note that there can be some valid arguments over the interpretations of what each of them meant when using these words in order to elucidate their thoughts, it is on us to interpret them in the way we like for the adoption of our own code to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of who we are is an intriguing one and even more so when we are to discuss one of the very interesting philosophical analogies of all time, which has been used as a plot device in several anime and movies such as &lt;em&gt;Ghost in the Shell&lt;/em&gt;. The concept is generalised and popularly known as the Ship of Theseus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premise of the argument is based on the historical and mythical artefact of the Ship used by Theseus in his journey. If the Ship of Theseus is displayed in a museum, it’s safe to assume that after some time, some parts will start rotting and will have to be replaced with new parts. Say, the rotten parts of the ship are preserved, in order to restore them when the adequate technology is available. Gradually, all parts of the original ship are replaced and they are kept in a store house. The question which arises, at this point of time, is if this Ship, the one which has been entirely replaced with new parts, is still the same ship which Theseus used for his journey?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s say that thanks to technology, we can restore the rotten parts of the ship in a proper manner. If we gradually replace the ship with its original parts, can I consider this ship to be the original one? The question being explored is how can we still call it the same ship if it has none of its original parts. If after dismantling and reorganising, what makes the ship, the same original ship used by Theseus? Are we right in the way we approach this problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to this philosophical question has been debated and deliberated upon since the time of Plato.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been several arguments which have been made in order to determine what would be the consequence of such an action. There have been propositions, made on the basis of ‘forms’, by Aristotle, in which he argues that anything is formed out of four essential causes: the formal cause (on the basis of its form), material cause (on the basis of its constituent materials), efficient cause (on the basis of its principle) and the final cause (which is indiscrete in its mannerisms but is a part of all the above causes). He argues that the causes are more or less consistent in all the cases with only one divergence in every case, and therefore it is in principle the same ship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another argument is that of the transitive property via which it relates to all the forms of the ship to be the representative of the ship itself. There is also the argument that there is loss of identity over time, and therefore, it is not the same ship anymore and can be regarded as a different ship in the frame of time. This theory, however, has been heavily criticised owing to the assumptions it makes on several fronts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem of the Ship of Theseus is an intriguing one, and questions the understanding of ourselves from within, that if we are in the same position, being replaced, what makes us the same person as before? What makes us, us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donald Davidson in his paper, &lt;em&gt;Knowing one’s own mind&lt;/em&gt;, gives an example of The Ship of Theseus. He talks about the possibility of a clone being born out of his dead body in a thunderstorm. How will his family or anyone else differentiate between the actual him, who is dead, and the clone borne out of the thunderstorm?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He argues that ‘there will be an inherent difference’ but he does not further enunciate his point. It places us under a precarious and delicate situation. Does it benefit us if we define ourselves within some definition and make sense out of ourselves? Do we need to know the difference?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The identity crisis may be a philosophically daunting question, but from a stoic’s perspective, this will not matter because the world we live in will not change with the change in me, and thus it will still be us in some way. Which goes on to say that there is no need to think about it anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, is it wrong to explore and understand ourselves better in order to develop the characteristics of self resolution within us? Maybe we will never know or maybe knowing the answer defeats the human purpose which is not to define but keep a limited form in order to open up more interpretation. Thus, knowing who we are is a small fragment of understanding our consciousness, the universe beyond us and our purpose in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next section, I will dig deeper into the realm of our nature to find clues as to what makes me so different from you on the other side of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes me, me and you, you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay Tuned!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“What makes you, well, you?”- Michael Stevens, Vsauce.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Nefertiti: The Modern Queen of Ancient Egypt</title>
      <link href="/Nefertiti" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nefertiti: The Modern Queen of Ancient Egypt" />
      <published>2019-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Nefertiti</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Nefertiti">&lt;p&gt;You might be wondering: why Nefertiti of all people? I could have written about Cleopatra, who won the hearts of Mark Antony and Julius Caesar or perhaps, Hatshepsut, who put on the guise of a man to rule Egypt as a Pharaoh. I could even have written about the successful male Pharaohs of Egypt like Khufu, the king behind the Great Pyramid of Giza or even Nefertiti’s own husband, Akhenaten or her step-son, Tutankhamun. Why would I want to dedicate an entire article to Nefertiti? What is so &lt;em&gt;special&lt;/em&gt; about her?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Camille Paglia would tell you- “Nefertiti is like Athena. Born from the brow of Zeus, a head-heavy armored goddess. She is beautiful but desexed.” Well, at least, that is how she sees it. My answer to the same, however, is multifold. For one, she was a powerful symbol of love in ancient Egypt. Never before were ancient Egyptian Kings and Queens portrayed in the writings, statues and inscriptions of the time as a couple madly in love. This was probably because most of the royal couples were siblings. But, this was not the case for Nefertiti and her husband, Akhenaten. They were not siblings. Absolutely nothing is known about Nefertiti’s parents. Many have speculated that she might have been the daughter of Ay, in line to the throne after Tutankhamun. Some have even linked her to a Mitanni princess, Tadukhipa. However, nothing exists to confirm either of the theories. In my opinion, given the amount of information we currently have, it is possible that she was a commoner. Remains from 14th century Egypt, however, show the couple publicly holding hands, embracing or riding chariots and kissing. In fact, Akhenaten even wrote a poem for his beloved Nefertiti. This adequately proves that they were indeed in love with each other and were certainly not, at least directly, related. This is rather surprising because incest was the norm among members of the royal family. Deviation from the norm did not, however, affect her position and Nefertiti soon became the principal wife and chief consort of Pharaoh Akhenaten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any other beloved queen of the ancient world, Nefertiti was a symbol of great beauty. Her name literally translates to ‘the beautiful one has come’. Ideals of beauty were largely defined by what the rulers looked like at the time. Artefacts from this period of history, however, are vastly different from the reigns of other Pharaohs. This is because Akhenaten, his daughter Meritaten, and other members of the royal court are depicted with drastically elongated skulls, extremely narrow rib cages, chicken legs and protruding bellies. It goes without saying that that is very different from contemporary standards of beauty, they’d probably “ugly” and not regal today. Of course, it is possible that they took pride in what they looked like and did not want to be depicted any differently. As for the seemingly disfigured body parts, it wasn’t very uncommon because incest was a common practice. Lack of genetic diversity led to genetic deformations. The issue arises when we start inspecting Nefertiti, for she too was depicted with a long, bald head and a swan-like neck, and she was, almost certainly, not a product of incest. Many have questioned if her portrayal was so because Akhenaten and perhaps, Nefertiti herself wanted to be portrayed in this manner. Some pseudo-scientific theorists have also speculated the possibility of her being an extraterrestrial being. This would indeed explain her unusual looks. It is, however, in my opinion, likely that she was in fact a product of incest or that her elongated head was only a decorated head gear meant to give her a specific look. As for now, there is no direct evidence to support or reject any claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to how most historical characters of this period in Egyptian history are depicted, Nefertiti is showcased as much more ‘beautiful’. In fact she even meets modern standards of beauty. We know this because of one of the most famous finds of all time: the bust of Nefertiti. Currently housed in a museum in Berlin, the bust was found by German archaeologist, Ludwig Borchardt, on the 6th of December, 1912, in an artist’s studio in the then mostly unexcavated South-West Amarna. The British carried out expeditions in 1891 and 1892 in Tell-el Amarna, and concluded their endeavour with the statement that all that was left to be discovered had been retrieved by them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bust is extremely beautiful and exceptionally well preserved, in stark contrast to the other busts found nearby that date back to the same time period. In fact, a bust of Akhenaten, found almost alongside that of Nefertiti’s, was found to be completely disfigured by nature. This raised some questions about the authenticity of the find. &lt;em&gt;Is the famous bust of Nefertiti even real?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What bothers me the most is how Nefertiti looks like a modern beauty- olive skin, impeccable eyebrows, long neck and high cheekbones. A missing eye has also led to speculation that she might have suffered from an ophthalmic infection. It is weird to even think of the sculpture as a 3,000 year old object because, as many Egyptologists say, ‘it is simply too beautiful’, both in terms of conservation and good looks. Careful investigation reveals something even more strange, the style is inconsistent with the time period. The shoulders, in the case of Nefertiti’s bust, are cut vertically as opposed to the usual horizontal cut along the shoulder line. However, another piece of work found during Borchardt’s excavation has the same kind of cut. Thus, there exists, at least one other bust from the same time period, sculpted in the same style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Borchardt left behind extensive notes on his dig and findings at Amarna. He claims that the bust was found 50 cm under gravel. He explains that the artwork was sitting on a shelf, about 1.5 m from the ground, when the city was abandoned. As time passed, the walls decayed and the bust fell face down. The problem with this theory is that only the ears in the bust are damaged. If it did fall from such a height, that too face down, the nose would have been damaged, most definitely, especially because it is a delicate limestone sculpture. Is it possible that the bust was forged, then? Some modern experiments do reveal, however, that the plaster used in the bust is from the Amarna period. Although it is certainly possible that usable plaster, dating back to Akhenaten’s reign found in the same dig, was used if the bust is indeed fake. One thing that makes this theory less plausible, however, is the fact that the person who did forge the bust would have to have known all about ancient Egyptian hand and finger measurements. This is unlikely as the forger must have been a local Egyptian, probably not well versed with Egyptology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also the question of why. &lt;em&gt;Why forge something like this?&lt;/em&gt; When Kaiser William realised that Germany was lagging behind in the field of Egyptology, he ordered German Egyptologists to get him something, whatever might be the cost, to shock the world. In addition, one of Germany’s princely families was in Egypt at the time of the dig. Borchardt, who specialised in the domestic lives of ancient Egyptians, might have hired an artist to work on the limestone and plaster, in an attempt to understand the process involved. When the German princely family arrived at the dig, he just couldn’t explain to them that the bust was fake, fearing that he might commit the crime of disrespecting the royalty and be prosecuted for it. As a matter of fact, he did not allow the sculpture to be displayed publicly for almost 10 years after it was found. As for now, it is difficult to be sure as to what exactly underwent on the 6th of December, 1912.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Nefertiti’s importance in the modern perception of ancient history is highly limited, it is undeniable that Nefertiti, in fact, commanded immense power and was incredibly important in her time. She quickly rose to the post of a co-regent; a position equivalent to that of a Pharaoh himself. In most paintings, she is shown to be of equal size as her husband. This is rather rare because size was often used as a metaphor for power. In a relic from a temple in Tell-el Amarna, dating back to Akhenaten’s reign, Nefertiti is even seen smiting a foreign enemy with a mace. She is often depicted wearing the regal crown. Such depictions were usually reserved for the Pharaoh alone. She did have a title that declared her as the Ruler of the Nile and the Daughter of Gods. But, the question is, &lt;em&gt;was she more than that?&lt;/em&gt; Perhaps, she might even have ruled as a Pharaoh for a while?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions like these are very difficult to answer, especially when it comes to the Amarna period (approximately 1353 to 1336 BCE- Akhenaten’s reign). A lot of events distinguish this particular period in Egyptian history from others. It all starts with Akhenaten’s decision to shift the capital to Tell-el Amarna, in the middle of the desert, in the second year of his roughly 17 year reign. Very soon, Amarna became a modern (for ancient times) city with 50,000 residents. Akhenaten and Nefertiti also started advocating a new monotheistic religion, Atenism. It is the worship of the Sun disc. Monotheism indeed sounds like an Anno Dominic concept. In fact, priests of the time weren’t very happy as the new religion failed to answer important questions about death, something that had been central to their religion for many years. Their successor, Tutankhaten was, however, unable to carry forward the legacy and eventually gave in to the priests. Upon their advice, he changed his name to Tutankhamun and embraced the polytheistic religion that everyone was used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mystery surrounding Nefertiti is not just limited to her parentage. She disappears from all records in the 12th year of Akhenaten’s reign and no one seems to know why. Many believe that she died at this point, victimised by a plague that had claimed several lives around that time. Some Egyptologists fail to agree to such an explanation, especially since Nefertiti’s tomb was never found. In 2015, Nicholas Reeves came up with a highly debated and popular alternative theory. While going through some high resolution pictures, he noticed cracks that looked like doors in the northern and eastern walls of Tutankhamun’s burial chamber in the Valley of Kings. Infrared thermography revealed different temperature readings confirming two possible hidden passages. Reeves theorised that Tutankhamun &lt;strong&gt;inherited&lt;/strong&gt; the tomb of Nefertiti. In fact, Tutankhamun’s tomb is rather unusual: it is small and was made in a hurry. Close examinations reveal dripping marks of the paint, impressions of hasty brush strokes and mould, proving that the tomb was closed before the paint dried. A tomb needs to be sealed within 70 days of the Pharaoh’s death. Tutankhamun was only 19 when he passed away. Usually tombs take the entire lifetime of the pharaohs to be built. But Tutankhamun’s tomb decorations couldn’t have taken more than a week to be done with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Reeves, the hidden passage could lead to Nefertiti’s burial chamber. Zahi Hawas, the former Egyptian Minister of Antiquities, rejected this idea stating that Nefertiti was nothing more than a wife to Pharaoh Akhenaten and thus there was no reason for the priest of Amun to honour her by putting her to rest in the Valley of Kings. He further claims that a wall sealing the Queen’s burial chamber would restrict her passage to the afterlife. I, however, find this slightly problematic as all tombs are, in fact, sealed. Recently, however, Italian geophysicists used Ground Penetrating Radar to confirm the absence of a hidden chamber, putting all speculations to rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that surprises many is the fact that Nefertiti is portrayed guarding Akhenaten’s granite sarcophagus; a position traditionally reserved for the female deities of Egypt, Isis, Nepthys, Selket and Neith. Her influence remained strong even after her death. Or did it? Did she really die in the 10th year of her residence in Amarna? Many believe that she did not. Right after Nefertiti’s name disappears from the records, a new figure appears; a co-regent with whom Akhenaten actively shared the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is speculated that Nefertiti might even have taken the throne as a female king, following the footsteps of previous female rulers, like Sobekneferu and Hatshepsut. Two such co-regents’ names have been associated with Nefertiti; Neferneferuaten and Smenkhkare. Surprisingly, the latter is male. But, then again, even Hatshepsut had to disguise as a man to rule. In fact, some even go to the extent of saying that Nefertiti took the throne for herself after Akhenaten’s death as Tutankhamun was too young to rule. Tutankhaten changed his name, capital and reverted back to the old religion only in the 3rd year of reign, around the time Nefertiti would have finally died. Nothing, however, is known with certainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like a lot of other influential female personalities of the ancient world, Nefertiti’s name and contributions have largely been whitewashed by the future and patriarchy. Not much is known of her today. In fact, what we do know and understand is very little compared to even some of the oldest (male) Pharaohs. This implies that she is unable to boast of the popularity that she deserves. Zoe Saldana once said, “I would love to play Nefertiti or Cleopatra or the Queen of Sheba. We preserve more male history than we do female. We have to preserve [female history]. No more complaining. We have to do it.” We can only hope that one day everyone understands her worth, importance and contribution to our history. A search must start for the lost histories of womankind.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">You might be wondering: why Nefertiti of all people? I could have written about Cleopatra, who won the hearts of Mark Antony and Julius Caesar or perhaps, Hatshepsut, who put on the guise of a man to rule Egypt as a Pharaoh. I could even have written about the successful male Pharaohs of Egypt like Khufu, the king behind the Great Pyramid of Giza or even Nefertiti’s own husband, Akhenaten or her step-son, Tutankhamun. Why would I want to dedicate an entire article to Nefertiti? What is so special about her?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Mind-Numbingness of Black Mirror</title>
      <link href="/The-Mind-Numbingness-of-Black-Mirror" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Mind-Numbingness of Black Mirror" />
      <published>2019-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Mind-Numbingness-of-Black-Mirror</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Mind-Numbingness-of-Black-Mirror">&lt;p&gt;I remember being flabbergasted and mesmerised by &lt;em&gt;The National Anthem&lt;/em&gt; - the
very first episode of Charlie Brooker’s surreal and maddening piece of art that
we call &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;. It took me a while to understand why it was called that,
and the revelation hit me like a brick. The idea of calling a screen ‘black
mirror’ because it reflects your image is not just genius on the surface but is
also a teaser for the show’s intention: to tell you about yourself through
technology. It is exceedingly difficult to watch the show one episode at a time.
&lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; is discomforting due to the darkness in its content; dark enough
to send any brain on a whirlwind spin. It is potent, razor-sharp, and
brilliantly critical of the ways in which we abuse technology. If I ever had a
horror recommendation for someone, movie or TV show, &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; was what I
would first go with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It isn’t the first time that Charlie Brooker has scathingly criticised
technology. He previously wrote &lt;em&gt;Deadset&lt;/em&gt; - a show where a zombie apocalypse
breaks out in the &lt;em&gt;Big Brother&lt;/em&gt; (or as Indians call it, &lt;em&gt;Bigg Boss&lt;/em&gt;) house. It
is often called a precursor to &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;. He’s also hosted &lt;em&gt;How TV Ruined
Your Life&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;TVGoHome&lt;/em&gt; - very self-explanatory titles about his disdain for
reality television’s outlandish premises. That is not to say he hates everything
about mainstream media. He is quite the pop culture and video game buff, having
hosted shows on both. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; was the culmination of all of his thought
processes from earlier shows. It was prophetic and innovative, and told us
things about ourselves we did not wish to hear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not a problem, as long as you do not become the very thing you had hoped
to destroy. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; was picked up by Netflix after two seasons and one
Christmas special, and since then, it has run on for three seasons with one
groundbreaking style of narration in the form of the interactive film,
&lt;em&gt;Bandersnatch&lt;/em&gt;. Undoubtedly, it gave us too much to think about again; the power
of technology to affect relationships, rattle politics, reveal sexual subtext,
create near-dystopian scenarios with social credit scores, prove that free will
is a myth, and show how the head of a state can be blackmailed into having sex
with a pig are on full display in this show. Surely, many would agree that, of
late, the episodes have been lacklustre as compared to the first few seasons.
However, that isn’t my concern here, because there is still enough food for
thought in those episodes. I’m concerned with why we find them lacklustre and
the entire culture that has formed around the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Netflix acquired the rights to Channel 4 production, one might have noted
a growing anxiety in people to want the streaming giant to release one more
season of the show. It ends too quickly for viewers, partly because of the
binge-watching culture that has engulfed the experience of &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;. Irony
kicks in strong here. We are willing to subject ourselves to the control of
technology because it has us hooked like a tight fishing rod. Sure, you get
quite a lot to think about, but you end up not realising the ridiculousness of
what you are doing. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; then becomes a show about how much it can
surprise and shock you, which, in all fairness, it continues to do in cruel and
sometimes gruesome ways. But the real question remains, to what extent have we
been able to grasp what those episodes imply about the future or the present.
This is also where the discomfort attached to the show matters. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;
is not here to spare your feelings, it is unafraid of destroying the lives of
all the protagonists in a single stroke, after around 40 minutes of intense
build up. How does one watch so many episodes of gruesome emotional intensity
and brutal philosophies, all in one go? It contributes to the culture of
incessant, mindless consumption of pop culture, without a pause. Our willingness
to consume such uncomfortable subject matter with such ease and speed is
indicative of how much we have let pop culture consume us, instead of the other
way round. Brooker himself said that bingeing the show is like getting hit by a
car, and that’s just one season worth of episodes. One might even argue that
&lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;, like all else, is just a show and it isn’t meant to convince or
change status quo vastly. However, it feels really preachy, especially once you
consider Charlie Brooker’s own beliefs. He wants to sell to us why our
increasing reliance on technology won’t get us too far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I also find discouraging is the idea of Netflix backing this show. It’s a
terrible idea to pressurise your content creators to churning out further
content. I believe that is, in part, why the show has been declining in quality
lately. Netflix is still trying to find footing in this vast market that has now
been opened up due to the entry of giants like Disney and WarnerBros, not to
mention the existence of Amazon. It’s trying its hardest to keep subscribers
hooked by releasing new series and films continuously. In the midst of companies
taking back their content from Netflix, to host on their own sites, Netflix has
no choice but to create a niche of its own as soon as it can, like HBO, which is
perceived by many as one of the best content producers. A glaring example of
this strategy’s volatility was when Netflix purchased streaming rights to
&lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt; for $100 million. Months later, this year, Warner Media took the
rights back when they announced the entry of their own streaming site. Netflix
has progressed in that sphere very well - originals like &lt;em&gt;Orange Is The New
Black, Narcos, House of Cards,&lt;/em&gt; etc. have carved their own space in the internet
sphere. However, at the end of the day, Netflix is run primarily on data
analytics, and every operation is based on that concept. While it’s the right
way to go about understanding your audience, increasing competition may worsen
the pace at which it wants to expand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does this strategy have such a paramount effect on a show? It’s because of
the resources that Netflix has put in for just this show alone. Before a season
launch, it would release a trailer for every single episode, which isn’t the
usual practice. A heavy marketing campaign will then follow, for engagement with
users on Twitter, YouTube and Facebook; something Netflix is really good at
because it has &lt;em&gt;humanised&lt;/em&gt; itself by replying to comments. Under Channel 4,
&lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; was relatively obscure. Now, it’s Netflix’s marquee signing. More
funds also mean more high-profile celebrities act in the show, some of which
include Miley Cyrus and Jodie Foster. It also means smarter programming, like
the choose-your-own-adventure &lt;em&gt;Bandersnatch&lt;/em&gt;. However, the flip side of this
means that time doesn’t wait for quality, or the overall delivery of the
message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With escalating technological developments, there’s no way to tell whether we
will really use virtual reality or artificial intelligence the way the show
depicts. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; is definitely a glimpse of the most vulnerable
tendencies of the human mind, because behind all the gizmo, it’s really a show
about what it means to be human and not about the hi-fi stuff itself.
Unfortunately, in the millennial age, we’re losing our human connections, and
&lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; is just being co-opted into this stream of unconsciousness that
includes being stuck to some form of a screen. The show is prophetic for sure,
but is it going to impact how we approach technology? The use of apps like
FaceApp by a population unaware of the privacy policy or the unwanted potential
of machine learning, does not bode well for this question. We will no doubt have
more seasons of &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; in the future, which will be different than the
previous ones. Despite all the meta-level, self-aware marketing Netflix might do
when it parodies itself as being part of the &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; universe, we all
know what it really means. We’ll just absorb more of it with gleeful abandon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we really need another screen to tell us not to be hooked to one?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pranav Manie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I remember being flabbergasted and mesmerised by The National Anthem - the very first episode of Charlie Brooker’s surreal and maddening piece of art that we call Black Mirror. It took me a while to understand why it was called that, and the revelation hit me like a brick. The idea of calling a screen ‘black mirror’ because it reflects your image is not just genius on the surface but is also a teaser for the show’s intention: to tell you about yourself through technology. It is exceedingly difficult to watch the show one episode at a time. Black Mirror is discomforting due to the darkness in its content; dark enough to send any brain on a whirlwind spin. It is potent, razor-sharp, and brilliantly critical of the ways in which we abuse technology. If I ever had a horror recommendation for someone, movie or TV show, Black Mirror was what I would first go with. It isn’t the first time that Charlie Brooker has scathingly criticised technology. He previously wrote Deadset - a show where a zombie apocalypse breaks out in the Big Brother (or as Indians call it, Bigg Boss) house. It is often called a precursor to Black Mirror. He’s also hosted How TV Ruined Your Life, and TVGoHome - very self-explanatory titles about his disdain for reality television’s outlandish premises. That is not to say he hates everything about mainstream media. He is quite the pop culture and video game buff, having hosted shows on both. Black Mirror was the culmination of all of his thought processes from earlier shows. It was prophetic and innovative, and told us things about ourselves we did not wish to hear. That is not a problem, as long as you do not become the very thing you had hoped to destroy. Black Mirror was picked up by Netflix after two seasons and one Christmas special, and since then, it has run on for three seasons with one groundbreaking style of narration in the form of the interactive film, Bandersnatch. Undoubtedly, it gave us too much to think about again; the power of technology to affect relationships, rattle politics, reveal sexual subtext, create near-dystopian scenarios with social credit scores, prove that free will is a myth, and show how the head of a state can be blackmailed into having sex with a pig are on full display in this show. Surely, many would agree that, of late, the episodes have been lacklustre as compared to the first few seasons. However, that isn’t my concern here, because there is still enough food for thought in those episodes. I’m concerned with why we find them lacklustre and the entire culture that has formed around the show. Since Netflix acquired the rights to Channel 4 production, one might have noted a growing anxiety in people to want the streaming giant to release one more season of the show. It ends too quickly for viewers, partly because of the binge-watching culture that has engulfed the experience of Black Mirror. Irony kicks in strong here. We are willing to subject ourselves to the control of technology because it has us hooked like a tight fishing rod. Sure, you get quite a lot to think about, but you end up not realising the ridiculousness of what you are doing. Black Mirror then becomes a show about how much it can surprise and shock you, which, in all fairness, it continues to do in cruel and sometimes gruesome ways. But the real question remains, to what extent have we been able to grasp what those episodes imply about the future or the present. This is also where the discomfort attached to the show matters. Black Mirror is not here to spare your feelings, it is unafraid of destroying the lives of all the protagonists in a single stroke, after around 40 minutes of intense build up. How does one watch so many episodes of gruesome emotional intensity and brutal philosophies, all in one go? It contributes to the culture of incessant, mindless consumption of pop culture, without a pause. Our willingness to consume such uncomfortable subject matter with such ease and speed is indicative of how much we have let pop culture consume us, instead of the other way round. Brooker himself said that bingeing the show is like getting hit by a car, and that’s just one season worth of episodes. One might even argue that Black Mirror, like all else, is just a show and it isn’t meant to convince or change status quo vastly. However, it feels really preachy, especially once you consider Charlie Brooker’s own beliefs. He wants to sell to us why our increasing reliance on technology won’t get us too far. What I also find discouraging is the idea of Netflix backing this show. It’s a terrible idea to pressurise your content creators to churning out further content. I believe that is, in part, why the show has been declining in quality lately. Netflix is still trying to find footing in this vast market that has now been opened up due to the entry of giants like Disney and WarnerBros, not to mention the existence of Amazon. It’s trying its hardest to keep subscribers hooked by releasing new series and films continuously. In the midst of companies taking back their content from Netflix, to host on their own sites, Netflix has no choice but to create a niche of its own as soon as it can, like HBO, which is perceived by many as one of the best content producers. A glaring example of this strategy’s volatility was when Netflix purchased streaming rights to Friends for $100 million. Months later, this year, Warner Media took the rights back when they announced the entry of their own streaming site. Netflix has progressed in that sphere very well - originals like Orange Is The New Black, Narcos, House of Cards, etc. have carved their own space in the internet sphere. However, at the end of the day, Netflix is run primarily on data analytics, and every operation is based on that concept. While it’s the right way to go about understanding your audience, increasing competition may worsen the pace at which it wants to expand.  Why does this strategy have such a paramount effect on a show? It’s because of the resources that Netflix has put in for just this show alone. Before a season launch, it would release a trailer for every single episode, which isn’t the usual practice. A heavy marketing campaign will then follow, for engagement with users on Twitter, YouTube and Facebook; something Netflix is really good at because it has humanised itself by replying to comments. Under Channel 4, Black Mirror was relatively obscure. Now, it’s Netflix’s marquee signing. More funds also mean more high-profile celebrities act in the show, some of which include Miley Cyrus and Jodie Foster. It also means smarter programming, like the choose-your-own-adventure Bandersnatch. However, the flip side of this means that time doesn’t wait for quality, or the overall delivery of the message. With escalating technological developments, there’s no way to tell whether we will really use virtual reality or artificial intelligence the way the show depicts. Black Mirror is definitely a glimpse of the most vulnerable tendencies of the human mind, because behind all the gizmo, it’s really a show about what it means to be human and not about the hi-fi stuff itself. Unfortunately, in the millennial age, we’re losing our human connections, and Black Mirror is just being co-opted into this stream of unconsciousness that includes being stuck to some form of a screen. The show is prophetic for sure, but is it going to impact how we approach technology? The use of apps like FaceApp by a population unaware of the privacy policy or the unwanted potential of machine learning, does not bode well for this question. We will no doubt have more seasons of Black Mirror in the future, which will be different than the previous ones. Despite all the meta-level, self-aware marketing Netflix might do when it parodies itself as being part of the Black Mirror universe, we all know what it really means. We’ll just absorb more of it with gleeful abandon. Do we really need another screen to tell us not to be hooked to one?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why So Bad *rse?</title>
      <link href="/Why-So-Bad-Arse" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why So Bad *rse?" />
      <published>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-So-Bad-Arse</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-So-Bad-Arse">&lt;p&gt;Raise your hand if you remember the &lt;em&gt;Frozen&lt;/em&gt; fever that gripped Hollywood - and
pretty much the rest of the world too - in the fall of 2013. If you remember the
glittering reviews and the innumerable times ‘&lt;em&gt;shattered the glass ceiling&lt;/em&gt;’,
‘&lt;em&gt;badass princesses&lt;/em&gt;’ or ‘&lt;em&gt;Oscar worthy&lt;/em&gt;’ flashed before your eyes, till you
were made certain that all of life was meaningless unless you booked first-day,
deluxe seat tickets. If you remember how Disney Renaissance enthusiasts, across
the globe, made sure you knew that Anna and Elsa were &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt;, unlike the
&lt;em&gt;girly-girls&lt;/em&gt; you see in other princess movies. They are &lt;em&gt;empowered,&lt;/em&gt; with their
M-slit gowns and absence of a romantic wedding for an ending, jot that down. If
you remember how you found yourself at the theatre, semi-guilt tripped into
watching the movie, and finally realised that Jennifer Lee’s retelling of &lt;em&gt;The
Snow Queen&lt;/em&gt; to be, at most, a well-intentioned but weak tea nod as to what made
a woman ‘badass’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s funny, actually, because when one sits down to look back upon this legacy
of retconning traditionally feminine roles as &lt;em&gt;weak&lt;/em&gt;, so as to prop up
tomboyish, often desensitised heroines, it’s not just the creators, critics and
audience of present day showbiz media who are to blame. Even adored and revered
works like those of C S Lewis and Rowling, &lt;em&gt;yes, Rowling&lt;/em&gt;, have often sought to
perpetuate this trope, often under a carefully arranged veneer of offering
simple didactic messages in children’s literature. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let’s talk about &lt;em&gt;these girly-girls&lt;/em&gt;. Not just the predecessor Disney
princesses, no, but the so-called wimpy girls in the media, the featherbrained
airheads, the wet blankets. The ones who can’t and won’t punch assassins, knife
through captors or ride horses into sandstorms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For as long as I can remember, it was a struggle for me to find feminine,
unapologetically girly characters in literature and media, who were not
dismissed as prissy, uppity damsels or useless, shivering waifs whose plethora
of interests - sewing, fashion, painting, music, and so forth - were not
dismissed as completely decorative and impractical in the general context of the
storyline. Worse still, if I did manage to find a rare favourite, it was quite
the feat to avoid the barrage of snide remarks from acquaintances, friends, and
even more terrible - overenthusiastic vloggers and literary dissenters who were
sure to hammer home the fact that Sansa Stark and Amy March are, in fact,
horrible sinners doomed to burn in eternal hellfire for their crimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sansa Stark, from George R R Martin’s &lt;em&gt;A Song of Ice and Fire,&lt;/em&gt; is a textbook
example of the stern fact that a non-tomboyish, non-sexualised female lead can
do nothing without being written off as a wimp. A young, naive lady of merely
eleven&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; when the series begins, Sansa is held captive, forced to endure the
slaughter of her family and shoulders through being a political pawn and a
hostage with kindness, bravery and resilience. She has no dragons and no swords,
she loves lemon cakes, ballads and handsome knights, and is therefore, by
default, painted by the &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt; fandom as a wet blanket airhead. She’s
even seen as a veritable ableist demon for not feeling sexually attracted
towards a man thrice her age (and he hails from the house that murdered her
family, no less). She only manages to garner some sympathy after she is violated
in the TV adaptation, a scene that doesn’t even exist in the books. It is hardly
surprising that many male characters in the series, who do much worse, get away
with their misdeeds way easily. &lt;em&gt;Thrones’&lt;/em&gt; treatment of non-warrior women is
particularly repulsive. Sansa is made to mouth lines showing stoic gratitude
towards her assaulters for teaching her strength, and another female character,
who is often praised for being the snarky cool kid, demurely announces that she
doesn’t plan to be useless during battle, namely ‘sit knitting by the fire’.
Non-canonical lines, inserted because of the directors’ knowledge that they
specifically pander to the audience’s needs and explicit scenes where women
condemn softness and acts of ‘predictable’ ladyship, thereby metamorphosing into
&lt;em&gt;badasses,&lt;/em&gt; are aplenty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is alarming that such scenes, in books and films, are often revered and
portrayed as a sort of phoenix-from-the-ashes-moment, worthy of wolf-whistles
and printed merchandise. Even more alarming is how the notion of empowerment has
grown so utterly distorted that nothing, save for panning people who do not go
against the grain, can properly qualify as a wholesome depiction of strong
women. Why, after all, is knitting by the fire, or working in the kitchen so
problematic? Do soldiers magically grow their uniforms? Does food come to us
without the contribution of those who make it? Demeaning the choice of a woman
to do as she pleases or act as she wants, is but an elaborately twisted route,
ultimately ending in degrading womanhood itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When C S Lewis published &lt;em&gt;The Last Battle&lt;/em&gt; in 1956 the final instalment of his
Narnia series, there was quite a bit of hue and outcry over his decision to
close the gates of Narnia upon Susan Pevensie, the older, calmer, more beautiful
and ladylike of the Pevensie sisters. After her family is killed in a car
accident and the souls of her siblings find eternal refuge in Narnia, (a clear
metaphor of an Eden-like realm) Susan is left alone, literally and figuratively
locked out of heaven, her dismissal most summarily executed by Lewis in a couple
of lines: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;My sister Susan,” answered Peter shortly and gravely, “is no longer a friend
of Narnia.&lt;/em&gt;” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this a problem? Because it’s not so much a question of &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; her fate
was, as it is of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; she deserved such a peremptory conclusion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Oh Susan!” said Jill. “She’s interested in nothing nowadays except nylons and
lipsticks and invitations. She always was a jolly sight too keen on being
grown-up&lt;/em&gt;…” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, yes, of course. Dresses and makeup, wanting to socialise and have peers;
what could be more heinous a crime for an adolescent? Surely, a crime worthy of
being unpardonable, in a book replete with Biblical imagery and repeated
emphasis on the need to keep the innocence in children untainted, with a fervour
that would make Blake proud. If you are shaking your head at this, slightly
unconvinced, here’s a snippet from Lewis himself, where he makes it clear that
our lipstick-wearing, nylon-loving lady is not enjoying the fruits of the
Promised Land anytime soon:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The books don’t tell us what happened to Susan. She is left alive in this
world at the end, having by then turned into a rather silly, conceited young
woman. But there’s plenty of time for her to mend and perhaps she will get to
Aslan’s country in the end… in her own way&lt;/em&gt;…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even while he offers us a glimmer of hope, one can’t help but wince at the last
lines. ‘Plenty of time for her to mend’ what, exactly? What is so indisputably
repulsive about Susan craving extremely normal things, for a girl of her age?
Why is there an immediate need to demonise a female character who chooses to
beautify herself with makeup and pretty clothes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, Susan’s crisis has attracted plenty of sympathetic voices from the
literary community: Philip Pullman, Neil Gaiman, J K Rowling - to name a few,
with Gaiman even creating a sort of spinoff short story with a very Susan-esque
protagonist, giving her a much-needed voice and agency. Still, the older
Pevensie sister remains an outcast of Narnia, a scarring reminder of what
happens to girls who dare to be…well, just be. The ugly implications of
girlish existence in Lewis’ ramrod world of old laws and deep magic are proof
enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of Rowling, an interesting and somewhat ironic fact is that while the
&lt;em&gt;Harry Potter&lt;/em&gt; series, on the forefront, seems chock-full of strong,
three-dimensional female characters, there is something slightly problematic in
the way she treats any character that teeters dangerously into &lt;em&gt;girly-girl&lt;/em&gt;
territory. Two classic examples are Cho Chang, Harry’s first girlfriend, who is
constantly vilified for being ‘too emotional’ and too mopey over her dead
boyfriend, and Fleur Delacour, who while she gets a much better conclusion, is
still written off as the shallow dumb blonde, with a subpar performance in the
Triwizard tournament where she’s the only female competitor. Cho is eventually
cast aside for Ginny, whom Harry considers wonderful because she is ‘rarely
weepy’. Constant misogynistic and slightly racist jabs are directed at Fleur by
none other than Molly and Ginny Weasley, two of the most glorified and
celebrated women in Harry’s life. Not even the minor characters escape
judgement: the Patil twins and Lavender Brown, bubblier and more extroverted
classmates of Hermione, are often reduced to nothing but cartoonish caricatures
vying for Harry and Ron’s affections in the movies. Besides the evocation of
unpleasant racial overtones, it’s something to think about, really. Where does
mild, school cliché-centric humour end and perpetual bracketing-and-bashing of
softness and &lt;em&gt;generic&lt;/em&gt; girlishness begin?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My personal favourite though, is the much-hated Amy March from &lt;em&gt;Little Women&lt;/em&gt;.
Amy’s case is particularly interesting because Alcott never meant to malign her,
no, it’s the audience, unable to look past their ‘JO x LAURIE ENDGAME’ stupor,
who miss the whole point of Amy’s arc - the resourcefulness in her choice to
work within the conventions of traditional femininity instead of rebelling
against it, the raw honesty in her desire as an impoverished girl to enjoy
pretty material pleasures, the flaws and petty mistakes she succumbs to, because
she is not written to be liked, she is written to be &lt;em&gt;real.&lt;/em&gt; Jo’s struggles are
very earthy and very honest, and her staunch refusal to fit in and fulfil
societal expectations is admirable, but Amy’s willingness to maintain a sort of
harmony with her community and work towards self-fulfilment…how is that, in
any way, less gratifying?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for that matter, what do all these endless debates actually uncover? What
does this hollow classification system of girls into &lt;em&gt;badasses&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;girly-girls&lt;/em&gt; entail?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is uncertain, but it’s surely not an easy one. One cannot simply go
for a shallow deconstruction of the &lt;em&gt;not-like-other-girls syndrome&lt;/em&gt; without
looking into why this syndrome had to arise at all. And then one finds that the
root of this bizarre phenomenon lies in square one: the &lt;em&gt;trivialisation&lt;/em&gt; of
tenderness in girls and women, leading many to think that female voices and
characters might not be taken seriously unless they are stripped away of all
that could possibly hint at compassion and clemency. While Katniss Everdeen,
Merida and the warrior heroines of some of the later Young Adult franchises may
have arrived at exactly the right moment to prevent oversaturation of the market
by the same kind of feminine representation, the boomerang effect that arose out
of this is girls, in the younger demographic, seeking validation by rejecting
and loudly denouncing traits that could possibly mark them as girly. This
denunciation shows an almost vitriolic hatred in harmless things, marked out as
extremely feminine motifs: anything pink and/or coded as &lt;em&gt;princessy&lt;/em&gt; being the
commonest examples. It’s alarming, it’s potentially harmful that the psyche of
girls is shaped by what they &lt;em&gt;shouldn’t&lt;/em&gt; be as opposed to what they prefer to
be, it leans towards the patriarchy having the last laugh at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, as hackneyed as this sounds, there is nothing more
reproachable than the actions and behaviour of one woman being tainted so as to
glorify another. Feminism and badassery don’t spring &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; from elaborate fight
sequences or by being completely stone-cold or perpetually displeased and in a
fighting stance. Yes, female characters so portrayed are valid, beautiful, even
necessary. But they are not the beginning and end of all that’s marvellous and
awe-inspiring about women. It’s definitely heartening to see a much more
positive and varied portrayal of sharp and brilliant women in contemporary
media, who don’t always depend on brawn or magic to achieve unanimous approval,
take the famous Elle Woods (&lt;em&gt;Legally Blonde)&lt;/em&gt; for example, a wonderful
subversion of the dumb blonde stereotype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while we praise Arya for knifing through her tormentors, we cannot forget
Sansa, who comforts children and women with songs during a battle; we can
celebrate angry, rebellious spirits without coming for gentle, tranquil hearts.
We can cherish both sides of the spectrum. We can appreciate that some
rebellions happen quietly, in utter tranquillity, glossed with pink and flowers.
We can, for once, not let the patriarchy win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And maybe, just maybe at the end, Susan, the outcast of Narnia, no longer a
powerful queen but just gloriously and heartbreakingly a human girl, will have
the last laugh.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sritama Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Raise your hand if you remember the Frozen fever that gripped Hollywood - and pretty much the rest of the world too - in the fall of 2013. If you remember the glittering reviews and the innumerable times ‘shattered the glass ceiling’, ‘badass princesses’ or ‘Oscar worthy’ flashed before your eyes, till you were made certain that all of life was meaningless unless you booked first-day, deluxe seat tickets. If you remember how Disney Renaissance enthusiasts, across the globe, made sure you knew that Anna and Elsa were different, unlike the girly-girls you see in other princess movies. They are empowered, with their M-slit gowns and absence of a romantic wedding for an ending, jot that down. If you remember how you found yourself at the theatre, semi-guilt tripped into watching the movie, and finally realised that Jennifer Lee’s retelling of The Snow Queen to be, at most, a well-intentioned but weak tea nod as to what made a woman ‘badass’. It’s funny, actually, because when one sits down to look back upon this legacy of retconning traditionally feminine roles as weak, so as to prop up tomboyish, often desensitised heroines, it’s not just the creators, critics and audience of present day showbiz media who are to blame. Even adored and revered works like those of C S Lewis and Rowling, yes, Rowling, have often sought to perpetuate this trope, often under a carefully arranged veneer of offering simple didactic messages in children’s literature.  So, let’s talk about these girly-girls. Not just the predecessor Disney princesses, no, but the so-called wimpy girls in the media, the featherbrained airheads, the wet blankets. The ones who can’t and won’t punch assassins, knife through captors or ride horses into sandstorms.  For as long as I can remember, it was a struggle for me to find feminine, unapologetically girly characters in literature and media, who were not dismissed as prissy, uppity damsels or useless, shivering waifs whose plethora of interests - sewing, fashion, painting, music, and so forth - were not dismissed as completely decorative and impractical in the general context of the storyline. Worse still, if I did manage to find a rare favourite, it was quite the feat to avoid the barrage of snide remarks from acquaintances, friends, and even more terrible - overenthusiastic vloggers and literary dissenters who were sure to hammer home the fact that Sansa Stark and Amy March are, in fact, horrible sinners doomed to burn in eternal hellfire for their crimes. Sansa Stark, from George R R Martin’s A Song of Ice and Fire, is a textbook example of the stern fact that a non-tomboyish, non-sexualised female lead can do nothing without being written off as a wimp. A young, naive lady of merely eleven, when the series begins, Sansa is held captive, forced to endure the slaughter of her family and shoulders through being a political pawn and a hostage with kindness, bravery and resilience. She has no dragons and no swords, she loves lemon cakes, ballads and handsome knights, and is therefore, by default, painted by the Game of Thrones fandom as a wet blanket airhead. She’s even seen as a veritable ableist demon for not feeling sexually attracted towards a man thrice her age (and he hails from the house that murdered her family, no less). She only manages to garner some sympathy after she is violated in the TV adaptation, a scene that doesn’t even exist in the books. It is hardly surprising that many male characters in the series, who do much worse, get away with their misdeeds way easily. Thrones’ treatment of non-warrior women is particularly repulsive. Sansa is made to mouth lines showing stoic gratitude towards her assaulters for teaching her strength, and another female character, who is often praised for being the snarky cool kid, demurely announces that she doesn’t plan to be useless during battle, namely ‘sit knitting by the fire’. Non-canonical lines, inserted because of the directors’ knowledge that they specifically pander to the audience’s needs and explicit scenes where women condemn softness and acts of ‘predictable’ ladyship, thereby metamorphosing into badasses, are aplenty. It is alarming that such scenes, in books and films, are often revered and portrayed as a sort of phoenix-from-the-ashes-moment, worthy of wolf-whistles and printed merchandise. Even more alarming is how the notion of empowerment has grown so utterly distorted that nothing, save for panning people who do not go against the grain, can properly qualify as a wholesome depiction of strong women. Why, after all, is knitting by the fire, or working in the kitchen so problematic? Do soldiers magically grow their uniforms? Does food come to us without the contribution of those who make it? Demeaning the choice of a woman to do as she pleases or act as she wants, is but an elaborately twisted route, ultimately ending in degrading womanhood itself. When C S Lewis published The Last Battle in 1956 the final instalment of his Narnia series, there was quite a bit of hue and outcry over his decision to close the gates of Narnia upon Susan Pevensie, the older, calmer, more beautiful and ladylike of the Pevensie sisters. After her family is killed in a car accident and the souls of her siblings find eternal refuge in Narnia, (a clear metaphor of an Eden-like realm) Susan is left alone, literally and figuratively locked out of heaven, her dismissal most summarily executed by Lewis in a couple of lines:  “My sister Susan,” answered Peter shortly and gravely, “is no longer a friend of Narnia.”  Why is this a problem? Because it’s not so much a question of what her fate was, as it is of why she deserved such a peremptory conclusion: “Oh Susan!” said Jill. “She’s interested in nothing nowadays except nylons and lipsticks and invitations. She always was a jolly sight too keen on being grown-up…”  Ah, yes, of course. Dresses and makeup, wanting to socialise and have peers; what could be more heinous a crime for an adolescent? Surely, a crime worthy of being unpardonable, in a book replete with Biblical imagery and repeated emphasis on the need to keep the innocence in children untainted, with a fervour that would make Blake proud. If you are shaking your head at this, slightly unconvinced, here’s a snippet from Lewis himself, where he makes it clear that our lipstick-wearing, nylon-loving lady is not enjoying the fruits of the Promised Land anytime soon: “The books don’t tell us what happened to Susan. She is left alive in this world at the end, having by then turned into a rather silly, conceited young woman. But there’s plenty of time for her to mend and perhaps she will get to Aslan’s country in the end… in her own way…” Even while he offers us a glimmer of hope, one can’t help but wince at the last lines. ‘Plenty of time for her to mend’ what, exactly? What is so indisputably repulsive about Susan craving extremely normal things, for a girl of her age? Why is there an immediate need to demonise a female character who chooses to beautify herself with makeup and pretty clothes? Since then, Susan’s crisis has attracted plenty of sympathetic voices from the literary community: Philip Pullman, Neil Gaiman, J K Rowling - to name a few, with Gaiman even creating a sort of spinoff short story with a very Susan-esque protagonist, giving her a much-needed voice and agency. Still, the older Pevensie sister remains an outcast of Narnia, a scarring reminder of what happens to girls who dare to be…well, just be. The ugly implications of girlish existence in Lewis’ ramrod world of old laws and deep magic are proof enough. Speaking of Rowling, an interesting and somewhat ironic fact is that while the Harry Potter series, on the forefront, seems chock-full of strong, three-dimensional female characters, there is something slightly problematic in the way she treats any character that teeters dangerously into girly-girl territory. Two classic examples are Cho Chang, Harry’s first girlfriend, who is constantly vilified for being ‘too emotional’ and too mopey over her dead boyfriend, and Fleur Delacour, who while she gets a much better conclusion, is still written off as the shallow dumb blonde, with a subpar performance in the Triwizard tournament where she’s the only female competitor. Cho is eventually cast aside for Ginny, whom Harry considers wonderful because she is ‘rarely weepy’. Constant misogynistic and slightly racist jabs are directed at Fleur by none other than Molly and Ginny Weasley, two of the most glorified and celebrated women in Harry’s life. Not even the minor characters escape judgement: the Patil twins and Lavender Brown, bubblier and more extroverted classmates of Hermione, are often reduced to nothing but cartoonish caricatures vying for Harry and Ron’s affections in the movies. Besides the evocation of unpleasant racial overtones, it’s something to think about, really. Where does mild, school cliché-centric humour end and perpetual bracketing-and-bashing of softness and generic girlishness begin? My personal favourite though, is the much-hated Amy March from Little Women. Amy’s case is particularly interesting because Alcott never meant to malign her, no, it’s the audience, unable to look past their ‘JO x LAURIE ENDGAME’ stupor, who miss the whole point of Amy’s arc - the resourcefulness in her choice to work within the conventions of traditional femininity instead of rebelling against it, the raw honesty in her desire as an impoverished girl to enjoy pretty material pleasures, the flaws and petty mistakes she succumbs to, because she is not written to be liked, she is written to be real. Jo’s struggles are very earthy and very honest, and her staunch refusal to fit in and fulfil societal expectations is admirable, but Amy’s willingness to maintain a sort of harmony with her community and work towards self-fulfilment…how is that, in any way, less gratifying? And for that matter, what do all these endless debates actually uncover? What does this hollow classification system of girls into badasses and girly-girls entail? The answer is uncertain, but it’s surely not an easy one. One cannot simply go for a shallow deconstruction of the not-like-other-girls syndrome without looking into why this syndrome had to arise at all. And then one finds that the root of this bizarre phenomenon lies in square one: the trivialisation of tenderness in girls and women, leading many to think that female voices and characters might not be taken seriously unless they are stripped away of all that could possibly hint at compassion and clemency. While Katniss Everdeen, Merida and the warrior heroines of some of the later Young Adult franchises may have arrived at exactly the right moment to prevent oversaturation of the market by the same kind of feminine representation, the boomerang effect that arose out of this is girls, in the younger demographic, seeking validation by rejecting and loudly denouncing traits that could possibly mark them as girly. This denunciation shows an almost vitriolic hatred in harmless things, marked out as extremely feminine motifs: anything pink and/or coded as princessy being the commonest examples. It’s alarming, it’s potentially harmful that the psyche of girls is shaped by what they shouldn’t be as opposed to what they prefer to be, it leans towards the patriarchy having the last laugh at the end. Most importantly, as hackneyed as this sounds, there is nothing more reproachable than the actions and behaviour of one woman being tainted so as to glorify another. Feminism and badassery don’t spring just from elaborate fight sequences or by being completely stone-cold or perpetually displeased and in a fighting stance. Yes, female characters so portrayed are valid, beautiful, even necessary. But they are not the beginning and end of all that’s marvellous and awe-inspiring about women. It’s definitely heartening to see a much more positive and varied portrayal of sharp and brilliant women in contemporary media, who don’t always depend on brawn or magic to achieve unanimous approval, take the famous Elle Woods (Legally Blonde) for example, a wonderful subversion of the dumb blonde stereotype. So while we praise Arya for knifing through her tormentors, we cannot forget Sansa, who comforts children and women with songs during a battle; we can celebrate angry, rebellious spirits without coming for gentle, tranquil hearts. We can cherish both sides of the spectrum. We can appreciate that some rebellions happen quietly, in utter tranquillity, glossed with pink and flowers. We can, for once, not let the patriarchy win. And maybe, just maybe at the end, Susan, the outcast of Narnia, no longer a powerful queen but just gloriously and heartbreakingly a human girl, will have the last laugh.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Beauty And Brazen: The World Of Berserk</title>
      <link href="/Beauty-and-Brazen" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beauty And Brazen: The World Of Berserk" />
      <published>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Beauty-and-Brazen</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Beauty-and-Brazen">&lt;p&gt;“No matter how strong, for a human to fight a monster means he has submerged his
humanity and transformed himself into a greater monster.” – Schierke in
&lt;em&gt;Berserk.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friedrich Nietzsche was a philosopher who was well beyond the comprehension of
other philosophers of his time or even those of modern times. He had, to say the
least, an interesting childhood, which transformed him into what he was as an
adult, and also metamorphosed him into a lunatic during the later stages of his
life. His biography largely signifies what it is to be a human dangerously close
to the &lt;strong&gt;Truth&lt;/strong&gt; and yet so far away. This is what makes his works all the more
interesting and true gems in the realm of literary masterpieces. Little did he
know how much he was going to inspire a certain mangaka named Kentaro Miura to
script a saga. This saga is Miura’s visualisation of the struggle Nietzsche
refers to as the journey of a man to defy his limits and be, what he considered
to be, the future of humanity, &lt;em&gt;Ubermensch&lt;/em&gt;, roughly translated to ‘Over Man’.
Thus begins the journey of &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; and its protagonist, the most bad*rse
anime/manga character in history, &lt;em&gt;Guts&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; is a story which encompasses the journey of an individual, against the
very flow of his fate. Causality plays an integral part in the tale. The story
is clear on how a man is bound by his fate and whether he likes it or not, fate
&lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; overtake him and he &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be entwined with his future, with what is
already pre-decided for him. It is a brutal reminder that our free will is not
always free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche was a sceptic about causality and his views are well illustrated in
&lt;em&gt;Twilight of the Idols&lt;/em&gt;, where he referred to causality as the cause of
humankind’s general inability to accept the unknown. Humans are always yearning
to explain the ‘logic and reason’ behind events. Nietzsche calls this the cause
behind ‘The Four Great Errors’; arguing that causes are reimagined in order to
support the reason for our existence. Nietzsche denied in &lt;em&gt;Twilight&lt;/em&gt; that free
will is free at all and rather argued that it is a method by which theologians
exert their control over humanity. The invention of a human free will, Nietzsche
thought, was rooted in a human drive to punish and judge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; challenges the very concept of faith or judgement through a
protagonist who faces the vicious current of fate and still goes on defying it,
at every turn. Guts was born from the corpse of his dead mother, who had been
hanged. He was found by a mercenary and his wife, who then took care of him.
When his adoptive mother passes away, his adoptive father tries to kill him.
Guts is forced to escape the mercenary camp and the only family he has known, to
survive in the wild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironic though it may be, our protagonist, Guts ends up joining another mercenary
group that was under the leadership of a charming leader called Griffith. He
falls in love with a female soldier named Casca. Several events take place, and
the ‘causality’ of events ultimately leads to a betrayal, whereby Griffith
sacrifices all the members of his group in order to gain power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sacrificial event, commonly referred to as &lt;em&gt;Eclipse&lt;/em&gt;, is a momentous image
of Nietzsche’s views on human struggle. Guts helplessly watches his comrades get
killed and devoured by monsters and is forced to watch the love of his life get
violated by the same person he once considered to be his friend, Griffith. He
does eventually find his way out of the situation but not without sustaining
several scars of his own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guts’ story is a struggle of achieving the unimaginable. Nietzsche in, arguably
his most interesting piece of work, &lt;em&gt;Thus Spoke Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt; introduced the
concept of the ‘Overman’. He discusses how we are spiritually and
philosophically entwined with the struggles of our mind and overcoming them is
an integral part of one’s journey. He discusses man’s journey in three steps:
The Camel, The Lion and The Child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Camel is the first step of one’s journey. The Camel yearns to gain the
knowledge of the &lt;em&gt;Dragon&lt;/em&gt; (the essence of the ultimate knowledge) and therefore
listens to whatever everyone says and acts on it, without listening to himself.
As Guts put it himself, “One who does something he hates just because he is told
to…is called an errand boy.” This is the nature of the Camel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Camel finally sees how futile it is to lose one’s own will to others’
demands and begins to challenge himself is when the transformation to become a
Lion takes place. The Lion is a symbol of aggression and rage against the system
in order to challenge the themes which are generally considered rightful. The
Lion challenges concepts of right and wrong and is a passive aggressor, most of
the time presenting his views against the system, whilst remaining within the
system himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is until the final transition to being a Child takes place. According to
Nietzsche, this is the final transition, when the Lion transcends into a being
who is above the constraints of society, and is therefore powerful enough to
struggle and overcome. I believe this is how Kentaro Miura too visualises Guts’
transition, whose change from a person who fought for no reason and wanted to
integrate with society to someone who is ready to challenge everyone else who
defies his goal, which is to protect the person closest to him. Guts is the very
epitome of the Overman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very interesting philosophy of Nietzsche is presented in the dynamics of the
Higher Man and the Common. According to Nietzsche, all company is bad company,
unless it is the company of the equal. Nietzsche stressed on the philosophy of a
society being divided into two parts; the Higher Man and the Common Man.
Nietzsche says that it is very difficult for either of them to understand the
other, however, the Common Man places his trust in the Higher Man as a part of
this ambition. &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt;, in the same manner, brings about the reference of
Higher Man, which is Griffith. The men, who are led by Griffith, do not
understand him completely and Griffith, in the same manner, does not understand
the wants of his own men. The only thing that mattered was Griffith’s goal, the
light of which is “strong enough for every one of them to bring together all
their goals and dreams as one.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche once said, “There have been two great narcotics in the history of
Europe. Christianity and Alcohol.” He saw religion as a restriction to
resentment and envy, which he believed to be the driving source of one’s true
goals in life. He saw religion as a way for Common Men to cling to their beliefs
and demonise and ostracise whatever they could not gain. This symbolism has been
highlighted in &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt;, where we are informed of the existence of a
monotheistic religion, termed as the &lt;em&gt;Holy See&lt;/em&gt;, whose ideals bear similarity to
Christianity. The greatest proponents of the Holy See were hideous creatures who
could go to any lengths in order to protect their faith (duh much). Kentaro
Miura, yet again, portrays the meanings of resentment and struggling against all
odds, through Guts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt; has given us a character whom we all can understand, someone who is
all too human; made up of faults like the rest of us, truly embodying the spirit
of a fighter. &lt;em&gt;Berserk&lt;/em&gt;, in its own uncanny ways, could be discussed and
deliberated upon as a testament of Nietzsche’s greatest influences, all compiled
under a single saga: a struggle of one who is always destined to be the ‘Higher
Man’, despite not being from the nobility. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“No matter how strong, for a human to fight a monster means he has submerged his humanity and transformed himself into a greater monster.” – Schierke in Berserk. Friedrich Nietzsche was a philosopher who was well beyond the comprehension of other philosophers of his time or even those of modern times. He had, to say the least, an interesting childhood, which transformed him into what he was as an adult, and also metamorphosed him into a lunatic during the later stages of his life. His biography largely signifies what it is to be a human dangerously close to the Truth and yet so far away. This is what makes his works all the more interesting and true gems in the realm of literary masterpieces. Little did he know how much he was going to inspire a certain mangaka named Kentaro Miura to script a saga. This saga is Miura’s visualisation of the struggle Nietzsche refers to as the journey of a man to defy his limits and be, what he considered to be, the future of humanity, Ubermensch, roughly translated to ‘Over Man’. Thus begins the journey of Berserk and its protagonist, the most bad*rse anime/manga character in history, Guts. Berserk is a story which encompasses the journey of an individual, against the very flow of his fate. Causality plays an integral part in the tale. The story is clear on how a man is bound by his fate and whether he likes it or not, fate will overtake him and he will be entwined with his future, with what is already pre-decided for him. It is a brutal reminder that our free will is not always free. Nietzsche was a sceptic about causality and his views are well illustrated in Twilight of the Idols, where he referred to causality as the cause of humankind’s general inability to accept the unknown. Humans are always yearning to explain the ‘logic and reason’ behind events. Nietzsche calls this the cause behind ‘The Four Great Errors’; arguing that causes are reimagined in order to support the reason for our existence. Nietzsche denied in Twilight that free will is free at all and rather argued that it is a method by which theologians exert their control over humanity. The invention of a human free will, Nietzsche thought, was rooted in a human drive to punish and judge. Berserk challenges the very concept of faith or judgement through a protagonist who faces the vicious current of fate and still goes on defying it, at every turn. Guts was born from the corpse of his dead mother, who had been hanged. He was found by a mercenary and his wife, who then took care of him. When his adoptive mother passes away, his adoptive father tries to kill him. Guts is forced to escape the mercenary camp and the only family he has known, to survive in the wild. Ironic though it may be, our protagonist, Guts ends up joining another mercenary group that was under the leadership of a charming leader called Griffith. He falls in love with a female soldier named Casca. Several events take place, and the ‘causality’ of events ultimately leads to a betrayal, whereby Griffith sacrifices all the members of his group in order to gain power. The sacrificial event, commonly referred to as Eclipse, is a momentous image of Nietzsche’s views on human struggle. Guts helplessly watches his comrades get killed and devoured by monsters and is forced to watch the love of his life get violated by the same person he once considered to be his friend, Griffith. He does eventually find his way out of the situation but not without sustaining several scars of his own. Guts’ story is a struggle of achieving the unimaginable. Nietzsche in, arguably his most interesting piece of work, Thus Spoke Zarathustra introduced the concept of the ‘Overman’. He discusses how we are spiritually and philosophically entwined with the struggles of our mind and overcoming them is an integral part of one’s journey. He discusses man’s journey in three steps: The Camel, The Lion and The Child. The Camel is the first step of one’s journey. The Camel yearns to gain the knowledge of the Dragon (the essence of the ultimate knowledge) and therefore listens to whatever everyone says and acts on it, without listening to himself. As Guts put it himself, “One who does something he hates just because he is told to…is called an errand boy.” This is the nature of the Camel. When the Camel finally sees how futile it is to lose one’s own will to others’ demands and begins to challenge himself is when the transformation to become a Lion takes place. The Lion is a symbol of aggression and rage against the system in order to challenge the themes which are generally considered rightful. The Lion challenges concepts of right and wrong and is a passive aggressor, most of the time presenting his views against the system, whilst remaining within the system himself. That is until the final transition to being a Child takes place. According to Nietzsche, this is the final transition, when the Lion transcends into a being who is above the constraints of society, and is therefore powerful enough to struggle and overcome. I believe this is how Kentaro Miura too visualises Guts’ transition, whose change from a person who fought for no reason and wanted to integrate with society to someone who is ready to challenge everyone else who defies his goal, which is to protect the person closest to him. Guts is the very epitome of the Overman. A very interesting philosophy of Nietzsche is presented in the dynamics of the Higher Man and the Common. According to Nietzsche, all company is bad company, unless it is the company of the equal. Nietzsche stressed on the philosophy of a society being divided into two parts; the Higher Man and the Common Man. Nietzsche says that it is very difficult for either of them to understand the other, however, the Common Man places his trust in the Higher Man as a part of this ambition. Berserk, in the same manner, brings about the reference of Higher Man, which is Griffith. The men, who are led by Griffith, do not understand him completely and Griffith, in the same manner, does not understand the wants of his own men. The only thing that mattered was Griffith’s goal, the light of which is “strong enough for every one of them to bring together all their goals and dreams as one.” Nietzsche once said, “There have been two great narcotics in the history of Europe. Christianity and Alcohol.” He saw religion as a restriction to resentment and envy, which he believed to be the driving source of one’s true goals in life. He saw religion as a way for Common Men to cling to their beliefs and demonise and ostracise whatever they could not gain. This symbolism has been highlighted in Berserk, where we are informed of the existence of a monotheistic religion, termed as the Holy See, whose ideals bear similarity to Christianity. The greatest proponents of the Holy See were hideous creatures who could go to any lengths in order to protect their faith (duh much). Kentaro Miura, yet again, portrays the meanings of resentment and struggling against all odds, through Guts. Berserk has given us a character whom we all can understand, someone who is all too human; made up of faults like the rest of us, truly embodying the spirit of a fighter. Berserk, in its own uncanny ways, could be discussed and deliberated upon as a testament of Nietzsche’s greatest influences, all compiled under a single saga: a struggle of one who is always destined to be the ‘Higher Man’, despite not being from the nobility. </summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
