<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/culture/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-02-28T16:50:30+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/culture/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Nationalism Through the Lens of a Love Triangle</title>
      <link href="/Nationalism-Through-the-Lens-of-a-Love-Triangle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nationalism Through the Lens of a Love Triangle" />
      <published>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Nationalism-Through-the-Lens-of-a-Love-Triangle</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Nationalism-Through-the-Lens-of-a-Love-Triangle">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghare Baire&lt;/em&gt; was one of Bengali cinematic maestro Satyajit Ray’s last films and the last one to be adapted from the works of Nobel Laureate Rabindranath Tagore&lt;em&gt;, The Home and the World&lt;/em&gt;. The film is set around the Indian ‘Swadeshi’ movement of 1905 (which arose as a response to the Partition of Bengal in the same year). It offers a complex insight into the relationship between the home and the world, the status of a liberated woman during that period and the various facets of nationalism. Bimala, our liberated woman, is an equal in her marriage and when encouraged to interact with Sandip, an activist friend of Nikhil, Bimala’s rich landowning husband, by Nikhil himself, she ends up forming an emotional bond with Sandip and commits adultery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the story does not deal with a love triangle only—it shows the fragility of marriage, patriotic ideals and society. The affair and opposing ideologies stir up conflicts both in the marriage and in the society around the characters. The happy marriage eventually breaks down and communal riots break out in the province. Tagore and Ray end the tale on a tragic note. Through the course of the film, Ray effectively portrays Tagore’s ideals through the institution of marriage, and shows how conflicting ideologies create dissent and discord in the marriage and in society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tagore once wrote, “Nationalism is a great menace. It is the particular thing which for years has been at the bottom of India’s troubles.” It is this critical thought which he implements while writing the novel in 1916. What Ray deals with is a multi-faceted outlook on nationalism by the Nobel laureate. Is nationalism solely concerned with pride and love for one’s country? If that is true, then perhaps Sandip’s perspective justifies this ideal. However, as Tagore wrote, pride can transform into toxic vanity and hatred for others. This pride “breeds blindness at the end”. Ray also realises that Tagore upholds the importance of Western education and influence, especially in uplifting women and the marginalised sections of society. The movie presents both sides of the issue through Bimala. She abhors the Partition but has conflicting opinions about the radical Swadeshi and Boycott movements. She herself uses foreign goods, perfume and furniture. She admires Miss Gilby, her governess, and is shocked when she is assaulted by Amulya (a teenager who joins Sandip’s radical group). When she finally steals from her husband, Ray makes his audience infer that her ‘home’ is a part of this ‘world’, and no nationalistic ideals can be adhered to if one is unfaithful to one’s home and roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikhil, on the other hand, tries to balance both sides, believing nationalism is not radical and overtly extremist, but an idea upholding liberty and equality. He maintains nationalism cannot be practiced at the expense of marginalised communities. Tagore’s views are somehow mirrored through Nikhil’s character. The poet was quite anti-colonial himself but never supported militant nationalism and vigilantism. Sandip represents the latter, showing everything wrong with toxic nationalism. To quote Tagore, “I have no hesitation in saying that those who are gifted with the moral power of love and vision of spiritual unity, who have the least feeling of enmity against aliens, and the sympathetic insight to place themselves in the position of others will be the fittest to take their permanent place in the age that is lying before us, and those who are constantly developing their instinct of fight and intolerance of aliens will be eliminated.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting aspect is the use of the institution of marriage. Marriage, unlike most other social structures, is sensitive and dynamic. Ray and Tagore centre their tale around a marriage which is advanced, compared to the contemporary matrimonial laws and customs. The very existence of a Western-educated, socialite wife who indulges in infidelity is bold, and the stakes are further raised when the criteria for the woman choosing the man becomes his views and not mere lust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikhil practices what he believes in: equality and empowerment of women and the poor. Sandip, the marriage-breaker, is a hypocrite who, under the garb of his nationalistic view, is exploitative and flat-out selfish. Nikhil recognises that for any nation to prosper, the home must prosper. He lets his wife make the choice and happily accepts her when she realises her mistake and apologises for her delusional activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critics have argued about the equality presented in the marriage. Some believe that Tagore keeps the setting real by showing that despite the intention to attain equality, the husband’s ideas and views have a pervasive and effective influence upon the wife’s thinking (in this case, his opinionated nationalism). The woman (Bimala) also gets influenced by another man’s opinions (Sandip), and not the other way round. The depiction that, during the period, most women were intellectually dependent on men is haunting yet real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film ultimately boils down to the relation between the ‘home’ and the ‘world’. The ‘home’ will prosper when there is absolute harmony among the members. The ‘world’ is, after all, a conglomeration of homes on a large scale. What is largely practiced across several homes magnifies to a world level. When Bimala realises that she is cheating on her ideals of nationalism by stealing from her own home, she breaks down and seeks reconciliation. Ray proves that nationalistic ideals have no significance if they are not followed at ‘home’ or at any personal level. Ray effectively depicts the reciprocal relationship between the home and the world. What happens in the former affects the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end of the extra-marital affair hurts Sandip’s ego and he instigates the riots in the province as an act of revenge on Bimala and also to coerce the Muslim workers to conform to his political ideologies. The ‘world’ also enters the affairs of the ‘home’. Tagore and Ray also show a juxtaposition by having two major themes as the backdrop of the story: liberty and freedom of women in the ‘home’ and freedom of the nation in the ‘world’. Both struggles to attain freedom are depicted in the film. Bimala goes beyond the boundaries of marriage in her quest to attain her ideals and struggles to restore her marriage and mental peace. The nation is struggling to achieve freedom via nationalistic movements that do not cater to or benefit all sections of society. Neither Tagore nor Ray deal with a definite conclusion by the end; there is no remark about the outcome of the struggles. It is the emotional and social struggle with which they are concerned, not the outcome. The film is not an argument for how gender equality in society can be successfully attained; nor does it show how the Swadeshi movement led to Indian independence. But it is an insightful account on what repercussions these struggles can lead to and how lives can be drastically affected. The discord in the marriage and society are the examples of such repercussions, and Tagore and Ray caution their audience to take heed to the darker side of such struggles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the issues presented through the film adaptation are universal. Virtually every polity across the world has as its foundation some ideology of national self-assertion. Whenever there is an idea, there are conflicting perspectives on that idea. Varying opinions on a matter like nationalism can often lead to polarisation, which in extreme cases can even lead to violence and the disruption of peace and harmony. The representation of nationalistic leaders like Sandip is also significant. Sandip represents all those leaders who under their garb of selflessness, are unconcerned, conniving, exploitative hypocrites masquerading as philanthropists full of care and concern. Just like Sandip who used Bimala for his personal interests, several leaders treat their subjects as pawns and exploit them to their advantage. Thus Ray, through the adaptation of Tagore’s novel, proposes his audience to make a choice - a choice between violent, oppressive nationalism, and a balanced, compassionate and harmonious patriotism.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sarbesh Chaudhury</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Ghare Baire was one of Bengali cinematic maestro Satyajit Ray’s last films and the last one to be adapted from the works of Nobel Laureate Rabindranath Tagore, The Home and the World. The film is set around the Indian ‘Swadeshi’ movement of 1905 (which arose as a response to the Partition of Bengal in the same year). It offers a complex insight into the relationship between the home and the world, the status of a liberated woman during that period and the various facets of nationalism. Bimala, our liberated woman, is an equal in her marriage and when encouraged to interact with Sandip, an activist friend of Nikhil, Bimala’s rich landowning husband, by Nikhil himself, she ends up forming an emotional bond with Sandip and commits adultery.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Durga Puja: Cultural or Religious Festival?</title>
      <link href="/Durga-Puja-Cultural-or-Religious-Festival" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Durga Puja: Cultural or Religious Festival?" />
      <published>2020-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Durga-Puja-Cultural-or-Religious-Festival</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Durga-Puja-Cultural-or-Religious-Festival">&lt;p&gt;Being a Bengali girl who has lived her entire life up to the age of 18 in the Eastern state of West Bengal in India, visiting any other Indian state inevitably results in a major culture shock for me. Much of what we do and how we live our lives is vastly different from the rest of India. These divergences are more apparent to me now that I live in the state of Goa, and yet they always prove to be surprising. To give an example: when one of my friends asked me why I did not abstain from non-vegetarian food during Durga Puja, the most important festival for Bengalis, I was taken aback. I love non-vegetarian food and so do most of my people. Stepping away from enjoying a specific kind of food during a festival when we are expected to enjoy ourselves to the fullest did not make any sense to me. It seems, however, that that is certainly not how the rest of India looks at Hindu festivals. The way we celebrate our holy days is poles apart from what other Hindu cultures envision a festival to be. Not only that, the way we look at our own methods of celebration changes from age to age, to suit the trends of the era we live in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindu festivals in general are very colourful and often involve various rites and rituals. However, Hinduism in itself is perceived very differently by people of varying backgrounds. The first of these distinctions is the caste system which, very broadly, categorises Hindus into Brahmins (the highest caste), Kshatriyas, Vaishyas and Shudras (the lowest caste). Over the years, these castes have also faced segregation into multiple sub-castes. The kind of rituals that are performed, or more accurately, allowed to be performed depends on one’s caste. While many claim that the divisions have eroded over time, countless continue to be very strict with the customs and traditions and uphold the caste system as an integral part of their religion. There are also restrictions based on gender and time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to this, the aforementioned customs and traditions have developed very differently in the multitude of diverse Hindu communities that reside in India and abroad. The same festival celebrated by different communities may involve the employment of varying mechanisms for similar rites and rituals. Very often, different communities celebrate different festivals and it is not unlikely to find an individual hailing from one community to have absolutely no clue about a festival that is very important to another community. Hindus, as a collective, believe in 330 million different deities and the various festivals are primarily celebrated to worship one of these gods or goddesses. Each community celebrates multiple festivals but one of them is almost like an identifying feature of the same; just as Christmas is for Christians and Eid is for Muslims. For Bengali Hindus, &lt;em&gt;Durga Puja *or *Pujo&lt;/em&gt; is the most important festival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Durga Puja is celebrated every year by primarily the people of Bengal, Assam, Tripura and Odisha in autumn. The phrase “Durga Puja” literally translates to “the worship of Goddess Durga” and it marks the mythological event of Mother Goddess Durga’s win over the malicious shape-shifting demon, Mahisasura. The goddess is a symbol of “Good” for many and is worshipped by Hindus across the world in her different forms or avatars. In my home province, it is certainly more of a cultural event than a religious one. Bengalis from across the world drive, ride and fly in to celebrate this auspicious occasion with their families. The crowds at the railway stations and airports across the state of West Bengal are unimaginably large around this time. For Bengalis, Maa Durga is a member of their own family and they need to be there to greet her when she arrives. The word “Maa” translates to “mother”, but Bengalis often use the word as a term of endearment for the female members of their families. The story goes that Durga is a daughter of our mortal family who married Shiva, another Hindu god and thus, now resides in her heavenly abode in the Himalayas. She visits her parents’ family (us) once a year and this visitation is what Bengalis celebrate as Durga Puja.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The festival is primarily celebrated over five days, although traditionally, it was meant to be a ten day event. The last five days of the aforementioned ten days is what is celebrated with the craze and passion often associated with the festivity. These five days are referred to as Sashti, Saptami, Ashtami, Navami and Dashami which literally translates to six to ten, respectively, in Sanskrit. These names are generally used to mark the corresponding days of any Hindu lunar month. The festival is a big tourist magnet and the celebrations often start much before Sashti. Several months leading up to the festival is spent in preparations. Idols of Goddess Durga and her four children: Saraswati, Laxmi, Kartik and Ganesh are placed inside beautifully decorated pandals (a kind of a religious marquee). Various kinds of rites and rituals are performed over the days of pujo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why I choose to call it a cultural festival rather than a religious one has its roots in the manner in which the festival is celebrated. While many Hindus across India abstain from non-vegetarian food and indulge in rigorous rituals and worship during auspicious times such as these, many Bengalis choose to go about it all differently. It is an occasion of happiness for Bengalis as Durga is returning to meet them with her children and they hardly see a reason to refrain from things that make them happy - good non-vegetarian food and fancy clothing, among other things. Besides, Bengalis spend the months leading up to the festival in rigorous preparation for Durga’s arrival. They go shopping for new “fashion-forward” clothes, get their hair and nails done and, of course, invest a considerable amount of their time planning whom to hang out with, where to eat and what pandals to visit during the days of pujo itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was born and brought up in Kolkata, the capital of West Bengal, and every year I witness my city light up in colourful lights for the festival. It is genuinely impossible to express the feeling that comes with it in words. “Parar bondhura” (friends who live in the same neighbourhood) come together to decorate the pandals keeping a theme in mind. Several events are organised and they cater to a seemingly endless number of interests. There are dance competitions, drawing contests, cooking tournaments, fashion shows and so on and so forth. There are also competitions meant to felicitate the best decorated pandals across the state. These pandals are often artistic masterpieces and assume themes from the most abstract to the most obvious. The masses spend the nights giving these pandals a visit and conveying their intellectual interpretation of the theme and their assessment of how well the artists have brought the theme to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best thing about it is the fact that it is not a festival for the Bengali Hindus alone. All are welcome, and many Muslims, Christians, Parsis, Sikhs and people of other religious backgrounds who reside in Bengal get themselves involved in the festivities alongside the Hindus. For instance, some of the idol artists are Muslims, who form the majority of the population apart from the Hindus. Numerous members of the Islamic community in Bargachia, about 30 km from Kolkata, have devoted their lives to the subtle art of making Maa Durga’s lustrous hair. This has been in practice for at least five decades. Besides, people of all religions can be seen spending their nights pandal hopping, helping Hindus in their preparation for the rituals and sometimes even taking part in them. People of other faiths are no less important than Bengali Hindus themselves when it comes to organising and celebrating the festival that is so close to their hearts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navratri is celebrated majorly in Northern India on the days Bengalis celebrate Durga Pujo. It is the celebration of the nine forms of Goddess Durga and comprises 9 days of rigorous rites and rituals and living under restrictions like abstaining from non-vegetarian food, fasting and so on. These rituals are often limited only to the Hindus and sometimes restricted to just a single caste among them - the Brahmins. The people do indulge in activities like dancing and feasting, mostly at the end of the festival. Although Navratri has a grandeur of its own, nothing can really match the intensity, colour and craze of Durga Pujo in Bengal and thus, spending Pujo away from home is undoubtedly among the most difficult things Bengalis can be expected to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have established that Durga Pujo is indeed celebrated very differently by Bengalis, as compared to the people of the other states, let’s talk about how the manner of celebration changes among Bengalis themselves every year. As I have previously mentioned in one of my own articles, Bengalis are very fond of political and societal revolutions and reforms. They love change and they try to do everything they can to bring about or, at the very least, support a change for the betterment of their lives, the lives of those around them and their state. This attitude finds reflection in Bengali art and literature. Bengali Nobel Laureate Rabindranath Tagore’s poems and novels are heavily influenced by his critical attitude towards the western concept of nationalism and celebrated pre-independence era Bengali poet Kazi Nazrul Islam’s poems, which led many to overcome their fear of the British and to take a strong stance against them during the colonial rule. This trend exists today too. Artforms like poetry, novels, songs and, of course, pandal decorations bring to light the various issues that has infected Indian society. Themes highlighting the crisis due to the implementation of the National Register for Citizens, the Pulwama Attack and other political issues were major crowd pullers last year. Themes based on social issues are no less in number and are equally appreciated. They have one motive: to inspire change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern Hinduism often fails to address issues surrounding LGBTQIA+ community. In fact, the transgender community is often looked down upon and gay relationships are shunned by the majority of Indian society. The fact that gay sex was legalised only in 2018 doesn’t help the case for them either. The Dum Dum Park Tarul Dal Durga Pujo committee, a group of pujo organisers  in Kolkata, believed that Hinduism at heart supports and loves all kinds of genders. To spread their message, they had a LGBTQIA+ themed pujo last year. They stated their theme as “Tumi dekho nari purush, ami dekhi shudui manush” (you see women and men, I see only humans). Not only did they have an idol which was half female (Durga) and half male (Krishna), they decorated the pandal to showcase the pain of being in a closet or being discriminated against for not being cis-gendered or straight. Hundreds flocked to this pandal to appreciate the artwork and the emotion around the idea behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While global warming skeptics around the world continue to win elections and lead nations, the poor but highly talented artists in Bengal decorated the pandal of Dum Dum Park with artwork showcasing what the world would be like in the years to come: commoners carrying oxygen cylinders around all the time, government rations including oxygen supply and scientists desperately trying to keep the last plant on earth alive. They topped it off with sculptures of the goddess wearing oxygen masks. These extremely graphic depiction of the possible consequences of our ways sent a very strong message to the huge crowd that flooded the pandal at all times: our planet is dying and we need to do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the pujo of 2019, artwork wasn’t the only way the Bengalis decided to get people thinking about their ways and the society. Their beliefs found a place in the rituals too. Proposals to change the wording of the various religious chants are fairly regular these days and not out of the ordinary. For example, it is fairly common for the traditional invocation requesting a son to be replaced by a more modern one merely seeking a child, regardless of sex. However, this year what shocked everyone was when the Beleghata 33 Pally Durga Puja committee, another pujo organiser, decided to play the &lt;em&gt;Azan&lt;/em&gt; (a form of a Muslim call for ritual prayer) in their pandal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the rituals during Durga Pujo involves praying to a young woman or “kumari”. Traditionally, she is expected to belong to the Brahmin caste (the highest caste). While this rule lost its relevance a long time back, she is still, at least popularly, expected to be Hindu in the very least. However, to join the fight for communal harmony, Bidhannagar Ramkrishna Vivekananda Kendra, Salt Lake, another pujo organiser in Kolkata decided to have a Muslim “kumari”. Having Muslim “kumaris” is not an absolutely unheard of concept though, despite what one might assume, given Bengal’s history of communal violence and post-Independence partitioning of the state on primarily religious lines. Bengali Hindu spiritual leader Ramkrishna Paramahamsa converted to Islam but continued to preach “Joto mot, toto poth” (the doctrine that all paths lead to God) to the people of 19th century Bengal. His disciple, famous freedom fighter Swami Vivekananda worshipped a young Muslim girl as “kumari” in pre-Independence India. Besides, Belur Math, which serves as the headquarters for Ramkrishna Mission (a Hindu spiritual organisation founded by Vivekananda himself), houses a Mazhar within its perimeters. This inclusivity is magnified by certain groups of Muslims from Kolkata and other Muslim majority districts in Bengal when they come together to celebrate Durga Pujo themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This practice is not just limited to the state of West Bengal. The “Blood Drop” club of the Sipahijala district of Tripura was in the news in 2015 when they elected a Muslim president for themselves to organise their annual Durga Pujo. Hasem Ali, a devout Muslim and an artist from Darrang district of Assam became famous in 2018 because of his unusual practices in terms of art: he made Hindu idols including those of Goddess Durga for a living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People often use Durga Pujo as a platform to speak out against regressive religious ideas and taboos and pave the way for change. While for the longest time sex workers were exempted from the celebrations, the last couple of years brought drastic changes in favour of them. Sonagachi, India’s largest red-light district, organised a theme Pujo for the first time in 2019. Although, all the celebrations are centred on worshipping a goddess, various taboos restrict many women’s access to the festivities. The hard crusts of these orthodox Hindu rules have, however, eroded over the years and barely exist today among most Bengali communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The festivities of Durga Pujo end with “shidur khela” on Dashami, which literally translates to “vermillion game”. Married women, draped in (usually, but not always) beautiful white sarees with red borders smear vermillion on each other’s faces. This part of the celebration is traditionally limited to married women. Sex workers, transgenders, divorcees and widows are not given a place. This taboo exists even today. &lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Times of India&lt;/em&gt; launched a “No conditions apply” campaign in Kolkata with an aim to bring about a change in 2019. As a result, marginalised women from the LGBTQIA+ community, single women and so on and so forth were invited to participate in “shidur khela”. Hundreds supported the cause to change this 400 year-old custom to be more inclusive and with the great strength in participation, the movement was a success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most atheists believe that religion is useless and, in its true form, rather harmful to human society, the people of Bengal continue to use religious ceremonies to raise political and social issues and attempt to usher in change. The marriage of religion with the Bengali culture and society allows the promotion of unorthodox ideologies like communal harmony and inclusivity not just among the privileged and educated, but also among the downtrodden. While the world continues to think that religious traditions either shouldn’t be changed or simply cannot be changed, Bengalis beg to differ. They use religion as a medium to influence change while changing religious practices themselves to suit the millennium. They bear testimony to the fact that change in all realms of human life is indeed within the grasps of possibility.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Being a Bengali girl who has lived her entire life up to the age of 18 in the Eastern state of West Bengal in India, visiting any other Indian state inevitably results in a major culture shock for me. Much of what we do and how we live our lives is vastly different from the rest of India. These divergences are more apparent to me now that I live in the state of Goa, and yet they always prove to be surprising. To give an example: when one of my friends asked me why I did not abstain from non-vegetarian food during Durga Puja, the most important festival for Bengalis, I was taken aback. I love non-vegetarian food and so do most of my people. Stepping away from enjoying a specific kind of food during a festival when we are expected to enjoy ourselves to the fullest did not make any sense to me. It seems, however, that that is certainly not how the rest of India looks at Hindu festivals. The way we celebrate our holy days is poles apart from what other Hindu cultures envision a festival to be. Not only that, the way we look at our own methods of celebration changes from age to age, to suit the trends of the era we live in.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">American Psycho, Capitalism and the Hindu Gods</title>
      <link href="/American-Psycho-Capitalism-and-the-Hindu-Gods" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="American Psycho, Capitalism and the Hindu Gods" />
      <published>2020-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/American-Psycho-Capitalism-and-the-Hindu-Gods</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/American-Psycho-Capitalism-and-the-Hindu-Gods">&lt;p&gt;The morning routine scene in &lt;em&gt;American Psycho&lt;/em&gt; is, without a doubt, ensnaring. The intricate detail with which Patrick Bateman describes the various toiletries he uses, the near-artistic manner in which he applies facemask, and the way in which he innocently cautions against using alcohol-based aftershave is hauntingly beautiful. The question is: apart from the obvious aesthetics of the scene (and Christian Bale’s perfect physique and looks), why is a bloody personal hygiene tutorial so enchanting? Is the scene so surreal that it somehow reminds us of our own reality?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;American Psycho&lt;/em&gt;, it is acknowledged across the board, takes a dig at the hyper materialism and obsessive image-consciousness of 80’s American yuppie culture. But its relevance to today’s advanced capitalist society is unmistakable. Patrick Bateman’s obsessive beauty regimen is a mirror for the multiple ways in which we craft detailed masks to project an image that conforms to certain appearances of wealth, happiness and even ‘liberalism’. It mirrors Elon Musk’s workaholism, which seeks to portray him as a self-made man, when in fact his father was the owner of multiple emerald mines. It mirrors the life of many Instagram models whose very source of income is a self-objectification of their bodies. It mirrors Pride Month, which is nothing more than liberal hogwash, and it mirrors us, the people who check-in on Facebook when visiting an expensive restaurant or put up such perfect pictures when visiting sweaty, crowded, dirty and drug-filled music festivals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, the morning routine scene in &lt;em&gt;American Psycho&lt;/em&gt; serves as a perfect allegory for the way in which society immaculately creates the face of capitalism. In providing this allegory, it serves as a starting point for a much more profound idea: that ‘capitalism’, instead of being a mere economic system is actually an elaborate socio-psychological construct that moulds human beings in a certain way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference between capitalism per se and an economic system merely involving private ownership of material wealth is, rather curiously, provided by the Hindu tale of Ganesha and Kubera. For those who may not be aware, Ganesha, typically portrayed with an elephant head and pot belly, is the lord of wealth in Hinduism, he is traditionally associated with all things related to business and commerce and is the favourite god of all traders and merchants. Kubera, is a &lt;em&gt;yaksha&lt;/em&gt;, he is a ‘lesser being’ when compared to a ‘god’, but still one among the divine. Kubera is known for his fabulous wealth and rotund figure, he is known for being a great hoarder of riches and fine things, from perfumes and food to mythical flying chariots and gold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/6/64/Ganesha_Basohli_miniature_circa_1730_Dubost_p73.jpg/472px-Ganesha_Basohli_miniature_circa_1730_Dubost_p73.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Ganesha_Basohli.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Ganesha, the Hindu god of wealth.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day, Kubera decided to host a grand feast in his opulent home to please all the gods, the intellectuals and other beings. He invited Ganesha as well. At the same time, he taunted Ganesha for living with his parents, the gods Shiva and Kali, who represent the destruction of all material reality, stating that the latter must not get well-fed in a household of literal destroyers. Ganesha accepted the invitation, and when he turned up to the feast, he ate like no other. Kubera was initially pleased to feed such an important god, but Ganesha kept on devouring the food, eating more and more and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Ganesha had consumed all that was in the kitchen, he began to eat all of Kubera’s possessions: his gold, his furniture, his home, everything. Kubera ran to lord Shiva, the destroyer of the universe and Ganesha’s father, seeking help. Shiva calmly instructed Kubera to carry with him a small pot of plain rice to the lord of wealth and to offer it up in all humility. Kubera did as told, the lord of wealth was placated. After finishing his rice, the lord of wealth asked Kubera if he had finally understood the rationale behind Ganesha’s actions, Kubera confessed he had not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/0/03/Jambhala.jpg/435px-Jambhala.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Jambhala.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Kubera, the wealthy yaksha.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ganesha explained that Kubera was a hoarder of wealth, that he saw material pleasure not as the part and parcel of life but as the end in itself, while Ganesha was the lord of wealth, he ate not to blindly chase more food but to appreciate the goodness that good food and wealth brings. Kubera’s feast, Ganesha said, was made to honour excess, and Ganesha was only seeking to illustrate the folly of believing in excess—by showing Kubera the true meaning of consuming for the sake of consuming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that it is Ganesha—the child of the destroyer god—who is the lord of wealth instead of Kubera. Being the lord of wealth means one has mastery over it, and Kubera, instead of having mastery over wealth has wealth itself as his master. And this is what capitalism is: not a mastery of wealth but of service to it, of slavery to it. It is this slavery to wealth which is making us literally consume like Ganesha consuming Kubera’s vanity feast. Corporations are prepared to destroy our whole planet in order to create products for our consumption. While we do not go killing and eating people like Patrick Bateman because of our envy of another’s slightly different business card, we do, in our desire to have more and to be recognised as having more, devour goods like sharks frenzied by chum. We’re all Kuberas today, unable to understand that it is the sumptuousness of plain rice we must cherish over the newest (and-not-at-all-upgraded) iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the story of Brahma, the creator god of Hinduism, comes in. After Brahma created the universe, he ventured to create the first woman, once he created her, he did the most egregious thing: he fell in love with her, his own daughter. He tried to chase her wherever she went, sprouting four heads to keep an eye on her in every direction. He even sprouted a fifth head when his daughter tried to jump over him to avoid his lecherous gaze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/1/13/Brahma_sarawati.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Brahma_sarawati.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Brahma, the creator god of Hinduism.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story represents what capitalism does to the human mind. The act of creating the woman involves Brahma carrying out complex fire sacrifices and reciting great hymns, much like the creation of goods in an industrialised, capitalist society involves complex contractual and credit arrangements along with the furnaces of factories and the sacrifice of the millions who contribute their labour. The fire sacrifice has a &lt;em&gt;yajaman&lt;/em&gt;, the declared officiator of the fire sacrifice, the one who must reap the benefits, in other words, the capitalist and all of society itself. Brahma’s taboo act of falling in love with his own daughter represents our love for everything capitalism has to provide. It represents our yearning to dominate and control everything by gaining full control of the material world through the means of production. Brahma’s fifth head represents our ego, our narcissistic belief in having subdued all of creation through the fire sacrifice of capitalism. It must be noted here that Kubera, i.e. the one who invited Ganesha to his feast, is a direct descendant of Brahma, very clearly implying that Brahma’s will to create and consume literally gives birth to a servitude towards wealth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parallels of Brahma’s lustful and forbidden act are drawn even more starkly in &lt;em&gt;American Psycho&lt;/em&gt;. Patrick Bateman looks at himself with great admiration when he engages in that threesome with two prostitutes, much like capitalism looks at its billboards and high rises with awe. He video records himself having sex and then proceeds to inflict very serious wounds on the women as a declaration of his might, much like the capitalist overworks and abuses the labour that gives him his profits. In killing one of the prostitutes later on, he declares his will to power, much like Brahma sprouting a fifth head, illustrating the extent to which he will go to fulfill his bloodlust and hunger for the allegorical carnal pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is after this point that the parallels between &lt;em&gt;American Psycho&lt;/em&gt; and Brahma’s story end.* American Psycho* ends with Patrick Bateman declaring that there’s no escape even when he has confessed to his crimes. In a way, it reflects the quagmire that the Marxist accuses the Liberal of being in, i.e. that the Liberal has no way to escape capitalism even if he recognises it is bad because capitalism itself animates him so fully. To the Marxist, true escape lies in the ending of capitalism itself, it lies in ending the superstructures and narratives (like private property) that sustain our reality and justify the idiotic sum of material relations, so that we may have true common ownership of wealth. And it is here that the story of Brahma arrives again to educate us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once Brahma’s fifth head grows, Shiva, the destroyer god, who is usually lost in meditation awakens. He takes the most fearsome form, called Kala Bhairav (literally ‘dark frightful creature’). Kala Bhairav rides dogs, which are unclean animals according to Hindu priests, and has great talons. It is with these talons that he hacks off Brahma’s head, which he then turns it into a cup for drinking hemp. The symbolism of this act should not be lost on anybody, Shiva here is literally beheading the human ego, dramatically forcing contemplation. In converting the head into a drinking cup, he’s reminding humans of the falsehood of capitalism that leaves them lost in an unreality of their own making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e1/Kala_Bhairava_in_the_night.JPG/425px-Kala_Bhairava_in_the_night.JPG&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Kala_Bhairava_in_the_night.jpeg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Kala Bhairav, the frightful form of Shiva.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, Shiva’s act, even if seemingly mirroring Marx’s call for the death of capitalism, is radically different from it. Marx’s dialectic materialism is, ultimately, that only, it is materialism. Marx’s philosophy, by putting economic relations or property relations as the base, stupidly puts Brahma’s fifth head as the one true thing, calling for the other four to be cut off. Marxism does not go to the very thing that drives the fire sacrifice of capitalism and the sprouting of the fifth head: the human desire to dominate material reality, the human ego which seeks to consume, create and serve wealth as an extension of itself. Shiva’s act seeks to destroy that very thing, to release the human being from his need for capitalism, to release the human being from his need to control material reality in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moment we stop conceiving capitalism as an economic theory but rather as a psychological, social and even spiritual state of society is the moment we understand what it truly is. Capitalism is an outgrowth of our very consciousness, it is an attempt at fashioning reality itself, which places the material as paramount. It represents our need to control the world around us, to subdue the elements to do our bidding, and in the process to create goods and services that will give our lives meaning and worth. But it is in the process of creating meaning that the human ego rears itself, seeing its petty creation as all that matters, when reality is much larger than we would realise. To overcome capitalism, we must destroy it at its roots which lie deep within the human psyche, we must cut off our heads, allowing a better one to take its place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*I owe my gratitude to Devdutt Pattanaik, Slavoj Zizek and Adi Shankara for this article, without their ideas and teachings I would not have even conceived of this article. *&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The morning routine scene in American Psycho is, without a doubt, ensnaring. The intricate detail with which Patrick Bateman describes the various toiletries he uses, the near-artistic manner in which he applies facemask, and the way in which he innocently cautions against using alcohol-based aftershave is hauntingly beautiful. The question is: apart from the obvious aesthetics of the scene (and Christian Bale’s perfect physique and looks), why is a bloody personal hygiene tutorial so enchanting? Is the scene so surreal that it somehow reminds us of our own reality?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Women of Ancient Egypt</title>
      <link href="/Women-of-Ancient-Egypt" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Women of Ancient Egypt" />
      <published>2019-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Women-of-Ancient-Egypt</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Women-of-Ancient-Egypt">&lt;p&gt;With the rise of movements like #MeToo and #TimesUp, it is abundantly clear to us that women have been and continue to be discriminated against across the world, whether it is in the most modern of societies like the USA or the ones that are not as modern like Saudi Arabia. Feminists say that women have been historically marginalised and their talents underestimated. They believe that societal structures and social machinery work in a way to favour men, disregarding women’s capabilities, preferences, freedoms or requirements. Today, the fight for equal opportunities and equal pay are not just limited to the efforts of non-males. Men who realise that there exists a disparity that needs to be rectified have started joining in. But have women always been subjected to the kind of treatment that is meted out to them today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a common notion that ancient civilisations were in fact extremely backward when it comes to their social lives and societies. For instance, Athenian democracy allowed only adult males of the “&lt;em&gt;polis&lt;/em&gt;” to run it. Non-males were completely barred from activities like administration, security and so on. In fact, women were not permitted to own property. They were often excluded from getting a part of the inheritance as well. Females were not citizens of the &lt;em&gt;polis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scene in ancient Egypt was very different. Surprisingly, they were much better off than the Greeks and perhaps, some of the modern societies too. Now, don’t get me wrong; society was primarily patriarchal. But this did not, in any way, imply that women could not hold high positions in religious institutions, the administration and so on. They did own property and had a right to inheritance. Their words had equal weight as that of men in court. Besides, lineage was traced back through the lines of &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; parents. This kind of equality of treatment is possibly because of their mythology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Egyptian mythology revolves around a fantastic brother-sister duo married to each other - Isis, the goddess of magic, and Osiris, the god of the afterlife. Astonishingly, Isis is the dominant partner in this relationship. She is often depicted as being extremely powerful and possessed of great knowledge. In fact, she was even believed to have the power to resurrect dead humans. In one of the legends, she brings Osiris back to life after his death, a feat that remains unimaginable for the rest of the deities, men and women alike. This was reflected in the social lives of the Egyptians too as women were often depicted as holding their husband’s hands and sometimes even protecting them. Besides this godly pair, there were several other deities; and male and female gods were equally abundant and powerful. However, some rather important positions were occupied by goddesses alone, unlike most other religions or mythologies. For example, the four gods depicted on the four corners of a tomb, symbolising the fact that they were entrusted with the job of guarding the tomb, are all female. The domain of healing also comes under a goddess, Sekhmet. Besides, the patron deity of cats, an animal sacred to the Egyptians, was female too - Bastet. And the feminine influence was not just limited to the realm of the gods: it penetrated the domain of humans too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most of the high positions of administration were generally reserved for men, it is not unusual to find several exceptions to the rule in the case of Egypt. The women of this ancient society were certainly not exclusively stay-at-home mothers; they frequently engaged in several professions, some of which would have proven to be rather unorthodox in patriarchal societies - weavers, farmers, etc. The vizier was the highest state official after the Pharaoh. Nebet, a woman of great talent and importance took the office as early as Sixth Dynasty Egypt. She would inspire several other women to do the same. The first of the female rulers of ancient Egypt, Merneith’s reign dates back to the first dynasty. The highest positions in religious institutions were not exclusive to men, either, and thus, were often occupied by women, who did not necessarily have to be from a noble background either. Motherhood was very sacred to this ancient civilisation. Very often, mothers were honoured more than fathers and this found manifestation in their literature, scriptures and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest position that an ancient Egyptian could possibly hold was the position of a pharaoh. Egyptians preferred to be ruled by a woman of the royal bloodline rather than a man who wasn’t blue-blooded. Besides, whenever there was a crisis involving succession, no one really objected to giving the throne to a woman. At least fifteen great queens have ruled ancient Egypt and their stories are just as sparkling with tales of success as their male counterparts. Unfortunately our preference for a male-dominated history meant that their stories were easily forgotten or grossly misinterpreted or distorted by later civilisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most popular of these queens was Hatshepsut or Matcaray. After the death of her husband, she took over the affairs of the palace as the heir to the throne was far too young to take on royal responsibilities. Very soon, she took up the royal title of the pharaoh. Eventually, her daughter, Neferure assumed roles beyond that of a conventional princess, almost that of a queen. Hatshepshut happens to have been a very controversial figure in the history of Egypt because she found it necessary to wear a fake beard to make herself look more like a pharaoh and legitimise her authority. In fact, her statues that have survived the millenia distinctly show that her beard was fake. The fact that she was a woman was no secret. Many Egyptologists today suspect that several other pharaohs might have been female too. The 20 years of Hatshepsut’s reign was full of remarkable accomplishments - her temple at Luxor, Egypt’s tallest standing obelisk at the temple complex of Karnak, new trade contracts with Punt and military conquests that she herself headed, among others. Egyptologists believed that most stories about her, that were obtained from the scriptures on the temple walls, were exaggerations of what she did for her country for the longest time. However, we know today that she did indeed achieve everything that has found a place on those walls because of the various artifacts like cups of raisin from Punt and so on that have been found. Her existence was, however, unknown for a very long time. This is probably because the later pharaohs were ashamed of the fact that a woman ruled as the pharaoh and they believed that this affected ‘Ma’at’- balance. Scriptures were destroyed, temples taken down, obelisks demolished to remove all signs of her existence. Hatshepsut was however, never meant to be completely forgotten or to be the last female pharaoh to lead Egypt. She would go on to inspire several other female leaders of Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsinoë, the second pharaoh of the last dynasty is much less celebrated and yet, just as charismatic as Hatshepsut herself. After the death of her first husband, she fled Greece to return to Egypt where she persuaded her younger brother to marry her. This would eventually pave her way to become the pharaoh of not just Egypt, but also the Greek Mediterranean. Arsinoë would go on to bring prosperity to Egypt like no other. She established trade contracts with distant civilisations like India and the Far East. Under Arsinoë, coins started being used and slowly began to replace the barter system. Being the intelligent woman that she was, she knew that she could use coins to establish her authority. Her face appeared on these coins, making it abundantly clear to all who was in power. Arsinoë was extremely proud of the feminine history of Egypt. In one of her temples, she is shown wearing a grand crown which is today the object of a lot of research. Her crown had several parts symbolising various aspects of Egypt. The red crown represented Upper Egypt and the fact that she ruled from the new capital of Alexandria. Two tall feathers and a bull horn represented Neferari, the wife of pharaoh Ramses II, who was known for her skills in diplomacy. Twisted ram horns represented Amun-Ra who also happened to be the favourite god of Hatshepsut. Finally the sun disc, often associated with the Old Kingdom and Hetepheres, the mother of Pharaoh Khufu, who built the Great Pyramid of Giza, completed her crown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most famous of all the pharaohs is probably Cleopatra. However, she is famous for all the wrong reasons - reasons that might as well be made up and undermine her talents. Cleopatra has absolutely no comparison. She is the first of the Ptolemaic dynasty (they are of Macedonian-Greek descent and became the ruling family after Alexander the Great’s successful conquest of Egypt in 332 BC) to learn the Egyptian tongue. She is known to be multilingual, having command over at least 9 languages. This greatly helped her in her administrative role. Remains of written declarations with her signature show that she was a very able and respected administrator. Cleopatra was extremely educated in chemistry, astronomy, literature and so on. She even owned a perfume factory and is frequently associated with several advancements in the alchemy of the time. Popular media today depicts her as a woman of unparalleled beauty who seduced both Julius Caesar and Mark Antony with her beauty and charm, leading to the notion that she was a characterless seductress. However, objections to her ‘character’ in ancient times comes primarily from Roman writers, who often objected to her reign solely because she was a woman. They claimed that she was responsible for several conflicts because of her ways. Sadly, they failed to realise that both Mark Antony and Julius Caesar had equal responsibility as Cleopatra in their respective relationships. People often question Cleopatra’s character and, yet, fail to do the same for Julius Caesar, who was married when he started his affair with Cleopatra and at one point, even refused to claim his son with the queen as his own. In fact, today most egyptologists believe that she was not even conventionally beautiful as Hollywood movies often portray her. She, just like most other members of the royal family, was a product of incest, and the lack of genetic diversity would have, without a doubt, left its marks in the form of deformed bodily features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cleopatra was the last of the great pharaohs of ancient Egypt. Her reign ended with her suicide and it put an end to over 3000 years of glory. However, as many might think, Egypt did not die because of Cleopatra’s inadequacy in the position of power, but rather due to the fact that Rome was not ready to see a woman rule, at least not as well as the male pharaohs and certainly not better. What would have happened had the Roman belief of female inferiority not interfered with this great civilisation is something that we probably will never get to know. Some might say that Egypt would have eventually made its way to a truly egalitarian society. However, we cannot be so sure, especially since examples like the Vedic ages of India exist in which a society where women were considered equal to men gradually becomes not only patriarchal but also cruelly oppressive towards women over time. What is undeniable is that ancient Egypt was certainly far ahead of its time and remains one of the most feminist civilisations to have ever existed.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">With the rise of movements like #MeToo and #TimesUp, it is abundantly clear to us that women have been and continue to be discriminated against across the world, whether it is in the most modern of societies like the USA or the ones that are not as modern like Saudi Arabia. Feminists say that women have been historically marginalised and their talents underestimated. They believe that societal structures and social machinery work in a way to favour men, disregarding women’s capabilities, preferences, freedoms or requirements. Today, the fight for equal opportunities and equal pay are not just limited to the efforts of non-males. Men who realise that there exists a disparity that needs to be rectified have started joining in. But have women always been subjected to the kind of treatment that is meted out to them today?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What if Veritaserum was Real?</title>
      <link href="/What-If-Veritaserum-was-Real" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What if Veritaserum was Real?" />
      <published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-If-Veritaserum-was-Real</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-If-Veritaserum-was-Real">&lt;p&gt;For those of you who don’t know what Veritaserum is (seriously?), it is a
magical truth potion from the universe of Harry Potter. As a collegiate debater,
I have faced my fair share of &lt;em&gt;meta&lt;/em&gt; motions. One of the most intriguing ones
that I have come across is: ‘This house prefers a world where no one can lie.’
Although it sounds like a very common, overused motion, it got me thinking, is
it really possible? What would the world be like? And would I want to live in
that world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us start with the first question: can Veritaserum indeed be a reality one
day? Well, let me break this to you- truth serums very much exist. In fact, they
have been available since the 1920’s. They are primarily mind-altering
(psychoactive) drugs which slow down the process of transfer of messages from
the spinal cord to the brain. Lying usually requires a lot of effort, unless you
are a compulsive liar. These drugs simply hinder your capability to concentrate
and thus, make it difficult to lie. They don’t, however, completely inhibit your
ability to lie. Some common examples include &lt;em&gt;sodium thiopental&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;scopolamine&lt;/em&gt;
and &lt;em&gt;sodium amytal&lt;/em&gt;. Historically, they have been used for various other
purposes. During World War II, they were used as anti-anxiety drugs on soldiers.
Until 2011, they were also used as anaesthetics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very rarely have truth serums been used for interrogation though, due to ethical
conflicts. A myriad of historical examples, however, portray the positives of
using such drugs in a criminal investigation. The 2007 Noida serial killer case
(in India) could only be solved when the suspect confessed, under the influence
of &lt;em&gt;sodium amytal&lt;/em&gt;, to the heinous crimes that had been committed by him.
However, the use of truth serums during interrogation is considered to be a
direct violation of the Fifth Amendment of the US Constitution (the Right to
remain silent) and is, thus, illegal in the US. Many consider the administration
of truth serums, in order to extract information, to not only be a violation of
the human right to be free from degrading treatment but also a form of torture.
Besides, these drugs have some serious side-effects, including the development
of false memories, addiction and even death in case of an overdose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of such concerns, research is on to find and develop a drug that can
completely prevent a person from lying, including compulsive liars, without any
grave side-effects: &lt;em&gt;the ultimate Veritaserum&lt;/em&gt;. But just because something can
be done doesn’t mean that it should be done. Whether it is morally right or
wrong requires thinking through a lot of different things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One side of the debate might argue that taking away the right to lie is a severe
encroachment upon the right to choose. At times, it might, in fact, be necessary
to lie- white lies. Thomas Paine once said, “He who dares not offend cannot be
honest”. In a world where being polite is deemed a great virtue, it is
impossible to get by without lying, if one hopes to follow the etiquettes set by
a genteel society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a child, still in the formative years, tries to learn something new, we
provide them encouragement shrouded in little lies. This is necessary to prevent
them from losing interest or giving up. It is also unfortunate that the modern
world isn’t very progressive when it comes to accepting the LGBTQIA+ community,
often forcing people of the community to lie about their sexuality or gender to
save themselves from questions, comments and bullies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At times, lies are crucial to one’s safety. Celebrities lie about where they
live to prevent stalkers from breaking in, spies put on a disguise and lie to
unveil the secrets of underground institutions and terrorist cells, while also
ensuring personal safety against potential harm from the people they spy upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When doctors fail to see alternative options to save a person’s life, they often
resort to placebo. This involves actively lying to the patient about the effects
the drugs have been having on the person’s health- telling them that the
medicines have actually been working well and that they will get well soon when
that is probably not the case. In some cases, patients actually have a positive
response to this. While many see this practice as unethical, owing to the fact
that a doctor has to blatantly lie to a patient, others think that using placebo
as a last resort to help them is justified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most of these cases are rather niche, there are many which are not as
individualistic. Taking a step back and looking at the big picture, reveals
other interesting aspects. The avenues that greatly affect our day to day lives
like politics, religion, media, etc. tend to hurt us mostly when lies in some
form or the other are involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk politics. Populist demagogues, who tend to make fake promises based
on what the majority of the populace desires instead of using rational
arguments, are the biggest disgrace to modern politics. Their campaigns and
popularity are based on lies. Commoners fall prey to their words because these
leaders pander to what people already want to hear. Examples of such leaders
include Adolf Hitler and Benito Mussolini. Stephen Hawking once tagged even
Donald Trump as a demagogue. It isn’t unknown to any of us what their ‘reigns’
have been like. Even though stripping politicians of the ability to lie won’t
solve the problems that pervade politics, it does ensure that commoners do not
get cheated into hoping for something that is never meant to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing to affect our lives immensely is crime. False charges, corruption
and plantation of fake evidence are not unusual. It is common practice among
convicts, facing the possibility of a long sentence, to lie about the severity
of their crimes to hinder the prosecution. Psychopaths and sociopaths are able
to lie without any remorse whatsoever. Most serial killers can be classified as
either of the two and their flawless lying makes them incredibly difficult to
spot. The problems of adjudication, conviction and prosecution will simply fail
to exist in a world where people are unable to lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unethical marketing cheats people into believing that a product provides certain
benefits which it actually doesn’t. Tech giants like Google, Amazon, Facebook,
Qualcomm and so on have come under a lot of heat in recent years. Immense
capital is spent on investigating these companies to find the truth. In a
lie-less world, these problems would simply cease to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cases of fraud often take several years to be solved and have justice served
for, like the Enron scandal. It is easier to live in a world where committing
fraud is an impossibility than to have so many duped before spending big bucks
to rectify the situation. The morality of the work done by certain companies
itself is questionable. Take Ashley Madison for example, it is a dating site
catering to those who are currently in a committed relationship or married. The
profits of this company are based on how well they are able to lie without
taking into consideration the fact that they hurt people in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is widespread misinformation in the world owing to the phenomena of ‘fake
news’. Lies about the intentions of a party creates misunderstandings, leading
to conflict and divided masses. Social media has enabled lying to a whole new
extent. It is fashionable to lie about not having make-up on or not having had
plastic surgery in the past, or even about living perfect lives. These set
unrealisable standards of lifestyle and beauty for everyone. This eventually
culminates in depression among teenagers and adults who fail to achieve these
unreal standards- something that is more common now than ever. In fact,
celebrities, like K-Pop idols, are forced to undergo surgeries to comply with
certain beauty standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that shapes society drastically is religion. Problems arise from
lies about what God desires. While this can be used as a powerful positive tool
too, there exist other alternatives to achieve the same. For example, it is
better to tell a person not to cut a tree because they provide us with oxygen
rather than using some religious reference to drive the point home. This is
because, for one, atheism is on the rise and will, in the future, be the
dominant ‘belief’ (atheism is expected to overtake religion by 2041). These
atheists associate religion with regressiveness of thought and religious
justifications are unacceptable to them. Secondly, religious beliefs do not have
the same appeal among people belonging to different religions or sects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While freedom of choice is essential for everyone, this freedom cannot affect
someone else- hurt the other person or encroach upon their freedom. Social
contract theorists argue that everyone in a society moves into a contract with
each other and the government, and the government can partially take away
certain rights of individuals to ensure greater benefits for society at large.
If this ‘sacrifice’ is what society operates upon, I personally feel that it is
justified to take away the right to lie if greater benefits can be ensured in
the process.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all problems can be solved by just stopping people from lying. A world where
no one can lie is not the ideal world. Crimes will be committed. Bad people will
continue to exist. They will have evil intentions; they just will not be able to
lie about them. While it might seem that taking away the right to lie infringes
upon individual rights, the greater benefits it provides makes me question if
the argument of ‘rights’ is sufficient grounds to argue against it. A world like
this, however, is a reality left in store for those who come after us (unless
someone is secretly preparing for a Nobel Prize). For now, we are doomed to live
in a world of lies, fraud and betrayal where we can only hope that the ones we
trust the most do not lie to us.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For those of you who don’t know what Veritaserum is (seriously?), it is a magical truth potion from the universe of Harry Potter. As a collegiate debater, I have faced my fair share of meta motions. One of the most intriguing ones that I have come across is: ‘This house prefers a world where no one can lie.’ Although it sounds like a very common, overused motion, it got me thinking, is it really possible? What would the world be like? And would I want to live in that world? Let us start with the first question: can Veritaserum indeed be a reality one day? Well, let me break this to you- truth serums very much exist. In fact, they have been available since the 1920’s. They are primarily mind-altering (psychoactive) drugs which slow down the process of transfer of messages from the spinal cord to the brain. Lying usually requires a lot of effort, unless you are a compulsive liar. These drugs simply hinder your capability to concentrate and thus, make it difficult to lie. They don’t, however, completely inhibit your ability to lie. Some common examples include sodium thiopental, scopolamine and sodium amytal. Historically, they have been used for various other purposes. During World War II, they were used as anti-anxiety drugs on soldiers. Until 2011, they were also used as anaesthetics. Very rarely have truth serums been used for interrogation though, due to ethical conflicts. A myriad of historical examples, however, portray the positives of using such drugs in a criminal investigation. The 2007 Noida serial killer case (in India) could only be solved when the suspect confessed, under the influence of sodium amytal, to the heinous crimes that had been committed by him. However, the use of truth serums during interrogation is considered to be a direct violation of the Fifth Amendment of the US Constitution (the Right to remain silent) and is, thus, illegal in the US. Many consider the administration of truth serums, in order to extract information, to not only be a violation of the human right to be free from degrading treatment but also a form of torture. Besides, these drugs have some serious side-effects, including the development of false memories, addiction and even death in case of an overdose. In spite of such concerns, research is on to find and develop a drug that can completely prevent a person from lying, including compulsive liars, without any grave side-effects: the ultimate Veritaserum. But just because something can be done doesn’t mean that it should be done. Whether it is morally right or wrong requires thinking through a lot of different things. One side of the debate might argue that taking away the right to lie is a severe encroachment upon the right to choose. At times, it might, in fact, be necessary to lie- white lies. Thomas Paine once said, “He who dares not offend cannot be honest”. In a world where being polite is deemed a great virtue, it is impossible to get by without lying, if one hopes to follow the etiquettes set by a genteel society. When a child, still in the formative years, tries to learn something new, we provide them encouragement shrouded in little lies. This is necessary to prevent them from losing interest or giving up. It is also unfortunate that the modern world isn’t very progressive when it comes to accepting the LGBTQIA+ community, often forcing people of the community to lie about their sexuality or gender to save themselves from questions, comments and bullies. At times, lies are crucial to one’s safety. Celebrities lie about where they live to prevent stalkers from breaking in, spies put on a disguise and lie to unveil the secrets of underground institutions and terrorist cells, while also ensuring personal safety against potential harm from the people they spy upon. When doctors fail to see alternative options to save a person’s life, they often resort to placebo. This involves actively lying to the patient about the effects the drugs have been having on the person’s health- telling them that the medicines have actually been working well and that they will get well soon when that is probably not the case. In some cases, patients actually have a positive response to this. While many see this practice as unethical, owing to the fact that a doctor has to blatantly lie to a patient, others think that using placebo as a last resort to help them is justified. While most of these cases are rather niche, there are many which are not as individualistic. Taking a step back and looking at the big picture, reveals other interesting aspects. The avenues that greatly affect our day to day lives like politics, religion, media, etc. tend to hurt us mostly when lies in some form or the other are involved. Let’s talk politics. Populist demagogues, who tend to make fake promises based on what the majority of the populace desires instead of using rational arguments, are the biggest disgrace to modern politics. Their campaigns and popularity are based on lies. Commoners fall prey to their words because these leaders pander to what people already want to hear. Examples of such leaders include Adolf Hitler and Benito Mussolini. Stephen Hawking once tagged even Donald Trump as a demagogue. It isn’t unknown to any of us what their ‘reigns’ have been like. Even though stripping politicians of the ability to lie won’t solve the problems that pervade politics, it does ensure that commoners do not get cheated into hoping for something that is never meant to happen. Another thing to affect our lives immensely is crime. False charges, corruption and plantation of fake evidence are not unusual. It is common practice among convicts, facing the possibility of a long sentence, to lie about the severity of their crimes to hinder the prosecution. Psychopaths and sociopaths are able to lie without any remorse whatsoever. Most serial killers can be classified as either of the two and their flawless lying makes them incredibly difficult to spot. The problems of adjudication, conviction and prosecution will simply fail to exist in a world where people are unable to lie. Unethical marketing cheats people into believing that a product provides certain benefits which it actually doesn’t. Tech giants like Google, Amazon, Facebook, Qualcomm and so on have come under a lot of heat in recent years. Immense capital is spent on investigating these companies to find the truth. In a lie-less world, these problems would simply cease to exist. Cases of fraud often take several years to be solved and have justice served for, like the Enron scandal. It is easier to live in a world where committing fraud is an impossibility than to have so many duped before spending big bucks to rectify the situation. The morality of the work done by certain companies itself is questionable. Take Ashley Madison for example, it is a dating site catering to those who are currently in a committed relationship or married. The profits of this company are based on how well they are able to lie without taking into consideration the fact that they hurt people in the process. There is widespread misinformation in the world owing to the phenomena of ‘fake news’. Lies about the intentions of a party creates misunderstandings, leading to conflict and divided masses. Social media has enabled lying to a whole new extent. It is fashionable to lie about not having make-up on or not having had plastic surgery in the past, or even about living perfect lives. These set unrealisable standards of lifestyle and beauty for everyone. This eventually culminates in depression among teenagers and adults who fail to achieve these unreal standards- something that is more common now than ever. In fact, celebrities, like K-Pop idols, are forced to undergo surgeries to comply with certain beauty standards. Another thing that shapes society drastically is religion. Problems arise from lies about what God desires. While this can be used as a powerful positive tool too, there exist other alternatives to achieve the same. For example, it is better to tell a person not to cut a tree because they provide us with oxygen rather than using some religious reference to drive the point home. This is because, for one, atheism is on the rise and will, in the future, be the dominant ‘belief’ (atheism is expected to overtake religion by 2041). These atheists associate religion with regressiveness of thought and religious justifications are unacceptable to them. Secondly, religious beliefs do not have the same appeal among people belonging to different religions or sects. While freedom of choice is essential for everyone, this freedom cannot affect someone else- hurt the other person or encroach upon their freedom. Social contract theorists argue that everyone in a society moves into a contract with each other and the government, and the government can partially take away certain rights of individuals to ensure greater benefits for society at large. If this ‘sacrifice’ is what society operates upon, I personally feel that it is justified to take away the right to lie if greater benefits can be ensured in the process.   Not all problems can be solved by just stopping people from lying. A world where no one can lie is not the ideal world. Crimes will be committed. Bad people will continue to exist. They will have evil intentions; they just will not be able to lie about them. While it might seem that taking away the right to lie infringes upon individual rights, the greater benefits it provides makes me question if the argument of ‘rights’ is sufficient grounds to argue against it. A world like this, however, is a reality left in store for those who come after us (unless someone is secretly preparing for a Nobel Prize). For now, we are doomed to live in a world of lies, fraud and betrayal where we can only hope that the ones we trust the most do not lie to us.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">To Walk Again: On Love In Shinkai’s Anime</title>
      <link href="/To-Walk-Again" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To Walk Again: On Love In Shinkai’s Anime" />
      <published>2019-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/To-Walk-Again</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/To-Walk-Again">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Narukami no sukoshi toyomite&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
(A faint clap of thunder)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;sashi kumori&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
(Clouded skies)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ame mo furanu ka?&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
(Perhaps rain comes)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kimi wo todomemu&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
(If so, will you stay here with me?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fate, sometimes, begets in itself the funniest stories as well as the most
melancholic ones. It writes its own comedies and tragedies. The way we interpret
it, however, is what finalises the effect fate has on us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Makoto Shinkai is a giant in the world of anime. Deservedly and frequently does
he get compared to Miyazaki; a genius in the field. I do not wish to compare two
of the most amazing anime directors. Their work and their storytelling have
always touched a chord in my heart; a reaction spanning all of the people who
have watched their movies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shinkai is, however, criticised due to his lack of versatility in approaching
the themes of stories. &lt;em&gt;Most&lt;/em&gt; of his stories pertain to separation and love,
requited or otherwise. &lt;em&gt;Garden of Words&lt;/em&gt;, one of his works, is not any
different. However, the multitude of perspectives that went behind the making of
the story’s concept is what makes the story stand out, in the midst of a
plethora of influential anime films.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Garden of Words&lt;/em&gt; sets up an atmosphere which most of us can relate to on a
superficial level. Shinkai has never been afraid to work on stuff he personally
connects to, as a result of which three things come forth in his films as
defining motifs: train, rain, and pain, strangely enough they rhyme too. &lt;em&gt;Garden
of words&lt;/em&gt; interweaves a beautiful love story between the two protagonists and
despite their mutual feelings for each other, they remain visibly disconnected
from each other. They remain separated by the immense difference in age that
exists between the two of them. 27-year-old, Yukari Yukino is a teacher in the
same school as the 15-year-old Takao Akizuki, albeit unbeknownst to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a fine rainy day, both of them chance upon each other in a Japanese-themed
garden where they both had sought refuge from the rain. The two share a moment
of connectedness. Yukino leaves him, after sharing with him a cryptic &lt;em&gt;tanka&lt;/em&gt; (a
short Japanese poem). Yukino and Takao end up forming a connection and start
meeting each time it rains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things turn topsy-turvy when Yukino is wrongfully accused of being involved in a
relationship with a student. She is in a soup herself, left with feelings of
remorse and shame even though she had done no wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Takao is an aspiring shoemaker. He comes from a broken family; having been
abandoned by their mother, he and his elder brother lived together. Takao is a
responsible human despite being a mere high school student, he assumes a
part-time job in order to ensure ends meet. Takao, helps Yukino ‘to walk again’
and get back up on her feet. His affection and bond with Yukino make him resolve
to make a shoe for her, a project he works passionately and dedicatedly for.
&lt;em&gt;Love&lt;/em&gt; is the central theme that runs throughout the story. Ultimately, the
rainy season is over and despite wanting each other’s company, they both
hesitate to meet. Takao still continues to work on the shoe. On one particular
day, he realises how Yukino is a teacher in his school and has been wrongfully
accused of something that she did not even commit. Takao decides to take it upon
himself to resolve the issue, and ends up getting involved in a fight. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One certain day, Takao and Yukino get a chance to meet up again. In the midst of
a conversation, Takao confesses his love for her. Yukino, unable to process it,
makes him realise that she is still technically his teacher. Takao and Yukino
share their feelings with each other but realise the limitations of their own
understanding and that of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Garden of Words&lt;/em&gt; provides a unique perspective, a tale of love, which is
unrequited and beautiful in its own way. It was Takao’s behaviour towards her,
and his compassion, respect and love that ultimately heals Yukino. This story
makes one introspect upon a form of love that was much popularised by the
philosopher Plato himself: platonic love. There are no boundaries, no
restrictions and no limitations in platonic love and every form of expressing
this love is pure, considerate and understandable. &lt;em&gt;Garden of Words&lt;/em&gt; gives us a
look into a world of people to whom we can relate, beings we can understand and
sympathise with. It makes us realise the harshness with which society conditions
us and shapes our views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separation is the ultimate form of connection because it provides a &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt; for
two people to connect, and know each others’ places in their lives better than
ever. &lt;em&gt;Garden of Words,&lt;/em&gt; with its sensitively structured soundtracks and
breathtaking animation, helps us make a connection in separation. A separation
of ages does not restrict a human from pacifying and helping the other person
‘learn to walk again’. Japanese culture is founded on the principles of mutual
respect, understanding and love. The story provides us with that and more. One
must learn to enjoy the things one takes for granted, take the opportunity to
understand someone better and maybe heal them as well as ourselves in the
process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the world is a cold place and all we have is ourselves, and the crucial
key to understanding our own selves is to understand the ones who need our help.
Maybe we are all Takao, living in a broken, mundane, disjunctive world but we
can still always try to find someone like ourselves, broken and battered and
unable to walk, and learn to walk together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of trying to search for the love that we seek all our lives, we can try
to help one another and seek acceptance within ourselves. After all, “We all are
humans, we all have our own quirks, don’t we?”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Narukami no sukoshi toyomite (A faint clap of thunder) sashi kumori (Clouded skies) Ame mo furanu ka? (Perhaps rain comes) Kimi wo todomemu (If so, will you stay here with me?) Fate, sometimes, begets in itself the funniest stories as well as the most melancholic ones. It writes its own comedies and tragedies. The way we interpret it, however, is what finalises the effect fate has on us. Makoto Shinkai is a giant in the world of anime. Deservedly and frequently does he get compared to Miyazaki; a genius in the field. I do not wish to compare two of the most amazing anime directors. Their work and their storytelling have always touched a chord in my heart; a reaction spanning all of the people who have watched their movies. Shinkai is, however, criticised due to his lack of versatility in approaching the themes of stories. Most of his stories pertain to separation and love, requited or otherwise. Garden of Words, one of his works, is not any different. However, the multitude of perspectives that went behind the making of the story’s concept is what makes the story stand out, in the midst of a plethora of influential anime films. Garden of Words sets up an atmosphere which most of us can relate to on a superficial level. Shinkai has never been afraid to work on stuff he personally connects to, as a result of which three things come forth in his films as defining motifs: train, rain, and pain, strangely enough they rhyme too. Garden of words interweaves a beautiful love story between the two protagonists and despite their mutual feelings for each other, they remain visibly disconnected from each other. They remain separated by the immense difference in age that exists between the two of them. 27-year-old, Yukari Yukino is a teacher in the same school as the 15-year-old Takao Akizuki, albeit unbeknownst to him. On a fine rainy day, both of them chance upon each other in a Japanese-themed garden where they both had sought refuge from the rain. The two share a moment of connectedness. Yukino leaves him, after sharing with him a cryptic tanka (a short Japanese poem). Yukino and Takao end up forming a connection and start meeting each time it rains. Things turn topsy-turvy when Yukino is wrongfully accused of being involved in a relationship with a student. She is in a soup herself, left with feelings of remorse and shame even though she had done no wrong. Takao is an aspiring shoemaker. He comes from a broken family; having been abandoned by their mother, he and his elder brother lived together. Takao is a responsible human despite being a mere high school student, he assumes a part-time job in order to ensure ends meet. Takao, helps Yukino ‘to walk again’ and get back up on her feet. His affection and bond with Yukino make him resolve to make a shoe for her, a project he works passionately and dedicatedly for. Love is the central theme that runs throughout the story. Ultimately, the rainy season is over and despite wanting each other’s company, they both hesitate to meet. Takao still continues to work on the shoe. On one particular day, he realises how Yukino is a teacher in his school and has been wrongfully accused of something that she did not even commit. Takao decides to take it upon himself to resolve the issue, and ends up getting involved in a fight.  One certain day, Takao and Yukino get a chance to meet up again. In the midst of a conversation, Takao confesses his love for her. Yukino, unable to process it, makes him realise that she is still technically his teacher. Takao and Yukino share their feelings with each other but realise the limitations of their own understanding and that of society. Garden of Words provides a unique perspective, a tale of love, which is unrequited and beautiful in its own way. It was Takao’s behaviour towards her, and his compassion, respect and love that ultimately heals Yukino. This story makes one introspect upon a form of love that was much popularised by the philosopher Plato himself: platonic love. There are no boundaries, no restrictions and no limitations in platonic love and every form of expressing this love is pure, considerate and understandable. Garden of Words gives us a look into a world of people to whom we can relate, beings we can understand and sympathise with. It makes us realise the harshness with which society conditions us and shapes our views. Separation is the ultimate form of connection because it provides a reason for two people to connect, and know each others’ places in their lives better than ever. Garden of Words, with its sensitively structured soundtracks and breathtaking animation, helps us make a connection in separation. A separation of ages does not restrict a human from pacifying and helping the other person ‘learn to walk again’. Japanese culture is founded on the principles of mutual respect, understanding and love. The story provides us with that and more. One must learn to enjoy the things one takes for granted, take the opportunity to understand someone better and maybe heal them as well as ourselves in the process. Perhaps the world is a cold place and all we have is ourselves, and the crucial key to understanding our own selves is to understand the ones who need our help. Maybe we are all Takao, living in a broken, mundane, disjunctive world but we can still always try to find someone like ourselves, broken and battered and unable to walk, and learn to walk together.  Instead of trying to search for the love that we seek all our lives, we can try to help one another and seek acceptance within ourselves. After all, “We all are humans, we all have our own quirks, don’t we?”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Kalām Cosmological Argument for God’s Existence</title>
      <link href="/Cosmological-Argument" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Kalām Cosmological Argument for God’s Existence" />
      <published>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Cosmological-Argument</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Cosmological-Argument">&lt;p&gt;This is the first article that I have been privileged to write for &lt;em&gt;The Pangean&lt;/em&gt; on the existence of God. Some might be surprised at this. &lt;em&gt;The Pangean&lt;/em&gt;,  after all, is not a philosophical quarterly. How is this relevant, some might say? To put it simply: in every way. This is an immensely relevant topic because the question of whether or not God exists is surely one of the most significant questions we can ask (in fact, I consider it the most significant). The answer we give to this question will inevitably impact the rest of our worldview as well as influence how we choose to live our lives. Not merely that, this article shall be a bit of an introduction to the field of natural theology: that branch of philosophy devoted to arguments for the existence of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before we proceed further, a few disclaimers must be made. Here’s the first one: I am not claiming to provide &lt;em&gt;empirical&lt;/em&gt; evidence for God. Some people have quipped to me in the past, “Show me God, and I’ll believe in Him.” But this statement/challenge presupposes that God is an empirical entity that can be ‘shown’. But God is not an empirical entity; I would argue that He is immaterial and transcendent, not enclosed within space and time. As such, it is not possible for anyone to ‘show’ God to you. But empirical evidence is not the only valid source of knowledge. Logical and philosophical reasoning can play a crucial role too. In fact, the idea that only empirical observations are true sources of knowledge (also called Empiricism) is &lt;em&gt;itself&lt;/em&gt; not an empirical observation – it is rather a philosophical assertion, based upon (I imagine) some kind of inductive (probabilistic) reasoning. To claim that only empirical observations can be true sources of knowledge is by its very nature self-defeating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As this is an article tailored for a general audience, this article will not presuppose any prior philosophical or theological training. And thus, the argument that has been chosen for this paper is one of the simplest ones out there – the &lt;em&gt;Kalām&lt;/em&gt; Cosmological Argument. However, its simplicity does not imply a lack of strength – quite the contrary, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now here’s the second disclaimer: this article is also not going to be extremely comprehensive. Yes, it will be to the point, but it is my hope to reach as broad an audience as I can. As such, the article will not be answering every possible objection that can be made to the argument; instead it will focus primarily on seeking to explain what it actually is rather than defend it in excruciating detail. Comprehensive defences of the argument have already been made by Christian philosophers and there is no need for a humble writer, such as myself, to add to the (quite frankly, saturated) bulk of scholarly literature that already exists on this subject. If you want to study deeper, look no further than Chapter 3 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wiley.com/en-us/The+Blackwell+Companion+to+Natural+Theology-p-9781444350852&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Blackwell Companion to Natural Theology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, one of the most elegantly argued natural theology textbooks of our time (though this present author does not agree with everything that is asserted in that work). Or you can look &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reasonablefaith.org/writings/popular-writings/existence-nature-of-god/the-kalam-cosmological-argument/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for an exposition of the argument, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gtfVds8Kn4s&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for responses to the most popular objections that have been made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main purpose of this article is to explain why God exists in as simple a manner as I possibly can. This will also give the reader an idea of how philosophical reasoning normally works and how classical theists have argued for the rationality of their faith in God. For, sadly, many of the popular YouTube ‘vlogs’ on the Kalām argument (usually made by posturing theatrical self-congratulatory millennials and other assorted hippies) clearly betray a pitiful lack of understanding of the argument itself, as well as the reasoning that runs through it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here is a third disclaimer, which may seem trivial, but which I feel must be made for the sake of conscience. While I heartily acclaim the argument itself, I do not endorse every aspect of the philosophy that has been put forward by some of its chief proponents. Particularly, I take issue with the philosopher William Lane Craig’s (one of the argument’s most vocal defenders) denial of God’s intrinsic immutability. However, this does not affect the core of the argument, and so there should be no issue in presenting it as is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, without further ado, let us get into the argument. It can be formulated as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P1.&lt;/strong&gt; Everything which begins to exist must have a cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P2.&lt;/strong&gt; The universe began to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C1.&lt;/strong&gt; (From P1 and P2) Therefore, the universe must have a cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P4.&lt;/strong&gt; If the universe has a cause, then an uncaused, Personal Creator of the universe exists, Who sans the universe is beginningless, changeless, immaterial, timeless, spaceless and enormously powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C2.&lt;/strong&gt; (From C1 and P4) Therefore, an uncaused, Personal Creator of the universe exists, Who sans the universe is beginningless, changeless, immaterial, timeless, spaceless and enormously powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we proceed, something very crucial in &lt;strong&gt;P1&lt;/strong&gt; must be pointed out. It is a common question, often posed by young internet atheists: “If everything which exists must have a cause, then what caused God?” However, this question misses the point of what we are saying. &lt;strong&gt;P1&lt;/strong&gt; does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; say that &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; which exists must have a cause – rather, it simply asserts that &lt;em&gt;everything which &lt;strong&gt;begins&lt;/strong&gt; to exist&lt;/em&gt; must have a cause. On the face of it, the syllogism is extremely simple and straightforward. P1 is obviously true – or, at the very least, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reasonablefaith.org/media/reasonable-faith-podcast/why-think-whatever-begins-to-exist-has-a-cause/&quot;&gt;it is far, far more probable than its alternative&lt;/a&gt;. As for &lt;strong&gt;P2&lt;/strong&gt;, it can be verified by philosophical arguments as well as scientific evidence. Notice also that the argument is what philosophers call a &lt;em&gt;deductive&lt;/em&gt; argument – meaning that if the premises of the argument are true, the conclusion necessarily and inescapably follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the universe has a cause. But, some ask, why does this cause have to be God? Richard Dawkins, for instance, argues that there is no reason at all to believe that this universal cause (if It indeed exists) possesses the attributes that have been traditionally ascribed to It by Jewish, Christian and Muslim theologians. However, in this, Dawkins is thoroughly mistaken. The divine attributes have been rationally argued for and logically defended for centuries now, and they go back all the way &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; to Aristotle and Plotinus, philosophers who lived before the time of Christ and who – although they were neither Jews nor Christians in the formal sense of the term – did come up with a belief in a monotheistic God. It is therefore no wonder that Christian philosophers like St Thomas Aquinas took Aristotle with such enthusiasm (in fact, Catholic theology to this day makes use of Aristotelian terminology to describe spiritual realities).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So, why does the Cause of the Universe have to be God?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument can be laid out as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Firstly&lt;/em&gt;, there must be an Ultimate Uncaused Cause of all things. In other words, we cannot postulate the existence of an infinite regress of causes (the idea that the Universe is caused by A, which is caused by B, which is caused by C… etc. all the way to infinity).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The philosophers William Lane Craig and James D Sinclair offer a simple reason: the reason is that actual infinites cannot exist in reality. Actual infinites do enjoy mathematical existence, that is undeniable. However, mathematical existence does not necessarily equate to metaphysical existence, or existence in the real world. The great German mathematician David Hilbert himself observed, “The infinite is nowhere to be found in reality. It neither exists in nature nor provides a legitimate basis for rational thought… The role that remains for the infinite to play is solely that of an idea”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actual infinites cannot exist in reality simply because, if they did, they would create insoluble absurdities. A good example of this is the famous paradox of Hilbert’s Hotel, an exposition of which you can see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lobeX6ft6PA&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some, however, claim that infinites exist all around us. For example, they point to the fact that any given distance can be infinitely subdivided. However, here we must make the distinction Aristotle made between an actual and a potential infinite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An actual infinite is something which, to put it bluntly, is &lt;em&gt;actually infinite&lt;/em&gt; – that is, it is a completed infinite. For example, the set of all even numbers truly contains an infinite number of members. However, a potential infinite is quite different. It is anything which keeps increasing and which keeps moving towards infinity but which never actualizes or achieves infinity – it always remains an ever-increasing (or ever-decreasing) finitude. For example, the age of the universe which began to exist but which will never cease to exist in the future. The age would be increasing with every passing moment and be forever progressing towards infinity, but it would never actually reach infinity. It is the same with the example of a finite distance being potentially divisible infinitely. To quote Craig and Sinclair: “The only legitimate sense in which one can speak of the infinite is in terms of potentiality: something may be infinitely divisible or susceptible to infinite addition, but this type of infinity is potential only and can never be fully actualized”. So, “While one can continue indefinitely to divide conceptually any distance, the series of subintervals thereby generated is merely potentially infinite, in that infinity serves as a limit that one endlessly approaches but never reaches”. The same goes for time. “This is the thoroughgoing Aristotelian position on the infinite: only the potential infinite exists. This position does not imply that minimal time atoms, or chronons, exist. Rather time, like space, is infinitely divisible in the sense that division can proceed indefinitely, but time is never actually infinitely divided, neither does one arrive at an instantaneous point.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, when we seek to subdivide any given distance, we must remember that the distance we are seeking to divide is strictly finite – it is not infinite. We can keep dividing it for years and years if we please, but we will never actually reach an infinite number of divisions. At any given point in time, the number of divisions we will have created will still be finite, the size of each division will still be finite and the sum total of the divisions will still be what it originally was: the finite distance we set out to divide. We will never arrive at an actually infinite number of divisions; we will keep on moving towards the infinite without realising it. This is a &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; infinite, not an actual one. For more on the paradoxes related to the infinite, readers can refer to the Oxford philosopher A W Moore’s book &lt;em&gt;The Infinite&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, an actual infinite cannot exist in reality. This naturally implies that the regress of causes cannot be actually infinite; it must terminate in a First/Ultimate Cause. And this First/Ultimate Cause must naturally be Uncaused (otherwise, it would not be a First/Ultimate Cause). So, we have established the first premise of all monotheistic religion – that there is an Ultimate Uncaused Cause of all things. Let us continue with the divine attributes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the second place&lt;/em&gt;,  an Uncaused Cause must be beginning-less since everything which is uncaused has no beginning to it (we can derive this by contraposition of &lt;strong&gt;P1&lt;/strong&gt; of the original argument).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thirdly&lt;/em&gt;, there is good reason to believe that the Entity is Immaterial and Timeless. This is powerfully suggested by the fact that it is, in fact, the cause of space and time (causation, it must be remembered, does not itself have to be temporal). But if the Entity is Itself the cause of space and time, it cannot itself be enclosed within space and time. Of course, this assertion itself probably doesn’t clinch the argument on its own. However, there are other arguments by other philosophers which have proven convincing to me that the Ultimate Cause is indeed immaterial and timeless. If you’re interested in reading up on this, refer to Chapters 1 and 3 of philosopher and former atheist Edward Feser’s book &lt;em&gt;Five Proofs for the Existence of God&lt;/em&gt;. However, since the Immateriality and Timelessness of the First Cause is not – strictly speaking – crucial to the core of the argument, we shall carry on without dwelling on it for too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fourthly&lt;/em&gt;, the Entity in question must possess enormous power, since it brought the entirety of the universe into existence quite literally from nothing. This is fairly straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fifthly and finally&lt;/em&gt;, the Ultimate Cause of all Things must be Personal. This is the linchpin. Craig and Sinclair offer three arguments for this (though many, many more can be offered) in &lt;em&gt;The Blackwell Companion to Natural Theology&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first place, as the Oxford philosopher Richard Swinburne notes, there are two types of causal explanations: “scientific explanations in terms of laws and initial conditions and personal explanations in terms of agents and their volitions”. For example, two answers can be given to the question, “Why is the kettle boiling?” We could say: “The heat of the flame is being conducted via the bottom of the kettle to the water, increasing the kinetic energy of the molecules such that they vibrate so violently that they break the surface tension of the water and are thrown off in the form of steam.” Or we could simply say: “I put the kettle on to make a cup of tea.” Both these explanations are true, and one does not necessarily exclude the other. However, one is scientific in nature; the other personal. The ‘First State of the Universe’ cannot have a scientific explanation, since there is nothing before it and it cannot, therefore, be accounted for in terms of laws operating on initial conditions. The only other explanation is in terms of an Agent and His volitions (the personal explanation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the Personhood of the Ultimate/First Cause also seems to follow from the other properties we have laid out in our argumentation. There are only two kinds of things which can be said to be uncaused, beginningless, timeless, spaceless and immaterial – either abstract objects or unembodied minds. However, abstract objects (like numbers for example, or things like roundness, redness, etc.) cannot cause anything at all – that’s part of what it means to be abstract. The only alternative that springs to mind is that of an Unembodied Mind. No other alternatives seem possible, and indeed none have been suggested so far by any major critic of the argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third argument begins by observing that while the cause is clearly eternal, the effect is not. But this seems strange. Is it not reasonable to expect that if the cause is eternal, the effect would also be co-eternal with it? And yet, we see that the effect only came to be a finite time ago, instead of forever existing side-by-side with its eternal cause, like a person and her shadow, or a subject and his/her reflection in the mirror. The easiest way out of this dilemma, Craig and Sinclair argue, is to accept that the Cause is Personal and Free. That way, it can be Eternal, while still being the cause of a temporal and finite effect. God simply chooses eternally to create a temporally finite world. This does not, of course, mean, that God “one day woke up and decided all upon a sudden to create the world”. No, that assertion is deeply problematic philosophically. Rather, the classical theist position is simply to assert that God eternally wills to create/cause the temporal universe. This decision is eternal (as would be expected if God is omniscient and immutable – though that is a topic for another day), but still, free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those were the arguments made by some of the mainstream philosophers. In addition, I would boldly venture a suggestion of my own. Although I myself lack the credentials of an Oxford don, the example I am about to give I have thought about for some time and – so far – have found no flaw in it. You could take it as a personal insight, which is not too different from Swinburne’s argument described in point one above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example is that of a stone. A stone is an inanimate object. It can never think nor freely chose to do things. This means that it cannot do anything at all unless external forces act upon it. If a stone comes flying through the air and hits you on the head, you can legitimately say, “The stone has hit me!” But because the stone is inanimate (it can neither think nor take free will decisions of its own), you must also recognize that it did not hit you by its own strength or power or will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if there is indeed an Ultimate/First Cause of all things, then it must be animate/living, personal, conscious and endowed with free will. Otherwise, it could not do (or, to be more accurate, cause) anything on its own unless external forces acted upon it – much like the stone. However, the Ultimate/First Cause has no such forces to rely upon – that is precisely &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; it is the Ultimate/First Cause to begin with! Therefore, Personhood and Freedom of the Will seem inescapable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, in a nutshell, is the Kalām Cosmological Argument. It is a very old argument, having roots in the Islamic tradition, but it has recently been popularised by philosopher of religion William Lane Craig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is up to you, dear reader, at the end of the day to judge whether or not the argument is sound. You must do your own research and make up your own mind. But even if you ultimately disagree, I hope you can at least see that the Classical Theist philosophical tradition is nothing like what it is so often made out to be by the New Atheists and their enthusiastic YouTube supporters. Al-Ghazali, Aquinas, Anselm, Aristotle, Augustine, Bonaventure, Scotus – these were not like the illiterate country bumpkins they are so often made out to be. They were brilliant and careful thinkers. Centuries later, their insights still remain true and science has, in fact, confirmed many of their philosophical deductions (for example: al-Ghazali argued centuries ago, on the basis of philosophical argumentation, that time is finite; modern cosmology largely seems to have vindicated him). If you want to see how the argument holds up in the context of debate, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0tYm41hb48o&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9JVRy7bR7zI&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I hope has become obvious, although I have peppered this article with hyperlinks that will prove useful to you, I have not taken it upon myself to answer every question or refute every objection. There are others who have done that and this article has already exceeded 3,000 words. You’ll have to be satisfied with this much for now, at least from me. Plus, since this is an extremely provocative topic, what better way to end it than with a provocative and cliff-hanging conclusion?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This is the first article that I have been privileged to write for The Pangean on the existence of God. Some might be surprised at this. The Pangean, after all, is not a philosophical quarterly. How is this relevant, some might say? To put it simply: in every way. This is an immensely relevant topic because the question of whether or not God exists is surely one of the most significant questions we can ask (in fact, I consider it the most significant). The answer we give to this question will inevitably impact the rest of our worldview as well as influence how we choose to live our lives. Not merely that, this article shall be a bit of an introduction to the field of natural theology: that branch of philosophy devoted to arguments for the existence of God.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Stoic’s Path to Happiness</title>
      <link href="/Stoic-Path-to-Happiness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Stoic’s Path to Happiness" />
      <published>2019-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Stoic-Path-to-Happiness</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Stoic-Path-to-Happiness">&lt;p&gt;Call it an endless string of experiences or a series of vivid sensations of the world around, we are all suffering from a mysterious condition, called life or existence. Existence is difficult to define in objective terms. One can only derive a vague understanding of existence through the complex fabric of encounters and experiences that shape how we see the world. But does one’s myopic and vague understanding stop one from expressing one’s subjective take on the matter? Certainly not. Discussions on existence have permeated through the history of humankind. Myriad answers have been proposed and rejected over the years but a solitary troubling question has remained unchanged: what is the best way to live?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the peculiar existential ‘situatedness’ that is exclusive to every individual, there remains one universal narrative that has seemed to establish its grip on everyone. An idea that has been passionately explored by myriad traditions of the past and the present – life is suffering; a meld of ephemeral pleasures and perpetual despair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The murky river of existence, to which we are eternally stuck, is, well, doomed. With every meandering turn it inflicts painful blows, pulverises hopes and leaves us in a state of absolute despondence and melancholia. Sorrow is inextricably linked to existence. Sorrow stems from attachments and poisons our lives; an idea deeply rooted in Buddhist philosophy. This realisation itself is sufficient to make a person depressed for the rest of his life, knowing that whatever he does shall in no way improve his dull existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much deliberation went into the matter, in response to which a Greek man proposed his own tenets to lead a joyful life. This later took the form of a full-fledged school of thought called &lt;em&gt;Stoicism&lt;/em&gt;. Far removed from other philosophies, that expound obscure esoteric questions pertaining to the metaphysics or epistemology of existence, stoicism employs the Socratic approach to discuss practical issues which have a direct bearing on the lives of common people. The idea was to search for the best means to lead a happy life, in the face of the pandemonium that had descended over the political landscape of the Hellenistic period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our tale begins with a sailing merchant by the name of Zeno who, after surviving a major shipwreck, ends up in the city of Athens. During his stay, he visited a bookstore which proved to be the turning point of his life. That was the day he was introduced to the philosophy of Socrates. Fascinated by his findings, Zeno decided to pursue his newly developed interest in philosophy and asked the librarian to suggest a teacher who could guide him. The librarian recommended a man named Crates, who, for the coming years, instructed Zeno on the idea of Cynicism; an outgrowth of Socratic thought. A passionate student, Zeno studied not only Cynicism but also other schools of thought that prevailed during that time. This equipped him with the ability to understand the world through multiple lenses, and much later helped him develop a theory of his own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Cynicism exposed Zeno to a brand new world of naturalistic existence, one that defied all societal norms, it didn’t quite resonate with his own personal beliefs. After all who would want to lie around, naked in broad daylight, disturbing everybody passing by, like the cynic Diogenes? Dissatisfied with whatever knowledge he had acquired so far, he decided to part ways with the school and set out on a new journey. Zeno took up teaching. He lectured pupils on his own precepts, in the middle of the city, which actually turned out to be quite successful. Several students flocked to the beautiful building of Stoa Poikile, to hear their great teacher speak. It is here that the foundations of Stoicism were finally laid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Zeno remains a major player in our story, he isn’t the only one. Several other intellectuals also subscribed and greatly contributed to the doctrine. These thinkers included greats such as Seneca, Marcus Aurelius and Epictetus. They, together with Zeno, spoke in great detail about the various facets of Stoicism. Here, I’ll be discussing aspects of Stoic ethics that surprisingly enough remain relevant till date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that is studied in Ethics today has a very direct connection with the ideas that were propounded by these thinkers. Stoic ethics mainly investigated happy existence and the conditions required to reach that state. The aim is to end suffering and live in harmony with nature. So, how did they achieve it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the core of Stoic ethics lies the idea of &lt;em&gt;Oikeiosis&lt;/em&gt;, loosely translating to orientation. Every living thing in the world has a basic constitution, assigned to it by the natural order. For animals it is self-preservation, but in the case of humans, the oikeiosis is much greater as it involves our extraordinary ability to reason. Thus stoicism takes into account our primitive behaviour along with the potentiality to transcend it, since to be rational one is required to step out of the realm of primitive desires. It ascribes greater importance to the actions that are motivated by reason rather than animalistic desires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very simple doctrine of the Stoics, from which one can derive a massive life lesson is that one needs to make a demarcation between things that fall under one’s control and things which don’t. All that is external to us is, quite naturally, in a state of chaos and something that’s independent of us. We can’t impose ourselves on the mechanisms of nature which remain outside the clutches of our will. However, we can change our perspectives and actions towards it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about it. In a brief session of introspection, we can easily discern that our lives are stranded between regrets of the past and fears of the future. All that stoicism asks is - why give a damn? To be Stoic is to remain indifferent to whatever lies beyond you. And it is when you become indifferent that you begin to act out of reason rather than passion. The Stoics may as well be dubbed the Buddhists of the western tradition, in some respects. Their ethics have a striking resemblance to the 2nd noble truth of the Buddha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever something bothers you, stop a second and ask - “Can I change this situation?” If yes, then strive towards that change otherwise be unfazed by it. This might seem difficult at first but if this little ritual of interrupting negativity is followed, life can transform drastically. The key is to halt expectations and to be at peace with oneself. In the words of Marcus Aurelius:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If you work at that which is before you, following right reason seriously, vigorously, calmly, without allowing anything else to distract you, but keeping your divine part pure, as if you were bound to give it back immediately; if you hold to this, expecting nothing, but satisfied to live now according to nature, speaking heroic truth in every word that you utter, you will live happy. And there is no man able to prevent this.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understand stoicism as a philosophy that prepares you to face the bitter truths of life, without getting affected. It engineers you in a manner such that you can’t help but walk a virtuous path. It imparts the lesson that one must moderate one’s desires and emotions by employing reason, untouched by the highs and lows of life. Stoicism values self-control and an acceptance of whatever comes one’s way. Above all, however, stoicism is about empowering the ‘ruler within you.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is obvious that in the 21st century, the age of despair and silenced voices, humans are drawn towards a philosophy which can offer them tranquillity and order. Ours is a generation being pulled by desire with a force we can’t resist. We end up either letting go of the reins of control, becoming slaves to our passions, or fretting over situations which we can’t possibly control. It, therefore, becomes imperative to adopt Stoicism, because honestly, what is a life without happiness? Stoicism is the emancipatory force to guide us towards the path of a more fulfilled and joyful existence.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Call it an endless string of experiences or a series of vivid sensations of the world around, we are all suffering from a mysterious condition, called life or existence. Existence is difficult to define in objective terms. One can only derive a vague understanding of existence through the complex fabric of encounters and experiences that shape how we see the world. But does one’s myopic and vague understanding stop one from expressing one’s subjective take on the matter? Certainly not. Discussions on existence have permeated through the history of humankind. Myriad answers have been proposed and rejected over the years but a solitary troubling question has remained unchanged: what is the best way to live?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How Hayao Miyazaki Sees The Beauty in The Mundane</title>
      <link href="/Beauty-In-The-Mundane" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Hayao Miyazaki Sees The Beauty in The Mundane" />
      <published>2019-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Beauty-In-The-Mundane</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Beauty-In-The-Mundane">&lt;p&gt;One of the most enjoyed and oft-recounted anecdotes about Hayao Miyazaki- filmmaker, manga author, animator and co-founder of Japan’s Studio Ghibli- is his tussle with Hollywood’s now infamous mascot of predatory behaviour, Harvey Weinstein. Originally printed in &lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt;, the story runs thus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Harvey Weinstein, one of Hollywood’s most belligerent producers, received a samurai sword in the post because his reputation preceded him. It came with a note that said simply: “No cuts.” By 1997, Weinstein’s Miramax Company had been taken over by Disney, which had a distribution deal with Japanese animation revolutionaries Studio Ghibli.  Weinstein became one of Hollywood’s most powerful producers by acquiring and ruthlessly cutting films to make them as commercial as possible. Fearing his masterpiece Princess Mononoke would be butchered, director and animator Hayao Miyazaki sent Weinstein the sword with the note advising him not to do it.
[….]” I did go to New York to meet this man, this Harvey Weinstein, and I was bombarded with this aggressive attack, all these demands for cuts. I defeated him.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot to unpack in this tale. Obviously, it carries all the red flags that would later come to be associated with Weinstein. It is an amusing snippet of a battle between two of the biggest names in the global filmmaking industry. But more poignantly, it is, perhaps, a real-life enactment of Miyazaki’s favourite story to tell in each of his works: the desire to preserve a rapidly fading simplicity, which has its roots in a kind of psycho-emotional-cultural nostalgia, but which also faces the risk of obliteration by the hideous tide of forced Western assimilation and glitzy consumerism that Japanese culture and media faces to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I defeated him. No cuts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While he is often popularly addressed by the epithet &lt;em&gt;Walt Disney of Japan&lt;/em&gt;,  I have personally always disliked this particular comparison between the animators, each a legend in his own right. That is because Studio Ghibli, the Tokyo-based animation house that is often described as Disney’s whimsical Japanese twin in many ways, acts more like a foil as opposed to a mere Eastern counterpart of the former. Where Disney seeks to impress with the opulence of scale and blissfully escapist glamour (think bewitchingly beautiful princesses, operatic songs, almost demonic villains), Ghibli seeks out what’s relatable even in the extraordinary, tries to make a mark in more subtle ways, not through escapism but through its polar opposite really, through well-crafted realism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, if you ask someone to tell you what the best part is about Ghibli films, nine out of ten times the answer will inevitably end up being, either the delightfully animated technicolour food or the painstakingly drawn verdant landscapes of some sort of quasi-utopian, Kyoto countryside-meets-wonderland realm, peopled with mythical beasts and bizarre spirits. Or perhaps it might just be the underlying extended allegories of ethnic traditions and a love for environmentalism, which seeps through pretty much every Ghibli film in the past two and a half decades. Whatever it is, one thing stands out in crystal-sharp clarity: Miyazaki’s philosophy centres not around grandiose but around the mundane, which he moulds to his own liking through the most skillful blending of cinematic, emotive and artistic devices till the ordinary is idyllic and the commonplace enchanting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what constitutes the Hayao Miyazaki school of thought, exactly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his informative visual essay, &lt;em&gt;The Immersive Realism of Studio Ghibli&lt;/em&gt;,  video journalist Asher Isbruker chalks out the main reasons as to why Miyazaki’s creations feel so disarmingly familiar and relevant, despite some of them being as displaced from reality as most of our childhood bedtime tales. “No matter how far-fetched and imaginary [is] the story,” Isbruker emphasizes, “the world of a Ghibli film consistently feels tactile and realistic.” To prove his point, he cites the example of the 2001 Academy Award winning film &lt;em&gt;Spirited Away&lt;/em&gt;, directed and written by Miyazaki. The film revolves around Chihiro, a young human girl forced to work as a servant in a bathhouse frequented and operated by the most incredible array of ghosts and spirits. She does so in an effort to save her parents, who - courtesy of a whirlwind series of unfortunate events - have been turned into pigs by a malevolent witch. While you stop to reread and completely understand that sentence, it is worthwhile to take a look at what Isbruker says about world-building in the film:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…the bathhouse feels alive and real. While it is inherently unbelievable, we believe it exists in the context of the world (of the film) because it’s so well established. There are employees with jobs to do, sleeping quarters, a coal-powered furnace that heats the baths, different kinds of soaps for different clients… If you followed another employee, what would their day be like? That’s fun to imagine.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting that in a story bristling with absolutely wild events (a river becomes a dragon, the dragon becomes a boy, a witch ‘steals’ the names of her employees, thus rendering them disoriented, a faceless spirit materialises gold coins by clenching his fist) what sticks out as the most endearing bits are the little, uncharted moments that could have easily been from any slice-of-life indie film: waking up alone in an unfamiliar room to the view of an ocean, menial-labour employees gathering at the end of the day on a balcony to wistfully share their future plans of moving to the big city where prospects are better, two young children eating rice cakes in a garden full of spring flowers, the simple beauty of a wide-angle animated shot, downpour on the streets of a ghost-town. Nothing grand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isbruker also speaks of the very specific attention Miyazaki devotes to details as unostentatious as personalising the action of running in different characters. “Movement must be used to convey a sense of relative scale and weight,” he says. “Ghibli not only accomplishes this with grace but also conveys the emotions and traits of their characters through attention to minute details of their behaviour.” Instead of using technical shortcuts like pre-generated run cycles or rotoscoping (tracing live action footage), the veteran director and his animating team painstakingly created different patterns of movement to suit the circumstances and motives of every character, major or minor, be it the swift catlike sprint of wild, mountain-bred San and her horde of wolves from &lt;em&gt;Princess Mononoke&lt;/em&gt; (1997), the giddy, happy, flighty run of the innocent Kusakabe sisters joyfully exploring their new house in &lt;em&gt;My Neighbour Totoro&lt;/em&gt; (1988) or the comical, laboured struggles of the young witch from &lt;em&gt;Kiki’s Delivery Service&lt;/em&gt; (1989) to mount an enchanted broom. These details, seemingly unimportant, embellish and enrich the Ghibli cinematic experience, attesting yet again to the importance of the &lt;em&gt;extraordinary&lt;/em&gt;, so to speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there is food. Even those not well acquainted with that particular brand of Japanese animation are largely familiar with the mouth-watering, aesthetically pleasing scenes of food in every single Ghibli film. When we think of a retelling of &lt;em&gt;The Little Mermaid&lt;/em&gt;, food is not the first thing that comes to mind. Yet, it is the most enduring motif in &lt;em&gt;Ponyo On the Cliff&lt;/em&gt; (2008), Miyazaki’s lightest, brightest film yet. The most iconic scene in his take on Hans Christian Andersen’s Danish fairytale is a simple, homely scene of little importance plot-wise, where Lisa, the mother of Ponyo’s human companion Sōsuke, prepares a wholesome meal for her; ham and a bowl of steaming ramen noodles. It is a slow, drowsy scene, right after an extended, fatiguing driving sequence through the storm; the warmth and gastronomic aspect of it feel deliciously homely. Not just &lt;em&gt;Ponyo&lt;/em&gt;, who can forget the enchanted buffets of &lt;em&gt;Spirited Away&lt;/em&gt;, the mouth-watering Bento boxes from &lt;em&gt;Totoro&lt;/em&gt;, or the eggs-and-bacon breakfast scene in &lt;em&gt;Howl’s Moving Castle&lt;/em&gt; (2004)? None of these movies are wanting for magic and mischief, conflicts and adventures, yet what we take back at the end of the film are these small, humane moments of nurture and domesticity, opportunities to forge reel-to-real kinship with the protagonists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we speak of Ghibli food and Ghibli landscapes, we cannot avoid the underlying theme that Miyazaki strives to emphasise in his craft: romanticising the ordinary and trying to achieve a sense of balance between the magical extravaganzas of spirit-infested bathhouses and flying castles and benevolent cat-bear tree deities. One of Ghibli’s favourite tropes to use is the incomplete or unexplained aspects of its multilayered, kaleidoscopic universes. We are given rich tapestries of magical worlds- enchanted forests, prehistoric oceans, deserted valleys and idyllic small towns, with creatures and people unlike any of our own- but not all of it revealed through exposition, just enough to make us already familiar with, aware of the sensory experience we’re being thrust into. It definitely helps that Miyazaki prefers to work with young, starry-eyed protagonists for most of his films- it helps to convey a sense of newness and wonder at the good in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A section of critics have theorised that Miyazaki’s repeated emphasis on the synthesis of human-nature relationships, traditional and sustainable ways of living versus technology and economic progress, the portrayal of largely pacifist protagonists, ambiguous and somewhat redeemable antagonists, and anti-war motifs have much to do with Hayao Miyazaki’s personal experiences during the Second World War, particularly the 1945 bombings of Utsunomiya. “The characters who pursue war — generally government officials — are portrayed as vainglorious and arrogant schemers who rashly court cataclysm for the sake of their grandiose ambitions,” writes Dan Sanchez in his essay &lt;em&gt;Miyazaki’s Beautiful Anti War Dreams&lt;/em&gt;, while also noting that Miyazaki allows for even such seemingly irredeemable paragons of wickedness their moments to redeem themselves. “The climax of the film comes not with the hero impaling or detonating his foe, as in so many Hollywood movies, or in the villain falling to his doom, as in so many Disney animated films. Miyazaki’s heroes achieve victory, not through the destruction of their enemies, but by foiling their plans enough such that the belligerents finally relent …. sometimes even …. to the point of converting villains into friends.” He adds, “…. (Although) Tolkien’s &lt;em&gt;Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt; is a profound meditation on the corruption of power, its discussion of war and peace is crudely Manichean. Yet on this subject, and so many others, the fantasy of Studio Ghibli — &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; the work of the creative genius Hayao Miyazaki— is wise and deeply moral, as well as exhilarating and achingly beautiful. It is a cultural treasure that stands and soars in a class of its own.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others note that Miyazaki might have been significantly influenced by the ethno-Japanese &lt;em&gt;Shinto&lt;/em&gt; ideology, which attaches great importance to the worship of &lt;em&gt;kami&lt;/em&gt;: the sacred presence that manifests itself everywhere in nature, from rocks to rivers to forests to the creatures that dwell in them. The sacredness and fragility of the Shinto balance is well portrayed in one of Miyazaki’s earliest and most powerful works, &lt;em&gt;Nausicaä of the Valley of Wind&lt;/em&gt; (1984), where the titular protagonist Nausicaä battles fascist forces to establish harmony between the human world and the ancient creatures of the forest- dangerous, insect-like beasts called Ohms- even as Earth teeters on the brink of apocalypse. &lt;em&gt;Mononoke&lt;/em&gt; deals with the same ordeal, when the forest gods are disturbed as their homes are destroyed by an industrial settlement that derives resources from hacking down the pristine mountain foliage. These may sound rather far-fetched in theory, but with the skill that only a Ghibli animator can demonstrate, Miyazaki spreads his messages in a beautiful art-on-celluloid format, preferring to concentrate, as always, more on the ordinary than the other-worldly; not the rampages, or the grand battles, but the lives at the centre of the crossfire between enemies, at the motivations of every character, princess or chieftain or sailor or just a small-town boy with big dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all of Miyazaki’s movies come laden with ladles of fantasy, however. &lt;em&gt;Whisper of the Heart&lt;/em&gt; (1995), written by him, is a heart-warming, lush take on childhood and childish dreams, yearning, hoping, loving and losing, all embodied in the very non-fantastic and yet endearing host of characters, especially Shizuku, the 14 year old, book-smart, imaginative protagonist. It is in these understated and realistic films, that could easily be swapped for live-action works, that Miyazaki’s touch works the best. For it is here that you get to see the legacy of Studio Ghibli. How everything becomes dreamy and magical with just the right dose of attention and love, with just the exact dollops of childish whimsy and adult musings to balance each other out. As Isbruker says, “Pay attention to the ordinary, the inconsequential, seemingly unimportant actions and elements … every single one was a conscious choice.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We depict hatred, but it is to depict that there are more important things. We depict a curse, to depict the joy of liberation,” says Miyazaki himself. He goes on to talk about the joys of hand-drawn animation, “When I think about the way the computer has taken over and eliminated a certain experience of life, that makes me sad. When we were animating fire some staff said they had never seen wood burning. I said, “Go watch!” It has disappeared from their daily lives. Japanese baths used to be made by burning firewood. Now you press a button. I don’t think you can become an animator if you don’t have any experience.” His words bring us full-circle- the Harvey Weinstein episode, the chronicle of the samurai sword, no cuts … a testament to a mind as fresh and transcendental as it was during his first endeavour, a staunch refusal to bow to artificialities and be a cheap copy of the West. No more being the Walt Disney of Japan, thank you very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The celebration of the common is, then, both the hallmark and the most overlooked facet of Studio Ghibli. There is magic in a nighttime flight across a village on the wings of your friendly neighbour forest spirit, or in your everyday battle against evil scheming fascists, but there is also magic enough in the simple pleasures of a bowl of warm, home-cooked food, served at the right time to suit the right mood, in a lilting conversation with a friendly stranger. It is a befitting paradox really, the harmony of opposites brought about with poise and delicacy. For you see, animation isn’t just for dragons and demons and great spectacles. It is also a medium to narrate stories in their purest, most non-distilled state, unfettered by the boundaries of logistics and science. It is the medium of dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what is Hayao Miyazaki after all, but a dreamer?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sritama Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the most enjoyed and oft-recounted anecdotes about Hayao Miyazaki- filmmaker, manga author, animator and co-founder of Japan’s Studio Ghibli- is his tussle with Hollywood’s now infamous mascot of predatory behaviour, Harvey Weinstein. Originally printed in The Guardian, the story runs thus:</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Exploration of Ourselves</title>
      <link href="/Exploration-of-Ourselves" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploration of Ourselves" />
      <published>2019-08-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Exploration-of-Ourselves</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Exploration-of-Ourselves">&lt;p&gt;“What makes you, well, you?”- Michael Stevens, Vsauce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plato in his thesis and conceptualisation of perfect beings, explored and introduced to us the concept of Forms and how the ‘World of Forms’ is the state of perfection of every being in our world, the achievement of which may be well beyond our capabilities, owing to the limitations that bound us. The World of Forms is a utopian disposition, a state of perfection, which exists only in the mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the question which arises from it is: what kind of a being would be a perfect form of us? To understand this, we must question ourselves on our true nature and the most fundamentally important, yet unanswered question we are faced with. The question is: who are we?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re probably thinking that this is another clichéd take on who you are, or on how who someone &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; is can never be defined and yet there will be attempts to explore this subject, leading to countless innovative and daring philosophical initiatives in order to reach a comprehensive definition of our being? Oh blimey! That’s some misplaced and crooked jugular, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, you could be right, this probably is another one of those inquiries that we dive into, modelling ourselves into the Thinker’s pose, trying to figure out what defines us, what it means to &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; us. Rene Descartes once remarked, “I think, therefore I am”, posing keen albeit ambiguous arguments on the definition of a man, on the basis of his consciousness first, after which we can define our being. Sartre took his chance and played with “Cogito, ergo sum” to make his own phrase, “I am, therefore I think” and even though it may seem to be just a play of words which it is (maybe). It does, however, attempt to make more sense from Jean Paul’s version of existentialist propagation, prioritising our being over the form of mind. Note that there can be some valid arguments over the interpretations of what each of them meant when using these words in order to elucidate their thoughts, it is on us to interpret them in the way we like for the adoption of our own code to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of who we are is an intriguing one and even more so when we are to discuss one of the very interesting philosophical analogies of all time, which has been used as a plot device in several anime and movies such as &lt;em&gt;Ghost in the Shell&lt;/em&gt;. The concept is generalised and popularly known as the Ship of Theseus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premise of the argument is based on the historical and mythical artefact of the Ship used by Theseus in his journey. If the Ship of Theseus is displayed in a museum, it’s safe to assume that after some time, some parts will start rotting and will have to be replaced with new parts. Say, the rotten parts of the ship are preserved, in order to restore them when the adequate technology is available. Gradually, all parts of the original ship are replaced and they are kept in a store house. The question which arises, at this point of time, is if this Ship, the one which has been entirely replaced with new parts, is still the same ship which Theseus used for his journey?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s say that thanks to technology, we can restore the rotten parts of the ship in a proper manner. If we gradually replace the ship with its original parts, can I consider this ship to be the original one? The question being explored is how can we still call it the same ship if it has none of its original parts. If after dismantling and reorganising, what makes the ship, the same original ship used by Theseus? Are we right in the way we approach this problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to this philosophical question has been debated and deliberated upon since the time of Plato.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been several arguments which have been made in order to determine what would be the consequence of such an action. There have been propositions, made on the basis of ‘forms’, by Aristotle, in which he argues that anything is formed out of four essential causes: the formal cause (on the basis of its form), material cause (on the basis of its constituent materials), efficient cause (on the basis of its principle) and the final cause (which is indiscrete in its mannerisms but is a part of all the above causes). He argues that the causes are more or less consistent in all the cases with only one divergence in every case, and therefore it is in principle the same ship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another argument is that of the transitive property via which it relates to all the forms of the ship to be the representative of the ship itself. There is also the argument that there is loss of identity over time, and therefore, it is not the same ship anymore and can be regarded as a different ship in the frame of time. This theory, however, has been heavily criticised owing to the assumptions it makes on several fronts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem of the Ship of Theseus is an intriguing one, and questions the understanding of ourselves from within, that if we are in the same position, being replaced, what makes us the same person as before? What makes us, us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donald Davidson in his paper, &lt;em&gt;Knowing one’s own mind&lt;/em&gt;, gives an example of The Ship of Theseus. He talks about the possibility of a clone being born out of his dead body in a thunderstorm. How will his family or anyone else differentiate between the actual him, who is dead, and the clone borne out of the thunderstorm?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He argues that ‘there will be an inherent difference’ but he does not further enunciate his point. It places us under a precarious and delicate situation. Does it benefit us if we define ourselves within some definition and make sense out of ourselves? Do we need to know the difference?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The identity crisis may be a philosophically daunting question, but from a stoic’s perspective, this will not matter because the world we live in will not change with the change in me, and thus it will still be us in some way. Which goes on to say that there is no need to think about it anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, is it wrong to explore and understand ourselves better in order to develop the characteristics of self resolution within us? Maybe we will never know or maybe knowing the answer defeats the human purpose which is not to define but keep a limited form in order to open up more interpretation. Thus, knowing who we are is a small fragment of understanding our consciousness, the universe beyond us and our purpose in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next section, I will dig deeper into the realm of our nature to find clues as to what makes me so different from you on the other side of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes me, me and you, you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay Tuned!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Udayon Sen</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“What makes you, well, you?”- Michael Stevens, Vsauce.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
