<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/culture/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-04-07T07:51:30+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/culture/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Dialectic on Cultural Relativism</title>
      <link href="/A-Dialectic-on-Cultural-Relativism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Dialectic on Cultural Relativism" />
      <published>2019-03-28T01:45:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-28T01:45:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Dialectic-on-Cultural-Relativism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Dialectic-on-Cultural-Relativism">&lt;p&gt;In this kaleidoscopic world, cultural diversity is a phenomenon that is standard
to every institution and organisation. Adorned with a plethora of societies and
people dressed in almost every colour on the palette, communicating in different
languages, and following all sorts of customs and traditions, the world
certainly is a beautiful place to live in. Wherever you go, whatever you do, you
are bound to encounter differences and unfamiliarity in the form of people and
the cultures they manifest. With every nook and corner characterised by its own
uniqueness, diversity has certainly become an undeniable reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we are always taught to appreciate and embrace this diversity, we must
also be cautious of its potential to cause morally problematic situations.
Consider for instance, how would you feel if someone sticks out their tongue at
you? I am sure humiliated would be the answer. But, what if I tell you that it’s
the way people greet each other in Tibet. This would certainly change things a
little bit, however, still, the whole idea of sticking out your tongue to greet
others would seem unnatural or rather weird to you, something you’ll never dare
to do to out of fear of embarrassment, unless you’re from Tibet of course! This
becomes very troubling. With divergent practices exclusive to each culture,
often questions pertaining to the “ideal conduct” are raised. One may, in fact,
be inclined to ask “Is there an ideal way at all?” And this is where the theory
of cultural relativism steps in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans have always been very intimately linked with the culture they’re brought
up in, to the extent that their choices, tastes and behaviours resonate with the
spirit and essence of their culture. Especially with respect to actions and
demeanours, culture is believed to exercise a profound influence on the lives of
people. Therefore, it is quite natural for them to cling onto their own cultural
standards and view other cultures with suspicion. Activities like the
recreational use of cemeteries in Denmark, or the Greek practice of pretending
to spit on a married couple for good luck, or the exhuming of dead bodies by
Trojan tribes, long-ringed necks in Thailand, foot binding in China, etc. might
seem a little strange to hear at first and even impel us to pass a negative
judgement. But, according to the idea of cultural relativism, such judgements
would be wrong and irrational, as they are evaluated on the basis of our own
cultural sense and sensibilities, which fail to cover the moral codes of other
cultures. According to the theory of cultural relativism, the conception of good
and evil, right and wrong, is relative to cultures and so there can never be any
universal moral code of judgment. In other words, we can’t asses other cultures
by employing our own cultural standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This becomes immensely important, given the phenomenal rise in ethnocentrism and
intolerance. With culture assuming supremacy over our lives in governing our
views and judgements, often acceptance of others becomes a little challenging.
In the face of such strict cultural conditioning, it would seem the theory of
cultural relativism is our only way out to advance towards a world characterised
by harmony and brotherhood. This seems to make cultural relativism an impeccable
theory. But is it so?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider a world with strict cultural relativism. Here, there shall be no
cross-cultural judgements; humanity would function on the principle of
tolerance, almost to the extent that everything would be approved. All cultures,
with their boons and banes, would be embraced blindly, without any reservation.
As a result, if a culture commands its male members to rape women as a
traditional custom, then cultural relativism would be able to do very little
about it. And this is where the theory takes a problematic turn. Blind
acceptance of practices paves way for certain evil tendencies to proliferate,
and since no culture is immune to defects, the theory would essentially place
the entire humanity under a grave threat. For example, women in parts of Africa
are robbed of sexual pleasure by the age-old barbaric custom of female
circumcision. But, because of cultural relativism, it becomes almost impossible
to eradicate this ill practice. While the theory does leave some scope for
intra-cultural judgements, very seldom are people seen raising voices of dissent
against their own cultures, given it is something that pulsates through their
veins. Like any other theory, cultural relativism is not a viable solution for
all situations. However, before rejecting the theory completely, it’s also
important to appreciate certain aspects of it, so that one can find a more
nuanced version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution here could be perhaps to design a new relativism altogether, one
which is based on respect, not just for the culture as a whole, but also for
individual subjects belonging to the culture. This new relativism can have a
separate mechanism to address the issues of members, who get victimised in the
name of cultural customs. With people’s participation (and not interference) in
a peaceful, rational dialogue, the seeds of change can be sown in any culture to
do away with the inherent ferocity in it. Whatever be the case, it is difficult
to deny that cultural relativism promotes an atmosphere of tolerance and amity.
By eliminating the views of dogmatism surrounding one’s culture, it makes a
person more grounded and open to greater acceptance by others. Further, it
strengthens the intercultural relationships and builds a world based on the
principles of universal brotherhood. With communities being able to understand
and empathise with each other, the world certainly becomes a better place. Of
course, cultural relativism like any theory is harmful at its logical extreme,
but so long as it is caveated with a spirit of earnest dialogue, critique, and
individual respect, it works as a theory that makes a better world.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In this kaleidoscopic world, cultural diversity is a phenomenon that is standard to every institution and organisation. Adorned with a plethora of societies and people dressed in almost every colour on the palette, communicating in different languages, and following all sorts of customs and traditions, the world certainly is a beautiful place to live in. Wherever you go, whatever you do, you are bound to encounter differences and unfamiliarity in the form of people and the cultures they manifest. With every nook and corner characterised by its own uniqueness, diversity has certainly become an undeniable reality. While we are always taught to appreciate and embrace this diversity, we must also be cautious of its potential to cause morally problematic situations. Consider for instance, how would you feel if someone sticks out their tongue at you? I am sure humiliated would be the answer. But, what if I tell you that it’s the way people greet each other in Tibet. This would certainly change things a little bit, however, still, the whole idea of sticking out your tongue to greet others would seem unnatural or rather weird to you, something you’ll never dare to do to out of fear of embarrassment, unless you’re from Tibet of course! This becomes very troubling. With divergent practices exclusive to each culture, often questions pertaining to the “ideal conduct” are raised. One may, in fact, be inclined to ask “Is there an ideal way at all?” And this is where the theory of cultural relativism steps in. Humans have always been very intimately linked with the culture they’re brought up in, to the extent that their choices, tastes and behaviours resonate with the spirit and essence of their culture. Especially with respect to actions and demeanours, culture is believed to exercise a profound influence on the lives of people. Therefore, it is quite natural for them to cling onto their own cultural standards and view other cultures with suspicion. Activities like the recreational use of cemeteries in Denmark, or the Greek practice of pretending to spit on a married couple for good luck, or the exhuming of dead bodies by Trojan tribes, long-ringed necks in Thailand, foot binding in China, etc. might seem a little strange to hear at first and even impel us to pass a negative judgement. But, according to the idea of cultural relativism, such judgements would be wrong and irrational, as they are evaluated on the basis of our own cultural sense and sensibilities, which fail to cover the moral codes of other cultures. According to the theory of cultural relativism, the conception of good and evil, right and wrong, is relative to cultures and so there can never be any universal moral code of judgment. In other words, we can’t asses other cultures by employing our own cultural standards. This becomes immensely important, given the phenomenal rise in ethnocentrism and intolerance. With culture assuming supremacy over our lives in governing our views and judgements, often acceptance of others becomes a little challenging. In the face of such strict cultural conditioning, it would seem the theory of cultural relativism is our only way out to advance towards a world characterised by harmony and brotherhood. This seems to make cultural relativism an impeccable theory. But is it so? Consider a world with strict cultural relativism. Here, there shall be no cross-cultural judgements; humanity would function on the principle of tolerance, almost to the extent that everything would be approved. All cultures, with their boons and banes, would be embraced blindly, without any reservation. As a result, if a culture commands its male members to rape women as a traditional custom, then cultural relativism would be able to do very little about it. And this is where the theory takes a problematic turn. Blind acceptance of practices paves way for certain evil tendencies to proliferate, and since no culture is immune to defects, the theory would essentially place the entire humanity under a grave threat. For example, women in parts of Africa are robbed of sexual pleasure by the age-old barbaric custom of female circumcision. But, because of cultural relativism, it becomes almost impossible to eradicate this ill practice. While the theory does leave some scope for intra-cultural judgements, very seldom are people seen raising voices of dissent against their own cultures, given it is something that pulsates through their veins. Like any other theory, cultural relativism is not a viable solution for all situations. However, before rejecting the theory completely, it’s also important to appreciate certain aspects of it, so that one can find a more nuanced version. The solution here could be perhaps to design a new relativism altogether, one which is based on respect, not just for the culture as a whole, but also for individual subjects belonging to the culture. This new relativism can have a separate mechanism to address the issues of members, who get victimised in the name of cultural customs. With people’s participation (and not interference) in a peaceful, rational dialogue, the seeds of change can be sown in any culture to do away with the inherent ferocity in it. Whatever be the case, it is difficult to deny that cultural relativism promotes an atmosphere of tolerance and amity. By eliminating the views of dogmatism surrounding one’s culture, it makes a person more grounded and open to greater acceptance by others. Further, it strengthens the intercultural relationships and builds a world based on the principles of universal brotherhood. With communities being able to understand and empathise with each other, the world certainly becomes a better place. Of course, cultural relativism like any theory is harmful at its logical extreme, but so long as it is caveated with a spirit of earnest dialogue, critique, and individual respect, it works as a theory that makes a better world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">And the Academy Award goes to…Mexico?</title>
      <link href="/Academy-Award-Mexico" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="And the Academy Award goes to…Mexico?" />
      <published>2019-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Academy-Award-Mexico</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Academy-Award-Mexico">&lt;p&gt;I love the Oscars. I acknowledge this without a hint of shame and I’m more than happy to admit it. With the television ratings slumping to 26.6 million in 2018 (a 39% decrease from 2014), and remaining below 30 million for this year’s broadcast, it’s safe to say that I am part of a rare breed – a young person still interested in the Academy Awards. However, the caveat is that I watch the show ‘almost completely ironically’. Every year for the past four years, myself and another film buff nit-pick the entirety of the marathon show. We do have a few reasons for it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, to make the near 240-minute programme bearable, you have to do something a bit more exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, if you think that the Academy Awards are merely a ‘celebration of cinematic excellence’, then you are truly mistaken. There are many different film festivals and ceremonies that take place during the awards season, and there is definitely a debate to be had over which is the most prestigious or important. Whether the Oscars will admit it or not, they feast on the grand spectacle as much as, or perhaps even more than, simply rewarding genuine talent. From #oscarssowhite, to &lt;em&gt;La La Land&lt;/em&gt; winning by mistake, to this year’s host debacle. It is these controversies which make people watch the Oscars. So, by critiquing it, we subconsciously embrace the farce and fanfare of the show. Thus, we make the whole experience of watching it far more enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly and finally, predicting the Oscars is an artform and each year we have just one opportunity to test our skills. I highly recommend Insider’s Youtube Video: “Are the Oscars Rigged?” if you’ve never thought about the logistics of winning Best Picture, or any Academy Award for that matter. To state the obvious, it doesn’t just simply happen on merit. There are tried and tested formulas on how the system works, with each critic or film buff having their own method of guessing the winners. As the great film critic Roger Ebert wrote in 2005:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Shhhhhh. Don’t tell a soul. Close Oscar-watchers (and Academy insiders) know that what you are about to read is true but few like to talk about these things. When it comes to picking Oscar winners, you can study the statistics of the past Oscars in search of patterns and clues, but there are certain influential paradigms that defy and transcend conventional statistical analysis.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He goes on to give a few examples, all of which are worth a read, but my favourite is definitely the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;Having a Period&lt;/strong&gt;: The showiest way to flaunt your budget (besides spending it on astronomical marquee names) is to set your movie in the past, so you can see all the departments – costumes, production design, cinematography, makeup – working hard all the time. It’s astonishing, but the only Best Picture winners in the last 20 years to be set in contemporary times (real or fantasy) were “Rain Man,” “The Silence of the Lambs,” and “American Beauty” – which are also among the few that weren’t historical biographies.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you know (or think you know) the formula, guessing all of the 24 awards is simple…or so it seems. As Ebert notes, “&lt;em&gt;count on at least one surprise, off-the-wall winner&lt;/em&gt;”, and in my experience it is not usually the obscure categories that trip you up, usually it is one of the big ones, such as Best Supporting Actor/Actress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cynic might say that by watching the Oscars, in this manner, we are just making a mockery of the Academy Awards; and, despite its over-exuberance, by ridiculing the show we are also ridiculing the pieces of art that the show is rewarding. Now, I do partially agree with this; the Oscars will, for a lot of people, always be the watermark of good cinema. Moreover, in recent years the Oscars have helped promote smaller indie films that without the Best Picture nomination or win, would never have achieved such success. Indeed, in a world where five films made over US$1 billion in 2018, the past six Best Picture Winners all grossed under US$100 million in the United States. To cite some prime examples, films such as &lt;em&gt;Birdman&lt;/em&gt; (2014) and the &lt;em&gt;Shape of Water&lt;/em&gt; (2017) would never have gotten the exposure that they did, without the Academy Awards, or more specifically, the Academy’s reputation as representing prestigious cinema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said earlier that I watch the Oscars “almost completely ironically” and it is time to address the ‘almost’ part of that statement. There is one part of the annual broadcast that I do take seriously, namely the meteoric rise of ‘New Mexican Cinema’ that surely would have gone largely unnoticed by the general public, but for the Oscars. Now, if you’re thinking, “I am an average film-goer, and I have literally no idea what New Mexican Cinema is”, that’s fine. In fact, I think this is the beauty of this movement; it has quietly infiltrated Hollywood, and apart from film buffs and industry experts, nobody was even aware it was happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I deliberately listed the examples of &lt;em&gt;Birdman&lt;/em&gt; (2014) and the &lt;em&gt;Shape of Water&lt;/em&gt; (2017) earlier, and both of these have Mexican directors: Alejandro González Iñárritu and Guillermo Del Toro, who along with Alfonso Cuarón make ‘Los Tres Amigos’, the leading lights of the second wave of this movement. Incredibly, between the three of them they have won five of the past six Academy Awards for Best Director. They have an astonishing ten Academy Awards between them and show no signs of slowing down. Yet, perhaps what is more impressive is how they have been able to blend this critical success with commercial “Hollywood” box office hits. Remember, these are the very same directors that made &lt;em&gt;Hellboy&lt;/em&gt; (2004), &lt;em&gt;Pacific Rim&lt;/em&gt; (2013), &lt;em&gt;Children of Men&lt;/em&gt; (2006), &lt;em&gt;The Revenant&lt;/em&gt; (2015) and &lt;em&gt;*Harry Potter&lt;/em&gt; and the Prisoner of Azkaban* (2004). Yet, the three have stayed true to their roots as well. They continue to make Spanish language films, with the best and most recent example being Cuarón’s &lt;em&gt;Roma&lt;/em&gt; (2018), winner of three Oscars this year and, in my opinion, robbed of Best Picture. It is available to view on Netflix, and whilst a black and white Spanish language drama about a maid for a middle-class Mexican family might not be everybody’s cup of tea, it is definitely my favourite film of the past few months and worth a watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as a Spanish and Portuguese student, foreign language films have always been more accessible to me than they might be for the average viewer. I know that subtitles can be a little unpalatable for some people, and it is usually easier to relate to something if you have shared culture or understanding. That said, despite all I may critique about the Oscars, they have actually taken note of the genuine movement of foreign cinematic talent that has hijacked the awards over the past few years. By recognising these directors, it validates the movement as a whole, bringing respect and recognition from a global audience. Films such as &lt;em&gt;Y tu Mamá También&lt;/em&gt; (2001), &lt;em&gt;El Laberinto del Fauno&lt;/em&gt; (2006) and &lt;em&gt;Amores Perros&lt;/em&gt; (2001) were all nominated for Oscars in various categories; they were just the first indication of what was to come. Moreover, it is not just directors that are receiving recognition. The cinematographer Emmanuel Lubezki won Best Achievement in Cinematography, three years running from 2013 to 2015, and actors such as Gael García Bernal (&lt;em&gt;Coco&lt;/em&gt;, 2017) and Diego Luna (&lt;em&gt;Rogue One&lt;/em&gt;, 2016) are stepping into the spotlight of Western cinema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I do make fun of the Academy, perhaps a little too much. However, I am somewhat part of the snobbery that make the Oscars what it is; I love the inside jokes, the awards scandals, the predicting of formulas. Even if I critique the ridiculous nature of it, that in and of itself just contributes to the grand annual spectacle. With all the said, what brings me back to the Academy is the small belief that it still does do what it should do; reward some of the best cinema that the world has to offer. And maybe the success of New Mexican Cinema is a sign that the Academy is getting back on track.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Daniel Harris</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I love the Oscars. I acknowledge this without a hint of shame and I’m more than happy to admit it. With the television ratings slumping to 26.6 million in 2018 (a 39% decrease from 2014), and remaining below 30 million for this year’s broadcast, it’s safe to say that I am part of a rare breed – a young person still interested in the Academy Awards. However, the caveat is that I watch the show ‘almost completely ironically’. Every year for the past four years, myself and another film buff nit-pick the entirety of the marathon show. We do have a few reasons for it:</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The ‘Bhakt’ and The Bhakti</title>
      <link href="/The-Bhakt-and-The-Bhakti" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The ‘Bhakt’ and The Bhakti" />
      <published>2019-03-21T11:01:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-21T11:01:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Bhakt-and-The-Bhakti</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Bhakt-and-The-Bhakti">&lt;p&gt;There comes a time in history when a nation as a whole needs to stop, take a
step back, reflect and re-examine its assumptions and perceptions about
language. We forget the value that words hold. It doesn’t cross our minds when
they are too cheap to type, tweet, post, and share. We quite wilfully forget the
degree of social investment that was poured into empowering the different
factions and sections of the world population with literacy, technology, and
vast infrastructure. Was it endowed upon us so that we could hurl abuses at each
other using these mediums or platforms of communication?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent times, the public discourse in India has witnessed one of the greatest
concepts of our civilisation turn into a meaningless word, an insult, even.
However, the context in which this has happened has been within a debate about
‘civility’ on the internet. Quite ironic as one might say. Yet it has failed to
realise how easily it has turned something as sacred and pious an idea as
‘bhakti’ into a currency of political, electoral and communal invective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complete ease with which the word ‘bhakt’ (devotee) is being hurled around,
like a derogatory term, an abuse, should be seen as a warning by us. It depicts
the extent to which our imagination, our thought process, has been colonised. It
portrays how distant we’ve become from our deeply spiritual, life-affirming and
non-violent sensibilities. After all, &lt;em&gt;‘bhakti’&lt;/em&gt;(devotion) is not just some
‘trait’ of Indian culture that needs to be protected and fought over like some
religious symbol that might offend some group or the other. It goes beyond that.
It is way deeper than that. It is at the very core of what it means to be human,
and what it means to live and not just exist. Bhakti means to live for love in
the face of formidable political, economic and social challenges. Only when we
acknowledge the widespread existence of its opposite, the value of ‘bhakti’ will
be understood. The opposite is lovelessness. This is a monster. If you are
privileged enough to not have encountered it yet, thank your stars. Even if you
have not experienced it personally, it does exist in this brutal, so-called
‘modern’ chaotic world where violence penetrates every sphere of society and
spares none.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue, of course, lies in the fact that too often we perceive lovelessness
as a personal problem. But we forget that it is also a systemic social and
cultural failure. We need to ask ourselves: if at all today’s media environment
with its enormous miasma of stories, images, and words, teaches us to cultivate
love, whether human, non-human, divine, call it what you will. Sadly, it does
not. What the media and the educational system mostly has to offer primarily
centres around being efficient (or inefficient). These platforms are formed on
the basis of the principle of lovelessness by managers, professors, narcissists
and consumers―mutually adjusting self-interests, nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet, in this land, in this great civilisation called India, there still is a
better way to live. And this, the people have been doing, for several centuries
now, against the greatest odds. India’s religiosity, its culture of ‘bhakti’ has
been fighting a relentless battle for the idea of love in ways that the scholars
of today can barely even decipher, let alone understand. After all, what do you
do when the facade of emptiness stares you down coldly, almost like a rapacious
army circling your house or a tyrannical boss stabbing out your sense of worth?
You pray. What do you do, but sing your soul out to the different manifestations
of the divine, to Lord Rama, to Jesus, to Allah or whoever it is who you think
is listening to your faint whispers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of this sense of desperation, this feeling of
urgency, this flight from a disastrous world beyond our control to a moment of
agency when we can say, I will still see You, I will still feel love, and I will
be okay. When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of the voice of my Guru, and the
philosophy of Mahatma Gandhi—who through the “love force” of peaceful agitation
reversed centuries of colonisation. When I think of bhakti, I think of the
profound truth hidden in the anonymity of these words, which for a moment make a
friendship between you and me that for a gives us the hope that language in its
decency and communion, in its &lt;em&gt;bhaava&lt;/em&gt; (emotion), will one day become something
more real and meaningful than any of our policies, and manifestos, and op-eds
can ever be. The late modern world with its refined, idealistic and now
contorted words like pluralism and secularism can only pitter-patter around the
idea of ‘bhakti’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bhakti is a very precious word, it simply &lt;strong&gt;CANNOT&lt;/strong&gt; be denigrated. Far from
mocking bhakti, what we really ought to be cultivating now, here in the
wilderness of the digital spaces in which we live and seethe, is a little more
bhakti in practice too; perhaps a sense of bhakti towards language itself. After
all, just a few generations ago our elders learned to write with a finger
tracing imperishable symbols into hot sand. Would they have found it so easy to
trivialise language itself the way we do today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Censoring words and ideas is a meaningless solution. However, thinking of this
differently, resolving to grow in understanding, kindness, and love–through
language–is the way civilisation can restore itself in its wild new frontiers
too. I really hope therefore that all those in India who think ‘bhakt’ is some
primitive mindset or an insult will seriously rethink their assumptions. You
need to take it as a surrender of what you might feel is a principled resistance
against a political figure or his boisterous fans. You need to do better with
your criticism, and perhaps yourself.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There comes a time in history when a nation as a whole needs to stop, take a step back, reflect and re-examine its assumptions and perceptions about language. We forget the value that words hold. It doesn’t cross our minds when they are too cheap to type, tweet, post, and share. We quite wilfully forget the degree of social investment that was poured into empowering the different factions and sections of the world population with literacy, technology, and vast infrastructure. Was it endowed upon us so that we could hurl abuses at each other using these mediums or platforms of communication? In recent times, the public discourse in India has witnessed one of the greatest concepts of our civilisation turn into a meaningless word, an insult, even. However, the context in which this has happened has been within a debate about ‘civility’ on the internet. Quite ironic as one might say. Yet it has failed to realise how easily it has turned something as sacred and pious an idea as ‘bhakti’ into a currency of political, electoral and communal invective. The complete ease with which the word ‘bhakt’ (devotee) is being hurled around, like a derogatory term, an abuse, should be seen as a warning by us. It depicts the extent to which our imagination, our thought process, has been colonised. It portrays how distant we’ve become from our deeply spiritual, life-affirming and non-violent sensibilities. After all, ‘bhakti’(devotion) is not just some ‘trait’ of Indian culture that needs to be protected and fought over like some religious symbol that might offend some group or the other. It goes beyond that. It is way deeper than that. It is at the very core of what it means to be human, and what it means to live and not just exist. Bhakti means to live for love in the face of formidable political, economic and social challenges. Only when we acknowledge the widespread existence of its opposite, the value of ‘bhakti’ will be understood. The opposite is lovelessness. This is a monster. If you are privileged enough to not have encountered it yet, thank your stars. Even if you have not experienced it personally, it does exist in this brutal, so-called ‘modern’ chaotic world where violence penetrates every sphere of society and spares none. The issue, of course, lies in the fact that too often we perceive lovelessness as a personal problem. But we forget that it is also a systemic social and cultural failure. We need to ask ourselves: if at all today’s media environment with its enormous miasma of stories, images, and words, teaches us to cultivate love, whether human, non-human, divine, call it what you will. Sadly, it does not. What the media and the educational system mostly has to offer primarily centres around being efficient (or inefficient). These platforms are formed on the basis of the principle of lovelessness by managers, professors, narcissists and consumers―mutually adjusting self-interests, nothing more. And yet, in this land, in this great civilisation called India, there still is a better way to live. And this, the people have been doing, for several centuries now, against the greatest odds. India’s religiosity, its culture of ‘bhakti’ has been fighting a relentless battle for the idea of love in ways that the scholars of today can barely even decipher, let alone understand. After all, what do you do when the facade of emptiness stares you down coldly, almost like a rapacious army circling your house or a tyrannical boss stabbing out your sense of worth? You pray. What do you do, but sing your soul out to the different manifestations of the divine, to Lord Rama, to Jesus, to Allah or whoever it is who you think is listening to your faint whispers? When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of this sense of desperation, this feeling of urgency, this flight from a disastrous world beyond our control to a moment of agency when we can say, I will still see You, I will still feel love, and I will be okay. When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of the voice of my Guru, and the philosophy of Mahatma Gandhi—who through the “love force” of peaceful agitation reversed centuries of colonisation. When I think of bhakti, I think of the profound truth hidden in the anonymity of these words, which for a moment make a friendship between you and me that for a gives us the hope that language in its decency and communion, in its bhaava (emotion), will one day become something more real and meaningful than any of our policies, and manifestos, and op-eds can ever be. The late modern world with its refined, idealistic and now contorted words like pluralism and secularism can only pitter-patter around the idea of ‘bhakti’. Bhakti is a very precious word, it simply CANNOT be denigrated. Far from mocking bhakti, what we really ought to be cultivating now, here in the wilderness of the digital spaces in which we live and seethe, is a little more bhakti in practice too; perhaps a sense of bhakti towards language itself. After all, just a few generations ago our elders learned to write with a finger tracing imperishable symbols into hot sand. Would they have found it so easy to trivialise language itself the way we do today? Censoring words and ideas is a meaningless solution. However, thinking of this differently, resolving to grow in understanding, kindness, and love–through language–is the way civilisation can restore itself in its wild new frontiers too. I really hope therefore that all those in India who think ‘bhakt’ is some primitive mindset or an insult will seriously rethink their assumptions. You need to take it as a surrender of what you might feel is a principled resistance against a political figure or his boisterous fans. You need to do better with your criticism, and perhaps yourself.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Picture of Dorian Gray – Final Thoughts from the Composer’s Desk</title>
      <link href="/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray-2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Picture of Dorian Gray – Final Thoughts from the Composer’s Desk" />
      <published>2019-03-07T03:30:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-07T03:30:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray-2</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray-2">&lt;p&gt;It strikes me that whenever I announced to people that I had set about writing
an opera, I never actually received that reaction I expected. I was certain I’d
be met with derision – “What makes you think YOU can write one, Bowes?” Up to
the point that I began working on &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt;, I had only really written choral
music and a few songs. My only forays into purely instrumental music consisted
of a piano quintet I concocted for my A-level coursework, an arrangement of a
school song (&lt;em&gt;Bedford by the River&lt;/em&gt; – won a cash prize for it, to be fair), and
a frankly ridiculous setting of the &lt;em&gt;Requiem Mass&lt;/em&gt;, which I hope will never be
performed in its current state. Yet, the reaction, especially when I told
everyone of the subject-matter of this opera, Wilde’s seminal novella &lt;em&gt;The
Picture of Dorian Gray&lt;/em&gt;, was unanimously positive. A few more knowledgeable
friends asked whether it had been done before, to which I ask: how many versions
of &lt;em&gt;Faust&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Romeo and Juliet&lt;/em&gt; are there? Answer: frankly too many, not that I
wouldn’t consider doing a &lt;em&gt;Faust&lt;/em&gt;-related one at some point – indeed, one can
see &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt; itself as a Faustian tale. Nevertheless, the reception to the idea
was that I ought to push on, and so I did. Thus, I have reached the end of the
compositional process (barring edits after the fact) and I have more than enough
time to sit and worry about the show. Which I do – all too often, in fact. And
which also led me to write this pair of articles for &lt;em&gt;The Pangean&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray&quot;&gt;last
article&lt;/a&gt;, I had reflected on
the music of the first Act, but I came to realize after its publication that I
had failed to actually discuss compositional process, which I suppose is far
more interesting than simply taking you, arm-in-arm, on a promenade through what
you will, in just a matter of months, be able to hear for yourself. Therefore,
while I will still move chronologically through the final Act, wouldn’t you
rather hear about how I did the composing, rather than what composing I did?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all honesty, I have not been composing for long enough to have entirely
unified a process. Different pieces require different things from me. Some
pieces can go from just the little scribblings in a notebook straight into my
computer, where I will transform them from the idea into an actual functioning
piece. Others, such as the song-cycle I am currently working on, &lt;em&gt;Crow&lt;/em&gt;, needed
to be mapped out in full-score on paper first, and in ink – it felt particularly
necessary for &lt;em&gt;Crow&lt;/em&gt;, as it lent a sparseness to the writing that was very
helpful (although, I must say that it has been an absolute b*tch to write up on
my computer.) These are the two ends of a sliding scale upon which &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt; sat
somewhere in the middle. Or, in fact, off of either end. Some scenes, such as
the theatre scene in Act One went straight from my brain into the computer, as
the nature of the scurrying accompaniment made it a real bore to hand-write,
without the joy of copy-and-paste and editing after the fact. Others, such as
the entire last scene, were almost entirely drafted on paper first and then
written up – although I admit that at least part of the reason for hand-writing
the entire last scene was that my laptop was on the blink and I was 3,000 miles
from home. But, it keeps the romantic notion of the composer scribbling away
with pen and ink alive, so I’ve got to keep up appearances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so we come to the last Act. Although much of this was drafted last, the
prelude to the first scene was, in fact, finished long before most of Act One,
as it gave me, frankly, a nice compositional break from the Prologue. My
librettist Jamie and I had to come up with some way to symbolise several years
of debauchery that the audience missed by swanning out for their interval drinks
in the bar. I assume that the debauched years will be lived through in the minds
of our performers during this interval; it would be nicely ‘method’ of them. But
how to illustrate it in music? I gave the audience a brief, slow moment in which
to mourn Basil and Sybil, both brutally killed at the end of the first Act,
before setting about the musical debauchery. Decadence and wild abandon are
often achieved in music through the use of rowdy dances. Ravel was a master of
this, especially in the finale of &lt;em&gt;La Valse&lt;/em&gt;, or consider Stravinsky’s &lt;em&gt;Rite of
Spring&lt;/em&gt; – the poor girl dances herself to death at the end. But, as those of you
who know me can testify, I am no dancer. So how should I go after the same
effects? It’s actually fairly obvious: the thing that makes a dance a dance is
the rhythm, with which I have very little issue (getting the legs to do what
they’re told on the other hand…). Therefore, I took one of the rhythmic motifs
that described the den of iniquity that was the theatre in Act One, and laid it
underneath a pulsating Yoruba-inspired cross-rhythm from a pair of drums to
create a heady mix of open fifths and driving rhythms that symbolises Dorian’s
embracing of Harry’s lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the segue into the first scene, which itself takes place in an opium
den, takes its influences from Debussy’s use of the quartal harmony to lend an
air of intentionally fake orientalism, with added xylophonic twinkling. This is
undercut by the following chorus ‘number’ – Dorian, his mind full of a romantic
poems, hallucinates that the other patrons of this establishment all begin
singing, in French, about the beauty of Venice, at odds with both the Chinese-y
music of the den, as well as with the general dinginess of London at the end of
the 19th century. And, as a unifying feature of this scene, the music is still
Debussy-inspired. With a French poem, especially by a poet such as Théophile
Gautier, one can’t not look to Debussy, I feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Sur une gamme chromatique, &lt;br /&gt;

Le sein de perles ruisselant, &lt;br /&gt;

La Vénus de l’Adriatique, &lt;br /&gt;

Sort de l’eau son corps rose et blanc.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remainder of the first scene is dominated by the one appearance of Sybil’s
brother James, who rages like a bull in a china-shop while attempting to pursue
Dorian. His aria was one for which I did the most planning – James had to be
able to arrive on the scene and make enough of an impact to make him feel like a
threat for the remainder of the show, despite not having been seen in the
previous acts. Thus, he demanded a full-on show-stopper of an aria. What makes
music sound angry? It’s much the same as that which makes music sound debauched,
as both violent anger and wild abandon stray from the comfortable emotional
spectrum. Thus, I focused on rhythm again. I wrote out his words, some of the
most violent I have read in Wilde, and began to speak them to myself over and
over again. Individual lines became something of a rapid chant, savagely
thumping away, until I was able to write down specific rhythms I had associated
with them. The aria became very caballetic, with compound rhythms driving
underneath the singer’s howling. And then I worked out the melody. It’s not
greatly complicated, just arpeggiating through the chords underneath. Far more
important is the tessitura: James was, in my head, a Bass, albeit one with a
very solid top range, and this aria is one that exploits it, as I push the
singer to the upper extreme, bellowing away in righteous fury, while the
orchestra churns away tempestuously around him, until he disappears into the
night to hunt his sister’s ‘killer’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second scene, the last scene to be written, and not appearing in the
novella, we return to Lord Henry’s house. Yet the house has a much darker aspect
than when we had seen it in the first Act. For one thing, it is about three in
the morning. But, more importantly, Henry’s wife has made a decision that will
cast a pall on the man for the rest of the show. To give a sense of this
foreboding, I searched back through her brief appearance in Act One for melodies
associated with Lady Victoria, finally picking the languorous downwardly
meandering tune she uses to describe her enjoyment of pianists to manipulate
into a mournful prelude to the scene, descending through the strings in a canon,
before a quote from Tchaikovsky’s &lt;em&gt;Eugene Onegin&lt;/em&gt; foreshadows the fateful letter
that she has written for Harry. Harry’s music, on the other hand, is much
brighter and jolly – he’s drunk, and he sings in a drunkenly twisted patter,
while Victoria drums up the courage to tell him she is leaving. When she finally
pours forth all her upset, we move from twisted patter into a driving
baroque-esque raging, reminiscent of Handel’s more overtly furious moments, most
particularly Dejanira’s aria, &lt;em&gt;Where Shall I Fly&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;Hercules,&lt;/em&gt; in which the
overwrought Dejanira is driven mad by guilt, having caused the death of her
god-like husband. But, for me, there was a deeper meaning behind the baroque
façade that I had Victoria put up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jamie and I discussed this scene at great length, deliberating over how to stop
Victoria from seeming like a shrewish, nagging wife, and more like the bright,
free woman she ought to be. Neither of us understand women (or, in my case,
people in general) as well as we’d like to think, I suspect, but I truly believe
we have drawn here a very human event: Victoria pretends, in her baroque raging,
that her divorce is for all sorts of moral and societal reasons, citing Harry’s
insalubrious behaviour as more than enough reason for her to leave him. Yet, she
ultimately confesses that this is a pretence. She married him because that
behaviour, fuelled as it was by his Byronic intelligence, was highly attractive.
However, he has now ceased being Byronic, and is simply being indulgent and
destructive whilst ignoring her as a wife. All the romance has gone from his
behaviour. It’s a far more interesting character that Jamie has drawn through
this dichotomy than what could have been there: a shrew reprimanding a wastrel
for his wastefulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We finally return to Dorian, still suffering shock from his encounter with James
Vane, on retreat in the country. We find him alone in the grounds of the Duchess
of Monmouth’s house, musing on the events of the previous few days. For this
scene, we took full advantage of the non-linear storytelling we had introduced
with the appearance of Sybil at the end of Act One. There is, in Wilde’s
original, a scintillating scene of witty repartee between Harry and several
other pillars of society after a dinner hosted by the Duchess. However, in
streamlining the show, we feared we would lose this in order to focus more
clearly on Dorian himself. That is, we feared until one of us realised we could
just do another pseudo-flashback, as Dorian recalls the events of the previous
evening. Therefore, we have another moment of lighthearted patter from Harry,
who is joined by the chorus – I felt I was channelling all of my love for &lt;em&gt;Die
Fledermaus&lt;/em&gt; or even the great Victorian partnership of Gilbert and Sullivan,
trying to create some feeling of effervescence in the midst of the terror that
is consuming Dorian here. This continues into the next big chorus moment, after
the flashback, when these society lords and ladies enter the field in which
Dorian has been sitting in order to go shooting, singing words by Rudyard
Kipling, from his &lt;em&gt;Verses on Games&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Peace upon Earth, Goodwill to men” &lt;br /&gt;

So greet we Christmas Day! &lt;br /&gt;

Oh, Christian, load your gun and then &lt;br /&gt;

Oh, Christian, out and slay.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This joyful entrance is set to a reharmonisation of Sullivan’s tune Noel, known
to most of us as &lt;em&gt;It Came Upon A Midnight Clear.&lt;/em&gt; At the same time, something of
RVW’s &lt;em&gt;Antiphon&lt;/em&gt; or Bruckner’s &lt;em&gt;Te Deum&lt;/em&gt; was never far from my mind, in terms of
the orchestration. It may have become obvious to you that I am always thinking
of other things to relate my music to. It is a problem I run into occasionally –
am I being influenced, which is fine: music does not exist in a vacuum; or am I
simply copying? Quoting things is fine, especially in such a long work as this
(there are many quotes in &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt;, most of which I have not pointed out, but
all of which make me irrationally, self-indulgently happy), but copying is not
just plagiaristic but, personally, pointless – even if my original thought, at
the inception of this opera, was that “I wish Britten had written a Dorian
Gray.” Hopefully, my style has become distinct enough from just “a kid copying
Britten”. Hopefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving on, there is so much to point to in the final scene. Therefore, I will
keep my comments limited to two particular moments. In this last scene, we see
Dorian and Harry finally alone in Dorian’s living room. Dorian is by now
incredibly stressed – Vane hunted him all the way to the Duchess’ estate, and,
in trying to creep up on him, was shot by one of the Lords on their morning
shoot – which Dorian took as a terribly ill omen. Returning to London, Harry has
been keeping tabs on his young protégé, making sure the fear and stress doesn’t
get to him. Therefore, he ups the levels of inane babble. The treatment of his
final moment of inane babble is possibly one of my favourite bits of composition
I’ve done to date. I say my composition, but actually, Harry’s last aria is
founded entirely upon a piece by Alexander Scriabin, who, although I mention him
very infrequently, is one of my favourite composers, if only for his absolutely
insane theories about the end of the world (and attempts to bring said end
about) and his pretence at having synaesthesia, which he tried to use to create
a light-organ or ‘&lt;em&gt;clavier à lumières&lt;/em&gt;’ with which to compose for the
colour-spectrum―which is, I think you’ll agree, fairly bonkers. Nevertheless, I
got it into my head to use this moment at the end of the piece to highlight
musically a big change in Dorian: before we meet Dorian in the Prologue, we hear
him from offstage, playing a snippet from Schumann’s &lt;em&gt;Waldszenen&lt;/em&gt;, a very calm,
nature-themed work for the piano – a piece of innocence, if you will. But now,
at the end of the evening, many years later for the two remaining characters,
Dorian returns to the piano to ignore Harry’s inanities, and plays Scriabin’s
&lt;em&gt;Nocturne&lt;/em&gt; for the left hand. This highlights a change in Dorian in several
ways. Firstly, it is significantly more technically and harmonically challenging
than the Schumann, in part because it is specifically for the left hand, but
also because of Scriabin’s tense, dense harmonic language, which is
significantly more discordant and much less innocent than Schumann’s. Moreover,
Schumann published &lt;em&gt;Waldszenen&lt;/em&gt; in 1849, whereas the &lt;em&gt;Nocturne&lt;/em&gt; was composed in
1894; there is nearly half a century of musical development, pushing the
boundaries of tonality and taste, between the two, indicative of the passage of
time within the show, perhaps, and certainly indicative again of the corruption
of Dorian’s innocence over that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we come to the grand collapse that is the ending. I shan’t spoil the
last few pages by discussing exactly how the show closes, because that would
undoubtedly be a travesty. What I would like to discuss is the allegorical use
of the story of &lt;em&gt;Belshazzar&lt;/em&gt; in the closing moments. In my first plan of the
end, I had refused the idea of an off-stage chorus as too ‘operatic’ for an
intimate close to this show, much too close to the end of &lt;em&gt;Don Giovanni&lt;/em&gt; or the
countless other shows that copied that dramatic close, with the lecher dragged
into hell by an immaterial chorus. However, one chat with Jamie transformed my
conception entirely: I was not overly keen on my first draft’s ending, and he
wrote some new words to close the show – they were splendid. In a tangent to
Dorian’s flashback or his vision of Sybil, Jamie brought up an off-stage chorus,
symbolic perhaps of Dorian’s frantic brain or of heavenly judgement (I’m
inclined to think one particular way, but others may disagree), singing the
&lt;em&gt;“writing on the wall”&lt;/em&gt; that appeared at &lt;em&gt;Belshazzar’s Feast&lt;/em&gt;: “&lt;em&gt;Mene Mene Tekel
Upharsin&lt;/em&gt;” or, as Jamie put it, “&lt;em&gt;Thou art in the balances, and art found
wanting.&lt;/em&gt;” Dorian, in his desperate bid to redeem himself after his years of
immorality, cannot help but hear these words, directly paralleling the
condemnation that is his own portrait hanging upon the wall. Thus, in
composition, I had to avoid not just the links to Don Giovanni but also to
Walton’s own &lt;em&gt;Belshazzar’s Feast&lt;/em&gt;, again a favourite work of mine. Fortunately,
context saved me here, as the chorus slowly makes itself known, crescendoing slowly to become just about audible on-stage, before making a final fortissimo
statement and leaving Dorian to contemplate his fate – with little over a minute
left of the opera.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Olly Bowes</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It strikes me that whenever I announced to people that I had set about writing an opera, I never actually received that reaction I expected. I was certain I’d be met with derision – “What makes you think YOU can write one, Bowes?” Up to the point that I began working on Dorian, I had only really written choral music and a few songs. My only forays into purely instrumental music consisted of a piano quintet I concocted for my A-level coursework, an arrangement of a school song (Bedford by the River – won a cash prize for it, to be fair), and a frankly ridiculous setting of the Requiem Mass, which I hope will never be performed in its current state. Yet, the reaction, especially when I told everyone of the subject-matter of this opera, Wilde’s seminal novella The Picture of Dorian Gray, was unanimously positive. A few more knowledgeable friends asked whether it had been done before, to which I ask: how many versions of Faust or Romeo and Juliet are there? Answer: frankly too many, not that I wouldn’t consider doing a Faust-related one at some point – indeed, one can see Dorian itself as a Faustian tale. Nevertheless, the reception to the idea was that I ought to push on, and so I did. Thus, I have reached the end of the compositional process (barring edits after the fact) and I have more than enough time to sit and worry about the show. Which I do – all too often, in fact. And which also led me to write this pair of articles for The Pangean. At the end of my last article, I had reflected on the music of the first Act, but I came to realize after its publication that I had failed to actually discuss compositional process, which I suppose is far more interesting than simply taking you, arm-in-arm, on a promenade through what you will, in just a matter of months, be able to hear for yourself. Therefore, while I will still move chronologically through the final Act, wouldn’t you rather hear about how I did the composing, rather than what composing I did? In all honesty, I have not been composing for long enough to have entirely unified a process. Different pieces require different things from me. Some pieces can go from just the little scribblings in a notebook straight into my computer, where I will transform them from the idea into an actual functioning piece. Others, such as the song-cycle I am currently working on, Crow, needed to be mapped out in full-score on paper first, and in ink – it felt particularly necessary for Crow, as it lent a sparseness to the writing that was very helpful (although, I must say that it has been an absolute b*tch to write up on my computer.) These are the two ends of a sliding scale upon which Dorian sat somewhere in the middle. Or, in fact, off of either end. Some scenes, such as the theatre scene in Act One went straight from my brain into the computer, as the nature of the scurrying accompaniment made it a real bore to hand-write, without the joy of copy-and-paste and editing after the fact. Others, such as the entire last scene, were almost entirely drafted on paper first and then written up – although I admit that at least part of the reason for hand-writing the entire last scene was that my laptop was on the blink and I was 3,000 miles from home. But, it keeps the romantic notion of the composer scribbling away with pen and ink alive, so I’ve got to keep up appearances. And so we come to the last Act. Although much of this was drafted last, the prelude to the first scene was, in fact, finished long before most of Act One, as it gave me, frankly, a nice compositional break from the Prologue. My librettist Jamie and I had to come up with some way to symbolise several years of debauchery that the audience missed by swanning out for their interval drinks in the bar. I assume that the debauched years will be lived through in the minds of our performers during this interval; it would be nicely ‘method’ of them. But how to illustrate it in music? I gave the audience a brief, slow moment in which to mourn Basil and Sybil, both brutally killed at the end of the first Act, before setting about the musical debauchery. Decadence and wild abandon are often achieved in music through the use of rowdy dances. Ravel was a master of this, especially in the finale of La Valse, or consider Stravinsky’s Rite of Spring – the poor girl dances herself to death at the end. But, as those of you who know me can testify, I am no dancer. So how should I go after the same effects? It’s actually fairly obvious: the thing that makes a dance a dance is the rhythm, with which I have very little issue (getting the legs to do what they’re told on the other hand…). Therefore, I took one of the rhythmic motifs that described the den of iniquity that was the theatre in Act One, and laid it underneath a pulsating Yoruba-inspired cross-rhythm from a pair of drums to create a heady mix of open fifths and driving rhythms that symbolises Dorian’s embracing of Harry’s lessons. Similarly, the segue into the first scene, which itself takes place in an opium den, takes its influences from Debussy’s use of the quartal harmony to lend an air of intentionally fake orientalism, with added xylophonic twinkling. This is undercut by the following chorus ‘number’ – Dorian, his mind full of a romantic poems, hallucinates that the other patrons of this establishment all begin singing, in French, about the beauty of Venice, at odds with both the Chinese-y music of the den, as well as with the general dinginess of London at the end of the 19th century. And, as a unifying feature of this scene, the music is still Debussy-inspired. With a French poem, especially by a poet such as Théophile Gautier, one can’t not look to Debussy, I feel. “Sur une gamme chromatique, Le sein de perles ruisselant, La Vénus de l’Adriatique, Sort de l’eau son corps rose et blanc.” The remainder of the first scene is dominated by the one appearance of Sybil’s brother James, who rages like a bull in a china-shop while attempting to pursue Dorian. His aria was one for which I did the most planning – James had to be able to arrive on the scene and make enough of an impact to make him feel like a threat for the remainder of the show, despite not having been seen in the previous acts. Thus, he demanded a full-on show-stopper of an aria. What makes music sound angry? It’s much the same as that which makes music sound debauched, as both violent anger and wild abandon stray from the comfortable emotional spectrum. Thus, I focused on rhythm again. I wrote out his words, some of the most violent I have read in Wilde, and began to speak them to myself over and over again. Individual lines became something of a rapid chant, savagely thumping away, until I was able to write down specific rhythms I had associated with them. The aria became very caballetic, with compound rhythms driving underneath the singer’s howling. And then I worked out the melody. It’s not greatly complicated, just arpeggiating through the chords underneath. Far more important is the tessitura: James was, in my head, a Bass, albeit one with a very solid top range, and this aria is one that exploits it, as I push the singer to the upper extreme, bellowing away in righteous fury, while the orchestra churns away tempestuously around him, until he disappears into the night to hunt his sister’s ‘killer’. In the second scene, the last scene to be written, and not appearing in the novella, we return to Lord Henry’s house. Yet the house has a much darker aspect than when we had seen it in the first Act. For one thing, it is about three in the morning. But, more importantly, Henry’s wife has made a decision that will cast a pall on the man for the rest of the show. To give a sense of this foreboding, I searched back through her brief appearance in Act One for melodies associated with Lady Victoria, finally picking the languorous downwardly meandering tune she uses to describe her enjoyment of pianists to manipulate into a mournful prelude to the scene, descending through the strings in a canon, before a quote from Tchaikovsky’s Eugene Onegin foreshadows the fateful letter that she has written for Harry. Harry’s music, on the other hand, is much brighter and jolly – he’s drunk, and he sings in a drunkenly twisted patter, while Victoria drums up the courage to tell him she is leaving. When she finally pours forth all her upset, we move from twisted patter into a driving baroque-esque raging, reminiscent of Handel’s more overtly furious moments, most particularly Dejanira’s aria, Where Shall I Fly from Hercules, in which the overwrought Dejanira is driven mad by guilt, having caused the death of her god-like husband. But, for me, there was a deeper meaning behind the baroque façade that I had Victoria put up. Jamie and I discussed this scene at great length, deliberating over how to stop Victoria from seeming like a shrewish, nagging wife, and more like the bright, free woman she ought to be. Neither of us understand women (or, in my case, people in general) as well as we’d like to think, I suspect, but I truly believe we have drawn here a very human event: Victoria pretends, in her baroque raging, that her divorce is for all sorts of moral and societal reasons, citing Harry’s insalubrious behaviour as more than enough reason for her to leave him. Yet, she ultimately confesses that this is a pretence. She married him because that behaviour, fuelled as it was by his Byronic intelligence, was highly attractive. However, he has now ceased being Byronic, and is simply being indulgent and destructive whilst ignoring her as a wife. All the romance has gone from his behaviour. It’s a far more interesting character that Jamie has drawn through this dichotomy than what could have been there: a shrew reprimanding a wastrel for his wastefulness. We finally return to Dorian, still suffering shock from his encounter with James Vane, on retreat in the country. We find him alone in the grounds of the Duchess of Monmouth’s house, musing on the events of the previous few days. For this scene, we took full advantage of the non-linear storytelling we had introduced with the appearance of Sybil at the end of Act One. There is, in Wilde’s original, a scintillating scene of witty repartee between Harry and several other pillars of society after a dinner hosted by the Duchess. However, in streamlining the show, we feared we would lose this in order to focus more clearly on Dorian himself. That is, we feared until one of us realised we could just do another pseudo-flashback, as Dorian recalls the events of the previous evening. Therefore, we have another moment of lighthearted patter from Harry, who is joined by the chorus – I felt I was channelling all of my love for Die Fledermaus or even the great Victorian partnership of Gilbert and Sullivan, trying to create some feeling of effervescence in the midst of the terror that is consuming Dorian here. This continues into the next big chorus moment, after the flashback, when these society lords and ladies enter the field in which Dorian has been sitting in order to go shooting, singing words by Rudyard Kipling, from his Verses on Games: “Peace upon Earth, Goodwill to men” So greet we Christmas Day! Oh, Christian, load your gun and then Oh, Christian, out and slay.” This joyful entrance is set to a reharmonisation of Sullivan’s tune Noel, known to most of us as It Came Upon A Midnight Clear. At the same time, something of RVW’s Antiphon or Bruckner’s Te Deum was never far from my mind, in terms of the orchestration. It may have become obvious to you that I am always thinking of other things to relate my music to. It is a problem I run into occasionally – am I being influenced, which is fine: music does not exist in a vacuum; or am I simply copying? Quoting things is fine, especially in such a long work as this (there are many quotes in Dorian, most of which I have not pointed out, but all of which make me irrationally, self-indulgently happy), but copying is not just plagiaristic but, personally, pointless – even if my original thought, at the inception of this opera, was that “I wish Britten had written a Dorian Gray.” Hopefully, my style has become distinct enough from just “a kid copying Britten”. Hopefully. Moving on, there is so much to point to in the final scene. Therefore, I will keep my comments limited to two particular moments. In this last scene, we see Dorian and Harry finally alone in Dorian’s living room. Dorian is by now incredibly stressed – Vane hunted him all the way to the Duchess’ estate, and, in trying to creep up on him, was shot by one of the Lords on their morning shoot – which Dorian took as a terribly ill omen. Returning to London, Harry has been keeping tabs on his young protégé, making sure the fear and stress doesn’t get to him. Therefore, he ups the levels of inane babble. The treatment of his final moment of inane babble is possibly one of my favourite bits of composition I’ve done to date. I say my composition, but actually, Harry’s last aria is founded entirely upon a piece by Alexander Scriabin, who, although I mention him very infrequently, is one of my favourite composers, if only for his absolutely insane theories about the end of the world (and attempts to bring said end about) and his pretence at having synaesthesia, which he tried to use to create a light-organ or ‘clavier à lumières’ with which to compose for the colour-spectrum―which is, I think you’ll agree, fairly bonkers. Nevertheless, I got it into my head to use this moment at the end of the piece to highlight musically a big change in Dorian: before we meet Dorian in the Prologue, we hear him from offstage, playing a snippet from Schumann’s Waldszenen, a very calm, nature-themed work for the piano – a piece of innocence, if you will. But now, at the end of the evening, many years later for the two remaining characters, Dorian returns to the piano to ignore Harry’s inanities, and plays Scriabin’s Nocturne for the left hand. This highlights a change in Dorian in several ways. Firstly, it is significantly more technically and harmonically challenging than the Schumann, in part because it is specifically for the left hand, but also because of Scriabin’s tense, dense harmonic language, which is significantly more discordant and much less innocent than Schumann’s. Moreover, Schumann published Waldszenen in 1849, whereas the Nocturne was composed in 1894; there is nearly half a century of musical development, pushing the boundaries of tonality and taste, between the two, indicative of the passage of time within the show, perhaps, and certainly indicative again of the corruption of Dorian’s innocence over that time. Finally, we come to the grand collapse that is the ending. I shan’t spoil the last few pages by discussing exactly how the show closes, because that would undoubtedly be a travesty. What I would like to discuss is the allegorical use of the story of Belshazzar in the closing moments. In my first plan of the end, I had refused the idea of an off-stage chorus as too ‘operatic’ for an intimate close to this show, much too close to the end of Don Giovanni or the countless other shows that copied that dramatic close, with the lecher dragged into hell by an immaterial chorus. However, one chat with Jamie transformed my conception entirely: I was not overly keen on my first draft’s ending, and he wrote some new words to close the show – they were splendid. In a tangent to Dorian’s flashback or his vision of Sybil, Jamie brought up an off-stage chorus, symbolic perhaps of Dorian’s frantic brain or of heavenly judgement (I’m inclined to think one particular way, but others may disagree), singing the “writing on the wall” that appeared at Belshazzar’s Feast: “Mene Mene Tekel Upharsin” or, as Jamie put it, “Thou art in the balances, and art found wanting.” Dorian, in his desperate bid to redeem himself after his years of immorality, cannot help but hear these words, directly paralleling the condemnation that is his own portrait hanging upon the wall. Thus, in composition, I had to avoid not just the links to Don Giovanni but also to Walton’s own Belshazzar’s Feast, again a favourite work of mine. Fortunately, context saved me here, as the chorus slowly makes itself known, crescendoing slowly to become just about audible on-stage, before making a final fortissimo statement and leaving Dorian to contemplate his fate – with little over a minute left of the opera.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Hard Reality of Hardcopies</title>
      <link href="/The-Hard-Reality-on-Hardcopies" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Hard Reality of Hardcopies" />
      <published>2019-03-07T03:15:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-07T03:15:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Hard-Reality-on-Hardcopies</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Hard-Reality-on-Hardcopies">&lt;p&gt;Spring, which has almost become non-existential in Calcutta, is a much revered
and coveted time of the year for any of us living in the tropical zone,
especially when it precedes a season of pig-like sweating. The breezy streets
are a delight to the souls dampened by the winter, and a walk through those
streets with an old friend hits just the right note on the Spring Symphony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An old friend and I have shared a long, uneven but all the more enjoyable
friendship over the years, and our unending love for books has still, with old,
straining strings, held our friendship. Here, I must mention, with much
gratitude, that she was the person to introduce me to the vast, unending, and
marvellous land of books, lending me the first book I ever read by Sidney
Sheldon. When I raised my reservations about the unappealing demeanour of a
book, she just asked me to read for only thirty minutes every day before sleep,
and stated that if after a week I still found it ‘uninteresting’, I could drop
it and return it to her, with her promising to never again insist that I read a
book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprise! Surprise! I finished the book within a week, returned it to her, told
her I finished it and was prized with a look of priceless shock from her. I am
not such an active reader anymore, but what occurred to me then was how
immensely romantic holding the spine of a book is; and of the many sins that our
education system and technology has caused, one is causing a holocaust on the
romance of holding a book. Needless to say, books, since then, became an
inseparable part of my regime and my birthday gifts. But I must confess, after
my first read, I was still sceptical whether this enchantment I felt was
ephemeral or actually enduring. It persisted. Even though initially, I raised
doubts about the ‘unappealing’ demeanour of a book, it was that which drove me
most to the habit of reading books: the mellow chirps of the pages, the letters
marching on the beige field, the weaving and unravelling of tales, and the
hundreds of lives coming to life on those very seemingly lifeless pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, coming back to the spring evening of breezy streets: it was an occasion of
me returning my friend her long-given books, and as we were merrily discussing
things of grave concern to us, something graver ambushed us – what is the future
of hardcopies? I have always been troubled by the growing popularity of ebooks,
but it did not hit harder than when I heard her saying that she has to do her
college’s research work from an ebook. The general argument here would be that
an ebook offers almost everything that a book does, but god forbid the day when
writers romanticise reading an ebook by the window on a rainy day in their
novels or their Instagram posts per se. Leaving aside the romantic values, how
would an ebook ever satiate the bourgeois need of the book-hoarding class? Who
do you think would be impressed by your listless list of books on your device,
instead of the piles of webbed and tattered books with missing pages and
crumpled edges? How can looking up from your well-lit Kindle be the same as a
distracted stare into the distance as Tolstoy drones on in a thick copy of &lt;em&gt;War
and Peace&lt;/em&gt;? What would be more charming, lending book by just a few taps, or
rummaging through the hundreds of dust sprinkled books, whilst being cast under
the perverse magic of nostalgia?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a not so recent finding in 2017, it was published that the United States of
America recorded a greater sale of ebooks compared to hardcopies. I became
fairly unstable after reading this and looked with greater awe than ever at my
meagre collection of whatever hardcopies I possess. I, too, am guilty of
possessing ebooks. Of course, I am not all against ebooks (this article is being
published online, after all), it does provide many the opportunity to read
things that otherwise would be inaccessible to them and it certainly is a great
aid when travelling. Although the emergence of ebooks feels like a personal
defeat to me, I concede to the importance of ebooks in times of such great
distress to nature and society. And in fear that I might be misconstrued as a
privileged brat, let me tell you, I buy books using fees earned from part-time
teaching, which most assuredly isn’t much. Yet, still, for me, books and their
essence lies in their old-school charm that keeps us turning actual pages.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrei Tarkovsky once said that artists are there because the world is not
perfect, and such imperfection is reminded to us by those hardcopies that seem
frayed and old and decaying just like our world. The ebook is too perfect a
vessel for works that are born out of imperfection. It swerves us into a path
away from nature, away from reality into a dark realm of complete machine
dominance. In the end, maybe I am simply a hopeless romantic stuck in the past
when the world is aggressively progressing into the future, but I hope my voice
of unreason reaches a few romantic hearts so that we can keep the lineage of
hardcopies from dying a most ignominious and unromantic death.  &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Spring, which has almost become non-existential in Calcutta, is a much revered and coveted time of the year for any of us living in the tropical zone, especially when it precedes a season of pig-like sweating. The breezy streets are a delight to the souls dampened by the winter, and a walk through those streets with an old friend hits just the right note on the Spring Symphony. An old friend and I have shared a long, uneven but all the more enjoyable friendship over the years, and our unending love for books has still, with old, straining strings, held our friendship. Here, I must mention, with much gratitude, that she was the person to introduce me to the vast, unending, and marvellous land of books, lending me the first book I ever read by Sidney Sheldon. When I raised my reservations about the unappealing demeanour of a book, she just asked me to read for only thirty minutes every day before sleep, and stated that if after a week I still found it ‘uninteresting’, I could drop it and return it to her, with her promising to never again insist that I read a book. Surprise! Surprise! I finished the book within a week, returned it to her, told her I finished it and was prized with a look of priceless shock from her. I am not such an active reader anymore, but what occurred to me then was how immensely romantic holding the spine of a book is; and of the many sins that our education system and technology has caused, one is causing a holocaust on the romance of holding a book. Needless to say, books, since then, became an inseparable part of my regime and my birthday gifts. But I must confess, after my first read, I was still sceptical whether this enchantment I felt was ephemeral or actually enduring. It persisted. Even though initially, I raised doubts about the ‘unappealing’ demeanour of a book, it was that which drove me most to the habit of reading books: the mellow chirps of the pages, the letters marching on the beige field, the weaving and unravelling of tales, and the hundreds of lives coming to life on those very seemingly lifeless pages. Now, coming back to the spring evening of breezy streets: it was an occasion of me returning my friend her long-given books, and as we were merrily discussing things of grave concern to us, something graver ambushed us – what is the future of hardcopies? I have always been troubled by the growing popularity of ebooks, but it did not hit harder than when I heard her saying that she has to do her college’s research work from an ebook. The general argument here would be that an ebook offers almost everything that a book does, but god forbid the day when writers romanticise reading an ebook by the window on a rainy day in their novels or their Instagram posts per se. Leaving aside the romantic values, how would an ebook ever satiate the bourgeois need of the book-hoarding class? Who do you think would be impressed by your listless list of books on your device, instead of the piles of webbed and tattered books with missing pages and crumpled edges? How can looking up from your well-lit Kindle be the same as a distracted stare into the distance as Tolstoy drones on in a thick copy of War and Peace? What would be more charming, lending book by just a few taps, or rummaging through the hundreds of dust sprinkled books, whilst being cast under the perverse magic of nostalgia? In a not so recent finding in 2017, it was published that the United States of America recorded a greater sale of ebooks compared to hardcopies. I became fairly unstable after reading this and looked with greater awe than ever at my meagre collection of whatever hardcopies I possess. I, too, am guilty of possessing ebooks. Of course, I am not all against ebooks (this article is being published online, after all), it does provide many the opportunity to read things that otherwise would be inaccessible to them and it certainly is a great aid when travelling. Although the emergence of ebooks feels like a personal defeat to me, I concede to the importance of ebooks in times of such great distress to nature and society. And in fear that I might be misconstrued as a privileged brat, let me tell you, I buy books using fees earned from part-time teaching, which most assuredly isn’t much. Yet, still, for me, books and their essence lies in their old-school charm that keeps us turning actual pages.   Andrei Tarkovsky once said that artists are there because the world is not perfect, and such imperfection is reminded to us by those hardcopies that seem frayed and old and decaying just like our world. The ebook is too perfect a vessel for works that are born out of imperfection. It swerves us into a path away from nature, away from reality into a dark realm of complete machine dominance. In the end, maybe I am simply a hopeless romantic stuck in the past when the world is aggressively progressing into the future, but I hope my voice of unreason reaches a few romantic hearts so that we can keep the lineage of hardcopies from dying a most ignominious and unromantic death.  </summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Jungian Shadow</title>
      <link href="/The-Jungian-Shadow" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Jungian Shadow" />
      <published>2019-02-18T12:46:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-18T12:46:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Jungian-Shadow</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Jungian-Shadow">&lt;p&gt;What if you’ve got it all wrong: the whole idea of who you are, your identity and how you want to be seen. What if there’s more to your personality: another dimension maybe, or even a caliginous shadow, harbouring in it the nasty demonic tendencies of your very being? While this idea may seem bizarre, the truth of it is hard to deny. There lies in all of us a mysterious unconscious realm seated within the deepest recesses of our personality. This is the Shadow archetype, the Id, or the dark side. Devoid of the conscious light, it is in this tenebrous side where thrives the primitive, malicious, even creative aspects of our being that have long been repressed by the Freudian Ego. Engulfed in obscurity, the Shadow largely remains hidden from the understanding of the Self, making us live in pretence and deception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Propounded by the very renowned Swiss psychoanalyst Carl Jung, the concept of the Shadow operates on the Pleasure Principle. Subdued ideas, primitive instincts, desires, drives, abjections, fears, all are encompassed by this concept, which further mirrors the latent, unknown and dark aspects of the psyche that the conscious Ego fails to resonate with. The Shadow is of two types: the personal and the collective. While the personal Shadow pertains to the individual psyche, the collective Shadow emanates from a united unconsciousness of society-members, a projection of which has resulted in the greatest of evils, in the form of prejudice advanced by society against other communities to conceal their own weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lying under unfathomable depths, the Shadow develops alongside the Ego and Persona. As a child gets culturally conditioned to differentiate between good and bad, certain possessed behaviours and qualities are evaluated by them as deplorable and, ultimately, despised and rejected. In the whole process of growing up, humans also tend to masquerade their identity and don on a façade to gain greater acceptance in society. This is known as a Persona. But the Persona only hides the Shadow, it doesn’t eliminate its gestating potency to unleash the worst in human beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is essential for one to accept the Shadow rather than seeking validation in the Persona. For a harmonious universe, the intermingling of both the aspects of good – bad, order - chaos, the yin and yang, becomes necessary. Likewise, for a balanced personality, one needs to unearth the dark aspects of one’s soul from the dreary suppressions of the Ego and integrate them with their conscious side. This is extremely important, for the very reason that each time your Ego represses a part of you, your Shadow gets denser, sprouting in it the destructive potential to completely overshadow your conscious light and cast on you a dark cloud of gloom for the rest of your life. A convenient trick is to think like the antagonist or villain in books or movies, learning to work with the people one hates or feels irritated around, and identifying the lies that they can unravel to challenge ‘the good’―both in society and in themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of exploring one’s Shadow is not to bring forth some inner Machiavelli. It is about ensuring one truly understands oneself and accepts that there is a very horrible, unspeakable side to one’s own psyche. Without such knowledge and such humility, one is bound to remain a Nietzschean Last Man, afraid of life and it’s problems, driven not by a sense of true purpose but primal instincts. However, by overcoming the Shadow and directing its destructive forces on the right path, one can achieve true inner peace and the ability to fully realise oneself as The Super Man―thereby taming the demon within to achieve inner peace.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">What if you’ve got it all wrong: the whole idea of who you are, your identity and how you want to be seen. What if there’s more to your personality: another dimension maybe, or even a caliginous shadow, harbouring in it the nasty demonic tendencies of your very being? While this idea may seem bizarre, the truth of it is hard to deny. There lies in all of us a mysterious unconscious realm seated within the deepest recesses of our personality. This is the Shadow archetype, the Id, or the dark side. Devoid of the conscious light, it is in this tenebrous side where thrives the primitive, malicious, even creative aspects of our being that have long been repressed by the Freudian Ego. Engulfed in obscurity, the Shadow largely remains hidden from the understanding of the Self, making us live in pretence and deception.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">An Anthropological Consideration of Ugandan Knuckles: The Opiate for a Poisoned State</title>
      <link href="/An-Anthropological-Consideration-of-Ugandan-Knuckles" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Anthropological Consideration of Ugandan Knuckles: The Opiate for a Poisoned State" />
      <published>2019-02-07T03:20:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T03:20:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/An-Anthropological-Consideration-of-Ugandan-Knuckles</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/An-Anthropological-Consideration-of-Ugandan-Knuckles">&lt;p&gt;I know, dear reader, that you have thought of this before, as I have; there may, in fact, be far more to the Ugandan Knuckles meme than meets the eye. Could it be that in this chaotic, disorganised vision of a cultural dead space, this wellspring of enjoyment is reflective of our times far more than was initially thought?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ugandan Knuckles meme encompasses, in truth and upon further inspection, a highly complex social structure. It has a diaspora of ethnographically observed motifs spawned forth from its hierarchies, with inner conflicts and philosophical, spiritual quandaries levied against the outside world from the safe confines of VRChat. After all, the people propagating the meme remain, if anything, human. And so from them, we may examine human nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one thing, the acolytes of this subculture organise themselves into a diverse and very complicated hierarchy. It is quite hard to discern, but I believe Knuckles avatars sporting a blue skin as opposed to the common red are still part of the same clan, though there may be a position in the social system implied, which is possibly the &lt;em&gt;“Ugandan Warrior”&lt;/em&gt; class. These will protect the Queen (more on her later). Yellow skin is likely the mark of &lt;em&gt;“The Commander”&lt;/em&gt;, a high position seemingly not coveted but accepted with humility by new initiates. It is likely that they frequently cycle this position over a short term in office and they do this because their true calling is to form a party capable of locating a female monarch.
They operate under a Sacral Democratic Monarchy, for they elect a Queen and will follow this Queen under the belief that she will grant them sacred knowledge of &lt;em&gt;“The Way”&lt;/em&gt;. The requirements for this position are few and, at times, scant or plentifully observed depending on the weeaboo and anime fan presence in the Chat Room. She need only be female, Japanese idol-like (Hatsune Mikus are frequently accosted), or Moe – fluorescent-haired preferable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once they find a Queen, they will fawn over her and begin to voice their contentment with an a-linguistic motif. This is ‘clucking’, a vocalized ‘clock’ sound, as an aspirated glottal &lt;em&gt;/’klɒk/&lt;/em&gt; made with the tongue behind the teeth (very culturally unique) and would be called in linguistic anthropology a non-verbal acoustic call, conveying emotion. If the Queen can be found to have led them astray, the roving pack of miniatures will engage in a ‘spitting’, to indicate their rejection of this false divine saviour. They demand respect for the Queen, crave her love but will also spit on her.
Unfortunately, Ugandan Knuckles politics is far too complex to outline here, but it is apparent that conflicts of interest are quite common. Splinter groups forming as different female players displaying a lolicon aesthetic are frequently happened upon and hailed, willingly or no, as the next holy monarch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the anthropology of religion, The Divine Right, or Holy Mandate to rule is a frequently observed feature of cultures on planet earth where church and state are one. We might point in this case to the cause of such a phenomenon seen here with this meme format being a growing atheistic worldview in our society. As we feel a detachment from the spirit, we see the humorous taking on the responsibility of the severe, in a nervous rebuttal of the empty, godless nation-state. For how can we have faith in leaders who possess no faith themselves? Of course, such practices in the West date back to pre-Christian, Pagan Europe, a paradoxically dark, yet ethno-nationally enlightened time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ugandan Knuckles Clan members’ spiritual path, &lt;em&gt;The Way&lt;/em&gt;, is a nomadistic, possibly nihilistic, and devotional philosophy of the self defined by space and sovereignty tied to one’s destiny. In anthropological terms, this is a Durkheimian consideration of how society maintains coherence and integrity in the modern era, when traditionalism is lost and replaced by less organically defined economic, social institutions. A brother is kin, a member of the clan provides a sense of belonging, the love found in belonging to one’s nation allows for the fortitude necessary to sustain it. To ask, &lt;em&gt;“Why are you running?”&lt;/em&gt;, is to wonder how a friend can flee his destiny. Why doubt oneself? This exemplifies a unique rudimentary cultural Kismet ideology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ugandan Knuckles clans seek only to find meaning and satisfaction in their existence by being close to their Queen and their spiky brethren. This anthropological sense of self is defined as and functions by the mechanisms of Cultural Memory. If they find one of their flock to have strayed from &lt;em&gt;The Way&lt;/em&gt;, or to be in any manner unholy, they will voice sympathy and announce: &lt;em&gt;“We must pray for this one, my brothers”&lt;/em&gt;. Such camaraderie reflects a beauteous, shared heritage in shouldering the burden of life with one’s ethnocultural peers, a sentiment sadly lacking in today’s society, and it ought to be observed! One might say it is the trauma of meandering about, in search of one’s home which acts as what we call in anthropology a &lt;em&gt;“rite of passage”&lt;/em&gt;, serving the purpose of bonding together a generation of young men that they may go out into the world as brothers-in-arms—though this usually applies to something like the Mukanda ritual ceremony of the Ndembu people in Zambia, wherein young boys are taken away from the village at a certain age to have the extremities of their manhood cut-off. During this &lt;em&gt;rite of passage&lt;/em&gt;, young men enter what anthropologists call the Liminal State. In this state, young men are neither man nor child, which allows for the personal transformation of the self, body, and spirit. But how does this happen? Simple. To take from the famous adage;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;i&gt;“Gamers are the most oppressed group”.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the most cursory glance at &lt;em&gt;“Gamer Fashion”&lt;/em&gt;, a subset in the nomenclature formerly known as Gamer/Geek Culture (from which the Ugandan Knuckles ensued) has much to inform us. Gamer T-Shirts, which we will here be using as ethnographic evidence of their material culture, read thusly: &lt;em&gt;“Hey, SNOWFLAKE, there are only two genders, so get over it!”&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;“If you are reading this I’ll have you know I was forced to put my controller down and enter society”&lt;/em&gt;; or &lt;em&gt;“I’m a gamer, not because I don’t have a life, but because I choose to have many!”&lt;/em&gt;. Such a study clearly identifies these G-Fuelled, never-pulled, but-very-virile-in-the-season-pass plucky young miscreants. For these young men belong to the techno-fanatical, pseudo-radical, and pseudo-puritanical generation called Y-Z millennials. A less prudent man might cut themselves on this level of edginess, but not these brave souls, though they do face terrible hardship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, more articles have been published by various millennial plaintiffs decrying this Ugandan Knuckles meme, which they deem to be racist, therefore further displaying just how oppressed these poor, unfortunate outcast souls find themselves. Time and time again, they are dissatisfied with what their society gives them, as the West disowns itself with the neo-feminist, cultural-Marxist criticism of the post-colonial Occident. And yet still as they seek refuge, they are blasted in a flame war to light our skies in Cyberspace for generations. Down the line, they will speak of these days when the completed their rite of passage, as they do of the great Meme Wars, and tales of &lt;em&gt;The Way&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Pepe&lt;/em&gt; alike will be told around pixelated campfires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the same, it ought not be forgotten that the creators of the 2010 Ugandan film &lt;em&gt;Who Killed Captain Alex?&lt;/em&gt;, having originated the quotes whose accents and manners were taken-on by the scarlet Ugandan Faithful have themselves endorsed the meme, sharing many iterations and supporting the sub-culture as best they can from their twitter page, @Wakaliwood. And really, it must not be omitted from the debate that in modern anthropological circles, the principle of Cultural Relativism posits that we should treat all cultures equally! And yet. And yet must this come at the expense of some cultures in favour of others?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To speak as the Geek is to know the Geek; In the words of the ancient 10th-century Anglo-Saxon poem &lt;em&gt;The Wanderer&lt;/em&gt;, as repurposed into King Théoden’s monologue by J. R. R. Tolkien for his LOTR book &lt;em&gt;The Two Towers&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;i&gt;“Where is the horse and the rider? &lt;br /&gt;
Where is the horn that was blowing? &lt;br /&gt;
They have passed like rain on the mountains, &lt;br /&gt;
like wind in the meadow. &lt;br /&gt;
The days have gone down in the West, &lt;br /&gt;
behind the hills... Into Shadow.”&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gentlemen, I say, in recalling the outcry and sensitivity previously observed within the Gaming community by the refrain, &lt;em&gt;“where is the justice for Harambe?”&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;“where is the respect due for this honourable and noble meme which may soon face oblivion?” &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in observing such criticisms, this comes from the same media-climate as the cultural motifs which allowed and indeed enabled the late, bait, sombre-fated Gillette advert to happen, whence we see this same accusatory thought-process levelled against not only all white, cisgendered men but all men in general! Is it any wonder the self-removed would seek solace in the virtual arms of a neon-lit loli?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our current cultural climate is unassertive, unsure and self-destructing. When a culture is diseased, it may find when turning around to scrub behind itself in the shower one day that oddly-formed but quite enigmatically defined growths in the shapes of secondary Sonic the Hedgehog characters have developed upon the rump! Visions beholding plagues of frogs reoccur…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then again, and from a laboratory perspective, the difference between a contemporary consideration of a “model society”, perhaps sat on a table as a maquette of what we might be (as envisioned by those who would have us constantly be in self-un-realisation) and a VR vat containing a vile, porous, clucking swarm of social parasites is that, scientifically speaking, such bacteria will eventually develop its own culture.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Morgan Black</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I know, dear reader, that you have thought of this before, as I have; there may, in fact, be far more to the Ugandan Knuckles meme than meets the eye. Could it be that in this chaotic, disorganised vision of a cultural dead space, this wellspring of enjoyment is reflective of our times far more than was initially thought?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">2001: A Metaphysical Odyssey</title>
      <link href="/2001-A-Metaphysical-Odyssey" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2001: A Metaphysical Odyssey" />
      <published>2019-02-07T02:33:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T02:33:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/2001-A-Metaphysical-Odyssey</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/2001-A-Metaphysical-Odyssey">&lt;p&gt;Stanley Kubrick has produced phenomenal works throughout his career. His relentless, unflinching approach to the subjects he chose certainly showed in his films and we cannot be thankful enough for his contribution to the art of filmmaking. That said, any further discourse on how great a filmmaker he was seems pointless to me as it has already been addressed umpteen times by several, far more accomplished personas at greater lengths. What I would prefer to bring under the microscope today is his magnum opus &lt;em&gt;2001: A Space Odyssey&lt;/em&gt; and what lay at its heart. The film, which has now been minced to mere GIFs and iconic ringtones, was presumably his life’s most important and ambitious work, although I have no grounds to claim so. He started to work on &lt;em&gt;2001&lt;/em&gt; in 1964 after his overture to Arthur C. Clarke, who co-wrote the script for the film and authored a book of the same name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2001&lt;/em&gt; opens with a black screen and eerie music, giving a sense of void with all its horror. From the very beginning, Kubrick made sure he doesn’t send the wrong signal about this odyssey being just any sci-fi. This void was then succeeded by a scene of the camera rising up to behold the sun from beyond the edges of the moon and the Earth to the tune of Richard Strauss’ &lt;em&gt;Thus Spake Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt;. Now, this is where things get real. The use of &lt;em&gt;Thus Spake Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt; was no mere coincidence, and it should not be with someone as seminal as Kubrick. The extraordinary work by Friedrich Nietzsche at the dusk of his life was indeed the prime theme of the entire project, which Kubrick concurred to later on. And as for the scene in question, it was clearly the beckoning of the new morning that Nietzsche suggested in the book when he said, &lt;i&gt;“The noon when man stands the middle of his way between beast and Superman… a way to a new morning.”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film primarily addresses three important themes: The Superman, Evolution and the Dionysian and Apollonian.
Now, if you’re familiar with these concepts you can avoid this paragraph and move on to the next, and if not I will walk you through them briefly. The Superman is a term coined not by DC comics but by Friedrich Nietzsche in his &lt;em&gt;Thus Spake Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt;. In it, he points out that it is not right for us to assume that evolution has ended. He argued that we are currently in the middle of our evolution, that we are the bridge between the hominids and the far superior Superman. Nietzsche declares in his book: &lt;i&gt;“What is ape to man? A laughing stock or a painful embarrassment. And man shall be that to the Superman: a laughing stock and painful embarrassment.”&lt;/i&gt; Nietzsche says his future Supermen would have their own values, being independently-minded, and forging their own path. These Supermen will accept the fact that they might need to hurt people for the sake of great things, that selfishness isn’t a vice but a necessity. They won’t despise the success of others and will accept suffering as a means to good things. They will also bear the cross of loneliness as a price for their hard nature. They will be gentle towards the weak because of their consciousness of their own strength and will exult at their capabilities. The other Nietzschean concepts, the Dionysian and Apollonian, are paradigms of human nature. The Dionysian engages in revelry, wine, and dance, in chaos and irrationality, he is instinctive and emotional; the Apollonian, on the other hand, is cultured, intellectual, engaging with logic and rationality, and wise and controlled. Finally there is evolution: while it is clear that our ancestors were Dionysian and we have evolved to be Apollonian, according to Nietzsche, we would further evolve to find the sublime balance between these two ideologies to forge our own paths.
Kubrick held Nietzsche in high regard and took dear to his views almost devoutly. He too believed that we are not at the end of evolution and must march forward to acquire greater psychological abilities. And even though many have foreseen machinery to be the biggest possible threat to humanity, Kubrick believed there’s nothing that our species cannot conquer given our superior psychological faculty, be it the leopards that once ambushed and attacked the apes or be it an artificially intelligent computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film starts at the dawn of mankind, when the ape-men amid their daily struggles to survive  and maintain their territory,  witnessed the first of four monoliths that supposedly changed the course of their lives. It bestowed them with the idea of using bones as weapons— this is Kubrick subtly asserting that violence underpins basic human nature. The second monolith is unearthed in the Moon, suggesting that humans are ready for their advent toward the next stage of evolution, to acquire the next level of intelligence. And thus the journey begins; the quiet and long journey which Kubrick infallibly filmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, the audience felt the tediousness of the journey. This is also the part where we come across the iconic Hal 9000 which till date is a big reference in pop culture. This artificially intelligent computer was given to monitor and supervise the journey but it all changed when it started making a few mistakes stoking doubts in the minds of the two other passengers – Dave and Frank - about its reliability. What follows is an epochal scene where Dave and Frank discuss in private in a pod bay about their plans to disconnect Hal which Hal oversees through the glass door of the pod bay. Dave first shows the signs of a Superman when he lets go of Frank to enter the spaceship himself without a moment’s trepidation. He sacrificed his colleague for the greater cause. When Dave struggled his way into the spaceship, he without delay hurried to disconnect Hal despite the constant pleadings from Hal, who tried to convince Dave into not disconnecting him.  Later, whilst he was disconnecting Hal, there was a moment when Dave took dear to Hal’s pleas and responded in kindness, knowing Hal’s final moments were soon approaching. Dave was gentle towards the weak Hal, even if he was ‘killing’ him, being aware of his own superiority. Dave personified independency of mind, being willing to act on his own accord even though he remained alone in the entire spaceship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, in the neoclassical room we see Dave, ageing and perishing in front of our eyes, approaching his final moments at the bridge, taking the next and final step towards evolution when he extends his hand toward the fourth monolith like Adam did in the painting, &lt;em&gt;Creation of Adam&lt;/em&gt; by Michelangelo. Nietzsche, through his character Zarathustra, says in his magnum opus, &lt;i&gt;“I love him who willeth the creation of something beyond himself and then perisheth.”&lt;/i&gt; Dave gives in to something greater than himself, he is the Star child on his deathbed. &lt;em&gt;Space Odyssey&lt;/em&gt; is about going beyond good and evil, it is Kubrick’s take on how we must evolve and embrace the Superman within in a future that may not be so far away.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aritra Dutta Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Stanley Kubrick has produced phenomenal works throughout his career. His relentless, unflinching approach to the subjects he chose certainly showed in his films and we cannot be thankful enough for his contribution to the art of filmmaking. That said, any further discourse on how great a filmmaker he was seems pointless to me as it has already been addressed umpteen times by several, far more accomplished personas at greater lengths. What I would prefer to bring under the microscope today is his magnum opus 2001: A Space Odyssey and what lay at its heart. The film, which has now been minced to mere GIFs and iconic ringtones, was presumably his life’s most important and ambitious work, although I have no grounds to claim so. He started to work on 2001 in 1964 after his overture to Arthur C. Clarke, who co-wrote the script for the film and authored a book of the same name.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Picture of Dorian Gray</title>
      <link href="/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Picture of Dorian Gray" />
      <published>2019-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Picture-of-Dorian-Gray">&lt;p&gt;Several years ago, in quite another place, I began work upon the largest
compositional process I have ever undergone. I seemed to get it into my head as
I prepared to spend a year waving my hands at the poor, unfortunate singers of
St Mark’s Anglican Church, Florence, that I was far enough developed as a
composer that I could write for myself an opera. Not only that, but that I could
distil on my own one of the great works of Victorian literature, Oscar Wilde’s
&lt;em&gt;The Picture of Dorian Gray&lt;/em&gt; into a stage-show that would combine the sparkle of
&lt;em&gt;Die Fledermaus&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Figaro&lt;/em&gt; with the grim horror of one of Britten’s darker
dramas, &lt;em&gt;The Turn of the Screw&lt;/em&gt; or perhaps &lt;em&gt;Owen Wingrave&lt;/em&gt;. I was mistaken. It
took a chance encounter with one Jamie Fox, who had had similar ideas of taking
some time out in that magnificent Tuscan city, to turn my fantasy of an opera
into a more cohesive reality. Over several Negroni-fuelled evenings, and many
more ale-fuelled ones since our return to the UK, we translated Wilde’s
effervescent and yet shockingly terror-filled novella into a two-and-a-half act
show that now, slightly over three years later, has not only reached its
completion, but is, even as we speak, being prepared to be brandished before the
public by the wonderful people at &lt;em&gt;LoveOpera&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, no small part of me is turned towards retrospection: three years ago,
almost to the day of writing, I was asked by Jay Wolfe of &lt;em&gt;The Wolfian&lt;/em&gt; to write
a small article on the subject of setting about composing something of this
magnitude. I did my best – I had, at that point, only just finished &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt;’s
Prologue (the –and-a-half act) and had only vague ideas what the rest of the
opera had in store for me. Nevertheless, I now look back upon that article and
see that there is a compositional thread that stayed with me throughout the
process, even from the pre-Foxian beginnings. I knew then as I know now that
Wilde’s novella brought together the myriad elements of philosophy, dark humour,
and gothic horror. Musically, that meant each of these strands had to be
individually emphasised without any single one dominating the general effect of
the music. Of course, this was no easy task. But I did find a solution, if I can
really claim to have one. I studied closely how the likes of Henry Purcell,
Benjamin Britten, Claude Debussy, and Richard Wagner musically synthesised
various themes in their operas. I also made it a point to follow the man
himself: Oscar Wilde, taking note of how he balanced these themes to create such
a fine piece of art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that there is a fortunate divide between the Prologue of the work and the
two Acts. It is a divide that I touched on in my previous article: much of the
dialogue of the Prologue, taken from the first two chapters of Wilde’s work,
consists of Basil, the painter, philosophising with his friend Lord Henry, the
prime corruptive influence upon young Dorian before the boy actually arrives to
kick-start the drama. This leads to moments of the Prologue that feel somewhat
slower than the rest of the show, a turgid calm before a hopefully more driving
roller-coaster of a storm. And I believe this is as it should be, but I may well
be wrong – I shall have to see after I hear from the audiences in July and
September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as the previous article focussed so heavily upon the Prologue, on
account of the fact that neither of the other two acts actually yet existed, I
feel it may be much more suitable for us now to turn ourselves to a brief
musical guided tour, as it were, through at least some of the show. Therefore,
some introductions must be made:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt; has a main cast of six – it was quite a task to reduce down the large,
high-society focused drama into six characters, but what else is a chorus for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The characters are, in order of appearance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basil Hallward, (tenor) - the artist who holds Dorian as his muse,
unfortunately;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Henry “Harry” Wotton, (baritone) - a modern-day Mephistopheles with a
heart, somewhere deep down in there;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dorian himself, (mezzo-soprano) - I had this idea when watching Mozart’s
&lt;em&gt;Marriage of Figaro&lt;/em&gt; and realising Dorian and the teenage sex-pest Cherubino,
also a trouser-role, are not so very different if you gave the latter money and
immortality;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lady Victoria Wotton, (soprano) - aside from a few witty flashes in the novella,
Henry’s wife is reduced to acting off-screen, as it were. Jamie and I changed
that, as you will see;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sybil Vane, (soprano) – Poor Sybil. To fall in love with an as-yet not fully
corrupted Dorian, only to so quickly jilted after one bad night on the stage;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James Vane, (bass) – Sybil’s brother arrives in the 2nd Act, and will avenge his
sister… or, at least, he’ll try his utmost, raging best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behind these six there comes a host of minor characters that make up our show’s
chorus: the society lords and ladies, the audience of a run-down theatre, the
whores and opium fiends that make up the rich tapestry that is Victorian London
in Oscar’s (and our) minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so Act one begins, with Dorian, now in possession of Basil’s masterful
portrait of him, sitting alone in Lord Henry’s living-room, awaiting his friend.
It is here that I can illustrate the first influence of any of the composers
mentioned in my previous article: the act opens with a harp gesture (Fig. 1)
that is at once a textural back-cloth for the scene, and also acts as a
leitmotif, to borrow from Richard Wagner’s vocabulary. The theme, extended by
the strings and later the flute, can be said, therefore to be a genius loci – it
represents the building, musically, suggesting the luxurious, lavish
surroundings of the Wottons’ town-house. When, therefore, it reappears to
introduce use to Dorian’s own house, in both acts one and two, it possibly tells
us something about Dorian’s own following of Henry’s teachings – indeed, this
ability to manipulate melodies is an incredibly useful tool, compositionally, as
melodies are often indelibly linked with the emotion, location or character
alongside which they first appear. Thus, the twisting of a motif by introducing
it to a new context can suggest many things to an audience – watch out for it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/Dorian1.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 1&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we hear Henry’s own leitmotif, languorous triplets in the horns, except
this time it isn’t Henry, but his wife, whom neither we nor Dorian are expecting
to see. She has some interesting things to say on the subject of Wagner, too: “I
like Wagner’s music more than anyone’s. It is so loud that one can talk the
whole time without other people hearing what you say!” (I must say, I hope no
one uses &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt; to gossip under!) Nevertheless, as Victoria is here only for
some witty repartee and to avoid her husband at this point in the drama, when
Henry does finally show up she departs in short order – it’s not the healthiest
of relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry’s real entrance is accompanied by a different sort of music, though. He’s
a little drunk, and announces himself with a lop-sided little fanfare, before
launching in a duettino of banter with Dorian, which again manipulates his own
triplet motif into some fast-paced patter, as Dorian tells us that he has fallen
in rapturously love with an actress, “a rather commonplace debut” as Henry puts
it, named Sybil Vane. This confession leads to the first overtly romantic music
of the evening, as Dorian narrates how he came across his new sweetheart in a
sequence that is, structurally, a reflection of the early-Verdian style of
cantabile-cabaletta, but turned entirely on its head: in Verdi, or indeed,
Donizetti or Bellini, a cantabile-cabaletta consists of (as the name suggests) a
slow, more relaxed section that is very ‘sing-able’ followed by a more
barnstorming or pyrotechnic section. However, here Dorian sings them the wrong
way ‘round: first a fast, rhythmically twisting section (Fig. 2) describing her
beauty, and then two slower sections discussing first her acting ability and
then how lost he is in the romance of it all (Fig. 3), before the scene peters
out, and we transition to the next night, at the theatre&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/Dorian2.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/Dorian3.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 3&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, the theatre scene. This was a lot of fun to devise – I recall Jamie
gesticulating wildly as he explained to me that this was to be no great work of
Shakespearean spectacle, but a farcical experience, with a wooden, nervous
Juliet and a stout, middle-aged Romeo with a bit too much gut and far too much
Brian Blessed. And in the midst of it all sits Dorian, trying desperately to
convince Henry and Basil that Sybil is, in truth, a wonderful actress and well
worth his love. Therefore, I put my comedy hat on, and have tried to construct a
woeful imitation of Gilbert and Sullivan as an overture to this
play-within-a-play. There is no emotional core to this moment, no attempt to tug
at the heart-strings as one would expect from an overture to a performance of
&lt;em&gt;Romeo and Juliet&lt;/em&gt;. It’s just dross. As is the acting that follows it, but for
that I had to get more creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/Dorian4.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 4&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I set up a sense of scurrying tension within the on-stage audience by way
of a tiny fragment of melody that, when repeated over and over, becomes an
ostinato-texture which, much like the harp motif of Fig. 1, serves as a backdrop
for the entire scene. Over this, both our trio and the on-stage audience mutter
between each other until the curtain comes up and we see a sequence of three
scenes from the play, each successively worse: steadily, we progress from thin,
dull orchestration and bad singing, add in meandering, meaningless chromaticism
and unstable harmonies, and finally top it all off with some bombastic as the
crowd get steadily more unimpressed with the performance (Fig. 4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I write quite good ‘bad’ music, sometimes…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, Basil and Henry resolve to leave before the end of the show and
leave Dorian behind to talk to poor Sybil. Poor Sybil who is, in point of fact,
much more vivacious in real life than she ever was on stage, and so very much in
love with Dorian, as illustrated by her motif, which is itself an extension of
Dorian and the portrait’s own melody (Fig. 5, showing Dorian’s melody on top,
and Sybil’s extension below it), before flourishing into a much more lush
romantic gesture, and finally a re-hashing of one of Dorian’s own earlier
cantabile sections. She is so consumed by what could kindly be called her
infatuation or, worse, obsession with Dorian that she does not create her own
music, merely adopts his. And yet, in his refusal, Dorian himself mimics Henry’s
own more impassioned music from the Prologue; neither of them is, in truth, free
from obsessive thoughts about another person, or the ideals that they represent.
Unfortunately for Sybil, Dorian’s ideals lead him to abandon her, storm out,
have a wild night on the town before returning to his house, alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/Dorian5.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 5&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To cap the act off, Jamie and I had a bit of a predicament: the novella contains
a long time-skip before a certain climactic scene that we both wanted to include
as the finale of Act One. Whilst this reads incredibly well on paper – as the
years pass, Dorian becomes more and more corrupt until he goes beyond the pale –
this does not work near so well on a stage, where the audience is best served by
having a cohesive narrative, at least according to critics as far back as
Aristotle and the classical unities (of action, time and place). Thus, we
conflated several scenes from the book in order to make this finale to Act One
as impactful as can be. As Dorian recovers from his hangover, portrayed by slow,
chromatic triplet descents, his torpor is interrupted by the arrival of Basil,
who has bad news. This is the first change, as Wilde has Henry come to Dorian’s
house to deliver this particular news – that Sybil has committed suicide. Basil
is, therefore, able to finally act more overtly and lovingly towards his muse.
This also sets up a further conflation, as there are two scenes of Basil, in his
moralising fashion, trying to help Dorian. In the one, he asks to see the
portrait and is rebuffed, and on the other, many years later, Dorian crosses a
line. Basil is never seen again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we conflated these three scenes into one, I introduced, musically, one last
thing: the poor soprano playing Sybil would otherwise have only two scenes, and,
feeling sorry for her, I wrote her voice into the scene. Dorian, so affected by
the news of her death, can almost hear her calling out to him, turning a duet
into a trio, and having the final action of the scene, and indeed of the first
half of the Opera, become the deaths of two of &lt;em&gt;Dorian&lt;/em&gt;’s principals (Game of
Thrones style). I don’t believe I know of another opera where both the tenor and
the soprano are killed before we make it half-way. That ought to make an impact
– and hopefully leave the audience as eager to see the conclusion of the drama
as you may well be to read the final instalment of this little-guided tour
through my opera!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Olly Bowes</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Several years ago, in quite another place, I began work upon the largest compositional process I have ever undergone. I seemed to get it into my head as I prepared to spend a year waving my hands at the poor, unfortunate singers of St Mark’s Anglican Church, Florence, that I was far enough developed as a composer that I could write for myself an opera. Not only that, but that I could distil on my own one of the great works of Victorian literature, Oscar Wilde’s The Picture of Dorian Gray into a stage-show that would combine the sparkle of Die Fledermaus or Figaro with the grim horror of one of Britten’s darker dramas, The Turn of the Screw or perhaps Owen Wingrave. I was mistaken. It took a chance encounter with one Jamie Fox, who had had similar ideas of taking some time out in that magnificent Tuscan city, to turn my fantasy of an opera into a more cohesive reality. Over several Negroni-fuelled evenings, and many more ale-fuelled ones since our return to the UK, we translated Wilde’s effervescent and yet shockingly terror-filled novella into a two-and-a-half act show that now, slightly over three years later, has not only reached its completion, but is, even as we speak, being prepared to be brandished before the public by the wonderful people at LoveOpera.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Order in Chaos</title>
      <link href="/The-Order-in-Chaos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Order in Chaos" />
      <published>2019-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Order-in-Chaos</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Order-in-Chaos">&lt;p&gt;What is the most common phenomenon that binds together a seemingly bitter reality that manifests itself in nearly everything present in the universe? The answer, believe it or not, is chaos. Deep down we all know what chaos is, we have all experienced it and that’s why we despise it. From crowded halls to cluttered rooms to the endless traffic on the roads, chaos has been a most fundamental feature deeply woven into the fabric of our lives. It is not just in our day-to-day experiences, where chaos reigns. This miraculous yet notorious concept has also made its way into the most certain discipline of science as the “theory of chaos”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While chaos as a feature of human existence has been a cause of concern since time immemorial, its presence in the sciences as a separate area of study is relatively new. From the outset, the prime objective of science has always been about addressing the questions of uncertainty, and uncovering the underlying pattern in what is seemingly disoriented in nature. It was this pursuit of “pattern recognition” that resulted in the blossoming of Newtonian physics along with the belief that mathematics is the ultimate truth capable of generating precise predictions of the future. The universe was assumed to be a mechanical entity operating in accordance with certain unalterable mathematical principles and norms, making order and harmony almost synonymous with reality and existence. This belief, however, was short-lived. The prescient beauty of Newtonian claims of universal order crumbled into nothingness as Einsteinian theories and New Age Physics shook the scientific world. This advent of the new and the bold provided fertile ground for the recognition of “the chaos” hidden in the complexities of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of chaos was first brought into scientific scrutiny by the French mathematician Henri Poincaré in the 1880’s, during his study of the interaction between the planets, where he noted that even the slightest error or change in the initial conditions can produce enormous consequences in the final phenomenon. Later this took the form of the “butterfly effect” advanced by Edward Lorenz a mathematician and meteorologist in the 1960’s, who in spite of his precise calculations, could not predict the weather accurately. His findings culminated in his famous speech “Does the flutter of a butterfly’s wings in Brazil set up a tornado in Texas?” This speech was a major breakthrough in the history of chaos, establishing uncertainty to be the only certainty in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The butterfly effect is inherently present everywhere, be it in the uncertainty of weather mechanisms or in the most remarkable episodes of human history. After all, it was a rejected application to the Vienna Academy of Fine Art that caused the Holocaust and the Second World War. While this may sound utterly ridiculous, it is true that the Academy of Fine Arts did reject the application letter of the very infamous dictator, Adolf Hitler, which, as his autobiography &lt;i&gt;Mein Kampf&lt;/i&gt; itself tells you, culminated in his anti-Semitic feelings, his enrolment in the German army and much later the Second World War! Imagine how the world would have been had the Academy accepted him. History is replete with examples of how things could have turned out differently if only one tiny event were altered in the slightest way: Had Mughal Emperor Jahangir not been drinking buddies with Sir Thomas Roe―an emissary from England―the East India Company might never really have gained a true foothold in India. The very fact that you are reading this article right now makes the world function in a particular way than it would have otherwise. Who knows! Maybe two minutes of procrastination today may make you question your career choices tomorrow and lead you somewhere you never expected to be in 40 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is where do we find order? Is it even possible to find order in a world, which is so consumed and immersed in chaos? In a world of chaos, how did we attain our present form endowed with thinking and reasoning abilities, when we are in actuality nothing but a combination of molecules? How do simple cells with no central control system divide and differentiate on their own to form a complex foetus in the womb? This is precisely what the English mathematician Alan Turing discussed in his work, &lt;i&gt;The Chemical Basis of Morphogenesis &lt;/i&gt;, where he underscored the miraculously ingrained patterns of self-organisation observed in living organisms. This spontaneous order stems from the “local interactions” within the disordered system, such as a majestic flock of birds soaring high in the sky, or the schools of fish underwater. While these biological systems may seem chaotic when viewed from the standpoint of an individual constituent within the system (i.e. a bird flying in a flock), they exhibit extraordinary order and exquisite patterns, when analysed as a whole from a third person’s perspective (a human observing the flock of birds). It is self-organisation that leads to grains of sands being unconsciously assembled such that they create magnificent sand dunes. Trees, rivers and blood vessels branching into stunning patterns of self-similarity, all beautifully demonstrate this paradox of order in disorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this means that we, in our petty human lives, fail to understand that chaos is nothing but a masked form of order and the key lies not in evading it but embracing it. While chaos may cause momentary frustration, it enables man to see the greater truth, showing him how his pathetic attempts to control everything around him may verily be the cause of his misery. In the words of the Buddha, “&lt;i&gt;Chaos is inherent in all compounded things. Strive on with diligence&lt;/i&gt;”. The beauty of life lies in the perfect blend of both the systems and not merely escaping from one. Embrace the chaos, rise every morning in the expectation of being surprised and learning something new, let life teach you how to have peace in all this turmoil that you cannot control.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Namya Tewari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">What is the most common phenomenon that binds together a seemingly bitter reality that manifests itself in nearly everything present in the universe? The answer, believe it or not, is chaos. Deep down we all know what chaos is, we have all experienced it and that’s why we despise it. From crowded halls to cluttered rooms to the endless traffic on the roads, chaos has been a most fundamental feature deeply woven into the fabric of our lives. It is not just in our day-to-day experiences, where chaos reigns. This miraculous yet notorious concept has also made its way into the most certain discipline of science as the “theory of chaos”.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
