<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/khushboo.pandey/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2022-03-06T09:57:21+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/khushboo.pandey/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Water Supply &amp;amp; Sanitation: Private vs Public Sector</title>
      <link href="/Water-Supply-Sanitation-Private-vs-Public-Sector" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Water Supply &amp; Sanitation: Private vs Public Sector" />
      <published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Water-Supply-Sanitation-Private-vs-Public-Sector</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Water-Supply-Sanitation-Private-vs-Public-Sector">&lt;p&gt;Today, about 2.6 billion people live without basic sanitation and nearly 1.1 billion live without access to safe drinking water. Around 13% of the world population still defecates in the open. The&amp;nbsp; diarrhoeal diseases that result from poor sanitation kill more than five million children every year and 9% of these deaths happen to be of children aged less than five years. Up to 50% of malnutrition is attributable to poor water, sanitation and hygiene, as are many neglected tropical diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Death and disease due to inadequate sanitation not only burdens a country's healthcare system, it also causes a huge emotional and financial cost to families. Children drop out of school and fail to reach their potential, especially young girls. Moreover, research shows how poor sanitation has a substantial impact on the economy as well. Countries with poor access to sanitation are losing significant proportions of their GDP – in India, this figure is over 5%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It thus stands to reason that we need better sanitation for a better economy, a better society and a better world. The question is: how do we achieve that? Moreover, which sector should cater to Water Supply and Sanitation (WSS)? Private or Public?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economists champion public sector involvement in cases of market failures and unequal distribution of economic outcomes. The prime justification for public provision of WSS is market failures such as natural monopoly, externalities, and public good characteristics. A sole profit-oriented producer of a good with declining long-term average cost will restrict output to monopoly level, thereby leading to a social welfare loss. Thus, government intervention is essential to restore efficiency. Moreover, the positive externalities gained from use of WSS further strengthens this argument. It is the responsibility of the government to not just focus on efficiency (the primary focus of profit-oriented enterprises) but also to make sure that distribution is provided to all, without any disparity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, experiences from the past have shown that public-owned utilities have not always been successful both in developed and developing nations. This has been especially so in the latter case owing to various non-market failures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public WSS services have remained lacking on grounds of efficiency. Large proportions of the population have little or no access to public WSS services, while the remaining who receive it often face issues of poor quality, characterised by frequent breakdowns and unreliable supply.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simultaneously, these water utilities barely have enough to cover operational costs, leaving no surplus available to finance the expansion of networks, eventually leading to a downward spiral in customer service. This results in the consumer's reluctance to pay higher tariffs ultimately leading to a deterioration of assets and squandering of financial resources. This descending cycle attracts political interference and furthers the velocity of the fall.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, divergence of personal gains of employees from the social goals and absence of reliable measures to hold such officials accountable further exacerbates the deplorable functioning of such organisations. These organisations become hotbeds of corruption and maladministration. Hence, there have been growing views in favour of privatisation for increased competition and better efficiency. Furthermore, WSS does fulfil the prerequisite of a private good by being rivalrous in nature, and the additional benefits associated with its consumption generates a stronger incentive for individuals to pay higher for obtaining better quality services.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The private sector has long played a role in the water sector, particularly in the industrialised economies. Historically, water supplies in many cities of the US were provided by private players until the government reverted the ownership to itself. The WSS services are entirely provided by the private sector in countries such as the UK, France, Philippines, etc.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Owing to the principal role of Water and Sanitation, such countries do have in place mechanisms where the government has oversight over the private sector. It accomplishes this through models which outsource management and supply of WSS while retaining public ownership, or by providing concessions against contracts, or through the presence of a regulatory agency. The only exception is France where there exists no sort of supervision by the administration. Private sector involvement in such a key area of the economy presents numerous risks for the former, such as commercial, financial, technical, legal and political risks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commercial risks involve the fear that the private investors may not be able to recoup their investment and make a profit, while technical risks pertain to insufficient knowledge about the state of installations resulting in operational failures. Legal risks occur as a result of contractual disputes, while financial risks relate to currency devaluations and convertibility of local to foreign currency, especially when foreign borrowings are used to finance services. Political risks stem from governments' changing policy in the course of implementation of the contract or due to their reluctance in charging higher tariffs.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example to illustrate the risks posed could be seen in the case of Argentina. Water privatisation in Argentina began in 1992, where certain concessions were awarded by the administration to private companies. Post 2001, all concessions were terminated under the leadership of a different government on the basis that the contracts were not fulfilled by the providing company. The private companies conceded to their failure in meeting the targets, but argued that a freeze in tariffs at the time of the devaluation of the Peso during the Argentine economic crisis violated the contract, and thus, made it impossible for them to achieve the set targets. In July 2010, the International Centre for the Settlement of Investment Disputes (ICSID) ruled in favour of the private concessionaires and entitled them to compensation. Thus, there were losses faced by both the private companies and the government, with no winners in such a fight.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Private sector participation (in such areas) has generally been touted as the solution to the pressing need of huge capital investments in the water sector. However, the ability of the private sector to actually invest in water infrastructure is doubtful. As per the Global Water Partnership, estimates of the total investment needs for new water infrastructure amounted to $180 billion per year for the period of 2000–2005. However, according to historical data, total private investment in WSS has averaged $3.3 billion per year, i.e. only about 1.8% of the annual investment needs of developing countries. In Asia, the annual average private investment of $1.9 billion in water (World Bank PPI database) accounts for 7.9% of the total financing needs of the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another claimed basis for involvement of private players is increased competition so as to improve the overall efficiency. However, the investment level in the distribution networks is massive relative to the size of the market, which obscures the potential for direct product market competition in developing countries. The entry to this market is often done on contractual basis from governments but factors like political risks, long payback periods, huge sunk costs and high degree of non-transparency while awarding the contracts deter private sector participation. Additionally, there has not been any substantial data to evidently prove the productive efficiency of the private sector in sanitation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, one of the most important arguments in favour of private sector participation is the expansion in the scope of services due to the huge resources it brings with it. However, this theoretical abundance is difficult to translate into actions in the developing economies for the following reasons: 1) On the demand side, the unwillingness of the consumers to pay cost-recovering tariffs (maybe due to unawareness of the benefits of WSS); and 2) on the supply side, neglect of the poor by profit-oriented firms which pursue only the wealthy section to recoup their large investments. Moreover, rural areas have scattered populations that often present technical, organisational, and financial sustainability issues, thus proving to be unviable for private companies. As per data, private investments have appeared to have benefited the relatively wealthier countries due to the lower risks associated with them in ways such as market friendly policy and institutional environments, high household incomes, effective regulatory mechanisms, etc.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To illustrate, in the period 1990–2005, of the total&amp;nbsp; investment of $46.2 billion in WSS, the upper middle, lower middle and the lowest income nations captured 56%, 43% and 1% respectively.&amp;nbsp; Thus, one can conclude that provision of water supply and sanitation is not a game of either-or, rather an affair where the nation needs to create an enabling environment that can harness innovation and good governance for achieving success.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      
        <category term="humanity" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Today, about 2.6 billion people live without basic sanitation and nearly 1.1 billion live without access to safe drinking water. Around 13% of the world population still defecates in the open. The&amp;nbsp; diarrhoeal diseases that result from poor sanitation kill more than five million children every year and 9% of these deaths happen to be of children aged less than five years. Up to 50% of malnutrition is attributable to poor water, sanitation and hygiene, as are many neglected tropical diseases. Death and disease due to inadequate sanitation not only burdens a country's healthcare system, it also causes a huge emotional and financial cost to families. Children drop out of school and fail to reach their potential, especially young girls. Moreover, research shows how poor sanitation has a substantial impact on the economy as well. Countries with poor access to sanitation are losing significant proportions of their GDP – in India, this figure is over 5%. It thus stands to reason that we need better sanitation for a better economy, a better society and a better world. The question is: how do we achieve that? Moreover, which sector should cater to Water Supply and Sanitation (WSS)? Private or Public? Economists champion public sector involvement in cases of market failures and unequal distribution of economic outcomes. The prime justification for public provision of WSS is market failures such as natural monopoly, externalities, and public good characteristics. A sole profit-oriented producer of a good with declining long-term average cost will restrict output to monopoly level, thereby leading to a social welfare loss. Thus, government intervention is essential to restore efficiency. Moreover, the positive externalities gained from use of WSS further strengthens this argument. It is the responsibility of the government to not just focus on efficiency (the primary focus of profit-oriented enterprises) but also to make sure that distribution is provided to all, without any disparity.&amp;nbsp; However, experiences from the past have shown that public-owned utilities have not always been successful both in developed and developing nations. This has been especially so in the latter case owing to various non-market failures. Public WSS services have remained lacking on grounds of efficiency. Large proportions of the population have little or no access to public WSS services, while the remaining who receive it often face issues of poor quality, characterised by frequent breakdowns and unreliable supply.&amp;nbsp; Simultaneously, these water utilities barely have enough to cover operational costs, leaving no surplus available to finance the expansion of networks, eventually leading to a downward spiral in customer service. This results in the consumer's reluctance to pay higher tariffs ultimately leading to a deterioration of assets and squandering of financial resources. This descending cycle attracts political interference and furthers the velocity of the fall.&amp;nbsp; Secondly, divergence of personal gains of employees from the social goals and absence of reliable measures to hold such officials accountable further exacerbates the deplorable functioning of such organisations. These organisations become hotbeds of corruption and maladministration. Hence, there have been growing views in favour of privatisation for increased competition and better efficiency. Furthermore, WSS does fulfil the prerequisite of a private good by being rivalrous in nature, and the additional benefits associated with its consumption generates a stronger incentive for individuals to pay higher for obtaining better quality services.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The private sector has long played a role in the water sector, particularly in the industrialised economies. Historically, water supplies in many cities of the US were provided by private players until the government reverted the ownership to itself. The WSS services are entirely provided by the private sector in countries such as the UK, France, Philippines, etc.&amp;nbsp; Owing to the principal role of Water and Sanitation, such countries do have in place mechanisms where the government has oversight over the private sector. It accomplishes this through models which outsource management and supply of WSS while retaining public ownership, or by providing concessions against contracts, or through the presence of a regulatory agency. The only exception is France where there exists no sort of supervision by the administration. Private sector involvement in such a key area of the economy presents numerous risks for the former, such as commercial, financial, technical, legal and political risks.&amp;nbsp; Commercial risks involve the fear that the private investors may not be able to recoup their investment and make a profit, while technical risks pertain to insufficient knowledge about the state of installations resulting in operational failures. Legal risks occur as a result of contractual disputes, while financial risks relate to currency devaluations and convertibility of local to foreign currency, especially when foreign borrowings are used to finance services. Political risks stem from governments' changing policy in the course of implementation of the contract or due to their reluctance in charging higher tariffs.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; An example to illustrate the risks posed could be seen in the case of Argentina. Water privatisation in Argentina began in 1992, where certain concessions were awarded by the administration to private companies. Post 2001, all concessions were terminated under the leadership of a different government on the basis that the contracts were not fulfilled by the providing company. The private companies conceded to their failure in meeting the targets, but argued that a freeze in tariffs at the time of the devaluation of the Peso during the Argentine economic crisis violated the contract, and thus, made it impossible for them to achieve the set targets. In July 2010, the International Centre for the Settlement of Investment Disputes (ICSID) ruled in favour of the private concessionaires and entitled them to compensation. Thus, there were losses faced by both the private companies and the government, with no winners in such a fight.&amp;nbsp; Private sector participation (in such areas) has generally been touted as the solution to the pressing need of huge capital investments in the water sector. However, the ability of the private sector to actually invest in water infrastructure is doubtful. As per the Global Water Partnership, estimates of the total investment needs for new water infrastructure amounted to $180 billion per year for the period of 2000–2005. However, according to historical data, total private investment in WSS has averaged $3.3 billion per year, i.e. only about 1.8% of the annual investment needs of developing countries. In Asia, the annual average private investment of $1.9 billion in water (World Bank PPI database) accounts for 7.9% of the total financing needs of the region. Another claimed basis for involvement of private players is increased competition so as to improve the overall efficiency. However, the investment level in the distribution networks is massive relative to the size of the market, which obscures the potential for direct product market competition in developing countries. The entry to this market is often done on contractual basis from governments but factors like political risks, long payback periods, huge sunk costs and high degree of non-transparency while awarding the contracts deter private sector participation. Additionally, there has not been any substantial data to evidently prove the productive efficiency of the private sector in sanitation.&amp;nbsp; Lastly, one of the most important arguments in favour of private sector participation is the expansion in the scope of services due to the huge resources it brings with it. However, this theoretical abundance is difficult to translate into actions in the developing economies for the following reasons: 1) On the demand side, the unwillingness of the consumers to pay cost-recovering tariffs (maybe due to unawareness of the benefits of WSS); and 2) on the supply side, neglect of the poor by profit-oriented firms which pursue only the wealthy section to recoup their large investments. Moreover, rural areas have scattered populations that often present technical, organisational, and financial sustainability issues, thus proving to be unviable for private companies. As per data, private investments have appeared to have benefited the relatively wealthier countries due to the lower risks associated with them in ways such as market friendly policy and institutional environments, high household incomes, effective regulatory mechanisms, etc.&amp;nbsp; To illustrate, in the period 1990–2005, of the total&amp;nbsp; investment of $46.2 billion in WSS, the upper middle, lower middle and the lowest income nations captured 56%, 43% and 1% respectively.&amp;nbsp; Thus, one can conclude that provision of water supply and sanitation is not a game of either-or, rather an affair where the nation needs to create an enabling environment that can harness innovation and good governance for achieving success.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Evergrande: A Cave-in of Real Estate?</title>
      <link href="/Evergrande" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evergrande: A Cave-in of Real Estate?" />
      <published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Evergrande</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Evergrande">&lt;p&gt;The year 2020 was the worst year for economic growth since World War II - all economies came to a standstill with the raging spread of the virus. However, China, the country where the first outbreak of COVID-19 was reported, was the only major economy in the world to report a positive GDP growth in that year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to November 2021, the second-largest economy seems to be in a precarious situation with various credit rating firms cutting down on its growth forecasts owing to glaring uncertainties in the nation.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my last article, I covered &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;China's crackdown on its tech sector&lt;/a&gt;. Now the ball has come rolling to its real estate sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evergrande Group, China's second-largest property developer and the world’s most indebted real estate firm with liabilities amounting to $300 billion, informed bondholders in early September about its inability to honour its interest obligation. (For context, Russia's state debt &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.themoscowtimes.com/2021/02/24/russias-government-debt-rose-40-in-2020-a73044&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;in 2020 was $257 billion&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evergrande was founded by Mr Xu Jiayin, who was once the country’s richest man, in 1996, and was in the bottled water business. Later the company expanded into several areas, including pig farming, owning a football club, wealth management and the electric car segment. However, it was its real estate business for which it was widely known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, it recorded a gross profit of nearly $19 billion and in the year before that, it was on the Fortune Global 500 list. The company owns 2% of all newly-constructed real estate in China and employs about 200,000 people directly and helps in sustaining more than 3.8 million jobs indirectly every year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The possible collapse of an organisation this big can be brushed aside as a one-time occurrence, however, one cannot turn a blind eye when many such firms in that line of business are on the same path: Chinese luxury developer Fantasia Holding Group and the Sinic Holdings group have also announced a default on their debt repayment obligations in mid-October.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cause of worry intensifies when one observes that around 30% of China’s Gross Domestic Product (GDP) is related to its real estate sector. Therefore, the fall of real estate companies can leave a dent not only in the Chinese economy but the global economy as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The State Of Real Estate In China&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the late 1980's, China started moving from public housing to the commercial property model. Post-1994, The central government decentralised the goals and interests of the policymakers - passing the responsibility of social welfare services to local administration but with taxes to be submitted back to them.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The imbalance of funds led provincial governments to create state-owned shell companies called Local Government Financing Vehicles (LGFV). They gave these LGFV free valuable lands which were then used to take out loans that the administration themselves could not. Consequently, this made the administration seem healthier because their debt was now hidden while at the same time they met quotas set by Beijing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, land became the backbone of local economies.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, steep discounts and low-interest rates were offered to citizens as an act of welfare. Strict regulation by the government on how much money leaves the country left citizens with limited investment options - stock markets became synonymous with volatility and risk and housing gained the reputation of safe and profitable investments in the country. Housing prices were also such that they fell only once in the two decades that followed the Asian Financial Crisis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the aforementioned reasons, real estate is one of the most loved sectors of the economy with homeownership in China being the highest in the world, i.e. around 90%. It has become the country's leading pillar of economic growth with a contribution of around 15-30% to the GDP. In the COVID-19 period alone, the sector has grown by 4.9%.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, an unusual trend is seen in the country. The boom in real estate is coming at a cost: high vacancy rates in cities due to the vast majority of home purchases being second/third homes. In 2018, 87% of new home buyers already owned at least one flat.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the societal norm in China is such that male marriages demand homeownership. Decades of the one-child policy have resulted in an imbalance between males and females with scales tipping in favour of the latter. As a result, female families have become awfully picky, with the groom's homeownership being one of the prerequisites. As per a study, home prices are higher in cities of disproportionate male-to-female ratios.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In cities like Shenzhen, Beijing, Shanghai - it takes nearly 40 years worth of an accumulated average income to afford a home. Thus the vast majority of homes are purchased even before the construction has begun, sometimes years in advance.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With overhead demand, some developers undertake techniques such as selling batches of properties in glitzy online events or through raffles-off in lotteries where thousands of apartments are often sold out in minutes, giving the winners mere hours to submit down payments or lose the opportunity.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What all these instances, numbers and facts point towards is that of a speculative market, i.e. the assumption that prices would only go up.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However the demographic of the country suggests otherwise. In the next ten years, the country’s over-55 cohort will increase in size by 120 million, but by the end of the century, the overall population will be cut in half. The majority of present home buyers are precisely from this segment which China would soon lose. In addition, with age, home requirements keep differing.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was reasonable to anticipate a decade ago that the rapid urbanisation demand would be met by bringing in more than enough migrants to effectively cancel out the effects of ageing. Nonetheless, the statistics prove otherwise with the migration rate falling below the country’s 60% urbanisation rate. Moreover, such exorbitant home prices act as a further deterrent to the very people that were to be attracted by the construction of so many homes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the demand-supply misproportion is haunting the real estate space.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coming Back&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the context of speculative and overpriced real estate being understood, what consequences are in store, given the defaults of Evergrande and other real estate firms?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trigger for this fall is attributed to new guidelines, known as The Red Lines, introduced by the government in August 2020 for property developers. The rule requires the ratio of liabilities-to-assets of developers and their net debt-to-equity ratio to be below 70% and 100% respectively whilst requiring real estate firms to maintain the cash-to-short term debt ratio at a minimum of 100%.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any borrower failing to meet these requirements would be restricted from raising more funds, practically cutting off developers from taking on more debts. This means a complete alteration in the nature of the real estate business, which relies heavily on borrowing for its capital requirements.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crackdown on developers is in line with China’s supremo Xi Jinping's slogan of ‘Common Prosperity’, where the estate market is being regulated so as to puncture the property bubble and make housing more affordable. Some also see this as an example of the government taking on influential private businessmen under the guise of the ‘common prosperity’ programme to fight income inequality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This rule is about-turn, the government previously encouraged developers to take on huge debt through the heavily state-controlled financial sector to develop new properties. In the past, they have even bailed out troubled business entities thereby leading to the indiscriminate allocation of resources to the sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per an analyst, “&lt;em&gt;A regime shift is occurring without necessarily the markets fully comprehending the enormous underlying change to the structure of the economy.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many have called the Evergrande fiasco China’s own ‘Lehman moment', alluding to the failure of the US bank Lehman Brothers, which precipitated the 2008 financial crisis. Some observers believe that the current crisis was a long time coming owing to the company's unsustainable business model.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2012, Andrew Left of Citron Research argued that Evergrande was insolvent and that the company was engaged in aggressive accounting practices to cover up its troubles.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was said that the company held properties that it could not sell on its balance sheet as inventory, thus avoiding the booking of losses. The company was also accused of running a Ponzi scheme as it relied on the constant inflow of funds to prop up a business model that is fundamentally unsustainable. Interestingly, Evergrande has over the years consistently reported strong profits and has showcased a strong balance sheet with sufficient liquid assets.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A letter leaked last year by &lt;em&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/em&gt; showed Evergrande’s executives seeking financial assistance from the Chinese government by admitting their inability to meet their debt obligations to banks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per a &lt;em&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/em&gt; report, the administration is potentially going ahead with the restructuring of debt. The company has sold off various units at a discounted price to meet funding requirements. The organisation's deal with state-owned Yuexiu Property to sell a 51% stake in its property services unit has also been put on hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markets are closely observing the Chinese economic environment owing to growing uncertainties. Various countries are concerned about a possible slowdown resulting from the rebalancing of the economy away from the property sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China is the biggest steel importer and a drop in construction activities would affect the global steel prices. The IMF has estimated that a fall of 1% in demand from China would decrease global GDP by 25%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chinese administration has sent a clear signal: the only expectation one should have is unpredictability and nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The year 2020 was the worst year for economic growth since World War II - all economies came to a standstill with the raging spread of the virus. However, China, the country where the first outbreak of COVID-19 was reported, was the only major economy in the world to report a positive GDP growth in that year. Fast forward to November 2021, the second-largest economy seems to be in a precarious situation with various credit rating firms cutting down on its growth forecasts owing to glaring uncertainties in the nation.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; In my last article, I covered China's crackdown on its tech sector. Now the ball has come rolling to its real estate sector.&amp;nbsp; Evergrande Group, China's second-largest property developer and the world’s most indebted real estate firm with liabilities amounting to $300 billion, informed bondholders in early September about its inability to honour its interest obligation. (For context, Russia's state debt in 2020 was $257 billion.) Evergrande was founded by Mr Xu Jiayin, who was once the country’s richest man, in 1996, and was in the bottled water business. Later the company expanded into several areas, including pig farming, owning a football club, wealth management and the electric car segment. However, it was its real estate business for which it was widely known. In 2020, it recorded a gross profit of nearly $19 billion and in the year before that, it was on the Fortune Global 500 list. The company owns 2% of all newly-constructed real estate in China and employs about 200,000 people directly and helps in sustaining more than 3.8 million jobs indirectly every year. The possible collapse of an organisation this big can be brushed aside as a one-time occurrence, however, one cannot turn a blind eye when many such firms in that line of business are on the same path: Chinese luxury developer Fantasia Holding Group and the Sinic Holdings group have also announced a default on their debt repayment obligations in mid-October. The cause of worry intensifies when one observes that around 30% of China’s Gross Domestic Product (GDP) is related to its real estate sector. Therefore, the fall of real estate companies can leave a dent not only in the Chinese economy but the global economy as well.&amp;nbsp; The State Of Real Estate In China&amp;nbsp; In the late 1980's, China started moving from public housing to the commercial property model. Post-1994, The central government decentralised the goals and interests of the policymakers - passing the responsibility of social welfare services to local administration but with taxes to be submitted back to them.&amp;nbsp; The imbalance of funds led provincial governments to create state-owned shell companies called Local Government Financing Vehicles (LGFV). They gave these LGFV free valuable lands which were then used to take out loans that the administration themselves could not. Consequently, this made the administration seem healthier because their debt was now hidden while at the same time they met quotas set by Beijing.&amp;nbsp; As a result, land became the backbone of local economies.&amp;nbsp; Additionally, steep discounts and low-interest rates were offered to citizens as an act of welfare. Strict regulation by the government on how much money leaves the country left citizens with limited investment options - stock markets became synonymous with volatility and risk and housing gained the reputation of safe and profitable investments in the country. Housing prices were also such that they fell only once in the two decades that followed the Asian Financial Crisis.&amp;nbsp; Due to the aforementioned reasons, real estate is one of the most loved sectors of the economy with homeownership in China being the highest in the world, i.e. around 90%. It has become the country's leading pillar of economic growth with a contribution of around 15-30% to the GDP. In the COVID-19 period alone, the sector has grown by 4.9%.&amp;nbsp; However, an unusual trend is seen in the country. The boom in real estate is coming at a cost: high vacancy rates in cities due to the vast majority of home purchases being second/third homes. In 2018, 87% of new home buyers already owned at least one flat.&amp;nbsp; Additionally, the societal norm in China is such that male marriages demand homeownership. Decades of the one-child policy have resulted in an imbalance between males and females with scales tipping in favour of the latter. As a result, female families have become awfully picky, with the groom's homeownership being one of the prerequisites. As per a study, home prices are higher in cities of disproportionate male-to-female ratios.&amp;nbsp; In cities like Shenzhen, Beijing, Shanghai - it takes nearly 40 years worth of an accumulated average income to afford a home. Thus the vast majority of homes are purchased even before the construction has begun, sometimes years in advance.&amp;nbsp; With overhead demand, some developers undertake techniques such as selling batches of properties in glitzy online events or through raffles-off in lotteries where thousands of apartments are often sold out in minutes, giving the winners mere hours to submit down payments or lose the opportunity.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; What all these instances, numbers and facts point towards is that of a speculative market, i.e. the assumption that prices would only go up.&amp;nbsp; However the demographic of the country suggests otherwise. In the next ten years, the country’s over-55 cohort will increase in size by 120 million, but by the end of the century, the overall population will be cut in half. The majority of present home buyers are precisely from this segment which China would soon lose. In addition, with age, home requirements keep differing.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; It was reasonable to anticipate a decade ago that the rapid urbanisation demand would be met by bringing in more than enough migrants to effectively cancel out the effects of ageing. Nonetheless, the statistics prove otherwise with the migration rate falling below the country’s 60% urbanisation rate. Moreover, such exorbitant home prices act as a further deterrent to the very people that were to be attracted by the construction of so many homes.&amp;nbsp; Thus, the demand-supply misproportion is haunting the real estate space.&amp;nbsp; Coming Back With the context of speculative and overpriced real estate being understood, what consequences are in store, given the defaults of Evergrande and other real estate firms?&amp;nbsp; The trigger for this fall is attributed to new guidelines, known as The Red Lines, introduced by the government in August 2020 for property developers. The rule requires the ratio of liabilities-to-assets of developers and their net debt-to-equity ratio to be below 70% and 100% respectively whilst requiring real estate firms to maintain the cash-to-short term debt ratio at a minimum of 100%.&amp;nbsp; Any borrower failing to meet these requirements would be restricted from raising more funds, practically cutting off developers from taking on more debts. This means a complete alteration in the nature of the real estate business, which relies heavily on borrowing for its capital requirements.&amp;nbsp; The crackdown on developers is in line with China’s supremo Xi Jinping's slogan of ‘Common Prosperity’, where the estate market is being regulated so as to puncture the property bubble and make housing more affordable. Some also see this as an example of the government taking on influential private businessmen under the guise of the ‘common prosperity’ programme to fight income inequality. This rule is about-turn, the government previously encouraged developers to take on huge debt through the heavily state-controlled financial sector to develop new properties. In the past, they have even bailed out troubled business entities thereby leading to the indiscriminate allocation of resources to the sector.&amp;nbsp; As per an analyst, “A regime shift is occurring without necessarily the markets fully comprehending the enormous underlying change to the structure of the economy.” Many have called the Evergrande fiasco China’s own ‘Lehman moment', alluding to the failure of the US bank Lehman Brothers, which precipitated the 2008 financial crisis. Some observers believe that the current crisis was a long time coming owing to the company's unsustainable business model.&amp;nbsp; In 2012, Andrew Left of Citron Research argued that Evergrande was insolvent and that the company was engaged in aggressive accounting practices to cover up its troubles.&amp;nbsp; It was said that the company held properties that it could not sell on its balance sheet as inventory, thus avoiding the booking of losses. The company was also accused of running a Ponzi scheme as it relied on the constant inflow of funds to prop up a business model that is fundamentally unsustainable. Interestingly, Evergrande has over the years consistently reported strong profits and has showcased a strong balance sheet with sufficient liquid assets.&amp;nbsp; A letter leaked last year by Bloomberg showed Evergrande’s executives seeking financial assistance from the Chinese government by admitting their inability to meet their debt obligations to banks.&amp;nbsp; As per a Bloomberg report, the administration is potentially going ahead with the restructuring of debt. The company has sold off various units at a discounted price to meet funding requirements. The organisation's deal with state-owned Yuexiu Property to sell a 51% stake in its property services unit has also been put on hold. Markets are closely observing the Chinese economic environment owing to growing uncertainties. Various countries are concerned about a possible slowdown resulting from the rebalancing of the economy away from the property sector.&amp;nbsp; China is the biggest steel importer and a drop in construction activities would affect the global steel prices. The IMF has estimated that a fall of 1% in demand from China would decrease global GDP by 25%. The Chinese administration has sent a clear signal: the only expectation one should have is unpredictability and nothing more.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Power Play: China’s Command &amp;amp; Control</title>
      <link href="/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Power Play: China's Command &amp; Control" />
      <published>2021-09-21T02:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-21T02:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Power-Play-China-s-Command-Control">&lt;p&gt;In November 2020, I authored an article on China’s move of&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Derailing-of-the-World-s-Biggest-IPO&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt; scuttling Ant Group Co.’s blockbuster $37 billion listing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Little did we know that it was just the beginning of an excessive clampdown on the country's technological sector.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To continue with the story of e-commerce giant Alibaba, the country’s authorities imposed a record fine - $2.8 billion in 2021, after an investigation that found it had abused its dominant market position for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China’s unprecedented crackdown on its tech industry has cost several companies and their investors hundreds of billions of dollars. Tencent alone has &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/markets/stocks/news/market-darling-tencent-turns-into-worlds-worst-stock-bet-with-170-billion-wipeout/articleshow/84853892.cms&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;had $170 billion shaved off its value&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; For context, that’s more than ten Byju’s, India’s biggest startup, which is valued at $16.5 billion.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The July Roundup by Goldman Sachs Group Inc shows that since November, the country’s regulators have taken more than 50 actual or reported actions on areas spanning antitrust, finance, data security and social equality, i.e. more than one move a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, China has assiduously built up its tech sector, and has borrowed an industrial and internet model from the West. Arguably it was a resounding success, then why is it now trying to strangle the golden goose it had once cradled?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.natlawreview.com/article/china-issues-data-security-law&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;adopted a new cybersecurity law in June&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which builds on the foundation of the 2017 Cyber Security Law, that started tightening the control of data flow. However, since the measure was vaguely worded, it remained unclear how it would be implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around the same time, the Chinese economy was rebounding from its bout with COVID-19, lifting the nation's&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/06/10/didi-chuxing-files-for-ipo-booked-6point4-billion-revenue-in-q1.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/06/10/didi-chuxing-files-for-ipo-booked-6point4-billion-revenue-in-q1.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;ride, hailing giant Didi Global&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s revenue with it as the US stock market continued to be in a bull run. Didi's long venture investors, including Softbank’s Vision Fund, urged seizing the moment to take the company public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company made its debut at $14 on the New York Stock Exchange on the last day of June 2021, raising $4.4 billion - the biggest stock sale by a Chinese company since the 2014 listing of Alibaba Group Holding Ltd.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its shares briefly topped $18 in the first days of trading, before China’s cyber security watchdog - Cyberspace Administration of China (CAC) stunned investors on July 2 by launching a data-security probe into Didi and blocking its China business from adding new users.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crackdown worsened on July 9, when 25 more Didi apps - including ones used by drivers - were ordered to be removed from app stores, potentially crippling the company’s operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this was not enough, the administration further extended its clampdown on other sectors in&amp;nbsp; July. On July 22, the government &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/tech/startups/china-strengthens-protection-for-food-delivery-workers-in-setback-for-meituan-alibaba/articleshow/84755202.cms&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;announced new worker protection rules&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, under which online food platforms must cover minimum wage and insurance benefits. This gutted the share price of delivery giants such as Meituan and its rival, Alibaba's Ele.me; which had drawn severe criticism on social media for their treatment of riders and guaranteed time-bound delivery which has compelled riders to undertake dangerous routes, risking their lives.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the following day, Beijing effectively torpedoed a multibillion-dollar industry - after-school tutoring - with a single administrative order. The new rules banned companies that teach the K-12 school curriculum from going public and registering themselves as non-profits. The shares of the three largest US-listed Chinese edtech firms - TAL Education, New Oriental and Gaotu Techedu, fell by 65-70% on the announcement, and the founders of the latter two companies went from billionaires to millionaires almost instantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The corporate intervention that has hammered internet stocks is now driving investors to sectors still in Beijing’s good graces, such as high-tech manufacturing and renewable energy. Indexes for new energy stocks, semiconductor makers and electric vehicle companies, outperformed the market from 4% to 18% since the beginning of July.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Broadly, Beijing is concerned about four pillars of stability: banking, antitrust regulation, data security and social equality. For example, social equality being at the heart of the ban of for-profit after-school tutors or rights concerning gig economy workers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some market participants believe China is trying to direct capital and human resources from internet companies into sectors that will help the country become more self-reliant. A portfolio manager at M&amp;amp;G Investments, Singapore, tracking the Chinese economy said, “&lt;em&gt;They are trying to reach a new equilibrium because it seems capital flows were not in line with long-term, top- down priorities.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts believe the government’s latest initiatives are motivated by a bigger ambition to realign the relationship between private business and the state, with a goal of ensuring companies do more to serve the Communist Party’s economic, social and national security concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it is worth noticing that Huawei, which should fall under the purview of the state on every possible reason in law, is entirely untouched.&amp;nbsp; As per some observers, the reason for the telecom giant being solidly backed by Beijing is due to the mutual benefit of both parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China’s vision for a domestic adversary as opposed to a Silicon Valley has benefited the private companies for years from lax regulatory oversight. However, leaders now worry that the tech giants have become too big and could be using personal and corporate digital records as leverage to build &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/china-blocked-jack-mas-ant-ipo-after-an-investigation-revealed-who-stood-to-gain-11613491292?mod=searchresults_pos10&amp;amp;page=1&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;alternative power centers&lt;/a&gt; in the one-party state.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, the government has often demanded data from private firms, and could sometimes enforce its wishes, especially for hunting down criminal suspects and silencing dissent but the tech companies have pushed back on requests to share and centralise their statistics.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, Beijing now wishes to undo these through their complex cyber security laws and regulations which would make it harder for companies to resist data sharing requests.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chinese regulators have formally made the data localisation requirement a prerequisite for foreign institutions trying to get a foothold in China, enabling the government to have more authority over the records. Western companies have long complained such “data localisation” requirements could stifle innovation in their global operations or enable Chinese authorities to steal their proprietary information.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US electric car maker &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/market-data/quotes/TSLA&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Tesla&lt;/a&gt; Inc has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/tesla-to-store-china-data-locally-in-new-data-center-11622015001?mod=article_inline&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pledged&lt;/a&gt; to build more data centers in China and to keep information generated by the vehicles it sells there, within Chinese borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Less invasive private-sector data collection anywhere is a good thing,” says analyst Ryan Fedasiuk at Georgetown University’s Center for Security and Emerging Technology. “But China’s push for data privacy strikes me as yet another move to strengthen the role of the government and the party vis-à-vis tech companies.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the EU rules, the Chinese version lacks restrictions on government entities when it comes to gathering information on people’s call logs, contact lists, location and other data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, these laws should also be seen against the backdrop of high tensions between US-China relations, which has sharpened President Xi’s focus on security and self-sufficiency. Beijing prohibits foreign ownership of larger sections of the Chinese economy, especially the profitable parts involving digital technology and data, and hence the companies follow a concept of&amp;nbsp; Variable-Interest-Entity or VIE, where the companies selling shares in foreign markets (including Hong Kong) can do so only quasi-legally at best. The workaround for VIE was the transparency that would come with foreign ownership and control which could reveal more about the state of the economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under a 2020 law signed by then-President, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/topics/person/donald-trump&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Donald Trump&lt;/a&gt;, Chinese companies would have to share their audit working papers with the US regulators. Failure to do so would lead to delisting of companies from US exchanges.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For China, that could risk allowing key data, such as detailed information about Chinese consumers and government agencies that may be included in the papers, to end up in the hands of a foreign government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both the second largest economy in the world and West see tech as a possible disrupter, however, it’s the Chinese who seem to be turbocharging a move towards the real tech, where they are ready to destroy the ‘pre-tender’ that exists today.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In November 2020, I authored an article on China’s move of scuttling Ant Group Co.’s blockbuster $37 billion listing. Little did we know that it was just the beginning of an excessive clampdown on the country's technological sector.&amp;nbsp; To continue with the story of e-commerce giant Alibaba, the country’s authorities imposed a record fine - $2.8 billion in 2021, after an investigation that found it had abused its dominant market position for years. China’s unprecedented crackdown on its tech industry has cost several companies and their investors hundreds of billions of dollars. Tencent alone has had $170 billion shaved off its value. For context, that’s more than ten Byju’s, India’s biggest startup, which is valued at $16.5 billion.&amp;nbsp; The July Roundup by Goldman Sachs Group Inc shows that since November, the country’s regulators have taken more than 50 actual or reported actions on areas spanning antitrust, finance, data security and social equality, i.e. more than one move a week. For decades, China has assiduously built up its tech sector, and has borrowed an industrial and internet model from the West. Arguably it was a resounding success, then why is it now trying to strangle the golden goose it had once cradled?&amp;nbsp; China adopted a new cybersecurity law in June, which builds on the foundation of the 2017 Cyber Security Law, that started tightening the control of data flow. However, since the measure was vaguely worded, it remained unclear how it would be implemented. Around the same time, the Chinese economy was rebounding from its bout with COVID-19, lifting the nation's ride, hailing giant Didi Global’s revenue with it as the US stock market continued to be in a bull run. Didi's long venture investors, including Softbank’s Vision Fund, urged seizing the moment to take the company public. The company made its debut at $14 on the New York Stock Exchange on the last day of June 2021, raising $4.4 billion - the biggest stock sale by a Chinese company since the 2014 listing of Alibaba Group Holding Ltd.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Its shares briefly topped $18 in the first days of trading, before China’s cyber security watchdog - Cyberspace Administration of China (CAC) stunned investors on July 2 by launching a data-security probe into Didi and blocking its China business from adding new users.&amp;nbsp; The crackdown worsened on July 9, when 25 more Didi apps - including ones used by drivers - were ordered to be removed from app stores, potentially crippling the company’s operations. If this was not enough, the administration further extended its clampdown on other sectors in&amp;nbsp; July. On July 22, the government announced new worker protection rules, under which online food platforms must cover minimum wage and insurance benefits. This gutted the share price of delivery giants such as Meituan and its rival, Alibaba's Ele.me; which had drawn severe criticism on social media for their treatment of riders and guaranteed time-bound delivery which has compelled riders to undertake dangerous routes, risking their lives.&amp;nbsp; On the following day, Beijing effectively torpedoed a multibillion-dollar industry - after-school tutoring - with a single administrative order. The new rules banned companies that teach the K-12 school curriculum from going public and registering themselves as non-profits. The shares of the three largest US-listed Chinese edtech firms - TAL Education, New Oriental and Gaotu Techedu, fell by 65-70% on the announcement, and the founders of the latter two companies went from billionaires to millionaires almost instantly. The corporate intervention that has hammered internet stocks is now driving investors to sectors still in Beijing’s good graces, such as high-tech manufacturing and renewable energy. Indexes for new energy stocks, semiconductor makers and electric vehicle companies, outperformed the market from 4% to 18% since the beginning of July.&amp;nbsp; Broadly, Beijing is concerned about four pillars of stability: banking, antitrust regulation, data security and social equality. For example, social equality being at the heart of the ban of for-profit after-school tutors or rights concerning gig economy workers.&amp;nbsp; Some market participants believe China is trying to direct capital and human resources from internet companies into sectors that will help the country become more self-reliant. A portfolio manager at M&amp;amp;G Investments, Singapore, tracking the Chinese economy said, “They are trying to reach a new equilibrium because it seems capital flows were not in line with long-term, top- down priorities.” Analysts believe the government’s latest initiatives are motivated by a bigger ambition to realign the relationship between private business and the state, with a goal of ensuring companies do more to serve the Communist Party’s economic, social and national security concerns. However, it is worth noticing that Huawei, which should fall under the purview of the state on every possible reason in law, is entirely untouched.&amp;nbsp; As per some observers, the reason for the telecom giant being solidly backed by Beijing is due to the mutual benefit of both parties. China’s vision for a domestic adversary as opposed to a Silicon Valley has benefited the private companies for years from lax regulatory oversight. However, leaders now worry that the tech giants have become too big and could be using personal and corporate digital records as leverage to build alternative power centers in the one-party state.&amp;nbsp; In the past, the government has often demanded data from private firms, and could sometimes enforce its wishes, especially for hunting down criminal suspects and silencing dissent but the tech companies have pushed back on requests to share and centralise their statistics.&amp;nbsp; Nonetheless, Beijing now wishes to undo these through their complex cyber security laws and regulations which would make it harder for companies to resist data sharing requests.&amp;nbsp; Chinese regulators have formally made the data localisation requirement a prerequisite for foreign institutions trying to get a foothold in China, enabling the government to have more authority over the records. Western companies have long complained such “data localisation” requirements could stifle innovation in their global operations or enable Chinese authorities to steal their proprietary information.&amp;nbsp; US electric car maker Tesla Inc has pledged to build more data centers in China and to keep information generated by the vehicles it sells there, within Chinese borders. “Less invasive private-sector data collection anywhere is a good thing,” says analyst Ryan Fedasiuk at Georgetown University’s Center for Security and Emerging Technology. “But China’s push for data privacy strikes me as yet another move to strengthen the role of the government and the party vis-à-vis tech companies.” Unlike the EU rules, the Chinese version lacks restrictions on government entities when it comes to gathering information on people’s call logs, contact lists, location and other data. Meanwhile, these laws should also be seen against the backdrop of high tensions between US-China relations, which has sharpened President Xi’s focus on security and self-sufficiency. Beijing prohibits foreign ownership of larger sections of the Chinese economy, especially the profitable parts involving digital technology and data, and hence the companies follow a concept of&amp;nbsp; Variable-Interest-Entity or VIE, where the companies selling shares in foreign markets (including Hong Kong) can do so only quasi-legally at best. The workaround for VIE was the transparency that would come with foreign ownership and control which could reveal more about the state of the economy.&amp;nbsp; Under a 2020 law signed by then-President, Donald Trump, Chinese companies would have to share their audit working papers with the US regulators. Failure to do so would lead to delisting of companies from US exchanges.&amp;nbsp; For China, that could risk allowing key data, such as detailed information about Chinese consumers and government agencies that may be included in the papers, to end up in the hands of a foreign government. Both the second largest economy in the world and West see tech as a possible disrupter, however, it’s the Chinese who seem to be turbocharging a move towards the real tech, where they are ready to destroy the ‘pre-tender’ that exists today.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Decoding Cryptic Cryptos</title>
      <link href="/Decoding-Cryptic-Cryptos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Decoding Cryptic Cryptos" />
      <published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Decoding-Cryptic-Cryptos</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Decoding-Cryptic-Cryptos">&lt;p&gt;Cryptocurrencies have yet again gone through one of the many roller coaster rides in the past few months. They can synonymously be used for volatility – they are that highly erratic. In this article, we will try to decode the entire episode and present it to you from scratch.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin with, cryptocurrency is a digital asset or a form that is secured by cryptography. Cryptography refers to the process of converting legible information into an almost uncrackable code. The first-ever cryptocurrency, Bitcoin, was introduced in 2009 by a mysterious individual (or a group of people) with the pseudonym Satoshi Nakamoto. The creator's objective was to eliminate the intermediaries (eg, banks) in the backdrop of the 2008 debacle, also known as The Great Recession. Therefore, it did not want any third party's involvement, which raises the transaction cost (by way of transaction fees) and risk via exposure to mortgage lending. Additionally, the value of fiat currency is dependent on money circulation in the economy, which can fluctuate depending on the monetary authority. These interventions, per se, are not wrong; however, the component of uncertainty and dependence on third-party necessitated the absence of intermediaries in the eyes of Nakamoto.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next big question arises: if no intermediary involvement is present, then who develops and verifies these digital currencies? Through the process of mining, these digital coins are created and verified by way of blockchain networks. Simply put, blockchains are digital ledgers where the transactional data are stored in an encrypted, decentralised format such that no person can own, control or manipulate the particulars.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mining is a laborious procedure involving solving complex computational puzzles. Nonetheless, it still appeals to various individuals (known as miners) because of its reward in terms of ownership of the new crypto tokens. Initially, mining could be done with basic devices. When crypto participants and engagement increased, the activity became further complicated. It can no longer be solved by basic computers and instead requires supercomputers. Cryptos have a fixed supply; hence, unlike government-backed fiat money, their supply cannot go up suddenly. The disadvantageous element of this process is the carbon footprint it accounts for.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A University of Cambridge study has stated that mining of the largest cryptocurrency by market capitalisation – Bitcoins, consumes more than 120 Terawatt Hours (Twh) each year, using more electricity annually than countries like Malaysia or Sweden. Furthermore, studies claim that mining should follow the adoption rate of other broadly adopted technologies, and Bitcoin could alone produce enough carbon dioxide emissions to push global warming above 2°C within less than three decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It goes without saying that other much smaller cryptocurrencies have a far lower energy footprint due to their much smaller scale. However, if scaled up, they are equally carbon-heavy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, proponents of cryptos say that mining is increasingly being done with electricity generated from renewable sources. Nevertheless, environmentalists continue to decry mining since miners will keep up consuming coal (it is the cheapest source) for electricity generation, thus giving us its ecological aftermath.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from environment lovers, government and monetary officials view these digital assets as potential threats due to their operation outside government control, which can potentially overturn an economy if not supervised.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several risks are associated with cryptocurrencies. Firstly, a high degree of market manipulation due to the lack of backing by any tangible assets questions their intrinsic value, marking their price discovery in uncharted territory.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, asymmetrical information raises the likelihood of money laundering, hacking, cyber extortion, and more, damaging consumer protection and systemic stability.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some risks are familiar with other financial products; however, crypto's information opacity disrupts the adjustment. For example, as per a &lt;em&gt;Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Journal &lt;/em&gt;finding, Hamas, the Palestinian militant group, saw a spike in Bitcoin donations during the violence between Israel and Palestine in mid-May. Hamas, which rules the Gaza Strip, is designated as a terrorist entity by the US, the European Union (EU) and other Western nations and has sanctions imposed upon it. Nonetheless, its funding remained unaffected due to anonymous digital transactions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In another such instance, according to the analytics firm Elliptic, DarkSide, a hacking group, shut down a critical US oil pipeline in May and collected over $90 million in hard-to-trace Bitcoin from 47 victims. That hack ended after Colonial Pipeline paid nearly $5 million as ransom to regain control of systems needed to supply gasoline to the Eastern US.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these complications, cryptocurrencies are seeing huge public acceptance. There are multiple reasons for broader acceptance of these digital assets, owing to their higher yields on the back of low-interest rates, hedging against inflation, or their growing acceptance by corporate leaders. For example, digital assets are pretty popular in Argentina as a way for locals to hedge against cyclical economic crises, including repeat currency devaluations, defaults and hyperinflation, with the recent imposition of foreign exchange controls and now a three-year recession made worse by the pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The massive monthly rally of cryptos in early 2021 and the big sell-off in mid-May, as per market observers, was caused by Elon Musk's tweets. The American electric car maker, Tesla, announced in its February, 2021 filing to the market regulator that it had bought $1.5 billion worth of Bitcoins and would soon start accepting the digital currency for payments. A few weeks back, its CEO Musk hinted as much by adding '#bitcoin' to his Twitter bio. Followers and the general public went into a frenzy, and the market price surged. However, the plunge in crypto prices in mid-May was sparked when the Tesla chief tweeted the company’s u-turn on Bitcoin acceptance and criticised it for the environmental hazard posed by aggressive power mining.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk has a track record of influencing the market price of asset classes. Back in 2018, Musk and Tesla, each paid $20 million to the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) to settle fraud charges for tweeting about a potential buyout of the car-making company, leading to a spike in share prices followed by a fall when the buyout could not be negotiated. Many regulators are worried about the concentration of social power among a few individuals and organisations to influence prices of various asset classes, which can hamper price stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another key reason for slumping prices of crypto in the early morning of May 19 in Wall Street was attributed to China, after the country barred its financial institutions from dealing in cryptocurrencies.&amp;nbsp;China accounts for more than 70% of all bitcoin mining in the world. Due to its cheap energy, the country's Inner Mongolia Autonomous region accounts for around 8% globally, a more significant share than the US. The move is part of the government's target of achieving carbon neutrality by 2060.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China had such a ban in 2017, but the 2021 ban has a broader scope. The ban prohibits institutions from accepting or settling payments in crypto or providing exchange services to convert crypto to fiat currencies, including the Chinese yuan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In India, are cryptocurrency banned? No, they are not 100% legal, so it is all right for us to trade in crypto exchanges like WazirX or CoinDCX. However, they are not legal tender of money, so you cannot purchase any goods or services and make payments in these digitised currencies. Back in 2018, the Indian central bank had issued a circular to refrain financial institutions from having any relation with any crypto assets or crypto organisations; however, the ban was lifted by an Indian Supreme Court decision in the very same year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court in March 2020 said the central bank could notify cryptocurrencies as ‘other similar instruments’ under the definition of the term 'currency' in the Indian Foreign Exchange Management Act (FEMA). Therefore, the trading in crypto can fall within the purview of the central bank. In May 2021, the central bank came out with a circular reiterating its commitment to upholding the Court's decision. However, it did ask institutions and other entities to carry out due diligence processes in line with customer protection and economic stability as per the FEMA Act. The Indian Finance Minister in her 2021-22 budget hinted that the government would take a ‘calibrated approach’ towards digital assets. Hence, some regulation or oversight by the government is expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will get to know whether these computerised assets are the future of payments in years to come. However, administrations need to acknowledge the public involvement and bridge the loopholes these instruments carry with themselves as soon as possible.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Cryptocurrencies have yet again gone through one of the many roller coaster rides in the past few months. They can synonymously be used for volatility – they are that highly erratic. In this article, we will try to decode the entire episode and present it to you from scratch.&amp;nbsp; To begin with, cryptocurrency is a digital asset or a form that is secured by cryptography. Cryptography refers to the process of converting legible information into an almost uncrackable code. The first-ever cryptocurrency, Bitcoin, was introduced in 2009 by a mysterious individual (or a group of people) with the pseudonym Satoshi Nakamoto. The creator's objective was to eliminate the intermediaries (eg, banks) in the backdrop of the 2008 debacle, also known as The Great Recession. Therefore, it did not want any third party's involvement, which raises the transaction cost (by way of transaction fees) and risk via exposure to mortgage lending. Additionally, the value of fiat currency is dependent on money circulation in the economy, which can fluctuate depending on the monetary authority. These interventions, per se, are not wrong; however, the component of uncertainty and dependence on third-party necessitated the absence of intermediaries in the eyes of Nakamoto.&amp;nbsp; The next big question arises: if no intermediary involvement is present, then who develops and verifies these digital currencies? Through the process of mining, these digital coins are created and verified by way of blockchain networks. Simply put, blockchains are digital ledgers where the transactional data are stored in an encrypted, decentralised format such that no person can own, control or manipulate the particulars.&amp;nbsp; Mining is a laborious procedure involving solving complex computational puzzles. Nonetheless, it still appeals to various individuals (known as miners) because of its reward in terms of ownership of the new crypto tokens. Initially, mining could be done with basic devices. When crypto participants and engagement increased, the activity became further complicated. It can no longer be solved by basic computers and instead requires supercomputers. Cryptos have a fixed supply; hence, unlike government-backed fiat money, their supply cannot go up suddenly. The disadvantageous element of this process is the carbon footprint it accounts for.&amp;nbsp; A University of Cambridge study has stated that mining of the largest cryptocurrency by market capitalisation – Bitcoins, consumes more than 120 Terawatt Hours (Twh) each year, using more electricity annually than countries like Malaysia or Sweden. Furthermore, studies claim that mining should follow the adoption rate of other broadly adopted technologies, and Bitcoin could alone produce enough carbon dioxide emissions to push global warming above 2°C within less than three decades. It goes without saying that other much smaller cryptocurrencies have a far lower energy footprint due to their much smaller scale. However, if scaled up, they are equally carbon-heavy.&amp;nbsp; However, proponents of cryptos say that mining is increasingly being done with electricity generated from renewable sources. Nevertheless, environmentalists continue to decry mining since miners will keep up consuming coal (it is the cheapest source) for electricity generation, thus giving us its ecological aftermath.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Apart from environment lovers, government and monetary officials view these digital assets as potential threats due to their operation outside government control, which can potentially overturn an economy if not supervised.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Several risks are associated with cryptocurrencies. Firstly, a high degree of market manipulation due to the lack of backing by any tangible assets questions their intrinsic value, marking their price discovery in uncharted territory.&amp;nbsp; Secondly, asymmetrical information raises the likelihood of money laundering, hacking, cyber extortion, and more, damaging consumer protection and systemic stability.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; Some risks are familiar with other financial products; however, crypto's information opacity disrupts the adjustment. For example, as per a Wall Street Journal finding, Hamas, the Palestinian militant group, saw a spike in Bitcoin donations during the violence between Israel and Palestine in mid-May. Hamas, which rules the Gaza Strip, is designated as a terrorist entity by the US, the European Union (EU) and other Western nations and has sanctions imposed upon it. Nonetheless, its funding remained unaffected due to anonymous digital transactions.&amp;nbsp; In another such instance, according to the analytics firm Elliptic, DarkSide, a hacking group, shut down a critical US oil pipeline in May and collected over $90 million in hard-to-trace Bitcoin from 47 victims. That hack ended after Colonial Pipeline paid nearly $5 million as ransom to regain control of systems needed to supply gasoline to the Eastern US.&amp;nbsp; Despite these complications, cryptocurrencies are seeing huge public acceptance. There are multiple reasons for broader acceptance of these digital assets, owing to their higher yields on the back of low-interest rates, hedging against inflation, or their growing acceptance by corporate leaders. For example, digital assets are pretty popular in Argentina as a way for locals to hedge against cyclical economic crises, including repeat currency devaluations, defaults and hyperinflation, with the recent imposition of foreign exchange controls and now a three-year recession made worse by the pandemic.&amp;nbsp; The massive monthly rally of cryptos in early 2021 and the big sell-off in mid-May, as per market observers, was caused by Elon Musk's tweets. The American electric car maker, Tesla, announced in its February, 2021 filing to the market regulator that it had bought $1.5 billion worth of Bitcoins and would soon start accepting the digital currency for payments. A few weeks back, its CEO Musk hinted as much by adding '#bitcoin' to his Twitter bio. Followers and the general public went into a frenzy, and the market price surged. However, the plunge in crypto prices in mid-May was sparked when the Tesla chief tweeted the company’s u-turn on Bitcoin acceptance and criticised it for the environmental hazard posed by aggressive power mining.&amp;nbsp; Elon Musk has a track record of influencing the market price of asset classes. Back in 2018, Musk and Tesla, each paid $20 million to the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) to settle fraud charges for tweeting about a potential buyout of the car-making company, leading to a spike in share prices followed by a fall when the buyout could not be negotiated. Many regulators are worried about the concentration of social power among a few individuals and organisations to influence prices of various asset classes, which can hamper price stability. Another key reason for slumping prices of crypto in the early morning of May 19 in Wall Street was attributed to China, after the country barred its financial institutions from dealing in cryptocurrencies.&amp;nbsp;China accounts for more than 70% of all bitcoin mining in the world. Due to its cheap energy, the country's Inner Mongolia Autonomous region accounts for around 8% globally, a more significant share than the US. The move is part of the government's target of achieving carbon neutrality by 2060. China had such a ban in 2017, but the 2021 ban has a broader scope. The ban prohibits institutions from accepting or settling payments in crypto or providing exchange services to convert crypto to fiat currencies, including the Chinese yuan.&amp;nbsp; In India, are cryptocurrency banned? No, they are not 100% legal, so it is all right for us to trade in crypto exchanges like WazirX or CoinDCX. However, they are not legal tender of money, so you cannot purchase any goods or services and make payments in these digitised currencies. Back in 2018, the Indian central bank had issued a circular to refrain financial institutions from having any relation with any crypto assets or crypto organisations; however, the ban was lifted by an Indian Supreme Court decision in the very same year. The Supreme Court in March 2020 said the central bank could notify cryptocurrencies as ‘other similar instruments’ under the definition of the term 'currency' in the Indian Foreign Exchange Management Act (FEMA). Therefore, the trading in crypto can fall within the purview of the central bank. In May 2021, the central bank came out with a circular reiterating its commitment to upholding the Court's decision. However, it did ask institutions and other entities to carry out due diligence processes in line with customer protection and economic stability as per the FEMA Act. The Indian Finance Minister in her 2021-22 budget hinted that the government would take a ‘calibrated approach’ towards digital assets. Hence, some regulation or oversight by the government is expected. We will get to know whether these computerised assets are the future of payments in years to come. However, administrations need to acknowledge the public involvement and bridge the loopholes these instruments carry with themselves as soon as possible.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Taxing Verdict for the Indian Tax Man</title>
      <link href="/A-Taxing-Verdict-for-the-Indian-Tax-Man" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Taxing Verdict for the Indian Tax Man" />
      <published>2021-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Taxing-Verdict-for-the-Indian-Tax-Man</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Taxing-Verdict-for-the-Indian-Tax-Man">&lt;p&gt;The Permanent Court of Arbitration at the Hague, in its arbitral ruling, has once again dealt a blow to the Government of India by ruling in favour of the gas and oil exploration company, Cairn Energy Plc over tax disputes. The verdict comes post the September 25, 2020 victory of Vodafone International Holdings BV against the Indian government over the same dispute relating to the retrospective tax amendment in 2012.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2006-07, Cairn UK, as part of an internal rearrangement process, transferred shares of Cairn India Holdings to Cairn India. Later, in 2011, the Edinburgh-headquartered organisation sold its Cairn India stake to the mining conglomerate Vedanta. In January 2014, the Indian income tax authorities, in view of the retroactive amended income tax law, alleged that the gas exploration firm made capital gains of ₹245.03 billion in the rearrangement process and hence was liable to pay a tax of ₹102.47 billion to the authorities. The company’s interpretation of Indian laws on capital gains differed, and consequently, it refused to pay the amount. In response, the authorities stopped the sale of the 10% stake to Vedanta and froze dividend pay-out to UK based parent company.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2015, Cairn initiated an international arbitration proceeding against the Indian authorities under article 9 of the Agreement between the Government of the Republic of India and the Government of Great Britain and Northern Ireland for Promotion and Protection of Investments (India-UK BIT). Countries enter into treaties, especially tax treaties, to prevent double taxation of corporations’ incomes earned by foreign investments, so as to promote a healthy business relationship and trade between two countries in this growing globalised world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose behind the said BIT provision was also the same, i.e. ensuring protection of the investors of the contracting state against any disruption/harassment of business in the territory of the host state. (See, Fair and Equitable Treatment – UNCTAD Series on Issues in International Investment Agreement II).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A final assessment order was slapped on the oil corporation in 2016, which included interest amounting to ₹188 billion, in addition to the principal tax amount.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three-member international arbitration tribunal, including a nominee of the Indian government, unanimously ruled in favour of the exploration organisation, and ordered the Indian administration to compensate the former for the total harm suffered including interest and the costs of arbitration. In its judgment, the arbitration panel said, “&lt;em&gt;Tax demand against the claimants (Cairn Energy Plc and Cairn UK Holdings Limited) in respect of AY (assessment year) 2007-08 is inconsistent with the treaty and the claimants are relieved from any obligation to pay it and [the tribunal] orders the respondent (Indian government) to neutralise the continuing effect of the demand by permanently withdrawing the demand.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sovereign country has the power to impose tax from a retrospective date. Nonetheless, such an action when a past transaction, which was not liable to taxation as on that date, is taxed under the aegis of a retrospective amendment, it is naturally seen to be unjust and discriminatory. Officials usually defend the amendments by stating that such moves are brought into effect to correct earlier flaws that defeated the purpose of the legislation in the first place.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be interesting to observe India’s follow-up on the issue. The government has until this month to challenge the award in a higher court in Singapore. By February end, Cairn’s CEO &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?rlz=1C1RXQR_enIN928IN928&amp;amp;sxsrf=ALeKk03IPhQp-AiVjX-3f-BE1qS7-EiNXw:1614752810068&amp;amp;q=Simon+Thomson&amp;amp;stick=H4sIAAAAAAAAAOPgE-LUz9U3sDCxtCxX4gIx85LzcgqNtBSzk63084vSE_MyqxJLMvPzUDhWyan5i1h5gzNz8_MUQjLyc4vz83awMgIATPkbn08AAAA&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjgi5P9vpPvAhWTXSsKHSlvCAoQmxMoATApegQIIRAD&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Simon Thomson&lt;/a&gt; in his conversation with the Ministry of&amp;nbsp; Finance conveyed the corporation’s desire for a speedy resolution that is in the interest of all stakeholders involved. The government has hinted that the only possible solution for both parties to avoid further litigation is for the former to agree to the government’s&amp;nbsp;'&lt;a href=&quot;https://indianexpress.com/article/explained/direct-tax-vivad-se-vishwas-bill-how-govt-aims-to-reduce-direct-tax-litigation-6254981/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Vivad se Vishwas&lt;/a&gt;' (From Litigation to Trust) &amp;nbsp;tax amnesty. This scheme, announced in the Indian Budget 2020, provides speedy resolution for tax disputes in the forms of certain compensation between individuals and the tax department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The oil discovery company aims to enforce the award under international arbitration rules, and can use this judgment to approach courts in countries like the UK, USA to seize any overseas property owned by India, to recover the money if the award is not honoured. If it does happen, India would not be the first country to face seizure of its international assets from an energy company. In 2019, US Oil firm ConocoPhillips, under international arbitration law, seized Venezuela’s overseas assets to execute an arbitration award of more than $8 billion. Cairn is reportedly identifying India’s overseas assets, including bank accounts and even Air India planes or Indian ships, that could be seized in the absence of a settlement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also worthwhile to note that if the Indian government accepts the award, then this move would be welcomed by the business corporations. India's reputation has taken a severe beating as a result of these cases. The BJP government has, in the past, denounced the introduction of a retrospective tax amendment by the previous Congress government as &quot;tax terrorism&quot;. Prime Minister Narendra Modi had promised to bring an end to &quot;tax terror&quot; after coming to power in 2014. However, the opposite happened when the government carried on with the case.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a government struggling to find revenue and seeking to boost its economy post-COVID-19, it is essential for the government to reduce compliance troubles and stumbling blocks such as retrospective taxation, lest it finds itself seriously damaging its potential post economic liberalisation.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Permanent Court of Arbitration at the Hague, in its arbitral ruling, has once again dealt a blow to the Government of India by ruling in favour of the gas and oil exploration company, Cairn Energy Plc over tax disputes. The verdict comes post the September 25, 2020 victory of Vodafone International Holdings BV against the Indian government over the same dispute relating to the retrospective tax amendment in 2012.&amp;nbsp; In 2006-07, Cairn UK, as part of an internal rearrangement process, transferred shares of Cairn India Holdings to Cairn India. Later, in 2011, the Edinburgh-headquartered organisation sold its Cairn India stake to the mining conglomerate Vedanta. In January 2014, the Indian income tax authorities, in view of the retroactive amended income tax law, alleged that the gas exploration firm made capital gains of ₹245.03 billion in the rearrangement process and hence was liable to pay a tax of ₹102.47 billion to the authorities. The company’s interpretation of Indian laws on capital gains differed, and consequently, it refused to pay the amount. In response, the authorities stopped the sale of the 10% stake to Vedanta and froze dividend pay-out to UK based parent company.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; In 2015, Cairn initiated an international arbitration proceeding against the Indian authorities under article 9 of the Agreement between the Government of the Republic of India and the Government of Great Britain and Northern Ireland for Promotion and Protection of Investments (India-UK BIT). Countries enter into treaties, especially tax treaties, to prevent double taxation of corporations’ incomes earned by foreign investments, so as to promote a healthy business relationship and trade between two countries in this growing globalised world. The purpose behind the said BIT provision was also the same, i.e. ensuring protection of the investors of the contracting state against any disruption/harassment of business in the territory of the host state. (See, Fair and Equitable Treatment – UNCTAD Series on Issues in International Investment Agreement II). A final assessment order was slapped on the oil corporation in 2016, which included interest amounting to ₹188 billion, in addition to the principal tax amount.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The three-member international arbitration tribunal, including a nominee of the Indian government, unanimously ruled in favour of the exploration organisation, and ordered the Indian administration to compensate the former for the total harm suffered including interest and the costs of arbitration. In its judgment, the arbitration panel said, “Tax demand against the claimants (Cairn Energy Plc and Cairn UK Holdings Limited) in respect of AY (assessment year) 2007-08 is inconsistent with the treaty and the claimants are relieved from any obligation to pay it and [the tribunal] orders the respondent (Indian government) to neutralise the continuing effect of the demand by permanently withdrawing the demand.” A sovereign country has the power to impose tax from a retrospective date. Nonetheless, such an action when a past transaction, which was not liable to taxation as on that date, is taxed under the aegis of a retrospective amendment, it is naturally seen to be unjust and discriminatory. Officials usually defend the amendments by stating that such moves are brought into effect to correct earlier flaws that defeated the purpose of the legislation in the first place.&amp;nbsp; It would be interesting to observe India’s follow-up on the issue. The government has until this month to challenge the award in a higher court in Singapore. By February end, Cairn’s CEO Simon Thomson in his conversation with the Ministry of&amp;nbsp; Finance conveyed the corporation’s desire for a speedy resolution that is in the interest of all stakeholders involved. The government has hinted that the only possible solution for both parties to avoid further litigation is for the former to agree to the government’s&amp;nbsp;'Vivad se Vishwas' (From Litigation to Trust) &amp;nbsp;tax amnesty. This scheme, announced in the Indian Budget 2020, provides speedy resolution for tax disputes in the forms of certain compensation between individuals and the tax department. The oil discovery company aims to enforce the award under international arbitration rules, and can use this judgment to approach courts in countries like the UK, USA to seize any overseas property owned by India, to recover the money if the award is not honoured. If it does happen, India would not be the first country to face seizure of its international assets from an energy company. In 2019, US Oil firm ConocoPhillips, under international arbitration law, seized Venezuela’s overseas assets to execute an arbitration award of more than $8 billion. Cairn is reportedly identifying India’s overseas assets, including bank accounts and even Air India planes or Indian ships, that could be seized in the absence of a settlement. It is also worthwhile to note that if the Indian government accepts the award, then this move would be welcomed by the business corporations. India's reputation has taken a severe beating as a result of these cases. The BJP government has, in the past, denounced the introduction of a retrospective tax amendment by the previous Congress government as &quot;tax terrorism&quot;. Prime Minister Narendra Modi had promised to bring an end to &quot;tax terror&quot; after coming to power in 2014. However, the opposite happened when the government carried on with the case.&amp;nbsp; For a government struggling to find revenue and seeking to boost its economy post-COVID-19, it is essential for the government to reduce compliance troubles and stumbling blocks such as retrospective taxation, lest it finds itself seriously damaging its potential post economic liberalisation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Big Daddy’s Gamble: the Indian Securities Regulator Challenges India’s Oligarch</title>
      <link href="/Big-Daddy-s-Gamble-the-Indian-Securities-Regulator-Challenges-India-s-Oligarch" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Big Daddy’s Gamble: the Indian Securities Regulator Challenges India's Oligarch" />
      <published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Big-Daddy-s-Gamble-the-Indian-Securities-Regulator-Challenges-India-s-Oligarch</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Big-Daddy-s-Gamble-the-Indian-Securities-Regulator-Challenges-India-s-Oligarch">&lt;p&gt;On January 1, 2021, the Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI) slapped a fine on the largest company in India by market capitalisation, i.e. Reliance Industries Limited (RIL), and its Chairman and Managing Director Mukesh Ambani of ₹250 million and ₹150 million respectively, along with two other entities, for manipulative trading in the shares of the erstwhile Reliance Petroleum Limited (RPL) in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what activity did RIL engage in to receive a penalty from the market regulator?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reliance Petroleum Limited (RPL) was a refinery, partly owned by RIL, which later got merged with the latter in 2009. However, the conglomerate got itself under the radar of the watchdog for the transaction that occurred between the company and its agents in November, 2007, in the cash and futures segment of the secondary market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RIL had decided to sell off its 4.1% stake in RPL. According to SEBI, in order to make undue gains from the sale, the former had entered into an agreement with 12 agents, who booked large short positions of the refinery’s shares in the futures market. Short positions refer to a situation when a trader sells the security first with the intention of repurchasing it later at a lower price, hence the steeper the decline, greater is the profit for the trader. Following this, in the last ten minutes of the trading session of November 29, 2007, RIL sold close to 20 million RPL shares. This large scale selling triggered mass panic and within a moment’s notice, the stock price collapsed.&amp;nbsp; Interestingly, it also happened to be the same day that the futures contracts were meant to pay-out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, SEBI contends that RIL and the agents colluded together in a bid to make a profit estimated to be around ₹44.7 billion off of this transaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selling of securities by promoters in the capital markets in order to raise cash is a widely accepted practice, however, this act of secretive plotting that can distort the natural price discovery system in the market and cheat investors via non-transparent mechanisms is impermissible and against the objectives of the SEBI or any securities regulator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SEBI’s adjudicating officer B J Dilip said, “&lt;em&gt;any manipulation in the volume or price of securities always erodes investor confidence in the market when investors find themselves at the receiving end of market manipulators&lt;/em&gt;.” He further added, “&lt;em&gt;In the instant case, the general investors were not aware that the entity behind the above F&amp;amp;O segment transactions was RIL. The execution of the... fraudulent trades affected the price of the RPL securities in both cash and F&amp;amp;O [Futures and Options] segments and harmed the interests of other investors&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SEBI order states that Mukesh Ambani as the Managing Director of RIL was equally involved in the malpractice. Apart from the conglomerate and its chairman, SEBI also imposed penalties of ₹2 million and ₹1 million on Navi Mumbai SEZ Pvt Ltd and Mumbai SEZ Ltd respectively, both promoted by Anand Jain, a former member of the Reliance Group, for providing margin payments for the agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In March 2017, the market watchdog had ordered RIL and other entities to disgorge ₹4.47 billion in the RPL’s case, against which the latter appealed in the Securities Appellate Tribunal (SAT). The verdict announced by the tribunal in November 2020 was against the appellant. However, the petrochemicals to telecommunication multinational corporation said that it would appeal against the Tribunal’s ruling in the Indian Supreme Court.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not the first time that RIL and a government entity were at loggerheads. In 2014, the Indian market regulator had imposed a fine of ₹1.3 million on the corporation for non-disclosure of a key earnings ratio, which would have impacted investors’ evaluation on the shares. In 2018, the RIL-led consortium of BP Plc and Niko Resources won an award against the Indian government in international arbitration. The case related to a dispute over a penalty of $1.55 billion slapped by the Indian government on the petrochemical companies for allegedly drawing gas from the Oil and Natural Gas Corporation or ONGC’s (a state-owned oil and gas concern) block in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SEBI was established with the purpose of protecting investors and the development and regulation of capital markets in India. Over the years, it has evolved to meet its objective and has always taken a strong stance against any form of malpractice. However, it is essential that in order to mitigate any future wrongdoing, it penalises defaulters such that cost in fulfilling the punishment supersedes the gain.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On January 1, 2021, the Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI) slapped a fine on the largest company in India by market capitalisation, i.e. Reliance Industries Limited (RIL), and its Chairman and Managing Director Mukesh Ambani of ₹250 million and ₹150 million respectively, along with two other entities, for manipulative trading in the shares of the erstwhile Reliance Petroleum Limited (RPL) in 2007. So, what activity did RIL engage in to receive a penalty from the market regulator?&amp;nbsp; Reliance Petroleum Limited (RPL) was a refinery, partly owned by RIL, which later got merged with the latter in 2009. However, the conglomerate got itself under the radar of the watchdog for the transaction that occurred between the company and its agents in November, 2007, in the cash and futures segment of the secondary market. RIL had decided to sell off its 4.1% stake in RPL. According to SEBI, in order to make undue gains from the sale, the former had entered into an agreement with 12 agents, who booked large short positions of the refinery’s shares in the futures market. Short positions refer to a situation when a trader sells the security first with the intention of repurchasing it later at a lower price, hence the steeper the decline, greater is the profit for the trader. Following this, in the last ten minutes of the trading session of November 29, 2007, RIL sold close to 20 million RPL shares. This large scale selling triggered mass panic and within a moment’s notice, the stock price collapsed.&amp;nbsp; Interestingly, it also happened to be the same day that the futures contracts were meant to pay-out. So, SEBI contends that RIL and the agents colluded together in a bid to make a profit estimated to be around ₹44.7 billion off of this transaction. Selling of securities by promoters in the capital markets in order to raise cash is a widely accepted practice, however, this act of secretive plotting that can distort the natural price discovery system in the market and cheat investors via non-transparent mechanisms is impermissible and against the objectives of the SEBI or any securities regulator. SEBI’s adjudicating officer B J Dilip said, “any manipulation in the volume or price of securities always erodes investor confidence in the market when investors find themselves at the receiving end of market manipulators.” He further added, “In the instant case, the general investors were not aware that the entity behind the above F&amp;amp;O segment transactions was RIL. The execution of the... fraudulent trades affected the price of the RPL securities in both cash and F&amp;amp;O [Futures and Options] segments and harmed the interests of other investors.” The SEBI order states that Mukesh Ambani as the Managing Director of RIL was equally involved in the malpractice. Apart from the conglomerate and its chairman, SEBI also imposed penalties of ₹2 million and ₹1 million on Navi Mumbai SEZ Pvt Ltd and Mumbai SEZ Ltd respectively, both promoted by Anand Jain, a former member of the Reliance Group, for providing margin payments for the agents. In March 2017, the market watchdog had ordered RIL and other entities to disgorge ₹4.47 billion in the RPL’s case, against which the latter appealed in the Securities Appellate Tribunal (SAT). The verdict announced by the tribunal in November 2020 was against the appellant. However, the petrochemicals to telecommunication multinational corporation said that it would appeal against the Tribunal’s ruling in the Indian Supreme Court.&amp;nbsp; This is not the first time that RIL and a government entity were at loggerheads. In 2014, the Indian market regulator had imposed a fine of ₹1.3 million on the corporation for non-disclosure of a key earnings ratio, which would have impacted investors’ evaluation on the shares. In 2018, the RIL-led consortium of BP Plc and Niko Resources won an award against the Indian government in international arbitration. The case related to a dispute over a penalty of $1.55 billion slapped by the Indian government on the petrochemical companies for allegedly drawing gas from the Oil and Natural Gas Corporation or ONGC’s (a state-owned oil and gas concern) block in 2016. SEBI was established with the purpose of protecting investors and the development and regulation of capital markets in India. Over the years, it has evolved to meet its objective and has always taken a strong stance against any form of malpractice. However, it is essential that in order to mitigate any future wrongdoing, it penalises defaulters such that cost in fulfilling the punishment supersedes the gain.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Derailing of the World’s Biggest IPO</title>
      <link href="/Derailing-of-the-World-s-Biggest-IPO" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Derailing of the World’s Biggest IPO" />
      <published>2020-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Derailing-of-the-World-s-Biggest-IPO</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Derailing-of-the-World-s-Biggest-IPO">&lt;p&gt;The IPO of &lt;em&gt;Ant Group&lt;/em&gt;, the world's most valuable unicorn- or billion-dollar unlisted tech firm- was all set for a $37 billion dual listing in Hong Kong and Shanghai's STAR Market in the first week of November until news of a halt in its listing process hit the market just 48 hours before its trading debut on both stock exchanges.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simultaneous listing of &lt;em&gt;Ant Group&lt;/em&gt;, the financial service arm of the e-commerce giant &lt;em&gt;Alibaba&lt;/em&gt;, could have been the world's largest IPO. It would have surpassed the record set by oil giant &lt;em&gt;Saudi Aramco's&lt;/em&gt; $29.4 billion float last December. The company could have been worth more than many global banks after its share sale. So what turn of events lead to the suspension of the massive size IPO?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2003, Jack Ma, co-founder of &lt;em&gt;Alibaba&lt;/em&gt; created &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/alipay-and-the-world/finally-after-15-years-weve-found-alipay-s-very-first-buyer-jiao-zhengzhong-33d2c663d4f2&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a service called &lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alipay&lt;/em&gt;. It helped e-commerce take off. Under his leadership, he spun the service out in 2011 as a separate entity- &lt;em&gt;Ant Group&lt;/em&gt;, setting off a tiff with &lt;em&gt;Yahoo&lt;/em&gt;, which was then a major &lt;em&gt;Alibaba&lt;/em&gt; investor.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alipay&lt;/em&gt; became the largest player in China's $62 trillion third-party mobile payments market. It has more than 730 million monthly users, more than twice the population of the United States. &lt;em&gt;Ant &lt;/em&gt;says its systems processed 459,000 payments a second at the peak of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/11/11/technology/alibaba-singles-day.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Chinese shopping holiday&lt;/a&gt; in 2019 whereas &lt;em&gt;Visa&lt;/em&gt;, by contrast, says it can handle &lt;a href=&quot;https://usa.visa.com/dam/VCOM/download/corporate/media/visanet-technology/aboutvisafactsheet.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;65,000 transactions a second&lt;/a&gt;. Its wide range of functions include facilitating payments, granting loans, providing opportunities for investment and insurance, selling financial technology to enterprises, and much more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite being a fintech giant, the Shanghai stock exchange suspended the group’s IPO just 2 days before its trading debut, following which the company decided to halt the Hong Kong listing as well. The former stock exchange in a notice to the organisation stated that the company did not meet the “perquisites” owing to the changes in financial technology regulatory requirements.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new&lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2020/11/03/pulled-ant-group-ipo-costs-alibaba-nearly-60b-in-market-cap/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;s sent shock waves through&lt;/a&gt; the financial world, and other Chinese tech companies looking to raise capital. For months now, overseas exchanges have grown increasingly hostile towards Chinese firms, and exchanges within their home turf have offered solace. Retail investors alone bid a record of $3 trillion worth of institution’s shares in its twofold listing. However, this event is also a reminder of the challenges in their home country.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is believed that such scrutiny from regulators was to ensure the nation's financial stability and other related factors like privacy which is a concern all over the world. The fintech industry lies in a grey area, with not many regulations. The authorities were concerned about the increasing size and dominance of the company, and its possibility to jeopardize the country’s financial structure.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chinese foreign ministry spokesman Wang Wenbin said, &lt;em&gt;“The decision (of suspension of the IPO) is made by relevant exchange institutes based on laws to better safeguard capital market stability and protect investor rights and interests”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The loan segment forms a significant proportion of &lt;em&gt;Alipay&lt;/em&gt;’s business model where most of the credit risk is taken by banks, and hence the authorities were sceptical of this lending as it was done by an institution other than a bank. Hence, they wanted more involvement from the firm in the process and altered the requirement of maintaining capital reserve from 1% to almost 30%, which could effectively affect the group’s revenue stream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 weeks prior to the listing, China’s richest man, Jack Ma, who also is the largest shareholder of the fintech company made certain critical remarks about the regulatory framework not supporting fintech companies enough. Many also see it as a punishment for being so vocal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chinese government has always been a major participant in all aspects of the functioning of the nation. For years, the leadership has sought to facilitate the growth of its tech giants. Its internet restrictions also referred to as the 'Great Firewall', homegrown tech has been protected from foreign competitors and thus dominate the domestic market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take, for instance, &lt;em&gt;WeChat&lt;/em&gt;- the country’s alternative to social media sites like Facebook and Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this advantage to domestic firms comes at a cost, where they must never outgrow the regime’s grasp. The system has various measures to keep businesses in-check, such as the introduction of new laws and restrictions that it can impose on a whim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2017, &lt;em&gt;Tencent&lt;/em&gt; drew Beijing's ire after its &lt;em&gt;Honor of Kings&lt;/em&gt; gaming app was said to be too addictive and a few days later the government imposed sweeping reforms on the nations’ mobile gaming industry that included content and playing time restrictions. The most recent example could be the sudden imposition of restrictions on exporting ‘Artificial Intelligence’ technology, which immediately affected &lt;em&gt;ByteDance’s&lt;/em&gt; sale procedure to comply with the US’s threat to ban &lt;em&gt;TikTok&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This instance with &lt;em&gt;Ant Group&lt;/em&gt; should not be seen in isolation and more of such interferences could be expected in the future for tech firms. This could be a hurdle at a time when China faces extreme scrutiny over data privacy issues and aversion for coronavirus.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The IPO of Ant Group, the world's most valuable unicorn- or billion-dollar unlisted tech firm- was all set for a $37 billion dual listing in Hong Kong and Shanghai's STAR Market in the first week of November until news of a halt in its listing process hit the market just 48 hours before its trading debut on both stock exchanges.&amp;nbsp; Simultaneous listing of Ant Group, the financial service arm of the e-commerce giant Alibaba, could have been the world's largest IPO. It would have surpassed the record set by oil giant Saudi Aramco's $29.4 billion float last December. The company could have been worth more than many global banks after its share sale. So what turn of events lead to the suspension of the massive size IPO? In 2003, Jack Ma, co-founder of Alibaba created a service called Alipay. It helped e-commerce take off. Under his leadership, he spun the service out in 2011 as a separate entity- Ant Group, setting off a tiff with Yahoo, which was then a major Alibaba investor.&amp;nbsp; Alipay became the largest player in China's $62 trillion third-party mobile payments market. It has more than 730 million monthly users, more than twice the population of the United States. Ant says its systems processed 459,000 payments a second at the peak of a Chinese shopping holiday in 2019 whereas Visa, by contrast, says it can handle 65,000 transactions a second. Its wide range of functions include facilitating payments, granting loans, providing opportunities for investment and insurance, selling financial technology to enterprises, and much more. Despite being a fintech giant, the Shanghai stock exchange suspended the group’s IPO just 2 days before its trading debut, following which the company decided to halt the Hong Kong listing as well. The former stock exchange in a notice to the organisation stated that the company did not meet the “perquisites” owing to the changes in financial technology regulatory requirements.&amp;nbsp; The news sent shock waves through the financial world, and other Chinese tech companies looking to raise capital. For months now, overseas exchanges have grown increasingly hostile towards Chinese firms, and exchanges within their home turf have offered solace. Retail investors alone bid a record of $3 trillion worth of institution’s shares in its twofold listing. However, this event is also a reminder of the challenges in their home country.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; It is believed that such scrutiny from regulators was to ensure the nation's financial stability and other related factors like privacy which is a concern all over the world. The fintech industry lies in a grey area, with not many regulations. The authorities were concerned about the increasing size and dominance of the company, and its possibility to jeopardize the country’s financial structure.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Chinese foreign ministry spokesman Wang Wenbin said, “The decision (of suspension of the IPO) is made by relevant exchange institutes based on laws to better safeguard capital market stability and protect investor rights and interests”. The loan segment forms a significant proportion of Alipay’s business model where most of the credit risk is taken by banks, and hence the authorities were sceptical of this lending as it was done by an institution other than a bank. Hence, they wanted more involvement from the firm in the process and altered the requirement of maintaining capital reserve from 1% to almost 30%, which could effectively affect the group’s revenue stream. 2 weeks prior to the listing, China’s richest man, Jack Ma, who also is the largest shareholder of the fintech company made certain critical remarks about the regulatory framework not supporting fintech companies enough. Many also see it as a punishment for being so vocal.&amp;nbsp; The Chinese government has always been a major participant in all aspects of the functioning of the nation. For years, the leadership has sought to facilitate the growth of its tech giants. Its internet restrictions also referred to as the 'Great Firewall', homegrown tech has been protected from foreign competitors and thus dominate the domestic market. Take, for instance, WeChat- the country’s alternative to social media sites like Facebook and Twitter. However, this advantage to domestic firms comes at a cost, where they must never outgrow the regime’s grasp. The system has various measures to keep businesses in-check, such as the introduction of new laws and restrictions that it can impose on a whim. In 2017, Tencent drew Beijing's ire after its Honor of Kings gaming app was said to be too addictive and a few days later the government imposed sweeping reforms on the nations’ mobile gaming industry that included content and playing time restrictions. The most recent example could be the sudden imposition of restrictions on exporting ‘Artificial Intelligence’ technology, which immediately affected ByteDance’s sale procedure to comply with the US’s threat to ban TikTok.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; This instance with Ant Group should not be seen in isolation and more of such interferences could be expected in the future for tech firms. This could be a hurdle at a time when China faces extreme scrutiny over data privacy issues and aversion for coronavirus.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">COVID-19: RBI’s Take and What Now?</title>
      <link href="/RBI-Take-What-Now" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19: RBI’s Take and What Now?" />
      <published>2020-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/RBI-Take-What-Now</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/RBI-Take-What-Now">&lt;p&gt;The Central bank of a nation is tasked with multiple responsibilities to maintain the dynamic, complex and entangled macroeconomic variables with the sole objective of economic development of the country. The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) follows the same pursuit of growth by working out the price and financial stability of the state. The gigantic wave of virus that swept the world in late 2019 and hit India in early 2020 has inevitably accelerated the socio-economic division, the footprint of which will be felt for years to come. With the advent of such unprecedented times, all eyes are turned to the Central bank and to the government for rescue from the ramifications of this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the late evening of March 24, 2020, Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi announced a 21-day complete lockdown which got extended for months due to the rising number of COVID-19 cases in the country. This declaration meant an absolute halt for businesses leading to complete disruption of market forces of demand and supply, money creation, etc. In short, it was a difficult affair for the economy. Nonetheless, the RBI sailed through it almost effortlessly, supporting the economy through the various tools:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) &lt;strong&gt;Rate cuts&lt;/strong&gt;: To incentivise investments and loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b) &lt;strong&gt;Liquidity Infusion&lt;/strong&gt;: Increasing the availability of funds in banks via various policy rates like CRR, Repo rate, Reverse Repo Rate, OMOs, and special windows for financial institutions to borrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;c) &lt;strong&gt;Regulatory Easing&lt;/strong&gt;: Via mechanisms like a moratorium, etc to support the borrowers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These steps resulted in a liquidity spree in the banking system, drawing concerns of inflationary pressure in an already high inflation economy (CPI inflation rate in July was 6.93%). In addition to this, the influx of dollars in the country through Foreign Direct Investments (FDIs) and Foreign Portfolio Investments (FPIs) fuelled the additional circulation of Indian currency in the economy. This, supported by collapsing net imports, led to the pile-up of RBIs forex kitty to an all-time high of $541billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In layman’s language, it looks like a rosy picture. However from an economist’s point of view, this means appreciation of the Indian rupee with respect to the mighty US dollar. Thus, putting exports at a disadvantage. It adds to the already concerning topic of inflation as now excess money will be spent on the imported items, increasing our dependence on imported goods. At the same time, we will be letting go of the opportunity of utilising the liquidity available in the system which could have been used to build productive capacities like infrastructure that will lead to the creation of employment, income and welfare of the nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, inflation will only occur when the monetary surplus in the banking system actually reaches the hands of the consumers via businesses and loans, but banks are averse in lending out due to skyrocketing Non-Performing Assets (NPAs). Hence the overflowing liquidity is limited within these financial intermediaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to an article published in &lt;em&gt;Business Today&lt;/em&gt;, despite the Central bank reducing the Reverse Repo Rate (RRR) from 4.9% to 3.35%, the number of deposits increased during the period of the pandemic. Unused funds in the financial system have further been increasing as businesses and firms are reluctant in taking loans for investments due to low production and capacity utilisation. Moreover, rising COVID-19 cases engulf the future with a blanket of uncertainty for businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The jump in the deposits with the RBI is a cause of worry as the excess money sitting idle with banks now requires the Central bank to pay interest on these deposits. Additionally, the money is never actually entering the productive sector for money creation, which was the prime motive of slashing the RRR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, governments too have a vital role in reviving the economy through its targeted expenditures. But the Union government’s fiscal deficit has soared to 109% of the budgeted target in just 5 months of the current financial year. State governments have been facing a shortage of funds owing to the shortfall of revenues due to sluggish economic activities and failure on part of the Union government to settle the compensation for Goods and Services Tax (GST). Hence, the governments’ bank stepped in to facilitate the reduction of that deficit by borrowing from the bond market. The Center has stuck to its borrowing plan of ₹12 trillion in 2020-21. The superfluity of funds in the financial system is managing to keep the yields in the bond market low, benefitting the borrowers in borrowing funds at low-interest rates. The Central government borrowed ₹7.66 trillion at a weighted rate of 5.82%, the lowest in 15 years, in the first half of the ongoing fiscal year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting the rate of economic expansion back on track is a daunting task and RBI has managed the situation quite decently, but the major chunk of work now lies on the government to use their borrowing for capital expenditure and revival of demand. Better demand sentiments would enable restoration of the market disruptions and lead to an expansion in the trade deficit which would perhaps reduce the balance of payment surplus and minimise the intervention by the Central bank to some extent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest projection by the US Federal Reserve to keep its interest rate near zero till 2023 would result in a sustained flow of foreign funds into countries like India. Therefore, the bankers’ bank needs to be watchful and avoid unnecessary currency appreciation which will not only affect exports but also other macroeconomic variables, thus risking the financial stability of the nation. The biggest challenge will perhaps come when pandemic recedes and activity picks back up but for now, the Reserve Bank needs to maintain a fine balance between the intertwined variables of inflation, bond yields, and currency market for the economic interest of India.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Central bank of a nation is tasked with multiple responsibilities to maintain the dynamic, complex and entangled macroeconomic variables with the sole objective of economic development of the country. The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) follows the same pursuit of growth by working out the price and financial stability of the state. The gigantic wave of virus that swept the world in late 2019 and hit India in early 2020 has inevitably accelerated the socio-economic division, the footprint of which will be felt for years to come. With the advent of such unprecedented times, all eyes are turned to the Central bank and to the government for rescue from the ramifications of this situation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Wirecard: The Financial Collapse of the Century</title>
      <link href="/Wirecard-The-Financial-Collapse-of-the-Century" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wirecard: The Financial Collapse of the Century" />
      <published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Wirecard-The-Financial-Collapse-of-the-Century</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Wirecard-The-Financial-Collapse-of-the-Century">&lt;p&gt;The finance industry already grappling with the effects of COVID-19, faced yet another shock with one of the biggest financial scandals in the world coming to the limelight - the Wirecard scandal. Wirecard, a Munich-based payment processing company, once seen as a darling of investors with a market capitalisation of over $28 billion at its peak, filed for bankruptcy on June 25, 2020, after disclosing a $2.1 billion hole in its balance sheet. But what went wrong with the company?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fintech company incorporated in 1999, joined the Frankfurt stock exchange in 2005 and ascended to the ranking of Germany’s 30 leading companies, also known as the DAX Index. It claimed to have subsidiaries across the globe, with payments being processed for more than 200,000 merchants and clients including major European supermarket chains and airlines. It attracted notable investors such as SoftBank. Wirecard was like any other payment processing company that facilitated transactions between consumers and merchants, and earned a certain percentage per transaction. However what set the company apart from its competitors was its rapid expansion in Asia for the reason that it marketed itself as the leader in this system, claiming to have superior technology and highly capitalising on the shift to a cashless society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2008, the first allegations of accounting irregularities against the firm came to light and in the wake of the attack, the company appointed Ernst &amp;amp; Young (EY), one of the largest accounting enterprises in the world, to conduct a special audit on these claims. EY soon then became the Chief Auditor of the organisation for the next 10 years, signing off the firm’s balance sheet. As allegations against the firm of inflating its operational numbers in Asia continued to surface over the years, a pattern emerged with how the company dealt with these criticisms. They would aggressively deny any wrongdoings and announce that it was an attempt to manipulate their stock prices. However, the stock prices kept rising, undeterred by any negative news coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As claims of malpractice mounted, BaFin- the German financial regulator, during its probe focussed more on the accusers rather than the claims against the enterprise. Various analysts believe that authorities’ protection stemmed as it was a huge moment to see a European home-grown company competing against tech titans of Silicon Valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2019, the regulator announced an unprecedented 2-month ban on short-selling of the company’s shares due to its stock price plummeting below €100, citing its importance to the economy and serious threats to market confidence. Some also point to Germany’s corporate culture being wary of foreign speculators, since many allegations were brought forward by the British newspaper &lt;em&gt;Financial Times&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;FT&lt;/em&gt;). However, the regulators denied all allegations against the organisation and even filed a criminal investigation against &lt;em&gt;FT&lt;/em&gt; for colluding with short-sellers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wirecard mainly functioned by buying shell companies that acted as third party payment processors for the organisation. In return, these companies paid them a commission. However, instead of funds flowing into their Munich bank, it was all transferred to escrow accounts. These are special accounts where multiple parties can use them, hence convincing the public that large sums of money existed in them and were used by its subsidiaries. These accounts held more than $2 billion, all of Wirecard’s profit of more than a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, &lt;em&gt;FT&lt;/em&gt; published an article after being alerted by a whistle-blower, that the organisation was cooking accounting books, hiking up its sales and profit numbers of Asia and Pacific operations. Hence, to put an end to these allegations, the company, in 2019, hired Klynveld Peat Marwick Goerdeler (KPMG) to conduct a special audit. The audit report stated that it could not verify the authenticity of these escrow accounts. As more events unfolded, the company stated that all of the money was stored in the Philippines, and not in these escrow accounts. When EY went to examine these claims from the Philippines bank, the former was notified that the documents submitted by the company were all spurious and money never really entered their financial system, thus the $2.1 billion never existed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This announcement led to the arrest of Markus Braun, CEO and CTO of Wirecard since 2002, on June 23, 2020, on suspicion of inflating the value of the company through feigning business with third parties. Two days later, the company filed for insolvency, making it the biggest accounting scandal in post-war German history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The disclosure of malpractice of such a magnitude has eroded the trust in the country’s authorities, giving a heavy blow to Germany’s reputation as a financial centre - impacting its businesses and the confidence of market participants. This revelation has increased the scrutiny of not only accounting firms, especially EY, for failing to inspect the legitimacy of such an account, but also on regulators for their inadequacy. Various critics argued that Germany’s regulatory system is neither equipped to handle large scale processing enterprises like Wirecard nor does it have the power to oversee the investigation of potential malpractices. This highlights the need for transparency in financial systems and various regulatory reforms such as incentives for whistleblowers, a better framework for fintech companies, etc. With the expansion of inquiry, more details are yet to come, nonetheless, investigators worldwide are trying to comprehend how the company used the loopholes to present itself as a profitable business for more than a decade.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Pandey</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The finance industry already grappling with the effects of COVID-19, faced yet another shock with one of the biggest financial scandals in the world coming to the limelight - the Wirecard scandal. Wirecard, a Munich-based payment processing company, once seen as a darling of investors with a market capitalisation of over $28 billion at its peak, filed for bankruptcy on June 25, 2020, after disclosing a $2.1 billion hole in its balance sheet. But what went wrong with the company?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
