<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/millennial/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-07-18T17:18:34+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/millennial/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Millennials, the Gentle Souls</title>
      <link href="/Millennials-the-Gentle-Souls" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Millennials, the Gentle Souls" />
      <published>2019-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Millennials-the-Gentle-Souls</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Millennials-the-Gentle-Souls">&lt;p&gt;It is perhaps for the first time ever that postmodernism has found such a lovely
home: social media. The diffusion of the political, philosophical and
sociological microphones has done more than just prove that multiple conflicting
truths coexist; it has given a voice to all of those narratives, to all of our
realities. Contradictions are not grounds to invalidate your story. Social media
has shaped how today’s youth discusses the world they inhabit. We are exposed to
a vivid pluralism of beliefs and ideas, almost on a real-time basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point on the axis of time, Facebook and Instagram became places to
discuss our collective anguish over misogyny, casteism, racism, homophobia, our
parents and pineapple pizza. Candidly, the discourse that exists as of today, is
not ideal, in fact far from it. It’s a chaos of constantly clashing opinions.
And not the most sophisticated of chaoses even. It’s not the most nuanced or
informed discussion, our arguments don’t necessarily feature brilliance or dare
I say, intelligence. However, I am not looking for a great emancipatory utility
to this discourse. I am merely looking at the hint of nobility that underlies
this chaos. What’s noble is that we care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A concern that is evident in the endearing frustration of our angry tweets about
how bras are a tool of the patriarchy or the activist pages on Instagram which
tell you that it’s okay to not be able to orgasm. It’s visible in the
fifteen-year-old slam poets who dream of changing the world, often not for
themselves but for others, and in all of us, a type of audience, clicking our
fingers in praise. We realise the passivity of the nature of our activism. We
face the brunt of accusations that tell us all we can do is yell at each other
in our insular echo chambers. We realise the frustration that this social media
activism will get us nowhere. But are we not already somewhere? Especially, the
moment we begin to realise the inadequacies and fallibility of our own
endeavours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of my insistence upon this chaotic discussion being romantically beautiful
is reduced to hokum with the words ‘woke culture.’ The ‘woke millennial’ gives
up plastic straws and embraces veganism only because it is suddenly cool to care
about the environment, not out of actual concern for the Earth. Atrocious
millennials!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Woke culture’ is criticised, as it should be. But the very fact that caring
about social issues is now a metric for social acceptance and approval, is
nothing short of a paradigm shift. We are trying to create the socially ratified
moral compass we never inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennial culture extends beyond the political or social, it enters the deeply
intimate, personal spaces of our lives. Here’s where bullying comes into the
picture, and what, I believe, shapes us into being the gentler generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bullying arises, mostly, from differences in historically sanctioned prowess;
like beauty in women and toughness in men or things like wealth and having a
favourable orientation. What most generations have absently done is aspire to be
like their bullies. The ‘prowess’ that our intimidators possessed was fed as
aspirational. And the moment you begin to believe that your inadequacies are to
blame for your pain, you stop empathising with yourself and with others. But
here we have our millennials who have gone a step beyond the condemnation of
bullies. They are questioning the arbitrary distributions of power and prowess.
We are disarming power itself. We are gentler, not only with others but, more
courageously, also with ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world has been hungover on patriarchal ideas that seek glory in strength,
for far too long. We are saying, it is okay to feel. What I am saying is our
generation fights the urge to want to be like Regina George and instead embraces
the freaky Janis Ian who lurks within. Millennials exhibit the ferociousness of
daring to live authentically. The history of our world has strung together
stories of the suppression of any kind of human authenticity. From Victorian
women who could not renounce corsets and religious laws that tell us men cannot
f*ck other men to mothers who tell their daughters not to laugh too loud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you contextualise the past, you begin to see what a rebellious idea it is
to dream to live unencumbered. Social reinforcements are what make it painful to
be yourself; the eye rolls and the condescending laughs when something about you
hints at you being different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we are well on our way towards breaking those stringent, stringent shackles.
We are breaking notions of propriety, right down to the way we converse with
each other. We let each other be the dramatic, flamboyant and weird creatures
humans were meant to be. We are not just secretly engaging with our indecorous
selves, but finally talking about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The millennial ability to let people be the way they want to be, in short,
acceptance, arises from somewhere. We admit our imperfections and the colossal
mountains of our insecurities. It is this admittance that lends us the empathy
to be able to see the fallibility of other humans without feeling the need to
shame it. We have stopped holding ourselves up to a pedestal of perfection and
have accepted how utterly human it is to be flawed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our personal and political capacities, we are striving towards one thing; the
complete utter and humanisation of humans. Our empathy manifests both in the
acrimonious outrage over the romanticisation of sexual violence in our cinema
and in the tenderness with which we listen to our friends’ cathartic rants.
Millennial sensitivity is seen in how they will call out a certain brand of
motivational videos for being the inspiration porn that they are. Millennials
will tell you that the first step to respecting pain is to not voyeur over it.
Let humans be human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They say millennials are lonely, and maybe we are, but we are also surviving
through the solidarities we have constructed for ourselves. Sometimes that
solidarity is sisterhood, sometimes it is merely commenting ‘Me, as hell’ on a
meme rooted in self-deprecation.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Stuti Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is perhaps for the first time ever that postmodernism has found such a lovely home: social media. The diffusion of the political, philosophical and sociological microphones has done more than just prove that multiple conflicting truths coexist; it has given a voice to all of those narratives, to all of our realities. Contradictions are not grounds to invalidate your story. Social media has shaped how today’s youth discusses the world they inhabit. We are exposed to a vivid pluralism of beliefs and ideas, almost on a real-time basis. At some point on the axis of time, Facebook and Instagram became places to discuss our collective anguish over misogyny, casteism, racism, homophobia, our parents and pineapple pizza. Candidly, the discourse that exists as of today, is not ideal, in fact far from it. It’s a chaos of constantly clashing opinions. And not the most sophisticated of chaoses even. It’s not the most nuanced or informed discussion, our arguments don’t necessarily feature brilliance or dare I say, intelligence. However, I am not looking for a great emancipatory utility to this discourse. I am merely looking at the hint of nobility that underlies this chaos. What’s noble is that we care. A concern that is evident in the endearing frustration of our angry tweets about how bras are a tool of the patriarchy or the activist pages on Instagram which tell you that it’s okay to not be able to orgasm. It’s visible in the fifteen-year-old slam poets who dream of changing the world, often not for themselves but for others, and in all of us, a type of audience, clicking our fingers in praise. We realise the passivity of the nature of our activism. We face the brunt of accusations that tell us all we can do is yell at each other in our insular echo chambers. We realise the frustration that this social media activism will get us nowhere. But are we not already somewhere? Especially, the moment we begin to realise the inadequacies and fallibility of our own endeavours. All of my insistence upon this chaotic discussion being romantically beautiful is reduced to hokum with the words ‘woke culture.’ The ‘woke millennial’ gives up plastic straws and embraces veganism only because it is suddenly cool to care about the environment, not out of actual concern for the Earth. Atrocious millennials! ‘Woke culture’ is criticised, as it should be. But the very fact that caring about social issues is now a metric for social acceptance and approval, is nothing short of a paradigm shift. We are trying to create the socially ratified moral compass we never inherited. Millennial culture extends beyond the political or social, it enters the deeply intimate, personal spaces of our lives. Here’s where bullying comes into the picture, and what, I believe, shapes us into being the gentler generation. Bullying arises, mostly, from differences in historically sanctioned prowess; like beauty in women and toughness in men or things like wealth and having a favourable orientation. What most generations have absently done is aspire to be like their bullies. The ‘prowess’ that our intimidators possessed was fed as aspirational. And the moment you begin to believe that your inadequacies are to blame for your pain, you stop empathising with yourself and with others. But here we have our millennials who have gone a step beyond the condemnation of bullies. They are questioning the arbitrary distributions of power and prowess. We are disarming power itself. We are gentler, not only with others but, more courageously, also with ourselves. The world has been hungover on patriarchal ideas that seek glory in strength, for far too long. We are saying, it is okay to feel. What I am saying is our generation fights the urge to want to be like Regina George and instead embraces the freaky Janis Ian who lurks within. Millennials exhibit the ferociousness of daring to live authentically. The history of our world has strung together stories of the suppression of any kind of human authenticity. From Victorian women who could not renounce corsets and religious laws that tell us men cannot f*ck other men to mothers who tell their daughters not to laugh too loud. Once you contextualise the past, you begin to see what a rebellious idea it is to dream to live unencumbered. Social reinforcements are what make it painful to be yourself; the eye rolls and the condescending laughs when something about you hints at you being different. But we are well on our way towards breaking those stringent, stringent shackles. We are breaking notions of propriety, right down to the way we converse with each other. We let each other be the dramatic, flamboyant and weird creatures humans were meant to be. We are not just secretly engaging with our indecorous selves, but finally talking about them. The millennial ability to let people be the way they want to be, in short, acceptance, arises from somewhere. We admit our imperfections and the colossal mountains of our insecurities. It is this admittance that lends us the empathy to be able to see the fallibility of other humans without feeling the need to shame it. We have stopped holding ourselves up to a pedestal of perfection and have accepted how utterly human it is to be flawed. In our personal and political capacities, we are striving towards one thing; the complete utter and humanisation of humans. Our empathy manifests both in the acrimonious outrage over the romanticisation of sexual violence in our cinema and in the tenderness with which we listen to our friends’ cathartic rants. Millennial sensitivity is seen in how they will call out a certain brand of motivational videos for being the inspiration porn that they are. Millennials will tell you that the first step to respecting pain is to not voyeur over it. Let humans be human. They say millennials are lonely, and maybe we are, but we are also surviving through the solidarities we have constructed for ourselves. Sometimes that solidarity is sisterhood, sometimes it is merely commenting ‘Me, as hell’ on a meme rooted in self-deprecation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Housing -The Millennial Pipe Dream</title>
      <link href="/The-Millennial-Pipe-Dream" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Housing -The Millennial Pipe Dream" />
      <published>2019-07-12T16:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-12T16:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Millennial-Pipe-Dream</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Millennial-Pipe-Dream">&lt;p&gt;“Like generations before them, the demographic cohort known as the millennials …
has shaped a number of social and cultural aspects, including fashion,
technology, and politics,” wrote The Fed. “One area where they’re facing
challenges in leaving their mark, however, is the economy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty years ago, the median price of a regular condominium settlement in an
American city was $108,900. Now, the figure is at $337,200. Even if one
accounts for inflation, the price has still risen astronomically, despite the
fact that the current working demographic cohort, the millennials, have
exhibited an involuntary disinclination towards homeownership, which is
reflected in the shift of the median age of homeownership from 29 in the 1970’s
to 33 presently. This global behavioural shift is attributed to more than just
the generation gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One would assume that it was the Boomers and the Gen Xers who were the hardest
hit when the housing bubble burst a decade ago, for they lost the jobs and bore
the fury of the deflated real estate and stock market. But the millennials, then
aged between their pre-teens to early 20s, had their average age of graduation
in 2010, right in the midst of the global economic meltdown. Naturally, when
they joined the workforce, the job market was rough, with lower wages and puny
scope for raises. Additionally, there was a lack of income stability, since it’s
common for most millennials to switch jobs at least three times in the five
years that follow graduation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, however, is not entirely a question of affordability, for, even
comparatively better-off millennials, earning over $50,000 a year, have chosen
not to purchase a home. Real estate is not an ‘impulse’ purchase. Many young
graduates already have the burden of student loans that overwhelms the benefits
of going to college, and upsets the debt-to-income ratio and their credit score,
despite having a reasonably good income level. As a result, it becomes harder
for them to acquire loans with easy down payment terms. Moreover, post the
foreclosure of millions of American homes during the Great Recession, new
lending reforms were implemented by most of the developed nations, like the
Dodd-Frank Act in the USA, which further exacerbated the down payment
requirements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another survey found that the millennials had an average tipping point of at
least five years of rental residentship before they would decide to purchase a
home in the area, and by this logic, even the older segment of the millennials
would have made a decision to own a home post-2013. And, at that point, the
easing of the global economy had begun to recede, and rate hikes were soon on
the table, thus making Adjustable Rate Mortgage an unattractive option, due to
the loss that would accompany the refinancing process. These economic
fluctuations at such a delicate transition point in life definitely had a
subconscious impact on the minds of young millennials, who have turned
risk-averse. Consequently, the tendency of careful considerations has
accompanied their decisions in most avenues of life, ranging from commitment to
a family to an investment like real estate. The Boomers have accused the
‘crypto-crazed’ millennials of destroying the housing markets, when in fact,
they are becoming victims to the vicious cycle of the renting market. As a
result of the unaffordability, a greater number of millennials are moving to the
rental space, pushing up the demand and thus the rents, which then lowers their
savings, and further delays homeownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it would not be fair to entirely blame the Great Recession for the modern
housing crisis. Urban sprawling is at its peak. Currently, 54% of the global
population lives in cities, and another 2.5 billion people are expected to be
added to this figure by 2050. The scarce land contributes to the skyrocketing
prices of accommodation, and there is a limit to which the cities can grow
vertically. This limit is not merely a variable of the architectural abilities
but also depends on the return factor. While most big cities have the ability to
build high skyscrapers, it becomes unaffordable once the government weighs in
all the indirect costs. When you graph the marginal construction costs against
the number of floors on the abscissa, it gives out a familiar U-shaped curve,
whose viability lies at the bottom-most point (only cost is considered, because
the return from public residential projects is one-time and only aims to cover
costs). Another reason that tall buildings are being avoided, is the NIMBYism
(Not in my backyard) displayed by the existing residents, who oppose progressive
developmental projects, citing how it would contribute to greater pollution,
rising traffic and would deflate the price of their properties. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The working population, largely composed of millennials, battles the crisis not
only in the usual suspect cities like NY, Tokyo, Hong Kong, London, Mumbai etc.,
but also has to face it in other smaller cities like Dubai. The crisis takes an
especially risky turn when it comes to the developing nations, where a
combination of bureaucratic red tape and rapidly growing population clamps
people down to an impoverished existence. Take the example of Mumbai, India,
about which the Scottish urban planner Patrick Geddes had famously remarked,
“Mumbai is not housing its workers, it’s warehousing them”. Nearly 52% of this
city’s population lives on 9% of its land, in informal settlements called slums.
Many of these slum-dwellers are educated people working in MNCs, who can afford
monthly dine-ins at the most high-end restaurants in the city, but not a decent
settlement. The slums appear to be a poverty problem for Asia, when they
actually are a real estate problem. The crisis is mainly associated with two
flawed policies. The city has an unnaturally low Floor-Space Index (FSI) at 1.3,
while cities in other Asian nations flourish at an average FSI of 7-8. The FSI
is the ratio of the floor area to the plot area. So an FSI of, say, 2, would
allow us to construct two stories if the process includes the entire plot area,
and four stories if we leave half the plot vacant. The next flawed policy for
Mumbai is one that has been famously dubbed the easiest way to destroy a city,
next only to a bombing - rent control. The rent is frozen at pre-Independence
levels, robbing landowners of any incentive to rent it out to tenants in fear of
encroachment. Such a policy often results in the formation of dilapidated ghost
towns, which has happened to many cities of China, Turkey, and the like. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, governments all over the world have come to the rescue of the working
millennials with rash and hasty policies like rent control, which have only
exacerbated the situation. The lack of attention and forethought that a basic
amenity like housing faces globally is an important contributor to a class
divide in modern cities, resulting in other socio-economic issues. Shirish B.
Patel, an urban planner, in his piece in the &lt;em&gt;Economic and Political Weekly&lt;/em&gt;,
had perfectly summed up the situation of the working class millennials of the
cities with the analogy of a big ship, which has many workers, who perform every
petty to intricate task on board, throughout the day, for which the captain pays
them well, but does not allow them to spend the night on the ship. If they
manage to survive the night in water, without getting eaten by the sharks, they
must report to work the next morning. If not, there are plenty of fish in the
sea.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Like generations before them, the demographic cohort known as the millennials … has shaped a number of social and cultural aspects, including fashion, technology, and politics,” wrote The Fed. “One area where they’re facing challenges in leaving their mark, however, is the economy.” Twenty years ago, the median price of a regular condominium settlement in an American city was $108,900. Now, the figure is at $337,200. Even if one accounts for inflation, the price has still risen astronomically, despite the fact that the current working demographic cohort, the millennials, have exhibited an involuntary disinclination towards homeownership, which is reflected in the shift of the median age of homeownership from 29 in the 1970’s to 33 presently. This global behavioural shift is attributed to more than just the generation gap. One would assume that it was the Boomers and the Gen Xers who were the hardest hit when the housing bubble burst a decade ago, for they lost the jobs and bore the fury of the deflated real estate and stock market. But the millennials, then aged between their pre-teens to early 20s, had their average age of graduation in 2010, right in the midst of the global economic meltdown. Naturally, when they joined the workforce, the job market was rough, with lower wages and puny scope for raises. Additionally, there was a lack of income stability, since it’s common for most millennials to switch jobs at least three times in the five years that follow graduation.  This, however, is not entirely a question of affordability, for, even comparatively better-off millennials, earning over $50,000 a year, have chosen not to purchase a home. Real estate is not an ‘impulse’ purchase. Many young graduates already have the burden of student loans that overwhelms the benefits of going to college, and upsets the debt-to-income ratio and their credit score, despite having a reasonably good income level. As a result, it becomes harder for them to acquire loans with easy down payment terms. Moreover, post the foreclosure of millions of American homes during the Great Recession, new lending reforms were implemented by most of the developed nations, like the Dodd-Frank Act in the USA, which further exacerbated the down payment requirements.  Another survey found that the millennials had an average tipping point of at least five years of rental residentship before they would decide to purchase a home in the area, and by this logic, even the older segment of the millennials would have made a decision to own a home post-2013. And, at that point, the easing of the global economy had begun to recede, and rate hikes were soon on the table, thus making Adjustable Rate Mortgage an unattractive option, due to the loss that would accompany the refinancing process. These economic fluctuations at such a delicate transition point in life definitely had a subconscious impact on the minds of young millennials, who have turned risk-averse. Consequently, the tendency of careful considerations has accompanied their decisions in most avenues of life, ranging from commitment to a family to an investment like real estate. The Boomers have accused the ‘crypto-crazed’ millennials of destroying the housing markets, when in fact, they are becoming victims to the vicious cycle of the renting market. As a result of the unaffordability, a greater number of millennials are moving to the rental space, pushing up the demand and thus the rents, which then lowers their savings, and further delays homeownership. But it would not be fair to entirely blame the Great Recession for the modern housing crisis. Urban sprawling is at its peak. Currently, 54% of the global population lives in cities, and another 2.5 billion people are expected to be added to this figure by 2050. The scarce land contributes to the skyrocketing prices of accommodation, and there is a limit to which the cities can grow vertically. This limit is not merely a variable of the architectural abilities but also depends on the return factor. While most big cities have the ability to build high skyscrapers, it becomes unaffordable once the government weighs in all the indirect costs. When you graph the marginal construction costs against the number of floors on the abscissa, it gives out a familiar U-shaped curve, whose viability lies at the bottom-most point (only cost is considered, because the return from public residential projects is one-time and only aims to cover costs). Another reason that tall buildings are being avoided, is the NIMBYism (Not in my backyard) displayed by the existing residents, who oppose progressive developmental projects, citing how it would contribute to greater pollution, rising traffic and would deflate the price of their properties.  The working population, largely composed of millennials, battles the crisis not only in the usual suspect cities like NY, Tokyo, Hong Kong, London, Mumbai etc., but also has to face it in other smaller cities like Dubai. The crisis takes an especially risky turn when it comes to the developing nations, where a combination of bureaucratic red tape and rapidly growing population clamps people down to an impoverished existence. Take the example of Mumbai, India, about which the Scottish urban planner Patrick Geddes had famously remarked, “Mumbai is not housing its workers, it’s warehousing them”. Nearly 52% of this city’s population lives on 9% of its land, in informal settlements called slums. Many of these slum-dwellers are educated people working in MNCs, who can afford monthly dine-ins at the most high-end restaurants in the city, but not a decent settlement. The slums appear to be a poverty problem for Asia, when they actually are a real estate problem. The crisis is mainly associated with two flawed policies. The city has an unnaturally low Floor-Space Index (FSI) at 1.3, while cities in other Asian nations flourish at an average FSI of 7-8. The FSI is the ratio of the floor area to the plot area. So an FSI of, say, 2, would allow us to construct two stories if the process includes the entire plot area, and four stories if we leave half the plot vacant. The next flawed policy for Mumbai is one that has been famously dubbed the easiest way to destroy a city, next only to a bombing - rent control. The rent is frozen at pre-Independence levels, robbing landowners of any incentive to rent it out to tenants in fear of encroachment. Such a policy often results in the formation of dilapidated ghost towns, which has happened to many cities of China, Turkey, and the like.  Clearly, governments all over the world have come to the rescue of the working millennials with rash and hasty policies like rent control, which have only exacerbated the situation. The lack of attention and forethought that a basic amenity like housing faces globally is an important contributor to a class divide in modern cities, resulting in other socio-economic issues. Shirish B. Patel, an urban planner, in his piece in the Economic and Political Weekly, had perfectly summed up the situation of the working class millennials of the cities with the analogy of a big ship, which has many workers, who perform every petty to intricate task on board, throughout the day, for which the captain pays them well, but does not allow them to spend the night on the ship. If they manage to survive the night in water, without getting eaten by the sharks, they must report to work the next morning. If not, there are plenty of fish in the sea.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Educating the Millennials: Whose Responsibility?</title>
      <link href="/Educating-the-Millennials" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Educating the Millennials: Whose Responsibility?" />
      <published>2019-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Educating-the-Millennials</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Educating-the-Millennials">&lt;p&gt;“Education is the most powerful weapon which you can use to change the world.” These words of Nelson Mandela capture the importance of obtaining an education for every individual across any generation. Millennials, too, recognise the importance of getting educated. In fact, according to the Pew Research Center, they are the most educated generation yet. However, the major impediment that comes in their way of entering the formal schooling system and, later, higher education is limited availability of finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Education funding is the most important means to strengthen education systems in the world. This has evolved over the years. In mid-19th century, governments across the world did most of the funding using revenue from taxes levied at the local level. Around the 20th century, the growth of the education sector became a global phenomenon. Other sources of education financing such as external grants or loans provided by foreign government, private organisations such as NGOs, and local administrations were being increasingly tapped. The amount spent by developing countries on improving the condition was close enough to the average spent in developed countries. A historical decline in education inequalities was observed during this time. UNGC’s Millennium Development Goals were signed in 2000, in which the second goal was to achieve universal primary education. The first decade of the 21st century saw increased international financial flows for development assistance. Post-2010, there was a notable reduction in the amount of public funds being used to finance education. Secondary and tertiary levels of education receive more funding than the primary level. Notable examples in this regard would be Europe and Sub-Saharan Africa where less development assistance is provided for primary education. The UNICEF report, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unicef.org/publications/files/Investment_Case_for_Education_and_Equity_FINAL.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Investment Case for Education and Equity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;2015&lt;/em&gt;, shows that in low-income countries, on average 46% of public resources for education are allocated to the 10% of students who are most educated – while this figure goes down to 26% and 13% in lower-middle and upper-middle income countries respectively. Larger allocation to higher education is important to ensure better national competitiveness through innovation, and to enhance the skills of millennials. Moreover, there is cross-country heterogeneity with respect to the importance of the education sector vis-à-vis other sectors. For example, American Samoa and Kiribati spend more than 12% of their national income on education while countries such as Bangladesh and Bermuda spend only about 1% for this purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is interesting to note is even when more public funds are allocated and private funding is also playing its part towards higher education financing, they are not enough. The demand for higher education among millennials is constantly growing and this is inevitably transforming this sector from an elite to a mass system across different parts of the world. The traditional revenue-driven model was based on public funding, student tuition fees and other charges collected from them, along with endowments. A major component of the revenue so collected goes into paying salaries to the faculty. It is necessary because of the increased opportunity cost of employment avenues. Besides dwindling public funding, the rate of increase in the cost of higher education exceeds the inflation rate in most countries. As a result, the cost of higher education is escalating at an alarming rate. Even in a country like India, where higher education has traditionally been highly subsidised, the government is pulling its purse strings. Across the world, public funding is moving from committal funds to assessment-based funding. Now even the youngest millennial is an adult and is ready for higher education. It is the responsibility of all stakeholders to ensure that education is within the means of each interested millennial. Christensen and Eyring in 2011 introduced the concept of ‘disruptive innovation’ in their book &lt;em&gt;The Innovative University&lt;/em&gt;. This idea was used to implement information and communication technology in education, which was done by the introduction of online courses. Virtual education not only reduced the cost of education for millennials but also helped improve the quality of teaching. Many universities have ‘Work-Study Programs’ and offer an opportunity to study and work part-time simultaneously under such initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Countries are designing different models for sustainable funding of education. In some countries, like Germany, need-based student aid is provided for students, while in the UK, financial institutions are generally tapped to raise capital. New Zealand follows a Performance-Linked Funding Policy wherein students over the 50th percentile receive 100% government funding, while the remaining students receive 95%. To keep a check on the exorbitant tuition fees, a Tuition Grant Scheme (TGS) is in place in Singapore where students enjoy a substantially subsidised tuition. A new system of philanthro-capitalism has been introduced in India where capitalistic style objectives direct the entry of philanthropic enterprises in the education sector. Compared to the slow growth rate in higher education enrolment in North America and Europe, India enjoys the advantage of a large youth population so higher education sees enrolment in huge numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennials are doing their bit to reduce strain on resources. Some students enter the workforce while being enrolled in higher education to either financially support themselves or to gain practical experience. Many start-up stories unfold in universities. Many millennials believe in the ‘earn while you learn’ concept. Education loans are becoming increasingly popular as a means to finance education in developed as well as developing countries. According to an estimate by CNBC, student debt stands at nearly $1.5 trillion and, roughly, one in four American adults is paying off student loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financing of higher education institutions assumes great significance in today’s extremely competitive world. Higher education makes an immense contribution towards building the social capital of a nation. The government should have a futuristic outlook and increase spending on education with a focus on the quality. This is important because millennials see education as a means not only to acquire a degree but an avenue to enhance their knowledge and employability. While need-based grants and scholarships are available to some students, there are many who are denied these. Industry can provide lucrative internship opportunities to students, which help them finance their education. Policymakers should assess the impact of student loans as a source of financing education. Loan servicing results in reduced disposable income, which may impact the economic growth of a country adversely. For example, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.federalreserve.gov/econresdata/feds/2016/files/2016010pap.pdf&quot;&gt;Federal Reserve Board of Washington,&lt;/a&gt; DC concluded in a study that increasing student debt in the US has resulted in reduced homeownership. The growth of the housing sector is important for the economic revival of any country because of backward and forward linkages. High student debt will have implications for workforce composition as well. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nerdwallet.com/blog/investing/millennial-grad-retirement-age-is-75/&quot;&gt;A study&lt;/a&gt; from NerdWallet predicts that students who graduated from US colleges in 2015 will have to delay retirement until the age of 75, in part because of the increasing burden of student debt. It is, thus, imperative for policymakers across the world to brainstorm and find ways to finance education in a manner that it becomes a win-win situation for millennials and their successors – Generation Z.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Education is the most powerful weapon which you can use to change the world.” These words of Nelson Mandela capture the importance of obtaining an education for every individual across any generation. Millennials, too, recognise the importance of getting educated. In fact, according to the Pew Research Center, they are the most educated generation yet. However, the major impediment that comes in their way of entering the formal schooling system and, later, higher education is limited availability of finance.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The State of the Millennial in 2019</title>
      <link href="/The-State-of-the-Millennial-in-2019" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The State of the Millennial in 2019" />
      <published>2019-07-07T01:40:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-07T01:40:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-State-of-the-Millennial-in-2019</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-State-of-the-Millennial-in-2019">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Millennials (smh). Pampered and nurtured by parents, trying to avoid the
mistakes of a previous generation. You are late to graduate, late to marry and
late to have children. You’re even late to find a job (IF you find a job). To
this ever-determined and ambitious generation, we dedicate the series, ‘for’ and
‘by’ the Millennials, who are most likely still living with their parents. It’s
time we spoke about our host of issues, Gen-Y style.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a Millennial, you &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be angry. Also, if you’re a Millennial
who’s about to hit the job market, I’ve got disappointing news for you. The
Millennial unemployment rate now stands at an &lt;a href=&quot;https://americansforprosperity.org/?utm_source=GO&amp;amp;utm_medium=banner&amp;amp;utm_campaign=redirect&amp;amp;utm_content=main&quot;&gt;astounding
12.8%&lt;/a&gt;,
dwarfing the US national average. Furthermore, if you are a Millennial who has
gone through the past decade unemployed or not, you have also had to endure the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Counting-down-the-biggest-economic&quot;&gt;biggest financial
disaster&lt;/a&gt; of the past
half-century, so kudos to you for sticking around and having a firsthand account
of the experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were robbed, I tell you. The Millennials were supposed to be the ‘greatest
generation’ yet, the most technologically advanced and by far the most educated
generation ever. We were expected to come in and revolutionise the industry, do
away with the old-fashioned and bear the torch of progress. Well, so much for
trying. We have still not cracked into the industry as smoothly as we would have
wanted. Employers are unsatisfied with our over-expectant attitudes (Note: most
of them being baby-boomers, the slackers of Generation X never made it).
Overall, it has been a struggle. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, we are hard to please, overconfident and maybe a tad bit narcissistic.
We dream too much about having it all, without taking our daily dose of reality.
Flashy cars, jewellery, big condos, champagne and caviar. Well, that’s what was
sold to us ever since we got on to &lt;em&gt;MTV&lt;/em&gt; or were young enough to watch
television. We also focus too much on ourselves, often losing track of the &lt;em&gt;‘Big
Picture’.&lt;/em&gt; But we never had to answer the call of the GI generation or the
rallying cry of growth and economic development in the 80’s and 90’s. How often
were you taught to think as a generation, and not as individuals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter what, one thing is for sure. The Millennial Generation or Gen-Y as it
is called, is the most highly educated generation to date, and we are definitely
proud of it. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2018/03/16/how-millennials-compare-with-their-grandparents/ft_millennials-education_031715/&quot;&gt;Pew Research
Center&lt;/a&gt;
recently conducted a study showing that 21% and 27% of men and women (aged
18-33) had a college degree, as compared to the Baby Boomers (17% and 14%) and
Generation X (18% and 20%). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Oh, what do I hear? We aren’t learning interpersonal and communication skills?
Really?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True adulthood only hits us when we realize that these numbers do not mean
anything to the people hiring out there. They say we lack team building and the
ability to communicate effectively, and are more adept at theoretical knowledge
than actual applicable skills. Which in essence is saying that our school and
college education did not really help us at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, that just rubs us off the wrong way, especially with how
increasingly expensive university education has become, with ballooning student
debt plaguing much of the Western world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If the employer is just having a problem with me and my ways, then guess what,
I quit!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://66.media.tumblr.com/504bc9dab4a70c6c69a5696be0456568/tumblr_n22rf1CVMY1tq4of6o1_500.gif&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//lalalala.gif&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there lies another innate flaw deep within us. Maybe, it is
because a lot of us are still young and haven’t grown out of the habit of
denial. But for many, it is very hard for us to come to terms with our
shortcomings. Much too often we will just dismiss them, or much worse, put the
blame on the employer. But as we all know, that’s just a quicker way to get the
boot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are to make up ground, and reach our expectations (sky high!), we will
have to adjust to the ways of the world and not be so adamant as we strive to
perfection. But why ‘perfection’? Why are we so obsessed with getting it right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/shohan.mukherjee/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//millennials1.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer lies with the world that has been built by the last generation to
earn the ‘greatest’ title before us: the baby boomers. As baby boomers emerged
from childhood, they soon had a very jolting experience into the foray of the
professional worker. Their journey into adulthood was not as long and smoothed
out as ours. Most of them emerged from the growing middle class, at a time when
countries all across the world were engaged in a GDP scoring competition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, most of this generation were thrust directly into the workforce and found
a way to sustain themselves, thanks to their resilient nature. They ended up
earning far more than their parents, a trend which had been continuing since the
1900’s. Later on in life, most of them ended up giving birth to Generation X as
well as the Millennials. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it seems like the buck stops here, as the Millennials are suited to be the
first generation to earn &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; than their parents. It is not a surprise that
rising difficulties to secure a job coupling with employment opportunities
bottoming out post the Great Recession have led to employment protests
throughout Europe, the USA and Asia. And although Millennials are believed to be
far more open-minded and tolerant, the dire circumstances have led to growing
support for right-wing politics in many European and South Asian nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The super-saturated job market has lead to increasingly weird paradoxes. Here’s
one story from &lt;em&gt;The Huffington Post&lt;/em&gt;, which could be one of many:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“I was literally paying to work,” says Elena, a 29-year-old dietician in Texas.
As part of her master’s degree, she was required to do a yearlong “internship”
in a hospital. It was supposed to be training, but she says she worked the same
hours and did the same tasks as paid staffers. “I took out an extra \$20,000 in
student loans to pay tuition for the year I was working for free,” she says.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse yet, with the increase of contractor companies which deal especially in
security, storage and inventory management, or housekeeping activities, the
future of low-income workers is further at risk. Take the example of Mr Joe, the
security guard at the mall, who is actually signed to a contractor that has
inked a deal with the mall. In this way, the mall just has to pay the contractor
and not the individual person who is doing the job. This cuts out a lot of costs
including any form of pension or benefits. Of course, that goes out of Mr Joe’s
pocket. And out goes any form of career advancement either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Princeton-LSE grad Michael Lewis made a fortune and a legacy out of his book,
&lt;em&gt;Liar’s Poker&lt;/em&gt;, which details the rise of Lewie Ranieri and his team of traders
who made big money at Salomon Brothers back in the late-80’s. In the book he
often spoke of back office workers, including people who worked the fax and
xerox machines, later trying their hand at trading for the company after slowly
rising through the ranks over the years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, thanks to him for documenting another list of practices that went out the
window during the Financial Crisis. You can wave goodbye to that sort of career
mobility in the 21st century. After all, the Great Crash of 2008 was all about
under-skilled people working over-skilled jobs. Look at where we have arrived
now with the current wave of Millennial underemployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is because of things like these that we fear a slip up so much, even a little
one, that could send us hurtling down the tunnel of underemployment,
unemployment, and at last, poverty. No, no, don’t laugh, this is serious. You
might not have gotten out of your post-sack funk by the time you realise that
you have fallen below the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sanford.duke.edu/people/faculty/krishna-anirudh&quot;&gt;Anirudh Krishna&lt;/a&gt;, a
professor at Duke University, has documented over 1,000 cases of people who fell
into poverty, and only some of whom managed to escape it. He conducted his
search throughout India and Kenya, and revealed that poverty arises from a
series of mishaps. One broken leg, one lost job, one sick family member and you
find yourself below the line. And it is this chance of slipping (literally),
coupled with humongous college and healthcare costs, that force us Millennials
to hope against hope to strive for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inverse.com/article/53091-millennials-largest-ever-perfectionism-study&quot;&gt;perfection at every living
moment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, here we stand at the brink of a period of flux and change. Our
generation’s defining moment has come and gone in 2008, we are just afraid
another one might &lt;a href=&quot;http://fortune.com/2019/06/04/next-recession-2020-predictions/&quot;&gt;come along too
soon&lt;/a&gt;. We might
well be the first generation in decades to earn less than our parents. We will
delay our marriages as well as moving out of home. Yes, buying a home now is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://globalnews.ca/news/3230146/numbers-show-its-harder-for-millennials-to-buy-a-home-than-it-was-for-their-parents/&quot;&gt;exponentially
tougher&lt;/a&gt;
than 30 years ago. Deal with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/jan/05/perfectionism-mental-health-millennial-social-media&quot;&gt;a
problem&lt;/a&gt;
with that? We don’t, we have no choice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the future (FML).&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shohan Mukherjee</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Millennials (smh). Pampered and nurtured by parents, trying to avoid the mistakes of a previous generation. You are late to graduate, late to marry and late to have children. You’re even late to find a job (IF you find a job). To this ever-determined and ambitious generation, we dedicate the series, ‘for’ and ‘by’ the Millennials, who are most likely still living with their parents. It’s time we spoke about our host of issues, Gen-Y style. If you are a Millennial, you should be angry. Also, if you’re a Millennial who’s about to hit the job market, I’ve got disappointing news for you. The Millennial unemployment rate now stands at an astounding 12.8%, dwarfing the US national average. Furthermore, if you are a Millennial who has gone through the past decade unemployed or not, you have also had to endure the biggest financial disaster of the past half-century, so kudos to you for sticking around and having a firsthand account of the experience. We were robbed, I tell you. The Millennials were supposed to be the ‘greatest generation’ yet, the most technologically advanced and by far the most educated generation ever. We were expected to come in and revolutionise the industry, do away with the old-fashioned and bear the torch of progress. Well, so much for trying. We have still not cracked into the industry as smoothly as we would have wanted. Employers are unsatisfied with our over-expectant attitudes (Note: most of them being baby-boomers, the slackers of Generation X never made it). Overall, it has been a struggle.  Alright, we are hard to please, overconfident and maybe a tad bit narcissistic. We dream too much about having it all, without taking our daily dose of reality. Flashy cars, jewellery, big condos, champagne and caviar. Well, that’s what was sold to us ever since we got on to MTV or were young enough to watch television. We also focus too much on ourselves, often losing track of the ‘Big Picture’. But we never had to answer the call of the GI generation or the rallying cry of growth and economic development in the 80’s and 90’s. How often were you taught to think as a generation, and not as individuals? No matter what, one thing is for sure. The Millennial Generation or Gen-Y as it is called, is the most highly educated generation to date, and we are definitely proud of it. The Pew Research Center recently conducted a study showing that 21% and 27% of men and women (aged 18-33) had a college degree, as compared to the Baby Boomers (17% and 14%) and Generation X (18% and 20%).  “Oh, what do I hear? We aren’t learning interpersonal and communication skills? Really?” True adulthood only hits us when we realize that these numbers do not mean anything to the people hiring out there. They say we lack team building and the ability to communicate effectively, and are more adept at theoretical knowledge than actual applicable skills. Which in essence is saying that our school and college education did not really help us at all. To be honest, that just rubs us off the wrong way, especially with how increasingly expensive university education has become, with ballooning student debt plaguing much of the Western world.  “If the employer is just having a problem with me and my ways, then guess what, I quit!” Unfortunately, there lies another innate flaw deep within us. Maybe, it is because a lot of us are still young and haven’t grown out of the habit of denial. But for many, it is very hard for us to come to terms with our shortcomings. Much too often we will just dismiss them, or much worse, put the blame on the employer. But as we all know, that’s just a quicker way to get the boot! If we are to make up ground, and reach our expectations (sky high!), we will have to adjust to the ways of the world and not be so adamant as we strive to perfection. But why ‘perfection’? Why are we so obsessed with getting it right? The answer lies with the world that has been built by the last generation to earn the ‘greatest’ title before us: the baby boomers. As baby boomers emerged from childhood, they soon had a very jolting experience into the foray of the professional worker. Their journey into adulthood was not as long and smoothed out as ours. Most of them emerged from the growing middle class, at a time when countries all across the world were engaged in a GDP scoring competition.  Thus, most of this generation were thrust directly into the workforce and found a way to sustain themselves, thanks to their resilient nature. They ended up earning far more than their parents, a trend which had been continuing since the 1900’s. Later on in life, most of them ended up giving birth to Generation X as well as the Millennials.  But it seems like the buck stops here, as the Millennials are suited to be the first generation to earn less than their parents. It is not a surprise that rising difficulties to secure a job coupling with employment opportunities bottoming out post the Great Recession have led to employment protests throughout Europe, the USA and Asia. And although Millennials are believed to be far more open-minded and tolerant, the dire circumstances have led to growing support for right-wing politics in many European and South Asian nations. The super-saturated job market has lead to increasingly weird paradoxes. Here’s one story from The Huffington Post, which could be one of many: “I was literally paying to work,” says Elena, a 29-year-old dietician in Texas. As part of her master’s degree, she was required to do a yearlong “internship” in a hospital. It was supposed to be training, but she says she worked the same hours and did the same tasks as paid staffers. “I took out an extra \$20,000 in student loans to pay tuition for the year I was working for free,” she says. Worse yet, with the increase of contractor companies which deal especially in security, storage and inventory management, or housekeeping activities, the future of low-income workers is further at risk. Take the example of Mr Joe, the security guard at the mall, who is actually signed to a contractor that has inked a deal with the mall. In this way, the mall just has to pay the contractor and not the individual person who is doing the job. This cuts out a lot of costs including any form of pension or benefits. Of course, that goes out of Mr Joe’s pocket. And out goes any form of career advancement either. Princeton-LSE grad Michael Lewis made a fortune and a legacy out of his book, Liar’s Poker, which details the rise of Lewie Ranieri and his team of traders who made big money at Salomon Brothers back in the late-80’s. In the book he often spoke of back office workers, including people who worked the fax and xerox machines, later trying their hand at trading for the company after slowly rising through the ranks over the years.  Well, thanks to him for documenting another list of practices that went out the window during the Financial Crisis. You can wave goodbye to that sort of career mobility in the 21st century. After all, the Great Crash of 2008 was all about under-skilled people working over-skilled jobs. Look at where we have arrived now with the current wave of Millennial underemployment. It is because of things like these that we fear a slip up so much, even a little one, that could send us hurtling down the tunnel of underemployment, unemployment, and at last, poverty. No, no, don’t laugh, this is serious. You might not have gotten out of your post-sack funk by the time you realise that you have fallen below the line. Anirudh Krishna, a professor at Duke University, has documented over 1,000 cases of people who fell into poverty, and only some of whom managed to escape it. He conducted his search throughout India and Kenya, and revealed that poverty arises from a series of mishaps. One broken leg, one lost job, one sick family member and you find yourself below the line. And it is this chance of slipping (literally), coupled with humongous college and healthcare costs, that force us Millennials to hope against hope to strive for perfection at every living moment. Thus, here we stand at the brink of a period of flux and change. Our generation’s defining moment has come and gone in 2008, we are just afraid another one might come along too soon. We might well be the first generation in decades to earn less than our parents. We will delay our marriages as well as moving out of home. Yes, buying a home now is exponentially tougher than 30 years ago. Deal with it. And you have a problem with that? We don’t, we have no choice.  Welcome to the future (FML).</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Fall of Religion in the Millennial West</title>
      <link href="/The-Fall-of-Religion" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fall of Religion in the Millennial West" />
      <published>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Fall-of-Religion</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Fall-of-Religion">&lt;p&gt;One of the most important demographic changes, in recent times, is the rise of the ‘nones’ in Western society. These are a group of people who refuse to identify themselves with any mainstream religious group or denomination. A 2012 article, by the Pew Research Center, noted that “[o]ne-fifth of the U.S. public – and a third of adults under 30 – are religiously unaffiliated today” and “[i]n the last five years alone, the unaffiliated have increased from just over 15% to just under 20% of all U.S. adults. Their ranks now include more than 13 million self-described atheists and agnostics (nearly 6% of the U.S. public), as well as nearly 33 million people who say they have no particular religious affiliation (14%)”. If we look at certain Western European countries and even in some parts of Eastern Europe, the numbers will undoubtedly be higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this happening? Why are young people increasingly disassociating themselves from organised religion, especially in what can only be fittingly described as a post-Christian society?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are four main reasons which I put forward, all of which can be summed up in a single sentence: &lt;strong&gt;Christianity – and, especially, Catholicism - has lost its credibility in the minds of our youth.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1: The Dominant Historical Narrative&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each one of us has heard it sometime or the other. The popular narrative runs thus: human society began well and reached summits of excellence and achievement, especially in the classical age. But when Christianity came, all that progress and achievement, as well as the scientific impulse, came to an end and was effectively destroyed. For centuries, the West was embroiled in a quagmire of oppressive feudalism and religious intolerance, in which free-thinkers were labelled heretics and persecuted fiercely. This was called the &lt;em&gt;Dark Ages&lt;/em&gt;, and rightly so, because human civilisation was truly held in captivity in the darkness of religious bigotry and superstition. All of this was the case, until the time of the Renaissance and the Enlightenment when, finally, we were able to break free of the chains of theocracy and emerge into the bright new world, to build our future for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least, that is how countless millennials understand the Medieval period. It is certainly the way history is taught in our schools, and thus the way many millennials understand this era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Added to this is the stigma of the Crusades and the Inquisitions, both of which are believed to be butcheries of human life and liberty based on religious (and especially Catholic) dogmatism and fanaticism. Fresh in the mind of many of our fellow millennials is the Galileo Affair, in which – it is believed – the geocentric Catholics tried to murder the heliocentric Galileo for the crime of trying to think rationally and not superstitiously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of this narrative, however, is myopic, and fails to take into account the various other factors which were at play. But, unfortunately for people like me, many of my fellow millennials believe this to be the Gospel truth. And naturally, it has distanced them from a religion which, they are convinced, is responsible for stifling human civilisation and progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2: The Widening Gap Between the Jesus of History and the Christ of Faith&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan Brown is one of the most popular fiction authors in the world today. I have had the chance of reading parts of his books, and have found his style to be most engaging. However, Brown is more than your average thriller writer. Thanks to books like &lt;em&gt;The Da Vinci Code&lt;/em&gt;, Brown has managed to bring the ‘Lost Gospels’ to the forefront of public discourse. And boy, has it fired the imagination of the masses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What people like Brown have managed to do is convince the populace – and especially the youth – that there is big difference between the Jesus of Catholicism and the actual Jesus whom we read about in works like the Gospel of Peter and Phillip, for example. He has also managed to alert people regarding the issue of the Biblical canon; why are these four Gospels part of the Bible and not others? Why has the Church chosen to only highlight these particular narratives and declare others heretical?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way information is put out in books such as these has convinced countless many that in the very early history of Christianity, there emerged a power-hungry faction which sought to glorify their own theology at the expense of others. We are told that there was not one but several ‘Christianities’ in the beginning. But one faction – which today exists as the Catholic Church – gained ascendancy and, with quite a bit of patronage from Romam Emperor Constantine, persecuted the other factions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This adds to the impression that today’s youth already has regarding the Christian faith and leaves them with a deep distrust towards anything related to Catholicism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3: The Rise of Philosophical Naturalism and Postmodern Nihilism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone looks at the world through a set of lenses. We all operate with basic metaphysical and epistemological presuppositions. However, in recent times, especially in universities, a particular philosophical perspective has been put forward vociferously, and other points of view have largely been isolated and marginalized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, for a while, was an undergraduate philosophy student at a well-respected university in India. And what I encountered from my professors was not a careful treatment of the various opposing perspectives but rather open and brazen bias, especially when it came to the philosophy of religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What young undergraduates are consistently taught is that the arguments for the existence of God – as put forward by people like Augustine, Aquinas, Leibniz and others – are all extremely poor and fallacious bits of reasoning which can be so easily debunked that one wonders how such eminent men came to such bizarre conclusions. We are also told that these people were motivated by their own personal religious beliefs, and sought to back them up the best they could. What remained was a set of arguments that would only convince people who already had faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least, that is the dominant narrative in philosophical academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And young philosophers usually accept this without question, without delving deeper into the works of Augustine and Aquinas to see if this is indeed true. Most of them don’t bother to later study the philosophy of religion, but rather end up specialising in other fields. And so what they uncritically accept as true in their early years, they end up carrying throughout life. And it is in this way that a consistent naturalist philosophical narrative has been built up over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this has led our young people to be extremely skeptical of any supernatural claims and has, therefore, led them to the conclusion that this world is all there is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting development happening simultaneously is the rise of postmodernism. This is entirely different from the dogmatic atheism I have just described. Rather, this is a dogmatic rejection of all dogmatism, an objective denial of all objectivity. It is a position some might characterise as absurd, but this appellation is readily embraced by some of its vociferous proponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Postmodernism is basically summed up in three maxims: “Truth is what you make of it. Morality is what you shape of it. God is Who you think He/She/It is.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways, this attitude is the product of the younger generation’s exposure to other cultures, viewpoints and ways of thinking. Young people see heated debates in which scholars on both sides put forward their cases and state their opinions, each backing themselves up with copious argumentation. They see different religions and ways of life, entirely different from the ones they had been exposed to. And having no strong rational grounds to support the religion of their upbringing, they naturally come to the conclusion that ‘man is the measure of all things’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This understanding of life is indeed very attractive since it promises a kind of godhood. One is free to shape one’s reality and one’s destiny as one sees it. One is free to identify as whatever one pleases and be whoever one wishes to be. Above all, one is liberated from the shackles of dogmatism, free to believe whatever they wish to believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, anyone addicted to this euphoria of freedom will find organised religion, with all its creeds and ancient affirmations, very unattractive indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4: The Transformation of Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps the most important and significant of all, since it strikes not merely at our intellect but also at our emotions. The cultural elite of the West are working very hard to change and transform culture. They do this through books, films, magazines and mass media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example: Imagine that you have grown up in a very conservative society, your parents told you that the right thing to do was to dress modestly, especially in front of the opposite sex. What happens when you are constantly exposed to pictures of men and women in states of partial or complete undress, when you can hardly go to the movies or even switch on a television without coming across some scene or advertisement that is either sexually explicit or has strong sexual themes, that too being performed by men and women who are great artists whom you admire?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, your perception is going to shift. You would in all likelihood rather imitate your heroes and role models rather than your parents, in this case. And in all probability, your friends have similar attitudes in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these factors come together and compound in such a way that it is possible to change views about something as fundamental as human sexuality across the course of a generation! Changing one’s views on sexual ethics is nothing more and nothing less than a paradigm shift. Instead of being something that is sacred and to be enjoyed within the context of marriage in a reproductively responsible manner, young people are offered the alluring option of ‘sex with no strings attached’. Rather than being the self-giving expression of commitment and love between two spouses (as Christians have traditionally believed), it has become a ‘casual’ affair. It is, therefore, no wonder that our young people are losing their faith in traditional Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popular music has played an inestimable role in detaching young people from the Christian faith. Young people see singers who are clearly extraordinarily talented, beloved by all their friends and peer groups, and who sing songs that contain themes that are clearly contrary to Christian faith and morals, in more ways than one. Naturally, over time, one comes to favour one’s friend groups rather than one’s parents and one begins to side with the more secularising culture rather than traditional ways of living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I am a millennial myself. But I am not your average millennial. In fact, I am a convert to the Catholic Church, having come from a liberal Hindu background myself. I am the black sheep, so to speak, of this modern and enlightened generation. What causes me to remain traditional and Catholic? Why don’t I simply join the great secular bus and enjoy all the many benefits its offers? Why do I remain in the shadows and willingly disassociate myself from much of the modern world and even isolate myself, at times, enjoying but a few friends?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons are endless, but I will summarise it in a few brief points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, it is my firmest conviction that the conventional narrative about the &lt;em&gt;Dark Ages&lt;/em&gt; is thoroughly erroneous, and in fact holds little water in academic circles, thank God. This view of the Medieval Church as an oppressive, science-persecuting religion has been increasingly discredited in modern times, not least by the excellent work of the Pulitzer-Prize winning Rodney Stark who, although himself a non-Catholic, has taken it upon himself to work towards exonerating the Catholic Church from baseless myths and lies, as can be seen in his work &lt;em&gt;Bearing False Witness&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, this idea that the Church persecuted scientists fails to take into account the immense contributions the Church made to science, in the Middle Ages and after as well. It is true that Galileo was persecuted – on charges of heresy. But what is left unmentioned is that Copernicus’s heliocentrism fascinated the Pope of his time, who spoke highly of him on numerous occasions. What is also conveniently left out is the devoutly Christian spirit of the countless intellectuals across the course of history who laid the foundations of modern science, believing that their study and analysis of the natural world was a kind of worship of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are we then left with? Is there no future for religion in the West?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religion will survive. The Church will always be there in the West, even if it is weakened and marginalised. Popular culture and the mass media already brand the Christian faith as regressive. It is perhaps only a matter of time before popular opinion turns into political legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Church will survive. It always has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only that, it has found a new homeland. As the West continues to go down this slippery slope and continues to schism itself from its Christian roots, the great African continent has already opened its arms wide open, in welcome of the Gospel and the Church.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the most important demographic changes, in recent times, is the rise of the ‘nones’ in Western society. These are a group of people who refuse to identify themselves with any mainstream religious group or denomination. A 2012 article, by the Pew Research Center, noted that “[o]ne-fifth of the U.S. public – and a third of adults under 30 – are religiously unaffiliated today” and “[i]n the last five years alone, the unaffiliated have increased from just over 15% to just under 20% of all U.S. adults. Their ranks now include more than 13 million self-described atheists and agnostics (nearly 6% of the U.S. public), as well as nearly 33 million people who say they have no particular religious affiliation (14%)”. If we look at certain Western European countries and even in some parts of Eastern Europe, the numbers will undoubtedly be higher.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Are We ‘Doing It’ Enough?</title>
      <link href="/Are-We-Doing-It-Enough" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are We ‘Doing It’ Enough?" />
      <published>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Are-We-Doing-It-Enough</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Are-We-Doing-It-Enough">&lt;p&gt;The generation that fails all? After a myriad of people belting out how we, the Millennials, have failed the world, there’s a new complaint in the game, and if I may, a superfluous one. If you haven’t heard about it yet, let me enlighten you, we, are falling, yet again; falling behind on our duty as sexual beings. We’re not having enough intercourse, the coitus is lacking, we’re not hiding the salami right, we are to fornicate/copulate more often, I can go ahead and call it a thousand more names, but what it comes down to is that we are not having enough sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sexual economy of the world seems to be in danger. Of course, this conclusion is met with evidence from surveys done on American grounds and on Americans but there seems to lie an innate truth to it. &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt;’s December cover story threw light on this. I’m sure Kate Julian’s extensive research on the topic and terming of the phenomenon ‘Sexual Recession’ brought her just as much hate as it did fame, but from what I could procure, she left no page unturned, except the veil of obvious bias, but we’ll come to that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a full tell-all, supported by a General Social Survey (GSS) in 2016, conducted at the University of Chicago, she lists out reasons behind the recession―the assumed ones, why it occurred in the first place and why this recession is specific to the Millennials. Her article is a long read―heavy with insight and stories from across her social sphere―and, given a choice, I’d award her. Her article shone light upon something that we were all aware of in parts, and albeit she only showed off the parts that worked in her favour, she did make sure that all was listed, with enough to make us not counter her points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Foucault would say, we love talking about sex, we enjoy discussing it not just as a primal need rather as a form of entertainment. Sexuality, he said, was a construct of human discourse. “We convince ourselves that we have never said enough on the subject,” he wrote in his (four-volume) &lt;em&gt;The History of Sexuality&lt;/em&gt;. “It is possible that where sex is concerned, the most long-winded, the most impatient of societies is our own.” Personally, I’d say, few fields of human behaviour—and none more important—are this hard to explain. As something that has been talked about ever so often, from religious scriptures telling us how and when to do it, oh, and of course, when not to, to trilogies earning billions with 1001 pages of ‘teeth-clenchingly good’ sex. We all know of it, but why and how it became the talk of the town, albeit uttered only in hushed tones, is vague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned GSS determined that people who are in their early 20s right now are two and a half times as likely to be abstinent as Gen Xers were at the same age. Specifically, between the years 1990 to 2014, the average adult went from having sex 62 times a year to 54 times a year, therefore, the hoola-hoo about the downfall in the Sexual Economy. If I were to meet the ‘spokesperson’ of this Sexual Economy that we all have now been made aware of, I’d only have one word to say: ‘Damn.’ Just so one is kept in the know, it’s not just an American problem. Most countries don’t track their citizens’ sex lives closely. But those that try, mostly the ones who are extremely wealthy, are reporting their own sex delays and declines. One of the most respected sex studies in the world, Britain’s National Survey of Sexual Attitudes and Lifestyles, reported in 2001 that people between the ages of 16 to 44 were having sex more than six times a month, on average. By 2012, the rate had dropped to fewer than five times. Over approximately the same period, Australians in relationships went from having sex around 1.8 times a week to 1.4 times. Finland’s ‘Finsex’ study found declines in frequency of coitus, coupled with increasing rates of masturbation. In the Netherlands, the median age at which people first have intercourse rose from 17.1 in 2012 to 18.6 in 2017, and other types of physical contact also got pushed back, even kissing. In fertility-challenged Japan, which is already in the midst of a demographic crisis and has become something of a case study in the dangers of sexlessness, a third of single people aged 18 to 34 were virgins as of the year 2005; but by 2015, 43% of people reported the same. Japan has been infiltrated by several cultural complexes: Hikikomori (the phenomenon of complete isolation from society) being one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, whatever’s going on here does not seem like a ‘millennial trend’. It really probably pertains to people in their 20s, so younger millennials or Gen-Z. We tend to talk about millennials as if they are some group that just landed here intact, whereas it’s more useful to talk about what it’s like to be a young person, at this point. Not to mention, the fear of a “sex recession” is misdirected. A drop in sexual encounters from 62 to 54 times a year means that the average adult is still having sex more than once a week. Millennials are having to deal with things previous generations haven’t dealt with, and it’s useful to clarify that. As and when I read more about this, I found that people think online connectivity and smartphones have had a dramatic effect on how people’s lives are shaped and their behaviours. That’s probably true for most generational groups, and for the groups that use technology more, that’d be truer. Tinder has only made things easier, so why the lack? My only problem was why 2 and 2 didn’t add up to 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I went digging, and found a &lt;em&gt;Cosmopolitan&lt;/em&gt; article (yes, I went there) and believe me, if &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt; makes you believe you’re not having enough sex, &lt;em&gt;Cosmopolitan&lt;/em&gt; will assure you enough for a lifetime, or well, at least a couple of months. The survey research showed a decline in sex mainly among white, middle-aged, married couples, which, of course, is a very, very small bracket to be construed as an entire generation’s problem. Julian’s tone in &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt;––listing a myriad of theories to explain the drop, from smartphones to economic instability to Tinder––was cautionary, I’ll give her that. But, news of the so-called “sex recession” provoked reactions across the internet, from &lt;em&gt;Vox&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Vice&lt;/em&gt;—not to mention the plethora of comments which turned it into madness with no method. Companies have picked up on this, more researches are being based on the same and while all that is great, there’s a problem that doesn’t exist and is yet being worked upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are different now; sex is different now. Dictionaries may still consider sex to be vaginal penetration, but to us—it may be anything from second base to the seventh one. Sexuality is explored more. People are more aware of what it is that they want, there’s more to it than just genitals having a meet and greet, pleasure plays a huge role in how sex is seen. I would highly recommend that people read Julian’s article and all the reasons she gives for us to not be having enough sex: from stress to bad, painful encounters, but with a grain of salt. We may be failing to do a gazillion more things, but for once, I can attest sex is something we’re doing a bang-up job of (all puns intended.) Tinder, Bumble and Grindr have only made it more relevant. Nothing one does to explore it can be wrong, not until someone is harmed. There is no ‘normal’ amount of sex. Worrying about how much sex one’s having—which can increase anxiety, decrease body confidence, and hinder healthy communication—is not good for one’s sex life, either. Ironic, isn’t it? In terms of desired sexual activity, every individual, and every couple is different, including people who identify as asexual. Just the idea of #MeToo challenges the notion that we can measure our sex lives by anything other than our own generational values and self-reported satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a fundamental level, I share Julian’s concern when she writes that she “was taken aback by what seemed like heartbreaking changes in the way many people were relating—or not relating—to one another.” This is what we should focus our attention on. It turns out, though, that a small drop in aggregate annual sexual frequency has no demonstrable effect on how couples form and sustain, fulfilling relationships. If people aren’t having sex but they’re doing other things they find fulfilling, that’s great. But if people are not having sex, and wish they were, that’s more of a concern, wouldn’t you say?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I have to say is that every generation has its faults counted, every generation has to face things the previous ones didn’t have to endure. While one is yet to see how much more can be done, can be changed or morphed, I am sure that our shapeshifter of a generation won’t be a disappointment. Sex or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The generation that fails all? After a myriad of people belting out how we, the Millennials, have failed the world, there’s a new complaint in the game, and if I may, a superfluous one. If you haven’t heard about it yet, let me enlighten you, we, are falling, yet again; falling behind on our duty as sexual beings. We’re not having enough intercourse, the coitus is lacking, we’re not hiding the salami right, we are to fornicate/copulate more often, I can go ahead and call it a thousand more names, but what it comes down to is that we are not having enough sex.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
