<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/khushboo.agrawal/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-11-19T16:51:01+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/khushboo.agrawal/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Pace of EV Adoption in India</title>
      <link href="/Pace-of-EV-Adoption-in-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pace of EV Adoption in India" />
      <published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Pace-of-EV-Adoption-in-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Pace-of-EV-Adoption-in-India">&lt;p&gt;Over the past ten years, the automobile sector has been gravitating towards electrification. Electrification is essentially the replacement of conventionally used Internal Combustion Engine (ICE) vehicles with more powerful, simpler, smarter and greener Electric Vehicles (EV).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EVs came into being before its ICE counterparts but due to lack of infrastructure, high upfront costs and absence of incentives, they could not gain the deserved spotlight. So, are we to believe that the right time has come to think about the electrification of our cars?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand the situation better, let us look at why it is imperative for India to adopt electric mobility. The Indian automobile market has earned the distinction of being a unique market; the Indian auto and ancillary market is among the largest in the world and constitutes 9% of the country’s GDP. 84% of vehicles sold domestically are either two or three Wheelers (2W/3Ws) and therefore, it is imperative for the nation to adapt to electrification now.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EV adoption in India is more than just a technological upgradation in the automotive sector. There are varying reasons which make it essential for the fifth largest economy to pace up the process of electrification.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extensive and often reckless use of ICE vehicles paired with exorbitant industrial pollution has worsened the nation’s Air Quality Index (AQI), making it the third most polluted country in the world. Moreover, considering the macroeconomic factors, India imports $100 billion worth of crude oil to quench its industrial and retail demand (which is mostly generated by operational ICE vehicles).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that the intent is clear, let’s see how long is the road ahead of our goal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electric mobility targets can only be achieved with joint efforts of all the players in the EV ecosystem. Government incentives, appropriate charging infrastructures, battery costs and manufacturing coupled with Original Equipment Manufacturers (OEMs) transitioning from ICE to EV can help in&amp;nbsp; ramping up the process of electrification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last decade, Indian policymakers have been extensively promoting adoption of electric vehicles, mostly under the umbrella of the National Mission for Electric Mobility (The EV Mission) led by the Department of Heavy Industries (DHI).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction of schemes like FAME II (Faster Adoption and Manufacturing of Hybrid &amp;amp; Electric Vehicles) and Production Linked Incentive (PLI) coupled with GST incentives are pushed to achieve adoption targets, localisation of key components with an aim to foster electric adoption in both private and public transportation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FAME II aims to provide direct financial benefits to EV manufacturers which would benefit in reducing the cost of acquisition for end-customers. As a mechanism, OEMs first pass on the subsidy support to the end-customer by way of decreased purchase price, and later claim the amount from the DHI.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a mismatch between the market demand and the policy’s vision, as since inception, FAME II has only been able to achieve less than 10% of its target of supporting one million electric two-wheelers, half a million of 3Ws, 55,000 four-wheelers and 7,000 buses by 2022. To tackle the same, new amendments were introduced in June 2021 to reduce the overall vehicle cost and revamp the EV adoption scenario in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per the new amendments, the subsidy offered has been revised from ₹10,000 to ₹15,000 per kWh per electric 2W vehicle, thereby increasing the demand incentive by 50%. Maximum cap on subsidies offered has also increased from 20% to 40% of the cost of E-2W, which drastically bridged the Total Cost of Ownership (TCO) gap between conventional ICE and electric two wheelers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electric charging infrastructure in the country is at a very nascent stage and the charging grid is more like a mandate to support the operational leg of the electrification process. Therefore, it is important for India to have the required charging infrastructure to accelerate the process.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India needs about 400 thousand charging stations to meet the requirement for two million&amp;nbsp;electric vehicles&amp;nbsp;that could potentially move on its roads by 2026. Currently, it has about 18 hundred charging stations, most of which are slow chargers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest players in this segment is Tata Power which owns a network of over 500 public chargers in 100+ cities across India, and has recently tied up with HPCL to further expand its network.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To support the forecasted electricity demand that EV adoption is expected to bring with itself, it is a must for the nation to develop grids which are capable of handling the multitudinous increase in load. India relying on its coal dependent grid is said to be one of the most inefficient ones in the world, thus giving a reason for the nation to shift the composition of the grid towards renewables to truly address the pollution problem.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one of his announcements, the Union Power and New and Renewable Energy Minister Raj Kumar Singh disclosed the country’s plans to set up around 14 gigawatt-hour (GWh) grid-scale battery storage system at the world’s largest renewable energy park at Khavda in Gujarat. This is in addition to the plan to invite bids for the largest global tender for setting up a 13GWh grid-scale battery storage system in Ladakh. This strategic push is to make India’s grid-scale battery storage programme the largest in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is encouraging to see the government's action in this regard but there still lays a long road ahead for the nation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another gap which needs to be bridged to achieve EV adoption is the TCO (Total Cost Ownership) disparity between ICE and EVs. TCO is the sum of upfront and operational costs which a customer has to incur through the life of the vehicle. With batteries constituting 35% of the vehicle cost, it is one of the major drivers of EV’s upfront costs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With inefficient indigenous cell technology and limited access to battery raw materials like Lithium and Cobalt, India is yet to become a leading player in the EV battery industry. Local players like Exicom Power, Amar Raja Batteries, Tata Power have plans to turn this around.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electric 2W are smaller vehicles and are easier to electrify, hence they require smaller and simpler batteries and are much closer to economic parity. Li-ion battery based e-rickshaws form a major portion of electric 3W base in the country and have in fact achieved TCO parity and are benefitting from the lower charging costs and time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there still exists a wide gap between TCO parity of electric 4W and buses with their ICE counterparts, mostly due to large battery sizes requirements and lack of complementary infrastructure.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tesla in its recent pitch to the government was successful in lowering import duties on EVs which would eventually make electric vehicles more affordable for the Indian masses. However, the administration is in favor of high import duties as it wishes to encourage domestic production. Therefore, it's too early to show such excitement as only time can vouch for its implementation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the 2W segment being the frontrunner followed by 3W in the ICE-EV shift in India and 4W premium and commercial vehicles yet to achieve the value for money proposition, a lot more has to be done by the government on many fronts such as OEMs transitioning to electric mobility, customers considering EVs over ICE vehicles and other players in the EV segment actively working to achieve India’s goal of becoming a 100% electric vehicle nation by 2030.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Agrawal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Over the past ten years, the automobile sector has been gravitating towards electrification. Electrification is essentially the replacement of conventionally used Internal Combustion Engine (ICE) vehicles with more powerful, simpler, smarter and greener Electric Vehicles (EV).&amp;nbsp; EVs came into being before its ICE counterparts but due to lack of infrastructure, high upfront costs and absence of incentives, they could not gain the deserved spotlight. So, are we to believe that the right time has come to think about the electrification of our cars?&amp;nbsp; To understand the situation better, let us look at why it is imperative for India to adopt electric mobility. The Indian automobile market has earned the distinction of being a unique market; the Indian auto and ancillary market is among the largest in the world and constitutes 9% of the country’s GDP. 84% of vehicles sold domestically are either two or three Wheelers (2W/3Ws) and therefore, it is imperative for the nation to adapt to electrification now.&amp;nbsp; EV adoption in India is more than just a technological upgradation in the automotive sector. There are varying reasons which make it essential for the fifth largest economy to pace up the process of electrification.&amp;nbsp; Extensive and often reckless use of ICE vehicles paired with exorbitant industrial pollution has worsened the nation’s Air Quality Index (AQI), making it the third most polluted country in the world. Moreover, considering the macroeconomic factors, India imports $100 billion worth of crude oil to quench its industrial and retail demand (which is mostly generated by operational ICE vehicles).&amp;nbsp; Now that the intent is clear, let’s see how long is the road ahead of our goal.&amp;nbsp; Electric mobility targets can only be achieved with joint efforts of all the players in the EV ecosystem. Government incentives, appropriate charging infrastructures, battery costs and manufacturing coupled with Original Equipment Manufacturers (OEMs) transitioning from ICE to EV can help in&amp;nbsp; ramping up the process of electrification. Over the last decade, Indian policymakers have been extensively promoting adoption of electric vehicles, mostly under the umbrella of the National Mission for Electric Mobility (The EV Mission) led by the Department of Heavy Industries (DHI).&amp;nbsp; Introduction of schemes like FAME II (Faster Adoption and Manufacturing of Hybrid &amp;amp; Electric Vehicles) and Production Linked Incentive (PLI) coupled with GST incentives are pushed to achieve adoption targets, localisation of key components with an aim to foster electric adoption in both private and public transportation.&amp;nbsp; FAME II aims to provide direct financial benefits to EV manufacturers which would benefit in reducing the cost of acquisition for end-customers. As a mechanism, OEMs first pass on the subsidy support to the end-customer by way of decreased purchase price, and later claim the amount from the DHI.&amp;nbsp; There was a mismatch between the market demand and the policy’s vision, as since inception, FAME II has only been able to achieve less than 10% of its target of supporting one million electric two-wheelers, half a million of 3Ws, 55,000 four-wheelers and 7,000 buses by 2022. To tackle the same, new amendments were introduced in June 2021 to reduce the overall vehicle cost and revamp the EV adoption scenario in the country. As per the new amendments, the subsidy offered has been revised from ₹10,000 to ₹15,000 per kWh per electric 2W vehicle, thereby increasing the demand incentive by 50%. Maximum cap on subsidies offered has also increased from 20% to 40% of the cost of E-2W, which drastically bridged the Total Cost of Ownership (TCO) gap between conventional ICE and electric two wheelers.&amp;nbsp; Electric charging infrastructure in the country is at a very nascent stage and the charging grid is more like a mandate to support the operational leg of the electrification process. Therefore, it is important for India to have the required charging infrastructure to accelerate the process.&amp;nbsp; India needs about 400 thousand charging stations to meet the requirement for two million&amp;nbsp;electric vehicles&amp;nbsp;that could potentially move on its roads by 2026. Currently, it has about 18 hundred charging stations, most of which are slow chargers.&amp;nbsp; One of the biggest players in this segment is Tata Power which owns a network of over 500 public chargers in 100+ cities across India, and has recently tied up with HPCL to further expand its network.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; To support the forecasted electricity demand that EV adoption is expected to bring with itself, it is a must for the nation to develop grids which are capable of handling the multitudinous increase in load. India relying on its coal dependent grid is said to be one of the most inefficient ones in the world, thus giving a reason for the nation to shift the composition of the grid towards renewables to truly address the pollution problem.&amp;nbsp; In one of his announcements, the Union Power and New and Renewable Energy Minister Raj Kumar Singh disclosed the country’s plans to set up around 14 gigawatt-hour (GWh) grid-scale battery storage system at the world’s largest renewable energy park at Khavda in Gujarat. This is in addition to the plan to invite bids for the largest global tender for setting up a 13GWh grid-scale battery storage system in Ladakh. This strategic push is to make India’s grid-scale battery storage programme the largest in the world. It is encouraging to see the government's action in this regard but there still lays a long road ahead for the nation.&amp;nbsp; Another gap which needs to be bridged to achieve EV adoption is the TCO (Total Cost Ownership) disparity between ICE and EVs. TCO is the sum of upfront and operational costs which a customer has to incur through the life of the vehicle. With batteries constituting 35% of the vehicle cost, it is one of the major drivers of EV’s upfront costs.&amp;nbsp; With inefficient indigenous cell technology and limited access to battery raw materials like Lithium and Cobalt, India is yet to become a leading player in the EV battery industry. Local players like Exicom Power, Amar Raja Batteries, Tata Power have plans to turn this around.&amp;nbsp; Electric 2W are smaller vehicles and are easier to electrify, hence they require smaller and simpler batteries and are much closer to economic parity. Li-ion battery based e-rickshaws form a major portion of electric 3W base in the country and have in fact achieved TCO parity and are benefitting from the lower charging costs and time.&amp;nbsp; However, there still exists a wide gap between TCO parity of electric 4W and buses with their ICE counterparts, mostly due to large battery sizes requirements and lack of complementary infrastructure.&amp;nbsp; Tesla in its recent pitch to the government was successful in lowering import duties on EVs which would eventually make electric vehicles more affordable for the Indian masses. However, the administration is in favor of high import duties as it wishes to encourage domestic production. Therefore, it's too early to show such excitement as only time can vouch for its implementation.&amp;nbsp; With the 2W segment being the frontrunner followed by 3W in the ICE-EV shift in India and 4W premium and commercial vehicles yet to achieve the value for money proposition, a lot more has to be done by the government on many fronts such as OEMs transitioning to electric mobility, customers considering EVs over ICE vehicles and other players in the EV segment actively working to achieve India’s goal of becoming a 100% electric vehicle nation by 2030.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Tyranny of Trends</title>
      <link href="/The-Tyranny-of-Trends" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Tyranny of Trends" />
      <published>2021-06-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Tyranny-of-Trends</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Tyranny-of-Trends">&lt;p&gt;Where does your clothing go when it's not needed anymore?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every second, a truck full of clothes is burned or dumped in a landfill. Every year, 92 million tonnes of fast fashion items are thrown away. Every year, 79 trillion litres of water is consumed by the fashion industry. Consequently, every year, more than $500 billion of value is lost due to clothing underutilisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were just a few of the many facts illustrating the case of ‘TYRANNY OF TRENDS’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With new trends taking over the market everyday, fast fashion is blooming like never before, leading to excessive carbon emissions, imprudent waste generation, giving birth to a new water crisis and to top it all, the lack of recycling is worsening the existing situation of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is imperative for the world to know that it takes more than just a piece of cloth and a few designers to design the trendsetting high-on-bling clothes that influencers wear, the head-turning long trails that brides want to wear or the gorgeous Italian-cut tuxedos that men wish to wear. The essence of sustainability lies in finding plausible alternatives to the existing resources being used because soon there will be a time when we won’t be left with any. It’s high time that we buckle up and start working in the direction to find new resources in order to keep the existing ones available for generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we wrap our heads around finding implementable solutions to the problem of fast fashion, let’s get into the nitty gritties of the concept of fast fashion. As a consequence of the fickle trends, which seem to change while you are reading this article, there exists a never ending demand for affordable, high-in-fashion garments to fulfil the quest of the masses to be in-trend. Which in turn compels and gives fashion brands and garment manufacturers a new avenue to mint money by producing cheap, in-trend fashion to keep up with the demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast fashion is a by-product of trends, so let's take a look at how this frenzy around trends is created? Saying that trends come and go like seasons would be wrong in this day and age as these trends are way more volatile to be able to stay for a full season. The real question is how are these trends set in the first place, compelling people to be in trend all the time. The following are a few ways in which trends are introduced to the world:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Runway Trends - Many-a-times certain runway looks created by designers catch the eyes of people and the next thing we know is every other brand starts incorporating those elements in their collection to be able to fill their pockets by pushing trends and fast fashion forward.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Celebrities - Trends are fuelled by celebrities the minute they are spotted wearing something which no one has seen before. People who idolise celebrities are always on a hunt for similar pieces eventually paving a way for a new trend to enter.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Social media and influencers -&amp;nbsp; The impact social media has on one’s life is immense so much so that everyone wants to follow and replicate the well-fabricated lives portrayed by influencers on their well-curated handles. To top it all, designers and brands approach influencers just as they approach celebrities to make new trends enter the market.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main problem which fast fashion brings with itself is the problem of disposal. Once a piece of clothing goes out of trend, both the consumers and the fashion labels do not think twice before dumping huge heaps of clothes which no longer continues to quench their thirst for trends so much so that every second, enough clothes&amp;nbsp;to fill a garbage truck full are either burned or sent to a landfill. Extortion of environmental resources, excessive waste generation, carbon emissions are all consequences of a choice that we have opted for, a choice to simply wear clothes for a shorter span of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the aforementioned heinous consequences of fast fashion pose one question to mankind, should we stop buying clothes at all? The answer is NO! You can still stand out and manage to be a trendsetter just by being a little mindful of your actions and choices.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most efficient way of tackling the problem at hand is by adopting sustainable fashion in order to achieve a circular fashion economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circular fashion economy proposes a progressive system of circulating a piece of clothing in the economy till the time its maximum value gets exhausted and the cycle is completed by safely disposing off the no-longer-in-use piece back to the environment.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sustainability is a two-way stream, brands and consumers are the two main players who can pave the way for circular and sustainable fashion. Before looking at how long is the road ahead, let’s see how far we have come on this long journey of achieving sustainability in its true sense. On the manufacturer’s side we have brands like H&amp;amp;M, which is now planning to deviate from the well-trodden path of fast fashion to reduce their environmental footprint by introducing sustainable collections made of organic cotton and recycled polyester.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a brand which has now stepped up its game in circular fashion by accepting and recycling unwanted garments from customers, H&amp;amp;M has set a benchmark for brands in the similar line. Levi’s, on the other hand, has been trying to reduce the notorious amounts of water required to make a pair of jeans by 96% which is a huge step towards making judicial use of existing resources. Like H&amp;amp;M and Levi’s there are many more brands which are working in the same direction but there is still a lot to be done. On the other hand, consumers of fashion can adopt the following steps with a motive to convert their vision for the fashion industry into reality:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Keep and wear the clothes for a longer span of time.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Think twice before dumping clothes which no longer please you. Instead, upcycle, alter, repair or donate them.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Buy sustainable fashion, go for upcycled, thrifted pieces.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bigger question is, can sustainability and profitability ever go hand-in-hand? It’s the demand which can make or break a brand’s fate. With more and more consumers becoming environmentally conscious, the demand for sustainable fashion has hiked up over the course of the years, which has led to brands supplying more and more sustainable garments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aware and conscious customers, especially Gen Z and millennials are ready to buy sustainable clothing even if they have to shell out more money for it, which makes it profitable for brands to go sustainable. And the ones whose pockets are holding them back from supporting the cause, they tend to take another route by turning to thrift stores which are sustainable and pocket friendly too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These small measures are just a few steps on the ladder towards achieving our goal of a sustainable and circular fashion economy which is all about covering one full circle from growing, designing, wearing, thrifting to finally passing the cloth to the biosphere by safely composting it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Khushboo Agrawal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Where does your clothing go when it's not needed anymore? Every second, a truck full of clothes is burned or dumped in a landfill. Every year, 92 million tonnes of fast fashion items are thrown away. Every year, 79 trillion litres of water is consumed by the fashion industry. Consequently, every year, more than $500 billion of value is lost due to clothing underutilisation. These were just a few of the many facts illustrating the case of ‘TYRANNY OF TRENDS’. With new trends taking over the market everyday, fast fashion is blooming like never before, leading to excessive carbon emissions, imprudent waste generation, giving birth to a new water crisis and to top it all, the lack of recycling is worsening the existing situation of climate change. It is imperative for the world to know that it takes more than just a piece of cloth and a few designers to design the trendsetting high-on-bling clothes that influencers wear, the head-turning long trails that brides want to wear or the gorgeous Italian-cut tuxedos that men wish to wear. The essence of sustainability lies in finding plausible alternatives to the existing resources being used because soon there will be a time when we won’t be left with any. It’s high time that we buckle up and start working in the direction to find new resources in order to keep the existing ones available for generations to come. Before we wrap our heads around finding implementable solutions to the problem of fast fashion, let’s get into the nitty gritties of the concept of fast fashion. As a consequence of the fickle trends, which seem to change while you are reading this article, there exists a never ending demand for affordable, high-in-fashion garments to fulfil the quest of the masses to be in-trend. Which in turn compels and gives fashion brands and garment manufacturers a new avenue to mint money by producing cheap, in-trend fashion to keep up with the demand. Fast fashion is a by-product of trends, so let's take a look at how this frenzy around trends is created? Saying that trends come and go like seasons would be wrong in this day and age as these trends are way more volatile to be able to stay for a full season. The real question is how are these trends set in the first place, compelling people to be in trend all the time. The following are a few ways in which trends are introduced to the world: Runway Trends - Many-a-times certain runway looks created by designers catch the eyes of people and the next thing we know is every other brand starts incorporating those elements in their collection to be able to fill their pockets by pushing trends and fast fashion forward. Celebrities - Trends are fuelled by celebrities the minute they are spotted wearing something which no one has seen before. People who idolise celebrities are always on a hunt for similar pieces eventually paving a way for a new trend to enter.&amp;nbsp; Social media and influencers -&amp;nbsp; The impact social media has on one’s life is immense so much so that everyone wants to follow and replicate the well-fabricated lives portrayed by influencers on their well-curated handles. To top it all, designers and brands approach influencers just as they approach celebrities to make new trends enter the market. The main problem which fast fashion brings with itself is the problem of disposal. Once a piece of clothing goes out of trend, both the consumers and the fashion labels do not think twice before dumping huge heaps of clothes which no longer continues to quench their thirst for trends so much so that every second, enough clothes&amp;nbsp;to fill a garbage truck full are either burned or sent to a landfill. Extortion of environmental resources, excessive waste generation, carbon emissions are all consequences of a choice that we have opted for, a choice to simply wear clothes for a shorter span of time. All the aforementioned heinous consequences of fast fashion pose one question to mankind, should we stop buying clothes at all? The answer is NO! You can still stand out and manage to be a trendsetter just by being a little mindful of your actions and choices.&amp;nbsp; The most efficient way of tackling the problem at hand is by adopting sustainable fashion in order to achieve a circular fashion economy.&amp;nbsp; Circular fashion economy proposes a progressive system of circulating a piece of clothing in the economy till the time its maximum value gets exhausted and the cycle is completed by safely disposing off the no-longer-in-use piece back to the environment.&amp;nbsp; Sustainability is a two-way stream, brands and consumers are the two main players who can pave the way for circular and sustainable fashion. Before looking at how long is the road ahead, let’s see how far we have come on this long journey of achieving sustainability in its true sense. On the manufacturer’s side we have brands like H&amp;amp;M, which is now planning to deviate from the well-trodden path of fast fashion to reduce their environmental footprint by introducing sustainable collections made of organic cotton and recycled polyester.&amp;nbsp; As a brand which has now stepped up its game in circular fashion by accepting and recycling unwanted garments from customers, H&amp;amp;M has set a benchmark for brands in the similar line. Levi’s, on the other hand, has been trying to reduce the notorious amounts of water required to make a pair of jeans by 96% which is a huge step towards making judicial use of existing resources. Like H&amp;amp;M and Levi’s there are many more brands which are working in the same direction but there is still a lot to be done. On the other hand, consumers of fashion can adopt the following steps with a motive to convert their vision for the fashion industry into reality: Keep and wear the clothes for a longer span of time.Think twice before dumping clothes which no longer please you. Instead, upcycle, alter, repair or donate them.&amp;nbsp;Buy sustainable fashion, go for upcycled, thrifted pieces. The bigger question is, can sustainability and profitability ever go hand-in-hand? It’s the demand which can make or break a brand’s fate. With more and more consumers becoming environmentally conscious, the demand for sustainable fashion has hiked up over the course of the years, which has led to brands supplying more and more sustainable garments.&amp;nbsp; Aware and conscious customers, especially Gen Z and millennials are ready to buy sustainable clothing even if they have to shell out more money for it, which makes it profitable for brands to go sustainable. And the ones whose pockets are holding them back from supporting the cause, they tend to take another route by turning to thrift stores which are sustainable and pocket friendly too.&amp;nbsp; These small measures are just a few steps on the ladder towards achieving our goal of a sustainable and circular fashion economy which is all about covering one full circle from growing, designing, wearing, thrifting to finally passing the cloth to the biosphere by safely composting it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
