<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/cherry.sharma/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-01-13T21:51:33+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/cherry.sharma/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Promoting Free Trade in South Asia: SAFTA and Beyond</title>
      <link href="/Promoting-Free-Trade-in-South-Asia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Promoting Free Trade in South Asia: SAFTA and Beyond" />
      <published>2020-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Promoting-Free-Trade-in-South-Asia</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Promoting-Free-Trade-in-South-Asia">&lt;p&gt;South Asia experienced rapid GDP growth in the 1980’s, averaging around 6 % per annum across the region. This has attracted much global attention to the region. In addition to policy and institutional reforms that have been instrumental in tackling unemployment and poverty, market integration and regional cooperation have also been key to rapid growth and development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the 1990’s, South Asian countries have made efforts to enhance their trade and investment flows with the larger objective of poverty alleviation and economic development. Historically, changes in the trade policies of the region have been driven by the unilateral liberalisation of individual countries. However, preferential trade agreements were initiated after the formation of the South Asian Association for Regional Cooperation (SAARC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South Asian Preferential Trade Agreement (SAPTA) was signed by SAARC in 1995 as a step towards strengthening regional trade. However, SAPTA was not successful in enhancing trade among the member nations because its product coverage and tariff concessions were too limited. Thus, the South Asian Free Trade Agreement (SAFTA) was introduced. It aimed towards eventually bringing tariffs down to zero. SAFTA was signed on January 6, 2004, during the 12th SAARC Summit, held at Islamabad. The tariff liberalisation began to be implemented only in July 2006. In accordance with the first phase of the agreement, India, Pakistan, and Srilanka reduced their tariffs to 20% while Bangladesh, Bhutan and Maldives reduced their tariffs to nearly 30%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The introduction of SAFTA provided many opportunities to SAARC countries, but at the same time, it posed a few challenges. This was mainly because the agreement would have a significant impact on the welfare of member nations and on domestic producers. Critics say that SAFTA was unsuccessful in changing the existing trade patterns among South Asian countries to the extent that was initially proclaimed. Though SAFTA was introduced to counter the problems posed by SAPTA, it is considered to be an extension of the previous agreement. The only changes seemed to be the inclusion of trade facilitation elements and the switching of the trade liberalisation process from a positive list to a negative list approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main purpose of introducing the SAFTA was to encourage trade and also increase economic cooperation among the SAARC countries by reducing the tariffs and non-tariff barriers (NTBs) as well as by bringing transparency and equity among the nations. There was also a special preference to the Least Development Countries (LDCs) among the SAARC nations. SAFTA was also viewed as a South Asian Counterpart of the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA). By the end of 2013, the total exports by the member states under SAFTA had reached close to $3 billion. The question that arises is regarding the success of SAFTA over the years in achieving the goals that it set out for itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outcomes and Beyond&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality of the implementation of SAFTA was far different from the expectations that it had established. SAFTA’s main objective was to enable smooth movement of goods across borders with low tariffs, similar to what the European Union had been able to achieve. However, the governments of South Asia were not able to streamline their relations often due to conflicts between two or more nations. For example, the conflict between India and Pakistan has prevented many SAARC summits from taking place, thereby hindering the objectives of regional cooperation. A 2006 article in &lt;em&gt;Economic and Political Weekly&lt;/em&gt; titled ‘Does SAFTA have a Future?’ by Dushni Weerakoon and Jayanthi Thennakoon stated that nearly 53% of import trade amongst South Asian countries was excluded from the trade liberalisation as required under SAFTA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tariff Liberalisation Program (TLP) that was adopted under this agreement provided a clear system of tariff reduction. Non-LDCs were required to reduce existing tariffs to 0-5% within five years post-implementation, whereas LDCs were required to reduce tariffs to 30% within two years and to 0-5% within eight years. However, this system was criticised as it could potentially lead to the back-loading of tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TLP also excludes those goods which come under the sensitive list given by the member countries. This limits the range of goods available for trade. However, on the positive side, SAFTA puts a limit on the maximum number of sensitive goods that a country can list. This provision was not included in previous regional trade agreements such as the India-Sri Lanka Free Trade Agreement and the India-Pakistan Free Trade Agreement. Some features even hinted at turning a new page for trade policy, such as the provision of compensation for revenue losses that small countries were expected to face in the event of tariff reductions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also draw a comparison between the ASEAN Free Trade Area (AFTA) and the South Asian Free Trade Area (SAFTA). Under AFTA, between 1992-2017, exports increased from 21 to 27%. However, under SAFTA, this figure was very low. During the period that SAFTA came into effect, around 6-7% of the South Asian country’s exports were intra-regional exports. However, in recent years, this has declined to around 5%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Examining the Reasons for SAFTA’s Unsuccessful Run&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Asian Development Bank estimates that even after 35 years of SAARC’s establishment, it has not been able to significantly affect intra-regional trade. Many economists are of the view that SAFTA’s ineffectiveness could be attributed to the fact that it maintains a sensitive list which allows the exclusion of goods from the trade liberalisation process. The problem lies in the fact that these sensitive goods account for 6-45% of intra-regional imports in South Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The World Bank’s report titled &lt;em&gt;A Glass Half Full: The Promise of Regional Trade in South Asia&lt;/em&gt; (2018) examines SAFTA’s ineffectiveness in more depth. It is estimated that SAFTA’s proper application could have increased South Asian regional trade by more than $2 billion. However, SAFTA’s trade remains the lowest in the world among all other Regional Trade Agreements (RTAs) because South Asian countries are keener on trading with the US or the European Union. While intra-EU trade has a 70% success rate and the intra-NAFTA trade has a 50% success rate, the intra-SAARC trade has a meagre 5% success rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another notable finding is that within this region, there is a tendency of introducing para-tariffs that are levied on imports and not on domestic production. In Bangladesh, it is known as Supplementary Duty, whereas in Sri Lanka it is known as Ports and Airports Development Levy. These para-tariffs increase protection for domestic producers but also increase non-transparency between nations which hinders the process of free trade. This is a point of concern as these para-tariffs are not under the purview of SAFTA negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to a World Bank report, trade in South Asia can triple from its current volume of $23 billion to $67 billion. Considering this untapped potential, SAARC nations need to come together to address these issues. This will not only promote economic liberalisation by providing a higher variety of goods at lower prices, expanded markets and job creation, but will also take these nations to new heights of development. SAARC nations should also take a proactive role in implementing lower tariffs, lesser Non-Tariff Barriers to Trade (NTBs) and a common external tariff. Other initiatives such as creating a South Asian economic corridor and resolving disputes between countries in the region will go a long way in facilitating regional cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India plays an especially large role in turning around the fate of SAFTA. India is the dominant trading partner for most South Asian countries. About 90% of the foreign trade of countries such as Bangladesh, Nepal and Srilanka is achieved through bilateral trade relations with India. Thus, the creation of a free trade area is heavily reliant on India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, we can say that at the macro level, many initiatives are being taken to enable trade among South Asian countries and to limit trade with other regional unions for the collective prosperity of South Asia. However, the much anticipated SAFTA has fallen short of expectations. Factors such as simplifying the tariff structure, easing foreign exchange controls, transit facilities for the landlocked countries and easier banking facilities for import financing can help to build confidence among the SAARC nations. Apart from focusing solely on securing SAARC objectives, South Asian nations should also pay attention to bilateralism and sub-regionalism within South Asia. In 2014, Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi at the 18th SAARC Summit focussed on the need for relationships of South Asian countries to shift beyond SAARC. There is also a need for the launch of another free trade agreement that counters the issues of the SAFTA trade agreement to achieve the objective of establishing a South Asian Union. It is yet to be seen whether a new trade agreement is launched or not and if it is, how successfully does it tackle the issues of SAFTA or does it become an extension of SAFTA, just like the latter became of SAPTA.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Cherry Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">South Asia experienced rapid GDP growth in the 1980’s, averaging around 6 % per annum across the region. This has attracted much global attention to the region. In addition to policy and institutional reforms that have been instrumental in tackling unemployment and poverty, market integration and regional cooperation have also been key to rapid growth and development.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Breaking Up Big Tech</title>
      <link href="/Breaking-Up-Big-Tech" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breaking Up Big Tech" />
      <published>2020-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Breaking-Up-Big-Tech</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Breaking-Up-Big-Tech">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“It’s about as likely as is Mexico paying for Trump’s wall”&lt;/em&gt;, commented an equity researcher in response to Elizabeth Warren’s proposal. Have Google and Facebook become too powerful in our economy, should they be broken up? Are they creating some sort of monopoly in the technology space? All these are questions that have been in our minds for quite some time now. A decade ago, Amazon, Google, Facebook, Apple, and other networking sites were not a part of our lives the way they are today. However, in recent times, the emergence of these e-commerce websites and search engines has immensely increased, with everything, from purchasing groceries to online classes, taking place through these established tech agents. The issue cropped up after the US Senator Elizabeth Warren proposed to break down these companies into smaller units. This is gaining quite some popularity on both sides of the US political divide. Even President Donald Trump has made comments disparaging big tech and called for the government to sue companies like Google and Facebook. Lawmakers back in the US are thinking to disintegrate these companies because they feel that these companies have absolutely dismantled the healthy competitive spirit in their respective domains and have completely violated the antitrust laws of the country. So, let’s start unfolding the various layers of this recently heated debate by getting down to the history of the antitrust laws of the USA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Brief History of the Antitrust Laws in the USA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States has a history of breaking up large companies. Back then the railroad, oil, steel and sugar industries formed monopolies because of the very few competitors they had. Thus, they became wealthier at the expense of the consumer. The most well-known example is that of Standard Oil which controlled the entire industry of oil due to which they could completely change the price of the product by changing the supply. The oil industry at that time was prone to natural monopolies because of the rarity of the products. At this juncture, the federal government was forced to bust many of these large businesses with the help of the newly created ‘Antitrust Laws’ to protect the interests of the consumers. The first of these was the Sherman Act, passed in 1890 which aimed at preventing mergers between companies that led to unfair competition in the market. Despite this Act’s approval in 1890, the next fifty years saw the formation of many monopolies. Also, the profits of  Standard Oil and the generous dividends encouraged investors to invest in monopolistic firms. Succeeding it in 1914, the Federal Trade Commission Act was passed to monitor and track unfair business practices that deter the spirit of competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very well-known example of this Act being used is that of Microsoft  which was believed to be the tech giant of its time and aimed at establishing dominance in the area of web browsing but then the federal government intervened and sued it for violating anti-monopoly laws and reached an agreement with it. One school of thought says that the antitrust case on Microsoft that time helped shape a path for big tech giants like Google and Amazon to emerge. However, some analysts are of the view that in today’s times these antitrust laws seem inapplicable to the tech giants because they are already a century old and they were created to protect the interests of the consumers differently, specifically we mean that they were built in an era where financial domination led to the creation of monopolies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Role of Big Tech and the Present Debate Related to It&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US economy has been on an upward trend which can to some extent be attributed to the tech sector. Nearly, half of the e-commerce goes through Amazon, more than 70% of all internet referral traffic goes through sites owned and operated by Google and Facebook. Instagram, today, has one billion active monthly users – two-thirds of whom visit the platform on a daily basis. More than two million businesses have bought ads there, many of which are intended to drive users to their websites to buy products. And Senator Elizabeth Warren feels that these companies have too much power over our economy, society and democracy. Presidential candidate Bernie Sanders has also clashed with Amazon on multiple occasions, and criticised Facebook and Google for destroying local media. He said that he will look into breaking up big tech companies. This proposal enjoys support from not just the majority of Democrats but in similar proportions of Republicans and Independents, claiming it to be a bipartisan issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent online poll, it has been shown that around 7 in 10 Americans say it’s a good idea to break up big tech companies when the content that they are showing is ranked depending on whether the company is making money or not. On these lines, it is being argued that the current landscape of technology has left consumers with little privacy even as their data is converted into vast corporate profit. These American big tech companies have mainly achieved the level of dominance by using two strategies- using mergers to limit competition and using the proprietary marketplace to limit competition. Take the example of Facebook, which purchased potential competitors such as Instagram and WhatsApp. Amazon used its extreme market power to force smaller competitors such as Diapers.com to sell its products at a discounted rate. Weak antitrust enforcement laws have led to the culminating dominance created by these tech companies in the last few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venture capitalists are also hesitant to fund new tech because they feel that either these start-ups would be purchased by these monopolists or else, they will completely crash. It is also claimed that with fewer tech companies entering the market, these large tech agents don’t have to compete in matters such as protecting our data privacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two sorts of measures that can be taken to break these monopolies, first by passing legislation that requires large tech platforms to be designated as ‘platform utilities’ (companies with annual global revenue of $25 billion or more that offer to the public an online marketplace, an exchange, or a platform connecting third parties would be termed as ‘platform utilities’) that would be broken apart from any participant on that platform, with them not being allowed to share data with any third parties. Also, they should be required to meet a standard of fair, reasonable and non-discriminatory dealing with third parties. Such measures would also ensure that the sovereignty of America is upheld and no third-country can influence its election results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will Breaking Up these Tech Giants Really Fix it Up?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experts from Wharton have challenged Warren’s proposals and said that breaking them up won’t actually provide a level playing field, but instead in the long term would again route down profits to other successful business ventures. I believe that the reason why this political debate has come up is completely valid but the solution that is being offered is not the most practical, this is because even in the past this has not worked. The breaking up of AT&amp;amp;T into eight companies unleashed competition for a time, lowering prices but as landlines gave way for wireless, the industry reconsolidated. Thus, the enforcement of antitrust laws will not solve the issues of high prices and privacy. For example, removing WhatsApp from Facebook won’t let Facebook collect any lesser data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consumers would also be at a loss because, if suppose, we disintegrate Google then we won’t be able to simultaneously use Google Drive and Google Chrome, imagine the number of complexities involved. Also, the Antitrust Doctrine has focused on two things, one is the conduct and the other is the structure. The Federal Trade Commission and Department of Justice should focus on the conduct and behaviour of big tech companies to make sure that they don’t use their market power to become anticompetitive. The size of these companies have enabled them to make big investments in future, if we try to break them up, we’re going to lose that. Also, even if antitrust laws would prevent mergers, we need to understand the chain reaction that would follow, which is when prices are lowered the wages will be lowered too, jobs would be cut, and product quality would also fall discouraging innovation. All of these changes would unknowingly harm the consumers in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s in Store for these Large Tech Giants?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we can not deny the fact that these large tech giants have created some sort of dominance in the society with their products, lucrative offers and better policies at hand to gain maximum profits and to drive out other competitors from the business, we should not deny the fact that they have always driven the economy on an upward trend, providing better opportunities for employees. We should also realise the fact that disintegrating them based on antitrust laws is not correct because globalisation and the ever-increasing world economy have called out for the retirement of the antitrust laws. Further, ultimately, we as consumers are also to be blamed because, in the end, it’s we who have given them the title of large tech giants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning, most of them started on a level playing field and now they have reached their present level due to a lot of effort. Instead of just relying on one individual’s statement and subsequently taking action against these tech giants is not justified, the regulators and politicians should ask the consumers how ‘bad’ they find the tech giants to be at present and then decide. We need to understand that instead of breaking them up, we should think of fixing up issues like data privacy. Moreover, we should look at the fact that even though an investigation can be carried on for years accusing them of many things but ultimately proving them in court with proofs would be another thing because they would also leave no stone unturned to prove themselves not guilty. With some forces standing against them and others supporting it, the future of these big tech companies remains uncertain and largely depends on what shall happen in the courts.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Cherry Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="repost" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“It’s about as likely as is Mexico paying for Trump’s wall”, commented an equity researcher in response to Elizabeth Warren’s proposal. Have Google and Facebook become too powerful in our economy, should they be broken up? Are they creating some sort of monopoly in the technology space? All these are questions that have been in our minds for quite some time now. A decade ago, Amazon, Google, Facebook, Apple, and other networking sites were not a part of our lives the way they are today. However, in recent times, the emergence of these e-commerce websites and search engines has immensely increased, with everything, from purchasing groceries to online classes, taking place through these established tech agents. The issue cropped up after the US Senator Elizabeth Warren proposed to break down these companies into smaller units. This is gaining quite some popularity on both sides of the US political divide. Even President Donald Trump has made comments disparaging big tech and called for the government to sue companies like Google and Facebook. Lawmakers back in the US are thinking to disintegrate these companies because they feel that these companies have absolutely dismantled the healthy competitive spirit in their respective domains and have completely violated the antitrust laws of the country. So, let’s start unfolding the various layers of this recently heated debate by getting down to the history of the antitrust laws of the USA.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">JioMart: The Disruptor?</title>
      <link href="/JioMart" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JioMart: The Disruptor?" />
      <published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/JioMart</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/JioMart">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Don’t find customers for your products, find products for your customers”&lt;/em&gt;, they say, and truly, those who have always thought about their consumers, are the ones whose products have been the most successful. I would not be wrong in saying that the economic development of any country starts and ends with the consumers of that country. Any consumer-related business can rise to great heights if the creators of that business model cater to the needs of the consumers and provide them with efficient services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving along these lines, Mukesh Ambani has now become the fourth richest in the Forbes Global Rich List 2020 as Reliance Industries’ market capitalisation, including the partly paid shares, topped the ₹13 trillion mark. With the recent rise in the e-commerce sector, Reliance Industries has aimed to extend its reach here, which is in contrast with its previous approach wherein they limited themselves to the oil refinery and petroleum sector. To put this in context, we have to take a look at the facts to see why Reliance Industries is where it is today. In the last few years, the launch of Reliance Jio Infocomm Ltd has been able to attract customers even from other rivals such as Vodafone-Idea, Airtel and other telecom operators in India, with its cheap data plans, free calls, and other exciting features. Due to this, it now has the largest user base in India. The launch of Jio was game-changing for India because it redefined the limits of internet usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With its e-commerce platform JioMart, Reliance plans to cause a similar disruption that Jio caused in the telecom sector. The aim is to “completely transform”  India’s unorganised retail market of mostly mom-and-pop stores, which account for nearly 90% of the nation’s retail industry. Through this online-offline model, JioMart won’t sell products to the customers directly but instead, it would link the online buyers with offline retailers in their locality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reliance estimates that through this platform it would be able to link 30 million offline retailers with 200 million households. The digital platform, unlike other foreign competitors, would link producers, traders, small merchants, consumer brands, and consumers under a common shed. Hence, JioMart is a strategically planned holistic model that aims to usher in opportunities not only to Reliance Industries but also to other people directly linked to the same industry. Moreover, at a time when other ventures of Reliance in the grocery segment such as Reliance Retail and Reliance Fresh, which have a strong offline presence over the country, are doing quite well, we can expect this online platform to be a ‘cash cow’ for the giant. To make them completely digitised, JioMart claims to integrate local &lt;em&gt;kirana&lt;/em&gt; (corner) stores and provide them with Points of Sale (PoS) terminals, educate them about inventory management skills, supply chain management, and Goods and Service Tax (GST) compliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analysts and experts are of the view that Facebook’s recent investment in Jio could help JioMart grow. The deal is expected to bear fruits for both the giants. On one side, Jio would gain from the technological expertise that Facebook brings to the table. At the same time, the payments made on the platform through WhatsApp Pay would help the messaging app to overcome the regulatory issues it has been facing. Moreover, Reliance being an already established brand in India would increase the customer base of the Facebook-owned company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to market the online retail platform, Jio has been sending invites to all its users to avail the preliminary discounts. Furthermore, it claims that all its listed products are sold at 5% below the Maximum Retail Price (MRP), this feature is quite similar to DMart’s model that made it quite successful overnight. Additionally, it is still offering the cash-on-delivery option that a lot of existing competitors have stopped. Claims have also been made that JioMart delivers 400,000 orders in a single day which is significantly higher than other grocery home delivery companies. Hence, if JioMart continues working in the same direction, it is bound to give a tough competition to its counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the launch of JioMart, rivals such as Amazon, have started taking steps to maintain their foothold. Amazon has signed a deal with Kishore Biyani’s Future Group to deliver its products. It has also started to broaden the options it provides and has resorted to selective discounting. Amazon has also launched ‘Local Shops’ which has enabled 5,000 offline retailers to set up shop online and has established 10 new warehouses to expand their storage capacity. Additionally, Flipkart said that it would reapply for a food retail license in India. Most importantly, Flipkart has bought Walmart India’s wholesale business in July and is expected to launch a digital marketplace, Flipkart Wholesale in August. So, these already established online platforms have identified the threat being posed by JioMart, and have buckled themselves up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At present, all that we can expect is that with the launch of JioMart, competitive intensity is likely to increase and nothing can be said about who will win the race. Everything is completely dependent upon who would be able to gain the eyes of more consumers and attract them easily with their lucrative offers, but it also seems to be a stiff competition since both JioMart and other established e-commerce websites are leaving no stone unturned. So, whether established e-commerce platforms retain their place or JioMart takes over is what remains to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Cherry Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Don’t find customers for your products, find products for your customers”, they say, and truly, those who have always thought about their consumers, are the ones whose products have been the most successful. I would not be wrong in saying that the economic development of any country starts and ends with the consumers of that country. Any consumer-related business can rise to great heights if the creators of that business model cater to the needs of the consumers and provide them with efficient services.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Green Bonds: A New Revolution towards Sustainable Finance in India?</title>
      <link href="/A-New-Revolution-towards-Sustainable-Finance-in-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Green Bonds: A New Revolution towards Sustainable Finance in India?" />
      <published>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-New-Revolution-towards-Sustainable-Finance-in-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-New-Revolution-towards-Sustainable-Finance-in-India">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;We need bold action on climate change, our generation may not be able to solve all the problems related to climate change, but we can do our part to leave a better planet for the next generation&lt;/em&gt;”, said Kristalina Georgieva, World Bank Group and Interim Chief Executive Officer. Climate change has caused an unprecedented risk to the growth of societies and economies. According to a recent report by Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), it has been estimated that around $6-7 trillion of annual investment is globally required to achieve the objective of moving the world economy towards a ‘greener economy’. To get the entire globe out of this trap, we need to make substantial investments that fund projects focussing on creating low carbon economies, clean energy, water transportation, etc. Only with such effective measures shall we be able to build a climate-resilient economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many countries around the world have been pursuing a shift towards a more sustainable environment. Recently, the European Union launched the Next Generation EU (NGEU) fund to tackle the coronavirus pandemic. The deal puts the issue of climate change at the forefront. According to the deal document, a total of 30% of the expenditure of the €1.82 trillion will be used to reach the climate targets in conformity to the objectives of the Paris agreements. It also has a provision that rules that the European Commission should publish a report on climate expenditure annually. In order to ensure that such legislations bear fruitful results, it is important to provide investors with alternative options of investments, with higher returns and which also give them a feeling of having satisfied their responsibility towards the environment. This is where ‘Green Bonds’ come into the picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the current status and impetus given to green finance globally, we can not only give credit to institutions that have introduced green bonds but also to the dynamic shift witnessed in the corporate bond market wherein we have more socially responsible investors who want to invest their money in the funding of those projects that would lead to a positive impact on the society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite knowing the unmeasured potential of green finance all over the world, the total number of green bonds issued was only around 3% as a percentage of the total corporate bonds issued. This reveals the percentage of untapped potential of the green bond market which should be effectively realised to create a sustainable environment. So, how are these bonds currently being exploited in India?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Indian Green Bond Market and the Road Ahead.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a time when governments across the world are emphasising on creating low carbon economies, India is not lagging behind in showing its efforts in the same direction. Indian financial institutions such as the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) and the Securities Exchange Board of India (SEBI) are effectively trying to promote green bonds in the country. India is aiming to build 175 gigawatts of renewable energy capacity by 2022. Thus, the financing needs of the renewable energy sector can effectively be addressed by the issuance of green bonds in our country. In the last few years Indian investors, banking institutions, and the government have played a crucial role in developing sustainable finance. They have recognised it as a fundamental tool towards financing the nation’s renewable energy targets through developing strategies for sustainable economic growth and effective policy framework for judicious utilisation of all-natural resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green bonds in India were introduced in 2015 when Yes Bank issued the first series of green bonds in the country for financing projects of ₹10 billion followed by ₹6 billion issuances of green bonds by CLP India. In order to regulate these issuances, SEBI issued the green bond guidelines on lines of the green bond principles issued by the Institute of Cost and Management Accountants (ICMA). By 2018, the Indian green bond market had risen to ₹500 billion. This clearly indicates that India has an enormous capacity for the development of sustainable finance which just needs to be unlocked with appropriate policies and measures. According to Climate Transparency’s &lt;em&gt;Brown to Green&lt;/em&gt; report, wherein a study was conducted among the G20 countries measuring the Green Bond Issuance as a share of the country’s overall debt, India was ranked 5th, hence, Indian financial institutions and investors should realise that the green bond market has a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the enormous potential, the market is yet to overcome several barriers such as greenwashing, false claims of environmental compliance, etc. Additionally, there exist mismatches between long-term green investment and short-term interests of the investors which tend to make the market less efficient. Exorbitant currency hedging costs because of the high volatility of the Indian rupee, poor sovereign rating, and low tenure of the green bonds pose a hurdle in the path of creating a highly advanced green bond market. Moreover, we need to realise that till date the green bonds that have been issued in India have only been offered by highly established finance companies, whereas internationally, other organisations such as local governments, climate change organisations, and other corporate firms are all coming together to address this issue by diversifying the green bond market in their countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On analysing the above situation of green finance in the country, we can clearly conclude that India’s full potential still needs to be explored because currently there exists a shortage of supply as well as the demand for green bonds in the market because of various constraints. In order to increase the efficiency of this particular market, the government and the authorities need to formulate relevant policies and implement them. For starters, the short-term interests of investors as well as issuers, need to be removed by educating them that the advancement of the market in the country not only will fund the necessary environmental projects but also would allow issuers to generate a positive public reputation. Since the main reason for the lack of demand of green bonds in our country is the investors’ perception that they are not competitive enough to give them high financial returns, the governmental agencies need to step up by guaranteeing a fixed rate of return which is marginally higher than other investments so that large institutional investors and retail investors would heavily invest under this domain. Other measures such as reducing foreign exchange hedging costs will attract investors from overseas to invest in clean energy projects of India. RBI, SEBI, Indian Renewable Energy Development Agency Ltd. (IREDA), and the Ministry of Finance can play an important role in the nascent stage development of Green Finance in the country by creating more rupee denominated bonds such as the IFC-Yes Bank Green Masala Bond of 2015. Launching credited and standardised Indian green bonds that would reduce the stigma of the attached risk with green bonds can completely flip the situation upside-down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, in order to attract domestic demand, the government should provide tax incentives to individuals for investment in such bonds. The development of sustainable stock exchanges just like the Shanghai Stock Exchange did is essential for continued growth. It has a special index to monitor the green finance situation in the country. Efforts of the government and other institutions have borne positive results. According to the Indian Economic Survey 2019-20, India has become the second-largest market for green bonds after China with $10.3 billion transactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government support and a dedicated policy at hand are necessarily required to scale up the level of green bonds market in the country. An enhanced policy framework is required in action to upgrade the current situation of the green finance market in the country. This can also be done by educating investors, and removing information asymmetry between issuers and investors. An increase in investor confidence could give a new shape to the outlook of sustainable finance in our country. Only enhanced collective participation of issuers, corporate firms, financial institutions, policymakers, and regulators will give the fundamental push to the boundary of the green bond market, and would further give rise to other such opportunities in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, green bonds can be seen as the interlinking bridge connecting sustainable finance with funding quintessential environmental projects. Growth in the green bonds in India would set a precedent for other theme-based bonds such as social bonds, water bonds, and sustainability bonds that raise finance for specific developmental purposes.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Cherry Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“We need bold action on climate change, our generation may not be able to solve all the problems related to climate change, but we can do our part to leave a better planet for the next generation”, said Kristalina Georgieva, World Bank Group and Interim Chief Executive Officer. Climate change has caused an unprecedented risk to the growth of societies and economies. According to a recent report by Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), it has been estimated that around $6-7 trillion of annual investment is globally required to achieve the objective of moving the world economy towards a ‘greener economy’. To get the entire globe out of this trap, we need to make substantial investments that fund projects focussing on creating low carbon economies, clean energy, water transportation, etc. Only with such effective measures shall we be able to build a climate-resilient economy.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
