<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/avinash.naidu/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-06-28T23:19:28+01:00</updated>
  <id>/author/avinash.naidu/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Reasons Why Traditional Employment is Becoming Obsolete</title>
      <link href="/Traditional-Employment-is-Becoming-Obsolete" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reasons Why Traditional Employment is Becoming Obsolete" />
      <published>2019-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Traditional-Employment-is-Becoming-Obsolete</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Traditional-Employment-is-Becoming-Obsolete">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;gig economy&lt;/em&gt;: a term we are becoming more familiar with each passing day.
We are constantly reminded about the rise of the gig economy but only a few
understand the factors that are accelerating this process. In this article, I
will be breaking down some of these factors as simply as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.  Real Estate Prices have been going up&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economicshelp.org/blog/5709/housing/market/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//uk-house-prices.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economicshelp.org/blog/5709/housing/market/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.economicshelp.org/blog/5709/housing/market/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the late 90’s, real estate prices have seen a steady growth rate, with the
only drop being between 2008-2012 during the housing crisis, before increasing
again steadily. With the continual increases in prices, getting office spaces
for large companies is becoming less affordable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. The rise of co-working spaces&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like a new co-working space pops up every couple of months. It has been
estimated that there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://allwork.space/2019/05/coworking-is-the-new-normal-and-these-stats-prove-itt/&quot;&gt;35,000 flexible office spaces covering 521 million
square feet of real estate in the entire
world&lt;/a&gt; - a number that is growing very rapidly. With the increased competition,
co-working spaces are becoming more affordable with far more services becoming
available. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.  Commuting times are increasing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The increasing population density in cities is leading to overcrowding.
Transport infrastructures can no longer keep up with the increased load, leading
to bumper-to-bumper traffic jams and overcrowding of public transport where we
all feel like canned sardines. Besides discomfort, a lot of time is lost daily.
Because of this, more and more people are opting to work from home to get back
those additional hours which they used to waste earlier in travel. And what
better way to do it than to be a freelancer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. There are more entrepreneurs and startups than ever before&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the growth of the digital economy, it has become easier than ever to start
a new business. With access to large markets globally and a wealth of resources
to help push the business forward; starting a business is an enticing option. No
more 9-5 jobs, increased fulfilment, flexibility and so much more have turned
&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/tag/millennial/&quot;&gt;millennials&lt;/a&gt; away from the traditional
job market. With many of these startups being run from home with no additional
employees, most of these companies are more likely to hire a freelancer to
complete any work that is out of their scope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Almost everything can be done online&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New ways of working. A phrase thrown around in big companies all over the world.
With more tools and better connectivity, collaboration no longer requires the
team to be in the same country anymore, let alone a shared office space. Data
sharing and real-time updates have led to a far more seamless online
collaboration. Collaboration tools aside, online transactions are far easier,
safer and more secure than ever before. With the click of a button, money can be
transferred around the world instantaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Reduced barriers to a globalised workforce&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A marketing executive in Malaysia, a programmer in America and ales teams that
span across 10 countries. With the increase in available collaboration tools and
English becoming the global business language, working across borders is
becoming increasingly easier. With further improvements to the laws and
regulations, global-scale projects are becoming the norm. &lt;a href=&quot;https://singularityhub.com/2017/10/22/peak-globalization-is-the-path-to-a-sustainable-economy/&quot;&gt;With a whole host of
benefits to going
global&lt;/a&gt;,
companies are all gearing up for the workforce revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Better Freelancing platforms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, the increased availability of freelancing platforms which
are getting more effective at connecting employers to freelancers. Not only are
they better at connecting collaborators but they also provide a host of services
to make the collaboration as risk-free and hassle-free as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at these seven reasons, it is easy to see why companies are more likely
to downsize their operations and rely more heavily on freelance work. This helps
further develop the gig economy in a continuous growth cycle and someday the
traditional 9-5 job will just be a long-forgotten memory.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Avinash Naidu</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The gig economy: a term we are becoming more familiar with each passing day. We are constantly reminded about the rise of the gig economy but only a few understand the factors that are accelerating this process. In this article, I will be breaking down some of these factors as simply as possible. 1.  Real Estate Prices have been going up Source: https://www.economicshelp.org/blog/5709/housing/market/ Since the late 90’s, real estate prices have seen a steady growth rate, with the only drop being between 2008-2012 during the housing crisis, before increasing again steadily. With the continual increases in prices, getting office spaces for large companies is becoming less affordable. 2. The rise of co-working spaces It seems like a new co-working space pops up every couple of months. It has been estimated that there are 35,000 flexible office spaces covering 521 million square feet of real estate in the entire world - a number that is growing very rapidly. With the increased competition, co-working spaces are becoming more affordable with far more services becoming available.  3.  Commuting times are increasing The increasing population density in cities is leading to overcrowding. Transport infrastructures can no longer keep up with the increased load, leading to bumper-to-bumper traffic jams and overcrowding of public transport where we all feel like canned sardines. Besides discomfort, a lot of time is lost daily. Because of this, more and more people are opting to work from home to get back those additional hours which they used to waste earlier in travel. And what better way to do it than to be a freelancer.  4. There are more entrepreneurs and startups than ever before With the growth of the digital economy, it has become easier than ever to start a new business. With access to large markets globally and a wealth of resources to help push the business forward; starting a business is an enticing option. No more 9-5 jobs, increased fulfilment, flexibility and so much more have turned millennials away from the traditional job market. With many of these startups being run from home with no additional employees, most of these companies are more likely to hire a freelancer to complete any work that is out of their scope. 5. Almost everything can be done online New ways of working. A phrase thrown around in big companies all over the world. With more tools and better connectivity, collaboration no longer requires the team to be in the same country anymore, let alone a shared office space. Data sharing and real-time updates have led to a far more seamless online collaboration. Collaboration tools aside, online transactions are far easier, safer and more secure than ever before. With the click of a button, money can be transferred around the world instantaneously. 6. Reduced barriers to a globalised workforce A marketing executive in Malaysia, a programmer in America and ales teams that span across 10 countries. With the increase in available collaboration tools and English becoming the global business language, working across borders is becoming increasingly easier. With further improvements to the laws and regulations, global-scale projects are becoming the norm. With a whole host of benefits to going global, companies are all gearing up for the workforce revolution. 7. Better Freelancing platforms Last but not least, the increased availability of freelancing platforms which are getting more effective at connecting employers to freelancers. Not only are they better at connecting collaborators but they also provide a host of services to make the collaboration as risk-free and hassle-free as possible. Looking at these seven reasons, it is easy to see why companies are more likely to downsize their operations and rely more heavily on freelance work. This helps further develop the gig economy in a continuous growth cycle and someday the traditional 9-5 job will just be a long-forgotten memory.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Watch Me Watch You Watch Me</title>
      <link href="/Watch-Me-Watch-You-Watch-Me" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Watch Me Watch You Watch Me" />
      <published>2019-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Watch-Me-Watch-You-Watch-Me</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Watch-Me-Watch-You-Watch-Me">&lt;p&gt;Most of us in some way, shape or form love social media. We spend hours
scrolling through content, liking and commenting as we go along. All of our
actions generate data which is then collected by these social media companies
and used, to encourage us to use their platforms more: the so-called addictive
factor. The more data a social media platform collects, the larger their profit
margins. Not only do we consume content, but we also partake in the creation of
content which further keeps users on these platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take Instagram for example. When you upload a photo of yourself on a beach
holiday in Mauritius, it is added to the collective of all posts by Instagram.
Now Instagram is going to do its best to get as many people to view, like and
comment on your post. This brings two benefits to them. One, it learns about the
consumer’s preferences and interests based on what they look at. Two, each
notification you receive about that post will trigger a dopamine response making
you more likely to click on it and get back on the app. Now you can see from
just one post, Instagram is able to keep your followers on the app as well as
yourself. And every additional action carried out on Instagram generates a data
point on us to be sold to the highest bidder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media sites are also designed to make it as easy as possible for us to
post something. By studying how we use the app, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/habits-five-ways-to-help-users-change-them&quot;&gt;UI/UX designers are further
improving apps to make creating content a force of
habit&lt;/a&gt;.
These habits slowly meld into our lives to the point we don’t even have to think
before carrying out all the actions required to open Facebook on our phones and
get onto a Livestream. Now that we have come full circle, we realise the
horrible truth, that we are the creators of our own downfall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;em&gt;“Social media, it’s just the market’s answer to a generation that demanded to
perform. So the market said, ‘Here, perform everything to each other, all the
time, for no reason.’ It’s prison. It’s horrific. It is performer and audience
melded together,”&lt;/em&gt; He then goes on to add, &lt;em&gt;“I know very little about anything,
but what I do know is that if you can live your life without an audience, you
should do it.”&lt;/em&gt; - Bo Burnham's comedy special &lt;em&gt;Make Happy&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does this mean for us? Once you understand how social media works, you
begin to realise that the platforms only have power because we give it to them.
And if we can give them the power, we can also take it back. Sometimes it feels
like one person can’t make a difference, but much like democracy, every single
person counts. The next time you find yourself appalled by Facebook’s unethical
data practices. Just stop and think for a little, how much of an accomplice are
you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media is a great tool to connect, discover and learn but failure to
understand the machinations behind how social media works can lead us down a
vicious cycle of consumption. Sometimes all we need to take control… is to
take a step back.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Avinash Naidu</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Most of us in some way, shape or form love social media. We spend hours scrolling through content, liking and commenting as we go along. All of our actions generate data which is then collected by these social media companies and used, to encourage us to use their platforms more: the so-called addictive factor. The more data a social media platform collects, the larger their profit margins. Not only do we consume content, but we also partake in the creation of content which further keeps users on these platforms. Let’s take Instagram for example. When you upload a photo of yourself on a beach holiday in Mauritius, it is added to the collective of all posts by Instagram. Now Instagram is going to do its best to get as many people to view, like and comment on your post. This brings two benefits to them. One, it learns about the consumer’s preferences and interests based on what they look at. Two, each notification you receive about that post will trigger a dopamine response making you more likely to click on it and get back on the app. Now you can see from just one post, Instagram is able to keep your followers on the app as well as yourself. And every additional action carried out on Instagram generates a data point on us to be sold to the highest bidder. Social media sites are also designed to make it as easy as possible for us to post something. By studying how we use the app, UI/UX designers are further improving apps to make creating content a force of habit. These habits slowly meld into our lives to the point we don’t even have to think before carrying out all the actions required to open Facebook on our phones and get onto a Livestream. Now that we have come full circle, we realise the horrible truth, that we are the creators of our own downfall. “Social media, it’s just the market’s answer to a generation that demanded to perform. So the market said, ‘Here, perform everything to each other, all the time, for no reason.’ It’s prison. It’s horrific. It is performer and audience melded together,” He then goes on to add, “I know very little about anything, but what I do know is that if you can live your life without an audience, you should do it.” - Bo Burnham's comedy special Make Happy. So what does this mean for us? Once you understand how social media works, you begin to realise that the platforms only have power because we give it to them. And if we can give them the power, we can also take it back. Sometimes it feels like one person can’t make a difference, but much like democracy, every single person counts. The next time you find yourself appalled by Facebook’s unethical data practices. Just stop and think for a little, how much of an accomplice are you? Social media is a great tool to connect, discover and learn but failure to understand the machinations behind how social media works can lead us down a vicious cycle of consumption. Sometimes all we need to take control… is to take a step back.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Bright Side of Sharing Our Data</title>
      <link href="/The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-our-Data" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Bright Side of Sharing Our Data" />
      <published>2019-10-08T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-our-Data</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-our-Data">&lt;p&gt;In recent times, there has been a wave of anger towards companies which use
individual data without his or her knowledge. Campaigns like #OwnYourData,
#MEGA and most recently, the movie documentary &lt;em&gt;The Great Hack&lt;/em&gt; have brought
the issue to the limelight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, I won’t argue that there is no malicious use of personal data,
I would like to show that though there are some cases where data is used for
&lt;em&gt;‘nefarious’&lt;/em&gt; -  I quote nefarious because it is subjective to each individual -
purposes on a whole, the tool known as &lt;em&gt;data analytics&lt;/em&gt; has brought far more
benefits than harm to society. Fake news and data analytics are separate tools
which though used simultaneously need to be separated. Whilst data analytics is
instrumental in the distribution of fake news, it is not the cause of it.
Gossiping, fear mongering and rumours have been used long before data analytics
even existed. Though I must add that fake news is completely illegal and should
never be condoned. Now that I have set the stage, let’s dive right into this
hidden world of data analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//data-sharing-fb-avi.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt; An example of the ads section on Facebook.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook- A name that triggers a whole array of feelings for everyone. A tool
for communicating, connecting and gathering for like-minded people or long-lost
friends, or  a tool to gather our personal data, process it and sell it to the
highest bidder. Not many of us know that we can ourselves see if Facebook is
being &lt;em&gt;‘mischievous’&lt;/em&gt; with us. Open the ads section under settings to see where
your data has been used. So let’s say Spotify received your data from Facebook,
based on that, they would be able to provide you with music that will most
likely fit your taste. It seems trivial but in this day and age where content is
being created at an exponentially increasing rate, it would be impossible to go
through everything to find something we like. To put perspective on that,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessofapps.com/data/youtube-statistics/#4&quot;&gt;YouTube is estimated to upload 500 hours of content every minute. That
essentially means that a lifetime of content is uploaded every 2
days.&lt;/a&gt; It may be
online shopping, holiday booking, travel planning and they all have one goal… to
make our lives easier so we continue using their platforms. In the case of
Facebook, we have a friend that ensures that we get the best options to choose
from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arguably, Spotify, YouTube and Facebook are luxury goods, however this is also
prevalent in healthcare. Let’s dive into a hospital to see how data is changing
the way we work. Most hospitals, nowadays, have some sort of digital
ticketing/queuing system which still requires you to wait for hours for your
treatment. With the increased amount of data and software as a Service Business
Intelligence (SaaS BI) tool, hospitals will be able to predict the busiest parts
of the day and staff accordingly to deal with these peaks. This will allow
hospitals to handle more patients more effectively and hence save more lives in
the long run. After getting into your appointment, doctors would be able to have
a full view of your entire medical history, if it was shared. This will, in
turn, allow them to better understand your history which saves time and provides
a more accurate diagnosis. These are two very simple examples which only can
work effectively when medical data is shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A third and less obvious example; &lt;em&gt;what if the medical data was given to
insurance companies?&lt;/em&gt; The fear is that with access to medical data, we will be
charged additionally for all the problems they will find out about. But I argue
differently. With more data available using analytical tools, insurance
companies would be able to better personalize insurance offers which could
actually lead to cheaper premiums due to the removal of unnecessary coverage. On
top of that, insurance companies will be able to better reward people for taking
steps to maintain good health. Lastly, with access to medical data, insurers
will be able to better identify insurance fraud leading to more applicants being
able to claim insurance when required. There is always a risk that some
companies will implement some unfair practices leading to increased premiums.
However, with the growing digital economy and a multitude of options, these
companies are likely to be outcompeted in the free market, making them
unsustainable in the long run. Whilst this is something that will arise in the
future, let’s look at it in a very contemporary context - data analytics in
Political Campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before diving into the data analytics of campaigning, I want to highlight that a
campaign is defined as ‘a planned group of especially political, business, or
military activities that are intended to achieve a particular aim&lt;em&gt;.’ &lt;/em&gt; In the
case of political campaigns, the focus is to convince those who are on the fence
to support your party. Long before the infamy of Cambridge Analytica,
campaigners have been collecting polling data to decide how to target their
campaigns. So why are we suddenly so afraid? Well, mostly it is thanks to our
favourite six-inch toy that we never stop playing with. Due to advancements in
smartphone technology, we are becoming far more connected to the internet, which
in turn leads to more data collected on us. This was the cost of a &lt;em&gt;‘free’&lt;/em&gt;
internet. The free internet came with the major benefit of allowing everyone a
chance of getting access. That meant that companies needed a different way to
make money online, hence the rise of data collection. Initially, starting out as
a harmless tool to provide advertisers with the attention of relevant
potential-customers. It has now evolved into a behemoth that not only provides
the things we may like but also tries to shift our preferences ever so slightly.
Doesn’t seem so bad, but these subtle nudges to shift our opinions slowly push
us further and further down the extreme path we are on - which is proven by the
increased polarization (shown in multiple studies
&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.stanford.edu/~gentzkow/research/PolarizationIn2016.pdf&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apsanet.org/portals/54/Files/Task%20Force%20Reports/Chapter2Mansbridge.pdf&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://reutersinstitute.politics.ox.ac.uk/sites/default/files/2019-03/Polarisation_and_the_news_media_in_Europe.pdf&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/115/37/9216&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;) around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Donald Trump’s 2016 digital campaign director claimed to have run 5.9 million
visual ads on Facebook, in contrast to Hillary Clinton’s 66,000”- The Great
Hack.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This statement made at the end of &lt;em&gt;The Great Hack&lt;/em&gt; further highlights
that this negative opinion on data analytics is also due to some tactics of fear
mongering and misrepresentation of information&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; Without any context, it seems
like Donald Trump paid to win an election. Then you consider the fact that in
total Hillary Clinton spent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/politics/2016-election/campaign-finance/?noredirect=on&quot;&gt;1.4 Billion compared to Trump’s 957.6
Million&lt;/a&gt;
on their respective campaigns. The main reason Trump spent more on online ads
was that his fundraising had lagged behind Hillary Clinton, so he had missed out
on the opportunity to spend on TV ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many examples of data being used to make our lives better, but at
the end of the day, data analytics is just a tool. In the hands of the right
person, it could bring unprecedented benefits to society. If we go down the
extreme path of fearing the tool, we have lots to lose. That being said, I still
highly recommend everyone to find out what is happening with your data.
Knowledge is power, and we can learn a lot about ourselves from the way our data
is being used.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Avinash Naidu</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In recent times, there has been a wave of anger towards companies which use individual data without his or her knowledge. Campaigns like #OwnYourData, #MEGA and most recently, the movie documentary The Great Hack have brought the issue to the limelight. In this article, I won’t argue that there is no malicious use of personal data, I would like to show that though there are some cases where data is used for ‘nefarious’ -  I quote nefarious because it is subjective to each individual - purposes on a whole, the tool known as data analytics has brought far more benefits than harm to society. Fake news and data analytics are separate tools which though used simultaneously need to be separated. Whilst data analytics is instrumental in the distribution of fake news, it is not the cause of it. Gossiping, fear mongering and rumours have been used long before data analytics even existed. Though I must add that fake news is completely illegal and should never be condoned. Now that I have set the stage, let’s dive right into this hidden world of data analytics. An example of the ads section on Facebook. Facebook- A name that triggers a whole array of feelings for everyone. A tool for communicating, connecting and gathering for like-minded people or long-lost friends, or  a tool to gather our personal data, process it and sell it to the highest bidder. Not many of us know that we can ourselves see if Facebook is being ‘mischievous’ with us. Open the ads section under settings to see where your data has been used. So let’s say Spotify received your data from Facebook, based on that, they would be able to provide you with music that will most likely fit your taste. It seems trivial but in this day and age where content is being created at an exponentially increasing rate, it would be impossible to go through everything to find something we like. To put perspective on that, YouTube is estimated to upload 500 hours of content every minute. That essentially means that a lifetime of content is uploaded every 2 days. It may be online shopping, holiday booking, travel planning and they all have one goal… to make our lives easier so we continue using their platforms. In the case of Facebook, we have a friend that ensures that we get the best options to choose from. Arguably, Spotify, YouTube and Facebook are luxury goods, however this is also prevalent in healthcare. Let’s dive into a hospital to see how data is changing the way we work. Most hospitals, nowadays, have some sort of digital ticketing/queuing system which still requires you to wait for hours for your treatment. With the increased amount of data and software as a Service Business Intelligence (SaaS BI) tool, hospitals will be able to predict the busiest parts of the day and staff accordingly to deal with these peaks. This will allow hospitals to handle more patients more effectively and hence save more lives in the long run. After getting into your appointment, doctors would be able to have a full view of your entire medical history, if it was shared. This will, in turn, allow them to better understand your history which saves time and provides a more accurate diagnosis. These are two very simple examples which only can work effectively when medical data is shared. A third and less obvious example; what if the medical data was given to insurance companies? The fear is that with access to medical data, we will be charged additionally for all the problems they will find out about. But I argue differently. With more data available using analytical tools, insurance companies would be able to better personalize insurance offers which could actually lead to cheaper premiums due to the removal of unnecessary coverage. On top of that, insurance companies will be able to better reward people for taking steps to maintain good health. Lastly, with access to medical data, insurers will be able to better identify insurance fraud leading to more applicants being able to claim insurance when required. There is always a risk that some companies will implement some unfair practices leading to increased premiums. However, with the growing digital economy and a multitude of options, these companies are likely to be outcompeted in the free market, making them unsustainable in the long run. Whilst this is something that will arise in the future, let’s look at it in a very contemporary context - data analytics in Political Campaigns. Before diving into the data analytics of campaigning, I want to highlight that a campaign is defined as ‘a planned group of especially political, business, or military activities that are intended to achieve a particular aim.’  In the case of political campaigns, the focus is to convince those who are on the fence to support your party. Long before the infamy of Cambridge Analytica, campaigners have been collecting polling data to decide how to target their campaigns. So why are we suddenly so afraid? Well, mostly it is thanks to our favourite six-inch toy that we never stop playing with. Due to advancements in smartphone technology, we are becoming far more connected to the internet, which in turn leads to more data collected on us. This was the cost of a ‘free’ internet. The free internet came with the major benefit of allowing everyone a chance of getting access. That meant that companies needed a different way to make money online, hence the rise of data collection. Initially, starting out as a harmless tool to provide advertisers with the attention of relevant potential-customers. It has now evolved into a behemoth that not only provides the things we may like but also tries to shift our preferences ever so slightly. Doesn’t seem so bad, but these subtle nudges to shift our opinions slowly push us further and further down the extreme path we are on - which is proven by the increased polarization (shown in multiple studies [1] [2] [3] [4]) around the world. “Donald Trump’s 2016 digital campaign director claimed to have run 5.9 million visual ads on Facebook, in contrast to Hillary Clinton’s 66,000”- The Great Hack. This statement made at the end of The Great Hack further highlights that this negative opinion on data analytics is also due to some tactics of fear mongering and misrepresentation of information. Without any context, it seems like Donald Trump paid to win an election. Then you consider the fact that in total Hillary Clinton spent 1.4 Billion compared to Trump’s 957.6 Million on their respective campaigns. The main reason Trump spent more on online ads was that his fundraising had lagged behind Hillary Clinton, so he had missed out on the opportunity to spend on TV ads. There are so many examples of data being used to make our lives better, but at the end of the day, data analytics is just a tool. In the hands of the right person, it could bring unprecedented benefits to society. If we go down the extreme path of fearing the tool, we have lots to lose. That being said, I still highly recommend everyone to find out what is happening with your data. Knowledge is power, and we can learn a lot about ourselves from the way our data is being used.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
