<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/daniel.harris/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-08-27T20:35:44+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/daniel.harris/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Portuguese Drug Decriminalisation – Has it Worked?</title>
      <link href="/Portuguese-Drug-Decriminalisation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Portuguese Drug Decriminalisation – Has it Worked?" />
      <published>2019-07-10T16:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-10T16:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Portuguese-Drug-Decriminalisation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Portuguese-Drug-Decriminalisation">&lt;p&gt;In 2001, Portugal became a global leader in the war against drugs when it
decriminalised the possession and consumption of all illegal substances. When
this topic comes up in conversation, most people (especially those from the UK
and the US) are rather shocked when they find out. Two obvious questions then
arise. Firstly, how and why could a traditionally conservative country, tucked
away at the edge of Europe, just decriminalise all drugs? The second question
is, of course, did it work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background to this article&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is inspired by a university project that I completed whilst
spending 5 months in Lisbon. The interviews referenced are personal interviews
that I completed in April, 2019. Some have been translated from Portuguese to
English. The three interviews I will reference are of the following people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;João Santa Maria&lt;/em&gt; – Peer mediator in the NGO IN-Mouraria – a harm reduction
centre for drug users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brendan Hughes&lt;/em&gt; – Principal Scientist and expert in Drug Legislation at the
European Monitoring Centre for Drugs and Drug Addiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;João Goulão&lt;/em&gt; – Director of SICAD, the government department for Intervention
on Addictive Behaviours and Dependencies, and the architect for Portugal’s drug
policy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The History&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Portugal’s decision to decriminalise drugs cannot be understood without first
looking at the recent history of the country. From 1933 to 1974, Portugal was
under the rule of the Estado Novo regime, a right-wing, Catholic, authoritarian
government led by Antonio Salazar. If this name sounds familiar, it’s because it
was the inspiration behind Salazar Slytherin, as J.K. Rowling used to live and
teach in Porto. Portugal was shut off from the outside world, with its only
neighbouring country Spain under a similarly restrictive right-wing
dictatorship, so Portugal “missed out on the experimentation and mind-expanding
culture of the 1960s.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the colonial troops came back from Africa, they brought cannabis with them;
soon after, heroin entered the country. As João Santa Maria explains, “freedom
gave us the right to do whatever we wanted.” However, there would be
consequences to this liberty. By the end of the 90s, heroin addiction, HIV and
Hepatitis C had ravaged the country. In truth, nobody quite knows how many
people were addicted, but it’s estimated that 1 in 10 people were using heroin,
1 in 100 were battling heroin addiction, and HIV rates reached a high of 104.2
new cases per million in 2000. To put that into context, the current HIV rate is
4.2 per million. One of the most important things to understand is that heroin
use was not limited to a certain class of people. Bankers, lawyers, doctors,
teachers; João Goulão remembers how everybody seemed to know a heroin addict. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, implementing wide-scale change and challenging the social norms of a drug
policy was a far more realistic and achievable task in Portugal than it would be
in the UK or the US today. Furthermore, the policy was not a result of left-wing
liberalisation, as some people might assume. The motivation, as explained, was a
response to a health crisis, not an ideological movement. In 2001, the new
decriminalisation law was implemented and although there have been some small
alterations, it essentially remains the same to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, it is important to address exactly what decriminalisation
actually means. Brendan Hughes has made a very useful video
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v9NKhpujqOXc&quot;&gt;www.youtube.com/watch?v9NKhpujqOXc&lt;/a&gt;)
which I highly recommend watching. To explain it briefly, decriminalisation is
&lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; the same as legalisation. In the diagram below, taken from Hughes’
video, the red dots indicated illegal activity, and the green dots, legal
activity. Decriminalisation, or a non-criminal offence, does not pass the line
from criminal to legal. It simply becomes an administrative offence, rather than
a criminal one. For example, bad parking is not a criminal offence, but may
still be fined and punished. The same can be said for the possession and
consumption of illegal substances in Portugal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//drug-decriminalisation.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Image result for drug decriminalisation explained&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main issues with decriminalisation in Portugal, and across the world,
is that the general public does not seem to understand what it entails. In
Lisbon, this is not helped by the fact that tourist areas are filled with ‘drug
dealers’, who offer unsuspecting tourists cannabis, hashish and cocaine. The
drugs are almost always fake (which is why the police do not intervene), but
this gives visitors the impression that drugs are legal in Portugal which
definitely muddies the water. Another issue is that the concept of
decriminalisation has become incredibly and dangerously politicised. Here is an
extract from my interview with Brendan, wherein he concisely details the issues
with decriminalisation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brendan Hughes: “From what I see, a chunk of it is to with this horrible word
decriminalisation, which evokes so many feelings in different people, despite
the fact that most of them don’t actually know what it is or what it means. They
imagine it to mean something, and therefore either they are greatly in favour of
what they think it means, or they are greatly against. So, they are in favour
because it means people don’t get criminal records, or people get treated and
treated as humans, and they have dignity, and you take the drug users away from
contact with the police or the criminal justice system. And people are against
it because they think that it takes away the threat, and it suggests somehow
society considers that this offence isn’t particularly that bad after all and
therefore it will encourage a bunch of other people to do it - those are the
main arguments. And because neither of them are fully correct - but again,
people don’t really seem to talk so much about the facts.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Me: “And, you know, that decriminalisation doesn’t lead to increased use.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brendan Hughes: “It doesn’t. We don’t know! It doesn’t lead to anything
predictable.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Me: “It’s not about liberalisation. And I guess I think some people think that
it’s a left-wing policy.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brendan Hughes: “And that’s what I say. People think it’s a badge, and it’s
either a badge of achievement to say that you’ve done it, or it’s a badge of
achievement to say that you’ve resisted it, when neither side really sees the
full picture.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Extract from my interview with Brendan Hughes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the politics, what have been the quantifiable outcomes of the policy?
Well, it is not a simple answer. Statistically speaking, Portugal has
dramatically improved. HIV rates have plummeted, overall drug use is down,
though Hepatitis C and problem drug use are still an issue. If you are caught
with an illegal substance, you are either fined, given a warning, or sent to a
commission. These commissions have the mantra of ‘treatment before punishment’,
and the vast majority of cases are dismissed. If you are a drug addict, then
there is no possibility of a fine, only treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of policing, the local authorities rarely bother anybody on the street,
and it is extremely common to smell cannabis at any time of the day. The
attitude towards drug addicts has also improved, and heroin-assisted treatment
centres, in Lisbon, are finally about to open, having been promised for over two
years. The improvements listed above definitely qualify as drastic progress, in
comparison to where Portugal was in the 80s and the 90s, yet it would be an
oversimplification to credit all of this to decriminalisation. João Goulão has
detailed how they could have done the whole policy without decriminalisation,
and still put in place the social services and commissions that exist today. In
fact, there is definitely a symbolic element to Portuguese decriminalisation;
allowing the Portuguese population the freedoms that they had so badly missed
for the majority of the 20th century. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, upon speaking to various street teams involved with drug use, homelessness
and other issues, I discovered that there is definitely the feeling that the
policy did not go far enough; some believe that legalisation and regulation are
the only solutions. Financing, from the state and local governments, has
dwindled, and drug users still feel punished purely for being drug users. Though
people are more accepting, Santa Maria notes that, “although they support our
work, they don’t want to deal with it on their own doorstep”. When I asked João
Goulão about these complaints, he responded in an empathetic but pragmatic way.
It is clear that he cares about how his policy is perceived by those it affects,
but being an activist and being a politician are two separate things; in charge
of a delicate political balancing act, it is a tricky task to please
politicians, the public and drug users all at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The global trend towards cannabis legalisation is also causing problems. Part of
the basis for the entire Portuguese policy is that there is no such thing as
‘hard’ drugs and ‘soft’ drugs; all of them are treated as equal. However, with
other countries starting to legalise cannabis, this creates a sticky situation
for the Portuguese. It would be very difficult, if not impossible, to justify
the legalisation of cannabis; if all drugs are equally ‘good’ or ‘bad’, then if
you legalise one, you must legalise them all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking ahead - Is Portugal an example to follow?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I stated earlier, it is hard to label the policy in a binary sense of ‘it
works’ or ‘it does not work’. That said, I find it difficult not to see the
Portuguese policy as progress in the right direction. There are clearly some
issues, but these generally take the form of improvements that need to be made,
rather than fundamental problems of the policy itself. As more and more
countries start to think about and implement similar policies, the Portuguese
2001 legislation is still relevant nearly twenty years later. Whether or not it
serves as an example or model for other countries is debatable. Drug policy is
very nuanced, and each individual country has its own idiosyncrasies and culture
that would affect whether decriminalisation would work. To try and imitate the
Portuguese success by replicating them would not work; the policy was reacting
to a specific situation at a specific time. However, using the Portuguese as an
inspiration of alternative policymaking, and thus reviewing our own beliefs
about drug and drug policy could be a way forward. Too often, we follow the
dogma that we have been taught by friends, family, politicians, looking for an
easy, ‘one size fits all’ answer to the very difficult question of drug policy.
The Portuguese have shown us that there is another way, and maybe we should take
note.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Daniel Harris</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In 2001, Portugal became a global leader in the war against drugs when it decriminalised the possession and consumption of all illegal substances. When this topic comes up in conversation, most people (especially those from the UK and the US) are rather shocked when they find out. Two obvious questions then arise. Firstly, how and why could a traditionally conservative country, tucked away at the edge of Europe, just decriminalise all drugs? The second question is, of course, did it work? Background to this article This article is inspired by a university project that I completed whilst spending 5 months in Lisbon. The interviews referenced are personal interviews that I completed in April, 2019. Some have been translated from Portuguese to English. The three interviews I will reference are of the following people: João Santa Maria – Peer mediator in the NGO IN-Mouraria – a harm reduction centre for drug users. Brendan Hughes – Principal Scientist and expert in Drug Legislation at the European Monitoring Centre for Drugs and Drug Addiction. João Goulão – Director of SICAD, the government department for Intervention on Addictive Behaviours and Dependencies, and the architect for Portugal’s drug policy.  The History Portugal’s decision to decriminalise drugs cannot be understood without first looking at the recent history of the country. From 1933 to 1974, Portugal was under the rule of the Estado Novo regime, a right-wing, Catholic, authoritarian government led by Antonio Salazar. If this name sounds familiar, it’s because it was the inspiration behind Salazar Slytherin, as J.K. Rowling used to live and teach in Porto. Portugal was shut off from the outside world, with its only neighbouring country Spain under a similarly restrictive right-wing dictatorship, so Portugal “missed out on the experimentation and mind-expanding culture of the 1960s.”  When the colonial troops came back from Africa, they brought cannabis with them; soon after, heroin entered the country. As João Santa Maria explains, “freedom gave us the right to do whatever we wanted.” However, there would be consequences to this liberty. By the end of the 90s, heroin addiction, HIV and Hepatitis C had ravaged the country. In truth, nobody quite knows how many people were addicted, but it’s estimated that 1 in 10 people were using heroin, 1 in 100 were battling heroin addiction, and HIV rates reached a high of 104.2 new cases per million in 2000. To put that into context, the current HIV rate is 4.2 per million. One of the most important things to understand is that heroin use was not limited to a certain class of people. Bankers, lawyers, doctors, teachers; João Goulão remembers how everybody seemed to know a heroin addict.  Thus, implementing wide-scale change and challenging the social norms of a drug policy was a far more realistic and achievable task in Portugal than it would be in the UK or the US today. Furthermore, the policy was not a result of left-wing liberalisation, as some people might assume. The motivation, as explained, was a response to a health crisis, not an ideological movement. In 2001, the new decriminalisation law was implemented and although there have been some small alterations, it essentially remains the same to this day. At this point, it is important to address exactly what decriminalisation actually means. Brendan Hughes has made a very useful video (www.youtube.com/watch?v9NKhpujqOXc) which I highly recommend watching. To explain it briefly, decriminalisation is not the same as legalisation. In the diagram below, taken from Hughes’ video, the red dots indicated illegal activity, and the green dots, legal activity. Decriminalisation, or a non-criminal offence, does not pass the line from criminal to legal. It simply becomes an administrative offence, rather than a criminal one. For example, bad parking is not a criminal offence, but may still be fined and punished. The same can be said for the possession and consumption of illegal substances in Portugal. Image result for drug decriminalisation explained One of the main issues with decriminalisation in Portugal, and across the world, is that the general public does not seem to understand what it entails. In Lisbon, this is not helped by the fact that tourist areas are filled with ‘drug dealers’, who offer unsuspecting tourists cannabis, hashish and cocaine. The drugs are almost always fake (which is why the police do not intervene), but this gives visitors the impression that drugs are legal in Portugal which definitely muddies the water. Another issue is that the concept of decriminalisation has become incredibly and dangerously politicised. Here is an extract from my interview with Brendan, wherein he concisely details the issues with decriminalisation: Brendan Hughes: “From what I see, a chunk of it is to with this horrible word decriminalisation, which evokes so many feelings in different people, despite the fact that most of them don’t actually know what it is or what it means. They imagine it to mean something, and therefore either they are greatly in favour of what they think it means, or they are greatly against. So, they are in favour because it means people don’t get criminal records, or people get treated and treated as humans, and they have dignity, and you take the drug users away from contact with the police or the criminal justice system. And people are against it because they think that it takes away the threat, and it suggests somehow society considers that this offence isn’t particularly that bad after all and therefore it will encourage a bunch of other people to do it - those are the main arguments. And because neither of them are fully correct - but again, people don’t really seem to talk so much about the facts.” Me: “And, you know, that decriminalisation doesn’t lead to increased use.” Brendan Hughes: “It doesn’t. We don’t know! It doesn’t lead to anything predictable.” Me: “It’s not about liberalisation. And I guess I think some people think that it’s a left-wing policy.” Brendan Hughes: “And that’s what I say. People think it’s a badge, and it’s either a badge of achievement to say that you’ve done it, or it’s a badge of achievement to say that you’ve resisted it, when neither side really sees the full picture.” (Extract from my interview with Brendan Hughes). The Results Beyond the politics, what have been the quantifiable outcomes of the policy? Well, it is not a simple answer. Statistically speaking, Portugal has dramatically improved. HIV rates have plummeted, overall drug use is down, though Hepatitis C and problem drug use are still an issue. If you are caught with an illegal substance, you are either fined, given a warning, or sent to a commission. These commissions have the mantra of ‘treatment before punishment’, and the vast majority of cases are dismissed. If you are a drug addict, then there is no possibility of a fine, only treatment. In terms of policing, the local authorities rarely bother anybody on the street, and it is extremely common to smell cannabis at any time of the day. The attitude towards drug addicts has also improved, and heroin-assisted treatment centres, in Lisbon, are finally about to open, having been promised for over two years. The improvements listed above definitely qualify as drastic progress, in comparison to where Portugal was in the 80s and the 90s, yet it would be an oversimplification to credit all of this to decriminalisation. João Goulão has detailed how they could have done the whole policy without decriminalisation, and still put in place the social services and commissions that exist today. In fact, there is definitely a symbolic element to Portuguese decriminalisation; allowing the Portuguese population the freedoms that they had so badly missed for the majority of the 20th century.  Yet, upon speaking to various street teams involved with drug use, homelessness and other issues, I discovered that there is definitely the feeling that the policy did not go far enough; some believe that legalisation and regulation are the only solutions. Financing, from the state and local governments, has dwindled, and drug users still feel punished purely for being drug users. Though people are more accepting, Santa Maria notes that, “although they support our work, they don’t want to deal with it on their own doorstep”. When I asked João Goulão about these complaints, he responded in an empathetic but pragmatic way. It is clear that he cares about how his policy is perceived by those it affects, but being an activist and being a politician are two separate things; in charge of a delicate political balancing act, it is a tricky task to please politicians, the public and drug users all at the same time. The global trend towards cannabis legalisation is also causing problems. Part of the basis for the entire Portuguese policy is that there is no such thing as ‘hard’ drugs and ‘soft’ drugs; all of them are treated as equal. However, with other countries starting to legalise cannabis, this creates a sticky situation for the Portuguese. It would be very difficult, if not impossible, to justify the legalisation of cannabis; if all drugs are equally ‘good’ or ‘bad’, then if you legalise one, you must legalise them all. Looking ahead - Is Portugal an example to follow? As I stated earlier, it is hard to label the policy in a binary sense of ‘it works’ or ‘it does not work’. That said, I find it difficult not to see the Portuguese policy as progress in the right direction. There are clearly some issues, but these generally take the form of improvements that need to be made, rather than fundamental problems of the policy itself. As more and more countries start to think about and implement similar policies, the Portuguese 2001 legislation is still relevant nearly twenty years later. Whether or not it serves as an example or model for other countries is debatable. Drug policy is very nuanced, and each individual country has its own idiosyncrasies and culture that would affect whether decriminalisation would work. To try and imitate the Portuguese success by replicating them would not work; the policy was reacting to a specific situation at a specific time. However, using the Portuguese as an inspiration of alternative policymaking, and thus reviewing our own beliefs about drug and drug policy could be a way forward. Too often, we follow the dogma that we have been taught by friends, family, politicians, looking for an easy, ‘one size fits all’ answer to the very difficult question of drug policy. The Portuguese have shown us that there is another way, and maybe we should take note.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Can Effective Altruism Truly Work?</title>
      <link href="/Effective-Altruism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can Effective Altruism Truly Work?" />
      <published>2019-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Effective-Altruism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Effective-Altruism">&lt;p&gt;If I told you about a $60 million project aimed at providing water pumps for villages in Africa to 10 million people backed by the US government and various celebrities, you would probably think it’s a sound idea. The way the project actually works, is that the pump is connected to a merry-go-round and as children play on the apparatus, the energy is used to power the pump. It sounds like a great idea, which is why in 2006 this very project was put into place. However, it turned out to be a complete disaster. After some number crunching, it was calculated that children would have to be playing on the roundabout non-stop for 27 hours each day to reach the water production targets set by the initiative. Moreover, simply investing the money into regular water pumps would have been far less expensive and more efficient. As a different water NGO put it; “their marketing is perfect, but the final idea does not work.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The takeaway here is not about water pumps, or even water aid in general. This is but one of hundreds of examples of &lt;em&gt;heart over head&lt;/em&gt; charity. In a world which is inundated with people who need help, it is becoming increasingly hard to know how and where we should give our time and money. Indeed, I would argue that we all experience “charity fatigue”; with so many causes available, it becomes increasingly difficult for an individual charity to stand out. Consequently, charities turn to shock advertising to draw our attention – think of heart-breaking pictures of starving children. By using this visceral imagery, the charities are appealing directly to your heart, to your emotions. They are not asking you to think about the cause, but to believe in it; two very different propositions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, giving any sort of charity is better than giving none at all. However, for those looking for a more critical and rational approach to charity, I would highly suggest examining effective altruism. Simply put, effective altruism is a quasi-utilitarian form of charity. It aims to do the most good possible with the resources available. As Peter Singer, one of the gurus of the theory, puts it;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s important because it combines both the heart and the head. The heart, of course, you feel… But it’s really important to use the head as well to make sure that what you do is effective and well-directed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example that Singer gives, that I think concisely explains how one would practically apply the theory. In this instance, he talks about service dogs for blind people, a cause which most definitely fits the criteria of ‘pulling at the heartstrings.’ It costs about $40,000 in the US to train a guide dog and to train the recipient so that the guide dog can be of effective help to the blind person. It costs somewhere between $20 and $50 to cure a blind person in a developing country, if they have trachoma. After doing the maths, it works out that you could provide one guide dog for one blind American, or you could cure between 400 and 2,000 people of blindness. He finishes by stating that he thinks it’s perfectly clear what the better thing to do is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find his argument truly compelling, and in recent years it has become increasingly relevant in my own personal life. After completing various volunteer roles, I became fully aware of the importance and necessity of critically examining and evaluating our altruistic efforts. Indeed, volunteering serves as a very good example of ineffective altruism. International volunteers are usually low-skilled, studying or recently graduated young people from affluent countries. Often, they come for short periods of time, do not speak the local language, and do not have expertise in the field of work that they are helping in. A particular issue in South America and other developing parts of the world, these volunteers are frequently assumed to have more knowledge and relevant skills, purely because they come from more developed countries. Add into the mix the issues of voluntourism, and what you are left with is a situation where volunteers do not benefit, or even harm the local community. We all love the idea of helping other people, but unfortunately it is not so simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economics of volunteering are unconvincing at best, and I am going to use myself as an example to demonstrate it. A bit of background first; I spent five months volunteering in an NGO in a very small town near Cusco, Peru. The NGO works with disabled and disadvantaged children, and my work specifically consisted of helping out at a school for disabled children and also a care home for children who cannot live with their parents. I speak Spanish and have relevant work experience with children, so I, at least, was able to offset some of the issues that I mentioned earlier. However, a deeper look at the money is where problems start to arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost of return flights = £600&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accommodation costs for 5 months= £1,600&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living costs = £40/week x 20 = £800&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total = £3000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, even without taking into account my various trips to other South American countries whilst I was there, and any other additional costs, we are looking at a value of at least £3,000. When people ask me about the experience, I always say that it is one of the best things I have done in my life, and I felt that I made a real positive impact on the people I worked with. But asking about my experience is not the question that should be asked. As an effective altruist, the real question is, was the help I gave worth what a £3,000 investment could have done in my local area? In my mind, the answer is clearly no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Herein lies one of the main problems with effective altruism. Altruism is, inevitably, emotional and personal. It is very hard to simply give without caring at all. A consequence of this is that we, the giver, also gain something through the act of giving. I would argue, therefore, that it is impossible to be altruistic in a purely selfless way. Whether personal gain is your primary aim or not, some part of giving away your time or your money positively benefits yourself. And here it gets complicated. How can we possibly be effective altruists, if we are at the same time, emotional altruists? How is it possible to analyse and calculate the best possible use of your money, without letting your subconscious emotions affect this decision? Peter Singer does come up with an answer for this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Many effective altruists say that in doing good, they feel good. Effective altruists directly benefit others, but indirectly they often benefit themselves. If doing the most you can for others means that you are also flourishing, then that is the best possible outcome for everyone.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not disagree with him, but like most things, this is far simpler in theory than in practice. It is near-impossible to act without any self-interest, and the line between benefiting ourselves and benefiting other people is very thin. Once the giver starts to achieve their own goals through giving to charity, then it is hard for the process to not become emotional rather than rational. Moreover, it is human nature to generally favour ourselves and people similar to us, instead of others who may need and deserve the help more. It is easier to relate to somebody with whom we share common traits or experiences; another potential pitfall of where our emotions interfere with the aim of being rational and critical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory also suffers from the same critiques that utilitarianism faces. Strictly adhering to benefitting the greatest number of people, instead of individual cases, can lead to some particularly troubling moral decisions. A good example of this was given in the Guardian; “would you really save a large bag of cash from a burning building rather than your neighbour’s terrified child, even if you could donate that cash and save the lives of a thousand strangers?” It’s good food for thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with these two valid criticisms, I am still a firm believer in effective altruism. Perhaps its applications are limited in practice, and not everyone has the luxury of being able to take the time or have the money, to give to charity in such a specific way. Yet, I believe that many people would greatly benefit by at least being aware of the theory and taking inspiration from it. The more rational and critical we can be, the better equipped we are to make informed, successful and effective altruistic decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An image that helps visualise the theory of effective altruism -&amp;gt; https://blog.ted.com/why-how-effective-altruism-peter-singer-visualized/ (Blog)&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Daniel Harris</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">If I told you about a $60 million project aimed at providing water pumps for villages in Africa to 10 million people backed by the US government and various celebrities, you would probably think it’s a sound idea. The way the project actually works, is that the pump is connected to a merry-go-round and as children play on the apparatus, the energy is used to power the pump. It sounds like a great idea, which is why in 2006 this very project was put into place. However, it turned out to be a complete disaster. After some number crunching, it was calculated that children would have to be playing on the roundabout non-stop for 27 hours each day to reach the water production targets set by the initiative. Moreover, simply investing the money into regular water pumps would have been far less expensive and more efficient. As a different water NGO put it; “their marketing is perfect, but the final idea does not work.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">“It’s hard to be down when you’re up” – Control, Understanding and The City.</title>
      <link href="/Control-Understanding-and-The-City" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“It’s hard to be down when you’re up” – Control, Understanding and The City." />
      <published>2019-05-14T23:18:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-14T23:18:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Control-Understanding-and-The-City</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Control-Understanding-and-The-City">&lt;p&gt;“I wonder what is the source of this pleasure of “seeing the whole,” of looking
down on, totalizing the most immoderate of human texts. To be lifted to the
summit of the World Trade Center is to be lifted out of the city’s grasp… It’s
hard to be down when you’re up.” Michel de Certeau&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This quote from French psychoanalyst Michel de Certeau condenses a feeling that
many will have had, though cannot quite fully explain: Why do we take pleasure
in viewpoints, lookouts and the top floors of skyscrapers? What is it about
these vantage points that give us that ‘larger than life’ feeling?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city is a confusing entity. Whether it has been meticulously planned, or has
simply developed naturally over centuries, it is often incredibly difficult to
truly understand. When arriving for the first time, we are hit with a barrage of
new sights, smells, people and culture. Indeed, the first reaction is usually to
find something to orient ourselves, finding a system or service that we know
exists in other similar cities that we have already inhabited, and then working
from there. Examples of this could be a train station, bank, church,
supermarket; by finding universal facilities that exist in nearly all cities, it
becomes easier to navigate a new environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Settling in to a new urban environment can be seen as matching and modifying an
old system of living to fit a new and different place. The building blocks of
how we live, work and function will be similar, but the specificities of how we
do it must adapt. Once you are settled, you solidify this routine until it
becomes second nature. You might even forget the way that you used to live, the
consequence of becoming accustomed to a new style of living, in a city that you
now call home. When eventually you move on, the same process is repeated. Now
you may draw on multiple past experiences, but the process is essentially the
same. By using tried and tested formulas, we manage our inherent human desire
for routine, and implement these plans on whatever the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The city also falls into this dual scripting. It is often branded as
  “evil”, harbouring the underbelly of modern society, while at the same time,
  it is heralded as the pinnacle of civilization, as man’s triumph over the
  barbarism of uncivilized earlier times and as a hallmark of the success of
  the project for pushing forwards the frontier of a wild and untamed nature.”
  Maria Kaika&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawing on what Kaika comments, it can be argued that the city, in its most
basic form, is the representation of the human need to exercise control over
their surroundings. We do not wish to simply live in nature but to tame it,
master it, and modify it for our own desires. Moreover, this does not only apply
to the design of cities themselves but the way in which an individual chooses to
inhabit cities. We create routines, schedules and centre our whole way of living
around having control. The very thought of being out of control can lead to
serious mental health consequences, anxiety and a lack of self-worth. Although,
as stated before in this article, the building blocks of our lives are generally
constant and non-changeable, having the autonomy to decide the details, the
small things, is absolutely key. Your choice of supermarket, regular coffee
shop, the route you take to work; all of these are small but significant ways in
which we exert control over our schedules. Our habits are not just customs we
coincidentally act out, but an integral part of how we inhabit a city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning to de Certeau, it is this relationship between control, understanding
and the city, that explains our love for skyscrapers, viewpoints and lookouts.
By simply being above all of the chaos of the city, above of all the individuals
going about their normal routines, we exercise control not just of ourselves,
but of the very city itself. New York, La Paz and Lisbon all provide perfect
examples of confusing, alive, bustling cities, with spectacular and stunning
lookouts. Suddenly, all of the confusion and anxiety of occupying the city is
lost, and the city is legible and intelligible. We transform into, as de Certeau
explains, a ‘god’, gaining the omniscient perspective that is simply not
possible from the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“His elevation transfigures him into a voyeur. It puts him at a distance. It
  transforms the bewitching world by which one was “possessed” into a text
  that lies before one’s eyes. It allows one to read it, to be a solar Eye,
  looking down like a god.” Michel de Certeau&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, power is the key dynamic at play. Rather than the being the
inhabitant, the apprehensive pedestrian who is just trying to survive in a
confusing and ever-changing environment, all of us wish to be, at least for a
while, sitting up on high reading and understanding the beauty and confusion of
the city. It sure is hard to be down when you are up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//harris_image1.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//harris_image2.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//harris_image3.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//harris_image4.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//harris_image5.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;A selection of my own photos, demonstrating how elevation helps to understand
the city.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Daniel Harris</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“I wonder what is the source of this pleasure of “seeing the whole,” of looking down on, totalizing the most immoderate of human texts. To be lifted to the summit of the World Trade Center is to be lifted out of the city’s grasp… It’s hard to be down when you’re up.” Michel de Certeau This quote from French psychoanalyst Michel de Certeau condenses a feeling that many will have had, though cannot quite fully explain: Why do we take pleasure in viewpoints, lookouts and the top floors of skyscrapers? What is it about these vantage points that give us that ‘larger than life’ feeling? The city is a confusing entity. Whether it has been meticulously planned, or has simply developed naturally over centuries, it is often incredibly difficult to truly understand. When arriving for the first time, we are hit with a barrage of new sights, smells, people and culture. Indeed, the first reaction is usually to find something to orient ourselves, finding a system or service that we know exists in other similar cities that we have already inhabited, and then working from there. Examples of this could be a train station, bank, church, supermarket; by finding universal facilities that exist in nearly all cities, it becomes easier to navigate a new environment. Settling in to a new urban environment can be seen as matching and modifying an old system of living to fit a new and different place. The building blocks of how we live, work and function will be similar, but the specificities of how we do it must adapt. Once you are settled, you solidify this routine until it becomes second nature. You might even forget the way that you used to live, the consequence of becoming accustomed to a new style of living, in a city that you now call home. When eventually you move on, the same process is repeated. Now you may draw on multiple past experiences, but the process is essentially the same. By using tried and tested formulas, we manage our inherent human desire for routine, and implement these plans on whatever the environment. “The city also falls into this dual scripting. It is often branded as “evil”, harbouring the underbelly of modern society, while at the same time, it is heralded as the pinnacle of civilization, as man’s triumph over the barbarism of uncivilized earlier times and as a hallmark of the success of the project for pushing forwards the frontier of a wild and untamed nature.” Maria Kaika Drawing on what Kaika comments, it can be argued that the city, in its most basic form, is the representation of the human need to exercise control over their surroundings. We do not wish to simply live in nature but to tame it, master it, and modify it for our own desires. Moreover, this does not only apply to the design of cities themselves but the way in which an individual chooses to inhabit cities. We create routines, schedules and centre our whole way of living around having control. The very thought of being out of control can lead to serious mental health consequences, anxiety and a lack of self-worth. Although, as stated before in this article, the building blocks of our lives are generally constant and non-changeable, having the autonomy to decide the details, the small things, is absolutely key. Your choice of supermarket, regular coffee shop, the route you take to work; all of these are small but significant ways in which we exert control over our schedules. Our habits are not just customs we coincidentally act out, but an integral part of how we inhabit a city. Returning to de Certeau, it is this relationship between control, understanding and the city, that explains our love for skyscrapers, viewpoints and lookouts. By simply being above all of the chaos of the city, above of all the individuals going about their normal routines, we exercise control not just of ourselves, but of the very city itself. New York, La Paz and Lisbon all provide perfect examples of confusing, alive, bustling cities, with spectacular and stunning lookouts. Suddenly, all of the confusion and anxiety of occupying the city is lost, and the city is legible and intelligible. We transform into, as de Certeau explains, a ‘god’, gaining the omniscient perspective that is simply not possible from the ground. “His elevation transfigures him into a voyeur. It puts him at a distance. It transforms the bewitching world by which one was “possessed” into a text that lies before one’s eyes. It allows one to read it, to be a solar Eye, looking down like a god.” Michel de Certeau Once again, power is the key dynamic at play. Rather than the being the inhabitant, the apprehensive pedestrian who is just trying to survive in a confusing and ever-changing environment, all of us wish to be, at least for a while, sitting up on high reading and understanding the beauty and confusion of the city. It sure is hard to be down when you are up. A selection of my own photos, demonstrating how elevation helps to understand the city.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">And the Academy Award goes to…Mexico?</title>
      <link href="/Academy-Award-Mexico" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="And the Academy Award goes to…Mexico?" />
      <published>2019-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Academy-Award-Mexico</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Academy-Award-Mexico">&lt;p&gt;I love the Oscars. I acknowledge this without a hint of shame and I’m more than happy to admit it. With the television ratings slumping to 26.6 million in 2018 (a 39% decrease from 2014), and remaining below 30 million for this year’s broadcast, it’s safe to say that I am part of a rare breed – a young person still interested in the Academy Awards. However, the caveat is that I watch the show ‘almost completely ironically’. Every year for the past four years, myself and another film buff nit-pick the entirety of the marathon show. We do have a few reasons for it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, to make the near 240-minute programme bearable, you have to do something a bit more exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, if you think that the Academy Awards are merely a ‘celebration of cinematic excellence’, then you are truly mistaken. There are many different film festivals and ceremonies that take place during the awards season, and there is definitely a debate to be had over which is the most prestigious or important. Whether the Oscars will admit it or not, they feast on the grand spectacle as much as, or perhaps even more than, simply rewarding genuine talent. From #oscarssowhite, to &lt;em&gt;La La Land&lt;/em&gt; winning by mistake, to this year’s host debacle. It is these controversies which make people watch the Oscars. So, by critiquing it, we subconsciously embrace the farce and fanfare of the show. Thus, we make the whole experience of watching it far more enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly and finally, predicting the Oscars is an artform and each year we have just one opportunity to test our skills. I highly recommend Insider’s Youtube Video: “Are the Oscars Rigged?” if you’ve never thought about the logistics of winning Best Picture, or any Academy Award for that matter. To state the obvious, it doesn’t just simply happen on merit. There are tried and tested formulas on how the system works, with each critic or film buff having their own method of guessing the winners. As the great film critic Roger Ebert wrote in 2005:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Shhhhhh. Don’t tell a soul. Close Oscar-watchers (and Academy insiders) know that what you are about to read is true but few like to talk about these things. When it comes to picking Oscar winners, you can study the statistics of the past Oscars in search of patterns and clues, but there are certain influential paradigms that defy and transcend conventional statistical analysis.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He goes on to give a few examples, all of which are worth a read, but my favourite is definitely the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;Having a Period&lt;/strong&gt;: The showiest way to flaunt your budget (besides spending it on astronomical marquee names) is to set your movie in the past, so you can see all the departments – costumes, production design, cinematography, makeup – working hard all the time. It’s astonishing, but the only Best Picture winners in the last 20 years to be set in contemporary times (real or fantasy) were “Rain Man,” “The Silence of the Lambs,” and “American Beauty” – which are also among the few that weren’t historical biographies.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you know (or think you know) the formula, guessing all of the 24 awards is simple…or so it seems. As Ebert notes, “&lt;em&gt;count on at least one surprise, off-the-wall winner&lt;/em&gt;”, and in my experience it is not usually the obscure categories that trip you up, usually it is one of the big ones, such as Best Supporting Actor/Actress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cynic might say that by watching the Oscars, in this manner, we are just making a mockery of the Academy Awards; and, despite its over-exuberance, by ridiculing the show we are also ridiculing the pieces of art that the show is rewarding. Now, I do partially agree with this; the Oscars will, for a lot of people, always be the watermark of good cinema. Moreover, in recent years the Oscars have helped promote smaller indie films that without the Best Picture nomination or win, would never have achieved such success. Indeed, in a world where five films made over US$1 billion in 2018, the past six Best Picture Winners all grossed under US$100 million in the United States. To cite some prime examples, films such as &lt;em&gt;Birdman&lt;/em&gt; (2014) and the &lt;em&gt;Shape of Water&lt;/em&gt; (2017) would never have gotten the exposure that they did, without the Academy Awards, or more specifically, the Academy’s reputation as representing prestigious cinema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said earlier that I watch the Oscars “almost completely ironically” and it is time to address the ‘almost’ part of that statement. There is one part of the annual broadcast that I do take seriously, namely the meteoric rise of ‘New Mexican Cinema’ that surely would have gone largely unnoticed by the general public, but for the Oscars. Now, if you’re thinking, “I am an average film-goer, and I have literally no idea what New Mexican Cinema is”, that’s fine. In fact, I think this is the beauty of this movement; it has quietly infiltrated Hollywood, and apart from film buffs and industry experts, nobody was even aware it was happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I deliberately listed the examples of &lt;em&gt;Birdman&lt;/em&gt; (2014) and the &lt;em&gt;Shape of Water&lt;/em&gt; (2017) earlier, and both of these have Mexican directors: Alejandro González Iñárritu and Guillermo Del Toro, who along with Alfonso Cuarón make ‘Los Tres Amigos’, the leading lights of the second wave of this movement. Incredibly, between the three of them they have won five of the past six Academy Awards for Best Director. They have an astonishing ten Academy Awards between them and show no signs of slowing down. Yet, perhaps what is more impressive is how they have been able to blend this critical success with commercial “Hollywood” box office hits. Remember, these are the very same directors that made &lt;em&gt;Hellboy&lt;/em&gt; (2004), &lt;em&gt;Pacific Rim&lt;/em&gt; (2013), &lt;em&gt;Children of Men&lt;/em&gt; (2006), &lt;em&gt;The Revenant&lt;/em&gt; (2015) and &lt;em&gt;*Harry Potter&lt;/em&gt; and the Prisoner of Azkaban* (2004). Yet, the three have stayed true to their roots as well. They continue to make Spanish language films, with the best and most recent example being Cuarón’s &lt;em&gt;Roma&lt;/em&gt; (2018), winner of three Oscars this year and, in my opinion, robbed of Best Picture. It is available to view on Netflix, and whilst a black and white Spanish language drama about a maid for a middle-class Mexican family might not be everybody’s cup of tea, it is definitely my favourite film of the past few months and worth a watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as a Spanish and Portuguese student, foreign language films have always been more accessible to me than they might be for the average viewer. I know that subtitles can be a little unpalatable for some people, and it is usually easier to relate to something if you have shared culture or understanding. That said, despite all I may critique about the Oscars, they have actually taken note of the genuine movement of foreign cinematic talent that has hijacked the awards over the past few years. By recognising these directors, it validates the movement as a whole, bringing respect and recognition from a global audience. Films such as &lt;em&gt;Y tu Mamá También&lt;/em&gt; (2001), &lt;em&gt;El Laberinto del Fauno&lt;/em&gt; (2006) and &lt;em&gt;Amores Perros&lt;/em&gt; (2001) were all nominated for Oscars in various categories; they were just the first indication of what was to come. Moreover, it is not just directors that are receiving recognition. The cinematographer Emmanuel Lubezki won Best Achievement in Cinematography, three years running from 2013 to 2015, and actors such as Gael García Bernal (&lt;em&gt;Coco&lt;/em&gt;, 2017) and Diego Luna (&lt;em&gt;Rogue One&lt;/em&gt;, 2016) are stepping into the spotlight of Western cinema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I do make fun of the Academy, perhaps a little too much. However, I am somewhat part of the snobbery that make the Oscars what it is; I love the inside jokes, the awards scandals, the predicting of formulas. Even if I critique the ridiculous nature of it, that in and of itself just contributes to the grand annual spectacle. With all the said, what brings me back to the Academy is the small belief that it still does do what it should do; reward some of the best cinema that the world has to offer. And maybe the success of New Mexican Cinema is a sign that the Academy is getting back on track.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Daniel Harris</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I love the Oscars. I acknowledge this without a hint of shame and I’m more than happy to admit it. With the television ratings slumping to 26.6 million in 2018 (a 39% decrease from 2014), and remaining below 30 million for this year’s broadcast, it’s safe to say that I am part of a rare breed – a young person still interested in the Academy Awards. However, the caveat is that I watch the show ‘almost completely ironically’. Every year for the past four years, myself and another film buff nit-pick the entirety of the marathon show. We do have a few reasons for it:</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
