<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/soham.gupta/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-04-10T22:58:02+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/soham.gupta/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Not Peace but a Sword: The New Religious War in Ukraine</title>
      <link href="/Religious-War-In-Ukraine" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Not Peace but a Sword: The New Religious War in Ukraine" />
      <published>2019-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Religious-War-In-Ukraine</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Religious-War-In-Ukraine">&lt;p&gt;The year is 2014. Violent protests have erupted across Ukraine. President Viktor Yanukovych’s perceived pro-Russian policies have angered a large section of the population, who have firmly come out in support of closer ties with the European Union. However, the predominantly Russian-speaking East is not that happy about the prospect of a European alliance. Unfortunately for them, Yanukovych is soon ousted from power by a violent revolution. This new development is not, however, universally acclaimed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly afterwards, armed revolutionaries seize control of the Crimean Parliament and allegedly install a pro-Russian Prime Minister, who quickly calls upon Vladimir Putin for military assistance. Cries of “Putin is my President!” are now commonly heard in the streets of Crimea. Eventually, a referendum is held and the results indicate that the people of Crimea have overwhelmingly voted for union with Russia. Crimea then becomes a part of the Russian Federation, a development condemned by the European Union, the United States and much of the rest of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia and Ukraine share a long inter-woven history. Both of them look upon Kievan Rus as their cultural ancestor – the monarchy that once included much of the East Slavic and Finnic peoples of Europe, and which lasted from the late 9th to the mid-13th century. However, over time, their relationship has grown steadily worse. The events of 2014 are but a modern manifestation of a long-festering division that has only been exacerbated as the years have passed by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, Ukraine is a part of Eastern Europe, a region many people consider to be the heartland of the Eastern Orthodox Church. Known for its hardline stances on many issues of faith and morals, this ancient federation of ecclesiastical communities claims a line of unbroken continuity with the Church of the Apostles. Proponents call it a relatively pure Church, undefiled by the erroneous ideologies of the modern world. Critics call it a reactionary, patriarchal organisation, which still refuses to ordain women and considers abortion to be immoral and sinful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the vast majority of Western European culture and society – the historic stronghold of the Roman Church – has been usurped by the forces of liberalism, secularism and the sexual revolution, the same cannot be said about Eastern Orthodoxy. This is highly ironic, given that the Russian Orthodox Church, in particular, was strongly persecuted by the Soviet Union, as were as the other Slavic Orthodox Churches, such the Serbian, Bulgarian and Romanian Patriarchates. However, since the fall of the USSR, the Orthodox Church has come to wield a level of influence over local politics unseen since the time of the Tsars. While the Russian Federation continues to claim non-affiliation with any religious body as such, the alliance between Putin and the Moscow Patriarchate is the &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religion is a very strong preserver. After all, the Roman Catholic Church – the world’s largest, most powerful and longest-running monarchy – is, in many ways, the only remaining bastion of medieval Western culture. This is easily apparent especially if you visit traditionalist monasteries which still follow the rules in all their strictness. It is, of course, true that even many Roman Catholic priests and bishops don’t practice their faith well and have become lax, but there are still many strongholds of conservatism within that Church―despite the forces of liberalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is true also of the Eastern Orthodox Church, which, in general, suffers much less from the plague of liberals within their hierarchy. Some observers have noted the remarkable similarity between the alliance of Putin and Patriarch Kirill of Moscow today and the traditional diarchy of Byzantium, in which the Emperor and the Patriarch would be the most powerful political figures in the land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, while the Russian Federation may no longer possess the territorial jurisdiction of Kievan Rus, the Patriarchate of Moscow has a much stronger boast to that. The Russian Church claims jurisdiction not merely over Russia but also over all of Ukraine. In fact, the single largest Church in Ukraine continues to be under the jurisdiction of Moscow. It is called the Ukrainian Orthodox Church of the Moscow Patriarchate. It is autonomous, but not autocephalous. In other words, it is mostly self-governing, but not wholly independent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, many of the nationalists of Ukraine have despised what they see as the continued intrusion of Russian imperialist influence in their homeland. And it is precisely such sentiments as these that were responsible, in part, for the splintering of the Orthodox Church in Ukraine into two new denominations – the Ukrainian Orthodox Church of the Kievan Patriarchate and the Ukrainian Autocephalous Orthodox Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to this, there is the Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church, which looks like the Orthodox Church, prays like the Orthodox Church, smells like the Orthodox Church, but is – in fact – a Catholic Church in full communion with Rome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, the Kiev Patriarchate and the Ukrainian Autocephalous Orthodox Church were considered by the rest of the Orthodox world to be nationalist fanatics and schismatics who have damaged the unity of Orthodoxy. The Metropolitan Onufriy, under the authority of the Moscow Patriarch, was considered to be the rightful primate of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, quite recently, the situation has taken a sharp turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Patriarch of Constantinople Bartholomew I, long considered the “first among equals” of the Orthodox Patriarchs has taken it upon himself to grant the Church of Ukraine (specifically the two splinter groups from Moscow) complete independence from Russia. While it is true that the Patriarch of Constantinople does not enjoy the same authority in Orthodoxy that the Pope does in Catholicism, he does have some prerogatives – among them is the responsibility of hearing appeals from the rest of the Orthodox world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has led to the Patriarchate of Moscow excommunicating the Patriarch of Constantinople. And the vast majority of the Orthodox Churches have sided with Moscow. Bartholomew, however, has been undeterred. As a result of his efforts, the two splinter groups have now been united as the “Orthodox Church of Ukraine” with the full blessing and support of Ukrainian President Petro Poroshenko. Their new leader calls himself Metropolitan Epiphany (Dumenko). As of now, no Orthodox Church has given recognition to this new Church apart from Constantinople itself, and it has received heated condemnation not only from Moscow but also from the Primate of Serbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What implications could this have for the political situation? First of all, it is almost without question that the new Orthodox Church will come to represent the face of Ukrainian nationalism against “Russian imperialism”. It is no wonder that President Poroshenko is such an avid supporter of the move. Millions of Ukrainians still consider the Patriarch of Moscow to be their spiritual leaders. This new move represents an opportunity to break that perception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the new Church has also received surprising support from sectors of the Roman Catholic Church. It is very ironic indeed – four centuries ago, nationalism played a very important role in rousing extreme opposition to the Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church, members of which were looked upon as traitors who had defected to Rome. Now, it is the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religious freedom still remains strongly restricted in many parts of Eastern Europe. Russia, for instance, has banned the Jehovah’s Witnesses. There was also a famous attempt to ban the &lt;em&gt;Bhagavad Gita As It Is&lt;/em&gt; in 2011. In 2016, the premises of a Vedic monastery in Nizhny Novgorod were demolished by local authorities, after having been declared illegal a year back. Meanwhile, the Russian Orthodox Church is busy rebuilding Churches demolished during the time of the Soviet Union and is enjoying the presence of Putin at Church services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does the future hold for Russia and Ukraine? Will Russia try to resurrect its orthodox heritage, perhaps even, as some suggest, restore the monarchy? Will we see a new cold war, between Russia and the West, with Ukraine caught in the middle? What is the future for the Orthodox faithful?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, my friends, only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The year is 2014. Violent protests have erupted across Ukraine. President Viktor Yanukovych’s perceived pro-Russian policies have angered a large section of the population, who have firmly come out in support of closer ties with the European Union. However, the predominantly Russian-speaking East is not that happy about the prospect of a European alliance. Unfortunately for them, Yanukovych is soon ousted from power by a violent revolution. This new development is not, however, universally acclaimed.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Most Hated Religion in the World</title>
      <link href="/The-Most-Hated-Religion-in-the-World" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Most Hated Religion in the World" />
      <published>2019-03-07T04:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-07T04:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Most-Hated-Religion-in-the-World</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Most-Hated-Religion-in-the-World">&lt;p&gt;If you were to ask the Joe on the street “Which is the most
hated/persecuted/marginalized religious group in the world?” you would probably
get a range of different answers, depending upon the interviewee’s political
orientation(s).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People leaning towards the left would most likely say, “Islam. Islamophobia is a
big problem in the West. Definitely.” Others leaning towards the right would
probably say “The Jews. They have suffered the most and even now, Israel is
under threat from Islamic fundamentalists. We must stand with Israel.” In India,
it would probably be, “The Hindus! Just look at the Kashmiri Pandits.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I don’t deny that each of these groups has suffered immensely in the past. I
sympathise strongly with anyone who has been persecuted or discriminated against
in the secular sphere on the basis of their race, religion, economic status or
sex. It goes without saying that I condemn all forms of religious bigotry. But
in my humble opinion, neither Islam nor Judaism can claim the title. In my mind,
the most hated religion in the world today is Catholic Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“What?!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know. It sounds strange. But spare me the incredulous look, because I am just
about to back up my claims with extraordinarily strong evidence. But before I do
that, let me tell you my story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I myself was raised in the Hindu community, but after a decade-long search for
the truth, I lost faith in the faith of my forefathers. I am now making my way
across to Christianity, and in all likelihood, I will end up either Roman
Catholic or in Eastern Orthodoxy. I have studied more religions and
denominations than I can remember – from the Ahl-e-Hadith (and the lesser known
Ahl-e-Qur’an) to the long-extinct Zurvanism – and I will soon begin an
undergraduate degree in Theology at the University of Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friends, I can testify with all my heart that there is no religious group
that is more maligned, slandered and attacked in popular culture than the
Catholic Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each and every worldview is built upon some major controlling narrative or the
other. Modern society is the offspring of three great ideological uprisings in
the past, all of which are overtly and vehemently anti-Catholic, either
prominently or tangentially. You might have guessed two of them, but the third
one may surprise you. I am speaking of the Enlightenment, the Protestant
Reformation and the rise of Marxism. Now let’s consider their controlling
narratives one by one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Enlightenment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world had great and immense potential since the evolution of the &lt;em&gt;homo
sapiens&lt;/em&gt;. A great example of this was Europe, which in the classical world was a
great hub of learning, philosophy, art, and science. Great thinkers and minds
arose who tirelessly “stretched forward their hands towards perfection” in
Greece and Rome. All of this was happening – until the rise of Christianity, the
most intolerant branch of which is the Catholic Church. Led by the theocratic
impositions of Constantine, the Catholic Church brought all of Europe under
their tyrannical captivity. Superstition reigned; science was stifled; the
freedom of the heart was curbed; man was put into chains. The growth and
progress of Europe were stunted… until the great Renaissance dawned upon
mankind, and Europe was reborn – a phoenix rising from the ashes. The captivity
of Rome was overthrown and the great continent emerged, to build its future on
its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Protestant Reformation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning, Christ and the Apostles built up the Church and commanded them
to preach the Gospel far and wide. All was going well… but over the centuries,
slowly but gradually, pagan influence began to creep into the Church.
Superstition and idolatry gradually came to cloud the Gospel, and eventually, it
was lost for good! The situation was especially bad in Western Europe, where the
Pope presided in the place of God, reigning down his ungodly tyranny upon the
masses, chaining the Christian and denying him his rightful freedom. The Spirit
of God departed for a while from the pagan Roman church… until at last, the
seeds laid by the great martyrs Wycliffe and Hus bore fruit, and the heroes of
the faith – Luther, Zwingli, and Calvin – emerged. These luminaries showed us
the path and helped us break the chains of Roman tyranny. The Reformation was a
glorious cleansing of the church, and countless souls were freed from the
captivity of the Roman harlot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marxism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History is marked primarily by class-struggle. From ages past, the privileged
(the haves) have oppressed the have-nots. A prime example of this is seen in the
decadent, superstitious Catholic Church. This is an organisation that has
promoted colonialism (the Crusades being a great example) and continues to have
an authoritarian patriarchal structure of clericalism and privilege that
oppresses the common man. To this day, the Pope and his henchmen participate in
the oppression of the masses, by opposing abortion, contraception and denying
women equality by not ordaining them to the priesthood. This organisation must
change, or perish. The common people must arise out of the chains of this
tyranny!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you have been studying the three movements I describe, you will quickly
see that absolutely nothing I have written is an exaggeration. For example, if
you are acquainted with Protestant polemical literature (as I am), you will
notice that many of the terms I have used – “Roman harlot”, “Roman [Babylonian]
captivity”, “freedom of the Christian”, “chains of bondage and superstition”,
“false gospel”, etc. – are not mine, but the exact terms used by Protestants to
this day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice also, another thing: though these movements all originated in Europe,
they have since then been widely disseminated. There are more than 900 million
Protestants around the world (almost an eighth of the world population). The
philosophy of the Enlightenment has spread around the globe as well, as
evidenced by the fact that most of the countries in the world are (or, at least,
claim to be) liberal secular democracies. And, of course, Marxism has claimed
the most populous country in the world as its own and continues to have a loud
presence around the world (particularly among the students and youth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it just me? Am I just seeing it this way because I myself strongly lean RC?
(Well, technically, I began leaning RC after I saw its theology being vastly
misrepresented and slandered in Protestant fundamentalist circles on the
internet). But it’s not just me by any stretch of the imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is what pro-life activist, journalist and Orthodox Jew Ben Shapiro had to
say at a conference in Dana Point, CA: “Unfortunately, the attacks [by radical
leftists] on Catholics have come first and foremost […] It’s really fascinating
to watch, not just from a Jewish perspective. Usually, we’re the first on the
hit list. Now it’s you guys.” Shapiro went on to note several instances of
anti-Catholic prejudice in the popular media. But one could also note the
attitude of contempt several Democrat politicians displayed towards conservative
Catholicism as we see, for example, US Senator Diane Feinstein’s bluntly stated
to the Catholic judicial nominee Amy Barrett, “The dogma lives loudly within
you”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about the historical data? Don’t they prove that the Catholic Church
is, indeed, so to speak, “guilty as charged”? Not so, says non-Catholic
sociologist, University of California Berkeley scholar and Pulitzer
Prize-winning author Rodney Stark, who has written many books on Christian
history, including several defending Catholicism from what he says as unfounded
attacks and slanderous misrepresentations. Among his many works are &lt;em&gt;God’s
Battalions: The Case for the Crusades&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Reformation Myths and Bearing False
Witness: Debunking Centuries of Anti-Catholic Lies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;America, of course, is historically extremely anti-Catholic. And with the
worldwide dominance of American culture as well as the proliferation of
American-style Evangelicalism, anti-Catholicism too has spread around the world.
But don’t take my word for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ryan Reeves is Cambridge scholar and a professor of Church history at
Gordon-Conwell Theological Seminary, one of the eminent Protestant institutions
in the USA. Several of his lectures are available on his YouTube channel (in my
opinion, an invaluable contribution to public education). I highly recommend his
lecture &lt;em&gt;Catholics in America&lt;/em&gt;. In it, Reeves discusses how, historically, large
sections of the Protestant population in America have always tried to,
especially in the face of Catholic immigration, “slander and to mock and to
lampoon Catholics, in an effort to demoralize and ideally to get them to convert
to Protestantism”. (Since Professor Reeves is teaching at a well-respected
Protestant institution, I will similarly assume that he is a Protestant and has
no dog in this fight.) He goes on to discuss historically famous instances of
anti-Catholic propaganda, including the ghost-written 18th century bestseller
autobiography of “Maria Monk”, which claimed to expose scandalous debauchery and
immorality within Catholic convents, and which – according to Dr. Reeves - we
now know to be a complete hoax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-evidently, hatred against Catholics must change due to the simple social
rule that one ought not to be persecuted for one’s beliefs. Here are three
things which I think need to happen in order to help the situation change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, people need to better appreciate and understand the Catholic Church’s
rich and vibrant intellectual history, especially the glories of the Middle Ages - figures like Aquinas, Anselm, Ockham, Peter Abelard, Duns Scotus and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the anti-fideism of Catholic theology needs to be properly recognised
as well (I’m looking at you, Christopher Hitchens). The doctrine of the
interplay and complementary nature of faith and reason, popularised by Aquinas
and officially adopted by the Catholic Church at the First Vatican Council, will
only lead the devout Catholic to a deeper admiration of and respect towards the
sciences, not a fear of them. Hence, we have great Catholic scientists like
Gregor Mendel, George Lemaitre, Roger Bacon, Albertus Magnus and – of course –
Nicolaus Copernicus (who, by the way, was respected and admired by several
Catholic clergymen of his time, including Pope Clement VII). For example, on
November 1, 1536, Cardinal Nikolaus von Schönberg, Archbishop of Capua, wrote to
Copernicus expressing profound admiration, and requesting him to tell him more
about his new cosmology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, people need to remember the mistakes made by Catholics in the past.
Yes, Catholics are not, and have never been, perfect people. They have made
mistakes, like any other group. We must not repeat the errors of antiquity, and
we must remember and learn from them. But, at the same time, we must also
recognise the fact that the Catholic hierarchy (I’m talking about folks like
Popes John Paul II and Francis I) has publicly apologised for many of the past
excesses and sought forgiveness for the same. An institution that is ready to
own up to its mistakes in such a public manner shines a ray of hope for the
world. And it is only such an attitude of humility, repentance, and desire to
change that will help contemporary Catholics overcome the ecclesiastical abuses
and errors of the modern world.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">If you were to ask the Joe on the street “Which is the most hated/persecuted/marginalized religious group in the world?” you would probably get a range of different answers, depending upon the interviewee’s political orientation(s). People leaning towards the left would most likely say, “Islam. Islamophobia is a big problem in the West. Definitely.” Others leaning towards the right would probably say “The Jews. They have suffered the most and even now, Israel is under threat from Islamic fundamentalists. We must stand with Israel.” In India, it would probably be, “The Hindus! Just look at the Kashmiri Pandits.” And I don’t deny that each of these groups has suffered immensely in the past. I sympathise strongly with anyone who has been persecuted or discriminated against in the secular sphere on the basis of their race, religion, economic status or sex. It goes without saying that I condemn all forms of religious bigotry. But in my humble opinion, neither Islam nor Judaism can claim the title. In my mind, the most hated religion in the world today is Catholic Christianity. “What?!” I know. It sounds strange. But spare me the incredulous look, because I am just about to back up my claims with extraordinarily strong evidence. But before I do that, let me tell you my story. I myself was raised in the Hindu community, but after a decade-long search for the truth, I lost faith in the faith of my forefathers. I am now making my way across to Christianity, and in all likelihood, I will end up either Roman Catholic or in Eastern Orthodoxy. I have studied more religions and denominations than I can remember – from the Ahl-e-Hadith (and the lesser known Ahl-e-Qur’an) to the long-extinct Zurvanism – and I will soon begin an undergraduate degree in Theology at the University of Oxford. My friends, I can testify with all my heart that there is no religious group that is more maligned, slandered and attacked in popular culture than the Catholic Church. Each and every worldview is built upon some major controlling narrative or the other. Modern society is the offspring of three great ideological uprisings in the past, all of which are overtly and vehemently anti-Catholic, either prominently or tangentially. You might have guessed two of them, but the third one may surprise you. I am speaking of the Enlightenment, the Protestant Reformation and the rise of Marxism. Now let’s consider their controlling narratives one by one. The Enlightenment The world had great and immense potential since the evolution of the homo sapiens. A great example of this was Europe, which in the classical world was a great hub of learning, philosophy, art, and science. Great thinkers and minds arose who tirelessly “stretched forward their hands towards perfection” in Greece and Rome. All of this was happening – until the rise of Christianity, the most intolerant branch of which is the Catholic Church. Led by the theocratic impositions of Constantine, the Catholic Church brought all of Europe under their tyrannical captivity. Superstition reigned; science was stifled; the freedom of the heart was curbed; man was put into chains. The growth and progress of Europe were stunted… until the great Renaissance dawned upon mankind, and Europe was reborn – a phoenix rising from the ashes. The captivity of Rome was overthrown and the great continent emerged, to build its future on its own. The Protestant Reformation In the beginning, Christ and the Apostles built up the Church and commanded them to preach the Gospel far and wide. All was going well… but over the centuries, slowly but gradually, pagan influence began to creep into the Church. Superstition and idolatry gradually came to cloud the Gospel, and eventually, it was lost for good! The situation was especially bad in Western Europe, where the Pope presided in the place of God, reigning down his ungodly tyranny upon the masses, chaining the Christian and denying him his rightful freedom. The Spirit of God departed for a while from the pagan Roman church… until at last, the seeds laid by the great martyrs Wycliffe and Hus bore fruit, and the heroes of the faith – Luther, Zwingli, and Calvin – emerged. These luminaries showed us the path and helped us break the chains of Roman tyranny. The Reformation was a glorious cleansing of the church, and countless souls were freed from the captivity of the Roman harlot. Marxism History is marked primarily by class-struggle. From ages past, the privileged (the haves) have oppressed the have-nots. A prime example of this is seen in the decadent, superstitious Catholic Church. This is an organisation that has promoted colonialism (the Crusades being a great example) and continues to have an authoritarian patriarchal structure of clericalism and privilege that oppresses the common man. To this day, the Pope and his henchmen participate in the oppression of the masses, by opposing abortion, contraception and denying women equality by not ordaining them to the priesthood. This organisation must change, or perish. The common people must arise out of the chains of this tyranny! Now, if you have been studying the three movements I describe, you will quickly see that absolutely nothing I have written is an exaggeration. For example, if you are acquainted with Protestant polemical literature (as I am), you will notice that many of the terms I have used – “Roman harlot”, “Roman [Babylonian] captivity”, “freedom of the Christian”, “chains of bondage and superstition”, “false gospel”, etc. – are not mine, but the exact terms used by Protestants to this day! Notice also, another thing: though these movements all originated in Europe, they have since then been widely disseminated. There are more than 900 million Protestants around the world (almost an eighth of the world population). The philosophy of the Enlightenment has spread around the globe as well, as evidenced by the fact that most of the countries in the world are (or, at least, claim to be) liberal secular democracies. And, of course, Marxism has claimed the most populous country in the world as its own and continues to have a loud presence around the world (particularly among the students and youth). Is it just me? Am I just seeing it this way because I myself strongly lean RC? (Well, technically, I began leaning RC after I saw its theology being vastly misrepresented and slandered in Protestant fundamentalist circles on the internet). But it’s not just me by any stretch of the imagination. Here is what pro-life activist, journalist and Orthodox Jew Ben Shapiro had to say at a conference in Dana Point, CA: “Unfortunately, the attacks [by radical leftists] on Catholics have come first and foremost […] It’s really fascinating to watch, not just from a Jewish perspective. Usually, we’re the first on the hit list. Now it’s you guys.” Shapiro went on to note several instances of anti-Catholic prejudice in the popular media. But one could also note the attitude of contempt several Democrat politicians displayed towards conservative Catholicism as we see, for example, US Senator Diane Feinstein’s bluntly stated to the Catholic judicial nominee Amy Barrett, “The dogma lives loudly within you”. But what about the historical data? Don’t they prove that the Catholic Church is, indeed, so to speak, “guilty as charged”? Not so, says non-Catholic sociologist, University of California Berkeley scholar and Pulitzer Prize-winning author Rodney Stark, who has written many books on Christian history, including several defending Catholicism from what he says as unfounded attacks and slanderous misrepresentations. Among his many works are God’s Battalions: The Case for the Crusades, Reformation Myths and Bearing False Witness: Debunking Centuries of Anti-Catholic Lies. America, of course, is historically extremely anti-Catholic. And with the worldwide dominance of American culture as well as the proliferation of American-style Evangelicalism, anti-Catholicism too has spread around the world. But don’t take my word for it. Ryan Reeves is Cambridge scholar and a professor of Church history at Gordon-Conwell Theological Seminary, one of the eminent Protestant institutions in the USA. Several of his lectures are available on his YouTube channel (in my opinion, an invaluable contribution to public education). I highly recommend his lecture Catholics in America. In it, Reeves discusses how, historically, large sections of the Protestant population in America have always tried to, especially in the face of Catholic immigration, “slander and to mock and to lampoon Catholics, in an effort to demoralize and ideally to get them to convert to Protestantism”. (Since Professor Reeves is teaching at a well-respected Protestant institution, I will similarly assume that he is a Protestant and has no dog in this fight.) He goes on to discuss historically famous instances of anti-Catholic propaganda, including the ghost-written 18th century bestseller autobiography of “Maria Monk”, which claimed to expose scandalous debauchery and immorality within Catholic convents, and which – according to Dr. Reeves - we now know to be a complete hoax. Self-evidently, hatred against Catholics must change due to the simple social rule that one ought not to be persecuted for one’s beliefs. Here are three things which I think need to happen in order to help the situation change. Firstly, people need to better appreciate and understand the Catholic Church’s rich and vibrant intellectual history, especially the glories of the Middle Ages - figures like Aquinas, Anselm, Ockham, Peter Abelard, Duns Scotus and so on. Secondly, the anti-fideism of Catholic theology needs to be properly recognised as well (I’m looking at you, Christopher Hitchens). The doctrine of the interplay and complementary nature of faith and reason, popularised by Aquinas and officially adopted by the Catholic Church at the First Vatican Council, will only lead the devout Catholic to a deeper admiration of and respect towards the sciences, not a fear of them. Hence, we have great Catholic scientists like Gregor Mendel, George Lemaitre, Roger Bacon, Albertus Magnus and – of course – Nicolaus Copernicus (who, by the way, was respected and admired by several Catholic clergymen of his time, including Pope Clement VII). For example, on November 1, 1536, Cardinal Nikolaus von Schönberg, Archbishop of Capua, wrote to Copernicus expressing profound admiration, and requesting him to tell him more about his new cosmology. Thirdly, people need to remember the mistakes made by Catholics in the past. Yes, Catholics are not, and have never been, perfect people. They have made mistakes, like any other group. We must not repeat the errors of antiquity, and we must remember and learn from them. But, at the same time, we must also recognise the fact that the Catholic hierarchy (I’m talking about folks like Popes John Paul II and Francis I) has publicly apologised for many of the past excesses and sought forgiveness for the same. An institution that is ready to own up to its mistakes in such a public manner shines a ray of hope for the world. And it is only such an attitude of humility, repentance, and desire to change that will help contemporary Catholics overcome the ecclesiastical abuses and errors of the modern world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Christendom Today: How Christianity is still Shaping the Modern World</title>
      <link href="/Christendom-Today" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Christendom Today: How Christianity is still Shaping the Modern World" />
      <published>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Christendom-Today</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Christendom-Today">&lt;p&gt;There are many religions in the world, but only Christianity can boast of having more than two billion followers across the world, comprising people from nearly every ethnicity, race, and social class. Even Islam – its closest contender and the “fastest growing religion in the world” is nearly a billion followers behind. But how is the religion that names itself after Jesus the Messiah influencing the 21st century? The answer may surprise you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christianity certainly is a house divided. The Protestant Reformation played a major role in this (and the proliferation of Protestant denominations continues to prove this) but it also made the Catholic Church wake up from centuries of semi-stagnation, resulting in a major resurgence of traditionalism, as we see in the great world missions of the Counter-Reformation. Indeed, the Jesuits – zealous evangelists and promoters of the Roman faith – probably wouldn’t have existed hadn’t it been for the polarising catalyst that was Martin Luther.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those divisions haven’t yet come to an end, rather Christianity is even more diverse than it was in the 17th century. Thankfully, the different bodies calling themselves Christian are reaching out to each other in a spirit of sincerity and dialogue and are repenting the terrible sectarian bloodshed that so often categorised post-Enlightenment Europe. But the various Christian ‘sects’ are still very different and continue to operate and influence the world in their own unique way. Let us begin with the largest group of all – the Roman Catholic Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“The Spirit of Vatican II”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mid-20th century, the Catholic Church held a worldwide pastoral council called the Second Council of the Vatican, or – to put it simply – “Vatican II” (hereafter referred to as V2). Unlike previous councils, V2 never chose to define dogma or clarify church teaching – rather it wanted to bring about ecclesiastical reforms to be able to better respond to the new world of the 20th century. But many Catholics agree that V2 was an absolute disaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V2 resulted in the sharp splintering of the Church. The liberals and the ‘modernists’ complain that it didn’t go far enough in eroding “medieval superstition”, while the conservatives argue that the ambiguous language in its documents creates a great danger for doctrinal error to be spread. In addition to these two groups, there are more than half-a-million traditionalist Catholics who reject it altogether, calling it a non-infallible “robber’s council” – the best example of this is the Priestly Society of St Pius X, with supporters around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, V2 has resulted in a change of attitude among many believers. Today, Catholics are much more focused on preaching about “social justice” than before. This is best seen in the lives of Mother Teresa and Oscar Romero, both saints of the Catholic Church, as well as in the current Pontiff, Pope Francis. The rise of the so-called “Liberation theology” has created a great impact in Latin America (particularly Brazil), with some calling it the “Marxist version of Catholicism”. The “left-wing Church” in this part of the world has played an instrumental role in protesting against totalitarian right-wing bigotry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberation theologians contend that the root cause of poverty and social injustice is sin (the implication being that social justice cannot return unless people begin to lead saintly lives) and that the poor, the oppressed and the marginalized are the “privileged channels of God’s grace”. The result is that a direct link has been made between theology and social activism. To be a good Christian, one must fight against and oppose oppressive structures of power, say the Liberation theologians. While Liberation theology is certainly not a branch of Communism in any formal sense of the word, the similarity with Marxist rhetoric has, at times, concerned many conservatives, not least among them being Pope Emeritus Benedict XVI. This is very ironic because the Catholic Church of the 20th century was one of the most powerful anti-Communist forces in the world, with many (including New York Times bestselling author and scholar Paul Kengor) crediting Pope St John Paul II as having played an instrumental role in the fall of the Soviet Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luther’s Revenge: The Worldwide Resurgence of Evangelicalism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evangelical Christianity is by far the most powerful and dynamic religious force in the world today. Evangelicalism is converting people by the hundreds of thousands. The best example of this is the late Baptist missionary Billy Grace, who preached to more than 3 billion people during his career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evangelicalism is characterised by both simplicity and zeal. There is no Pope or central authority structure to dictate dogma – the Bible is the only rule. There is no long and boring liturgy as we see in Catholic and Orthodox Churches – rather, church services tend to have contemporary music that is very appealing to the youth. They are not led by old and haggard clerics barely able to even speak a word – on the contrary, their leaders tend to be charismatic, scholarly and lively. The sacramental emphasis is replaced by a much freer and fluid form of spirituality, and it is not uncommon to hear the phrase “Christianity is a relationship, not a religion”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the Christian apologists defending the veracity of Christian truth in the academia are also Evangelicals. William Lane Craig, Ravi Zacharias, NT Wright, Richard Bauckham, Michael F Bird, Craig Keener, Craig Blomberg, James DG Dunn, Alvin Plantinga – the list is very impressive indeed. Not only are these devoted (Evangelical) Christians eager to convert souls, they also represent the top brass of scholarship in their respective fields. For instance, William Lane Craig and Alvin Plantinga are one of the most cited scholars in the philosophy of religion, while Wright and Bauckham have both had an association with universities like Oxford and Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny enough, Evangelical Christianity is very American, and very, very Republican. So, while Catholics seem to veer leftward, Evangelicals are solidly in support of capitalism and the notion of a culturally advanced Western Civilisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Holy Mother Russia: The Re-Baptism of Rus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the fall of the USSR, the resurgence of Eastern Orthodoxy was all but inevitable. Today, the Moscow Patriarchate can be called the unofficial state religion of the Russian Federation. Now operating with Vladimir Putin’s open consent and cooperation, they are rebuilding Churches long destroyed and reconstructing schools that had been annihilated by anti-religious sentiment. In fact, some Orthodox followers and clergy are actively advocating the restoration of a Christian state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orthodox Christians are very, well, ‘orthodox’. When the Pope visited Serbia, he was greeted by sloganeers protesting “the Papist heresy”. Even the Patriarch – while having met the Pope at the airport – refused to offer Mass with him. Similarly, Russia is cracking down on “fringe groups” – not least among them being the non-Trinitarian Jehovah’s Witnesses, who have had to face fierce persecution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What animates these people? It a vision of the legendary Byzantium, an empire so wonderful that it may be fittingly called the kingdom of God on earth. When the ambassadors of Prince Vladimir of Kiev first saw the Latin Mass, they were not too impressed, but when they witnessed the Byzantine Divine Liturgy, they wrote back exclaiming that this was the most heavenly thing they had ever seen. In the Orthodox narrative, the Church of Rome fell into heresy when it started claiming for itself ecclesiastical supremacy. It was then excommunicated and replaced by the Church of Constantinople, the New Rome. And when Constantinople fell under the sword of Islam, God raised up Moscow – the “Third Rome”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that if there will ever be a Christian state in the 21st century, it will exist mainly in Orthodox-dominated lands (and perhaps in Catholic Poland). For the rest of the Christian world, political Christendom is dead and gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atheists and critics of religion sometimes contend that Christianity is on the decline. But is this true? While it is without a doubt correct to say that Europe and the Western World is secularising at an exponential rate, this does not hold true with regard to the rest of the world. There is an explosion of Christian growth in the global south, particularly in Africa which has proven to be a fertile mission field for the Christian message. As far as academia is concerned, the resurgence of orthodox Christian scholarship in recent years is also a sign of life. However unpopular the faith may be among young white people, it certainly has a long and bright future ahead.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There are many religions in the world, but only Christianity can boast of having more than two billion followers across the world, comprising people from nearly every ethnicity, race, and social class. Even Islam – its closest contender and the “fastest growing religion in the world” is nearly a billion followers behind. But how is the religion that names itself after Jesus the Messiah influencing the 21st century? The answer may surprise you.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Transphobia, Political Correctness and the Jordan Peterson Phenomenon</title>
      <link href="/Jordan-Peterson-Phenomenon" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transphobia, Political Correctness and the Jordan Peterson Phenomenon" />
      <published>2019-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Jordan-Peterson-Phenomenon</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Jordan-Peterson-Phenomenon">&lt;p&gt;Hero. Mentor. Thinker. Professor. Ideologue. Right-Winger. Transphobic Hate-Monger. “Mean Mad White Man.” These are but some of the epithets which have been used to refer to Jordan B. Peterson, an eminent clinical psychologist who became famous overnight for opposing legislation that intended to make it illegal for people to not refer to transgender people by their preferred pronouns. Since then, he has been at the epicentre of a raging controversy about political correctness that has made an impact over most of the Western Anglophone world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peterson is a professor at the University of Toronto. He earned his doctorate from McGill University and has taught at eminent institutions, including Harvard University. He is the author of &lt;i&gt;Maps of Meaning: The Architecture of Belief &lt;/i&gt; and a more recent international bestseller &lt;i&gt;12 Rules for Life: An Antidote to Chaos&lt;/i&gt;. An erudite Jungian and Nietzschean scholar and a gifted speaker, he has inspired countless young men to “embrace their masculinity”. However, his opposition to government-backed impositions on free speech and his critique of the feminist concept of patriarchy has made him an almost hated figure in some circles. The foundation of all these positions, however, is his staunch opposition to political correctness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are approximately 3 million people in the European Union and the United States of America put together who identify as transgender. The exact estimate the world over is difficult to ascertain. Nonetheless, however minute they might be in proportion to the total world population, this is a sizable number of people. But can a trans woman be considered a “real woman”? That is the question Jo Coburn of the BBC’s &lt;i&gt;The Daily Politics&lt;/i&gt; asked Peterson. His reply was simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No. […] Because I think that women are capable, generally speaking, of having babies and they have female genitalia and they have an XX Chromosome and I think the biological markers are relevant.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are Peterson’s comments controversial? Certainly. Insulting? For many, yes. But transphobic? Discriminatory? Prejudiced? Is Peterson taking his alleged “freedom of speech” a bit too far? How would we react if someone today claimed that a black person was not a “real person” or a “real human” and would use that as a basis for denying that such a person is entitled to human rights? I am not making this up. That is precisely what many Southern Americans believed about non-white people. The idea was that humanoid beings pre-existed before Adam, and that blacks were among the “beasts of the field” described in the initial chapters of the Book of Genesis. White supremacists used this religious belief in order to justify slavery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone were to make this claim today, we would be appalled, and rightly so. But how different is Professor Peterson’s claim? At least, that’s the argument that might be made by some on the left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, numerous trans-people claim a number of distinctive rights. The right to be called by their preferred pronouns is one of them. Another is the right to use public bathrooms of their own choice, that correspond to their “gender identity”. But are they actually entitled to these rights?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not my intention to comment on whether transgenderism is legitimate or not. That is a topic for the experts and I am not sure I have any opinion on this. What I want to focus on though is the concept of free speech. Nowhere is free speech upheld in an absolute manner, and rightly so because that would lead to dangerous anarchy. There are a number of things which people are forbidden from saying, which would constitute “hate speech”. We cannot, for instance, encourage people to engage in acts of genocide. Well and good. The real dilemma lies, however, in the simple fact that the precise demarcation between authentic speech and hate speech can be very blurred at times. Doubtlessly, many transgenders have probably felt Peterson’s comments to be extremely offensive. But does this constitute “hate”? The man has not called for violence of any kind; quite the contrary, he advocates treating transgender people with the same respect and dignity that we would any other ordinary human being. It is the same with Ben Shapiro. The latter is not calling for persecution; from his perspective, he is merely exercising his freedom of speech to express his genuinely held opinion that transgenderism is mental illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question that arises then is this: What do we do when genuinely held opinions are so offensive for some on the other side that it almost &lt;i&gt;sounds&lt;/i&gt; hateful to their ears? What opinions are permissible, and what are not? Who decides?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some might say “Hate speech is when we call upon people to engage in violence”. But this presents its own problems. What if someone were to salute the grave of Hitler and publicly hang swastika flags over their homes? They may not be explicitly calling for hatred and violence, but can we deny that such actions are, at least to some extent, ‘hateful’? Others might argue, “We must restrict speech which goes against the common good of society”. This, of course, is even more vague – what exactly constitutes the “common good of society”? From such a perspective, it could be argued that “heretics” should be prevented from preaching, because by spreading heresies, they would be leading countless souls to hell – at least that was the argument of St. Thomas Aquinas. Or do we take a utilitarian view, and measure common good in terms of material happiness? Such measurements are, of course, very difficult to make. Because Stalin would probably argue that speaking out against Communism is against the common good of society because it creates unrest, raises discontent against the “ideal form of government” and misleads simple people, who are too illiterate and ignorant of the principles of economics to make a sound judgment in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is in these dilemmas that we see the absurdity of liberal democracy. If the goal of the state is to provide ‘liberty’ to all, then failure is unavoidable. What is liberal to one is inevitably oppressive to the other. What is freedom of speech to one is violation of rights to another. There are, of course, many states which call themselves ‘liberal’. But in each and every one of them, one will find people who are discontented, for whom the revolution has not even begun. So, while Dr. Peterson may be offensive and hateful to so many, he cannot be deemed to lie in the hate speech side of things. To deem his exercise of free speech as hateful would be to draw an arbitrary line between free speech and hate speech on the basis of offense, which, like any other arbitrary separation explained above cannot be sustained. As Peterson pointed out in the Cathy Newman Interview, he has to be able to risk offense to be able to honestly communicate.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Hero. Mentor. Thinker. Professor. Ideologue. Right-Winger. Transphobic Hate-Monger. “Mean Mad White Man.” These are but some of the epithets which have been used to refer to Jordan B. Peterson, an eminent clinical psychologist who became famous overnight for opposing legislation that intended to make it illegal for people to not refer to transgender people by their preferred pronouns. Since then, he has been at the epicentre of a raging controversy about political correctness that has made an impact over most of the Western Anglophone world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A World Without God</title>
      <link href="/US-A-World-Without-God" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A World Without God" />
      <published>2019-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/US-A-World-Without-God</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/US-A-World-Without-God">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt; “I am my own god. We are here to unlearn the teachings of the church, state, and our educational system. We are here to drink beer. We are here to kill war. We are here to laugh at the odds and live our lives so well that Death will tremble to take us.”&lt;/em&gt; – Charles Bukowski&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We live in a society which has dethroned God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proof of this we see all around us – in our parliaments and senates, in our schools, colleges and educational institutions, in our homes and families, in our movies and games and, above all, in our hearts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not saying that the world has turned atheist. Quite the contrary – the 20th century was the century of atheism. But now, faith in God is having a resurgence as theist scientists, philosophers and theologians are hitting back against the wave of atheist literature that once dominated the market. One need only look at William Lane Craig and his debates against atheists as prominent as Christopher Hitchens and Lawrence Krauss to see the proof of this. People still believe that God exists, but He has become the existential equivalent of a national flag. One doesn’t obsess or fuss over it or think too much about it, but one is careful to give it the occasional salute. Indeed, one might even have love for it. But at the end of the day, it is just that: a national flag. Religious ceremonies have become just that – rather than the sacramental, life-giving well-spring of sanctification, they have become flag-hoisting ceremonies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A growing number of people who identify as theists, tend to reject any form of “institutionalized religion”, denying doctrine, dogma and faith. But I will deal with them another time. Today, I want to consider the dogma that there is no God. Today, I invite you to consider the implications of such a worldview, a worldview in which universes pop in and out of being by pure chance and the wonderful tapestry of life is merely the accidental product of random selection that is without purpose or design, in which the wonderful and beautiful reality of love and meaning is reduced to a series of chemical reactions in the brain giving an illusion of beauty that is really not there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friends, I invite you to consider the absurdity of a world without God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is no God, there is no objective purpose for your existence or mine. After all, the universe never &lt;i&gt;intended&lt;/i&gt;for us to come into being – we just simply &lt;i&gt;happened&lt;/i&gt; to be. It is like the roll of a dice. There was no guarantee that you would be here, reading this article I wrote. It just happened. You were not meant to be. You were an accident. You have no purpose and no goal. You simply sprang into existence, and in due time, you will be snuffed out forever. You are nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is no God, there is no objective basis for the morals we so revere and hold dear. Human beings are fundamentally ethical – nearly every society has had a moral code of conduct. That has not changed. But if atheism is true, then morality is not objective but subjective. While considering the epistemology of morality, we ignore questions of the ontology of morality. My friends, what is morality? If it is merely a human construct, then it is arbitrary and fallible, for human beings are by nature arbitrary and fallible. If it is the invention of men, then it has no intrinsic value, but only imparted  value, imparted by each society as it sees fit. If the Nazis came to dominate the world, we would have had a very different society and a very different set of moral codes indeed. There is no objective basis for moral judgments if there is no universal code of conduct that we can hold all men and all societies of all times accountable to. And if there is no God, there is certainly no universal moral code, for then morality would simply be the invention of men, a self-deceiving attempt to convince ourselves that there is meaning when, in fact, there is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the words of Nietzsche, when he said: “God is dead. God remains dead. And we have killed him. How shall we comfort ourselves, the murderers of all murderers? What was holiest and mightiest of all that the world has yet owned has bled to death under our knives: who will wipe this blood off us? What water is there for us to clean ourselves? What festivals of atonement, what sacred games shall we have to invent? Is not the greatness of this deed too great for us? Must we ourselves not become gods simply to appear worthy of it?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is no God, then objective morality is a myth, beauty is an illusion and purpose is lost. We are left to our own devices, to construct our own morality (and to hope against hope that we can avoid the cesspool of cultural relativism), to invent our own purposes (and to brainwash ourselves into following them), to somehow deceive ourselves into believing there is beauty when, in fact, there is nothing at all except the great black void which didn’t want us, didn’t make us, doesn’t even know about us, out of which we came out for no reason to all, and into which we shall be dissolved one day, for no reason at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To replace God with nothing is to replace the objective with the subjective, the eternal with the temporal, the spiritual with the material, the eschaton with the void.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if there is a God (as the cosmological, ontological, axiological, teleological and various other arguments seem to indicate), then it surely follows that He had a purpose for generating the world. After all, we have no knowledge of a conscious entity that performs actions for no reason at all – all free-will decisions have a purpose behind them. It is, therefore, reasonable to expect, on the basis of inductive logic, that if an intelligent entity chose to create the world, He had a purpose for doing so. What the purpose is, is for you to discover. But you cannot search for long without coming into what may be a life-changing encounter with The Greatest Story Ever Told.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“I am my own god. We are here to unlearn the teachings of the church, state, and our educational system. We are here to drink beer. We are here to kill war. We are here to laugh at the odds and live our lives so well that Death will tremble to take us.” – Charles Bukowski</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Morality, the Clash of Civilizations and the Democratic Dilemma</title>
      <link href="/Morality-the-Clash-of-Civilizations-and-the-Democratic-Dilemma" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Morality, the Clash of Civilizations and the Democratic Dilemma" />
      <published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Morality-the-Clash-of-Civilizations-and-the-Democratic-Dilemma</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Morality-the-Clash-of-Civilizations-and-the-Democratic-Dilemma">&lt;p&gt;“Civilization will not attain to its perfection until the last stone from the last church falls on the last priest.” Émile Zola&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Freedom consists not in doing what we like, but in having the right to do what we ought.” Pope John Paul II&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mid-1900s, hundreds of millions hoped (and feared) that the “spectre of Communism” would overshadow the world. Less than 100 years later, this hope appears to have all but vanished. The Soviet Union has collapsed. Communism is either dying or dead. Liberal democracy is considered the norm, and societies which deviate from it are considered either barbaric or backward (sometimes both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what is all this in aid of? Well, proponents argue, liberal democracy ensures that each person will have an infallible guarantee of their most intrinsic human rights, and that, if they are violated, the guilty party will be swiftly brought to justice. The problem, of course, arises when we consider the question of what constitutes “human rights”. The phrase is rather nebulous and subject to a wide range of possible interpretations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, consider the so-called “Right to Life”. To whom does this extend? Well, the human being, obviously. But can the unborn foetus be considered a “human being”? Who gets to define this term “human being”? At what stage does an entity start to be “human”? And what about criminals? Do they also enjoy the right to life, or have they – by their transgressions and woeful iniquities (again, a very debatable issue at times) – forfeited that right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the problem. There are 1.3 billion Catholics in the world who (if they are good Catholics) affirm that human life begins at conception. They also have (so their apologists claim) a number of medical experts and embryologists to back them up on that. On the other hand, there are countless self-professed “feminists” who believe that to protect without exception the foetus from being aborted would be to endanger the life of the mother. One is, the argument goes, trying to prioritize the life of an unborn, half-developed “creature” over that of a fully developed, free citizen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is clearly a clash of civilizations, a war of opposing ideologies. If the pro-choice crowd is in the right, then the right to abortion is an intrinsic right of the woman. If the pro-life factions are correct, then abortion is the biggest cause of genocide since the Holocaust. Both sides agree that human rights are being violated to this day. This brings us to a very pressing question: Is Liberal Democracy even realistic? Or does it try to bite off more than it can chew? It tries to keep the “religious busybodies” out of government, but at the same time imposes a morality on the rest of the population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a philosophical perspective, can non-religious people even have objective moral values? According to a sizeable number of atheists and naturalists, morality is simply a human construct, created by societies in order to facilitate greater synergy and efficiency of operation. Each tribe of people, the story goes, tries over time to organize its own affairs and, in order to do so, “invents” a moral code to better facilitate that purpose. But if it is purely a human construct, then it has no intrinsic value – only imparted value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Jews, Christians and Muslims all believe (and together, they constitute more than 3 billion people), that morality is ordained by God. Some go even further and say that morality is nothing other than God’s own eternal, immutable nature. With the rise of postmodernism, moral relativism has been skyrocketing, and the old-school atheists are desperately scrambling to produce a scientific basis for objective moral values. The religious camp is claiming that such an operation is in vain since science (they say) cannot possibly adjudicate on matters on ethics. Only time will tell which side wins out in the end. But both factions are united in an affirmation that relativism is dangerous and toxic. Here is why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If morality is purely a human construct, then there is no universal moral code everyone has to abide by. Each person gets to invent his/her own moral rules and one would have no objective basis to refute that. In a relativistic worldview, if one disagrees with someone else, one cannot say that the other side is “wrong” – merely that they disagree. Now imagine if the Nazis suddenly had a worldwide resurgence. The Christian, Muslim and Jew would be able to unite and condemn them on the basis that they are violating God’s eternal unchangeable law and are &lt;em&gt;ipso facto&lt;/em&gt; condemned. But what can the relativist say? Only that he/she disagrees with their moral code, but since – according to his/her own definition – morality is merely a human construct, he/she cannot make an objective claim that they are “wrong” in an absolute sense of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Democracy must be better delineated. The fact is that there exist in the world irreconcilable worldviews. People of different ethnicities, races, communities and genders might coexist, but can a pro-lifer eat at the same table as an abortionist, when the fact is – according to the pro-lifer – the latter is nothing other than a murderer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One cannot live in two worlds. Liberal Democracy cannot not take a stand, but if it does take a stand, it ceases to be liberal. And when it ceases to be liberal, can it be called democracy? In a world of exclusive ideologies, absolute inclusivism is an impossibility. And in a world of conflicting moral systems, the state and the law cannot act as impartial umpires. Either abortion is legal, or it isn’t. The question then remains, that if the state is ready to impose its own moral values on the rest of the populace, then it must ask itself a question: does it have any objective basis for those values or not? If it does not, it undermines its own authority. And if it is non-religious, it is hard to see how it’s ethical code can have any objective basis at all.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Civilization will not attain to its perfection until the last stone from the last church falls on the last priest.” Émile Zola</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A House Divided: The Secret Civil War of the Catholic Church</title>
      <link href="/A-House-Divided-The-Secret-Civil-War-of-the-Catholic-Church" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A House Divided: The Secret Civil War of the Catholic Church" />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-House-Divided-The-Secret-Civil-War-of-the-Catholic-Church</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-House-Divided-The-Secret-Civil-War-of-the-Catholic-Church">&lt;p&gt;The Catholic Church is perhaps the most troubled religious organization in modern times. No other sect or group is going through the same crisis Catholics are undergoing today, although this is not immediately apparent to those on the outside. This century – the 21st century – will truly determine the shape of the faith for generations to come. But before we move on, a bit of background information is welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1960’s, the Catholic Church held a worldwide council of bishops, called the Second Vatican Council. This was the 21st of the so-called Ecumenical Councils, the deliberations and decrees of which are meant to expound and explain Catholic doctrine in light of contemporary challenges to the faith whilst seeking unity with all other Christian sects. This youngest of the councils was meant to be the Church’s response to the modern world—an attempt at providing a modern discourse not unlike the philosophical consolidation provided by the great Thomas Aquinas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, the Church has focused more on dialogue rather than debate, collaboration rather than conflict. After nearly a thousand years of separation, Pope Paul VI met with Patriarch Athenagoras of the Greek Orthodox Church, and the two hierarchs lifted excommunications which had been in force since 1054. After centuries of war and bloodshed, the Church reached out to the Lutherans and the two groups even drafted a joint declaration on the most controversial point of doctrinal difference between Catholicism and Protestantism. Hopes are high for an eventual reunion of all Christians. And the more general calls for dialogue and peace have been extended not merely to other Christians but even to the various religions of the world, from the folk traditions of North America to the now-resurgent Islam. The Church has not, of course, diluted a single point of Church teaching (both Popes John Paul II and Benedict XVI make that abundantly clear), but the practice of the Church has changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the outside, things might appear to be warm and merry. But under the appearance of serenity lies a harsh reality. The Church is in a state of great turmoil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early 20th century, Pope Pius X spent much of his time and energy as head of the Catholic Church to combat a movement called “Modernism”. The Modernists were clerics and laypeople who, while professing to be Catholics and uniting themselves with the external structures of the Church, nevertheless watered down and diluted several elements of Church doctrine and teaching. Pius X was particularly ruthless – he ordered that all priests and seminary professors take the “Oath Against Modernism”. Needless to say, under his pontificate, the modernists were forced to go underground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, after the Second Vatican Council, under the guise of “pastoral reforms”, the Modernists have had a remarkable resurgence. While they have failed utterly to change official Church teaching, they nonetheless hold opinions at variance with what many consider to unchanging dogma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the Popes post the Vatican II have been very strict against this newly resuscitated trend. John Paul II, in particular, reaffirmed orthodox doctrine in his catechism and encyclicals and Benedict promulgated reforms that led to a revival of traditionalism among clerics and laypeople. But the most recent ascendant to the Throne of Peter does not appear to be in the same vein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Is the Pope Catholic?” was considered to be a joke English Catholics said to themselves in the 19th century. It isn’t funny anymore as the current pontiff, Pope Francis, repeatedly makes ambiguous statements that appear to: firstly, question the necessity of faith for salvation; secondly, allow for divorced and remarried couples to receive Communion; thirdly, imply that Catholic couples should control the number of children they have (which some might interpret as a contradiction of age-old Church doctrine on contraception); and fourthly, call for a change in the teaching on the death penalty and sympathy for homosexuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these statements are ambiguously worded, and it is not always clear if a denial has taken place or if it is simply yet another case of authentic doctrine being stated in a slipshod manner. But what is certainly without question is that this is the most controversial pontificate in recent memory. The situation became so bad that it prompted four high-ranking Church leaders to make public an appeal (called “dubia”) to the Pope seeking clarification on his statements – an appeal which, since then, has gone unanswered. There was even talk of a “public fraternal correction” of the Pope, and there has already been a more grass-roots level “filial correction” involving scores of distinguished signatories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what is even more worrying is the Holy Father’s response to his critics. When calls for clarification come, the Pope is silent. Subtle attacks on his critics and dissenters abound in his Sunday homilies. Conservative laypeople are up in arms, not least among them being the historian Henry Sire, author of the controversial bestseller The Dictator Pope. While Francis tries his level best to maintain an image of compassion, can that really square with what many are now calling a tyrannical method of internal governance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On August 25, 2018, a prominent prelate, Archbishop Carlo Maria Vigano, released a damning 11-page letter describing a network of sexual abuse cover-ups that had spread its tentacles all the way to upper echelons of power. In a move virtually unprecedented in recent history, the bishop called upon the pontiff and the others complicit to resign. This is more than a question of moral corruption. In the eyes of countless conservatives, the laxity of moral standards among prelates and priests is not separate from but is rather a direct result of the “Modernist conspiracy” to liberalize Catholic doctrine. The fact that the majority of these abuse cases are instances of homosexual abuse has only added fuel to the fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not just a regional crisis. This is a battle for the very heart of the Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a conservative Christian with deep sympathy for the Catholic Church’s mission and an appreciation of the richness of her theological heritage, I propose a three-point programme to deal with this crisis once and for all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Initiate a Church-wide search-and-destroy operation – better still, if this is handled by outside non-ecclesiastical bodies. Defrock priests found guilty of sexual abuse and hand them over to the secular authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Allow, for the time being, married men to become priests, in accordance with the historical precedents of the Byzantine and other Oriental traditions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Renovate the formation process in theological seminaries
– restore traditional practices abandoned since Vatican II and work to foster ascetic rigour among candidates for the priesthood.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these three points are successfully implemented, we may find ourselves with a smaller Catholic Church. But this will not be a loss. It will be a victory, and the Church will finally have a chance to reclaim her former glory in the modern world.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Catholic Church is perhaps the most troubled religious organization in modern times. No other sect or group is going through the same crisis Catholics are undergoing today, although this is not immediately apparent to those on the outside. This century – the 21st century – will truly determine the shape of the faith for generations to come. But before we move on, a bit of background information is welcome.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
