<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/soham.gupta/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-04-14T18:42:48+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/soham.gupta/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Atheism Destroys Science and Progress. Here’s How.</title>
      <link href="/Atheism-Destroys" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Atheism Destroys Science and Progress. Here’s How." />
      <published>2019-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Atheism-Destroys</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Atheism-Destroys">&lt;p&gt;It might sound strange to say that atheism destroys science. Indeed, many will laugh merely upon reading the heading of this article. However, my interactions with sceptics and postmodernists have convinced me that while it may seem to many that atheism leads to science and moral progress, the truth is exactly the opposite. Rather than upholding science, atheism destroys the foundations that underlie science; and far from promoting human progress, atheism degrades humanity and inevitably leads to moral decay in society. Not only that, I am also deeply convinced that a postmodernist attitude is simply the result of centuries of atheist influence upon the West; a true atheist will, in my opinion, adopt a postmodern outlook sooner or later. In this article, I hope to show why I think this is the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am a Christian, let’s talk about Christianity for a moment. As the Oxford mathematician and Christian thinker John Lennox has remarked multiple times, many of the scientists of the early Modern era were Christians because their faith in God led them to expect order and stability in the universe. Indeed, many of the very people who laid the foundations of science in the post-Reformation West were devoutly Christian people, believing that the study of the creation was a kind of worship to God. Indeed, that is my own opinion as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Christian, I believe that God gave us rationality so that we could use it to study and learn more about the world in which we live. My belief that my mind and my sense organs are a gift of God gives me sufficient ground to trust it as being reliable in giving me information about this wonderful universe which we are privileged to call home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, an atheist cannot say the same thing. For suppose that we live in a world that is merely a cosmic accident, and suppose – for the sake of argument – that the material reality is all that exists and there is no spiritual dimension whatsoever. Under this view, the mind is purely a material phenomenon and is directly equivalent to the brain. There is no aspect whatsoever to the mind that is immaterial under this view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the brain is merely a conglomeration of nerves and chemicals. In a purely physical, materialistic world, what we perceive as emotions, thoughts and feelings are merely the result of chemicals firing around in our brain. Even our deepest moral sentiments are simply the products of how our brain has been evolved to think and perceive reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if this is true, then how can the atheist say that his senses and rational powers are capable of giving him an accurate depiction of reality? If the mind is simply a physical organ that is determined to function and act in a particular way (because of the evolutionary path that it happened to take), then there are no rational grounds for trusting your perception or your ability to reason. After all, everything – in an atheistic worldview – is a cosmic accident and the way your brain thinks and perceives something to be ‘rational’ or ‘logical’ or ‘reasonable’ is merely an accident as well. If evolution had taken a different path, then your brain might not even have existed… or it would have existed, but it would be operating in a different manner, giving you a different perception of what you call ‘reality’. But in that situation, you would have had radically different beliefs and ways of perceiving the world. What you today call ‘reasonable’ might under that circumstance appear absurd or farcical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is here that the atheist falls into a bit of a quandary. One alternative is that he can admit the fact and say that he simply ‘trusts’ his ability to reason and operates with that as his basic epistemological presupposition. But if this is so, then he cannot in good conscience criticize religious faith, since that too is a kind of trust in things we might not be able to “prove” with mathematical accuracy. Another alternative is that he can admit the fact I have mentioned and collapse into a kind of postmodernism, looking at all things – science included! – with scepticism, since even scientific observations are dependant upon human perception, which cannot be ‘proven’ per se to be reliable!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, if we were living in the Matrix, chances are we wouldn’t know that we were!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same thing holds true for morality. We all – atheists and Christians included – have basic moral instincts. From a Christian point of view, I believe that God is perfect and he gives us a basic knowledge of what is right and wrong. Thus, as a Christian, I can say with conviction that certain things are basically right and others are basically wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But can the atheist say such a thing? Certainly, atheists have moral beliefs, but can they justify those beliefs? After all, if there is no God and if materialistic naturalism is true, then there are no objective moral principles. Whatever morality we might have is purely subjective. Our mind is conditioned to think in a particular way – morally speaking - because of external accidental circumstances. Morality, in an atheistic worldview, inevitably becomes either a psychological construct or a societal one. On the former view, it is primarily evolution that conforms us to have certain moral instincts – and, remember, there is no guarantee that evolution would have taken the path it ultimately took! On the latter view, morality is primarily the result of societal conditioning – we happen to live in a society that values liberty and freedom; therefore, we have learned to value them as well. Had we lived in a cannibalistic society we would have had different moral values. This is called the doctrine of Cultural Relativism, and in this philosophy, no particular moral code is intrinsically superior to another, since they are all cultural constructs and all cultures are equally true and equally false.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is not that atheists don’t have a sense of morality – they certainly do. The problem, rather, is that their metaphysical worldview cripples them from having an objective foundation for their morality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is heart-breaking for me as a Christian to see prominent thinkers and philosophers encourage people to embrace a worldview in which everything is fundamentally meaningless and to “get used to it” (quoting Dr Susan Blackwood in her dialogue with Professor Jordan Peterson on the &lt;em&gt;Unbelievable?&lt;/em&gt; radio podcast). It is just as upsetting to see the rise of postmodern thinking in our world. I am convinced that such a mode of looking at the world will inevitably give birth to a society of depression and despair. And this observation vindicates my deeply Christian belief that only God can give true meaning and value to our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People might find it similarly shocking that I claim atheism degrades human beings. After all, don’t many atheists identify as ‘humanists’? Don’t so many atheists fight so vigorously for human rights and don’t humanists try and oppose oppression around the world? An atheist friend of mine once quipped to me that the modern West is proof that we can have morality without God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t disagree more. And here’s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give one example: most atheists don’t, as far as I know, fight for the rights of the unborn. In fact, prominent atheists like Sam Harris complain that religious bigots such as myself still try to stop embryonic stem cell research. Similarly, I have never heard an atheist oppose the recent legislations that have effectively allowed the monstrosity of late-term abortions in New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not only the unborn who are being marginalized. Peter Singer, a prominent atheist ethicist, openly declares that – like unborn foetuses – new-born infants similarly lack what he calls the essential characteristics of personhood. The troubling implications of such a horrendous line of thinking are so alarming that words fail to convey the emotions that stir up in my heart as I write this article. And what is even more scandalous is that Singer is a vegan, although – as he would put it – a ‘flexible vegan’. In other words, he goes to great lengths to ensure that cows and buffaloes don’t suffer because of him… but that same privilege is not extended even to new-born babies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here’s the thing. I believe that deep down, everyone has a sense of right and wrong. And this sense has been given to them by God. If you want proof that a Divine Law does indeed exist, then turn to your own conscience. I believe that deep down, everyone knows that good and evil are real, but over time they manufacture philosophies and ideologies to rationalise away what they do not want to be true. Because if there is a Divine Law, you are not ‘free’ to enjoy things that are evil, however attractive or pleasurable that might be. And if there is a Divine Law, there must also be a Divine Law-giver before whom we are all accountable for our actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not saying that you can’t be good without fear of punishment. On the contrary, I believe that the good should be sought for its own sake, rather than merely out of servile fear. Rather, what I am saying is that if there is no God, then good and evil are both illusions and have no real existence. And if that is so, then everything is permitted, since all things are then morally equal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the disastrous implications of the revolution that our world has initiated against God. And you will then forgive me when I say that atheism is not a boon. It is, in fact, poison.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It might sound strange to say that atheism destroys science. Indeed, many will laugh merely upon reading the heading of this article. However, my interactions with sceptics and postmodernists have convinced me that while it may seem to many that atheism leads to science and moral progress, the truth is exactly the opposite. Rather than upholding science, atheism destroys the foundations that underlie science; and far from promoting human progress, atheism degrades humanity and inevitably leads to moral decay in society. Not only that, I am also deeply convinced that a postmodernist attitude is simply the result of centuries of atheist influence upon the West; a true atheist will, in my opinion, adopt a postmodern outlook sooner or later. In this article, I hope to show why I think this is the case.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Kalām Cosmological Argument for God’s Existence</title>
      <link href="/Cosmological-Argument" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Kalām Cosmological Argument for God’s Existence" />
      <published>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Cosmological-Argument</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Cosmological-Argument">&lt;p&gt;This is the first article that I have been privileged to write for &lt;em&gt;The Pangean&lt;/em&gt; on the existence of God. Some might be surprised at this. &lt;em&gt;The Pangean&lt;/em&gt;,  after all, is not a philosophical quarterly. How is this relevant, some might say? To put it simply: in every way. This is an immensely relevant topic because the question of whether or not God exists is surely one of the most significant questions we can ask (in fact, I consider it the most significant). The answer we give to this question will inevitably impact the rest of our worldview as well as influence how we choose to live our lives. Not merely that, this article shall be a bit of an introduction to the field of natural theology: that branch of philosophy devoted to arguments for the existence of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before we proceed further, a few disclaimers must be made. Here’s the first one: I am not claiming to provide &lt;em&gt;empirical&lt;/em&gt; evidence for God. Some people have quipped to me in the past, “Show me God, and I’ll believe in Him.” But this statement/challenge presupposes that God is an empirical entity that can be ‘shown’. But God is not an empirical entity; I would argue that He is immaterial and transcendent, not enclosed within space and time. As such, it is not possible for anyone to ‘show’ God to you. But empirical evidence is not the only valid source of knowledge. Logical and philosophical reasoning can play a crucial role too. In fact, the idea that only empirical observations are true sources of knowledge (also called Empiricism) is &lt;em&gt;itself&lt;/em&gt; not an empirical observation – it is rather a philosophical assertion, based upon (I imagine) some kind of inductive (probabilistic) reasoning. To claim that only empirical observations can be true sources of knowledge is by its very nature self-defeating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As this is an article tailored for a general audience, this article will not presuppose any prior philosophical or theological training. And thus, the argument that has been chosen for this paper is one of the simplest ones out there – the &lt;em&gt;Kalām&lt;/em&gt; Cosmological Argument. However, its simplicity does not imply a lack of strength – quite the contrary, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now here’s the second disclaimer: this article is also not going to be extremely comprehensive. Yes, it will be to the point, but it is my hope to reach as broad an audience as I can. As such, the article will not be answering every possible objection that can be made to the argument; instead it will focus primarily on seeking to explain what it actually is rather than defend it in excruciating detail. Comprehensive defences of the argument have already been made by Christian philosophers and there is no need for a humble writer, such as myself, to add to the (quite frankly, saturated) bulk of scholarly literature that already exists on this subject. If you want to study deeper, look no further than Chapter 3 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wiley.com/en-us/The+Blackwell+Companion+to+Natural+Theology-p-9781444350852&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Blackwell Companion to Natural Theology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, one of the most elegantly argued natural theology textbooks of our time (though this present author does not agree with everything that is asserted in that work). Or you can look &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reasonablefaith.org/writings/popular-writings/existence-nature-of-god/the-kalam-cosmological-argument/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for an exposition of the argument, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gtfVds8Kn4s&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for responses to the most popular objections that have been made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main purpose of this article is to explain why God exists in as simple a manner as I possibly can. This will also give the reader an idea of how philosophical reasoning normally works and how classical theists have argued for the rationality of their faith in God. For, sadly, many of the popular YouTube ‘vlogs’ on the Kalām argument (usually made by posturing theatrical self-congratulatory millennials and other assorted hippies) clearly betray a pitiful lack of understanding of the argument itself, as well as the reasoning that runs through it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here is a third disclaimer, which may seem trivial, but which I feel must be made for the sake of conscience. While I heartily acclaim the argument itself, I do not endorse every aspect of the philosophy that has been put forward by some of its chief proponents. Particularly, I take issue with the philosopher William Lane Craig’s (one of the argument’s most vocal defenders) denial of God’s intrinsic immutability. However, this does not affect the core of the argument, and so there should be no issue in presenting it as is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, without further ado, let us get into the argument. It can be formulated as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P1.&lt;/strong&gt; Everything which begins to exist must have a cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P2.&lt;/strong&gt; The universe began to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C1.&lt;/strong&gt; (From P1 and P2) Therefore, the universe must have a cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P4.&lt;/strong&gt; If the universe has a cause, then an uncaused, Personal Creator of the universe exists, Who sans the universe is beginningless, changeless, immaterial, timeless, spaceless and enormously powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C2.&lt;/strong&gt; (From C1 and P4) Therefore, an uncaused, Personal Creator of the universe exists, Who sans the universe is beginningless, changeless, immaterial, timeless, spaceless and enormously powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we proceed, something very crucial in &lt;strong&gt;P1&lt;/strong&gt; must be pointed out. It is a common question, often posed by young internet atheists: “If everything which exists must have a cause, then what caused God?” However, this question misses the point of what we are saying. &lt;strong&gt;P1&lt;/strong&gt; does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; say that &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; which exists must have a cause – rather, it simply asserts that &lt;em&gt;everything which &lt;strong&gt;begins&lt;/strong&gt; to exist&lt;/em&gt; must have a cause. On the face of it, the syllogism is extremely simple and straightforward. P1 is obviously true – or, at the very least, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reasonablefaith.org/media/reasonable-faith-podcast/why-think-whatever-begins-to-exist-has-a-cause/&quot;&gt;it is far, far more probable than its alternative&lt;/a&gt;. As for &lt;strong&gt;P2&lt;/strong&gt;, it can be verified by philosophical arguments as well as scientific evidence. Notice also that the argument is what philosophers call a &lt;em&gt;deductive&lt;/em&gt; argument – meaning that if the premises of the argument are true, the conclusion necessarily and inescapably follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the universe has a cause. But, some ask, why does this cause have to be God? Richard Dawkins, for instance, argues that there is no reason at all to believe that this universal cause (if It indeed exists) possesses the attributes that have been traditionally ascribed to It by Jewish, Christian and Muslim theologians. However, in this, Dawkins is thoroughly mistaken. The divine attributes have been rationally argued for and logically defended for centuries now, and they go back all the way &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; to Aristotle and Plotinus, philosophers who lived before the time of Christ and who – although they were neither Jews nor Christians in the formal sense of the term – did come up with a belief in a monotheistic God. It is therefore no wonder that Christian philosophers like St Thomas Aquinas took Aristotle with such enthusiasm (in fact, Catholic theology to this day makes use of Aristotelian terminology to describe spiritual realities).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So, why does the Cause of the Universe have to be God?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument can be laid out as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Firstly&lt;/em&gt;, there must be an Ultimate Uncaused Cause of all things. In other words, we cannot postulate the existence of an infinite regress of causes (the idea that the Universe is caused by A, which is caused by B, which is caused by C… etc. all the way to infinity).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The philosophers William Lane Craig and James D Sinclair offer a simple reason: the reason is that actual infinites cannot exist in reality. Actual infinites do enjoy mathematical existence, that is undeniable. However, mathematical existence does not necessarily equate to metaphysical existence, or existence in the real world. The great German mathematician David Hilbert himself observed, “The infinite is nowhere to be found in reality. It neither exists in nature nor provides a legitimate basis for rational thought… The role that remains for the infinite to play is solely that of an idea”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actual infinites cannot exist in reality simply because, if they did, they would create insoluble absurdities. A good example of this is the famous paradox of Hilbert’s Hotel, an exposition of which you can see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lobeX6ft6PA&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some, however, claim that infinites exist all around us. For example, they point to the fact that any given distance can be infinitely subdivided. However, here we must make the distinction Aristotle made between an actual and a potential infinite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An actual infinite is something which, to put it bluntly, is &lt;em&gt;actually infinite&lt;/em&gt; – that is, it is a completed infinite. For example, the set of all even numbers truly contains an infinite number of members. However, a potential infinite is quite different. It is anything which keeps increasing and which keeps moving towards infinity but which never actualizes or achieves infinity – it always remains an ever-increasing (or ever-decreasing) finitude. For example, the age of the universe which began to exist but which will never cease to exist in the future. The age would be increasing with every passing moment and be forever progressing towards infinity, but it would never actually reach infinity. It is the same with the example of a finite distance being potentially divisible infinitely. To quote Craig and Sinclair: “The only legitimate sense in which one can speak of the infinite is in terms of potentiality: something may be infinitely divisible or susceptible to infinite addition, but this type of infinity is potential only and can never be fully actualized”. So, “While one can continue indefinitely to divide conceptually any distance, the series of subintervals thereby generated is merely potentially infinite, in that infinity serves as a limit that one endlessly approaches but never reaches”. The same goes for time. “This is the thoroughgoing Aristotelian position on the infinite: only the potential infinite exists. This position does not imply that minimal time atoms, or chronons, exist. Rather time, like space, is infinitely divisible in the sense that division can proceed indefinitely, but time is never actually infinitely divided, neither does one arrive at an instantaneous point.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, when we seek to subdivide any given distance, we must remember that the distance we are seeking to divide is strictly finite – it is not infinite. We can keep dividing it for years and years if we please, but we will never actually reach an infinite number of divisions. At any given point in time, the number of divisions we will have created will still be finite, the size of each division will still be finite and the sum total of the divisions will still be what it originally was: the finite distance we set out to divide. We will never arrive at an actually infinite number of divisions; we will keep on moving towards the infinite without realising it. This is a &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; infinite, not an actual one. For more on the paradoxes related to the infinite, readers can refer to the Oxford philosopher A W Moore’s book &lt;em&gt;The Infinite&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, an actual infinite cannot exist in reality. This naturally implies that the regress of causes cannot be actually infinite; it must terminate in a First/Ultimate Cause. And this First/Ultimate Cause must naturally be Uncaused (otherwise, it would not be a First/Ultimate Cause). So, we have established the first premise of all monotheistic religion – that there is an Ultimate Uncaused Cause of all things. Let us continue with the divine attributes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the second place&lt;/em&gt;,  an Uncaused Cause must be beginning-less since everything which is uncaused has no beginning to it (we can derive this by contraposition of &lt;strong&gt;P1&lt;/strong&gt; of the original argument).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thirdly&lt;/em&gt;, there is good reason to believe that the Entity is Immaterial and Timeless. This is powerfully suggested by the fact that it is, in fact, the cause of space and time (causation, it must be remembered, does not itself have to be temporal). But if the Entity is Itself the cause of space and time, it cannot itself be enclosed within space and time. Of course, this assertion itself probably doesn’t clinch the argument on its own. However, there are other arguments by other philosophers which have proven convincing to me that the Ultimate Cause is indeed immaterial and timeless. If you’re interested in reading up on this, refer to Chapters 1 and 3 of philosopher and former atheist Edward Feser’s book &lt;em&gt;Five Proofs for the Existence of God&lt;/em&gt;. However, since the Immateriality and Timelessness of the First Cause is not – strictly speaking – crucial to the core of the argument, we shall carry on without dwelling on it for too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fourthly&lt;/em&gt;, the Entity in question must possess enormous power, since it brought the entirety of the universe into existence quite literally from nothing. This is fairly straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fifthly and finally&lt;/em&gt;, the Ultimate Cause of all Things must be Personal. This is the linchpin. Craig and Sinclair offer three arguments for this (though many, many more can be offered) in &lt;em&gt;The Blackwell Companion to Natural Theology&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first place, as the Oxford philosopher Richard Swinburne notes, there are two types of causal explanations: “scientific explanations in terms of laws and initial conditions and personal explanations in terms of agents and their volitions”. For example, two answers can be given to the question, “Why is the kettle boiling?” We could say: “The heat of the flame is being conducted via the bottom of the kettle to the water, increasing the kinetic energy of the molecules such that they vibrate so violently that they break the surface tension of the water and are thrown off in the form of steam.” Or we could simply say: “I put the kettle on to make a cup of tea.” Both these explanations are true, and one does not necessarily exclude the other. However, one is scientific in nature; the other personal. The ‘First State of the Universe’ cannot have a scientific explanation, since there is nothing before it and it cannot, therefore, be accounted for in terms of laws operating on initial conditions. The only other explanation is in terms of an Agent and His volitions (the personal explanation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the Personhood of the Ultimate/First Cause also seems to follow from the other properties we have laid out in our argumentation. There are only two kinds of things which can be said to be uncaused, beginningless, timeless, spaceless and immaterial – either abstract objects or unembodied minds. However, abstract objects (like numbers for example, or things like roundness, redness, etc.) cannot cause anything at all – that’s part of what it means to be abstract. The only alternative that springs to mind is that of an Unembodied Mind. No other alternatives seem possible, and indeed none have been suggested so far by any major critic of the argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third argument begins by observing that while the cause is clearly eternal, the effect is not. But this seems strange. Is it not reasonable to expect that if the cause is eternal, the effect would also be co-eternal with it? And yet, we see that the effect only came to be a finite time ago, instead of forever existing side-by-side with its eternal cause, like a person and her shadow, or a subject and his/her reflection in the mirror. The easiest way out of this dilemma, Craig and Sinclair argue, is to accept that the Cause is Personal and Free. That way, it can be Eternal, while still being the cause of a temporal and finite effect. God simply chooses eternally to create a temporally finite world. This does not, of course, mean, that God “one day woke up and decided all upon a sudden to create the world”. No, that assertion is deeply problematic philosophically. Rather, the classical theist position is simply to assert that God eternally wills to create/cause the temporal universe. This decision is eternal (as would be expected if God is omniscient and immutable – though that is a topic for another day), but still, free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those were the arguments made by some of the mainstream philosophers. In addition, I would boldly venture a suggestion of my own. Although I myself lack the credentials of an Oxford don, the example I am about to give I have thought about for some time and – so far – have found no flaw in it. You could take it as a personal insight, which is not too different from Swinburne’s argument described in point one above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example is that of a stone. A stone is an inanimate object. It can never think nor freely chose to do things. This means that it cannot do anything at all unless external forces act upon it. If a stone comes flying through the air and hits you on the head, you can legitimately say, “The stone has hit me!” But because the stone is inanimate (it can neither think nor take free will decisions of its own), you must also recognize that it did not hit you by its own strength or power or will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if there is indeed an Ultimate/First Cause of all things, then it must be animate/living, personal, conscious and endowed with free will. Otherwise, it could not do (or, to be more accurate, cause) anything on its own unless external forces acted upon it – much like the stone. However, the Ultimate/First Cause has no such forces to rely upon – that is precisely &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; it is the Ultimate/First Cause to begin with! Therefore, Personhood and Freedom of the Will seem inescapable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, in a nutshell, is the Kalām Cosmological Argument. It is a very old argument, having roots in the Islamic tradition, but it has recently been popularised by philosopher of religion William Lane Craig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is up to you, dear reader, at the end of the day to judge whether or not the argument is sound. You must do your own research and make up your own mind. But even if you ultimately disagree, I hope you can at least see that the Classical Theist philosophical tradition is nothing like what it is so often made out to be by the New Atheists and their enthusiastic YouTube supporters. Al-Ghazali, Aquinas, Anselm, Aristotle, Augustine, Bonaventure, Scotus – these were not like the illiterate country bumpkins they are so often made out to be. They were brilliant and careful thinkers. Centuries later, their insights still remain true and science has, in fact, confirmed many of their philosophical deductions (for example: al-Ghazali argued centuries ago, on the basis of philosophical argumentation, that time is finite; modern cosmology largely seems to have vindicated him). If you want to see how the argument holds up in the context of debate, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0tYm41hb48o&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9JVRy7bR7zI&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I hope has become obvious, although I have peppered this article with hyperlinks that will prove useful to you, I have not taken it upon myself to answer every question or refute every objection. There are others who have done that and this article has already exceeded 3,000 words. You’ll have to be satisfied with this much for now, at least from me. Plus, since this is an extremely provocative topic, what better way to end it than with a provocative and cliff-hanging conclusion?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This is the first article that I have been privileged to write for The Pangean on the existence of God. Some might be surprised at this. The Pangean, after all, is not a philosophical quarterly. How is this relevant, some might say? To put it simply: in every way. This is an immensely relevant topic because the question of whether or not God exists is surely one of the most significant questions we can ask (in fact, I consider it the most significant). The answer we give to this question will inevitably impact the rest of our worldview as well as influence how we choose to live our lives. Not merely that, this article shall be a bit of an introduction to the field of natural theology: that branch of philosophy devoted to arguments for the existence of God.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘What Do You Believe?’ How Ideology Will Shape the Culture Wars of the 21st Century</title>
      <link href="/What-Do-You-Believe" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘What Do You Believe?’ How Ideology Will Shape the Culture Wars of the 21st Century" />
      <published>2019-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-Do-You-Believe</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-Do-You-Believe">&lt;p&gt;In a way, all of human history is an endless cycle of war and peace. As the old proverb goes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hard times create strong men.&lt;br /&gt;
Strong men create good times.&lt;br /&gt;
Good times create weak men.&lt;br /&gt;
Weak men create hard times.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all at war – in some way or the other, with something or the other. We are all fighting, even for our daily bread. Whether it be bargaining with the local shopkeeper or actually taking up arms against an invader, conflict of some sort or the other pervades our very social existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In centuries past, certain nations decided that the best way to promote their own interest would be to colonise faraway lands located across the seas. This was the age of Conquest, the age of Empires. The result was that entire nations and civilisations came under the commercial and political dominance of unreachable overlords, living in another world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people of these subjugated races and tribes suddenly found themselves living as if on rent on the very land which their ancestors had tilled, ploughed and reaped for their own benefit. Hardship led to resentment. Resentment led to anger. Anger led to rage. Rage led to rebellion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tired of being mocked, of being made to feel ashamed for the colour of their skin or the rhythm of their tongue or the lyric of their songs, they rose in revolt against the imperialist yoke. Those who were wise, left. But those who underestimated the fury of an oppressed race came to rue it to their very last breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nation fought nation; tribe fought tribe. People of one language ostracised those who spoke a different tongue. Those of a particular hue of skin detested those who looked different. These were the ways of a time when one’s loyalty and one’s pride was still rooted to the soil upon which one lived and toiled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that age is no more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;War remains, perhaps ever more keenly than before. But it is a different kind of war. Out of the crucible of human conflict, a new world is being forged. There are several things which have led to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first was the shocking discovery that this Earth could indeed be tamed by the force of human ingenuity. We were told that only the sky is the limit – but even this has proven to be false. The Earth has shown itself to be a very small place indeed, and a new frontier has emerged – the great dark horizon of space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this contraction has only brought people closer together – geographically speaking. We are no longer bound to the soil on which our ancestors lived, moved and had their being. The coming together of continents, facilitated by the meteoric rise of modern transport, has led to the birth of multicultural and multi-ethnic societies around the world, where people of different beliefs and various walks of life have been forced to live their lives side-by-side. Seldom do we think of this, but the fact remains that what we see today – people of myriad ethnicities working together in the same office – would have been unthinkable even a century ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has led to the trivialisation of what originally divided mankind. The white man has come to see in the black man not an inferior creature, but a fellow human being. And the black man has come to see in his white neighbour not a fiendish oppressor from the pits of the underworld, but rather a mere man – with faults and flaws, just like everyone else. The close contact of daily interaction has ensured this. And this has led to a radical change in thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow’s battles will not be fought on the basis of race, language or ethnicity. Tomorrow’s wars will be wars of ideology, wars of belief, wars of religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideology, you see, is not like skin colour or tribal identity. It cannot be as easily brushed aside. Abortion is either right or wrong. It cannot be both right and wrong. Pornography is either moral or immoral. Giving condoms to high school students is either a magnificent step forward in promoting safe sex and sexual freedom, or it is a sign of growing decadence and degeneracy in a society which shamelessly normalises the divorce of sex from marriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when an unstoppable force meets an immovable mass? What happens when one belief system clashes with another? Two world views which are diametrically opposed to each other cannot coexist peacefully. One must prevail; the other must fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The political scientist Samuel P. Huntington famously argued that what the post-Cold War era was about to see was not conflict between countries, but rather between cultures. He called it &lt;em&gt;The Clash of Civilizations&lt;/em&gt;, and hypothesised that ideology – and especially religion – would play a crucially important role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you lived, say, three thousand years ago, you would probably have been born in a monolithic homogeneous society, where there would have been one main philosophy of life, which would have answered all the big questions for you. And in all likelihood, you could have lived your entire life without questioning it – quite natural, given that everyone you knew believed the same things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that is no longer true. The confluence of cultures has resulted in people being exposed to a myriad of different philosophies and beliefs, each quite distinct from their own. Man can no longer be satisfied with accepting answers by faith alone. He has to think and rethink the big questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is his place in the world? Where does he come from? What does it all mean? And what ought one to do while one lives in this changing, transient world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are big questions, and this sudden clash of civilisations has forced the different camps to stop and regroup. And since interaction between different communities is all but inevitable, the conflict of ideas has begun anew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result can easily be seen. Muslims are studying the New Testament and trying to understand what implications it might have on their own beliefs. Christians are studying Arabic and seeking to understand what the Quran actually says. Atheists are studying theology in universities and devout religious believers are devouring the works of Nietzsche and Russell with vigour. And this very happy situation is causing conversions on all sides, of the most lucrative and imaginative kinds. The clash certainly continues and democracy has played a crucial role in ensuring this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The struggle for power is natural to all human societies. In the Middle Ages, it was restricted mostly to the ruling class – aristocrats, nobles, princes, royal families and the like. But the advent of democracy has ensured that the vast citizenry have a vital and crucial say in who ultimately becomes King. And this means that people are much more informed and critical than ever before. Everyone has a vested interest. And everyone is trying to realize their own vision of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;em&gt;belief&lt;/em&gt; plays a crucial role in all this. What do people &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; would be the best for their country, and for the world? Should abortion be legalised or criminalised? Is patriarchy real or is it a myth? Should borders be opened or closed? Is climate change real or is it a hoax? Should churches be taxed or should they be exempted? Should we seek to establish a one world government or do we support the idea of independent, autonomous nation states?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideology shapes the world we live in. And this naturally means that every election – which inevitably guarantees a victory for one side and a defeat for all others – is a microcosm of the great culture war playing out around the world. Whichever side wins, the other naturally feels aggrieved, oppressed and persecuted, and blames the ‘decadent’ victor for ruining the world. This is the sad, but unavoidable result, of a small world in which beliefs and philosophies of life are this varied and polarised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fruits of this are often surprising and, at times, humorous. Today, conservative white Christian folk would rather have fellow Christians of different ethnicities, races and cultures as their neighbours and citizens rather than those of their own race who don’t hold similar values. It’s the same with the Muslim community. Generally speaking, racial differences are becoming less and less relevant, and ideological differences are becoming more pronounced and prominent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, ironically, means that religion and philosophy will come to enjoy an influence they perhaps have not had in the immediate past. The new world war will not be over race or national identity, but over one’s vision for life. The main question our young people will be asked is not “Where do you come from?” but rather “What do you believe?”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In a way, all of human history is an endless cycle of war and peace. As the old proverb goes:</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Fall of Religion in the Millennial West</title>
      <link href="/The-Fall-of-Religion" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fall of Religion in the Millennial West" />
      <published>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Fall-of-Religion</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Fall-of-Religion">&lt;p&gt;One of the most important demographic changes, in recent times, is the rise of the ‘nones’ in Western society. These are a group of people who refuse to identify themselves with any mainstream religious group or denomination. A 2012 article, by the Pew Research Center, noted that “[o]ne-fifth of the U.S. public – and a third of adults under 30 – are religiously unaffiliated today” and “[i]n the last five years alone, the unaffiliated have increased from just over 15% to just under 20% of all U.S. adults. Their ranks now include more than 13 million self-described atheists and agnostics (nearly 6% of the U.S. public), as well as nearly 33 million people who say they have no particular religious affiliation (14%)”. If we look at certain Western European countries and even in some parts of Eastern Europe, the numbers will undoubtedly be higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this happening? Why are young people increasingly disassociating themselves from organised religion, especially in what can only be fittingly described as a post-Christian society?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are four main reasons which I put forward, all of which can be summed up in a single sentence: &lt;strong&gt;Christianity – and, especially, Catholicism - has lost its credibility in the minds of our youth.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1: The Dominant Historical Narrative&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each one of us has heard it sometime or the other. The popular narrative runs thus: human society began well and reached summits of excellence and achievement, especially in the classical age. But when Christianity came, all that progress and achievement, as well as the scientific impulse, came to an end and was effectively destroyed. For centuries, the West was embroiled in a quagmire of oppressive feudalism and religious intolerance, in which free-thinkers were labelled heretics and persecuted fiercely. This was called the &lt;em&gt;Dark Ages&lt;/em&gt;, and rightly so, because human civilisation was truly held in captivity in the darkness of religious bigotry and superstition. All of this was the case, until the time of the Renaissance and the Enlightenment when, finally, we were able to break free of the chains of theocracy and emerge into the bright new world, to build our future for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least, that is how countless millennials understand the Medieval period. It is certainly the way history is taught in our schools, and thus the way many millennials understand this era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Added to this is the stigma of the Crusades and the Inquisitions, both of which are believed to be butcheries of human life and liberty based on religious (and especially Catholic) dogmatism and fanaticism. Fresh in the mind of many of our fellow millennials is the Galileo Affair, in which – it is believed – the geocentric Catholics tried to murder the heliocentric Galileo for the crime of trying to think rationally and not superstitiously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of this narrative, however, is myopic, and fails to take into account the various other factors which were at play. But, unfortunately for people like me, many of my fellow millennials believe this to be the Gospel truth. And naturally, it has distanced them from a religion which, they are convinced, is responsible for stifling human civilisation and progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2: The Widening Gap Between the Jesus of History and the Christ of Faith&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan Brown is one of the most popular fiction authors in the world today. I have had the chance of reading parts of his books, and have found his style to be most engaging. However, Brown is more than your average thriller writer. Thanks to books like &lt;em&gt;The Da Vinci Code&lt;/em&gt;, Brown has managed to bring the ‘Lost Gospels’ to the forefront of public discourse. And boy, has it fired the imagination of the masses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What people like Brown have managed to do is convince the populace – and especially the youth – that there is big difference between the Jesus of Catholicism and the actual Jesus whom we read about in works like the Gospel of Peter and Phillip, for example. He has also managed to alert people regarding the issue of the Biblical canon; why are these four Gospels part of the Bible and not others? Why has the Church chosen to only highlight these particular narratives and declare others heretical?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way information is put out in books such as these has convinced countless many that in the very early history of Christianity, there emerged a power-hungry faction which sought to glorify their own theology at the expense of others. We are told that there was not one but several ‘Christianities’ in the beginning. But one faction – which today exists as the Catholic Church – gained ascendancy and, with quite a bit of patronage from Romam Emperor Constantine, persecuted the other factions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This adds to the impression that today’s youth already has regarding the Christian faith and leaves them with a deep distrust towards anything related to Catholicism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3: The Rise of Philosophical Naturalism and Postmodern Nihilism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone looks at the world through a set of lenses. We all operate with basic metaphysical and epistemological presuppositions. However, in recent times, especially in universities, a particular philosophical perspective has been put forward vociferously, and other points of view have largely been isolated and marginalized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, for a while, was an undergraduate philosophy student at a well-respected university in India. And what I encountered from my professors was not a careful treatment of the various opposing perspectives but rather open and brazen bias, especially when it came to the philosophy of religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What young undergraduates are consistently taught is that the arguments for the existence of God – as put forward by people like Augustine, Aquinas, Leibniz and others – are all extremely poor and fallacious bits of reasoning which can be so easily debunked that one wonders how such eminent men came to such bizarre conclusions. We are also told that these people were motivated by their own personal religious beliefs, and sought to back them up the best they could. What remained was a set of arguments that would only convince people who already had faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least, that is the dominant narrative in philosophical academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And young philosophers usually accept this without question, without delving deeper into the works of Augustine and Aquinas to see if this is indeed true. Most of them don’t bother to later study the philosophy of religion, but rather end up specialising in other fields. And so what they uncritically accept as true in their early years, they end up carrying throughout life. And it is in this way that a consistent naturalist philosophical narrative has been built up over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this has led our young people to be extremely skeptical of any supernatural claims and has, therefore, led them to the conclusion that this world is all there is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting development happening simultaneously is the rise of postmodernism. This is entirely different from the dogmatic atheism I have just described. Rather, this is a dogmatic rejection of all dogmatism, an objective denial of all objectivity. It is a position some might characterise as absurd, but this appellation is readily embraced by some of its vociferous proponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Postmodernism is basically summed up in three maxims: “Truth is what you make of it. Morality is what you shape of it. God is Who you think He/She/It is.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways, this attitude is the product of the younger generation’s exposure to other cultures, viewpoints and ways of thinking. Young people see heated debates in which scholars on both sides put forward their cases and state their opinions, each backing themselves up with copious argumentation. They see different religions and ways of life, entirely different from the ones they had been exposed to. And having no strong rational grounds to support the religion of their upbringing, they naturally come to the conclusion that ‘man is the measure of all things’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This understanding of life is indeed very attractive since it promises a kind of godhood. One is free to shape one’s reality and one’s destiny as one sees it. One is free to identify as whatever one pleases and be whoever one wishes to be. Above all, one is liberated from the shackles of dogmatism, free to believe whatever they wish to believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, anyone addicted to this euphoria of freedom will find organised religion, with all its creeds and ancient affirmations, very unattractive indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4: The Transformation of Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps the most important and significant of all, since it strikes not merely at our intellect but also at our emotions. The cultural elite of the West are working very hard to change and transform culture. They do this through books, films, magazines and mass media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example: Imagine that you have grown up in a very conservative society, your parents told you that the right thing to do was to dress modestly, especially in front of the opposite sex. What happens when you are constantly exposed to pictures of men and women in states of partial or complete undress, when you can hardly go to the movies or even switch on a television without coming across some scene or advertisement that is either sexually explicit or has strong sexual themes, that too being performed by men and women who are great artists whom you admire?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, your perception is going to shift. You would in all likelihood rather imitate your heroes and role models rather than your parents, in this case. And in all probability, your friends have similar attitudes in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these factors come together and compound in such a way that it is possible to change views about something as fundamental as human sexuality across the course of a generation! Changing one’s views on sexual ethics is nothing more and nothing less than a paradigm shift. Instead of being something that is sacred and to be enjoyed within the context of marriage in a reproductively responsible manner, young people are offered the alluring option of ‘sex with no strings attached’. Rather than being the self-giving expression of commitment and love between two spouses (as Christians have traditionally believed), it has become a ‘casual’ affair. It is, therefore, no wonder that our young people are losing their faith in traditional Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popular music has played an inestimable role in detaching young people from the Christian faith. Young people see singers who are clearly extraordinarily talented, beloved by all their friends and peer groups, and who sing songs that contain themes that are clearly contrary to Christian faith and morals, in more ways than one. Naturally, over time, one comes to favour one’s friend groups rather than one’s parents and one begins to side with the more secularising culture rather than traditional ways of living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I am a millennial myself. But I am not your average millennial. In fact, I am a convert to the Catholic Church, having come from a liberal Hindu background myself. I am the black sheep, so to speak, of this modern and enlightened generation. What causes me to remain traditional and Catholic? Why don’t I simply join the great secular bus and enjoy all the many benefits its offers? Why do I remain in the shadows and willingly disassociate myself from much of the modern world and even isolate myself, at times, enjoying but a few friends?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons are endless, but I will summarise it in a few brief points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, it is my firmest conviction that the conventional narrative about the &lt;em&gt;Dark Ages&lt;/em&gt; is thoroughly erroneous, and in fact holds little water in academic circles, thank God. This view of the Medieval Church as an oppressive, science-persecuting religion has been increasingly discredited in modern times, not least by the excellent work of the Pulitzer-Prize winning Rodney Stark who, although himself a non-Catholic, has taken it upon himself to work towards exonerating the Catholic Church from baseless myths and lies, as can be seen in his work &lt;em&gt;Bearing False Witness&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, this idea that the Church persecuted scientists fails to take into account the immense contributions the Church made to science, in the Middle Ages and after as well. It is true that Galileo was persecuted – on charges of heresy. But what is left unmentioned is that Copernicus’s heliocentrism fascinated the Pope of his time, who spoke highly of him on numerous occasions. What is also conveniently left out is the devoutly Christian spirit of the countless intellectuals across the course of history who laid the foundations of modern science, believing that their study and analysis of the natural world was a kind of worship of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are we then left with? Is there no future for religion in the West?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religion will survive. The Church will always be there in the West, even if it is weakened and marginalised. Popular culture and the mass media already brand the Christian faith as regressive. It is perhaps only a matter of time before popular opinion turns into political legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Church will survive. It always has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only that, it has found a new homeland. As the West continues to go down this slippery slope and continues to schism itself from its Christian roots, the great African continent has already opened its arms wide open, in welcome of the Gospel and the Church.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the most important demographic changes, in recent times, is the rise of the ‘nones’ in Western society. These are a group of people who refuse to identify themselves with any mainstream religious group or denomination. A 2012 article, by the Pew Research Center, noted that “[o]ne-fifth of the U.S. public – and a third of adults under 30 – are religiously unaffiliated today” and “[i]n the last five years alone, the unaffiliated have increased from just over 15% to just under 20% of all U.S. adults. Their ranks now include more than 13 million self-described atheists and agnostics (nearly 6% of the U.S. public), as well as nearly 33 million people who say they have no particular religious affiliation (14%)”. If we look at certain Western European countries and even in some parts of Eastern Europe, the numbers will undoubtedly be higher.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Understanding Jihad</title>
      <link href="/Understanding-Jihad" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding Jihad" />
      <published>2019-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Understanding-Jihad</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Understanding-Jihad">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jihad&lt;/em&gt;; possibly the most polarising word in the Arabic language. It provokes a range of varied reactions, depending on the perspective through which one looks at it. And it is true to say that the word has largely been misunderstood in non-Muslim circles. So before I even begin said analysis, I must make a series of clarifications and preliminary disclaimers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, my article is not intended to be an attack upon the Muslim community. Nor is it meant to be a criticism of individual Muslims. Some of the most kind, brotherly and loving people I have met are devout practicing Muslims and I am grateful to God for their friendship. I also recognise that there are countless members of the Islamic &lt;em&gt;ummah&lt;/em&gt; who are peaceful and humane people, truly worthy of our respect as fellow human beings. My article is not meant to be an indictment of the entire Muslim people. Rather, my goal is to analyse the concept of &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt;, and how it has been understood by most of the mainstream Islamic schools of thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I recognise and mourn the tragedies and persecutions which Muslim people have had to endure. I condemn in no uncertain terms the attacks upon innocent Muslims that have taken place on account of their faith. No one should ever be harmed or attacked or despised or be held in suspicion simply for being a Muslim. Indeed, my goal is not to spread suspicion against Muslims. I invite all people to extend their arms wide open in welcome for their Muslim friends, neighbours and fellow human beings, especially to Muslim refugees in need, and to give them the love and the affection that we indeed owe them as fellow citizens of this Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, my criticisms will not apply to quite a few schools of thought in Islam. They do not apply, for example, to the Ahmadi Muslim Community, which I consider to be the most peaceful sect of Islam. Nor do they apply to the Ibadis, who have proven themselves to be very tolerant and welcoming, and regarding their theology I have little knowledge and have no wish to pontificate. My criticisms mostly apply to Sunni and Shia schools of thought, but even among them there are exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I do not pretend to be a scholar of Islam. I am merely an interested layperson. So take all my claims with a grain of salt. Fact-check them and see if they are correct. I write with little formal authority on the subject, but with the firmest of convictions that I am right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourthly, please don’t be surprised that the views I document, describe and criticise in this article are not held by many of the average Muslims. Laypeople of all religions are known to have a poor track record of understanding what their religion actually teaches, and it is not uncommon to see that at times the views of laypeople are significantly at variance with the views of their own religious leaders. A good example is seen among some ‘Catholics’ in North America, many of whom practice contraception and have no problem with abortion, both of which are strongly condemned by the leaders of the Church they belong to and claim to profess faith in. Similarly, many ‘Protestants’ in England and Northern Europe don’t even believe in a physical Resurrection anymore, a belief which is absolutely central to historic Protestant orthodoxy. The views of laypeople are rarely barometers for the beliefs of the religion they follow, though, of course, there are exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all that said, let us press on the main subject matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you are me and you hail from a liberal background and you’ve had the same experience I’ve had, one of the first things you would have heard about Islam – especially from Westernised non-Muslim liberals – is how wonderful it truly is. You would have been told that Islam promotes peace, harmony, cultural diversity, coexistence and the emancipation of women. You would even have been informed that the word ‘Islam’ has its roots in a word which means ‘peace’. And, of course, you would have been told that the word ‘jihad’ does not mean ‘terrorism’ or ‘holy war’ but rather ‘struggle’. And don’t we all struggle against something or the other, especially against the faults in our own personality?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, much of these claims are true, to some degree or the other. However, the problem is that this narrative, although it certainly has a grain of truth, does not tell the whole story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is true that ‘jihad’ does not mean ‘terrorism’ or ‘violence’ but ‘struggle’. But what many people aren’t told is that the ‘struggle’ in Islam is not merely against personal faults, but also against injustice in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, some of you might be wondering, “Well, what’s wrong with that? Surely, we all have a duty to fight injustice?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem, of course, is not that Islam exhorts war against injustice. The issue, however, is how Islam defines injustice. And injustice, in the Islamic context, is quite different from the SJW conception of ‘injustice’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Islamic word for this is &lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt;. It literally means ‘corruption’ or ‘rottenness’. Consider, for instance, the following passage from the Quran, which talks about people who promote &lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;When they are told, ‘Do not cause corruption on the earth,’ they say, ‘We are only reformers!’
Look! They are themselves the agents of corruption, but they are not aware.”&lt;/em&gt; (Quran 2:11-12).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To whom does this passage refer? To corruption in general? To things like stealing, murder, adultery, etc., which most human beings would agree are corrupt deeds? No doubt, in Islam, these things are certainly sinful and are also part of corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in the context of this particular passage, the corruption refers not to sin in general, but very specifically to the sin of unbelief. Here’s what the preceding five verses say. I have added some emphasis to bring out the major themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As for the &lt;strong&gt;faithless&lt;/strong&gt;, it is the same to them whether you warn them or do not warn them, &lt;strong&gt;they will not have faith&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allah has set a seal on their hearts and their hearing, and there is a blindfold on their sight, and there is a great punishment for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And among the people are those who say, ‘We have faith in Allah and the Last Day,’ but &lt;strong&gt;they have no faith&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They seek to deceive Allah and those who have faith, yet they deceive no one but themselves, but they are not aware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sickness in their hearts; then Allah increased their sickness, and there is a painful punishment for them &lt;strong&gt;because of the lies they used to tell.&lt;/strong&gt;” (Quran 2:6-10)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this passage is condemning a very specific form of &lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt; – the sin of &lt;em&gt;kufr&lt;/em&gt; or unbelief, and the telling of lies based upon this &lt;em&gt;kufr&lt;/em&gt;. The word &lt;em&gt;kufr&lt;/em&gt; is the one from which comes the word &lt;em&gt;kafir&lt;/em&gt; or non-believer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the point even clearer, here is what the Quranic passage says right after verse 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;And when they are told, ‘Believe like the people who have believed,’ they say, &lt;strong&gt;‘Shall we believe like the fools who have believed?’&lt;/strong&gt; Look! They are themselves the fools, but they do not know.
When they meet the faithful, they say, ‘We believe,’ &lt;strong&gt;but when they are alone with their devils, they say, ‘We are with you; we were only deriding [them].&lt;/strong&gt;’
It is Allah who derides them, and leaves them bewildered in their rebellion.&lt;/em&gt;” (Quran 2:13-15).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So not only is the passage condemning a particular form of &lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt; (corruption) – &lt;em&gt;kufr&lt;/em&gt; (unbelief) – it is condemning a very specific kind of &lt;em&gt;kufr&lt;/em&gt;: the sin of pretending to be a Muslim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As noted before, Islam places a lot of emphasis upon justice (&lt;em&gt;adl&lt;/em&gt;). Striving to achieve justice is a virtue in Islam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, once more, the simple fact is that justice is defined very differently in Islam from the way a liberal might understand justice. Justice in Islam is, to put it simply, &lt;em&gt;Islam itself&lt;/em&gt;, and anything which detracts from Islam or diverges from Islam is, in some sense, to varying degrees, injustice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the struggle (&lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt;) against corruption (&lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt;) in order to achieve justice (&lt;em&gt;adl&lt;/em&gt;) is nothing more and nothing less than a struggle to achieve the triumph of Islam, in every sphere of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, there are different kinds of &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt; in Islam. And there are many interpretations of jihad. Hardly any of these interpretations are pacifistic, but not all of them are hyper-militaristic. Let’s stop there for a moment and consider some important facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Islamic theology and jurisprudence are based upon the Quran (believed to be the Word of God) and the Sunnah (the path of the Prophet). The latter is known from the various &lt;em&gt;hadith&lt;/em&gt;. These are narrations, orally transmitted across several centuries, which relate stories about or quotations from the Prophet and/or his family (the &lt;em&gt;Ahlul Bayt&lt;/em&gt;) and/or his companions. Sunnis and Shias have different Hadith collections. The Sunnis have the six books, chief among them being Sahih Bukhari and Sahih Muslim. The Shias have the Kitab-al-Kafi and three others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all hadith are uncritically accepted. Some are strong (that is, believed to be reliable narrations). Others are thought weak and unreliable. And contradictions among them abound, thereby producing a variety of schools of thought and interpretations thereof. Generally speaking, however, there are three main classifications of &lt;em&gt;hadith&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;em&gt;sahih&lt;/em&gt; (authentic), &lt;em&gt;hasan&lt;/em&gt; (good) and &lt;em&gt;da’if&lt;/em&gt; (weak). &lt;em&gt;Sahih&lt;/em&gt; is the highest epithet that can be applied to a hadith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Islamic theology about &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt; comes from the Quran. But the Quran is not written like other books. For one, it is not arranged chronologically in the order in which it was written. The first chapter of the Quran that was allegedly revealed to Muhammad was Chapter 96, &lt;em&gt;Surah Al-Alaq&lt;/em&gt;. Even the different passages in the Quran were sometimes revealed at different times and in very specific contexts. All of these are haphazard in arrangement. This can be seen especially in &lt;em&gt;Surah Maryam&lt;/em&gt;, in which several Biblical prophets are mentioned, but in a mixed up order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why on the one hand you have passages which seem to call for peace and others which seem to urge violence. Unless we want to affirm that the author(s) of the Quran was/were confused, we must realise that there is great ambiguity in understanding the intent, purposes and context of these conflicting verses. Some scholars even say that if commands in the Quran contradict, the one which was revealed later repeals the one which came before. This interpretation is quite common and well-known among scholars in the Muslim world (though not, thankfully, universally accepted) and is itself based upon a Quranic verse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Whatever communications We abrogate or cause to be forgotten, We bring one better than it or like it. Do you not know that Allah has power over all things?&lt;/em&gt;” (Quran 2:106)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with this interpretation, of course, is that many of the violent passages seem to have popped up at a later date than the more peaceful ones, according to Islam’s own sources! If this interpretation is to be followed, we would perhaps have to adopt a more violent form of Islam, because the more militaristic-sounding verses would then repeal the more peaceful and tolerant-sounding ones and become, as David Wood says, “the final marching orders” of that religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, of course, interpretations are manifold and varied. As stated before, while &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt; is an integral part of Islam, it is certainly true that not every school of thought takes a hyper-militaristic view of it. In many schools, &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt; is non-violent for the most part. However, once &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt; becomes successful and Islam gains dominance in society, a different picture emerges. Most of the mainstream Islamic schools of jurisprudence affirm that if Islam manages to take hold of a society, it should become the state religion and the entire country – both Muslims and non-Muslims - should be governed according to the law of Allah. It is now that the persecution of minorities becomes almost inescapable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider for instance what is considered one of the most peaceful verses in the Quran:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;On that account: We ordained for the Children of Israel that if any one slew a person - unless it be for murder or for spreading mischief in the land - it would be as if he slew the whole people: and if any one saved a life, it would be as if he saved the life of the whole people.&lt;/em&gt;” (Qur’an 5:32)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberals often cite this verse as an evidence of the peaceful and tolerant nature of Islam, but what they fail to understand is that “spreading mischief in the land” (the word originally used in Arabic, again, is &lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt;) means a whole host of things in Islam, and many Islamic scholars and theologians would gladly agree that insulting the religion, mocking the prophet or preaching other religions to Muslims is a part of &lt;em&gt;fasad&lt;/em&gt;. In other words, rather than being an exhortation to promote equality and egalitarianism as some silly liberals vainly imagine, the exhortation would actually justify the killing and/or incarceration of Christian missionaries who preach Christianity in Muslim lands!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another good example is the case of apostasy. What if there is a Muslim who has lost faith and wishes to leave the &lt;em&gt;ummah&lt;/em&gt;? Here again, the Islamic testimony seems contradictory. Qur’an 2:256 literally states that there is ‘no compulsion in religion’. For many ears, this sounds pretty peaceful. However, can this text be applied to apostates, or does it refer only to the non-Muslim embracing Islam (for the first time)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain &lt;em&gt;hadith&lt;/em&gt; seem to indicate that it is the latter. Consider for instance the following citation from Sahih Bukhari, one of the most respected Sunni Hadith collections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Narrated Abdullah:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allah’s Messenger said, “The blood of a Muslim who confesses that none has the right to be worshipped but Allah and that I am His Apostle, cannot be shed except in three cases: In Qisas for murder, a married person who commits illegal sexual intercourse and the one who reverts from Islam (apostate) and leaves the Muslims.” Sahih Bukhari 9:83:17&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar Hadith are also found in Sahih Muslim 16:4152 and 4154. And all three of these &lt;em&gt;hadith&lt;/em&gt; are considered authentic (&lt;em&gt;sahih&lt;/em&gt;) which, as stated earlier, is the highest epithet that can be given to a &lt;em&gt;hadith&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As noted before, the evidence seems ambiguous and difficult to interpret. However, historically, most of the major Islamic schools of jurisprudence have indeed advocated the death penalty for apostasy. Even a peaceful liberal Muslim who interprets the texts in a different way cannot deny this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once one understands this, one will realise why Muslim countries tend to be more religiously intolerant than non-Muslim countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is true that many Muslim scholars and theologians advocate a non-violent form of Jihad which mostly involves prayer, memorising the Quran, fasting and preaching Islam in a peaceful, non-coercive manner. However, once Islam gains dominance and a large portion of the population has embraced the faith, most schools of jurisprudence would gladly advocate the setting up of an Islamic state. And one need only look at the Middle East to see what that would be like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One must also realise that Islam is quite stringently theocratic. Except in certain less influential schools of thought, setting up a religious state is always considered the ideal. The only thing is, setting up an Islamic state is not always possible for Muslims, especially in lands where Islam has little influence. It is only in these settings that puritanical Muslims advocate secularism. The separation of mosque and state is always considered a compromise by the mainstream schools of jurisprudence, never the ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideal is always an Islamic state. And all jihad – even the most peaceful forms of it – is ultimately meant to accomplish the ideal. And I will only leave the reader to contemplate the ominous implications that entails.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Jihad; possibly the most polarising word in the Arabic language. It provokes a range of varied reactions, depending on the perspective through which one looks at it. And it is true to say that the word has largely been misunderstood in non-Muslim circles. So before I even begin said analysis, I must make a series of clarifications and preliminary disclaimers.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How to Talk About Islam</title>
      <link href="/How-to-Talk-about-Islam" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Talk About Islam" />
      <published>2019-04-25T14:05:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-25T14:05:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/How-to-Talk-about-Islam</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/How-to-Talk-about-Islam">&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt that Islam is by far the most powerful religion in the world
today. With a presence on almost every continent inhabited by man, a powerful
theocratic political influence in countries dominated by its adherents, a
rapidly increasing immigrant population in post-Christian European countries, an
ever-strengthening missionary influence, and a global following of more than a
billion people, it has come to influence much of the modern world. In 2008, the
Vatican revealed that Muslims have overtaken Catholics as far as the number of
members is concerned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, it is no longer possible for people to simply ignore the Islamic
phenomenon, no matter what their opinion of it might be. The reason is that
Islam is quite unavoidable. There is hardly a place on earth when the &lt;em&gt;adhan&lt;/em&gt;
cannot be heard. There is a hardly a skyline which does not have a minaret
reaching up to the heavens. No matter where you go, Islam is there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a convert from Hinduism to orthodox Catholicism, there is much in Islam that
I admire, despite the deeply troubled history that my Church has shared with the
followers of Muhammad. I deeply admire, for instance, Islam’s teachings on
modesty. I am appreciative of many of the values which Islam inculcates in its
adherents – the devotion to one’s parents and the respect for elders.
Catholicism and Islam both profess to be monotheistic and eschew the joining of
partners with Almighty God, although our views about the nature of Almighty God
are radically different. And it goes without saying that I condemn any and all
forms of violence, hatred, and bigotry towards Muslims on the basis of their
religious affiliation as unethical, immoral and – above all – un-Christian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are also elements in Islam that I find deeply troubling. Now,
notice that I use the word “elements in Islam”, rather than simply “Islam”.
After all, there are many different groups that profess to be Muslim and which
have different interpretations of Islam. For instance, the Ahmadiyya Muslim
Community is entirely pacifistic in nature and condemns any and all forms of
religious terrorism. There are also many Sufis, Salafis, and mainstream Sunnis
who have condemned violence against non-Muslims and advocate a more apolitical
form of Islam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I acknowledge and respect the fact that the texts which &lt;em&gt;seem&lt;/em&gt; to call for
violence – in the Quran and the Hadith – are open to interpretation. As such, it
is not my intention to paint all Muslims with a broad brush, or to pretend that
Islam is monolithic. Just as it would be disingenuous for someone to paint my
faith or any other faith with gross overgeneralizations, so would be to do the
same with Islam. However, there are certainly some trends in the modern media
that are problematic and need to be addressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a tendency (among many secularists, liberals and the left-leaning) to
classify all critics of Islam as part of the far-right. This is not only
inaccurate, but also extremely dangerous, and contrary to the principle of the
freedom of expression. The act of criticising a particular
ideology/proposition/belief system is not the same as advocating violence,
hatred, discrimination or bigotry against proponents of that
ideology/proposition/belief system&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is true that all those who advocate violence against proponents of a
particular ideology/proposition/belief system also happen to be critics of that
particular ideology/proposition/belief system. But not all who criticise the
ideology/proposition/belief system are calling for violence against proponents
of that ideology/proposition/belief system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give an example from everyday life: all oranges are fruits, but not all
fruits are oranges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oranges might be bad, and all oranges might be fruits, but the fact that all
oranges are bad does not imply that all fruits are bad, even though all oranges
are fruits. This is because of the very simple fact that there are some fruits
which are not oranges. In other words, all anti-Muslim bigots are critics of
Islam, but not all critics of Islam are anti-Muslim bigots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider, for example, the case of David Wood, a convert from atheism to
Christianity. Wood is a fairly prominent critic of Islam. He has criticised the
teachings of Islam as inherently violent, the founder of Islam as an immoral
man, and the claims of Islam as intellectually deficient. However, I am yet to
come across a single video in which he has called for hatred against Muslims. On
the contrary, I follow him regularly and can testify that, as far as I can see,
he has nothing in his heart but love for Muslims, whom he believes to be in
error. This he has demonstrated on numerous occasions in many ways. One of the
best examples I can give is when he actually attempted to meet with someone who
had threatened to kill him. He recorded the occasion on camera when he visited
the agreed-upon venue and found that his would-be assassin hadn’t turned up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a professed Christian evangelist, Wood’s goal is not to spread bigotry
against Muslims, but to show Muslims (what he considers to be) the defects in
Islam, and to invite them to (what he believes to be) a better way:
Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what has been the response to his criticism? Intelligent, counter-critiques
from Muslims? On occasion, yes, as we see in the case of the Islamic scholar
(and gentleman) Shabir Ally who has debated him on numerous occasions and who
has always treated him with dignity, respect, and goodwill. However, much of the
backlash against his work has been neither intelligent, nor reasoned, nor
humane. Much of the responses to his criticism include death threats and the
mockery of his disabled children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, not every Muslim has responded in this manner. Of course, there are
many Muslims who would consider such barbaric behaviour to be un-Islamic. Of
course, such aforementioned peaceful Muslims may (and probably do) have peaceful
interpretations of Islam. But what we must realise is that there is a powerful
party within the religion of Islam which is violent, intolerant of criticism,
aggressively imperialist and which bases their beliefs not on political
convictions but on religiously motivated interpretations of Quranic and Hadithic
texts. And it is these hyper-fundamentalists who are making use of the
atmosphere of ‘tolerance’ and political correctness to advance an agenda that is
diabolical and toxic. Attempts to suppress peaceful, intelligent critics of
Islam is not ‘tolerance’. It is intolerance. And such attempts play right into
the hands of the Islamists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interesting thing that we see in the case of Wood is that a number of these
internet jihadis have started false-flagging his content. The shocking result
has been that Facebook has notified him that some of his posts “go against”
their community guidelines. These include posts in which Wood simply informed
his audiences of the most recent threats he had gotten from jihadis! Not a
single one of them included a call to violence, but only an appeal to keep-up
the criticism and satire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems, at times, that the people running Facebook have an extremely warped
idea of what hate speech is. Criticising an ideology as intellectually and
morally deficient is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; hate speech, but threatening someone for making those
criticisms certainly is. Indeed, as I have been at pains to emphasise: we have
to love our Muslim friends, condemn acts of violence against Muslims and fight
anti-Muslim discrimination. But that doesn’t mean we must be naïve and pretend
that Islam is a wholly pacifistic religion and that all the IS terrorists are
merely politically-motivated people using religion as a cover to gain support
for their cause. Such an analysis is not only painfully ignorant of the facts,
but is also dangerous since it encourages complacency against what is clearly a
rising tide of religiously-motivated Islamic fundamentalism in the world today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should we similarly pretend that the founder of Islam was a feminist and a
pacifist? No. If the historical evidence does not indicate that he was such, we
should not pretend that he was such. We should portray him in as historically
accurate a manner as possible – even if that portrayal is deemed offensive and
blasphemous by violent cyber-jihadists who have only one goal: the violent
promulgation of a religious system and the suppression of all criticism of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many peaceful, kind, gentlemanly and dignified people in the Muslim
community who would consider themselves orthodox and who would, in fact, agree
with what I am saying today. Yet, that still begs the question: how &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; we
talk about Islam? We should seek to honestly evaluate the religion itself. But
how should we judge what the religion is? There are peaceful Muslims and violent
Muslims, just as there are peaceful Christians and violent Christians. Which are
the true followers, and which are more influenced by other ideologies rather
than the doctrine itself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience (having extensively and intensively studied religion for around
ten years now), we should always judge a religion on the basis of its &lt;em&gt;Sources&lt;/em&gt;
and its &lt;em&gt;Heroes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I mean by this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Sources&lt;/em&gt; of a religion are essentially its authorities and/or sources of
doctrine. In Protestant Christianity, the &lt;em&gt;Source&lt;/em&gt; is Scripture alone, and its
plain perspicuous teaching. In Catholic Christianity, the source is Scripture
and Apostolic Tradition as received and interpreted by the Magisterium (i.e.,
the Church itself).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Heroes&lt;/em&gt; of a religion are those figures which have been deemed by the
Sources/Authorities as having followed the religion well (though not necessarily
perfectly, and there are different grades of heroes in every religion). The
ultimate Hero of all Christianity is Jesus Himself, who is believed to be the
perfect man. In Catholicism, the heroes are (to a certain degree) the saints.
Although it is generally agreed that the canonisation process only grants us
certainty that the deceased is in heaven, not that the person always lived an
exemplary life. This gives room for the believing Catholic to criticise even the
acts of saints, as many traditionalists have done with St. Mother Teresa, to
give an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Islam, the greatest hero is Muhammad himself, who is considered to be the
perfect example for all mankind. In Sunni Islam, Muhammad is closely followed by
the Four Rightly Guided Caliphs, whereas in Shia Islam, Muhammad is but one of
Fourteen Infallibles, which include – besides the founder himself – Fatima and
the Twelve Imams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, when we judge Islam, we should first distinguish between the various schools
of Islam. Sunni Islam is not the same as Shia Islam or Ibadi Islam or Ahmadi
Islam. There are, so to speak, quite a few ‘Islams’, just as there are different
interpretations of Marxism, democracy, libertarianism, capitalism, feminism and
just about everything else. In other words, the next time you see some act of
violence perpetrated by fundamentalists of any religion or sect, ask yourself
the question: is this act of violence commanded by the Sources of the faith in
question? Is there any precedent for this sort of terror in the behaviour of its
heroes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should ask the same question when it comes to the good actions of peaceful
adherents. When you see followers of a religion endorsing pacifism or separation
of religion and state, are they acting faithfully according to their Sources and
Heroes? Or are there more influenced by other ideologies, in light of which they
interpret their religion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I end this article with a comparison between the Christian Crusades and the
Islamic Mujahideen. The Crusades were an administrative decision, in part made
by the Pope. Catholicism does not require its adherents to consider Papal
administrative decisions as infallible – the only infallible things coming out
of the Pope are his ratifications of ecumenical councils and ex-cathedra
statements; that is to say, matters which &lt;em&gt;solely&lt;/em&gt; concern doctrine and dogma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Administrative decisions, as per Catholic ecclesiology, are &lt;em&gt;entirely&lt;/em&gt; fallible.
As a matter of fact, it is the conservatives in the Church who are very loud in
criticising the administrative decisions of recent Popes, such as the decision
of Pope Paul VI to allow the priest to celebrate the Mass facing the
congregation (&lt;em&gt;versus populum&lt;/em&gt;) rather than the East (&lt;em&gt;ad orientem&lt;/em&gt;) as has
traditionally been practised. So, largely, the Crusades are not part of Catholic
doctrine, if at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not say this in order to “wash my hands clean” of the Crusades, so to
speak. Personally, I think the Crusades had a noble intent in &lt;em&gt;theory&lt;/em&gt; (i.e.,
that of defending Christendom), but I lament the fact that in &lt;em&gt;practice&lt;/em&gt; many of
the Crusaders became too extreme. Rather than simply defeating enemy military
forces, they committed unspeakable atrocities upon civilians which are
horrendous, lamentable and condemnable. As a traditional and orthodox Catholic,
I am &lt;em&gt;ashamed&lt;/em&gt; of the misdeeds that were perpetrated in the name of the
Crusades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here’s the thing: my religion gives me the liberty to say this. My faith
does not compel me to believe that the Crusaders were “inspired by God”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when you study the early Muslim invasions of neighbouring civilisations, ask
yourself the question: can we say the same about Islam? Who led these invasions?
Were these figures deemed by Islam to be inspired by God in their acts and to
be, in some sense, infallible? Do the chief sources command its adherents to
consider their acts of war as virtuous on the part of a ruler? Our judgment of
Islam should be based on these facts. I will leave you to make up your own mind.
It may turn out that, in fact, Islam is an extremely peaceful and humane
religion. Or it may turn out another way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only ask you to use sound judgment in your study and to not be afraid of the
truth, however hard it may turn out to be. However, in all our critique or
appraisal, we must remember that our analysis of a doctrine should not seep into
a generalisation of the moral character of the adherents of that doctrine. This
attitude allows me to be extremely kind and respectful to my Muslim friends
while, at the same time, giving me total liberty to analyse and evaluate the
religion as my conscience commands me. And that is how we should talk about
Islam today, condemning it where we see condemnation due, fighting for and
respecting its adherents when they so require, and accepting or rejecting it for
what it is when truth so demands.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There is no doubt that Islam is by far the most powerful religion in the world today. With a presence on almost every continent inhabited by man, a powerful theocratic political influence in countries dominated by its adherents, a rapidly increasing immigrant population in post-Christian European countries, an ever-strengthening missionary influence, and a global following of more than a billion people, it has come to influence much of the modern world. In 2008, the Vatican revealed that Muslims have overtaken Catholics as far as the number of members is concerned. As such, it is no longer possible for people to simply ignore the Islamic phenomenon, no matter what their opinion of it might be. The reason is that Islam is quite unavoidable. There is hardly a place on earth when the adhan cannot be heard. There is a hardly a skyline which does not have a minaret reaching up to the heavens. No matter where you go, Islam is there. As a convert from Hinduism to orthodox Catholicism, there is much in Islam that I admire, despite the deeply troubled history that my Church has shared with the followers of Muhammad. I deeply admire, for instance, Islam’s teachings on modesty. I am appreciative of many of the values which Islam inculcates in its adherents – the devotion to one’s parents and the respect for elders. Catholicism and Islam both profess to be monotheistic and eschew the joining of partners with Almighty God, although our views about the nature of Almighty God are radically different. And it goes without saying that I condemn any and all forms of violence, hatred, and bigotry towards Muslims on the basis of their religious affiliation as unethical, immoral and – above all – un-Christian. However, there are also elements in Islam that I find deeply troubling. Now, notice that I use the word “elements in Islam”, rather than simply “Islam”. After all, there are many different groups that profess to be Muslim and which have different interpretations of Islam. For instance, the Ahmadiyya Muslim Community is entirely pacifistic in nature and condemns any and all forms of religious terrorism. There are also many Sufis, Salafis, and mainstream Sunnis who have condemned violence against non-Muslims and advocate a more apolitical form of Islam. I acknowledge and respect the fact that the texts which seem to call for violence – in the Quran and the Hadith – are open to interpretation. As such, it is not my intention to paint all Muslims with a broad brush, or to pretend that Islam is monolithic. Just as it would be disingenuous for someone to paint my faith or any other faith with gross overgeneralizations, so would be to do the same with Islam. However, there are certainly some trends in the modern media that are problematic and need to be addressed. There is a tendency (among many secularists, liberals and the left-leaning) to classify all critics of Islam as part of the far-right. This is not only inaccurate, but also extremely dangerous, and contrary to the principle of the freedom of expression. The act of criticising a particular ideology/proposition/belief system is not the same as advocating violence, hatred, discrimination or bigotry against proponents of that ideology/proposition/belief system Yes, it is true that all those who advocate violence against proponents of a particular ideology/proposition/belief system also happen to be critics of that particular ideology/proposition/belief system. But not all who criticise the ideology/proposition/belief system are calling for violence against proponents of that ideology/proposition/belief system. To give an example from everyday life: all oranges are fruits, but not all fruits are oranges. Oranges might be bad, and all oranges might be fruits, but the fact that all oranges are bad does not imply that all fruits are bad, even though all oranges are fruits. This is because of the very simple fact that there are some fruits which are not oranges. In other words, all anti-Muslim bigots are critics of Islam, but not all critics of Islam are anti-Muslim bigots. Consider, for example, the case of David Wood, a convert from atheism to Christianity. Wood is a fairly prominent critic of Islam. He has criticised the teachings of Islam as inherently violent, the founder of Islam as an immoral man, and the claims of Islam as intellectually deficient. However, I am yet to come across a single video in which he has called for hatred against Muslims. On the contrary, I follow him regularly and can testify that, as far as I can see, he has nothing in his heart but love for Muslims, whom he believes to be in error. This he has demonstrated on numerous occasions in many ways. One of the best examples I can give is when he actually attempted to meet with someone who had threatened to kill him. He recorded the occasion on camera when he visited the agreed-upon venue and found that his would-be assassin hadn’t turned up. As a professed Christian evangelist, Wood’s goal is not to spread bigotry against Muslims, but to show Muslims (what he considers to be) the defects in Islam, and to invite them to (what he believes to be) a better way: Christianity. But what has been the response to his criticism? Intelligent, counter-critiques from Muslims? On occasion, yes, as we see in the case of the Islamic scholar (and gentleman) Shabir Ally who has debated him on numerous occasions and who has always treated him with dignity, respect, and goodwill. However, much of the backlash against his work has been neither intelligent, nor reasoned, nor humane. Much of the responses to his criticism include death threats and the mockery of his disabled children. Of course, not every Muslim has responded in this manner. Of course, there are many Muslims who would consider such barbaric behaviour to be un-Islamic. Of course, such aforementioned peaceful Muslims may (and probably do) have peaceful interpretations of Islam. But what we must realise is that there is a powerful party within the religion of Islam which is violent, intolerant of criticism, aggressively imperialist and which bases their beliefs not on political convictions but on religiously motivated interpretations of Quranic and Hadithic texts. And it is these hyper-fundamentalists who are making use of the atmosphere of ‘tolerance’ and political correctness to advance an agenda that is diabolical and toxic. Attempts to suppress peaceful, intelligent critics of Islam is not ‘tolerance’. It is intolerance. And such attempts play right into the hands of the Islamists. The interesting thing that we see in the case of Wood is that a number of these internet jihadis have started false-flagging his content. The shocking result has been that Facebook has notified him that some of his posts “go against” their community guidelines. These include posts in which Wood simply informed his audiences of the most recent threats he had gotten from jihadis! Not a single one of them included a call to violence, but only an appeal to keep-up the criticism and satire. It seems, at times, that the people running Facebook have an extremely warped idea of what hate speech is. Criticising an ideology as intellectually and morally deficient is not hate speech, but threatening someone for making those criticisms certainly is. Indeed, as I have been at pains to emphasise: we have to love our Muslim friends, condemn acts of violence against Muslims and fight anti-Muslim discrimination. But that doesn’t mean we must be naïve and pretend that Islam is a wholly pacifistic religion and that all the IS terrorists are merely politically-motivated people using religion as a cover to gain support for their cause. Such an analysis is not only painfully ignorant of the facts, but is also dangerous since it encourages complacency against what is clearly a rising tide of religiously-motivated Islamic fundamentalism in the world today. Should we similarly pretend that the founder of Islam was a feminist and a pacifist? No. If the historical evidence does not indicate that he was such, we should not pretend that he was such. We should portray him in as historically accurate a manner as possible – even if that portrayal is deemed offensive and blasphemous by violent cyber-jihadists who have only one goal: the violent promulgation of a religious system and the suppression of all criticism of it. There are many peaceful, kind, gentlemanly and dignified people in the Muslim community who would consider themselves orthodox and who would, in fact, agree with what I am saying today. Yet, that still begs the question: how should we talk about Islam? We should seek to honestly evaluate the religion itself. But how should we judge what the religion is? There are peaceful Muslims and violent Muslims, just as there are peaceful Christians and violent Christians. Which are the true followers, and which are more influenced by other ideologies rather than the doctrine itself? In my experience (having extensively and intensively studied religion for around ten years now), we should always judge a religion on the basis of its Sources and its Heroes. What do I mean by this? The Sources of a religion are essentially its authorities and/or sources of doctrine. In Protestant Christianity, the Source is Scripture alone, and its plain perspicuous teaching. In Catholic Christianity, the source is Scripture and Apostolic Tradition as received and interpreted by the Magisterium (i.e., the Church itself). The Heroes of a religion are those figures which have been deemed by the Sources/Authorities as having followed the religion well (though not necessarily perfectly, and there are different grades of heroes in every religion). The ultimate Hero of all Christianity is Jesus Himself, who is believed to be the perfect man. In Catholicism, the heroes are (to a certain degree) the saints. Although it is generally agreed that the canonisation process only grants us certainty that the deceased is in heaven, not that the person always lived an exemplary life. This gives room for the believing Catholic to criticise even the acts of saints, as many traditionalists have done with St. Mother Teresa, to give an example. In Islam, the greatest hero is Muhammad himself, who is considered to be the perfect example for all mankind. In Sunni Islam, Muhammad is closely followed by the Four Rightly Guided Caliphs, whereas in Shia Islam, Muhammad is but one of Fourteen Infallibles, which include – besides the founder himself – Fatima and the Twelve Imams. So, when we judge Islam, we should first distinguish between the various schools of Islam. Sunni Islam is not the same as Shia Islam or Ibadi Islam or Ahmadi Islam. There are, so to speak, quite a few ‘Islams’, just as there are different interpretations of Marxism, democracy, libertarianism, capitalism, feminism and just about everything else. In other words, the next time you see some act of violence perpetrated by fundamentalists of any religion or sect, ask yourself the question: is this act of violence commanded by the Sources of the faith in question? Is there any precedent for this sort of terror in the behaviour of its heroes? You should ask the same question when it comes to the good actions of peaceful adherents. When you see followers of a religion endorsing pacifism or separation of religion and state, are they acting faithfully according to their Sources and Heroes? Or are there more influenced by other ideologies, in light of which they interpret their religion? I end this article with a comparison between the Christian Crusades and the Islamic Mujahideen. The Crusades were an administrative decision, in part made by the Pope. Catholicism does not require its adherents to consider Papal administrative decisions as infallible – the only infallible things coming out of the Pope are his ratifications of ecumenical councils and ex-cathedra statements; that is to say, matters which solely concern doctrine and dogma. Administrative decisions, as per Catholic ecclesiology, are entirely fallible. As a matter of fact, it is the conservatives in the Church who are very loud in criticising the administrative decisions of recent Popes, such as the decision of Pope Paul VI to allow the priest to celebrate the Mass facing the congregation (versus populum) rather than the East (ad orientem) as has traditionally been practised. So, largely, the Crusades are not part of Catholic doctrine, if at all. I do not say this in order to “wash my hands clean” of the Crusades, so to speak. Personally, I think the Crusades had a noble intent in theory (i.e., that of defending Christendom), but I lament the fact that in practice many of the Crusaders became too extreme. Rather than simply defeating enemy military forces, they committed unspeakable atrocities upon civilians which are horrendous, lamentable and condemnable. As a traditional and orthodox Catholic, I am ashamed of the misdeeds that were perpetrated in the name of the Crusades. But here’s the thing: my religion gives me the liberty to say this. My faith does not compel me to believe that the Crusaders were “inspired by God”. But when you study the early Muslim invasions of neighbouring civilisations, ask yourself the question: can we say the same about Islam? Who led these invasions? Were these figures deemed by Islam to be inspired by God in their acts and to be, in some sense, infallible? Do the chief sources command its adherents to consider their acts of war as virtuous on the part of a ruler? Our judgment of Islam should be based on these facts. I will leave you to make up your own mind. It may turn out that, in fact, Islam is an extremely peaceful and humane religion. Or it may turn out another way. I only ask you to use sound judgment in your study and to not be afraid of the truth, however hard it may turn out to be. However, in all our critique or appraisal, we must remember that our analysis of a doctrine should not seep into a generalisation of the moral character of the adherents of that doctrine. This attitude allows me to be extremely kind and respectful to my Muslim friends while, at the same time, giving me total liberty to analyse and evaluate the religion as my conscience commands me. And that is how we should talk about Islam today, condemning it where we see condemnation due, fighting for and respecting its adherents when they so require, and accepting or rejecting it for what it is when truth so demands.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Not Peace but a Sword: The New Religious War in Ukraine</title>
      <link href="/Religious-War-In-Ukraine" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Not Peace but a Sword: The New Religious War in Ukraine" />
      <published>2019-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Religious-War-In-Ukraine</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Religious-War-In-Ukraine">&lt;p&gt;The year is 2014. Violent protests have erupted across Ukraine. President Viktor Yanukovych’s perceived pro-Russian policies have angered a large section of the population, who have firmly come out in support of closer ties with the European Union. However, the predominantly Russian-speaking East is not that happy about the prospect of a European alliance. Unfortunately for them, Yanukovych is soon ousted from power by a violent revolution. This new development is not, however, universally acclaimed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly afterwards, armed revolutionaries seize control of the Crimean Parliament and allegedly install a pro-Russian Prime Minister, who quickly calls upon Vladimir Putin for military assistance. Cries of “Putin is my President!” are now commonly heard in the streets of Crimea. Eventually, a referendum is held and the results indicate that the people of Crimea have overwhelmingly voted for union with Russia. Crimea then becomes a part of the Russian Federation, a development condemned by the European Union, the United States and much of the rest of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia and Ukraine share a long inter-woven history. Both of them look upon Kievan Rus as their cultural ancestor – the monarchy that once included much of the East Slavic and Finnic peoples of Europe, and which lasted from the late 9th to the mid-13th century. However, over time, their relationship has grown steadily worse. The events of 2014 are but a modern manifestation of a long-festering division that has only been exacerbated as the years have passed by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, Ukraine is a part of Eastern Europe, a region many people consider to be the heartland of the Eastern Orthodox Church. Known for its hardline stances on many issues of faith and morals, this ancient federation of ecclesiastical communities claims a line of unbroken continuity with the Church of the Apostles. Proponents call it a relatively pure Church, undefiled by the erroneous ideologies of the modern world. Critics call it a reactionary, patriarchal organisation, which still refuses to ordain women and considers abortion to be immoral and sinful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the vast majority of Western European culture and society – the historic stronghold of the Roman Church – has been usurped by the forces of liberalism, secularism and the sexual revolution, the same cannot be said about Eastern Orthodoxy. This is highly ironic, given that the Russian Orthodox Church, in particular, was strongly persecuted by the Soviet Union, as were as the other Slavic Orthodox Churches, such the Serbian, Bulgarian and Romanian Patriarchates. However, since the fall of the USSR, the Orthodox Church has come to wield a level of influence over local politics unseen since the time of the Tsars. While the Russian Federation continues to claim non-affiliation with any religious body as such, the alliance between Putin and the Moscow Patriarchate is the &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religion is a very strong preserver. After all, the Roman Catholic Church – the world’s largest, most powerful and longest-running monarchy – is, in many ways, the only remaining bastion of medieval Western culture. This is easily apparent especially if you visit traditionalist monasteries which still follow the rules in all their strictness. It is, of course, true that even many Roman Catholic priests and bishops don’t practice their faith well and have become lax, but there are still many strongholds of conservatism within that Church―despite the forces of liberalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is true also of the Eastern Orthodox Church, which, in general, suffers much less from the plague of liberals within their hierarchy. Some observers have noted the remarkable similarity between the alliance of Putin and Patriarch Kirill of Moscow today and the traditional diarchy of Byzantium, in which the Emperor and the Patriarch would be the most powerful political figures in the land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, while the Russian Federation may no longer possess the territorial jurisdiction of Kievan Rus, the Patriarchate of Moscow has a much stronger boast to that. The Russian Church claims jurisdiction not merely over Russia but also over all of Ukraine. In fact, the single largest Church in Ukraine continues to be under the jurisdiction of Moscow. It is called the Ukrainian Orthodox Church of the Moscow Patriarchate. It is autonomous, but not autocephalous. In other words, it is mostly self-governing, but not wholly independent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, many of the nationalists of Ukraine have despised what they see as the continued intrusion of Russian imperialist influence in their homeland. And it is precisely such sentiments as these that were responsible, in part, for the splintering of the Orthodox Church in Ukraine into two new denominations – the Ukrainian Orthodox Church of the Kievan Patriarchate and the Ukrainian Autocephalous Orthodox Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to this, there is the Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church, which looks like the Orthodox Church, prays like the Orthodox Church, smells like the Orthodox Church, but is – in fact – a Catholic Church in full communion with Rome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, the Kiev Patriarchate and the Ukrainian Autocephalous Orthodox Church were considered by the rest of the Orthodox world to be nationalist fanatics and schismatics who have damaged the unity of Orthodoxy. The Metropolitan Onufriy, under the authority of the Moscow Patriarch, was considered to be the rightful primate of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, quite recently, the situation has taken a sharp turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Patriarch of Constantinople Bartholomew I, long considered the “first among equals” of the Orthodox Patriarchs has taken it upon himself to grant the Church of Ukraine (specifically the two splinter groups from Moscow) complete independence from Russia. While it is true that the Patriarch of Constantinople does not enjoy the same authority in Orthodoxy that the Pope does in Catholicism, he does have some prerogatives – among them is the responsibility of hearing appeals from the rest of the Orthodox world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has led to the Patriarchate of Moscow excommunicating the Patriarch of Constantinople. And the vast majority of the Orthodox Churches have sided with Moscow. Bartholomew, however, has been undeterred. As a result of his efforts, the two splinter groups have now been united as the “Orthodox Church of Ukraine” with the full blessing and support of Ukrainian President Petro Poroshenko. Their new leader calls himself Metropolitan Epiphany (Dumenko). As of now, no Orthodox Church has given recognition to this new Church apart from Constantinople itself, and it has received heated condemnation not only from Moscow but also from the Primate of Serbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What implications could this have for the political situation? First of all, it is almost without question that the new Orthodox Church will come to represent the face of Ukrainian nationalism against “Russian imperialism”. It is no wonder that President Poroshenko is such an avid supporter of the move. Millions of Ukrainians still consider the Patriarch of Moscow to be their spiritual leaders. This new move represents an opportunity to break that perception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the new Church has also received surprising support from sectors of the Roman Catholic Church. It is very ironic indeed – four centuries ago, nationalism played a very important role in rousing extreme opposition to the Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church, members of which were looked upon as traitors who had defected to Rome. Now, it is the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religious freedom still remains strongly restricted in many parts of Eastern Europe. Russia, for instance, has banned the Jehovah’s Witnesses. There was also a famous attempt to ban the &lt;em&gt;Bhagavad Gita As It Is&lt;/em&gt; in 2011. In 2016, the premises of a Vedic monastery in Nizhny Novgorod were demolished by local authorities, after having been declared illegal a year back. Meanwhile, the Russian Orthodox Church is busy rebuilding Churches demolished during the time of the Soviet Union and is enjoying the presence of Putin at Church services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does the future hold for Russia and Ukraine? Will Russia try to resurrect its orthodox heritage, perhaps even, as some suggest, restore the monarchy? Will we see a new cold war, between Russia and the West, with Ukraine caught in the middle? What is the future for the Orthodox faithful?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, my friends, only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The year is 2014. Violent protests have erupted across Ukraine. President Viktor Yanukovych’s perceived pro-Russian policies have angered a large section of the population, who have firmly come out in support of closer ties with the European Union. However, the predominantly Russian-speaking East is not that happy about the prospect of a European alliance. Unfortunately for them, Yanukovych is soon ousted from power by a violent revolution. This new development is not, however, universally acclaimed.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Most Hated Religion in the World</title>
      <link href="/The-Most-Hated-Religion-in-the-World" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Most Hated Religion in the World" />
      <published>2019-03-07T04:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-07T04:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Most-Hated-Religion-in-the-World</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Most-Hated-Religion-in-the-World">&lt;p&gt;If you were to ask the Joe on the street “Which is the most
hated/persecuted/marginalized religious group in the world?” you would probably
get a range of different answers, depending upon the interviewee’s political
orientation(s).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People leaning towards the left would most likely say, “Islam. Islamophobia is a
big problem in the West. Definitely.” Others leaning towards the right would
probably say “The Jews. They have suffered the most and even now, Israel is
under threat from Islamic fundamentalists. We must stand with Israel.” In India,
it would probably be, “The Hindus! Just look at the Kashmiri Pandits.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I don’t deny that each of these groups has suffered immensely in the past. I
sympathise strongly with anyone who has been persecuted or discriminated against
in the secular sphere on the basis of their race, religion, economic status or
sex. It goes without saying that I condemn all forms of religious bigotry. But
in my humble opinion, neither Islam nor Judaism can claim the title. In my mind,
the most hated religion in the world today is Catholic Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“What?!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know. It sounds strange. But spare me the incredulous look, because I am just
about to back up my claims with extraordinarily strong evidence. But before I do
that, let me tell you my story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I myself was raised in the Hindu community, but after a decade-long search for
the truth, I lost faith in the faith of my forefathers. I am now making my way
across to Christianity, and in all likelihood, I will end up either Roman
Catholic or in Eastern Orthodoxy. I have studied more religions and
denominations than I can remember – from the Ahl-e-Hadith (and the lesser known
Ahl-e-Qur’an) to the long-extinct Zurvanism – and I will soon begin an
undergraduate degree in Theology at the University of Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friends, I can testify with all my heart that there is no religious group
that is more maligned, slandered and attacked in popular culture than the
Catholic Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each and every worldview is built upon some major controlling narrative or the
other. Modern society is the offspring of three great ideological uprisings in
the past, all of which are overtly and vehemently anti-Catholic, either
prominently or tangentially. You might have guessed two of them, but the third
one may surprise you. I am speaking of the Enlightenment, the Protestant
Reformation and the rise of Marxism. Now let’s consider their controlling
narratives one by one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Enlightenment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world had great and immense potential since the evolution of the &lt;em&gt;homo
sapiens&lt;/em&gt;. A great example of this was Europe, which in the classical world was a
great hub of learning, philosophy, art, and science. Great thinkers and minds
arose who tirelessly “stretched forward their hands towards perfection” in
Greece and Rome. All of this was happening – until the rise of Christianity, the
most intolerant branch of which is the Catholic Church. Led by the theocratic
impositions of Constantine, the Catholic Church brought all of Europe under
their tyrannical captivity. Superstition reigned; science was stifled; the
freedom of the heart was curbed; man was put into chains. The growth and
progress of Europe were stunted… until the great Renaissance dawned upon
mankind, and Europe was reborn – a phoenix rising from the ashes. The captivity
of Rome was overthrown and the great continent emerged, to build its future on
its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Protestant Reformation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning, Christ and the Apostles built up the Church and commanded them
to preach the Gospel far and wide. All was going well… but over the centuries,
slowly but gradually, pagan influence began to creep into the Church.
Superstition and idolatry gradually came to cloud the Gospel, and eventually, it
was lost for good! The situation was especially bad in Western Europe, where the
Pope presided in the place of God, reigning down his ungodly tyranny upon the
masses, chaining the Christian and denying him his rightful freedom. The Spirit
of God departed for a while from the pagan Roman church… until at last, the
seeds laid by the great martyrs Wycliffe and Hus bore fruit, and the heroes of
the faith – Luther, Zwingli, and Calvin – emerged. These luminaries showed us
the path and helped us break the chains of Roman tyranny. The Reformation was a
glorious cleansing of the church, and countless souls were freed from the
captivity of the Roman harlot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marxism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History is marked primarily by class-struggle. From ages past, the privileged
(the haves) have oppressed the have-nots. A prime example of this is seen in the
decadent, superstitious Catholic Church. This is an organisation that has
promoted colonialism (the Crusades being a great example) and continues to have
an authoritarian patriarchal structure of clericalism and privilege that
oppresses the common man. To this day, the Pope and his henchmen participate in
the oppression of the masses, by opposing abortion, contraception and denying
women equality by not ordaining them to the priesthood. This organisation must
change, or perish. The common people must arise out of the chains of this
tyranny!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you have been studying the three movements I describe, you will quickly
see that absolutely nothing I have written is an exaggeration. For example, if
you are acquainted with Protestant polemical literature (as I am), you will
notice that many of the terms I have used – “Roman harlot”, “Roman [Babylonian]
captivity”, “freedom of the Christian”, “chains of bondage and superstition”,
“false gospel”, etc. – are not mine, but the exact terms used by Protestants to
this day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice also, another thing: though these movements all originated in Europe,
they have since then been widely disseminated. There are more than 900 million
Protestants around the world (almost an eighth of the world population). The
philosophy of the Enlightenment has spread around the globe as well, as
evidenced by the fact that most of the countries in the world are (or, at least,
claim to be) liberal secular democracies. And, of course, Marxism has claimed
the most populous country in the world as its own and continues to have a loud
presence around the world (particularly among the students and youth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it just me? Am I just seeing it this way because I myself strongly lean RC?
(Well, technically, I began leaning RC after I saw its theology being vastly
misrepresented and slandered in Protestant fundamentalist circles on the
internet). But it’s not just me by any stretch of the imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is what pro-life activist, journalist and Orthodox Jew Ben Shapiro had to
say at a conference in Dana Point, CA: “Unfortunately, the attacks [by radical
leftists] on Catholics have come first and foremost […] It’s really fascinating
to watch, not just from a Jewish perspective. Usually, we’re the first on the
hit list. Now it’s you guys.” Shapiro went on to note several instances of
anti-Catholic prejudice in the popular media. But one could also note the
attitude of contempt several Democrat politicians displayed towards conservative
Catholicism as we see, for example, US Senator Diane Feinstein’s bluntly stated
to the Catholic judicial nominee Amy Barrett, “The dogma lives loudly within
you”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about the historical data? Don’t they prove that the Catholic Church
is, indeed, so to speak, “guilty as charged”? Not so, says non-Catholic
sociologist, University of California Berkeley scholar and Pulitzer
Prize-winning author Rodney Stark, who has written many books on Christian
history, including several defending Catholicism from what he says as unfounded
attacks and slanderous misrepresentations. Among his many works are &lt;em&gt;God’s
Battalions: The Case for the Crusades&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Reformation Myths and Bearing False
Witness: Debunking Centuries of Anti-Catholic Lies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;America, of course, is historically extremely anti-Catholic. And with the
worldwide dominance of American culture as well as the proliferation of
American-style Evangelicalism, anti-Catholicism too has spread around the world.
But don’t take my word for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ryan Reeves is a Cambridge scholar and a professor of Church history at
Gordon-Conwell Theological Seminary, one of the eminent Protestant institutions
in the USA. Several of his lectures are available on his YouTube channel (in my
opinion, an invaluable contribution to public education). I highly recommend his
lecture &lt;em&gt;Catholics in America&lt;/em&gt;. In it, Reeves discusses how, historically, large
sections of the Protestant population in America have always tried to,
especially in the face of Catholic immigration, “slander and to mock and to
lampoon Catholics, in an effort to demoralize and ideally to get them to convert
to Protestantism”. (Since Professor Reeves is teaching at a well-respected
Protestant institution, I will similarly assume that he is a Protestant and has
no dog in this fight.) He goes on to discuss historically famous instances of
anti-Catholic propaganda, including the ghost-written 18th century bestseller
autobiography of “Maria Monk”, which claimed to expose scandalous debauchery and
immorality within Catholic convents, and which – according to Dr. Reeves - we
now know to be a complete hoax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-evidently, hatred against Catholics must change due to the simple social
rule that one ought not to be persecuted for one’s beliefs. Here are three
things which I think need to happen in order to help the situation change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, people need to better appreciate and understand the Catholic Church’s
rich and vibrant intellectual history, especially the glories of the Middle Ages - figures like Aquinas, Anselm, Ockham, Peter Abelard, Duns Scotus and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the anti-fideism of Catholic theology needs to be properly recognised
as well (I’m looking at you, Christopher Hitchens). The doctrine of the
interplay and complementary nature of faith and reason, popularised by Aquinas
and officially adopted by the Catholic Church at the First Vatican Council, will
only lead the devout Catholic to a deeper admiration of and respect towards the
sciences, not a fear of them. Hence, we have great Catholic scientists like
Gregor Mendel, George Lemaitre, Roger Bacon, Albertus Magnus and – of course –
Nicolaus Copernicus (who, by the way, was respected and admired by several
Catholic clergymen of his time, including Pope Clement VII). For example, on
November 1, 1536, Cardinal Nikolaus von Schönberg, Archbishop of Capua, wrote to
Copernicus expressing profound admiration, and requesting him to tell him more
about his new cosmology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, people need to remember the mistakes made by Catholics in the past.
Yes, Catholics are not, and have never been, perfect people. They have made
mistakes, like any other group. We must not repeat the errors of antiquity, and
we must remember and learn from them. But, at the same time, we must also
recognise the fact that the Catholic hierarchy (I’m talking about folks like
Popes John Paul II and Francis I) has publicly apologised for many of the past
excesses and sought forgiveness for the same. An institution that is ready to
own up to its mistakes in such a public manner shines a ray of hope for the
world. And it is only such an attitude of humility, repentance, and desire to
change that will help contemporary Catholics overcome the ecclesiastical abuses
and errors of the modern world.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">If you were to ask the Joe on the street “Which is the most hated/persecuted/marginalized religious group in the world?” you would probably get a range of different answers, depending upon the interviewee’s political orientation(s). People leaning towards the left would most likely say, “Islam. Islamophobia is a big problem in the West. Definitely.” Others leaning towards the right would probably say “The Jews. They have suffered the most and even now, Israel is under threat from Islamic fundamentalists. We must stand with Israel.” In India, it would probably be, “The Hindus! Just look at the Kashmiri Pandits.” And I don’t deny that each of these groups has suffered immensely in the past. I sympathise strongly with anyone who has been persecuted or discriminated against in the secular sphere on the basis of their race, religion, economic status or sex. It goes without saying that I condemn all forms of religious bigotry. But in my humble opinion, neither Islam nor Judaism can claim the title. In my mind, the most hated religion in the world today is Catholic Christianity. “What?!” I know. It sounds strange. But spare me the incredulous look, because I am just about to back up my claims with extraordinarily strong evidence. But before I do that, let me tell you my story. I myself was raised in the Hindu community, but after a decade-long search for the truth, I lost faith in the faith of my forefathers. I am now making my way across to Christianity, and in all likelihood, I will end up either Roman Catholic or in Eastern Orthodoxy. I have studied more religions and denominations than I can remember – from the Ahl-e-Hadith (and the lesser known Ahl-e-Qur’an) to the long-extinct Zurvanism – and I will soon begin an undergraduate degree in Theology at the University of Oxford. My friends, I can testify with all my heart that there is no religious group that is more maligned, slandered and attacked in popular culture than the Catholic Church. Each and every worldview is built upon some major controlling narrative or the other. Modern society is the offspring of three great ideological uprisings in the past, all of which are overtly and vehemently anti-Catholic, either prominently or tangentially. You might have guessed two of them, but the third one may surprise you. I am speaking of the Enlightenment, the Protestant Reformation and the rise of Marxism. Now let’s consider their controlling narratives one by one. The Enlightenment The world had great and immense potential since the evolution of the homo sapiens. A great example of this was Europe, which in the classical world was a great hub of learning, philosophy, art, and science. Great thinkers and minds arose who tirelessly “stretched forward their hands towards perfection” in Greece and Rome. All of this was happening – until the rise of Christianity, the most intolerant branch of which is the Catholic Church. Led by the theocratic impositions of Constantine, the Catholic Church brought all of Europe under their tyrannical captivity. Superstition reigned; science was stifled; the freedom of the heart was curbed; man was put into chains. The growth and progress of Europe were stunted… until the great Renaissance dawned upon mankind, and Europe was reborn – a phoenix rising from the ashes. The captivity of Rome was overthrown and the great continent emerged, to build its future on its own. The Protestant Reformation In the beginning, Christ and the Apostles built up the Church and commanded them to preach the Gospel far and wide. All was going well… but over the centuries, slowly but gradually, pagan influence began to creep into the Church. Superstition and idolatry gradually came to cloud the Gospel, and eventually, it was lost for good! The situation was especially bad in Western Europe, where the Pope presided in the place of God, reigning down his ungodly tyranny upon the masses, chaining the Christian and denying him his rightful freedom. The Spirit of God departed for a while from the pagan Roman church… until at last, the seeds laid by the great martyrs Wycliffe and Hus bore fruit, and the heroes of the faith – Luther, Zwingli, and Calvin – emerged. These luminaries showed us the path and helped us break the chains of Roman tyranny. The Reformation was a glorious cleansing of the church, and countless souls were freed from the captivity of the Roman harlot. Marxism History is marked primarily by class-struggle. From ages past, the privileged (the haves) have oppressed the have-nots. A prime example of this is seen in the decadent, superstitious Catholic Church. This is an organisation that has promoted colonialism (the Crusades being a great example) and continues to have an authoritarian patriarchal structure of clericalism and privilege that oppresses the common man. To this day, the Pope and his henchmen participate in the oppression of the masses, by opposing abortion, contraception and denying women equality by not ordaining them to the priesthood. This organisation must change, or perish. The common people must arise out of the chains of this tyranny! Now, if you have been studying the three movements I describe, you will quickly see that absolutely nothing I have written is an exaggeration. For example, if you are acquainted with Protestant polemical literature (as I am), you will notice that many of the terms I have used – “Roman harlot”, “Roman [Babylonian] captivity”, “freedom of the Christian”, “chains of bondage and superstition”, “false gospel”, etc. – are not mine, but the exact terms used by Protestants to this day! Notice also, another thing: though these movements all originated in Europe, they have since then been widely disseminated. There are more than 900 million Protestants around the world (almost an eighth of the world population). The philosophy of the Enlightenment has spread around the globe as well, as evidenced by the fact that most of the countries in the world are (or, at least, claim to be) liberal secular democracies. And, of course, Marxism has claimed the most populous country in the world as its own and continues to have a loud presence around the world (particularly among the students and youth). Is it just me? Am I just seeing it this way because I myself strongly lean RC? (Well, technically, I began leaning RC after I saw its theology being vastly misrepresented and slandered in Protestant fundamentalist circles on the internet). But it’s not just me by any stretch of the imagination. Here is what pro-life activist, journalist and Orthodox Jew Ben Shapiro had to say at a conference in Dana Point, CA: “Unfortunately, the attacks [by radical leftists] on Catholics have come first and foremost […] It’s really fascinating to watch, not just from a Jewish perspective. Usually, we’re the first on the hit list. Now it’s you guys.” Shapiro went on to note several instances of anti-Catholic prejudice in the popular media. But one could also note the attitude of contempt several Democrat politicians displayed towards conservative Catholicism as we see, for example, US Senator Diane Feinstein’s bluntly stated to the Catholic judicial nominee Amy Barrett, “The dogma lives loudly within you”. But what about the historical data? Don’t they prove that the Catholic Church is, indeed, so to speak, “guilty as charged”? Not so, says non-Catholic sociologist, University of California Berkeley scholar and Pulitzer Prize-winning author Rodney Stark, who has written many books on Christian history, including several defending Catholicism from what he says as unfounded attacks and slanderous misrepresentations. Among his many works are God’s Battalions: The Case for the Crusades, Reformation Myths and Bearing False Witness: Debunking Centuries of Anti-Catholic Lies. America, of course, is historically extremely anti-Catholic. And with the worldwide dominance of American culture as well as the proliferation of American-style Evangelicalism, anti-Catholicism too has spread around the world. But don’t take my word for it. Ryan Reeves is a Cambridge scholar and a professor of Church history at Gordon-Conwell Theological Seminary, one of the eminent Protestant institutions in the USA. Several of his lectures are available on his YouTube channel (in my opinion, an invaluable contribution to public education). I highly recommend his lecture Catholics in America. In it, Reeves discusses how, historically, large sections of the Protestant population in America have always tried to, especially in the face of Catholic immigration, “slander and to mock and to lampoon Catholics, in an effort to demoralize and ideally to get them to convert to Protestantism”. (Since Professor Reeves is teaching at a well-respected Protestant institution, I will similarly assume that he is a Protestant and has no dog in this fight.) He goes on to discuss historically famous instances of anti-Catholic propaganda, including the ghost-written 18th century bestseller autobiography of “Maria Monk”, which claimed to expose scandalous debauchery and immorality within Catholic convents, and which – according to Dr. Reeves - we now know to be a complete hoax. Self-evidently, hatred against Catholics must change due to the simple social rule that one ought not to be persecuted for one’s beliefs. Here are three things which I think need to happen in order to help the situation change. Firstly, people need to better appreciate and understand the Catholic Church’s rich and vibrant intellectual history, especially the glories of the Middle Ages - figures like Aquinas, Anselm, Ockham, Peter Abelard, Duns Scotus and so on. Secondly, the anti-fideism of Catholic theology needs to be properly recognised as well (I’m looking at you, Christopher Hitchens). The doctrine of the interplay and complementary nature of faith and reason, popularised by Aquinas and officially adopted by the Catholic Church at the First Vatican Council, will only lead the devout Catholic to a deeper admiration of and respect towards the sciences, not a fear of them. Hence, we have great Catholic scientists like Gregor Mendel, George Lemaitre, Roger Bacon, Albertus Magnus and – of course – Nicolaus Copernicus (who, by the way, was respected and admired by several Catholic clergymen of his time, including Pope Clement VII). For example, on November 1, 1536, Cardinal Nikolaus von Schönberg, Archbishop of Capua, wrote to Copernicus expressing profound admiration, and requesting him to tell him more about his new cosmology. Thirdly, people need to remember the mistakes made by Catholics in the past. Yes, Catholics are not, and have never been, perfect people. They have made mistakes, like any other group. We must not repeat the errors of antiquity, and we must remember and learn from them. But, at the same time, we must also recognise the fact that the Catholic hierarchy (I’m talking about folks like Popes John Paul II and Francis I) has publicly apologised for many of the past excesses and sought forgiveness for the same. An institution that is ready to own up to its mistakes in such a public manner shines a ray of hope for the world. And it is only such an attitude of humility, repentance, and desire to change that will help contemporary Catholics overcome the ecclesiastical abuses and errors of the modern world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Christendom Today: How Christianity is still Shaping the Modern World</title>
      <link href="/Christendom-Today" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Christendom Today: How Christianity is still Shaping the Modern World" />
      <published>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Christendom-Today</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Christendom-Today">&lt;p&gt;There are many religions in the world, but only Christianity can boast of having more than two billion followers across the world, comprising people from nearly every ethnicity, race, and social class. Even Islam – its closest contender and the “fastest growing religion in the world” is nearly a billion followers behind. But how is the religion that names itself after Jesus the Messiah influencing the 21st century? The answer may surprise you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christianity certainly is a house divided. The Protestant Reformation played a major role in this (and the proliferation of Protestant denominations continues to prove this) but it also made the Catholic Church wake up from centuries of semi-stagnation, resulting in a major resurgence of traditionalism, as we see in the great world missions of the Counter-Reformation. Indeed, the Jesuits – zealous evangelists and promoters of the Roman faith – probably wouldn’t have existed hadn’t it been for the polarising catalyst that was Martin Luther.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those divisions haven’t yet come to an end, rather Christianity is even more diverse than it was in the 17th century. Thankfully, the different bodies calling themselves Christian are reaching out to each other in a spirit of sincerity and dialogue and are repenting the terrible sectarian bloodshed that so often categorised post-Enlightenment Europe. But the various Christian ‘sects’ are still very different and continue to operate and influence the world in their own unique way. Let us begin with the largest group of all – the Roman Catholic Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“The Spirit of Vatican II”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mid-20th century, the Catholic Church held a worldwide pastoral council called the Second Council of the Vatican, or – to put it simply – “Vatican II” (hereafter referred to as V2). Unlike previous councils, V2 never chose to define dogma or clarify church teaching – rather it wanted to bring about ecclesiastical reforms to be able to better respond to the new world of the 20th century. But many Catholics agree that V2 was an absolute disaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V2 resulted in the sharp splintering of the Church. The liberals and the ‘modernists’ complain that it didn’t go far enough in eroding “medieval superstition”, while the conservatives argue that the ambiguous language in its documents creates a great danger for doctrinal error to be spread. In addition to these two groups, there are more than half-a-million traditionalist Catholics who reject it altogether, calling it a non-infallible “robber’s council” – the best example of this is the Priestly Society of St Pius X, with supporters around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, V2 has resulted in a change of attitude among many believers. Today, Catholics are much more focused on preaching about “social justice” than before. This is best seen in the lives of Mother Teresa and Oscar Romero, both saints of the Catholic Church, as well as in the current Pontiff, Pope Francis. The rise of the so-called “Liberation theology” has created a great impact in Latin America (particularly Brazil), with some calling it the “Marxist version of Catholicism”. The “left-wing Church” in this part of the world has played an instrumental role in protesting against totalitarian right-wing bigotry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberation theologians contend that the root cause of poverty and social injustice is sin (the implication being that social justice cannot return unless people begin to lead saintly lives) and that the poor, the oppressed and the marginalized are the “privileged channels of God’s grace”. The result is that a direct link has been made between theology and social activism. To be a good Christian, one must fight against and oppose oppressive structures of power, say the Liberation theologians. While Liberation theology is certainly not a branch of Communism in any formal sense of the word, the similarity with Marxist rhetoric has, at times, concerned many conservatives, not least among them being Pope Emeritus Benedict XVI. This is very ironic because the Catholic Church of the 20th century was one of the most powerful anti-Communist forces in the world, with many (including New York Times bestselling author and scholar Paul Kengor) crediting Pope St John Paul II as having played an instrumental role in the fall of the Soviet Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luther’s Revenge: The Worldwide Resurgence of Evangelicalism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evangelical Christianity is by far the most powerful and dynamic religious force in the world today. Evangelicalism is converting people by the hundreds of thousands. The best example of this is the late Baptist missionary Billy Grace, who preached to more than 3 billion people during his career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evangelicalism is characterised by both simplicity and zeal. There is no Pope or central authority structure to dictate dogma – the Bible is the only rule. There is no long and boring liturgy as we see in Catholic and Orthodox Churches – rather, church services tend to have contemporary music that is very appealing to the youth. They are not led by old and haggard clerics barely able to even speak a word – on the contrary, their leaders tend to be charismatic, scholarly and lively. The sacramental emphasis is replaced by a much freer and fluid form of spirituality, and it is not uncommon to hear the phrase “Christianity is a relationship, not a religion”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the Christian apologists defending the veracity of Christian truth in the academia are also Evangelicals. William Lane Craig, Ravi Zacharias, NT Wright, Richard Bauckham, Michael F Bird, Craig Keener, Craig Blomberg, James DG Dunn, Alvin Plantinga – the list is very impressive indeed. Not only are these devoted (Evangelical) Christians eager to convert souls, they also represent the top brass of scholarship in their respective fields. For instance, William Lane Craig and Alvin Plantinga are one of the most cited scholars in the philosophy of religion, while Wright and Bauckham have both had an association with universities like Oxford and Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny enough, Evangelical Christianity is very American, and very, very Republican. So, while Catholics seem to veer leftward, Evangelicals are solidly in support of capitalism and the notion of a culturally advanced Western Civilisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Holy Mother Russia: The Re-Baptism of Rus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the fall of the USSR, the resurgence of Eastern Orthodoxy was all but inevitable. Today, the Moscow Patriarchate can be called the unofficial state religion of the Russian Federation. Now operating with Vladimir Putin’s open consent and cooperation, they are rebuilding Churches long destroyed and reconstructing schools that had been annihilated by anti-religious sentiment. In fact, some Orthodox followers and clergy are actively advocating the restoration of a Christian state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orthodox Christians are very, well, ‘orthodox’. When the Pope visited Serbia, he was greeted by sloganeers protesting “the Papist heresy”. Even the Patriarch – while having met the Pope at the airport – refused to offer Mass with him. Similarly, Russia is cracking down on “fringe groups” – not least among them being the non-Trinitarian Jehovah’s Witnesses, who have had to face fierce persecution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What animates these people? It a vision of the legendary Byzantium, an empire so wonderful that it may be fittingly called the kingdom of God on earth. When the ambassadors of Prince Vladimir of Kiev first saw the Latin Mass, they were not too impressed, but when they witnessed the Byzantine Divine Liturgy, they wrote back exclaiming that this was the most heavenly thing they had ever seen. In the Orthodox narrative, the Church of Rome fell into heresy when it started claiming for itself ecclesiastical supremacy. It was then excommunicated and replaced by the Church of Constantinople, the New Rome. And when Constantinople fell under the sword of Islam, God raised up Moscow – the “Third Rome”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that if there will ever be a Christian state in the 21st century, it will exist mainly in Orthodox-dominated lands (and perhaps in Catholic Poland). For the rest of the Christian world, political Christendom is dead and gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atheists and critics of religion sometimes contend that Christianity is on the decline. But is this true? While it is without a doubt correct to say that Europe and the Western World is secularising at an exponential rate, this does not hold true with regard to the rest of the world. There is an explosion of Christian growth in the global south, particularly in Africa which has proven to be a fertile mission field for the Christian message. As far as academia is concerned, the resurgence of orthodox Christian scholarship in recent years is also a sign of life. However unpopular the faith may be among young white people, it certainly has a long and bright future ahead.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There are many religions in the world, but only Christianity can boast of having more than two billion followers across the world, comprising people from nearly every ethnicity, race, and social class. Even Islam – its closest contender and the “fastest growing religion in the world” is nearly a billion followers behind. But how is the religion that names itself after Jesus the Messiah influencing the 21st century? The answer may surprise you.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Transphobia, Political Correctness and the Jordan Peterson Phenomenon</title>
      <link href="/Jordan-Peterson-Phenomenon" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transphobia, Political Correctness and the Jordan Peterson Phenomenon" />
      <published>2019-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Jordan-Peterson-Phenomenon</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Jordan-Peterson-Phenomenon">&lt;p&gt;Hero. Mentor. Thinker. Professor. Ideologue. Right-Winger. Transphobic Hate-Monger. “Mean Mad White Man.” These are but some of the epithets which have been used to refer to Jordan B. Peterson, an eminent clinical psychologist who became famous overnight for opposing legislation that intended to make it illegal for people to not refer to transgender people by their preferred pronouns. Since then, he has been at the epicentre of a raging controversy about political correctness that has made an impact over most of the Western Anglophone world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peterson is a professor at the University of Toronto. He earned his doctorate from McGill University and has taught at eminent institutions, including Harvard University. He is the author of &lt;i&gt;Maps of Meaning: The Architecture of Belief &lt;/i&gt; and a more recent international bestseller &lt;i&gt;12 Rules for Life: An Antidote to Chaos&lt;/i&gt;. An erudite Jungian and Nietzschean scholar and a gifted speaker, he has inspired countless young men to “embrace their masculinity”. However, his opposition to government-backed impositions on free speech and his critique of the feminist concept of patriarchy has made him an almost hated figure in some circles. The foundation of all these positions, however, is his staunch opposition to political correctness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are approximately 3 million people in the European Union and the United States of America put together who identify as transgender. The exact estimate the world over is difficult to ascertain. Nonetheless, however minute they might be in proportion to the total world population, this is a sizable number of people. But can a trans woman be considered a “real woman”? That is the question Jo Coburn of the BBC’s &lt;i&gt;The Daily Politics&lt;/i&gt; asked Peterson. His reply was simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No. […] Because I think that women are capable, generally speaking, of having babies and they have female genitalia and they have an XX Chromosome and I think the biological markers are relevant.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are Peterson’s comments controversial? Certainly. Insulting? For many, yes. But transphobic? Discriminatory? Prejudiced? Is Peterson taking his alleged “freedom of speech” a bit too far? How would we react if someone today claimed that a black person was not a “real person” or a “real human” and would use that as a basis for denying that such a person is entitled to human rights? I am not making this up. That is precisely what many Southern Americans believed about non-white people. The idea was that humanoid beings pre-existed before Adam, and that blacks were among the “beasts of the field” described in the initial chapters of the Book of Genesis. White supremacists used this religious belief in order to justify slavery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone were to make this claim today, we would be appalled, and rightly so. But how different is Professor Peterson’s claim? At least, that’s the argument that might be made by some on the left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, numerous trans-people claim a number of distinctive rights. The right to be called by their preferred pronouns is one of them. Another is the right to use public bathrooms of their own choice, that correspond to their “gender identity”. But are they actually entitled to these rights?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not my intention to comment on whether transgenderism is legitimate or not. That is a topic for the experts and I am not sure I have any opinion on this. What I want to focus on though is the concept of free speech. Nowhere is free speech upheld in an absolute manner, and rightly so because that would lead to dangerous anarchy. There are a number of things which people are forbidden from saying, which would constitute “hate speech”. We cannot, for instance, encourage people to engage in acts of genocide. Well and good. The real dilemma lies, however, in the simple fact that the precise demarcation between authentic speech and hate speech can be very blurred at times. Doubtlessly, many transgenders have probably felt Peterson’s comments to be extremely offensive. But does this constitute “hate”? The man has not called for violence of any kind; quite the contrary, he advocates treating transgender people with the same respect and dignity that we would any other ordinary human being. It is the same with Ben Shapiro. The latter is not calling for persecution; from his perspective, he is merely exercising his freedom of speech to express his genuinely held opinion that transgenderism is mental illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question that arises then is this: What do we do when genuinely held opinions are so offensive for some on the other side that it almost &lt;i&gt;sounds&lt;/i&gt; hateful to their ears? What opinions are permissible, and what are not? Who decides?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some might say “Hate speech is when we call upon people to engage in violence”. But this presents its own problems. What if someone were to salute the grave of Hitler and publicly hang swastika flags over their homes? They may not be explicitly calling for hatred and violence, but can we deny that such actions are, at least to some extent, ‘hateful’? Others might argue, “We must restrict speech which goes against the common good of society”. This, of course, is even more vague – what exactly constitutes the “common good of society”? From such a perspective, it could be argued that “heretics” should be prevented from preaching, because by spreading heresies, they would be leading countless souls to hell – at least that was the argument of St. Thomas Aquinas. Or do we take a utilitarian view, and measure common good in terms of material happiness? Such measurements are, of course, very difficult to make. Because Stalin would probably argue that speaking out against Communism is against the common good of society because it creates unrest, raises discontent against the “ideal form of government” and misleads simple people, who are too illiterate and ignorant of the principles of economics to make a sound judgment in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is in these dilemmas that we see the absurdity of liberal democracy. If the goal of the state is to provide ‘liberty’ to all, then failure is unavoidable. What is liberal to one is inevitably oppressive to the other. What is freedom of speech to one is violation of rights to another. There are, of course, many states which call themselves ‘liberal’. But in each and every one of them, one will find people who are discontented, for whom the revolution has not even begun. So, while Dr. Peterson may be offensive and hateful to so many, he cannot be deemed to lie in the hate speech side of things. To deem his exercise of free speech as hateful would be to draw an arbitrary line between free speech and hate speech on the basis of offense, which, like any other arbitrary separation explained above cannot be sustained. As Peterson pointed out in the Cathy Newman Interview, he has to be able to risk offense to be able to honestly communicate.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Soham Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Hero. Mentor. Thinker. Professor. Ideologue. Right-Winger. Transphobic Hate-Monger. “Mean Mad White Man.” These are but some of the epithets which have been used to refer to Jordan B. Peterson, an eminent clinical psychologist who became famous overnight for opposing legislation that intended to make it illegal for people to not refer to transgender people by their preferred pronouns. Since then, he has been at the epicentre of a raging controversy about political correctness that has made an impact over most of the Western Anglophone world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
