<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/raghav.dhariwal/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2023-10-16T21:26:42+01:00</updated>
  <id>/author/raghav.dhariwal/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Choose France Tour 2022</title>
      <link href="/Choose-France-Tour-2022" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Choose France Tour 2022" />
      <published>2022-10-29T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2022-10-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Choose-France-Tour-2022</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Choose-France-Tour-2022">&lt;p&gt;As one graduates from school, they are already faced with one of the most important decisions of their lives, the inevitable: “What do I want to do after school?” In most cases, Indian students start looking for universities to apply to, to study further. A majority of these students stay in India to obtain a degree, some prefer to go abroad. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While an education abroad, like most other things, has its pros and cons, it is a fairly popular proposition that attracts millions of Indian students each year. People are willing to pay the high tuition fees and endure the expensive costs of living for the promise of a world-class education, a better quality of life, and the possibility of employment in a developed country. For these students, the first few countries on the list are always the US, Canada, the UK and Australia. It isn’t hard for one to understand why these would be the preferred options for Indians, these are English-speaking developed countries that have hosted Indian students for several decades now. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where the Choose France Tour 2022 comes in. It is an attempt by the French government to make France a solid option in the future for Indian students that are looking to pursue higher studies abroad. With a surprising three-fourths of all French University courses being taught in English, the assurance of lower economic commitment for the students (compared to other options abroad), and a vague but positive chance of employment opportunities post-graduation makes it sound like a lucrative offering. The eleven-crore-rupee sponsorship that the French government is offering as a stimulus for the initiative is also a great starting point. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even so, Indian students would have a hard time ignoring the fact that English is not France's primary language. Although 75% of the courses are in English, that is only restricted to the lectures and the curriculum material. A significant part of the university experience is outside the campus in the sphere of networking. Indians may feel disadvantaged compared to their French counterparts in these situations. However, the launch of the France Alumni India Chapter in 2016 provides Indian students who have studied in France with a unique channel for networking. Despite English being taught in French primary schools to children from as young as five years old, the language barrier will undoubtedly be felt in simple everyday life, socialising and interacting with locals. The French are certainly known to be very proud of their language, and rightfully so. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An optimist, however, would not view this as an obstacle but rather as an opportunity to learn the language. When you are in a foreign land, the cultural experience is much more enriching when you know the language. How cool would it be to be able to read Dumas’ original&lt;em&gt; Les Trois Mousquetaires&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;The Three Musketeers&lt;/em&gt;! Besides, being fluent in French can accelerate a student’s career. According to the &lt;em&gt;Business Standard&lt;/em&gt;, there are over 200 Indian companies, ranging from Tata Consultancy Services to United Phosphorus Limited, with offices all over France, and this number has been on the rise in recent years. Furthermore, top European firms heavily value fluency in an additional European language. Apart from the obvious social and occupational benefits, French is also known to be an analytical language that structures thought and develops critical thinking. It is no wonder that there are so many great French philosophers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question remains, why do the French even want to invest in Indian students? They could just focus on their own population instead. The truth is, France wants to tap into hot talent from a culture that values conscientiousness in education. Something that English-speaking developed countries have been doing for decades. Indian students’ GPAs are consistently above average in foreign universities. Today, the largest corporations in the world are run by Indians. What’s more, universities seek a diverse culture and an influx of Indian students would be another step in that direction for French universities. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the pandemic, in 2019, there were 10,000 Indian students pursuing higher education in France. The former French&amp;nbsp;Foreign Minister, Jean-Yves Le Drian&amp;nbsp;had set a target to double this number by 2025. Indian students currently enrolled in French universities appreciate the practical programme structure and the international outlook of these universities. Also very appealing is the option offered by the French government for international students after graduation to look for employment for a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All things considered, the Indo-French economic connection is already on the rise and this is certainly the beginning of a win-win situation that could benefit both the Indian student and the French government.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Raghav Dhariwal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="main" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As one graduates from school, they are already faced with one of the most important decisions of their lives, the inevitable: “What do I want to do after school?” In most cases, Indian students start looking for universities to apply to, to study further. A majority of these students stay in India to obtain a degree, some prefer to go abroad. While an education abroad, like most other things, has its pros and cons, it is a fairly popular proposition that attracts millions of Indian students each year. People are willing to pay the high tuition fees and endure the expensive costs of living for the promise of a world-class education, a better quality of life, and the possibility of employment in a developed country. For these students, the first few countries on the list are always the US, Canada, the UK and Australia. It isn’t hard for one to understand why these would be the preferred options for Indians, these are English-speaking developed countries that have hosted Indian students for several decades now. This is where the Choose France Tour 2022 comes in. It is an attempt by the French government to make France a solid option in the future for Indian students that are looking to pursue higher studies abroad. With a surprising three-fourths of all French University courses being taught in English, the assurance of lower economic commitment for the students (compared to other options abroad), and a vague but positive chance of employment opportunities post-graduation makes it sound like a lucrative offering. The eleven-crore-rupee sponsorship that the French government is offering as a stimulus for the initiative is also a great starting point. Even so, Indian students would have a hard time ignoring the fact that English is not France's primary language. Although 75% of the courses are in English, that is only restricted to the lectures and the curriculum material. A significant part of the university experience is outside the campus in the sphere of networking. Indians may feel disadvantaged compared to their French counterparts in these situations. However, the launch of the France Alumni India Chapter in 2016 provides Indian students who have studied in France with a unique channel for networking. Despite English being taught in French primary schools to children from as young as five years old, the language barrier will undoubtedly be felt in simple everyday life, socialising and interacting with locals. The French are certainly known to be very proud of their language, and rightfully so. An optimist, however, would not view this as an obstacle but rather as an opportunity to learn the language. When you are in a foreign land, the cultural experience is much more enriching when you know the language. How cool would it be to be able to read Dumas’ original Les Trois Mousquetaires instead of The Three Musketeers! Besides, being fluent in French can accelerate a student’s career. According to the Business Standard, there are over 200 Indian companies, ranging from Tata Consultancy Services to United Phosphorus Limited, with offices all over France, and this number has been on the rise in recent years. Furthermore, top European firms heavily value fluency in an additional European language. Apart from the obvious social and occupational benefits, French is also known to be an analytical language that structures thought and develops critical thinking. It is no wonder that there are so many great French philosophers. The question remains, why do the French even want to invest in Indian students? They could just focus on their own population instead. The truth is, France wants to tap into hot talent from a culture that values conscientiousness in education. Something that English-speaking developed countries have been doing for decades. Indian students’ GPAs are consistently above average in foreign universities. Today, the largest corporations in the world are run by Indians. What’s more, universities seek a diverse culture and an influx of Indian students would be another step in that direction for French universities. Before the pandemic, in 2019, there were 10,000 Indian students pursuing higher education in France. The former French&amp;nbsp;Foreign Minister, Jean-Yves Le Drian&amp;nbsp;had set a target to double this number by 2025. Indian students currently enrolled in French universities appreciate the practical programme structure and the international outlook of these universities. Also very appealing is the option offered by the French government for international students after graduation to look for employment for a year. All things considered, the Indo-French economic connection is already on the rise and this is certainly the beginning of a win-win situation that could benefit both the Indian student and the French government.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">NFTs: Desperate for Utility</title>
      <link href="/NFTs-Desperate-for-Utility" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NFTs: Desperate for Utility" />
      <published>2022-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/NFTs-Desperate-for-Utility</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/NFTs-Desperate-for-Utility">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It could be really difficult for one to understand why someone would pay $69 million for a digital image that can be easily copied and pasted for free. What one needs to understand is that the value of such an item is not in its utility but in its value itself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;What are Non-Fungible Tokens? The first part of the term is 'non-fungible' which means unique, and that such a token cannot be traded or replaced with another one of itself. Fungible items are non-unique and divisible items such as fiat currencies like the US Dollar, a lot of them exist and the one in your pocket is worth the same as the one in Donald Trump’s dollar. NFTs are on blockchains with most of them being on the Ethereum blockchain.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As most things do, status symbols have evolved over the centuries from Mayans pressing their children’s skulls into a variety of shapes to reflect their place in society to fancy watches and rare sneakers. As has been the case with most aspects of humankind, status symbols are getting digitised.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;If, like many others including me, you have failed to understand the utility of NFTs, in most cases, there isn’t any. Just like the tulips in Amsterdam in the 1600's or the Beanie Babies of the 1980’s. If you own any expensive NFTs at the moment, the two aforementioned examples must be ringing alarm bells in your head, or if they aren’t, then they should. The Dutch Tulip Mania of the 1600’s saw prices of tulips (the flowers that are now very common in the Netherlands) shoot up to US$ 750,000 per piece in today’s money before crashing completely.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A similar narrative played out for Beanie Babies. These two stories illustrate the inevitable disaster that follows the brewing of a financial bubble of a relatively meaningless asset class. In other words, when people buy utterly useless stuff only with the motive of flipping it for profit, the buying spree ends eventually and dramatically. Gary Vaynerchuk’s NFT restaurant located in New York City perfectly demonstrates the desperation of stakeholders in the NFT market to add utility to them.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Although the signs are there, it would be hard to say with the utmost certainty that NFTs are going to go down the same path as the other assets mentioned above. NFTs are still quite new from a global perspective with only a very small group of people truly understanding them. Twitter’s verified NFT profile picture is a positive sign towards widespread acceptance but there’s still a long road ahead for it to compete with more conventional symbols like fast cars or designer clothes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Since NFTs can be easily copied and pasted, it makes their apparent utility almost zero. Hence, it is easy for one to conclude that a person only possesses the NFT for either (1) flipping it for profit or (2) to flex. Unfortunately, both scenarios are problematic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The former points to a classic financial bubble, overinflated rates for little-to-no utility assets being held just for the sake of flipping. While the latter fuels the bubble, it also has its own limitations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Anybody that has enough money can buy an NFT, there are not many barriers to entry into the NFT game apart from possession of money. This makes NFTs a very limited status symbol as there is no exclusivity attached to them. Although money and status have a strong correlation, money does not guarantee status, hence the sheer ownership of NFTs only guarantees an abundance of money but does not guarantee status or honour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Unlike overly expensive clothes whose purchase can be justified by vastly exaggerating their additional comfort and style quotient compared to regular clothes, NFTs do not have an alibi for purchase. They are very loud and clear status symbols that are bought in an attempt to motion status. However, purposefully motioning status is a low-status action itself. Successful status symbols require alibis, their consumption needs to be legitimised by their progressed utility. To this end, extravagant brands talk unendingly about extraordinary craftsmanship, splendid planning or designing ability - to sell a facade of functionalism that conceals crude positional stamping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While indicative expenses and vindications are crucial, the most basic part of a status symbol is a cachet, a clear marker of a relationship with existing high-status gatherings. Both Ferraris and metropolitan waste vehicles are pricey, yet just Ferraris fill in as status symbols since rich individuals don't drive dump trucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;NFTs clear the principal bar of status symbols: they are extremely expensive. Steph Curry just paid $180,000 for Bored Ape #7990. For the people who got in ahead of schedule, time turns into the flagging expense. It may seem that the expenses of faking an NFT are incredibly low - screenshotting a Bored Ape is free - however, with the assurance of provenance in Blockchain, fake use can be uncovered right away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Then, do NFTs have any myth of utility? One cannot find anything more than the flimsiest common sense utility of &quot;workmanship&quot; (as Roose says, Pudgy Penguins are &quot;in a general sense inconsequential&quot;). In any case, there is a more essential issue: there is no real way to possess and show NFTs without aim. They aren't ‘normal’ portions of a high-status way of life. Each NFT recounts the narrative of a person taking the time and cash to get an NFT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Be that as it may, this is the place where things get extremely confusing. The best vindication for NFTs is that they are a venture. Steph Curry didn't squander $180,000 on a jpeg - he got it to sell it for a profit later. Simultaneously, the whole superficial point of interest story itself fills in as a vindication for the presence of NFTs: Without them being used in individual self-articulation, they are just unstable and speculative monetary vehicles. There is a circle, where NFTs are acting like status symbols acting like speculations. In any event, the way that individuals with such ease wield their speculation properties to exhibit taste says a great deal regarding our age. Most likely nobody in the 70's conveyed receipts for corn fates as their vacation cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In regards to cachet, NFTs right now offer no unambiguous relationship with high-status networks. Gary Vaynerchuk, Steve Aoki, Mike Tyson, and numerous renowned crypto-evangelists use NFT symbols, however, so do mysterious nobodies. Any individual who peruses a couple of bulletin articles can sort out some way to get one. That being said, aggregate proprietorship makes a ‘symbol club’. For Kyle, they are a &quot;weird blend of gated web-based local area, stock-shareholding gathering, and workmanship appreciation society.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;NFTs hence fill in as section level status symbols to join these gatherings. Once inside the ‘swamp club for chimps’, Bored Ape proprietors can partake in the warm sparkle of acknowledgement from outsiders. Kevin Roose, after purchasing a Pudgy Penguin, noticed, &quot;My notices were spilling over with bulbous and angled intruders, all praising me…&quot; But NFT groups have people of both low- and high-status positions, making them generally not quite the same as national clubs or VIP lounges. Anybody can join, assuming they have the cash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, many NFTs fill in as brilliant passes to these clubs. Right now, NFTs are just compelling for the individuals who wish to join the envisioned networks around NFTs. In the best-case scenario, NFTs might motion toward ordinary individuals’ profound information in crypto, speculation ability, and experience with state of the art mainstream society. Be that as it may, in our pre-metaverse world, NFTs draw no worth from being important to a high-status way of life; they just point out the cash expected to purchase them. This conspicuousness checks their viability. To be better status symbols, they should turn out to be more casual, like fine Swiss watches, they must be something worth acquiring as part of an attempt to symbolise aspirations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Raghav Dhariwal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It could be really difficult for one to understand why someone would pay $69 million for a digital image that can be easily copied and pasted for free. What one needs to understand is that the value of such an item is not in its utility but in its value itself.&amp;nbsp; What are Non-Fungible Tokens? The first part of the term is 'non-fungible' which means unique, and that such a token cannot be traded or replaced with another one of itself. Fungible items are non-unique and divisible items such as fiat currencies like the US Dollar, a lot of them exist and the one in your pocket is worth the same as the one in Donald Trump’s dollar. NFTs are on blockchains with most of them being on the Ethereum blockchain.&amp;nbsp; As most things do, status symbols have evolved over the centuries from Mayans pressing their children’s skulls into a variety of shapes to reflect their place in society to fancy watches and rare sneakers. As has been the case with most aspects of humankind, status symbols are getting digitised.&amp;nbsp; If, like many others including me, you have failed to understand the utility of NFTs, in most cases, there isn’t any. Just like the tulips in Amsterdam in the 1600's or the Beanie Babies of the 1980’s. If you own any expensive NFTs at the moment, the two aforementioned examples must be ringing alarm bells in your head, or if they aren’t, then they should. The Dutch Tulip Mania of the 1600’s saw prices of tulips (the flowers that are now very common in the Netherlands) shoot up to US$ 750,000 per piece in today’s money before crashing completely.&amp;nbsp; A similar narrative played out for Beanie Babies. These two stories illustrate the inevitable disaster that follows the brewing of a financial bubble of a relatively meaningless asset class. In other words, when people buy utterly useless stuff only with the motive of flipping it for profit, the buying spree ends eventually and dramatically. Gary Vaynerchuk’s NFT restaurant located in New York City perfectly demonstrates the desperation of stakeholders in the NFT market to add utility to them.&amp;nbsp; Although the signs are there, it would be hard to say with the utmost certainty that NFTs are going to go down the same path as the other assets mentioned above. NFTs are still quite new from a global perspective with only a very small group of people truly understanding them. Twitter’s verified NFT profile picture is a positive sign towards widespread acceptance but there’s still a long road ahead for it to compete with more conventional symbols like fast cars or designer clothes.&amp;nbsp; Since NFTs can be easily copied and pasted, it makes their apparent utility almost zero. Hence, it is easy for one to conclude that a person only possesses the NFT for either (1) flipping it for profit or (2) to flex. Unfortunately, both scenarios are problematic. The former points to a classic financial bubble, overinflated rates for little-to-no utility assets being held just for the sake of flipping. While the latter fuels the bubble, it also has its own limitations.&amp;nbsp; Anybody that has enough money can buy an NFT, there are not many barriers to entry into the NFT game apart from possession of money. This makes NFTs a very limited status symbol as there is no exclusivity attached to them. Although money and status have a strong correlation, money does not guarantee status, hence the sheer ownership of NFTs only guarantees an abundance of money but does not guarantee status or honour. Unlike overly expensive clothes whose purchase can be justified by vastly exaggerating their additional comfort and style quotient compared to regular clothes, NFTs do not have an alibi for purchase. They are very loud and clear status symbols that are bought in an attempt to motion status. However, purposefully motioning status is a low-status action itself. Successful status symbols require alibis, their consumption needs to be legitimised by their progressed utility. To this end, extravagant brands talk unendingly about extraordinary craftsmanship, splendid planning or designing ability - to sell a facade of functionalism that conceals crude positional stamping. While indicative expenses and vindications are crucial, the most basic part of a status symbol is a cachet, a clear marker of a relationship with existing high-status gatherings. Both Ferraris and metropolitan waste vehicles are pricey, yet just Ferraris fill in as status symbols since rich individuals don't drive dump trucks. NFTs clear the principal bar of status symbols: they are extremely expensive. Steph Curry just paid $180,000 for Bored Ape #7990. For the people who got in ahead of schedule, time turns into the flagging expense. It may seem that the expenses of faking an NFT are incredibly low - screenshotting a Bored Ape is free - however, with the assurance of provenance in Blockchain, fake use can be uncovered right away. Then, do NFTs have any myth of utility? One cannot find anything more than the flimsiest common sense utility of &quot;workmanship&quot; (as Roose says, Pudgy Penguins are &quot;in a general sense inconsequential&quot;). In any case, there is a more essential issue: there is no real way to possess and show NFTs without aim. They aren't ‘normal’ portions of a high-status way of life. Each NFT recounts the narrative of a person taking the time and cash to get an NFT. Be that as it may, this is the place where things get extremely confusing. The best vindication for NFTs is that they are a venture. Steph Curry didn't squander $180,000 on a jpeg - he got it to sell it for a profit later. Simultaneously, the whole superficial point of interest story itself fills in as a vindication for the presence of NFTs: Without them being used in individual self-articulation, they are just unstable and speculative monetary vehicles. There is a circle, where NFTs are acting like status symbols acting like speculations. In any event, the way that individuals with such ease wield their speculation properties to exhibit taste says a great deal regarding our age. Most likely nobody in the 70's conveyed receipts for corn fates as their vacation cards. In regards to cachet, NFTs right now offer no unambiguous relationship with high-status networks. Gary Vaynerchuk, Steve Aoki, Mike Tyson, and numerous renowned crypto-evangelists use NFT symbols, however, so do mysterious nobodies. Any individual who peruses a couple of bulletin articles can sort out some way to get one. That being said, aggregate proprietorship makes a ‘symbol club’. For Kyle, they are a &quot;weird blend of gated web-based local area, stock-shareholding gathering, and workmanship appreciation society.&quot; NFTs hence fill in as section level status symbols to join these gatherings. Once inside the ‘swamp club for chimps’, Bored Ape proprietors can partake in the warm sparkle of acknowledgement from outsiders. Kevin Roose, after purchasing a Pudgy Penguin, noticed, &quot;My notices were spilling over with bulbous and angled intruders, all praising me…&quot; But NFT groups have people of both low- and high-status positions, making them generally not quite the same as national clubs or VIP lounges. Anybody can join, assuming they have the cash. However, many NFTs fill in as brilliant passes to these clubs. Right now, NFTs are just compelling for the individuals who wish to join the envisioned networks around NFTs. In the best-case scenario, NFTs might motion toward ordinary individuals’ profound information in crypto, speculation ability, and experience with state of the art mainstream society. Be that as it may, in our pre-metaverse world, NFTs draw no worth from being important to a high-status way of life; they just point out the cash expected to purchase them. This conspicuousness checks their viability. To be better status symbols, they should turn out to be more casual, like fine Swiss watches, they must be something worth acquiring as part of an attempt to symbolise aspirations.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Bitcoin: The 21st Century Dutch Tulip Mania</title>
      <link href="/Bitcoin-The-21st-Century-Dutch-Tulip-Mania" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bitcoin: The 21st Century Dutch Tulip Mania" />
      <published>2022-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Bitcoin-The-21st-Century-Dutch-Tulip-Mania</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Bitcoin-The-21st-Century-Dutch-Tulip-Mania">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Amsterdam Stock Exchange (AEX), regarded as the predecessor of contemporary investing, paved the way for modern stock exchanges. However, it was also responsible for facilitating the first financial bubble in history, namely, the ‘Dutch tulip bulb market bubble’. It happened in Holland during the early 1600’s when speculation drove the value of tulip bulbs to extremes. At the market’s peak, the rarest tulip bulbs were traded for as much as six times the average person's annual salary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Tulips first arrived in Western Europe from native Turkey in the late 1500’s. Initially purchased as a status symbol by the wealthy, they attracted the attention of the middle class. In 1634, tulip mania swept through Holland. Charles Mackay stated: &quot;The rage among the Dutch to possess (tulip bulbs) was so great that the ordinary industry of the country was neglected, and the population, even to its lowest dregs, embarked in the tulip trade.&quot; According to McKay, a single bulb could be worth as much as 4,000 or even 5,500 florins. In today's monetary terms, the best tulips would cost upwards of $750,000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;By 1636, the demand for the tulip trade was so high that regular marts for their sale were established on the Stock Exchange of Amsterdam, in Rotterdam, Haarlem, and other towns. Professional traders joined in at that time, and everyone seemed to be making money just by purchasing these rare bulbs. The price of tulips seemed to only go up. People began buying tulips with leverage, using derivatives contracts to acquire more than they could afford. Despite the promising start, confidence got quickly shattered.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;By the end of the year 1637, prices began to decline and then never really went up. The rapid decline was largely caused by people purchasing bulbs on credit in the hope of repaying their loans when they sold them for a profit. As prices fell, the bulb holders were forced to liquidate and declare bankruptcy.&amp;nbsp; By 1638, tulip bulb prices had crashed, returning to the price levels they had once commanded upon their arrival in Holland. As a result of the Dutch tulip mania, the economy slowed down in the Dutch Golden Age. As the prices fell, demand decreased along with household spending, resulting in a shrinking economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, the actual impact of the incident is often questioned by cynics. Irrespective of the scale of the event, it does teach us an important lesson in investing: be wary of financial bubbles. Bubbles occur when market value erupts rapidly, particularly in the price of assets. Following this rapid inflation, a subsequent contraction occurs. A bubble usually forms when asset prices surge due to exuberant market behaviour. During a bubble, assets typically trade at prices that exceed their intrinsic value by a significant margin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Several such economic bubbles have occurred throughout history, such as the South Sea Bubble of 1720, Japan's Asset Price Bubble of the 1980's, the Dotcom bubble, and the 2008 US Housing Bubble. These are some of history's largest financial bubbles, but in recent times, Michael Hartnett, Chief Investment Strategist at Bank of America, has dubbed Bitcoin &quot;the mother of all bubbles.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The scenario around Bitcoin has almost all of the signs of a financial bubble. Bitcoin was launched in 2009 and took two years to reach the price of $1 in February, 2011. However, ten years later, in 2021, at one point it was worth just under $45,000. Hence, it has grown a staggering 45,000 times in ten years, a CAGR (compound annual growth rate) of 191.16%.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Even now, when Bitcoin has become culturally mainstream, it continues to be volatile. It doubled investors’ wealth in 2020, but it also halved in 30 days from mid-April to mid-May in 2021. These fluctuations have started to have major impacts on conventional markets such as the stock markets. Bitcoin reached a market cap of over $1 trillion in May of 2021, which is more than the combined market cap of Visa and JPMorgan. Due to its sheer size and the amount of money tied up in this cryptocurrency, when the bubble bursts and Bitcoin hits near-zero, it will be the 'mother of all financial bubbles'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Besides the inexplicable astronomical rise in value, there are numerous other indicators that point to Bitcoin being a quintessential financial bubble. Bitcoin has been labelled as a speculative bubble by eight winners of the Nobel Prize in Economics namely, Paul Krugman, Robert J Shiller, Joseph Stiglitz, Richard Thaler, James Heckman, Thomas Sargent, Angus Deaton, and Oliver Hart. While these economists have discussed a variety of issues concerning Bitcoin and cryptocurrency, the following are the primary reasons for classifying it as a speculative bubble:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lack of Intrinsic Value:&lt;/em&gt; While fiat currencies, which have been in use for as long as one can remember, have no intrinsic value and are backed by faith in the government, they work as a store of value because they can be used to trade almost anywhere and anytime. Furthermore, fluctuations in these currencies are effectively monitored by governments in order to avoid excessive volatility and protect people from unwarranted losses. It is in this regard that Bitcoin completely fails. According to Maddie Shepherd of Fundera, out of an estimated 582 million entrepreneurs in the world, only 15,174 businesses accept Bitcoin as of December 2020. Since it is not an effective medium of exchange, it also fails as a real store of value since it lacks real utility. Furthermore, its volatility is another reason why it is not a reliable store of value. As a result, it is not a real asset and has no intrinsic value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Susceptibility to market manipulation: &lt;/em&gt;Bitcoin has been artificially driven by tweets from eminent personalities such as Tesla CEO Elon Musk, demonstrating how fickle this market is. The Tesla boss initially supported Bitcoin. In February, he purchased $1.5 billion in Bitcoin for Tesla's balance sheet, and a month later, he announced that the company would begin accepting Bitcoin for electric vehicle purchases. After 49 days, he tweeted that Tesla would no longer accept Bitcoin due to the adverse environmental impact of mining it and subsequently turned his attention to Dogecoin. Thus, tweets with little or no substance are creating and erasing hundreds of billions of dollars in Bitcoin market value. This is a clear indication that a bubble has been brewing for some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Price is driven by momentum and attention from retail investors: &lt;/em&gt;Two factors that are behind the soaring price of Bitcoin are momentum and the attention that people pay to it. Momentum means that if Bitcoin goes up more than usual, it will, on average, continue to rise. The fear of missing out on this supposed ‘get rich quick scheme’ keeps the prices high. Similarly, if there are more Google searches for the word Bitcoin, for example, Bitcoin prices tend to go up. Hence, a large proportion of Bitcoin's gains are due to hype, as Bitcoin seems to be at the ‘Peak of Inflated Expectations’ phase on Gartner’s Hype Cycle for Emerging Technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another noteworthy point is that there are no readily identifiable real-world correlations. For example, it is well-known that gold and the US dollar have an inverse relationship. When the dollar is declining in value, gold is likely rising in value. This is a correlation that's been established over a long period. Enthusiasts have pointed out how Bitcoin is a hedge against inflation, but they forget that Bitcoin has both risen and fallen when the money supply expanded rapidly or slowly. Cryptocurrency is driven by emotion and technical analysis, primarily because it has no real-world correlations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Due to its monumental returns and growing popularity, Bitcoin has gone from being a relatively small niche of the tech industry to a cheat code for institutional investors to boost fund returns at the expense of ignorant retail investors. While the arrival of these investors triggers a spurt in prices, it also marks the beginning of the end for most financial bubbles. There is very little contrast between the Tulip Mania of 400 years ago and the current Bitcoin situation. Both started insignificantly, only to become public frenzies very soon. And in the pursuit of making an easy profit, the Tulip Bulbs imploded, which points to what is inevitably coming for Bitcoin. The bubble will eventually burst.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Raghav Dhariwal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Amsterdam Stock Exchange (AEX), regarded as the predecessor of contemporary investing, paved the way for modern stock exchanges. However, it was also responsible for facilitating the first financial bubble in history, namely, the ‘Dutch tulip bulb market bubble’. It happened in Holland during the early 1600’s when speculation drove the value of tulip bulbs to extremes. At the market’s peak, the rarest tulip bulbs were traded for as much as six times the average person's annual salary. Tulips first arrived in Western Europe from native Turkey in the late 1500’s. Initially purchased as a status symbol by the wealthy, they attracted the attention of the middle class. In 1634, tulip mania swept through Holland. Charles Mackay stated: &quot;The rage among the Dutch to possess (tulip bulbs) was so great that the ordinary industry of the country was neglected, and the population, even to its lowest dregs, embarked in the tulip trade.&quot; According to McKay, a single bulb could be worth as much as 4,000 or even 5,500 florins. In today's monetary terms, the best tulips would cost upwards of $750,000. By 1636, the demand for the tulip trade was so high that regular marts for their sale were established on the Stock Exchange of Amsterdam, in Rotterdam, Haarlem, and other towns. Professional traders joined in at that time, and everyone seemed to be making money just by purchasing these rare bulbs. The price of tulips seemed to only go up. People began buying tulips with leverage, using derivatives contracts to acquire more than they could afford. Despite the promising start, confidence got quickly shattered.&amp;nbsp; By the end of the year 1637, prices began to decline and then never really went up. The rapid decline was largely caused by people purchasing bulbs on credit in the hope of repaying their loans when they sold them for a profit. As prices fell, the bulb holders were forced to liquidate and declare bankruptcy.&amp;nbsp; By 1638, tulip bulb prices had crashed, returning to the price levels they had once commanded upon their arrival in Holland. As a result of the Dutch tulip mania, the economy slowed down in the Dutch Golden Age. As the prices fell, demand decreased along with household spending, resulting in a shrinking economy. However, the actual impact of the incident is often questioned by cynics. Irrespective of the scale of the event, it does teach us an important lesson in investing: be wary of financial bubbles. Bubbles occur when market value erupts rapidly, particularly in the price of assets. Following this rapid inflation, a subsequent contraction occurs. A bubble usually forms when asset prices surge due to exuberant market behaviour. During a bubble, assets typically trade at prices that exceed their intrinsic value by a significant margin. Several such economic bubbles have occurred throughout history, such as the South Sea Bubble of 1720, Japan's Asset Price Bubble of the 1980's, the Dotcom bubble, and the 2008 US Housing Bubble. These are some of history's largest financial bubbles, but in recent times, Michael Hartnett, Chief Investment Strategist at Bank of America, has dubbed Bitcoin &quot;the mother of all bubbles.&quot; The scenario around Bitcoin has almost all of the signs of a financial bubble. Bitcoin was launched in 2009 and took two years to reach the price of $1 in February, 2011. However, ten years later, in 2021, at one point it was worth just under $45,000. Hence, it has grown a staggering 45,000 times in ten years, a CAGR (compound annual growth rate) of 191.16%.&amp;nbsp; Even now, when Bitcoin has become culturally mainstream, it continues to be volatile. It doubled investors’ wealth in 2020, but it also halved in 30 days from mid-April to mid-May in 2021. These fluctuations have started to have major impacts on conventional markets such as the stock markets. Bitcoin reached a market cap of over $1 trillion in May of 2021, which is more than the combined market cap of Visa and JPMorgan. Due to its sheer size and the amount of money tied up in this cryptocurrency, when the bubble bursts and Bitcoin hits near-zero, it will be the 'mother of all financial bubbles'. Besides the inexplicable astronomical rise in value, there are numerous other indicators that point to Bitcoin being a quintessential financial bubble. Bitcoin has been labelled as a speculative bubble by eight winners of the Nobel Prize in Economics namely, Paul Krugman, Robert J Shiller, Joseph Stiglitz, Richard Thaler, James Heckman, Thomas Sargent, Angus Deaton, and Oliver Hart. While these economists have discussed a variety of issues concerning Bitcoin and cryptocurrency, the following are the primary reasons for classifying it as a speculative bubble: Lack of Intrinsic Value: While fiat currencies, which have been in use for as long as one can remember, have no intrinsic value and are backed by faith in the government, they work as a store of value because they can be used to trade almost anywhere and anytime. Furthermore, fluctuations in these currencies are effectively monitored by governments in order to avoid excessive volatility and protect people from unwarranted losses. It is in this regard that Bitcoin completely fails. According to Maddie Shepherd of Fundera, out of an estimated 582 million entrepreneurs in the world, only 15,174 businesses accept Bitcoin as of December 2020. Since it is not an effective medium of exchange, it also fails as a real store of value since it lacks real utility. Furthermore, its volatility is another reason why it is not a reliable store of value. As a result, it is not a real asset and has no intrinsic value. Susceptibility to market manipulation: Bitcoin has been artificially driven by tweets from eminent personalities such as Tesla CEO Elon Musk, demonstrating how fickle this market is. The Tesla boss initially supported Bitcoin. In February, he purchased $1.5 billion in Bitcoin for Tesla's balance sheet, and a month later, he announced that the company would begin accepting Bitcoin for electric vehicle purchases. After 49 days, he tweeted that Tesla would no longer accept Bitcoin due to the adverse environmental impact of mining it and subsequently turned his attention to Dogecoin. Thus, tweets with little or no substance are creating and erasing hundreds of billions of dollars in Bitcoin market value. This is a clear indication that a bubble has been brewing for some time. Price is driven by momentum and attention from retail investors: Two factors that are behind the soaring price of Bitcoin are momentum and the attention that people pay to it. Momentum means that if Bitcoin goes up more than usual, it will, on average, continue to rise. The fear of missing out on this supposed ‘get rich quick scheme’ keeps the prices high. Similarly, if there are more Google searches for the word Bitcoin, for example, Bitcoin prices tend to go up. Hence, a large proportion of Bitcoin's gains are due to hype, as Bitcoin seems to be at the ‘Peak of Inflated Expectations’ phase on Gartner’s Hype Cycle for Emerging Technologies. Another noteworthy point is that there are no readily identifiable real-world correlations. For example, it is well-known that gold and the US dollar have an inverse relationship. When the dollar is declining in value, gold is likely rising in value. This is a correlation that's been established over a long period. Enthusiasts have pointed out how Bitcoin is a hedge against inflation, but they forget that Bitcoin has both risen and fallen when the money supply expanded rapidly or slowly. Cryptocurrency is driven by emotion and technical analysis, primarily because it has no real-world correlations. Due to its monumental returns and growing popularity, Bitcoin has gone from being a relatively small niche of the tech industry to a cheat code for institutional investors to boost fund returns at the expense of ignorant retail investors. While the arrival of these investors triggers a spurt in prices, it also marks the beginning of the end for most financial bubbles. There is very little contrast between the Tulip Mania of 400 years ago and the current Bitcoin situation. Both started insignificantly, only to become public frenzies very soon. And in the pursuit of making an easy profit, the Tulip Bulbs imploded, which points to what is inevitably coming for Bitcoin. The bubble will eventually burst.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
