<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/sanjana.chandaliya/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-08-01T23:01:23+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/sanjana.chandaliya/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Turkish Diaries</title>
      <link href="/Turkish-Diaries" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Turkish Diaries" />
      <published>2019-07-06T14:40:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-06T14:40:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Turkish-Diaries</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Turkish-Diaries">&lt;p&gt;Before writing this piece, I had a couple of rather conflicting thoughts, that
made me resist the urge to write a personal account of my visit to Turkey. My
initial enthusiasm to pen down my extraordinary experience was soon met by a
greater impediment when I searched the internet to gather more information about
Turkey, as I will explain later. I would not have done justice to myself if I
would have written an article instead of a personal account. And so, I have
decided to shut down those thoughts and do what I wanted to do anyway, i.e. to
enlighten you about my journey, along with the aftermath, as it was in Turkey.
Nothing more and nothing less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turkey, one of the five countries to be a part of both Europe and Asia, was a
journey of a lifetime. Having visited five cities and towns over a course of
twelve days, I experienced breath-taking architecture (mosques, museums,
palaces, theatres and natural beauty), talked to Turks and ate traditional
Turkish delicacies. I consider myself to be in a position to form an opinion
about the country and its citizens. An Islamic country, where 99.8% of the
population follows Islam as its religion, Turkey was truly a blend of modernity
and cultural heritage, where people had accepted the reality of the modern era
while remaining true to their own roots. It rightfully stood in the middle
ground, embodying the qualities of both Europe and Asia. The country’s two
wonders of the ancient world: The Temple of Artemis and The Mausoleum of
Halicarnassus, its rich traditional architecture, a blend of Islam and
Christianity, was intellectually stimulating and visually captivating at the
same time. The cherry on top was the state-of-the-art infrastructure, pristine
surroundings, the technologically-advanced society and the open-minded people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a little hard to digest that an Islamic society can be so advanced and
modern, isn’t it? Turkey certainly broke the few stereotypes I might have had
against Muslims and reinforced the sense of respect I had for the religion.
There were some incidents that took place during the journey that compelled me
to think highly of Islam. In Islam, women are often expected to wear traditional
dresses (like burqa, hijab, niqab, etc.), look after the domestic chores, and
behave in a modest and polite way. However, men and women in Turkey wore western
attire; jeans and t-shirts among other dresses. In the entirety of my journey,
from a big city like Istanbul to a small town like Selcuk, I did not see more
than 20% of the women with headscarves, let alone garments fully covering their
body. The work culture was inclusive and women were financially independent. I
remember eating at restaurants and cafes where women waited tables, even at
night, a phenomenon uncommon in my supposedly more liberal home country, India.
Furthermore, unlike India, smoking in public was not considered a taboo in
Turkey and both men and women openly smoked in the streets. Although smoking
does not imply modernity, yet to experience it in an Islamic country is a big
deal.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was one incident that stood out from the rest and acted as an ‘inception’
for my exploration of the Islamic world. It was when I visited the Suleymaniye
Mosque in Istanbul, where a college student had volunteered to explain the
history of the mosque to visitors. While explaining the prayer pattern, he said
that women stood at the back during Namaz so as to ensure that men do not get
distracted during prayer. I found this absurd and initiated a discussion on the
point. My father was apprehensive that the discussion might turn into a heated
argument and tried to stop me. To this, the gentleman instantly replied, “I want
to hear her opinion. She (Muslim women, not me) is the disadvantaged one.” This
incident indicated both a positive as well as a negative point for Turkish
Islam: positive because the younger generations were open-minded and negative
because the religion put women in a position of disadvantage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To further my proposition, let us take a look at some statistics. According to
the Central Intelligence Agency of the USA, Turkey is a developed country and is
considered advanced in terms of infrastructure, technology, industrialisation,
per capita income and standards of living. For a better understanding of
Turkey’s economic and social situation, let us compare it with India:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turkey&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Male-Female percentage of population&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;49.1% - 50.9%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;51.8% - 48.2%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Population density&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;104.5 people/sq km&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;415.63 people/ sq km&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literacy Rate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;95.6%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;74.04%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Male literacy rate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;98%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;80.9%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Female literacy rate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;92%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;64.6%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quality of Life Index (Rank)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;44/70&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;52/70&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Population living in Urban areas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;70%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;33%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Source:&lt;/b&gt; World Population Review, 2019&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of some troublesome trends like rising unemployment and inflation, the
above statistics provide enough evidence that Turkey is a developed nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My curiosity to learn more about Turkish Islam and to uphold my findings led me
to collect pamphlets everywhere I went and undertake an in-depth search on the
internet. But, what I read online was in stark contrast to what I saw through my
eyes. I was appalled by the negative portrayal of Turkey in almost all of the
articles I read! All of them had some common themes: economic and political
instability, humanitarian crisis, disputes based on religion, and so on. I was
distressed to find out that a staggering 477 women were killed and another 232
injured at the hands of violent men in Turkey in 2018. It was only when one of
Turkey’s biggest pop stars Sıla Gencoglu filed abuse charges against her actor
boyfriend in 2018 that a media frenzy was set off, which sparked the
long-awaited national debate about violence against women. Furthermore, the
&lt;em&gt;Women in Statistics 2017&lt;/em&gt; report stated that only 28% of women above 15 years
of age were part of the Turkish labour force. These incidences reduced the
confidence I had in Turkish Islam. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthering my research, I found out that Turkey’s current President Recep Tayyip
Erdogan and his AK party have made the constitutionally secular country more
conservative and religious. The pro-Islamic authoritarian President aims to
raise a ‘pious generation’ and thus promotes the growth of state-funded
religious education in the country. Although the AK party claims to be secular,
it seeks to change the country’s laws to greater reflect its growing Muslim
identity. So, why did the modern people of Turkey elect Erdogan into power in
the first place? This is because, in the first decade of his rule starting from
2003, he initiated several rapid economic and democratic reforms in the country.
However, legal and democratic standards quickly deteriorated after 2013, and his
focus shifted to the promotion of Islam. As a result, people became fearful that
the President might slowly erase the line between Religion and the State, and
make Turkey a non-secular country, upsetting the great balance put in place by
the great Atatürk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These steps have received a backlash from the Turks, especially the younger
generation, and the level of piety has declined over the years, despite an
increase in religious education. There has been a significant drop in people
calling themselves ‘religious conservative’, from 32% in 2008 to 25% in 2018.
People who say they fast during the Muslim holy month of Ramadan declined from
77% to 65%. Figures for ‘nonbeliever’ and ‘atheist’, which had been barely
registered in 2008, increased to 2% and 3% respectively. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now comes the final question. Is Turkey a modern or a conservative Islamic
nation? The internet is full of Turkey’s past, which lost its way under
President Erdogan, both economically and socially. However, what I saw was
Turkey’s future, where the so-called ‘pious generation’ is changing course and
embracing people from all religions and backgrounds. There is no chance that the
AK party will come back to power in the next Parliamentary elections if it
continues with the same narrow mindset of making Turkey an Islamist nation. I
would urge the readers to develop a positive outlook towards Turkey, a country
adapting itself with the changing times while retaining its cultural heritage.
There’s more to this beautiful nation than what meets the internet!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sanjana Chandaliya</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Before writing this piece, I had a couple of rather conflicting thoughts, that made me resist the urge to write a personal account of my visit to Turkey. My initial enthusiasm to pen down my extraordinary experience was soon met by a greater impediment when I searched the internet to gather more information about Turkey, as I will explain later. I would not have done justice to myself if I would have written an article instead of a personal account. And so, I have decided to shut down those thoughts and do what I wanted to do anyway, i.e. to enlighten you about my journey, along with the aftermath, as it was in Turkey. Nothing more and nothing less. Turkey, one of the five countries to be a part of both Europe and Asia, was a journey of a lifetime. Having visited five cities and towns over a course of twelve days, I experienced breath-taking architecture (mosques, museums, palaces, theatres and natural beauty), talked to Turks and ate traditional Turkish delicacies. I consider myself to be in a position to form an opinion about the country and its citizens. An Islamic country, where 99.8% of the population follows Islam as its religion, Turkey was truly a blend of modernity and cultural heritage, where people had accepted the reality of the modern era while remaining true to their own roots. It rightfully stood in the middle ground, embodying the qualities of both Europe and Asia. The country’s two wonders of the ancient world: The Temple of Artemis and The Mausoleum of Halicarnassus, its rich traditional architecture, a blend of Islam and Christianity, was intellectually stimulating and visually captivating at the same time. The cherry on top was the state-of-the-art infrastructure, pristine surroundings, the technologically-advanced society and the open-minded people.  It’s a little hard to digest that an Islamic society can be so advanced and modern, isn’t it? Turkey certainly broke the few stereotypes I might have had against Muslims and reinforced the sense of respect I had for the religion. There were some incidents that took place during the journey that compelled me to think highly of Islam. In Islam, women are often expected to wear traditional dresses (like burqa, hijab, niqab, etc.), look after the domestic chores, and behave in a modest and polite way. However, men and women in Turkey wore western attire; jeans and t-shirts among other dresses. In the entirety of my journey, from a big city like Istanbul to a small town like Selcuk, I did not see more than 20% of the women with headscarves, let alone garments fully covering their body. The work culture was inclusive and women were financially independent. I remember eating at restaurants and cafes where women waited tables, even at night, a phenomenon uncommon in my supposedly more liberal home country, India. Furthermore, unlike India, smoking in public was not considered a taboo in Turkey and both men and women openly smoked in the streets. Although smoking does not imply modernity, yet to experience it in an Islamic country is a big deal.   There was one incident that stood out from the rest and acted as an ‘inception’ for my exploration of the Islamic world. It was when I visited the Suleymaniye Mosque in Istanbul, where a college student had volunteered to explain the history of the mosque to visitors. While explaining the prayer pattern, he said that women stood at the back during Namaz so as to ensure that men do not get distracted during prayer. I found this absurd and initiated a discussion on the point. My father was apprehensive that the discussion might turn into a heated argument and tried to stop me. To this, the gentleman instantly replied, “I want to hear her opinion. She (Muslim women, not me) is the disadvantaged one.” This incident indicated both a positive as well as a negative point for Turkish Islam: positive because the younger generations were open-minded and negative because the religion put women in a position of disadvantage.  To further my proposition, let us take a look at some statistics. According to the Central Intelligence Agency of the USA, Turkey is a developed country and is considered advanced in terms of infrastructure, technology, industrialisation, per capita income and standards of living. For a better understanding of Turkey’s economic and social situation, let us compare it with India: &amp;nbsp; Turkey India Male-Female percentage of population 49.1% - 50.9% 51.8% - 48.2% Population density 104.5 people/sq km 415.63 people/ sq km Literacy Rate 95.6% 74.04% Male literacy rate 98% 80.9% Female literacy rate 92% 64.6% Quality of Life Index (Rank) 44/70 52/70 Population living in Urban areas 70% 33% Source: World Population Review, 2019 In spite of some troublesome trends like rising unemployment and inflation, the above statistics provide enough evidence that Turkey is a developed nation. My curiosity to learn more about Turkish Islam and to uphold my findings led me to collect pamphlets everywhere I went and undertake an in-depth search on the internet. But, what I read online was in stark contrast to what I saw through my eyes. I was appalled by the negative portrayal of Turkey in almost all of the articles I read! All of them had some common themes: economic and political instability, humanitarian crisis, disputes based on religion, and so on. I was distressed to find out that a staggering 477 women were killed and another 232 injured at the hands of violent men in Turkey in 2018. It was only when one of Turkey’s biggest pop stars Sıla Gencoglu filed abuse charges against her actor boyfriend in 2018 that a media frenzy was set off, which sparked the long-awaited national debate about violence against women. Furthermore, the Women in Statistics 2017 report stated that only 28% of women above 15 years of age were part of the Turkish labour force. These incidences reduced the confidence I had in Turkish Islam.  Furthering my research, I found out that Turkey’s current President Recep Tayyip Erdogan and his AK party have made the constitutionally secular country more conservative and religious. The pro-Islamic authoritarian President aims to raise a ‘pious generation’ and thus promotes the growth of state-funded religious education in the country. Although the AK party claims to be secular, it seeks to change the country’s laws to greater reflect its growing Muslim identity. So, why did the modern people of Turkey elect Erdogan into power in the first place? This is because, in the first decade of his rule starting from 2003, he initiated several rapid economic and democratic reforms in the country. However, legal and democratic standards quickly deteriorated after 2013, and his focus shifted to the promotion of Islam. As a result, people became fearful that the President might slowly erase the line between Religion and the State, and make Turkey a non-secular country, upsetting the great balance put in place by the great Atatürk.  These steps have received a backlash from the Turks, especially the younger generation, and the level of piety has declined over the years, despite an increase in religious education. There has been a significant drop in people calling themselves ‘religious conservative’, from 32% in 2008 to 25% in 2018. People who say they fast during the Muslim holy month of Ramadan declined from 77% to 65%. Figures for ‘nonbeliever’ and ‘atheist’, which had been barely registered in 2008, increased to 2% and 3% respectively.  Now comes the final question. Is Turkey a modern or a conservative Islamic nation? The internet is full of Turkey’s past, which lost its way under President Erdogan, both economically and socially. However, what I saw was Turkey’s future, where the so-called ‘pious generation’ is changing course and embracing people from all religions and backgrounds. There is no chance that the AK party will come back to power in the next Parliamentary elections if it continues with the same narrow mindset of making Turkey an Islamist nation. I would urge the readers to develop a positive outlook towards Turkey, a country adapting itself with the changing times while retaining its cultural heritage. There’s more to this beautiful nation than what meets the internet!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
