<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/sanjana.chandaliya/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-10-08T20:50:35+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/sanjana.chandaliya/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Unending Battle of Keeping Trade Secrets a Secret</title>
      <link href="/The-Unending-Battle-of-Keeping-Trade-Secrets-Secret" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Unending Battle of Keeping Trade Secrets a Secret" />
      <published>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Unending-Battle-of-Keeping-Trade-Secrets-Secret</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Unending-Battle-of-Keeping-Trade-Secrets-Secret">&lt;p&gt;Ever heard of the secret recipe of the most popular drink in the world – Coca Cola? Or the algorithm Google uses to rank various websites in its search engine results pages? You would have heard rumours disclosing the special ingredients used to make Coke or the data used by Google to rank websites based on relevance to users. But, none of them would have the backing to be true, neither the practical applicability nor the affirmation from the companies themselves. These secrets are known as &lt;em&gt;trade secrets&lt;/em&gt;. As the name suggests, any sensitive information such as a formula, pattern, compilation, program, device, method, technique or process that needs to be protected from the general public comes under the purview of trade secrets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might wonder why Coca Cola and Google chose not to file for a patent instead. The obvious reason here is that the highly confidential information would have been disclosed to the public, despite giving the companies an exclusive right to the patented process, design or invention for a designated period. Unlike other intellectual property rights, trade secrets protect a much wider range of subject matter such as a business strategy, a new product roadmap, or lists of suppliers and customers and are not limited to set terms of protection. However, they can’t be enforced against anyone who independently discovers the secret. They are actionable only when there is any unlawful acquisition, disclosure or misuse either under breach of confidence or theft. Under such circumstances, the proprietor of the trade secret is eligible to get compensation from the party who committed this unlawful act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With growing cases of infringement of trade secrets, both the organisations and governments worldwide have responded by amending and introducing increasingly robust rules to protect trade secret owners and their rights. On the flip side, it must be ensured that the companies themselves do not misuse the protection provided to them by law and defraud the public by not disclosing harmful information that might lead the company to lose the competitive advantage it has earned due to the trade secret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classic example of a company engaged in this malpractice has been Theranos – the blood-testing startup with the big vision of testing patients for over 200 conditions off just a small sample of blood from the fingertip, thus saying goodbye to the big, bad needles. The innovative technology soon gained momentum, with the company valuing at $9 billion in 2015 and its CEO Elizabeth Holmes, the darling Stanford dropout of the Silicon Valley, continuously featuring in the lists of top global executives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before Theranos reached its peak in 2015, questions were raised regarding the reliability of the technology and the honesty of the company. The first decade of inception of Theranos in 2003 saw several collaborations such as partnering with Walgreens as well as Safeway to run health clinics, however, things started getting tense gradually when experts started showing concerns of discrepancies in blood test results of patients. The events that followed were clearly indicative of the secrets frauds committed by the company, with the chief scientist of Theranos committing suicide in 2013, President Sunny Balwani leaving the company in 2016 and an end to the partnerships with Walgreens and Safeway leading to the shutting down of wellness centres and clinical labs combined with the laying-off of employees and the piling up of lawsuits filed by investors, patients and collaborators. Such cases prove that although trade secrets give a competitive advantage to the owner of such confidential information, it can also result in misuse by way of not disclosing significant facts – the process of conducting tests in case of Theranos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many countries, like India, do not have sufficient laws to protect businesses from increasingly sophisticated infringers and at the same time to ensure that the companies make use of the protection provided to them by the state. The scenario is changing with the US and Europe, two of the most prominent markets, taking a step forward and implementing new laws that make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The protection of trade secrets was addressed by individual states in the EU before the implementation of Directive in 2016, which led to the harmonisation of laws across all EU member nations. The countries were given the autonomy to go beyond the minimum requirements and level of protection set out by the directive. The aim was not of full harmonisation, but rather to ensure that every EU nation at least achieves the bare minimum safeguard against the illegal acquisition, disclosure and use of trade secrets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK government introduced The Trade Secrets (Enforcement, etc.) Regulations in 2018 as a complement to the already existing Trade Secrets Directive applicable in the entire EU. The Directive was adopted by the UK so as to ensure that UK-based businesses having offices in other countries of the EU can rely on equivalent protection to their trade secrets in the local jurisdictions of other nations. Even post Brexit, the Directive will be applicable, regardless of where the secret holder is domiciled, provided the damage took place in a Member State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As per UK law, the cases are solved in a court of law wherein the plaintiff has to prove that the relevant information had the quality of confidence in the sense of not being generally known and not being of trivial nature. It has to be shown that the information was disclosed to the defendant in circumstances of confidence, and the defendant used or disclosed the information without permission or had threatened to do so. However, the Directive has placed restrictions by mandating the organisation to prove that it has taken reasonable steps to safeguard their secret, failing to do so results in loss of protection to the organisation. That apart, the Directive has scaled back the earlier system of confidential hearings and redacted publication of court documents, which may disincentivise companies to actually engage in litigation due to the fear of their trade secret becoming public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike other countries, the Defend Trade Secrets Act, 2016 of the US offers the parties the option of settling disputes under either state or federal laws. The parties have the option to choose from three different forums for litigation related to trade secrets – Federal District Courts, US state courts or the US International Trade Commission. These forums deal with any sensitive information acquired by “improper means” namely theft, bribery, misrepresentation, breach or inducement of breach of duty to maintain secrecy, espionage through electronic or other means. Although the laws at the state and central levels differ in some aspects, there is a great deal of similarity among state laws as the majority of them have adopted certain variations of the Uniform Trade Secrets Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prime onus to prevent misappropriation of trade secrets lies on the shoulders of the organisation itself, and not on the government. The business must clearly identify and classify its trade secrets, restrict access and educate employees on the importance of adhering to confidentiality. The employees must be made to sign Non-Disclosure Agreements (NDAs), legally restricting the employees from disclosing private information either to the competitor or the public at large. Exit interviews with outgoing employees can also be used to reinforce the organisation’s trade secret policy. Some special tactics of preventing data leak include &lt;em&gt;read-only&lt;/em&gt; files; password and firewall protection; check-in and check-out procedures; document destruction policies; and review of publications, presentations, at trade shows, on websites, etc. Wherein information is exorbitantly sensitive and would result in immense losses, the companies must segregate this precious information, under lock and key, designated as &lt;em&gt;confidential&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With rampant cybercrime, easier and faster decryption of data by hackers, the cases of data leak and misuse are growing day-by-day. In such an era, this serious yet undiscussed issue of trade secrets can be solved only by nudging the countries across the globe for the adoption of laws with stricter consequences of committing such crimes at international platforms.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sanjana Chandaliya</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Ever heard of the secret recipe of the most popular drink in the world – Coca Cola? Or the algorithm Google uses to rank various websites in its search engine results pages? You would have heard rumours disclosing the special ingredients used to make Coke or the data used by Google to rank websites based on relevance to users. But, none of them would have the backing to be true, neither the practical applicability nor the affirmation from the companies themselves. These secrets are known as trade secrets. As the name suggests, any sensitive information such as a formula, pattern, compilation, program, device, method, technique or process that needs to be protected from the general public comes under the purview of trade secrets.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Indian Economic Downturn: A Critique</title>
      <link href="/Indian-Economic-Downturn" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Indian Economic Downturn: A Critique" />
      <published>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Indian-Economic-Downturn</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Indian-Economic-Downturn">&lt;p&gt;The recent economic downturn in India has been the talk of the hour. The state of Indian economy is at its worst phase since the Modi Government came back to power in 2019. Having lost its coveted title of world’s fastest growing economy to China, India’s GDP growth rate has slipped to a six year low at 5% during the April-June quarter of 2019-20, putting the Reserve Bank of India’s projected GDP growth rate of 6.9% in grave danger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This decrease in the growth prospects of the Indian economy is largely due to the decline in manufacturing output and lack of consumption demand. This is clearly evidenced by the miserable state of Indian automobile sector, with an 18% dip in overall sales in July, 2019 alone. The worst hit was the passenger vehicles category, which saw a 35% decline in sales, followed by a decline in the sales of commercial vehicles by 25% and two-wheelers by 16%. Many automakers like Tata Motors and Ashok Leyland temporarily shut down their factories and suspended production so as to reduce excess inventories in a situation of weak demand. More than 300 dealerships have been closed and a mammoth of 230 thousand jobs have been lost in the sector. This heavy decline in sales has been caused due to a basket of factors, catalysed by upcoming changes related to environmental regulations and electric cars, and a lack of financing. India’s move to adopt new emission norms from April 1, 2020 has caused consumers to delay their consumption temporarily, partly because of the apprehension regarding validity of registration. A drop in rural demand is also evident from the reduced sale of tractors and two-wheelers in the country. In case of commercial vehicles, an increase in the freight carrying capacity of trucks has shrunk demand for new trucks. Further, an increase in the price of vehicles due to manufacturers having to comply with stringent safety regulations (airbags, anti-lock braking system and other crash norms) has weakened demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has tried to kick start the auto sector by taking steps such as lifting the ban on the purchase of vehicles by government departments, allowing additional 15% depreciation on vehicles acquired from mid-August till March 2020 to lower taxable profits and deferring the increase in one-time registration fee of vehicles until June 2020. However, many economists believe the downturn in auto sector to be cyclical caused by recent developments in the Indian economy which will eventually fade away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real problem comes in when people do not even have the money to buy things of everyday use like soaps, biscuits, tea, spices. The Fast Moving Consumer Goods (FMCG) market is in a lull with slowed down volume growth (number of packs sold) of companies like HUL, Daabur, Britannia during first quarter of the current financial year. On the other hand, the real estate sector is experiencing a downward trend in demand, with 1.28 million unsold houses as of March 2019, a 7% increase in the number from the previous year-end. This slowdown has affected more than 250 ancillaries that have forward and backward linkages with the housing sector, ranging from steel and cement to furnishings and paints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The underlying cause of the poor performance of the manufacturing sector is a fall in private consumption and investment. While turbulence in the world economy has impacted India’s exports, the slump in internal demand is a result of falling rural and urban wages. From having high double digit figures, growth rates of both rural and urban areas has plunged to dismal single digit figures, largely due to structural changes like demonetisation and GST in the country as well as a poor monsoon affecting the agricultural income in rural areas. This has resulted in stagnant per capita income (in real terms) and to keep the consumption expenditure at the same level, the household savings have declined, resulting in a subsequent decline in investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There exists a slow growth in retail loans such as home loans, vehicle loans and personal loans granted by banks and non-banking financial companies (NBFCs) during the first quarter of 2019-20. After the DHFL and IL&amp;amp;FS crisis, banks and mutual funds are reluctant to lend out to these institutions. This liquidity crunch of NBFCs has decreased their lending capacity. Borrowers too are apprehensive of their ability to repay loans in a period of decreasing real income and employee layoffs. Further, an inverted yield curve in the US, a symbol of long term lending rates being less than short term rates, is taken as an indicator of impending global recession. This is because banks borrow at short term rates and lend at long-term rates and the downward sloping curve means that the loans of these banks will become unprofitable, forcing banks to reduce their lending in the market, resulting in decreased economic activity globally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Modi Government has been quick in initiating a recovery process to bring back the economy on track and undoing the damage done by its Budget 2019. The government recently unveiled the mega plan to merge ten public sector banks into four, reducing the number of public sector banks to merely 12 in the country, as part of plans to create fewer and stronger global-sized lenders to boost economic growth. The Union Budget 2019 also talked about injecting ₹70 trillion for recapitalisation of public sector banks to increase credit offtake in the economy. The Reserve Bank of India has also cut the repo rate for the fourth time in a row in 2019 by 35 base points to peg it at 5.4% giving commercial banks a nudge to reduce their lending rates, thus passing on the benefit to customers and attracting them to borrow more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another smart move off late is certainly the transfer of surplus funds of the central bank, worth ₹176 trillion to the Indian government, which will not only reduce the government’s dependence on external borrowings to finance its fiscal deficit target of 3.3%, but also increase per capita income and job creation via increased government expenditure at a time of weakening private investment. However, this transfer will reduce the wide gap between estimated revenue and expenditure by merely ₹580 billion in this fiscal year, because an amount equivalent to ₹900 billion has already been proposed by the Budget 2019 and an interim dividend worth ₹280 billion has been transferred to the government in FY19. The government has further announced the rollback of enhanced surcharge on foreign portfolio Investments (FPIs) as well as exemption to startups and investors from paying an ‘angel tax’ so as to reverse the outflow of money from the Indian stock market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This current contraction in the Indian economy is neither wholly cyclical that is bound to eventually fade away nor is it wholly structural that will result in a massive recession. It is rather a combination of both, with lower per capita income, especially in rural areas, and low job growth being major structural issues plaguing the economy; and low consumer demand and liquidity crunch being the prime cyclical problems. The government has wisely used both monetary and fiscal measures to combat this slowdown, but there is still a lot that needs to be done like new infrastructure projects, affordable housing schemes, modified GST rates, better irrigation facilities and enhanced liquidity of NBFCs. In a time when the private sector is wary of investment, it is only the government that can nudge the economy out of the rock bottom.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sanjana Chandaliya</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The recent economic downturn in India has been the talk of the hour. The state of Indian economy is at its worst phase since the Modi Government came back to power in 2019. Having lost its coveted title of world’s fastest growing economy to China, India’s GDP growth rate has slipped to a six year low at 5% during the April-June quarter of 2019-20, putting the Reserve Bank of India’s projected GDP growth rate of 6.9% in grave danger.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Indian Startup Ecosystem: A Global Perspective</title>
      <link href="/A-Global-Perspective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Indian Startup Ecosystem: A Global Perspective" />
      <published>2019-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Global-Perspective</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Global-Perspective">&lt;p&gt;A proud moment for India was to have been ranked as the 5th most startup-friendly economy in the world, in 2019. This was based on five parameters: human capital investment, research and development, entrepreneurial infrastructure, technical workforce and policy dynamics. Despite losing the first four positions to the USA, UK, Canada and Israel, India has come a long way due to various government schemes such as Startup India, Make In India, Digital India, the setting up of the Biotechnology Industry Research Assistance Council (BIRAC) and many more which foster a culture of entrepreneurship and innovation in the country. However, India has lagged behind other countries in two aspects majorly; innovation and taxation. The persistent dearth of successful innovation and the recent ‘Angel tax issue’ have discouraged investors from providing funds to Indian entrepreneurs for the creation of their own startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As per Global Innovation Index 2019, India stood at the 52nd position out of a total of 129 countries for capacity and success in innovation. For a country that is the fifth leading startup- friendly economy globally, to rank so poorly in innovation is nothing short of a disgrace. This lack of innovation is clearly depicted by India’s relatively low expenditure on research and development. Although India stands at the 7th position when it comes to absolute money spent on R&amp;amp;D (after adjusting PPP) with a mammoth expenditure of $48.1 billion. However, this generally isn’t enough, given the large geographical area and population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relative figures show a different reality altogether. India’s expenditure on R&amp;amp;D continues to be as low as 0.8% of the GDP, much lower than countries like South Korea at 4.3%, Israel at 4.2% and Japan at 3.4%. The lack of quality research is evidenced by the fact that many of India’s startups are nothing but an emulation of successful global ideas fine-tuned to serve local needs. Talk about the American Uber and Indians have an Ola. Think about Spotify and we have the Indian version &lt;em&gt;Gaana&lt;/em&gt;. For Amazon, we have Indian competitors, Flipkart and Snapdeal. For Airbnb, we have OYO Rooms. We have the Indian Zomato and Swiggy as replacements of the middle-eastern Talabat. All these foreign startups were established before we Indians copied their ideas and made it our own. One cannot deny that India has become a startup hub with a total of 8625 startups in 2018 across various fields like edtech, traveltech, fintech, logistics and healthtech, yet it is even harder to disagree with the reality that the number of these startups formed out of original new ideas of Indians is laughably low. This is perhaps due to loopholes in the Indian education system that fails to provide the requisite infrastructure, skills and highly-qualified, research-oriented teaching faculty in universities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next lies the issue of the ‘Angel tax’ which has been tormenting the Indian startup ecosystem lately. Angel tax is an ‘income tax’ payable on capital raised by ‘unlisted’ companies via issue of shares, where income refers to the share price in excess of the fair market value of the shares sold. The investors providing funds to these companies also have to pay a ‘gift tax’ on the excess amount. The Angel tax was introduced in India in 2012 with the aim to curb money laundering by various small companies by imposing a high tax rate of 30.9% on all unlisted companies in the country, along with a tax on the investors. It all started when owners of small-scale companies started laundering their tax-evaded income by selling their shares to investors at a price above the fair market value. In reality, the investors got the money to be invested in the companies from the owners themselves and charged commission for helping the owners carry out the money laundering process smoothly. The Angel tax successfully curbed such malpractices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this started creating problems for startups (which are often unlisted companies), when honest angel investors who provided seed funding to these startups had to start paying an exorbitant tax on the excess amount, they began putting their money elsewhere. This gave entrepreneurs a hard time in finding that first cheque to kick start their business, thus, resulting in unnecessary road kills of many good ideas. However, there was a sigh of relief when Indian Finance Minister Nirmala Sitharaman announced in her 2019 Budget that startups and their investors, who will provide the requisite declarations on their returns, will not be subject to scrutiny under the Angel tax. The government also eased the norms for companies to qualify as startups by increasing the upper limit for the turnover of the tax exempt startups from ₹250 million to ₹1 billion. Furthermore, an entity will now be considered a startup for upto 10 years after its incorporation, as compared to 7 years earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India has definitely come a long way, but still has a lot to learn from how other countries have successfully implemented some out-of-the-box policies to create a vibrant startup ecosystem. The global startup economy has achieved great heights with a total economic value of nearly $3 trillion in 2019, a 20% increase in worth from the prior two periods. This growth is largely driven by high-tech startups in the fields of advanced manufacturing and robotics, blockchain, agritech and new food, and artificial intelligence. Meanwhile, sectors such as edtech, digital media, gaming and adTech have seen falling levels of investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some countries have outperformed others in terms of innovation, friendly government policies and entrepreneurial mindset. Israel is one such country which boasts of the highest venture capital investments as a percentage of GDP. The influx of highly educated Jewish immigrants in the 1990’s and the training of people in sophisticated technology, due to compulsory military service, has given a boost to technological research in this small Middle-Eastern country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has played an instrumental role in ensuring that this abundant human capital does not go to waste by providing adequate funding to convert their ideas into businesses. The Matching Grants Programme is one such government initiative that was launched with the aim to eliminate the financial risk associated with the ambiguity in the outcome of a research. The firms simply have to submit their R&amp;amp;D proposals to the chief scientist, and grants are awarded on a competitive basis, with 66% to 90% of the research costs covered. These grants act as high-risk loans, where successful projects repay the funding received via a deduction of a small percentage of annual sales whereas the government bears the costs of the unsuccessful projects. This policy played a major role in boosting the high-tech industry of Israel and made it the ‘Startup Nation’ that it is today. In India, the government does provide funds to startups to carry on R&amp;amp;D, but it does not bear the risk of failure of startup. With over 90% of Indian startups failing in the initial years due to lack of original ideas and innovation, a government policy mirroring Israel’s will inculcate a sense of confidence conducive to taking bolder risks by entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canada is also known for its startup hubs like Montreal, Vancouver and Toronto. Canada has successfully launched and implemented NextAI: the first global programme to build Canada’s Artificial Intelligence ecosystem. It not only provides funding to talented teams and individuals in AI ranging from $50,000 to an additional $150,000 to the top performers, but also provides them with education from AI experts, a network of like-minded innovators and corporate mentors, office space in AI-focused hubs, and easy access to visas to entrepreneurs from abroad. R&amp;amp;D on AI is non-existent in India and initiatives like NextAI must be undertaken in collaboration with educational institutions, the corporate sector and international governments to provide Indian researchers the required expertise and monetary support to kickstart such a programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In European countries, like the UK, private companies help individuals and firms in the paperwork of proving and estimating the costs of R&amp;amp;D for a meagre commission, a facility non-existent in India. This has great prospects in India because this Asian country requires every fund-raising request to go through 14 procedural stages against the global average of 4.3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the single most important aspect which Indians lack is the Israeli ‘chutzpah’, which literally translates to audacity and boldness. Entrepreneurs in countries like USA, UK, Canada, Japan and Germany are risk-takers who are not afraid to fail. Unlike India, where being practical and financially secure is given far more significance than the ability to dream big, failure is merely seen as a learning experience and a stepping stone to success in these counties. The Indian startup economy has not yet seen its full potential due to the timid and risk-averse nature of people, which is reiterated time and again, thus, creating a mental barrier in people. However, India is changing for the better, with a bold, young generation ready to take the risks of having their own businesses. India is treading the correct path. All it needs to do is learn from the best; whether that is innovative governmental policies or Chutzpah, and finally, implement it efficiently in their country.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sanjana Chandaliya</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A proud moment for India was to have been ranked as the 5th most startup-friendly economy in the world, in 2019. This was based on five parameters: human capital investment, research and development, entrepreneurial infrastructure, technical workforce and policy dynamics. Despite losing the first four positions to the USA, UK, Canada and Israel, India has come a long way due to various government schemes such as Startup India, Make In India, Digital India, the setting up of the Biotechnology Industry Research Assistance Council (BIRAC) and many more which foster a culture of entrepreneurship and innovation in the country. However, India has lagged behind other countries in two aspects majorly; innovation and taxation. The persistent dearth of successful innovation and the recent ‘Angel tax issue’ have discouraged investors from providing funds to Indian entrepreneurs for the creation of their own startups.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Turkish Diaries</title>
      <link href="/Turkish-Diaries" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Turkish Diaries" />
      <published>2019-07-06T14:40:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-06T14:40:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Turkish-Diaries</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Turkish-Diaries">&lt;p&gt;Before writing this piece, I had a couple of rather conflicting thoughts, that
made me resist the urge to write a personal account of my visit to Turkey. My
initial enthusiasm to pen down my extraordinary experience was soon met by a
greater impediment when I searched the internet to gather more information about
Turkey, as I will explain later. I would not have done justice to myself if I
would have written an article instead of a personal account. And so, I have
decided to shut down those thoughts and do what I wanted to do anyway, i.e. to
enlighten you about my journey, along with the aftermath, as it was in Turkey.
Nothing more and nothing less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turkey, one of the five countries to be a part of both Europe and Asia, was a
journey of a lifetime. Having visited five cities and towns over a course of
twelve days, I experienced breath-taking architecture (mosques, museums,
palaces, theatres and natural beauty), talked to Turks and ate traditional
Turkish delicacies. I consider myself to be in a position to form an opinion
about the country and its citizens. An Islamic country, where 99.8% of the
population follows Islam as its religion, Turkey was truly a blend of modernity
and cultural heritage, where people had accepted the reality of the modern era
while remaining true to their own roots. It rightfully stood in the middle
ground, embodying the qualities of both Europe and Asia. The country’s two
wonders of the ancient world: The Temple of Artemis and The Mausoleum of
Halicarnassus, its rich traditional architecture, a blend of Islam and
Christianity, was intellectually stimulating and visually captivating at the
same time. The cherry on top was the state-of-the-art infrastructure, pristine
surroundings, the technologically-advanced society and the open-minded people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a little hard to digest that an Islamic society can be so advanced and
modern, isn’t it? Turkey certainly broke the few stereotypes I might have had
against Muslims and reinforced the sense of respect I had for the religion.
There were some incidents that took place during the journey that compelled me
to think highly of Islam. In Islam, women are often expected to wear traditional
dresses (like burqa, hijab, niqab, etc.), look after the domestic chores, and
behave in a modest and polite way. However, men and women in Turkey wore western
attire; jeans and t-shirts among other dresses. In the entirety of my journey,
from a big city like Istanbul to a small town like Selcuk, I did not see more
than 20% of the women with headscarves, let alone garments fully covering their
body. The work culture was inclusive and women were financially independent. I
remember eating at restaurants and cafes where women waited tables, even at
night, a phenomenon uncommon in my supposedly more liberal home country, India.
Furthermore, unlike India, smoking in public was not considered a taboo in
Turkey and both men and women openly smoked in the streets. Although smoking
does not imply modernity, yet to experience it in an Islamic country is a big
deal.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was one incident that stood out from the rest and acted as an ‘inception’
for my exploration of the Islamic world. It was when I visited the Suleymaniye
Mosque in Istanbul, where a college student had volunteered to explain the
history of the mosque to visitors. While explaining the prayer pattern, he said
that women stood at the back during Namaz so as to ensure that men do not get
distracted during prayer. I found this absurd and initiated a discussion on the
point. My father was apprehensive that the discussion might turn into a heated
argument and tried to stop me. To this, the gentleman instantly replied, “I want
to hear her opinion. She (Muslim women, not me) is the disadvantaged one.” This
incident indicated both a positive as well as a negative point for Turkish
Islam: positive because the younger generations were open-minded and negative
because the religion put women in a position of disadvantage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To further my proposition, let us take a look at some statistics. According to
the Central Intelligence Agency of the USA, Turkey is a developed country and is
considered advanced in terms of infrastructure, technology, industrialisation,
per capita income and standards of living. For a better understanding of
Turkey’s economic and social situation, let us compare it with India:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turkey&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Male-Female percentage of population&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;49.1% - 50.9%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;51.8% - 48.2%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Population density&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;104.5 people/sq km&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;415.63 people/ sq km&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literacy Rate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;95.6%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;74.04%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Male literacy rate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;98%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;80.9%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Female literacy rate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;92%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;64.6%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quality of Life Index (Rank)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;44/70&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;52/70&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Population living in Urban areas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;70%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;33%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Source:&lt;/b&gt; World Population Review, 2019&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of some troublesome trends like rising unemployment and inflation, the
above statistics provide enough evidence that Turkey is a developed nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My curiosity to learn more about Turkish Islam and to uphold my findings led me
to collect pamphlets everywhere I went and undertake an in-depth search on the
internet. But, what I read online was in stark contrast to what I saw through my
eyes. I was appalled by the negative portrayal of Turkey in almost all of the
articles I read! All of them had some common themes: economic and political
instability, humanitarian crisis, disputes based on religion, and so on. I was
distressed to find out that a staggering 477 women were killed and another 232
injured at the hands of violent men in Turkey in 2018. It was only when one of
Turkey’s biggest pop stars Sıla Gencoglu filed abuse charges against her actor
boyfriend in 2018 that a media frenzy was set off, which sparked the
long-awaited national debate about violence against women. Furthermore, the
&lt;em&gt;Women in Statistics 2017&lt;/em&gt; report stated that only 28% of women above 15 years
of age were part of the Turkish labour force. These incidences reduced the
confidence I had in Turkish Islam. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthering my research, I found out that Turkey’s current President Recep Tayyip
Erdogan and his AK party have made the constitutionally secular country more
conservative and religious. The pro-Islamic authoritarian President aims to
raise a ‘pious generation’ and thus promotes the growth of state-funded
religious education in the country. Although the AK party claims to be secular,
it seeks to change the country’s laws to greater reflect its growing Muslim
identity. So, why did the modern people of Turkey elect Erdogan into power in
the first place? This is because, in the first decade of his rule starting from
2003, he initiated several rapid economic and democratic reforms in the country.
However, legal and democratic standards quickly deteriorated after 2013, and his
focus shifted to the promotion of Islam. As a result, people became fearful that
the President might slowly erase the line between Religion and the State, and
make Turkey a non-secular country, upsetting the great balance put in place by
the great Atatürk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These steps have received a backlash from the Turks, especially the younger
generation, and the level of piety has declined over the years, despite an
increase in religious education. There has been a significant drop in people
calling themselves ‘religious conservative’, from 32% in 2008 to 25% in 2018.
People who say they fast during the Muslim holy month of Ramadan declined from
77% to 65%. Figures for ‘nonbeliever’ and ‘atheist’, which had been barely
registered in 2008, increased to 2% and 3% respectively. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now comes the final question. Is Turkey a modern or a conservative Islamic
nation? The internet is full of Turkey’s past, which lost its way under
President Erdogan, both economically and socially. However, what I saw was
Turkey’s future, where the so-called ‘pious generation’ is changing course and
embracing people from all religions and backgrounds. There is no chance that the
AK party will come back to power in the next Parliamentary elections if it
continues with the same narrow mindset of making Turkey an Islamist nation. I
would urge the readers to develop a positive outlook towards Turkey, a country
adapting itself with the changing times while retaining its cultural heritage.
There’s more to this beautiful nation than what meets the internet!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sanjana Chandaliya</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Before writing this piece, I had a couple of rather conflicting thoughts, that made me resist the urge to write a personal account of my visit to Turkey. My initial enthusiasm to pen down my extraordinary experience was soon met by a greater impediment when I searched the internet to gather more information about Turkey, as I will explain later. I would not have done justice to myself if I would have written an article instead of a personal account. And so, I have decided to shut down those thoughts and do what I wanted to do anyway, i.e. to enlighten you about my journey, along with the aftermath, as it was in Turkey. Nothing more and nothing less. Turkey, one of the five countries to be a part of both Europe and Asia, was a journey of a lifetime. Having visited five cities and towns over a course of twelve days, I experienced breath-taking architecture (mosques, museums, palaces, theatres and natural beauty), talked to Turks and ate traditional Turkish delicacies. I consider myself to be in a position to form an opinion about the country and its citizens. An Islamic country, where 99.8% of the population follows Islam as its religion, Turkey was truly a blend of modernity and cultural heritage, where people had accepted the reality of the modern era while remaining true to their own roots. It rightfully stood in the middle ground, embodying the qualities of both Europe and Asia. The country’s two wonders of the ancient world: The Temple of Artemis and The Mausoleum of Halicarnassus, its rich traditional architecture, a blend of Islam and Christianity, was intellectually stimulating and visually captivating at the same time. The cherry on top was the state-of-the-art infrastructure, pristine surroundings, the technologically-advanced society and the open-minded people.  It’s a little hard to digest that an Islamic society can be so advanced and modern, isn’t it? Turkey certainly broke the few stereotypes I might have had against Muslims and reinforced the sense of respect I had for the religion. There were some incidents that took place during the journey that compelled me to think highly of Islam. In Islam, women are often expected to wear traditional dresses (like burqa, hijab, niqab, etc.), look after the domestic chores, and behave in a modest and polite way. However, men and women in Turkey wore western attire; jeans and t-shirts among other dresses. In the entirety of my journey, from a big city like Istanbul to a small town like Selcuk, I did not see more than 20% of the women with headscarves, let alone garments fully covering their body. The work culture was inclusive and women were financially independent. I remember eating at restaurants and cafes where women waited tables, even at night, a phenomenon uncommon in my supposedly more liberal home country, India. Furthermore, unlike India, smoking in public was not considered a taboo in Turkey and both men and women openly smoked in the streets. Although smoking does not imply modernity, yet to experience it in an Islamic country is a big deal.   There was one incident that stood out from the rest and acted as an ‘inception’ for my exploration of the Islamic world. It was when I visited the Suleymaniye Mosque in Istanbul, where a college student had volunteered to explain the history of the mosque to visitors. While explaining the prayer pattern, he said that women stood at the back during Namaz so as to ensure that men do not get distracted during prayer. I found this absurd and initiated a discussion on the point. My father was apprehensive that the discussion might turn into a heated argument and tried to stop me. To this, the gentleman instantly replied, “I want to hear her opinion. She (Muslim women, not me) is the disadvantaged one.” This incident indicated both a positive as well as a negative point for Turkish Islam: positive because the younger generations were open-minded and negative because the religion put women in a position of disadvantage.  To further my proposition, let us take a look at some statistics. According to the Central Intelligence Agency of the USA, Turkey is a developed country and is considered advanced in terms of infrastructure, technology, industrialisation, per capita income and standards of living. For a better understanding of Turkey’s economic and social situation, let us compare it with India: &amp;nbsp; Turkey India Male-Female percentage of population 49.1% - 50.9% 51.8% - 48.2% Population density 104.5 people/sq km 415.63 people/ sq km Literacy Rate 95.6% 74.04% Male literacy rate 98% 80.9% Female literacy rate 92% 64.6% Quality of Life Index (Rank) 44/70 52/70 Population living in Urban areas 70% 33% Source: World Population Review, 2019 In spite of some troublesome trends like rising unemployment and inflation, the above statistics provide enough evidence that Turkey is a developed nation. My curiosity to learn more about Turkish Islam and to uphold my findings led me to collect pamphlets everywhere I went and undertake an in-depth search on the internet. But, what I read online was in stark contrast to what I saw through my eyes. I was appalled by the negative portrayal of Turkey in almost all of the articles I read! All of them had some common themes: economic and political instability, humanitarian crisis, disputes based on religion, and so on. I was distressed to find out that a staggering 477 women were killed and another 232 injured at the hands of violent men in Turkey in 2018. It was only when one of Turkey’s biggest pop stars Sıla Gencoglu filed abuse charges against her actor boyfriend in 2018 that a media frenzy was set off, which sparked the long-awaited national debate about violence against women. Furthermore, the Women in Statistics 2017 report stated that only 28% of women above 15 years of age were part of the Turkish labour force. These incidences reduced the confidence I had in Turkish Islam.  Furthering my research, I found out that Turkey’s current President Recep Tayyip Erdogan and his AK party have made the constitutionally secular country more conservative and religious. The pro-Islamic authoritarian President aims to raise a ‘pious generation’ and thus promotes the growth of state-funded religious education in the country. Although the AK party claims to be secular, it seeks to change the country’s laws to greater reflect its growing Muslim identity. So, why did the modern people of Turkey elect Erdogan into power in the first place? This is because, in the first decade of his rule starting from 2003, he initiated several rapid economic and democratic reforms in the country. However, legal and democratic standards quickly deteriorated after 2013, and his focus shifted to the promotion of Islam. As a result, people became fearful that the President might slowly erase the line between Religion and the State, and make Turkey a non-secular country, upsetting the great balance put in place by the great Atatürk.  These steps have received a backlash from the Turks, especially the younger generation, and the level of piety has declined over the years, despite an increase in religious education. There has been a significant drop in people calling themselves ‘religious conservative’, from 32% in 2008 to 25% in 2018. People who say they fast during the Muslim holy month of Ramadan declined from 77% to 65%. Figures for ‘nonbeliever’ and ‘atheist’, which had been barely registered in 2008, increased to 2% and 3% respectively.  Now comes the final question. Is Turkey a modern or a conservative Islamic nation? The internet is full of Turkey’s past, which lost its way under President Erdogan, both economically and socially. However, what I saw was Turkey’s future, where the so-called ‘pious generation’ is changing course and embracing people from all religions and backgrounds. There is no chance that the AK party will come back to power in the next Parliamentary elections if it continues with the same narrow mindset of making Turkey an Islamist nation. I would urge the readers to develop a positive outlook towards Turkey, a country adapting itself with the changing times while retaining its cultural heritage. There’s more to this beautiful nation than what meets the internet!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
