<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/basketball/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-05-31T17:21:31+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/basketball/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Unlikely Stars Breakout in the NCAA March Madness Tournament</title>
      <link href="/March-Madness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unlikely Stars Breakout in the NCAA March Madness Tournament" />
      <published>2019-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/March-Madness</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/March-Madness">&lt;p&gt;The March Madness tournament has become an American holiday every mid-to-late March. College communities unite to support their basketball program with the hope of winning a national championship. Aside from those who support their respected universities, others watch the tournament for the superstar athletes predicted to be drafted to the NBA later in June. One of the most fascinating things about the tournament is that every year there are breakout stars that shine on the big stage when it matters most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past season the Duke Blue Devils were on center stage due to their three phenomenal freshmen: Zion Williamson, RJ Barrett, and Cam Reddish; all three are projected to be drafted among the top ten players this upcoming June. When the ACC tournament was played, all media attention was put on Duke basketball and Zion Williamson, and the  Duke Blue Devils were heavily favored coming into the NCAA tournament as the number one overall seed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Zion Williamson and company were in the spotlight for the first and second rounds, a few breakout stars carried their teams and shocked the world. Ja Morant, a sophomore guard from Murray State, is now being regarded as the second best player in the upcoming draft, right behind Williamson. Morant opened up round one with a victory over Marquette with an impressive triple-double where he had 16 assists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the regular college season, the only programs that receive coverage from the media are the universities with large national followings such as Duke and Kentucky. However, the upside of  The March Madness tournament is that it allows for athletes at smaller Division 1 schools to make an impact. A good example of this is Warriors point guard Steph Curry, who was severely under recruited due to his small size. The eventual three-time NBA champion’s introduction to the national media happened back in 2008 when he scored 40 points and led the Davidson Wildcats in upsetting the number 7 seed, Gonzaga. Curry ended up leading his team to the elite eight where they were knocked out by number 1 seed Kansas. As a result, Curry was later drafted in 2009 by the Golden State Warriors as the 7th overall pick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NCAA tournament provides such a large platform for college players to make their mark and be noticed, and the benefits can be enormous. Kemba Walker, for example, was not a highly regarded point guard when he led his UConn Huskies to the National Championship in 2011. Walker and the Huskies entered as a 3 seed where they ultimately beat Butler and claimed their third national championship. During their championship run, Walker played sensationally and was awarded the tournament’s Most Outstanding Player Award. Walker was later drafted 9th overall by the Charlotte Hornets and has been on three all-star teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NCAA tournament provides opportunities for players in smaller programs to showcase their talent on a national level. The media will always follow the athletes and programs that dominate in the regular season, and this is why March Madness is so special. Players like Steph Curry, Kemba Walker, and Ja Morant all have a place in NCAA history where their names were made.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tyler Pesavento</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="basketball" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The March Madness tournament has become an American holiday every mid-to-late March. College communities unite to support their basketball program with the hope of winning a national championship. Aside from those who support their respected universities, others watch the tournament for the superstar athletes predicted to be drafted to the NBA later in June. One of the most fascinating things about the tournament is that every year there are breakout stars that shine on the big stage when it matters most.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">NBA Midseason Awards: Will the Best be Recognized?</title>
      <link href="/NBA-Midseason-Awards" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NBA Midseason Awards: Will the Best be Recognized?" />
      <published>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/NBA-Midseason-Awards</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/NBA-Midseason-Awards">&lt;p&gt;We’re more than half way through the NBA season and already it’s been full of surprises. The Denver Nuggets are in the two seed in the west, the Sacramento Kings are in Playoff Contention, LeBron’s injury, and much more. We are looking to have a wild second half to this season. But first let’s take a look back and grant some recognition to the players that deserve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Valuable Player: James Harden&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many players putting up great numbers for the season so far, but nobody is even close to James Harden. He is putting up 36.7 points, 8.1 assists, 6.7 rebounds, and 2.1 steals per game. He is literally tearing up teams on a nightly basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He even went through a five game stretch where he averaged 52.2 points per game. Its beyond impressive how someone can do that against the world’s best basketball players. The Houston Rockets are a much worse team than last year, but they are still contenders because of what Harden is doing this season. If he keeps it up he might just earn back to back MVP awards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rookie of the Year: Luka Doncic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming into the NBA, Luka was considered the best international prospect ever. So far he has lived up to the hype. He is averaging 19.0 points per game, 6.7 rebounds per game, 5.1 assists per game, and 1.1 steals per game. He is already competing at a high level as a nineteen year old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doncic is a wizard with the ball, making shots you can’t believe and constantly coming up with clutch plays for the Mavericks. It’s a great feeling for a team to know that they have their franchise player, and the Mavericks are probably ecstatic knowing that they have their guy. The sky’s the limit for this young star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defensive Player of the Year: Paul George&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far Paul George is having the best offensive season of his career. It’s pretty extraordinary that his defense has been so impressive as well. He leads the NBA in steals and is third in defensive win shares. This award has typically gone to front court players in recent years, which emphasizes how remarkable Paul George’s defensive game has been. Instead of guarding down low, he has the task of locking down the other team’s best perimeter player every night. The Thunder have the best defensive rating in the NBA and a big reason why is because ‘PG’ is leading the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sixth Man of the Year: Domantas Sabonis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sabonis has been a key factor to the Pacers success this season. He is nearly averaging a double-double off the bench with 15.0 points and 9.6 rebounds per game. Sabonis is also pulling his weight in defense with one of the better defensive teams in the NBA. The Pacers are at their best when Sabonis is on the court which says a lot since they are currently third in the eastern conference. Why he’s not starting is a matter of logistics but with Victor Oladipo out for the rest of the year look for Domantas to have an even bigger role for the team going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most Improved Player: De’Aaron Fox&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sacramento Kings have been one of the big surprises this season. They are currently two and a half games out of the playoffs and a big reason for their unpredictable success is the development of De’Aaron Fox. He made a leap from last season going from 11.6 points, 2.8 rebounds, and 4.4 assist per game to 17.6 points, 3.7 rebounds, and 7.2 assist per game. Fox has stepped up as a leader for a team that hasn’t been this close to the playoffs in over a decade. He will be a key factor for the Kings in their late season push for the postseason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coach of the Year: Mike Budenholzer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Milwaukee Bucks are in the top seed in the East and Budenholzer is a big reason why. The Bucks have made a couple of tweaks this season which have them one of the best teams in the NBA. Offensively the Bucks have made great strides this season as Milwaukee has the second best offensive ranking in the association. With LeBron no longer playing in the East the conference is wide open and the Bucks are the favorites to win it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the second half of the season underway only time will tell if these players and teams can continue to play at the level they have been since the beginning of the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from: &lt;a href=&quot;http://basketball-reference.com/&quot;&gt;Basketball-reference.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Jacob Jones</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="basketball" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">We’re more than half way through the NBA season and already it’s been full of surprises. The Denver Nuggets are in the two seed in the west, the Sacramento Kings are in Playoff Contention, LeBron’s injury, and much more. We are looking to have a wild second half to this season. But first let’s take a look back and grant some recognition to the players that deserve it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Golden Era Continues with The Warriors</title>
      <link href="/The-Golden-Era-Continues" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Golden Era Continues with The Warriors" />
      <published>2019-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Golden-Era-Continues</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Golden-Era-Continues">&lt;p&gt;Year in, year out, winning is the goal at the beginning of the season. And every season the reigning champion is celebrated for conquering the beast that is a playoff run. Unless that team is the Golden State Warriors. For them it’s just another day (or season rather) at the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past four years in the NBA The Warriors have created a dynasty like no other. They have made four consecutive trips to the NBA finals, winning three of them and solidifying their team’s place in the record books forever. This current run of dominance in the NBA seems to be slowing down no time soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DeMarcus Cousins Finally Joins the Splash Family&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Warriors quickly jumped into the spotlight and became one of the best, if not the best team ever. They dominate opponents with their ability to heat up like no team in history. They are virtually unbeatable with their four All Stars Steph Curry, Kevin Durant, Klay Thompson and Draymond Green. Let it be known that the Warriors are the first team in 40 years to have four All Stars on a roster, and now they’ve added their fifth. What does this team have left to improve on?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the off season after the 2018 NBA Finals, Warriors General Manager Bob Myers made the move to acquire six-time All Star DeMarcus Cousins to fill the role as the Center for the 2018-2019 season. Cousins signed a 1 year, 5.4 million-dollar deal with the Warriors after tearing his achilles with the New Orleans Pelicans last January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cousins has been on the Injured Reserve all season, but on Friday he was fully cleared to play in his first game with Golden State. It was a good run, but the season might be over for the rest of the competition in the National Basketball Association. Cousins is a great physical presence down low in the post and will force teams to crash down, which ultimately spreads the floor open for teammate sharpshooters Steph Curry and Klay Thompson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big Men Can Shoot&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Warriors are respected for their three-point excellence and have many players with the ability to shoot from anywhere on the court. DeMarcus Cousins is one of the best shooting big men in the league, shooting a career 33.8 percent from behind the arc. His addition to the team now allows the Warriors to be even more deadly from beyond the three-point line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Warriors’ dominance over the past few years came out of nowhere and they have no doubt planted themselves in the history books. The addition of DeMarcus Cousins should strike fear in the rest of the NBA, and who knows who else the Warriors could acquire? With three championship titles in four seasons (winning back-to-back in 2017 and 2018), this team shows no signs of slowing down.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tyler Pesavento</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="basketball" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Year in, year out, winning is the goal at the beginning of the season. And every season the reigning champion is celebrated for conquering the beast that is a playoff run. Unless that team is the Golden State Warriors. For them it’s just another day (or season rather) at the office.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
