<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/tejasvi.joshi/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2022-05-26T23:10:12+01:00</updated>
  <id>/author/tejasvi.joshi/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Most Oppressive Fashion Trends Throughout History</title>
      <link href="/The-Most-Oppressive-Fashion-Trends-Throughout-History" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Most Oppressive Fashion Trends Throughout History" />
      <published>2021-09-21T01:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-21T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Most-Oppressive-Fashion-Trends-Throughout-History</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Most-Oppressive-Fashion-Trends-Throughout-History">&lt;p&gt;For much of history, women have lived as second-class citizens. American women were only given the right to vote in the twentieth century. As recently as in the 1970's, a woman should be denied a credit card unless it had her husband’s signature. The freedom we enjoy today is a fairly recent thing; our grandmothers lived in an era with fewer rights, and the generations that came before them had it even worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from having fewer legal rights, women in the past also had fewer fashion choices.&amp;nbsp; As recently as in the 1940's, women were arrested for wearing pants in public, as they were considered to be menswear. In some cases, historical fashion trends should even be deadly. Here are some of the most oppressive fashion trends that have existed throughout history, which give us a gruesome reminder of how women's bodies have been policed since time immemorial to achieve certain extremely artificial ideals of beauty.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Waist-cinching corsets made it difficult to breathe&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corsets are still worn today, but most of them aren’t nearly as restrictive as the ones our ancestors wore. The rise of the corset as a device to slash the waistline dates back to the 16th century. Historical corsets were notoriously uncomfortable, and constructed from confining materials such as whalebone.&amp;nbsp; When laced into a tight, rigid corset, women should not raise their arms above their heads, move too quickly without running out of breath, or slouch. The corsets made women have impeccable posture by essentially locking them in a cage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the 19th century, doctors were warning women against lacing their corsets too tightly. As the 20th century progressed, bras began to displace the corset as the undergarment of choice, but the corset hasn’t really died out and still sees widespread use in the 21st century.&amp;nbsp; Fortunately, it is no longer a fashion staple or considered societally mandated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chinese women had their feet broken to make them smaller&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most horrifying examples of oppressive fashion comes from China during the Tang Dynasty, which lasted from 618 to 906 AD.&amp;nbsp; In the 10th century, small feet were highly prized, and the practice of foot binding in order to achieve 'Golden Lotus' feet began. Girls as young as five would have their four smaller toes bent under their foot and then tightly bound. This would impede the growth of the foot, and permanently deform it. The feet would be kept bound (although the bindings would be regularly changed) for the rest of a woman’s life.&amp;nbsp; Losing toes to infection was not uncommon, and even women who kept all of their toes had great difficulty walking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the practice of foot binding was most common in the upper classes, the lower classes would sometimes adopt the process in order to improve the marriage prospects of their daughters. Foot binding continued well into the 20th century, in spite of several attempts over the centuries to ban it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ridiculously wide skirts led to deadly accidents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the many fashions that inhibited a woman’s ability to walk with ease, wide skirts were some of the most dangerous.&amp;nbsp; Full skirts have cycled in and out of style for centuries. They were in vogue during the Renaissance era. By the end of the 18th century, skirts were straight, but began expanding again in the first half of the 19th century. By the middle of the century, women were wearing massive hoop crinolines underneath their dresses. In Europe, this fad came to be known as Crinolinemania. Skirts could be as large as six feet in diameter, making it difficult to navigate crowded areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, however, wasn’t the greatest drawback of the crinoline. The voluminous skirts could also get stuck in carriage wheels, and also posed a fire hazard. Since the skirts were so large and difficult to maneuver, thousands of women managed to set their dresses aflame when walking by a fire or a lit candle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hobble skirts prevented women from taking large sters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ease of movement was clearly a pretty low priority for women’s fashion designers throughout history. This was particularly apparent in the 1900's, when a new trend hit the fashion scene. The decline of the crinoline resulted in narrower skirts, but this time the fashion went too far in the opposite direction. By the turn of the 20th century, women were wearing skirts so narrow that they were dubbed “hobble skirts.&quot; These hobble skirts were fitted so tightly around the lower legs that women were forced to take tiny steps, hobbling along in their stylish garments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women wearing these dresses not only had trouble walking and dancing, but many also found themselves in dangerous predicaments. The constricting garments led to accidents and even death, making the trend one of the most dangerous of the century. Many people in the era were confused by the popularity of the wildly impractical trend, and hobble skirts were widely mocked in the newspapers of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Absurdly large gigot sleeves made it difficult for women to move their arms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too often, clothing is designed to be aesthetically appealing without being functional. Beginning in the 1820's, women had limited use of their arms thanks to gigot sleeves, also known as leg o’ mutton sleeves.&amp;nbsp; While ruffed sleeves can still be found in clothes today, the sleeves of the 19th century were so outrageously large that women could barely move. The sleeve would balloon at the shoulders, then tarer down along the arm before ending tightly at the wrist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These sleeves would prevent women from raising their arms above their heads. The large sleeve trend would continue throughout the Vistorian era. Combined with other trends of the time including wider skirts, tighter corsets, and layers of undergarments, women in this era were so encased in fabric that the summer months must have been agonizing for them.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These trends resulted in a generation of women who were barely able to move, let alone breathe. A physical manifestation of oppression if we ever heard of one and a practical manifestation of the dangers of 'aesthetic&amp;nbsp; perfection'.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, we’re stepping into an age where the media is beginning to celebrate diversity of race and body type — though there’s still a long way to go. Before New York Fashion Week 2017, the Council of Fashion Designers of America sent out a memo to remind designers to seek out healthy models and a wider range of types saying, “New York Fashion Week is also a celebration of our city's diversity, which we hope to see on the runways.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing to remember is that most of the historical standards of beauty were based on a drawing or a painting of a man’s fantasy!&amp;nbsp; Nowadays Photoshop has the same effect, making already-petite models look unattainably perfect. One can’t possibly live up to a fictional piece of art or a masterfully altered photograph. Since standards have changed so much over history (just try to wear big 80's hair and makeup to look hot today), it proves that these standards are really just temporary ideals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your body isn’t considered 'perfect' today?&amp;nbsp; Who cares! 'Perfect' is an illusion that no one can attain. So, be happy with the body you have and celebrate all the things that make up your gorgeous, imperfect self.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tejasvi Joshi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For much of history, women have lived as second-class citizens. American women were only given the right to vote in the twentieth century. As recently as in the 1970's, a woman should be denied a credit card unless it had her husband’s signature. The freedom we enjoy today is a fairly recent thing; our grandmothers lived in an era with fewer rights, and the generations that came before them had it even worse. Aside from having fewer legal rights, women in the past also had fewer fashion choices.&amp;nbsp; As recently as in the 1940's, women were arrested for wearing pants in public, as they were considered to be menswear. In some cases, historical fashion trends should even be deadly. Here are some of the most oppressive fashion trends that have existed throughout history, which give us a gruesome reminder of how women's bodies have been policed since time immemorial to achieve certain extremely artificial ideals of beauty.&amp;nbsp; Waist-cinching corsets made it difficult to breathe Corsets are still worn today, but most of them aren’t nearly as restrictive as the ones our ancestors wore. The rise of the corset as a device to slash the waistline dates back to the 16th century. Historical corsets were notoriously uncomfortable, and constructed from confining materials such as whalebone.&amp;nbsp; When laced into a tight, rigid corset, women should not raise their arms above their heads, move too quickly without running out of breath, or slouch. The corsets made women have impeccable posture by essentially locking them in a cage. By the 19th century, doctors were warning women against lacing their corsets too tightly. As the 20th century progressed, bras began to displace the corset as the undergarment of choice, but the corset hasn’t really died out and still sees widespread use in the 21st century.&amp;nbsp; Fortunately, it is no longer a fashion staple or considered societally mandated. Chinese women had their feet broken to make them smaller One of the most horrifying examples of oppressive fashion comes from China during the Tang Dynasty, which lasted from 618 to 906 AD.&amp;nbsp; In the 10th century, small feet were highly prized, and the practice of foot binding in order to achieve 'Golden Lotus' feet began. Girls as young as five would have their four smaller toes bent under their foot and then tightly bound. This would impede the growth of the foot, and permanently deform it. The feet would be kept bound (although the bindings would be regularly changed) for the rest of a woman’s life.&amp;nbsp; Losing toes to infection was not uncommon, and even women who kept all of their toes had great difficulty walking. While the practice of foot binding was most common in the upper classes, the lower classes would sometimes adopt the process in order to improve the marriage prospects of their daughters. Foot binding continued well into the 20th century, in spite of several attempts over the centuries to ban it. Ridiculously wide skirts led to deadly accidents Of the many fashions that inhibited a woman’s ability to walk with ease, wide skirts were some of the most dangerous.&amp;nbsp; Full skirts have cycled in and out of style for centuries. They were in vogue during the Renaissance era. By the end of the 18th century, skirts were straight, but began expanding again in the first half of the 19th century. By the middle of the century, women were wearing massive hoop crinolines underneath their dresses. In Europe, this fad came to be known as Crinolinemania. Skirts could be as large as six feet in diameter, making it difficult to navigate crowded areas. This, however, wasn’t the greatest drawback of the crinoline. The voluminous skirts could also get stuck in carriage wheels, and also posed a fire hazard. Since the skirts were so large and difficult to maneuver, thousands of women managed to set their dresses aflame when walking by a fire or a lit candle. Hobble skirts prevented women from taking large sters Ease of movement was clearly a pretty low priority for women’s fashion designers throughout history. This was particularly apparent in the 1900's, when a new trend hit the fashion scene. The decline of the crinoline resulted in narrower skirts, but this time the fashion went too far in the opposite direction. By the turn of the 20th century, women were wearing skirts so narrow that they were dubbed “hobble skirts.&quot; These hobble skirts were fitted so tightly around the lower legs that women were forced to take tiny steps, hobbling along in their stylish garments. Women wearing these dresses not only had trouble walking and dancing, but many also found themselves in dangerous predicaments. The constricting garments led to accidents and even death, making the trend one of the most dangerous of the century. Many people in the era were confused by the popularity of the wildly impractical trend, and hobble skirts were widely mocked in the newspapers of the time. Absurdly large gigot sleeves made it difficult for women to move their arms Too often, clothing is designed to be aesthetically appealing without being functional. Beginning in the 1820's, women had limited use of their arms thanks to gigot sleeves, also known as leg o’ mutton sleeves.&amp;nbsp; While ruffed sleeves can still be found in clothes today, the sleeves of the 19th century were so outrageously large that women could barely move. The sleeve would balloon at the shoulders, then tarer down along the arm before ending tightly at the wrist. These sleeves would prevent women from raising their arms above their heads. The large sleeve trend would continue throughout the Vistorian era. Combined with other trends of the time including wider skirts, tighter corsets, and layers of undergarments, women in this era were so encased in fabric that the summer months must have been agonizing for them.&amp;nbsp; These trends resulted in a generation of women who were barely able to move, let alone breathe. A physical manifestation of oppression if we ever heard of one and a practical manifestation of the dangers of 'aesthetic&amp;nbsp; perfection'.&amp;nbsp; Luckily, we’re stepping into an age where the media is beginning to celebrate diversity of race and body type — though there’s still a long way to go. Before New York Fashion Week 2017, the Council of Fashion Designers of America sent out a memo to remind designers to seek out healthy models and a wider range of types saying, “New York Fashion Week is also a celebration of our city's diversity, which we hope to see on the runways.&quot; The thing to remember is that most of the historical standards of beauty were based on a drawing or a painting of a man’s fantasy!&amp;nbsp; Nowadays Photoshop has the same effect, making already-petite models look unattainably perfect. One can’t possibly live up to a fictional piece of art or a masterfully altered photograph. Since standards have changed so much over history (just try to wear big 80's hair and makeup to look hot today), it proves that these standards are really just temporary ideals. If your body isn’t considered 'perfect' today?&amp;nbsp; Who cares! 'Perfect' is an illusion that no one can attain. So, be happy with the body you have and celebrate all the things that make up your gorgeous, imperfect self.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Revolutionary Force of K-Pop</title>
      <link href="/The-Revolutionary-Force-of-K-Pop" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Revolutionary Force of K-Pop" />
      <published>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-07-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Revolutionary-Force-of-K-Pop</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Revolutionary-Force-of-K-Pop">&lt;p&gt;This year, K-pop accelerated its expansion into all sorts of mediums — &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5892708/jessica-jung-shine-interview/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;novels&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.billboard.com/articles/news/international/9342105/k-pop-podcasts-coronavirus-quarantine/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;podcasts&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.billboard.com/articles/news/movies/9446222/netflix-blackpink-documentary&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;documentaries&lt;/a&gt;. And yet, for all the satisfaction these new forms brought with them, the music remained the heart of this global phenomenon. Despite the pandemic’s impact on the worldwide recording industry, releases from&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/entertainer-of-the-year-2020-bts/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;South Korea&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;saw no decline in quantity or quality, and a slew of artists produced their best work to date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The K-pop songs and albums that defined the year transported us to places we miss most—from&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5912807/best-broadway-shows-to-stream/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the theat&lt;/a&gt;re&amp;nbsp;to the jazz bar to the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5870462/rick-steves-coronavirus-quarantine/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;island vacation&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;that lives only in our memories or imaginations. Some prompted nostalgia for things we&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5902420/hugging-coronavirus-amy-ephron/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;once took for granted&lt;/a&gt;, while others inspired hope for their return. Through these releases, many of our favorite artists experimented with their sounds, all while building deeper connections with an&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5912998/bts-army/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;audience&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;they could only interact with from a distance. A talented rookie class experimented with retro sounds, while K-pop's most successful women brazenly defied expectations. Disco completely took over, and noise music prevailed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was also a year for career breakthroughs and major milestones, as the world's biggest superstars&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.papermag.com/tag/bts&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;BTS&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;continued to shatter records left and right and break new ground for Korean artists. They're going into the new year with three number-one singles on the&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Billboard&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;Hot 100, a whole quarantine album, and a Grammy nomination. And while the world got smaller, K-pop went bigger and bolder — sonically and aesthetically.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the global coronavirus pandemic put an end to live touring, the K-pop industry brought the spectacle to our screens with&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.teenvogue.com/story/k-pop-future-of-live-music-immersive-online-concerts&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;immersive live concert&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;experiences. The music never stopped, not even for a second&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you're a casual listener, a stan, or someone who's just genuinely curious to see what K-pop is all about,&amp;nbsp;here are 10 songs from the heat of KPOP that made the hard 2020 much easier and eventually took the world by storm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1)&lt;strong&gt; BTS, 'Black Swan' (&lt;em&gt;Map of the Soul: 7&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BTS has connected with a worldwide fanbase in large part thanks to the universal-but-still-personal themes of their music, and 'Black Swan' represents one of their most intimate confessions. Dreamy, gloomy hip-hop soundscapes lay the backdrop for the chart-toppers to open up about their darkest fears: that they may one day fall out of love with music. Using the title as a metaphor – to represent both the one-of-a-kind phenomenon they are and the 2010 movie where a ballerina makes the ultimate sacrifice for her art – the superstar septet investigates their underlying anxieties whilst declaring that they won’t let fear win over passion in the end. It’s a full-fledged motion picture-packed into just over three minutes to tell a rare, real-life story of one of the world’s biggest stars&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2)&lt;strong&gt; TXT, 'Can’t You See Me' (&lt;em&gt;The Dream Chapter: ETERNITY&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 'Can’t You See Me' TXT pulls the dark undercurrent of their youthful whimsy out from under the bed. Crunchy electric guitars and a jaunty whistle add a refreshing contrast to the track’s trap underpinnings, but where it best exposes its murkiness is through the quintet's vocal performances. Alternating between distorted tremolo vocals, hushed whisper-raps, and delicate verses wisping like curls of smoke, the members’ voices lurch between dulcet and disorienting as they reveal the cracks in a friendship. Through unsettling sounds and an idyllic music video that devolves into something frightening, TXT lay bare a horror rarely spoken of: watching a friendship fade before your eyes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3)&lt;strong&gt; &amp;nbsp;Twice, “I CAN’T STOP ME” (&lt;em&gt;Eyes Wide Open)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Dua Lipa and Lady Gaga, Twice were hip to electro basslines this year in “I CAN’T STOP ME.” The girl group bask in the elastic, strobing synth that pulses under the glamorous nu-disco track, and it snaps into formation with the chorus. The song calls for a grand celebration, but they’re too distracted trying not to indulge in their own treacherous desires: “I just can’t go back anymore/ Out of control,” Chaeyoung sings before the rest of the group fully surrender to temptation. Twice fight to keep cool, though it’s hard to notice when they nail such a spotless performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4) WOODZ, “BUMP BUMP” (&lt;em&gt;WOOPS!&lt;/em&gt;)&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a great year for soloists in K-pop, and no one was more honest with themselves than WOODZ. The push-and-pull of any romance is often the most enticing yet stressful aspect of it all. Amidst airy promises from his lover is the dreary prospect of being left alone, but he approaches this mixed-messaging with a refreshing candour. In our own whirlpools of flirting and call backs, IG-reels and missed messages, “BUMP BUMP” was comfortingly straightforward – with WOODZ relaying what he wants, exactly how he wants it. It was the wrong year to be young and in love in 2020, but at least we had WOODZ to keep us company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5) Weki Meki, “COOL” (&lt;em&gt;NEW RULES&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weki Meki revamp their approach in 'Cool' by swapping their preppy dance-pop for steely electro. The group’s demeanor is as spartan as the icy beat, and they amplify their bratty voices to assert their flawlessness. Their cockiness peaks in the chorus, which doubles as a taunt and a mantra: &quot;Be hotter/ Beyond the control,” they sing like a drill instructor. “Get out of all the boring rules.” If “Cool” sounds standoffish, then the song succeeds at what it sets out to do. Weki Meki don’t aspire to be a role model for attainable, girl-crush cool but instead point out the gap between you and them. “Cool” is a conceited celebration of self, though sometimes it just feels satisfying to flaunt what you got.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6). GFRIEND, 'MAGO' (&lt;em&gt;回:Walpurgis Night&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'MAGO' distils disco to its very best qualities, shimmering – quite literally – with synths and steady beats, building a heady, atmospheric high. As cohesive as it is musically, its magic lies in how perfectly it fits into the ethos of&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;回:Walpurgis Night.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;The album&amp;nbsp;is built on the idea of modern witches, at the centre of which are women who exercise the same agency and power of the song’s namesake, and GFRIEND has fun while doing it. Interspersed with images of the girls dancing the night away – not what you’d expect from a concept dealing with the occult – are lyrics that brim with confidence and ambition. Instead of believing in fairy tales and waiting for a Prince Charming, their only love is the images of themselves smiling in the mirror. It’s a cheeky way to poke fun at how society perceives self-assured women since the title itself translates to 'wizard.' In celebrating their limitless ambition, 'MAGO' casts a spell that keeps you coming back for more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7) SEVENTEEN, 'Left &amp;amp; Right' (&lt;em&gt;Heng:garæ&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'LEFT &amp;amp; RIGHT' is so exuberant that every sound – from doorbell chimes to 808 cowbells, organ synth riffs to full-bodied brass&amp;nbsp; –&amp;nbsp; bursts forth like aural confetti. One could readily claim SEVENTEEN have made their own 'Cupid Shuffle' but they’re aiming for something beyond mere dance instructional: this is a song for transforming every moment into a cause for celebration. In a time when in-person parties aren’t possible, 'LEFT &amp;amp; RIGHT' converts bedrooms into dancefloors. And with exultant shouts and energized rapping, they tell you to keep your chin up, to run down red carpets, to&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;dance&lt;/em&gt;. SEVENTEEN act as leaders and hype men here, but the role they fill best is that of life coaches: despite their talk of races and finish lines, they exclaim that “not running is an answer too / who cares what we do.”&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They grant permission to simply be: a reminder that surviving every day is enough right now. And after all, if you’re not moving forward, why not move &quot;LEFT &amp;amp; RIGHT,”&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt;? They understand something that should be taught in schools around the world: busting your ass should be supplemented with time spent shaking it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8) Apink, 'Dumhdurum' (&lt;em&gt;LOOK&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;K-pop tends to be a young person's game – both the industry and its labels regularly shift their priorities to younger artists – but Apink’s 'Dumhdurum' makes an exceptional case for the continuing effort and investment in senior acts. The track opens with a swirling synth-pop hook strong enough to stand as a chorus on its own, before diving into verses and choruses that strike pop gold with just the right amount of catchy repetition and melancholy longing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apink detail the complexity of remaining calm in the presence of a past love, even when one’s heart's still beating&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;dumhdurum&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;for them – a concept that could be difficult for younger groups to believably pull off. This mature message successfully connected with a large audience, and 'Dumhdurum' became a knockout success in both Korea (topping all local music charts) and the&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;Billboard&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;charts (tying for their longest-running hit on&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.billboard.com/charts/world-digital-song-sales&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;World Digital Song Sales&lt;/a&gt;).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nine years into their career, Apink are still more than equipped to bring their A-Game, and that deserves larger recognition all in itself for the industry to pay equal attention to both its senior and developing artists. Matured musical magic awaits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9). EVERGLOW, 'LA DI DA' (&lt;em&gt;-77.82x-78.29&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to a virtual flattening of borders, musical trends in the States now get reflected in&amp;nbsp;K-pop in real-time. Throughout 2020 – in both the U.S. and South Korea – throwback sounds were ubiquitous. This year’s K-pop magnum opus, EVERGLOW’s 'LA DI DA' mirrored the US’ pop magnum opus, The Weeknd’s 'Blinding Lights' only months after its release. But where The Weeknd’s work is chilling and sinister in its search for love, EVERGLOW’s is a spry kiss-off to all the haters, the bad guys, and the players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A successful pastiche of the 80's that’s crafted by producer Ollipop, 'LA DI DA' blends myriad influences: the&amp;nbsp;layered cheerleader chants of Toni Basil's '&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0aqLwHP4y6Q&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mickey&lt;/a&gt;' the spunky girl power of Cyndi Lauper and the Go-Go's, the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HnYWmgSZdlM&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;na-na-nas&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;of Bananarama, and above all, the shimmering synth-pop sound that permeated the top half of that decade. 'LA DI DA' melds these all together, with K-pop twists: a killing part punctuated by handclaps, a tempo-shifting rap section carried by leader E:U, and an earworm of a melody evocative of early 2010's K-pop – a time when choruses were packed with hooky vocal melodies instead of hollow drops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10) 'Lovesick Girls', BLACKPINK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arrival of BLACKPINK’s first&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5896487/blackpink-the-album/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;full-length album&lt;/a&gt; — so highly anticipated at the project was simply titled&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;The Album&lt;/em&gt;—was one of K-pop’s biggest news events in 2020. While the pre-release singles&amp;nbsp;'&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5859277/blackpink-how-you-like-that/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;How You Like That&lt;/a&gt;'&amp;nbsp;and 'Ice Cream' with Selena Gomez charted higher on the &lt;em&gt;Billboard&lt;/em&gt; Hot 100, 'Lovesick Girls' is the true gem on the album. The heavy electronic production characteristic of BLACKPINK’s crowd-riling bops remains intact, but it’s stripped back to accentuate sung melodies from the four members. Their voices are layered over an acoustic guitar to create a breezy and mellow ambience, taking a more pensive and melancholic turn from the hard-hitting nature of the group’s 2018 and 2019 title track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While 2020 has been far from a banner year for K-pop, with the coronavirus pandemic impacting the industry through disbandments, cancelled tours, and shelved comebacks, there have been enough pleasant surprises to keep fans plugged in. BTS’ success these days can make it hard to recall that they were once considered the underdogs of the K-pop industry. The seven-piece group didn’t come from a big management firm, and at the time of their debut, they stood out for not sounding (or looking) overly packaged or produced. Instead, BTS was built by their fans — the 'Army' — who rallied behind the group. This month, the Army’s influence has extended beyond music and into social justice, when the loyal fanbase helped to match the group’s&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-news/bts-black-lives-matter-donation-1011198/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$1 million donation to Black Lives Matter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. That followed a&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-news/white-lives-matter-k-pop-1009581/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;coordinated campaign&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;by K-pop fans just days earlier, when fans came together to drown out the racist #WhiteLivesMatter hashtag on Twitter by spamming it with irreverent memes and fan cams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone who still thought K-pop was a passing fad or a niche subset best left to the 'world music' fringes, the recent rallying of the fandoms (not to mention a host of spirited new releases) has underlined the fact that K-pop is more than just another overseas import — it’s officially a global force.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tejasvi Joshi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This year, K-pop accelerated its expansion into all sorts of mediums — novels,&amp;nbsp;podcasts,&amp;nbsp;documentaries. And yet, for all the satisfaction these new forms brought with them, the music remained the heart of this global phenomenon. Despite the pandemic’s impact on the worldwide recording industry, releases from&amp;nbsp;South Korea&amp;nbsp;saw no decline in quantity or quality, and a slew of artists produced their best work to date. The K-pop songs and albums that defined the year transported us to places we miss most—from&amp;nbsp;the theatre&amp;nbsp;to the jazz bar to the&amp;nbsp;island vacation&amp;nbsp;that lives only in our memories or imaginations. Some prompted nostalgia for things we&amp;nbsp;once took for granted, while others inspired hope for their return. Through these releases, many of our favorite artists experimented with their sounds, all while building deeper connections with an&amp;nbsp;audience&amp;nbsp;they could only interact with from a distance. A talented rookie class experimented with retro sounds, while K-pop's most successful women brazenly defied expectations. Disco completely took over, and noise music prevailed.&amp;nbsp; It was also a year for career breakthroughs and major milestones, as the world's biggest superstars&amp;nbsp;BTS&amp;nbsp;continued to shatter records left and right and break new ground for Korean artists. They're going into the new year with three number-one singles on the&amp;nbsp;Billboard&amp;nbsp;Hot 100, a whole quarantine album, and a Grammy nomination. And while the world got smaller, K-pop went bigger and bolder — sonically and aesthetically.&amp;nbsp; When the global coronavirus pandemic put an end to live touring, the K-pop industry brought the spectacle to our screens with&amp;nbsp;immersive live concert&amp;nbsp;experiences. The music never stopped, not even for a second&amp;nbsp; Whether you're a casual listener, a stan, or someone who's just genuinely curious to see what K-pop is all about,&amp;nbsp;here are 10 songs from the heat of KPOP that made the hard 2020 much easier and eventually took the world by storm. 1) BTS, 'Black Swan' (Map of the Soul: 7) BTS has connected with a worldwide fanbase in large part thanks to the universal-but-still-personal themes of their music, and 'Black Swan' represents one of their most intimate confessions. Dreamy, gloomy hip-hop soundscapes lay the backdrop for the chart-toppers to open up about their darkest fears: that they may one day fall out of love with music. Using the title as a metaphor – to represent both the one-of-a-kind phenomenon they are and the 2010 movie where a ballerina makes the ultimate sacrifice for her art – the superstar septet investigates their underlying anxieties whilst declaring that they won’t let fear win over passion in the end. It’s a full-fledged motion picture-packed into just over three minutes to tell a rare, real-life story of one of the world’s biggest stars 2) TXT, 'Can’t You See Me' (The Dream Chapter: ETERNITY) On 'Can’t You See Me' TXT pulls the dark undercurrent of their youthful whimsy out from under the bed. Crunchy electric guitars and a jaunty whistle add a refreshing contrast to the track’s trap underpinnings, but where it best exposes its murkiness is through the quintet's vocal performances. Alternating between distorted tremolo vocals, hushed whisper-raps, and delicate verses wisping like curls of smoke, the members’ voices lurch between dulcet and disorienting as they reveal the cracks in a friendship. Through unsettling sounds and an idyllic music video that devolves into something frightening, TXT lay bare a horror rarely spoken of: watching a friendship fade before your eyes 3) &amp;nbsp;Twice, “I CAN’T STOP ME” (Eyes Wide Open) Like Dua Lipa and Lady Gaga, Twice were hip to electro basslines this year in “I CAN’T STOP ME.” The girl group bask in the elastic, strobing synth that pulses under the glamorous nu-disco track, and it snaps into formation with the chorus. The song calls for a grand celebration, but they’re too distracted trying not to indulge in their own treacherous desires: “I just can’t go back anymore/ Out of control,” Chaeyoung sings before the rest of the group fully surrender to temptation. Twice fight to keep cool, though it’s hard to notice when they nail such a spotless performance. 4) WOODZ, “BUMP BUMP” (WOOPS!)&amp;nbsp; This was a great year for soloists in K-pop, and no one was more honest with themselves than WOODZ. The push-and-pull of any romance is often the most enticing yet stressful aspect of it all. Amidst airy promises from his lover is the dreary prospect of being left alone, but he approaches this mixed-messaging with a refreshing candour. In our own whirlpools of flirting and call backs, IG-reels and missed messages, “BUMP BUMP” was comfortingly straightforward – with WOODZ relaying what he wants, exactly how he wants it. It was the wrong year to be young and in love in 2020, but at least we had WOODZ to keep us company. 5) Weki Meki, “COOL” (NEW RULES) Weki Meki revamp their approach in 'Cool' by swapping their preppy dance-pop for steely electro. The group’s demeanor is as spartan as the icy beat, and they amplify their bratty voices to assert their flawlessness. Their cockiness peaks in the chorus, which doubles as a taunt and a mantra: &quot;Be hotter/ Beyond the control,” they sing like a drill instructor. “Get out of all the boring rules.” If “Cool” sounds standoffish, then the song succeeds at what it sets out to do. Weki Meki don’t aspire to be a role model for attainable, girl-crush cool but instead point out the gap between you and them. “Cool” is a conceited celebration of self, though sometimes it just feels satisfying to flaunt what you got. 6). GFRIEND, 'MAGO' (回:Walpurgis Night) 'MAGO' distils disco to its very best qualities, shimmering – quite literally – with synths and steady beats, building a heady, atmospheric high. As cohesive as it is musically, its magic lies in how perfectly it fits into the ethos of&amp;nbsp;回:Walpurgis Night.&amp;nbsp;The album&amp;nbsp;is built on the idea of modern witches, at the centre of which are women who exercise the same agency and power of the song’s namesake, and GFRIEND has fun while doing it. Interspersed with images of the girls dancing the night away – not what you’d expect from a concept dealing with the occult – are lyrics that brim with confidence and ambition. Instead of believing in fairy tales and waiting for a Prince Charming, their only love is the images of themselves smiling in the mirror. It’s a cheeky way to poke fun at how society perceives self-assured women since the title itself translates to 'wizard.' In celebrating their limitless ambition, 'MAGO' casts a spell that keeps you coming back for more. 7) SEVENTEEN, 'Left &amp;amp; Right' (Heng:garæ) 'LEFT &amp;amp; RIGHT' is so exuberant that every sound – from doorbell chimes to 808 cowbells, organ synth riffs to full-bodied brass&amp;nbsp; –&amp;nbsp; bursts forth like aural confetti. One could readily claim SEVENTEEN have made their own 'Cupid Shuffle' but they’re aiming for something beyond mere dance instructional: this is a song for transforming every moment into a cause for celebration. In a time when in-person parties aren’t possible, 'LEFT &amp;amp; RIGHT' converts bedrooms into dancefloors. And with exultant shouts and energized rapping, they tell you to keep your chin up, to run down red carpets, to&amp;nbsp;dance. SEVENTEEN act as leaders and hype men here, but the role they fill best is that of life coaches: despite their talk of races and finish lines, they exclaim that “not running is an answer too / who cares what we do.”&amp;nbsp; They grant permission to simply be: a reminder that surviving every day is enough right now. And after all, if you’re not moving forward, why not move &quot;LEFT &amp;amp; RIGHT,”&amp;nbsp;right? They understand something that should be taught in schools around the world: busting your ass should be supplemented with time spent shaking it.&amp;nbsp; 8) Apink, 'Dumhdurum' (LOOK) K-pop tends to be a young person's game – both the industry and its labels regularly shift their priorities to younger artists – but Apink’s 'Dumhdurum' makes an exceptional case for the continuing effort and investment in senior acts. The track opens with a swirling synth-pop hook strong enough to stand as a chorus on its own, before diving into verses and choruses that strike pop gold with just the right amount of catchy repetition and melancholy longing. Apink detail the complexity of remaining calm in the presence of a past love, even when one’s heart's still beating&amp;nbsp;dumhdurum&amp;nbsp;for them – a concept that could be difficult for younger groups to believably pull off. This mature message successfully connected with a large audience, and 'Dumhdurum' became a knockout success in both Korea (topping all local music charts) and the&amp;nbsp;Billboard&amp;nbsp;charts (tying for their longest-running hit on&amp;nbsp;World Digital Song Sales).&amp;nbsp; Nine years into their career, Apink are still more than equipped to bring their A-Game, and that deserves larger recognition all in itself for the industry to pay equal attention to both its senior and developing artists. Matured musical magic awaits. 9). EVERGLOW, 'LA DI DA' (-77.82x-78.29) Thanks to a virtual flattening of borders, musical trends in the States now get reflected in&amp;nbsp;K-pop in real-time. Throughout 2020 – in both the U.S. and South Korea – throwback sounds were ubiquitous. This year’s K-pop magnum opus, EVERGLOW’s 'LA DI DA' mirrored the US’ pop magnum opus, The Weeknd’s 'Blinding Lights' only months after its release. But where The Weeknd’s work is chilling and sinister in its search for love, EVERGLOW’s is a spry kiss-off to all the haters, the bad guys, and the players. A successful pastiche of the 80's that’s crafted by producer Ollipop, 'LA DI DA' blends myriad influences: the&amp;nbsp;layered cheerleader chants of Toni Basil's 'Mickey' the spunky girl power of Cyndi Lauper and the Go-Go's, the&amp;nbsp;na-na-nas&amp;nbsp;of Bananarama, and above all, the shimmering synth-pop sound that permeated the top half of that decade. 'LA DI DA' melds these all together, with K-pop twists: a killing part punctuated by handclaps, a tempo-shifting rap section carried by leader E:U, and an earworm of a melody evocative of early 2010's K-pop – a time when choruses were packed with hooky vocal melodies instead of hollow drops. 10) 'Lovesick Girls', BLACKPINK The arrival of BLACKPINK’s first&amp;nbsp;full-length album — so highly anticipated at the project was simply titled&amp;nbsp;The Album—was one of K-pop’s biggest news events in 2020. While the pre-release singles&amp;nbsp;'How You Like That'&amp;nbsp;and 'Ice Cream' with Selena Gomez charted higher on the Billboard Hot 100, 'Lovesick Girls' is the true gem on the album. The heavy electronic production characteristic of BLACKPINK’s crowd-riling bops remains intact, but it’s stripped back to accentuate sung melodies from the four members. Their voices are layered over an acoustic guitar to create a breezy and mellow ambience, taking a more pensive and melancholic turn from the hard-hitting nature of the group’s 2018 and 2019 title track. While 2020 has been far from a banner year for K-pop, with the coronavirus pandemic impacting the industry through disbandments, cancelled tours, and shelved comebacks, there have been enough pleasant surprises to keep fans plugged in. BTS’ success these days can make it hard to recall that they were once considered the underdogs of the K-pop industry. The seven-piece group didn’t come from a big management firm, and at the time of their debut, they stood out for not sounding (or looking) overly packaged or produced. Instead, BTS was built by their fans — the 'Army' — who rallied behind the group. This month, the Army’s influence has extended beyond music and into social justice, when the loyal fanbase helped to match the group’s&amp;nbsp;$1 million donation to Black Lives Matter. That followed a&amp;nbsp;coordinated campaign&amp;nbsp;by K-pop fans just days earlier, when fans came together to drown out the racist #WhiteLivesMatter hashtag on Twitter by spamming it with irreverent memes and fan cams. For anyone who still thought K-pop was a passing fad or a niche subset best left to the 'world music' fringes, the recent rallying of the fandoms (not to mention a host of spirited new releases) has underlined the fact that K-pop is more than just another overseas import — it’s officially a global force.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
