<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/anshdeep.chadha/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-12-12T07:33:20+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/anshdeep.chadha/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Clout of A New World Order</title>
      <link href="/Clout-of-A-New-World-Order" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Clout of A New World Order" />
      <published>2020-09-25T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Clout-of-A-New-World-Order</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Clout-of-A-New-World-Order">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Social psychologists believe that feelings of frailty and uncertainty associate an individual with a tendency to believe in conspiracies”&lt;/em&gt;, said Karen M Douglas, Professor of Social Psychology at the University of Kent in the United Kingdom. Conceivably, it is true, to have something to lean on is an instinct to regain a sense of control, even if the conspiracy is unrelated to what caused the lack of control in an individual’s life. But what if this is just another conspiracy theory to dwarf all the other conspiracy theories?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you remember watching &lt;em&gt;The Matrix&lt;/em&gt;, you would probably remember Mr Anderson (Keanu Reaves), an otherwise rational person making the leap from prudent paranoia to a not so illogical conspiracy, which led him to the dilemma of choosing between the red and the blue pill. There exists a gnawing feeling of not having control over your life - the dissatisfaction which hinders you from living your life to the fullest. And that is what happened with Adam Weishaupt, founder of The Illuminati.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Born in 1748 in Ingolstadt, Bavaria, Weishaupt was a descendant of Jewish converts to Christianity. Orphaned at a young age, his uncle took care of his education. After completing his studies, Weishaupt became a Professor of canon law at the University of Ingolstadt, got married and started a family. He seemed to have a conventional career until 1784 when the Bavarian state learned about his distinct and provocative ideas. Since childhood, being an avid reader, Weishaupt was convinced that religious ideas were no longer an adequate belief system and hence, he decided to find another form of illumination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May 1, 1776 saw the first Illuminati meet in a forest near Ingolstadt to find the order and there, they established the rules that were to govern the order. The order was a set of scientific ideas and practices that could be applied to radically change the way European states were run. By the end of 1784, Weishaupt’s secret order grew considerably to 3,000 members and by the mid 1780’s, theIlluminati caught the Bavarian government’s attention, which put an end to the secret society. Weishaupt fled and gave up the secret shenanigans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does the Illuminati want?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conspiracy theorists obsessively analyse public events for evidence of Illuminati infiltration in the modern-day world. There have been many events which are said to be proof of the fact that the Illuminati has infiltrated the ranks of prominent leaders, celebrities, clergymen, business tycoons and pharmaceutical companies around the globe, who are affiliated with it and are collectively working to secure their main objective. Back in 2013, when Beyonce performed at superbowl and flashed a pyramid (believed to be the Illuminati’s symbol) with her hands, the internet was lit up with conjectures that she was a member of the secret society. While this might be a baseless conspiracy theory on the grounds of impracticality, it is logical for many who believe they have seen things. Moreover, there exists a condition called Pareidolia, which causes humans to see objective patterns in random stimuli, often attaching humane characteristics to non-living objects, for instance, seeing the face of Jesus in a cream cracker or the date of Apocalypse in Trump’s social security number. Though rationality makes conditions like Pareidolia seem utter nonsense, one can argue that wild-imagination has always fuelled pragmatic creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conspiracy theorists have been warning about a New World Order for decades, going all the way back to the isolationist critics of Franklin Delano Roosevelt. The New World Order or NWO is claimed to be a totalitarian world government led by a secretive power elite conspiring to rule the planet. Though it holds little significance whether any secret society wants to instigate a new world order or a group of power-hungry humans who want to control the world, it nonetheless merits some investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the New World Order?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New World Order is a supposedly autocratic world government (or a Cosmocratic government), which signifies the idea of having ONE central government for every country, institution and state in the world. A Cosmocratic style of government can come to power either through violent world domination or voluntary supranational union. Cosmocracy is a polity made up with recombinant structures that are themselves products of constantly changing, yet permanently unfolding processes. It is a moving target that produces unexpected and highly unstable targets. Though that is one way to look at it, there are numerous ways to perceive this form of world order. Having a single government for everybody will result in absolute harmony among different nations implying that most likely there will be no trade and nuclear wars, rather homogeneity will breed bonhomie between countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single government at the world stage may also ensure that after people become unbound from nature, they will create more anthropocentric forms of organizations, and one among them is democracy. Cosmocracy brings this cycle to a close and leads us back to the essential unity of all things - nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is something like the NWO feasible?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The likeliness of a Cosmocratic government’s rise to power is undoubtedly negligible, given the severe political and socio-economic turmoil it may bring. Any leader who is at the top of the world’s power structure and wields enormous power has a good chance of indulging in malpractices and corruption. The world surely cannot afford to give such power to a small group of individuals, because at the end of the day, they are just humans and have a good chance of becoming corrupt because of the unlimited power the position entails. Also, in the status quo, we live in a world in which people are inherently very proud of their cultural practices, which naturally results in any of their actions (at a macro level) aimed towards making their ‘nation’ great. In such a scenario, if we elect people from a particular country or even if we ensure that the Cosmocratic government is such which consists of equal representation from all parts of the world, there is no way we can eradicate personal bias towards their nations. This is a factor which defeats the purpose of having one government at a global level because if the leaders do not work to cater to the interests of all people across the world, the implementation of this new order will be futile. Moreover, setting up such a government is not pragmatic at all. We have around 200 countries in the world, albeit we cannot have 200 leaders at the world centre, so there has to be some type of filtration system to see from where the leaders are to be elected, which will naturally give the leaders from the first world nations an upper-hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, such a type of government may surely be beneficial in a post-apocalyptic scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the course of history, the most powerful advocates of change have emerged out of destructive circumstances. Citing some examples from history - the nation-state to geopolitics emerged from the Peace of Westphalia, which marked the end of the Thirty Years’ War (1618-48) in Central Europe. The political concept of balance of power gained greater importance with the Congress of Vienna, which emerged in the aftermath of the French Revolution and Napoleonic Wars (1792-1815). Besides, The League of Nations, a noble, yet short-lived experiment in circumscribing power competition, emerged from the First World War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transformation of the world order into a new world order may result from extremely farsighted diplomacy, for which diplomats and policymakers around the world will have to do more than push for incremental improvements within an inadequate system. A possibility entails that if not from diplomacy, the NWO may arise from an apocalypse, though it is terrifying to consider what might have to occur for a new order to emerge in this way, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Anshdeep Singh Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Social psychologists believe that feelings of frailty and uncertainty associate an individual with a tendency to believe in conspiracies”, said Karen M Douglas, Professor of Social Psychology at the University of Kent in the United Kingdom. Conceivably, it is true, to have something to lean on is an instinct to regain a sense of control, even if the conspiracy is unrelated to what caused the lack of control in an individual’s life. But what if this is just another conspiracy theory to dwarf all the other conspiracy theories? If you remember watching The Matrix, you would probably remember Mr Anderson (Keanu Reaves), an otherwise rational person making the leap from prudent paranoia to a not so illogical conspiracy, which led him to the dilemma of choosing between the red and the blue pill. There exists a gnawing feeling of not having control over your life - the dissatisfaction which hinders you from living your life to the fullest. And that is what happened with Adam Weishaupt, founder of The Illuminati. Born in 1748 in Ingolstadt, Bavaria, Weishaupt was a descendant of Jewish converts to Christianity. Orphaned at a young age, his uncle took care of his education. After completing his studies, Weishaupt became a Professor of canon law at the University of Ingolstadt, got married and started a family. He seemed to have a conventional career until 1784 when the Bavarian state learned about his distinct and provocative ideas. Since childhood, being an avid reader, Weishaupt was convinced that religious ideas were no longer an adequate belief system and hence, he decided to find another form of illumination. May 1, 1776 saw the first Illuminati meet in a forest near Ingolstadt to find the order and there, they established the rules that were to govern the order. The order was a set of scientific ideas and practices that could be applied to radically change the way European states were run. By the end of 1784, Weishaupt’s secret order grew considerably to 3,000 members and by the mid 1780’s, theIlluminati caught the Bavarian government’s attention, which put an end to the secret society. Weishaupt fled and gave up the secret shenanigans. What does the Illuminati want?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Role of Caste in Indian Elections</title>
      <link href="/The-Role-of-Caste" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Role of Caste in Indian Elections" />
      <published>2020-09-06T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Role-of-Caste</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Role-of-Caste">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Jaati na Poocho Sadhu ki, Pooch lijiye gyaan’&lt;/em&gt; is a part of a &lt;em&gt;doha&lt;/em&gt; (couplet) by an Indian mystic, poet and saint Kabir Das, which directly translates to – ‘Do not judge a saint by their caste, but ask for their knowledge’. Yet, this &lt;em&gt;doha&lt;/em&gt; is categorically ignored in Indian elections, when the most-asked question during an election is about the candidate’s surname, caste or religion and not what they have to offer or the values they will bring to the table. From political analysts to voters, everyone has this question on their mind, which is why the candidates standing in an election want to play their caste game right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what do you think of, when you first hear the word &lt;em&gt;caste&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be anything, literally. Albeit in the contemporary world, it mostly has a negative connotation attached to itself; being the sole reason for many ills which impair the world’s largest democracy. And, what is the caste system? It is an old social-stratification system that provides a hierarchy of social roles which hold inherent characteristics and, more importantly, are supposed to remain fixed throughout life. Even though Indian politicians didn’t create the mighty caste system, they surely know how to exploit this fault-line, exacerbating the caste animosities to build vote banks. In India, caste (and religion) is something people are very sensitive about and hence political parties face a difficult choice – they try to woo the oppressed castes in order to collect more votes. And in doing so, they antagonize some of the upper castes. Religiosity and tradition expect them to respect the caste boundaries, which is way too tempting to not exploit. A large number of parties draw up their poll strategies on the basis of the constituency’s caste demographic. Messages in the election speeches are tailored to suit the dominant caste of that constituency, and ideological coherence is sacrificed. And that’s why, while making the decision of choosing a candidate to represent them, voters tend to focus on caste and tend to overlook how adequately he/she would be able to represent them and focus on key issues. If a candidate belongs to caste X, his rival belonging to caste Y fields dummy candidates of caste X to divide the opponent’s votes. Caste determines the nature, organisation and working of most political parties, interest groups, and their functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of caste for gaining political popularity is not a new phenomenon and pre-Independence Indian politics also involved the use of caste, in different ways. The British Imperialists used religion as well as caste for political division of the nation. Unfortunately, even after Independence, India could not stop caste from becoming a factor that would influence politics. Even though the scenario is changing in urban India as voters are becoming more educated and aware about important issues, a large part of India still resides in rural areas, where people are not so much aware; for them, caste still plays a very important role in the election processes. Now, what can be the reason that people prefer to choose someone for their representation who belongs to their own caste rather than choosing someone who guarantees good work, amenities and development? It is because of an emotion – the feeling of belongingness. People tend to have an inherent desire to belong and be an important part of something that is greater than themselves; a relationship that is greater than simple acquaintance. This is a strong and inevitable feeling that exists in human nature. And due to this feeling, people have a strange natural trust that someone from their community, from their social group would be the apt representative for them; that he/she would protect them, provide them with opportunities and take care of them because after all, they belong to one big family, right? Sadly, that is not the case. Most of the times, this trust is taken for granted. Many political parties take advantage of these sentiments and fracture the society in such a manner that they gain from the divisions hence created; not to forget how deeply these divisions can damage the society. Politicians appeal to the sentiments of the voters of their respective caste groups and try to mobilize votes on that basis so as to capture and retain political power. Not only this, politicians have also managed to divert the attention of voters from issues relating to jobs, development, education, etc. by portraying caste as the paramount metric they should keep in mind while voting. The biggest harms of caste being involved in India’s electoral processes? There are many – incompetent leadership, ineffective governance, failed public policies, and most importantly, stagnancy. In a country where more than half of its population lives on less than 2$/day, it becomes highly important to make people realise the importance of proper representation and how it can change their lives. However, people are beginning to understand how such superficial factors are good for nothing and only poison the society at large. As is the case with any social evil, this is something which will require a lot of time and effort to be flushed out from the society, but that doesn’t mean it is impossible at all, right?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Anshdeep Singh Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">‘Jaati na Poocho Sadhu ki, Pooch lijiye gyaan’ is a part of a doha (couplet) by an Indian mystic, poet and saint Kabir Das, which directly translates to – ‘Do not judge a saint by their caste, but ask for their knowledge’. Yet, this doha is categorically ignored in Indian elections, when the most-asked question during an election is about the candidate’s surname, caste or religion and not what they have to offer or the values they will bring to the table. From political analysts to voters, everyone has this question on their mind, which is why the candidates standing in an election want to play their caste game right.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Importance of Human Connections, as Told by the Coronavirus</title>
      <link href="/The-Importance-of-Human-Connections" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Importance of Human Connections, as Told by the Coronavirus" />
      <published>2020-08-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Importance-of-Human-Connections</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Importance-of-Human-Connections">&lt;p&gt;Every day, we step out of our homes with ambition in our eyes,  aspirations in our heart  and a desire to change the world as we want to see it (until someone ate a bat somewhere?). At the heart of this colossal myriad of &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; lies something that defines our whole existence – the ability to connect with another human being. Human connection is the exchange of positive energy between people.  The potential of feeling understood and united through human connection is one of the most rewarding elements in life. It has the power to deepen the moment and the bond between people, inspire change and build trust. It has proven to lower anxiety &amp;amp; depression, help us regulate our emotions better and lead to higher self-esteem and empathy, which is actually said to change our immune systems for the better. A research study by Harvard, conducted over a period of 80 years, proves that human connections and healthy relationships are the number one &amp;amp; two drivers of longevity, respectively. Though, our inherent need for a human connection doesn’t mean that every introvert must become a social butterfly. Instead, having a human connection can look different for everyone. Irrespective of what it is for each person, it serves a purpose which nothing else can – make someone feel genuinely happy, and at peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Humans have this dire need to connect. Our brains have learned from brutal evolutionary lessons that social isolation is a death sentence”&lt;/em&gt; said James Coan, a Professor of Psychology at the University of Virginia. The power of touch releases oxytocin, the feel-good hormone. Albeit temporarily, the coronavirus has stripped us all of this supposed elixir for the mind. We are a social species and hence it is not easy to NOT touch each other, as so much of our communication is defined by these touches. While technology seems to be connecting us more than ever, the blue-light emitting screens disconnect us from nature, from ourselves, and from other human beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as people are struggling with an economic recession, they are struggling with an emotional recession too, due to loneliness. Loneliness is not just a feeling in one’s head; it is a biological instinct to seek out other human beings, just like hunger is a signal that sends a person to seek out food. In a situation where we have to stay at home, all by ourselves, such as the one caused by this pandemic, this feeling of loneliness might escalate for many, with limited ways of assuaging it. Even though in some parts of the world, nations have started to open up, the fear of catching the disease will remain in people’s minds, for a long time to come.  The isolation caused by this is proven by science to exact a physical toll on the brain’s circuitry. The confluence of multiple challenges during the pandemic – to health, education, jobs, access to resources has produced a bizarre assemblage of circumstances that increase the risk of depression and Post-traumatic Stress Disorder. In times of disaster, we seek respite in the fact that there is an ending to it which can be accurately predicted. But with this pandemic, we see no end in sight, which makes it more traumatic and compounds the negatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a situation where loneliness exacerbates the negative effects of the pandemic, how do we ensure that we connect in a way which is good for us and also reduces the risk of spreading the disease? In our current situation, the need to reduce physical distances, boost social or relational connections, and not see a rise in loneliness and related mental health problems poses a big problem for us. We need a connection culture, which is rich in relational connection while maintaining a physical distance between individuals. Technology has been a big boon for man since time immemorial, and it is this technology that comes to our rescue here. Be it a conventional video call with friends, a virtual cocktail party, gaming sites where people can compete virtually, watching movies and shows with your friends, or any other thing, we have seen a lot of new inventions throughout the course of this pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how does the coronavirus revolutionise human connection and communication? For the past few decades, humans have focused increasingly on earning money and material belongings, which coupled with rapid technological growth led to the neglect of human relationships, at large. But now that we’re stuck in our homes, the best means of surviving psychologically is to interact with people by whatever means possible. But most importantly, we have begun to understand the value of a human connection, a panacea for all mental health issues, that has no other substitute, in its true essence. &lt;em&gt;‘We realise the true value of anything, only after it is taken away from us’&lt;/em&gt; – asserts a very common saying. Each and every one of us, throughout the course of this pandemic, have felt the importance of a human connection, and it is this realisation in our hearts, which will make us value real connections over materialistic things. And it is this realisation, that finally helps us understand what’s more important: material wealth or mental health?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Anshdeep Singh Chadha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Every day, we step out of our homes with ambition in our eyes, aspirations in our heart and a desire to change the world as we want to see it (until someone ate a bat somewhere?). At the heart of this colossal myriad of everything lies something that defines our whole existence – the ability to connect with another human being. Human connection is the exchange of positive energy between people. The potential of feeling understood and united through human connection is one of the most rewarding elements in life. It has the power to deepen the moment and the bond between people, inspire change and build trust. It has proven to lower anxiety &amp;amp; depression, help us regulate our emotions better and lead to higher self-esteem and empathy, which is actually said to change our immune systems for the better. A research study by Harvard, conducted over a period of 80 years, proves that human connections and healthy relationships are the number one &amp;amp; two drivers of longevity, respectively. Though, our inherent need for a human connection doesn’t mean that every introvert must become a social butterfly. Instead, having a human connection can look different for everyone. Irrespective of what it is for each person, it serves a purpose which nothing else can – make someone feel genuinely happy, and at peace.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
