<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/eeshita.verma/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-11-19T16:51:01+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/eeshita.verma/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Fixating on The Male Gaze</title>
      <link href="/Fixating-on-The-Male-Gaze" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fixating on The Male Gaze" />
      <published>2021-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Fixating-on-The-Male-Gaze</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Fixating-on-The-Male-Gaze">&lt;p&gt;If you’ve seen&lt;em&gt; Emily in Paris&lt;/em&gt;, you must have come across the perfume advertisement shooting scene. For those who haven’t, here’s what the scene looked like: a naked model strolls down a bridge while a bunch of men stare at her. Yes, nothing more, nothing less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, our sensible Emily was disturbed to see that. She points out how this would lead to the objectification of the model through the 'Male Gaze', which is followed by the male client explaining to her how the model is wearing nothing but the perfume, which is meant to empower her, by giving her that sex appeal. Emily then went on to pose a very pertinent question, “&lt;em&gt;Is it ‘sexy or sexist?&lt;/em&gt;’” While the question initiates a separate debate altogether, let us first focus on understanding what ‘The Male Gaze’ is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The media that we consume are presented to us through the Male Gaze, where the female character is projected as an ‘object’ of heterosexual male desire. Positioning the cameras in such a manner that they exclusively follow a woman’s figure in zoom is the perfect example to illustrate my point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The visual presentation of the Male Gaze has three perspectives: (i) that of the man behind the camera, (ii) that of the male characters within the film; and lastly (iii) that of the spectator gazing at the image. Here’s an interesting&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/feministinfo/photos/a.977236942375184/3816179241814259/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/feministinfo/photos/a.977236942375184/3816179241814259/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Facebook post&lt;/a&gt; I stumbled upon a few days ago, which prompted me to take up this article. It perfectly spells out how to identify the ‘Male Gaze’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us visit different forms of media which employ the Male Gaze rather conveniently (and make millions out of it):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiatoday.in/movies/bollywood/story/depicting-women-in-bollywood-222702-2014-10-11&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;India Today&lt;/em&gt; article&lt;/a&gt; decodes how Bollywood has forever tacitly engaged in building female lead archetypes and depicting them as subtle caricatures of the Male Gaze. Depiction of female artists as 'Abla Naari' or &lt;em&gt;'the weaker sex'&lt;/em&gt; (Sana Ranaut from &lt;em&gt;Rajjo&lt;/em&gt;), 'Sanskari Ladki' or &lt;em&gt;'the traditional woman' &lt;/em&gt;(Amrita Rao from &lt;em&gt;Vivah&lt;/em&gt;), the selfless-devoted mother (Nirupa Roy from &lt;em&gt;Deewar&lt;/em&gt;) and the bad girl (Deepika Padukone from &lt;em&gt;Cocktail&lt;/em&gt;) are some examples, to name a few.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, any typical American comedy is incomplete without a slow, zoomed-in, down-up shot of a bimbo, in the backdrop of cheesy music. Not to mention the portrayal of women as supporting sexual objects in films like &lt;em&gt;Transformers&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Spectre&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Grown Ups&lt;/em&gt;, and some of Marvel’s/DC’s films.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that’s not enough, here’s an article that sums up what I’ve tried to convey so far: &lt;a href=&quot;https://talkiewood.com/2014/07/megan-vs-rosie-vs-nicola-who-was-the-best-transformers-girl-2/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Megan vs Rosie vs Nicola: Who was the best Transformers girl?&lt;/a&gt; (Do notice the title and the clipping of the article, especially the angle from which the shots have been taken: there’s more focus on the female’s body than her face).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;Three paragraphs into the Talkiewood article, and here’s what we get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;To determine the ‘winner’ (if we want to call it that), we have decided to rank the three actresses based on five criteria: Memorability, hotness in Transformers, hotness outside Transformers, desirability, and their character function.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why so shallow? Let’s be real; these are Michael Bay films. These actresses didn’t exactly play deep characters&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per research in 2012, women are ingredients for higher profitability, hence some critics argue that as sex sells, sexualising female bodies through the male gaze isn’t as concerned with objectification as it is with aesthetics. Thus the use of the erotic is a significantly above-average technique used by creators in communicating with the market. As a consequence, the marketing strategy worked well for &lt;em&gt;Transformers&lt;/em&gt; as it is the thirteenth highest-grossing film series, with a total of $4.8 billion in sales.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not just limited to movies but references of the Male Gaze can also be observed in music, ranging from men preferring a colour (&lt;em&gt;Chittiyaan Kalaiyaan-'White Wrists &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Brown Rang' or 'Brown Woman'&lt;/em&gt;) to men being okay with any colour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&quot;&lt;em&gt;Ek garam chai ki pyaali ho – May there be a hot cup of tea&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Koi usko pilaane waali ho… – May there be someone who serves me that&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chaahe gori ho ya kaali ho – She may be fair or dark toned&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Seene se lagaane waali ho – She should just embrace me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Raat ko jab main waapas aaoon – when I come at night&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Woh darwaaza khole – She'll open the door&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sajke mere saamne aaye – She'll adorn herself and come in front of me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Saare din ki thakaan mitaaye…– She'll erase all my tiredness of the day&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Voh meri gharwaali ho. – She'll be my wife&quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A point worth considering is that the female character doesn't necessarily have to be hyper-sexualised to be the object of the Male Gaze. As long as she, as the passive party, is able to incite the male protagonist to take action towards his ultimate goal, or act as a prop in the service of the male, we’re catching on to a million bucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not like this is absent from music industry either, listen to &lt;em&gt;Trap Queen, Blurred Lines, Wiggle&lt;/em&gt;, or almost every second rap song. As per a&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ijstr.org/final-print/feb2020/and-I-Swear-Profanity-In-Pop-Music-Lyrics-On-The-American-Billboard-Charts-2009-2018-And-The-Effect-On-Youtube-Popularity.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ijstr.org/final-print/feb2020/and-I-Swear-Profanity-In-Pop-Music-Lyrics-On-The-American-Billboard-Charts-2009-2018-And-The-Effect-On-Youtube-Popularity.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;recent study&lt;/a&gt;, Hip-Hop/Rap is the most popular genre in the US and by far the most explicit genre, containing on average, around 77% profane material, thus making it the most active tool to perpetuate the Male Gaze imagery.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commercialisation of the Male Gaze has increased incessantly over the past few years. Most of the so-called Bollywood item songs are not part of the narratives, however, they are placed for the sole purpose of titillation since the business of cinema is all about visuals. The huge online viewership illustrates how this objectification is used as bait for heterosexual males. Some illustrations of this can be grossing viewerships of songs like &lt;em&gt;Chikni Chameli&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp; (lubricious Chameli), any Honey Singh song or even Drake’s &lt;em&gt;Hotline Bling&lt;/em&gt; or Jason Derulo’s &lt;em&gt;Swalla.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence it is important to question whether such a gaze acts as an ‘audience bait ’- a means to improve visual aesthetics, or as a systemic tool to breed patriarchy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming on to the industry that majorly thrives on the sexualisation of the human body (most commonly females) - PORN. The fact that there is such a massive difference between the type of porn made for male vs female audiences, speaks volumes on how dehumanising and degrading the Male Gaze is. But the truth of the matter remains, the viler and more abusive the content is, the more profits it grosses. Current revenue estimates of the porn industry in The United States range from $9 billion - $97 billion a year, thus making it bigger than not only Netflix but also Hollywood as a whole. In other words, online porn is huge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, their audience is getting younger, which inherently means their market is getting bigger (and more problematic). And the million-dollar profits of porn aren’t just limited to this industry but also to many companies (like&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/porn/business/mainstream.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/porn/business/mainstream.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Yahoo!, AT&amp;amp;T, DirecTV, Marriott and General Motors&lt;/a&gt;) that seemingly have no relation with the porn industry. Emerging technologies such as VR are also getting a boost from this industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The male gaze does not spare the younger generation either, cutting across different configurations. The following section talks about this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comic books often serve as graphic repositories for a heterosexual male’s erotic fantasies. Take, for example, victims waiting to be rescued like Diana (&lt;em&gt;The Phantom&lt;/em&gt;), Lois Lane (&lt;em&gt;Superman&lt;/em&gt;), or DC’s empowered female protagonists like Catwoman and She-Hulk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The power and control that characters such as Wonder Woman seemingly have are, in fact, fake, because it is taken away by male writers at will when they depict their images in extremely provocative poses; bending over, arching their heads back, tossing their hair, fighting in the rain, etc, for absolutely no reason at all. In 2018, the total revenue for the comic book publishing industry was estimated at $865 million and moreover, half of the top 10 grossing films released in the same year were based on comic books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In video games, female characters are portrayed in two broad ways: Either the 'Damsel in Distress' or the 'Ultimate Warrior' (both being the perfect victims pandering to the Male Gaze), of which, the latter is unnecessarily hyper-sexualised (having a scantily clothed body with unrealistic proportions). According to an analysis by &lt;em&gt;Downs and Smith&lt;/em&gt;, playable and plot-relevant characters in the 60 best-selling video games of 2003 were predominantly male. Females who were depicted were frequently sexualised, reaffirming the buttery business of the Male Gaze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lara Croft’s (&lt;em&gt;Tomb Raider&lt;/em&gt; series) original character designer, Toby Gard, also known as ‘The Father of Lara’, acknowledged that he initially set the protagonist as a woman so that the 3D physical models could attract more male players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disney princesses’ movies were supposed to be one pure, uncharted territory but well, look where we are. In case you haven't noticed, the female protagonists in Disney movies are almost always white, cis women in corsets with tiny waists and big bosoms, most of whose stories end when they find love (and hence all their answers) in a man. If you look at it, almost none of these princesses ended up alone, happily. But this drama of the Male Gaze is where the money lies. As of today, Disney’s net worth lies close to $122.18 billion, which they only plan to augment by retelling the same story over and over again.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fitting example would be the recent adaptation of Disney’s 1992 animated film &lt;em&gt;Aladdin&lt;/em&gt;, which grossed over $1 billion worldwide, becoming the ninth-highest-grossing film of 2019. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.studiobinder.com/blog/what-is-the-male-gaze-definition/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;studiobinder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;article explains how Jasmine is nothing but a precious artefact locked away for safekeeping - for her father, a valuable commodity - for the villain, and a prize to be won - for &lt;em&gt;Aladdin&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was recently watching a video on ‘The Male Gaze’ on YouTube, and here’s the first comment I came across:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Women grew up watching successful, ‘beautiful’ women always portrayed through the male gaze and now that we ourselves are playing the role of the camera (selfies/Instagram), we present ourselves through the male gaze!”&lt;/em&gt;, which got me thinking about how we're all victims of the Male Gaze in some way or the other. The Male Gaze has stealthily crept into our minds like a parasite and is benefitting by feeding off our insecurities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hitherto, it wouldn’t take big brains to figure out how deeply problematic the Male Gaze is. Firstly, it normalises perceiving women as deserving of one-way surveillance by heterosexual men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, it negatively alters the way women look at themselves. They start to objectify themselves and inherently feel that their primary purpose is to please heterosexual men, whether it’s by being a doting mother succumbing to gender roles, a girl next door fulfilling your sexual desires, or a submissive subject desperately waiting to feed a man’s ego by being ‘saved’ by him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Male Gaze quietly typecasts women as the ‘aesthetic’ half of humankind and gradually detracts from them other ambitions that men and women have alike. Scarily enough, it even normalises predatory gazes at women and perpetuates rape culture. And it haunts me to think that we all, so ordinarily consume the ‘Male Gaze’ served to us on the platter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin Waters, CEO of Victoria's Secret said after the big announcement of the replacement of its spokespeople, &quot;&lt;em&gt;We're moving from what men want to what women want, from sexy for a few to sexy for all&lt;/em&gt;&quot;. In June 2021, Victoria's Secret ditched its Angels post a successful decade-long partnership after it realised that they were no longer ‘culturally relevant’, a euphemism for ‘morally acceptable’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the first&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriassecret.com/us/thevscollective&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriassecret.com/us/thevscollective&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;seven women selected&lt;/a&gt; to join the ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriassecret.com/us/thevscollective&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;VS Collective&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;’&lt;/em&gt; are professional soccer star Megan Rapinoe, actress Priyanka Chopra Jonas and LGBTQ model and activist Valentina Sampaio. Because hey, that’s what women are, a little bit of everything!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if Victoria’s Secret can identify the problem with the Male Gaze, I assume it’s not a secret anymore, is it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, let's come back to the question Emily raised at the beginning of the article. Who draws the line between sexy and sexist, or say, the line between Cardi B’s sexualisation in her music video and a French model’s sexualisation in an advertisement? Who’s to say one is empowering and the other is not? If women want to make money off the Male Gaze, who are we to stop them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the line is indisputably hard to draw. But here’s the thing, when a video agency sexualises a model while directing a perfume advertisement, the model is regulated, since she is a mere medium to convey what the agency wants to. However, when Cardi B sexualises herself, she does that as an independent artist, to express her own personal message, which is indeed empowering. Moreover, in either case, we end up normalising the unrealistic standards for and expectations from the women community at large, which is yet another ethical debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, as long as sexualisation is the subject’s choice, we, coming from a place of privilege, don’t get to draw the line. But that doesn’t mean it’s okay for men to unwarrantedly keep reducing women to objects of sexual gratification on the pretext of making money. Clearly, we need more women creators to present women through a more realistic, humane perspective, but we're far from that, as of now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also known that money will find its way to the Male Gaze, giving it all the more incentive to creep into every line of business. However, in the meantime, as rational consumers of media, we can actively identify the wrong type of content and consciously choose to not feed its business. After all, they make money off &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The choice is yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until then.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Eeshita Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">If you’ve seen Emily in Paris, you must have come across the perfume advertisement shooting scene. For those who haven’t, here’s what the scene looked like: a naked model strolls down a bridge while a bunch of men stare at her. Yes, nothing more, nothing less. Naturally, our sensible Emily was disturbed to see that. She points out how this would lead to the objectification of the model through the 'Male Gaze', which is followed by the male client explaining to her how the model is wearing nothing but the perfume, which is meant to empower her, by giving her that sex appeal. Emily then went on to pose a very pertinent question, “Is it ‘sexy or sexist?’” While the question initiates a separate debate altogether, let us first focus on understanding what ‘The Male Gaze’ is. The media that we consume are presented to us through the Male Gaze, where the female character is projected as an ‘object’ of heterosexual male desire. Positioning the cameras in such a manner that they exclusively follow a woman’s figure in zoom is the perfect example to illustrate my point. The visual presentation of the Male Gaze has three perspectives: (i) that of the man behind the camera, (ii) that of the male characters within the film; and lastly (iii) that of the spectator gazing at the image. Here’s an interesting Facebook post I stumbled upon a few days ago, which prompted me to take up this article. It perfectly spells out how to identify the ‘Male Gaze’. Let us visit different forms of media which employ the Male Gaze rather conveniently (and make millions out of it): An India Today article decodes how Bollywood has forever tacitly engaged in building female lead archetypes and depicting them as subtle caricatures of the Male Gaze. Depiction of female artists as 'Abla Naari' or 'the weaker sex' (Sana Ranaut from Rajjo), 'Sanskari Ladki' or 'the traditional woman' (Amrita Rao from Vivah), the selfless-devoted mother (Nirupa Roy from Deewar) and the bad girl (Deepika Padukone from Cocktail) are some examples, to name a few.&amp;nbsp; Similarly, any typical American comedy is incomplete without a slow, zoomed-in, down-up shot of a bimbo, in the backdrop of cheesy music. Not to mention the portrayal of women as supporting sexual objects in films like Transformers, Wolf of Wall Street, Spectre, Grown Ups, and some of Marvel’s/DC’s films. If that’s not enough, here’s an article that sums up what I’ve tried to convey so far: Megan vs Rosie vs Nicola: Who was the best Transformers girl? (Do notice the title and the clipping of the article, especially the angle from which the shots have been taken: there’s more focus on the female’s body than her face). &amp;nbsp;Three paragraphs into the Talkiewood article, and here’s what we get: “To determine the ‘winner’ (if we want to call it that), we have decided to rank the three actresses based on five criteria: Memorability, hotness in Transformers, hotness outside Transformers, desirability, and their character function. Why so shallow? Let’s be real; these are Michael Bay films. These actresses didn’t exactly play deep characters.” As per research in 2012, women are ingredients for higher profitability, hence some critics argue that as sex sells, sexualising female bodies through the male gaze isn’t as concerned with objectification as it is with aesthetics. Thus the use of the erotic is a significantly above-average technique used by creators in communicating with the market. As a consequence, the marketing strategy worked well for Transformers as it is the thirteenth highest-grossing film series, with a total of $4.8 billion in sales.&amp;nbsp; This is not just limited to movies but references of the Male Gaze can also be observed in music, ranging from men preferring a colour (Chittiyaan Kalaiyaan-'White Wrists and Brown Rang' or 'Brown Woman') to men being okay with any colour. &amp;nbsp;&quot;Ek garam chai ki pyaali ho – May there be a hot cup of tea Koi usko pilaane waali ho… – May there be someone who serves me that Chaahe gori ho ya kaali ho – She may be fair or dark toned Seene se lagaane waali ho – She should just embrace me Raat ko jab main waapas aaoon – when I come at night Woh darwaaza khole – She'll open the door&amp;nbsp; Sajke mere saamne aaye – She'll adorn herself and come in front of me Saare din ki thakaan mitaaye…– She'll erase all my tiredness of the day Voh meri gharwaali ho. – She'll be my wife&quot; A point worth considering is that the female character doesn't necessarily have to be hyper-sexualised to be the object of the Male Gaze. As long as she, as the passive party, is able to incite the male protagonist to take action towards his ultimate goal, or act as a prop in the service of the male, we’re catching on to a million bucks. It's not like this is absent from music industry either, listen to Trap Queen, Blurred Lines, Wiggle, or almost every second rap song. As per a recent study, Hip-Hop/Rap is the most popular genre in the US and by far the most explicit genre, containing on average, around 77% profane material, thus making it the most active tool to perpetuate the Male Gaze imagery.&amp;nbsp; The commercialisation of the Male Gaze has increased incessantly over the past few years. Most of the so-called Bollywood item songs are not part of the narratives, however, they are placed for the sole purpose of titillation since the business of cinema is all about visuals. The huge online viewership illustrates how this objectification is used as bait for heterosexual males. Some illustrations of this can be grossing viewerships of songs like Chikni Chameli&amp;nbsp; (lubricious Chameli), any Honey Singh song or even Drake’s Hotline Bling or Jason Derulo’s Swalla. Hence it is important to question whether such a gaze acts as an ‘audience bait ’- a means to improve visual aesthetics, or as a systemic tool to breed patriarchy? Coming on to the industry that majorly thrives on the sexualisation of the human body (most commonly females) - PORN. The fact that there is such a massive difference between the type of porn made for male vs female audiences, speaks volumes on how dehumanising and degrading the Male Gaze is. But the truth of the matter remains, the viler and more abusive the content is, the more profits it grosses. Current revenue estimates of the porn industry in The United States range from $9 billion - $97 billion a year, thus making it bigger than not only Netflix but also Hollywood as a whole. In other words, online porn is huge. Furthermore, their audience is getting younger, which inherently means their market is getting bigger (and more problematic). And the million-dollar profits of porn aren’t just limited to this industry but also to many companies (like Yahoo!, AT&amp;amp;T, DirecTV, Marriott and General Motors) that seemingly have no relation with the porn industry. Emerging technologies such as VR are also getting a boost from this industry. The male gaze does not spare the younger generation either, cutting across different configurations. The following section talks about this point. Comic books often serve as graphic repositories for a heterosexual male’s erotic fantasies. Take, for example, victims waiting to be rescued like Diana (The Phantom), Lois Lane (Superman), or DC’s empowered female protagonists like Catwoman and She-Hulk. The power and control that characters such as Wonder Woman seemingly have are, in fact, fake, because it is taken away by male writers at will when they depict their images in extremely provocative poses; bending over, arching their heads back, tossing their hair, fighting in the rain, etc, for absolutely no reason at all. In 2018, the total revenue for the comic book publishing industry was estimated at $865 million and moreover, half of the top 10 grossing films released in the same year were based on comic books. In video games, female characters are portrayed in two broad ways: Either the 'Damsel in Distress' or the 'Ultimate Warrior' (both being the perfect victims pandering to the Male Gaze), of which, the latter is unnecessarily hyper-sexualised (having a scantily clothed body with unrealistic proportions). According to an analysis by Downs and Smith, playable and plot-relevant characters in the 60 best-selling video games of 2003 were predominantly male. Females who were depicted were frequently sexualised, reaffirming the buttery business of the Male Gaze. Lara Croft’s (Tomb Raider series) original character designer, Toby Gard, also known as ‘The Father of Lara’, acknowledged that he initially set the protagonist as a woman so that the 3D physical models could attract more male players. Disney princesses’ movies were supposed to be one pure, uncharted territory but well, look where we are. In case you haven't noticed, the female protagonists in Disney movies are almost always white, cis women in corsets with tiny waists and big bosoms, most of whose stories end when they find love (and hence all their answers) in a man. If you look at it, almost none of these princesses ended up alone, happily. But this drama of the Male Gaze is where the money lies. As of today, Disney’s net worth lies close to $122.18 billion, which they only plan to augment by retelling the same story over and over again.&amp;nbsp; A fitting example would be the recent adaptation of Disney’s 1992 animated film Aladdin, which grossed over $1 billion worldwide, becoming the ninth-highest-grossing film of 2019. A studiobinder article explains how Jasmine is nothing but a precious artefact locked away for safekeeping - for her father, a valuable commodity - for the villain, and a prize to be won - for Aladdin.&amp;nbsp; I was recently watching a video on ‘The Male Gaze’ on YouTube, and here’s the first comment I came across: “Women grew up watching successful, ‘beautiful’ women always portrayed through the male gaze and now that we ourselves are playing the role of the camera (selfies/Instagram), we present ourselves through the male gaze!”, which got me thinking about how we're all victims of the Male Gaze in some way or the other. The Male Gaze has stealthily crept into our minds like a parasite and is benefitting by feeding off our insecurities. Hitherto, it wouldn’t take big brains to figure out how deeply problematic the Male Gaze is. Firstly, it normalises perceiving women as deserving of one-way surveillance by heterosexual men. Secondly, it negatively alters the way women look at themselves. They start to objectify themselves and inherently feel that their primary purpose is to please heterosexual men, whether it’s by being a doting mother succumbing to gender roles, a girl next door fulfilling your sexual desires, or a submissive subject desperately waiting to feed a man’s ego by being ‘saved’ by him. The Male Gaze quietly typecasts women as the ‘aesthetic’ half of humankind and gradually detracts from them other ambitions that men and women have alike. Scarily enough, it even normalises predatory gazes at women and perpetuates rape culture. And it haunts me to think that we all, so ordinarily consume the ‘Male Gaze’ served to us on the platter. Martin Waters, CEO of Victoria's Secret said after the big announcement of the replacement of its spokespeople, &quot;We're moving from what men want to what women want, from sexy for a few to sexy for all&quot;. In June 2021, Victoria's Secret ditched its Angels post a successful decade-long partnership after it realised that they were no longer ‘culturally relevant’, a euphemism for ‘morally acceptable’. Among the first seven women selected to join the ‘VS Collective’ are professional soccer star Megan Rapinoe, actress Priyanka Chopra Jonas and LGBTQ model and activist Valentina Sampaio. Because hey, that’s what women are, a little bit of everything! Now if Victoria’s Secret can identify the problem with the Male Gaze, I assume it’s not a secret anymore, is it? Finally, let's come back to the question Emily raised at the beginning of the article. Who draws the line between sexy and sexist, or say, the line between Cardi B’s sexualisation in her music video and a French model’s sexualisation in an advertisement? Who’s to say one is empowering and the other is not? If women want to make money off the Male Gaze, who are we to stop them? Well, the line is indisputably hard to draw. But here’s the thing, when a video agency sexualises a model while directing a perfume advertisement, the model is regulated, since she is a mere medium to convey what the agency wants to. However, when Cardi B sexualises herself, she does that as an independent artist, to express her own personal message, which is indeed empowering. Moreover, in either case, we end up normalising the unrealistic standards for and expectations from the women community at large, which is yet another ethical debate. Still, as long as sexualisation is the subject’s choice, we, coming from a place of privilege, don’t get to draw the line. But that doesn’t mean it’s okay for men to unwarrantedly keep reducing women to objects of sexual gratification on the pretext of making money. Clearly, we need more women creators to present women through a more realistic, humane perspective, but we're far from that, as of now. It is also known that money will find its way to the Male Gaze, giving it all the more incentive to creep into every line of business. However, in the meantime, as rational consumers of media, we can actively identify the wrong type of content and consciously choose to not feed its business. After all, they make money off your attention. The choice is yours. Until then.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Have We Judged the Abrogation Too Quickly?</title>
      <link href="/Have-We-Judged-the-Abrogation-Too-Quickly" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Have We Judged the Abrogation Too Quickly?" />
      <published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Have-We-Judged-the-Abrogation-Too-Quickly</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Have-We-Judged-the-Abrogation-Too-Quickly">&lt;p&gt;On August 5, 2019, India awoke to a bewildering, unanticipated change of heart. The Modi government abrogated Articles 370 and 35A of the Indian Constitution, which rendered the Constitution of Jammu and Kashmir ineffectual, revoked the state’s special status, and bifurcated it into two union territories: J&amp;amp;K and Ladakh, besides many other blatant measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I proceed, I’d like to clarify that I am not here to criticise what the government did, nor am I here to defend the Right against attacks by the Left, I am simply here to present the Right’s case rightfully, which yet remains undone and is long overdue.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move comes off as unconstitutional to many, and in all fairness, it was. Prime Minister Narendra Modi's modern solution to the Kashmir problem was to turn the tables at a time when there was no state government to defy it. Critics of the move also reason that one cannot simply change the jurisprudence that governs a people, without them having so much as an inkling of the move. However, deep down, we would all concur, there is no other way in which this could have been enforced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might argue that indeed, there is no other way this could have been enforced because the move itself is groundless and insensitive, since it deprives the Kashmiris of their well-deserved rights. But I would like to point out that whatever has been taken away was never a right, but a privilege, for the humble reason that if it were a right, it could simply not be taken away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LPG, 1999 and the Abrogation, 2019: a Parallel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To strengthen my case, I’d like to draw a parallel from the archives of our very own history, the New Economic Policy of 1991.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NEP, to sum up in three words, introduced Liberalisation-Privatisation-Globalisation, contracted to LPG. Before LPG, domestic producers enjoyed what can be described as an era of protectionism, a euphemism for ‘privilege’. The affairs of the outside world did not concern them whatsoever, neither did they deem it important to step out of their comfort zone, and justifiably so. Mind you, when I use the word ‘privilege’, in no way do I try to imply that it has a negative connotation. Whatever growth we have come to witness over the past years, can be easily credited to protectionism, which stood sentinel for years, providing the necessary time and space for the Indian producers to stand, fall and get back up again. However, every wave of privilege offered comes with a period of validity, beyond which the privilege has a negative impact. And so came the reversal of protectionism in 1991.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though a sensible move, the reversal was widely resisted by domestic producers, and with good reason, because no one would ever willingly forgo their privilege. As apprehended, it also brought in a wave of destruction, a creative one nonetheless. However, in hindsight, Indians embrace the move, despite its disruptive nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I submit that the abrogation of Article 370 is much like the NEP: a reform that was long overdue and will benefit India in the long run&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I admit that it is not my domain to decide what is and what is not right for the Kashmiris, I would like to highlight a rather obvious proposition - the Kashmiris would dissent even if the move is right, considering it is their privilege in question.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, given the history and trauma of Kashmir, it undoubtedly deserved the privileges conferred upon the state (a separate constitution, a separate flag, permanent residency, bar on foreign ownership of property in J&amp;amp;K among other benefits, now revoked). But what is worth noting here is that Article 370 was originally supposed to be a ‘temporary provision’. As much as we might like to ignore it, one cannot live in denial forever, and keep stalling the decision to open up Kashmir’s economy, given that the privilege period has long lost its validity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Good Part&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming back to LPG, since 1991, the Budget of the Union government has grown 19 times in size, the economy has grown nine times, and your income, five times. Empirically, poverty has descended, standards of living have shot up, as have capital flows and foreign investment. Visibly, the country is more integrated with the world economy, which has led to increased opportunities for all. In the words of the former Indian Finance Minister the Late Arun Jaitley,&lt;em&gt; “What decades of state hand-outs could not accomplish for the backward communities, economic opportunities have. Caste barriers are eroding and today we can speak of Dalit entrepreneurship in a way that would have been unimaginable decades ago and in a way that would have pleased Dr. Ambedkar. The geographical spread of opportunities and the increase in migration have contributed to nation-building.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now before I dwell upon the welfare the abrogation pours in, I’d like to elucidate how Articles 370 and 35A inadvertently entrenched Kashmir’s liberty and growth prospects. The former entailed rules defining permanent residency in the state of Jammu and Kashmir while the latter conferred certain privileges to the class so defined. A point worth noting here is that this residency does not necessarily cover all those who have thrived in J&amp;amp;K for the required period. To quote an example, West Pakistan Refugees, who came to India in 1947, could not enjoy the basic rights and privileges as enjoyed by the permanent residents, which is to say, being Indian citizens, they could vote in the Parliamentary elections, but being non-permanent residents of J&amp;amp;K, they could not vote in the local body elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Employment in public offices, admission in government educational institutes, access to government scholarship, rights of acquisition of property in J&amp;amp;K are certain privileges offered to and reserved exclusively for permanent citizens. After all these years, whether these privileges still hold significance or not is an issue open to deliberation, just like the incessant debate on whether Indians lower castes deserve quotas in government jobs and institutions. However, coming back to my first point, it is certain that these are not privileges one will conveniently dispense with. Besides, just like J&amp;amp;K has a stake in the rest of India, the rest of India deserves one in J&amp;amp;K too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t come as a surprise that these privileges act as an impediment in letting opportunities flow into J&amp;amp;K. The healthcare, education, and industrial sector reforms have stagnated, since there is no impetus driving the private sector to invest in the state, and it’s only natural, given the bar on land acquisition for non-residents. There is no competition-driven growth since children of non-state subjects cannot get admission to state colleges and skilled human capital would not permanently migrate to the state. Among all the states, Jammu &amp;amp; Kashmir had the highest monthly average unemployment rate of 15% between January 2016 and July 2019. New investments declined by over 19 per cent in 2018-19 compared to the previous financial year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By rescinding the privileges offered to the chosen ones, the move will overturn the above-mentioned deterrents and bring peace and development, at least in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Deciding Trials&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is completely valid and healthy to dissent and be concerned over something that renders your future uncertain, because the move is but a gamble. However, I don’t find it justified to judge something that may take decades to bring in the required change, within one or two years. This brings me to my last point - the issue of expecting concrete results to kick-in immediately. It has been less than two years since the revocation was effected, and while everyone is talking about how the tourism sector has been crippled and how the unemployment rate has been rising, what happened to patience? Everything takes time. And while there are contradictory sets of statistics available for both sides of the coin, I won't cite them, simply because it's too soon to judge.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, COVID-19 has been giving us company for the major part of the observation period. Yes, J&amp;amp;K’s statistics are saddening, but so are those of other states, some even worse off, and it is largely attributable to the pandemic. It all boils down to relativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cons and Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be it privileges offered and enjoyed, or the reluctance to give them up; the unpredictable nature of the action, or the uncertainty regarding the tenure one must wait out before it’s showtime - we have faced it all before, and we’re facing it again. Clearly, the Modi move is so much more than LPG, but in essence, both matters intend to place a frog out of its well, into the ocean, simply because it deserves to see and participate in what goes on beyond the wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all objectivity, it would be unfair on my part, to not point out the defects of the move: it is far from perfect with regard to its unconstitutional implementation, clampdown on dissent (communication blackout, unforeseen curfew, internet shutdown), and most importantly, the reduction of the state of J&amp;amp;K to a union territory. However, while the move is far too complex to be labelled ‘right’ or ‘wrong’, it certainly deserves a moment of objective evaluation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I’d like to ask you the same question I posed in the title, and while I don’t expect answers right away, I’d like you to think about it. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Eeshita Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On August 5, 2019, India awoke to a bewildering, unanticipated change of heart. The Modi government abrogated Articles 370 and 35A of the Indian Constitution, which rendered the Constitution of Jammu and Kashmir ineffectual, revoked the state’s special status, and bifurcated it into two union territories: J&amp;amp;K and Ladakh, besides many other blatant measures. Before I proceed, I’d like to clarify that I am not here to criticise what the government did, nor am I here to defend the Right against attacks by the Left, I am simply here to present the Right’s case rightfully, which yet remains undone and is long overdue.&amp;nbsp; The move comes off as unconstitutional to many, and in all fairness, it was. Prime Minister Narendra Modi's modern solution to the Kashmir problem was to turn the tables at a time when there was no state government to defy it. Critics of the move also reason that one cannot simply change the jurisprudence that governs a people, without them having so much as an inkling of the move. However, deep down, we would all concur, there is no other way in which this could have been enforced. One might argue that indeed, there is no other way this could have been enforced because the move itself is groundless and insensitive, since it deprives the Kashmiris of their well-deserved rights. But I would like to point out that whatever has been taken away was never a right, but a privilege, for the humble reason that if it were a right, it could simply not be taken away. LPG, 1999 and the Abrogation, 2019: a Parallel To strengthen my case, I’d like to draw a parallel from the archives of our very own history, the New Economic Policy of 1991.&amp;nbsp; The NEP, to sum up in three words, introduced Liberalisation-Privatisation-Globalisation, contracted to LPG. Before LPG, domestic producers enjoyed what can be described as an era of protectionism, a euphemism for ‘privilege’. The affairs of the outside world did not concern them whatsoever, neither did they deem it important to step out of their comfort zone, and justifiably so. Mind you, when I use the word ‘privilege’, in no way do I try to imply that it has a negative connotation. Whatever growth we have come to witness over the past years, can be easily credited to protectionism, which stood sentinel for years, providing the necessary time and space for the Indian producers to stand, fall and get back up again. However, every wave of privilege offered comes with a period of validity, beyond which the privilege has a negative impact. And so came the reversal of protectionism in 1991.&amp;nbsp; Though a sensible move, the reversal was widely resisted by domestic producers, and with good reason, because no one would ever willingly forgo their privilege. As apprehended, it also brought in a wave of destruction, a creative one nonetheless. However, in hindsight, Indians embrace the move, despite its disruptive nature. I submit that the abrogation of Article 370 is much like the NEP: a reform that was long overdue and will benefit India in the long run While I admit that it is not my domain to decide what is and what is not right for the Kashmiris, I would like to highlight a rather obvious proposition - the Kashmiris would dissent even if the move is right, considering it is their privilege in question.&amp;nbsp; Secondly, given the history and trauma of Kashmir, it undoubtedly deserved the privileges conferred upon the state (a separate constitution, a separate flag, permanent residency, bar on foreign ownership of property in J&amp;amp;K among other benefits, now revoked). But what is worth noting here is that Article 370 was originally supposed to be a ‘temporary provision’. As much as we might like to ignore it, one cannot live in denial forever, and keep stalling the decision to open up Kashmir’s economy, given that the privilege period has long lost its validity. The Good Part Coming back to LPG, since 1991, the Budget of the Union government has grown 19 times in size, the economy has grown nine times, and your income, five times. Empirically, poverty has descended, standards of living have shot up, as have capital flows and foreign investment. Visibly, the country is more integrated with the world economy, which has led to increased opportunities for all. In the words of the former Indian Finance Minister the Late Arun Jaitley, “What decades of state hand-outs could not accomplish for the backward communities, economic opportunities have. Caste barriers are eroding and today we can speak of Dalit entrepreneurship in a way that would have been unimaginable decades ago and in a way that would have pleased Dr. Ambedkar. The geographical spread of opportunities and the increase in migration have contributed to nation-building.” Now before I dwell upon the welfare the abrogation pours in, I’d like to elucidate how Articles 370 and 35A inadvertently entrenched Kashmir’s liberty and growth prospects. The former entailed rules defining permanent residency in the state of Jammu and Kashmir while the latter conferred certain privileges to the class so defined. A point worth noting here is that this residency does not necessarily cover all those who have thrived in J&amp;amp;K for the required period. To quote an example, West Pakistan Refugees, who came to India in 1947, could not enjoy the basic rights and privileges as enjoyed by the permanent residents, which is to say, being Indian citizens, they could vote in the Parliamentary elections, but being non-permanent residents of J&amp;amp;K, they could not vote in the local body elections. Employment in public offices, admission in government educational institutes, access to government scholarship, rights of acquisition of property in J&amp;amp;K are certain privileges offered to and reserved exclusively for permanent citizens. After all these years, whether these privileges still hold significance or not is an issue open to deliberation, just like the incessant debate on whether Indians lower castes deserve quotas in government jobs and institutions. However, coming back to my first point, it is certain that these are not privileges one will conveniently dispense with. Besides, just like J&amp;amp;K has a stake in the rest of India, the rest of India deserves one in J&amp;amp;K too. It doesn’t come as a surprise that these privileges act as an impediment in letting opportunities flow into J&amp;amp;K. The healthcare, education, and industrial sector reforms have stagnated, since there is no impetus driving the private sector to invest in the state, and it’s only natural, given the bar on land acquisition for non-residents. There is no competition-driven growth since children of non-state subjects cannot get admission to state colleges and skilled human capital would not permanently migrate to the state. Among all the states, Jammu &amp;amp; Kashmir had the highest monthly average unemployment rate of 15% between January 2016 and July 2019. New investments declined by over 19 per cent in 2018-19 compared to the previous financial year. By rescinding the privileges offered to the chosen ones, the move will overturn the above-mentioned deterrents and bring peace and development, at least in the long run. The Deciding Trials It is completely valid and healthy to dissent and be concerned over something that renders your future uncertain, because the move is but a gamble. However, I don’t find it justified to judge something that may take decades to bring in the required change, within one or two years. This brings me to my last point - the issue of expecting concrete results to kick-in immediately. It has been less than two years since the revocation was effected, and while everyone is talking about how the tourism sector has been crippled and how the unemployment rate has been rising, what happened to patience? Everything takes time. And while there are contradictory sets of statistics available for both sides of the coin, I won't cite them, simply because it's too soon to judge.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, COVID-19 has been giving us company for the major part of the observation period. Yes, J&amp;amp;K’s statistics are saddening, but so are those of other states, some even worse off, and it is largely attributable to the pandemic. It all boils down to relativity. Cons and Conclusions Be it privileges offered and enjoyed, or the reluctance to give them up; the unpredictable nature of the action, or the uncertainty regarding the tenure one must wait out before it’s showtime - we have faced it all before, and we’re facing it again. Clearly, the Modi move is so much more than LPG, but in essence, both matters intend to place a frog out of its well, into the ocean, simply because it deserves to see and participate in what goes on beyond the wall. In all objectivity, it would be unfair on my part, to not point out the defects of the move: it is far from perfect with regard to its unconstitutional implementation, clampdown on dissent (communication blackout, unforeseen curfew, internet shutdown), and most importantly, the reduction of the state of J&amp;amp;K to a union territory. However, while the move is far too complex to be labelled ‘right’ or ‘wrong’, it certainly deserves a moment of objective evaluation.&amp;nbsp; In the end, I’d like to ask you the same question I posed in the title, and while I don’t expect answers right away, I’d like you to think about it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Are the Stock Markets Crazier than They Should Be?</title>
      <link href="/Are-the-Stock-Markets-Crazier-than-They-Should-Be" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are the Stock Markets Crazier than They Should Be?" />
      <published>2021-07-23T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-07-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Are-the-Stock-Markets-Crazier-than-They-Should-Be</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Are-the-Stock-Markets-Crazier-than-They-Should-Be">&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt that sudden chill that runs down your spine when you bite on that ice cream too hard? That, to the degree of 100, is the sensitivity of today’s internet, and well, more specifically, the stock market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realised the stock market's reactivity to news when I first participated in a mock stock, and thought “&lt;em&gt;So it’s just an exaggerated version of how the stock market reacts to news&lt;/em&gt;”. Turns out, it’s not so exaggerated. Because if Elon Musk tweeting out a meme can sway the market, then anything can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article deals with how sensitive the stock market can be to seemingly useless pieces of information and how that may have amplified due to COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Has the Stock Market become a Joke?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stock market is Elon Musk’s world and we’re just trading in it. Wonder why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On July 1, 2021, Musk tweeted, “&lt;em&gt;Baby Doge, doo, doo, doo, doo, doo.. Baby Doge, doo, doo, doo, doo, doo.. Baby Doge&lt;/em&gt;”&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t scratch your heads trying to find a deeper meaning, for it’s exactly as it sounds. After the tweet, Dogecoin surged 3%, while more interestingly, Bitcoin, the largest cryptocurrency in the world, plunged nearly 3%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developers Mr Markus and Jackson Palmer co-created Dogecoin as a joke in 2013. It is mainly based on the Doge meme that swept the Internet in the same year (and has now created a monopoly in WhatsApp sticker collections).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Musk once expressed his interest in the coin, saying, &quot;&lt;em&gt;Doge barking at the stars&lt;/em&gt;.&quot; and the price of Dogecoin soared by 20%. It’s called the ‘&lt;em&gt;Musk Effect&lt;/em&gt;’. If you scroll through Elon Musk’s Twitter account, you’ll find an array of Doge memes that have gone on to move markets. The meme cryptocurrency once even became the fourth-largest cryptocurrency by market capitalisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An episode that shook the stock market- The GameStop Incident!! One day, retail investors on Reddit decided that (i) the short sellers were evil, (ii) punishing them would cause the stock to sky-rocket, and (iii) this would all be pretty funny. So the stock peaked at $483.00, which is 185.7% above the current share price. And mind you, the current price itself is grossly overvalued. Honestly, why wouldn’t it be? After all, GameStop is a meme stock (a stock that sees dramatic price increases, mostly fueled by people on social media, primarily Reddit, Twitter and Tik Tok).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let’s delve into practicalities. It’s humanly impossible to follow the news religiously, so how exactly does the impact intensify?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter HFT. High-frequency trading (HFT) is an automated trading platform that large investment and trading parties (like hedge funds, investment banks, and institutional investors) employ. It uses powerful computers to analyse the markets and spot emerging trends in a fraction of a second.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By being able to recognise such shifts, the trading systems send hundreds of baskets of stocks out into the marketplace at bid-ask spreads that are advantageous to the traders. For context, a bid-ask spread is the difference between the highest price a buyer is willing to pay for an asset and the lowest price that a seller is willing to accept for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how do these computer programmes do this? According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://business.time.com/2013/04/24/how-does-one-fake-tweet-cause-a-stock-market-crash/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Irene Aldrige&lt;/a&gt;, Managing Partner at ABLE Alpha Trading, high-frequency traders compile a list of news sources like Stock Exchange Commission filings, business publications, and social media platforms like Twitter, and tell their computer programmes to skim through those sources looking for specific keywords (like ‘bankruptcy’ or ‘merger’) that signal something about the market.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So can a fake tweet cause a stock market crash? Potentially, yes. But these bots are programmed to filter through so much information that in the grand scheme of things, these methods prove more advantageous than inaccurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But my point is, &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; is moving?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meme stocks.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; is moving them?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Memes (or computer systems)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these incidents make one question if we’re all just pretending that investing and trading is as calculative and artful as it seems? Because if Elon Musk’s tweets or some stranger Redditors can randomly decide for me the value of my investments, then why the hell am I wasting my time on Fundamental and Technical Analyses?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Pandemic and the Instability of the Stock Market&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all know about Cristiano Ronaldo’s Coca Cola fiasco. For those who don’t: he arbitrarily removed two bottles of Coca-Cola during a press conference at the Euro 2020, while asking for them to be replaced by water. The video gained a lot of traction. It inspired at least five more such moments across the world. Overall, it was pretty funny.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you see, it wasn’t funny for Coca Cola, because in the aftermath, the giant suffered a staggering loss of $4 billion. The story seems pretty nonsensical to me, but it sure makes me wonder if things would have panned out the same way if it weren’t for COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is research that asserts the stock market has been more sensitive to the news during the COVID pandemic than otherwise. Just like us, humans! For instance, the findings of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12559-021-09819-8#Sec12&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;comparative study&lt;/a&gt; confirm that the drop in stock prices during the COVID-19 era was more dramatic than the Swine Flu period, because of the presence of more speculation, rumours and negative news.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another plausible reason for this could be that our existence has been shifting online minute-by-minute, during the pandemic. What’s virtual, seems real. So any piece of news online is more impactful than it would have been in normalcy. In other words, it’s harder to filter out what news would have had a bearing on your investing decisions pre-COVID and what news wouldn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, it’s no secret that investors detest uncertainty. The pandemic has tossed onto us a record-breaking, all-time high of unpredictability, and that had to materialise as overly-sensitive stock market indices and traders, some time or the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these are just hypotheses, only time can tell us if we will ever recover from this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why is Sensitivity Important?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By now it’s clear that it is important to acknowledge that sometimes, the stock market can be a little crazy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But still, sensitivity is important. If people want to invest mindlessly, let them exercise their choice too. It sends a signal to the government and monopolists, that if the people are wronged, in the way of faulty policies or immoral corporate behaviour, consequences will follow, and the economy will tumble. And if every once in a while, we happen to observe notorious stock market activity, prices will readjust and bounce back to their intrinsic value.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conclude, sensitive stock markets are like a well-functioning democracy. Which is to say, as long as the common people in it have the power to bring the entire system down, we’re doing okay. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Eeshita Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Have you ever felt that sudden chill that runs down your spine when you bite on that ice cream too hard? That, to the degree of 100, is the sensitivity of today’s internet, and well, more specifically, the stock market. I realised the stock market's reactivity to news when I first participated in a mock stock, and thought “So it’s just an exaggerated version of how the stock market reacts to news”. Turns out, it’s not so exaggerated. Because if Elon Musk tweeting out a meme can sway the market, then anything can. This article deals with how sensitive the stock market can be to seemingly useless pieces of information and how that may have amplified due to COVID-19. Has the Stock Market become a Joke? The stock market is Elon Musk’s world and we’re just trading in it. Wonder why? On July 1, 2021, Musk tweeted, “Baby Doge, doo, doo, doo, doo, doo.. Baby Doge, doo, doo, doo, doo, doo.. Baby Doge”&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Don’t scratch your heads trying to find a deeper meaning, for it’s exactly as it sounds. After the tweet, Dogecoin surged 3%, while more interestingly, Bitcoin, the largest cryptocurrency in the world, plunged nearly 3%. Developers Mr Markus and Jackson Palmer co-created Dogecoin as a joke in 2013. It is mainly based on the Doge meme that swept the Internet in the same year (and has now created a monopoly in WhatsApp sticker collections). Musk once expressed his interest in the coin, saying, &quot;Doge barking at the stars.&quot; and the price of Dogecoin soared by 20%. It’s called the ‘Musk Effect’. If you scroll through Elon Musk’s Twitter account, you’ll find an array of Doge memes that have gone on to move markets. The meme cryptocurrency once even became the fourth-largest cryptocurrency by market capitalisation. An episode that shook the stock market- The GameStop Incident!! One day, retail investors on Reddit decided that (i) the short sellers were evil, (ii) punishing them would cause the stock to sky-rocket, and (iii) this would all be pretty funny. So the stock peaked at $483.00, which is 185.7% above the current share price. And mind you, the current price itself is grossly overvalued. Honestly, why wouldn’t it be? After all, GameStop is a meme stock (a stock that sees dramatic price increases, mostly fueled by people on social media, primarily Reddit, Twitter and Tik Tok). Now let’s delve into practicalities. It’s humanly impossible to follow the news religiously, so how exactly does the impact intensify? Enter HFT. High-frequency trading (HFT) is an automated trading platform that large investment and trading parties (like hedge funds, investment banks, and institutional investors) employ. It uses powerful computers to analyse the markets and spot emerging trends in a fraction of a second.&amp;nbsp; By being able to recognise such shifts, the trading systems send hundreds of baskets of stocks out into the marketplace at bid-ask spreads that are advantageous to the traders. For context, a bid-ask spread is the difference between the highest price a buyer is willing to pay for an asset and the lowest price that a seller is willing to accept for it. But how do these computer programmes do this? According to Irene Aldrige, Managing Partner at ABLE Alpha Trading, high-frequency traders compile a list of news sources like Stock Exchange Commission filings, business publications, and social media platforms like Twitter, and tell their computer programmes to skim through those sources looking for specific keywords (like ‘bankruptcy’ or ‘merger’) that signal something about the market.&amp;nbsp; So can a fake tweet cause a stock market crash? Potentially, yes. But these bots are programmed to filter through so much information that in the grand scheme of things, these methods prove more advantageous than inaccurate. But my point is, what is moving?&amp;nbsp; Meme stocks.&amp;nbsp; And what is moving them?&amp;nbsp; Memes (or computer systems) All these incidents make one question if we’re all just pretending that investing and trading is as calculative and artful as it seems? Because if Elon Musk’s tweets or some stranger Redditors can randomly decide for me the value of my investments, then why the hell am I wasting my time on Fundamental and Technical Analyses? The Pandemic and the Instability of the Stock Market We all know about Cristiano Ronaldo’s Coca Cola fiasco. For those who don’t: he arbitrarily removed two bottles of Coca-Cola during a press conference at the Euro 2020, while asking for them to be replaced by water. The video gained a lot of traction. It inspired at least five more such moments across the world. Overall, it was pretty funny.&amp;nbsp; But you see, it wasn’t funny for Coca Cola, because in the aftermath, the giant suffered a staggering loss of $4 billion. The story seems pretty nonsensical to me, but it sure makes me wonder if things would have panned out the same way if it weren’t for COVID-19. There is research that asserts the stock market has been more sensitive to the news during the COVID pandemic than otherwise. Just like us, humans! For instance, the findings of a comparative study confirm that the drop in stock prices during the COVID-19 era was more dramatic than the Swine Flu period, because of the presence of more speculation, rumours and negative news.&amp;nbsp; Another plausible reason for this could be that our existence has been shifting online minute-by-minute, during the pandemic. What’s virtual, seems real. So any piece of news online is more impactful than it would have been in normalcy. In other words, it’s harder to filter out what news would have had a bearing on your investing decisions pre-COVID and what news wouldn’t. Second, it’s no secret that investors detest uncertainty. The pandemic has tossed onto us a record-breaking, all-time high of unpredictability, and that had to materialise as overly-sensitive stock market indices and traders, some time or the other. While these are just hypotheses, only time can tell us if we will ever recover from this. Why is Sensitivity Important? By now it’s clear that it is important to acknowledge that sometimes, the stock market can be a little crazy.&amp;nbsp; But still, sensitivity is important. If people want to invest mindlessly, let them exercise their choice too. It sends a signal to the government and monopolists, that if the people are wronged, in the way of faulty policies or immoral corporate behaviour, consequences will follow, and the economy will tumble. And if every once in a while, we happen to observe notorious stock market activity, prices will readjust and bounce back to their intrinsic value.&amp;nbsp; To conclude, sensitive stock markets are like a well-functioning democracy. Which is to say, as long as the common people in it have the power to bring the entire system down, we’re doing okay.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Transgenders in Sports: Translating Equity vs Equality</title>
      <link href="/Transgenders-in-Sports" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transgenders in Sports: Translating Equity vs Equality" />
      <published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-05-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Transgenders-in-Sports</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Transgenders-in-Sports">&lt;p&gt;Throughout the U.S., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2021/03/18/978716732/wave-of-new-bills-say-trans-athletes-have-an-unfair-edge-what-does-the-science-s&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;roughly 35 bills have been introduced by state legislators&lt;/a&gt; that would limit or prohibit transgender women from competing in women's athletics. That's up from only two in 2019. What’s this sudden discourse all about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Terminology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before delving into the specifics, let’s understand some terms first. Most people use the words ‘biological male’ to define a transwoman. Using the words ‘biological male’ is problematic on two grounds: One, it is inaccurate (because biology is much more complex than that) and two, it’s immoral to disregard someone’s identity like that. So hereon, I’ll use the words ‘cis woman’ and ‘trans woman’ to point out the distinctions I intend to. For context, a cisgender person is a person whose gender identity matches their sex assigned at birth and a transgender person is a person whose gender identity is different from their sex assigned at birth. Now that the terminology is clear, let’s understand the issue at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Issue at Hand&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The participation of transgenders in competitive sports (notably transwomen competing with cis women) is a widely debated issue worldwide, with an audience deeply divided into two radical, yet valid schools of thought. Let’s try to view the issue from both perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘unfair’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand this side of the argument, let’s understand why the need to differentiate sports for men and women arose in the first place. In sports, the average performance gap between elite males and elite females is 10-12%. When we translate these statistics into real-world results, we see that on average, non-elite schoolboys beat elite cis women in some domains of sports rather effortlessly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just in the single year of 2017, Olympic, World and US Champion Tori Bowie's &lt;strong&gt;100 meters&lt;/strong&gt; lifetime best of 10.78 seconds was beaten 15,000 times by non-elite men and boys. &lt;a href=&quot;https://law.duke.edu/sports/sex-sport/comparative-athletic-performance/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The same is true of the Olympics, World, and US Champion Allyson Felix’s 400 meters lifetime best of 49.26 seconds&lt;/a&gt;. This differential isn’t the result of boys and men having a male identity, more resources, or better training/motivation - it’s because they have an androgenised body.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to puberty, there is no remarkable sex difference in circulating testosterone concentrations or athletic performance, but from puberty onwards, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6391653/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a clear sex difference in athletic performance emerges&lt;/a&gt; (with circulating testosterone in men exceeding 15-fold that of women at any age). The sex difference in circulating testosterone of adults explains most, if not all, of the sex differences in sporting performance (like increased muscle mass and strength, bone size and strength (density), and circulating haemoglobin, each of which individually increases athletic capacity). And this is precisely why competition has to be divided into male and female categories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if testosterone-driven puberty gives transwomen a surmountable edge over cis women, what’s the way out? Some trans women identify their gender early into their lives and use hormone-blockers, as a result of which, they never experience testosterone-driven puberty, which solves the problem partially. But what about the other trans women?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One solution is hormone therapy/testosterone suppression treatment. The National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) recommends that schools require transgender athletes to complete one year of hormone treatment before competing on a female team. Similarly, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.olympic.org/the-ioc&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;International Olympic Committee&lt;/a&gt; (IOC) guidelines require transgender athletes competing on a female team to demonstrate &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/01/sports/transgender-idaho-ban-sports.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;testosterone levels below 10 nanomoles per litre for one year&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the problem is, these guidelines are far from perfect. A recent study found that a year of hormone therapy decreased muscle mass in transgender women only modestly (around 5%). (&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ki.se/new-study-on-changes-in-muscle-mass-and-strength-after-gender-affirming-treatment-may-have-an&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;) Even when trans athletes take cross-sex hormones, some advantages, such as their bigger bone structure, greater lung capacity, and larger heart size remain, which would forever continue to provide them an athletic edge over cis women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might contend that some regulation is better than no regulation, which is true. But bear in mind that the regulation we’re talking about is only present in higher level, centralised sports authorities. What about the institutions outside their purview or the local level authorities?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connecticut’s state athletic conference is one of the 19 such conferences that allow athletes to compete based solely on their expressed gender identity (that is, without hormone treatments). Since Connecticut’s athletic conference enacted its liberal gender-identity policy, two male-to-female transgenders (who went through testosterone-driven puberty, and did not undergo hormone treatment) have won 15 women’s state championships - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/a-connecticut-girl-challenges-male-domination-of-female-sports-11562885421#&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;titles that were held by 10 different Connecticut cis girls the previous year&lt;/a&gt;. Within just three years, girls across the state were &lt;a href=&quot;https://mspolicy.org/an-interview-with-selina-soule-a-brave-young-woman-standing-up-for-womens-sports/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;denied over 85 chances to compete in elite athletic competitions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now consider this: while the two trans athletes in question won the Girls’ state championship, their times were not good enough to even qualify for the Boys’ state championship. This transforms the debate into a question of equity, instead of equality.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ramifications of such competition aren’t that easy to decode, they amplify especially in track and field, which might manifest into the erasure of records set by cis women after years of toil, detracting a level playing field, and loss of motivation for cis women to compete. For now, let’s put this on hold and try to understand the issue from another lens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘fair’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To argue requires us to understand the history of transgenders in sports. The alienation from their body felt by the trans community is often temporarily mitigated when they participate in sports. Their historical under-representation in sports makes their exclusion unscrupulous. Before calling them a ‘threat’ or discrediting their success, it is also important to note that transgenders suffer from higher rates of bullying, anxiety and depression, and even stand at a greater risk for suicide - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hsph.harvard.edu/news/hsph-in-the-news/transgender-youth-at-risk-for-depression-suicide/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;all of which makes it all the more difficult for them to train and compete&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of proponents of trans inclusivity in sports assert that the science of whether testosterone actually provides an advantage in competitions is not clearly established.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if we still choose to talk about a level playing field by enforcing sex-verification exams or transgender conversion therapy/treatment, there arises another issue: the trauma associated with it. One must note that transgenders, under no circumstance, need conversion therapy/treatment to be considered valid. And while undergoing conversion is absolutely the discretion of the person in question, it becomes essential and mandatory in sports governed by authorities like IOC and NCAA, as mentioned earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, many argue that even after treatment, differences persist, which makes one question if a ‘level playing field’ exists at all. When we talk about gender differentials in percentages, it’s important to recognize that sometimes, the average difference between men and women could be more or less the same as that between the weakest and strongest woman, or the shortest and tallest woman. After all, sports is all about diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then a lot also depends on the sport. For sports like cycling (especially uphill), a lighter body might be more helpful than a large, heavy skeleton. In sports like boxing, wrestling and weightlifting, separate weight categories exist, enabling athletes to compete against competitors of their size. Besides, higher levels of testosterone have empirically led to better performance only in a very small number of athletic disciplines: 400 meters, 800 meters, hammer throw, pole vault, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2021/03/18/978716732/wave-of-new-bills-say-trans-athletes-have-an-unfair-edge-what-does-the-science-s&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;which means other sports don’t require one to be ‘male’ to have an edge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These arguments make one feel relieved, since they may point towards hormone therapy as the ultimate equilibrium we seek to achieve. But unfortunately, the story doesn't end here. Currently, only a few sport-governing organisations have adopted trans-inclusive policies, the rest remain indifferent or even discriminatory. For instance, Idaho is the first state in the US to ban transgender girls from participating in girls’ and women’s sports. The law also includes a provision that allows for anyone to file a claim questioning the sex of an athlete, which could ultimately lead to sex testing (genital exams, genetic testing and hormone testing). Most anti-trans participation bills propose such invasive, accusation-based testing, which is deeply problematic since it not only weaponises transness but also endangers all women and girls.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This raises another question, how athletically outstanding can a girl or woman be before we see her as transgender?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible Solutions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing off the table, rather conspicuously, is banning transgenders from competing, since that is outright discriminatory and unfair. A possible approach toward inclusivity could be to create a third category for people who don’t fit neatly into the male/female dichotomy. But that requires answering a lot of unresolved questions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For starters, it would only strengthen the temptation to draw a hard biological line against &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/trumps-plan-to-redefine-gender-makes-no-scientific-sense/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the limits of what science can offer&lt;/a&gt;, which means scientific identification of Transgenders, DSDs (explained later) and other people whose gender and sex fall beyond the precincts of male and female. Also, in such a scenario, who draws the line between transgenders who have undergone conversion and those who haven't, transgenders who have identified their gender before puberty and those after puberty? Secondly, should the distinction start right from elementary/junior high school or when puberty actually starts to give an athletic edge, i.e. high school, college? Thirdly, what if there are not enough transgenders to fill out a team or offer proper competition? Is that a healthy sport?&amp;nbsp; Lastly, adding categories needs to be well-thought-out to ensure equal and fair access to benefits, like scholarships. Otherwise, it would create a category of second class citizens, which is certainly not the agenda.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another approach (and the most feasible one yet) is keeping the two categories intact, but allowing people to compete in girls’ and women’s events only if they identify as such, and they transition their testosterone levels to within the female (ovarian) range. The only moral question here is, would it be acceptable for sports authorities to require a transwoman first to transition physically, at least her testosterone levels, so that - although she would still be competing with a lot of developed male traits useful for athletics - all competitors would compete on equal footing in terms of testosterone levels?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, one ideal yet far-fetched approach is erasing the categories divided by “male” and “female” altogether and instead defining them based on different physiological parameters such as testosterone, haemoglobin levels, height, and endurance capacity, as well as social factors like gender identity and socioeconomic status. Athletes would be placed in a category that best mitigates unfair physical and social advantage. The algorithm would require to be sport-specific, and thus, producing it would be a cumbersome task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If none of these options strikes the right balance between the two important stakeholders, is there another option that does? Even if there is, there are yet a lot of unaddressed questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions still unsolved&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To begin with, why are sports scandalous only when male-to-female transgenders are involved? What about female-to-male transgenders?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trans boys and men are not perceived as a threat when it comes to sports, which keeps them away from media and controversy. However, they can become an afterthought when talking about inclusion. At the school level, especially in team sports, transboys are denied opportunities of competing in sports because apparently, they are absolutely not at an advantage against cisgender boys who have gone through masculinising puberty. Some are even persuaded to stay in the girls’ team in order to win, which is disheartening, given that they had just asked their entire community to view them as male, to use he/him pronouns and yet have to bear the weight of still being identified as something they chose to give up long ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Moving on, what about Intersex people?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intersex, (now referred to as disorders (or differences) of sex development aka DSDs) is a general term used for situations in which a person is born with reproductive or sexual anatomy that doesn’t fit the boxes of “female” or “male.” Some may have 3 chromosomes instead of the usual 2, some may have reproductive organs that don’t correspond with their sex chromosomes and some may even have both male and female reproductive organs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a person is identified as ‘intersex’ at birth, sometimes at puberty and sometimes they can live their whole life without ever discovering that they’re intersex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To sum up, DSDs are a hugely complex group of conditions and the controversy on how to ‘test’ for DSD still remains. It seems far more likely that female athletes with DSD are doing their best to compete as the sex chosen for them at birth rather than attempting to attain an unfair advantage through masquerading their gender. In such a scenario, compulsory gender verification seems unfair and humiliating in the majority of situations. Long story short, there is still a long way to go about fairness in this arena as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where to draw the line between inclusivity for transgender athletes and fairness for cis ones is an ethical question that is so subjective, that even an eternity of discourse couldn’t produce a concrete answer. To think that trans women threaten the fabric of women's sports would repudiate all the inclusivity they’ve achieved so far. Besides, so many of us don't care about sports or fairness until a trans woman wants to play. If we truly want to play ‘fair’, we can start by combating the main barrier to access for sports: socioeconomic disparity, often intertwined with systemic oppression such as racism, and leave the opinions to those who are actually affected by it: sportspersons. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Eeshita Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Throughout the U.S., roughly 35 bills have been introduced by state legislators that would limit or prohibit transgender women from competing in women's athletics. That's up from only two in 2019. What’s this sudden discourse all about? Terminology Before delving into the specifics, let’s understand some terms first. Most people use the words ‘biological male’ to define a transwoman. Using the words ‘biological male’ is problematic on two grounds: One, it is inaccurate (because biology is much more complex than that) and two, it’s immoral to disregard someone’s identity like that. So hereon, I’ll use the words ‘cis woman’ and ‘trans woman’ to point out the distinctions I intend to. For context, a cisgender person is a person whose gender identity matches their sex assigned at birth and a transgender person is a person whose gender identity is different from their sex assigned at birth. Now that the terminology is clear, let’s understand the issue at hand. The Issue at Hand The participation of transgenders in competitive sports (notably transwomen competing with cis women) is a widely debated issue worldwide, with an audience deeply divided into two radical, yet valid schools of thought. Let’s try to view the issue from both perspectives. POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘unfair’ To understand this side of the argument, let’s understand why the need to differentiate sports for men and women arose in the first place. In sports, the average performance gap between elite males and elite females is 10-12%. When we translate these statistics into real-world results, we see that on average, non-elite schoolboys beat elite cis women in some domains of sports rather effortlessly: Just in the single year of 2017, Olympic, World and US Champion Tori Bowie's 100 meters lifetime best of 10.78 seconds was beaten 15,000 times by non-elite men and boys. The same is true of the Olympics, World, and US Champion Allyson Felix’s 400 meters lifetime best of 49.26 seconds. This differential isn’t the result of boys and men having a male identity, more resources, or better training/motivation - it’s because they have an androgenised body.&amp;nbsp; Prior to puberty, there is no remarkable sex difference in circulating testosterone concentrations or athletic performance, but from puberty onwards, a clear sex difference in athletic performance emerges (with circulating testosterone in men exceeding 15-fold that of women at any age). The sex difference in circulating testosterone of adults explains most, if not all, of the sex differences in sporting performance (like increased muscle mass and strength, bone size and strength (density), and circulating haemoglobin, each of which individually increases athletic capacity). And this is precisely why competition has to be divided into male and female categories. So if testosterone-driven puberty gives transwomen a surmountable edge over cis women, what’s the way out? Some trans women identify their gender early into their lives and use hormone-blockers, as a result of which, they never experience testosterone-driven puberty, which solves the problem partially. But what about the other trans women?&amp;nbsp; One solution is hormone therapy/testosterone suppression treatment. The National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) recommends that schools require transgender athletes to complete one year of hormone treatment before competing on a female team. Similarly, the International Olympic Committee (IOC) guidelines require transgender athletes competing on a female team to demonstrate testosterone levels below 10 nanomoles per litre for one year.&amp;nbsp; But the problem is, these guidelines are far from perfect. A recent study found that a year of hormone therapy decreased muscle mass in transgender women only modestly (around 5%). (Source) Even when trans athletes take cross-sex hormones, some advantages, such as their bigger bone structure, greater lung capacity, and larger heart size remain, which would forever continue to provide them an athletic edge over cis women. One might contend that some regulation is better than no regulation, which is true. But bear in mind that the regulation we’re talking about is only present in higher level, centralised sports authorities. What about the institutions outside their purview or the local level authorities?&amp;nbsp; Connecticut’s state athletic conference is one of the 19 such conferences that allow athletes to compete based solely on their expressed gender identity (that is, without hormone treatments). Since Connecticut’s athletic conference enacted its liberal gender-identity policy, two male-to-female transgenders (who went through testosterone-driven puberty, and did not undergo hormone treatment) have won 15 women’s state championships - titles that were held by 10 different Connecticut cis girls the previous year. Within just three years, girls across the state were denied over 85 chances to compete in elite athletic competitions. Now consider this: while the two trans athletes in question won the Girls’ state championship, their times were not good enough to even qualify for the Boys’ state championship. This transforms the debate into a question of equity, instead of equality.&amp;nbsp; The ramifications of such competition aren’t that easy to decode, they amplify especially in track and field, which might manifest into the erasure of records set by cis women after years of toil, detracting a level playing field, and loss of motivation for cis women to compete. For now, let’s put this on hold and try to understand the issue from another lens. POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘fair’ To argue requires us to understand the history of transgenders in sports. The alienation from their body felt by the trans community is often temporarily mitigated when they participate in sports. Their historical under-representation in sports makes their exclusion unscrupulous. Before calling them a ‘threat’ or discrediting their success, it is also important to note that transgenders suffer from higher rates of bullying, anxiety and depression, and even stand at a greater risk for suicide - all of which makes it all the more difficult for them to train and compete. A lot of proponents of trans inclusivity in sports assert that the science of whether testosterone actually provides an advantage in competitions is not clearly established. However, if we still choose to talk about a level playing field by enforcing sex-verification exams or transgender conversion therapy/treatment, there arises another issue: the trauma associated with it. One must note that transgenders, under no circumstance, need conversion therapy/treatment to be considered valid. And while undergoing conversion is absolutely the discretion of the person in question, it becomes essential and mandatory in sports governed by authorities like IOC and NCAA, as mentioned earlier. Moreover, many argue that even after treatment, differences persist, which makes one question if a ‘level playing field’ exists at all. When we talk about gender differentials in percentages, it’s important to recognize that sometimes, the average difference between men and women could be more or less the same as that between the weakest and strongest woman, or the shortest and tallest woman. After all, sports is all about diversity. And then a lot also depends on the sport. For sports like cycling (especially uphill), a lighter body might be more helpful than a large, heavy skeleton. In sports like boxing, wrestling and weightlifting, separate weight categories exist, enabling athletes to compete against competitors of their size. Besides, higher levels of testosterone have empirically led to better performance only in a very small number of athletic disciplines: 400 meters, 800 meters, hammer throw, pole vault, which means other sports don’t require one to be ‘male’ to have an edge. These arguments make one feel relieved, since they may point towards hormone therapy as the ultimate equilibrium we seek to achieve. But unfortunately, the story doesn't end here. Currently, only a few sport-governing organisations have adopted trans-inclusive policies, the rest remain indifferent or even discriminatory. For instance, Idaho is the first state in the US to ban transgender girls from participating in girls’ and women’s sports. The law also includes a provision that allows for anyone to file a claim questioning the sex of an athlete, which could ultimately lead to sex testing (genital exams, genetic testing and hormone testing). Most anti-trans participation bills propose such invasive, accusation-based testing, which is deeply problematic since it not only weaponises transness but also endangers all women and girls.&amp;nbsp; This raises another question, how athletically outstanding can a girl or woman be before we see her as transgender? Possible Solutions One thing off the table, rather conspicuously, is banning transgenders from competing, since that is outright discriminatory and unfair. A possible approach toward inclusivity could be to create a third category for people who don’t fit neatly into the male/female dichotomy. But that requires answering a lot of unresolved questions.&amp;nbsp; For starters, it would only strengthen the temptation to draw a hard biological line against the limits of what science can offer, which means scientific identification of Transgenders, DSDs (explained later) and other people whose gender and sex fall beyond the precincts of male and female. Also, in such a scenario, who draws the line between transgenders who have undergone conversion and those who haven't, transgenders who have identified their gender before puberty and those after puberty? Secondly, should the distinction start right from elementary/junior high school or when puberty actually starts to give an athletic edge, i.e. high school, college? Thirdly, what if there are not enough transgenders to fill out a team or offer proper competition? Is that a healthy sport?&amp;nbsp; Lastly, adding categories needs to be well-thought-out to ensure equal and fair access to benefits, like scholarships. Otherwise, it would create a category of second class citizens, which is certainly not the agenda.&amp;nbsp; Another approach (and the most feasible one yet) is keeping the two categories intact, but allowing people to compete in girls’ and women’s events only if they identify as such, and they transition their testosterone levels to within the female (ovarian) range. The only moral question here is, would it be acceptable for sports authorities to require a transwoman first to transition physically, at least her testosterone levels, so that - although she would still be competing with a lot of developed male traits useful for athletics - all competitors would compete on equal footing in terms of testosterone levels? Lastly, one ideal yet far-fetched approach is erasing the categories divided by “male” and “female” altogether and instead defining them based on different physiological parameters such as testosterone, haemoglobin levels, height, and endurance capacity, as well as social factors like gender identity and socioeconomic status. Athletes would be placed in a category that best mitigates unfair physical and social advantage. The algorithm would require to be sport-specific, and thus, producing it would be a cumbersome task. If none of these options strikes the right balance between the two important stakeholders, is there another option that does? Even if there is, there are yet a lot of unaddressed questions. Questions still unsolved To begin with, why are sports scandalous only when male-to-female transgenders are involved? What about female-to-male transgenders? Trans boys and men are not perceived as a threat when it comes to sports, which keeps them away from media and controversy. However, they can become an afterthought when talking about inclusion. At the school level, especially in team sports, transboys are denied opportunities of competing in sports because apparently, they are absolutely not at an advantage against cisgender boys who have gone through masculinising puberty. Some are even persuaded to stay in the girls’ team in order to win, which is disheartening, given that they had just asked their entire community to view them as male, to use he/him pronouns and yet have to bear the weight of still being identified as something they chose to give up long ago. Moving on, what about Intersex people? Intersex, (now referred to as disorders (or differences) of sex development aka DSDs) is a general term used for situations in which a person is born with reproductive or sexual anatomy that doesn’t fit the boxes of “female” or “male.” Some may have 3 chromosomes instead of the usual 2, some may have reproductive organs that don’t correspond with their sex chromosomes and some may even have both male and female reproductive organs.&amp;nbsp; Sometimes a person is identified as ‘intersex’ at birth, sometimes at puberty and sometimes they can live their whole life without ever discovering that they’re intersex. To sum up, DSDs are a hugely complex group of conditions and the controversy on how to ‘test’ for DSD still remains. It seems far more likely that female athletes with DSD are doing their best to compete as the sex chosen for them at birth rather than attempting to attain an unfair advantage through masquerading their gender. In such a scenario, compulsory gender verification seems unfair and humiliating in the majority of situations. Long story short, there is still a long way to go about fairness in this arena as well. Where to draw the line between inclusivity for transgender athletes and fairness for cis ones is an ethical question that is so subjective, that even an eternity of discourse couldn’t produce a concrete answer. To think that trans women threaten the fabric of women's sports would repudiate all the inclusivity they’ve achieved so far. Besides, so many of us don't care about sports or fairness until a trans woman wants to play. If we truly want to play ‘fair’, we can start by combating the main barrier to access for sports: socioeconomic disparity, often intertwined with systemic oppression such as racism, and leave the opinions to those who are actually affected by it: sportspersons.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">An Investor’s Déjà Vu</title>
      <link href="/An-Investor-s-D-j-Vu" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Investor’s Déjà Vu" />
      <published>2020-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/An-Investor-s-D-j-Vu</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/An-Investor-s-D-j-Vu">&lt;p&gt;Picture this, you’re having a conversation with your parents while opening the refrigerator door. You extend your hand towards the half-eaten chocolate and in a moment of suddenness, it seems you’ve already done this before. But you can’t seem to remember when. That, my friend, is &lt;em&gt;déjà vu&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picture another scenario. Say you’re reading the newspaper this time and the S&amp;amp;P index has dipped more than the usual. You think you’ve been here before, except this time, you exactly remember when: 2008. Your memory is bitter about the experience because the last time it happened, it didn’t bode well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 2008 Debacle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone with a rough idea of the 2008 housing bubble would know that it wasn’t pretty. To quote &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/a-guide-to-the-financial-crisis--10-years-later/2018/09/10/114b76ba-af10-11e8-a20b-5f4f84429666_story.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Moody’s&lt;/a&gt;, “&lt;em&gt;The stock market plummeted, wiping out nearly $8 trillion in value between late 2007 and 2009. Unemployment climbed, peaking at 10 percent in October 2009. Americans lost $9.8 trillion in wealth&lt;/em&gt;”.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, just like the human mood, changes in the stock market come in waves. Where there is a low, there is a high. Thus, it’s no wonder that the stock market made a comeback: the home prices rebounded and the employment rate ticked upward. But unfortunately, the story doesn’t end here. Here’s the catch: the market may forget, but the human cannot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stocks have more than doubled since the financial crisis, and yet, a lot of investors have remarkably tweaked down their equity exposure. (For some context, equity is that part of your investment portfolio which leans towards risk. The same is compensated by the possibility of higher returns). Sounds weird, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The vast majority of people have some equity holdings in their 401(k) plans&lt;/em&gt;”, said &lt;a href=&quot;https://in.reuters.com/article/us-usa-stocks-retailinvestors/insight-mom-and-pop-investors-miss-out-on-stock-market-gains-idUSBRE88T0AE20120930&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Brian Reid&lt;/a&gt;, Chief Economist at the Investment Company Institute (ICI), but fewer are willing to take above-average or substantial risk than they were in 2008 before the market plummeted.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent Cogent Research report found that risk aversion among all age groups has been on the rise since 2006, including Generation X and Y, who have lived through a number of market collapses. To simplify, investors have become more risk-averse since the 2008 financial crisis. But why?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Déjà Vu&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, the ramifications of a financial crisis are more profound than we think: they perpetuate biases. The underlying bias observed here is called ‘Experiential Bias’. This occurs when investors' memory of recent events makes them biased or leads them to believe that an event is far more likely to occur again. This culminates in a lot of investors permanently quitting the market or overestimating the impending hardships in a market.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Facing the Music&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warren Buffet once said, “&lt;em&gt;Our favourite holding period is forever&lt;/em&gt;”. According to him, the secret recipe to minting clever money is holding on to stocks, even when their price collapses, for the simple reason that they will bounce back up, over time. But what happens to the investors who left the market at the end of 2008 or early 2009? It wouldn’t take big brains to figure out that they paid a high price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a personal level, quitting the market midway deprives investors of the opportunity of recovering their losses during the recoil. Moreover, reluctance to invest in risky avenues strips you of the prospects of earning fancy rewards. On a larger level, this may also contribute to negative consumer sentiment. Let us see how.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If every second investor hurt by the 2008 crisis exits the stock market, and consciously or subconsciously propels fellow investors to quit too, won’t economic transactions and activity tumble? Sounds unlikely, right? Why would I succumb to and base my decisions on borrowed apprehensions, instead of my own independent analysis? Enter ‘Herd Bias’, yet another fragment of behavioural finance. We’re hard-wired to herd and imitate what other investors are doing. Contrary to traditional beliefs, investors are not invariably rational, they have limits to their self-control and are prone to falling ill to their own biases and fallacies.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say that the aggrieved investor doesn’t quit the market but instead reads every non-average (but normal) dip in S&amp;amp;P or Dow Jones as the onset of something critical. Consequently and gradually, the investor might begin to disinvest (the move is motivated by a fallacy, but is disinvestment nevertheless). If there are sufficient people believing this idea, it is enough to drive the market down. Note that financial markets are driven by popular beliefs, not logical beliefs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too far-fetched, right? It is. But replicate this on a large scale, and voila, you have investor sentiment tipping a slowdown. Those who are still firmly gripped by the ravages of the crisis, have lost all appetite for risk and thus, shirk any and every opportunity that knocks on their doors. They focus on the preservation of capital, not its growth. Sadly though, escapism isn’t the key. Turns out, a no-risk portfolio leaves you financially unprepared.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breaking the Bias&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there might be some empiricism and truth driving such behaviour, one must actively try not to fall prey to his/her own biases. Here is some advice to help you steer through the horrors of the past (and life, generally) and take decisions objectively:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be Reflective: There are two approaches to arriving at investment decisions: Reflexive and Reflective. While the former is the default, automatic gut response to situations, the latter is the logical and methodical one. Even though the reflective approach demands efforts and research, it assists in making informed choices. So step back, dwell over the situation from a bird’s eye view, and then decide.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let Bygones be Bygones: Don’t anchor everything in the present to the traumatic events in your past. If it has happened once, don’t be so sure it will happen again. Learn from your mistakes and let the rest go.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most News is Noise: Don’t believe everything you read and don’t shoehorn every market dip into your past trauma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t Indulge in Peer Pressure: To quote Warren Buffet once again, “&lt;em&gt;The most important quality for an investor is temperament, not intellect. You need a temperament that neither derives great pleasure from being with the crowd or against the crowd&lt;/em&gt;”. You do you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To sum up, ‘Experiential Bias’ is natural. It’s like holding the umbrella when the rains have ceased. You don’t want to let go of it just yet, because it takes more than just time to shake the trauma out. But you know you’ll have to because it’s going to block the sunlight that comes your way.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Eeshita Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Picture this, you’re having a conversation with your parents while opening the refrigerator door. You extend your hand towards the half-eaten chocolate and in a moment of suddenness, it seems you’ve already done this before. But you can’t seem to remember when. That, my friend, is déjà vu.&amp;nbsp; Picture another scenario. Say you’re reading the newspaper this time and the S&amp;amp;P index has dipped more than the usual. You think you’ve been here before, except this time, you exactly remember when: 2008. Your memory is bitter about the experience because the last time it happened, it didn’t bode well.&amp;nbsp; The 2008 Debacle Anyone with a rough idea of the 2008 housing bubble would know that it wasn’t pretty. To quote Moody’s, “The stock market plummeted, wiping out nearly $8 trillion in value between late 2007 and 2009. Unemployment climbed, peaking at 10 percent in October 2009. Americans lost $9.8 trillion in wealth”.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; However, just like the human mood, changes in the stock market come in waves. Where there is a low, there is a high. Thus, it’s no wonder that the stock market made a comeback: the home prices rebounded and the employment rate ticked upward. But unfortunately, the story doesn’t end here. Here’s the catch: the market may forget, but the human cannot. Stocks have more than doubled since the financial crisis, and yet, a lot of investors have remarkably tweaked down their equity exposure. (For some context, equity is that part of your investment portfolio which leans towards risk. The same is compensated by the possibility of higher returns). Sounds weird, right? “The vast majority of people have some equity holdings in their 401(k) plans”, said Brian Reid, Chief Economist at the Investment Company Institute (ICI), but fewer are willing to take above-average or substantial risk than they were in 2008 before the market plummeted.&amp;nbsp; A recent Cogent Research report found that risk aversion among all age groups has been on the rise since 2006, including Generation X and Y, who have lived through a number of market collapses. To simplify, investors have become more risk-averse since the 2008 financial crisis. But why?&amp;nbsp; The Déjà Vu&amp;nbsp; Apparently, the ramifications of a financial crisis are more profound than we think: they perpetuate biases. The underlying bias observed here is called ‘Experiential Bias’. This occurs when investors' memory of recent events makes them biased or leads them to believe that an event is far more likely to occur again. This culminates in a lot of investors permanently quitting the market or overestimating the impending hardships in a market.&amp;nbsp; Facing the Music Warren Buffet once said, “Our favourite holding period is forever”. According to him, the secret recipe to minting clever money is holding on to stocks, even when their price collapses, for the simple reason that they will bounce back up, over time. But what happens to the investors who left the market at the end of 2008 or early 2009? It wouldn’t take big brains to figure out that they paid a high price. On a personal level, quitting the market midway deprives investors of the opportunity of recovering their losses during the recoil. Moreover, reluctance to invest in risky avenues strips you of the prospects of earning fancy rewards. On a larger level, this may also contribute to negative consumer sentiment. Let us see how.&amp;nbsp; If every second investor hurt by the 2008 crisis exits the stock market, and consciously or subconsciously propels fellow investors to quit too, won’t economic transactions and activity tumble? Sounds unlikely, right? Why would I succumb to and base my decisions on borrowed apprehensions, instead of my own independent analysis? Enter ‘Herd Bias’, yet another fragment of behavioural finance. We’re hard-wired to herd and imitate what other investors are doing. Contrary to traditional beliefs, investors are not invariably rational, they have limits to their self-control and are prone to falling ill to their own biases and fallacies.&amp;nbsp; Let’s say that the aggrieved investor doesn’t quit the market but instead reads every non-average (but normal) dip in S&amp;amp;P or Dow Jones as the onset of something critical. Consequently and gradually, the investor might begin to disinvest (the move is motivated by a fallacy, but is disinvestment nevertheless). If there are sufficient people believing this idea, it is enough to drive the market down. Note that financial markets are driven by popular beliefs, not logical beliefs.&amp;nbsp; Too far-fetched, right? It is. But replicate this on a large scale, and voila, you have investor sentiment tipping a slowdown. Those who are still firmly gripped by the ravages of the crisis, have lost all appetite for risk and thus, shirk any and every opportunity that knocks on their doors. They focus on the preservation of capital, not its growth. Sadly though, escapism isn’t the key. Turns out, a no-risk portfolio leaves you financially unprepared.&amp;nbsp; Breaking the Bias While there might be some empiricism and truth driving such behaviour, one must actively try not to fall prey to his/her own biases. Here is some advice to help you steer through the horrors of the past (and life, generally) and take decisions objectively: Be Reflective: There are two approaches to arriving at investment decisions: Reflexive and Reflective. While the former is the default, automatic gut response to situations, the latter is the logical and methodical one. Even though the reflective approach demands efforts and research, it assists in making informed choices. So step back, dwell over the situation from a bird’s eye view, and then decide.&amp;nbsp; Let Bygones be Bygones: Don’t anchor everything in the present to the traumatic events in your past. If it has happened once, don’t be so sure it will happen again. Learn from your mistakes and let the rest go.&amp;nbsp; Most News is Noise: Don’t believe everything you read and don’t shoehorn every market dip into your past trauma. Don’t Indulge in Peer Pressure: To quote Warren Buffet once again, “The most important quality for an investor is temperament, not intellect. You need a temperament that neither derives great pleasure from being with the crowd or against the crowd”. You do you! To sum up, ‘Experiential Bias’ is natural. It’s like holding the umbrella when the rains have ceased. You don’t want to let go of it just yet, because it takes more than just time to shake the trauma out. But you know you’ll have to because it’s going to block the sunlight that comes your way.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
