<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/unnati.jain/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-08-18T19:33:49+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/unnati.jain/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Future of Islamic Finance in the Global Economy</title>
      <link href="/The-Future-of-Islamic-Finance" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Future of Islamic Finance in the Global Economy" />
      <published>2019-07-18T00:10:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-18T00:10:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Future-of-Islamic-Finance</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Future-of-Islamic-Finance">&lt;p&gt;Islamic banks do not have a long history. The first bank started its operations
in 1963 in Egypt. The main centres worldwide are in Iran, Saudi Arabia,
Malaysia, Europe, Great Britain and Switzerland. Islamic banking and religion
are correlated (shock!). However preposterous it may sound, it is a bank that
does not charge you interest. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider that you want to start a manufacturing plant. A conventional bank will
provide you with the money and charge interest on it: the concept of
‘multiplying’ money. On the contrary, Islamic banks are forbidden from charging
interest. Instead, they will offer to be partners in your business and share
profits and losses. This strengthens the economy by reducing the burden from the
promoter’s shoulders and sharing it with financial institutions. In fact, their
peculiar business model helped Islamic banks largely avert the adverse impact of
the 2008 crisis. In particular, it was investment portfolios that were smaller
in size, partially deleveraged, and adherence to &lt;em&gt;Shariah&lt;/em&gt; principles which
prevented Islamic banks from putting money in the kind of instruments that
affected their conventional competitors and helped limit the impact of the
crisis on them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A characteristic feature of Islamic banking is the role of the bank. The basic
mission is, surprisingly, not to generate profit for the bank or multiply the
income for customers but to support local development and entrepreneurship.
Everything in the Islamic banking system is made according to  &lt;em&gt;Shariah&lt;/em&gt; law.
The things which are allowed in Islam are called ‘&lt;em&gt;halal&lt;/em&gt;’ and the things which
are forbidden are ‘&lt;em&gt;haram&lt;/em&gt;’. So, the bank is not able to invest any of their
money in the products or services forbidden in Islam. For example, in production
or trade of alcohol, nicotine, drugs, or in sectors related to pornography, the
defence sector, casino, and nightclubs. So, a customer of the Islamic bank can
be well assured that his money would not be invested in anything inconsistent
with Islam. The rule of ‘&lt;em&gt;Money makes Money&lt;/em&gt;’ does not exist in Islam because
money has no value in itself and cannot be multiplied just by rotating it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two key aspects of Islamic finance. First, it has the advantage of
being asset-backed which makes it inherently less risky than conventional
finance. Second, a prevalent risk-reward sharing arrangement exists. Apart from
this, there are some rules which guide such institutions. For example, retaining
surplus profit is unfair in this system, it is strictly related to usury -
&lt;em&gt;‘Reba’&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Reba&lt;/em&gt; is one of the most important rules in the Islamic banking
system. The second rule is &lt;em&gt;gharar&lt;/em&gt;, which is related to risky or hazardous
sales and the fact that gambling is prohibited in the Islamic world. For
instance, you cannot sell the goods or services which are not yet produced. It
can be traded upon only once it comes into existence. Moreover, nothing can be
sold unless you acquire it. This essentially eliminates the risk of not
possessing the goods. All products offered in Islamic banks have to be observed
and accepted by the Council for Islamic Banks (by their lawyers and clergy). The
most popular transaction in Islamic banking is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/m/murabaha.asp&quot;&gt;‘Murabaha’-&lt;/a&gt; a cost-plus
financing structure where the client and the bank agree on the markup or
“cost-plus” price for the item being sold. In essence, the bank purchases the
item on behalf of the client and retains its ownership rights until the client
pays back the amount (which is the cost-plus profit on the item) to the bank. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Islamic finance is growing rapidly but remains concentrated on a few
jurisdictions. Its strong growth reflects a tremendous interest on the part of
the Muslim population who have previously been underserved by the banking
industry. For the past two decades, many Islamic banks have witnessed
double-digit growth rates, surpassing their conventional peers. The industry’s
total worth, across its three main sectors (banking, capital markets, and
&lt;em&gt;Takaful&lt;/em&gt;), was estimated to be $2.05 trillion in 2017. At a mere glance, all
seems well for the Islamic banking industry. However, several potential markets
with a considerable quantum of the Muslim population remain largely unbreached,
including India and the Commonwealth of Independent States countries, made up of
the former Soviet republics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Islamic finance holds great promise for promoting macroeconomic and financial
stability but to fulfil these promises three prerequisites really need to be
met: first, a further deepening of the standard and codes for the application of
Islamic finance and their consistent application globally. Secondly, it is
essential for &lt;em&gt;Shariah&lt;/em&gt;-compliant money markets to be developed. This will allow
Islamic banks to manage their liquidity in a more effective way and free up
resources for them to invest in growth-enhancing projects. The Islamic financial
market is now facing increased competition due to the establishment of other
Islamic financial institutions and conventional banks who have established
Islamic subsidiaries or windows. Islamic banks also suffer from an overhang of
bad loans, and they lag behind their Western counterparts in technology and
expertise. The religious dimension adds an extra layer of problems with respect
to introducing new products that need to cater to both the Islamic law and the
needs of the general public. Lastly, there is a vital need for institutional
reforms in the areas of tax policy and capital markets development, which will
be needed for Islamic finance to fulfil its promise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critics consider Islamic banking similar to having a boiled ice cream-cream, it
cannot exist in real life without trickling down our confidence. For instance,
if you need a loan for purchasing a house, Islamic Banks will not charge you
interest on this money. Instead, they will buy the house for you and sell it
back to you at a higher price, demanding this amount from you in, say, 15 years,
of course, interest-free. This is a backdoor policy of interest collection. In
other words, it is interest-collection in all but name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to India, which will soon be the home to most Muslims in the
world, there has been a long-standing debate on Islamic banking. Currently, the
rules don’t allow it. Critics say it’s a bad idea because it goes against
India’s secular fabric. Is India ready for it? Will it open a Pandora’s Box?
Should we look at it through a religious prism? The opinions are sharply
divided. The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 and the Banking Regulations Act,
1949 both prohibit the setting up of an Islamic banking system. Only an act of
Parliament can set up one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, growth has sparked optimism about the future of Islamic
finance. However, as competition intensifies, Islamic financial banks are still
left with work to do. Most Islamic banks need to function more efficiently along
the entire value chain, regardless of whether the strategy is aimed at entering
a niche market, at competing with traditional banks or at both. They need to
scrutinise strategic choices and focus on operational basics to grab unused
market opportunities and overcome the changing dynamics of the industry. In all,
Islamic finance is still at a nascent stage which is yet to meet its full
potential.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>sailesh.buchasia unnati.jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Islamic banks do not have a long history. The first bank started its operations in 1963 in Egypt. The main centres worldwide are in Iran, Saudi Arabia, Malaysia, Europe, Great Britain and Switzerland. Islamic banking and religion are correlated (shock!). However preposterous it may sound, it is a bank that does not charge you interest.  Consider that you want to start a manufacturing plant. A conventional bank will provide you with the money and charge interest on it: the concept of ‘multiplying’ money. On the contrary, Islamic banks are forbidden from charging interest. Instead, they will offer to be partners in your business and share profits and losses. This strengthens the economy by reducing the burden from the promoter’s shoulders and sharing it with financial institutions. In fact, their peculiar business model helped Islamic banks largely avert the adverse impact of the 2008 crisis. In particular, it was investment portfolios that were smaller in size, partially deleveraged, and adherence to Shariah principles which prevented Islamic banks from putting money in the kind of instruments that affected their conventional competitors and helped limit the impact of the crisis on them.  A characteristic feature of Islamic banking is the role of the bank. The basic mission is, surprisingly, not to generate profit for the bank or multiply the income for customers but to support local development and entrepreneurship. Everything in the Islamic banking system is made according to  Shariah law. The things which are allowed in Islam are called ‘halal’ and the things which are forbidden are ‘haram’. So, the bank is not able to invest any of their money in the products or services forbidden in Islam. For example, in production or trade of alcohol, nicotine, drugs, or in sectors related to pornography, the defence sector, casino, and nightclubs. So, a customer of the Islamic bank can be well assured that his money would not be invested in anything inconsistent with Islam. The rule of ‘Money makes Money’ does not exist in Islam because money has no value in itself and cannot be multiplied just by rotating it.  There are two key aspects of Islamic finance. First, it has the advantage of being asset-backed which makes it inherently less risky than conventional finance. Second, a prevalent risk-reward sharing arrangement exists. Apart from this, there are some rules which guide such institutions. For example, retaining surplus profit is unfair in this system, it is strictly related to usury - ‘Reba’. Reba is one of the most important rules in the Islamic banking system. The second rule is gharar, which is related to risky or hazardous sales and the fact that gambling is prohibited in the Islamic world. For instance, you cannot sell the goods or services which are not yet produced. It can be traded upon only once it comes into existence. Moreover, nothing can be sold unless you acquire it. This essentially eliminates the risk of not possessing the goods. All products offered in Islamic banks have to be observed and accepted by the Council for Islamic Banks (by their lawyers and clergy). The most popular transaction in Islamic banking is ‘Murabaha’- a cost-plus financing structure where the client and the bank agree on the markup or “cost-plus” price for the item being sold. In essence, the bank purchases the item on behalf of the client and retains its ownership rights until the client pays back the amount (which is the cost-plus profit on the item) to the bank.  Islamic finance is growing rapidly but remains concentrated on a few jurisdictions. Its strong growth reflects a tremendous interest on the part of the Muslim population who have previously been underserved by the banking industry. For the past two decades, many Islamic banks have witnessed double-digit growth rates, surpassing their conventional peers. The industry’s total worth, across its three main sectors (banking, capital markets, and Takaful), was estimated to be $2.05 trillion in 2017. At a mere glance, all seems well for the Islamic banking industry. However, several potential markets with a considerable quantum of the Muslim population remain largely unbreached, including India and the Commonwealth of Independent States countries, made up of the former Soviet republics. Islamic finance holds great promise for promoting macroeconomic and financial stability but to fulfil these promises three prerequisites really need to be met: first, a further deepening of the standard and codes for the application of Islamic finance and their consistent application globally. Secondly, it is essential for Shariah-compliant money markets to be developed. This will allow Islamic banks to manage their liquidity in a more effective way and free up resources for them to invest in growth-enhancing projects. The Islamic financial market is now facing increased competition due to the establishment of other Islamic financial institutions and conventional banks who have established Islamic subsidiaries or windows. Islamic banks also suffer from an overhang of bad loans, and they lag behind their Western counterparts in technology and expertise. The religious dimension adds an extra layer of problems with respect to introducing new products that need to cater to both the Islamic law and the needs of the general public. Lastly, there is a vital need for institutional reforms in the areas of tax policy and capital markets development, which will be needed for Islamic finance to fulfil its promise. Critics consider Islamic banking similar to having a boiled ice cream-cream, it cannot exist in real life without trickling down our confidence. For instance, if you need a loan for purchasing a house, Islamic Banks will not charge you interest on this money. Instead, they will buy the house for you and sell it back to you at a higher price, demanding this amount from you in, say, 15 years, of course, interest-free. This is a backdoor policy of interest collection. In other words, it is interest-collection in all but name. When it comes to India, which will soon be the home to most Muslims in the world, there has been a long-standing debate on Islamic banking. Currently, the rules don’t allow it. Critics say it’s a bad idea because it goes against India’s secular fabric. Is India ready for it? Will it open a Pandora’s Box? Should we look at it through a religious prism? The opinions are sharply divided. The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 and the Banking Regulations Act, 1949 both prohibit the setting up of an Islamic banking system. Only an act of Parliament can set up one. In recent years, growth has sparked optimism about the future of Islamic finance. However, as competition intensifies, Islamic financial banks are still left with work to do. Most Islamic banks need to function more efficiently along the entire value chain, regardless of whether the strategy is aimed at entering a niche market, at competing with traditional banks or at both. They need to scrutinise strategic choices and focus on operational basics to grab unused market opportunities and overcome the changing dynamics of the industry. In all, Islamic finance is still at a nascent stage which is yet to meet its full potential.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Robots: Magic to Manic to Toxic</title>
      <link href="/Magic-Manic-Toxic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Robots: Magic to Manic to Toxic" />
      <published>2019-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Magic-Manic-Toxic</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Magic-Manic-Toxic">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How can mankind prevail in the face of such exponential and encompassing technological change?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each new development comes at a cost. We frequently witness the dawn of a new era at the expense of the old, such as the Iron Age following the Bronze, which itself followed the Stone Age. The advent of the Industrial Revolution wiped out the livelihood of millions, such as cobblers and weavers who were forced to adapt or be left behind, and this dynamic process continues today, only now at a much faster rate. In this era of ‘The New Machine Age’, we enter a dramatical phase where even highly skilled jobs are at risk, and where there will be increasing technology and potentially decreasing jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The realities of the new Machine Age are becoming clear and we can use them to chart the challenging yet abundant economy that we are creating. According to research at Oxford University, almost one out of every two jobs has a high risk of being automated by machines. Machine Learning, the most powerful branch of Artificial Intelligence, is the technology which is to be blamed for this alarming disruption. It basically permits machines to learn from data and mimic some of the routine jobs that we humans perform, but much more efficiently. And, evidently, this can prove game-changing or extremely problematic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent study from Forrester Research goes so far as to predict that 25 million jobs might disappear over the next decade. To put that in perspective, that is three times as many as jobs lost in the aftermath of the Financial Crisis. In fact, 87% of the lost manufacturing jobs have been eliminated as a result of improvements to our own productivity through automation. Automation is spreading to every production sector in every country around the globe. Output in the manufacturing sector in the US is actually growing, but we are losing jobs and lots of them. In fact, from 2000-2010, 5.7 million manufacturing jobs were lost to machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just the blue-collar jobs that are at risk, even those at the top of the ladder, including the highest-paid people, will be affected. What is clear that no matter whatever your job, at least some of it will be done by a robot in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is that the reason why visionaries like Mark Zuckerberg and Bill Gates are talking about government-funded minimum income levels? By the time today’s elementary school students are college-aged, we could be living in a robotic world largely unemployed and stuck in an ‘ungreat depression’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is supplemented by the dangers of technological advancement beyond automation and job replacement. Consider the tasks that are now done by a phone. Navigating a strange city? Impossible without Google Maps. Can’t decide where to take your next trip? MakeMyTrip will tell me. No time to answer all my texts? Siri will do it for me. These “artificial brains” are modifying quickly from knowing me to representing me to being me. In fact, they are starting to become an e-copy of us—and if that thought is not yet disturbing, imagine the power of this digital human amplified 100x in the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose we give an AI programme the goal to make humans smile. When the AI is weak, it causes humans to smile by performing normal amusing actions. However, when the AI is super intelligent, it realises there is a more effective way to achieve this goal: take control of the world and stick electrodes into the facial muscles of humans to cause constant, beaming grins. Of course, while such a scenario sounds very alarmistic, it does highlight a fundamental problem. AI is a genie inside a bottle, so the only solution is to find a way that when it gets out, it is on our side through shared values. This does not involve spelling out a long list of what we care about in computer code, rather an AI could use its ‘intelligence’ to learn what we value. Because, after all, the real worry isn’t enmity, but competence. A superintelligent AI can attain its goals, however for the common good of the world, we need to ensure that its goals are aligned with ours. For instance, humans don’t generally hate bees, but we’re more intelligent than they are – so if humans want to build a home in the place of a beehive, too bad for the bees. The beneficial AI movement is simply a way of avoiding placing humanity in the position of those bees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work that brings everyday surprise is designed for humans and not machines. And an area in which we are most certainly able to compete with and beat any machine conceivable is creativity. Machines have made very little progress in tackling novel situations. The fundamental limitation of Machine Learning is that it requires huge volumes of past data which we humans don’t require. We have the capability to connect seemingly disparate threads to find a solution to crisis situations or problems we have never seen before. The ability of the human mind to take strands from reality and weave them into something beautiful using a vivid imagination cannot be surpassed by bits of code, no matter how intelligent it is. Indeed, an AI programme has made music, but the capacities of such programmes have a critical limitation: they cannot do something new, which is the foundation of human creativity, they can only replicate and mutate the data that is given them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, it would seem that, with the right kind of limitations on what Machine Learning is used for and an investment in human beings, we can really herald a society where man and AI work together. First, we need to change our educational institutions to help foster more and more creativity, thereby preparing the jobs market for a situation where humans no longer do many mundane jobs. The efficiencies created by this division of labour between humans and AI will reap rewards that can only be imagined. Second, we need to align AI with our value systems and morals, using it as a purposeful instrument for human betterment rather than as a sterile but disastrously potent machine. With these two broad approaches, we humans can reach even greater heights of civilisation in the coming Age. After all, to quote Max Tegmark, President of the Future of Life Institute:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Everything we love about civilization is a product of intelligence, so amplifying our human intelligence with artificial intelligence has the potential of helping a civilization flourish like never before – as long as we manage to keep the technology beneficial.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>unnati.jain sailesh.buchasia</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">How can mankind prevail in the face of such exponential and encompassing technological change?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Fintech Effect: How Digital Innovators are Disrupting Banking</title>
      <link href="/The-Fintech-Effect" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fintech Effect: How Digital Innovators are Disrupting Banking" />
      <published>2019-05-03T02:33:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-03T02:33:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Fintech-Effect</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Fintech-Effect">&lt;p&gt;The world stands on the brink of a 4th industrial revolution that will
fundamentally alter the way everyone functions, which includes the complete
disruption of many industries and their business models. Banking is one such
industry which has experienced major turmoil when it comes to digital services
and mechanisation. Every transaction, be it online shopping, foreign currency
exchange, stock investments, or money transfers, is possible digitally at our
fingertips. At the intersection of finance and technology lies this altering
phenomenon, Fintech, which has been accelerating the pace of change at a
remarkable rate and is reshaping the industry’s status quo. ‘Fintech’ is a term
that has become the new trend in the media and in technology circles. Yet,
despite being widely discussed, many – including tech-savvy and clued-up
entrepreneurs – don’t quite have a handle on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While traditionally fintech was used for back-office functions to help banks
manage customer databases, facilitate transactions and record accounts, today it
has DIY modes where customers have a plethora of digital platforms at their
disposal, almost eliminating their dependence on a brick and mortar bank. With
24/7 device-sceptic access, virtually every transaction is now digitally
possible. The relevance of having several brick and mortar bank branches is
reducing as banking permeates all digital channels (cell phones, social and
online channels). According to some studies, in the European Union itself, more
than nine thousand bank branches were closed at the end of 2016 due to the wider
introduction of electronic payments and online/mobile banking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digital Disruption: What next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legacy financial institutions looking to become digitally-enabled encounter two
main problems. First, the business models and personal skills that have been
imbibed in the industry for decades have been disrupted by digital innovation,
and no longer hold the same degree of importance in the new banking ecosystem.
Second is “the innovator’s dilemma”. The innovator’s dilemma implies that when
companies adopt new technology and allocate the resources accordingly, they end
up disrupting the existing methods, something which they were already nurturing.
Hence, they might prefer to focus resources on existing methods to avoid
disruption, which, in turn, might make them uncompetitive in the long run.
Tackling this dilemma distinguishes successful firms and how they react to
change or ‘innovation’. For banks, attempts to create new models for the digital
age will wallow unless people and organisations are willing to disrupt
themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fintech affects or disrupts the financial sector in many ways which are beyond
our supposition. For instance, the mechanism which works behind the software of
chatbots is designed to capture natural language and human interactions through
machine learning and artificial intelligence. They assist banks to direct
customers to relevant departments more efficiently while handling queries.
Leading banks in Japan have chatbots that guide customers to information on its
website. Erica, the Bank of America’s chatbot provides investment advice too.
Customer emails containing transaction orders or details can be scanned and
executed within two minutes by robots which would otherwise take over 45
minutes. This process reduces costs, improves customer satisfaction and saves
time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next big development: a blockchain for digital transactions - cryptocurrency - is triumphing over the financial industry by providing consumers with a
speedier and cheaper way to carry on transactions. According to NASDAQ, the
greatest visible application of blockchain will be in how it moulds the payment
mechanism for the banks and users in order to dwindle away the transaction time.
In addition, with a unique trust system, blockchain offers a complete trading
platform for exchanges of securities which is achieved through transparency,
minimisation of risk, human error and transaction costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The importance of fintech will increase as the next few years will see the
disappearance of the Baby Boomer generation and the coming forth of the
Millennials or Gen Y (people born between 1980-1999). As they gain purchasing
power, they will cause drastic changes in client pattern, behaviour, decision
making, demographics and expectations. Their preference for a state-of-the-art
customer experience, high speed and convenience at the click of a button will
further accelerate the inculcation of fintech solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, digital disruption is not only about the positives. Cyber-crimes are
ever growing (malware, ransomware, phishing, etc.) along with digitisation. So,
stereotyped verification mechanisms are no longer enough to thwart fraudulent
attempts. The answer to this problem also lies in technology. More secure
protocols and extreme and extensive real-time, cross-channel fraud detection
systems are now available to protect the industry. There exists machine Learning
as well as artificial intelligence for disclosure of fraudulent activities. The
security softwares generate alarms on the plausibility of a fraud. Thereupon, it
is up to the investigators to figure out whether the transaction is a false
positive or an actual peril. The adoption of data aggregation floors, machine
learning steered statistical modelling and process automation can revamp
anti-money laundering activities by inculcating advanced efficiencies. Data
aggregation platforms can provide a 360-degree client view and facilitate
speedier transaction validation as already discussed. Further, machine learning
algorithms can leverage historical records to ascertain patterns and foresee the
happening of fraud and attacks, curtailing human endeavour by nearly half of
what it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In search of a safe and personal banking experience, as well as applications for
mobile devices, smartphones, and online payments, a new chapter of introducing
financial technologies in the financial services sector is being adopted. Today,
fintech covers everything, from chatbots to customer service, from machine
learning algorithms to blockchains for fraud analysis, from digital transactions
to biometrics. Retail banks have become a new player in providing all this to
their customers, forcing traditional banks to strategically invest in innovative
technologies. All of this will eventually lead to higher consumer retention.
While fintech, like any other technology, brings with it its set of disruptions,
the best is yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>sailesh.buchasia unnati.jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The world stands on the brink of a 4th industrial revolution that will fundamentally alter the way everyone functions, which includes the complete disruption of many industries and their business models. Banking is one such industry which has experienced major turmoil when it comes to digital services and mechanisation. Every transaction, be it online shopping, foreign currency exchange, stock investments, or money transfers, is possible digitally at our fingertips. At the intersection of finance and technology lies this altering phenomenon, Fintech, which has been accelerating the pace of change at a remarkable rate and is reshaping the industry’s status quo. ‘Fintech’ is a term that has become the new trend in the media and in technology circles. Yet, despite being widely discussed, many – including tech-savvy and clued-up entrepreneurs – don’t quite have a handle on it. While traditionally fintech was used for back-office functions to help banks manage customer databases, facilitate transactions and record accounts, today it has DIY modes where customers have a plethora of digital platforms at their disposal, almost eliminating their dependence on a brick and mortar bank. With 24/7 device-sceptic access, virtually every transaction is now digitally possible. The relevance of having several brick and mortar bank branches is reducing as banking permeates all digital channels (cell phones, social and online channels). According to some studies, in the European Union itself, more than nine thousand bank branches were closed at the end of 2016 due to the wider introduction of electronic payments and online/mobile banking. Digital Disruption: What next? Legacy financial institutions looking to become digitally-enabled encounter two main problems. First, the business models and personal skills that have been imbibed in the industry for decades have been disrupted by digital innovation, and no longer hold the same degree of importance in the new banking ecosystem. Second is “the innovator’s dilemma”. The innovator’s dilemma implies that when companies adopt new technology and allocate the resources accordingly, they end up disrupting the existing methods, something which they were already nurturing. Hence, they might prefer to focus resources on existing methods to avoid disruption, which, in turn, might make them uncompetitive in the long run. Tackling this dilemma distinguishes successful firms and how they react to change or ‘innovation’. For banks, attempts to create new models for the digital age will wallow unless people and organisations are willing to disrupt themselves. Fintech affects or disrupts the financial sector in many ways which are beyond our supposition. For instance, the mechanism which works behind the software of chatbots is designed to capture natural language and human interactions through machine learning and artificial intelligence. They assist banks to direct customers to relevant departments more efficiently while handling queries. Leading banks in Japan have chatbots that guide customers to information on its website. Erica, the Bank of America’s chatbot provides investment advice too. Customer emails containing transaction orders or details can be scanned and executed within two minutes by robots which would otherwise take over 45 minutes. This process reduces costs, improves customer satisfaction and saves time. The next big development: a blockchain for digital transactions - cryptocurrency - is triumphing over the financial industry by providing consumers with a speedier and cheaper way to carry on transactions. According to NASDAQ, the greatest visible application of blockchain will be in how it moulds the payment mechanism for the banks and users in order to dwindle away the transaction time. In addition, with a unique trust system, blockchain offers a complete trading platform for exchanges of securities which is achieved through transparency, minimisation of risk, human error and transaction costs. The importance of fintech will increase as the next few years will see the disappearance of the Baby Boomer generation and the coming forth of the Millennials or Gen Y (people born between 1980-1999). As they gain purchasing power, they will cause drastic changes in client pattern, behaviour, decision making, demographics and expectations. Their preference for a state-of-the-art customer experience, high speed and convenience at the click of a button will further accelerate the inculcation of fintech solutions. However, digital disruption is not only about the positives. Cyber-crimes are ever growing (malware, ransomware, phishing, etc.) along with digitisation. So, stereotyped verification mechanisms are no longer enough to thwart fraudulent attempts. The answer to this problem also lies in technology. More secure protocols and extreme and extensive real-time, cross-channel fraud detection systems are now available to protect the industry. There exists machine Learning as well as artificial intelligence for disclosure of fraudulent activities. The security softwares generate alarms on the plausibility of a fraud. Thereupon, it is up to the investigators to figure out whether the transaction is a false positive or an actual peril. The adoption of data aggregation floors, machine learning steered statistical modelling and process automation can revamp anti-money laundering activities by inculcating advanced efficiencies. Data aggregation platforms can provide a 360-degree client view and facilitate speedier transaction validation as already discussed. Further, machine learning algorithms can leverage historical records to ascertain patterns and foresee the happening of fraud and attacks, curtailing human endeavour by nearly half of what it was. In search of a safe and personal banking experience, as well as applications for mobile devices, smartphones, and online payments, a new chapter of introducing financial technologies in the financial services sector is being adopted. Today, fintech covers everything, from chatbots to customer service, from machine learning algorithms to blockchains for fraud analysis, from digital transactions to biometrics. Retail banks have become a new player in providing all this to their customers, forcing traditional banks to strategically invest in innovative technologies. All of this will eventually lead to higher consumer retention. While fintech, like any other technology, brings with it its set of disruptions, the best is yet to come.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
