<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/tom.perrett/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-09-10T22:59:26+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/tom.perrett/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Against a Liberal Anti-racism</title>
      <link href="/Against-a-Liberal-Anti-racism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Against a Liberal Anti-racism" />
      <published>2020-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Against-a-Liberal-Anti-racism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Against-a-Liberal-Anti-racism">&lt;p&gt;The months following the killing of George Floyd saw sales of books about race increase by up to 6,800%. The top seller was Robin DiAngelo’s &lt;em&gt;White Fragility&lt;/em&gt;, which increased sales by over 400,000 copies from May to June this year, a startling increase of over 2,000%. DiAngelo, a ‘diversity consultant’, has since been invited to deliver keynote speeches, charging up to $35,000 for a two-hour workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DiAngelo’s central premise, that white Americans must reckon with their own implicit biases and engage in rigorous introspection to remedy them, appears less of a repudiation of centuries-old institutional racism than it does an instructional manual for white liberals working in corporate jobs to avoid getting into trouble with HR. It characterises racism merely as an antipathy felt by individuals towards other individuals, leaving untouched the edifice of America’s racist socio-economic structure. It fails to acknowledge that white supremacy is not simply the supremacy of white over black, but also the supremacy of rich whites over poorer whites who can be trusted to vote themselves into economic ruin in return for the illusion of superiority. And even more egregiously, it focuses attention on the self-aggrandising antics of the white liberal, repackaging the fight against racism as a culture war between educated white liberals and less educated whites, many of whom do not view themselves as the beneficiaries of ‘privilege’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the first Africans arrived in Virginia in 1619, there were no ‘white’ people there. It would be another 60 years before colonial records would describe the settlers as ‘white’, as the idea of the ‘white’ race was deliberately constructed by the ruling class as a form of social control, dividing poor European indentured servants and African chattel-bond labourers, assimilating the Europeans into the ‘middle class’, and preventing the likelihood of the reemergence of an event such as Bacon’s Rebellion (1676). Europeans and Africans had jointly demanded the imposition of a land tax and Virginia’s transition from a large plantation economy to a diversified economy of small freeholders, chasing the planter bourgeoisie to the shore and burning Jamestown to the ground. Ira Berlin stated that in the aftermath of Bacon’s Rebellion &lt;em&gt;“they enact laws which say that people of African descent are hereditary slaves. And they increasingly give some power to the independent white farmers and land holders”&lt;/em&gt;. Therefore, rather than being simply a form of prejudice on the basis of skin colour, racism can be understood as a complex form of social control. Theodore W Allen’s book &lt;em&gt;The Invention of the White Race&lt;/em&gt; made a similar argument that racism is a “sociogenic” rather than a “phylogenic” phenomenon, analysing how the (phenotypically similar) British used racial oppression against Irish Catholics, later allowing the Irish Catholic bourgeoisie to assimilate into the oppressive structure, accepting the disenfranchisement of the forty-shilling freeholders in return for meagre ‘emancipation’ in 1829.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, liberal anti-racism of the DiAngelo variety, largely devoid of this analysis, becomes an exercise in narcissistic self-indulgence on the part of white liberals, who reframe discussions about race in terms of how they can be better people, and how it is incumbent on all whites to unlearn their white privilege. As this approach to anti-racism fails to acknowledge how racism functions as a tool of socioeconomic disenfranchisement by the ruling class, it assumes that all whites benefit equally from white privilege, ignoring and minimising the plight of working-class whites. A 2019 sociological study by E Cooley, etc. found that learning about white privilege did nothing to increase empathy for people of colour among white liberals, but simply made them less likely to empathise with poorer whites, placing greater personal blame on them on the basis that their privilege outweighed other social factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, reactionary and racist ideology abounds among the white working class, and this article is not intended to downplay such attitudes or pretend that they do not exist. It is to argue that if there is a hope that cross-racial solidarity can be achieved, and these reactionary tendencies extinguished, it will not be accomplished by lecturing working-class whites who are beset by low wages, deindustrialisation, and the opioid epidemic about their ‘privilege’, but by encouraging them to recognise that they have more in common with other races than with elites of the same race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term ‘class reductionist’ is consistently deployed against socialists who recognise that racism and capitalism are intimately connected as if this recognition downplays the significance of racism. But some of the most pernicious forms of American institutional racism, such as redlining and the prison-industrial complex, have explicitly capitalistic imperatives. For example, exclusion from ‘prime’ credit has forced black communities to secure housing through subprime loans and substandard rental accommodation. During the subprime lending boom, predatory loans were five times more likely to be made in black neighbourhoods than in white neighbourhoods, while black Americans were four times as likely as white Americans to be denied loans from the Bank of America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisations such as the Blackstone Group have conspired to engage in predatory lending practices, buying up houses at cheap prices and selling them on for higher prices or charging exorbitant rents. Invitation Homes, a subsidiary of the Blackstone Group and a prominent lender to black communities, may have broken laws to give tenants loans that maximised profits as they could easily outbid first time buyers. It is issues such as these, the pervasive, material disparities which have concentrated generational wealth in the hands of white communities and generational disadvantage in the hands of black communities that should be the focus of anti-racists, not trivial ideas such as ‘white fragility’. These are not injustices that can be solved simply by more representation of black people within the highest echelons of power, but only through the de-privatisation and de-commodification of housing at a minimum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another consequence of viewing racism through a reductive, individualistic lens is the over-medicalisation of the problem, which treats racism as a pathology on the part of its perpetrators. As Kenan Malik writes, &lt;em&gt;“It was not unconscious bias that made a police officer place his knee on George Floyd’s neck”&lt;/em&gt;. A meta-analysis of nearly 500 studies found that unconscious bias training only had a “weak” effect on the behaviour of individuals. Reframing racism as a product of original sin, an aberration that could never be held by ‘normal’ people simply absolves those who are responsible for perpetuating it, as racial bigotry can, and often is, the product of a sound mind. The Nazi war criminals at Nuremberg, for instance, all tested as medically sane, had high IQs, and included a disproportionate number of PhDs. Far from being the irrational judgement of an insane mind, racism is the mendacious, calculated judgement of the elites who perpetuate it, to provide a constant stream of alienated unfree labour from those they impoverish, to divide and conquer and to subjugate. Only an approach that acknowledges the systemic and institutional manifestations of racism can grasp this central point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The systemic racism on which the United States was founded, that still exists today, cannot be expunged with ‘unconscious bias training’ or the recognition of white fragility. The injustices will remain, but white corporate consultants such as Robin DiAngelo will become very rich. What is required is not white guilt but white solidarity on a mass scale, such as has been seen in the recent protests, and a recognition that, as Karl Marx stated, &lt;em&gt;“Labour in the white skin cannot emancipate itself where in the black it is branded.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The months following the killing of George Floyd saw sales of books about race increase by up to 6,800%. The top seller was Robin DiAngelo’s White Fragility, which increased sales by over 400,000 copies from May to June this year, a startling increase of over 2,000%. DiAngelo, a ‘diversity consultant’, has since been invited to deliver keynote speeches, charging up to $35,000 for a two-hour workshop.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Capitalism, Confucius and China’s Great Leap Backward</title>
      <link href="/Capitalism-Confucius" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Capitalism, Confucius and China’s Great Leap Backward" />
      <published>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Capitalism-Confucius</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Capitalism-Confucius">&lt;p&gt;On October 1, 1949, 200,000 people gathered in Tiananmen Square as Mao Zedong proclaimed victory in the People’s War of Liberation. The nationalistic Kuomintang government had been banished to Taiwan, the ‘Century of Humiliation’ was at its end, and the People’s Republic of China had announced its arrival onto the stage of world history. China, Mao argued, would no longer lie prostrate in front of Western powers, but had begun a journey toward emancipation and self-sufficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, nearly 71 years later, it appears at first glance as though the Chinese people have indeed ‘stood up’ (although it is disputed whether Mao actually used this phrase). Between 1978 and 2013, the Chinese economy grew by an average of 10% per annum. In 1949, the life expectancy of the average Chinese citizen was 35 years, compared with 76 years today. China’s share of world income rose from 2.2% in 1980 to 14.4% by 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet statistics often paint a misleading picture; the China of today is a far cry from the agrarian, peasant-led nation that Mao envisioned, as the predominance of foreign capital and ethnonationalist repression of minorities within China reveals a dark underside to the thin veneer of prosperity and harmony depicted at the 2008 Olympic Games, for instance. Xi Jinping can simultaneously venerate Lenin and advocate for supply-side economics, as the CCP’s ideology, ‘Socialism with Chinese Characteristics’ promulgates that the growth of private enterprise within China does not contradict or inhibit socialism. Indeed, Article 13 of China’s Constitution explicitly safeguards the right to private property. China’s SOEs (State Owned Enterprises) largely function according to capitalist imperatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Century of Humiliation’, which lasted from the mid-19th Century until the mid-20th Century, was marked by the systematic pauperisation and impoverishment of the Chinese people by foreign capital. In the Opium Wars, the British, who were running out of silver to exchange for Chinese porcelain, turned to smuggling opium into China despite the prohibitions laid down by Imperial Commissioner Lin Zexu in 1839. The ratification of the Treaty of Nanking in 1842 forced China to cede control over tariff autonomy and the court system while opening up treaty ports to foreign control. European finance capital continued to subjugate China throughout the 19th and early 20th Century, as HSBC was set up to assist Britain in leaching profits from accounts in China, Malaysia, and Singapore. This legacy has arguably since been inverted, as China now engages in the subordination of other nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maoist thought once held that the ‘Third World’ (nations with antagonistic relations towards the Imperialist First World and the developing Second World) was the primary engine of the revolution, standing to gain nothing from the current system. The role that China has since assumed, as a creditor for infrastructural projects in Global South nations, may seem a method of modernising them, but actually functions as a means of driving these countries further into debts that inordinate sums of money must be spent to forgive. In 2017, for instance, Sri Lanka spent 95% of government expenditure avoiding defaulting on debts induced by Chinese loans. The failure to repay loans is typically followed by the privatisation of national assets including education and healthcare, following the coercive ‘structural adjustment’ model imposed on Global South nations by the World Bank and IMF. Moreover, there are clear ethnonationalist overtones to these programmes, as more than 95% of China’s ventures in Africa involve a requirement of 70% of Chinese contracted personnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lenin, writing in Imperialism: &lt;em&gt;Highest Stage of Capitalism&lt;/em&gt;, argued that &lt;em&gt;“imperialism is capitalism at the stage of development at which the export of Capital has acquired pronounced importance….at which the division of all territories of the globe among the biggest Capitalist powers has been completed”.&lt;/em&gt; The expansion of China’s ‘Belt and Road Initiative’ and ‘Digital Silk Road’ indicate that the modern methods of harvesting data and imposing state-led surveillance have become the modus operandi of Chinese predation. China’s record of eroding the civil liberties of citizens in Tajikistan and Turkmenistan is well documented, as instruments ranging from traffic cameras to cameras inside schools have been used to subject potential political dissidents to incessant government monitoring. This display of political and technological might demonstrates just how far removed modern China is from the ideals of Maoism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nationalistic and chauvinist character of the Chinese State is not just observable from economic and foreign policy, but from the way in which Xi Jinping’s conception of the identity of China as a nation diverges from Mao’s. China has frequently eschewed solidarity with the DPRK, following UN sanctions against them. This includes voting in favour of sanctioning the DPRK, banning all coal imports from 2017, and prohibiting imports of petroleum products and textiles. China remains the DPRK’s only viable trading partner, yet the CCP chooses to ingratiate China further with Western powers at the expense of a potential ally. This indicates that China interprets its role in the world differently; the CCP now views China as a prosperous and independent power in its own right, rather than a nation constrained by the dictates of Marxist theory and a necessity to show solidarity with other ‘Communist’ countries. Mao, in late 1950, sent 200,000 ‘people’s volunteers’ into Korea to help Kim Il-Sung resist US intervention. Prior to the foundation of the PRC, North Korea had assisted Chinese communists in overthrowing the Kuomintang nationalists and had allowed the People’s Liberation Army to use the Korean peninsula as a land base during the Chinese Civil War. The mutual support that existed between China, North Korea, and the Soviet Union during this time has not been replicated since, as China continues to take the side of Western Imperialists, even selling drones to Saudi Arabia to continue their genocide in Yemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xi Jinping’s decision to neglect socialist solidarity and proletarian internationalism not only represents a break from Mao’s policies but a regression to a pre-PRC understanding of the nature of the Chinese State. The new embrace of Confucianism, which was previously condemned by Mao as anti-Marxist and anti-materialist, indicates that Xi is attempting to reinstate an understanding of the national and historical roots of the Chinese people. In 2014, Xi referred to Confucianism as &lt;em&gt;“the cultural soil that nourishes the Chinese people”&lt;/em&gt;. Obedience to authority and correct behaviour are widely considered central tenets of Confucianism, as are rituals of the &lt;em&gt;Zhou&lt;/em&gt; dynasty and the inherent legitimacy of the family as an institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The continuation of accepted values and norms contradicts dialectical materialism, which as a product of the Enlightenment, holds that human history is a linear progression, driven by class struggle and control over the forces of production. Culture, religion, and family are considered ‘superstructures’ which are superseded by the economic ‘base’ that determines the material conditions of a society. Dialectical and historical materialism are therefore antithetical to any philosophy, including Confucianism, that denies the power of ‘progress’ and the uprooting of any social force that stands in the way of revolutionising the productive forces. Marx, for instance, championed the destructive potential of capitalism to undermine the conservative vestiges of feudal society, and to “drown” them in the “icy water of egotistical calculation”, to sow the seeds of its own destruction, and to pave the way for Communism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China may have risen to world power status since the Century of Humiliation ended in 1949, but it is a country with a manifestly different outlook and a hugely different identity. The principles of Marxism, proletarian internationalism and agrarian reform have been sidelined as debt-trap diplomacy and revanchist ultranationalism characterise Xi Jinping’s despotic rule. Material conditions including national share of world income may have improved, but morally, socially and with regard to its foreign policy, China has arguably undergone a Great Leap Backward.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On October 1, 1949, 200,000 people gathered in Tiananmen Square as Mao Zedong proclaimed victory in the People’s War of Liberation. The nationalistic Kuomintang government had been banished to Taiwan, the ‘Century of Humiliation’ was at its end, and the People’s Republic of China had announced its arrival onto the stage of world history. China, Mao argued, would no longer lie prostrate in front of Western powers, but had begun a journey toward emancipation and self-sufficiency.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Echoes of the Estates-General: A Comparison between Ancient Regime France and 21st Century America (Part II)</title>
      <link href="/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Echoes of the Estates-General: A Comparison between Ancient Regime France and 21st Century America (Part II)" />
      <published>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General-II</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General-II">&lt;p&gt;The similarities between 18th century France and modern America apply not only to the background to the French Revolution but to the early stages of the Revolution in which a moderate, professional bourgeoisie sought to consolidate their power and stem the tide of economic and political radicalism emanating from the peasantry and sans-culottes. This article chronicles the various aspects of this divide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Representative Problem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tim Blanning, writing in &lt;em&gt;The Pursuit of Glory&lt;/em&gt;, argued that the French Revolution “wrapped into one explosive package the three great abstractions of modern politics: the People, the State, and the Nation”, and that “the French people announced their arrival as the main actors in the nation’s political life.” That sovereignty resided in the nation and that Louis XVI was answerable not to God but to the constitutional law of the State (for the first part of the Revolution anyway), were principles that would lead to the self-assertion of the French people, as mass participation in assemblies and demonstrations and universal conscription under the Jacobins meant that they could no longer be ignored. But for the first part of the Revolution, representation was monopolised by the most middle-class, reformist elements of the French society. America today suffers from a similar problem, as the DNC continuously props up Joe Biden’s campaign, and acts as an obstacle to any substantive change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Estates-General sat on May 5, 1789, Louis XVI having had little choice over its convocation following the difficulties in levying taxes and rents on an increasingly recalcitrant peasantry, coupled with the fears of the bourgeoisie that the loans they had made to the State might not be paid back. The Third Estate was represented by 610 men, about 1/6th of whom were capitalists and bankers, and many of whom were lawyers, indicating that despite representing 95% of the French people, the Third Estate exclusively advanced the interests of the educated middle classes. As such, the Declaration of the Rights of Man and the Citizen, which Lafayette consulted Thomas Jefferson in drawing up, was a crystallisation of Enlightenment principles that affirmed the universal power of reason, the ability of man to surmount all obstacles and control his own government and society, and the principle of equality before the law with noble privileges abolished. Article IV of the Declaration stated that liberty constituted anything that did not harm others by infringing on the rights to liberty, property and security and that only the rule of law could delineate these boundaries. Private property remained a ‘natural right’, and the unchecked ability to accumulate capital and influence the political process did not infringe any of the aforementioned negatively-defined ‘rights’, and so was sanctified by law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Eric Hobsbawm, “A constitutional monarchy based on a propertied oligarchy expressing itself through a representative assembly was more congenial to most bourgeois liberals than the democratic republic which might have seemed a more logical expression of their theoretical aspirations.” The demands articulated by the peasantry for the restoration of communal lands and material prosperity could be ignored, and by August 10, 1789, the bourgeoisie had taken up arms against the peasantry in Dauphine and Burgundy. Characterising peasant agitations as the work of ‘brigands’, the troops were called out to crush all men without professions and domiciles. This brutality saw 160 prisoners killed at Cluny, and 80 hanged in Lyon. Following the storming of the Bastille and the August 4 reforms that established equality in taxation and admission to public office, in addition to the redemption of manorial lands, it was clear that the peasantry and sans-culottes were the vessels of social change, repelled by bourgeois anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The glaring flaws in a supposedly ‘representative’ system have also shown themselves in the recent Democratic primaries, where Bernie Sanders’ campaign has cratered. In Iowa last month, the app meant to coordinate the results of the Caucus mysteriously crashed, and it later transpired that the app was built by a for-profit company named Shadow Inc. that Pete Buttigieg’s campaign had paid millions of dollars. The US Constitution, like France’s Declaration of the Rights of Man, protects the rights of private business to hike prices, depress wages and lock other competitors out of the market, and the rights of political institutions such as the DNC to sabotage the electoral process in favour of candidates who are more conducive to a capitalist economic setting. Nothing legally prevents the DNC from limiting the number of debates and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/us-politics/bernie-sanders-democratic-primary-dnc-convention-superdelegates-nomination-2020-election-a9363626.html&quot;&gt;blocking Bernie Sanders from winning the nomination.&lt;/a&gt; The freedoms of speech and voluntary exchange are theoretical abstractions that give way to the realities of market competition and the profit motive, as while individuals enjoy the superficial freedoms to participate in democracy, the real power lies in the hands of multinational corporations or nepotistic political behemoths like the DNC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two Shades of Moderation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moderate voices within the National Assembly, who would later go on to form the Legislative Assembly in 1791, recognised that their interests were broadly in line with a limited monarchy, rather than a democratic republic. In what became the National Constituent Assembly, a class of propertied ‘active citizens’ formed a constitutional monarchy that banned trade unions and guild corporations, instituted the enclosure of communal lands and sold off ecclesiastical domains. These reforms were designed to create an internal market for goods, rather than to satiate the demands of the peasantry, as the ensuing price fluctuations led to agitations in rural areas. The distinction between the property-owning moderates of the Legislative Assembly who favoured opening up internal markets and creating a class of landless agrarian wage-labourers, and the peasantry and sans-culottes who favoured the communal ownership of land and higher income and inheritance tax was becoming more evident. The storming of the Tuileries and the establishment of the National Convention in 1792 was the apotheosis of this struggle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The incompatibility of moderate defenders of the status quo with the vast numbers demanding transformative change is also characteristic of the schisms between Bernie Sanders and his supporters with the centrist Democrats. Much like the Girondins and moderates in the National Constituent Assembly, Joe Biden and his supporters pretend to rail against the corruption and despotism of the Trump administration while obscuring how much they have in common with the Republicans. In addition to his already disastrous record of voting in favour of NAFTA, supporting the war in Iraq and playing a key role in the war on drugs that has devastated many families (particularly Black and Hispanic), Biden continues to oppose Medicare for All, even suggesting that he would &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politifact.com/factchecks/2020/mar/10/facebook-posts/when-biden-was-asked-if-he-would-veto-medicare-all/&quot;&gt;veto it if it passed both houses and came to his desk.&lt;/a&gt; Furthermore, the centrist Democrats and Bernie Sanders’ supporters are separated not only by policy disagreements but a profound and seemingly irreconcilable divergence in worldview. The centrist Democrats are consequentialist; it is unsurprising that a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2020/03/suburbanites-are-backing-biden/607726/&quot;&gt;base of primarily middle-class professionals&lt;/a&gt; are concerned with results and efficacy above all else, and maintain that the ends (beating Trump) justify the means (nominating Biden). Much like the bureaucratic moderates in the Legislative Assembly, the centrist Democrats view capitalism as a natural accompaniment to their utilitarian, consequentialist worldview. If one believes that man is a rational, utility maximising agent entering into voluntary exchanges with others, then the consequences of mutual trade and transaction are all that matters, and anything not amenable to the rationalist calculus of profitability can be discarded. Bernie Sanders’ supporters are more ideological (and, indeed, deontological), advocating for transformative measures such as Medicare for all and the abolition of ICE as ends in themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must be mentioned, however, that the situation in France that enabled the storming of the Bastille in 1789 and the Tuileries in 1792 is not entirely analogous to the modern American situation, as the peasantry and sans-culottes in France represented a broadly unified coalition, committed to establishing communally-owned land and preventing monopolisation and speculation. They had both suffered the effects of inflation and famine during the 1770’s and 1780’s, and both saw their enemy as the nobility and bourgeois professionals. The American working class, by contrast, remains divided along racial lines, as well as on geographic and occupational lines. &lt;a href=&quot;https://aese.psu.edu/directory/smm67/Election16.pdf?wpisrc=nl_daily202&amp;amp;wpmm=1&quot;&gt;A study from Penn State University&lt;/a&gt; showed that Donald Trump performed best in swing states that were worst affected by deindustrialisation and the opioid epidemic, and had experienced employment losses over recent decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The political divisions between professional, liberal capitalists who sought to make an existing system more amenable to their interests and the disaffected masses who sought radical change are common to both late Ancien Regime France and 21st century America. The disillusionment with the machinery of governance that led the sans-culottes to believe that the Estates General did not represent them also motivates many Bernie Sanders supporters who view the DNC as an obstacle to power. If the French Revolution was the time for the French people to assert themselves as a prominent force, then the coming economic depression may foreground the schism between unrepresentative political institutions and the people they have disenfranchised.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The similarities between 18th century France and modern America apply not only to the background to the French Revolution but to the early stages of the Revolution in which a moderate, professional bourgeoisie sought to consolidate their power and stem the tide of economic and political radicalism emanating from the peasantry and sans-culottes. This article chronicles the various aspects of this divide.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Echoes of the Estates-General: A Comparison between Ancient Regime France and 21st Century America (Part I)</title>
      <link href="/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Echoes of the Estates-General: A Comparison between Ancient Regime France and 21st Century America (Part I)" />
      <published>2020-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Echoes-of-the-Estates-General">&lt;p&gt;The background to the French Revolution chronicles the decline of the once-powerful State, beset by a multitude of economic and social problems. Chief among these issues were: a bourgeoning national debt brought on by the cost of war, the increasing antagonisms between an unproductive class of nepotistic oligarchs and an impoverished mass of peasants and small artisans, and the increasing irrelevance of the country in comparison to other, more economically dynamic states. The United States in the 21st Century bears striking similarities to the pre-revolutionary France, as discontent with stagnating wages and widening inequality reaches a fever pitch as the 2020 election draws nearer. This is the first of two articles examining the economic and political similarities between them, at a volatile time in the history of both nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;State Debt and Poor Finances&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between 1720 and 1780, France’s overseas trade had quadrupled, yet commercial prosperity was not enough to offset the abysmal condition of state finances. The combined cost of fighting the Seven Years’ War and the American War of Independence was 3.1 billion livres, over 4 times the Crown’s annual revenue. This was exacerbated by the fact that spending on war, the navy and diplomacy constituted 25% of Crown expenditure, in addition to the 50% that serviced the existing debt. Coupled with high interest rates that deterred moneylenders and an inefficient tax system that failed to raise revenue and allowed the nobility to remove officials who attempted to raise either direct or indirect taxes on them, there was a serious economic crisis by 1789.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 9/11, the United States has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2016/09/cost-wars-iraq-afghanistan/499007/&quot;&gt;poured $3.2 trillion into wars, reaching a total of $4.8 trillion once obligations to veterans have been paid.&lt;/a&gt;  Engagements in Iraq, Afghanistan, Libya, Syria and other places have caused excessive deficit spending, and like in France in the 1780’s, an inefficient system of taxation that has involved lower taxes on the wealthy has only shifted the burden of debt onto the poor and future generations. George W Bush’s tax cuts in 2001 and 2003, and the tax breaks given to the billionaires by Trump are analogous to the exemptions that the French nobles received at the time of mass social breakdown at the end of the 1780’s. Against the backdrop of ballooning debt and the 2008 Financial Crisis, the concerns of the younger generations of Americans who have flocked to Bernie Sanders can be understood as a revolt against a system that allocates inordinate amounts of money towards wars and bank bailouts, but claims that education and healthcare are too costly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inequality and Social Unrest&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The schisms and fissures that have opened up in American society as a result of widening inequality and resentment at excessive accumulation and monopolisation by unaccountable billionaires is reminiscent of the tax immunities and feudal privileges that exempted the French nobility from accountability along with the predominance of feudal privileges such as internal customs barriers and tolls that prevented the establishment of a home market for manufacturers, which Turgot’s reforms had failed to redress in 1774. The stultifying stagnation imposed on the French economy by the system of noble privileges made the conditions of the peasantry significantly worse, indicating that it was not only the burden of debt but mass social unrest that resulted from the Ancien Regime. Eric Hobsbawm, in his book the &lt;em&gt;Age of Revolution&lt;/em&gt; stated that the nobility encroached considerably on the autonomy of the peasantry as feudal dues, tithes and taxes occupied an increasing share of peasants’ income. Ground between the millstones of noble exactions and price inflation, social breakdown and revolts among the peasantry were made practically inevitable by the late 1780’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Kropotkin, writing in &lt;em&gt;The Great French Revolution&lt;/em&gt;, argued that the inequalities between the nobility and the peasantry, combined with the obstinacy of those in power, illustrated the sclerotic and outdated nature of what would later become the first and second estates of the Estates-General. He stated that “if despair and misery impelled the people to riot, it was the hope of obtaining some relief that incited them to revolt”. In 1777, 1,100,000 peasants were declared to be beggars. Between 1730 and 1789, wages rose by 22% but were unable to keep pace with prices, which rose by 60%, causing further immiseration for the French peasantry and precipitating risings of both the rural and the urban poor in 1788/1789. Inflation of the price of agrarian produce prevented the urban workers from gaining access to bread, and wage stagnation crippled a key market for manufactured goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three wealthiest billionaires in the United States: Jeff Bezos, Bill Gates and Warren Buffett, own as much wealth as the bottom half of the American population combined, indicating that capitalist accumulation has acted as an enormous fetter on the development of the productive forces, and that the majority of sectors of the economy have been sacrificed on the altar of short-term profit. Capital simply ‘goes on strike’ until it can find an adequate return on investment, as Big Pharma, for instance, has not produced a single new antibiotic in the nearly 4 decades since it was deregulated. Apple and Samsung, in lieu of investing in new technologies, have spent 7 years engaged in a costly ‘patent war’ over copying iPhones, have outsourced production to the Global South, or simply gambled on the stock exchange. The billionaire class in America has become a parasitic oligarchy that mirrors the nobility in Ancien Regime France, suffused with government subsidies and content with shoring up their positions on the market, as the nobility once clung to their feudal dues and court pensions. The unproductive nobility, who were not earners by birth, and who were barred from entering professions, influenced politics to increase their privileges, much as America’s unproductive billionaires buy off politicians today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether anything resembling the 1788/1789 agrarian riots will happen in America remains to be seen, although the levels of poverty in America have continued to climb recently. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2016/05/my-secret-shame/476415/&quot;&gt;49% of Americans now live paycheck to paycheck&lt;/a&gt;, and recent studies have linked &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-healthcare-deaths/study-links-45000-u-s-deaths-to-lack-of-insurance-idUSTRE58G6W520090917&quot;&gt;45,000 deaths per year to lack of health insurance.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loss of Global Hegemony&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The loss of power and influence on the world stage to other countries with expanding economies and greater political and technological capabilities is another major point of comparison between latter-day Ancien Regime France and 21st Century America. By the late 1780’s, Great Britain was already beginning to industrialise, buoyed by the prospect of free trade with the newly independent United States, the growing importance of slave-picked cotton from the American South, and the opening up of new markets in Latin America such as Brazil and Cuba whose economies of scale made them more profitable than mercantilist West Indian markets. The 1770’s and 1780’s saw the development of puddling furnaces, rolling mills and James Watt’s steam engine, alongside agricultural techniques that increased enclosures and developed profitable cash crops. France, by contrast, was still hampered by the inefficiency of feudal dues and tithes during Louis XVI’s administration, remaining &lt;em&gt;“a nation of agriculture and handicrafts”&lt;/em&gt; according to Georges Lefebvre. Its commercial and colonial supremacy began to decline, and its traditional economic methods, internal trade restrictions and inadequate transport links acted as a bottleneck on economic progress, as Great Britain surged ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collapse of American hegemony and the rise of China is one of the defining changes in modern geopolitics that radically &lt;em&gt;reorients&lt;/em&gt; the global balance of power. Once again, the domestic unrest and discontent fermenting amongst a people can be contextualised within the decline of the country at large. There are countless examples in history of leaders using patriotism and perceived national importance to distract from economic failures by galvanising the spirit of the population. This becomes increasingly difficult at a time of national decline, as shown by Trump’s recent attempts to escalate tensions with Iran. Public opinion polls found that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.people-press.org/2019/07/30/climate-change-and-russia-are-partisan-flashpoints-in-publics-views-of-global-threats/&quot;&gt;just 43% of the American public approved of the killing of General Soleimani&lt;/a&gt;, showing that the cynical use of patriotism to offset economic decline is becoming less tenable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the United States’ persistent refusal to allow the state to play a directing role in the allocation of resources has culminated in the United States ceding ground to the bureaucratic and ruthlessly efficient Chinese State, whose monopolistic tech companies exert a growing influence over countries ranging from Central Asia to Latin America. The United States remains a service economy, sustained by low wages, cheap credit and cheap imports which have led to a ballooning trade deficit of $616.8 billion (by late 2019). The Chinese, on the other hand, have understood the importance of digital infrastructure to the modern, interconnected global economy through the expansion of the Belt and Road Initiative and the Digital Silk Road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The background to the French Revolution shows that national decline, combined with economic stagnation and an unaccountable and bureaucratic class of elites who produce and contribute little of value can mobilise a mass of the labouring poor who recognise the injustice of the system they are living under. The concept of the ‘American Dream’ is becoming increasingly untenable as neoliberal capitalism proves itself incapable of innovation and only of injecting money into assets and speculation, while concentrating power and wealth in the hands of a few billionaires. From the demise of Bernie Sanders’ campaign to the desperate attempts of the ruling class to consolidate power in the wake of the Coronavirus by printing $1.5 trillion to stabilise markets while millions are still without health insurance, there is a significant chance that the current crisis of American neoliberalism may result in either social upheaval, or a revolutionary transformation of the economic system.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The background to the French Revolution chronicles the decline of the once-powerful State, beset by a multitude of economic and social problems. Chief among these issues were: a bourgeoning national debt brought on by the cost of war, the increasing antagonisms between an unproductive class of nepotistic oligarchs and an impoverished mass of peasants and small artisans, and the increasing irrelevance of the country in comparison to other, more economically dynamic states. The United States in the 21st Century bears striking similarities to the pre-revolutionary France, as discontent with stagnating wages and widening inequality reaches a fever pitch as the 2020 election draws nearer. This is the first of two articles examining the economic and political similarities between them, at a volatile time in the history of both nations.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Corruption and Coercion on the Digital Silk Road</title>
      <link href="/Corruption-and-Coercion" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Corruption and Coercion on the Digital Silk Road" />
      <published>2020-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Corruption-and-Coercion</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Corruption-and-Coercion">&lt;p&gt;The squalid conditions of the Xinjiang region of Northwestern China, in which Uighur Muslims, Khazakhs and Uzbeks are forced to surrender DNA and blood samples, remain a stark reminder of the extent to which civil liberties can be assailed in the name of ‘counter-terrorism’. 47-year old Bakitali Nur, a fruit and vegetable exporter from Khargos, &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5735411/china-surveillance-privacy-issues/&quot;&gt;told &lt;em&gt;Time&lt;/em&gt; magazine&lt;/a&gt; that he and seven other inmates were forced to sit still on plastic stools for seventeen consecutive hours as their movements were monitored by security cameras. In Xinjiang, 2.5 million citizens have their whereabouts tracked by CCTV whilst being subjected to a punitive social credit system that discourages behaviour not approved of by the Chinese State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These dystopian scenes are a microcosm of a much broader and more complex web of technological and economic strategies through which the Chinese State is attempting to construct a digital panopticon that ensnares Central Asia and large parts of Africa and Latin America in its grip. Announced in a 2015 Government White Paper, the Belt and Road Initiative (BRI) attempts to enhance digital connectivity, impose high-level technologies and Artificial Intelligence on neighbouring countries, and to establish China as a regional hegemon and world leader in physical and digital infrastructure. The Digital Silk Road, which involves State-owned enterprises and private companies developing fiber optic cables that can monitor and divert data traffic, has led to a $79 billion investment in 80 different countries. The implications of fiber optic expansion and data centres are immense: the ability of the CCP to monitor and control foreign citizens, to proliferate State propaganda and quell ideological dissent is augmented through the process of data localisation, which requires foreign corporations to maintain data in China, where the State has access to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collusion between the Chinese State and the technological corporations responsible for accessing civilian data and implementing everything from facial recognition cameras to traffic control devices is most strikingly expressed in the 2017 National Intelligence Law, which promulgated that Chinese corporations had to support the values of Chinese Intelligence Agencies. Within the context of this Law, it seems all the more disturbing that Hikvision, a company whose controlling shares are owned by the Chinese government, has installed facial recognition cameras in Kazakhstan and facilitated surveillance in Uzbekistan’s educational system. In February 2019, the Tajik government &lt;a href=&quot;https://foreignpolicy.com/2019/11/15/huawei-xinjiang-kazakhstan-uzbekistan-china-surveillance-state-eyes-central-asia/&quot;&gt;announced an identification system&lt;/a&gt; requiring phone users to provide fingerprints and privacy-invasive medical information when buying SIM cards. The potential for China to establish itself as a global superpower by harvesting data and establishing e-commerce is limitless, particularly in an era in which our economies are increasingly based around digital information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the rise of China has frequently been touted as an event of epochal significance, which threatens to overthrow the established global order and is driven by an implacable hostility to every aspect of modern economics, the reality is that China seeks to maintain many elements of globalisation and free trade. The regimentation of large corporations behind a bureaucratic state apparatus instead represents the degeneration of modern capitalism: where once it was associated with freedom, liberal democracy and pluralism, and contrasted with ‘authoritarian’ communist regimes, modern capitalism arguably works most effectively and efficiently when under the auspices of a centralised, technocratic state apparatus. That China remains keen to promote areas of digital ‘e-commerce’ and free-trade areas to reduce costs of international shipments and cross-border trade indicates that capitalistic imperatives still govern much of the productive process, in an ostensibly Hegelian synthesis of authoritarian politics and liberal economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the imperialistic nature of the Digital Silk Road, which involves putting countries into debt by proliferating infrastructural projects and making them dependent on loans from the Chinese State, mirrors tactics used after the 1970’s Third World debt crisis caused by the World Bank and the IMF. For instance, in 2017, 95% of Sri Lankan government spending went to paying off debt, much of which was issued to China. These foreign loans function as a means of subordinating neighbouring countries economically, facilitating Chinese access to natural resources and opening markets to offset domestic overproduction. The case of Chinese involvement in Africa is another example of how the neo-mercantilist formulations of the modern Chinese economy are not socialistic as some on the hard-right (in addition to a small minority of communists) claim; rather, it is reminiscent of European colonialism. Sino-African trade increased by $169 billion between the 1980’s and 2018, mainly composed of crude oil and agricultural products. Raw materials are converted into finished goods and resold to African nations at high prices, increasing their dependency on China. The monopolisation of data is a major part of this; &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepeninsulaqatar.com/article/27/02/2019/Egypt-to-host-Huawei-s-first-MENA-cloud-platform-Cairo&quot;&gt;Huawei opened its first cloud data centre in Egypt in February 2019&lt;/a&gt;, and Algeria and Tunisia continue to host Chinese tech firms intent on harvesting consumer data. In Morocco, ‘smart city’ Tangier Tech is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.globalconstructionreview.com/news/tangier-tech-city-plans-revived-selection-chinese-/&quot;&gt;soon to host 200 Chinese companies.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Mason, writing in &lt;em&gt;Postcapitalism: A Guide to Our Future&lt;/em&gt;, argued that “today, the main contradiction in modern capitalism is between the possibility of free, abundant socially produced goods, and a system of monopolies, banks and governments struggling to maintain, control of over power and information.”  The emergence of a bureaucratic, unaccountable Chinese Empire which seeks to monopolise and patent information can therefore be contextualised within a wider phenomenon: the attempts by capitalistic institutions to apply market dynamics to otherwise freely-exchangeable data. Information is a public good: it is non-rival and non-excludable, freely replicable and devoid of the scarcity that enables markets to capture and commodify it in the way that other things can be easily commodified. Therefore, it circumscribes the ability of markets to form prices; infinite supply means that prices will fall close to zero unless giant tech monopolies can maintain patents on information which artificially create scarcity. The function of the Chinese tech monopolies is to do precisely this: Huawei has issued 1,500 5G patents as of 2019, and Chinese companies own 36% of all 5G patents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This demonstrates what can be referred to in Marxist terms as a contradiction between the forces and relations of production. Karl Marx wrote that “from forms of development of the productive forces, these relations turn into their fetters,” a point clearly demonstrated by observing modern reality; the productive forces have developed to the point where we can share socially-produced information freely, yet market forces capture and privatise this information. The Chinese State’s attempts to combine economic and technological imperialism, shoring up hegemony on the world stage, have also allowed it to save capitalism from its own contradictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expansion of the social credit system, which has seen citizens submit personal data about their personal lives and shopping habits to the Chinese government in an attempt to gain a favourable rating, is emblematic of how the commodification of information entails separating data from people and diminishing the amount of control they have over confidential, personal information. The removal of direct access to information as a pretext to its subjection to market imperatives parallels the way in which 17th Century English peasants were deprived of direct access to their land holdings so that it could be privatised and contractually regulated by entrepreneurial landlords, a point succinctly summarised by Mark Andrejevic, who stated, “If land enclosure helped produce the spatial conditions for the exploitation of wage labor, digital enclosures enable the exploitation of information generated by users as they go about their daily lives.” The enclosure (via digital means) of what legal scholar James Ball refers to as the  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dhi.ac.uk/san/waysofbeing/data/citizenship-robson-andrejevic-2007.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“intangible commons of the mind”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; constantly extends the boundaries of what is available for patenting and copywriting, allowing a restrictive legal infrastructure determining “intellectual property rights” to accompany the new forms of alienation engendered by the privatisation and monopolisation of data. While this may seem to be a mere marketing strategy for companies to sell products based on already established information about consumers from their Google searches, the social credit system indicates that the implications are altogether more sinister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our present epoch is defined by the waning of the American Empire and the rise of Chinese hegemony, as the two powers compete in an ongoing technological Cold War that accompanies the already existing trade war. In 1980, US share of world income was 24.6%, but had fallen to 19.1% by 2011. China, by contrast, has seen a meteoric rise from 2.2% in 1980 to 14.4% in 2011. The United States, recognising this shift in the balance of power, has attempted to dissuade other countries from using Huawei to develop their 5G networks. Yet the Digital Silk Road has allowed China to establish itself as a world leader in exporting digital infrastructure, attempting to use this as a conduit for the maintenance of ‘sharp’ power, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pacforum.org/sites/default/files/issuesinsights_Vol19%20WP8FINAL.pdf&quot;&gt;“manipulation of ideas, political perceptions and electoral processes”.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Men make history, but not as they choose”,  stated Karl Marx in &lt;em&gt;The Eighteenth Brumaire of Louis Napoleon&lt;/em&gt;. Underlying forces and wider contexts determine the conditions that allow certain powers to establish geopolitical dominance at certain times. For the American Empire, financial power and military muscle forged a new American century in the aftermath of World War I, the nominally victorious Entente dependent upon American loans for many of the offensives of 1918, lying prostrate before America’s export-driven economic boom. For China, it is the collapse of globalisation, recurring crises of the neoliberal model, and the increasing importance of data that have heralded a new Chinese century, as the Digital Silk Road carves out a new sphere of influence. The pendulum has swung to the Far East, as with opened wallets and closed minds, we may all soon be subjects of Xi Jinping.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The squalid conditions of the Xinjiang region of Northwestern China, in which Uighur Muslims, Khazakhs and Uzbeks are forced to surrender DNA and blood samples, remain a stark reminder of the extent to which civil liberties can be assailed in the name of ‘counter-terrorism’. 47-year old Bakitali Nur, a fruit and vegetable exporter from Khargos, told Time magazine that he and seven other inmates were forced to sit still on plastic stools for seventeen consecutive hours as their movements were monitored by security cameras. In Xinjiang, 2.5 million citizens have their whereabouts tracked by CCTV whilst being subjected to a punitive social credit system that discourages behaviour not approved of by the Chinese State.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘Woke’ Capital: Pinkwashing Exploitation</title>
      <link href="/Pinkwashing-Exploitation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘Woke’ Capital: Pinkwashing Exploitation" />
      <published>2020-01-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Pinkwashing-Exploitation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Pinkwashing-Exploitation">&lt;p&gt;“What do we have to show for the billions spent on pink ribbon products? A lot of us are done with awareness. We want action.” - Karuna Jagger, Executive Director of Breast Cancer Action&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is no longer enough to simply sell a product. The percolation of market fundamentalism into every facet of life has blurred the distinction between our identities and our consumption habits, meaning that we now desire products that carry a deeper significance, i.e. a message about social justice. The result? A pernicious and contradictory phenomenon: Capital with a human face. ‘Woke’ Capitalism involves corporations cynically utilising socially progressive causes such as LGBTQ and women’s issues, or climate change, to sell their products while maintaining the same underlying structures of profit-maximisation and exploitation of workers and resources around the world, particularly in the global South. Moreover, in a post-2008 era of economic turmoil, ‘Woke Capital’ provides an opportunity for the Right to assert that large corporations are in fact, the tools of a left-wing elite that is hostile to the common man, and so doing, to downplay the culpability of capitalism itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘free’ market is not an entity that exists in a vacuum, independent of the social and cultural paradigms surrounding it. To consistently make profits and remain competitive in a crowded marketplace, businesses must appeal to the ever-changing social attitudes of consumers, and the growing acceptance of LGBTQ identity has provided an ideal marketing opportunity for large corporations. Pride parades festooned with the presence of multinational corporations are not uncommon in the modern day: Pharmaceuticals company Gilead sponsored New York Pride, despite having patented the HIV risk-reducing drug Truvada, causing some of the poorest people in the United States to die due to lack of access to it. LGBTQ Black men, who have a higher HIV rate than any other group in the United States, comprise just 9% of applicants for Truvada, demonstrating the effects of these barriers to entry. Although this is arguably one of the most galling examples of the hypocrisy of corporations who cynically feign awareness and progressivism while continuing the profiteering, it is by no means the only example. The establishment of monopoly control over production and distribution through patents is no aberration; it is a logical step for large corporations, and will continue for as long as the profit motive continues to be the dominant force in the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, former San Francisco 49ers Quarterback Colin Kaepernick became the face of Nike’s campaign, which celebrated the 30th anniversary of its’ ‘Just Do It’ slogan. The cooptation of Kaepernick’s protest against police brutality and the maltreatment of African-Americans is particularly striking given that it has come from Nike, a company that still employs Black and Brown workers at below poverty wages in the global South. Despite co-founder Phil Knight being forced to admit to using sweatshops and child labour in 1998 and to change Nike’s business practices, a fresh wave of recent accusations have impugned the company further. In Vietnam, where Nike employs 400,000 workers and has 91 factories, workers are being paid at wage rates that are only just over half of the living wage. In Indonesia, where Nike has 39 factories and around 200,000 workers, the wages paid to workers were $200 less than that which would be required to meet their basic needs. It is, therefore, unsurprising that Nike has earned the support of William Stepp of the libertarian Mises Institute, who has argued against the minimum wage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The response from corporations such as Nike, Ford and others to the climate crisis and increasing awareness of environmental issues is, perhaps, the most egregious illustration of their hypocrisy. Apple, for instance, displays its low carbon footprint as an example of its progressivism while outsourcing production to China, where &lt;a href=&quot;https://spectator.us/pursuit-woke-capital/&quot;&gt;greenhouse gases are pumped into the atmosphere at alarming rates.&lt;/a&gt; Nestle also promotes environmental sustainability on their website, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2017/jul/21/pepsico-unilever-and-nestle-accused-of-complicity-in-illegal-rainforest-destruction&quot;&gt;were accused of complicity in the illegal destruction of rainforests in Sumatra&lt;/a&gt;. The exacerbation of the conditions of already critically endangered species in the region is one of many consequences that large corporations’ vast economies of scale have on the environment, but environmentalism to them is merely a discardable fad that will generate revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pernicious impact of ‘Woke’ Capital goes beyond just its hypocrisy and continuation of exploitation; it affords the Right an opportunity to portray the Left as elites while exonerating themselves and obscuring the true problem: the underlying imperatives in the forces and relations of production. Why acknowledge that the aforementioned ‘woke’ corporations are simply doing what corporations have always done: appeal to consumers in the interests of short-term profits, when you could brand them as ideologically-motivated, left-wing, virtue signalling elites who despise ordinary people and their families? Indeed, this is exactly what Tucker Carlson is extremely effective at doing: arguing that 2019 is the year of the ‘woke’ billionaire, he has claimed that an unholy alliance had taken place between virtue-signalling billionaires and the ‘socialist’ Democratic Party. This tactic is quintessential to the reactionary Right, as the portrayal of the Left and the Billionaires being motivated by the same progressive, internationalist ideology makes it easier to appeal to ‘Middle America’, and to dissuade them from examining the root of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Hobsbawm, writing in his book &lt;em&gt;Age of Extremes&lt;/em&gt; about the rise of fascism, argued that one of the common themes in these movements was the resentment of “&lt;em&gt;the little man&lt;/em&gt;” in a society dominated by the interests of big business and organised labour. The reactionary Right, in an attempt to preserve the status quo in a time of economic collapse, would attempt to stave off forces of socialism and internationalism by portraying themselves as the allies of working people against the perceived unholy alliance between ‘the Left’ and big business. In Europe’s fascist States during the 1930’s, this was an important tool that brought such regimes to power. A concoction of privatisation, tax cuts for the wealthy and a bonfire of workers’ rights followed, demonstrating the true nature of their regimes. The recent attempts by Tucker Carlson to deflect from the culpability of the neoliberal system in an era of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/u-s-income-inequality-highest-level-50-years-economic-gap-n1058956&quot;&gt;rampant inequality&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hamiltonproject.org/assets/files/UnionsEA_Web_8.19.pdf&quot;&gt;limited bargaining power &lt;/a&gt;and &lt;a href=&quot;https://fas.org/sgp/crs/misc/R45090.pdf&quot;&gt;plummeting wages&lt;/a&gt; are clearly part of a similar ploy; arguing that the large corporations are acting in the interests of the Left increases Middle America’s hatred of socialism, and in doing so, prevents any substantive anti-capitalist case from being heard, thereby maintaining the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Woke Capital, therefore, absolves the reactionary Right of having to face the consequences of their own economic orthodoxy. The Right do not have to face the fact that mass immigration to Western nations is, in part, a result of unequal terms of trade that have subjected the local farming and small industries of global South nations to debilitating competition, forcing vast numbers of people to flee, if they can argue that immigration is a deliberate tool of ‘woke corporations’. Once again, the portrayal of corporate greed as a Leftist idea precludes any rigorous analysis of Capital from taking place, and reduces the factors precipitating mass immigration from material realities to abstract ideological forces. The consequent scapegoating and vilification of immigrants that characterises them as interlopers in Western societies, which parties across Europe and North America continue to engage in, allows the rich to get richer and maintain their power at the expense of the rest of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The veneer of altruism and inclusivity feigned by ‘progressive’ multinational corporations disappears with a cursory examination of their productive processes, which reveal that, at heart, their modus operandi is driven by the same unscrupulous exploitation of labour-power and resources that it always was. The rejection of liberal, faux-progressive corporatism and the bogus contention that Capitalism can be made any less ruthless or exploitative by dressing it up in rainbow colours is an important part of a genuine socialist ethos. Only a persuasive, comprehensive and thorough analysis of the contradictions of capitalism will allow the Left to fight back against the contention that ‘Woke’ Capitalism is in any way progressive, and to champion the cause of those who are most exploited by it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“What do we have to show for the billions spent on pink ribbon products? A lot of us are done with awareness. We want action.” - Karuna Jagger, Executive Director of Breast Cancer Action</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Labour’s Tale of Woe: Reflections on the British General Election</title>
      <link href="/Labour-s-Tale-of-Woe-Reflections-on-the-British-General-Election" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Labour's Tale of Woe: Reflections on the British General Election" />
      <published>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Labour-s-Tale-of-Woe-Reflections-on-the-British-General-Election</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Labour-s-Tale-of-Woe-Reflections-on-the-British-General-Election">&lt;p&gt;In last Thursday’s British general election, the Conservative Party won a resounding majority of 356 seats to Labour’s 203, in what proved to be the Labour Party’s worst election defeat since 1935. The Conservatives saw significant gains in Britain’s Leave-voting constituencies in the North East and the Midlands, as Boris Johnson’s promise to ‘get Brexit done’ clearly resonated with many voters in traditional Labour strongholds. The certainty of an exit from the EU, coupled with the SNP gaining 13 seats in Scotland including that of the Liberal Democrat leader Jo Swinson, has also left many contemplating the future of the Union and the probability of a Scottish secession. But the most striking aspect of the election was the collapse of the Labour Party, which lost 59 seats from their 2017 results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boris Johnson, in pledging not only to deliver Brexit but to increase public expenditure by £13.4 billion in 2020–2021, which would be the largest increase in spending in 15 years, clearly provided a theoretical break from the austerity policies and supply-side economics which had characterised the Conservatives’ previous administrations in the wake of the Financial Crisis, enabling him to win over voters in Labour strongholds. It is unclear, however, if this ‘One-Nation Conservative’ rhetoric will translate into policy, as Boris Johnson has voted consistently in favour of austerity policies since being returned as an MP in 2015. Moreover, it is entirely probable that having won a demonstrable majority, the Conservatives may use their relative unaccountability to continue the same cuts to income tax and spending that they were previously committed to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Labour, a schism between the Europhile, metropolitan, London-centric PLP and the Eurosceptic so-called ‘Red Wall’ of Northern, working class seats was the main source of their undoing. Labour lost 10.4% of the vote share in seats where 60% or more people voted Leave, as seats such as Sedgefield, Bolsover and Workington fell to the Conservatives. Dennis Skinner, a veteran Labour MP and former miner, lost his Bolsover seat after 49 years in Parliament. In 2017, when Labour had promised to honour the result of the referendum, they held 72 of the 100 constituencies in the most working class (C2DE) households. In 2019, this figure fell to 53, and the Conservatives increased their share from 13 to 31. Labour’s decision to cleave towards the centre to placate the Blairite elements of the Party was, therefore, an unmitigated catastrophe. Ian Lavery MP, who held onto his seat in Wansbeck in Northumberland by an unfathomably slender majority of just 800 votes, stated: “Ignore democracy and to be quite honest the consequences will come back and bite you up the backside.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many voters in the aforementioned deindustrialised Northern towns now beset by a dismal combination of unemployment and precarious, low-wage service sector work, the fact that Labour had failed to completely acknowledge their Eurosceptic stance eroded their faith in democracy. Devoid for the most part of media influence or capital, the vote was the only way of making their voices heard. Having been neglected by a London-centric party and a political consensus dominated for decades by financialisation, the City of London and an obsession with GDP as the sole indicator of the prosperity of the nation, they struck a lethal blow against those who purported but failed to represent them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perception of Jeremy Corbyn as an inadequate leader was another prevalent theme both on the doorstep and in mainstream political coverage throughout the election. Media coverage of Corbyn was relentlessly brutal. The virulent anti-Corbyn rhetoric even predated the election, as during the past 3 years, he has been referred to as a Czech spy, a Russian agent, an anti-semite and a Communist. It is undeniable that there are antisemitic elements within the Labour Party that Corbyn has been indecisive in removing, and that the British Left has a long and disgraceful history of indulging antisemitism, aptly described by August Bebel as “the socialism of fools”. Keir Hardie, the first ever Labour leader, blamed Jewish financial houses for the outbreak of the First World War. However, Corbyn himself has a long and understated history of opposing antisemitism. As far back as 1977, for example, Corbyn organised a counter-demonstration in defence of London’s Jewish community against 1,000 National Front members who attempted to march through Wood Green.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blairites and moderate voices within the Labour movement continue to portray this election as proof that it is left wing policies that are unpopular rather than the party’s Brexit stance and alienation of its core voting bloc. They suggest that the Labour Party must revert to a pro-corporate ideology, being at ease with privatisation, marketisation and a bellicose foreign policy. Yet this is directly contradicted by the available evidence: a 2017 YouGov poll found that 60% of the British public support renationalising the railways, 59% support taking water into public ownership, and 53% supported public ownership of the energy companies. 60% also back higher levels of taxation and spending. To argue that the statistical success of Tony Blair compared to Jeremy Corbyn represents a necessity to return to a Blairite brand of politics is to misunderstand that the political context has changed significantly since 1997. A global financial crash, the longest squeeze in wages since the Napoleonic Wars, and house prices rising to 7.8 times the amount of annual salaries demonstrate that a significantly greater amount of fiscal intervention is required to alleviate the crises of the present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The technocratic, Blairite conception of politics, which focuses entirely on winning power for its own sake and ignores the broader contexts in which new political and economic ideas come to the fore, has subsided. It has been proposed, therefore, that the future of the Labour Party is a combination of a culturally conservative, patriotic communitarianism with economic leftism of the kind espoused by figures such as Clement Attlee and George Lansbury. The resurgence of ‘Blue Labour’ attests to this. However, it must be acknowledged that Labour is a party that, for decades, has attempted to straddle a coalition of voters with fundamentally different outlooks and views of the world that may be considered irreconcilable. Socially-liberal graduates in Manchester and London, harbouring an instinctual aversion to the monarchy and the nation-state, on whom the Labour Party also depends, would be alienated by such a platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reconnect with its core vote, and to pull together its fractured coalition of voters, Labour will need a sustained and coordinated presence within areas of the country which perceive them to be London-centric and elitist, rather than merely turning up a week prior to the election and expecting votes. The neoliberal atomisation and individualism which characterise the present political era have torn asunder many community institutions which once fostered political dialogue and enabled people to become involved with politics. Therefore, much of the impetus must come from the grassroots elements of the party, with a priority placed on engaging in programmes such as the National Food Service and serving the concerns of local residents regarding ordinary issues such as education, housing and healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that the schisms and fissures within the Labour Party, and between the party and the electorate have been destructive and have led to the party’s near annihilation. There is a significant amount of soul-searching to be done, as the Labour Party desperately attempts to avoid decades in political oblivion. Reconnection with the party’s Northern heartlands will be a clear priority, as will grassroots level organising and education. But some of these ideological vicissitudes, such as the gap between voters in the Northern heartlands and those in the major cities, run so deep that it is difficult to see the party recovering from them.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In last Thursday’s British general election, the Conservative Party won a resounding majority of 356 seats to Labour’s 203, in what proved to be the Labour Party’s worst election defeat since 1935. The Conservatives saw significant gains in Britain’s Leave-voting constituencies in the North East and the Midlands, as Boris Johnson’s promise to ‘get Brexit done’ clearly resonated with many voters in traditional Labour strongholds. The certainty of an exit from the EU, coupled with the SNP gaining 13 seats in Scotland including that of the Liberal Democrat leader Jo Swinson, has also left many contemplating the future of the Union and the probability of a Scottish secession. But the most striking aspect of the election was the collapse of the Labour Party, which lost 59 seats from their 2017 results.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
