<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/abhishek.sancheti/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-08-04T11:00:51+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/abhishek.sancheti/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">CLO’s - The New Danger to Financial Markets?</title>
      <link href="/CLO" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CLO’s - The New Danger to  Financial Markets?" />
      <published>2019-04-25T14:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-25T14:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/CLO</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/CLO">&lt;p&gt;It’s funny to see the people who run financial markets so eagerly rushing into
committing the same mistake. Rushing for what? The same old, usual story. The
enticement of higher profits by undertaking higher risks provides the same high
to these investors as drugs do to teens. The global financial markets, which had
a near-death experience with CDOs just a decade ago, face a new product ready to
facilitate its total obliteration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The product in question this time is CLOs, or Collateralized Loan Obligations.
Believed to be a safer version of the infamous CDOs, or Collateralized Debt
Obligations, which was one of the main culprits of the 2008 Financial Crisis,
CLOs are already raising eyebrows all around the world. With the Governor of The
Bank of England Mark Carney and the former Fed Chairman Janet Yellen warning
about the potential risks, governments and the public are becoming wary.
However, it looks like these warnings are having no effect on banks and
institutional investors, for whom it was intended, as they continue buying CLOs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A CLO is very similar to a CDO which, as mentioned earlier, was the main reason
for the downfall of the financial markets in 2008. A CLO is basically a huge
collection of loans given out by a bank for sale to banks and institutional
investors in small tranches or groups. The benefit that an investor gains from
buying a CLO is that he gets to earn the entire interest from the loans in his
group or “tranche”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the amount of CLOs currently outstanding in the world crossing  $700
billion, and with $100 billion being added each year, the amount of CLOs has
already reached the levels of CDOs before the Financial Crisis of 2008. The
structuring of a CLO is the same as a CDO. The groups of CLOs are rated by
rating agencies on the basis of the overall creditworthiness and mortgaged
assets. The CLO groups are majorly rated into AA, BBB+, BBB- and so on. Within
each individual group, each specific tranche is also rated. Hence, in an AA
class group, there are tranches rated AA, BBB+, BBB- and so forth. The same goes
for the BBB+ class group and all the other groups which follow. The highest
tranche of the highest group is paid first, followed by all the tranches in the
highest group, which is followed by all the groups and their respective
tranches. Hence, the lowest class tranche of the lowest group is the riskiest,
and promises the highest return, whereas, the highest class tranche of the
highest group is the safest and promises least return. This allows investors to
invest in groups and tranches according to their risk appetite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way in which CLOs have differed from CDOs have been stricter banking
regulations and the type of loans which are being put into the groups. Instead
of having only housing loans, CLOs offer a wide variety of loans such as
automobiles, housing, retail and so on. Moreover, stricter regulations demand
that banks hold some proportion of each group of CLOs in order to ensure that to
earn a riskless profit, the banks are not just giving loans to any individual
they meet, which happened in the case of CDOs during the Financial Crisis of
2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proponents of CLOs point towards the double-digit returns, low default rates and
resilience to rising interest rates. With banks such as Credit Suisse, Nomura,
Barclays and JP Morgan Chase showing confidence in CLOs due to its high returns
and substantially low risks, the demand for CLOs is rising in international
markets. The industry is stressing the fact that CLOs are not as vulnerable to
rising interest rates as CDOs were a decade ago. They also stress the fact that
only 36 tranches among the 1500 plus CLOs rated by S&amp;amp;P Global Ratings have
defaulted since 1994.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are downfalls. Investors assume that the portfolios are safer as
they are better diversified. But, diversification of portfolios has led to them
being made of fewer and larger loans, which increases concentration risk. These
leveraged loans are highly sensitive to economic conditions, with many loans
defaulting as soon as the economic conditions take a downturn. The condition
will be particularly adverse for Japanese banks, which have bought 75% of AAA
tranches and one-third of all CLOs, finance their operations by borrowing from
international markets. Losses can lead to difficulties in continuing operations,
which in turn may lead to a liquidity squeeze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of a downturn, the CLOs pose a risk of creating adverse feedback
loops. Banks will be stuck with unsold loans clogging up inventories due to a
decrease in demand. Falling prices and tightening credit availability will cause
credit markets to seize up. Tighter credit will feed into the real economy
triggering losses, selling and price declines. Fears about the financial
positions of banks and investors will create havoc as depositors refuse to fund
banks and investors demand their money back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, it is clear that governments need to set in motion regulations and a
robust framework on how to go about dealing with CLOs. This is extremely
necessary as everyone today is accepting the fact that CLOs are a potentially
dangerous item capable of causing devastating chaos in the international
markets. Still, banks and institutional investors are pouring money into this
product with the hopes of higher returns from the higher risks they undertake.
It is clear that CLOs have the capability to topple the global financial markets
if it spirals out of control. Therefore, with the world talking of another
financial crisis, the question that needs to be answered is will it be the
phoenix of CDOs that proves to be the catalyst? The danger that currently
beholds us is that if we keep allowing investment junkies to get their
risk-fuelled fix, it will be the rest of us left to pick up the tab if the
international financial system enters rehab.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhishek Sancheti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It’s funny to see the people who run financial markets so eagerly rushing into committing the same mistake. Rushing for what? The same old, usual story. The enticement of higher profits by undertaking higher risks provides the same high to these investors as drugs do to teens. The global financial markets, which had a near-death experience with CDOs just a decade ago, face a new product ready to facilitate its total obliteration. The product in question this time is CLOs, or Collateralized Loan Obligations. Believed to be a safer version of the infamous CDOs, or Collateralized Debt Obligations, which was one of the main culprits of the 2008 Financial Crisis, CLOs are already raising eyebrows all around the world. With the Governor of The Bank of England Mark Carney and the former Fed Chairman Janet Yellen warning about the potential risks, governments and the public are becoming wary. However, it looks like these warnings are having no effect on banks and institutional investors, for whom it was intended, as they continue buying CLOs. A CLO is very similar to a CDO which, as mentioned earlier, was the main reason for the downfall of the financial markets in 2008. A CLO is basically a huge collection of loans given out by a bank for sale to banks and institutional investors in small tranches or groups. The benefit that an investor gains from buying a CLO is that he gets to earn the entire interest from the loans in his group or “tranche”. With the amount of CLOs currently outstanding in the world crossing  $700 billion, and with $100 billion being added each year, the amount of CLOs has already reached the levels of CDOs before the Financial Crisis of 2008. The structuring of a CLO is the same as a CDO. The groups of CLOs are rated by rating agencies on the basis of the overall creditworthiness and mortgaged assets. The CLO groups are majorly rated into AA, BBB+, BBB- and so on. Within each individual group, each specific tranche is also rated. Hence, in an AA class group, there are tranches rated AA, BBB+, BBB- and so forth. The same goes for the BBB+ class group and all the other groups which follow. The highest tranche of the highest group is paid first, followed by all the tranches in the highest group, which is followed by all the groups and their respective tranches. Hence, the lowest class tranche of the lowest group is the riskiest, and promises the highest return, whereas, the highest class tranche of the highest group is the safest and promises least return. This allows investors to invest in groups and tranches according to their risk appetite. The only way in which CLOs have differed from CDOs have been stricter banking regulations and the type of loans which are being put into the groups. Instead of having only housing loans, CLOs offer a wide variety of loans such as automobiles, housing, retail and so on. Moreover, stricter regulations demand that banks hold some proportion of each group of CLOs in order to ensure that to earn a riskless profit, the banks are not just giving loans to any individual they meet, which happened in the case of CDOs during the Financial Crisis of 2008. Proponents of CLOs point towards the double-digit returns, low default rates and resilience to rising interest rates. With banks such as Credit Suisse, Nomura, Barclays and JP Morgan Chase showing confidence in CLOs due to its high returns and substantially low risks, the demand for CLOs is rising in international markets. The industry is stressing the fact that CLOs are not as vulnerable to rising interest rates as CDOs were a decade ago. They also stress the fact that only 36 tranches among the 1500 plus CLOs rated by S&amp;amp;P Global Ratings have defaulted since 1994. However, there are downfalls. Investors assume that the portfolios are safer as they are better diversified. But, diversification of portfolios has led to them being made of fewer and larger loans, which increases concentration risk. These leveraged loans are highly sensitive to economic conditions, with many loans defaulting as soon as the economic conditions take a downturn. The condition will be particularly adverse for Japanese banks, which have bought 75% of AAA tranches and one-third of all CLOs, finance their operations by borrowing from international markets. Losses can lead to difficulties in continuing operations, which in turn may lead to a liquidity squeeze. In the case of a downturn, the CLOs pose a risk of creating adverse feedback loops. Banks will be stuck with unsold loans clogging up inventories due to a decrease in demand. Falling prices and tightening credit availability will cause credit markets to seize up. Tighter credit will feed into the real economy triggering losses, selling and price declines. Fears about the financial positions of banks and investors will create havoc as depositors refuse to fund banks and investors demand their money back. Hence, it is clear that governments need to set in motion regulations and a robust framework on how to go about dealing with CLOs. This is extremely necessary as everyone today is accepting the fact that CLOs are a potentially dangerous item capable of causing devastating chaos in the international markets. Still, banks and institutional investors are pouring money into this product with the hopes of higher returns from the higher risks they undertake. It is clear that CLOs have the capability to topple the global financial markets if it spirals out of control. Therefore, with the world talking of another financial crisis, the question that needs to be answered is will it be the phoenix of CDOs that proves to be the catalyst? The danger that currently beholds us is that if we keep allowing investment junkies to get their risk-fuelled fix, it will be the rest of us left to pick up the tab if the international financial system enters rehab.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">“HELICOPTER” MONEY: The Way Ahead?</title>
      <link href="/Helicopter-Money" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“HELICOPTER” MONEY: The Way Ahead?" />
      <published>2019-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Helicopter-Money</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Helicopter-Money">&lt;p&gt;Suppose, a developed economy is experiencing a period of stagnation coupled with really low-interest rates and the government approaches the central bank to devise a way to spur spending and output in the economy. The central bank tries the conventional way of reducing interest rates to stimulate spending, inflation, growth and output but it falls flat as the interest rates were already very close to zero. Hence, the changes in the interest rates were not substantial enough to bring about a major change in output and spending. Worried, the central bank finds itself in a tough spot with limited monetary options to get out of this fix, none of which are effective. According to Friedman, the only solution would be to fly a helicopter above a community, literally dropping 100 dollar notes out of the sky for the general public to freely spend on commodities and services, therefore stimulating spending, output, and growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially developed as a classroom theory, ‘Helicopter Money’ refers to direct money transfers, virtual or cash, from the central bank to the general public with an aim of increasing spending, output, inflation and growth in an economy trapped in stagnation coupled with a liquidity crisis. The tool remained as a textbook chapter for most of the latter part of the 20th century. However, it was brought to light in 2002 by the then Fed governor Ben Bernanke who considered it as a suitable option to revive the US as well as Japan from the deflation which hit most developed countries at the beginning of the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, how does ‘Helicopter Money’ succeed when all other monetary methods fail to stimulate expenditure and output in the economy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that quantitative easing, rate cuts and other monetary methods generally adopted by a central bank fail when the interest rates hover around zero. This is because when the interest rates are near zero, a further rate cut, buying up of government bonds or negative interest rates would not increase the money supply in the economy sufficiently to increase spending. Moreover, most of these traditional financial methods have already been used and proven inefficient in various developed economies at various points in time, such as Japan in the 1990’s and the US in the early 2000’s. Hence, the only method which still remains unused is the Helicopter Drop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helicopter Drop has been hypothetically proven to stimulate demand in the economy. As the measure requires a one-time direct cash transfer to the general public, it is sure to stimulate spending. This is because the money supply in the economy increases by the amount of cash transferred by the central bank to the public which then increases the purchasing power of the individual. Naturally, with a higher purchasing power, spending would increase by the MPC (Marginal Propensity to Consume) amount in the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prospect of a Helicopter Drop is rather fascinating and sounds too good to be true. Realistically, Helicopter Drops and similar stimulus pose many questions to the central bank, from accounting to distribution. In spite of logistical issues such as how to disperse the amount equitably among the general public, another question which comes up is how will the central bank account for these Helicopter Drops?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the cases of traditional quantitative easing methods, such as open market operations, it is very easy for the central bank to account how much high-powered money has been circulated in the economy. As each accounting transaction has two sides, a debit and a credit, the central bank has to ensure that each accounting debit has its respective credit entry as well. In the case of open market operations, the amount of bonds bought from the market is an increase in the assets of the central bank, which is a debit entry. While the money circulated in the economy is a reduction in the assets of the central bank, hence a credit entry. However, in the case of Helicopter Drop, there is only a reduction in the assets of the central bank. This means that there is only a credit side to this entry, which violates the fundamental principle of accounting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To counter this, the central bank assumes that it has bought perpetual bonds from the market which have zero interest coupons on it. Basically, this means that The Central Banks assumes that for the money circulated among the general public as helicopter drops, it has bought from the market bonds which are irredeemable for perpetuity and which do not pay interest at all. This ensures that there is a debit side to the accounting entry for Helicopter Drops and that the fundamental principles of accounting are not violated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this solves the issue of accounting, it raises another important question. Nowadays, most economists are concerned with whether a monetary method is reversible or not. In the case of traditional monetary methods such as rate cuts, open market operations, and reserve ratios, all are reversible. Rates and reserve ratios can be increased or decreased as per the situation as the central bank can always buy or sell back government bonds in the market. However, Helicopter Drops are irreversible in nature. That is, once a drop is made, neither its effects on the economy nor the drop itself can be reversed. This limitation makes the economists weary and they argue as a normative proposition, that these drops, if used, should be at most used as a stimulus package to increase one-time spending, output, growth, and inflation in the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inconvertible fiat currency is unique in the fact that it has a positive exchange value against commodities as it can be produced at essentially zero cost. Therefore, there is always a potential temptation for central banks to undertake such action by the virtue of printing more and more currency. However, one needs to keep a check on the amount of currency circulated in the economy to ensure that hyperinflation does not occur and the intrinsic value of all commodities do not fall to zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helicopter Drops are dangerous as they conjure up the illusion that monetary magic can whip up real goods and services out of nothing. If this notion holds among those who influence monetary policy, then rational policymaking would become literally impossible. This is because policymakers would become so addicted to Helicopter Money that the overissue of fiat currency would only be dealt with a larger issue of currency until the economy collapses. Therefore, there is a good reason why Helicopter Money has not been used as a monetary policy tool but kept as a classroom experiment. And if Milton Friedman would have been alive today, he would have been horrified at what the Keynesians, the Classicals and the world at large have done to his innocent classroom experiment.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhishek Sancheti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Suppose, a developed economy is experiencing a period of stagnation coupled with really low-interest rates and the government approaches the central bank to devise a way to spur spending and output in the economy. The central bank tries the conventional way of reducing interest rates to stimulate spending, inflation, growth and output but it falls flat as the interest rates were already very close to zero. Hence, the changes in the interest rates were not substantial enough to bring about a major change in output and spending. Worried, the central bank finds itself in a tough spot with limited monetary options to get out of this fix, none of which are effective. According to Friedman, the only solution would be to fly a helicopter above a community, literally dropping 100 dollar notes out of the sky for the general public to freely spend on commodities and services, therefore stimulating spending, output, and growth.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">“Ti Amo Italia”, the EU’s Rhetoric?</title>
      <link href="/the-EU-Rhetoric" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Ti Amo Italia”, the EU's Rhetoric?" />
      <published>2019-03-15T15:18:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-15T15:18:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/the-EU-Rhetoric</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/the-EU-Rhetoric">&lt;p&gt;Although the rest of the world may think so, Brexit and Greece are not the only
problems which are troubling the European Union right now. While there is no
denying the fact that the Union has seen many ups-and-downs in its 26-year
history and has averted many crises, it now stands at a juncture where its
future looks bleak, at best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From getting the upper-hand in the Brexit negotiations to bailing out Greece,
the European Union saw to it that it tackled both these headaches. On one hand,
it has punished Britain for leaving the Union while on the other hand, it has
somewhat saved the Euro and the Grecian economy from going haywire. At the
moment, however, it is concerned about the third largest economy of the Union
which is at the verge of failure even though it was branded as “too big to
fail”. This economy, called Italy, is marred with high levels of unemployment
and unsustainable levels of debt. If it fails, no matter what measures Paris and
Berlin may take, the European Union would most probably break up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Italy’s condition was not always like that. The economy had been doing
pretty good, growing at a respectable pace of 4% up until the global financial
crisis of 2008. The Italians were taking full advantage of the available cheap
credit and were borrowing freely and heavily from the market to finance their
developmental and infrastructural projects. Before anyone could know, the total
debt of Italy was already more than 100% of the GDP. Even though the situation
was alarming, the banks and investors had confidence in Italy paying off its
debt as its economy was prospering and taking full advantage of the boom.
However, when the financial crisis of 2008 hit the Italians, it hit them hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economy was pushed into a recession and since then, Italy has lost 6-7% of
its GDP, the largest loss in the European Union after Greece. When it tried to
recover, the 2011 debt crisis hit back, with the investors losing confidence in
the Euro. What saved Italy from bankruptcy and the European Union from
destruction was Mario Draghi, the Italian President of the European Central
Bank. He famously stated, “I will do whatever it takes me to preserve the Euro.
And believe me, it will be enough.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His decision of printing money to buy up government bonds in the European Union,
reluctantly supported by Germans, is what averted the crisis and pushed it back
further. However, the debt crisis and the lost confidence of investors in the
Euro led to the ousting of the then Prime Minister of Italy, Silvio Berlusconi
in the year 2011. Since then, political instability has also added to the woes
of the Italian economy as the country did not have an elected Prime Minister
till the end of 2018. The present government is being headed by Giuseppe Conte
and is a coalition of the extreme-left Five Star Movement and the extreme-right
League. To add to that instability, the government is currently facing a dilemma
between the European Union and its citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real GDP of Italy is still below what it was before the financial crisis of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The per capita GDP is lower than what it was two decades ago. Industrial
production is down by 25%, which has led to massive outbursts of unemployment.
Currently, the official unemployment rate in Italy stands at 10%. However, youth
unemployment is currently between 30-35%. In South Italy, the situation is
absolutely catastrophic with devastating unemployment rates of 60-70%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly speaking, the Italian government does not have money to finance projects
for employment generation. Italy’s sovereign debt stands at $2.1 trillion and
it pays $80 billion as interest each year. Hence, the investors are losing
confidence in Italian government bonds, which is reflected in Moody’s rating of
Baa3, its lowest investment grade above junk status. This has made the cost of
raising debt far too costly for the government of Italy as the difference
between the rate of interest of Italian bonds and German bonds has already
breached the 300-point mark, which is a sign of concern for Italy right now.
This is why foreign investors are selling their Italian bonds like hot cakes in
the market and getting the hell out of the country as they fear Italy to be the
next Greece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason for the empty pockets of the government is shadow economy and tax
evasion. 30% of the economy is unaccounted for, which leads to the government
losing out on a huge amount of tax revenue. Moreover, low labour productivity
coupled with minimum wages makes Italy unattractive as a manufacturing hub. To
add to this, the population of Italy is ageing. Each woman on an average
produces only 1.3 children which has led to the rapid ageing of the Italian
population. This means a higher expenditure for the government on social
security and lower productivity of the citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of its empty pockets, the left-right government of Italy has proposed
ambitious plans for the restructuring and redevelopment of the economy and
various employment generation programmes for its citizens in its budget of 2019.
This led to the fiscal deficit of the government to rise to 2.4% of the GDP
which is beyond the accepted limits of 2% of the European Union. Hence, the
European Union Commission asked the Italian government to reduce its fiscal
deficit in order to comply with the EU norms or face severe penalties of up to
0.5% of the GDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, doing so would mean the government would have to cut out on employment
generation programmes or drop some of its plans for the redevelopment of the
economy. This would lead to its citizens going through at least one more year of
unemployment and low standards of living. It is clear that the Italian
government can choose either of the two. Either its citizens or the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Negotiations and talks with the European Union Commission and its President
Jean-Claude Juncker haven’t resulted in any resolutions or compromises from
either side. With both sides in a deadlock, this clash could easily be a recipe
for a disaster. Jean-Claude Juncker has expressed his feelings by voicing his
thoughts, “&lt;em&gt;Ti Amo Italia&lt;/em&gt;” and promising to do something about the situation.
However, this looks more like a crowd-pleasing, fake promise in the form of
rhetoric from the Commission President. Matteo Salvini, Italy’s most powerful
politician, has voiced the government’s anger on the stance of the ECB and the
EU on this matter, stating that “&lt;em&gt;the enemies of Europe are those barricaded in
the bunker of Brussels&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This clash between Italy’s populists and the EU’s imperialists could all too
easily set a chain of motions which would lead to far bigger problems for the
EU. This time, the damage would be greater than Brexit or Greece, or both
combined. All that is required is one decision of the government, one investor
losing confidence or one bank failing. With the economists already predicting a
global financial crisis, would Italy be the one to start it all?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhishek Sancheti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Although the rest of the world may think so, Brexit and Greece are not the only problems which are troubling the European Union right now. While there is no denying the fact that the Union has seen many ups-and-downs in its 26-year history and has averted many crises, it now stands at a juncture where its future looks bleak, at best. From getting the upper-hand in the Brexit negotiations to bailing out Greece, the European Union saw to it that it tackled both these headaches. On one hand, it has punished Britain for leaving the Union while on the other hand, it has somewhat saved the Euro and the Grecian economy from going haywire. At the moment, however, it is concerned about the third largest economy of the Union which is at the verge of failure even though it was branded as “too big to fail”. This economy, called Italy, is marred with high levels of unemployment and unsustainable levels of debt. If it fails, no matter what measures Paris and Berlin may take, the European Union would most probably break up. But Italy’s condition was not always like that. The economy had been doing pretty good, growing at a respectable pace of 4% up until the global financial crisis of 2008. The Italians were taking full advantage of the available cheap credit and were borrowing freely and heavily from the market to finance their developmental and infrastructural projects. Before anyone could know, the total debt of Italy was already more than 100% of the GDP. Even though the situation was alarming, the banks and investors had confidence in Italy paying off its debt as its economy was prospering and taking full advantage of the boom. However, when the financial crisis of 2008 hit the Italians, it hit them hard. The economy was pushed into a recession and since then, Italy has lost 6-7% of its GDP, the largest loss in the European Union after Greece. When it tried to recover, the 2011 debt crisis hit back, with the investors losing confidence in the Euro. What saved Italy from bankruptcy and the European Union from destruction was Mario Draghi, the Italian President of the European Central Bank. He famously stated, “I will do whatever it takes me to preserve the Euro. And believe me, it will be enough.” His decision of printing money to buy up government bonds in the European Union, reluctantly supported by Germans, is what averted the crisis and pushed it back further. However, the debt crisis and the lost confidence of investors in the Euro led to the ousting of the then Prime Minister of Italy, Silvio Berlusconi in the year 2011. Since then, political instability has also added to the woes of the Italian economy as the country did not have an elected Prime Minister till the end of 2018. The present government is being headed by Giuseppe Conte and is a coalition of the extreme-left Five Star Movement and the extreme-right League. To add to that instability, the government is currently facing a dilemma between the European Union and its citizens. The real GDP of Italy is still below what it was before the financial crisis of The per capita GDP is lower than what it was two decades ago. Industrial production is down by 25%, which has led to massive outbursts of unemployment. Currently, the official unemployment rate in Italy stands at 10%. However, youth unemployment is currently between 30-35%. In South Italy, the situation is absolutely catastrophic with devastating unemployment rates of 60-70%. Frankly speaking, the Italian government does not have money to finance projects for employment generation. Italy’s sovereign debt stands at $2.1 trillion and it pays $80 billion as interest each year. Hence, the investors are losing confidence in Italian government bonds, which is reflected in Moody’s rating of Baa3, its lowest investment grade above junk status. This has made the cost of raising debt far too costly for the government of Italy as the difference between the rate of interest of Italian bonds and German bonds has already breached the 300-point mark, which is a sign of concern for Italy right now. This is why foreign investors are selling their Italian bonds like hot cakes in the market and getting the hell out of the country as they fear Italy to be the next Greece. Another reason for the empty pockets of the government is shadow economy and tax evasion. 30% of the economy is unaccounted for, which leads to the government losing out on a huge amount of tax revenue. Moreover, low labour productivity coupled with minimum wages makes Italy unattractive as a manufacturing hub. To add to this, the population of Italy is ageing. Each woman on an average produces only 1.3 children which has led to the rapid ageing of the Italian population. This means a higher expenditure for the government on social security and lower productivity of the citizens. In spite of its empty pockets, the left-right government of Italy has proposed ambitious plans for the restructuring and redevelopment of the economy and various employment generation programmes for its citizens in its budget of 2019. This led to the fiscal deficit of the government to rise to 2.4% of the GDP which is beyond the accepted limits of 2% of the European Union. Hence, the European Union Commission asked the Italian government to reduce its fiscal deficit in order to comply with the EU norms or face severe penalties of up to 0.5% of the GDP. However, doing so would mean the government would have to cut out on employment generation programmes or drop some of its plans for the redevelopment of the economy. This would lead to its citizens going through at least one more year of unemployment and low standards of living. It is clear that the Italian government can choose either of the two. Either its citizens or the EU. Negotiations and talks with the European Union Commission and its President Jean-Claude Juncker haven’t resulted in any resolutions or compromises from either side. With both sides in a deadlock, this clash could easily be a recipe for a disaster. Jean-Claude Juncker has expressed his feelings by voicing his thoughts, “Ti Amo Italia” and promising to do something about the situation. However, this looks more like a crowd-pleasing, fake promise in the form of rhetoric from the Commission President. Matteo Salvini, Italy’s most powerful politician, has voiced the government’s anger on the stance of the ECB and the EU on this matter, stating that “the enemies of Europe are those barricaded in the bunker of Brussels.” This clash between Italy’s populists and the EU’s imperialists could all too easily set a chain of motions which would lead to far bigger problems for the EU. This time, the damage would be greater than Brexit or Greece, or both combined. All that is required is one decision of the government, one investor losing confidence or one bank failing. With the economists already predicting a global financial crisis, would Italy be the one to start it all?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Micro Economies: Big Challenges and Small Opportunities</title>
      <link href="/Micro-Economies" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Micro Economies: Big Challenges and Small Opportunities" />
      <published>2019-03-08T23:30:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-08T23:30:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Micro-Economies</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Micro-Economies">&lt;p&gt;Niue (a small island nation in the Pacific Ocean) has a population even less
than the number of students studying in the Shri Ram College of Commerce,
University of Delhi. According to the World Bank, all economies with a
population of less than 0.5 million are considered to be “micro.” At present,
there are 29 such countries which constitute around 15% of the total number of
countries in the world. They are usually found together in groups and are
prevalent in three regions: the Caribbean, the Pacific, and Africa. Despite
their spread across the world, they have negligible say in the functioning of
the world economy. And this article is an attempt to understand the economic
systems of the ‘subaltern’ countries of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These economies (also called micro-economies) are either landlocked countries or
island nations, mostly present in the middle of nowhere. In either case, they
are isolated from the ‘markets’. This increases the cost of transportation as
the goods either have to travel long distances over oceans or through several
countries. This increases the overall cost of production which makes the goods
produced in these countries unattractive in international markets, and imports
costly. As a result, exports in the commodity sector is low in these economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Micro-economies have limited labour supply in the market. A labourer is expected
to perform several duties which leads to the overburdening of work. This reduces
labour productivity and labourers are unable to specialise in one kind of work.
Thus, the economy cannot receive the benefits of specialisation and division of
labour. Contrary to enjoying economies of scale, micro-economies face
‘&lt;em&gt;diseconomies of size’&lt;/em&gt; due to low demand and high production costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very evidently, micro-economies are unattractive for new market entrants. Hence,
these markets are generally a monopoly or an oligopoly, which provide a limited
range of products and services at high costs. High costs, in turn, lead to
poverty and large income inequalities. This can be substantiated from the fact
that countries like Lesotho, Guinea-Bissau, Gambia, Gabon, Suriname have more
than 40% of their total population living below the internationally accepted
poverty line of $1.90 per day. Limited production also leads to extremely low
GNP per capita: Comoros, Gambia, Guinea-Bissau and Sao Tome and Principe have a
GNP per capita of less than $500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Production is not the only area where economies of scale benefit a country. It
is seen that economies of scale greatly benefits an economy when it comes to
providing social security and creating social and economic infrastructure, as
well. A country with a huge population and a higher number of taxpayers has huge
amounts of money to spend on infrastructure. The cost of social security, as
well as social and economic infrastructure, is spread over a larger population.
This reduces the cost incurred per person for providing these facilities. In the
case of small economies, the population, as well as the number of taxpayers, is
low. Hence, the governments of these countries have almost no money to spend on
building and developing economic infrastructures such as highways and roadways,
and social infrastructures like schools and hospitals. All this ensures foreign
investment never comes into these countries, creating a &lt;em&gt;chakravyuh&lt;/em&gt; (vicious cycle) of poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With limited production capacities and little diversification, micro-economies
are generally capable of specialising in the production of one good or service,
in which they have an advantage over other economies. Due to the low population,
the demand for their commodities is low and limited. This means that they are
ready to export the commodity in which they have a competitive advantage over
the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of these economies are also highly dependent on tourism. This is evident
from the fact that tourism constitutes more than 50% in Fiji and more than 40%
in Vanuatu and the Caribbean States as part of their total exports. In fact,
imports and exports combined constitute more than 100% of the GDP of these
countries. But this high degree of openness also makes it highly vulnerable to
international events and shocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their vulnerability can be seen as how these economies developed at staggering
paces of more than 8% per annum before 2008. But, as soon as the 2008 financial
crisis hit, the income from tourism sector plummeted rapidly. This had such an
impact on the economies that these countries grew at -1% to 0% for the next two
years. Vulnerability also makes income more volatile. It is seen that the
standard deviation of the real per capita GDP growth is more than 9. This means
that there can be an average of 9% change per annum in their per capita GDP, as
compared to the world average of 3.2%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These economies also function as parasites. Just like parasites feed upon the
parent trees, these economies feed and depend upon a large economy which is
beside them. The Caribbean States depend upon Mexico and the US, the African
island nations in the Indian Ocean depend upon India, and those in the Pacific
depend upon Australia and New Zealand. Most of their trade (over 90%) is carried
out with these large economies and in most cases, they take up their currency as
well. Therefore, how these large economies fare in the global market decides the
fate of these micro-economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these ‘parent economies’ seldom take interest in investing in their
children. Hence, micro-economies turn towards the International Monetary Fund,
the International Development Association and various other regional and
international development banks for grants and unilateral advances for
developmental funding. These grants go a long way in helping micro-economies
provide their citizens with basic necessities. Research suggests that these
grants have helped reduce poverty levels by around 2-5% in different
micro-economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the recent challenges that these countries face is global warming and
increased danger of disasters. As most of these countries are islands or chains
of islands, they are just metres above sea level. The rising sea level and
the increased frequency of natural disasters has increased the risk of complete
disappearance of these island nations. Adequate disaster management is
necessary, which requires funds. Owing to lack of funds, these countries have to
look towards the international community and the United Nations for their
sustenance and to equip them with various techniques of disaster risk
management. &lt;em&gt;Debt bells ringing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of having so many problems, micro-economies have some advantages as
well. As most of these small economies are a group of islands, they have access
to huge amounts of the ocean as their territory. Thus, these economies have
Exclusive Economic Zones (EEZ’s) in the oceans. These economies usually grant
foreign multinational corporations permission for fishing and extract resources
from the EEZs against a charge. This has become one of the main sources of
income, apart from allowing military bases of other countries to be set up on
their territory (China and India are watching closely).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these economies also serve as tax havens for the rich billionaires and
multinational corporations. They have very lax to no tax laws. The most
prominent example would be of Cayman Islands (population - 23,000), which by the
mid-1990’s, became the world’s fifth largest banking centre measured by
deposits. There are more than 560 banks registered in this micro-nation,
including major accounting, audit and law firms. The Caymans are the ideal tax
haven as they provide “tax efficient asset protection”. There are no taxes, no
exchange controls and no threat to the ‘confidentiality’ of deposits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Alberto Alesina said in his book &lt;em&gt;Size of Nations&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Whether country size matters for economic prosperity depends on a country’s
degree of economic integration with the rest of the world.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, these economies too, have to integrate with the world economy if they
wish to develop and prosper. They cannot depend on a single economy or a single
commodity for their development. Maldives and Fiji are two micro-economies which
have seen tremendous growth in these recent years after opening up their
economies to the world. They are not totally dependent on their regional powers
or a single commodity for trade. However, they are still part of the exception
than the norm. Other micro-economies too can look up to them, and try, develop,
progress and finally contribute to the global economy. Recognising the existence
of microeconomics, and understanding their nuanced problems, will go a long way
in bringing a change.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhishek Sancheti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Niue (a small island nation in the Pacific Ocean) has a population even less than the number of students studying in the Shri Ram College of Commerce, University of Delhi. According to the World Bank, all economies with a population of less than 0.5 million are considered to be “micro.” At present, there are 29 such countries which constitute around 15% of the total number of countries in the world. They are usually found together in groups and are prevalent in three regions: the Caribbean, the Pacific, and Africa. Despite their spread across the world, they have negligible say in the functioning of the world economy. And this article is an attempt to understand the economic systems of the ‘subaltern’ countries of the world. These economies (also called micro-economies) are either landlocked countries or island nations, mostly present in the middle of nowhere. In either case, they are isolated from the ‘markets’. This increases the cost of transportation as the goods either have to travel long distances over oceans or through several countries. This increases the overall cost of production which makes the goods produced in these countries unattractive in international markets, and imports costly. As a result, exports in the commodity sector is low in these economies. Micro-economies have limited labour supply in the market. A labourer is expected to perform several duties which leads to the overburdening of work. This reduces labour productivity and labourers are unable to specialise in one kind of work. Thus, the economy cannot receive the benefits of specialisation and division of labour. Contrary to enjoying economies of scale, micro-economies face ‘diseconomies of size’ due to low demand and high production costs. Very evidently, micro-economies are unattractive for new market entrants. Hence, these markets are generally a monopoly or an oligopoly, which provide a limited range of products and services at high costs. High costs, in turn, lead to poverty and large income inequalities. This can be substantiated from the fact that countries like Lesotho, Guinea-Bissau, Gambia, Gabon, Suriname have more than 40% of their total population living below the internationally accepted poverty line of $1.90 per day. Limited production also leads to extremely low GNP per capita: Comoros, Gambia, Guinea-Bissau and Sao Tome and Principe have a GNP per capita of less than $500. Production is not the only area where economies of scale benefit a country. It is seen that economies of scale greatly benefits an economy when it comes to providing social security and creating social and economic infrastructure, as well. A country with a huge population and a higher number of taxpayers has huge amounts of money to spend on infrastructure. The cost of social security, as well as social and economic infrastructure, is spread over a larger population. This reduces the cost incurred per person for providing these facilities. In the case of small economies, the population, as well as the number of taxpayers, is low. Hence, the governments of these countries have almost no money to spend on building and developing economic infrastructures such as highways and roadways, and social infrastructures like schools and hospitals. All this ensures foreign investment never comes into these countries, creating a chakravyuh (vicious cycle) of poverty. With limited production capacities and little diversification, micro-economies are generally capable of specialising in the production of one good or service, in which they have an advantage over other economies. Due to the low population, the demand for their commodities is low and limited. This means that they are ready to export the commodity in which they have a competitive advantage over the rest of the world. Many of these economies are also highly dependent on tourism. This is evident from the fact that tourism constitutes more than 50% in Fiji and more than 40% in Vanuatu and the Caribbean States as part of their total exports. In fact, imports and exports combined constitute more than 100% of the GDP of these countries. But this high degree of openness also makes it highly vulnerable to international events and shocks. Their vulnerability can be seen as how these economies developed at staggering paces of more than 8% per annum before 2008. But, as soon as the 2008 financial crisis hit, the income from tourism sector plummeted rapidly. This had such an impact on the economies that these countries grew at -1% to 0% for the next two years. Vulnerability also makes income more volatile. It is seen that the standard deviation of the real per capita GDP growth is more than 9. This means that there can be an average of 9% change per annum in their per capita GDP, as compared to the world average of 3.2%. These economies also function as parasites. Just like parasites feed upon the parent trees, these economies feed and depend upon a large economy which is beside them. The Caribbean States depend upon Mexico and the US, the African island nations in the Indian Ocean depend upon India, and those in the Pacific depend upon Australia and New Zealand. Most of their trade (over 90%) is carried out with these large economies and in most cases, they take up their currency as well. Therefore, how these large economies fare in the global market decides the fate of these micro-economies. However, these ‘parent economies’ seldom take interest in investing in their children. Hence, micro-economies turn towards the International Monetary Fund, the International Development Association and various other regional and international development banks for grants and unilateral advances for developmental funding. These grants go a long way in helping micro-economies provide their citizens with basic necessities. Research suggests that these grants have helped reduce poverty levels by around 2-5% in different micro-economies. One of the recent challenges that these countries face is global warming and increased danger of disasters. As most of these countries are islands or chains of islands, they are just metres above sea level. The rising sea level and the increased frequency of natural disasters has increased the risk of complete disappearance of these island nations. Adequate disaster management is necessary, which requires funds. Owing to lack of funds, these countries have to look towards the international community and the United Nations for their sustenance and to equip them with various techniques of disaster risk management. Debt bells ringing. In spite of having so many problems, micro-economies have some advantages as well. As most of these small economies are a group of islands, they have access to huge amounts of the ocean as their territory. Thus, these economies have Exclusive Economic Zones (EEZ’s) in the oceans. These economies usually grant foreign multinational corporations permission for fishing and extract resources from the EEZs against a charge. This has become one of the main sources of income, apart from allowing military bases of other countries to be set up on their territory (China and India are watching closely). Some of these economies also serve as tax havens for the rich billionaires and multinational corporations. They have very lax to no tax laws. The most prominent example would be of Cayman Islands (population - 23,000), which by the mid-1990’s, became the world’s fifth largest banking centre measured by deposits. There are more than 560 banks registered in this micro-nation, including major accounting, audit and law firms. The Caymans are the ideal tax haven as they provide “tax efficient asset protection”. There are no taxes, no exchange controls and no threat to the ‘confidentiality’ of deposits. As Alberto Alesina said in his book Size of Nations: “Whether country size matters for economic prosperity depends on a country’s degree of economic integration with the rest of the world.” Similarly, these economies too, have to integrate with the world economy if they wish to develop and prosper. They cannot depend on a single economy or a single commodity for their development. Maldives and Fiji are two micro-economies which have seen tremendous growth in these recent years after opening up their economies to the world. They are not totally dependent on their regional powers or a single commodity for trade. However, they are still part of the exception than the norm. Other micro-economies too can look up to them, and try, develop, progress and finally contribute to the global economy. Recognising the existence of microeconomics, and understanding their nuanced problems, will go a long way in bringing a change.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">East Asia - The Lesson Learnt?</title>
      <link href="/East-Asia-The-Lesson-Learnt" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="East Asia - The Lesson Learnt?" />
      <published>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/East-Asia-The-Lesson-Learnt</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/East-Asia-The-Lesson-Learnt">&lt;p&gt;All human beings have an insatiable need to continuously develop themselves, be it monetarily, spiritually or physically. The same applies to economies, just that they crave GDP, HDI, and other economic indices. Over time, humans have understood that there is no shortcut to success, except hard work. But the irony remains that economies, which are run by these same humans, tend to forget this. In order to accelerate their economic growth, some economies like Indonesia, South Korea, Thailand, and Malaysia had turned towards various short-cut methods. While these methods help an economy to boom in the short run, they have adverse effects in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same happened with these East Asian economies. They witnessed exponential growth in the 1980’s and early 1990’s. But this quest for rapid growth and development lead to various cracks in the economy. Eventually, these cracks burst the growth bubble which led to severe impacts on the economy and dipping of growth rates. People, society, and the economy suffered. Therefore, what these economies needed now was &lt;i&gt;‘sustainable growth and development’&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/East-Asia-Growth-in-a-Bubble&quot;&gt;This was part 1 of the edition on East Asia&lt;/a&gt;. This part will focus on the question of whether the East Asian economies have learnt their lesson or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aftermath of the 1997 Asian Financial Crisis saw the end of many ruling political parties and policymakers. In most of these economies, long-standing governments were removed and replaced with new ones, peacefully in most of them, and in some, with force. The new governments took the help of the International Monetary Fund (IMF) to overcome their external debt crisis. The IMF proposed a series of bailout packages for these economies in return of austere monetary and fiscal measures to curb the damage. These measures included higher interest rates on loans, reduced government expenditure, restructuring of financial and banking sector, and a period of curbed international borrowings to reduce the overall debt in the economy. All East Asian economies except Indonesia accepted the bailout package proposed by the IMF. Indonesia, who didn’t accept the terms and conditions of the IMF, unofficially implemented the same in its economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Austerity measures had a devastating impact on the economy in the short term. Reduced government expenditure led to cuts in many social benefits and services provided by the governments to their people. There was reduced spending on healthcare, education and other socio-economic overheads which directly impacted the lives of citizens. Reduced sanctioning of loans led to reduced investment in infrastructure development projects. Thus, thousands of jobs were lost in the informal sector due to the unavailability of work. The citizens found themselves wanting new jobs with no government support behind them in this acute crisis. Naturally, this led to constant civil unrests and uprisings in these economies which was followed by frequent government changes. However, nothing could be done about this as this was for the “greater good”, according to the leaders of these economies, and more importantly, the IMF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These economies witnessed a major overhaul in the banking and financial sector as well. The banking sector was revamped with tighter regulations and policies in place. Several private banks, which had defaulted, were shut down, instead of being merged with other nationalized banks. This meant several thousand employees without a job, which furthered heightened the unemployment problem. New rules and regulations were also brought to keep a check on the amount of external debt being borrowed and ensured an adequate amount of liquidity and solvency in the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stringent measures were necessary to upgrade the economy and ensure its “sustainable growth and development”. However, a huge cost in terms of time, resources, and people had to be paid. These measures put the economy back by 5 years at least. While there was nominal growth in GDP in 1999, real growth in GDP was recorded only in 2002. This is when these East Asian economies regained the confidence of investors and the international community. A renewed flow of foreign capital finally provided the basis for long-term sustainable growth and development, which was slow and steady.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, the East Asian economies were careful not to commit the same mistake which dearly cost them during the 1997 Financial Crisis. They created and maintained huge amounts of International Reserves (IR). Basically, they stockpiled hard currency in order to ensure that there were no major fluctuations in their local currency in times of crisis. Such was the implementation of this policy that today these economies hold 19-20% of the world’s entire forex reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like a dramatic turnover, right? Not so fast, there is a slight problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;85% of trade by these economies is carried out in US Dollars. Moreover, 80% of their IR is made up of US Dollars. This makes these economies highly vulnerable to the monetary and fiscal policies of the United States. Basically, these economies are unguarded from any action that the US takes or any action which affects the US Dollar. This is why their trade cycles closely match with that of the US. Booms and busts in the US trade cycle are exactly reproduced in these economies. This is because, in times of recession, the interest rates in the US shoot up, which leads to outflow and flight of capital from these economies to the US. However, the great stock of forex reserves helps these economies in maintaining their exchange rates and nominal values of their foreign debt, keeping the situation in control. This is precisely what happened in the aftermath of the 2008 Recession. Thanks to the forex reserves, the situation was in control and these economies passed 2008 off as a normal blip in the trade cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, with predictions of another worldwide recession in 2020, and with the rise of the Chinese Renminbi as the currency of global choice, it is very interesting to see what would happen to these economies. Will these East Asian economies manage to stay on their path of slow and steady “sustainable growth and development”? Or, will the shortcut which they took by pegging all their trade and reserves to the US Dollar cost them dearly in the near future?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhishek Sancheti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">All human beings have an insatiable need to continuously develop themselves, be it monetarily, spiritually or physically. The same applies to economies, just that they crave GDP, HDI, and other economic indices. Over time, humans have understood that there is no shortcut to success, except hard work. But the irony remains that economies, which are run by these same humans, tend to forget this. In order to accelerate their economic growth, some economies like Indonesia, South Korea, Thailand, and Malaysia had turned towards various short-cut methods. While these methods help an economy to boom in the short run, they have adverse effects in the long run.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">East Asia - Growth in a Bubble</title>
      <link href="/East-Asia-Growth-in-a-Bubble" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="East Asia - Growth in a Bubble" />
      <published>2019-01-15T00:35:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-15T00:35:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/East-Asia-Growth-in-a-Bubble</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/East-Asia-Growth-in-a-Bubble">&lt;p&gt;The Second World War had just ended. Even though the Axis powers had lost, one could argue that all of humanity was the loser. Millions of people had been killed, wounded or displaced. Assets worth billions of dollars were lost and socio-economic infrastructure in various countries was in tatters. The war, directly or indirectly, also contributed to the freedom of various colonies in Asia. But the question remained was that how these former colonies would prosper economically after being completely decimated by a war between their colonial masters? It would require a miracle, no less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a miracle it was. Between 1965-90, the East Asian Economies and the High Performing Asian Economies (HPAEs) grew at an average of more than 5% per annum. Their growth rate was three times faster than Latin America and South Asia, and five times faster than Sub-Saharan Africa. During the same period, their real income per capita more than doubled. It was clear that this group of economies, which included Indonesia, Malaysia, Thailand, South Korea, Japan, Hong Kong and Singapore had clearly outperformed the rest of the world in terms of economic growth and development. Some analysts and economists have argued that these seven economies shared some common economic characteristics which set them apart from the rest. Even though these seven countries were highly diverse in population, culture, economic policy, natural resources and types of governance, there were some characteristics common to all of them which led to the growth story of these highly diverse economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Textbook Economics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For starters, public policy played a major contributing role in the rapid development of these economies. These countries were simply able to get the basics right. The governments of these economies were able to provide a stable macroeconomic environment, a sound legal framework, limited fiscal deficit, and moderate and predictable inflation. They also invested extensively in education, infrastructure and technological know-how. They welcomed investment both in terms of domestic savings and Foreign Direct Investment (FDI) by providing a favourable environment which included high and steady interest rates and lax tax policy. These initiatives by the government boosted growth and development in the economy along with human capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workforce forms the base of any economy. And government-financed education led to an increase in the literacy rate of these economies. The pains taken by the government in the field of education bore fruit: all these countries had a strong, educated and dedicated workforce. These economies also followed a unique and creative approach while dealing with labour problems and unions. Instead of giving in to the demand of labour unions to increase wages, the government focused on job creation. The increase in the number of jobs led to an increase in the demand for labour which automatically increased the productivity as well as the wage of labour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To rapidly develop their economies, the governments focused on infrastructure development, leading to a booming real estate market. And this (keeping in mind the high wages) ensured housing for the population which once again kept the people happy. The governments ensured that the investment coming from domestic as well as foreign investors was fully utilized. They also specifically invested in particular sectors so as to gain a comparative advantage in that sector (example, South Korea in the electronics sector). This extra effort paid its dividends as there was a rapid increase in the number of MSMEs and full-scale industries, which led to an increase in total output and increased exports. East Asia was a beautiful car ride where everyone was happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Illiquidity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as it is said, all good things must end. As already mentioned, these governments had kept high-interest rates and kept on encouraging FDI. Soon, it was seen that the amount of short-term foreign debt obligations which these economies had to pay in the international market far exceeded their foreign exchange reserves. This type of a situation in which the amount of short-term foreign debt obligations exceeded the total reserves of foreign exchange is called international illiquidity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;International illiquidity became one of the main factors contributing to the fall of these economies in the Asian Financial Crisis of 1997. These countries had excessively liberalized their financial structure to attract more foreign investment. Foreign loans kept piling up as late as May 1997 before someone took notice of it. But alas, it was too late to notice. The ratio of short-term debt to foreign reserves rose to about 7 in Indonesia and Korea, and 4.5 in the Philippines. In other East Asian Economies of Malaysia, Bangkok, Singapore, and Japan, this ratio was well above 1. The government policies of these East Asian Economies to increase investment by moving towards a freer, more market-oriented financial system came to bite them back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it happened, most of these economies kept a fixed exchange rate to maintain real interest rates and to woo investors. They maintained the exchange rate by buying up foreign exchange in case of excess supply and selling foreign exchange in case of excess demand. However, as the short-term debt was well over the amount of foreign exchange these economies had, the economy would not be able to meet all the short-term debt obligations if they came at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, on the other half of the globe, the US Federal reserve started increasing the interest rates on US Treasury Bonds to woo investment and revive America from the 1990-91 recession. As this increase in interest rates was not matched by these East Asian Economies, the investors started pulling out investments from these economies and started investing in risk-free US Bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let the Speculation Begin…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 14 and 15, 1997, the Thai Bhat was hit by speculative crisis and investors started pulling out their investments. As feared, the economy ran out of forex reserves to maintain the exchange rate and it was forced to devalue the Bhat. Consequently, the Thai Bhat lost more than 60% of its value in a single day of trading. The news spread like wildfire in the international community and the sentiment of the investors turned against the East Asian Economies. As markets are run on sentiments, investors viewed these economies to be highly volatile and started pulling out their investments. In a span of few days, the Indonesian Rupiah, the Malaysian Ringgit, the Philippine Peso, and the Korean Won were also devalued. These currencies were losing as much as 85% of their face value in a single day of trading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This devaluation of currency led to an increase in the nominal value of loans which these economies had borrowed from the international market. As the economy had taken these loans in hard currency and loaned the general public in local currency, this burden could not be passed on to the general public. Therefore, the economy and private banks had to take this hit and sell off their assets in order to repay these loans. An increase in the supply of assets in the markets led to fall in the price of these assets in the markets. And the banks were not able to raise enough funds to pay back these loans to the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Thing Leads to Another…Again&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, a large number of banks and financial institutions collapsed in these economies. Thousands of jobs were lost, there was a fall in nominal GNP per capita, a fall in income per capita, a fall in purchasing power parity, and a fall in economic growth rate. Moreover, the economy had little to no funds to undertake developmental projects and provide subsidies and concessions. The real estate market, MSME sector, education sector, human resource sector, and others, which depended on government aid and support, crashed terribly. As a result, economic growth and prosperity of these countries almost came to a standstill. It is believed that more than 10,000 people committed suicide in Hong Kong, Japan, and South Korea as a result of this crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What started as a blessing for these East Asian Economies and helped them undertake rapid growth in a span of 30 years took all it gave in a matter of few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Were the East Asian Economies able to bounce back in the international community and reach the pinnacle of growth and prosperity? Or, was this setback the final nail in the coffin and led them to a period of economic darkness? The second part of this story in the next article.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Abhishek Sancheti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Second World War had just ended. Even though the Axis powers had lost, one could argue that all of humanity was the loser. Millions of people had been killed, wounded or displaced. Assets worth billions of dollars were lost and socio-economic infrastructure in various countries was in tatters. The war, directly or indirectly, also contributed to the freedom of various colonies in Asia. But the question remained was that how these former colonies would prosper economically after being completely decimated by a war between their colonial masters? It would require a miracle, no less.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
