<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/gurleen.kaur/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-11-04T22:19:12+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/gurleen.kaur/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Indian Anchor in the Baltic Sea</title>
      <link href="/Indian-Anchor-in-the-Baltic-Sea" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Indian Anchor in the Baltic Sea" />
      <published>2019-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Indian-Anchor-in-the-Baltic-Sea</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Indian-Anchor-in-the-Baltic-Sea">&lt;p&gt;The Vice President of India, M Venkaiah Naidu visited the three Baltic nations: Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia from August 17-21, 2019. The visit was unprecedented, it was the first high-level trip from India to these nations. While India has hosted the Lithuanian Vice President, the Latvian President and Prime Minister and the Foreign Minister of Estonia in the past, there had been no reciprocal high-level visits until recently. It was only in 2016 when Minister for Electronics and Information Technology, Mr Ravishankar Prasad visited Estonia. This visit corrected the imbalance between incoming and outgoing heads of states, sending out the message that India recognises the importance of the Baltic nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Baltic nations have come a long way from the history of occupations, finally gaining independence in 1991. Today, they stand as global leaders in artificial intelligence, e-governance and e-security. Coming to the Fourth Industrial Revolution, India sees an organic alliance with these countries, thus, calling for outreach from the Indian side. Furthermore, China is fast increasing its footprint in the Baltic region in the setup of the ‘New Great Game,’ so, India has to step up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s foreign policy for Europe has concentrated only on Western Europe, with the UK, France, Germany, Italy and Spain. The Baltic outreach is a correction of this skewed worldview and a move to strengthen bilateral relations with small nations rather than treating them as subsets of their relationships with other big powers. The Vice President’s visit is expected to open more novel opportunities for cooperation in sectors discussed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trade&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bilateral trade between India and Latvia stood at about US$141 million in 2015-16. Major Indian exports were tea, coffee, tools, pharmaceuticals, chemicals, garments, iron and steel. Indian imports majorly composed of chemicals, fertilizers, iron and steel, and machinery. In the case of Estonia, total bilateral trade in 2018-19 was US$172.53 million with machinery and equipment, garments, knitwear, coffee, tea, spices, footwear and pharmaceutical products as major export items. Imports from Estonia were mainly in iron and steel, fertilizers, electrical machinery, paper and paperboard, and paper pulp. Bilateral trade between India and Lithuania stood at about US$ 215 million in 2015-16. Major Indian exports to Lithuania included vegetable saps and extracts, fish fillets and other fish meat, medicaments, footwear, ferroalloys, carpets and rice. Lithuanian exports to India included mineral or chemical fertilizers, potassic, dried leguminous vegetables, wadding of textile materials, nickel waste and scrap, diagnostic or laboratory reagents on backing and machzone-therapy appliances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a scope for growth of textiles, agro-products, gems and jewellery, chemical dyes and pharmaceuticals exports to the Baltic nations. Import of technology would be an important area in the relationship between these nations and India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connectivity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a response to China’s Belt and Road Initiative, India is keenly pushing the International North-South Transport Corridor. This is meant to provide an alternative to the Mediterranean Sea and the Suez Canal as a shorter route for the movement of trade through Central Asia and Russia. A major plus point of the project is that it will help Asian and European countries to transport their cargo at double the speed compared to the Suez Canal. This route can be expanded to connect Baltic, Nordic and Arctic regions and thus enhance connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latvia’s ice-free Riga port connects the Baltic region with the rest of Europe, Russia and Central Asia. An agreement on this port can help Indian exports reach European markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Union is developing the “Rail Baltica” project under the Trans-European Transport Network (TEN-T). This project connects cooperating member states to the Baltic nations with the existing European Rail network. This project aimed at taking the Baltic nations out of the Soviet shadow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cyber-Security and IT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estonia is a world leader in information technology, e-governance, cyber-security and innovation. The software developers from the country developed the code for Skype and Kazaa. The country is home to NATO Cooperative Cyber Defence Centre of Excellence. In 2007, it became the first country to allow online voting in the general elections. High-tech industries now account for 15% of the country’s GDP. The Indian government and businesses are trying to come to terms with the disruption caused by artificial intelligence and big data. Deeper collaboration between Estonian and Indian businesses can reap benefits for both. The experiments with proxy voting and simultaneous polls would call for government-to-government collaboration and best practices from Estonia would come handy. An MoU for Cooperation in e-Governance and emerging digital technologies and Cooperation in Cyber Security has been signed in this regard. Lithuania sees an opportunity in Brexit and is fast emerging as a hub in Fintech. With the Fourth Industrial revolution, these bilateral relationships will become vital for India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Science &amp;amp; Technology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lithuania can be a strong technology partner in agro-processing and pharma, with expertise in dairy and cheese production. Agri-tech can help realise the vision of improving agricultural productivity hence, doubling farmer incomes by 2022 for India. It can help fuel growth in India’s food processing industry which is at a nascent stage with only 5% of the total production being processed. Laser technology has emerged as a strategic trade item from Lithuania to India, especially sought after by Indian universities and research centres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Renewable Energy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania have very high energy dependence on Russian gas pipelines, owing to their Soviet past. The European Union Climate and Energy Package has helped the Baltic Nations improve the energy security stance by increasing production from renewable sources of energy. Despite its shale oil reserves, Estonia is transitioning away from fossil fuels to biofuels, photovoltaics (PV) and wind. Estonia was the first European country to adopt electric and hybrid cars. It hosts big solar parks with a total capacity of 3GWh. The Baltic nation is planning to plunge into wind power, despite the shale reserves fulfilling 85% of the energy needs. Lithuania too is venturing into the renewable energy space through wind power and biomass (biogas and waste). The country aims to increase the share of renewables in its electricity mix to 23% by 2023.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the speed with which these nations are diversifying their energy needs, they can be useful partners in the International Solar Alliance started in Paris by PM Modi. They could play a vital role in enabling the rapid deployment of solar energy globally and facilitating technology transfer. Given high import dependency for its energy needs, India can facilitate study tours for officials for the transfer of best practices from these countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Education &amp;amp; Employment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been an increase in the number of outbound students to the Baltic Nations. According to data from the Indian embassy, 100 Indian students are currently studying in Latvia, 211 in Estonia and 600 in Lithuania. The main attraction is affordable education without compromising on the quality. Indian Vice President also lauded the e-residency scheme launched in 2014 by Estonia as “a launchpad for Indians in the Baltic, Nordic and European markets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite encouraging numbers, the mobility of students and the workforce is still below potential. Education fairs and awareness programmes are essential to tap the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indian companies such as Indorama, Wipro, Tata Consultancy Services, Larsen &amp;amp; Toubro and Bharat Forge have made investments in the region. Indian companies are being wooed by promoting this region as a cost-effective and productive destination with high research capabilities. An investment of US$200 million has been made by Indorama, a Lohia Group company in the Klaipeda Economic Zone in Lithuania on a plant to manufacture plastic resin. The Indian embassy and Assocham carried out ‘Make in India: Roadshow’ to promote India as an exciting investment location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India and Baltic regions have common linguistic roots and cultural similarities. For instance, Sanskrit and Lithuanian have around 10,000 words in common. The study of Indian languages (mainly Hindi and Sanskrit) is carried in Vilnius University at the Centre of Indian Studies, under the Department of Oriental Studies. The University of Tartu in Estonia began teaching Sanskrit in 1837. The Baltic nations have a great interest in Yoga and Ayurveda. The University of Latvia in collaboration with the Arya Vaidya Pharmacy, Coimbatore has been conducting a 3-month Diploma course in Introduction to Ayurveda since February 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cooperation in Multilateral Forums&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outreach to Baltic nations has helped India secure a non-permanent seat in the United Nations Security Council from 2021-22. These nations have also supported India as a permanent member in an enlarged and reformed UNSC. The support from small nations puts pressure on bigger nations to pay attention to the agenda of reforms. Besides, Estonia would have a non-permanent seat in the UNSC beginning from 2020. India and Estonia can support each other in the UNSC if bilateral relations see an upward trend. A seasoned diplomat noted that these nations can prove to be good interlocutors for India vis-a-vis the European Union. A bone of contention between India and the European Union has been the Comprehensive Bilateral Trade and Investment Agreement (BTIA), and Baltic nations can play a constructive role in negotiating that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the vibrancy of the partnership, it can be safely concluded that only sky’s the limit. Governmental support, availability of skilled labour, ease of doing business and a conducive environment are essential to realise the objectives of the partnership. Godspeed.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gurleen Kaur</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Vice President of India, M Venkaiah Naidu visited the three Baltic nations: Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia from August 17-21, 2019. The visit was unprecedented, it was the first high-level trip from India to these nations. While India has hosted the Lithuanian Vice President, the Latvian President and Prime Minister and the Foreign Minister of Estonia in the past, there had been no reciprocal high-level visits until recently. It was only in 2016 when Minister for Electronics and Information Technology, Mr Ravishankar Prasad visited Estonia. This visit corrected the imbalance between incoming and outgoing heads of states, sending out the message that India recognises the importance of the Baltic nations.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Greying World: An Opportunity for India</title>
      <link href="/The-Greying-World" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Greying World: An Opportunity for India" />
      <published>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Greying-World</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Greying-World">&lt;p&gt;In his Independence Day address to the Indian nation, Prime Minister Narendra Modi flagged the challenges posed by population explosion. He suggested that keeping a small family was patriotism in the truest sense. Surely, this had to do with the UN forecast of India overtaking China as the most populous country by 2027. Thus, an analysis of the demographic trends would be essential to understand the issue in-depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A basic development studies course would tell you that a sustained increase in per capita income is necessary to bring about economic growth. However, when the rate of growth of population overtakes the growth in the GDP, per capita income starts falling. At present, Sub-Saharan Africa is witnessing a negative per capita economic growth because of the same reason. Thus, highlighting the importance of population studies for comprehensive economic planning. Academicians believe that an indispensable indicator in comparative population studies is the &lt;strong&gt;Total Fertility Rate (TFR)&lt;/strong&gt;. It measures the number of children born to a woman at the end of the child-bearing age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sample Registration System (SRS) under the Registrar General of India, the sole authority responsible for analysing and collecting demographic surveys of the country, pegged the TFR at 2.2. This is marginally higher than the replacement rate (2.1), which is the average number of children per woman to keep the population size constant. The latest figures are a sign of relief, as the birth rate is moving closer towards stabilisation levels. Total Fertility Rates declined from 5.2 in 1971 to 4.5 in 1981. The decade in discussion was infamous for coercive population control measures, unveiled during the Emergency of 1975-77, imposed by the then-Prime Minister Indira Gandhi. BBC described this as a gruesome campaign to sterilise poor men, with police cordoning off entire villages and forcefully taking men for the surgery. From 1991 to 2017, TFR gradually declined from 3.6 to 2.2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Indian Experience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven Indian states - Uttar Pradesh, Bihar, Madhya Pradesh, Rajasthan, Assam, Chhattisgarh and Jharkhand - account for 45% of the total population in 2011 Census. Some of these are part of the BIMARU (translates into ‘sick’ in English; acronym for the Indian states of Bihar, Madhya Pradesh, Rajasthan and Uttar Pradesh) states and lag behind on most socio-economic and health parameters. The latest data found TFR being higher than the national average in all the states, with Bihar topping the charts with a TFR of 3.2. While relatively well-off states - Kerala, Tamil Nadu, Karnataka, Maharashtra, Andhra Pradesh and Telangana - demonstrate fertility rates below the replacement level. An intimate relationship between economic development and fertility rates can thence be established. The difference in fertility rates would result in an ageing population in the South, while the North would host a significantly younger population. This polarity would result in interesting economic implications - the South would open caregiving-related jobs for the young workforce of the North, fueling migration southwards and remittance flow northwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In urban areas, TFR declined from 4.1 in 1971 to 1.7 in 2017. The rural areas also witnessed a decline in TFR from 5.4 in 1971 to 2.4 in 2017. The fertility rate of urban areas is lower than the replacement level, while it is quite higher than the replacement level in the rural areas. This disparity indicates a population pressure in the rural areas, which would further accentuate rural-urban migration in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Experience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s TFR, which is marginally higher than the replacement rate, will help evolve a demographic profile that is more favourable to economic growth. The UN Population Fund (UNFPA) estimated India’s working age population to reach a maximum of 65% in 2030, and then decline thereafter. The report further estimated that the demographic dividend would be available for 5 decades, from 2005 to 2055, longer than any other country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China, on the other hand, witnessed a TFR of 1.62 in 2016. By 2050, a third of its population would be above the age of 60, which has the potential to derail the economic powerhouse of the world. Alarmed by the possible consequences, the Chinese establishment dropped the One-Child Policy in 2013, and unveiled a plan to incentivise couples to have a second child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further East, in Japan, TFR stood at 1.41 in 2016. There is a societal problem behind falling birth rates in Japan. Fewer opportunities for young people creates a class of men who do not want to marry and have kids, simply because they cannot afford to. Longer work hours and absence of job security are quoted to be the main issues. The vicious cycle of low fertility and lower spending has led to a loss in the GDP and a population decline of 1 million people. If left unchecked, a severe economic downturn due to ageing population and rising social security costs is imminent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In European countries such as France, Denmark, Ireland and Sweden, TFR is in the range of 1.7-2. However, in Czech Republic, Lithuania, Poland and Slovenia, TFR is much below 1.3. The trend of ‘demographic ageing’ is observed in the Western and Central Europe, and will worsen the economic situation of EU27 in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Road Ahead for India&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There lies a definite opportunity for India to be the next economic powerhouse in the greying world. But it needs to concentrate on promoting family planning to retain the gains and accelerate fertility decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important challenge that family planning (FP) programmes face is funding. The FP component gets only 4% of the total budget available under the National Health Mission. In the financial year 2016-17, only 60.7% of the funds available for family planning were utilised. Underutilisation of funds hinders expansion of family planning services. The news of the death of several women in sterilisation camps, such as that in Chhattisgarh in 2014, demotivates the couples. Only 56% of married women in India report contraception usage. Access to safe contraceptive methods is a fundamental right. India’s neighbour Bangladesh implemented a fairly effective, non-coercive family planning programme which led to a dramatic reduction in fertility in a short time, from TFR being 7 in 1971 to 2.2 in 2011. There is a high level of awareness about family planning matters and higher reported usage of contraceptive techniques. India, similar to Bangladesh, can employ its ASHA workforce to spread awareness about these. Recently, an initiative by USAID (United States Agency for International Development) and the Government of India led to a campaign promoting usage of oral contraceptive pills titled “Hai Goli Mein Vishwas (Trust the pill).” Such awareness programmes at the micro-regional rural areas can go a long way in fulfilling the above objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain policies have not rewarded the states which have taken effective measures for controlling population growth. Population growth in North and Central India is far greater than Southern India. Between 1971 and 2011, the population of Kerala grew by 56%, while there was a 140% rise in case of Bihar, Uttar Pradesh and Madhya Pradesh. The 15th Finance Commission has retained 2011 population census for Centre-State revenue allocations as its term of reference. This formula, if used, would lead to higher flow of funds to the North-Central states at the expense of the Southern States, leaving them feeling penalised for better performance in reducing fertility. Using 1971 population numbers for State allocations of Central resources could be a better formula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female education is yet a very important move to fight population explosion. Data from the Sample Registration System shows that a class 10-pass or GCSE equivalent qualified woman produces 2 children on average. The TFR further falls to 1.8 in case a woman clears Class 12 exam or the A-level equivalent. A woman with education levels of a graduate or above has a TFR of 1.4. Thus, the total fertility rate falls with the increase in levels of education. And an educated mother is a prerequisite for population stabilisation as she is able to play an active role in family planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature of the family planning programme should continue to be ‘voluntary’, as suggested by the National Population Policy in 2000. Recently, an eminent Congress leader called for a law on population control. A BJP Rajya Sabha MP introduced a private member’s Bill seeking to enforce a two-child norm. A prominent businessman-yoga guru called for a law ‘disenfranchising’ the third child to prevent larger family size. The fact that 23 states and union territories have fertility rates below 2.1 shows that support works rather than control. In addition, we have the Chinese example to tell us that coercive methods might take things out of control. “The people who have maintained small families need to be honoured, and by setting them as examples, we need to inspire the segment of the society who are still not thinking on those lines,” said PM Modi. Though we have come a long way, still a lot needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gurleen Kaur</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In his Independence Day address to the Indian nation, Prime Minister Narendra Modi flagged the challenges posed by population explosion. He suggested that keeping a small family was patriotism in the truest sense. Surely, this had to do with the UN forecast of India overtaking China as the most populous country by 2027. Thus, an analysis of the demographic trends would be essential to understand the issue in-depth.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Of Diplomacy, Domination and the South China Sea</title>
      <link href="/Dominaion-and-the-South-China-Sea" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Of Diplomacy, Domination and the South China Sea" />
      <published>2019-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Dominaion-and-the-South-China-Sea</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Dominaion-and-the-South-China-Sea">&lt;p&gt;In his book, &lt;em&gt;On China&lt;/em&gt;, notable American diplomat Henry Kissinger wrote, “The
highest form of warfare is to attack [the enemy’s] Strategy itself; the next, to
attack [his] Alliances. The next, to attack Armies”. As elaborated by Kissinger,
China seems to be following the art of strategic encirclement in diplomacy’s new
theatre, the South China Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/de/South_China_Sea_claims_map.jpg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//South_China_Sea_claims_map.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Geography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South China Sea is a part of the Pacific Ocean, with the Strait of Taiwan in
the Northeast and the Straits of Malacca in the Southwest (as shown in the map).
The littoral countries of this disputed sea are China, Taiwan, Philippines,
Malaysia, Brunei, Indonesia, Singapore, Cambodia, Thailand and Vietnam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary island chains in the South China Sea are The Paracel, the Pratas and
Spratly Islands. The Scarborough Shoal, a triangle-shaped chain of reefs and
rocks with a total area of 150 square kilometres, is another important
geographical entity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Conflict&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till the end of World War II, not a single island in the South China Sea had
been occupied. In 1947, China demarcated its claims over the South China Sea
with a U-shaped line made up of eleven dashes, covering almost the entire area.
Newer dimensions were added to the conflict following the formation of Taiwan in
1949.  In 1953, the &lt;em&gt;nine-dash line&lt;/em&gt; prevailed over the earlier eleven dashes,
when China withdrew its claim over the Gulf of Tonkin. The claimed area
stretches from Hainan Island, covering Paracel and Spratly Islands which
comprise over 90% of the South China Sea. On diplomatic fora, China justifies
its claim stating the Treaty of Tientsin with France after the Sino-French War
in 1885, and the Cairo and Potsdam declarations after the defeat of Japan in
World War II. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Claimants for the Paracel Islands include Taiwan, Vietnam and China. Vietnam
cites 17th century, Vietnamese scholar Do Ba to justify the fact that it once
actively ruled over Paracel and Spratly islands, and thus has territorial rights
over them. As for the Pratas Islands, they are administered by Taiwan but
claimed by China. Malaysia and Brunei also claim the territory that falls in
their exclusive economic zones. While Malaysia claims some islands in Spratly,
Brunei does not. Philippines, Taiwan and China claim the Scarborough Shoal,
which China also calls the Huangyan Island.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Importance of the South China Sea&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South China Sea is an important trade route, supporting trade worth $5
trillion. Secondly, it is a rich source of hydrocarbons and is an abundant
fishing ground. According to the United States Energy Information Agency, there
are 11 billion barrels of oil and 190 trillion cubic feet of natural gas in
deposits under the South China Sea. Its fisheries account for 10% of the global
total.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South China Sea holds strategic importance for China for two more reasons.
First, China is dependent upon West Asia for its energy needs. The trade via sea
has many choke points like the Straits of Malacca, Sunda Strait and Lombok
Strait that have remained blocked in the past. This proved harmful for China and
thus domination of the sea would be pre-emptive action to save this important
route. Secondly, aggressive posturing in the South China Sea would help China
enhance its domination in the Indian Ocean. This would be a countermeasure to
the United States’ growing hegemony in the Indo-Pacific region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vietnam-China Dispute&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1974, China and South Vietnam fought the battle for Paracel Islands. China
won and took over the entire archipelago. Following the Vietnam War, North
Vietnam, which earlier supported China’s claim, put forth a united front against
Chinese domination. As discussed earlier, Vietnam claims the Paracel Islands and
denounces the violation of Vietnam’s sovereignty by the forceful occupation of
these islands. In 1988, another standoff occurred following a skirmish between
Vietnamese and Chinese soldiers over the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johnson_South_Reef&quot;&gt;Johnson South
Reef&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spratly_Islands&quot;&gt;Spratly
Islands&lt;/a&gt; that killed 64
Vietnamese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2014 China-Vietnam Oil rig crisis heightened tensions relating to the
ownership of islands in the South China Sea. On May 2, 2014, China National
Offshore Oil Corporation moved its $1 billion &lt;em&gt;Hai Yang Shi You 981&lt;/em&gt; oil rig to
a location closer to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triton_Island&quot;&gt;Triton
Island&lt;/a&gt;s, the southwestern-most
island of the Paracels. The location was near Vietnam’s hydrocarbon blocks 142
and 143. Vietnam protested by sending 29 ships to disrupt the rig’s operations.
The tensions at sea led to anti-China protests in Vietnam which escalated into
riots. Many foreign businesses and Chinese workers were subjected to looting and
vandalism. On July 15, China National Offshore Oil Corporation withdrew one
month earlier than originally announced, defusing the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July 2019, a large-scale standoff took place between the coast guard ships of
China and Vietnam when a Chinese oil exploration ship entered disputed waters
near the Spratly Islands. Vietnam demanded an immediate withdrawal, while China
refused to do so, leading to another dispute between the nations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;China-Philippines Dispute&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until 2012, Philippines exercised de-facto control over the shoal. The 2012
Scarborough standoff was initiated when the Philippines accused Chinese
fishermen of illegally collecting corals, giant clams and live sharks. Following
a tense standoff wherein the Chinese vessels refused to leave the shoal, the
unsuccessful bilateral negotiations forced the Philippines to back off. China
gained control and drove Filipino fishermen away from Scarborough Shoal. In
2013, the Philippines took China to the Permanent Court of Arbitration, to
challenge the &lt;em&gt;nine-dash line&lt;/em&gt; that violated the Philippines’ sovereignty under
the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Seas (1982). The court ruled
that China had violated the Philippines’ sovereign waters as the &lt;em&gt;nine-dash
line&lt;/em&gt; included the Scarborough Shoal and the Philippines’ Exclusive Economic
Zone (EEZ). China outrightly rejected the ruling and refused to vacate the
Scarborough Shoal, questioning the court’s ‘jurisdiction’. Philippines rejoiced
this judgement as the ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/opinion/2016/07/philippines-wins-trial-century-160714115011745.html&quot;&gt;trial of the
century&lt;/a&gt;’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the ruling of the Hague tribunal, China continues to violate the
Philippines’ Exclusive Economic Zone and engages in overfishing. On June 9,
2019, a Chinese vessel was involved in a boat ramming incident, which threatened
the lives of 22 Filipino fishermen. In another incident in late July, 113
Chinese fishing vessels were spotted near the Philippine-administered Pag-asa
Island in the Spratly archipelago. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite continuous violations, the Malacañang seems to be wanting warmer ties
with its Chinese counterpart. President Duterte recently revealed that he had
reached a ‘verbal agreement’ with President Xi, for allowing Chinese fishermen
in the Philippines EEZ. As a part of Duterte’s bilateral visit to China in 2018,
a preliminary agreement was reached for oil and gas exploration in the South
China Sea. Critics smell foul play at the increasing proximity and condemn
Duterte for failing to act on the Philippines’ arbitral victory. The reason for
this shift is attributed to China’s economic clout and growing investments in
the infrastructure sector, essential to support the Philippines’ economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aspiring hegemon is proactively utilising money diplomacy to win strategic
partners. According to reports, a secret deal was signed with Cambodia to allow
Chinese forces to use the Ream naval base. As in the Philippines, Chinese funded
soft loans and investment in Cambodian infrastructure projects have brought
‘warmth’ to the bilateral ties. Encirclement Attack is the norm being adopted by
China, and how the nation’s money diplomacy further polarises the South China
Sea dispute would be something to watch out for.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gurleen Kaur</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In his book, On China, notable American diplomat Henry Kissinger wrote, “The highest form of warfare is to attack [the enemy’s] Strategy itself; the next, to attack [his] Alliances. The next, to attack Armies”. As elaborated by Kissinger, China seems to be following the art of strategic encirclement in diplomacy’s new theatre, the South China Sea. Geography The South China Sea is a part of the Pacific Ocean, with the Strait of Taiwan in the Northeast and the Straits of Malacca in the Southwest (as shown in the map). The littoral countries of this disputed sea are China, Taiwan, Philippines, Malaysia, Brunei, Indonesia, Singapore, Cambodia, Thailand and Vietnam. The primary island chains in the South China Sea are The Paracel, the Pratas and Spratly Islands. The Scarborough Shoal, a triangle-shaped chain of reefs and rocks with a total area of 150 square kilometres, is another important geographical entity.  The Conflict Till the end of World War II, not a single island in the South China Sea had been occupied. In 1947, China demarcated its claims over the South China Sea with a U-shaped line made up of eleven dashes, covering almost the entire area. Newer dimensions were added to the conflict following the formation of Taiwan in 1949.  In 1953, the nine-dash line prevailed over the earlier eleven dashes, when China withdrew its claim over the Gulf of Tonkin. The claimed area stretches from Hainan Island, covering Paracel and Spratly Islands which comprise over 90% of the South China Sea. On diplomatic fora, China justifies its claim stating the Treaty of Tientsin with France after the Sino-French War in 1885, and the Cairo and Potsdam declarations after the defeat of Japan in World War II.  Claimants for the Paracel Islands include Taiwan, Vietnam and China. Vietnam cites 17th century, Vietnamese scholar Do Ba to justify the fact that it once actively ruled over Paracel and Spratly islands, and thus has territorial rights over them. As for the Pratas Islands, they are administered by Taiwan but claimed by China. Malaysia and Brunei also claim the territory that falls in their exclusive economic zones. While Malaysia claims some islands in Spratly, Brunei does not. Philippines, Taiwan and China claim the Scarborough Shoal, which China also calls the Huangyan Island. Importance of the South China Sea The South China Sea is an important trade route, supporting trade worth $5 trillion. Secondly, it is a rich source of hydrocarbons and is an abundant fishing ground. According to the United States Energy Information Agency, there are 11 billion barrels of oil and 190 trillion cubic feet of natural gas in deposits under the South China Sea. Its fisheries account for 10% of the global total. The South China Sea holds strategic importance for China for two more reasons. First, China is dependent upon West Asia for its energy needs. The trade via sea has many choke points like the Straits of Malacca, Sunda Strait and Lombok Strait that have remained blocked in the past. This proved harmful for China and thus domination of the sea would be pre-emptive action to save this important route. Secondly, aggressive posturing in the South China Sea would help China enhance its domination in the Indian Ocean. This would be a countermeasure to the United States’ growing hegemony in the Indo-Pacific region. Vietnam-China Dispute In 1974, China and South Vietnam fought the battle for Paracel Islands. China won and took over the entire archipelago. Following the Vietnam War, North Vietnam, which earlier supported China’s claim, put forth a united front against Chinese domination. As discussed earlier, Vietnam claims the Paracel Islands and denounces the violation of Vietnam’s sovereignty by the forceful occupation of these islands. In 1988, another standoff occurred following a skirmish between Vietnamese and Chinese soldiers over the Johnson South Reef in the Spratly Islands that killed 64 Vietnamese. The 2014 China-Vietnam Oil rig crisis heightened tensions relating to the ownership of islands in the South China Sea. On May 2, 2014, China National Offshore Oil Corporation moved its $1 billion Hai Yang Shi You 981 oil rig to a location closer to the Triton Islands, the southwestern-most island of the Paracels. The location was near Vietnam’s hydrocarbon blocks 142 and 143. Vietnam protested by sending 29 ships to disrupt the rig’s operations. The tensions at sea led to anti-China protests in Vietnam which escalated into riots. Many foreign businesses and Chinese workers were subjected to looting and vandalism. On July 15, China National Offshore Oil Corporation withdrew one month earlier than originally announced, defusing the crisis. In July 2019, a large-scale standoff took place between the coast guard ships of China and Vietnam when a Chinese oil exploration ship entered disputed waters near the Spratly Islands. Vietnam demanded an immediate withdrawal, while China refused to do so, leading to another dispute between the nations.  China-Philippines Dispute Until 2012, Philippines exercised de-facto control over the shoal. The 2012 Scarborough standoff was initiated when the Philippines accused Chinese fishermen of illegally collecting corals, giant clams and live sharks. Following a tense standoff wherein the Chinese vessels refused to leave the shoal, the unsuccessful bilateral negotiations forced the Philippines to back off. China gained control and drove Filipino fishermen away from Scarborough Shoal. In 2013, the Philippines took China to the Permanent Court of Arbitration, to challenge the nine-dash line that violated the Philippines’ sovereignty under the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Seas (1982). The court ruled that China had violated the Philippines’ sovereign waters as the nine-dash line included the Scarborough Shoal and the Philippines’ Exclusive Economic Zone (EEZ). China outrightly rejected the ruling and refused to vacate the Scarborough Shoal, questioning the court’s ‘jurisdiction’. Philippines rejoiced this judgement as the ‘trial of the century’. Despite the ruling of the Hague tribunal, China continues to violate the Philippines’ Exclusive Economic Zone and engages in overfishing. On June 9, 2019, a Chinese vessel was involved in a boat ramming incident, which threatened the lives of 22 Filipino fishermen. In another incident in late July, 113 Chinese fishing vessels were spotted near the Philippine-administered Pag-asa Island in the Spratly archipelago.  Despite continuous violations, the Malacañang seems to be wanting warmer ties with its Chinese counterpart. President Duterte recently revealed that he had reached a ‘verbal agreement’ with President Xi, for allowing Chinese fishermen in the Philippines EEZ. As a part of Duterte’s bilateral visit to China in 2018, a preliminary agreement was reached for oil and gas exploration in the South China Sea. Critics smell foul play at the increasing proximity and condemn Duterte for failing to act on the Philippines’ arbitral victory. The reason for this shift is attributed to China’s economic clout and growing investments in the infrastructure sector, essential to support the Philippines’ economy.  The aspiring hegemon is proactively utilising money diplomacy to win strategic partners. According to reports, a secret deal was signed with Cambodia to allow Chinese forces to use the Ream naval base. As in the Philippines, Chinese funded soft loans and investment in Cambodian infrastructure projects have brought ‘warmth’ to the bilateral ties. Encirclement Attack is the norm being adopted by China, and how the nation’s money diplomacy further polarises the South China Sea dispute would be something to watch out for.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Voting Rights for Prisoners: A Conundrum</title>
      <link href="/Voting-Rights-for-Prisoners" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Voting Rights for Prisoners: A Conundrum" />
      <published>2019-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Voting-Rights-for-Prisoners</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Voting-Rights-for-Prisoners">&lt;p&gt;As 2020 US Presidential election campaigning is in full swing, heated debates on contentious issues have taken the centre stage. Among these is the issue of voting rights for incarcerated citizens during their prison terms. A staunch supporter of voting rights for prisoners is Vermont Senator Bernie Sanders. In a CNN town hall on April 22, Bernie supported the right to vote to include even the Boston Marathon bomber Dzhokhar Tsarnaev, who was sentenced to death in July 2015. Sanders believes that the commission of any crime or horrific act should not debar a citizen from his right to vote. To quote him, “I think the right to vote is inherent to our democracy. Yes, even for terrible people because once you start chipping away … you’re running down a slippery slope,” Sanders said, attracting a strong rebuttal from the Republicans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Outlier&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 6.1 million people in the United States have lost their voting rights as a result of felony convictions. The United States is an outlier, compared to many nations across the world where the voting rights of prisoners are protected. Twenty-six European countries protect the voting rights of prisoners who are convicted for non-violent crimes such as drunk driving, possession of a small amount of marijuana or fleeing the police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eighteen countries grant this fundamental right even in case of murder convictions. When Britain imposed a blanket ban on voting in 2005, the European Court of Human Rights ruled this to be a grave violation of human rights. Canada, South Africa and Kenya also grant voting rights to their felons. During the Presidential elections in North Macedonia, ballots were brought from prisoner’s home voting district in thirteen prisons of the country. Ahead of the recent referendum, election officers initiated a program to renew expired voting documents of the incarcerated people. In Bosnia and Herzegovina, prisoners convicted for crimes unrelated to the Bosnian War have the right to vote. In Germany, Norway and Portugal, only those convicted for crimes that target the state or democratic order, like terrorism or political violence, are disenfranchised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vermont and Maine are the only two states that allow prisoners to vote in the United States. Twenty-six American states stripped this right away from former prisoners for a lifetime. Joining the bandwagon are Armenia and Chile, where prisoners lost their voting rights. In Belgium, prisoners with sentences longer than seven years are not allowed to vote. In India, prisoners and those under preventive detention lose their voting rights under Section 62(5) of The Representation of People Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Reflection of Racism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A socio-political dimension to the voting rights debate is the political representation of the black community in America, given the disproportionate incarceration of black people in the country. In the colonial era of America, the concept of “civil death” was prevalent. It was believed that some bad actions render a person ineffective in utilising his civil rights. A racial twist to the story came following the Jim Crow laws, enacted in the late 19th and early 20th century. Black Codes were enacted in the South following the Civil War to constrain rights of black people, criminalising disobedience and “disrespect to the employer”. The subjectivity left it to the discretion of the authorities and enforcement targeted and criminalised the black community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most blacks lived in the South and were effectively disenfranchised following the Jim Crow laws. Analysts believe that the 1912 Presidential election was steeply slanted against the interests of the Black Americans. The brunt of poll taxes and literacy requirements was borne by the poor and illiterate Americans (a large proportion belonged to the black community), while European Americans were exempted from meeting these requirements. Literacy testing clauses were consciously used to single out Black Americans in Virginia, Oklahoma and Florida.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Barack Obama said at an NAACP convention in 2015, “African-Americans are more likely to be arrested. They are more likely to be sentenced to more time for the same crime.” There were 5.1 times more Black prisoners than white incarcerated in state prisons. According to Ashley Nellis, a senior research analyst with the Sentencing Project, the disparity between black and white felons was more than ten times in five states. New Jersey had the highest disparity, with twelve black people to one in its prison system. This was followed by Wisconsin, Iowa, Minnesota, and Vermont. Oklahoma had 2,625 black inmates per one hundred thousand residents, with only 7.7% of the population being black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the sheer population of black felons, the disenfranchisement results in skewed participation of the community in the elections. This takes a toll on all aspects of the electoral process: from the inclusion of their demands in the agenda to allowing leaders from the community to run for positions. This hampers the socio-political empowerment of the community, an objective that has not been accomplished since the Civil Rights Movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voting: A Fundamental Right&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamental rights, by definition, are not meant to expire on the commission of a crime. Other than for crimes related to terrorism and civil strife, depriving the citizen of his right to vote should be an exception and not a norm. Universal suffrage is meant to be universal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question at the heart of the debate is: What is the purpose of a prison? Is it meant to be a punishment which includes restriction of rights, or a place for repentance and rehabilitation? Prisons should be a place for reeducation and providing the inmates with skills and values to reintegrate with society upon their release. Giving them voting rights and making them realise the fundamental rights as well as duties is an important component of the reeducation drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Silver Lining&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, Florida voted for a constitutional amendment to end the policy of permanent disenfranchisement of felons. The supermajority voting for the motion helped to restore the voting rights of 1.5 million convicted felons. The District of Columbia and fifteen other states joined the bandwagon to end this draconian policy. Those on parole or probation were allowed to vote in New York. With such examples in the neighborhood, the process of rethinking about prisoner rights has begun in the other states as well. This would go a long way in achieving Martin Luther King’s vision of a racially just society.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gurleen Kaur</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As 2020 US Presidential election campaigning is in full swing, heated debates on contentious issues have taken the centre stage. Among these is the issue of voting rights for incarcerated citizens during their prison terms. A staunch supporter of voting rights for prisoners is Vermont Senator Bernie Sanders. In a CNN town hall on April 22, Bernie supported the right to vote to include even the Boston Marathon bomber Dzhokhar Tsarnaev, who was sentenced to death in July 2015. Sanders believes that the commission of any crime or horrific act should not debar a citizen from his right to vote. To quote him, “I think the right to vote is inherent to our democracy. Yes, even for terrible people because once you start chipping away … you’re running down a slippery slope,” Sanders said, attracting a strong rebuttal from the Republicans.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘Missing’ Firms in GDP Calculation</title>
      <link href="/Missing-Firms-in-GDP-Calculation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="'Missing' Firms in GDP Calculation" />
      <published>2019-06-13T17:34:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-13T17:34:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Missing-Firms-in-GDP-Calculation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Missing-Firms-in-GDP-Calculation">&lt;p&gt;The controversies regarding India’s GDP numbers, with 2011-2012 as the base
year, seem to be not coming to an end. The Indian National Sampling Survey
Office’s (NSSO) study, ending June 2017, revealed that 38% of the companies
which are a part of the MCA21 database (the Modi government’s e-governance
initiative) were missing. The study implied that the inclusion of data from such
companies would grossly overestimate GDP figures.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, the Central Statistical Office (CSO) of India issued a new GDP series,
wherein the routine 2004-05 base year was replaced with 2011-12. According to Dr
R. Nagaraj, such a revision usually leads to a slight expansion of the absolute
GDP in the base year, keeping the growth rate constant. But this time, the
absolute GDP was reduced slightly in the base year and the growth rate had an
unprecedented rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were significant changes in the methodology this time. The CSO had shifted
to the latest global template, the System of National Accounts 2008, for
calculations. Moreover, the income accruing to the Private Corporate Sector
(PCS) was directly estimated using the Ministry of Corporate Affairs’ (MCA)
statutory filing of financial returns, i.e. the aforementioned MCA-21. The PCS
accounts for over one-third of the GDP, and has affected estimates of many
industries. The CSO claims that GDP calculation through MCA-21, which is a
larger database than the Annual Survey of Industries for Manufacturing used
previously, better captures the economy’s value addition, especially of smaller
enterprises and services activities. The critics, however, fear that this has
led to a gross overestimation of GDP.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The NSSO Survey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent report of the NSSO titled &lt;em&gt;Technical Report on Service Sector
Enterprises in India&lt;/em&gt; found nearly 38% of the companies surveyed using MCA21
database to be unusable for data collection purposes. Of this, 21% were “out of
coverage” firms, 12% were designated untraceable and 4.5% were closed. Many of
these companies according to Dr R. Nagaraj, are shell/fake/spurious entities
that remain legally registered (but merely on paper) but do not produce goods
and services. The only purpose is to help the owner hide the profits and, thus,
reduce the taxable income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is GDP Overestimated?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Pronab Sen, former Chief Statistician, disagrees with the fact that GDP is
overestimated due to the data from the ‘missing’ firms. He explains that for the
purpose of measurement of GDP, it is more important for the statisticians that
the shell companies are submitting their balance sheets regularly to the MCA21.
These firms are involved in some form of economic activity, and not measuring
their output would mean severe underestimation of the GDP. The value creation is
happening by some other company, but the transactions are being routed through
these shell companies. Ignoring them would mean a part of the business of the
registered company is being ignored, which is wrong. Hence, the GDP will only be
correctly estimated if we include the data from the shell companies. However,
the taxable income accruing to the private sector and thus the private savings
will surely be underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, growth rates are measured over a period of time and are influenced by
the regularity with which the companies file the returns. Thus, the fact that a
large number of companies are not being measured affects the level of the
economy, but not the growth profile.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the MCA21 database is a compilation of the audited financial returns
filed by the companies. The returns are reconciled with the corporate tax
collected by the Income Tax Department. Mr Sen explains that the audit data from
MCA21 would always be better than unaudited data, the one collected from the
field. The MCA data captures value creation by an entity which is a registered
corporate. The value may be coming from the company itself or simply a book
entry from some other company. This doesn’t matter as far as gross value
addition (GVA) is concerned.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MCA21: Foolproof?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of MCA21 database, however, does have its disadvantages. The presence of
spurious firms creates low-level problems related to growth rates and gross
value addition (GVA) by different sectors. For instance, a manufacturing company
can create a shell company as a trading firm. The creation of a fake company of
such kind will lead to some of the GVA by the manufacturing sector being counted
as the GVA by the services sector.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To consider the argument that all active companies under the MCA have filed
statutory returns at least once during the last three years to be true will be a
mistake. If it were true, there would at least be one year for which there would
existent data for seven to eight hundred thousand companies, which has never
been the case. For most years data is available for around three hundred
thousand active companies. The estimates of gross value added for these three
hundred thousand companies is inflated to obtain the GVA of the universe of 10
hundred thousand companies.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There can be no denying the fact that MCA21 contains information from shell
companies. The data from such fictitious units cannot be ignored to prevent
underestimation. The only way to make the process of GDP calculation efficient
and transparent would be to weed out these shell companies. The Ministry of
Corporate Affairs (MCA) has started the process of geo-tagging the registered
offices in the returns filed with the Registrar of Companies (RoC). Geo-tagging
is the process of attaching geographical meta-data (exact latitudinal and
longitudinal information) with an online return filing system, alerting the
government if too many companies are registered on the same premises. The
process of geo-tagging is still underway and it would be too early to comment on
its effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debate on the inclusion of figures from shell companies for the calculation
of GDP and the veracity of the GDP numbers is raging. There is a need for
statisticians, economists and policymakers to sit together and find solutions to
these technical issues related to GDP calculation. Additional steps need to be
taken by the Income Tax Department and the Enforcement Directorate (India’s
white collar crime watchdog) to clamp down on the operations of such spurious
companies. The Justice Shah Commission, constituted in 2015, highlighted the
role of such companies in money laundering, which is a punishable offence under
Prevention of Money Laundering Act, 2002. A holistic government approach is
necessary to fight the menace of shell companies.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gurleen Kaur</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The controversies regarding India’s GDP numbers, with 2011-2012 as the base year, seem to be not coming to an end. The Indian National Sampling Survey Office’s (NSSO) study, ending June 2017, revealed that 38% of the companies which are a part of the MCA21 database (the Modi government’s e-governance initiative) were missing. The study implied that the inclusion of data from such companies would grossly overestimate GDP figures.   The Background In 2015, the Central Statistical Office (CSO) of India issued a new GDP series, wherein the routine 2004-05 base year was replaced with 2011-12. According to Dr R. Nagaraj, such a revision usually leads to a slight expansion of the absolute GDP in the base year, keeping the growth rate constant. But this time, the absolute GDP was reduced slightly in the base year and the growth rate had an unprecedented rise. There were significant changes in the methodology this time. The CSO had shifted to the latest global template, the System of National Accounts 2008, for calculations. Moreover, the income accruing to the Private Corporate Sector (PCS) was directly estimated using the Ministry of Corporate Affairs’ (MCA) statutory filing of financial returns, i.e. the aforementioned MCA-21. The PCS accounts for over one-third of the GDP, and has affected estimates of many industries. The CSO claims that GDP calculation through MCA-21, which is a larger database than the Annual Survey of Industries for Manufacturing used previously, better captures the economy’s value addition, especially of smaller enterprises and services activities. The critics, however, fear that this has led to a gross overestimation of GDP.   The NSSO Survey A recent report of the NSSO titled Technical Report on Service Sector Enterprises in India found nearly 38% of the companies surveyed using MCA21 database to be unusable for data collection purposes. Of this, 21% were “out of coverage” firms, 12% were designated untraceable and 4.5% were closed. Many of these companies according to Dr R. Nagaraj, are shell/fake/spurious entities that remain legally registered (but merely on paper) but do not produce goods and services. The only purpose is to help the owner hide the profits and, thus, reduce the taxable income. Is GDP Overestimated? Mr Pronab Sen, former Chief Statistician, disagrees with the fact that GDP is overestimated due to the data from the ‘missing’ firms. He explains that for the purpose of measurement of GDP, it is more important for the statisticians that the shell companies are submitting their balance sheets regularly to the MCA21. These firms are involved in some form of economic activity, and not measuring their output would mean severe underestimation of the GDP. The value creation is happening by some other company, but the transactions are being routed through these shell companies. Ignoring them would mean a part of the business of the registered company is being ignored, which is wrong. Hence, the GDP will only be correctly estimated if we include the data from the shell companies. However, the taxable income accruing to the private sector and thus the private savings will surely be underestimated. Second, growth rates are measured over a period of time and are influenced by the regularity with which the companies file the returns. Thus, the fact that a large number of companies are not being measured affects the level of the economy, but not the growth profile.   Moreover, the MCA21 database is a compilation of the audited financial returns filed by the companies. The returns are reconciled with the corporate tax collected by the Income Tax Department. Mr Sen explains that the audit data from MCA21 would always be better than unaudited data, the one collected from the field. The MCA data captures value creation by an entity which is a registered corporate. The value may be coming from the company itself or simply a book entry from some other company. This doesn’t matter as far as gross value addition (GVA) is concerned.   MCA21: Foolproof? The use of MCA21 database, however, does have its disadvantages. The presence of spurious firms creates low-level problems related to growth rates and gross value addition (GVA) by different sectors. For instance, a manufacturing company can create a shell company as a trading firm. The creation of a fake company of such kind will lead to some of the GVA by the manufacturing sector being counted as the GVA by the services sector.   To consider the argument that all active companies under the MCA have filed statutory returns at least once during the last three years to be true will be a mistake. If it were true, there would at least be one year for which there would existent data for seven to eight hundred thousand companies, which has never been the case. For most years data is available for around three hundred thousand active companies. The estimates of gross value added for these three hundred thousand companies is inflated to obtain the GVA of the universe of 10 hundred thousand companies.   There can be no denying the fact that MCA21 contains information from shell companies. The data from such fictitious units cannot be ignored to prevent underestimation. The only way to make the process of GDP calculation efficient and transparent would be to weed out these shell companies. The Ministry of Corporate Affairs (MCA) has started the process of geo-tagging the registered offices in the returns filed with the Registrar of Companies (RoC). Geo-tagging is the process of attaching geographical meta-data (exact latitudinal and longitudinal information) with an online return filing system, alerting the government if too many companies are registered on the same premises. The process of geo-tagging is still underway and it would be too early to comment on its effectiveness. The debate on the inclusion of figures from shell companies for the calculation of GDP and the veracity of the GDP numbers is raging. There is a need for statisticians, economists and policymakers to sit together and find solutions to these technical issues related to GDP calculation. Additional steps need to be taken by the Income Tax Department and the Enforcement Directorate (India’s white collar crime watchdog) to clamp down on the operations of such spurious companies. The Justice Shah Commission, constituted in 2015, highlighted the role of such companies in money laundering, which is a punishable offence under Prevention of Money Laundering Act, 2002. A holistic government approach is necessary to fight the menace of shell companies.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Newbies in the House</title>
      <link href="/Newbies-In-The-House" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Newbies in the House" />
      <published>2019-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Newbies-In-The-House</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Newbies-In-The-House">&lt;p&gt;Ukraine is now a hot topic in international news due to the historic victory of comedian Volodymyr Zelensky in its Presidential elections. The 41-year old will be Ukraine’s youngest President, with a sweeping victory that comprised 73% of the vote share. The star of The Servant of the People sitcom got the chance of a lifetime as he transitioned from the ‘reel’ to the ‘real’. Zelensky has often been referred to as the ‘Ukrainian Trump’, precisely because of him being a political novice and acquiring the highest public office. With Trump and Zelensky around, the big question is what do the ‘newbies’ have in store for international diplomacy and the world order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A possible implication could be a newer perspective to domestic as well as foreign politics. In an interview in December 2018, Zelensky stressed on ending the ongoing War in Donbass by negotiating with Russia. This is in stark contrast to the policy steered by the previous President Petro Poroshenko. Moreover, his election campaign targeted voters online, and through social media, ditching conventional campaigning in the form of rallies and interviews. His experiments did bear fruit as he emerged victorious, becoming the youngest President in the history of the nation. Similarly, Trump’s somewhat right-wing nationalist construct had significant impacts on both the domestic and international front. His ‘America First’ policy stood diametrically opposed to the longstanding pro-globalisation policy. And his silent acquiescence to white supremacists and major disregard for feminist movements have challenged the American ideals of inclusiveness and equality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One would believe a political neophyte brings fresher waves in the working of the bureaucracy. Their ideas, derived from their work experience in a non-government sector, bring in a newer set of work ethics, for better or for worse. The Ukrainians voted for Zelensky because of his promise to fight corruption, which seemed unlikely with the ‘oligarch’ Poroshenko. One of Zelensky’s prominent poll promises was of crowdsourcing important appointments and policies, making the administrative setup truly democratic. This may be a groundbreaking idea, given that the public sector universally suffers from elitism and is blamed for poor transparency in its functioning. Trump’s official economic advisors have included the elites of business and finance, with negligible government or academic experience. The appointments are justified by the fact that big names of the private sector have much more practical exposure to real-life business and economics over academicians. While the impact of these changes is yet to be assessed, this could be an excellent case study for public sectors across the globe to emulate–if it really shakes things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newbies put forward an interesting opportunity for governments: new strategic alliances can be forged and existing alliances can go for a toss. In Trump’s case, we have witnessed the case of the Iran Nuclear Deal. Formally called the Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action (JCPOA), the withdrawal of the US from the Deal heightened tensions with the pro-deal European Union. In addition, both are engaged in a tussle over defense spending on NATO. Reportedly, Trump plans to withdraw from the military body in 2019. This would strike a blow to the partnership that carried out ambitious missions in the Balkans, Afghanistan, and Libya. Moreover, the President’s soft-corner for Kremlin, in the face of Mueller investigation has raised many eyebrows. In our Ukrainian protagonist’s case, the hypothesis of radical foreign policy changes cannot be rejected, given his willingness to also “make a deal” with Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting feature about the working of newbies is that as they begin their work, they start with a clean slate: no prior experience of governance. This can be a boon, which can result in out-of-the box and creative solutions to administrative bottlenecks. This can further refine relationships between the executive, judiciary and legislature. Political newbies enjoy a unique advantage over their politically-active counterparts—they have no track record. It may not make sense at the first go, but is, in fact, a great strength. People have known the latter for quite a long time, a career politician’s ideologies and way of working are constantly exposed to the public eye. Anti-incumbency is easy to creep in and vote swings are common. However, a novice is judged by his intent, not past performance. In most of these cases, people would prefer to give the new face with promising plans a chance. Zelensky won because of this psychological phenomenon. As did Trump with his firebrand nationalist rhetoric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump was inaugurated as President in January 2017. More than two years have passed by, with an eventful international arena. From trade wars with China to the recognition of Jerusalem as the capital of Israel, there has been a lot the world order has had to process. President Trump has been criticised for his thoughtless and confrontational foreign policy. The decision to move the US embassy to Jerusalem has been seen as an appeal to the Jewish vote bank, that Trump seems to enjoy back home. The US pulled out of UNESCO in January 2019, in protest of the organisation’s ‘Anti-Israel’ bias. Failure of the Second Peace Talks with North Korea in Vietnam also points to the same confrontational design that his policies have been accused of. But, admittedly, the political newbie has brought tremors and movements to world politics that have not been since the Iraq and Afghanistan wars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emmanuel Macron, another political novice was elected as the President of France in 2017. He is the founder of the political movement “En Marche!”, and won against the right-wing Marine Le Pen. As opposed to Trump, Macron’s foreign policy has been observed as ‘accommodative’ and ‘cooperative’. From Climate Change to a secure Indo-Pacific, Macron has been known for his decisive contribution to international diplomacy. However, at the domestic front, he has faced a backlash in the form of Yellow Vest Protests against high taxes on Gasoline. In December 2018, his approval ratings fell to 23%, following the poor handling of the Protests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wouldn’t be unwise to say that the political movements across the world have nothing specifically to do with the age and the field of the leader. Leaders can emerge from all walks of life. From the victory of Zelensky, a comedian, to Imran Khan changing the pitch from cricket to politics, the newbies have been quite successful in their endeavours. It might just have to do with the fact that there are always limitations to imagination and career politicians get stale after a point of time. The aspirations of this generation lie with the hope of a faster system and a transparent one. People from the other side of the spectrum are often required to remind the ‘grey-haired’ dinosaurs of what the society really wants.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gurleen Kaur</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Ukraine is now a hot topic in international news due to the historic victory of comedian Volodymyr Zelensky in its Presidential elections. The 41-year old will be Ukraine’s youngest President, with a sweeping victory that comprised 73% of the vote share. The star of The Servant of the People sitcom got the chance of a lifetime as he transitioned from the ‘reel’ to the ‘real’. Zelensky has often been referred to as the ‘Ukrainian Trump’, precisely because of him being a political novice and acquiring the highest public office. With Trump and Zelensky around, the big question is what do the ‘newbies’ have in store for international diplomacy and the world order.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Indian Handicrafts Industry: Craft Beyond the Label</title>
      <link href="/Craft-Beyond-The-Label" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Indian Handicrafts Industry: Craft Beyond the Label" />
      <published>2019-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Craft-Beyond-The-Label</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Craft-Beyond-The-Label">&lt;p&gt;India has always been a land of diversity. It has always welcomed various cultures and traditions. It is a country which has mixed its rich cultural diversity with the economy and markets. The handicraft industry is one of such industries. In India, the industry means more than just work, they are an expression of a particular community, ethnicity, or tradition, employing local craftsmanship and locally sourced materials. The handicrafts have evolved over the centuries, acquiring its present form which is aesthetically pleasing and culturally valuable. The folklores, the dialects, and the tribal lifestyles have inspired the prints. These handicrafts have, thus, shaped the value systems and the vision of the society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the Indian traditional crafts flourished as a result of noble patronage. During the Gupta Period of Indian History (mid-3rd century-5th century), crafts were highly demanded even outside the country. Under the Mughal rule, all kinds of crafts reached their zenith. However, the glory of the Indian handicrafts industry came to the end by the mid-19th century. This was attributed to the ‘Discriminatory tariff policy’, wherein heavy duties were charged on Indian goods entering Britain, India’s colonial masters, while English goods to India were charged nominal duties. This price discrimination, coupled with the growing popularity of machine-made goods was the last nail in the coffin. After India’s Independence in 1947, the emphasis was laid on heavy industries so as to tap the country’s manufacturing potential. Though not on a priority basis, efforts were still made to restore the lost legacy of Indian handicrafts, especially since they were used by Gandhi as part of India’s freedom struggle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The All-India Handicrafts Board was established in November 1952 to identify the problems hampering the development of handicrafts. And the Handicraft and Handloom Export Corporation of India Ltd. was established for the promotion of handicrafts exports. While the institutional structure was apt, the vision was misleading. These institutions focused on promoting the handicrafts, without really improving the productivity of artisans through various incentive models. As a result, the exports grew, however, not up to their full potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Doha Round negotiation of the WTO, in 2005, mandated the removal of quotas for at least 97% of goods from the least-developed countries. Post the negotiation, the Indian handicraft export was expected to improve. And the exports did rise from 155,876 to 170,000 in 2006. But in 2008-09, the exports fell to 80,000 as a result of a global meltdown. India’s share in the world handicraft market is an appalling 2%, as compared to the 17% market share of China. India is home to 6.8 million artisans, but local artisans and traditional craftsmen have failed to crack into the international market. The exports have been controlled by already flourishing designers and a handful of master weavers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The handicrafts industry is largely cottage-based, predominantly located in villages and small towns. Based on Hirschman’s arguments, it is can be easily concluded that the success of any industry depends on the strength of its forward and backward linkages. For the handicraft industry, the diseconomies of scale occur in two forms: (i) high cost of access to markets for raw material (poor backward linkage), and (ii) high cost of access to output market (poor forward linkage). Poor transport infrastructure and facilities cut access to organised input markets. As a result, if the artisans wish to continue, they have to rely on middlemen, who charge higher prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Textbook economics tells us that the seller would sell his produce only in the market which offers the highest possible remuneration. In the handicrafts industry, the local artisans often get a much lower remuneration due to inaccessibility to the highest paying market. For example, jute handicrafts are gaining popularity in the cities (especially after plastic bans). However, an artisan producing in Murshidabad, West Bengal would not be able to take advantage of this due to lack of perfect information. He would be compelled to sell the produce at a lower price to a local trader. However, the trader exploits asymmetric information to earn higher profits in the cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cultural Entrepreneurship entails creating organisations of arts, by and for artists, that are financially sustainable and viable and have a cultural and societal impact. This would enrich the artist’s work by providing support and services and generate more opportunities for collaboration and cooperation. For example, Bhu:sattva, a natural garment brand sources its garments from women self-help groups (SHG) in four districts of the Indian state of Gujarat. Here, community participation through SHGs improved the bargaining power of the artisans and made their businesses profitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community participation can help revive a system more inclusive but similar to what is called the ‘jajmani’ system, credited for the evolution of crafts in the pre-British era. Promoting cluster development for skill training, quality improvement and policy support has been the objective of the SFURTI (Scheme of Fund for Regeneration of Traditional Industries). Reducing tariffs (such as 18% GST on Handicrafts) and giving subsidies will lower average costs, and certainly improve the ease of doing business for the handicraft industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success story of the Japanese craft of ‘basket weaving’, gives us an example of how branding can help an industry survive. Product differentiation did not just save it from extinction, but also elevated it to an art form. The Indian handicrafts industry has failed to carve a niche in the international market as it has failed to effectively utilise branding and marketing techniques. Despite the finesse, their reach is extremely limited. On the other hand, US-based Lisa Fine and John Robshaw have gained recognition by branding the same crafts well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the Indian government is focusing on the skills training of rural artisans under the ‘&lt;em&gt;Deen Dayal Upadhyaya Grameen Kaushalya Yojna&lt;/em&gt;’, a policy for rural empowerment. Designers from the National Institute of Design (NID) and National Institute of Fashion Technology (NIFT) have developed courses to upskill Self-Help Groups (SHGs) and individual artisans. Soft skills training programmes in export marketing, packaging and technology are organised as well. With certification, artisans see a hike in their earnings. A unique initiative by the Union Ministry of Minority Affairs, Hunar Haat (literally, skilled hands) display the rich heritage and skills of master craftsmen from minority communities. This serves several objectives: social and financial inclusion, skill development and the preservation and marketing of cultural traditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we wish to keep up a high price, a high supply has to be matched by high demand. In order to increase the demand, dissemination of information to potential buyers is the key. This can be achieved through better marketing techniques in print and electronic media. In India, the Ministry of Culture is responsible for the promotion of folk and traditional arts through micro-regional targeting via zonal cultural centers. The idea behind education is simple: make people feel connected to indigenous traditions and in turn, make them practitioners or consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing up a new generation of Art patrons is an innovative approach towards increasing demand. In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Wt5_mdW6vTw&quot;&gt;TED Talk&lt;/a&gt;, Joanna Taft shares her idea of establishing a unique high school in Philadelphia. In this school, the curriculum was crafted around Art and Languages along with conventional Science and Social Sciences. Taft’s idea can be applied in the Indian context by designing suitable interventions in the education sector. It is important that young minds do not learn facts in isolation and also learn how art and science developed in tandem. In this way, next-gen leaders, appreciative of art, can be nurtured. This one step would open immense potentials for the handicrafts industry in the long run whilst making a more cultured populace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E-Commerce and the Internet have opened new opportunities for the handicraft industry. The online market has helped local artisans meet their prospective buyers, eliminating the need for middlemen. Government initiatives such as BharatNet for improving internet connectivity in rural areas would have socio-economic impacts for the sector. Conceptualising and implementing needed social, economic and technological interventions can help the handicraft industry reach a sweet spot in the international market, a place that is rightfully deserved.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gurleen Kaur</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">India has always been a land of diversity. It has always welcomed various cultures and traditions. It is a country which has mixed its rich cultural diversity with the economy and markets. The handicraft industry is one of such industries. In India, the industry means more than just work, they are an expression of a particular community, ethnicity, or tradition, employing local craftsmanship and locally sourced materials. The handicrafts have evolved over the centuries, acquiring its present form which is aesthetically pleasing and culturally valuable. The folklores, the dialects, and the tribal lifestyles have inspired the prints. These handicrafts have, thus, shaped the value systems and the vision of the society.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
