<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/sagnik.sarkar/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-08-26T19:12:42+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/sagnik.sarkar/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Self-Censorship By Video Streaming Platforms – Some Critical Issues</title>
      <link href="/Self-Censorship" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Self-Censorship By Video Streaming Platforms – Some Critical Issues" />
      <published>2019-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Self-Censorship</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Self-Censorship">&lt;p&gt;Early in January 2019, several online video streaming platforms – amongst them Amazon Prime, Netflix, Hotstar, and Eros Now – decided to self-censor content on their platforms for Indian viewers based on some general guiding principles. Soon enough, viewers on these platforms reported several scenes blurred in various movies. What are the possible implications of this move?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One argument is that this only brings online video streaming platforms at par with movie theatres and cinema halls. In India, all movies and series must be mandatorily certified by the Central Board of Film Certification (CBFC) before they are allowed to be screened in movie theatres, cinema halls, or on TV. The CBFC often orders some scenes to be cut or blurred out, failing which viewership is restricted to an adult audience only, or worse still, the film is not allowed to be screened at all. Scenes which are even remotely “obscene”, substantially against social morality, or which have the potential to create social friction are frequently the target of such restrictions. The CBFC’s ambit, however, does not extend to films streamed online. This attempt at self-censorship, based on general guiding principles which largely reflect how films are censored by the CBFC in practice, will – in theory – bring films streamed online on these platforms at par with those screened in movie theatres, cinema halls, and on TV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of self-censorship is not new. Advertisers, newspapers, TV channels, and other content publishers and disseminators across the world engage in varying levels of restraint in the content they publish, i.e. self-censorship, in-house or through a common self-regulatory mechanism set by a professional body. For instance, advertisers in India abide by the standards set by the Advertising Standards Council of India, a self-regulatory professional body constituted by advertisers and their representatives themselves. This policy of self-censorship by video streaming platforms is hence not unprecedented in the Indian media industry. However, it does raise its own, unique set of concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the unofficial ‘code’ video streaming platforms have committed themselves to at the moment is too vague, general, and broad. It risks building into the process a large degree of discretion, which may manifest itself as arbitrariness. At worst, it may lead to several versions of the same movie or series airing on different platforms. That will surely have disastrous business implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, there is a glaring lack of an appeals process. Video streaming platforms appear to have carte blanche so far as self-censorship is concerned. An appeals process needs to be built in for the same reason courts of appeal exist – as a remedy against fallible human judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, where are the filmmakers? Excluding filmmakers and film professionals from the process of censorship leads to peculiar, laughable results. For a case in example, consider the Amazon Prime Original series, &lt;i&gt;The Marvellous Mrs. Maisel&lt;/i&gt;. Mrs. Maisel routinely uses expletives while performing as a comedian – that is part of her unique charm. She even exposed her breasts before a club audience while performing an act. These acts get her arrested twice for public indecency, but she continues with them, largely unchanged. That is her unique charm, and it is a central quirk of the character. Now imagine if these expletives were to be censored, and the scene where Mrs. Maisel exposed her breasts cut out. It would strike at the core of the personality of the central character of a show, and therefore ruin the entire show completely. The persons best qualified to appreciate such artistic and cinematic nuances are film professionals, not tech corporates sitting in the air-conditioned offices of a video streaming platform. Delegating the job of censorship to non-film professionals risks this nuance of filmmaking getting lost in the process of censorship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-censorship by online video streaming platforms raises some critical concerns which need to be addressed. It is imperative that online video streaming platforms come up with a clearer, more specific and well-defined code to be guided by while censoring content. An appeals process – both in-house and, at the level of a self-constituted professional body – should be built into such a code. Film professionals must be involved in the entire process of framing a code. Content does not fall on a binary scale of obscene/not obscene. Cinematic nuances, amply illustrated by the example – for instance – of &lt;i&gt;The Marvellous Mrs. Maisel&lt;/i&gt;, need to be kept in mind both while framing the code and during self-censorship.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sagnik Sarkar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Early in January 2019, several online video streaming platforms – amongst them Amazon Prime, Netflix, Hotstar, and Eros Now – decided to self-censor content on their platforms for Indian viewers based on some general guiding principles. Soon enough, viewers on these platforms reported several scenes blurred in various movies. What are the possible implications of this move?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">US Rehab for Taliban Rebels – Finally, a Carrot in the Carrot &amp;amp; Stick?</title>
      <link href="/US-Rehab-for-Taliban-Rebels" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="US Rehab for Taliban Rebels – Finally, a Carrot in the Carrot &amp; Stick?" />
      <published>2019-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/US-Rehab-for-Taliban-Rebels</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/US-Rehab-for-Taliban-Rebels">&lt;p&gt;The United States Department of Defense has announced plans to rehabilitate Taliban rebels in Afghanistan willing to lay down arms. While this may seem like the carrot in the “carrot and stick approach” we desperately need, it is still too early to say much about it. The question this move begs is simple: what is more effective? the carrot or the stick? More often than not, the carrot and  the stick combined is, without a doubt, effective. There’s a reason why economists and management gurus swear it works wonders. Although, it may appear that the problem we’re dealing with has some peculiar issues that would indicate otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eliminating the Taliban from Afghanistan or at least mitigating their tyranny is a good end to strive for. While dealing with problems of a military nature, our general tendency happens to be to meet force with more force. This general rule (which it appears to be) of human nature stemming from a survival instinct is effective in its own way, focusing on it alone though as a strategy risks missing the wood for the trees. The naked strength of the State alone rarely solves many problems – it may allow for some short-term reprieve, but the spectre of the complications almost always eventually returns. We need other necessarily non-military measures to act as force multipliers in this “war” on the Taliban. For too long have the Afghan government and the US attacked the Taliban and been counter-attacked by it. This military conflict has been reminiscent of a cat and mouse game faintly resembling Tom and Jerry. And while this long-drawn conflict has been periodically punctuated by peace talks, they have not really yielded much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the world, many descend into a life of delinquency because that is their best choice. For many deprived of their basic needs, with little or no avenues of education or legal employment, a life of crime is the only (or the best) way to have a fighting chance to survive. Delinquency is therefore often the result of misaligned incentives. While the law can, by the threat of sanctions backed by the physical might of the State, keep this delinquency in check, eliminating the root cause – a lack of education and opportunities for legal employment – is far more effective. To bring existing delinquents out of a life of crime, positive incentives like the promise of a good life and job opportunities work far better than force and punishment alone. By this line of reasoning, this US DoD policy seems right. Taliban rebels can be categorized essentially as delinquents. To bring them out of a life of crime, positive incentives are therefore the need of the hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, are Taliban rebels more than mere delinquents? While it may be tempting to categorise Taliban rebels as mere delinquents like any other, it may also be argued – with good reason – that they are far more than just that. The distinction between terrorists and insurgents vis-à-vis the garden-variety of delinquents exists for a very good reason. The former is usually distinguished from the latter by a far higher degree of unbridled motivation and enthusiasm – much like how a Special Forces soldier is distinguished from the ordinary soldier. Therefore, Taliban rebels should, theoretically, be much less receptive to positive incentives such as these intended to draw them out of a life of insurgency and into civilian life. Their reasons for choosing a life of insurgency and belligerence are not driven solely by impoverishment and unemployment, for there is no denying that the Taliban has been a ruthless terrorist organisation with a sinister agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With both these factors in mind, will this US DoD policy work? Certainly, it may be helpful drawing out the “weakest” of the Taliban rebels. However, ultimately, whether the number of rebels it does bring out of a life of insurgency will be substantial is anyone’s guess. It’s not time to count our chickens yet, they are nowhere close to hatching. But it suffices to say that this US DoD policy is a long needed “carrot” in a largely “stick” approach. It is definitely better, though the jury is still out on how much  better. Meanwhile, Afghan security forces and US troops must continue the unhappy task of continuing their military offensive against the Taliban, even after Trump’s withdrawal decision, for this policy can only ever complement the use of force, not substitute it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sagnik Sarkar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The United States Department of Defense has announced plans to rehabilitate Taliban rebels in Afghanistan willing to lay down arms. While this may seem like the carrot in the “carrot and stick approach” we desperately need, it is still too early to say much about it. The question this move begs is simple: what is more effective? the carrot or the stick? More often than not, the carrot and the stick combined is, without a doubt, effective. There’s a reason why economists and management gurus swear it works wonders. Although, it may appear that the problem we’re dealing with has some peculiar issues that would indicate otherwise.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">India’s Witness Protection Scheme: Opportunities &amp;amp; Challenges</title>
      <link href="/India-Witness-Protection-Scheme" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="India’s Witness Protection Scheme: Opportunities &amp; Challenges" />
      <published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/India-Witness-Protection-Scheme</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/India-Witness-Protection-Scheme">&lt;p&gt;India now has a witness protection programme. Indeed, this is a watershed moment for witnesses, who can finally be protected. Yet, the scheme has many potential hurdles to cross.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016, 4 people moved a petition before the Indian Supreme Court. They had witnessed harassment, intimidation, and threats to witnesses related to them in the infamous Asaram Bapu case, which involved rape allegations against a towering Indian preacher. The SC found the issues of witness protection raised in the petition to be serious, and of pan-India importance, and impleaded the remaining states and UTs as respondents. The views of the states and UTs on a witness protection scheme was sought. The Attorney-General was instructed to frame a draft witness protection scheme. Showing uncommon alacrity, the Home Ministry began soon prepared a draft and placed it before the Court. The states and the UTs were asked to furnish comments on it. Further, the Ministry itself opened a public consultation on the draft, and considered comments from the National Legal Services Authority, High Courts, police personnel and civil society. Finally, taking the comments received from all these stakeholders into account, the Ministry framed the final Witness Protection Scheme, 2018 and placed it before the Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Court promptly accepted it. The Scheme is reproduced in full in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sci.gov.in/supremecourt/2016/34388/34388_2016_Judgement_05-Dec-2018.pdf&quot;&gt;the judgment&lt;/a&gt; of the SC. It came into force on the date of the judgment, December 5, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the level of threat during investigation, trial, or post-trial, witnesses have been categorised into 3 categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;-   Category A:&lt;/strong&gt; Where the threat extends to life of witness or his family members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;-   Category B:&lt;/strong&gt; Where the threat extends to the safety, reputation, or property of the witness or his family members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;-   Category C:&lt;/strong&gt; Where the threat is moderate and extends to harassment or intimidation of the witness or his family members, reputation or property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian States have been directed to set up a State Witness Protection Fund, which shall be the mother goddess feeding the expenditure on the Witness Protection Scheme. Every witness himself, his family members (clearly defined to include only specific relations), his lawyer, and multiple police officers involved in the investigation and imprisonment stage (also clearly defined) have been empowered to file an application for witness protection, preferably to be forwarded through the Prosecutor handling the case. A standard format has been laid down for the application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All such applications are to be considered by a Competent Authority to be set up in every district. The entire process is required to take place in private, and must be completed within 10 days of a request reaching the Authority. In the meanwhile, while processing the request, the Authority may order interim witness protection measures if a threat is imminent. Lastly, but most importantly, everyone involved in the entire process is sworn to secrecy. The investigating officer and the courts are required to acquaint witnesses with this scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witnesses in India are indeed a tired, pathetic lot. It is an open secret that many of them have to bear the brunt of every possible imaginable coercive tactic to silence them or make them go turncoat. Harassment, threats, bribes, attacks on one’s body, property and family are not uncommon. Even attempts on their life are not unheard of. The more powerful the accused the witness is testifying against, the more the danger of falling prey to some or all of these. These coercive tactics often make witnesses turn hostile. Witnesses often turn up dead. Cases built on the bulwark of witness testimony thus fall apart. Indeed, a large number of criminal cases in India continue to be built majorly on witness testimony. Justice thus falls prey to muscle power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, most witnesses and their families do not face outrageous threats. The garden variety, and a substantial part, of threats to witnesses can easily be countered by taking very basic steps, some of which are already standard &lt;em&gt;– viz&lt;/em&gt;. concealment of identity, providing police escorts, monitoring communications, etc. Stakeholders should, first and foremost, concentrate on getting these basics right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Witness Protection Scheme, 2018 has all the features of a world-class witness protection scheme. It provides for global best practices in the field of witness protection to be adopted in India. Properly implemented, this Scheme will be a game changer for the Indian justice system, and a messiah for troubled witnesses across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every successful witness protection scheme is built on the crux of confidentiality. The death of confidentiality is as good as the death of witness protection, and often the reputation, property, and even the life of the witness and his family. In a country where evidence and snippets of the internal working of investigations are often revealed to the media, maintaining the confidentiality of the entire process will be the challenge. The silver lining in the cloud, however, is that India follows an adversarial justice system. Hence, theoretically, every stakeholder in the witness protection scheme―be it the police officers or the prosecutors―works opposite to the defendant[s], and therefore they have an incentive to ensure such confidentiality. The challenge will be to ensure that no other (bad) external incentives &lt;em&gt;– viz&lt;/em&gt;. contacts, mala fide  intentions, etc. – are allowed to interfere with this fine balance. Confidentiality will then be automatically ensured. Instilling a culture of confidentiality amongst all stakeholders, including drilling in the knowledge that a failure to do so can often mean life and death for a person, would also go a long way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manpower and training is another challenge to be overcome. India’s police-people ratio is abysmally low. It will be an uphill task to ensure enough boots on the ground to administer a witness protection programme. This problem is further compounded by the fact that witness protection is often no easy task. It requires specially-trained police officers. Stakeholders may often unwittingly compromise the process if not trained properly. Hence, training of police officers will be a major challenge. Again, the silver lining is that witness protection will be administered by a special Witness Protection Cell of the respective police force. This is a wonderful opportunity to specially train a subset of police officers to be islands of excellence in a sea of mediocrity, who can uphold the ethos of confidentiality and administer witness protection with aplomb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Witness Protection Scheme, 2018 marks a watershed moment in the history of India. It is fraught with opportunities. The time is ripe to make this Scheme into a turning point for the justice system in India. It is now up to us to overcome the hurdles and challenges which lie in the way of its implementation, and make this Scheme the grand success Lady Justice deserves.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sagnik Sarkar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">India now has a witness protection programme. Indeed, this is a watershed moment for witnesses, who can finally be protected. Yet, the scheme has many potential hurdles to cross.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
