<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/morgan.black/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-03-21T21:59:58+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/morgan.black/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">An Anthropological Consideration of Ugandan Knuckles: The Opiate for a Poisoned State</title>
      <link href="/An-Anthropological-Consideration-of-Ugandan-Knuckles" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Anthropological Consideration of Ugandan Knuckles: The Opiate for a Poisoned State" />
      <published>2019-02-07T03:20:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T03:20:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/An-Anthropological-Consideration-of-Ugandan-Knuckles</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/An-Anthropological-Consideration-of-Ugandan-Knuckles">&lt;p&gt;I know, dear reader, that you have thought of this before, as I have; there may, in fact, be far more to the Ugandan Knuckles meme than meets the eye. Could it be that in this chaotic, disorganised vision of a cultural dead space, this wellspring of enjoyment is reflective of our times far more than was initially thought?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ugandan Knuckles meme encompasses, in truth and upon further inspection, a highly complex social structure. It has a diaspora of ethnographically observed motifs spawned forth from its hierarchies, with inner conflicts and philosophical, spiritual quandaries levied against the outside world from the safe confines of VRChat. After all, the people propagating the meme remain, if anything, human. And so from them, we may examine human nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one thing, the acolytes of this subculture organise themselves into a diverse and very complicated hierarchy. It is quite hard to discern, but I believe Knuckles avatars sporting a blue skin as opposed to the common red are still part of the same clan, though there may be a position in the social system implied, which is possibly the &lt;em&gt;“Ugandan Warrior”&lt;/em&gt; class. These will protect the Queen (more on her later). Yellow skin is likely the mark of &lt;em&gt;“The Commander”&lt;/em&gt;, a high position seemingly not coveted but accepted with humility by new initiates. It is likely that they frequently cycle this position over a short term in office and they do this because their true calling is to form a party capable of locating a female monarch.
They operate under a Sacral Democratic Monarchy, for they elect a Queen and will follow this Queen under the belief that she will grant them sacred knowledge of &lt;em&gt;“The Way”&lt;/em&gt;. The requirements for this position are few and, at times, scant or plentifully observed depending on the weeaboo and anime fan presence in the Chat Room. She need only be female, Japanese idol-like (Hatsune Mikus are frequently accosted), or Moe – fluorescent-haired preferable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once they find a Queen, they will fawn over her and begin to voice their contentment with an a-linguistic motif. This is ‘clucking’, a vocalized ‘clock’ sound, as an aspirated glottal &lt;em&gt;/’klɒk/&lt;/em&gt; made with the tongue behind the teeth (very culturally unique) and would be called in linguistic anthropology a non-verbal acoustic call, conveying emotion. If the Queen can be found to have led them astray, the roving pack of miniatures will engage in a ‘spitting’, to indicate their rejection of this false divine saviour. They demand respect for the Queen, crave her love but will also spit on her.
Unfortunately, Ugandan Knuckles politics is far too complex to outline here, but it is apparent that conflicts of interest are quite common. Splinter groups forming as different female players displaying a lolicon aesthetic are frequently happened upon and hailed, willingly or no, as the next holy monarch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the anthropology of religion, The Divine Right, or Holy Mandate to rule is a frequently observed feature of cultures on planet earth where church and state are one. We might point in this case to the cause of such a phenomenon seen here with this meme format being a growing atheistic worldview in our society. As we feel a detachment from the spirit, we see the humorous taking on the responsibility of the severe, in a nervous rebuttal of the empty, godless nation-state. For how can we have faith in leaders who possess no faith themselves? Of course, such practices in the West date back to pre-Christian, Pagan Europe, a paradoxically dark, yet ethno-nationally enlightened time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ugandan Knuckles Clan members’ spiritual path, &lt;em&gt;The Way&lt;/em&gt;, is a nomadistic, possibly nihilistic, and devotional philosophy of the self defined by space and sovereignty tied to one’s destiny. In anthropological terms, this is a Durkheimian consideration of how society maintains coherence and integrity in the modern era, when traditionalism is lost and replaced by less organically defined economic, social institutions. A brother is kin, a member of the clan provides a sense of belonging, the love found in belonging to one’s nation allows for the fortitude necessary to sustain it. To ask, &lt;em&gt;“Why are you running?”&lt;/em&gt;, is to wonder how a friend can flee his destiny. Why doubt oneself? This exemplifies a unique rudimentary cultural Kismet ideology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ugandan Knuckles clans seek only to find meaning and satisfaction in their existence by being close to their Queen and their spiky brethren. This anthropological sense of self is defined as and functions by the mechanisms of Cultural Memory. If they find one of their flock to have strayed from &lt;em&gt;The Way&lt;/em&gt;, or to be in any manner unholy, they will voice sympathy and announce: &lt;em&gt;“We must pray for this one, my brothers”&lt;/em&gt;. Such camaraderie reflects a beauteous, shared heritage in shouldering the burden of life with one’s ethnocultural peers, a sentiment sadly lacking in today’s society, and it ought to be observed! One might say it is the trauma of meandering about, in search of one’s home which acts as what we call in anthropology a &lt;em&gt;“rite of passage”&lt;/em&gt;, serving the purpose of bonding together a generation of young men that they may go out into the world as brothers-in-arms—though this usually applies to something like the Mukanda ritual ceremony of the Ndembu people in Zambia, wherein young boys are taken away from the village at a certain age to have the extremities of their manhood cut-off. During this &lt;em&gt;rite of passage&lt;/em&gt;, young men enter what anthropologists call the Liminal State. In this state, young men are neither man nor child, which allows for the personal transformation of the self, body, and spirit. But how does this happen? Simple. To take from the famous adage;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;i&gt;“Gamers are the most oppressed group”.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the most cursory glance at &lt;em&gt;“Gamer Fashion”&lt;/em&gt;, a subset in the nomenclature formerly known as Gamer/Geek Culture (from which the Ugandan Knuckles ensued) has much to inform us. Gamer T-Shirts, which we will here be using as ethnographic evidence of their material culture, read thusly: &lt;em&gt;“Hey, SNOWFLAKE, there are only two genders, so get over it!”&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;“If you are reading this I’ll have you know I was forced to put my controller down and enter society”&lt;/em&gt;; or &lt;em&gt;“I’m a gamer, not because I don’t have a life, but because I choose to have many!”&lt;/em&gt;. Such a study clearly identifies these G-Fuelled, never-pulled, but-very-virile-in-the-season-pass plucky young miscreants. For these young men belong to the techno-fanatical, pseudo-radical, and pseudo-puritanical generation called Y-Z millennials. A less prudent man might cut themselves on this level of edginess, but not these brave souls, though they do face terrible hardship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, more articles have been published by various millennial plaintiffs decrying this Ugandan Knuckles meme, which they deem to be racist, therefore further displaying just how oppressed these poor, unfortunate outcast souls find themselves. Time and time again, they are dissatisfied with what their society gives them, as the West disowns itself with the neo-feminist, cultural-Marxist criticism of the post-colonial Occident. And yet still as they seek refuge, they are blasted in a flame war to light our skies in Cyberspace for generations. Down the line, they will speak of these days when the completed their rite of passage, as they do of the great Meme Wars, and tales of &lt;em&gt;The Way&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Pepe&lt;/em&gt; alike will be told around pixelated campfires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the same, it ought not be forgotten that the creators of the 2010 Ugandan film &lt;em&gt;Who Killed Captain Alex?&lt;/em&gt;, having originated the quotes whose accents and manners were taken-on by the scarlet Ugandan Faithful have themselves endorsed the meme, sharing many iterations and supporting the sub-culture as best they can from their twitter page, @Wakaliwood. And really, it must not be omitted from the debate that in modern anthropological circles, the principle of Cultural Relativism posits that we should treat all cultures equally! And yet. And yet must this come at the expense of some cultures in favour of others?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To speak as the Geek is to know the Geek; In the words of the ancient 10th-century Anglo-Saxon poem &lt;em&gt;The Wanderer&lt;/em&gt;, as repurposed into King Théoden’s monologue by J. R. R. Tolkien for his LOTR book &lt;em&gt;The Two Towers&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;i&gt;“Where is the horse and the rider? &lt;br /&gt;
Where is the horn that was blowing? &lt;br /&gt;
They have passed like rain on the mountains, &lt;br /&gt;
like wind in the meadow. &lt;br /&gt;
The days have gone down in the West, &lt;br /&gt;
behind the hills... Into Shadow.”&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gentlemen, I say, in recalling the outcry and sensitivity previously observed within the Gaming community by the refrain, &lt;em&gt;“where is the justice for Harambe?”&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;“where is the respect due for this honourable and noble meme which may soon face oblivion?” &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in observing such criticisms, this comes from the same media-climate as the cultural motifs which allowed and indeed enabled the late, bait, sombre-fated Gillette advert to happen, whence we see this same accusatory thought-process levelled against not only all white, cisgendered men but all men in general! Is it any wonder the self-removed would seek solace in the virtual arms of a neon-lit loli?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our current cultural climate is unassertive, unsure and self-destructing. When a culture is diseased, it may find when turning around to scrub behind itself in the shower one day that oddly-formed but quite enigmatically defined growths in the shapes of secondary Sonic the Hedgehog characters have developed upon the rump! Visions beholding plagues of frogs reoccur…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then again, and from a laboratory perspective, the difference between a contemporary consideration of a “model society”, perhaps sat on a table as a maquette of what we might be (as envisioned by those who would have us constantly be in self-un-realisation) and a VR vat containing a vile, porous, clucking swarm of social parasites is that, scientifically speaking, such bacteria will eventually develop its own culture.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Morgan Black</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I know, dear reader, that you have thought of this before, as I have; there may, in fact, be far more to the Ugandan Knuckles meme than meets the eye. Could it be that in this chaotic, disorganised vision of a cultural dead space, this wellspring of enjoyment is reflective of our times far more than was initially thought?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Winter Solstice Ceremony at Stanton Drew Stone Circle</title>
      <link href="/Winter-Solstice-Ceremony" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winter Solstice Ceremony at Stanton Drew Stone Circle" />
      <published>2019-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Winter-Solstice-Ceremony</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Winter-Solstice-Ceremony">&lt;p&gt;How I wish, dear reader, that I might tell you of how blemishless this ceremony was, how perfectly it did unfold, but sadly, it rather unravelled to dismal disappointment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so it was, on Friday, December 21, 2018 at 5 o’clock in the morning, that myself, a cohort, a witch and two accidentally encountered friends (plucked completely by chance as we crossed paths with them on the way to an uber pick-up point) did become companions in the most bizarre but heartwarming of undertakings; there was to be a Druidic ceremony, at sunrise, at a Neolithic stone circle near the village of Stanton Drew on the outskirts of Bristol, UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are greeted by a film crew and a small contingency of middle-aged women cloaked in long robes and walking with staffs at their sides. The filmographic team will be shooting a documentary for National Geographic, with the footage of the ceremony to be narrated by Morgan Freeman (who sadly would not be attending our English rural romp in person).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Battered by wind and rain, we moved all of us through the emptiness of this winter night’s morning and into a dark field. Trundling across the expanse, it seemed our numbers did increase as if by magical apparitions of many who came from all directions, all to converge in a central mass, to become a large group, to surround and step into the circle which was the Stanton Drew Stones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The megaliths loomed out of the darkness as scars of grey, with rippling light, rain running across their listless and ancient surfaces as we shuffled, bustled and edged our way into position. Lights were erected by the film crew but were torn from their hinges by the furious wind, leaving whole swarms of people consumed in pitch black. Thankfully, as if by command, after half an hour, the elements lessened and eased upon us. Shivering in our boots, we were told by the Head Druid assembled with perhaps six or seven of his entourage that the ceremony would soon commence. A single bodhrán (a kind of drum) began playing a steady beat which seemed somehow suddenly louder than the heaviest of the weather—leaving us only with a harsh breeze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We formed, as instructed, a great circle of possibly seventy people all holding hands. The Head Druid came through the only passage of free movement in and out the circle, a parting at the Western stones reminiscent of the passages often seen in Neolithic round barrows. Followed by the others, this leader of neo-pagan priests began a song with simple words by which all could soon join-in, a pleasant if contrived jaunt of a hymn with text and melody likely an oft-heard ditty in such Neo-Pagan communities, mentioning personification of animals and land with a shared spiritual connection, but probably dating back no further than the New Age movement in the 1970’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This man proclaimed the start of this public ritual and the start of a new phase in time, telling us of how this is, at the solstice, a time for new beginnings and rebirth. Our druids then distributed, in perhaps one of the only truly ‘sacred’ moments of the proceeding, branches of mistletoe which had not yet touched the ground. Such a ritual for their procurement, performed by a druid who must climb an oak tree to cut the mistletoe with a golden sickle and allow it to be caught by others in a white cloak, is the only religious practice for which we have definite knowledge, coming to us from the Roman writings of Pliny the Elder. Coupled with the sacrifice of two white bulls, a brew made from this undertaking on the 6th day of the moon was heralded to bestow fertility and cure all ailments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This connection to mistletoe was later perhaps a little misconstrued at our ceremony—one of the druids giving speeches on behalf of the directions, light, darkness, etc, mentions Baldr, the beautiful god, son of Odin and Frigg, who was slain by Loki with an arrow of mistletoe, for though his mother had endeavoured to ask all things in the land to never harm her beloved child, she had neglected this harmless plant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In comparative mythology, one might see a link to the Llew of Welsh legends, who is nigh-unkillable until his beloved Blodeuwedd, the maiden made of flowers, betrays his weakness to an enemy. But this would be the only motif we might connect in this narrative to the ‘Celtic’ identity promulgated by these neo-druids. And until we see evidence of this legend being related to the winter solstice, reader, this punter of the ancient, the eldritch and the occult will not be convinced. In considering the fertility aspect of the divine associated with Celtic festivals, one druid opted to describe the passionate and sexual embrace of his male partner, complete with graphic descriptions of everything they would with their tongues and bodies. He also went about anointing this circular congregation with water, many times, even through the speeches of other druids, saying that water was life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, along with various (unsuccessful) attempts to set alight a soaked pile of bushes in the centre of the circle, multiple wishes that there be ‘peace throughout all the world’, and the gathering being generally unable to fully hear the druids speaking at a pathetically moderate volume on this magnificently windy morning (a far cry indeed from the thunderous tones of Christopher Lee’s operatic chanting atop the tower of Isengard) made the entire affair seem really rather tame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a drab conclusion, having closed once more the gates of the North, the East and company (but mistaking one for the other), the circle, now blessed by dim, grey daylight, concluded the happenings with probably the best part of that morning, this being a great skipping and hopping, a roving of the congregation that so that we became a revolving set of linked lines in a disorganised but joyful dance set to traditional music. We thence went our separate, hitch-hiking ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you ask me – and in fact, ask anyone you like – paganism ought to be something wild. Raw and uncompromising, within reason of course, and putting us in-mind at least in spirit of the fierce pre-Christian people who did once inhabit this noble and ancient land. And yet, bearing in consideration the words of these, in truth, well-meaning hippies, I begin to wonder, as a man must if he is to mean anything to himself and his close ones, what is it I must give up, in the new year? What is it that I must sacrifice? As my ancestors did before. And what is it I hope for in return?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I leave you with this; the solstice is a time of loss. With thoughts drawn as to what we must gain and what we cannot live without. In place of new year’s resolutions, let us have new year’s dissolutions, in considering the sacrifices we may make, and perhaps must make, in our personal lives. Here is hoping that one day, we will in the South of Britain be able to put on a show in a ritualistic, religious context the likes of which our friends in the North, the Scots, have achieved every year on April, 30 since 1988 at the Beltane Fire Festival, in Edinburgh. Scantily-clad, red-body-painted dancers, revellers and all. I will look for you in the slithy toves and among the bracken and the rough. I will be there in that wind-scathed paysage, upon yonder scraggy and leering hill. Will I see you?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Morgan Black</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">How I wish, dear reader, that I might tell you of how blemishless this ceremony was, how perfectly it did unfold, but sadly, it rather unravelled to dismal disappointment.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
