<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/morgan.black/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-09-09T17:33:08+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/morgan.black/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Jadis the Bells: The Pyres of Notre Dame</title>
      <link href="/The-Pyres-of-Notre-Dame" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jadis the Bells: The Pyres of Notre Dame" />
      <published>2019-04-25T14:05:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-25T14:05:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Pyres-of-Notre-Dame</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Pyres-of-Notre-Dame">&lt;p&gt;Jadis, the bells. Paris is in flames. Notre de Dame de Paris, my dearest, most
cherished Cathedral, our Lady of Paris, is burning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or certainly, it was when I began writing. Now it sits, an exhausted carcass,
divested of that eldest of jewels from the Parisian skyline. Much of the stained
glass is ruined. And the windows have been blinded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is particularly painful for all French people. I, like many of them, have a
long, difficult and passionate relationship with Notre Dame, mostly because of
how much I have sung about it. I remember the first time I saw the Cathedral
itself depicted, in the Disney film, &lt;em&gt;The Hunchback of Notre Dame&lt;/em&gt;. The most
gothic, the darkest piece in the mouse’s repertoire, it marked me as a child.
The first time I heard those voices, coupled with those spires, stabbing into
that sky, I was terrified, I was exhilarated, I was amazed at the power of the
artistic and dark marvel. It stayed with me forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The passion people can have for something so immortal as a building can truly
show how they can bring out the personhood within our creations, the moral in
the static. Anthropology has much to say about such things, particularly in the
works of Michel Foucault, especially on how architecture affects peoples’
feelings; how their surroundings affect their moods; how buildings can be so
evocative, purely because of this integral intransitive nature of the human
spirit, because of this very ghost within the shell. And what ghosts do haunt
our cities now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Victor Hugo knew this, in fact he published that famous hunchback’s tale in an
effort to generate public interest in the Cathedral, which was at the time
Paris’s local, dilapidated and forgotten ruin. His book, in time, helped garner
enough interest to pay for the restorations we saw crumble and part into dust
and smoke in the wind. And so that spirit passes. And so passes the old Europe,
into oblivion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I ever sang a solo in our rural town’s music conservatoire young
choir, at say 12 or 13, I knew what I would sing about. I still remember my name
being called, as I stepped out from behind the curtain to expectant applause,
and the bells shook, and the voices did swell, until my queue, on a little
accordion…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Morning in Paris, the city awakes to the Bells of Notre Dame. The fisherman
fishes, the bakerman bakes, to the Bells of Notre Dame. From the big bells as
LOUD as the Thunder, to the little bells as -soft- as a psalm, and SOME say the
SOUL of the city’s the TOLL of the bells… The Bells of Notre Dame. Kyrie
eleison…”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it was never the same for me again. I still remember sitting in the cellar
of our old 15th century house, in France, intermittently watching the musical
Notre Dame de Paris, waiting for my calls to help with the dinners we would host
at the Manor. I sat in awe as Bruneau Pelletier sang away about “a time of
Cathedrals”, becoming one of my vocal heroes, the song becoming one of my go-to
standards. That famous song of the successful musical show touches on the advent
of the Cathedral as a symbol of man’s growing ambition in Europe, heralded by
the Gothic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the passage from Romanesque to Gothic architecture, in making the buildings
bigger, European architecture had looked to nature to make the inside of
churches resemble the outside world and was inspired by the natural landscape
for decoration and adaptation of space. The very term ‘gothic’ itself was used
derogatively by writers like Molière to criticise a barbarous, pagan style
called monstrous by association with a less ‘civilised’ age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By very virtue of worshipping a ‘pagus’, a local spirit of nature, the earlier
pagans venerated nature, and medieval Christian churches began to take on
aspects emulative of the ‘nemetons’, sacred groves of the heathens from Europe
of yore. Greeks and Romans themselves had their ‘tenemos’, areas of vegetation
or clearings separated from public use, for a religious purpose (associated with
the female Oracle at Delphi; perhaps related to the Greek &lt;em&gt;delphus&lt;/em&gt;, ‘womb’).
The Norse Poetic &lt;em&gt;Edda&lt;/em&gt; features the open-air ‘hörgr’ (harrow, etymologically
related to ‘heathen’). D. Wilson notes that for the Anglo-Saxons, the hörgr is
specifically a “special type of religious site, that occupied a prominent
position on high land and was a communal place of worship for a specific group
of people”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon, almost as if inspired by a divine, pagan purpose sleeping within them, as
if it had been dictated to them by an ancestral wisdom, the medieval European
builders of gothic churches beheld the truly sacred, the natural world, and made
of it a cold, stone creation. They took the magical outside, brought it inside,
and made of it the prerogative of their one god and the possession of the mortal
man. All of this, in simple architecture, in ancient stone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the veneration of fertility in the form of resplendent, beautiful goddesses
was retained somehow by the Europeans of old Paris, for though referring to the
Virgin Mary, they made of this now presently wounded cathedral, ‘Our Lady’, of
the city.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I saw the place in person was in 2017 on a much belated visit to
the capital, I was shy and nervous about the city, like an estranged friend,
like a lost lover, but when I arrived with a companion acting as guide at the
station of the Isle de la Cité, then I knew. Then I felt it. The soul of Paris.
It was about time. It was about the enduring, deepest European aspect. And then
we went upstairs, and to the street. And I heard it. I heard them. The bells of
Notre Dame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I finally did go inside, it was a deeply spiritual experience, but not for
Christian reasons. For only then did I feel and know Paris. The high ceilings
and high halls, evoking Europe’s ancient sacred groves of tall trees, oak, pine
and poplar. The Cathedral’s small park by the Seine, watching the people of the
city go by, young people, young students, people from intelligent cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People love their cities, and they love the buildings which they and their kin
have woken up to and walked past for centuries. Such a paysage of human
construction acts to support a sort of consistency of a nation’s spirit. These
buildings are a skeleton, they are the frameworks which contain and maintain the
very culture of the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so everywhere, on our social media platforms, on our video-streaming
services, all that can be heard is that “Europe is dying!”. It is not the first
time a great fire having devastated a great edifice of cultural import has
prompted reactions of national significance. Most significantly, comparisons can
be drawn to the 1933 Reichstag Fire, when the burning of the historic German
Parliament building in Berlin allowed Adolf Hitler to put the country into a
state of national alert. This was the first and most conclusive step towards
seizing power on a national scale for Hitler, and it sealed Germany’s future
forever.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conspiracies have abounded for decades and ever will as to the cause of such
fires. But the consequences of such fires are inarguable: grim, dejected locals,
suddenly feeling a great need to protect what is theirs for pride and for
sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, poor Notre Dame. If her bells do not sound, Paris is made mute. If her
glass does not shine, Paris is blinded. But we must not forget that as long as
her children live, Our Lady of Paris survives. And so we must look to future
truth, and future Europeans. If their spirit built her, their spirit can do and
ought to do so much more than this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jadis, les cloches. Adieux Notre Dame. Adieux Paris. I owe you the letters after
my name. And I hear you forever in my heart. Jadis, the bells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this comes now, when we see ourselves go mad, when a black hole is seen for
the first time, and we stare into it; the abyss stares back, and smiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw fire, and as it presides over us now, the black hole sun dawns. A vile
rictus upon us. How destiny does smile, sickeningly. How the fates, as the
vates, do seem to have a sense of humour. Clown World begins. A Circle of fire
forms.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Morgan Black</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Jadis, the bells. Paris is in flames. Notre de Dame de Paris, my dearest, most cherished Cathedral, our Lady of Paris, is burning. Or certainly, it was when I began writing. Now it sits, an exhausted carcass, divested of that eldest of jewels from the Parisian skyline. Much of the stained glass is ruined. And the windows have been blinded. This is particularly painful for all French people. I, like many of them, have a long, difficult and passionate relationship with Notre Dame, mostly because of how much I have sung about it. I remember the first time I saw the Cathedral itself depicted, in the Disney film, The Hunchback of Notre Dame. The most gothic, the darkest piece in the mouse’s repertoire, it marked me as a child. The first time I heard those voices, coupled with those spires, stabbing into that sky, I was terrified, I was exhilarated, I was amazed at the power of the artistic and dark marvel. It stayed with me forever. The passion people can have for something so immortal as a building can truly show how they can bring out the personhood within our creations, the moral in the static. Anthropology has much to say about such things, particularly in the works of Michel Foucault, especially on how architecture affects peoples’ feelings; how their surroundings affect their moods; how buildings can be so evocative, purely because of this integral intransitive nature of the human spirit, because of this very ghost within the shell. And what ghosts do haunt our cities now. Victor Hugo knew this, in fact he published that famous hunchback’s tale in an effort to generate public interest in the Cathedral, which was at the time Paris’s local, dilapidated and forgotten ruin. His book, in time, helped garner enough interest to pay for the restorations we saw crumble and part into dust and smoke in the wind. And so that spirit passes. And so passes the old Europe, into oblivion. The first time I ever sang a solo in our rural town’s music conservatoire young choir, at say 12 or 13, I knew what I would sing about. I still remember my name being called, as I stepped out from behind the curtain to expectant applause, and the bells shook, and the voices did swell, until my queue, on a little accordion… “Morning in Paris, the city awakes to the Bells of Notre Dame. The fisherman fishes, the bakerman bakes, to the Bells of Notre Dame. From the big bells as LOUD as the Thunder, to the little bells as -soft- as a psalm, and SOME say the SOUL of the city’s the TOLL of the bells… The Bells of Notre Dame. Kyrie eleison…”. And it was never the same for me again. I still remember sitting in the cellar of our old 15th century house, in France, intermittently watching the musical Notre Dame de Paris, waiting for my calls to help with the dinners we would host at the Manor. I sat in awe as Bruneau Pelletier sang away about “a time of Cathedrals”, becoming one of my vocal heroes, the song becoming one of my go-to standards. That famous song of the successful musical show touches on the advent of the Cathedral as a symbol of man’s growing ambition in Europe, heralded by the Gothic. In the passage from Romanesque to Gothic architecture, in making the buildings bigger, European architecture had looked to nature to make the inside of churches resemble the outside world and was inspired by the natural landscape for decoration and adaptation of space. The very term ‘gothic’ itself was used derogatively by writers like Molière to criticise a barbarous, pagan style called monstrous by association with a less ‘civilised’ age. By very virtue of worshipping a ‘pagus’, a local spirit of nature, the earlier pagans venerated nature, and medieval Christian churches began to take on aspects emulative of the ‘nemetons’, sacred groves of the heathens from Europe of yore. Greeks and Romans themselves had their ‘tenemos’, areas of vegetation or clearings separated from public use, for a religious purpose (associated with the female Oracle at Delphi; perhaps related to the Greek delphus, ‘womb’). The Norse Poetic Edda features the open-air ‘hörgr’ (harrow, etymologically related to ‘heathen’). D. Wilson notes that for the Anglo-Saxons, the hörgr is specifically a “special type of religious site, that occupied a prominent position on high land and was a communal place of worship for a specific group of people”. Soon, almost as if inspired by a divine, pagan purpose sleeping within them, as if it had been dictated to them by an ancestral wisdom, the medieval European builders of gothic churches beheld the truly sacred, the natural world, and made of it a cold, stone creation. They took the magical outside, brought it inside, and made of it the prerogative of their one god and the possession of the mortal man. All of this, in simple architecture, in ancient stone. Even the veneration of fertility in the form of resplendent, beautiful goddesses was retained somehow by the Europeans of old Paris, for though referring to the Virgin Mary, they made of this now presently wounded cathedral, ‘Our Lady’, of the city.   The first time I saw the place in person was in 2017 on a much belated visit to the capital, I was shy and nervous about the city, like an estranged friend, like a lost lover, but when I arrived with a companion acting as guide at the station of the Isle de la Cité, then I knew. Then I felt it. The soul of Paris. It was about time. It was about the enduring, deepest European aspect. And then we went upstairs, and to the street. And I heard it. I heard them. The bells of Notre Dame. When I finally did go inside, it was a deeply spiritual experience, but not for Christian reasons. For only then did I feel and know Paris. The high ceilings and high halls, evoking Europe’s ancient sacred groves of tall trees, oak, pine and poplar. The Cathedral’s small park by the Seine, watching the people of the city go by, young people, young students, people from intelligent cities. People love their cities, and they love the buildings which they and their kin have woken up to and walked past for centuries. Such a paysage of human construction acts to support a sort of consistency of a nation’s spirit. These buildings are a skeleton, they are the frameworks which contain and maintain the very culture of the people. And so everywhere, on our social media platforms, on our video-streaming services, all that can be heard is that “Europe is dying!”. It is not the first time a great fire having devastated a great edifice of cultural import has prompted reactions of national significance. Most significantly, comparisons can be drawn to the 1933 Reichstag Fire, when the burning of the historic German Parliament building in Berlin allowed Adolf Hitler to put the country into a state of national alert. This was the first and most conclusive step towards seizing power on a national scale for Hitler, and it sealed Germany’s future forever.    Conspiracies have abounded for decades and ever will as to the cause of such fires. But the consequences of such fires are inarguable: grim, dejected locals, suddenly feeling a great need to protect what is theirs for pride and for sovereignty. And so, poor Notre Dame. If her bells do not sound, Paris is made mute. If her glass does not shine, Paris is blinded. But we must not forget that as long as her children live, Our Lady of Paris survives. And so we must look to future truth, and future Europeans. If their spirit built her, their spirit can do and ought to do so much more than this. Jadis, les cloches. Adieux Notre Dame. Adieux Paris. I owe you the letters after my name. And I hear you forever in my heart. Jadis, the bells. And this comes now, when we see ourselves go mad, when a black hole is seen for the first time, and we stare into it; the abyss stares back, and smiles. I saw fire, and as it presides over us now, the black hole sun dawns. A vile rictus upon us. How destiny does smile, sickeningly. How the fates, as the vates, do seem to have a sense of humour. Clown World begins. A Circle of fire forms.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Circle of Fire: A Lament and Lesson for Europe</title>
      <link href="/Circle-of-Fire" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Circle of Fire: A Lament and Lesson for Europe" />
      <published>2019-04-11T04:29:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-11T04:29:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Circle-of-Fire</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Circle-of-Fire">&lt;p&gt;1818, in a dusty, dawn-cast attic of a stately home, a statue begins to turn
from the grey of shaped limestone to the radiant gold of marble. It is a copy of
a very old Roman copy, of a Greek sculpture: “The Dying Gaul”, as commissioned
by Attalus I of Pergamon while celebrating his victory over the Celts of Turkey
in the 3rd Century BCE. In the dusty room, at daybreak, an amber light shines on
the torque tightly clasping the statue’s neck, a circle somehow proud, yet
broken, beneath his downcast brow. The “Dying Gaul” is depicted as so dismal, so
dejected a thing that many observe an inherent sadness in him. Admiring the
skill of the artist, even Lord Byron himself writes about the pathos engendered
by the scene. However, he dubs him &lt;em&gt;The Dying Gladiator&lt;/em&gt;, and so even as an art
piece, this lost, false picture of a man is, like his race, truly forgotten.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many miles away, in Lahore, modern-day Pakistan, a Sikh wears a “Chakram” as he
prepares for a wedding ceremony. These metal rings recalling the mythological
weapon of the Hindu god Krishna, the disc-bearer. Despite having lost their
practical functionality after the British arrived, “chakrams” retain their
symbolic importance. Even in a Punjabi wedding, Indo-European Vedic traditions
remain, as a bride to be wedded has her feet painted in Mehndi by a woman older
than herself and already happily married.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So telling, how these traits of myth may endure, even through the ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The role of mythology, of all “divine poetry”, is to act as superlative verse to
the layman’s consideration of the passing day, to act as sacred words which fill
colour into the profane of our world. In fact, we might see our culture itself
as a sort of divine consort, as a partner to our existence, and determine that
an individual divested of culture is lonely. Our cultural identity is,
therefore, our spouse and it is given to us by our heritage. Ultimately, the
only thing which separates one group of people from another is the place they
are situated in, and religious beliefs are formed dependent on the surroundings
of said people. You would only pray for the sorts of things your lands made
plentiful or precious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, what follows is this: all mythology encompasses the relationship of a
people with their geological environment. This makes all religion, all cultural
heritage an ontological understanding of one’s surroundings. We process the
existence we know. That is the truly pagan way of being in oneself, that is the
truly human way. Nature will teach you; it will teach you everything. Nature has
many faces, but one voice and we must remember that Mother Nature has no
obligation to be fair to you. Neither do natural forces. But you can try to
understand them. Even, dare I say, try to communicate with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All religion serves to reconcile the distance between the earthly and the
heavenly, and it seems one patch of Earth, lived upon by one people in
opposition to another, becomes a different Earth. And the force which marries us
to our geographically-defined culture, religion, etc., is the same which would
bind one person to another. Once, what was called Sati in one place was observed
in different forms in others. Accounts from Ibn Fadlan and the verses from the
&lt;em&gt;Sigurðarkviða hin skamma&lt;/em&gt; assert that Norse people would offer up a wealthy
Chieftain’s &lt;em&gt;thralls&lt;/em&gt; or slaves, to his funeral pyre after his passing, and
Julius Caesar says the same of the Celts in &lt;em&gt;De Bello Gallico&lt;/em&gt;. This Roman
account is the origin of the ‘Wicker Man’ stereotype, where beloved ‘dependants’
of the deceased are given up along with other offerings to be purified into
something others would call &lt;em&gt;Agni&lt;/em&gt;, the sacred fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be more virtuous to plaster all discourse pertaining to such things
with comments on the barbarous vestiges of a less appropriately enlightened
past, but it might be more useful still to understand why people would do such
things. And so go from “ignorance to truth, darkness to light, and death to
immortality,” as per that enigmatic mantra echoed in Hindu Yagna rituals, it
would seem. If truth could be light. If that light could be immortality, it
would take the shape of a fire fed by and specified by one’s very beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how our belief ties us to our people, to our lands. We live and die by
them. We do not simply have our culture follow us into the fire. We go because
of it. And whether that is ethically speaking without blemish or not, it is
certainly powerful. We do things which seem illogical, which other animals do
not do. A culture is a truth, it is an understanding of the world. In such a
way, it considers rules and identifies what is to be prized in this
understanding of the world, and what is to be deemed more unsightly. And this is
the nature of our identities, as humans, as ethnicities. This is how we are
married to our cultures, not in bondage, but in heritage, as per a hypernatural,
proto-legal contract. This is us. &lt;em&gt;Alive&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Europe is becoming even less alive itself, because it is becoming less
Christian, which in and of itself would not necessitate unfortunate
circumstances, if only it did not entail the rise of Atheism. As a consequence,
Europe becomes ‘more lonely’. It manages the extraordinary feat of being somehow
formed of so many countries which remain so impossibly isolated from each other.
Yet, indeed, it is natural that this continent should have no faith, and no
faith in itself, for such things were bored out of it by the Romans and
Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is my customary finding that things usually succeed in doing what they were
designed to do, and Christianity was designed to make the European people
complacent and easy to control. No wonder that as it falls, as the Church
awakens to every nightmare about paedophilia accusations in this hypocritical
bed it has made for itself, Europeans are not only impossible to control, but
they are directionless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christianity is more impactful from a cultural perspective than a spiritual one;
it served as a device of enforcing the Roman rule and extending the duration of
their Empire, supplanting an enduring (arguably militant) presence in their
lands as an oppressive crushing of culture on a local scale, imposing a single
identity-defining dogma. It was applied to control, and now the people are
uncontrollable, and inconsolably unruly since the Roman rule has decayed. Yet,
it is the state of the dominated to retain their chains after their master has
met their demise. It is surprising Europe has taken so long to throw off the
very yoke of Christendom in the first place. Albeit, Christianity had been
unknowingly preserving truly European, pagan culture. And, as it falls, so does
its inherited identity. Atheism has come and it brings with it a cold, stark
divestment of the European spirit from the European body. This makes every man
and woman less than human, for all different world cultures, all at least have a
notion of the spirit, and a cornered animal lashes out because it is afraid,
outnumbered, perhaps. &lt;em&gt;Alone&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a time of division. Even as we speak, conversations are cracking open
about the consequences of Brexit in regards to Ireland’s relationship with
Northern Ireland, and while a united Éire may seem like a step forward, it also
indicates the breaking down of a much older order. One thing upon which we all
can agree is that changes are afoot. For better or for worse, it seems this
great and old continent will never be the same again. The end of individual
difference, so surely the end of our differences altogether, no? Ultimate unity
through ultimate, violent equity. Of course, it is rather beneficial for Church
and State alike to have its people be without identity; they are so much easier
to pra(e)y upon! And so, behold the touted saviour: &lt;em&gt;Socialism&lt;/em&gt;. It is at the
heart of globalisation, but socialism was purely and only an advent of chaos, a
machine designed to destroy. Karl Marx did not want to help the working classes,
but he did want to make them kill people, often each other.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marx believed a great change was on the horizon, but the problem with his ideas
was that he believed the change could only and must be reached via great
conflict. He believed society was on the verge of collapse, he never incited
peaceful resolution or the empowerment of workers and always sought only to arm
them rather than communicate with them. When he visited the German Workers’
Education Society of London in 1845, he found self-educated, self-made men. They
were anti-liberal, anti-bohemian and practically-minded, and he saw them as
lowly for not sharing his apocalyptic ambitions for the future. They engaged in
practical discussion, though without academic training in philosophy (which is
why he disliked working men and thought them beneath himself). This was not what
he wanted. He wanted revolution and chaos, for as he stated: “Socialism cannot
be brought into existence without revolution”. When his father died in 1838, he
spent much of his inheritance of 6000 ₣ on arming Belgian workers with guns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly, the violent revolutions of the country I grew up in, France, have a
long history indeed of upheaving everything and distracting from the country’s
problems until they go away, but they ultimately benefited slightly wealthier
men seizing power, only to be deposed by men slightly less wealthy than
themselves. Every time, it is the slightly less hard-working man who gains
leadership at the expense of the slightly harder working man. The same can be
seen in the French-backed American Revolution, a systematic upheaval which
allowed wealthy English landowners in the New World to detach themselves from
their colonial control of ‘The British’ under the new identity of ‘The
American’, and they profited and suffered immensely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, marrying oneself to a new culture, a new identity, will dictate one’s
destiny. And so come into focus the fires of modern-day Paris, lit by the Gilets
Jaunes. Fire once more presides the times of chaos, the times of change. So how,
I ask, can this, revolution, be the answer? I cannot agree that Marx was right
in the larger sense that it is necessary, but I must wonder as to his related
belief that it is inevitable. Visions of fire, revolution and chaos, and one
must think of the Wheel of Fire, a Greek mythological image originating in the
punishment of Ixion after his lusting for Zeus’s divine consort, Hera. It
signifies a torturous chain of events leading to dire consequences, in result of
personal actions or flaws which are ultimately the victim’s fault. It provides a
caveat to be considered, in matters of want and misplaced ambition. It is the
fall from grace, and it is engendered by the foreboding betrayal of a sacred
matrimony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I attend a concert by the folk-rock band Faun, at the end, a skaldic
lutist/mandolin player speaks as a grandiose orator, transforming from the
humble, weaselly man he has been every other time we hear him speak into
something approaching the divine musician we have seen play, as when he
performs, as when he sings. His band’s spectacle reaches an emotive pinnacle as
he speaks, almost preaching now, but with such zeal the likes of which a
hurricane could not bring any modern Christian priest to muster, with the
passion not seen since they were not merely excused by the burning of our wise
women but corralled it. The kind of power not seen unless truth and conviction
bolster the rightful in their unextinguished focus; he says we must remember who
we are. Remember nature. Our own nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As he speaks in his complete form, finally, but only once, is mentioned the
creature who is the namesake of the band, the faun, the Pan figure, who just
like Krishna plays the flute and sits surrounded by the animals, a Master of
Beasts. And then he says how it was known by another name to the Celts, as
Cernunnos. Thus begins the cycle. A vision of a devil. A vision of nature,
personified. A herald of flame to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I contemplate this apple of my eye which I see on the horizon. Knowledge
of paganism is the knowledge of how to live and connect with our environment of
Europe, and so I say that, for the West, to transcend Christendom via the
produce of the trees of knowledge is the only way that we will be able to live
in this garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The serpent penetrates the apple. Perhaps, it is to be seized, like the
Snake-Witch Stone shows, perhaps it is to be defeated like the biblical
Leviathan. But it is no primitive return to nature which will save us now, but a
mature and learned taking into oneself the ways of yore. We must make of
ourselves ergonomic beings. A form of cultural bio-mimicry will be observed in
ancient lore, and this will tell us how to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, there are philosophies and facts to be observed in the natural
world, echoed in mythology, which can inform us on how to live our lives, so we
can be healthier, but also on how we should think, so we can be &lt;em&gt;holier&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I think on this vision, I must wonder what ‘true spiritual sun’ will be
unveiled to us, ‘hidden by a disc of golden light’. What truth will be known,
what duty done? What sacred feet, anointed now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking to the future, for Europe, for the world? &lt;em&gt;Fire&lt;/em&gt;. But will it be a wheel
or a dawn? This will depend on the nature, the aspect and, I fear, upon the
reception of this, the &lt;em&gt;Truth&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These tales of myth and history weave in and out of each other, they remind us
of our inherent shared heritage defined not as humans, but as people. For, in
commiseration with history, mythology serves not only to grant us stories from
the past where we may learn how to rise, but also stories of the soul, that we
may learn not to fall. And what these similarities do tell us is that Europe
should be united under common ground, regardless of any Union - so long as it
remains European. As such, it is time Europe decided to whom it would be married
and what is to be the philosophical companion to its destiny, what identity will
accompany it towards an uncertain future. Some would say we look outside, or
without. I merely say we look within.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Morgan Black</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">1818, in a dusty, dawn-cast attic of a stately home, a statue begins to turn from the grey of shaped limestone to the radiant gold of marble. It is a copy of a very old Roman copy, of a Greek sculpture: “The Dying Gaul”, as commissioned by Attalus I of Pergamon while celebrating his victory over the Celts of Turkey in the 3rd Century BCE. In the dusty room, at daybreak, an amber light shines on the torque tightly clasping the statue’s neck, a circle somehow proud, yet broken, beneath his downcast brow. The “Dying Gaul” is depicted as so dismal, so dejected a thing that many observe an inherent sadness in him. Admiring the skill of the artist, even Lord Byron himself writes about the pathos engendered by the scene. However, he dubs him The Dying Gladiator, and so even as an art piece, this lost, false picture of a man is, like his race, truly forgotten.   Many miles away, in Lahore, modern-day Pakistan, a Sikh wears a “Chakram” as he prepares for a wedding ceremony. These metal rings recalling the mythological weapon of the Hindu god Krishna, the disc-bearer. Despite having lost their practical functionality after the British arrived, “chakrams” retain their symbolic importance. Even in a Punjabi wedding, Indo-European Vedic traditions remain, as a bride to be wedded has her feet painted in Mehndi by a woman older than herself and already happily married. So telling, how these traits of myth may endure, even through the ages. The role of mythology, of all “divine poetry”, is to act as superlative verse to the layman’s consideration of the passing day, to act as sacred words which fill colour into the profane of our world. In fact, we might see our culture itself as a sort of divine consort, as a partner to our existence, and determine that an individual divested of culture is lonely. Our cultural identity is, therefore, our spouse and it is given to us by our heritage. Ultimately, the only thing which separates one group of people from another is the place they are situated in, and religious beliefs are formed dependent on the surroundings of said people. You would only pray for the sorts of things your lands made plentiful or precious. Therefore, what follows is this: all mythology encompasses the relationship of a people with their geological environment. This makes all religion, all cultural heritage an ontological understanding of one’s surroundings. We process the existence we know. That is the truly pagan way of being in oneself, that is the truly human way. Nature will teach you; it will teach you everything. Nature has many faces, but one voice and we must remember that Mother Nature has no obligation to be fair to you. Neither do natural forces. But you can try to understand them. Even, dare I say, try to communicate with them. All religion serves to reconcile the distance between the earthly and the heavenly, and it seems one patch of Earth, lived upon by one people in opposition to another, becomes a different Earth. And the force which marries us to our geographically-defined culture, religion, etc., is the same which would bind one person to another. Once, what was called Sati in one place was observed in different forms in others. Accounts from Ibn Fadlan and the verses from the Sigurðarkviða hin skamma assert that Norse people would offer up a wealthy Chieftain’s thralls or slaves, to his funeral pyre after his passing, and Julius Caesar says the same of the Celts in De Bello Gallico. This Roman account is the origin of the ‘Wicker Man’ stereotype, where beloved ‘dependants’ of the deceased are given up along with other offerings to be purified into something others would call Agni, the sacred fire. It might be more virtuous to plaster all discourse pertaining to such things with comments on the barbarous vestiges of a less appropriately enlightened past, but it might be more useful still to understand why people would do such things. And so go from “ignorance to truth, darkness to light, and death to immortality,” as per that enigmatic mantra echoed in Hindu Yagna rituals, it would seem. If truth could be light. If that light could be immortality, it would take the shape of a fire fed by and specified by one’s very beliefs. This is how our belief ties us to our people, to our lands. We live and die by them. We do not simply have our culture follow us into the fire. We go because of it. And whether that is ethically speaking without blemish or not, it is certainly powerful. We do things which seem illogical, which other animals do not do. A culture is a truth, it is an understanding of the world. In such a way, it considers rules and identifies what is to be prized in this understanding of the world, and what is to be deemed more unsightly. And this is the nature of our identities, as humans, as ethnicities. This is how we are married to our cultures, not in bondage, but in heritage, as per a hypernatural, proto-legal contract. This is us. Alive. But Europe is becoming even less alive itself, because it is becoming less Christian, which in and of itself would not necessitate unfortunate circumstances, if only it did not entail the rise of Atheism. As a consequence, Europe becomes ‘more lonely’. It manages the extraordinary feat of being somehow formed of so many countries which remain so impossibly isolated from each other. Yet, indeed, it is natural that this continent should have no faith, and no faith in itself, for such things were bored out of it by the Romans and Christianity. It is my customary finding that things usually succeed in doing what they were designed to do, and Christianity was designed to make the European people complacent and easy to control. No wonder that as it falls, as the Church awakens to every nightmare about paedophilia accusations in this hypocritical bed it has made for itself, Europeans are not only impossible to control, but they are directionless. Christianity is more impactful from a cultural perspective than a spiritual one; it served as a device of enforcing the Roman rule and extending the duration of their Empire, supplanting an enduring (arguably militant) presence in their lands as an oppressive crushing of culture on a local scale, imposing a single identity-defining dogma. It was applied to control, and now the people are uncontrollable, and inconsolably unruly since the Roman rule has decayed. Yet, it is the state of the dominated to retain their chains after their master has met their demise. It is surprising Europe has taken so long to throw off the very yoke of Christendom in the first place. Albeit, Christianity had been unknowingly preserving truly European, pagan culture. And, as it falls, so does its inherited identity. Atheism has come and it brings with it a cold, stark divestment of the European spirit from the European body. This makes every man and woman less than human, for all different world cultures, all at least have a notion of the spirit, and a cornered animal lashes out because it is afraid, outnumbered, perhaps. Alone. This is a time of division. Even as we speak, conversations are cracking open about the consequences of Brexit in regards to Ireland’s relationship with Northern Ireland, and while a united Éire may seem like a step forward, it also indicates the breaking down of a much older order. One thing upon which we all can agree is that changes are afoot. For better or for worse, it seems this great and old continent will never be the same again. The end of individual difference, so surely the end of our differences altogether, no? Ultimate unity through ultimate, violent equity. Of course, it is rather beneficial for Church and State alike to have its people be without identity; they are so much easier to pra(e)y upon! And so, behold the touted saviour: Socialism. It is at the heart of globalisation, but socialism was purely and only an advent of chaos, a machine designed to destroy. Karl Marx did not want to help the working classes, but he did want to make them kill people, often each other.   Marx believed a great change was on the horizon, but the problem with his ideas was that he believed the change could only and must be reached via great conflict. He believed society was on the verge of collapse, he never incited peaceful resolution or the empowerment of workers and always sought only to arm them rather than communicate with them. When he visited the German Workers’ Education Society of London in 1845, he found self-educated, self-made men. They were anti-liberal, anti-bohemian and practically-minded, and he saw them as lowly for not sharing his apocalyptic ambitions for the future. They engaged in practical discussion, though without academic training in philosophy (which is why he disliked working men and thought them beneath himself). This was not what he wanted. He wanted revolution and chaos, for as he stated: “Socialism cannot be brought into existence without revolution”. When his father died in 1838, he spent much of his inheritance of 6000 ₣ on arming Belgian workers with guns. Certainly, the violent revolutions of the country I grew up in, France, have a long history indeed of upheaving everything and distracting from the country’s problems until they go away, but they ultimately benefited slightly wealthier men seizing power, only to be deposed by men slightly less wealthy than themselves. Every time, it is the slightly less hard-working man who gains leadership at the expense of the slightly harder working man. The same can be seen in the French-backed American Revolution, a systematic upheaval which allowed wealthy English landowners in the New World to detach themselves from their colonial control of ‘The British’ under the new identity of ‘The American’, and they profited and suffered immensely. Again, marrying oneself to a new culture, a new identity, will dictate one’s destiny. And so come into focus the fires of modern-day Paris, lit by the Gilets Jaunes. Fire once more presides the times of chaos, the times of change. So how, I ask, can this, revolution, be the answer? I cannot agree that Marx was right in the larger sense that it is necessary, but I must wonder as to his related belief that it is inevitable. Visions of fire, revolution and chaos, and one must think of the Wheel of Fire, a Greek mythological image originating in the punishment of Ixion after his lusting for Zeus’s divine consort, Hera. It signifies a torturous chain of events leading to dire consequences, in result of personal actions or flaws which are ultimately the victim’s fault. It provides a caveat to be considered, in matters of want and misplaced ambition. It is the fall from grace, and it is engendered by the foreboding betrayal of a sacred matrimony. As I attend a concert by the folk-rock band Faun, at the end, a skaldic lutist/mandolin player speaks as a grandiose orator, transforming from the humble, weaselly man he has been every other time we hear him speak into something approaching the divine musician we have seen play, as when he performs, as when he sings. His band’s spectacle reaches an emotive pinnacle as he speaks, almost preaching now, but with such zeal the likes of which a hurricane could not bring any modern Christian priest to muster, with the passion not seen since they were not merely excused by the burning of our wise women but corralled it. The kind of power not seen unless truth and conviction bolster the rightful in their unextinguished focus; he says we must remember who we are. Remember nature. Our own nature. As he speaks in his complete form, finally, but only once, is mentioned the creature who is the namesake of the band, the faun, the Pan figure, who just like Krishna plays the flute and sits surrounded by the animals, a Master of Beasts. And then he says how it was known by another name to the Celts, as Cernunnos. Thus begins the cycle. A vision of a devil. A vision of nature, personified. A herald of flame to come. And so I contemplate this apple of my eye which I see on the horizon. Knowledge of paganism is the knowledge of how to live and connect with our environment of Europe, and so I say that, for the West, to transcend Christendom via the produce of the trees of knowledge is the only way that we will be able to live in this garden. The serpent penetrates the apple. Perhaps, it is to be seized, like the Snake-Witch Stone shows, perhaps it is to be defeated like the biblical Leviathan. But it is no primitive return to nature which will save us now, but a mature and learned taking into oneself the ways of yore. We must make of ourselves ergonomic beings. A form of cultural bio-mimicry will be observed in ancient lore, and this will tell us how to be. Simply put, there are philosophies and facts to be observed in the natural world, echoed in mythology, which can inform us on how to live our lives, so we can be healthier, but also on how we should think, so we can be holier. As I think on this vision, I must wonder what ‘true spiritual sun’ will be unveiled to us, ‘hidden by a disc of golden light’. What truth will be known, what duty done? What sacred feet, anointed now? Looking to the future, for Europe, for the world? Fire. But will it be a wheel or a dawn? This will depend on the nature, the aspect and, I fear, upon the reception of this, the Truth. These tales of myth and history weave in and out of each other, they remind us of our inherent shared heritage defined not as humans, but as people. For, in commiseration with history, mythology serves not only to grant us stories from the past where we may learn how to rise, but also stories of the soul, that we may learn not to fall. And what these similarities do tell us is that Europe should be united under common ground, regardless of any Union - so long as it remains European. As such, it is time Europe decided to whom it would be married and what is to be the philosophical companion to its destiny, what identity will accompany it towards an uncertain future. Some would say we look outside, or without. I merely say we look within.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">An Anthropological Consideration of Ugandan Knuckles: The Opiate for a Poisoned State</title>
      <link href="/An-Anthropological-Consideration-of-Ugandan-Knuckles" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Anthropological Consideration of Ugandan Knuckles: The Opiate for a Poisoned State" />
      <published>2019-02-07T03:20:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T03:20:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/An-Anthropological-Consideration-of-Ugandan-Knuckles</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/An-Anthropological-Consideration-of-Ugandan-Knuckles">&lt;p&gt;I know, dear reader, that you have thought of this before, as I have; there may, in fact, be far more to the Ugandan Knuckles meme than meets the eye. Could it be that in this chaotic, disorganised vision of a cultural dead space, this wellspring of enjoyment is reflective of our times far more than was initially thought?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ugandan Knuckles meme encompasses, in truth and upon further inspection, a highly complex social structure. It has a diaspora of ethnographically observed motifs spawned forth from its hierarchies, with inner conflicts and philosophical, spiritual quandaries levied against the outside world from the safe confines of VRChat. After all, the people propagating the meme remain, if anything, human. And so from them, we may examine human nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one thing, the acolytes of this subculture organise themselves into a diverse and very complicated hierarchy. It is quite hard to discern, but I believe Knuckles avatars sporting a blue skin as opposed to the common red are still part of the same clan, though there may be a position in the social system implied, which is possibly the &lt;em&gt;“Ugandan Warrior”&lt;/em&gt; class. These will protect the Queen (more on her later). Yellow skin is likely the mark of &lt;em&gt;“The Commander”&lt;/em&gt;, a high position seemingly not coveted but accepted with humility by new initiates. It is likely that they frequently cycle this position over a short term in office and they do this because their true calling is to form a party capable of locating a female monarch.
They operate under a Sacral Democratic Monarchy, for they elect a Queen and will follow this Queen under the belief that she will grant them sacred knowledge of &lt;em&gt;“The Way”&lt;/em&gt;. The requirements for this position are few and, at times, scant or plentifully observed depending on the weeaboo and anime fan presence in the Chat Room. She need only be female, Japanese idol-like (Hatsune Mikus are frequently accosted), or Moe – fluorescent-haired preferable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once they find a Queen, they will fawn over her and begin to voice their contentment with an a-linguistic motif. This is ‘clucking’, a vocalized ‘clock’ sound, as an aspirated glottal &lt;em&gt;/’klɒk/&lt;/em&gt; made with the tongue behind the teeth (very culturally unique) and would be called in linguistic anthropology a non-verbal acoustic call, conveying emotion. If the Queen can be found to have led them astray, the roving pack of miniatures will engage in a ‘spitting’, to indicate their rejection of this false divine saviour. They demand respect for the Queen, crave her love but will also spit on her.
Unfortunately, Ugandan Knuckles politics is far too complex to outline here, but it is apparent that conflicts of interest are quite common. Splinter groups forming as different female players displaying a lolicon aesthetic are frequently happened upon and hailed, willingly or no, as the next holy monarch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the anthropology of religion, The Divine Right, or Holy Mandate to rule is a frequently observed feature of cultures on planet earth where church and state are one. We might point in this case to the cause of such a phenomenon seen here with this meme format being a growing atheistic worldview in our society. As we feel a detachment from the spirit, we see the humorous taking on the responsibility of the severe, in a nervous rebuttal of the empty, godless nation-state. For how can we have faith in leaders who possess no faith themselves? Of course, such practices in the West date back to pre-Christian, Pagan Europe, a paradoxically dark, yet ethno-nationally enlightened time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ugandan Knuckles Clan members’ spiritual path, &lt;em&gt;The Way&lt;/em&gt;, is a nomadistic, possibly nihilistic, and devotional philosophy of the self defined by space and sovereignty tied to one’s destiny. In anthropological terms, this is a Durkheimian consideration of how society maintains coherence and integrity in the modern era, when traditionalism is lost and replaced by less organically defined economic, social institutions. A brother is kin, a member of the clan provides a sense of belonging, the love found in belonging to one’s nation allows for the fortitude necessary to sustain it. To ask, &lt;em&gt;“Why are you running?”&lt;/em&gt;, is to wonder how a friend can flee his destiny. Why doubt oneself? This exemplifies a unique rudimentary cultural Kismet ideology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ugandan Knuckles clans seek only to find meaning and satisfaction in their existence by being close to their Queen and their spiky brethren. This anthropological sense of self is defined as and functions by the mechanisms of Cultural Memory. If they find one of their flock to have strayed from &lt;em&gt;The Way&lt;/em&gt;, or to be in any manner unholy, they will voice sympathy and announce: &lt;em&gt;“We must pray for this one, my brothers”&lt;/em&gt;. Such camaraderie reflects a beauteous, shared heritage in shouldering the burden of life with one’s ethnocultural peers, a sentiment sadly lacking in today’s society, and it ought to be observed! One might say it is the trauma of meandering about, in search of one’s home which acts as what we call in anthropology a &lt;em&gt;“rite of passage”&lt;/em&gt;, serving the purpose of bonding together a generation of young men that they may go out into the world as brothers-in-arms—though this usually applies to something like the Mukanda ritual ceremony of the Ndembu people in Zambia, wherein young boys are taken away from the village at a certain age to have the extremities of their manhood cut-off. During this &lt;em&gt;rite of passage&lt;/em&gt;, young men enter what anthropologists call the Liminal State. In this state, young men are neither man nor child, which allows for the personal transformation of the self, body, and spirit. But how does this happen? Simple. To take from the famous adage;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;i&gt;“Gamers are the most oppressed group”.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the most cursory glance at &lt;em&gt;“Gamer Fashion”&lt;/em&gt;, a subset in the nomenclature formerly known as Gamer/Geek Culture (from which the Ugandan Knuckles ensued) has much to inform us. Gamer T-Shirts, which we will here be using as ethnographic evidence of their material culture, read thusly: &lt;em&gt;“Hey, SNOWFLAKE, there are only two genders, so get over it!”&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;“If you are reading this I’ll have you know I was forced to put my controller down and enter society”&lt;/em&gt;; or &lt;em&gt;“I’m a gamer, not because I don’t have a life, but because I choose to have many!”&lt;/em&gt;. Such a study clearly identifies these G-Fuelled, never-pulled, but-very-virile-in-the-season-pass plucky young miscreants. For these young men belong to the techno-fanatical, pseudo-radical, and pseudo-puritanical generation called Y-Z millennials. A less prudent man might cut themselves on this level of edginess, but not these brave souls, though they do face terrible hardship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, more articles have been published by various millennial plaintiffs decrying this Ugandan Knuckles meme, which they deem to be racist, therefore further displaying just how oppressed these poor, unfortunate outcast souls find themselves. Time and time again, they are dissatisfied with what their society gives them, as the West disowns itself with the neo-feminist, cultural-Marxist criticism of the post-colonial Occident. And yet still as they seek refuge, they are blasted in a flame war to light our skies in Cyberspace for generations. Down the line, they will speak of these days when the completed their rite of passage, as they do of the great Meme Wars, and tales of &lt;em&gt;The Way&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Pepe&lt;/em&gt; alike will be told around pixelated campfires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the same, it ought not be forgotten that the creators of the 2010 Ugandan film &lt;em&gt;Who Killed Captain Alex?&lt;/em&gt;, having originated the quotes whose accents and manners were taken-on by the scarlet Ugandan Faithful have themselves endorsed the meme, sharing many iterations and supporting the sub-culture as best they can from their twitter page, @Wakaliwood. And really, it must not be omitted from the debate that in modern anthropological circles, the principle of Cultural Relativism posits that we should treat all cultures equally! And yet. And yet must this come at the expense of some cultures in favour of others?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To speak as the Geek is to know the Geek; In the words of the ancient 10th-century Anglo-Saxon poem &lt;em&gt;The Wanderer&lt;/em&gt;, as repurposed into King Théoden’s monologue by J. R. R. Tolkien for his LOTR book &lt;em&gt;The Two Towers&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;i&gt;“Where is the horse and the rider? &lt;br /&gt;
Where is the horn that was blowing? &lt;br /&gt;
They have passed like rain on the mountains, &lt;br /&gt;
like wind in the meadow. &lt;br /&gt;
The days have gone down in the West, &lt;br /&gt;
behind the hills... Into Shadow.”&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gentlemen, I say, in recalling the outcry and sensitivity previously observed within the Gaming community by the refrain, &lt;em&gt;“where is the justice for Harambe?”&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;“where is the respect due for this honourable and noble meme which may soon face oblivion?” &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in observing such criticisms, this comes from the same media-climate as the cultural motifs which allowed and indeed enabled the late, bait, sombre-fated Gillette advert to happen, whence we see this same accusatory thought-process levelled against not only all white, cisgendered men but all men in general! Is it any wonder the self-removed would seek solace in the virtual arms of a neon-lit loli?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our current cultural climate is unassertive, unsure and self-destructing. When a culture is diseased, it may find when turning around to scrub behind itself in the shower one day that oddly-formed but quite enigmatically defined growths in the shapes of secondary Sonic the Hedgehog characters have developed upon the rump! Visions beholding plagues of frogs reoccur…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then again, and from a laboratory perspective, the difference between a contemporary consideration of a “model society”, perhaps sat on a table as a maquette of what we might be (as envisioned by those who would have us constantly be in self-un-realisation) and a VR vat containing a vile, porous, clucking swarm of social parasites is that, scientifically speaking, such bacteria will eventually develop its own culture.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Morgan Black</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I know, dear reader, that you have thought of this before, as I have; there may, in fact, be far more to the Ugandan Knuckles meme than meets the eye. Could it be that in this chaotic, disorganised vision of a cultural dead space, this wellspring of enjoyment is reflective of our times far more than was initially thought?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Winter Solstice Ceremony at Stanton Drew Stone Circle</title>
      <link href="/Winter-Solstice-Ceremony" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winter Solstice Ceremony at Stanton Drew Stone Circle" />
      <published>2019-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Winter-Solstice-Ceremony</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Winter-Solstice-Ceremony">&lt;p&gt;How I wish, dear reader, that I might tell you of how blemishless this ceremony was, how perfectly it did unfold, but sadly, it rather unravelled to dismal disappointment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so it was, on Friday, December 21, 2018 at 5 o’clock in the morning, that myself, a cohort, a witch and two accidentally encountered friends (plucked completely by chance as we crossed paths with them on the way to an uber pick-up point) did become companions in the most bizarre but heartwarming of undertakings; there was to be a Druidic ceremony, at sunrise, at a Neolithic stone circle near the village of Stanton Drew on the outskirts of Bristol, UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are greeted by a film crew and a small contingency of middle-aged women cloaked in long robes and walking with staffs at their sides. The filmographic team will be shooting a documentary for National Geographic, with the footage of the ceremony to be narrated by Morgan Freeman (who sadly would not be attending our English rural romp in person).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Battered by wind and rain, we moved all of us through the emptiness of this winter night’s morning and into a dark field. Trundling across the expanse, it seemed our numbers did increase as if by magical apparitions of many who came from all directions, all to converge in a central mass, to become a large group, to surround and step into the circle which was the Stanton Drew Stones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The megaliths loomed out of the darkness as scars of grey, with rippling light, rain running across their listless and ancient surfaces as we shuffled, bustled and edged our way into position. Lights were erected by the film crew but were torn from their hinges by the furious wind, leaving whole swarms of people consumed in pitch black. Thankfully, as if by command, after half an hour, the elements lessened and eased upon us. Shivering in our boots, we were told by the Head Druid assembled with perhaps six or seven of his entourage that the ceremony would soon commence. A single bodhrán (a kind of drum) began playing a steady beat which seemed somehow suddenly louder than the heaviest of the weather—leaving us only with a harsh breeze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We formed, as instructed, a great circle of possibly seventy people all holding hands. The Head Druid came through the only passage of free movement in and out the circle, a parting at the Western stones reminiscent of the passages often seen in Neolithic round barrows. Followed by the others, this leader of neo-pagan priests began a song with simple words by which all could soon join-in, a pleasant if contrived jaunt of a hymn with text and melody likely an oft-heard ditty in such Neo-Pagan communities, mentioning personification of animals and land with a shared spiritual connection, but probably dating back no further than the New Age movement in the 1970’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This man proclaimed the start of this public ritual and the start of a new phase in time, telling us of how this is, at the solstice, a time for new beginnings and rebirth. Our druids then distributed, in perhaps one of the only truly ‘sacred’ moments of the proceeding, branches of mistletoe which had not yet touched the ground. Such a ritual for their procurement, performed by a druid who must climb an oak tree to cut the mistletoe with a golden sickle and allow it to be caught by others in a white cloak, is the only religious practice for which we have definite knowledge, coming to us from the Roman writings of Pliny the Elder. Coupled with the sacrifice of two white bulls, a brew made from this undertaking on the 6th day of the moon was heralded to bestow fertility and cure all ailments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This connection to mistletoe was later perhaps a little misconstrued at our ceremony—one of the druids giving speeches on behalf of the directions, light, darkness, etc, mentions Baldr, the beautiful god, son of Odin and Frigg, who was slain by Loki with an arrow of mistletoe, for though his mother had endeavoured to ask all things in the land to never harm her beloved child, she had neglected this harmless plant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In comparative mythology, one might see a link to the Llew of Welsh legends, who is nigh-unkillable until his beloved Blodeuwedd, the maiden made of flowers, betrays his weakness to an enemy. But this would be the only motif we might connect in this narrative to the ‘Celtic’ identity promulgated by these neo-druids. And until we see evidence of this legend being related to the winter solstice, reader, this punter of the ancient, the eldritch and the occult will not be convinced. In considering the fertility aspect of the divine associated with Celtic festivals, one druid opted to describe the passionate and sexual embrace of his male partner, complete with graphic descriptions of everything they would with their tongues and bodies. He also went about anointing this circular congregation with water, many times, even through the speeches of other druids, saying that water was life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, along with various (unsuccessful) attempts to set alight a soaked pile of bushes in the centre of the circle, multiple wishes that there be ‘peace throughout all the world’, and the gathering being generally unable to fully hear the druids speaking at a pathetically moderate volume on this magnificently windy morning (a far cry indeed from the thunderous tones of Christopher Lee’s operatic chanting atop the tower of Isengard) made the entire affair seem really rather tame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a drab conclusion, having closed once more the gates of the North, the East and company (but mistaking one for the other), the circle, now blessed by dim, grey daylight, concluded the happenings with probably the best part of that morning, this being a great skipping and hopping, a roving of the congregation that so that we became a revolving set of linked lines in a disorganised but joyful dance set to traditional music. We thence went our separate, hitch-hiking ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you ask me – and in fact, ask anyone you like – paganism ought to be something wild. Raw and uncompromising, within reason of course, and putting us in-mind at least in spirit of the fierce pre-Christian people who did once inhabit this noble and ancient land. And yet, bearing in consideration the words of these, in truth, well-meaning hippies, I begin to wonder, as a man must if he is to mean anything to himself and his close ones, what is it I must give up, in the new year? What is it that I must sacrifice? As my ancestors did before. And what is it I hope for in return?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I leave you with this; the solstice is a time of loss. With thoughts drawn as to what we must gain and what we cannot live without. In place of new year’s resolutions, let us have new year’s dissolutions, in considering the sacrifices we may make, and perhaps must make, in our personal lives. Here is hoping that one day, we will in the South of Britain be able to put on a show in a ritualistic, religious context the likes of which our friends in the North, the Scots, have achieved every year on April, 30 since 1988 at the Beltane Fire Festival, in Edinburgh. Scantily-clad, red-body-painted dancers, revellers and all. I will look for you in the slithy toves and among the bracken and the rough. I will be there in that wind-scathed paysage, upon yonder scraggy and leering hill. Will I see you?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Morgan Black</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">How I wish, dear reader, that I might tell you of how blemishless this ceremony was, how perfectly it did unfold, but sadly, it rather unravelled to dismal disappointment.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
