<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/main/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2023-10-16T21:19:45+01:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/main/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Indo-British Empire: How Indians Built the Raj</title>
      <link href="/The-Indo-British-Empire" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Indo-British Empire: How Indians Built the Raj" />
      <published>2023-05-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2023-05-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Indo-British-Empire</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Indo-British-Empire">&lt;p&gt;The Indian independence movement was built on the supposed axiom that the British Empire in India was singularly evil. According to India's first Prime Minister Jawaharlal Nehru, India's long-suppressed soul found utterance after it was freed from the colonial yoke. Every Indian is taught that the Republic's Founding Fathers, despite their flaws, were fighting the good fight against the white man. In fact, figures like Gandhi and even Shubhas Chandra Bose are accorded a semi-divine status in the narrative of the Indian Freedom Struggle.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, any narrative that portrays one set of people as unequivocally 'good' and another as 'bad' is bound to be far from the truth. The question is: to what extent is the narrative of the evil British Empire in India, a false one? I venture to say that it is gravely so, not because I buy the imperial propaganda of the White Man's Burden but because I find that history shows that the British Empire in India was truly, as Enoch Powell stated in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/VsC6GBw9zew&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt;, the &quot;Indo-British Empire&quot; in India.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Raj formally began after the Government of India Act 1858 and the Queen's Proclamation. This was right after the uprising of 1857 which led to the defeat of the last Mughal Emperor (a mere figurehead at the time) at the hands of the East India Company. The said Government of India Act replaced the rule of the East India Company with the direct rule of the British Crown. The rule of the Company, for all practical purposes, began in 1757, when the Company defeated the forces of the &lt;em&gt;Nawab&lt;/em&gt; of Bengal (equivalent to a British Duke) and had a puppet installed in his stead.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Company had very little actual power prior to this point, apart from having trading privileges granted by the fourth Mughal Emperor. In fact, from 1686-1690, the East India Company had tried to carry out a blockade of Mughal ports with the intent of capturing Bengal when they were denied higher trading rights. His Majesty King James II had sent a formidable fleet of ships to assist in this regard. But the forces of the infamous Emperor Alamgir I (or Aurangzeb as he is better known) brought the Company to its knees, literally. The Company's envoys had to prostrate themselves before the last Great Khan, the Refuge of Allah, the Conqueror of Kings (the Mughals had comically grand imperial titles) and pay him a fine amounting to ₹150,000, which was a huge sum at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Alamgir I died in 1707, and the largest political economy of the time slowly descended into chaos and in-fighting. By 1756, the young Siraj ud-Daulah became the &lt;em&gt;Nawab &lt;/em&gt;of Bengal. The brash &lt;em&gt;Nawab &lt;/em&gt;was, to say the least, indelicate and prone to making enemies in the conduct of statecraft. He passed over many influential members of his family and the aristocracy when making official appointments. He also had his aunt's palaces raided to neutralise the threat posed by her. The &lt;em&gt;Nawab &lt;/em&gt;had no understanding of the day-to-day troubles of running a government and trusted a group of Hindu merchants led by one Jagat Seth to manage the treasury. Siraj threatened to have Jagat Seth (literally 'Banker to the World') circumcised upon learning that due to the deep debts of the &lt;em&gt;Nawab&lt;/em&gt;, there was not enough money to pay the salaries of the army.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was not a good move. As Aakar Patel, an eminent journalist &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/amp/s/www.livemint.com/Opinion/zgaDxyMuIrH3QWHElwkX3M/Blame-the-British-Raj-on-bankers.html%3ffacet=amp&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;noted&lt;/a&gt;, &quot;Jagat Seth ran the economy for Siraj ud Daulah, Mir Jafar, and later for Mir Qasim. It is recorded that&amp;nbsp;₹&amp;nbsp;3 out of&amp;nbsp;₹&amp;nbsp;4 collected as revenue in the state went straight to Jagat Seth, against loans he had already advanced to the nawabs.&quot; Jagat Seth and his group of merchants did not take slights such as these and the general mismanagement of the province lightly. They plotted with the young &lt;em&gt;Nawab'&lt;/em&gt;s rivals, chiefly one Mir Jafar, to have the young &lt;em&gt;Nawab&lt;/em&gt; removed. In this plot, the British were the natural allies of the shrewd &lt;em&gt;Bania&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the British had many grouses against the &lt;em&gt;Nawab&lt;/em&gt;, such as the alleged Black Hole of Calcutta incident, the real point of synergy between the Seth and the Company was the Company's adherence to the rules of good business. As pointed out by Patel once again, the Indian merchants of Bengal stored their commercial paper and cash in Calcutta. This was because the British could be trusted with keeping their end of the bargain. The British system of justice, the rule of law, ensured that contractual obligations were enforced and honoured. For a betting banker, the chances of getting a return on his investment from a capitalist force like the Company was far greater than an immature and whimsical aristocrat.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus in 1757, after recapturing Fort William, Robert Clive, a mentally unstable military genius won the Battle of Plassey against Siraj ud-Daulah, pursuant to a secret treaty between himself and Mir Jafar which was brokered by an agent of Jagat Seth, who operated in the shadows. Clive recognised Mir Jafar as the &lt;em&gt;Nawab &lt;/em&gt;and it was decided that a compensation of 22 million rupees would be made over to the Company by the treasury of the &lt;em&gt;Nawab&lt;/em&gt;. Jagat Seth hastened to the Mughal court in Delhi and succeeded in persuading the Mughal Emperor to give his rubber stamp of approval to the English victory and to the appointment of the new &lt;em&gt;Nawab&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When these facts are taken cognisance of, the beginning of the Empire looks more like a corporate takeover, as William Dalrymple suggests in &lt;em&gt;The Anarchy&lt;/em&gt;, rather than a true subjugation of an indigenous people by an imperialistic force. In fact, the complicity of the indigenous in this corporate takeover seems far greater than that of the imperialists. The Company could not have defeated Siraj in a fair battle. It could not have won without the support of a shrewd banker and a disgruntled relative of Siraj. Even the Company's foot soldiers or &lt;em&gt;sepoys&lt;/em&gt;, as they were called, were not European, but low-caste Indians on the Company's payroll.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foundation of the British Empire in India would have been impossible without Indians facilitating the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cultural developments of the time give further evidence of this. To congratulate Clive on his victory, a certain &lt;em&gt;zamindar &lt;/em&gt;or landlord by the name of &lt;em&gt;Raja &lt;/em&gt;(or 'King') Naba Krishna Dawn organised a grand festival in honour of the Hindu Goddess Durga. This was not strictly in accordance with scripture since the invocation of Durga was usually associated with spring. However, the celebration took hold of the imagination of the new aristocracy under the new masters of Bengal. It became ubiquitous and continued to grow in both scale and splendour. In fact, it has now become Bengal's most important festival and it is now rare to see Durga worship in spring.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India's native elites were happy to give up power for the centralisation that was brought about by the British. A patent example is the doctrine of subsidiary alliance formulated by Lord Wellesley - who was appointed Governor-General of India in 1798. This doctrine capitalised on the existence of the many bitter warring nobles in the subcontinent - who had grown in power and independence due to the decline of the Mughal Empire - but were deeply insecure due to the anarchy that was prevalent in those times.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The British offered protection to these nobles from the threats posed by their rivals and other colonising forces such as the French. In exchange, these nobles were required to maintain an army of the East India Company stationed permanently in their territory. More importantly, the Company would place an agent in the court of the noble as the point of contact and as a check on any potential betrayals by the nobles.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, this was an enticing deal for the near-independent vassals of the Mughals: They wouldn't really have to maintain their own armies to fight off constant threats, and business with the Company would ensure that the riches would keep flowing. The powerful and wealthy Nizam of Hyderabad, the region where the Kohinoor diamond was mined, was the first to sign up to the doctrine. After the defeat of Tipu Sultan, the Wodeyar rulers of the area of Mysore signed up. With the defeat of the Marathas in 1817-1819, the &lt;em&gt;Peshwa&lt;/em&gt; or Prime Minister of the Marathas accepted the doctrine as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, war and conquest were necessary in many cases, but the doctrine of subsidiary alliances was a success. India's ruling class was too selfish and too narrow-minded to resist British paramountcy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Indian kings were handsomely rewarded for giving up some of their powers. The riches of the Kings of Patiala, i.e. the successors to the Kings who gave up the Kohinoor to Her Majesty Empress Victoria - grew immensely during the Raj, with lavish parties and Rolls Royces characterising their rule. The Marathas and Rajputs who are upheld as the paragons of nationalism by Hindu Nationalists built palaces, held grand &lt;em&gt;darbars&lt;/em&gt;, and bathed themselves in decadence as junior partners of the Raj.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the establishment of the Empire was a consequence of Indian acquiescence, its continuation, especially during its heyday, was due to a special partnership. A partnership that had no parallel in any other part of the Empire. While the nobility ushered in the British Raj, the Hindu and Muslim landed elite, the Pandit and the Ashraf, made it the envy of the world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Brahmins and other upper castes (both Hindu and Muslim) of East India pursuant to the Permanent Settlement of 1793 were given ownership of the lands of which they were mere tax collectors under the Mughal regime. These aristocrats thus became the backbone of the Company's rule and the British Raj, they ensured that the flow of money extracted from the fertile lands of India to the coloniser remained undiminished. According to a research &lt;a href=&quot;https://egrove.olemiss.edu/hon_thesis/1886&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;, the collection of land revenue never really declined when famines broke out in North India where the &lt;em&gt;zamindars&lt;/em&gt; were dominant. In fact, during the 200 years of the Raj, which was afflicted by 17 major famines, land revenue collection only ever grew.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;zamindar&lt;/em&gt;, as the plinth of the Raj's revenue extraction infrastructure, grew very rich by exploiting the peasant. In fact, the Famine Commission of the British Raj itself remarked in 1880 that the objective of the feudal landlord was &quot;to harass the tenant and to diminish the value of his occupancy rights, by bringing suit after suit for enhancement of the rent.&quot;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If cultivators left their villages for relief work during a famine, the landlords would ruthlessly take over &lt;a href=&quot;https://ora.ox.ac.uk/objects/uuid:431f85b3-e454-4faa-9718-4c49cee32460/files/m71b80352b972c86747a7a64c00af818a&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;their lands&lt;/a&gt;, even if they had left women and children behind. British officials, when dealing with a famine in the United Provinces (present-day Uttar Pradesh), observed in 1879 that &quot;If&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;this famine lasts for a year there will not be an occupancy right left in the whole of&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moradabad&quot; due to the &lt;em&gt;zamindar&lt;/em&gt; of Moradabad remorselessly taking over the lands of his tenant farmers who had left for relief work. The famine became a tool for the upper caste &lt;em&gt;zamindar&lt;/em&gt; to advance profitability. He would hoard grain whenever the symptoms of famine became apparent instead of advancing any loans to his farmers. This hoarded grain would then be sold at extortionate prices, giving the &lt;em&gt;zamindar&lt;/em&gt; a windfall gain.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering all this, it should come as no surprise that India was ruled by a handful of British officials. Even as late as 1931, when India had a population of 300 million, there were only 60,000 Britons in the armed forces of India and a meagre 4,000 of them in the Indian civilian administration! The British did not need to actually do the dirty work of subjugating &quot;the bloody natives&quot; and extracting an estimated $45 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aljazeera.com/opinions/2018/12/19/how-britain-stole-45-trillion-from-india&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;trillion&lt;/a&gt; from their lands, they could rely on India's pre-existing social and economic upper-crust to do it for them.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, while it is all good fun for Indians to marvel at Shashi Tharoor's lambasting of the British Empire, it is extremely hard but extremely necessary to look within and ask ourselves whether we (or perhaps a section of us) are the ones responsible for our historic oppression.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="main" />
      
        <category term="featured" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Indian independence movement was built on the supposed axiom that the British Empire in India was singularly evil. According to India's first Prime Minister Jawaharlal Nehru, India's long-suppressed soul found utterance after it was freed from the colonial yoke. Every Indian is taught that the Republic's Founding Fathers, despite their flaws, were fighting the good fight against the white man. In fact, figures like Gandhi and even Shubhas Chandra Bose are accorded a semi-divine status in the narrative of the Indian Freedom Struggle.&amp;nbsp; Naturally, any narrative that portrays one set of people as unequivocally 'good' and another as 'bad' is bound to be far from the truth. The question is: to what extent is the narrative of the evil British Empire in India, a false one? I venture to say that it is gravely so, not because I buy the imperial propaganda of the White Man's Burden but because I find that history shows that the British Empire in India was truly, as Enoch Powell stated in an interview, the &quot;Indo-British Empire&quot; in India.&amp;nbsp; The Raj formally began after the Government of India Act 1858 and the Queen's Proclamation. This was right after the uprising of 1857 which led to the defeat of the last Mughal Emperor (a mere figurehead at the time) at the hands of the East India Company. The said Government of India Act replaced the rule of the East India Company with the direct rule of the British Crown. The rule of the Company, for all practical purposes, began in 1757, when the Company defeated the forces of the Nawab of Bengal (equivalent to a British Duke) and had a puppet installed in his stead.&amp;nbsp; The Company had very little actual power prior to this point, apart from having trading privileges granted by the fourth Mughal Emperor. In fact, from 1686-1690, the East India Company had tried to carry out a blockade of Mughal ports with the intent of capturing Bengal when they were denied higher trading rights. His Majesty King James II had sent a formidable fleet of ships to assist in this regard. But the forces of the infamous Emperor Alamgir I (or Aurangzeb as he is better known) brought the Company to its knees, literally. The Company's envoys had to prostrate themselves before the last Great Khan, the Refuge of Allah, the Conqueror of Kings (the Mughals had comically grand imperial titles) and pay him a fine amounting to ₹150,000, which was a huge sum at the time. But Alamgir I died in 1707, and the largest political economy of the time slowly descended into chaos and in-fighting. By 1756, the young Siraj ud-Daulah became the Nawab of Bengal. The brash Nawab was, to say the least, indelicate and prone to making enemies in the conduct of statecraft. He passed over many influential members of his family and the aristocracy when making official appointments. He also had his aunt's palaces raided to neutralise the threat posed by her. The Nawab had no understanding of the day-to-day troubles of running a government and trusted a group of Hindu merchants led by one Jagat Seth to manage the treasury. Siraj threatened to have Jagat Seth (literally 'Banker to the World') circumcised upon learning that due to the deep debts of the Nawab, there was not enough money to pay the salaries of the army.&amp;nbsp; This was not a good move. As Aakar Patel, an eminent journalist noted, &quot;Jagat Seth ran the economy for Siraj ud Daulah, Mir Jafar, and later for Mir Qasim. It is recorded that&amp;nbsp;₹&amp;nbsp;3 out of&amp;nbsp;₹&amp;nbsp;4 collected as revenue in the state went straight to Jagat Seth, against loans he had already advanced to the nawabs.&quot; Jagat Seth and his group of merchants did not take slights such as these and the general mismanagement of the province lightly. They plotted with the young Nawab's rivals, chiefly one Mir Jafar, to have the young Nawab removed. In this plot, the British were the natural allies of the shrewd Bania.&amp;nbsp; While the British had many grouses against the Nawab, such as the alleged Black Hole of Calcutta incident, the real point of synergy between the Seth and the Company was the Company's adherence to the rules of good business. As pointed out by Patel once again, the Indian merchants of Bengal stored their commercial paper and cash in Calcutta. This was because the British could be trusted with keeping their end of the bargain. The British system of justice, the rule of law, ensured that contractual obligations were enforced and honoured. For a betting banker, the chances of getting a return on his investment from a capitalist force like the Company was far greater than an immature and whimsical aristocrat.&amp;nbsp; Thus in 1757, after recapturing Fort William, Robert Clive, a mentally unstable military genius won the Battle of Plassey against Siraj ud-Daulah, pursuant to a secret treaty between himself and Mir Jafar which was brokered by an agent of Jagat Seth, who operated in the shadows. Clive recognised Mir Jafar as the Nawab and it was decided that a compensation of 22 million rupees would be made over to the Company by the treasury of the Nawab. Jagat Seth hastened to the Mughal court in Delhi and succeeded in persuading the Mughal Emperor to give his rubber stamp of approval to the English victory and to the appointment of the new Nawab.&amp;nbsp; When these facts are taken cognisance of, the beginning of the Empire looks more like a corporate takeover, as William Dalrymple suggests in The Anarchy, rather than a true subjugation of an indigenous people by an imperialistic force. In fact, the complicity of the indigenous in this corporate takeover seems far greater than that of the imperialists. The Company could not have defeated Siraj in a fair battle. It could not have won without the support of a shrewd banker and a disgruntled relative of Siraj. Even the Company's foot soldiers or sepoys, as they were called, were not European, but low-caste Indians on the Company's payroll.&amp;nbsp; The foundation of the British Empire in India would have been impossible without Indians facilitating the same.&amp;nbsp; The cultural developments of the time give further evidence of this. To congratulate Clive on his victory, a certain zamindar or landlord by the name of Raja (or 'King') Naba Krishna Dawn organised a grand festival in honour of the Hindu Goddess Durga. This was not strictly in accordance with scripture since the invocation of Durga was usually associated with spring. However, the celebration took hold of the imagination of the new aristocracy under the new masters of Bengal. It became ubiquitous and continued to grow in both scale and splendour. In fact, it has now become Bengal's most important festival and it is now rare to see Durga worship in spring.&amp;nbsp; India's native elites were happy to give up power for the centralisation that was brought about by the British. A patent example is the doctrine of subsidiary alliance formulated by Lord Wellesley - who was appointed Governor-General of India in 1798. This doctrine capitalised on the existence of the many bitter warring nobles in the subcontinent - who had grown in power and independence due to the decline of the Mughal Empire - but were deeply insecure due to the anarchy that was prevalent in those times.&amp;nbsp; The British offered protection to these nobles from the threats posed by their rivals and other colonising forces such as the French. In exchange, these nobles were required to maintain an army of the East India Company stationed permanently in their territory. More importantly, the Company would place an agent in the court of the noble as the point of contact and as a check on any potential betrayals by the nobles.&amp;nbsp; Naturally, this was an enticing deal for the near-independent vassals of the Mughals: They wouldn't really have to maintain their own armies to fight off constant threats, and business with the Company would ensure that the riches would keep flowing. The powerful and wealthy Nizam of Hyderabad, the region where the Kohinoor diamond was mined, was the first to sign up to the doctrine. After the defeat of Tipu Sultan, the Wodeyar rulers of the area of Mysore signed up. With the defeat of the Marathas in 1817-1819, the Peshwa or Prime Minister of the Marathas accepted the doctrine as well.&amp;nbsp; Indeed, war and conquest were necessary in many cases, but the doctrine of subsidiary alliances was a success. India's ruling class was too selfish and too narrow-minded to resist British paramountcy.&amp;nbsp; The Indian kings were handsomely rewarded for giving up some of their powers. The riches of the Kings of Patiala, i.e. the successors to the Kings who gave up the Kohinoor to Her Majesty Empress Victoria - grew immensely during the Raj, with lavish parties and Rolls Royces characterising their rule. The Marathas and Rajputs who are upheld as the paragons of nationalism by Hindu Nationalists built palaces, held grand darbars, and bathed themselves in decadence as junior partners of the Raj. If the establishment of the Empire was a consequence of Indian acquiescence, its continuation, especially during its heyday, was due to a special partnership. A partnership that had no parallel in any other part of the Empire. While the nobility ushered in the British Raj, the Hindu and Muslim landed elite, the Pandit and the Ashraf, made it the envy of the world.&amp;nbsp; The Brahmins and other upper castes (both Hindu and Muslim) of East India pursuant to the Permanent Settlement of 1793 were given ownership of the lands of which they were mere tax collectors under the Mughal regime. These aristocrats thus became the backbone of the Company's rule and the British Raj, they ensured that the flow of money extracted from the fertile lands of India to the coloniser remained undiminished. According to a research paper, the collection of land revenue never really declined when famines broke out in North India where the zamindars were dominant. In fact, during the 200 years of the Raj, which was afflicted by 17 major famines, land revenue collection only ever grew.&amp;nbsp; The zamindar, as the plinth of the Raj's revenue extraction infrastructure, grew very rich by exploiting the peasant. In fact, the Famine Commission of the British Raj itself remarked in 1880 that the objective of the feudal landlord was &quot;to harass the tenant and to diminish the value of his occupancy rights, by bringing suit after suit for enhancement of the rent.&quot;&amp;nbsp; If cultivators left their villages for relief work during a famine, the landlords would ruthlessly take over their lands, even if they had left women and children behind. British officials, when dealing with a famine in the United Provinces (present-day Uttar Pradesh), observed in 1879 that &quot;If&amp;nbsp; this famine lasts for a year there will not be an occupancy right left in the whole of&amp;nbsp; Moradabad&quot; due to the zamindar of Moradabad remorselessly taking over the lands of his tenant farmers who had left for relief work. The famine became a tool for the upper caste zamindar to advance profitability. He would hoard grain whenever the symptoms of famine became apparent instead of advancing any loans to his farmers. This hoarded grain would then be sold at extortionate prices, giving the zamindar a windfall gain.&amp;nbsp; Considering all this, it should come as no surprise that India was ruled by a handful of British officials. Even as late as 1931, when India had a population of 300 million, there were only 60,000 Britons in the armed forces of India and a meagre 4,000 of them in the Indian civilian administration! The British did not need to actually do the dirty work of subjugating &quot;the bloody natives&quot; and extracting an estimated $45 trillion from their lands, they could rely on India's pre-existing social and economic upper-crust to do it for them.&amp;nbsp; So, while it is all good fun for Indians to marvel at Shashi Tharoor's lambasting of the British Empire, it is extremely hard but extremely necessary to look within and ask ourselves whether we (or perhaps a section of us) are the ones responsible for our historic oppression.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Choose France Tour 2022</title>
      <link href="/Choose-France-Tour-2022" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Choose France Tour 2022" />
      <published>2022-10-29T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2022-10-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Choose-France-Tour-2022</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Choose-France-Tour-2022">&lt;p&gt;As one graduates from school, they are already faced with one of the most important decisions of their lives, the inevitable: “What do I want to do after school?” In most cases, Indian students start looking for universities to apply to, to study further. A majority of these students stay in India to obtain a degree, some prefer to go abroad. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While an education abroad, like most other things, has its pros and cons, it is a fairly popular proposition that attracts millions of Indian students each year. People are willing to pay the high tuition fees and endure the expensive costs of living for the promise of a world-class education, a better quality of life, and the possibility of employment in a developed country. For these students, the first few countries on the list are always the US, Canada, the UK and Australia. It isn’t hard for one to understand why these would be the preferred options for Indians, these are English-speaking developed countries that have hosted Indian students for several decades now. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where the Choose France Tour 2022 comes in. It is an attempt by the French government to make France a solid option in the future for Indian students that are looking to pursue higher studies abroad. With a surprising three-fourths of all French University courses being taught in English, the assurance of lower economic commitment for the students (compared to other options abroad), and a vague but positive chance of employment opportunities post-graduation makes it sound like a lucrative offering. The eleven-crore-rupee sponsorship that the French government is offering as a stimulus for the initiative is also a great starting point. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even so, Indian students would have a hard time ignoring the fact that English is not France's primary language. Although 75% of the courses are in English, that is only restricted to the lectures and the curriculum material. A significant part of the university experience is outside the campus in the sphere of networking. Indians may feel disadvantaged compared to their French counterparts in these situations. However, the launch of the France Alumni India Chapter in 2016 provides Indian students who have studied in France with a unique channel for networking. Despite English being taught in French primary schools to children from as young as five years old, the language barrier will undoubtedly be felt in simple everyday life, socialising and interacting with locals. The French are certainly known to be very proud of their language, and rightfully so. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An optimist, however, would not view this as an obstacle but rather as an opportunity to learn the language. When you are in a foreign land, the cultural experience is much more enriching when you know the language. How cool would it be to be able to read Dumas’ original&lt;em&gt; Les Trois Mousquetaires&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;The Three Musketeers&lt;/em&gt;! Besides, being fluent in French can accelerate a student’s career. According to the &lt;em&gt;Business Standard&lt;/em&gt;, there are over 200 Indian companies, ranging from Tata Consultancy Services to United Phosphorus Limited, with offices all over France, and this number has been on the rise in recent years. Furthermore, top European firms heavily value fluency in an additional European language. Apart from the obvious social and occupational benefits, French is also known to be an analytical language that structures thought and develops critical thinking. It is no wonder that there are so many great French philosophers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question remains, why do the French even want to invest in Indian students? They could just focus on their own population instead. The truth is, France wants to tap into hot talent from a culture that values conscientiousness in education. Something that English-speaking developed countries have been doing for decades. Indian students’ GPAs are consistently above average in foreign universities. Today, the largest corporations in the world are run by Indians. What’s more, universities seek a diverse culture and an influx of Indian students would be another step in that direction for French universities. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the pandemic, in 2019, there were 10,000 Indian students pursuing higher education in France. The former French&amp;nbsp;Foreign Minister, Jean-Yves Le Drian&amp;nbsp;had set a target to double this number by 2025. Indian students currently enrolled in French universities appreciate the practical programme structure and the international outlook of these universities. Also very appealing is the option offered by the French government for international students after graduation to look for employment for a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All things considered, the Indo-French economic connection is already on the rise and this is certainly the beginning of a win-win situation that could benefit both the Indian student and the French government.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Raghav Dhariwal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="main" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As one graduates from school, they are already faced with one of the most important decisions of their lives, the inevitable: “What do I want to do after school?” In most cases, Indian students start looking for universities to apply to, to study further. A majority of these students stay in India to obtain a degree, some prefer to go abroad. While an education abroad, like most other things, has its pros and cons, it is a fairly popular proposition that attracts millions of Indian students each year. People are willing to pay the high tuition fees and endure the expensive costs of living for the promise of a world-class education, a better quality of life, and the possibility of employment in a developed country. For these students, the first few countries on the list are always the US, Canada, the UK and Australia. It isn’t hard for one to understand why these would be the preferred options for Indians, these are English-speaking developed countries that have hosted Indian students for several decades now. This is where the Choose France Tour 2022 comes in. It is an attempt by the French government to make France a solid option in the future for Indian students that are looking to pursue higher studies abroad. With a surprising three-fourths of all French University courses being taught in English, the assurance of lower economic commitment for the students (compared to other options abroad), and a vague but positive chance of employment opportunities post-graduation makes it sound like a lucrative offering. The eleven-crore-rupee sponsorship that the French government is offering as a stimulus for the initiative is also a great starting point. Even so, Indian students would have a hard time ignoring the fact that English is not France's primary language. Although 75% of the courses are in English, that is only restricted to the lectures and the curriculum material. A significant part of the university experience is outside the campus in the sphere of networking. Indians may feel disadvantaged compared to their French counterparts in these situations. However, the launch of the France Alumni India Chapter in 2016 provides Indian students who have studied in France with a unique channel for networking. Despite English being taught in French primary schools to children from as young as five years old, the language barrier will undoubtedly be felt in simple everyday life, socialising and interacting with locals. The French are certainly known to be very proud of their language, and rightfully so. An optimist, however, would not view this as an obstacle but rather as an opportunity to learn the language. When you are in a foreign land, the cultural experience is much more enriching when you know the language. How cool would it be to be able to read Dumas’ original Les Trois Mousquetaires instead of The Three Musketeers! Besides, being fluent in French can accelerate a student’s career. According to the Business Standard, there are over 200 Indian companies, ranging from Tata Consultancy Services to United Phosphorus Limited, with offices all over France, and this number has been on the rise in recent years. Furthermore, top European firms heavily value fluency in an additional European language. Apart from the obvious social and occupational benefits, French is also known to be an analytical language that structures thought and develops critical thinking. It is no wonder that there are so many great French philosophers. The question remains, why do the French even want to invest in Indian students? They could just focus on their own population instead. The truth is, France wants to tap into hot talent from a culture that values conscientiousness in education. Something that English-speaking developed countries have been doing for decades. Indian students’ GPAs are consistently above average in foreign universities. Today, the largest corporations in the world are run by Indians. What’s more, universities seek a diverse culture and an influx of Indian students would be another step in that direction for French universities. Before the pandemic, in 2019, there were 10,000 Indian students pursuing higher education in France. The former French&amp;nbsp;Foreign Minister, Jean-Yves Le Drian&amp;nbsp;had set a target to double this number by 2025. Indian students currently enrolled in French universities appreciate the practical programme structure and the international outlook of these universities. Also very appealing is the option offered by the French government for international students after graduation to look for employment for a year. All things considered, the Indo-French economic connection is already on the rise and this is certainly the beginning of a win-win situation that could benefit both the Indian student and the French government.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Sri Lanka’s Economic Crisis: What Led to Such a Disaster</title>
      <link href="/Sri-Lanka-s-Economic-Crisis-What-Led-to-Such-a-Disaster" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sri Lanka’s Economic Crisis: What Led to Such a Disaster" />
      <published>2022-05-06T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2022-05-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Sri-Lanka-s-Economic-Crisis-What-Led-to-Such-a-Disaster</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Sri-Lanka-s-Economic-Crisis-What-Led-to-Such-a-Disaster">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Sri Lanka is currently facing its worst economic crisis in decades in the form of a combined &lt;strong&gt;balance of payment and sovereign debt crisis&lt;/strong&gt;. The Mahinda Rajapaksa government is finding it difficult to pay for essential imports after a 70% drop in foreign exchange reserves over two years which triggered a currency devaluation. Prices of food and essential goods have increased tremendously, fuel is in short supply and protests have broken out. With a population of 2.19 crore, Sri Lanka has announced its decision to &lt;em&gt;default on its foreign debt of $51 billion &lt;/em&gt;as of April 12. As per the data, Sri Lanka's primary creditors include China and the Asian Development Bank (ADB). 36.4% of Sri Lanka's debt is in international sovereign bonds, with ADB accounting for 14.6%, Japan 10.9% and China 10.8%. India has already extended a $1 billion line of credit to help Sri Lanka buy fuel, food and medicine but some analysts warned that this assistance might prolong the crisis rather than solve it. Sri Lanka is now seeking financial help from the IMF and Sri Lanka finance minister Basil Rajapaksa will also meet with World Bank officials next month to seek support from the United States-headquartered agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What really happened to the Sri Lankan economy?&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The crisis in Sri Lanka is broadly seen as a result of &lt;em&gt;mismanagement of government finances and ill-timed tax cuts, in addition to the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic&lt;/em&gt;. Post-independence in 1948, Sri Lanka's agriculture was dominated by export-oriented crops such as tea, coffee, rubber and spices. But a decline in exports put foreign exchange reserves under strain. Therefore, from 1965 onwards, Sri Lanka obtained 16 loans from the IMF. To make matters worse in April 2021, the government &lt;em&gt;banned the import of fertilizer&lt;/em&gt; which affected the production of tea and rubber. Though in November 2021 the ban was lifted, the earnings from agriculture had declined significantly.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A gloomy situation turned worse with two economic shocks in 2019&lt;/em&gt;. First, there was a series of bomb blasts in churches and hotels in Colombo in April 2019. This led to an 80% decline in tourist arrivals. At the same time, the world was struck by an unprecedented pandemic. Being a tourism dependent country, its situation got worse due to the pandemic. According to the IMF recent report, COVID-19 has severely hit the Sri Lankan economy. The annual GDP growth rate of 2.3% in 2019 declined to -3.6% in 2020. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Second, the Rajapaksa government introduced populist tax cuts prior to the pandemic, limiting the government’s revenue options from corporate tax revenue. Value added tax rates were cut from 15% to 8%, whereas the government reduced the corporate tax rates from 28% to 24%. Foreign remittances from Sri Lankan workers abroad were drying up already. With a weak revenue base, the adverse impact of COVID-19 and the announced relief spending measures led to higher government expenditure which made fiscal deficits to be larger than 10% of GDP in 2020 and 2021, while the economy witnessed a rapid expansion in public debt to 119% of GDP in 2021, i.e., it has borrowed more money than it can produce via goods and services.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In 2020, Sri Lanka lost its access to international capital markets, leading to a decline of international reserves to critically low levels and large-scale direct lending to the government by the Central Bank of Sri Lanka (CBSL). A widening current account deficit and huge external debt repayments led to foreign exchange (FX) shortages, while the official exchange rate remained de facto &lt;em&gt;fixed since&lt;/em&gt; April 2021. All these impacted imports of fuel and other essential goods which sent prices soaring. The war in Ukraine hasn't helped either; the cost of fuel surged by 40% within a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lives of people in Sri Lanka&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;For Sri Lankans, the crisis has turned their daily lives into an endless cycle of waiting in queues for essential goods, many of which are being rationed. Soldiers are stationed at gas stations to calm customers, who line up for hours in the searing heat to fill their tanks. Life of Sri Lankans is made more difficult by frequent power cuts that plunge Colombo into darkness, sometimes for more than 10 hours at a time. Shops have been forced to shut just because they can't run fridges, air conditioners, or fans. Hospitals have refused to do any surgeries because of shortage of medical supplies. People have to wait for hours for propane gas to cook food for their families. The situation in Sri Lanka is so bad that people have now started to flee out of the country. According to experts, bad macroeconomic policy management further accentuated the economic crisis making the common citizenry suffer. Public frustration and anger erupted on April 1, when thousands of people came out on the streets to protest the crippling power cuts and shortages of essential commodities caused by the country’s economic meltdown. Consequently, Sri Lanka’s President Gotabaya Rajapaksa &lt;strong&gt;declared an Emergency on April 1.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What should Sri Lanka do now ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;According to some experts, Sri Lanka should establish a &lt;em&gt;three-year repayment structure&lt;/em&gt;. They believe that doing so would reduce the burden on citizens of Sri Lanka. As per the Verité Research Executive Director and Economist Dr Nishan de Mel, &quot;&lt;em&gt;Sri Lanka is unreasonably committed to repaying its debt. It is more important to press pause on debt repayment and take care of critical economic needs&lt;/em&gt;”. The Lankan economy would need a robust path towards revenue based fiscal consolidation. Reforms must focus on strengthening value added taxes, income and corporate taxes, through gradual rate increases and base broadening measures. In order to reduce fiscal risks from loss-making public enterprises, fiscal adjustment would need to be accompanied by energy pricing reforms.  Short-term monetary contractionary policy is needed to reduce the inflation. As the IMF report suggests institution building reforms, such as revamping the fiscal rule, would also help ensure the credibility of the strategy. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Other longer-term reforms include establishing a flexible exchange rate policy and a medium-to-long-term debt reduction strategy, while ensuring that most of government spending is in targeted social areas for developmental objectives such as in areas of healthcare, education and social security goals.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Cheshta Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="main" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Sri Lanka is currently facing its worst economic crisis in decades in the form of a combined balance of payment and sovereign debt crisis. The Mahinda Rajapaksa government is finding it difficult to pay for essential imports after a 70% drop in foreign exchange reserves over two years which triggered a currency devaluation. Prices of food and essential goods have increased tremendously, fuel is in short supply and protests have broken out. With a population of 2.19 crore, Sri Lanka has announced its decision to default on its foreign debt of $51 billion as of April 12. As per the data, Sri Lanka's primary creditors include China and the Asian Development Bank (ADB). 36.4% of Sri Lanka's debt is in international sovereign bonds, with ADB accounting for 14.6%, Japan 10.9% and China 10.8%. India has already extended a $1 billion line of credit to help Sri Lanka buy fuel, food and medicine but some analysts warned that this assistance might prolong the crisis rather than solve it. Sri Lanka is now seeking financial help from the IMF and Sri Lanka finance minister Basil Rajapaksa will also meet with World Bank officials next month to seek support from the United States-headquartered agency. What really happened to the Sri Lankan economy?&amp;nbsp; The crisis in Sri Lanka is broadly seen as a result of mismanagement of government finances and ill-timed tax cuts, in addition to the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic. Post-independence in 1948, Sri Lanka's agriculture was dominated by export-oriented crops such as tea, coffee, rubber and spices. But a decline in exports put foreign exchange reserves under strain. Therefore, from 1965 onwards, Sri Lanka obtained 16 loans from the IMF. To make matters worse in April 2021, the government banned the import of fertilizer which affected the production of tea and rubber. Though in November 2021 the ban was lifted, the earnings from agriculture had declined significantly.&amp;nbsp; A gloomy situation turned worse with two economic shocks in 2019. First, there was a series of bomb blasts in churches and hotels in Colombo in April 2019. This led to an 80% decline in tourist arrivals. At the same time, the world was struck by an unprecedented pandemic. Being a tourism dependent country, its situation got worse due to the pandemic. According to the IMF recent report, COVID-19 has severely hit the Sri Lankan economy. The annual GDP growth rate of 2.3% in 2019 declined to -3.6% in 2020. &amp;nbsp; Second, the Rajapaksa government introduced populist tax cuts prior to the pandemic, limiting the government’s revenue options from corporate tax revenue. Value added tax rates were cut from 15% to 8%, whereas the government reduced the corporate tax rates from 28% to 24%. Foreign remittances from Sri Lankan workers abroad were drying up already. With a weak revenue base, the adverse impact of COVID-19 and the announced relief spending measures led to higher government expenditure which made fiscal deficits to be larger than 10% of GDP in 2020 and 2021, while the economy witnessed a rapid expansion in public debt to 119% of GDP in 2021, i.e., it has borrowed more money than it can produce via goods and services.&amp;nbsp; In 2020, Sri Lanka lost its access to international capital markets, leading to a decline of international reserves to critically low levels and large-scale direct lending to the government by the Central Bank of Sri Lanka (CBSL). A widening current account deficit and huge external debt repayments led to foreign exchange (FX) shortages, while the official exchange rate remained de facto fixed since April 2021. All these impacted imports of fuel and other essential goods which sent prices soaring. The war in Ukraine hasn't helped either; the cost of fuel surged by 40% within a week. Lives of people in Sri Lanka For Sri Lankans, the crisis has turned their daily lives into an endless cycle of waiting in queues for essential goods, many of which are being rationed. Soldiers are stationed at gas stations to calm customers, who line up for hours in the searing heat to fill their tanks. Life of Sri Lankans is made more difficult by frequent power cuts that plunge Colombo into darkness, sometimes for more than 10 hours at a time. Shops have been forced to shut just because they can't run fridges, air conditioners, or fans. Hospitals have refused to do any surgeries because of shortage of medical supplies. People have to wait for hours for propane gas to cook food for their families. The situation in Sri Lanka is so bad that people have now started to flee out of the country. According to experts, bad macroeconomic policy management further accentuated the economic crisis making the common citizenry suffer. Public frustration and anger erupted on April 1, when thousands of people came out on the streets to protest the crippling power cuts and shortages of essential commodities caused by the country’s economic meltdown. Consequently, Sri Lanka’s President Gotabaya Rajapaksa declared an Emergency on April 1. What should Sri Lanka do now ? According to some experts, Sri Lanka should establish a three-year repayment structure. They believe that doing so would reduce the burden on citizens of Sri Lanka. As per the Verité Research Executive Director and Economist Dr Nishan de Mel, &quot;Sri Lanka is unreasonably committed to repaying its debt. It is more important to press pause on debt repayment and take care of critical economic needs”. The Lankan economy would need a robust path towards revenue based fiscal consolidation. Reforms must focus on strengthening value added taxes, income and corporate taxes, through gradual rate increases and base broadening measures. In order to reduce fiscal risks from loss-making public enterprises, fiscal adjustment would need to be accompanied by energy pricing reforms.  Short-term monetary contractionary policy is needed to reduce the inflation. As the IMF report suggests institution building reforms, such as revamping the fiscal rule, would also help ensure the credibility of the strategy. &amp;nbsp; Other longer-term reforms include establishing a flexible exchange rate policy and a medium-to-long-term debt reduction strategy, while ensuring that most of government spending is in targeted social areas for developmental objectives such as in areas of healthcare, education and social security goals.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
